<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Acarologia</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24349/hzhq-damn</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Presence of Raoiella indica Hirst (Acari: Tenuipalpidae) at an unexpected altitude: in Mexico City.</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>12</day>
            <month>05</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Raoiella indica
Hirst
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Tenuipalpidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Raoiella indica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phoenix
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
canariensis
Chabaud
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phoenix roebelenii
O’Brien
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Raoiella indica
Hirst
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. indica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phoenix canariensis
Chabaud
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phoenix roebelenii
O’Brien
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. indica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. inidica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. indica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Washingtonia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Washingtonia robusta
H. Wendl
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phoenix canariensis
Chabaud
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Raoiella indica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Raoiella indica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. indica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Presence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Raoiella indica
Hirst
</tp:taxon-name>
(Acari: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tenuipalpidae</tp:taxon-name>
) at an unexpected altitude: in 
Mexico City
.

</p>
         <p>

Edith G. Estrada-Venegas 
K
a

, 

Ronald Ochoa 
K
b

, 

Armando Equihua-Martínez 
K
a
a

Colegio de Postgraduados, Instituto de Fitosanidad, Programa de Entomología y 
Acarología
. Km 36.5 carr. Mexico-Texcoco, Montecillo, 
Estado de Mexico
, C.P. 56230.

</p>
         <p>
b

Systematic Entomology Laboratory, ARS, USDA, Beltville, 
Maryland
20705, 
USA
.

</p>
         <p>
Short note
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
</title>
         <p>
&gt; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Raoiella indica
</tp:taxon-name>
or red palm mite, is reported for the first time from 
Mexico City
. It has now been found at 
2244 masl
which is the highest elevation documented for the species. Most of the specimens were collected from the underside of Canarian palms 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phoenix
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>
canariensis
Chabaud
</tp:taxon-name>
) fronds, however it is registered for the first time on the upper side as well. Some specimens were collected also from robellini palms (
<tp:taxon-name>
Phoenix roebelenii
O’Brien
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Keywords

Central 
Mexico

; 
high elevation
; 
landscaping
; 
ornamental palms
; 
red palm mite
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The red palm mite, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Raoiella indica
Hirst
</tp:taxon-name>
, was originally described from coconut palms in 
India
(

). It was first detected in the Americas on the Caribbean Island of 
Martinique
in 2004 (Flechtmann &amp; Etienne 2004), being considered a risk species since its arrival (

). Its progressive dispersion after reaching the New World is spectacular, spreading at an average rate of 
400 km
a year, so that it is now found from Florida in the North to 
Paraguay
in the south (

).
</p>
         <p>
The number of countries where this pest was registered increased from 
33 in
2010 to 
46 in
2022 [Africa (9), Asia (13), North America (17), South America (7)] but there are currently no confirmed records in Europe (Taylor, 2022). Although it was officially reported for the first time in 
Mexico
in 2009 (

), it was intercepted in the same locality (in the southern part of Mujeres Island, 
Quintana Roo
), in 2007 (foreing interception), from a cruise liner on a palm frond hat (Ochoa, personal communication). Since its establishment, the species has been moving along the coasts of the country and currently it is found on both borders, with the 
United States
to the north as well as with Guatemala-Belize to the south (

).
</p>
         <p>
In this paper, following the examination of several palm trees, we report the presence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. indica
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Mexico City
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Material and methods
</title>
         <p>
Sampling activities in search of mites were conducted from 

March to June 
2022

in 
Mexico City
, in Alcaldia Cuahtemoc along 
Oaxaca
Avenue (
19°25′16.8″N
99°09′54.7″W
; 
2234 m
asl), and Alcaldia Gustavo A. Madero, in the General Miguel Miramón Street (
19°29′19.5″N
99°06′37.7″W
; 
2244 m
asl), 510 Avenue (San Juan de Aragon 4° section) (
19°27′53.8″N
</p>
         <p>
99°05′09.6″W
; 
2231 m
asl), where a large number of 
3-10 m
high Canary palms (
<tp:taxon-name>
Phoenix canariensis
Chabaud
</tp:taxon-name>
) with severe chlorosis were observed (
Figure 1A, B
). A few samples from chlorotic robellini palm (
<tp:taxon-name>
Phoenix roebelenii
O’Brien
</tp:taxon-name>
) were collected from 
Oaxaca
Avenue (
19°28′50.1″N
99°07′35.1″W
; 
2234 m
asl).
</p>
         <p>
The collected mites were mounted in Hoyer’s medium for identification and were identified under a Carl Zeis Axioskop 2 plus phase contrast microscope using available taxonomic mite keys. Voucher specimens were saved in the synoptic collection of the Forest Entomology Collection at Colegio de Postgraduados, Montecillo, 
Mexico
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
From samples of fronds of Canary palms with chlorosis taken in March from 
Mexico City
, the damage appeared characteristic of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. indica
</tp:taxon-name>
, but the mites were not found initially. Only in a second examination they were located in protected sites, at the base of the fronds. Live adults, nymphs and eggs were collected from samples from 
Oaxaca
Avenue (
Figure 1C, D
). Exuviae of all stages of development were also observed. They were collected from the underside and, contrary to what was suggested by Di Palma 
et al.
, (2022), for the first time, they were also collected from the upper side of green fronds (
Figure 1D, E
), near the rachis, where the populations find protection. Live adult and immature mites were also collected on the underside of green fronds of chlorotic robellini palms in this study but they had already been found on the upper and lower sides of fronds in 
Yucatan
, 
Mexico
(Unpublished data). Both palm species were registered as hosts of the red palm mite in 
Mexico
(SENASICA 2015).
</p>
         <p>
Under the existing landscaping conditions, the total number of mites collected was limited. However, the successful finding of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. inidica
</tp:taxon-name>
under the prevailing circumstances, demonstrating its adaptative ability, is surprising. Indeed, Mexico City was not considered suitable given its altitude, temperature and humidity are not optimal for this mite based on its biology (

) even though some host plants are documented there. Many sites in Latin American countries and the 
USA
from where 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. indica
</tp:taxon-name>
has been reported are in the range of 0 to 500 meters above sea level, where tropical or sub-tropical conditions prevail [according to the CABI’s map revision (CABI, 2022)], while in Mexico City the climate is mainly temperate sub-humid (87%) and the remainder is a dry and semi-dry climate (7%) and temperate humid (6%) (

).
</p>
         <p>
Checking the distribution and dispersion of the species over time in 
Mexico
(
Figure 2
), suggests that it was well spread on the east coast by 2010 and that it reached the west coast in 2012 and then moved to north and south (

). Although this species is currently reported from the east and west coasts of 
Mexico
, given the conditions in which the species is able to develop (see 

), the central states of 
Mexico
(
Morelos
,
</p>
         <p>
State of 
Mexico
, 
Hidalgo
, 
Tlaxcala
, 
Puebla
, 
San Luis Potosi
, 
Aguascalientes
, 
Nuevo Leon
, 
Zacatecas
and 
Chihuahua
) and some of the coastal states (
Tamaulipas
and 
Baja California
Norte) have appropriate conditions for the establishment of the species.
</p>
         <p>
Based on our findings, we believe that this species will continue to disperse, adapt and settle further. More species of host plants used as ornamentals, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Washingtonia</tp:taxon-name>
palm (
<tp:taxon-name>
Washingtonia robusta
H. Wendl
</tp:taxon-name>
) and other species present in and around 
Mexico City
could facilitate the survival of the mite. The red palm mite is spreading into the interior of the country and is established in 
Mexico City
in low numbers, due to the environmental conditions, on the foliage of the host plants. It is considered that this species may already be present in other parts of 
Mexico City
where a large number of chlorotic or dying host palms are found.
</p>
         <p>
The presence of the species close to the 
USA
border is an important concern to the states of 
California
and 
Arizona
as similar conditions and host plants exist for the establishment of the mites (
Figure 2
). The results of this work may be an early indication of the effects of climate change that are forecast to continue to grow allowing red palm mite and other species into areas which were not considered appropriate for their survival, not only in 
Mexico
but in other places to which where the species is dispersing.
</p>
         <p>is indicated by a yellow point in the center (Drawing by Diana Montoya).</p>
         <p>
The study of the natural enemies of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. indica
</tp:taxon-name>
(insects, mites and pathogens) should be a priority in order to keep the species under control. Likewise, a similar analysis of landscaping plants should be carried out to ensure that some of them may not be possible substitutes for the known susceptible host plants. Similar occurrences of other mite pests have been described (Migeon 
et al.
, 2009) underling the impact a climate in state of flux. Development of new weather modeling could play a critical role in predicting potential future occurrences of adventive or invasive plant feeding mites moving into previously intemperate areas.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
We thank Andrew Ulsamer (SEL, USDA) for revision of the manuscript and suggestions. We also thank the three reviewers and the editor of the Journal Philippe Auger that improve this manuscript. We thank to the “Acari Team” (Ariana Corrales, Diana Montoya, Ivette Rios and 
Mauricio
Perez) for helping in the collection and preservation of the research material. Mention of trade names or commercial products in this publication is solely for the purpose of providing specific information and does not imply recommendation or endorsement by the USDA; USDA is an equal opportunity provider and employer.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ORCID
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Edith G. Estrada-Venegas 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1347-6369 Ronald Ochoa 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1680-3601 Armando Equihua-Martínez 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4392-3924

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Castilho R.C.
, 
Flechtmann C. H. W.
&amp; 
Etienne J.
2004
. 

The red palm mite, 
Raoiella indica
Hirst, a threat to palms in the Americas (Acari: Prostigmata: Tenuipalpidae)

. 
Syst. &amp; Appl. Acarol.
9
: 
109 - 110
. 
https://doi.org/10.11158/saa.9.1.16
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Di Palma A.
, 
Bauchan G.R.
, 
Beard J.J.
, 
Ochoa R.
, 
Seeman O.
&amp; 
Kitajima, E.W.
2022
. 

Erratum: Ultrastructure and functional morphology of the mouthparts in 
Raoiella
mites (Tetranychoidea: Tenuipalpidae): how they use the cheliceral stylets during feeding

. 
Syst. &amp; Appl. Acarol.
27
(
2
): 
347-367
. 
https://doi.org/10.11158/saa.27.4.12
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Estrada-Venegas E.G.
2014
. 

Estatus de 
Raoiella indica
Hirst (Acari: Tenuipalpidae) a cinco años de su arribo a México

. 
Entomología Mexicana.
1
: 
2-12
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Estrada-Venegas E.
, 
Martinez-Morales H.
&amp; 
Villa-Castillo J.
2010
. 

Raoiella indica
Hirst (Acari: Tenuipalpidae): first record and threat in Mexico

. In: 
de Moraes G.J.
, 
Castilho R.C.
, 
Flechtmann C.H.W.
, editors. 
Abstract book: XIII international congress of acarology
. 
Recife
. p. 
77
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fletchtmann, C.H.W.
&amp; J Etienne. 
2004
. 

The red palm mite 
Raoiella indica
Hirst. A threat to palms in the Americas (Acari: Prostgmata: Tenuipalpidae) Syst

. &amp; 
Appl. Acarol.
9
: 
109-110
. 
https://doi.org/10.11158/saa.9.1.16
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hirst S.
1924
. 
On some new species of red spider
. 
Ann Mag Nat Hist Ser
9
(
14
): 
522-527
. https: //doi.org/ 
10.1080/00222932408633151
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Martínez M. D.
; 
Otero-Colina, G.; González-Gómez, R.; Pérez-Panduro, A.; Valle-Mora, J. 2019. Fertility life tables of Raoiella indica (Trombidiformes: Tenuipalpidae) at different temperature and humidity levels
. 
Revista Colombiana de Entomología
2019
, 
45
(
1
): 
https://doi.org/10.25100/socolen.v45i0.7810
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
E. &amp; 
Navajas M.
2009
. 

Modelling the potential distribution of the invasive tomato red spider mite, 
Tetranychus evansi
(Acari: Tetranychidae)

. 
Experimental Applied Acarology
48
: 
199-212
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10493-008-9229-8
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodrigues J.C.V.
, 
Cosh M.H.
, 
Hunt Jr. E.R.
, 
de Moraes G.J.
, 
Barroso G.
, 
White W.A.
&amp; 
Ochoa R.
2020
. 
Tracking red palm mite damage in the Western Hemisphere invasion with Landsat remote sensing data
. 
Insects
11
(
9
): 
627
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/insects11090627
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
SENASICA. 
2015
. 

Ácaro rojo de las palmas (
Raoiella indica
Hirst)

. 
Servicio Nacional de Sanidad, Inocuidad y Calidad Agroalimentaria-Dirección General de Sanidad Vegetal - Programa de Vigilancia Epidemiológica Fitosanitaria
. 
México, D.F.
Ficha Técnica No.
14. 
22 p.
[March 18 2016] Available from: 
https://www.gob.mx/cms/uploads/attachment/file/120233/Ficha_Acaro_rojo_de_las_palmas_
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
2015
. 
pdf
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
SENASICA
, 
2021
. 
Mapa de distribución de la especie
. 
Estatus fitosanitario
. [June 18 2021]. Available from: 
http://sinavef.senasica.gob.mx/mdf/
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Talor B.
2022
. [May 15 2022]. 

Raoiella indica
(red palm mite) CABI Compendium

, 
Datasheet
. 
https://doi.org/10.1079/cabicompendium.46792
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Weatherspark
. 
2022
. 
Datos meteorológicos históricos de a ciudad de México [23 May, 2022]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
