<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Acarologia</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24349/eyu1-eweg</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A method for semi-field rearing of Varroa destructor (Acari: Varroidae) to obtain mites of controlled age and specific life cycle</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Varroa destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Varroidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>

Irina Muntaabski 
K

</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Varroa destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Apis mellifera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>

Varroa destructor

</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>

Apis mellifera

</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Varroa destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Varroidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Apis mellifera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Apidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Varroa destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. mellifera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Varroa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Irina Muntaabski 
K
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

A method for semi-field rearing of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Varroa destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
(Acari: 
<tp:taxon-name>Varroidae</tp:taxon-name>
) to obtain mites of controlled age and specific life cycle

</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>

Irina Muntaabski 
K
</tp:taxon-name>
a

, 

Romina 
M
. Russo 

K
a

, 

María C. Liendo 

K
a

, 
Lucas Landi
b

, 

Silvia B. Lanzavecchia 

K
a

, 

Alejandra C. Scannapieco 

K
a
a

Instituto de Genética ‘Ewald A. Favret’ - Grupo vinculado al IABIMO (INTA - CONICET), Hurlingham, 
Buenos Aires
, 
Argentina
.

</p>
         <p>
b

Instituto de Recursos Biológicos - INTA, Hurlingham, 
Buenos Aires
, 
Argentina
.

</p>
         <p>
Short note
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
ABSTRACT
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Varroa destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
is one of the most devastating ectoparasites of the honey bee, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Apis mellifera
</tp:taxon-name>
, worldwide. Given that 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
has very low survivability and exhibits no successful reproduction away from their natural environment and host and that the availability of mites for experimental purposes is limited by seasonality, several protocols of mite rearing under laboratory conditions have been developed. However, only one of these rearing systems has been able to yield a fertile second generation with a low mite survival. The aim of this study was to develop a semi-field rearing method to obtain mites of known age and life cycle that can be maintained through several generations. We registered and compared survival and reproductive parameters of mites of controlled age during four generations (P, F1, F2, F3) and evidenced no significant differences between these mite groups for these life-history traits. With present results we demonstrate that it is possible to successfully produce a third generation of mites under semi-field conditions. This study brings useful information about key conditions for the proper reproduction of mites in a controlled rearing system and provides a potential standardized method for 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
research, especially for host-parasite interaction experiments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Keywords
semi-field rearing
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Varroa destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
mite reproduction
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Apis mellifera
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
host-parasite interaction
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Varroa destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
(Acari: 
<tp:taxon-name>Varroidae</tp:taxon-name>
) is an obligate ectoparasite of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Apis mellifera
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Apidae</tp:taxon-name>
) that thrives exclusively in honey bee colonies (

). The life cycle of this mite is divided into two phases: a commonly called phoretic phase on adult honey bees and a reproductive phase that occurs inside the sealed honey bee brood cells (reviewed by 

). The process of obtaining 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
mites for experimental purposes under temperate climate is dependent upon season and weather conditions, time-consuming, and usually costly (

; 

). Indeed, the development of an 
in vitro
rearing method for 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
is quite challenging as the mite has highly specific life cycle requirements (

). Several authors have advanced in establishing different 
in vitro
and semi 
in vitro
rearing methods (

; 

; 

; 

; 

, 

; reviewed by 

). These approaches showed promising results, but all attempts failed to yield a reproductively mature and fertile second generation of female mites and to obtain relatively large sample sizes. Here, we designed a semi-field protocol for 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
rearing and evaluated biological parameters of adult mites across several generations. In particular,
</p>
         <p>the use of a mixed strategy of laboratory conditions alternated with the mite on its natural host, the honey bee, enabled the survey of four generations maintaining high mite survival and reproductive success. Our results provide key information to obtain mite progeny with controlled age and specific generation for biological assays.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Material and methods
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Varroa destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
mites were obtained from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. mellifera
</tp:taxon-name>
colonies located at the Instituto de Genética, Instituto Nacional de Tecnología Agropecuaria (INTA, 
Buenos Aires
, 
Argentina
), during the summers between 2017 and 2019. All honey bee colonies were maintained under regular beekeeping practices, with the use of synthetic acaricides once a year, during early autumn. Prior to the experiments, phoretic mite loads from these colonies were assessed following the method described by 

. Honey bee colonies were categorized according to their mite loads (high: &lt;5%, low: &lt;0.5%). Those colonies that exhibited a low mite load (hereafter named LL colonies, a total of 8 colonies) were used as donors of experimental honey bee combs (
Figure 1
) to prevent experimental brood cells from being naturally parasitized, prior to artificial infestation. Colonies with high mite loads (hereafter named HL colonies, a total of 8) were used as donors of phoretic mites (Figure
</p>
         <p>
1), which were collected through the powdered sugar method (

) and immediately transported to the laboratory. The mites in the powdered sugar were collected one by one with a fine-tipped paintbrush, rinsed with a drop of distilled water and transferred onto a wet paper towel placed in a petri dish with a lid. The mites were placed in a chamber with controlled conditions of temperature and humidity (35 ± 1 °C and 60 ± 2%, respectively).
</p>
         <p>HL</p>
         <p>Colonies</p>
         <p>LL</p>
         <p>Colonies</p>
         <p>LL</p>
         <p>Colonies</p>
         <p>LL</p>
         <p>Colonies</p>
         <p>(</p>
         <p>donors</p>
         <p>of</p>
         <p>mites</p>
         <p>)</p>
         <p>(</p>
         <p>donors</p>
         <p>of</p>
         <p>brood</p>
         <p>cells</p>
         <p>)</p>
         <p>(</p>
         <p>donors</p>
         <p>of</p>
         <p>brood</p>
         <p>cells</p>
         <p>)</p>
         <p>(</p>
         <p>donors</p>
         <p>of</p>
         <p>brood</p>
         <p>cells</p>
         <p>)</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>one reproductive cycle within the rearing system; group C (F1-C1): F1 daughter mites in their first reproductive cycle; group D (F1-C2): F1 foundress mites in their second reproductive cycle; group E (F2-C1): F2 daughter mites in their first reproductive cycle; and group F (F3-C1): daughter mites in their first reproductive cycle.</p>
         <p>
Frames with uncapped brood cells of LL colonies were chosen, and these cells were marked on a transparent acetate sheet (map). After the maps were drawn, the frames were placed back in the colonies. Five hours later, recently capped worker brood cells were identified, opened with a scalpel at one edge of the wax cap, and artificially infested with a mite (foundress) using a fine-tipped paintbrush. Subsequently, the cells were closed by gently pushing the capping back on the cell edge (Liendo 
et al.
, 2021). Mites were used within approximately 1 h after collection, and those that could not clutch the paintbrush bristles were considered unhealthy and discarded. A total of 1954 mites were artificially infested in honey bee brood cells.
</p>
         <p>
The frames containing the artificially-infested brood cells were placed in a chamber with controlled conditions of temperature and humidity (35 ± 1 °C and 60 ± 2%, respectively) for eleven days (
Figure 1
). Next, the capped brood cells were carefully opened with a scalpel, and the foundress and the presumably sexually mature daughters were collected. The daughter (F1) and foundress (P) mites were identified by their pigmentation (

). Once identified, female mites were separated, immediately mounted on nurse bees obtained from LL colony brood frames, and placed in glass flasks (3L) (
Figure 1
). Each glass flask of P or F1 mites harbored thirty nurse bees and ten mites. The flasks were provided with containers with honey and water 
ad libitum
and placed in a chamber with controlled conditions of temperature and humidity (35 ± 1 °C and 60%, respectively) in darkness for 4 days (Figure
</p>
         <p>
1). This period was previously described as the time needed for spermatozoa maturation inside the spermatheca, simulating a phoretic phase (

; 

). Then, the mites were recovered from the bees and re-infested in newly-capped brood cells from the LL colonies, restarting a new reproductive cycle (
Figure 1
). This procedure was repeated for three consecutive generations and, as a handling control, the removal of artificially-mite-infested cells by worker bees and mite mortality were registered at day 11 post-infestation in each generation.
</p>
         <p>
Reproductive parameters of 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
females were also recorded at day 11 post-infestation in six groups of mites that differed in generation (P: parental; F1: filial 1 mites;
</p>
         <p>
F2: filial 2 mites; F3: filial 3 mites) and reproductive cycle (C1: first or C2: second life cycle) (
Figure 1
). The mite groups were named and defined as follows: group A (P-Cn): P foundress mites with an unknown number of previous reproductive cycles; group B (P-Cn+1):
</p>
         <p>
P foundress mites with at least one reproductive cycle within the rearing system; group C (F1-C1): F1 daughter mites in their first reproductive cycle; group D (F1-C2): F1 foundress mites in their second reproductive cycle; group E (F2-C1): F2 daughter mites in their first reproductive cycle; and group F (F3-C1): daughter mites in their first reproductive cycle (
Figure 1
). Reproductive parameters were calculated according to 

and 

: fertility (proportion of female mites with at least 
one male
and/or female offspring); non-reproductive 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
(NRVD, proportion of female mites without offspring); non-viable offspring (NVO, proportion of female mites for which the entire offspring was male or the first female descendant emerged too late to allow reaching its sexual maturity before the bee emergence); and abnormal reproduction (AR, sum of NRVD and NVO). Data of reproductive parameters were analyzed by using the general linear mixed model (GLMM) with a binomial distribution and logit link function (NRVD 
vs.
reproductive mites, NVO 
vs.
viable offspring, and AR 
vs.
normal reproduction) considering mite group (A, B, C, D, E, F) as a fixed factor and colonies as random factors. Similarly, data of cell removal and mite mortality were analyzed by using GLMM with a binomial distribution and logit link function (cell removed 
vs.
cell not removed; dead mite 
vs.
live mite). Odds ratios were used to compare mite mortality, reproductive parameters, and cell removal. Multiple comparisons were performed using Fisher LSD (α = 0.05). In all cases, the dispersion of the residues was tested and analyzed. Random residues were analyzed with the Shapiro-Wilks test. To obtain the most appropriate structure of variance, the Akaike information criterion was used. All analyses were performed using the glmer function in R package “lme4” (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
From a total of 1954 mites artificially infested in honey bee brood cells, 707 (36.18%) were removed from cells by worker bees and 83 (4.25%) were registered dead (Supplementary Table S1). Statistical analysis showed no significant differences between P, F1, F2, and F3 generations for these variables (p&gt; 0.05, GLMM results, Supplementary Table S2; 
Figure 2
). As expected, the mean mite survival (95%) registered in our semi-field rearing experiment is higher than the values reported in 
in vitro
rearing systems (80.5% in 

, 78.5 and 50% for the first and the second mite generations, respectively, in 

.
</p>
         <p>
Regarding reproductive parameters analyzed on the remaining 1164 healthy female mites, we observed that 927 (79.64%) were fertile and 237 (20.36%) were non-fertile (Supplementary Table S1). This fertility value was similar to those obtained by 

and 

for 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
mites artificially infesting honey bee brood cells, and it was within the fertility range of 75–95% previously established for naturally reproducing 
<tp:taxon-name>
Varroa
</tp:taxon-name>
females in temperate climate (

; 

; 

; 

). The relatively high mite fertility might indicate that the host cues and/or physiological status required for 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
reproduction were maintained in our system regardless of mite handling, as previously described by 

and 

.
</p>
         <p>
Of the 927 fertile mites, 548 (59.12%) produced viable offspring (normal reproduction) and 379 mites (40.88%) produced non-viable offspring (NVO). The mean percentage of mites that exhibited abnormal reproduction (NVO + non-reproductive mites) was 52.92% (616 mites) (Supplementary Table S1). A relatively high percentage of successful reproducing mites (mean value of 47.1% of mites exhibited normal reproduction) was obtained in our system. Even though previous studies reported similar percentages of 24, 37, and 48% of reproductive F1 mites (

; 

; 

), these values were estimated by considering only mite fertility and not the actual 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
reproductive success, as in the present study.
</p>
         <p>
Paired comparisons between mite groups revealed no significant differences for mite fertility, NRVD, NVO, or AR (p&gt; 0.05; GLMM results, Supplementary Table S2; 
Figure 2
). Previous developed systems for maintaining 
in vitro
populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
on its natural host showed that female mites exhibited very limited reproduction (

) and that 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
reproduction 
in vitro
, specifically past F1 generation, continues to be a challenge (

). The use of our semi-field protocol would allow researchers to overcome this difficulty and, at the same time, enable a relatively large volume of rearing mites to be obtained and maintained for several generations. In addition, our results show that artificially introduced 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
females can reproduce at a rate similar to that of naturally-invaded mites informed in the bibliography. Hence, this semi-field protocol is a promising, effective, and inexpensive strategy to be included in standard methods for 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
research. As artificial infestation includes handling and physiological manipulation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
females, the analysis of other reproductive parameters, such as mite fecundity, must be further evaluated for our rearing system. More studies are also needed to clarify the factors involved in the potential differences observed in survival between 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
foundress and daughter mites beginning their first reproductive cycle, because these are crucial data for developing a large-scale rearing system for this mite species.
</p>
         <p>
In conclusion, the high and similar survival values and reproductive success registered across mite generations indicate that this semi-field rearing method is suitable to analyze biological parameters of 
<tp:taxon-name>
V. destructor
</tp:taxon-name>
in studies that involve a relatively high number of adult mites and several generations and reproductive cycles.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>We thank Dr. Maria Alejandra Palacio for her contributions on drafting the manuscript and Luciano Landi for his support in honey bee colony management.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Funding
</title>
         <p>
This study was funded by the Agencia Nacional de Promoción Científica y Tecnológica of 
Argentina
through the project Foncyt-PICT 2020-2564, and by Instituto Nacional de Tecnología Agropecuaria (INTA) through Grant PE-E1-I017.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ORCID
</title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Irina Muntaabski 
K
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A method for semi-field rearing of Varroa destructor (Acari: Varroidae) to obtain mites of controlled age and specific life cycle</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.24349/eyu1-eweg</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFC5F463FFA2FFDB790BFFAAFFA0FF8B</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24349/eyu1-eweg</pub-id>
               <issn>2107-7207</issn>
               <source>Acarologia</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Irina Muntaabski 
K
</tp:taxon-name>
https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0631-791X


Romina M. Russo 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6888-9123

</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

María C. Liendo 

K

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8464-5652

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Silvia B. Lanzavecchia 

K

https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5965-4082

</title>
         <p>
Alejandra C. Scannapieco 

K

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4228-2996
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bates D.
, 
Mächler M.
, 
Bolker B.M.
, 
Walker S.C.
2015
. 
Fitting Linear Mixed-Effects Models Using lme4
. 
J Stat Softw
67
: 
1-48
. 
https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v067.i01
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Beetsma J.
, 
Zonneveld K.
1992
. 

Observations on the initiation and stimulation of oviposition of the 
Varroa
mite

. 
Exp Appl Acarol
16
: 
303-312
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01218572
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bruce W.A.
, 
Chiesa F.
, 
Marchetti S.
, 
Griffiths D.A.
1988
. 

Laboratory feeding of 
Varroa jacobsoni
Oudemans on natural and artificial diets (Acari: Varroidae)

. 
Apidologie
19
: 
209-218
https://doi.org/10. 1051/apido:19880209
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chiesa F.M.
, Milani Ν., 
D’Agaro M.
1989
. 

Observations on the reproductive behaviour of 
Varroa Jacobsoni
Oud. Techniques and preliminary results

. In: 
Cavalloro R
(ed) 
Proceedings of a meeting of the ECExperts’ Group, Udine, Italy, 28-30 November 1988. Commission Of The European Communities, Brussels, Luxembourg
, pp 
213-222
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dietemann V.
, 
Nazzi F.
, 
Martin S.J.
, 
Anderson D.L.
, 
Locke B.
, 
Delaplane K.S.
, 
Wauquiez Q.
, 
Tannahill C.
, 
Frey E.
, 
Ziegelmann B.
, 
Rosenkranz P.
, 
Ellis J.D.
2013
. 

Standard methods for 
Varroa research

. 
J Apic Res
52
: 
1-54
. 
https://doi.org/10.3896/IBRA.1.52.1.09
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dietemann V.
, 
Pflugfelder J.
, 
Anderson D.
, 
Charriere J.D.
, 
Chejanovsky N.
, 
Dainat B.
, 
Neumann P.
2012
. 

Varroa destructor
: research avenues towards sustainable control

. 
J Apic Res
51
: 
125-132
. 
https://doi.org/10.3896/IBRA.1.51.1.15
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Donze G.
, 
Guerin P.M.
1994
. 

Behavioral-attributes and parental care of 
Varroa
mites parasitizing honey bee brood

. 
Behav Ecol Sociobiol
34
: 
305-319
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00197001
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Donzé G.
, 
Guerin P.M.
1997
. 

Time-activity budgets and space structuring by the different life stages of 
Varroa jacobsoni
in capped brood of the honey bee, 
Apis mellifera

. 
J Insect Behav
10
: 
371-393
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02765605
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Egekwu N.I.
, 
Posada F.
, 
Sonenshine D.E.
, 
Cook S.C.
2018
. 

Using an in vitro system for maintaining 
Varroa destructor
mites on 
Apis mellifera
pupae as hosts; studies of mite longevity and feeding behavior

. 
Exp Appl Acarol
74
: 
301-315
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10493-018-0236-0
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frey E.
, 
Odemer R.
, 
Blum T.
, 
Rosenkranz P.
2013
. 

Activation and interruption of the reproduction of 
Varroa destructor
is triggered by host signals (
Apis mellifera
)

. 
J Invertebr Pathol
113
: 
56-62
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jip.2013.01.007
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fries I.
, 
Lindström A.
, 
Rosenkranz P.
, 
Frey E.
, 
Odemer R.
, 
Schroeder A.
, 
de Miranda J.R.
, 
Yanez O.
, 
Paxton R.J.
2011
. 
The principal parasites and pathogenes of honeybees
. 
Bees in Europe and Sustainable Honey Production, ISBN: 978
-1- 
61209-336
-9
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Garrido C.
, 
Rosenkranz P.
, 
Paxton R.J.
, 
Gonçalves L.S.
2003
. 

Temporal changes in 
Varroa destructor
fertility and haplotype in Brazil

. 
Apidologie
34
: 
535-541
. 
https://doi.org/10.1051/apido:2003041
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harbo J.R.
, 
Harris J.W.
2009
. 

Responses to 
Varroa
by honey bees with different levels of Varroa Sensitive Hygiene

. 
J Apic Res
48
: 
156-161
. 
https://doi.org/10.3896/IBRA.1.48.3.02
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Häussermann C.K.
, 
Giacobino A.
, 
Munz R.
, 
Ziegelmann B.
, 
Palacio M.A.
, 
Rosenkranz P.
2020
. 

Reproductive parameters of female 
Varroa destructor
and the impact of mating in worker brood of 
Apis mellifera

. 
Apidologie
51
: 
342-355
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s13592-019-00713-9
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Häussermann C.K.
, 
Ziegelmann B.
, 
Rosenkranz P.
2016
. 

Spermatozoa capacitation in female 
Varroa destructor
and its influence on the timing and success of female reproduction

. 
Exp Appl Acarol
69
: 
371-387
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10493-016-0051-4 https://doi.org/10.1007/s10493-016-0051-4
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jack C.J.
, 
Dai P.L.
, 
van Santen E.
, 
Ellis J.D.
2020
. 

Comparing four methods of rearing 
Varroa destructor
in vitro

. 
Exp Appl Acarol
80
: 
463-476
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10493-020-00488-0
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kirrane M.J.
, 
De Guzman L.I.
, 
Rinderer T.E.
, 
Frake A.M.
, 
Wagnitz J.
, 
Whelan P.M.
2011
. 

Asynchronous development of honey bee host and 
Varroa destructor
(Mesostigmata: Varroidae) influences reproductive potential of mites

. 
J Econ Entomol
104
: 
1146-1152
. 
https://doi.org/10.1603/EC11035
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lourenço S.
, 
Palmeirim J.M.
2008
. 
Which factors regulate the reproduction of ectoparasites of temperatezone cave-dwelling bats?
Parasitol Res
104
: 
127-134
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00436-008-1170-6
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Martin S.
, 
Holland K.
, 
Murray M.
1997
. 

Non-reproduction in the honeybee mite 
Varroa jacobsoni

. 
Exp Appl Acarol
21
: 
539-549
. 
https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1018492231639
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nazzi F.
, 
Milani N.
1994
. 

A technique for reproduction of 
Varroa jacobsoni
Oud under laboratory conditions

. 
Apidologie
25
: 
579-584
. 
https://doi.org/10.1051/apido:19940608
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Piou V.
, 
Vétillard A.
2020
. 

Varroa destructor
rearing in laboratory conditions: importance of foundress survival in doubly infested cells and reproduction of laboratory-born females

. 
Apidologie
51
: 
968-983
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s13592-020-00775-0
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rosenkranz P.
, 
Aumeier P.
, 
Ziegelmann B.
2010
. 

Biology and control of 
Varroa destructor

. 
J Invertebr Pathol
103
:S96-S 
119
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jip.2009.07.016
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Traynor K.S.
, 
Mondet F.
, 
de Miranda J.R.
, 
Techer M.
, 
Kowallik V.
, 
Oddie M.A.
, 
Chantawannakul P.
, 
McAfee A.
2020
. 
Varroa destructor: A complex parasite, crippling honey bees worldwide
. 
Trends Parasitol.
36
(
7
): 
592-606
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pt.2020.04.004
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vilarem C.
, 
Piou V.
, 
Vogelweith F.
, 
Vétillard A.
2021
. 

Varroa destructor
from the laboratory to the field: Control, biocontrol and ipm perspectives-A review

. 
Insects
12
: 
800
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ insects12090800
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
