<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Acarologia</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24349/utkq-zek0</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Acaricide resistance in ticks from livestock farms in Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>17</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>

Hyalomma
spp

.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Theileria
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rickettsia
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hyalomma dromedarii</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. dromedarii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>anatolicum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hyalomma</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhipicephalus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
microplus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. microplus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. microplus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. dromedarii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma dromedarii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ixodidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>microplus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
microplus
(Can.)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Acaricide resistance in ticks from livestock farms in 
Abu Dhabi
, 
United Arab Emirates
</p>
         <p>

Shameem Habeeba 
K
a

, 

Oum K. Bensalah 
K
b

, 

Ayman Ibrahim 
K
c

, 
Salama Al Muhairi
a

, 

Zulaikha Al Hammadi 
K
a

, 

Abraham Commey 
K
a

, 

Ebrahim Osman 
K
b

, 
Meera Saeed
b

, 

Asma Shah 
K
a
</p>
         <p>
a

Veterinary Laboratories Division, Animal Wealth Sector, 
Abu Dhabi
Agriculture and Food Safety Authority (ADAFSA), 
Abu Dhabi
, 
UAE
.

</p>
         <p>
b

Animal Health Division, 
Abu Dhabi
Agriculture and Food Safety Authority (ADAFSA), 
Abu Dhabi
, 
UAE
.

</p>
         <p>
c

Policy and Regulatory Division, 
Abu Dhabi
Agriculture and Food Safety Authority (ADAFSA), 
Abu Dhabi
, 
UAE
.

</p>
         <p>
Original research
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
</title>
         <p>
The resistance status in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma
</tp:taxon-name>
ticks collected from animal farms in three different regions of the Emirate of 
Abu Dhabi
(
UAE
) was estimated using adult immersion tests with various concentrations of cypermethrin (50ppm, 100 ppm, 200 ppm, 400ppm and 800 ppm). Regression graphs of tick mortality plotted against cypermethrin concentrations were utilized to determine lethal concentrations (LC 
50
and LC 
90
). The data generated on different life history variables (mortality, egg mass weight, reproductive index, and percent inhibition of oviposition) were used to assess the resistance status. Results revealed level
</p>
         <p>
III cypermethrin resistance in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
of the Al Hamam region (Al Ain) and level II resistance in the Malaqet region (Al Ain), whereas level I resistance was observed
</p>
         <p>
in the other studied locations, except Sweihan (Al Ain) where the tick population was fully susceptible. The LC 
90
value of susceptible (Sweihan) 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
was 244.87ppm and
</p>
         <p>the discriminating dose (DC) was calculated to be 489.74ppm. The present study is the</p>
         <p>
first report of cypermethrin resistance in ticks of the 
United Arab Emirates
and highlights the need to further monitor resistance evolution during the implementation of tick control programs.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Keywords
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma
spp

.
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
ticks
; 
resistance
; 
cypermethrin
; 
in vitro bioassay
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Ticks constitute a major threat to the livestock industry of the 
MENA
(Middle East and North
</p>
         <p>
Africa) affecting the production of milk, meat, wool and hides (

). Productivity
</p>
         <p>losses due to the voracious blood-feeding habit of ticks, injection of toxins, and transmission of</p>
         <p>
pathogens such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Theileria
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rickettsia
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(

) have led to
</p>
         <p>
annual economic losses estimated at 
US
18.7 billion (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>These losses can be minimized by treating infected animals with acaricides. However, if poorly</p>
         <p>
supervised, the application of acaricides can result in the emergence of resistance in ticks (

</p>
         <p>
2004; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>Limited studies have been performed on the ticks and their associated host-parasite inter-</p>
         <p>actions in the Middle East region. Commonly available acaricides, like synthetic pyrethroids</p>
         <p>(cypermethrin and deltamethrin) and formamidines, are used indiscriminately for the control</p>
         <p>
of ticks by livestock owners (

). In the Al Ain region (
UAE
), high
</p>
         <p>
tick loads by 

<tp:taxon-name>Hyalomma dromedarii</tp:taxon-name>
,

the most prevalent tick species in the region, have been reported on camels (

), with up to 102 ticks/animal. To reduce infestations on camels, cypermethrin is the most commonly used acaricide (46.9% of camel owners), followed by diazinon (15.6%), α-cyper¬methrin (15.6%), fenvalerate (14.1%), and amitraz (

</p>
         <p>
and Muzaffar 2020). 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. dromedarii
</tp:taxon-name>
ticks were reported to be found on camels in a private
</p>
         <p>
farm in Al Ain over the entire year, despite monthly applications of an acaricide (

</p>
         <p>
al.
2020), suggesting either the inadequate use of the acaricide or the development of acaricide resistance.
</p>
         <p>
Diagnosing resistance to acaricides is performed primarily through bioassays, the most common being the adult immersion test (AIT) (

), the larval packet test (LPT) (

) and the larval immersion test (LIT) (

; 

</p>
         <p>
et al.
2022). The current study was undertaken to test for the development of resistance against cypermethrin in 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
in the Al Ain region using 
in vitro
AIT bioassays and ticks collected from farms in the three regions of the Emirate of 
Abu Dhabi
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Material and Methods
</title>
         <p>
Study Area
</p>
         <p>
by colored illustrations and the associated information on the farm is presented in 
Table 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Abu Dhabi
is located in the west and southwest part of the 
United Arab Emirates
(
UAE
)
</p>
         <p>
along the southern coast of the Persian Gulf (
Figure 1
). The Emirate’s high summer (June to
</p>
         <p>August) temperatures are associated with high relative humidity and winters are relatively mild</p>
         <p>favouring tick survival. In 2020, a questionnaire was designed to collect data from 15 farm</p>
         <p>
owners in three regions of 
Abu Dhabi
related to the frequency, 
type
, and mode of acaricide
</p>
         <p>treatment adopted and their experiences on the efficacy of commonly used molecules (see</p>
         <p>supplementary materials). Ticks were then collected from seven of these farms based on</p>
         <p>
questionnaire results (
Table 1
); we selected farms with mixed farming practices that had tick
</p>
         <p>
infestation problems and observed tick treatment failures. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
was the most
</p>
         <p>
common tick collected from these farms based on morphology (

) and was used for
</p>
         <p>resistance studies. Live engorged female ticks were collected from naturally infested livestock</p>
         <p>in vials, closed with muslin cloth to allow air and moisture exchange, and were brought to the</p>
         <p>laboratory for experimental assays.</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
*Animals housed indoor in stalls
</p>
         <p>
Adult Immersion Test (AIT)
</p>
         <p>
Adult immersion tests were performed as per the method of 

and
</p>
         <p>

. The AIT uses engorged females that are immersed in solutions made
</p>
         <p>with technical or commercial acaricides and compares oviposition rates between treated</p>
         <p>
and untreated groups. The eggs can likewise be analysed by weight and viability. Female mortality rate can also be evaluated, which reduces the time necessary to obtain results (1–2 weeks) compared to the time required to determine hatchability (5–6 weeks). In our study, a total of 560 engorged adult female ticks of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
were used and each drug concentration was replicated thrice using 
five adults
each time along with a control group. Ticks weighing less than 
150mg
or that were not fully engorged were discarded. Selected fully engorged female ticks were immersed in different concentrations of cypermethrin (50 ppm,
</p>
         <p>100 ppm, 200 ppm, 400 ppm, 800 ppm) prepared from an aqueous dilution of a commercial preparation of cypermethrin (10.25% EC) for two minutes and then were dried on filter paper before transferring them into individually labelled plastic tubes. Ticks were placed in a constant climate chamber (Memmert HPP) at 28 ± 2 °C and 85 ± 5% relative humidity for a period of</p>
         <p>
14 days. Tick mortality was recorded on the 14 
th
day post-treatment by observing the loss of mobility and pedal reflex after exposure to light. In this study, ticks which did not oviposit after 14 days were considered as dead as under optimal rearing conditions, the period of oviposition of engorged female ticks of 

H. a. 
<tp:taxon-name>anatolicum</tp:taxon-name>

was recorded as a range of 7-12days (

</p>
         <p>
2014; Akil, M. 
et al.
, 2019).
</p>
         <p>
Ticks collected from the same farm were treated on the same day with different drug concentrations along with a control (in distilled water) and data were recorded per farm. Observations on egg laying was performed 7-10 days post-treatment and egg mass was recorded on day 14. The reproductive index (RI) and the percent inhibition of oviposition for each acaricide concentration was calculated using the following formulae (

).
</p>
         <p>ԔԖԖ ԜԐԢԢ ԦԔ𝑖Ԗℎԣ 𝑅ԔԟԡԞԓԤԒԣ𝑖ԥԔ 𝑖ԝԓԔԧ (𝑅𝐼) = ԔԝԖԞԡԖԔԓ ԕԔԜԐԛԔ ԦԔ𝑖Ԗℎԣ</p>
         <p>𝑅𝐼 ԒԞԝԣԡԞԛ − 𝑅𝐼 ԣԡԔԐԣԔԓ 𝑃 ԔԡԒԔԝԣ 𝑖ԝℎ𝑖ԑ𝑖ԣ𝑖Ԟԝ Ԟԕ Ԟԥ𝑖ԟԞԢ𝑖ԣ𝑖Ԟԝ (𝐼𝑂%) = × 100 𝑅𝐼 ԒԞԝԣԡԞԛ</p>
         <p>
Statistical Analysis
</p>
         <p>
Dose response data were analyzed by the probit method (

) using IBM SPSS Version 28.0.0.0. A Chi-square test was used to compare the observed mortality for each dose with the frequency predicted by the probit function. The LC 
50
and LC 
90
values for cypermethrin were determined by applying regression equations to the probit transformed mortality data.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results and Discussion
</title>
         <p>(n=2 farms), and Al Ain (n=3 farms). The control group showed no mortality.</p>
         <p>As outlined above, mixed farms with heavy tick infestations and those for which pyrethroid</p>
         <p>acaricide treatment failure seemed to regularly occur were selected for the study based on</p>
         <p>
results of the questionnaire (n=7 farms, 
Table 1
). Tick infestations on these farms was observed
</p>
         <p>throughout the year and tick-borne diseases were previously diagnosed, particularly in sheep</p>
         <p>and cattle. Camels were reared in the same area with sheep and goats, separated only by a small</p>
         <p>net fence. Keeping animals together in herds and on sandy floors were considered as potential</p>
         <p>risk factors for the presence of ticks. Indeed, local farms can provide a suitable refuge for ticks</p>
         <p>because they provide a habitat with relatively high moisture sheltered from the harsh desert</p>
         <p>
environment (

).
</p>
         <p>
of cypermethrin based on three replicate treatments per concentration per farm in 
Abu Dhabi
(n=2 farms), Al Dhafra (n=2 farms), and Al Ain (n=3 farms).
</p>
         <p>Tick populations have an immense potential for rapidly developing resistance due to their</p>
         <p>biological and behavioral characteristics, and resistance to different active ingredients has</p>
         <p>
been reported in almost all countries where ticks occur (

). Synthetic pyrethroids are the most widely and frequently used acaricides to control tick populations. The present study aimed to detect acaricide resistance to the commonly used pyrethroid acaricide cypermethrin in field-collected 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
ticks from selected farms of the Emirate
</p>
         <p>
of 
Abu Dhabi
. A concentration dependent increase in adult tick mortality was observed for cypermethrin in 
Abu Dhabi
and Al Dhafra farms,whereas this relationship was weaker in Al Ain farms (
Figure 2
). The reproductive index (RI) declined as drug concentration increased (
Figure 3
), with the strongest decline for ticks from 
Abu Dhabi
farms. In contrast, the inhibition of oviposition increased with the cypermethrin dose (
Figure 4
) in all farms.
</p>
         <p>
tolicum
against different concentrations of cypermethrin.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>*Slope of mortality calculated from mean mortality of ticks to various concentrations of drug</p>
         <p>
Chisquare value χ 
2
</p>
         <p>
R 
2
goodness of fit, LC and LC calculated from the regression equation
</p>
         <p>
50 90
RF resistance factor
</p>
         <p>Among the three farms in Al Ain region, two farms namely Al Hamam (Farm2) and Malaqet</p>
         <p>(Farm3), showed low tick mortality at the tested doses and could not produce 100% mortality</p>
         <p>
even at the highest concentration. (
Figure 5
). The reproductive indices were not affected and
</p>
         <p>
the percent inhibition of oviposition was less than 45% (
Figures S1
and S 

2
in

Supplementary
</p>
         <p>Materials). These results indicate the acaricide resistance status of the ticks in these farms, with</p>
         <p>fully susceptible ticks present on farm 1 and very resistant ticks on farms 2 and 3.</p>
         <p>
The present study is the first of its kind in this region and throws some light on the resistance status of ticks against a frequently used acaricide. 
Abu Dhabi
and Al Dhafra regions harbour tick populations that are heterogenous in terms of resistance, with LC 
90
values falling within
</p>
         <p>
the discriminating dose reported by earlier studies (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma
</tp:taxon-name>
ticks from Sweihan (Farm 
1 in
Al Ain) were found to be susceptible to cypermethrin and the discriminating dose (2xLC90) was calculated as 489.74ppm in the present study.
</p>
         <p>

classified resistance in ticks based on the calculated resistance factor
</p>
         <p>
(
RF
): susceptible (
RF
≤1.4), level I resistant (
RF
= 1.5–5.0), level II resistant (
RF
= 5.1–25.0),
</p>
         <p>
level III resistant (
RF
= 25.1–40) and level IV resistance (
RF
&gt;40.1) in reference to a susceptible
</p>
         <p>
tick reference strain. Resistance factors (
RF
) for field tick samples were worked out by the
</p>
         <p>
quotient between LC 
50
of field ticks and LC 
50
of susceptible Sweihan 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
(Castro-
</p>
         <p>
Janer 
et al.
, 2009). Based on the regression analyses of the obtained data with the Sweihan
</p>
         <p>
isolate as the susceptible strain (

; 

; 

;
</p>
         <p>

), the resistance factor (
RF
) was calculated to ascertain the susceptibility and
</p>
         <p>resistant status of the other studied population. The Al Hamam isolates had Level III resistance,</p>
         <p>
Al Malaqet isolates had Level II and the four farms in the 
Abu Dhabi
and Dhafra regions
</p>
         <p>
showed Level I resistance (
Table 2
).
</p>
         <p>
In the current study, the LC 
90
value of susceptible ticks (Sweihan population) by AIT
</p>
         <p>bioassay was 244.87ppm, while it was over 5000ppm in the AlHamam farm of the same</p>
         <p>
region. Much reported work on cypermethrin resistance has been conducted 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhipicephalus
</tp:taxon-name>
on
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
microplus
</tp:taxon-name>
and a wide variation in LC 
90
values has been found. 

found
</p>
         <p>
an LC 
90
value of 183.07 ppm for 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. microplus
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Jalandhar district of 
Punjab
, 
India
.
</p>
         <p>
Singh 
et al.
(2015) reported level I resistance to cypermethrin in 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
collected from
</p>
         <p>
the 
Gujarat state
, 
India
using larval packet test. 

found a LC 
50
value of
</p>
         <p>
cypermethrin of 138.5 ppm with a 95% confidence interval of 134.5–142.6, while the LC 
95
</p>
         <p>value was 349.1 ppm with a 95% confidence interval of 323.2–377.0 using a laboratory reared</p>
         <p>
susceptible line of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. microplus
</tp:taxon-name>
in Izatnagar, 
India
. This variance among studies has been
</p>
         <p>
attributed to differences in the reference tick lines used and in the 
type
of bioassay adopted
</p>
         <p>
(AIT or LPT) (

; 

; 

; 

;
</p>
         <p>

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
This study forms the first report on acaricide resistance in ticks of the 
UAE
. A country
</p>
         <p>specific discriminating concentration (DC = two times the concentration that would kill 99%</p>
         <p>of ticks susceptible to the molecule) was not previously available for any tick species, hence</p>
         <p>the generation of baseline data for an abundant tick species is useful for monitoring changes</p>
         <p>in the resistance status of ticks in this Emirate. Here, we calculated the DC for commercially</p>
         <p>
available cypermethrin as 489.74 ppm for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
. This DC can now be used
</p>
         <p>as a screening mechanism because one can test for resistance in small samples from diverse</p>
         <p>
locations (

).
</p>
         <p>The development of resistance in a tick population can depend on factors related to acaricide</p>
         <p>
use, ecological niches and the genus of ticks involved (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>A limitation in the present study was the difficulty in obtaining adequate numbers of engorged</p>
         <p>
females for testing, which may affect the reproducibility of AIT values (

).
</p>
         <p>Further studies with higher sample sizes are recommended to obtain more predictive values of</p>
         <p>
AIT. Similarly, a commercial formulation of cypermethrin was used in the present study as the pure technical grade was unavailable. The presence of proprietary ingredients in commercial formulations can hinder the responses to active ingredients (

) which could alter the results and might be one of the reason for the relatively high 
90
LCvalue that we found. Tests based on technical grade cypermethrin would therefore be useful to validate our results. The frequent use of acaricides leading to the emergence of resistant population, as observed in our results, likely explains the presence of ticks on treated animals as reported by 

</p>
         <p>
2020. The present study reported only 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
ticks in the farms in the region. Based
</p>
         <p>
on morphological characteristics,only 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyalomma anatolicum
</tp:taxon-name>
(90%) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. dromedarii
</tp:taxon-name>
(10%)
</p>
         <p>
were identified (

). The practice of rearing camels with sheep and goats and mixing them on common grazing habitats likely increases the risk of ticks shifting among alternative hosts. Moreover, local farms provide suitable environments for ticks, with sand beds in which ticks can burrow a few centimeters below ground and find both favorable microhabitats for egg deposition and refuge from the chemical spraying. Improper use of acaricides in terms of dose, frequency and method of application can thus result in acaricide failure. Based on the data obtained on the emerging problem of tick resistance to chemical acaricides, an alert on good practices for tick control to improve the drug efficacy is recommended, along with the implementation of a program to monitor the evolution of acaricide resistance.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>The project investigators thank the veterinary officers Ashry Mohammed Ahmed, Raid Mohammed, Francis Falcon Joven, Atef Darwish, Ibraheem Ghazi, Mohamed Ibrahim Hassanein, Mahmud Hamed Abd Elaal, Manoj Shrawan Pradhan, the livestock and animal health assistants, the herders from the study areas and, the laboratory personnel for their support in the execution of the presented research.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ORCID
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Shameem Habeeba 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7311-4445

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Oum K. Bensalah 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8396-6358

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Ayman Ibrahim 
K
https://orcid.org/0009-0001-0251-5791

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Zulaikha Al Hammadi 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9090-6292

</title>
         <p>
Abraham Commey 
K
https://orcid.org/0009-0007-4694-5615
</p>
         <p>
Ebrahim Osman 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7445-3411
</p>
         <p>
Asma Shah 
K
https://orcid.org/0009-0000-1161-9018
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aguirre D.H.
, 
Vinabal A.E.
, 
Salatin A.O.
, 
Cafrune M.M.
, 
Volpogni M.M.
, 
Mangold A.J.
, 
Guglielmone A.A.
2000
. 

Susceptibility to two pyrethroids in 
Boophilus microplus
(Acari: Ixodidae) populations of north-west Argentina. Preliminary results. Vet

. 
Parasitol.
, 
88
: 
329-334
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alonso-Diaz M.A.
, 
Rodriguez-Vivas R.I.
, 
Fragoso-Sanchez H.
, 
Rosario-Cruz R.
2006
. 

Resistance of the 
Boophilus microplus
tick to ixodicides

. 
Arch. Med. Vet.
, 
38
: 
105-114
. 
https://doi.org/10.4067/ S0301-732X2006000200003
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Al-Deeb M.A.
, 
Muzaffar S.B.
, 
Abu Zeid Y.
, 
Enan M.R.
and 
Karim S.
2015
. 

First record and prevalence of 
Rickettsia
sp. and 
Theileria annulata
in 
Hyalomma drom¬edarii
(
Acari
: 
Ixodidae
) ticks in the UAE

. 
Fla. Entomol.
, 
98
: 
135-139
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Al-Deeb M.A.
, 
Muzaffar S.B.
2020
. 
Prevalence
, 
distribution on host’s body, and chemical control
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Akil M.
, 
Bagherwal R.K.
, 
Jayraw A.K.
, 
Rajput N.
and 
Singh R.
2019
. In 

vitro Assessment of Period of Oviposition and Hatching in 
Hyalomma anatolicum anatolicum

. 
Ind J Vet Sci and Biotech.
, 
15
: 
72-73
. 
https://doi.org/10.21887/ijvsbt.15.2.19
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Anusha M.
2014
. 

PCR evaluation for detection of 
Theileria annulata
and 
Hyalomma anatolicum anatolicum
ticks in Rayalaseema region of Andhra Pradesh. M.V.Sc. And A.H thesis

. 
Shree Venkateshwara Veterinary University, Tirupati, India
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Castro-Janer E.
, 
Rifran L.
, 
Piaggio J.
, 
Gil A.
, 
Miller R.J.
, 
Schumaker T.T.S.
2009
. In 

vitro tests to establish LC 
50
and discriminating concentrations for fipronil against 
Rhipicephalus (Boophilus) microplus

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dzemo W D.
, 
Thekisoe O.
, 
Vudriko P.
2022
. 
Development of acaricide resistance in tick populations of cattle: A systematic review and meta-analysis
. 
Heliyon
. 8: 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2022.e08718
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Drummond R.O.
, 
Ernst S.E
., 
Trevino J.L.
, 
Gladney W.J.
, 
Graham O.H.
1973
. 

Boophilus annulatus

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
FAO
. 
2004
. 
Resistance Management and Integrated Parasite Control in Ruminants. Guidelines
. 
Animal Production and Health Division. FAO
. p. 25-77.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

FAO

. 
Livestock Systems
. 
2020
. 
Available online
: 
http://www.fao.org/livestock-systems/en/
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Finney D.J.
1962
. 
Probit Analysis
- 
A Statistical Treatment of the Response Curve
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jonsson N.N.
, 
Miller R.J.
, 
Robertson J.L.
2007
. 

Critical evaluation of the modified-adult immersion test with discriminating dose bioassay for 
Boophilus microplus
using American and Australian isolates

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Klafke G.
, 
Webster A.
, 
Agnol B.D.
, 
Pradel E.
, 
Silv J.
, 
Henrique de La Canal L.
, 
Becker M.
, Os_orio M.F

., 
Mansson M.
, 
Barreto R.
, 
Scheffer R.
, 
Souza U.A.
, 
Corassini V.B.
, 
dos Santos J.
, 
Reck J.
, 
Martins J.R.
2017
. 

Multiple resistance to acaricides in populations of 
Rhipicephalus microplus
from 

Rio Grande 

do Sul state, Southern 
Brazil
. Ticks Tick Borne Dis., 8: 73-80. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ttbdis.2016.09.019



</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kunz S.E.
, 
Kemp D.H.
1994
. 
Insecticides and acaricides: resistance and environmental impact
. 
Rev. Sci. Tech. OIE.
13
: 
1249-1286
. 
https://doi.org/10.20506/rst.13.4.816
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Perveen N.
, 
Bin Muzaffar S.
, 
Al-Deeb M.A.
2020
. 

Population dynamics of 
Hyalomma dromedarii
on camels in the United Arab Emirates

. 
Insects.
11
: 
320
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/insects11050320
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Robertson J.L.
, 
Russell R.M.
, 
Preisler H.K.
, 
Savin N.E.
2006
. 
Pesticide Bioassays with Arthropods, 2nd ed
. 
CRC Press, Boca Raton, FL, USA
. pp.224. 
https://doi.org/10.1201/9781420004045
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodriguez Vivas R.I.
, 
Rivas A.L.
, 
Chowell G.
, 
Fragoso S.H.
, 
Rosario C.R.
, Garcııˇa V.Z., 
Smith S.D.
, 
Williams J.J.
, 
Schwager S.J.
2007
. 

Spatial distribution of acaricide profiles 
Boophilus

(

microplus

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sharma A.K.
, 
Rinesh Kumar, Sachin Kumar
, 
Gaurav Nagar
, 
Nirbhay K.S.
, 
Sumer S.R.
, 
Dhakad M.L.
, 
Rawat A.K.S.
, 
Ray D.D.
, 
Srikant G.
2012
. 

Deltamethrin and cypermethrin resistance status of 
Rhipicephalus (Boophilus) microplus
collected from six agro-climatic regions of India. Vet

. 
Parasitol.
, 
188
: 
337- 345
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vetpar.2012.03.050
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shaw R.D.
1966
. 

Culture of an organophosphorus resistant strain of 
Boophilus microplus
(Canestrini)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shyma K.P.
, 
Kumar S.
, 
Sharma A.K.
, 
Ray D.D.
, 
Ghosh S.
2012
. 
Acaricide resistance status in
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shyma K.P.
, 
Kumar S.A.
, 
Sangwan A.K.
, 
Sharma A.K.
, 
Nagar G.
, 
Ray D.D.
2013
. 

Acaricide resistance status of 
Rhipicephalus
(
Boophilus
) 
micro plus
and 
Hyalomma anatolicum
collected from Haryana

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singh N.K.
, 
Rath S.S.
2014
. 

Esterase mediated resistance against synthetic pyrethroids in field populations of 
Rhipicephalus
(
Boophilus
) 
microplus
(Acari: Ixodidae) in Punjab districts of India. Vet

. 
Parasitol.
, 
204
: 
330-338
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vetpar.2014.05.035
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singh N.K.
, 
Jyoti
., 
Nandi, A.
, 
Singh H.
2019
. 

Detection of Multi-Acaricide Resistance in 
Rhipicephalus
(
Boophilus
) 
Microplus
(Acari: Ixodidae)

. 
Explor. Anim. Med. Res.
, 
9
: 
24-28
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stone B.F.
, 
Haydock P.
, 
1962
. 
A method for measuring the acaricide susceptibility of the cat-
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sudha R.R.
, 
Placid ED’Souza
., 
Byregowda S.M.
, 
Veeregowda B. M.
, 
Sengupta P.P.
, 
Chandranaik B.M.
, 
Thimmareddy P.M.
2018
. 

In 
vitro

acaricidal efficacy of deltamethrin, cypermethrin and amitraz against sheep ticks in Karnataka. 
J. Entomol. and Zoology Studies.
6
: 
758-762
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sungirai M.
, 
Baron S.
, 
Moyo D.Z.
, 
De Clercqe P.
, 
Maritz-Olivier C.
, 
Madder M.
2018
. 

Genotyping acaricide resistance profiles of 
Rhipicephalus microplus
tick populations from communal land areas

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Surbhi
., 
Snehil G.
, 
Arun K.S.
, 
Nirmal S.
2018
. 

Synthetic pyrethroids and Amitraz resistance 
Hyalomma
in 
anatolicum
ticks of Sirsa district, Haryana

. 
The Pharma Innovation Journal.
7
: 
576-578
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Walker A.R.
2003
. 
Ticks of Domestic Animals in Africa: A Guide to Identification of Species
. 
Bioscience Reports, Edinburgh
. pp. 227.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Whitnall A.B.
, 
Bradford B.
1947
. 
An arsenic resistant tick and its control with gammexane dips
. 
Bull. Entomol. Res.
, 
38
: 
353-372
. 
https://doi.org/10.1017/S000748530002424X
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
