<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Acarologia</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24349/fgml-gv5c</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Is Eriophyes mali Nalepa present in Italy?</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>06</day>
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes mali
Nalepa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eriophyidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Malus domestica
Borkh.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aculus schlechtendali
(
Nalepa, 1890
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes pyri
(
Pagenstecher, 1857
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes mali
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes pyri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
var. 
mali
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
pyri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. mali
(Nal.) Liro
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. mali
Burts, 1970
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. mali
Nal.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. mali
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. pyri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eriophyidae COX</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eriophyidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. schlechtendali
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. schlechtendali
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes calycobius
(
Nalepa 1891
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Crataegus monogyna
Jacq.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. pyri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eriophyidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. schlechtendali
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. mali
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. mali</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aculus schlechtendali
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Calepitrimerus vitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aculops lycopersici
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Valeria Malagnini 
K
a

, 

Mario Baldessari 
K
a

, 

Federico Pedrazzoli 
K
a

, 

Alessia Tatti 
K
b
, 
c

, 

Carlo Duso 
K
d

, 

Enrico de Lillo 
K
e

, 

Gino Angeli 
K
a

, 

Mariusz Lewandowski 
K
f
</p>
         <p>
a

Fondazione Edmund Mach – Centro Trasferimento Tecnologico via E. Mach, 1 - 38010 San Michele all’Adige (TN) 
Italy
.

</p>
         <p>
b

Scuola Universitaria Superiore IUSS Pavia, Palazzo del Broletto, Piazza Vittoria 15, 27100 Pavia, 
Italy
.

</p>
         <p>
c

Center Agriculture Food Environment C3A, University of Trento and Fondazione Edmund Mach, Trento, 
Italy
.

</p>
         <p>
d

Department of Agronomy, Food, Natural resources, Animals and Environment, University of Padova Via dell’Università 16 - 35020 Legnaro (PD), 
Italy
.

</p>
         <p>
e

Dipartimento di Scienze del Suolo, della Pianta e degli Alimenti, University of Bari Aldo Moro, via Amendola, 165/a - 70126 Bari, 
Italy
.

</p>
         <p>
f
Department of Plant Protection, Institute of Horticultural Sciences, Warsaw University of Life Sciences,
</p>
         <p>
ul. Nowoursynowska 159 - 02776 Warsaw, 
Poland
.
</p>
         <p>

Proceedings of the 9 
th
Symposium of the EurAAc, Bari, July, 12 
th
–15 
th
2022

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
</title>
         <p>
In the last few years, blistering symptoms were observed on apple plants in commercial orchards. Blisters are commonly found on apple leaves as well as on small fruits. This symptom is compatible with that described for apple blister mites belonging to the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Eriophyidae</tp:taxon-name>
). To assess the identity of the etiological agent, leaf blisters
</p>
         <p>and buds of symptomatic apple and, as a control, pear plants were examined under the dissection microscope and eriophyoid mites were collected. Specimens were examined using both molecular and morphological approaches. The analysis of sequences confirmed</p>
         <p>
that eriophyoid mites collected from symptomatic apple and pear plants are genetically different. Our analyses highlight a complex scenario inside the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
</tp:taxon-name>
that is
</p>
         <p>worth to be studied in more detail.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Keywords
Eriophyoidea
; 
apple
; 
pear
; 
DNA barcoding
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Eriophyoid mites (Acari: Prostigmata: Eriophyoidea) are obligate plant feeders, and most of them exhibit high levels of host specificity and adaptability (

; 

; 

). They inhabit all plant parts except roots and can cause economically important damage to their hosts (

; 

). More than a dozen of eriophyoid species have been reported on apple plants (
<tp:taxon-name>
Malus domestica
Borkh.
</tp:taxon-name>
) all over the world (

; Amrine and de Lillo, unpublished database). Among them, the apple rust mite 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aculus schlechtendali
(
Nalepa, 1890
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, a vagrant mite causing damages with high population densities (

), is the most widespread species in 
Italy
.
</p>
         <p>
In the last few years, leaf blistering was widely observed on apple leaves in commercial orchards of Northern 
Italy
. These symptoms were reported for the first time in 
2017 in
Val
</p>
         <p>
di Non, which is one of the most important apple-growing areas of Northern 
Italy
, and in several orchards in the 
Emilia-Romagna region
. These damages were not compatible with those associated with the apple rust mite but looked like the blister galls described for the pear blister mite 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes pyri
(
Pagenstecher, 1857
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and the apple blister mite 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes mali
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>

.
</p>
         <p>
The apple blister mite was described for the first time by 

as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes pyri
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
var. 
mali
</tp:taxon-name>
and was considered for a long time as a variety 
E
of. 
<tp:taxon-name>
pyri
</tp:taxon-name>
because of the morphological
</p>
         <p>
similarities and the production of identical symptoms on apple leaves (blister galls) (

</p>
         <p>
al.
2014). Later, 

changed the mite’s taxonomic status and raised it
</p>
         <p>
to the rank of species [
<tp:taxon-name>
E. mali
(Nal.) Liro
</tp:taxon-name>
(nov. comb.)]. In the late 50s, 

described
</p>
         <p>
a new eriophyid species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. mali
Burts, 1970
</tp:taxon-name>
, which can be considered as a junior synonym
</p>
         <p>
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. mali
Nal.
</tp:taxon-name>
(

), on apple samples collected in 
Washington
(Pacific
</p>
         <p>
Northwestern 
USA
). So far, 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. mali
</tp:taxon-name>
has not been recorded in 
Italy
, while the presence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. pyri
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
is quite common and well-documented for a long time (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>In the present work, we carried out a molecular analysis to assess the identity of eriophyoid</p>
         <p>
mites causing blisters on apple leaves and recently found in Northern 
Italy
. As diagnostic
</p>
         <p>structures for morphological analysis are not always enough for species discrimination and this</p>
         <p>
often causes the misidentification of species (

), DNA-based approaches are
</p>
         <p>
often adopted to overcome this problem (

), like in the current case of
</p>
         <p>eriophyoid mites collected on apple vs pear plants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Material and methods
</title>
         <p>Eriophyoid mite specimens were collected from leaf blisters and buds of symptomatic apple and</p>
         <p>
pear plants in the 
Trentino-Alto Adige region
. Apple plants in three different orchards located
</p>
         <p>
in Trentino - Val di Non (Rumo, 
46.433975°N
and 
11.028116°E
, and Coredo, 
46.356663°N
</p>
         <p>
and 
11.083217°E
) and Alto Adige (Vadena, 
46.379604°N
and 
11.287893°E
) and some pear
</p>
         <p>
plants in Alto Adige (Salorno, 
46.241207°N
and 
11.205038°E
) were sampled in 2020 and
</p>
         <p>2021. Symptomatic leaves and buds were observed under a dissecting microscope, and single</p>
         <p>individuals were collected using a brush with only one bristle and placed in a 1.5 ml Eppendorf</p>
         <p>tube.</p>
         <p>
The DNA from single individuals was isolated using 5% Chelex® 100 (Bio-Rad) (

</p>
         <p>
et al.
2013). Each sample, after adding 10 µl of a solution of Chelex and proteinase K (95: 5),
</p>
         <p>was incubated at 50 °C for 1h and then at 95 °C for 10 min. Five individuals were analyzed for</p>
         <p>each population.</p>
         <p>The cytochrome oxidase subunit I (COX1) gene was amplified with the primer pair</p>
         <p>
LCO1490 and HCO2198 (

). Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) conditions
</p>
         <p>
were as reported in 

. PCR products, after purification with illustra ExoProStar1-
</p>
         <p>
Step (GE Healthcare, Little Chalfont, 
UK
), were sequenced with the BigDye Terminator v3.1
</p>
         <p>
cycle sequencing kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, 
USA
) on an Applied Biosystems
</p>
         <p>
3130 xl Genetic Analyzer (Carlsbad, CA, 
USA
). Sequences were manually checked, and
</p>
         <p>
BIOEDIT software (

) was used for corrections and alignments. Sequences obtained
</p>
         <p>were deposited in the GenBank (NCBI) (accession numbers from OP593091 to OP593101</p>
         <p>for samples from apple; OP593102 and OP593103 for samples from pear), and a search was</p>
         <p>conducted using BLAST (Basic Local Alignment Search Tool). Then, we first built a dataset</p>
         <p>
with a customed Python script retrieving 2,977 
<tp:taxon-name>Eriophyidae COX</tp:taxon-name>
1 sequences from Genbank.
</p>
         <p>
After aligning the sequences using MAFFT version 7.475 (

) with
</p>
         <p>the “adjust direction accurately” option and cleaning the alignment with a customed Python</p>
         <p>script, an alignment with 662 positions was obtained. We analyzed a Maximum Likelihood</p>
         <p>(ML) exploratory tree with all 2,977 sequences and selected the clade that contained our</p>
         <p>newly sequenced species, removing the sequences that could cause a long branch attraction</p>
         <p>
problem. The reduced dataset for the 
<tp:taxon-name>Eriophyidae</tp:taxon-name>
family contained 304 sequences. We further
</p>
         <p>trimmed the alignment obtaining a new alignment with 657 positions, and built the final ML</p>
         <p>
phylogenetic tree, using IQ-TREE 1.6.12 (

) with the “model selection”
</p>
         <p>
option, 10,000 bootstrap replicates, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. schlechtendali
</tp:taxon-name>
used as outgroup.
</p>
         <p>of the galls.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
Biological observations
</p>
         <p>
Early symptoms of the eriophyid mite presence, not ascribable to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. schlechtendali
</tp:taxon-name>
, were observed at the beginning of the spring. In this period, the upper surface of the leaves shows yellowish spots, while blisters, as well as the entry circular opening, are more visible in the undersurface (
Fig. 1
). Later in the season, blisters become larger and turn brownish, and the large under-epidermic cavities contain eriophyoids at different stages. These symptoms are similar to those described for apple blister mites (

). Galls can also occur on
</p>
         <p>
the superficial layers of small fruits (
Fig. 2
). During the winter, eriophyoid mites can be found under the bud scales (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
Genetic data
</p>
         <p>
The phylogenetic analysis indicates that eriophyoid mites collected from apple plants in different orchards of 
Trentino-Alto Adige
belong to the same species and that mites collected from apple are different from those collected from pear plants. The identity score obtained blasting the COX1 sequences of apple mites against sequences of pear mites suggests even
</p>
         <p>the possible presence of different genera (e.g., the GenBank identity score for OP593091 vs OP593102 is 79.97%).</p>
         <p>
This seems in contradiction with the preliminary morphological analyses (
in verbis
de Lillo)
</p>
         <p>of samples collected from apple and pear plants. In fact, the typical diagnostic characteristics</p>
         <p>
of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
</tp:taxon-name>
were observed in both mites, suggesting that they belong to the same genus.
</p>
         <p>
These contradictory data highlight a very complex scenario inside the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>For this reason, further molecular analyses, involving other molecular markers combined with morphological and ecological observations, are needed to better understand the identity of these samples.</p>
         <p>
The maximum likelihood tree calculated with IQ-TREE is shown in Fig. 4, where clades phylogenetically distant from the sequences of our samples are collapsed. The sequences submitted to GenBank as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
are scattered across the phylogenetic tree and do
</p>
         <p>in the small fruits.</p>
         <p>
not form a monophyletic group. According to this phylogenetic tree, the sister species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E.
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
pyri
from pear, with 100% bootstrap, is 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eriophyes calycobius
(
Nalepa 1891
)
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Crataegus monogyna
Jacq.
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) (the GenBank identity score between OP593102 and MW691980
</p>
         <p>
is 84.02%). Regarding apple eriophyoids, the sister species is 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. pyri
</tp:taxon-name>
(accession number EU254715.1), with 100% bootstrap. This sequence is 444 bp long, and the low GenBank identity score with apple eriophyoids suggests different species (e.g. the identity score between EU254715.1 and OP593091.1 is 84.20%).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Burts E.C.
1970
. 

Biology of blister mites, 
Eriophyes
spp., of pear and apple in the Pacific Northwest

. 
Melanderia
, 
4
: 
42-53
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Canestrini G.
1890
. 
Ricerche intorno ai Fitoptidi
. 
Atti della Soc. Veneto-Trentina di Sci. Nat.
, 
12
(
1
): 
1-26
+ pls. 6-7.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
de Lillo E.
, 
Craemer C.
, 
Amrine J.W.
, 
Nuzzaci G.
2010
. 
Recommended procedures and techniques for morphological studies of Eriophyoidea (Acari: Prostigmata)
. 
Exp. Appl. Acarol.
, 
51
(
1
): 
283-307
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10493-009-9311-x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
de Lillo E.
, 
Pozzebon A.
, 
Valenzano D.
, 
Duso C.
2018
. 
An intimate relationship between eriophyoid mites and their host plants - A review
. 
Front. Plant Sci.
, 
9
: 
1786
. 
https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2018.01786
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Duso C.
, 
Castagnoli M.
, 
Simoni S.
, 
Angeli G.
2010
. 
The impact of eriophyoids on crops: recent issues
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
EPPO
2021
. 
PM 7/129 (2) DNA barcoding as an identification tool for a number of regulated pests
. 
EPPO Bull.
, 
51
(
1
): 
100-143
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/epp.12724
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Folmer O.
, 
Black M.
, 
Hoeh W.
, 
Lutz R.
, 
Vrijenhoek R.
1994
. 
DNA primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit I from diverse metazoan invertebrates
. 
Mol. Mar. Biol. Biotechnol.
, 
3
(
5
): 
294-299
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hall T.A.
1999
. 
BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT
. 
Nucleic Acids Symp. Ser.
, 
41
: 
95-98
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Katoh K.
, 
Standley D.M.
2013
. 
MAFFT Multiple Sequence Alignment Software Version 7: Improvements
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lindquist E.E.
1996
. 
Chapter 1.1 External anatomy and systematics 1.1
.1. 
External anatomy and notation
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
of structures
. 
World Crop Pests
, 
6(Eriophyoid Mites Their Biology, Natural Enemies and Control)
: 
3-31
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S1572-4379(96)80003-0
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liro J.I.
, 
Roivainen H.
1951
. 
Äkämäpunkit Eriophyidae
. 
Suomen Eläimet. Poorvo-Helsinki: Werner Söderström Osakeyhtiö
. pp. 
1-281
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nalepa A.
1890
. 
Zur Systematik der Gallmilben. Sitzungsberichte der Kais. Akad. der Wissenschaften, Math
. 
Wien
, 
99
(
2
): 
40-69
+ 
7 pls.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nalepa A.
1891
. 
Genera und Species der Familie Phytoptida
. 
Denkschriften der Kais. Akad. der Wissenschaften, Math. Wien
, 
58
: 
867-884
+ 
4 pls.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nalepa A.
1926
. 
Zur Kenntnis der auf den einheimischen Pomaceen und Amygdaleen Lebenden Eriophyes-Arten
. 
Marcellia
, 
22
(1- 
6
): 
62-68
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Navajas M.
, 
Navia D.
2010
. 
DNA-based methods for eriophyoid mite studies: review, critical aspects, prospects and challenges
. 
Exp. Appl. Acarol.
, 
51
(
1
): 
257-271
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10493-009-9301-z
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nguyen L.T.
, 
Schmidt H.A.
, 
Von Haeseler A.
, 
Minh B.Q.
2015
. 
IQ-TREE: a fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies
. 
Mol. Biol. Evol.
, 
32
(
1
): 
268-274
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msu300
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oldfield G.N.
1996
. 1.4. 
3 Diversity and host plant specificity
. 
World Crop Pests, 6(Eriophyoid Mites Their Biology, Natural Enemies and Control)
: 
199-216
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S1572-4379(96)80011-X
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pagenstecher H.A.
1857
. 

Über Milben besonders die Gattung 
Phytoptus

. 
Verhandlungen des Naturhistorisch-medizinischen Vereins
, 1(
2
(Bund 
1857-1859
)): 46-53.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Skoracka A.
, 
Dabert M.
2010
. 

The cereal rust mite 
Abacarus hystrix
(Acari: Eriophyoidea) is a complex

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vidano C.
, 
Arzone A.
, 
Meotto F.
1978
. 
Alarming phytophagous in Piedmontese orchards today [Fitofagi preoccupanti di attualità in frutteti piemontesi]
. 
Ann. dell′Accademia di Agric. di Torino
, 
120
: 
65-78
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vidović B.
, 
Marinković S.
, 
Marić I.
, 
Petanović R.
2014
. 

Comparative morphological analysis of apple blister mite, 
Eriophyes mali
Nal., a new pest in Serbia

. 
Pestic. i fitomedicina
, 
29
(
2
): 
123-130
. 
https://doi.org/10.2298/PIF1402123V
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Walsh P.S.
, 
Metzger D.A.
, 
Higushi R.
2013
. 

Chelex 100 as a medium for simple extraction of DNA for PCR-based typing from forensic material. BioTechniques 10(4): 506-13 (
April 1991
)

. 
Biotechniques
, 
54
(
3
): 
134-139
. 
https://doi.org/10.2144/000114018
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Westphal E.
, 
Manson D.C.M.
1996
. 1.4. 
6 Feeding effects on host plants: Gall formation and other distortions
. 
World Crop Pests, 6(Eriophyoid Mites Their Biology, Natural Enemies and Control)
: 
231-242
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S1572-4379(96)80014-5
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
