<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Acarologia</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24349/cet8-2c2k</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>New records of the feather mite Pterolichus obtusus Robin, 1877 (Acariformes: Astigmata: Pterolichidae) parasitizing chickens Gallus gallus domesticus (L.) (Galliformes: Phasianidae) in Brazil</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>24</day>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1877
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Astigmata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pterolichidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gallus gallus domesticus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Phasianidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1877
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Astigmata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pterolichidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gallus gallus domesticus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Astigmata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pterolichidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1868
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Epistomolichus reticulatus
Mironov, Pérez et Palma, 2009
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Acari</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1877
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pterolichidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. lithodorus
Gaud, 1965
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. stenochaetus
Gaud, 1965
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Francolinus
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Phasianidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gallus gallus domesticus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1877
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pterolichidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Megninia
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Analgidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Allopsoroptoides galli
Mironov
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Psoroptoididae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

José Dantas Araújo Lacerda 
K
a

, 

Henri Castro Pacheco 
K
a

, 

Magno Chagas Souza 
K
a

, 

Nasly Cristianna Gonçalves Xavier 
K
a

, 

Wilton Pires da Cruz 
K
a

, 

Fabio Akashi Hernandes 
K
b
a

University Campus of Parauapebas, Universidade Federal Rural da Amazônia (UFRA), Via de acesso para a UFRA, Rodovia PA 275, Km 08, Zona Rural, mailbox 3017, zip code 68515-000, Parauapebas City, 
Pará
, 
Brazil
.

b

Departamento de Ecologia e Zoologia, CCB/ECZ, Trindade, Universidade Federal de 
Santa Catarina
, 88040-970 – Florianópolis, SC, 
Brazil
.

</p>
         <p>
Short note
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
</title>
         <p>
The feather mite 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1877
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Astigmata</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Pterolichidae</tp:taxon-name>
) is associated with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gallus gallus domesticus
</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) worldwide. Here, we report new records of this species from rustic chickens in 
Brazil
after a gap of 45 years, and for the first time in a northern area of this country. The major role of 
Brazil
as one of the main chicken meat producers and exporters highlights the importance of these new findings. Knowing and keeping track of the distribution of this ectoparasitic species might offer valuable information for the development of animal health programs and policies aimed at mitigating mite pest infestations, in addition to support decision-making processes regarding research funding to study the damage caused 
P
by. 
<tp:taxon-name>
obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
in domestic and wild fowl populations, contributing to the advancement of aviculture.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Keywords
feather mite
; 
rustic chickens
; 

Minas Gerais

; 

Pará

; 
Eastern Amazon
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
In addition to the prominent role of 
Brazil
as one of the leading producers and exporters of chicken meat in large-scale facilities (

; 

), the practice of raising chickens in small rural areas for subsistence is widespread across all regions of the country, particularly among low-income populations. Referred to as domestic poultry (“galinha caipira” in Brazilian Portuguese) (Feitosa Jr. 
et al.
2020), these rustic chickens are commonly bred in urban areas of rural towns. However, this situation can contribute not only to the spread of ectoparasites but also to the dissemination of other significant disease-causing agents. The chickens are often allowed to roam freely and come into close contact with other domestic and wild birds (

; 
Cunha
et al.
2020).
</p>
         <p>
Feather mites (Acariformes: 
<tp:taxon-name>Astigmata</tp:taxon-name>
) are a substantial group of ectoparasitic arthropods permanently and exclusively associated with birds. They encompass over 2500 species, classified into 34 families and two superfamilies: Analgoidea and Pterolichoidea (

; 

; 

; 

). A number of feather mite families from both the Analgoidea and Pterolichoidea have been documented in association with chickens worldwide. 

listed nine families of analgoidean mites, which representatives reside on the feathers, skin, in the quill cavities and respiratory tract of chickens, and of two families of pterolichoidean mites living on the feathers and in the quills.
</p>
         <p>
In the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Pterolichidae</tp:taxon-name>
, two species have been documented in association with domestic chickens, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1868
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epistomolichus reticulatus
Mironov, Pérez et Palma, 2009
</tp:taxon-name>
; the former worldwide (e.g. 

; 

; 

</p>
         <p>
&amp; Siores 1967; 

; 

; 

, 

, 

;
</p>
         <p>

; 

; 

; 

) and the latter from Galápagos Islands (

). In the New World, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
has been reported in various countries, including the 
USA
(

), 
Cuba
(

; Rodríguez 
et al.
2016; 

), 
Costa Rica
(

, 

), 
Argentina
(

), 
Peru
(

), and 
Brazil
(

</p>
         <p>
1943; 

).
</p>
         <p>
In the present paper, we report the presence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
on rustic chickens in two regions of 
Brazil
, marking a significant rediscovery of this mite after a gap of 45 years since its last reported occurrence in the country.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Materials and methods
</title>
         <p>
The mites reported herein came from small backyard chicken houses of two Brazilian administrative regions: 1) North: Marabá and Parauapebas, 
Pará State
; 2) Southeast: Pains, district of São Lourenço, 
Minas Gerais State
. In the case of the rustic chickens from Parauapebas, it was noticed that they appeared uncomfortable, and hardly gained weight – it was later shown that their wing feathers were full of parasitic mites. In the chickens from Marabá, the presence of mites was also observed. In the latter, the breeding conditions were more technical, with chickens resulted from cross breeds between rustic and Indian giant breed, in addition to being fed with a balanced diet, regularly vaccinated and dewormed – in these, the number of mites observed was visibly lower and there was no evidence of mite-related stress in the chickens. Feather samples were sent inside dry bags to the Laboratory of Entomology of the Universidade Federal Rural da Amazônia, Campus of Parauapebas, and to the Acarology laboratory of the Universidade Federal de 
Santa Catarina
, Florianópolis, for evaluation. The mite samples were collected from the feathers using a stereomicroscope. The mites specimens were mounted on slides using Hoyer’s medium (

) and identified using light microscope based on the appropriate taxonomic literature (e.g. 

;
</p>
         <p>

; 

). Voucher specimens are deposited at the 
<tp:taxon-name>Acari</tp:taxon-name>
Collection of the Department of Ecology and Zoology, Universidade Federal de 
Santa Catarina
(ECZ-UFSC).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
All examined mite specimens were identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1877
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Pterolichidae</tp:taxon-name>
) (
Fig. 1
). Three species are currently included in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus
</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. lithodorus
Gaud, 1965
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. stenochaetus
Gaud, 1965
</tp:taxon-name>
, the latter two species described from African francolins (
<tp:taxon-name>
Francolinus
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Phasianidae</tp:taxon-name>
, Gallini). The main diagnostic characters of this genus were outlined by 

, table I), and include: in both sexes, dorsal setae 
h1
absent; in males, legs III and IV subequal in thickness, subapical claw on tarsus IV absent, both setae 
d
and 
e
on tarsus IV filiform; and in females, dorsal setae 
d2
and 
e1
inserted on the main hysteronotal shield.
</p>
         <p>
Material examined. From 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gallus gallus domesticus
</tp:taxon-name>
(L.): 
6♂♂
, 
6♀♀
, 1n, Marabá (
5°12′26.75″S
; 
49°02′46.14″ W
), 
Pará State
, 
02.V.2022
; 
4♂♂
, 
9♀♀
, Parauapebas (
6°04′39.50″S
; 
49°51′43.57″W
), 
Pará State
, 
04.V.2022
, M.N.P. Cruz coll.; 
16♂♂
, 
15♀♀
, 1n, W.P. Cruz coll.; 
15♂♂
, 
8♀♀
, Pains (
20°19′19.40″S
; 
45°42′43.97″W
), district of São Lourenço, 
Minas Gerais
</p>
         <p>
State, 
8.II.2014
, L.F.O. Bernardi coll.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Pterolichus obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
was previously reported in 
Brazil
only twice: once in 
Minas Gerais state
(no specific locality mentioned, 

) and once in Mogi das Cruzes, 
São Paulo State
, from industrial flocks of laying hens (

). This current record represents a notable rediscovery of the species, as its last known occurrence in this country dates back 45 years.
</p>
         <p>
Among feather mites known to cause injury to farmed chickens globally, the most significant species include 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
(Pterolichoidea: 
<tp:taxon-name>Pterolichidae</tp:taxon-name>
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Megninia
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(Analgoidea: 
<tp:taxon-name>Analgidae</tp:taxon-name>
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Allopsoroptoides galli
Mironov
</tp:taxon-name>
(Analgoidea: 
<tp:taxon-name>Psoroptoididae</tp:taxon-name>
) (

</p>
         <p>
1985; 

). These species can cause dermatitis, leading to reduced performance and significant economic losses in poultry (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The observed symptoms in the chickens from Parauapebas are consistent with those previously reported in chickens infested with 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
, such as bird restlessness, weight loss, reduced egg production and irregular molting patterns (

). However, without a comprehensive systematic study under controlled conditions, it is not possible to definitively correlate these symptoms with the presence of these mites.
</p>
         <p>
The current findings reveal that 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
is more widely distributed in 
Brazil
than previously suggested from the limited literature sources (

; 

). We reveal that this species has persisted in the country despite the development of industrial rearing of chickens in large facilities, where young chicks are isolated from parental contact. This system impedes the primary mode of feather mite transmission between individuals – the vertical transmission (

). As demonstrated, small rural and backyard farms facilitate intergenerational contact between adult chickens and young chicks, maintaining populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
and other feather mites associated with chickens.
</p>
         <p>Consequently, these farms can serve as ongoing sources of mite infestation for chickens and other poultry in the region.</p>
         <p>
The importance of 
Brazil
as a major producer and exporter of chicken meat (

</p>
         <p>
2021; 

) underlines the significance of the present findings. By identifying the presence of these mites on chickens in 
Brazil
, this brief communication provides valuable information for the development of animal health programs and policies aimed at controlling mite infestations. Additionally, it provides essential support for decisionmaking processes related to research funding dedicated to studying the impact 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. obtusus
</tp:taxon-name>
of in both domestic and wild fowl populations, thus contributing to the advancement of aviculture in the country. Understanding the specific locations where these mites are prevalent enables the implementation of targeted measures to control their spread and prevent outbreaks and transfers between aviaries.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
To the Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq) for the scholarships to the first and second authors and the Universidade Federal Rural da Amazônia for providing the necessary tools for this study; To Leopoldo O.F. Bernardi, for sending feather samples from 
Minas Gerais state
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declarations
</title>
         <p>
Ethics approval and consent to participate
</p>
         <p>Not applicable.</p>
         <p>
Consent for publication
</p>
         <p>Not applicable.</p>
         <p>
Competing Interests
</p>
         <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
         <p>
Author contributions
</p>
         <p>All authors contributed to the elaboration of this study.</p>
         <p>
Funding
</p>
         <p>This study was not funded.</p>
         <p>
Availability of data and materials
</p>
         <p>Data is available from the authors upon reasonable request.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ORCID
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

José Dantas Araújo Lacerda 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4438-2322

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Henri Castro Pacheco 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4051-9216

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Magno Chagas Souza 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9475-4772

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Nasly Cristianna Gonçalves Xavier 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3379-7872

</title>
         <p>
Wilton Pires da Cruz 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7962-9108
</p>
         <p>
Fabio Akashi Hernandes 
K
https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3504-2609
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alekseev A.N.
1998
. 
Ticks and mites as permanent and temporary bird ectoparasites, vectors and disseminators of pathogens
. 
Bulletin of the Scandinavian Society for Parasitology
, 
8
(
2
): 
1-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aquino C.
2021
. 
Poultry and Products Annual
. 
Global Agricultural Information Network. Report Number: BR2021
-0033. 
https://usdabrazil.org.br/wp-content/uploads/2021/09/Poultryand-Products-Annual_ Brasilia_Brazil_09-01-2021-1.pdf
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Arends J.J.
1997
. 
External parasites and poultry pests
. In: 
Calnek B.W.
, 
Barnes H.J.
, 
Beard C.W.
, 
McDougald L.R.
, 
Saif Y.M.
eds. 
Diseases of Poultry
. 
Ames, Iowa, USA: Iowa State University Press
, 
785-813
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Atyeo W.T.
, 
Gaud J.
1992
. 

The identity of 
Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1877 with descriptions of new genera and species of feather mites (Acarina, Pterolichidae) from the Galliformes (Aves)

. 
Acarologia
, 
33
: 
193-206
. 
https://www1.montpellier.inrae.fr/CBGP/acarologia/article.php?id=2389
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Černý V.
1970
. 
Cerny Feather Mites (Sarcoptiformes, Analgoidea) of Domestic Fowl in Cuba
. 
Folia Parasitologica
, 
17
: 
233-238
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Corpuz-Raros L.A.
1993
. 
A checklist of Philippines mites and ticks (Acari) associated with vertebrates and their nests
. 
Asia Life Sciences
, 
2
(
2
): 
177-200
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
L.J., 
Oliveira P.R.
2020
. 
Validação de questionário para levantamentos de ocorrência e fatores de risco de ectoparasitos para avicultura
. 
Conexão Ciência
, 
15
: 
48-58
. 
https://doi.org/10.24862/cco.v15i1.1100
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Doña J.
, 
Potti J.
, 
Hera I.
, 
Blanco G.
, 
Frías O.
, 
Jovani R.
2017
. 
Vertical transmission in feather mites: insights into its adaptive value
. 
Ecological Entomology
, 
42
: 
492-499
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/een.12408
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
D’Souza P.E.
, 
Jagannath M.S.
, 
Murthy K.M.S.
2001
. 
Feather mite infestation in a broiler breeder farm
. 
VetRecord
, 
149
: 
777
. 
https://doi.org/10.1136/vr.149.25.777-a
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Feitosa Jr. A.B.
, 
Bezerra N.P.C.
, 
Bezerra D.C.
, 
Fonseca L.S.
, 
Negreiros R.C.A.
, 
Rios D.P.
, 
Coimbra V.C.S.
2020
. 
Influenza aviária: vigilância ativa em criações avícolas de subsistência no entorno do Sítio de aves migratórias de Panaquatira, Maranhão, Brasil
. 
Brazilian Journal of Development
, 
6
: 
17773-17782
. 
https://doi.org/10.34117/bjdv6n4-085
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
García D.R.
, 
Ferrer Y.G.
, 
Valdés Fraga L.
, 
Mendoza O.C.
, 
Navarrete M.G.
, 
Rodríguez M.V.
2021
. 
Evaluation of alpha-cypermethrin for the control of mites in laying hens under laboratory conditions
. 
Revista de Investigaciones Veterinarias del Perú
, 
32
(
3
): e 
20404
. 
https://doi.org/10.15381/rivep.v32i3.20404
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gaud J.
1965
. 
Acariens Sarcoptiformes plumicoles (Analgoidea) Parasites sur les oiseaux Galliformes d’Afrique. Annales du Musée Royal de l′Afrique Centrale
, Série 8, 
Sciences zoologiques
, 
136
: 
1-77
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gaud J.
, 
Atyeo W.T.
1996
. 
Feather mites of the World (Acarina, Astigmata): the supraspecific taxa
. 
Annales du Musée Royal de l′Afrique Centrale. Sciences Zoologiques
, 
277
, 
1-193
(Pt. 1, text) + 1-436
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gaud J.
, 
Atyeo W.T.
, 
Barré N.
1985
. 

Les acariens du genre 
Megninia
(Analgidae) parasites de 
Gallus gallus

. 
Acarologia
, 
26
: 
171-182
. 
https://www1.montpellier.inrae.fr/CBGP/acarologia/article.php?id=
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>2673</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hernandez-Divers S.M.
, 
Villegas P.
, 
Jimenez C.
, 
Hernandez-Divers S.J.
, 
Garcia M.
, 
Riblet S.M.
, 
Carroll C.R.
, 
OConnor B.M.
, 
Webb J.L.
, 
Yabsley M.J.
, 
Williams S.M.
, 
Sanchez S.
2008
. 
Backyard Chicken Flocks Pose a Disease Risk for Neotropic Birds in Costa Rica
. 
Avian Diseases
, 
52
: 
558-566
. 
https://doi.org/10.1637/8298-032808-Reg.1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hernandez S.M.
, 
Peters V.E.
, 
Weygandt P.L.
, 
Jimenez C.
, 
Villegas P.
, 
OConnor B.
, 
Yabsley M.J.
, 
Garcia M.
, 
Riblet S.M.
, 
Carroll C.R.
2013
. 
Do Shade-Grown Coffee Plantations Pose a Disease Risk for Wild Birds?
Eco Health
, 
10
: 
145-158
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10393-013-0837-3
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hipólito O.
, 
Freitas M.G.
1943
. 

Notas Ornitopatológicas (Observações sôbre alguns acarinos parasitos de 
Gallus gallus domesticus
em Minas Gerais)

. 
Anais do II Congresso Brasileiro de Veterinária
, 
6
: 
81-82
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hirst S.
1922
. 
Mites Injurious to Domestic Animals, with an Appendix on the Acarine Disease of Hive Bees
. 
Economic series (British Museum (Natural History))
, no. 
13
. 
https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.57139
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jankovska I.
, 
Bejcek V.
, 
Langrova I.
, 
Válek P.
, 
Vadlejch J.
, 
Čadková Z.
2012
. 
Black grouse in Czech Republic and its parasites
. 
Helminthologia
, 
49
: 
78-81
. 
https://doi.org/10.2478/s11687-012-0016-z
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kaschula V.R.
, 
Stephan S.A.R.
1947
. 
Mites, hitherto unrecorded in South Africa, collected in Natal from fowls, pigeons, turkeys, Guinea-fowls, wild birds and rabbits
. 
Onderstepoort Journal of Veterinary Science and Animal Industry
, 
22
(
1
): 
51-75
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Klimov P.
, 
OConnor B.M.
2008
. 
Origin and higher-level relationships of psoroptidian mites (Acari: Astigmata: Psoroptidia): Evidence from three nuclear genes
. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution
, 
47
(
3
): 
1135-1156
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2007.12.025
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Krantz G.W.
, 
Walter D.E.
2009
. 
A manual of Acarology. 3rd ed
. 
Lubbock (TX): Texas Tech University Press
; 
807 pp.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lakyat A.
, 
Pumnuan J.
, 
Thipmanee K.
2022
. 
Ectoparasite species attacking chicken in eastern area of Bangkok, Thailand
. 
International Journal of Agricultural Technology
, 
18
(
4
): 
1619-1632
.http: //www.ijat-aatsea.com/past_v18_n4.html
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Manuel M.F.
, 
Siores F.
1967
. 

Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1868, a common feather mite of chickens in the Philippines

. 
The Indian Veterinary Journal
, 
44
: 
1032-1035
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mironov S.V.
2013
. 

Allopsoroptoides galli
n. g., n. sp., a new genus and species of feather mites (Acari: Analgoidea: Psoroptoididae) causing mange in commercially raised domestic chicken in Brazil

. 
Systematic Parasitology
, 
85
: 
201-212
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11230-013-9422-y
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mironov S.V.
, 
Pérez T.M.
, 
Palma R.
2009
. 

A new genus and species of feather mite of the family Pterolichidae (Astigmata: Pterolichidae) from 
Gallus gallus
(Aves: Phasianidae) from the Galápagos Islands

. 
Acarina
, 
17
: 
89-100
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mironov S.V.
, 
Skirnisson K.
, 
Thorarinsdottir S.T.
, 
Nielsen O.K.
2010
. 

Feather mites (Astigmata: Psoroptidia) parasitising the rock ptarmigan 
Lagopus muta
(Montin) (Aves: Galliformes) in Iceland

. 
Systematic Parasitology
, 
75
: 
187-206
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11230-009-9219-1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mullen G.R.
, 
OConnor B.M.
2019
. 
Mites (Acari)
. In: 
Mullen GR
, 
Durden LA
(ed) 
Medical and veterinary entomology, 3rd edn. Elsevier, Academic Press
, pp 
533-602
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-814043-7. 00026-1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oba M.S.P.
, 
Pereira M.C.
, 
Schumaker T.T.S.
1978
. 

Pterolichus obtusus
Robin, 1868 (Acariformes: Dermoglyphidae) em 
Gallus gallus domesticus
no Estado de São Paulo, Brasil

. 
O Biológico
, 
44
: 
145-148
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pedroso L.
, 
Hernandes F.A.
2016
. 
New records of feather mites (Acariformes: Astigmata) from non-passerine birds (Aves) in Brazil
. 
Check List
12
: 
1-25
. 
https://doi.org/10.15560/12.6.2000
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Proctor H.C.
2003
. 
Feather mites (Acari: Astigmata): Ecology, behavior, and evolution
. 
Annual Review of Entomology
, 
48
: 
185-209
. 
https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ento.48.091801.112725
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
R. 
2016
. 

Comportamiento de los parásitos externos en aves (
Gallus gallus
) de diferentes líneas puras

. 
Revista Cubana de Ciencia Avícola
, 39.2 (
2015
): 
5-12
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rosen S.
, 
Hadani A.
, 
Shoham D.
1985
: 
Parasitic mites (Acarina: Arachnoïdea) in wild birds trapped in poultry farms in Israel
. 
I: Species of mites and their hosts Acarologia
, 
26
(
1
): 
79-85
.https: //www1.montpellier.inrae.fr/CBGP/acarologia/article.php?id=2684
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Roveda R.J.
, 
Boero J.J.
1962
. 
Acaros de las plumas
. 
Revista de la Facultad de Agronomia y Veterinaria. Buenos Aires
, 
51
(
2
): 
53-76
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sangvaranond A.
1993
. 
Studies on prevalence and outbreak of ectoparasites in native chickens in central part of Thailand
. 
Kasetsart Journal - Natural Sciences, Thailand
, 
27
: 
194-203
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sangvaranond A.
1994
. 
Ectoparasites of Bantams in the Central Region of Thailand. Agriculture and Natural Resources 28
(1). 
Bangkok, Thailand
: 
58-65
. 
https://li01.tci-thaijo.org/index.php/anres/article/ view/241376
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sangvaranond A.
2003
. 
Ectoparasites of Domesticated Chickens in Thailand
. 
Kasetsart Veterinarians
, 
13
: 
42-54
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Santana P.E.T.
, 
Pineda N.C.
2019
. 
Actualización de la lista de Ácaros (Arachnida: Acari) de Cuba
. 
Revista Ibérica de Aracnología
, 
34
: 
102-118
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang Z.-Y.
, 
Fan Q.-H.
2010
. 
Psoroptidia (Acari: Astigmatina) of China: a review of research progress. Zoosymposia 4: 260
-271. In: 
Zhang Z.-Q.
, 
Hong X.-Y.
, 
Fan Q.-H.
(eds) 
Xin Jie-Liu Centenary: Progress
in Chinese 
Acarology. Zoosymposia
, 
4
: 
1-345
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zoosymposia.4.1.16
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Uzundumlu A.S.
, 
Dilli M.
2023
. 
Estimating Chicken Meat Productions of Leader Countries for 2019-2025 Years. Ciência Rural
, 
Santa Maria
, v. 
53
: 
2
, e20210477. 
https://doi.org/10.1590/0103-8478cr20210477
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
