<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Acta Zoologica Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17109/AZH.69.4.399.2023</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Improving The Method Of Lens Mass Preparation For Age Assessment In The European Brown Hare (Lepus Europaeus)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>20</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
LEPUS EUROPAEUS
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lepus europaeus
Pall.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
NIKOLA MIHAJLOVIĆ 
1
*, STEFAN STEPIĆ 
1
, VUKAN LAVADINOVIĆ 
2
, DEJAN BEUKOVIĆ 
3
, ALEKSANDAR IGNJATOVIĆ 
1
and ZORAN POPOVIĆ 
1
</p>
         <p>
1
Faculty of Agriculture
, University of 
Belgrade
, Nemanjina 6, 11080 
Belgrade
, 
Serbia
2
Faculty of Forestry
, University of 
Belgrade
, Kneza Višeslava 16, 11030 
Belgrade
, 
Serbia
3
Faculty of Agriculture
, University of 
Novi Sad
, Trg Dositeja Obradovića 8, 21000 
Novi Sad
E-mails: nikola.mihajlovic@agrif.bg.ac.rs (corresponding author), https://orcid.org/0000

-0003-4280-7147 stefan.stepic@agrif.bg.ac.rs, https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2277-5213 vukan.lavadinovic@sfb.bg.ac.rs, https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8134-5849 dejan.beukovic@stocarstvo.edu.rs, https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1431-0475 aleksandar.ignjatovic@agrif.bg.ac.rs, https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6713-4415 zpopovic@agrif.bg.ac.rs, https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5989-3016
</p>
         <p>
Research was conducted on the European hare (
<tp:taxon-name>
Lepus europaeus
Pall.
</tp:taxon-name>
), one of the most numerous and important small game species both in Europe and in the 
Republic of Serbia
. The aim of the research was to examine the possibility of modifying the standard method, which is a standard in the 
Republic of Serbia
, for determining the age of hares based on the mass of their lenses in order to shorten its duration. Additionally, the goal was to investigate whether there was a difference in the age structure determined by the standard and modified methods. For the purpose of processing and analyzing samples, a total of 410 hare heads were collected from hunting grounds in Central 
Serbia
and Vojvodina, and only heads with intact lenses of both eyes (399) were included in the analysis, resulting in the examination of 798 lenses. It was determined that there was no statistically significant difference in the lens mass between the standard and modified methods, both for age categories of hares up to one year and over one year. High correlation coefficients were found, indicating a strong relationship between the lens mass obtained by the standard and modified methods within both age categories. Furthermore, the real growth rates of hares determined by the standard and modified methods were equal.
</p>
         <p>
Key words: 
Brown hare
, 
age determination
, 
eye lens
, 
age structure
, 
real growth rate
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
The European brown hare is probably the most important game animal in Europe throughout its historical distribution (

). Thanks to its high ecological plasticity, the European hare inhabits diverse habitats, with flat landscapes being the most suitable for its survival (

), making it a characteristic species of European agricultural areas (

). However, despite its large distribution range, influenced by numerous
</p>
         <p>
© Authors Published by the Hungarian Natural History Museum
factors, the hare population is increasingly being suppressed both in Europe (

, 

, 

, 

) and in 
Serbia
(

). The abundance of hares is influenced by natural factors such as climate, diseases, and predators, as well as anthropogenic factors including agricultural activities, traffic, and hunting (

, 

). One of the most significant factors is the intensification of agricultural production (

, JOHAN &amp; ARNOLD 2021), which has resulted in changes in living conditions, habitat loss, reduced food availability (EDWARDS 
et al
. 2000), and increased use of fertilizers and pesticides (

).
</p>
         <p>
The reduction in the population size of the European hare is a significant problem today. Considering that certain factors cannot be directly influenced, efforts should be focused on those aspects that breeders can directly or indirectly address, primarily through the improvement of management practices (

). The foundation of sustainable management lies in understanding and continuously monitoring the population dynamics through its structural elements, which include population density, sex and age structure, fertility (growth), and losses (

, NIKOLANDIĆ &amp; DEGMENČIĆ 2007). 

emphasize that population abundance of small game species is of utmost importance in game management. However, for management purposes, not only quantity but also the quality (age structure) of the population is crucial. The age structure of the hare population is an important indicator of growth and is used in planning the degree of hare utilization in hunting grounds (

, 

). As hares have a fast generation turnover, the age structure significantly affects the reproductive and vital capacity of the population, thus influencing its size. Additionally, 

highlight the importance of understanding population dynamics through knowledge of the age structure. Determining the age structure of a population can be a powerful mechanism for understanding the impact of hunting pressure and habitat management on the survival of young and old hares, as well as the overall population dynamics (

). The significance of the age structure lies in its ability to determine the actual growth of hares, specifically the ratio between young and old individuals, which forms the basis for planning harvest dynamics.
</p>
         <p>
Therefore, in the management of the hare population, it is necessary to determine the age of harvested individuals (

, 

) in order to determine the age structure of the observed population. There are several methods for determining the age of hares, which are based on specific parameters such as: ossification of the protuberance (Stroh’s sign) on the low- er ulna (

, 

, 

), assessment of the flexibility of the lacrimal processus (

), annual growth lines in the mandible (

, FRYLESTAM &amp; VON SCHANTZ 1977, 

, 

), estimation based on body mass (FLIS 
et al
. 2021), and lens mass (

, 

, 

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
The main drawback of most methods is that they cannot accurately determine the age but can only be used to differentiate between young and old individuals (

, 

, LOYD 2009, 

). However, based on the lens mass, the age of hares can be determined more accurately, which represents a significant advantage compared to other methods (RISTIĆ 
et al
. 2013). As stated by 

, hares can be classified into 6 classes based on the lens mass:
</p>
         <p>
− I age class, of up to 
100 mg
– hares up to 3 months;
</p>
         <p>
− II age class, of 
100 to 200 mg
– hares aged 3- 6 months;
</p>
         <p>
− III age class, of 
200 to 280 mg
– hares aged 6 -12 months;
</p>
         <p>
− IV age class, from 
280 to 310 mg
– hares aged 1 to 2 years;
</p>
         <p>
− V age class, of 
310 to 370 mg
– hares aged 2-3 years;
</p>
         <p>
− VI age class, over 
370 mg
– hares over 3 years of age.
</p>
         <p>
The determination of European hare age in the territory of the 
Republic of Serbia
, specifically in the Autonomous Province of Vojvodina, has been conducted annually since 1967 (

). The main reason for age determination is to calculate the age structure of the population in a particular hunting ground, based on which recommendations regarding further hunting, whether it should be conducted or not, are issued. The age determination is based on the mass of dried lenses, following the LORD’ s method (1959), which has been adjusted by 

. Although this method is used in various countries (
Hungary
, 
Czech Republic
), its greatest application has been recorded in Vojvodina (

). The aforementioned method has been used in numerous studies in the 
Republic of Serbia
(

, 

, 

, 

, 

), as well as in 
Croatia
(

). The method based on 

involves preserving eye lenses in a 10% formalin solution for 72 hours, followed by a drying process of 72 hours at 37°C. This requires 6 days for processing and analysis. Indeed, the main issue with the implementation of this method is its duration. In the 
Republic of Serbia
, hare hunting is conducted from October 15th to December 15th (Regulation on the proclamation of protected wildlife species hunting season, 2021), usually organized on Sundays. Since hunting is conducted on Sundays, using the described method, the final results would be ready on Saturday. Consequently, providing recommendations to hunting area users (whether to follow the hunting plan, adjust it, or suspend hunting) for the upcoming week would not be timely, potentially causing the next week’s hunt to be missed. Consequently, this approach reduces the number of hunting weeks during the hare hunting season by half.
</p>
         <p>The aim of this study was to investigate the possibility of modifying the standard method for determining the age of hares in order to shorten its duration. Additionally, the study aimed to examine whether there are differences in the age structure determined by the standard and modified methods.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
MATERIAL AND METHODS
</title>
         <p>
Determining the age structure of hares was primarily conducted using the LORD’ s method (1959), which was further modified by 

based on the mass of the eye lenses. However, since the aim was to investigate the possibility of reducing the duration of the standard method, which is a standard in the 
Republic of Serbia
, the eye lenses underwent various additional treatments.
</p>
         <p>
Hares were harvested during the hunting seasons of 2020/2021 and 2021/ 
2022 in
accordance with the Wildlife and Hunting Act (2010). Samples, specifically the heads of harvested hares, were collected from various locations in the 
Republic of Serbia
and delivered to the Physiology Laboratory at the Institute of Animal Science, Faculty of Agriculture, University of 
Belgrade
. The collection and analysis of samples were conducted during the hare hunting season, specifically in late October (last week) and throughout the month of November.
</p>
         <p>
During both hunting seasons, a total of 410 hare heads were submitted from hunting grounds in Central 
Serbia
and Vojvodina for the purpose of sample processing and analysis. However, not all samples could be analyzed. Only heads with both intact eye lenses (399) were included in the analysis, resulting in a total of 798 eye lenses analyzed. There were two main reasons for the exclusion of certain samples. Firstly, in some cases, the entire eye of the hare head was damaged by gunshot, making it impossible to extract and analyze the eye lenses. Secondly, for some samples, the extracted eye lenses were not compact, posing a challenge for further processing and analysis.
</p>
         <p>
After the samples, i.e., the hare heads, were delivered to the laboratory, they underwent processing. One eyeball was extracted from each head, and the eye lenses were then isolated for further processing using the standard (reference) method. The extracted eye lenses were rinsed with water and transferred to labeled test tubes containing a 10% solution of formalin. The treatment, i.e., fixation of the eye lenses in this solution, lasted for 72 hours. Afterward, the eye lenses were dried in an oven at a temperature of 37°C for another 72 hours. Once the drying process was complete, the eye lenses were measured using an analytical balance with a precision of ± 
1 mg
.
</p>
         <p>After removing one eye lens and completing its full processing using the reference method, all heads that had an undamaged second eyeball (with intact lens) were subjected to various treatments and procedures. Three different procedures were used for processing the eye lenses, involving modifications in the method and duration of formalin fixation for two procedures, while the drying method was changed for the third procedure.</p>
         <p>
The first
procedure involved reducing the duration of formalin fixation for the eye lenses. In this procedure, after removal and rinsing, the eye lenses were also fixed in a 10% formalin solution, but for a duration of 48 hours. The subsequent steps were identical to the reference method, including rinsing the lenses again and drying them in a drying oven at 37°C for 72 hours. Finally, the mass of the eye lenses was measured using an analytical balance with an accuracy of ± 
1 mg
, based on which the hares were classified into the aforementioned age classes. The largest number of samples (303 eye lenses) was processed using this treatment.
</p>
         <p>
A smaller number of samples were treated with 
second
procedure, which involved reducing the drying duration by increasing the drying temperature. The first part of the process, namely fixation, was identical to the reference method. However, after fixation, the drying of the eye lenses was carried out in a drying oven at a temperature of 48°C for a duration of 48 hours. The measurement and classification of hares into age classes were performed in the same manner as in the reference method. This procedure was applied to 65 samples.
</p>
         <p>
The 
third
procedure involved changing the formalin concentration and reducing the fixation duration. In the heads with intact second ocular lenses, after rinsing, the lens was fixed in a lower concentration solution, specifically a 6% formalin solution, for a shortened fixation time of 48 hours. Subsequently, the drying of ocular lenses followed the same process as in the reference method, with drying at a temperature of 37°C for 72 hours. The further analysis procedure was carried out in the same manner as in the reference method. A total of 31 ocular lenses were processed using this method.
</p>
         <p>Differences in sample sizes arose due to an unequal number of harvested individuals per hunting week. The research began in 2020 with a limited number of samples, resulting in the application of the first modified procedure to all samples. In the following year, with an expected increase in samples, all samples submitted in the first week were again processed using the first modified method, considering the previously limited number of samples. However, with a smaller number of samples in the following week, all were processed using the second modified procedure. In the last week, all samples were processed using the third procedure, adhering to the experimental plan and applying all three planned methods.</p>
         <p>After processing all the samples, basic statistical parameters of the ocular lens mass obtained using both the standard and modified methods were determined. Then, an assessment of the impact of the tested factors on the variation of ocular lens mass was performed using the General Linear Model in the statistical software SAS 9.3 (SAS Institute Inc., 2002-2010).</p>
         <p>
Afterwards, the correlation between the ocular lens mass obtained using the standard and modified methods was examined using the Pearson correlation coefficient. The strength of the relationship was interpreted based on a rough approximation of the correlation magnitude according to 

:
</p>
         <p>− 0.00-0.20 (negligible correlation)</p>
         <p>− 0.20-0.40 (weak correlation)</p>
         <p>− 0.40-0.70 (moderate correlation)</p>
         <p>− 0.70-1.00 (strong correlation).</p>
         <p>
At the end, based on the determined ocular lens mass using the standard and modified methods, hares were classified into 6 age classes as follows: 1) &lt;
100 mg
, hares aged up to 3 months; 2) 
100–200 mg
, hares aged 3-6 months; 3) 
200–280 mg
, hares aged from 6 months to 1 year; 4) 
280–310 mg
, hares aged 1–2 years; 5) 
310–370 mg
, hares aged 2–3 years; 6)&gt; 
370 mg
, hares older than 3 years. The age structure determined by the reference method served as the control group, and it was compared to the age structure obtained by the modified methods.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
RESULTS
</title>
         <p>
The procedure involved reducing the duration of fixation in 10% formalin from 72 hours to 48 hours
</p>
         <p>
Based on the measured masses of eye lenses, the average mass of samples in the age category under one year, processed by the standard method, was 
216.18 mg
. The minimum value was 126.00 mg, while the maximum value was 277.00 mg. Using the modified method, a slightly higher average mass of samples in the under one-year category was determined, with it being 
220.70 mg
, ranging from 127.00 mg to 279.00 mg. The difference in the mass of eye lenses determined by the standard and modified methods for this category averaged 
4.68 mg
, ranging from 0.00 mg to 11.00 mg.
</p>
         <p>
Similar to the category up to one-year, and in the category over one year, the average mass determined by the standard method was lower, at 
367.40 mg
, ranging from 282.00 mg to 469.00 mg. The average mass for the category over one year determined by the modified method was 
376.35 mg
, ranging from 280.00 mg to 477.00 mg. The difference in mass between the eye lenses determined by these two methods averaged 
9.11 mg
, ranging from 0.00 to 77.00 mg.
</p>
         <p>
Through statistical analysis, it has been determined that there is no statistically significant difference (p = 0.26) in the mass of eye lenses for the category of hares up to one year, depending on whether the standard or modified method is applied, as shown in 
Table 1
. Furthermore, a very high degree of correlation (r 
f
= 0.997; p &lt;0.0001) was observed between the masses of eye lenses of hares in the category up to one year obtained using the standard and modified methods.
</p>
         <p>
Similar to the category of hares up to one year, it has also been determined within the category of hares over one year that there is no statistically significant difference (p = 0.10) between the masses of eye lenses obtained using the standard and modified methods, as also depicted in 
Table 1
. Furthermore, a very high degree of correlation (r 
f
= 0.993; p &lt;0.0001) has been established between the masses of eye lenses of hares in the category over one year obtained using the standard and modified methods.
</p>
         <p>
Since it is necessary to have knowledge of age structure and real growth in population management of hares, an analysis of these two parameters was also conducted, comparing the results obtained using these two methods, separately for each year (
Tables 2
&amp; 
3
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

SS – sum of squares, df – degrees of freedom, MS – mean square, R 
2
– coefficient of determination, Statistical significance (p): ns – not significant

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Analysis of 520 eye lenses from 260 individuals, collected and processed in 2021 (
Table 3
), revealed a lower actual growth compared to the one determined in 2020. However, similar to the previous case, the actual growth determined by both the standard and modified applied method did not differ and amounted to 52.31%.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
The procedure for reducing the drying time from 72 hours to 48 hours is by increasing the drying temperature to 48°C
</p>
         <p>
By analyzing 130 eye lenses taken from 65 individuals, the basic statistical parameters of lens mass were determined for the categories up to one year and over one year using both the standard and modified methods (the second approach). The average mass of the analyzed samples in the category up to one year obtained with the standard method was 
226.06 mg
, with variations ranging from 139.00 mg to 278.00 mg. In comparison to the standard method, the modified method revealed a slightly lower average lens mass (
223.03 mg
), with a minimum of 148.00 mg and a maximum of 278.00 mg. The average difference in lens mass determined by these two methods for the up to one year category was 
6.62 mg
, with a range of 1.00 mg to 17.00 mg.
</p>
         <p>
For the over one-year category, a slightly higher average mass of eye lenses was also determined with the standard method, amounting to 
361.84 mg
. It ranged from 283.00 mg to 439.00 mg. Using the modified method, the average mass was found to be 
353.97 mg
, ranging from 281.00 mg to 434.00 mg. The average difference in mass for the over one-year category determined by these methods was 
11.16 mg
, varying from 1.00 to 39.00 mg.
</p>
         <p>
Statistical analysis of the processed samples revealed that the drying method did not have a statistically significant impact (p = 0.75) on the variation in lens mass within the category of hares up to one year (
Table 4
). The correlation between the masses obtained by the standard and modified methods within this group was very high, measuring r 
f
= 0.983.
</p>
         <p>
A similar situation was observed within the category of hares over one year, where it was also determined that there was no statistically significant difference (p = 0.43) in the mass of eye lenses processed by these two methods (
Table 4
). In this case as well, a very strong relationship (r 
f
= 0.981; p &lt;0.0001) was found between the masses of eye lenses determined by the standard and the presented modified method
</p>
         <p>
When it comes to the actual increase in lens mass determined by the standard and modified methods, it was found to be equal in both cases, amounting to 52.31% (
Table 5
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

SS – sum of squares, df – degrees of freedom, MS – mean square, R 
2
– coefficient of determination, Statistical significance (p): ns – not significant

</p>
         <p>standard and applied modified method.</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
The procedure involved shortening the duration of formalin fixation to 48 hours and using a lower concentration (6%) of formalin compared to the standard method
</p>
         <p>
The average mass of eye lenses for the category of hares up to one year, processed by the standard method, was 225.00 mg, with a minimum mass of 170.00 mg and a maximum of 273.00 mg. On the other hand, the average mass of eye lenses for the same category, processed using the applied modified method, was slightly lower (
215.40 mg
), ranging from 160.00 mg to 257.00 mg. The average difference in lens mass for the up to one-year category determined by these two methods was 
10.67 mg
, with variation between 4.00 mg and 16.00 mg.
</p>
         <p>
Similarly, in the category of hares over one year, the standard method revealed a slightly higher average mass (
385.37 mg
), with a range from 170.00 mg to 273.00 mg. The mass determined using the modified method was 
375.25 mg
, with a range from 297.00 mg to 477.00 mg. The difference in lens mass determined by these two methods for the over one-year category averaged 
13.37 mg
, with variations between 4.00 mg and 28.00 mg.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

SS – sum of squares, df – degrees of freedom, MS – mean square, R 
2
– coefficient of determination, Statistical significance (p): ns – not significant

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Similar to the previous methods, a statistical analysis was conducted on the masses of eye lenses obtained using the standard and the applied modified methods. It was determined that there is no statistically significant difference (p = 0.37) in the mass of eye lenses within the category of hares up to one year, depending on the method used (
Table 6
). Furthermore, a high correlation coefficient (r 
f
= 0.980; p &lt;0.0001) was observed between the masses of eye lenses obtained using the standard and the applied modified method.
</p>
         <p>
A statistically significant difference (p = 0.62) in the mass of eye lenses obtained by the standard and the applied modified method was not observed in hares older than one year. The relationship between the masses of eye lenses determined by these two methods was very strong, as indicated by a high correlation coefficient (r 
f
= 0.984; p &lt;0.0001).
</p>
         <p>
The real growth of hares determined by the standard and applied modified method is shown in 
Table 7
. The values of the real growth determined by these two methods did not differ and amounted to 48.39%.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
</title>
         <p>
It has been determined that there is no statistically significant difference in the mass of eye lenses processed using the standard and the applied modified methods in both age categories. Therefore, with the application of the first and third modified methods, the time required for obtaining the analyses is 5 days, with the fixation duration in formalin being 48 hours. In most of the available studies that dealt with determining the age of hares, the fixation time was longer and ranged from 3 days (

, 

), one week (CABOŃ- 

), one month (

), two months (

), to 5 months (ANDERSEN &amp; JENSEN 1979). Additionally, the third modified method involved the use of a 6% formalin solution, while the formalin concentration in the aforementioned studies was higher (10%).
</p>
         <p>
The duration of the second modified method is also 5 days, with the aim of shortening the drying time by one day by increasing the drying temperature from 37°C to 48°C. Therefore, the drying duration within the second modified method is 48 hours. This time is also shorter compared to most available studies on hare age determination. Drying time ranged from 3 days at 80°C (

) and 3 days at 37°C (

), 4 days at 90°C (ANDERSEN &amp; JENSEN 1979), 5 days at 80°C (

), all the way to 14 days at 85°C (

). On the other hand, in the study conducted by 

, the drying time was shorter (24 hours at a temperature of 100°C), following the methodology of MÉRES 
et al
. (2013).
</p>
         <p>The possibility of applying the modified methods is also supported by the very high correlation coefficients. By using these methods, the most common problem encountered in practice would be solved, which is the untimely acquisition of final results, especially in assessing real growth rate and providing recommendations for the next week’s hunting. In the case of positive results regarding real growth, missing the upcoming hunting week would be prevented, allowing for its successful implementation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
*
</title>
         <p>
Acknowledgment – This research was supported by Ministry of Science, Technological Development and Innovation of the 
Republic of Serbia
grant 451-03-47/2023-01/200116.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ANDERSEN, J.
&amp; 
JENSEN, B.
(
1972
): 
The weight of the eye lens in the European hares of known age
. – 

Acta Theriologica


17

: 
87–92
. 
https://doi.org/10.4098/AT.arch.72-8
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
BEUKOVIĆ, M.
, 
BEUKOVIĆ, D.
, 
POPOVIĆ, Z.
&amp; 
PERIŠIĆ, P.
(
2009
): 
Number and usage level dinamics of population brown hare (Lepus europaeus) round of river Tisa in Bačka district
. – 

Radovi sa XXIII savetovanja agronoma, veterinara i tehnologa


15

: 
173–179
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
BEUKOVIĆ, M.
, 
POPOVIĆ, Z.
&amp; 
ĐORĐEVIĆ, N.
(
2012
): 
Analiza gazdovanja populacijom zeca u Vojvodini u periodu od 1997–2011. godine
. – 

Međunarodni simpozijum o lovstvu, Savremeni aspekti održivog gazdovanja populacijama divljači, Zemun-Beograd

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ĐORĐEVIĆ, N.
, 
POPOVIĆ, Z.
, 
BEUKOVIĆ, D.
&amp; 
BEUKOVIĆ, M.
(
2014
): 
Climate impacts
, 

the degree of forestation and natural resources of food to the age structure of brown hare. – 
XXVIII savetovanje agronoma, veterinara, tehnologa i agroekonomista


20

: 
251–259
. UDK: 639.112
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
FLIS, M.
&amp; 
RATAJ, B.
(
2019
): 
Characteristics of population indicators of brown hare (Lepus europaeus Pall.) obtained during group hunting in the region with the highest density in western part of the lublin region in Poland
. – 

Applied Ecology and Environmental Research


17

: 
13701–13711
. 
https://doi.org/10.15666/aeer/1706_1370113711
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
FLIS, M.
, 
CZYŻOWSKI, P.
, 
BEEGER, S.
, 
RATAJ, B.
&amp; 
KARPIŃSKI, M.
(
2022
): 
Logistic Regression Model for determination of the age of Brown Hare (Lepus europaeus Pall.) based on body weight
. – 

Animals


12

: 
529
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ani12040529
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
FRYLESTAM, B.
(
1980
): 
Growth and body weight of European hares in southern Sweden
. – 

Ecography


3

: 
81–86
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0587.1980.tb00711.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
HACKLÄNDER, K.
(
2012
): 
Sustainable management of European hares in lower Austria
. – 

International symposium on hunting
, Мodern aspects of sustainable management of game population, Zemun-Belgrade

, pp. 
9–15
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
IASON, G. R.
(
1989
): 
Growth and mortality in mountain hares: the effect of sex and date of birth
. – 

Oecologia


81

: 
540–546
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00378966
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
JOHANN, F.
&amp; 
ARNOLD, J.
(
2021
): 
Scattered woody vegetation promotes European brown hare population
. – 

Basic and Applied Ecology


56

: 
322–334
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. baae.2021.08.012
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
LORD, D. R.
(
1959
): 
The lens as an indicator of age in cottontail rabbits
. – 

The Journal of Wildlife Management


23

: 
358–360
. 
https://doi.org/10.2307/3796900
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
LUDWIG, R. J.
&amp; 
DAPSON, W. R.
(
1977
): 
Use of insoluble lens proteins to estimate age in white-tailed deer
. – 

The Journal of Wildlife Management


41

: 
327–329
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

MALLIA, E.
, 
RUGGE, C.
, 
COSENTINO, C.
, 
GAMBACORTA, E.
, 
TROCCHI, V.
&amp; 
FRESCHI, P.
(
2009
): 

Postnatal
growth of 
Brown
hare (Lepus europaeus) in a 
South Italy
rearing centre

. – 


Italian Journal of Animal Science



8

: 
790–792
. 

https://doi.org/10.4081/ijas.2009. 
s2.790


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
NIKOLANDIĆ, Đ.
&amp; 
DEGMEČIĆ, D.
(
2007
): 
Recruitment rate of the Roe deer (Capreolus capreolus L.) in Baranja forests
. – 
Šumarski list

131

: 
565–574
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
OHTAISHI, N.
, 
HACHIYA, N.
&amp; 
SHIBATA, Y.
(
1976
): 
Age determination of the hare from annual layers in the mandibular bone
. – 

Mammal Research Institute of the Polish Academy of Sciences


21

: 
168–171
. 
https://doi.org/10.4098/AT.arch.76-13
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
PELOROSSO, R.
, 
BOCCIA, L.
&amp; 
AMICI, A.
(
2008
): 
Simulating Brown hare (Lepus europaeus Pallas) dispersion: A tool for wildlife management of wide areas
. – 

Italian Journal of Animal Science


7

: 
335–350
. 
https://doi.org/10.4081/ijas.2008.335
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
PETZ, B.
(
2004
): 

Osnovne statističke metode za nematematičare.
V izdanje. – Naklada Slap

, 
Zagreb
, 
211 pp.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
PINTUR, K.
, 
POPOVIĆ, N.
, 
ALEGRO, A.
, 
SEVERIN, K.
, 
SLAVICA, A.
&amp; 
KOLIĆ E.
(
2006
): 
Selected indicators of brown hare (Lepus europaeus Pallas, 1778) population dynamics in noerhwestern Croatia
. – 

Veterinary Archives


76

: 
199–209
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
POPOVIC, Z.
, 
BEUKOVIC, D.
&amp; 
BEUKOVIĆ, M.
(
2015
): 
Age structure determination of brown hare populations (Lepus europaeus Pall.) in 2014 year under management in different habitats
. – 

The international symposium on animal science (ISAS) &amp; 19th international congress on biotechnology in animal reproduction (ICBAR) Novi Sad, Serbia
,

pp. 
266–274
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
POPOVIĆ, Z.
, BEUKOVIĆ, М. &amp; 
MILOŠEVIĆ, G.
(
2013
): 
Istraživanje stanja populacije zeca u lovištima centralne Srbije
. – 

Međunarodni simpozijum o lovstvu, Savremeni aspekti održivog gazdovanja populacijama divljači, Novi Sad, Srbija
.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Regulation on the Declaration of Hunting Ban

for 
Protected Species of Game

. – 

Službeni glasnik RS
, 9/2012-97, 31/2013-75, 55/2015

-24, 67/ 
2015
-11, 
75
/ 
2016-6
, 92/2021-12.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
RIECK, W.
(
1962
): 
Analyse von feldhasenstrecken nach Gewicht der augenlinse
. – 

Ricerche di zoologie appl. alla Caccia


4

: 
21–29
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
RISTIĆ, Z. A.
, 
PONJIGER, I.
, 
MIJAILOVIĆ, V.
, 
TEŠIĆ, V.
, 
KOVAČEVIĆ, M.
, 
MATEJEVIĆ, M.
, PADE- 
JSKI, P.
, 
MARKOVIĆ, V.
&amp; 
LULIĆ, D.
(
2016
): 
Evaluation of the management of brown hare population in Vojvodina region for the period 1967
–2011. – 

Archives of Veterinary Medicine


9

(
1
): 
83–92
. 
https://doi.org/10.46784/e-avm.v9i1.98
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
SCHMIDT, N. M.
, 
ASFERG, T.
&amp; 
FORCHHAMMER, M. C.
(
2004
): 
Long-term patterns in European brown hare population dynamics in Denmark: effects of agriculture, predation and climate
. – 

BMC Ecol.


4

: 
15
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/1472-6785-4-15
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
STANKEVIČIŪTĖ, J.
, 
PĖTELIS, K.
, 
BARANAUSKAITĖ, J.
&amp; 
NARAUSKAITĖ, G.
(
2011
): 
Comparison of two age determination methods of the European Hares (Lepus europaeus Pallas, 1778) in southwest Lithuania
. – 

Acta biologica universitatis Daugavpiliensis


11

: 
22–28
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
STROH, G.
(
1931
): 
Zwei sichrer Altermerkmale beim Hasen
. – 

Berliner Tierärztliche Wochenschrift


47

: 
180–181
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
SUCHENTRUNK, F.
, 
WILLING, R.
&amp; 
HARTL, G. B.
(
1991
): 
On eye lens weights and other age criteria of the Brown hare (Lepus europaeus Pallas, 1778)
. – 

Z. Säugetierkunde


56

: 
365–374
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ŠELMIĆ, V.
&amp; 
ĐAKOVIĆ, D.
(
1997
): 
Number and usage level dynamics of brown hare megapopulation in Vojvodina in 1967
–1996. – 

Symposium – Brown hare and pratridges in present agroecosystems, Hunters association of Vojvodina, Novi Sad

, pp. 
127–135
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ŠIJAČKI, N.
&amp; 
ĐAKOVIĆ, D.
(
1997
): 
Determination of the brown hare age
. – 

Symposium – Brown hare and pratridges in present agroecosystems, Hunters association of Vojvodina, Novi Sad

, pp. 
148–157
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
YAMADA, F.
, 
SHIRAISHI, S.
, 
TANIGUCHI, A.
&amp; 
UCHIDA, T. A.
(
1990
): 
Growth, development and age determination of the Japanese Hare, Lepus brachyurus brachyurus
. – 

Journal of the Mammalogical Society of Japan


14

(
2
): 
65–77
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
