<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>American Museum Novitates</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1206/4008.1</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>An enigmatic euchelicerate from the Mississippian (Serpukhovian) and insights into invertebrate preservation in the Bear Gulch Limestone, Montana</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Anderella parva
Moore et al., 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Boeotiaspis longispinus
(
Schram, 1979
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Euproops
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eurypterida</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eurypterida</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Xiphosurida</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Chasmataspidida</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Anderella parva
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lunataspis
Rudkin et al., 2008
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Anderella parva
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bembicosoma
Laurie, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Maldybulakia
Tesakov and Alekseev, 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Offacolus
Orr et al., 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Brachyaglaspis singularis
Ortega-Hernández et al., 2016
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudoniscus roosevelti
Clarke, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Legrandella lombardii
Eldredge, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Offacolus kingi
Orr et al., 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dibasterium durgae
Briggs et al., 2012
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Offacolus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Offacolus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dibasterium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Octoberaspis ushakovi
Dunlop, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A M E R I C A N M U S E U M N O V I TAT E S
</title>
         <p>
Number 
4008
, 14 pp. 


February 1, 

2024
</p>
         <p>
RUSSELL D.C. BICKNELL
, 
1
JULIEN KIMMIG
, 
2
PATRICK M. SMITH
, 
3
AND 
TORSTEN SCHERER
4
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
ffle Bear Gulch Limestone houses a diverse, exceptionally preserved marine fauna from the early Carboniferous. A wealth of vertebrate and invertebrate forms has previously been recorded from this deposit, including fish, annelids, and several arthropods. To expand the record of Bear Gulch marine arthropods, a new enigmatic, possibly blind euchelicerate, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
gen. et sp. nov.
, is described. ffle new euchelicerate taxon displays a hypertrophied, ovate, and structureless prosoma—a morphology unique among marine euchelicerates. We explore how the large prosoma and lack of ocular structures reflect possible adaptations to an infaunal, burrowing lifestyle. fflis species represents the fourth euchelicerate genus described from the Bear Gulch Limestone, further highlighting the impressive disparity of marine arthropods preserved in the deposit. ffle addition of novel invertebrate forms found in previously unknown museum material suggests that the Bear Gulch Limestone likely houses a still undocumented diversity of Carboniferous arthropods.
</title>
         <p>
1
Division of Paleontology (Invertebrates), American Museum of Natural History, New 
York
; and Palaeoscience Research Centre, School of Environmental and Rural Science, University of New 
England
, Armidale, 
Australia
.
</p>
         <p>
2
Paläontologie und Evolutionsforschung, Abteilung Geowissenschafen, Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde Karlsruhe, Karlsruhe, 
Germany
; and the Harold Hamm School of Geology and Geological Engineering, University of North Dakota, Grand Forks.
</p>
         <p>
3
Palaeontology Department, Australian Museum Research Institute, Sydney, 
New South Wales
, 
Australia
; and Department of Biological Sciences, Macquarie University, Sydney, 
New South Wales
, 
Australia
.
</p>
         <p>
4
Institute of Nanotechnology (INT), Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT), Eggenstein-Leopoldshafen, 
Germany
; and Karlsruhe Nano Micro Facility (KNMFi), Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT), Eggenstein-Leopoldshafen, 
Germany
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
ffle Bear Gulch Limestone houses intervals of exceptional preservation—so-called Konservat-Lagerstätten (

; 

)—from the Mississippian (Serpukhovian) of 
Montana
that record a diverse fauna (

; 

; 

). In addition to the well-known cartilaginous fishes (

; 

), many invertebrates are known from the deposit (

). Recent examination of the Bear Gulch invertebrates has also uncovered novel records of various molluscs (

; 

; 

), suggesting a still undocumented record of other invertebrates. One apparently rare, but diverse animal group preserved within the Bear Gulch Limestone are the euchelicerate arthropods. To date, three euchelicerate species have been documented—the synziphosurine 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anderella parva
Moore et al., 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
, and two xiphosurids: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Boeotiaspis longispinus
(
Schram, 1979
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Euproops
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

; 

; 

). All of these are known from limited material. To expand this already impressive diversity of aquatic euchelicerates, here we document a new enigmatic, synziphosurine-like euchelicerate from the deposit.
</title>
         <p>
GEOLOGICAL SETTING
</p>
         <p>
The specimen was collected from the Bear Gulch Limestone in Fergus County, central 
Montana
. However, the precise collecting locality of the specimen is unknown. The Bear Gulch Limestone beds have been placed within both the Heath Formation and the overlying Tyler Formation (

; 

; 

; 

). The current consensus, based on cephalopod, conodont, and palynomorph occurrences, as well as regional stratigraphic relationships, places the Bear Gulch Limestone within the Tyler Formation (

; 

), dating the deposit as Serpukhovian (late Mississippian) in age. The Bear Gulch Limestone is part of a transgressive sequence that was likely deposited in the Big Snowy Trough (

; 

; 

). This trough connected the Big Snowy Basin to a N-S trending Cordilleran Miogeosyncline to the west, 
12° N
of the equator during deposition (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
ffle Bear Gulch Limestone is a plattenkalk, or lithographic limestone, consisting of nearly horizontal alternating massive argillaceous silty dolomitic micritic limestone beds and platy clayey dolomitic micritic beds (

; 

; 

; 

). fflese alternating units are typical of the Flinz and Fäule style of bedding made famous in other fine-grained lithographic limestones, for example, Solnhofen (

). Similar to Solnhofen, Bear Gulch also has layers with exceptional preservation, making it one of the most important Konservat-Lagerstätten in the early Carboniferous (

). Preservation information on Bear Gulch specimens is scarce, but scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and elemental energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDS) analyses of 
23 specimens
, covering invertebrates and vertebrates, have shown that most specimens were replaced by either calcium carbonate, calcium phosphate, or carbonate fluorapatite, with a couple of specimens preserving traces of carbon (fflomas, 2004). fflis suggests that many specimens have a diagenetic overprint, but some might preserve original carbon.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
MATERIAL AND METHODS
ffle examined specimen (part and counterpart) was collected by commercial collectors and sold in 1995 to the Staatliche Museum für Naturkunde Karlsruhe by Henzel Fossils, Celle, 
Germany
. ffle specimen is currently housed in the Staatliche Museum für Naturkunde, Karlsruhe, palaeontological collections. ffle specimen was photographed with a Canon EOS R5 camera mounted with an EF 100 f/2.8 Macro IS USM lens. ffle specimen was photographed under white light and 
365 nm
UV light in two mediums—air and immersed in ethanol. ffle color, contrast, and brightness of the images were adjusted using Adobe Photoshop Lightroom. Specimen measurements were made from photographs in ImageJ (

).
</title>
         <p>
ffle specimen was examined using SEM, and integrated EDS from Oxford Instruments (AZTEC-EDS) using a ZEISS LEO 1530 SEM at the Institute of Nanotechnology, Karlsruhe Institute of Technology. ffle fossil was secured to an SEM stub with copper tape and first investigated uncoated. fflis led to a high degree of charging because the electron beam point of impact was not earthed effectively by the natural conductivity of the specimen. To reduce the effects of charging, the specimen was wrapped in copper tape, so that only the analysed region was visible. To improve conductivity, the copper tape was placed in contact with the stage to earth the electrical charge. ffle specimen was then coated with carbon (
10 nm
). Analyses were conducted with the following operating conditions: accelerating voltage 20 keV with an aperture of 60 µm, a working distance of 
10 mm
, and 60 μm aperture for imaging and EDS analyses. A standard Everhart-fflornley Detector (ETD) and an InLens-SEdetector were used for secondary (topographic) electron imaging. EDS analyses were conducted using mainly the ETD, thus avoiding artifacts from charging. SEM maps have been recorded using an acquisition time of 100 µs/pixel for 20 frames with a resolution of 512×384 pixels. With an image width of 
3.2 mm
and height of 
2.4 mm
, 169 scan fields were constructed at this resolution to encompass the fossil. fflese parameters resulted in ~6.5 minutes per scan field and a total acquisition time of 18.5 hours. Scan fields were stitched together for the total element distribution map. For EDS data evaluation the sofware AZTEC 6.1 (Oxford Instruments) was used. When mapping elements, a detector dead time of ~30 % was used. For each pixel, 20 X-ray spectra were recorded with element-specific X-ray spectral lines displayed in a concentration-proportional image. fflis resulted in the spatial distribution of elements on the sample surface.
</p>
         <p>
When describing the material, we followed the systematic taxonomy of 

and the descriptive terminology from 

, 

, 

, and 

.
</p>
         <p>
INSTITUTIONAL ABBREVIATIONS: 
CM,
Carnegie Museum of Natural History, Pittsburgh, PA. 
SMNK,
Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde Karlsruhe, Karlsruhe, 
Germany
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
SYSTEMATIC PALAEONTOLOGY
</title>
         <p>
Subphylum: Chelicerata 

</p>
         <p>
Euchelicerata: 

</p>
         <p>Class: Incertae sedis</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eurypterida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eurypterida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Xiphosurida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Chasmataspidida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Anderella parva
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Lunataspis
Rudkin et al., 2008
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Anderella parva
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Bembicosoma
Laurie, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Maldybulakia
Tesakov and Alekseev, 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Offacolus
Orr et al., 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Brachyaglaspis singularis
Ortega-Hernández et al., 2016
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">An enigmatic euchelicerate from the Mississippian (Serpukhovian) and insights into invertebrate preservation in the Bear Gulch Limestone, Montana</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1206/4008.1</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FF83447BB20FFF813E6DFF975D415765</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1206/4008.1</pub-id>
               <issn>0003-0082</issn>
               <source>American Museum Novitates</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>gen. et sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
</p>
            <p>
ETYMOLOGY: ffle generic name reflects the hypertrophied (
titan
), ovate head-shield (
prosoma
). ffle specific name was selected in recognition of Gregory Edgecombe who has commit- ted his career to the examination and documentation of arthropods.
</p>
            <p>HOLOTYPE: SMNK-PAL 1271 (part and counterpart).</p>
            <p>TYPE LOCALITY, FORMATION, AND AGE: Fergus County, central Montana; Bear Gulch Limestone, Serpukhovian, Late Mississippian, Carboniferous.</p>
            <p>DIAGNOSIS: Distinguished from other euchelicerates by the presence of an effaced (structureless) ovate prosoma that is over half the length of the fossil and no discernable pretelson.</p>
            <p>PRESERVATION: ffle specimen is preserved as a compressed, two-dimensional exoskeleton in part and counterpart on brownish/gray micritic limestone.</p>
            <p>DESCRIPTION: Articulated prosoma, partial opisthosoma, and partial telson (fig. 1). Part more complete than counterpart (fig. 1A, D). SMNK-PAL 1271 is 38.1 mm long. Prosoma ovate, completely preserved, 22.0 mm long, 17.5 mm wide. Possible prosomal doublure observed. No other dorsal prosomal features noted, indicating an effaced (structureless) prosoma. Impressions of two prosomal appendages on the right side of prosoma noted under UV light, both ~2.6 mm long and ~0.4 mm wide.</p>
            <p>Opisthosoma triangular, 8.4 mm long and 11.8 mm wide, tapering to 2.8 mm. Seven opisthosomal tergites are observed. Anteriormost tergite largest section, 2.6 mm long, 11.6 mm wide. Section of first tergite removed on right side. Tergites 2–7 between 1.8–0.6 mm long, 6.7–3.2 mm wide (table 1). Tergal boundaries pronounced in more anterior tergites. No opisthosomal axial lobe, pleural lobes, or marginal rim noted. Telson 8.4 mm long, tapering from 3.1 mm wide to rock edge.</p>
            <p>REMARKS: The prosomal TABLE 1. Measurements of SMNK-PAL 1271 opisthosomal tergites. morphology of most euchelicerates is typically quadrate to cres-</p>
            <p>
Tergites: Dimensions
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
Length
2.6
1.1
0.8
1.4
1.5
1.8
0.6
Width
11.6
6.7
5.1
4.9
4.8
4.3
3.2
</p>
            <p>
centic (
Tollerton, 1989
; 
Anderson and Selden, 1997
), with fewer examples of ovate (
Eldredge,
</p>
            <p>
1974; 
Selden et al., 2019
; 
Lustri et al., 2021
) or rounded (
Lustri et al., 2021
) shapes. Further, prosomal sections commonly comprise ~30% of the exoskeleton. To date, the combination of an ovate prosoma consisting of half the body length is
</p>
            <p>
FIGURE 2. Proposed reconstruction of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
. Image credit: Katrina Kenny.
</p>
            <p>
unknown, distinguishing 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
, from other euchelicerates. Nonetheless, comparisons with other Paleozoic euchelicerates are required. The new taxon is distinct from 
<tp:taxon-name>Eurypterida</tp:taxon-name>
(sea scorpions) as 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
lacks a demonstrable metasoma, excluding the material from 
<tp:taxon-name>Eurypterida</tp:taxon-name>
(
Snodgrass, 1952
; 
Dunlop and Lamsdell, 2017
). Although SMNK-PAL 1271 is superficially comparable to 
<tp:taxon-name>Xiphosurida</tp:taxon-name>
(true horseshoe crabs), the lack of an opisthosoma fused into a plate (= thoracetron) excludes the new material from xiphosurids (
Dunlop and Lamsdell, 2017
; 
Bicknell and Pates, 2020
; Bicknell et al., 2021). 
<tp:taxon-name>Chasmataspidida</tp:taxon-name>
is another possibility. However, the lack of a bucklerlike morphology along the opisthosoma (
Marshall et al., 2014
; 
Lamsdell, 2020
) and nine postabdominal segments (
Dunlop and Lamsdell, 2017
) excludes the Bear Gulch material from the chasmataspidids. We can also consider the synziphosurines (
Bicknell and Pates, 2020
)—a paraphyletic assemblage containing basal crown-group euchelicerates (
Giribet and Edgecombe, 2019
). Morphologically, 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
is most comparable to synziphosurine taxa (
Bicknell and Pates, 2020
). However, synziphosurine species have at least eight expressed tergites, a pretelson, and lack ovate prosomas. This suggests SMNK-PAL 1271 is not a synziphosurine (
Bergström, 1975
; 
Moore et al., 2005
; 
Dunlop and Lamsdell, 2017
). Alternatively, if this animal is a synziphosurine, the morphology is distinct from other forms. Finally, the ovate prosomal morphology contrasts the cooccurring 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anderella parva
</tp:taxon-name>
that has a much more crescent-shaped prosoma, excluding SMNK-PAL 1271 from the known Bear Gulch synziphosurine (fig. 4). In sum, SMNK-PAL 1271 is distinct from all other Paleozoic euchelicerates. An additional consideration is that the specimen has a broad, horseshoe shape akin to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lunataspis
Rudkin et al., 2008
</tp:taxon-name>
, followed by the thoracetron and then a pretelson region (
Rudkin et al., 2008
; 
Lamsdell et al., 2023
). The 
holotype
does not preserve evidence for these morphologies.
</p>
            <p>
ffle euchelicerate fossil record contains forms that have not been placed within a higherorder grouping due to aberrant morphologies. fflis includes genera such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bembicosoma
Laurie, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Maldybulakia
Tesakov and Alekseev, 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Offacolus
Orr et al., 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
. We have taken a similarly conservative position in our placement of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
within Euchelicerata as the 
holotype
shows seven opisthosomal tergites; a morphology not observed in any marine Paleozoic euchelicerate groups (
Dunlop and Lamsdell, 2017
). One conservative perspective is that the additional tergites were telescoped under the large prosoma. However, more material of this rare animal is needed to confirm this assumption and additional specimens are likely to shed more light on the taxonomic position of this species.
</p>
            <p>
One final possibility is that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
could belong within Aglaspidida. At least 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachyaglaspis singularis
Ortega-Hernández et al., 2016
</tp:taxon-name>
, shows a larger cephalic region and a reduced number of trunk tergites. However, our material shows no evidence of postventral plates, a morphological characteristic observed in all aglaspidids (
Van Roy, 2005
; 
Ortega-Hernández et al., 2013
, 
2016
; 
Lerosey-Aubril et al., 2017
; 
Siveter et al., 2018
). As such, we can confidently exclude 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
from Aglaspidida.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
PRESERVATION
ffle more complete part of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
was analyzed using SEM-EDS (fig. 3). fflis specimen is preserved as a compressed, two-dimensional exoskeleton in part and counterpart on brownish/gray micritic limestone, parallel to bedding. ffle elemental composition of the host rock reveals it is a carbonate.
</title>
         <p>
The anterior of the specimen, as well as regions along the exoskeleton edge, are preserved as iron oxide and/or oxyhydroxide. These represent pyrite weathering products. Some unweathered pyrite is present on the left side of the prosoma, as indicated by the presence of sulfur and iron (fig. 3). The structures that are well visible under UV light (fig. 1B) are preserved as phosphorus, silica, and calcium, reflecting taphonomic phosphatization (fig. 3B, D, E). We suggest this is likely some form of apatite (

). The composition is similar to the apatite preservation in Bear Gulch polychaetae worms and the carbonate fluorapatite preservation of Bear Gulch shrimp specimens (Thomas, 2004), as well as Cambrian bradoriid carapaces (

; 

; 

). However, this preservational mode is restricted to the thicker exoskeletal regions. This suggests that fossil material in other regions of the specimen were too thin to be completely preserved and records a mix of carbonates and clay—the host sediment. In addition to this, the uncoated specimen preserved small patchy carbonaceous areas, which did not exist as consistent film and likely reflected weathering and/or metamorphic alteration of the rock.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
ffle large, ovate prosoma observed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
represents an extreme morphology for benthic euchelicerates. ffle larger prosomal size may have allowed the animal to burrow effectively, similar to modern xiphosurans (

; 

; 

). Burrowing would also have functioned as a means of protection. fflis contrasts the hypotheses that benthic Paleozoic euchelicerates may have enrolled to protect themselves (

; 

), at least for this taxon. Evidence for novel infaunal consumers indicates that benthic animals from the Bear Gulch Limestone are likely underdocumented and additional examination of the formation may uncover novel bottomdwelling species. ffle Bear Gulch Limestone has distinctive collection and publication bias (sensu 

) toward the exceptionally preserved fishes (e.g., 

; 

) and it is likely that future collections, and maybe museum digitization efforts, will yield more euchelicerates.
</title>
         <p>
ffle lack of ocular structures in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
is worth considering. Lateral compound eyes in basal Paleozoic crown-group euchelicerates are rare, with the structures known from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudoniscus roosevelti
Clarke, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Legrandella lombardii
Eldredge, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
, and putative evidence in other forms (

; 

; 

). It is possible that the lack of lateral compound eyes in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
is taphonomic. However, the Lagerstätten intervals of the Bear Gulch Limestone have preserved fossils in exceptional detail (

; 

; 

). Given the preservation of this fossil, the presence of compound eyes cannot be completely ruled out, especially if they lacked an ocular tubercle. We suggest that this lack of lateral compound eyes reinforces the aforementioned infaunal lifestyle, aligning with select trilobites and other possibly blind euchelicerates (fflomas, 2005; 

).
</p>
         <p>
An alternative explanation for a lack of ocular structures is that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
had a benthic epifaunal lifestyle similar to Silurian euchelicerates 
<tp:taxon-name>
Offacolus kingi
Orr et al., 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dibasterium durgae
Briggs et al., 2012
</tp:taxon-name>
. 

<tp:taxon-name>Offacolus</tp:taxon-name>
,

in particular, has been reconstructed as a relatively slow-moving animal that either preyed on slow-moving or sessile benthos, stirred up sof sediment for the infauna, or functioned as a scavenger (

). However, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Offacolus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dibasterium
</tp:taxon-name>
inhabited dim light conditions (

), while 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
lived within a well-lit, shallow basin (

; 

). As such, we can exclude this as an explaination for the lack of lateral compound eyes in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
It is important to consider whether the lower-than-expected number of opisthosomal segments in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
could be an artifact of telescoping. Telescoping of thoracic segments is relatively common in some post-Ordovician trilobites, which have highly vaulted exoskeletons or fused facial sutures (

). Similarly, telescoped chasmataspidids are common enough that in one species (
<tp:taxon-name>
Octoberaspis ushakovi
Dunlop, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
) the telescoped nature was initially considered evidence for possible sexual dimorphism (

). Conversely, taphonomic experiments on modern xiphosurans and scorpions demonstrated that telescoping is rare in these chelicerates (

). Likewise, telescoped eurypterids are extremely rare, with records known from six to eight species (

). This disparity in telescoping, particularly between eurypterids and chasmataspidids, is thought to reflect differences in molting techniques caused by fused opisthosomal structures (

). As there is no evidence of fused structures in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
, there is less evidence to support opisthosomal telescoping. Hence, we suggest that the seven segments documented here could reflect the true number of segments obtained by the animal in its adult stage. However, as mentioned above, more material of this rare animal is needed to confirm this assumption.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
fflis research was funded by a University of New 
England
Postdoctoral Fellowship (to R.D.C.B.) and a MAT Postdoctoral Fellowship (to R.D.C.B). We thank Albert Kollar and Mathias Vielsäcker for specimen images and we thank Katrina Kenny for the reconstruction of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Titanoprosoma edgecombei
</tp:taxon-name>
. We also thank Russell Garwood and Lorenzo Lustri for reviews that helped improve the manuscript.
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Anderson, L.I.
, and 
P.A. Selden
. 
1997
. 
Opisthosomal fusion and phylogeny of Palaeozoic Xiphosura
. 
Lethaia
30
: 
19–31
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bergström, J.
1975
. 
Functional morphology and evolution of xiphosurids
. 
Fossils and Strata
4
: 
291–305
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bicknell, R.D.C.
, and 
S. Pates
. 
2020
. 
Pictorial atlas of fossil and extant horseshoe crabs, with focus on Xiphosurida
. 
Frontiers in Earth Science
8
: 
98
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bicknell, R.D.C.
, and 
P.M. Smith
. 
2021
. 

Patesia
n. gen., a new Late Devonian stem xiphosurid genus

. 
Palaeoworld
30
: 
440–450
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bicknell, R.D.C.
, 
L. Amati
, and 
J. Ortega Hernández
. 
2019
. 
New insights into the evolution of lateral compound eyes in Palaeozoic horseshoe crabs
. 
Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society
187
: 
1061– 1077
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bicknell, R.D.C.
, 
B. Błażejowski
, 
O. Wings
, 
T. Hitij
, and 
M.L. Botton
. 
2021
. 

Critical re-evaluation of Limulidae reveals limited 
Limulus
diversity

. 
Papers in Palaeontology
7
: 
1525–1556
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bicknell, R.D.C.
, 
S.V. Naugolnykh
, and 
S.C. McKenzie
. 
2022
. 

On 
Paleolimulus
from the Mazon Creek Konservat-Lagerstätte

. 
Comptes Rendus Palevol
21
: 
303–322
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Briggs, D.E.G.
, et al. 
2012
. 
Silurian horseshoe crab illuminates the evolution of arthropod limbs
. 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America
109
: 
15702–15705
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chiu, H.
, and 
B. Morton
. 
2004
. 

ffle behaviour of juvenile horseshoe crabs, 
Tachypleus tridentatus
(Xiphosura), on a nursery beach at Shui Hau Wan, Hong Kong

. 
Hydrobiologia
523
: 
29–35
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Clarke, J.M.
1902
. 
Notes on Paleozoic crustaceans
. 
New York State Museum Report 54
: 
83–110
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Conway Morris, S.
, and 
J.-B. Caron
. 
2022
. 

A possible home for a bizarre Carboniferous animal: is 
Typhloesus
a pelagic gastropod?

Biology Letters
18
: 
20220179
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cox, R.S.
1986
. 
Preliminary report on the age and palynology of the Bear Gulch Limestone (Mississippian, Montana)
. 
Journal of Paleontology
60
: 
952–956
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dunlop, J.A.
2002
. 
Arthropods from the Lower Devonian Severnaya Zemlya Formation of October Revolution Island (Russia)
. 
Geodiversitas
24
: 
349–379
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dunlop, J.A.
, and 
J.C. Lamsdell
. 
2017
. 
Segmentation and tagmosis in Chelicerata
. 
Arthropod Structure and Development
46
: 
396–418
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eldredge, N.
1974
. 
Revision of the suborder Synziphosurina (Chelicerata, Merostomata), with remarks on merostome phylogeny
. 
American Museum Novitates
2543
: 
1–41
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fisher, D.C.
1977
. 

Functional significance of spines in the Pennsylvanian horseshoe crab 
Euproops danae

. 
Paleobiology
3
: 
175–195
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Giribet, G.
, and 
G.D. Edgecombe
. 
2019
. 
ffle phylogeny and evolutionary history of arthropods
. 
Current Biology
29
: R592–R 
602
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grogan, E.D.
, and 
R. Lund
. 
2000
. 

Debeerius ellefseni
(fam. nov., gen. nov., spec. nov.), an autodiastylic chondrichthyan from the Mississippian Bear Gulch Limestone of Montana (USA), the relationships of the Chondrichthyes, and comments on gnathostome evolution

. 
Journal of Morphology
243
: 
219–245
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grogan, E.D.
, and 
R. Lund
. 
2002
. 
The geological and biological environment of the Bear Gulch Limestone (Mississippian of Montana, USA) and a model for its deposition
. 
Geodiversitas
24
: 
295–315
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hagadorn, J.W.
2002
. 
Bear Gulch: an exceptional upper Carboniferous plattenkalk
. 
In
D.J
. 
Bottjer, W.
Etter, J.W.
Hagadorn, and 
C.M. Tang
(editors), Exceptional fossil preservation: a unique view on the evolution of marine life: 
167–183
. 
New York: Columbia University Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Haug, C.
, et al. 
2012
. 

A holomorph approach to xiphosuran evolution—a case study on the ontogeny of 
Euproops

. 
Development Genes and Evolution
222
: 
253–268
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Henningsmoen, G.
1975
. 
Moulting in trilobites
. 
Fossils and Strata
4
: 
179–200
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Heymons, R.
1901
. 
Die Entwicklungsgeschichte der Scolopender
. 
Zoologica
13
: 
1–244
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jackson, N.L.
, 
K.F. Nordstrom
, and 
D.R. Smith
. 
2005
. 
Influence of waves and horseshoe crab spawning on beach morphology and sediment grain-size characteristics on a sandy estuarine beach
. 
Sedimentology
52
: 
1097–1108
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Krzemiński, W.
, 
E. Krzemińska
, and 
D. Wojciechowski
. 
2010
. 

Silurian synziphosurine horseshoe crab 
Pasternakevia
revisited

. 
Acta Palaeontologica Polonica
55
: 
133–139
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lamsdell, J.C.
2011
. 

ffle eurypterid 
Stoermeropterus conicus
from the lower Silurian Pentland Hills, Scotland

. 
Palaeontographical Society Monograph
165
: 
1–84
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lamsdell, J.C.
2013
. 
Revised systematics of Palaeozoic ‘horseshoe crabs’ and the myth of monophyletic Xiphosura
. 
Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society
167
: 
1–27
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lamsdell, J.C.
2020
. 

A chasmataspidid affinity for the putative xiphosuran 
Kiaeria
Størmer

, 1934. 
PalZ
94
: 
449–453
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lamsdell, J.C.
, 
P.A. Isotalo
, 
D.M. Rudkin
, and 
M.J. Martin
. 
2023
. 

A new species of the Ordovician horseshoe crab 
Lunataspis

. 
Geological Magazine
160
: 
167–171
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Laurie, M.
1899
. 
On a Silurian scorpion and some additional eurypterid remains from the Pentland Hills
. 
Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh
39
: 
575–590
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lerosey-Aubril, R.
, 
J.R. Paterson
, 
S. Gibb
, and 
B.D. Chatterton
. 
2017
. 
Exceptionally-preserved late Cambrian fossils from the McKay Group (British Columbia, Canada) and the evolution of tagmosis in aglaspidid arthropods
. 
Gondwana Research
42
: 
264–279
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lund, R.
1989
. 
New petalodonts (Chondrichthyes) from the Upper Mississippian Bear Gulch Limestone (Namurian E2b) of Montana
. 
Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology
9
: 
350–368
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lund, R.
, 
H. Feldman
, 
W.L. Lund
, and 
C.G. Maples
. 
1993
. 
ffle depositional environment of the Bear Gulch Limestone, Fergus County, Montana
. 
In
1993 Field conference guidebook: old timers’ rendezvous edition: energy and mineral resources of central Montana
: 
87–96
. 
Billings, MT: Montana Geological Society
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lustri, L.
, 
L. Laibl
, and 
R.D.C. Bicknell
. 
2021
. 

A revision of 
Prolimulus woodwardi
Fritsch, 1899 with comparison to other paedomorphic belinurids

. 
PeerJ
9
: e 
10980
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mapes, R.H.
, 
N.H. Landman
, and 
C. Klug
. 
2019
. 
Caught in the act? Distraction sinking in ammonoid cephalopods
. 
Swiss Journal of Palaeontology
138
: 
141–149
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Marshall, D.J.
, 
J.C. Lamsdell
, 
E. Shpinev
, and 
S.J. Braddy
. 
2014
. 
A diverse chasmataspidid (Arthropoda: Chelicerata) fauna from the Early Devonian (Lochkovian) of Siberia
. 
Palaeontology
57
: 
631–655
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
McCoy, V.E.
, and 
D.S. Brandt
. 
2009
. 
Scorpion taphonomy: criteria for distinguishing fossil scorpion molts and carcasses
. 
ffle Journal of Arachnology
37
: 
312–320
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moore, R.A.
, 
D.E.G. Briggs
, and 
C. Bartels
. 
2005
. 

A new specimen of 
Weinbergina opitzi
(Chelicerata: Xiphosura) from the Lower Devonian Hunsrück Slate, Germany

. 
Paläontologische Zeitschrif
79
: 
399–408
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moore, R.A.
, 
S.C. McKenzie
, and 
B.S. Lieberman
. 
2007
. 
A Carboniferous synziphosurine (Xiphosura) from the Bear Gulch Limestone, Montana, USA
. 
Palaeontology
50
: 
1013–1019
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Munnecke, A.
, 
H. Westphal
, and 
M. Kölbl-Ebert
. 
2008
. 
Diagenesis of plattenkalk: examples from the Solnhofen area (Upper Jurassic, southern Germany)
. 
Sedimentology
55
: 
1931–1946
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Orr, P.J.
, 
D.J. Siveter
, 
D.E.G. Briggs
, 
D.J. Siveter
, and 
M.D. Sutton
. 
2000
. 
A new arthropod from the Silurian Konservat–Lagerstätte of Herefordshire, UK
. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B, Biological Sciences
267
: 
1497–1504
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ortega-Hernández, J.
, 
D.A. Legg
, and 
S.J. Braddy
. 
2013
. 
ffle phylogeny of aglaspidid arthropods and the internal relationships within Artiopoda
. 
Cladistics
29
: 
15–45
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ortega-Hernández, J.
, 
P. Van Roy
, and 
R. Lerosey-Aubril
. 
2016
. 
A new aglaspidid euarthropod with a six-segmented trunk from the Lower Ordovician Fezouata Konservat-Lagerstätte, Morocco
. 
Geological Magazine
153
: 
524–536
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Peel, J.S.
, 
C.B. Skovsted
, and 
E. Wallet
. 
2021
. 

Morphology and ecology of the bradoriid arthropods 
Spinospitella
and 
Nikolarites
from the Cambrian

(Series 2, 
Stage 4) of North Greenland (Laurentia). PalZ
95
: 
413–427
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rudkin, D.M.
, 
G.A. Young
, and 
G.S. Nowlan
. 
2008
. 
ffle oldest horseshoe crab: a new xiphosurid from Late Ordovician Konservat-Lagerstätten deposits, Manitoba, Canada
. 
Palaeontology
51
: 
1–9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schneider, C.A.
, 
W.S. Rasband
, and 
K.W. Eliceiri
. 
2012
. 
NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis
. 
Nature Methods
9
: 
671–675
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schram, F.R.
1979
. 
Limulines of the Mississippian Bear Gulch Limestone of Central Montana, USA
. 
Transactions of the San Diego Society of Natural History
19
: 
67–74
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Seilacher, A.
1970
. 
Begriff und Bedentung der Fossil-Lagerstatten Neues Jahrbuch für Geologie und Paläontologie Monatshefe
7
: 
34–39
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Seilacher, A.
, et al. 
1985
. 
Sedimentological, ecological and temporal patterns of fossil Lagerstatten
. 
Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London B, Biological Sciences
311
: 
5–24
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Selden, P.A.
, 
L. Simonetto
, and 
G. Marsiglio
. 
2019
. 
An effaced horseshoe crab (Arthropoda: Chelicerata: Xiphosura) from the Upper Carboniferous of the Carnic Alps (Friuli, NE Italy)
. 
Rivista Italiana di Paleontologia e Stratigrafia
125
: 
333–342
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singer, A.
, 
G.D. Stanley
, and 
N.W. Hinman
. 
2019
. 
Anatomy of the Book Canyon conglomerate: a sequence boundary at the top of the Bear Gulch Limestone in the Big Snowy Trough
. 
Facies
65
: 
1–13
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singer, A.E.
2021
. 
Benthic invertebrate paleontology of the Late Mississippian (Serpukhovian) Bear Gulch Limestone, Central Montana
. Ph.D. dissertation, 
Geosciences Department, University of Montana, Missoula
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Siveter, D.J.
, 
R.A. Fortey
, 
X. Zhu
, and 
Z. Zhou
. 
2018
. 
A three-dimensionally preserved aglaspidid euarthropod with a calcitic cuticle from the Ordovician of China
. 
Geological Magazine
155
: 
1427–1441
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Siveter, D.J.
, 
D.E.G. Briggs
, 
D.J. Siveter
, and 
M.D. Sutton
. 
2020
. 
ffle Herefordshire Lagerstätte: fleshing out Silurian marine life
. 
Journal of the Geological Society
177
: 
1–13
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Snodgrass, R.E.
1952
. 
A textbook of arthropod anatomy
. 
Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Streng, M.
, 
J.O.R. Ebbestad
, and 
M. Moczydłowska
. 
2008
. 

A 
Walcottella

- 
like bradoriid (Arthropoda) from the lower Cambrian of Sweden. GFF
130
: 
11–19
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stürmer, W.
, and 
J. Bergström
. 
1981
. 

Weinbergina
, a xiphosuran arthropod from the Devonian Hunsrück Slate

. 
Paläontologische Zeitschrif
55
: 
237–255
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tesakov, A.S.
, and 
A.S. Alekseev
. 
1992
. 
Myriapod-like arthropods from the Lower Devonian of central Kazakhstan
. 
Paleontologicheskii Zhurnal
26
: 
18–23
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
fflomas, A.T. 
2005
. 
Developmental palaeobiology of trilobite eyes and its evolutionary significance
. 
Earth-Science Reviews
71
: 
77–93
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
fflomas, N. 
2004
. 
ffle taphonomy of a Carboniferous Lagerstätte: the invertebrates of the Bear Gulch Limestone Member
. Ph.D. dissertation, 
Department of Geology, University of Leicester
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tollerton, V.P.
1989
. 
Morphology, taxonomy, and classification of the order Eurypterida Burmeister
, 1843. 
Journal of Paleontology
63
: 
642–657
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Van Roy, P.
2005
. 
An aglaspidid arthropod from the Upper Ordovician of Morocco with remarks on the affinities and limitations of Aglaspidida
. 
Earth and Environmental Science Transactions of the Royal Society of Edinburgh
96
: 
327–350
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vosatka, E.D.
1970
. 

Observations on the swimming, righting, and burrowing movements of young horseshoe crabs, 
Limulus polyphemus

. 
Ohio Journal of Science
70
: 
276–283
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Weygoldt, P.
, and 
H.F. Paulus
. 
1979
. 
Untersuchungen zur Morphologie, Taxonomie und Phylogenie der Chelicerata
. 
Zeitschrif für Zoologische Systematik und Evolutionsforschung 17: 85
– 
115
, 
177–200
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Whalen, C.D.
, and 
N.H. Landman
. 
2022
. 
Fossil coleoid cephalopod from the Mississippian Bear Gulch Lagerstätte sheds light on early vampyropod evolution
. 
Nature Communications
13
: 
1–11
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Whitaker, A.F.
, and 
J. Kimmig
. 
2020
. 
Anthropologically introduced biases in natural history collections, with a case study on the invertebrate paleontology collections from the middle Cambrian Spence Shale Lagerstätte
. 
Palaeontologia Electronica
23
: a 
58
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Whitaker, A.F.
, 
J.D. SchiDZauer
, 
D.E.G. Briggs
, 
W.W. Leibach
, and 
J. Kimmig
. 
2022
. 
Preservation and diagenesis of sof-bodied fossils and the occurrence of phosphate-associated rare earth elements in the Cambrian (Wuliuan) Spence Shale Lagerstätte
. 
Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology
592
: 
110909
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Williams, L.A.
1983
. 
Deposition of the Bear Gulch Limestone: a Carboniferous plattenkalk from central Montana
. 
Sedimentology
30
: 
843–860
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
