<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Biodiversity Data Journal</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.12.e112217</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Long-term monitoring of the fish community in the Minho Estuary (NW Iberian Peninsula)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>08</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Petromyzon marinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Anguilla anguilla
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alosa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cobitis paludica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Achondrostoma arcasii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudochondrostoma duriense
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Squalius carolitertii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Salmo trutta subsp. fario</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Salmo trutta subsp. trutta</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Atherina boyeri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chelon auratus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chelon labrosus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chelon ramada
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mugil cephalus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gasterosteus aculeatus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicentrarchus labrax
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Platichthys flesus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lepomis gibbosus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Micropterus salmoides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tinca tinca
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gobio lozanoi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Carassius auratus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cyprinus carpio
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Platichthys flesus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corbicula fluminea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Bivalvia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Corbiculidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alosa alosa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gobio lozanoi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Carassius auratus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mugil cephalus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Salmo trutta subsp. fario</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicentrarchus labrax
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chelon auratus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chelon labrosus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Squalius carolitertii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Petromyzon marinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alosa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Introduction
</p>
         <p>
Estuarine ecosystems play an important role in maintaining fish biodiversity. They are highly biologically productive ecosystems that provide important feeding, spawning, refuge and nursery habitats for various fish species at different stages of development (

, 

). Despite their high ecological and socio-economic value, estuaries are currently stressed by a variety of anthropogenic activities, including nutrient over-enrichment (

), habitat loss (

), overexploitation of natural resources (

), the introduction of invasive species (

), altered freshwater inflows (

), pollution (

) and climate change (

, 

). It is, therefore, important to establish long-term monitoring programmes that provide an accurate overview of the state of these ecosystems and how different species populations respond to these different pressures (in terms of abundance and population composition) over the years.
</p>
         <p>
For over a decade, the ichthyofauna within the Minho Estuary, located in the north-western region of the Iberian Peninsula, has been subject to consistent monitoring (

). The Minho River has been recognised as an EU Natura 2000 site and its estuary has obtained Special Protection Area status under the EU Birds Directive (Directive 2009/147/EC). This area is home to significant bird, macroinvertebrate and fish populations, including various migratory fish species (

). However, the ecological condition of the Minho Estuary has experienced a decline in recent decades, attributed to a combination of factors such as overfishing, pollution, the invasion of alien species and fluctuations in weather conditions (

, 

, 

, 

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>The objective of this study was to document the sampling effort and the abundance and composition of the fish community (allowing the calculation of the CPUE - Catch Per Unit Effort) inhabiting the Minho Estuary between 2010 and 2019. The primary goal was to record the temporal changes that have occurred within the fish community through time.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="project description">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Project description</p>
         <p>Study area description</p>
         <p>
The research was carried out in the LTSER-ESTUARIES - Portugal (https://deims.org/664177a4-a21a-4f59-9601-00909e275868), more especially at the Lenta Marina (
41°57'15.9"N
8°44'42.5"W
), a small (660 
x
80 m), semi-enclosed bay situated 14.5 km upstream in the Minho Estuary, which was chosen as a representative area of the estuary (Figs 
1
, 
4
). Lenta Marina occupies a location within an estuarine zone characterised by slight salinity fluctuations, with freshwater prevailing in accordance with the patterns of discharge of the river. In summer, Lenta Marina experiences minor saline intrusions, leading to relatively low salinity levels in the area. Specifically, salinity can range from 0 - 2 psu during late summer and drought conditions (

, 

). The Minho Estuary is classified as a mesotidal estuary, characterised by an average depth of 2.6 m and reaching a maximum depth of 26 m (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>Funding</p>
         <p>
This research was supported by national funds through FCT - Foundation for Science and Technology within the scope of UIDB/04423/2020 and UIDP/04423/2020. This work was partly carried out in the framework of the Migra 
Mino
Minho project "Protection and conservation of migratory fish in the conservation of migratory fish in the international stretch of the River Minho and its tributaries", a project co-financed by the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF) through the Interreg V-A Programme, Spain through the Interreg V-A Programme, Spain-Portugal (POCTEP), 2014-2020
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="sampling methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Sampling methods</p>
         <p>Sampling description</p>
         <p>
Fish samples were collected from January 2010 to November 2019. Fyke nets with a mesh size of 10 mm, a length of 7 m, a mouth diameter of 0.7 m and a central wing of 3.5 m were used to collect the fish (Fig. 
2
). These nets were consistently set in the morning and left submerged for 5.5 
+/-
2.6 days (average 
+/-
SD) (Fig. 
3
). To ensure even spatial coverage, the fyke nets were always set parallel to the shore and distributed close to the bay mouth at fixed locations (Fig. 
1
). Although the number of fyke nets used per sampling date varied due to technical issues (e.g. lost or damaged fyke nets), up to five fyke nets were employed per sampling date. After retrieving of the fyke nets, all captured individuals were identified (following 

and 

) and counted (Fig. 
5
). During the entire study period, a total of 3,029 samples (i.e. individual fyke nets) were collected.
</p>
         <p>Permission to collect fish within the study area was obtained in correspondence with the Portuguese Navy.</p>
         <p>Quality control</p>
         <p>
It is important to note that fyke netting is a passive gear and, therefore, considered a semi-quantitative method, which can be influenced by gear catchability and saturation, fish activity and behaviour, predation inside fyke nets, as well as environmental conditions (e.g. water temperature and transparecy) (

). The use of this dataset needs to account for these known issues.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="geographic coverage">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Geographic coverage</p>
         <p>Description</p>
         <p>This study was carried out in Lenta Marina in the Minho Estuary in the north-west of the Iberian Peninsula.</p>
         <p>Coordinates</p>
         <p>41°57'15.9'' and 41°57'15.9'' Latitude; 8°44'42.5'' and 8°44'42.5'' Longitude.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="taxonomic coverage">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Taxonomic coverage</p>
         <p>Description</p>
         <p>
The dataset comprised the records of 70,857 individuals belonging to 20 species, two subspecies and one genus (which has not been identified to the species level) taxa of fish from 12 families. The taxonomic list was defined, based on the presence of a taxonomic group in the entire dataset and the presence or absence of each taxonomic group in a eventID was recorded at occurrenceStatus. The taxon identification numbers (acceptedNameUsageID) were based on GBIF Backbone Taxonomy (

), whereas the common names of the species (vernacularName) were based on FishBase (

).
</p>
         <p>Taxa included</p>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="temporal coverage">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Temporal coverage</p>
         <p>
Data range:
2010-1-05 - 2019-11-12.
</p>
         <p>Notes</p>
         <p>
Sampling was performed on average every 6 days (5.7 
+/-
3.6) throught the study period, from January 2010 to November 2019. The interval between events was not constant and gaps of some days occurred, averaging 1.9 
+/-
3.5 (mean 
+/-
SD) days, with a minumum of 0 and a maximum of 34 days (Fig. 
3
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="usage licence">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Usage licence</p>
         <p>Usage licence</p>
         <p>Other</p>
         <p>IP rights notes</p>
         <p>CC BY 4.0</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="data resources">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Data resources</p>
         <p>Data package title</p>
         <p>Long-term monitoring of the fish community in the Minho Estuary (NW Iberian Peninsula)</p>
         <p>Resource link</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.10321946</p>
         <p>Number of data sets</p>
         <p>1</p>
         <p>Data set 1.</p>
         <p>Data set name</p>
         <p>Long-term monitoring of the fish community in the Minho Estuary (NW Iberian Peninsula)</p>
         <p>Data format</p>
         <p>TSV</p>
         <p>Download URL</p>
         <p>https://zenodo.org/records/10321946/files/DATASET_long-term-estuarine-fish_20231209_V05.tsv</p>
         <p>Description</p>
         <p>
The dataset contains data from fyke nets deployed in the Minho Estuary (Portugal) from 2010 to 2019. The sampling frequency varied but, on average, data were collected using up to five different fyke nets. However, due to technical issues, the sampling pattern was not constant, with some fyke nets staying underwater for shorter or longer periods and occasionally having a variable number of fyke nets per event. The dataset includes 34 terms that follow Darwin Core standard (

) whenever possible. These terms provide detailed information about the sampled organisms and their taxonomic classification. The dataset offers valuable insights into the biodiversity dynamics of the Minho Estuary ecosystem during the specific time period.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="additional information">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Additional information</p>
         <p>All sampling procedures were conducted in accordance with the European Directive 2010/63/EU on the protection of animals used for scientific purposes and its transposition into Portuguese law, "Decreto Lei" 113/2013.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>
The authors would like to thank Eduardo Martins, Diogo Novais, 
Patricio
Bouca
and Mafalda Fernandes for their collaboration in the fieldwork. ED and MII acknowledge support from FCT through the Strategic Funding to CIIMAR (UIDB/04423/2020 and UIDP/04423/2020) and research contracts to ED (DL57/2016/CP1344/CT0021) and MII (DL57/2016/CP1344/CT0018). This study has received funding from the European Union's Horizon Europe Research and Innovation Programme under grant agreement No 101057437 (BioDT project, https://doi.org/10.3030/101057437). Views and opinions expressed are those of the author(s) only and do not necessarily reflect those of the European Union or the European Commission. Neither the European Union nor the European Commission can be held responsible for them. This project has received funding from the European Union's Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation Programme under grant agreement No 871128 (eLTER PLUS). Open access funded by Helsinki University Library.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="author contributions">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Author contributions</p>
         <p>The authors have contributed to this data paper according to the following CRediT statements.</p>
         <p>Conceptualisation: CA</p>
         <p>Data curation: ATS, MII</p>
         <p>Formal analysis: ATS, MII</p>
         <p>Funding acquisition: CA</p>
         <p>Investigation: ACB, AL, AM, AR, ARC, CA, MJA, MHC, MM</p>
         <p>Methodology: CA</p>
         <p>Project administration: CA</p>
         <p>Resources: CA</p>
         <p>Software: ATS, MII</p>
         <p>Supervision: CA</p>
         <p>Validation: ATS, MII</p>
         <p>Visualisation: ATS, MII</p>
         <p>Writing - original draft: ATS, MII</p>
         <p>Writing - review &amp; editing: ATS, CA, ED, MII</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alves, A
, 
1996
. 

Causas e Processos da 
Dinamica
Sedimentar na 
Evolucao
Actual do Litoral do Alto Minho

. 
http://repositorium.sdum.uminho.pt/ (February 27, 2023)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Antunes, Carlos
, 

Araujo
, 
Mario
Jorge

, 
Braga, C
, 

Roleira, 
Antonio

, 
Carvalho, R
, 
Mota, Micaela
, 
2011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Beiras, Ricardo
, 
2016
. 
Assessing Ecological Status of Transitional and Coastal Waters; Current Difficulties and Alternative Approaches
. 
Frontiers in Marine Science
3
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cabral, Henrique N.
, 
Vasconcelos, Rita
, 
Vinagre, Catarina
, 

Franca
, Susana

, 
Fonseca, Vanessa
, 
Maia, Anabela
, 
Reis-Santos, Patrick
, 
Lopes, Marta
, 
Ruano, Miguel
, 
Campos, Joana
, 

Freitas, 
Vania

, 
Santos, Paulo T.
, 

Costa, Maria 
Jose

, 
2007
. 
Relative importance of estuarine flatfish nurseries along the Portuguese coast
. 
Journal of Sea Research
57
: 
209 - 217
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Group, Darwin Core Maintenance
, 
2021
. 
List of Darwin Core terms
. 
Biodiversity Information Standards (TDWG)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dias, E
, 
Morais, P
, 
Cotter, AM
, 
Antunes, C
, 
Hoffman, JC
, 
2016
. 
Estuarine consumers utilize marine, estuarine and terrestrial organic matter and provide connectivity among these food webs
. 
Marine Ecology Progress Series
554
: 
21 - 34
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dias, Ester
, 
Barros, Ana Gabriela
, 
Hoffman, Joel C.
, 
Antunes, Carlos
, 
Morais, Pedro
, 
2020
. 

Habitat use and food sources of European flounder larvae (

Platichthys flesus

, L. 1758) across the Minho River estuary salinity gradient (NW Iberian Peninsula)

. 
Regional Studies in Marine Science
34
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>Froese R. Pauly D. FishBase. World Wide Web electronic publication. www.fishbase.org 2023-12-08T00:00:00+02:00</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gao, Yangchun
, 
Yang, Qing
, 
Li, Hongjun
, 
Wang, Xiaocheng
, 
Zhan, Aibin
, 
2019
. 
Anthropogenic pollutant-driven geographical distribution of mesozooplankton communities in estuarine areas of the Bohai Sea, China
. 
Scientific Reports
9
(
1
)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>Secretariat GBIF GBIF Backbone Taxonomy. Checklist dataset. 10.15468/39omei 2023-08-08T00:00:00+03:00</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guerreiro, Milene Alexandra
, 
Martinho, Filipe
, 
Baptista, Joana
, 
Costa, Filipe
, 

Pardal, Miguel 
Angelo

, 

Primo, Ana 
Ligia

, 
2021
. 
Function of estuaries and coastal areas as nursery grounds for marine fish early life stages
. 
Marine Environmental Research
170
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hubert, W. A.
, 
Fabrizio, M. C.
, 
2007
. 
Analysis and interpretation of freshwater fisheries data
. 
American Fisheries Society
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ilarri, Martina
, 
Souza, Allan T.
, 
Dias, Ester
, 
Antunes, Carlos
, 
2022
. 
Influence of climate change and extreme weather events on an estuarine fish community
. 
Science of The Total Environment
827
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ilarri, M. I.
, 
Souza, A. T.
, 
Antunes, C.
, 
Guilhermino, L.
, 
Sousa, R.
, 
2014
. 

Influence of the invasive Asian clam 

Corbicula fluminea

(
Bivalvia
: 
Corbiculidae
) on estuarine epibenthic assemblages

. 
Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science
143
: 
12 - 19
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Levin, L. A.
, 
Crooks, J. A.
, 
2011
. 
Functional consequences of invasive species in coastal and estuarine systems
. In: 
Treatise on Estuarine and Coastal Science.
: 
17 - 51
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Martins, 
Rogelia

, 
Carneiro, Miguel
, 
2018
. 

Manual de 
Identificacao
de Peixes 
osseos
da Costa Continental Portuguesa

. 
IPMA, Lisboa
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mota, Micaela,
, 
Antunes, Carlos,
, 
2012
. 

A preliminary characterisation of the habitat use and feeding of Allis shad (

Alosa alosa

) juveniles in the Minho River tidal freshwater wetlands

. 
Limnetica
31
: 
165 - 172
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mota, Micaela
, 
Sousa, Ronaldo
, 
Bio, Ana
, 

Araujo
, Jorge

, 
Braga, Catarina
, 
Antunes, Carlos
, 
2014
. 
Seasonal changes in fish assemblages in the River Minho tidal freshwater wetlands, NW of the Iberian Peninsula
. 
Annales de Limnologie - International Journal of Limnology
50
(
3
): 
185 - 198
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nixon, Scott W.
, 
2009
. 
Eutrophication and the macroscope
. 
Hydrobiologia
629
(
1
): 
5 - 19
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Palmer, Terence A.
, 
Montagna, Paul A.
, 
Pollack, Jennifer Beseres
, 
Kalke, Richard D.
, 
DeYoe, Hudson R.
, 
2011
. 
The role of freshwater inflow in lagoons, rivers, and bays
. 
Hydrobiologia
667
(
1
): 
49 - 67
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sousa, Ronaldo
, 
Ilarri, Martina
, 
Souza, Allan T.
, 
Antunes, Carlos
, 

Guilhermino, 
Lucia

, 
2011
. 
Rapid decline of the greater European peaclam at the periphery of its distribution
. 
Annales de Limnologie - International Journal of Limnology
47
(
3
): 
211 - 219
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Souza, A.
, 
Dias, E.
, 
Antunes, C.
, 
Ilarri, M.
, 
2023
. 
Disruptions caused by invasive species and climate change on the functional diversity of a fish community
. 
ARPHA Preprints
e108383
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Souza, Allan T
, 
Ilarri, Martina I
, 
Dias, Ester
, 

Araujo
, 
Mario
Jorge

, 

Roleira, 
Antonio

, 
Braga, Ana Catarina
, 
Carvalho, Ana Rita
, 
Mota, Micaela
, 
Correia, Maria Helena
, 
Lages, Ana
, 
Moura, Ana
, 
Antunes, Carlos
, 
2023
. 
https://zenodo.org/record/8046541
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stamp, Thomas
, 
West, Elizabeth
, 
Robbins, Tim
, 
Plenty, Shaun
, 
Sheehan, Emma
, 
2022
. 
Large-scale historic habitat loss in estuaries and its implications for commercial and recreational fin fisheries
. 
ICES Journal of Marine Science
79
(
7
): 
1981 - 1991
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vasconcelos, R. P.
, 
Reis-Santos, P.
, 
Fonseca, V.
, 
Maia, A.
, 
Ruano, M.
, 

Franca
, S.

, 
Vinagre, C.
, 
Costa, M. J.
, 
Cabral, H.
, 
2007
. 
Assessing anthropogenic pressures on estuarine fish nurseries along the Portuguese coast: A multi-metric index and conceptual approach
. 
Science of The Total Environment
374
: 
199 - 215
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
