<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Biodiversity Data Journal</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.12.e113943</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Monitoring data on the effect of domestic livestock and rabbits on Androcymbium europaeum (Lange) K. Richt. and its xerophytiques pastures for thirteen years</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>26</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Colchicaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ziziphus lotus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cochicaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ziziphus lotus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Melianthium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Erythrostictus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. gramineum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colchicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colchicum europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Stipellula capensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gynandriris sisyrinchium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Filago pyramidata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Erodium chium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Liliopsida</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Magnoliopsida</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Liliales</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Poales</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asterales</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asparagales</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fabales</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Colchicaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Stipellula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gynandriris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Helianthemum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Filago
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Androcymbium gramineum (Cav.) Mc. Bride var. genuinum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium gramineum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Colchicaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Merendera montana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colchicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Maytenus senegalensis subsp. europaea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Scarabaeoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Introduction
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
(Lange) K. Richt., commonly known as Cape saffron or "
Azafran
del Cabo" (in Spanish), is an endemic plant found exclusively in the Ibero-Maghreb Region. Belonging to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Colchicaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family, this species is a winter-growing geophyte that undergoes vegetative development from October to March, strongly dependent of rainfall patterns. The flowering period of this plant occurs during autumn and winter, displaying a strong correlation with precipitation levels and temperature variation (

). Each plant produces 2-3 (occasionally 6) flowers, with pollination being facilitated by beetles, flies and bees. Remarkably, the pollen fertility rate is exceptionally high, at 99%. Following the onset of flowering, the first fruits emerge within 15-20 days and, under favourable conditions, almost all flowers bear fruit. As the aerial parts begin to desiccate from March onwards, the mature fruits detach and their seeds are dispersed after about a year (

). Germination of these seeds is facilitated by lower temperatures.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
inhabits the thermo-Mediterranean belt characterised by a semi-arid to arid ombroclimate, specifically, in xerophytic grasslands and open clearings, often found on stony or sandy substrates. The soil typically consists of skeletal, stony or sandy terrain, occasionally revealing limestone bedrock outcrops. This species is commonly found within winter ephemeral therophytic grasslands, which exhibit varying coverage and are rich in plant species (

, 

, 

). It is typically part of the edge of extensive scrublands dominated by jujube (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ziziphus lotus
</tp:taxon-name>
) vegetation, a priority habitat within the Habitats Directive (Directive 92/43/EEC) (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
Regarding its distribution, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
is primarily found in the south-eastern region of the Iberian Peninsula, in the Province of 
Almeria
(Fig. 
1
a), as well as in western Morocco. Currently, five populations are known, comprising between 255,000 and 630,000 individuals, scattered over 17 10 km x 10 km grid squares (Fig. 
1
b), with an area of occupancy distributed over 133 1 km x 1 km grid (

). The population sizes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
undergo notable yearly fluctuations, primarily influenced by the ever-changing climatic conditions. Moreover, in Almeria, its area of distribution has been reduced and it is classified as vulnerable. Since 1994, it has been included in the Catalogue of Threatened Wild Flora of Andalusia and, in 2000, it was included in the Red List of the Spanish Vascular Flora (

). The transformation of land use, characterised by the establishment of greenhouses of vegetables, extensive road construction, the development of tourist facilities and the relentless expansion of urban areas, plays a pivotal role in the deterioration of the species' habitat. In addition, other factors such us overgrazing, abandonment of agricultural land, mining operations, improper waste disposal, as well as the introduction and uncontrolled spread of alien and invasive plant species, are threatening the populations of this species, as it occurs with other threatened species located on the coast of 
Almeria
(

).
</p>
         <p>
Several species within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Cochicaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family have exhibited a positive relationship between the presence of small herbivores and livestock and their population density (

, 

). Interestingly, some species within this family are consumed by herbivores despite containing highly toxic alkaloids (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
, which shares similar secondary metabolites, such as colchicine, demelcocine, desmethylcolchicine and colchifolin, has been found to possess these compounds in both its vegetative and reproductive organs (

, 

), but this species vary across different locations (

). Additionally, the creeping growth habit of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
, with its leaves positioned close to the ground, suggests an adaptation to herbivory (

, 

). The south-eastern region of the Iberian Peninsula, where 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
is found, is known for its notable rabbit population and the persistence of traditional extensive grazing practices involving sheep and goats (

, 

). As a result, rabbits, sheep and goats can be regarded as potential consumers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
To enhance our comprehension of grazing's impact on the population dynamics of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
, we have been conducting a comprehensive monitoring programme at a specific site for the past 13 years. Our objective is to evaluate the contribution of both domesticated and wild animals in the status conservation of this species, while also examining the diversity of the pastures that serve as habitats for 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
. This long-term study aims to deepen our understanding of the interplay between grazing practices and the conservation of this species. This data-paper has focused on documenting a dataset to assess the impact of domestic livestock and rabbits on the density of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
(in excluded to livestock and rabbits and non-excluded plots) over a period of thirteen years (2010-2023) in one of the most well-preserved populations of the Cabo de 
Gata-Nijar
Natural Park.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="project description">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Project description</p>
         <p>Title</p>
         <p>
Monitoring data on the effect of domestic livestock and rabbits on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
pastures
</p>
         <p>Personnel</p>
         <p>
Ana 
Belen
Robles Cruz (Principal Investigator); 
Jose
Luis 
Gonzalez
Rebollar, 
Maria
Eugenia Ramos-Font, Mauro 
Jose
Tognetti Barbieri, Antonio 
Jesus
Perez-Luque
, Francisco Mario Cabezas-Arcas, Clara Montoya 
Roman
, Claudia Tribaldos Anda.
</p>
         <p>Design description</p>
         <p>
To evaluate the effect of sheep and rabbits on the population of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
and its plant communities, 18 plots of 2.5 m x 2.5 m were installed in the study area (Fig. 
2
). A randomised block design was followed and consisted of six blocks separated between 300 and 400 m, with three different treatments or management types (one plot by treatment and block): 
1)
with herbivory by sheep and rabbits (G+R+), 
2)
excluding only sheep (G-R+) (fenced with hunting netting) and 
3)
excluding rabbits and sheep (G-R-) (fenced with rhomboidal netting with a 4 cm mesh). Within each plot, the abundance of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
in each plot and year was evaluated by counting the number of individuals in 50 cm x 50 cm fixed squares, taking four quadrats per plot, distributed according to the four cardinal points (N, S, E and W): 24 quadrats per treatment (six blocks by four quadrats). The exclusion plots were installed in May 2010, after the first density sampling (March); thus, this year should be considered as year zero, without exclusion treatments. The density of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
was assessed between January and March, depending on the species phenology. Within each above-mentioned plot, two 2-m fixed-crossed transects were set to assess plant community composition, species richness, diversity and cover.
</p>
         <p>Funding</p>
         <p>
These data have been generated thanks to the funding of different projects, although the first samplings and the installation of the exclusion plots were funded by the 
Consejeria
de Medio Ambiente de la Junta de 
Andalucia
through the " 

Ganaderia
Extensiva y Biodiversidad

" project from 2008 to 2014. From this date on, it was financed through the CSIC intramural projects " 

Investigaciones sobre flora forrajera 
betica
: 
prospeccion
de especies, protocolo para su establecimiento en campo y 
valoracion
nutritiva

" and " 
Pastoralismo y Medioambiente
". From 2021 onwards, funding for monitoring came from the SUMHAL project (
Sustainability for Mediterranean Hotspots in Andalusia integrating LifeWatch ERIC)
(LIFEWATCH-2019-09-CSIC-04, POPE 2014-2020).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="sampling methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Sampling methods</p>
         <p>Sampling description</p>
         <p>
To evaluate the effect of sheep and rabbits on the population of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
and its plant communities diversity, 18 plots of 2.5 m x 2.5 m were installed in the study area. A randomised block design was followed, which consisted of six blocks separated between 300 and 400 m (Fig. 
1
c), with three different treatments or management types (one plot by treatment and block) (Fig. 
1
d): 1) with herbivory by sheep and rabbits (G+C+); 2) excluding only sheep (G-C+) (fenced with hunting netting) and 3) excluding rabbits and sheep (G-C-) (fenced with rhomboidal netting with a 4 cm mesh) (Fig. 
2
a).
</p>
         <p>
Abundance of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
The density of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
in each plot was yearly evaluated by counting the number of individuals in 50 cm x 50 cm fixed squares, taking four quadrats per plot, distributed according to the four cardinal points (N, S, E and W): 24 quadrats per treatment (six blocks by four quadrats) (Fig. 
2
b). As mentioned before, the exclusion plots were established in May 2010, following the initial density and biodiversity samplings (March and April).; thus, this year should be considered as year zero, without exclusion treatments.
</p>
         <p>Assessment of plant communities</p>
         <p>
The evaluation of plant communities where 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
lives was conducted annually during the spring season to ensure that most annual species had grown and flowered, allowing for accurate identification. In each plot, the point-intercept (non-destructive) method was applied, following a modification proposed by 

of the point-quadrat method originally described by 

. Two fixed crossed transects measuring 2 m in length were established (Fig. 
2
b), with 50 points surveyed per transect. These points were spaced 4 cm apart and the plant species in contact with a 2 mm needle were recorded. For each transect, the following variables were determined:
</p>
         <p>Coverages:</p>
         <p>specific plant cover: percentage of soil covered by each plant species</p>
         <p>vegetation cover: percentage of soil covered by vegetation</p>
         <p>total specific plant cover: sum of the specific vegetation cover of each species</p>
         <p>musk/lichen cover: percentage of soil covered by musk or lichen</p>
         <p>bare soil cover: percentage of bare soil</p>
         <p>Floristic composition:</p>
         <p>plant species richness: number of species</p>
         <p>Shannon diversity index (H'): where is the proportion of individuals of one particular species found divided by the total number of individuals found.</p>
         <p>Quality control</p>
         <p>For the abundance count and to reduce possible bias amongst observers, criteria for the correct identification of individuals were established and practised prior to sampling for each field campaign. In general, the results obtained from the beginning were quite coincident and without inter-observer bias.</p>
         <p>Each year, sampling was carried out by 2-4 observers, with at least one of them present in all the samplings. Plants for almost all species found were sampled and determined in the lab. Data where carefully implemented in a database and cross-check validations were carried out.</p>
         <p>
The sampling plots were georeferenced using a Kolida K20S high-precission GPS with an accuracy of 
+/-
10 mm. Digital colour orthophotographs derived from flights performed with an RGB camera (45 Megapixels; Zenmuse P1, DJI) on board a UAV drone (DJI Matrice 300 RTK) were also used to verify that the geographic coordinates of each sample plot were correct. The spatial data were originally recorded as UTM using the datum EPSG:25830, but were transformed to geographic coordinates (EPSG: 4326) for easy manipulation.
</p>
         <p>
The specimens were taxonomically identified using Flora Vascular de 
Andalucia
Oriental (

), Flora 
Iberica
(

) and Flora Europaea (

). The scientific names were checked with GBIF Backbone Taxonomy (

). We also used the R package 
taxize
(

) to verify the taxonomical classification.
</p>
         <p>
The data were accommodated to fulfil the Darwin Core Standard (

, 

, 

). We used Darwin Core Archive Validator tool (http://tools.gbif.org/dwca-validator/) to check whether the dataset met Darwin Core specifications. The Integrated Publishing Toolkit (

) of the Spanish node of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) (http://www.gbif.es/ipt) was used both to upload the Darwin Core Archive and to fill out the metadata.
</p>
         <p>Step description</p>
         <p>All data were stored in a normalised database using Microsot Access. Custom-made SQL views of the database were performed to gather event and occurrence data. In addition, some variables at transect level were computed (see Sampling description section). Data were exported and taxonomic and spatial validations were made on this database (see Quality-control description).</p>
         <p>Structure of the Darwin Core Archive (DwC-A).</p>
         <p>
The DwC-A encompasses comprehensive sampling event data (

) consisting of 
event-type
data, 
occurrence
data and 
extended measurement or fact
type data. This structure is organised, based on a hierarchical framework for sampling events. The event file contains a total of 1583 records distributed as follows: 18 events that describe the spatial coverage of the plots (with three plots per block and six blocks), 72 events that detail the spatial coverage of each of the four quadrat counts within each plot and 36 events that outline the spatial coverage of the two transects within each plot. The events related to quadrat count and transects contain 
aparentEventID
field, linking them to their respective plots. A total of 1456 records correspond to the temporal visits made to each of the aforementioned events (Fig. 
4
). The occurrence file comprises 4011 records, while the "extended measurement or fact" file encompasses 6922 records of various measurements associated with the transect and quadrat events.
</p>
         <p>
In order to facilitate the users with utilisation of the dataset, we wrote a detailed tutorial of how to download, process and prepare data from the GBIF dataset. This tutorial is available at https://ajpelu.github.io/dp_androcymbium_lab/ (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="geographic coverage">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Geographic coverage</p>
         <p>Description</p>
         <p>
The study area belongs to the Integral Reserve of Las Marinas-Amoladeras, one of the main steppe zones of the Cabo de 
Gata-Nijar
Natural Park, located in 
Almeria
(southern Spain) (Fig. 
1
). This area is considered a hunting refuge and zoological reserve. The limestone soils are poor and poorly developed. Biogeographically, it belongs to the Murcian-Almerian chorological province, Almeria sector, thermo-Mediterranean semi-arid-arid belt. The annual precipitation is 200 mm with strong intra- and interannual variation and the mean annual temperature is 19
°C
. The potential vegetation of the area consists of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ziziphus lotus
</tp:taxon-name>
thornscrub, but at present, shrubs of the 
Helianthemo-Siderition pusillae
alliance together with 
Eryngio ilicifoli-Plantaginetum ovatae
and 
Androcymbio-Tillaetum muscosae
alliances dominate (

), reflecting the former grazing-pastoral activity, now almost abandoned and of which only occasional pastoral use with sheep remains, together with hunting activity.
</p>
         <p>Coordinates</p>
         <p>36.831783 and 36.8381261 Latitude; -2.2435419 and -2.2552436 Longitude.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="taxonomic coverage">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Taxonomic coverage</p>
         <p>Description</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
has undergone different nomenclatural changes throughout its history, having been assigned to the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>
Melianthium
</tp:taxon-name>
L., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Erythrostictus
</tp:taxon-name>
Schltdl. or 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium
</tp:taxon-name>
Willd. (

). Its most widespread name is 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. gramineum
</tp:taxon-name>
; in fact, it is accepted in several regional, national and even European lists; however, recent molecular studies have concluded that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium
</tp:taxon-name>
is a paraphyletic group of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colchicum
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (

); thus, the currently accepted name of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
is 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colchicum europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
(Lange) J.C. Manning &amp; Vinnersten. In this work, we use the synonym 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
because it is widely accepted and used in most of the taxonomic lists and floras consulted.
</p>
         <p>
There are 100 taxa included in the dataset. The five most represented taxa in the dataset are: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
(Lange) K. Richt. (34.74%), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stipellula capensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(Thunb.) 
Roeser
&amp; Hamasha (11.09%), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gynandriris sisyrinchium
</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) Parl. (5.64%), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Filago pyramidata
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (3.51%) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Erodium chium
</tp:taxon-name>
(Burm.fil.) Willd. (2.37%). There are two classes represented in the dataset: 
<tp:taxon-name>Liliopsida</tp:taxon-name>
(57.14%) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Magnoliopsida</tp:taxon-name>
(42.86%). Twenty-one orders represented in the dataset being the five most represented: 
<tp:taxon-name>Liliales</tp:taxon-name>
(34.74%), 
<tp:taxon-name>Poales</tp:taxon-name>
(14.23%), 
<tp:taxon-name>Asterales</tp:taxon-name>
(11.2%), 
<tp:taxon-name>Asparagales</tp:taxon-name>
(8.14%) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Fabales</tp:taxon-name>
(4.97%). There are 31 families included in the dataset (Fig. 
3
). The five families most represented in the dataset are: 
<tp:taxon-name>Colchicaceae</tp:taxon-name>
(34.74%), 
<tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>
(14.23%), 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
(11.2%), 
<tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
(5.64%) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name>
(4.87%). Seventy-two genera are included in the dataset, with the five most represented being: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium
</tp:taxon-name>
(34.74%), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stipellula
</tp:taxon-name>
(11.09%), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gynandriris
</tp:taxon-name>
(5.64%), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Helianthemum
</tp:taxon-name>
(4.28%) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Filago
</tp:taxon-name>
(3.83%).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="temporal coverage">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Temporal coverage</p>
         <p>Notes</p>
         <p>2010-2023</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="collection data">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Collection data</p>
         <p>Collection name</p>
         <p>
This dataset belongs to the databases for monitoring Mediterranean silvopastoral systems (" 

Bases de datos de seguimiento de sistemas silvopastorales 
mediterraneos

") (https://www.gbif.es/coleccion/bases-de-datos-de-seguimiento-de-sistemas-silvopastorales-mediterraneos/) generated and managed by the Service for the Assessment, Restoration and Protection of Mediterranean Agrosystems (SERPAM, 

Servicio de 
Evaluacion
, 
Restauracion
y 
Proteccion
de Agrosistemas 
Mediterraneos

) of the 
Estacion
Experimental del 
Zaidin
(https://www.eez.csic.es/), belonging to Spanish National Research Council (CSIC).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="usage licence">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Usage licence</p>
         <p>Usage licence</p>
         <p>Creative Commons Public Domain Waiver (CC-Zero)</p>
         <p>IP rights notes</p>
         <p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC-BY-NC 4.0) Licence.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="data resources">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Data resources</p>
         <p>Data package title</p>
         <p>
Monitoring data on the effect of domestic livestock and rabbits on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
pastures
</p>
         <p>Resource link</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.15470/jpjhuu</p>
         <p>Alternative identifiers</p>
         <p>https://www.gbif.org/dataset/340aff40-1745-4d49-bf2a-adb2899bc428; https://ipt.gbif.es/resource?r=amoladeras</p>
         <p>Number of data sets</p>
         <p>1</p>
         <p>Data set 1.</p>
         <p>Data set name</p>
         <p>
Monitoring data on the effect of domestic livestock and rabbits on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
pastures. Event
</p>
         <p>Data format</p>
         <p>Darwin Core</p>
         <p>Data format version</p>
         <p>2.3</p>
         <p>Description</p>
         <p>
Dataset about the annual monitoring of the effect of herbivorism on the conservation status of endangered species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
. Since 2010, the SERPAM Department (Service for Evaluation, Restoration and Protection of Mediterranean Agrosystems) of the Zaidin Experimental Station belonging to the Spanish National Research Council (CSIC-EEZ), has been carrying out annual sampling to evaluate the effect of domestic and wild livestock (e.g. rabbits) on the pastures inhabited by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
. A randomised block design with three treatments (type of management: rabbit and domestic herbivorism; only excluded to livestock; and excluded to rabbit and livestock) was performed. In each treatment, two types of monitoring were carried out: abundance estimation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
by counting individuals on 50 cm x 50 cm quadrats; and plant species diversity in 2-m long transects using the modified Point-Quadrat method. This study was carried out in the Amoladeras Nature Reserve (
Almeria
) within the Cabo de 
Gata-Nijar
Natural Park (southern Spain). The dataset describes information from 2010 to 2023. Monitoring is performed annually. The dataset is deposited at GBIF (

).
</p>
         <p>Our dataset is composed by three files: event, occurrence and extendedmeasurementorfact, with a total of 41 columns.</p>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="additional information">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Additional information</p>
         <p>
If you use the data, please cite as: 
Perez-Luque
A J, Ramos-Font M E, Tognetti M J, Montoya 
Roman
C, Tribaldos Anda C, Robles A B (2023). Monitoring data on the effect of domestic livestock and rabbits on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Androcymbium europaeum
</tp:taxon-name>
pastures. Version 2.3. 
Estacion
Experimental del 
Zaidin
(CSIC). Sampling event dataset https://doi.org/10.15470/jpjhuu accessed via GBIF.org on 09-10-2023.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>
This work has been developed in the framework of the following projects " 

Ganaderia
Extensiva y Biodiversidad

" (
Consejeria
de Medio Ambiente de la Junta de 
Andalucia
), " 

Investigaciones sobre flora forrajera 
betica
: 
prospeccion
de especies, protocolo para su establecimiento en campo y 
valoracion
nutritiva

", " 
Pastoralismo y Medioambiente
" (Intramural project CSIC) and the SUMHAL project (
Sustainability for Mediterranean Hotspots in Andalusia integrating LifeWatch ERIC)
(LIFEWATCH-2019-09-CSIC-04, POPE 2014-2020). AJPL is currently funded by MCIN/AEI/10.13039/501100011033 and by "European Union NextGenerationEU/PRTR" with a "Juan de la Cierva" fellowship programme (Grant JDC2022-050056-I).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="author contributions">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Author contributions</p>
         <p>ABRC and JLGR conceived the idea; MJTB, MERF, CMR, FMCA and CTA incorporated the data into the database. All the authors contributed to field monitoring. AJPL normalised and standardised the data, adapted it to DwCA and submitted to GBIF. AJPL led the writing effort and conducted the visualisations. All the authors reviewed the manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alados, C. L.
, 
Pueyo, Y.
, 
Barrantes, O.
, 

Escos
, J.

, 
Giner, L.
, 
Robles, A. B.
, 
2004
. 
Variations in landscape patterns and vegetation cover between 1957 and 1994 in a semiarid Mediterranean ecosystem
. 
Landscape Ecology
19
(
5
): 
545 - 561
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alcaraz, Francisco
, 

Diaz
, T. E.

, 

Rivas-Martinez
, S.

, 

Sanchez-Gomez
, Francisco

, 
1989
. 

Datos sobre la 
vegetacion
del sureste de 
Espana
: provincia 
biogeografica
Murciano-almeriense

. 
Itinera Geobotanica
2
: 
5 - 133
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Bellot 
Rodriguez
, F.

, 
1946
. 

Sobre el 
Androcymbium gramineum (Cav.) Mc. Bride var. genuinum
Maire. Tres formas 
espanolas

. 

Anales del 
Jardon
Botanico
de Madrid

6
(
2
): 
439 - 450
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Blanca, G.
, 
Cabezudo, B.
, 

Hernandez-Bermejo
, J. E.

, 
Herrera, Carlos M.
, 
Mesa, J. Molero
, 

Munoz
, 
Joaquin

, 

Valdes
, B.

, 
1999
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Blanca, G.
, 
Cabezudo, B.
, 
Cueto, M.
, 
Salazar, C.
, 
Morales Torres, C.
, 
2011
. 

Flora Vascular de 
Andalucia
Oriental

. 

Universidades de 
Almeria
, Granada, 
Jaen
y 
Malaga
, Granada

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Borghi, C. E.
, 
Giannoni, S. M.
, 
1997
. 
Dispersal of geophytes by mole-voles in the Spanish Pyrenees
. 
Journal of Mammalogy
78
(
2
): 
550 - 555
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Boza, J.
, 
Robles-Cruz, A. B.
, 

Gonzalez-Hernandez
, A.

, 
Barroso, F.
, 

Fernandez-Rebollo
, P.

, 
Terradillos, A.
, 
1998
. 

Analisis
de los Pastos y 
Evaluacion
de la Capacidad Sustentadora del Parque Natural de Cabo de Gata-Nijar

. 

SINAMBA. 
Consejeria
de Medio Ambiente, Junta de 
Andalucia

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Castroviejo, S.
, 
2021
. 
Flora Iberica (vols 1-21).

Real 
Jardin
Botanico
, CSIC, Madrid

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Caujape-Castells, Juli
, 
Pedrola-Monfort, Joan
, 
1997
. 

Space-time patterns of genetic structure within a stand of 

Androcymbium gramineum

(Cay.) McBride (
Colchicaceae
)

. 
Heredity
79
: 
341 - 349
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chamberlain, Scott
, 
Szocs, Eduard
, 
2013
. 
taxize - taxonomic search and retrieval in R
. 
F1000Research
2
: 191
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Consejeria
de Agricultura 
Ganaderia
, Pesca y Desarrollo Sostenible. Junta de 
Andalucia
Mapping of distribution of threatened species of flora and fauna (and of interest) in Andalusia. Grids UTM 5x5 km https://descargasrediam.cica.es/repo/s/RUR?path=%2F04_RECURSOS_NATURALES%2F01_BIODIVERSIDAD%2F00_BIODIVERSIDAD%2FEspecies_amenazadas_5x5_2022_10 2023-05-10T00:00:00+03:00
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Daget, P.
, 
Poissonet, J.
, 
1971
. 

An ecological analysis method of prairies: 
criteria's
of application

. 
Annales Agronomiques
22
: 
5 - 41
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>Group Darwin Core Maintenance List of Darwin Core terms. Biodiversity Information Standards (TDWG) http://rs.tdwg.org/dwc/doc/list/</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>Group Darwin Core Maintenance Darwin Core quick reference guide. Biodiversity Information Standards (TDWG) https://dwc.tdwg.org/terms/</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ellington, E.
, 
Bastida, J.
, 
Viladomat, F.
, 

S̆
imanek
, V.

, 
Codina, C.
, 
2003
. 

Occurrence of colchicine derivatives in plants of the genus 

Androcymbium


. 
Biochemical Systematics and Ecology
31
(
7
): 
715 - 722
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Esler, Karen J.
, 
Rundel, Phillip W.
, 
Vorster, Piet
, 
1999
. 
Biogeography of prostrate-leaved geophytes in semi-arid South Africa: Hypotheses on functionality
. 
Plant Ecology
142
: 
105 - 120
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
GBIF,
, 
2018
. 
Best practices in publishing sampling-event data, version 2.2
. 
GBIF Secretariat, Copenhagen: GBIF Secretariat
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>Secretariat GBIF GBIF Backbone Taxonomy. Checklist dataset 10.15468/39omei 2023-05-01T00:00:00+03:00</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Gomez-Garcia
, D.

, 
Azorin, J.
, 
Aguirre, A. J.
, 
2009
. 
Effects of small-scale disturbances and elevation on the morphology, phenology and reproduction of a successful geophyte
. 
Journal of Plant Ecology
2
(
1
): 
13 - 20
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Gomez-Garcia
, Daniel

, 

Azorin
, 
Jose

, 
Bastida, Jaume
, 
Viladomat, Francesc
, 
Codina, Carles
, 
2003
. 

Seasonal and Spatial variations of alkaloids in 

Merendera montana

in relation to chemical defense and phenology

. 
Journal of Chemical Ecology
29
: 
1117 - 1126
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Levy, E. B.
, 
Madden, E.
, 
1933
. 
The point method for pasture analysis
. 
New Zealand Journal of Agriculture
46
: 
267 - 279
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Manning, John
, 
Forest, Felix
, 
Vinnersten, Annika
, 
2007
. 

The genus 

Colchicum

L. redefined to include 

Androcymbium

Willd. based on molecular evidence

. 
Taxon
56
(
3
): 
872 - 882
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Mendoza-Fernandez
, A. J.

, 

Martinez-Hernandez
, F.

, 

Perez-Garcia
, F. J.

, 
Garrido-Becerra, J. A.
, 
Benito, B. M.
, 

Salmeron-Sanchez
, E.

, 
Guirado, J.
, 
Merlo, M. E.
, 
Mota, J. F.
, 
2015
. 

Extreme habitat loss in a Mediterranean habitat: 
Maytenus senegalensis subsp. europaea

. 
Plant Biosystems
149
(
3
): 
503 - 511
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Monserrat, Pedro
, 
1961
. 

Contribucion
al Conocimiento de los Pastos Almerienses. 1

. 

Archivos Instituto de 
Aclimatacion

10
: 
17 - 31
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moreno, C.
, 
2008
. 

Lista Roja 2008 de la flora vascular 
espanola

. 

Direccion
General de Medio Natural y 
Politica
Forestal (Ministerio de Medio Ambiente, y Medio Rural y Marino, y Sociedad 
Espanola
de 
Biologia
de la 
Conservacion
de Plantas), Madrid, Spain

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moreno Saiz, J. C.
, 

Iriondo, 
Jose
Maria

, 

Martinez
Garcia
, F.

, 

Martinez
Rodriguez
, J.

, 

Salazar-Mendias
, Carlos

, 
2019
. 

Atlas y Libro Rojo de la Flora Vascular Amenazada de 
Espana
. Adenda 2017

. 

Ministerio para la 
Transicion
Ecologica-Sociedad
Espanola
de 
Biologia
de la 
Conservacion
de Plantas, Madrid, Spain

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Noy-Meir, Imanuel
, 
Oron, Talya
, 
2001
. 
Effects of grazing on geophytes in Mediterranean vegetation
. 
Journal of Vegetation Science
12
(
6
): 
749 - 760
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Osem, Yagil
, 
Perevolotsky, Avi
, 
Kigel, Jaime
, 
2002
. 
Grazing effect on diversity of annual plant communities in a semi-arid rangeland: interactions with small-scale spatial and temporal variation in primary productivity
. 
Journal of Ecology
90
(
6
): 
936 - 946
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Perez-Luque
, Antonio 
Jesus

, 
2023
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Perez-Luque
, Antonio Jesus

, 
Ramos-Font, Maria Eugenia
, 

Tognetti-Barbieri, Mauro 
Jose

, 

Montoya 
Roman
, Clara

, 
Tribaldos Anda, Clauda
, 

Robles Cruz, Ana 
Belen

, 
2023
. 
Monitoring data on the effect of domestic livestock and rabbits on Androcymbium europaeum pastures
. 

Estacion
Experimental del 
Zaidin
(CSIC). Samplingevent dataset

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Rivas-Martinez
, S.

, 

Diaz
, Tomas E.

, 

Fernandez-Gonzalez
, F.

, 
Izco, J.
, 
Loidi, J.
, 

Lousa
, M.

, 
Penas, A.
, 
2002
. 
Vascular plant communities of Spain and Portugal. Addenda to the syntaxonomical checklist of 2001
. 
Itinera Geobotanica
15
: 
5 - 432
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Robertson, Tim
, 

Doering
, Markus

, 
Guralnick, Robert
, 
Bloom, David
, 
Wieczorek, John
, 
Braak, Kyle
, 
Otegui, Javier
, 
Russell, Laura
, 
Desmet, Peter
, 
2014
. 
The GBIF Integrated Publishing Toolkit: Facilitating the efficient publishing of biodiversity data on the internet
. 
PLOS One
9
(
8
)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Robles, Ana 
Belen

, 
Cabezas-Arcas, Francisco Mario
, 

Ramos-Font, 
Maria
Eugenia

, 

Gonzalez-Rebollar
, 
Jose
Luis

, 
2014
. 

Efecto del herbivorismo en la 
conservacion
de la especie amenazada 

Androcymbium europaeum

(Lange) K. Richt

. 
Pastos
44
: 
44 - 55
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tirado, R.
, 
2009
. 
5220 Matorrales arborescentes con Ziziphus
. 
Ministerio de Medio Ambiente, y Medio Rural y Marino, Madrid, Spain
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tutin, TG
, 
Heywood, VH
, 
Burges, NA
, 
Moore, DM
, 
1980
. 
Flora Europaea (Vols I-V)
. 
Cambridge University Press, Cambridge
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Verdu, Jose R.
, 
Galante, Eduardo
, 
2002
. 

Climatic stress, food availability and human activity as determinants of endemism patterns in the Mediterranean region: the case of dung beetles (
Coleoptera
, 
Scarabaeoidea
) in the Iberian Peninsula

. 
Diversity and Distributions
8
(
5
): 
259 - 274
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wieczorek, John
, 
Bloom, David
, 
Guralnick, Robert
, 
Blum, Stan
, 

Doering
, Markus

, 
Giovanni, Renato
, 
Robertson, Tim
, 
Vieglais, David
, 
2012
. 
Darwin Core: An evolving community-developed biodiversity data standard
. 
PLOS One
7
(
1
)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
