<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>A Monograph of the Nematodes of the Super-family Dorylaimoidea</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>GENUS ENCHODELUS n. g.</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year/>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group/>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The generic identity of this specics is problematical. The presence of a gubernaculum indicates a possible nygoiaimoid relationship.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitai:
Soil, Island of Alfsburg, Germany.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
GENUS ENCHODELUS n. g.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Tylencholaiminae.
Spear lineate with very short aperture, extensions well developed, rod-like or broadly flanged. Guiding ring double, cuticularized. Enlarged portion of esophagus somewhat shortened, with two conspicuous ventrosubmedian gland nuclei locatcd ràther far forward. Ovaries two in ail known species. Ventromedian suppléments seven or more, generally rather closely approximated.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Type
species:
Enchodelus
macrodorus
(de Man, 1880). n. comb.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Synonym: 
Dorylaimus macrodorus
de M an, 1880.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Diagnosis:
Tylencholaiminae
with the above general descriptions. 
Distinctive
because of the lineate spear with its short aperture and well developed, rod-like or broadly flanged extensions.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
After publication of the 
Dorylaimus
monograph (158) the writer found three spécimens of 
Dorylaimellus
virginianus
Cobb, taken from near the type locality. It was immediately obvions thar the several species of long speared 
Dorylaimus,
assigned to 
Dorylaimellus
in the monograph, did nor belong there at ail. Accordingly the genus 
Enchodelus
is here establùhed to reçoive this very distinctive group of nemas.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The position of 
Enchodelus
in the 
Dorylaimidae
sériés should doubtless be locatcd immediately after 
Pungentus
to which the members appear to be most closely related.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Nemas of the genus 
Enchodelus
apparently feed entirely on plants. Frequently specimens are found filled with chlorophyll-like material, indicating that they had been feeding on the mosses among which they were collected.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
KF.Y TO SPECIES OF ENCHODELUS
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>1. Tails T ails hemispheroid elongate-conoid or, rounded-conoid straight or ventrally .......................................................................................... arcuate....................................................................... 2 9</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>2. Spear extension broadly flanged...................................................................................................... 3 Spear extensions not broadly flanged, lineate...............................................................................</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
3. Lips soirtewhat anguiar....................................................... .... 
hopedorus
(T horne) p. 63 bips low, rounded .............................................................................................................................. 4
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4. Length about 1.0 mm................................................................................... 
vesuvianus
(C obb! p. 63 Length LS mm orover................... ...................................................................................... 5
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
5. Length near 1.5 mm ............................................................................... 
macrodorus
(de M a N) p. 62 Length near 2.5 mm....................................................................... 
groenianàüus
(D itlevsen) p- 64
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>6. Tail elongate conoid....................................................................... coMicawdatws i D Îtlevsen) p. 66 Tails bluntly conoid.......................................................................................................................... 7</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
7. Lips angular............................................................................................................... 
teres
n. sp. p. 64 Lips low rounded.................... -.................................................. • 8
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
8. Spear length equal to lip région width ............................................■-........................ 
laevis a.
sp. p. 65 Spear length twice lip région width.......................................,. analaftM (D itlevsen) p. 65
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
9. Tail blunt. straight........................................................................... 
conicauàaius
(D ttlevsen) p. 66
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
"Z
Tail arcuate, acute or subacute............................................................... ................................ 10
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
10. Cuticle marked by heavy transverse striac.................................... 
striatus
n. sp. p. 68 Cuticle comparative!y smooth ..................................... ...................................
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>1 1. Spear length about eqnal to lip région width..........................................................................- 12 Spear length about twice lip région width............................................ -...................... 13</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
12. Lips angular.......................... 
brevidenlatus
n. sp. p. 68 Lips rounded................................................- ..................................... awwlw n. sp. P- 67
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
13. Lips set olf by constriction..., 
......................................... mucrodoroides
(S teiner) p. 66 Lips continuons with neck contour.................................................... 
iaeroensis
(Dm.nvsEN) p. 67
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus macrodorus
(de M an, Ï 880) n. comb.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Synonyms: 
Dorylaimus macrodorus
deMan 1880 
Dorylaimus
(Doryllium} macrodorus
(deMan) Dïtlhvsen, 1920 
Dorylaimellus
macrodorus
(deMan) T horne &amp; 
Swanger
, 1936
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Plate IX, Fig. 68-68rf
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
?: 1.6 mm; a = 24-28; b 4.5-5; e = 62-77; V-1* 42.u tf: 1.5 mm; a = 28; b = 
5
; e — 67; T-50.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Body tapering gradually both ways from near middlc. Neck convex-conoid near lips, nairowing rapidly until lip région is only about half as wide as neck opposite spear base. Catide marked by minute transverse striac; fine radial striae visible, cspecially on taii. Latéral cords narrow, rarely wider than twice curicle width at mid-body. Latéral pores in two Unes. Amphids escutcheon shaped, apertures almost encompassing lips. Sensillae apparcntly dorylaimoid, located about opposite spear guiding ring. Lips low, obscure, completely amalgamated. Vestibule and pharynx surrounded by thick muscular bundlc. Spear massive, tripartite, flanged, occupying about one-fourth neck length. Guiding ring double. Esophagus suddcnly enlarged slightly anterior to middle. Esophagcal gland nuclei three; one dorsal, two submedian. Cardia elongatc-hemispherical. Intestine six ceUs in circumference; granules scattered, dark, mctallic appearing. Prerectum length four to five times body width. Rectum length equal to anal body diameter. Ovaries symmetricai, reflexed onc-half to two-thirds distance to vulva. Egg length one and one-half times body width, half as wide aslong. Vulva transverse, heavily cuticularized, Female rails hemisphcrical to bluntly conoid. Males rare, only a single one observed in Utall among over 100 females. Suppléments 1 2. rather uniformly spaced, three within range of spicula. Spicula dorylaimoid. Latéral guiding pièces tapering distally.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The above description from Utah specimens. Females apparently identical to thosc of deMan. European males described with 6-1 1 suppléments, only the first one of these within range of spicula. The uniform supplément arrangement of the single male from Utah scarcely warrants establishing of a varicty. European records give varying lengths: 9i 1.0-2.2 mm; 
J:
1.12-2.16 mm, with proportional mcasurenients varying grcatly, indicating that perhaps more than one specics is involved.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitat:
A cosmopolitan species from many European countries, The Faroes and Nova Zembla. Common at élévations of 8,000 to 12,000 fect in Wasatch and Uinta Mountains, Utah, U. S. A.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Référencés:
1.5, 42, 43. 45. 53. 59, 63, 73, 74, 78, 80, 84, 90, 96, 111, 118, 122, 123, 133, 139, 140, 144, 145, 147, 150, 152, 159.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus vesuvianus
(C obb, 1893) n. comb.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Synonyms: 
Dorylaimus
vesuvianus
C obb, 1893 
Dorylaimellus
vesuvi&amp;nus
(C obb, 1893) T horne &amp; S wanger, 1936
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Plate IX, Fig. 69-696
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>?: 1.1 mm; a = 22; b — S.6, e — 63; V- i0 48.ïfl; LO mm; a = 24; b — 5.6; e — 83; T-64</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Lip région low, rounded, completely amalgamated, set off by siight dépression, papillae not interfering with contour. Amphids broad, stirnip-shaped. Spear, exclusive of extension, one and one-half finies as long as lip région width. Spear extension almost twice as long as spear, the basal portion bearing flanges. Esophagus enlargcd in posterior two-fifths. Cardia hemispherical, bail as wide as esophagus base. Intestinal celte with scattered brown granules. Fcmale prerectum length about twice body width, rectum a little longer than anal body diameter. Ovaries reflexed about half way to vulva. Anterior ovary of one specimen outstrctched. Suppléments 10, rather uniformly spaced, the first within range of spicula. Spicule thick; massive. Latéral guiding pièces simple, straight. Female tail bluntly conoid, male rail rounded, only half as long as anal body diameter.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus vesuvianus
is closely related to 
E.
macrodorus
from which it differs in the proportionately longer sections of the spear extension and more rounded, lower lip région.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Above description and figures from Dr. C obb ’s original balsam preserved spécimens, two males, two females and eight young, which are now, February 1938, just as perfectly preserved as when prepared by that master technician in 1889.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitai:
Moss collectcd on sides of Mount Vesuvius, Italy.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Re /erences:
15, 94, 144, 152, 159.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus hopedorus
(T horne, 1929) n. comb.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Synonym: 
Dorylaimellus
hopedorus
T horne, 1929

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Plate IX, Fig. 70-706
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>$: L43 mm; a = 25; b = 4.7; e = 50; V-*8 51.28</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Lip région set off by siight constriction, the lips somewhat angular. Spear length about twice width of lip région. In cross section the basal flanges of the spear extensions are symmetrically arranged (fig. 70a). Esophagus distinctly set off irom spear, enlarged ncar middle by rather sudden expansion. Lumen of intestine containing masses of green, chlorophyll-like material. Ovaries symmetrical, reflexed about half way back to vulva. Eggs one and one-half finies as long as body width and one-third as wide as long, as many as four were observed in the uteri at one time. Prerectum length two to three times body width. The blunt, dorsally convex-conoid tail usually ’ contains '10- 15 pairs of saccate bodies similar to those of 
Pungentus.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Diagnosis: Enchodelus
with the abovc nieasuremcnts and general description. Most closcly related to 
E. macrodorus
from which it differs in the more angular lips, mid-body location of vulva and conoid tail.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitat:
About roots of alpine plants and moss, summit of Longs Peak, Colorado, U. 
S
. A., élévation 14,255 ft.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus groeniandicus
(D jtlevsen, 1937) n. comb.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Synonyms: 
Dorylaimellus {Doryllium) groeniandicus
Ditlhvsen, 1927 
Dorylaimellus groeniandicus
(Ditlevsek. 2927) T horne &amp; 
Swanger
. 1936
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Plate IX. Fig. 71
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>9: 2.5 mm; a — 25; b = 6.0; e — 50; V-43.3</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Similar to 
Enchodelus
macrodorus
but grcater in size: spear and flanged extensions equal in length, the basal flanges ovate in contour; esophagus slightly shorter. Ovaries short, symmetrical.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Prercctum length about four times body width. 
Habitai:
Bank of a brook, Disco, Greenland. 
Reicrences:
42
, 159.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus
teres
n. sp.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Plate IX, Fig. 72, 72a
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>$: 1.5 mm; a = 25; b = 5.0; e — 50; V-2i 50.21</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Lips rather angular, set off by slight dépréssion, onc-fourth as wide as neck base. Spear length onlv one and one-half times Hp région width. Esophagus enlargcd in posterior two-ïifths by graduai expansion. Subrnedian pair of esophageal glands located about midway between dorsal gland and esophagus base. Cardia cyiindricai. Intestinal cclls with fine brown granules. Prcrectum length twice body width, rectum a little longer than anal body diameter. Ovaries synunetrical, reflexed half way to vulva, Egg length equal to one and one-half times body width, one-third as wide as long. Tail bluntly conoid with about 50 saccate bodies on each side very similar to those in 
Pungentus.
Males unknown and gravid femaïes contained no sperms.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Diagnosis: Enchodelus
with the above measurements and general description. This 
species
is distinguished from ils closest relative, 
Enchodelus
brevidens,
by the more angular lip région and greater number of saccate caudal bodies. Described from specimens preserved in balsam.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitat:
Seventeen females from soil about roots of alpine plants, élévation 11,295 feet, summit of Loue Peak, near Draper, Utah, U. 
S
. A.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus laevis
n. sp.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Plate IX, Fig. 73, 
73a
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>2: 1.3 mm; a = 25; b - 4.7; e = 50; V-« 49.”</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Lip région set off by slight dépréssion, about one-fourth width of ne 
4
&gt; base, laps rounded, amalgamatcd. Amphids alrnost as vide as head, sensillae opposite 
spear
base
. Spear, exclusive of extension, as long as lip région width, the apcrturc occupying one-fourth its length. Spear extension
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
well cuticularizcd but not forming flanges, set off from esophagus by constriction. Esophagus cnlarged a littlc back of middle. Intestine with scattered granules in its cells, the lumen filled with green organic material. Prcrectum length about twice body width. Rectum slightly longer than anal body diameter. Ovaries long, rcfkxed two-thirds distance to vulva. Eggs not quitc twice as long as body width. Sperms in utérus indicate that males exist. About 
25
pairs of saccaie 
bodies
présent in the tail, similar to those of 
Pungentus.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Diagnosis: Enchodelus
with the above measurements and general description. Most closcly related to 

Enchodelus 
teres

from which il differs in shorter 
spear
and Jess conspicuous lips.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitat:
A single gravid femate from stream bank soil, Broad Run, near Leesburg, Virginia, U. 
S
. A.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus
analatus
(DlTLEVSEN, 1927) n. comb,

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Synonyme: 
Dorylaimus
[Doryllium)
analatus
DEtlevsek, 1927. 
Dorylaimellus analatus
(
Ditlevsen
, 1927) Thorne A Swanger, 1936. 
Plate IX, Fig. 74, 74«
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
2; 1.8 mm; a = 24.4; b = 5.0; e = 
55
; V-50.9
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Body tapering rapidly anteriorly. Lip région truncaic. lips indistinct, papillae tiny. Spear proper three-fourths as long as its extensions, which lack definite flanges. Esophagus at first very narrov, then éxpanding rather suddenly back of nerve ring. Intcstineat first about twice width of esophagus. Prerectum length only about equal to body diameter. Ovaries symmetrical.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus
analatus
differs from 
E.
macrodorus
in the lack of basal spear flanges. very short prerectum and more tapenng 
neck.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitat:
Moss, Kapisigdlit (Fjord of Godthaab), and Upcrnivjk, Groenland.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Référencés:
42
. 159.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus conicandafus
(D itlevsen, 1927)n. comb.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Synonyms: 
Dorylaimus
conwandalus
D itlevsen, 1927 
Dorylaimellus
conicaudalus
(DITLEVSEN, 1927) T horne &amp; 
S
wanger, 1936
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Plate IX, Fig, 75-756
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>$; 2.0 mm; a = 30; b =6.1; e = 30; V-42.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Spear slender, ont and one-fourth times as long as width of lip région. Head amalgamated until</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>neither lips nor papillae are obvions. Esophagus slender to inconspicuous nerve ring, then increasing to about one-third neck width. An elongate, pear-shapedbody is located ventrally just back of nerve ring. Prerectum about half as long as esophagus. Tail conica! to rounded tip, varyitig in acuteuess with different specimens. Ovaries short, symmetrical.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitat:
Moss collected at Kapisigdlk, Fjord of Godthaab, Greenland.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Référencés:
42, 159.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus macrodoroides
(S teiner, 1914) n. comb.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Synonyms: 
Dorylaimus
macrodoroides
S teiner, 1914 
Dorylaimellus macrodoroides
(S teiner, 1914) T horne &amp; S wanger, 1936
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Plate X, Fig. 76-766
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>$: 1.9 mm; a = 33; b = 5.2; e = 31; V-«4a.“</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Lip région amalgamated, set off by slight constriction. Spear proper about two and one-half times lip région width. Extensions rather conspicuously developed but without broad flanges. Posterior two-fifths of esophagus enlarged by graduai expansion until more than half neck width. Intestinal cells with dark brown, metallic appearing granules. Prerectum length four to five times body width. Rectum almost as long as tail. Ovaries symmetrical, reflexed one-half to two-thirds the distance back to vulva. Eggs about two and one-half times as long as body diameter. Tail slightly ventrally arcuate to small blunt terminus.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The principal differentiating characters of this species are spear length and typical tail form.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitat:
Described by S teiner (143) from wet humus, Airolo, Switzerland. A rather commun species from soil about roots of alpine plants collected on Loue Peak, Mt. Timpanogos, Devils Castle, Mt. Deseret and other mountain peaks in Utah, U. 
S
. A. One female in Dr. C obb 's collection from Casa Poëtae, Pompeii, Italy.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Référencés:
94, 143, 152, 159.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus jaeroensis
(DrrLEVSEN, 1928) n. comb.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Synonyms: 
Dorylaimus (Doryllium}
jaeroensis
D hievsek, 1928 
Dorylaimellus
jaeroensis
(D itlevsen, I 
928
j T horne &amp; S wanger, 1936
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Plate 
X

, 

Fig. 77, 
77a
o; 2.8 mm. a = 26.1; b — 6.0; e = 28.3; V-41
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Body tapering rapidly at both extremities. Lips obscure, set off by slight dépréssion. Two cirelets of easily visible papillac. Spear, inciuding extensions, equa] to about one-third neck length. Basal flanges of 
spear
narrow. Prerectum length about two and one-half times body width. Tail ventrally arcuatc. Terminus subacute.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus faeroensis
is distinctive because of the obscurely set off lip région, relatively more tapering extremities, short prerectum and 
greater
body length.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitat:
Svino, short of the 
larger
of the two lakes south of Mannaskard, Faroe Islands.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Référencés:
43, 159.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Enchodelus
arcuatus
n. sp.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Plate 
X

, 
Fig. 78, 78a
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
2: i.Smm; a = 29; b = 5.6; e = 25; V-» 
53
“
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Transverse striae rather coarse. Lips low, rounded, amalgamated, set off by slight dépréssion. Amphids wide and deep. Spear length, exclusive of extension, onc and one-half times lip région width. Spear extension and muscles surrounding it conspicuous but not fonning Ranges. Esophagus enlarged by graduai expansion just back of middie. Three esophagcal gland nuclei easily seen. Cardia elongate-hemispherical. Intestinal colis with fine brown granules. Rectum about as long as tail. Prerectum twicç length of rectum. Ovaries long, rcflexed about half way to vulva. Egg length one and one-third times body width. Tail conoid arcuate to small blunt terminus.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
DmgMiWîs: 
Enchodelus
with the above measurcmems and general description. Most ciosely' related to 
E.
nuicrodoroidcs
and 
E. brevidentatus,
differing in the form of lip région and relative proportions of spear. Above formula frorn gravid Virginia 
specimens
. Thosc from Arizona and Utah attaineti a length of 2 inm, vulva of Arizona females at 48%, tail a little more slender than lhat figured from Virginia.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Habitat:
One fcmale from soil, pine woods, Arlington Farm, Virginia, two from Kaibab Forest, Arizona, and three from sod, Tryal Lake, Uinta Mountains, Utah, 
U
. S. A.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
