<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of Crustacean Biology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jcbiol/ruad044</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Grazing activity of Clibanarius corallinus (H. Milne Edwards, 1848) (Decapoda: Anomura: Diogenidae) on epilithic algae in Australian coral reefs</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>11</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Clibanarius corallinus
(H. 
Milne Edwards, 1848
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Diogenidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Clibanarius corallinus
(H. 
Milne Edwards, 1848
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Acropora
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Clibanarius corallinus
(H. 
Milne Edwards, 1848
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Acropora
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Acropora
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Clibanarius corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Clibanarius corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Acropora
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Carolina Castro-Sanguino</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Grazing activity of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Clibanarius corallinus
(H. 
Milne Edwards, 1848
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
: Anomura: 
<tp:taxon-name>Diogenidae</tp:taxon-name>
) on epilithic algae in Australian coral reefs

</p>
         <p>
Henrique Bravo
1,2,
and 
Ian R. Tibbetts
1
</p>
         <p>
1
School of Biological Sciences
, The University of 
Queensland
, St Lucia, Brisbane, 
Queensland
4072, 
Australia
</p>
         <p>
2
Groningen
Institute for Evolutionary Life Sciences (GELIFES), University of 
Groningen
, 9700 CC 

Groningen
, 
The Netherlands
</p>
         <p>Correspondence:H.Bravo; e-mail: henrique.bravo@rug.nl</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A B ST R A CT
</title>
         <p>
Following an incidental observation of captive 
<tp:taxon-name>
Clibanarius corallinus
(H. 
Milne Edwards, 1848
)
</tp:taxon-name>
supposedly removing algae from each other’s shells, we conducted a feeding experiment over 72 hours to understand its potential role as a mesograzer in coral reef ecosystems. Epiphytecovered, coral rubble fragments of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acropora
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
were exposed to hermit crab (
N
= 41) activity for 72 h in a flow-through seawater aquarium system at Heron Island, southern Great Barrier Reef, 
Australia
to understand whether hermit crabs could remove epilithic algae and if so, to what extent. Coral fragments exposed to the hermit crabs had 9.1% less chlorophyll at the end of the experiment. The detritus generated in the experimental set-up had 2.4 times more chlorophyll and 33.4% less organic biomass than the detritus generated in the control environment. The crabs did on average lose 
0.11 g
of their initial weight, which could have been a consequence of the experimental set-up. These results suggest that 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
has the potential to contribute to the control of epilithic algae in coral reefs, with such effect having hitherto been overlooked as a result of the cryptic behaviour of this hermit crab species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
KEY WORDS:
Crustacea
, 
Great Barrier Reef
, 
Heron Island
, 
mesograzer
, 
reef flat
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
The extent and frequency of coral bleaching events have increased in recent years (

), resulting in coral mortality and coral populations lacking time to recover between bleaching events (

). Reef-associated species are consequently vulnerable, with their disappearance potentially resulting in ecosystem restructuring (

; 

). The Great Barrier Reef (GBR) has been seriously affected by recent bleaching events, with an estimated 91% of reefs suffering from bleaching and a loss of 30% of live coral cover (

), leading to a phase shift from hard coral to an algal-dominated system. Herbivory is thought not only to enhance reef resilience to phase shifts but also to assist reef recovery by reducing macroalgal biomass that could otherwise smother the corals (

; 

), and even open up spaces on which coral larvae can settle (

)
</p>
         <p>
Understanding the roles that different species play in reef ecosystems is important, not only to determine their potential role in coral reef resilience, but also their fate should coral reefs bleach and not recover (

; 

). Coral reef grazers have different impacts on the ecosystem depending on their distribution, biomass, size, and functional role (

; 

; 

). Grazing by herbivorous fishes is often considered a key driver of coral reef biodiversity and resilience (

) and it has even been shown that species of cryptic fishes can represent an important component of the total biomass of grazing fishes (

).
</p>
         <p>
Fishes are nevertheless not the only herbivores active in reef systems. Turtles (

), sea urchins (

), large brachyuran crabs (

), and even small invertebrates (

) can also regulate algal communities. These small invertebrates have the potential to influence the density and assemblage structure of different species of macroalgae (

), and can access spaces and microhabitats that larger species cannot, but their role in controlling algal recruitment and abundance is seldom considered.
</p>
         <p>
Typically defined as small herbivores (i.e., &lt;
2.5 cm
), mesograzers such as amphipods, gastropods, small crabs and shrimps can reach densities that have the potential to alter the biomass of epiphytes and algae on coral reefs, particularly in the absence of the larger macrograzers (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Among the diversity of reef mesograzers, hermit crabs have received little attention. It is thought that some species may contribute to ecosystem functioning through grazing (

) or through the use of mollusc shells that would otherwise have been buried by sediments, promoting shell turnover (

), which in turn can sustain a new community of epibiotic and endolithic species (

).
</p>
         <p>
In an unpublished study (IRT, unpublished data), individuals of the hermit crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
Clibanarius corallinus
(H. 
Milne Edwards, 1848
)
</tp:taxon-name>
captured from Heron Island’s reef flat were kept in a bare saltwater aquarium overnight. The following morning, their shell homes, which when placed in the aquarium had been covered with a coat of epilithic algae, were bare. Presumably the hermit crabs had removed the algae from each other’s shells during this period. This observation led us to hypothesise that these hermit crabs might contribute to reef grazing by feeding on epilithic algae.
</p>
         <p>
Here we report the results of a short-term aquarium-based experiment to determine whether 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
is a potential member of the reef mesograzer assemblage, because whilst there is evidence of a preference for epilithic algae in congeners in other environments (

; 

; 

), nothing has been reported for this particular species of hermit crab as of yet. Specifically, we estimated chlorophyll removed by the crabs, as a proxy for algal grazing. We hypothesised that treatments with hermit crabs would have less chlorophyll on the coral substrate and that hermit crabs would remove more organic biomass in the dislodged detritus than controls that lacked their presence.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
M AT E R I A L S A N D M ET H O D S
</title>
         <p>
Forty-one individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected from the near-shore reef flat in 
August 2014
on the southern shore of Heron Island (

23°26 
ʹ
35.5″S

, 

151°54 
ʹ
46.3″E

) where they are known to congregate in high numbers at low tide (

). The reef flat, where they are commonly found, is dominated by coarse carbonate sand and coral fragments with few live corals and is less than 
50 cm
in depth at low tide. In addition, 82 dead and epilithic algal-covered 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acropora
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
coral rubble fragments were collected from the same area in which the hermit crabs had been collected, since this is on what they were previously seen feeding during 
in vivo
observations.
</p>
         <p>
Crabs were placed in 41 individual 50 ml perforated plastic containers inside an aquarium that was located outdoors, in a shaded area, and that was constantly supplied with flow-through sea water drawn in from the reef flat to mimic natural conditions (Supplementary material 
Figs. S1
, S2). Food was withheld for 24 h prior to the start of the experiment to eliminate any previously consumed material and avoid any overestimation in chlorophyll in faeces from feeding activity prior to collection. The experimental period started when we placed a piece of dead coral fragment (
4–5 cm
) with its associated epilithic algae inside the plastic container. A plastic mesh was placed several centimetres above the bottom of the container to prevent the crabs from eating either the material dislodged from the coral or their own faeces.
</p>
         <p>
The remaining 41 coral fragments covered with dead and epilithic algae were also put in individual plastic containers to serve as controls to determine the quantity of detritus and faeces (potentially from boring fauna) attributable to the presence of hermit crabs. Estimates of the levels of chlorophyll at the end of the experiment were made by using a stainless-steel spatula to scrape 4 × 
1 cm
2
of epilithic algae and any associated detritus from the 82 coral fragments. The material removed was placed on a GF/C filter paper (Whatman™, Springfield Mill, 
UK
). Each filter paper was placed inside a vial with a 10 ml solution of 9:1 acetone/water to extract chlorophyll and then refrigerated in the dark at 4 
ºC
for 24 hours. The solution was filtered once again to remove any detritus. Three aliquots of 200 µl of the solution were then analysed using a spectrophotometer (model UV-1700, Shimadzu, 
Kyoto
, 
Japan
) and read at wavelengths of 
630 nm
, 
647 nm
and 
664 nm
, the peak absorption wavelengths for chlorophyll c2 and c1, chlorophyll b and chlorophyll a, respectively (

).
</p>
         <p>
Chlorophyll concentration in milligrams per square centimetre was calculated using an equation initially proposed by 

:
</p>
         <p>
solution volume (11.85 × OD 
664
− 1.54× Chla mg × 
cm−2
= OD647 − 0.08 × OD630) mg 
l− l
</p>
         <p>scraped surface area</p>
         <p>where OD is optical density.</p>
         <p>
The detritus from both the control and experimental containers was filtered, at the end of the 72 h, using a vacuum pump filtering system and GF/C filters (Whatman™). The filters had been pre-labelled with unique numbers using a pencil and their weight subsequently measured (± 
0.01 g
) in a low-humidity, acclimatised environment using a top loading balance. The process was repeated for the 82 samples after which each filter paper was folded twice to secure the sediments within and placed in an oven at 60 
ºC
for 24 h (following 

). The weight of the filter paper with the detritus was measured and the original weight of the filter paper was subtracted to determine the weight of the detritus. This was then placed in a vial with 10 ml of 9:1 acetone water solution to extract chlorophyll and refrigerated in the dark at 4 
ºC
for 24 h. The solution was once again filtered to remove any detritus and three replicates of 200 µl of the filtrate were analysed using a spectrophotometer at wavelengths of 
630 nm
, 
647 nm
, and 
664 nm
. The chlorophyll concentration in milligrams per gram was then calculated with the aforementioned equation replacing the “scraped surface area” with “detritus weight.”
</p>
         <p>
The detritus was placed in separate pre-weighed crucibles and weighed again before and after treatment in a muffle furnace (S.E.M, Ferntree Gully, 
Australia
) at 450 
ºC
for 4 h. Organic biomass that was originally present in the detritus was estimated by subtracting the final ash weight from the original detritus weight, obtaining an ash-free dry weight.
</p>
         <p>
Generalised linear models (GLM) were used to test for differences in the amount of chlorophyll present in the coral fragments, amount of chlorophyll in the detritus, and amount of organic biomass between the two treatments. The differences in weight of the crabs before and after the treatment was computed using a paired samples Wilcoxon test after checking for normality using a Shapiro-Wilk test. All statistical analyses were performed using R (R 

). Starting levels of chlorophyll and organic biomass were not measured due to the potential effects from handling.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
R E SU LTS
</title>
         <p>
The 41 individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
occupied shells that had an average length of 
26 mm
(± 
4.7 mm
) and were observed feeding both day and night using their chelipeds to remove material from the coral fragments. They were also observed feeding, in some instances, on dislodged detritus trapped in the plastic mesh near the base of the container.
</p>
         <p>
After 72 h, coral fragments that were exposed to individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
had significantly less chlorophyll than those in a control environment (Χ 
2
= 0.073, 
df
= 1, 
P
= 0.003; 
Fig. 1A
). Chlorophyll was, on average, 9.1% lower in the coral fragments grazed by hermit crabs.
</p>
         <p>
At the end of the experiment, there was more detritus generated, on average, in each of the containers with crabs (5.91 ± 3.21), compared to those in the control containers (5.07 ± 2.33). Mean chlorophyll in the detritus generated by the hermit crabs, faeces included, was more than double that in the control treatment (Χ 
2
= 0.052, 
df
= 1, 
P
&lt;0.001; 
Fig. 1B
). Chlorophyll was approximately 2.4 times higher in the detritus in the grazed treatment, having a mean of 
0.05 mg
g 
–1
(± 0.01) compared to a mean of 
0.02 mg
g 
–1
(± 0.01) in the control treatment.
</p>
         <p>
Hermit crabs were also responsible for a significant reduction of organic biomass in the detritus when compared to organic biomass in detritus in the control treatment (Χ 
2
= 0.088, 
df
= 1, 
P
= 0.003). The amount of organic biomass was 33.4% lower in the grazed treatment (
0.132 ± 0.407 g
) compared to the control treatment (0.198 ± 
0.133 g
; 
Fig. 1C
).
</p>
         <p>
The weight of the crabs before (4.55 ± 
2.80 g
) and after (4.44 ± 
2.70 g
) the treatmen, differed significantly (V = 755.5, 
df
= 40, 
P &lt;
0.001), which indicates that they lost on average 2.4% (
0.11 g
) of their initial weight over the course of the experiment (Supplementary material Fig. S3).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
</title>
         <p>
Many brachyuran crabs have generally been recognised as ecosystem engineers due to their capacity to modify habitats (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). Historically the role of hermit crabs (Anomura) in ecosystem engineering has been mostly attributed to their ability to recycle gastropod shells (

), but there are studies that highlight the potential of hermit crabs to actively graze on epilithic algae (

; 

), which can aid in the regulation of particular algal communities (

; 

) or even in maintaining coral reef health (

). Reef-dwelling hermit crabs can reduce the amount of algae growing on corals (

) and are able to feed on them when many other herbivorous species are not due to the toxic compounds that some algal species possess that affect most fauna (

), but not some species of brachyuran crab (

).
</p>
         <p>
Our data confirm that 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
can graze epilithic algae, and thereby potentially contribute to reef health. Such finding
</p>
         <p>

Sample 
type
</p>
         <p>
was based on both the observed behaviour of the hermit crabs and the amount of chlorophyll removed from the corals under the experimental condition in comparison to controls (
Fig. 1A
). Levels of chlorophyll in the detritus also validated this finding, with chlorophyll in the detritus under the experimental set-up having higher levels than that in the control setting. Detritus that accumulated during the experiment, which was protected from the hermit crabs but was possibly increased as a consequence of their active grazing, may include fragments of algae dislodged by crabs, undigested material in their faeces as well as algal growth due to nutrients and carbon dioxide excreted by the crabs, which could help explain the significantly higher amount of chlorophyll (
Fig. 1B
). The fact that organic biomass was also lower in the experimental condition is concurrent with the crabs being mesograzers and feeding on epilithic algae, since this difference in the detritus is most likely a consequence of absorption of organic matter and expelling inorganic matter in the faeces (
Fig. 1C
).
</p>
         <p>
The individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
we used were subject to food deprivation for a period of 24 h, an amount of time that can significantly decrease the weight of hermit crabs (

) and which can alter feeding preference (

). Hermit crabs in our experiment experienced a minor but statistically significant weight loss after 72 h (Supplementary material Fig. S3). Given that the weight loss was minimal and considering the coral rubble habitat in which these crabs were found, we suggest that epilithic algae are an important food source for the hermit crabs. The small weight loss could either be due to the absence of other food sources or to the 24-h food deprivation period. Food choice experiments would be required to identify other foods in the trophic repertoire of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
In this short-term feeding experiment, we showed that 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
can remove epilithic algae growing on dead coral fragments. These hermit crabs, for their part, can aid the reefs in regulating the growth of algae due to the crabs’ active grazing, potentially making this relationship a mutually beneficial one. Given the possibility of hermit crabs to access small spaces that other grazers cannot and their increased grazing activity when present in more exposed areas (

), it is expected that the role of this and other meso- and micrograzers (e.g., other species of crustaceans, molluscs, and other small invertebrates) has been overlooked when predicting food web dynamics in reef systems. Our study is therefore one of the few investigations that looks at the ecology of a particular grazing species providing information that can be useful for future studies, particularly in the field of whole-ecosystem studies or in predicting future ecosystem changes by looking at the functional traits of species that inhabit a specific habitat.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL
</title>
         <p>
Supplementary material is available at 
Journal of Crustacean Biology
online.
</p>
         <p>
S1 Figure. Aquarium showing individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Clibanarius corallinus
</tp:taxon-name>
and fragments of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acropora
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>S2 Figure. Plan view of the experimental set-up.</p>
         <p>S3 Figure. Boxplot with average weight of the 41 hermit crabs before (left) and after (right) the experiment. Individual crabs are depicted with points and the grey lines link their initial and final weights.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ACK N O W LE D G E M E N TS
</title>
         <p>
We thank Dr 
<tp:taxon-name>Carolina Castro-Sanguino</tp:taxon-name>
for her time, equipment and willingness to make this experiment possible, Catriona Glendinning for assistance with collection of hermit crabs, and the staff of Heron Island Research Station, particularly Science Officer Kathy La Fauce. We further thank the helpful and useful feedback from two anonymous reviewers and the Associate Editor, Dr Edwin Cruz-Rivera, which significantly improved the manuscript. The authors have no competing interests to declare that are relevant to the content of this article.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Altman-Kurosaki, N.T.
, 
Priest, M.A.
, 
Golbuu, Y.
, 
Mumby, P.J.
&amp; 
Marshell, A.
2018
. 
Microherbivores are significant grazers on Palau’s forereefs
. 

Marine Biology

, 

165

: 
1–11
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bellgrove, A.
, 
Monk, J.
&amp; 
Quinn, G.P.
2014
. 
Effects of micro- and mesograzers on intertidal macroalgal recruitment
. 

Marine Biology

, 

161

: 
1207–1216
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Benvenuto, C.
, 
Sartoni, G.
&amp; 
Gherardi, F.
2003
. 

Foraging behaviour of the hermit crab 
Clibanarius erythropus
in a Mediterranean shore

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 

83

: 
457–461
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bertness, M.D.
1985
. 

Fiddler crab regulation of 
Spartina alterniflora
production on a New England salt marsh

. 

Ecology

, 

66

: 
1042–1055
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bravo, H.
, 
Xu, T.
&amp; 
van der Meij, S.E.T.
2021
. 
Conservation of coral-associated fauna
. In: 

Imperiled: The encyclopedia of conservation

(
D. DellaSala
&amp; 
M. Goldstein
, eds), pp. 
665–672
. 
Elsevier, Amsterdam
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Brawley, S.H.
&amp; 
Adey, W.H.
1981
. 
The effect of micrograzers on algal community structure in a coral reef microcosm
. 

Marine Biology

, 

61

: 
167–177
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cannicci, S.
, 
Burrows, D.
, 
Fratini, S.
, 
Smith, T.J.
, 
Offenberg, J.
&amp; Dahdouh- 
Guebas, F.
2008
. 
Faunal impact on vegetation structure and ecosystem function in mangrove forests: A review
. 

Aquatic Botany

, 

89

: 
186–200
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Carpenter, R.C.
1997
. 
Invertebrate predators and grazers
. In: 

Life and death of coral reefs

(
C. Birkeland
, ed.), pp. 
198–229
. 
Chapman and Hall, New York
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Christiansen, N.A.
, 
Kemp, A.
&amp; 
Tibbetts I.R.
2010
. 
Are the oral teeth of combtooth blennies (Salariini: Teleostei) merely combs?

Environmental Biology of Fishes

, 

87

: 
205–216
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Coen, L.D.
1988
. 
Herbivory by crabs and the control of algal epibionts on Caribbean host corals
. 

Oecologia

, 

75

: 
198– 203
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cronin, G.
&amp; 
Hay, M.E.
1996
. 
Susceptibility to herbivores depends on recent history of both the plant and animal
. 

Ecology

, 

77

: 
1531–1543
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Glynn, P.W.
&amp; 
Enochs, I.C.
2011
. 
Invertebrates and their roles in coral reef ecosystems
. In: 

Coral reefs: An ecosystem in transition

(
Z. Dubinsky
&amp; 
N. Stambler
, eds.), pp. 
273–325
. 
Springer, Dordrecht, The Netherlands
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gutiérrez, J.L.
, 
Jones, C.G.
, 
Strayer, D.L.
&amp; 
Iribarne, O.O.
2003
. 
Mollusks as ecosystem engineers: The role of shell production in aquatic habitats
. 

Oikos

, 

101

: 
79–90
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hay, M. E.
&amp; 
Fenical, W.
1988
. 
Marine plant-herbivore interactions: the ecology of chemical defense
. 

Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics

, 

19

: 
111–145
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hughes, T.P.
1994
. 
Catastrophes, phase shifts, and large-scale degradation of a Caribbean coral reef
. 

Science

, 

265

: 
1547–1551
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hughes, T.P.
, 
Anderson, K.D.
, 
Connolly, S.R.
, 
Heron, S.F.
, 
Kerry, J.T.
, 
Lough, J.M.
, 
Baird, A.H.
, 
Baum, J.K.
, 
Berumen, M.L.
, 
Bridge, T.C.
, 
Claar, D.C.
, 
Eakin, C.M.
, 
Gilmour, J.P.
, 
Graham, N.A.
, 
Harrison, H.
, 
Hobbs, J.P.A.
, 
Hoey, A.S.
, 
Hoogenboom, M.
, 
Lowe, R.J.
, 
McCulloch, M.T.
, 
Pandolfi, J.M.
, 
Pratchett, M.
, 
Schoepf, V.
, 
Torda, G.
&amp; 
Wilson, S.K.
2018
a. 
Spatial and temporal patterns of mass bleaching of corals in the Anthropocene
. 

Science

, 

359

: 
80–83
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hughes, T.P.
, 
Kerry, J.T.
, 
Álvarez-Noriega, M.
, 
Álvarez-Romero, J.G.
, 
Anderson, K.D.
, 
Baird, A.H.
, 
Babcock, R.C.
, 
Beger, M.
, 
Bellwood, D.R.
, 
Berkelmans, R.
, 
Bridge, T.C.
, 
Butler, I.R.
, 
Byrne, M.
, 
Cantin, N.E.
, 
Comeau, S.
, 
Connolly, S.R.
, 
Cumming, G.S.
, 
Dalton, S.J.
, Diaz- 
Pulido, G.
, 
Eakin, C.M.
, 
Figueira, W.F.
, 
Gilmour, J.P.
, 
Harrison, H.B.
, 
Heron, S.F.
, 
Hoey, A.S.
, 
Hobbs, J.P. A.
, 
Hoogenboom, M.O.
, 
Kennedy, E.V.
, 
Kuo, C.Y.
, 
Lough, J.M.
, 
Lowe, R.J.
, 
Liu, G.
, 
McCulloch, M.T.
, 
Malcolm, H.A.
, 
McWilliam, M.J.
, 
Pandolfi, J.M.
, 
Pears, R.J.
, 
Pratchett, M.S.
, 
Schoepf, V.
, 
Simpson, T.
, 
Skirving, W.J.
, 
Sommer, B.
, 
Torda, G.
, 
Wachenfeld, D.R.
, 
Willis, B.L.
&amp; 
Wilson, S.K.
2017
. 
Global warming and recurrent mass bleaching of corals
. 

Nature

, 

543

: 
373–377
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hughes, T.P.
, 
Kerry, J.T.
, 
Baird, A.H.
, 
Connolly, S.R.
, 
Dietzel, A.
, 
Eakin, C.M.
, 
Heron, S.F.
, 
Hoey, A.S.
, 
Hoogenboom, M.O.
, 
Liu, G.
, 
Mcwilliam, M.J.
, 
Pears, R.J.
, 
Pratchett, M.S.
, 
Skirving, W.J.
, 
Stella, J.S.
&amp; 
Torda, G.
2018
b. 
Global warming transforms coral reef assemblages
. 

Nature

, 

556

: 
492–496
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jeffrey, S.W.
&amp; 
Humphrey, G.F.
1975
. 

New spectrophotometric equations for determining chlorophylls a, b, c1 and c 
2 in
higher plants, algae and natural phytoplankton

. 

Biochemie und Physiologie der Pflanzen

, 

167

: 
191–194
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kuempel, C. D.
&amp; 
Altieri, A. H.
2017
. 
The emergent role of small-bodied herbivores in pre-empting phase shifts on degraded coral reefs
. 

Scientific Reports

, 
7
: [
https://doi.org/10.1038/srep39670]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kunze J.
&amp; 
Anderson, D.T.
1979
. 

Functional morphology of the mouthparts and gastric mill in the hermit crabs 
Clibanarius taeniatus
(Milne Edwards), 
Clibanarius virescens
(Krauss), 
Paguristes squamosus
Mcculloch and 
Dardanus setifer
(Milne-Edwards) (Anomura: Paguridae)

. 

Marine and Freshwater Research

, 

30

: 
683–722
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Laidre, M.E.
&amp; 
Elwood, R.W.
2008
. 

Motivation matters: cheliped extension displays in the hermit crab, 
Pagurus bernhardus
, are honest signals of hunger

. 

Animal Behaviour

, 

75

: 
2041–2047
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Larkum, A.W.D.
, 
Douglas, S.
&amp; 
Raven, J.A.
(eds.). 
2012
. 

Photosynthesis in algae. Advances in Photosynthesis and Respiration
, 
Vol. 14

. 
Kluwer, Dordrecht, The Netherlands
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Milne Edwards, H.
1848
. 
Note sur quelques nouvelles espèces du genre Pagure
. 

Annales des Sciences Naturelles, Zoologie

, 

3

: 
59–64
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mumby, P.J.
2006
. 
The impact of exploiting grazers (Scaridae) on the dynamics of Caribbean coral reefs
. 

Ecological Applications

, 

16

: 
747–769
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mumby, P.J.
, 
Steneck, R.S.
, 
Adjeroud, M.
&amp; 
Arnold, S.N.
2016
. 
High resilience masks underlying sensitivity to algal phase shifts of Pacific coral reefs
. 

Oikos

, 

125

: 
644–655
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Munday, P.L.
, 
Van Herwerden, L.
&amp; 
Dudgeon, C.L.
2004
. 
Evidence for sympatric speciation by host shift in the sea
. 

Current Biology

, 

14

: 
1498–1504
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pearson, R.M.
, 
Jinks, K.I.
, 
Brown, C.J.
, 
Schlacher, T.A.
&amp; 
Connolly, R.M.
2018
. 
Functional changes in reef systems in warmer seas: Asymmetrical effects of altered grazing by a widespread crustacean mesograzer
. 

Science of the Total Environment

, 

644

: 
976–981
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
R 
Core Team
. 
2019
. 
R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing
, 
Vienna, Austria
[
https://www.R-project.org/]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ruesink, J.L.
2000
. 
Intertidal mesograzers in field microcosms: Linking laboratory feeding rates to community dynamics
. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

248

: 
163–176
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Spadaro, A.J.
&amp; 
Butler, M. J.
2021
. 
Herbivorous crabs reverse the seaweed dilemma on coral reefs
. 

Current Biology

, 

31

: 
853–859
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stachowicz, J.J.
&amp; 
Hay, M.E.
1999
. 
Mutualism and coral persistence: The role of herbivore resistance to algal chemical defense
. 

Ecology

, 

80

: 
2085–2101
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stella, J.S.
, 
Pratchett, M.S.
, 
Hutchings, P.A.
&amp; 
Jones, G.P.
2011
. 
Coralassociated invertebrates: Diversity, ecological importance and vulnerability to disturbance
. 

Oceanography and Marine Biology: An Annual Review

, 

49

: 
43–104
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stuart-Smith, R.D.
, 
Brown, C.J.
, 
Ceccarelli, D.M.
&amp; 
Edgar, G.J.
2018
. 
Ecosystem restructuring along the Great Barrier Reef following mass coral bleaching
. 

Nature

, 

560

: 
92–96
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Townsend, K.A.
&amp; 
Tibbetts, I.R.
2004
. 
The ecological significance of the combtoothed blenny in a coral reef ecosystem
. 

Journal of Fish Biology

, 

65

: 
77–90
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Tran, M. 

V. 
2014


. 
Coexisting generalist scavengers occupy different feeding niches
. 

Marine Biology

, 

161

: 
2589–2596
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tudge, C.C.
1995
. 

Hermit crabs of the Great Barrier Reef and coastal Queensland

. 
School of Marine Science, The University of Queensland, Brisbane, QLD, Australia
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wabnitz, C.C.
, 
Balazs, G.
, 
Beavers, S.
, 
Bjorndal, K.A.
, 
Bolten, A.B.
, 
Christensen, V.
, 
Hargrove, S.
&amp; 
Pauly, D.
2010
. 

Ecosystem structure and processes at Kaloko Honokōhau, focusing on the role of herbivores, including the green sea turtle 
Chelonia mydas

, in 
reef resilience
. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series

, 

420

: 
27–44
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Webster, F.J.
, 
Babcock, R.C.
, 
Van Keulen, M.
&amp; 
Loneragan, N.R.
(
2015
). 
Macroalgae inhibits larval settlement and increases recruit mortality at Ningaloo Reef, Western Australia
. 

PLoS ONE

, 

10

(
4
): [
https://doi. org/10.1371/journal.pone.0124162]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Williams, J.D.
&amp; 
McDermott, J.J.
2004
. 
Hermit crab biocoenoses: A worldwide review of the diversity and natural history of hermit crab associates
. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

305

: 
1–128
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
