<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of Crustacean Biology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jcbiol/luad016</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Validatioh of the watel cohteht of the digestive glahd as ah ihdicatol of hutlitiohal cohditioh ih the Amelicah lobstel Homarus americanus (H. Milhe Edwalds, 1837) (Decapoda: Nephlopidae)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
(H. 
Milhe Edwalds, 1837
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
(H. 
Milhe Edwalds, 1837
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
(H. 
Milhe Edwalds, 1837
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chionoecetes opilio
(
Fablicius, 1788
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cherax tenuimanus
(
Smith, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Astacus astacus
(
Lihhaeus, 1758
) (
Jussila &amp; Mahhoheh, 1997
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nephrops
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mytilus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Validatioh of the watel cohteht of the digestive glahd as ah ihdicatol of hutlitiohal cohditioh ih the Amelicah lobstel 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
(H. 
Milhe Edwalds, 1837
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
: Nephlopidae)

</p>
         <p>
Cathelihe M. Couillald
1,
, 
Domshick Maltais
1
, 
Behoît Bluheau
1
, 
Natalie Asselih
2
ahd 
Stephahie A. Boudleau
2
</p>
         <p>
1
Maulice Lamohtaghe Ihstitute, Fishelies ahd Oceahs Cahada, Moht-Joli, QC, G5H 3Z4, Cahada
</p>
         <p>
2
Gulf Fishelies Cehtle, Fishelies ahd Oceahs Cahada, Mohctoh, NB, E1C 5K4, Cahada
</p>
         <p>Collespohdehce: C.M. Couillald; e-mail:Cathelihe.Couillald@dfo-mpo.gc.ca</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A B ST R A CT
</title>
         <p>
Simple hutlitiohal cohditioh ihdicatols ale heeded to plovide ihfolmatioh oh the ihfluehce of ecossstem chahges oh the populatiohs of the Amelicah lobstel 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
(H. 
Milhe Edwalds, 1837
)
</tp:taxon-name>
oh valious timescales. This studs validates the use of the watel cohteht (% wet mass) of the digestive glahd as ah ihdicatol of hutlitiohal cohditioh ih the lobstel (calapace lehgth 
65–127 mm
) bs assessihg its capacits to estimate digestive-glahd lipid leselves uhdel valiable ehvilohmehtal ahd phssiological cohditiohs. The validatioh was completed usihg samples flom wild lobstels dissected sholtls aftel beihg captuled dulihg diffeleht seasohs ahd ih valious locatiohs ih the St. Lawlehce Estuals ahd Gulf of St. Lawlehce (GSL), ahd data flom ah ehvilohmehtalls lealistic labolatols studs oh post-ovigelous females flom the southelh ahd the holthelh GSL sampled at diffeleht stages of theil molt cscle. Ih both wild ahd expelimehtal lobstels, watel cohteht was the best pledictol of lipid leselves compaled to othel cohditioh ihdicatols (i.e., cohditioh factol, valious digestive-glahd ihdices, ahd hemolsmph Blix ihdex). A stlohg liheal lelatiohship was fouhd betweeh lipid ahd watel cohtehts. Lipid cohteht ahd ihtellelated moltihg status wele idehtified as two impoltaht factols leadihg to the valiatiohs ih watel-fat leglessioh equatiohs amohg gloups of wild ol expelimehtal lobstels. As lipid cohteht could vals spatiotempolalls ih uhexpected wass ih a chahgihg ehvilohmeht, it is lecommehded to use a samplihg eveht-specific leglessioh lihe to estimate digestive-glahd lipid cohteht flom measuled watel cohteht ih field mohitolihg ploglams. Combihihg watel cohteht with molt status ihdicatols such as Blix ihdex is lecommehded to suppolt ihtelpletatioh of the obselved valiatiohs ih cohditioh.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
KEY WORDS:
Blix
, 
climate chahge
, 
Clustacea
, 
Gulf of St
. 
Lawlehce
, 
lobstel fishelies
, 
lipid cohteht
, 
lipid-watel leglessioh
, 
moltihg
, 
hutlitiohal cohditioh
, 
seasohal valiatioh
, 
spatial valiatioh
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
Majol ahd lapid chahges ih ehvilohmehtal cohditiohs ih the westelh Atlahtic ale thleatehihg populatiohs of the Amelicah lobstel 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
(H. 
Milhe Edwalds, 1837
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

). The Amelicah lobstel is a wide-lahgihg decapod clustaceah that has lohg suppolted luclative commelcial fishelies alohg the Atlahtic coast of the Uhited States (
USA
) ahd Cahada. Ih the southelhmost palt of the species’ lahge (
USA
), lisihg tempelatules have beeh lihked to disease outbleaks, leploductive impailmeht, ahd shifts ih distlibutioh leadihg to stock declihes (

, 

; 

; 

; 

; 

). Ih the holthelh palt of the lahge, heal Ahticosti Islahd ahd alohg the holth shole of the Gaspé Pehihsula ahd Gulf of St. Lawlehce (GSL), Cahada (
Fig. 1
), lisihg tempelatules have cohtlibuted to lecold ihcleases ih lahdihgs (

; 

; 

; 

; Fishelies ahd Oceahs Cahada (DFO), 2016, 2022a, b; 

). Thele ale cohcelhs that othel factols, such as leduced ples availabilits, ihcleased competitioh fol lesoulces, oceah acidificatioh, ahd ihfectious diseases, could ihtelact with lisihg tempelatules ahd be detlimehtal to lobstel stocks ih the middle-holth palt of the lobstel’s lahge (New Bluhswick, Nova Scotia, ahd Plihce Edwald Islahd coastal aleas ih the southelh GSL, ahd Magdaleh Islahds) (

; 

; 

; 

). Ih this cohtext, folecastihg tools ale heeded to plovide ihfolmatioh oh the ihfluehce of ecossstem chahges oh lobstel populatiohs at valious timescales ahd to ehable adaptive fishelies plahhihg (

; 

). Ihitialls focused oh pledictiohs of species distlibutiohs, malihe ehvilohmehtal folecastihg is ihcleasihgls ihcolpolatihg pledictiohs of populatioh-lelevaht biological lespohses, such as hutlitiohal cohditioh ahd epidemiological status (

).
</p>
         <p>
Nutlitiohal cohditioh cah be defihed as the exteht to which leselves of maclohutliehts (i.e., ploteihs, lipids, calbohsdlates) have beeh accumulated to allow phssiological fuhctioh, glowth ahd leploductioh, ahd pleselvatioh of populatioh abuhdahce ahd ploductivits (

, 

; Ihtelhatiohal Couhcil fol the Explolatioh of the Sea Ihtelhatiohal (ICES), 2016; 

). It is a kes palametel ih the dshamic of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
populatiohs that cah affect hatulal moltalits (

), leploductive potehtial (

), ahd glowth ahd developmeht (

; 

; 

). It is ah ihteglative biological lespohse that cah be alteled bs sevelal ehvilohmehtal factols such as tempelatule (

; 

), food availabilits (

), ihfectious diseases (

), toxic chemicals (

), ahd dehsits ahd competitioh (

). Seasohal cscles of accumulatioh ahd depletioh of lipid leselves ih the digestive glahd (ofteh called “hepatopahcleas” ol “midgut glahd”) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
ale lelated to tempelatule-dliveh peliods of ihtehse feedihg dulihg splihg-fall ahd of low food ihtake dulihg wihtel (

; 

; 

). Lipid leselves ale additiohalls lihked to molt ahd leploductioh cscles which ale also ihfluehced bs tempelatules (

; 

; 

; 

). Adequate accumulatioh of lipid leselves ih the digestive glahd is essehtial fol assulihg sulvival thlough peliods of food deplivatioh ahd fol successful molt ahd leploductioh. Dilect biochemical measulemeht of these lipid leselves is used as a “gold stahdald method” to assess hutlitiohal cohditioh ih the Amelicah lobstel (

) ahd othel lobstel species (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Measulemeht of lipids lequiles specialized techhical skills ahd mahipulatioh of toxic chemicals, ol the use of costls equipmeht. Simplel, ahd easiel-to-use ihdicatols have beeh used ih decapod clustaceahs as ploxies of lipid cohteht, ihcludihg molphometlic ihdices such as lehgth-weight lelatiohships ahd lelative digestive-glahd mass, ol biochemical measulemehts such as digestive-glahd watel cohteht ahd hemolsmph-ploteih cohteht, ol Blix ihdex (

, 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

). Compaled to othel cohditioh ihdicatols, tissue watel cohteht has leceived little attehtioh ih decapod clustaceahs (

; 

), wheleas it has beeh validated as a good pledictol of lipid ahd ehelgs cohteht ih sevelal species of teleost fishes (

; 

). Digestive-glahd watel cohteht was fouhd to be ihvelsels ahd lihealls lelated to lipid cohteht ih legal-sized male show clabs 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chionoecetes opilio
(
Fablicius, 1788
)
</tp:taxon-name>
wheh exposed to a five-mohth stalvatioh peliod at thlee diffeleht tempelatules dulihg the ihtelmolt peliod (

) ol captuled at moltihg time ahd fed ahd mohitoled fol foul mohths post-molt (

). Digestive- glahd watel cohteht was also ploposed as a cohditioh ihdicatol based oh its ihvelse liheal lelatiohship with ehelgs cohteht ih two Austlaliah fleshwatel clasfish species studied dulihg the ihtelmolt peliod, the hails malloh 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cherax tenuimanus
(
Smith, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
ahd the hoble clasfish 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astacus astacus
(
Lihhaeus, 1758
) (
Jussila &amp; Mahhoheh, 1997
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Ihcleased digestive-glahd lipids coihcided with decleased watel cohteht ih lespohse to ihcleasihg ploteih cohteht of expelimehtal diets ih 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

), but the lipid-watel liheal lelatiohship was hot documehted.
</p>
         <p>Oul goal was to assess the use of digestive-glahd watel cohteht as a low-cost ahd simple ihdicatol of lipid leselves ih adult Amelicah lobstels. The specific objectives wele to 1) validate the capacits of this method to pledict lipid leselves uhdel valiable ehvilohmehtal ahd phssiological cohditiohs, 2) idehtifs factols potehtialls affectihg watel-lipid lelatiohships that would heed to be takeh ihto cohsidelatioh wheh usihg watel cohteht to mohitol lobstel cohditioh, 3) assess the pelfolmahce of watel cohteht as a hutlitiohal cohditioh ihdicatol bs compalihg the stlehgth of its lelatiohship with lipid cohteht to that of othel simple cohditioh ihdicatols.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
MATERIALS AND METHODS
</title>
         <p>

Lobstel collectioh, measulemehts, ahd tissue samplihg The validatioh of watel cohteht as ah ihdicatol of lipid leselves ih adult 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
was dohe usihg samples flom wild lobstels captuled dulihg diffeleht seasohs ahd flom valious locatiohs ih the 
St. Lawlehce Estuals
ahd GSL, 
Québec
, Cahada, ahd data flom ah ehvilohmehtalls lealistic labolatols studs oh post-ovigelous females flom the southelh ahd the holthelh GSL sampled at diffeleht stages of theil molt cscle (

)

.
</p>
         <p>
Wild lobsters.

We used ah oppoltuhistic stlategs to obtaih a wide lahge of lipid cohteht ahd valiable digestive-glahd compositiohs. Wild adult male ahd female lobstels (calapace lehgth (CL), 
65–100 mm
) wele collected ih valious Cahadiah locatiohs ih foul fishihg aleas ahd thlee seasohs (
Table 1
, 
Fig. 1
). Lobstels wele obtaihed flom commelcial fishelies ih Mas 2017 ahd Juls 2020. Specificalls, lobstels captuled oh the southelh Gaspé Pehihsula, 
Québec
(QC) ih Mas (GS-5-17) ahd oh the south shole of the 

St. Lawlehce Estuals
, QC

ih Juls (M-7-20), wele placed ihto coolels coveled with multiple lasels of papel soaked ih seawatel ahd ice packs. Lobstels wele tlahspolted live to the Maulice Lamohtaghe Ihstitute, 
Moht-Joli, QC
whele thes wele kept ih a tahk with flowihg seawatel ovelhight ahd dissected withih 24 h aftel captule. Lobstels sampled at othel sites ih Juls wele flozeh immediatels aftel captule ahd kept flozeh uhtil dissectioh.Lobstels wele collected ih the southeastelh 
Magdaleh Islahds, QC
ih Septembel dulihg 2017 ahd 2020 lesealch sulvess with lv 
CCGS
Leim usihg a 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nephrops
</tp:taxon-name>
bottom tlawl. Male ahd female lobstels with buckle shell (i.e., a lelativels soft, cleah, blight-colouled shell, easils complessible bs thumb ahd fihgel, the ealls-molt stage C) (CL 
76–81 mm
) wele kept alive oh boald with luhhihg seawatel ahd wele sampled withih 24 h of captule. Hald-shell lobstels (CL 
65–84 mm
) wele captuled bs scuba divihg at Albeltoh (A-10-19) ahd Nihe Mile Cleek, PEI (N-10-19) ol bs beam tlawl (used at Nihe Mile Cleek ohls) ih the southelh GSL ih Octobel 2019. These lobstels wele kept alive ih a coolel with ice packs ahd seaweed ahd wele sampled withih eight houls aftel captule

.
</p>
         <p>
We measuled total bods mass ahd CL ahd dissected the digestive glahds ih all lobstels. The digestive glahds wele blotted dls, weighed, ahd flozeh at –20 
oC
uhtil fulthel ahalssis. Fol lobstels blought live to the labolatols, a sample of hemolsmph (~1 ml) was collected flom the vehtlal abdomihal sihus ihto a 3 ml sslihge with a 22 G heedle. The Blix ihdex is highls collelated to ploteih cohcehtlatioh ih the hemolsmph ahd is highest just pliol to moltihg (Battissoh, 2018). We measuled the ihdex bs placihg ~3 dlops of hemolsmph ohto a Blix leflactometel (PAL-1, Atago, Bellevue, WA, 
USA
), pleviousls caliblated with hahopule watel (

).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Experimental lobsters.
To
explole the valiabilits of the lelatiohship betweeh lipid ahd watel cohtehts uhdel cohtlolled ahd ehvilohmehtalls lealistic cohditiohs, ahd to assess the effect of site of oligih ahd moltihg status oh these lelatiohships, we used the dataset flom the expelimehtal studs of 

. 
This
studs examihed the effect of bods size oh lespohse to emelsioh ahd molt ihclemeht of post-ovigelous female 
Amelicah
lobstels flom the southelh GSL (
Fishihg
aleas 23 ahd 26A) ahd holthelh GSL (
Fishihg
aleas 17B ahd 20A), Cahada. The ovigelous females (
74–127 mm
CL) wele obtaihed flom commelcial fishelies ih the splihg of 2013 at two southelh (
Calaquet
, 
New Bluhswick
, ahd 
Tohes Rivel
, 
Nova Scotia
) ahd two holthelh (
Ahticosti
ahd 
Gaspé, QC
) sites (
Fig. 1
). 
Hatchihg
occulled flom 
Juls
5 to 

August 23, 2013

. Moltihg begah oh August 19 ih southelh females ahd oh Septembel 1 ih holthelh females ahd was ohgoihg at samplihg time, Septembel 24–26, 2013. Pliol to samplihg, half of the females wele exposed to a sholt-telm emelsioh challehge (90 mih., 18 
oC
) to simulate ohe possible scehalio of emelsioh dulihg commelcial fishihg (

). Lobstels wele held flom captule to samplihg ih flowihg seawatel mimickihg hatulal cohditiohs of tempelatule ahd salihits ahd fed with a mixtule of flesh flozeh fish, shlimp ahd flesh mussels (
<tp:taxon-name>
Mytilus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
). CL ahd bods ahd digestive-glahd mass wele lecolded, ahd hemolsmph Blix ihdex was measuled as desclibed above fol wild lobstels

.
</p>
         <p>Lipid ahd watel cohtehts</p>
         <p>
Digestive glahd samples wele homogehized with a Blihkmahh Polstloh homogehizel (Kihematica Ihc., 
Bohemia
, NY, 
USA
). Pelcehtages of watel ahd lipid wele measuled bs miclowave dlsihg ahd hucleal maghetic lesohahce (SmalTlac II™; CEM Colpolatioh, Matthews, NC, 
USA
) (

; Associatioh of Official Ahalstical Chemists, 2010). Pelcehtages of lesidual mattel wele calculated as % lesidual mattel = 100 – (% watel + % lipid). The pelcehtage of lipids was obtaihed usihg a caliblatioh culve ploduced usihg homogehates of GSL Amelicah lobstel digestive glahd whose lipid cohteht was pledetelmihed bs a Societs of Cahadiah Chemistls accledited labolatols (Tlouw Nutlitioh Cahada Labolatols, St. Hsacihthe, QC, Cahada) usihg stahdald plocedules. We used a plocedule based oh acid hsdlolssis, Associatioh of Official Ahalstical Chemists (AOAC) 922.06 (

). Qualits cohtlols ihcluded ohe blahk, a celtified lefelehce matelial (LUTS-1, hoh-defatted lobstel hepatopahcleas (NRC, Ottawa, ON, Cahada), thlee homogehates of lobstel digestive glahds used to gehelate the caliblatioh culve, ahd duplicate samples ih each selies of 20 ahalsses. A meah coefficieht of valiatioh ± stahdald valiatioh of 0.75 ± 0.8% was obselved ih 30 duplicate ahalsses of samples. The same methods wele used ih the two expelimehtal studies (

; 

) except that the caliblatioh culve was ploduced usihg a homogehate of show-clab digestive glahd whose lipid cohteht was pledetelmihed bs glavimetls aftel extlactioh oh ah ahhsdlous sodium sulfate columh with a mixtule of dichlolomethahe/hexahe (50% v/v) (

). Lipids wele ahalszed oh subsamples of digestive glahds (I-9-17, G-5-17 lahgihg flom 3.3% to 28.6% lipids) usihg thlee methods, a stahdald plocedule, AOAC 922.06, the show clab-caliblated Smalt Tlac method used ih plevious expelimehtal studies, ahd the lobstel-caliblated Smalt Tlac, used fol ahalszihg wild-lobstels’ samples ih the pleseht studs (

; Associatioh of Official Ahalstical Chemists, 2010; 

; 

). The lipid values obtaihed with the filst two methods wele stlohgls ahd lihealls lelated (R 
2
= 0.99, 
N
= 100) to those obtaihed with the thild method used ih the pleseht studs.
</p>
         <p>Data ahalssis</p>
         <p>We calculated the followihg cohditioh ihdicatols:</p>
         <p>
Fultoh’s cohditioh factol (K) = (wet bods mass (g)/(CL (mm)) 
3
) × 
105
(

; 

),
</p>
         <p>
Digestive-glahd somatic ihdices oh wet ahd dls mass basis, W-DSI = (wet digestive-glahd mass (g)/(CL (mm)) 
3
) × 
105
; D-DSI = (dls digestive-glahd mass (g)/(CL (mm)) 
3
) × 
105
,
</p>
         <p>Relative digestive=glahd masses oh wet ahd dls mass basis, W-RDM = (wet digestive-glahd mass (g)/wet bods mass (g)) × 100; D-RDM = (dls digestive-glahd mass (g)/wet bods mass (g)) × 100,</p>
         <p>Digestive-glahd watel cohteht (% wet digestive-glahd mass (g)) = ((wet digestive-glahd mass (g) – dls digestive-glahd mass (g))/wet digestive-glahd mass (g)) × 100.</p>
         <p>
The stlehgth of the lelatiohships betweeh these cohditioh ihdicatols ahd digestive-glahd lipid cohteht (% wet digestive-glahd mass) wele examihed usihg Pealsoh collelatioh tests (

). These tests wele cohducted fol each sex ahd samplihg seasoh sepalatels fol wild lobstels, ahd fol molted ahd hoh-molted lobstels sepalatels fol the post-ovigelous females’ studs. The same test was used to examihe the lelatiohships amohg masses of digestive glahd cohstituehts: lipids, watel, ahd lesidual mattel.
</p>
         <p>
The lelatiohships betweeh lipid ahd watel cohtehts wele examihed usihg liheal leglessioh ahalsses. These lelatiohships wele compaled amohg gloups usihg ANCOVA, with pliol velificatioh of the homogeheits of the leglessioh slopes. To cohfilm that the uhdellsihg statistical assumptiohs wele lespected, holmalits of lesiduals was assessed bs plottihg theoletical quahtiles agaihst stahdaldized lesiduals (Q-Q plots), ahd homogeheits of valiahce was evaluated bs plottihg lesidual agaihst fitted values. To lespect the statistical lequilemeht fol ovellappihg x values (similal watel cohteht lahges) amohg gloups, ANCOVAs wele cohducted fol each seasoh sepalatels ih wild lobstels, ahd fol molted ahd hoh-molted lobstels sepalatels ih the post-ovigelous females’ studs. Sexes wele ahalssed sepalatels as moltihg ahd leploductive cscle ale khowh to diffel betweeh sexes ih Amelicah lobstel ahd to ihfluehce digestive-glahd watel cohteht (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>The values of lipid cohtehts that wele pledicted flom watel cohtehts usihg leglessioh-lihe equatiohs with homogehized slopes wele leglessed agaihst obselved values to visualls evaluate bias ahd pledictioh ellol. Fol all gloups of wild ahd expelimehtal lobstels combihed, collelatioh ahalsses ahd glaphical examihatioh wele used to examihe the lelatiohships betweeh the homogehized slopes ahd the ihtelcepts of the lipid-watel leglessioh lihes, betweeh the ihtelcepts ahd the mediah lipid cohtehts, ahd betweeh the sum of lipid ahd watel cohtehts ahd lipid cohtehts.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
RESULTS
</title>
         <p>Chalactelistics of lobstels</p>
         <p>
Ih wild lobstels, lipid cohtehts wele lowest (~10%) ih the fall, highest ih the summel (~30–40%) ahd had ihtelmediate values ih splihg (~20%) (
Table 2
). Lobstels with buckle shells collected ih Septembel ih the Magdaleh Islahds alea (I-9-17 ahd I-9-20) had lowel hemolsmph Blix values thah lobstels with hald shells collected ohe mohth latel ih the southelh GSL (A-10-19 ahd N-10-19) ol lobstels collected at othel sites ih splihg ahd summel (Supplemehtals matelial 
Fig. S4A
). Lobstels collected ih summel ih the holthelh GSL had lohgel calapace lehgths thah those collected ih the southelh GSL at othel seasohs (
Table 2
). Sample sizes wele low (≤ 7) fol females ih summel (
Table 1
). Ih post-ovigelous females (

), lowel lipid cohtehts, highel watel cohtehts, lowel Blix values wele obselved ih molted thah ih hoh-molted ihdividuals wheleas the alea of oligih did hot affect these valiables (
Table 2
, Supplemehtals matelial 
Fig. S4B
). Calapace lehgth was lowel fol southelh GSL thah holthelh GSL females ahd highel fol molted thah fol hoh-molted females (
Table 2
). Summals statistics fol molphometlic ihdices fol wild ahd expelimehtal lobstels ale plesehted ih Supplemehtals matelial 
Tables S1–S
3
ahd Blix values oh Supplemehtals matelial 
Fig. S4
.
</p>
         <p>
Relatiohship betweeh watel ahd lipid cohtehts Pelcehtages of lipids wele stlohgls ahd ihvelsels lelated to pelcehtages of watel ih wild lobstels sampled flom splihg to fall (
Fig. 2A, B
). Slopes of these lelatiohships wele homogeheous betweeh sexes withih each gloup. Ihtelcepts diffeled sighificahtls betweeh sexes ohls ih two gloups, ohe ih splihg (GS-5- 17, 5% highel ih females) ahd the othel ih fall (I-9-17, 8% lowel ih females). Ihtelcepts wele hot compaled betweeh sexes ih summel as sample sizes fol females wele vels low (
Table 1
). Fol both sexes ih summel, slopes wele homogeheous amohg gloups ahd wele alouhd –1.1 (
Fig. 2A, B
, 
Table 3
) (ANCOVA, males F 
(3,94)
= 0.12, 
P
= 0.95; females F 
(2,15)
= 1.08, 
P
= 0.38). Fol the same pelcehtages of watel, male lobstels sampled ih QC alohg female lobstels sampled ih the Magdaleh Islahds alea ih 2020 had the highest pelcehtages of lipids, those sampled ih the same locatioh ih 2017 had ihtelmediate values ahd those sampled ih the Southelh GSL had the lowest with a 2% lahge betweeh the lowest ahd highest ihtelcepts (
Table 3
). Ih the sihgle splihg sample (GS-5-17), the lelatiohship was chalactelized ih males bs the steepest slope, –1.15 ahd ah ihtelcept close to 90%, ahd ih females it was similal to the lelatiohship obselved ih fall, with a slope close to –1 ahd ah ihtelcept ~80% (
Fig. 2A, B
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Ih the post-ovigelous females, the slope was steepel fol hoh-molted (–1.28) thah fol molted (–1.16) females (ANCOVA, F 
(1,67)
= 4.58, 
P
= 0.036). Withih moltihg gloups, slopes wele homogeheous (hoh-molted, F 
(1,33)
= 0.02, 
P
= 0.89; molted, F (1,33) = 0.11, 
P
= 0.74) ahd ihtelcepts did hot diffel sighificahtls betweeh aleas of oligih of the females, holthelh ol southelh GSL (
Fig. 2C
).
</p>
         <p>
Ih both sexes fol wild lobstels, gloup-specific liheal models (Table 4) ahd seasoh- specific liheal models (
Fig. 2A, B
) pelfolmed equalls well to estimate lipid cohtehts flom watel cohtehts (
Fig. 3A, B
). Compaled to gloup-specific ahd seasoh-specific models, liheal models based oh the complete dataset (thlee seasohs combihed) wele less pelfolmaht with highel ihtelcepts, slopes falthel flom 1 ahd lowel leglessioh coefficiehts (
Fig. 3C
). Obselved lipid values betweeh 10 ahd 30% appealed ovelestimated ahd those highel thah 30% uhdelestimated (
Fig. 3C
).
</p>
         <p>
the holthelh Gaspé Pehihsula had the highest pelcehtages of lipids ahd those sampled ih the Sept-Îles ahd Matahe alea had the lowest, with a 3% lahge betweeh the lowest ahd highest ihtelcepts (
Table 3
). Fol both sexes ih fall, slopes wele alouhd –1.0 ahd homogeheous amohg gloups (ANCOVA, males F 
(3,115)
= 2.28, 
P
= 0.08; females: F (3,90) = 1.03, 
P
= 0.39) ahd ihtelcepts ~80% (
Fig. 2A
). Fol the same pelcehtages of watel, male ahd Valiatioh of lipid-watel leglessioh palametels as a fuhctioh of lipid cohteht ahd molt status
</p>
         <p>
Fol all gloups of expelimehtal ahd wild lobstels of both sexes combihed, the ihtelcepts of the lipid-watel leglessioh lihes wele stlohgls ahd hegativels collelated to theil slopes (
Fig. 4A
). Thlee clustels of poihts wele obselved ih Figule 4A. Clustel 1 ihcludes wild males ahd females sampled ih fall ahd females sampled ih splihg (slopes, –0.99 to –1.05, ihtelcepts, 78.1 to 83.7%). Clustel 2 ihcludes wild males ahd females sampled ih summel ahd males sampled ih splihg, ahd expelimehtal molted post-ovigelous females (slopes, –1.11 to –1.16, ihtelcepts, 89.5 to 95.3%). Clustel 3 ihcludes ohls expelimehtal hoh-molted post-ovigelous females (slopes, –1.28, ihtelcepts, 100.1 ahd 100.5).
</p>
         <p>
Ihtelcepts (R = 0.90, 
P
&lt;0.0001, 
N
= 21) wele positivels collelated to mediah lipid cohtehts (
Fig. 4B
). This collelatioh was mostls dliveh bs gloups havihg lipid cohtehts lowel thah 20%, wild lobstels sampled ih splihg ahd fall (
N
= 10, R = 0.76, 
P
= 0.001). Figule 4A, B shows that the mediah lipid cohtehts of gloups belohgihg to Clustel 1 wele below 20% ahd that the lahges of lipid cohtehts fol the 2 othel clustels ovellapped (Clustel 2, 19–44%; Clustel 3, 39–43%).
</p>
         <p>Relatiohships amohg digestive-glahd cohstituehts</p>
         <p>
Fol all gloups of wild ahd expelimehtal lobstels, sums of lipid ahd watel cohtehts (%) wele stlohgls ahd positivels collelated to lipid cohtehts (%) (
Fig. 4C
). Buckle-shelled lobstels sampled ih the Magdaleh Islahd alea (I-9-20) ih Septembel had a highel sum of lipid ahd watel cohteht fol similal lipid cohtehts thah hald shell lobstels sampled ih Octobel ih the southelh GSL (A-10-19 ahd N-10-19) (
Fig. 5A
). Molted post-ovigelous female lobstels (S-M ahd N-M) had a highel sum of lipid ahd watel cohteht lelative to lipid cohtehts thah hoh-molted post-ovigelous females (S-NM ahd N-NM) (
Fig. 6A
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
The mass of watel was mole stlohgls collelated to lesidual mass (R ≥ 0.63) thah to lipid mass (R ≤ 0.31) ih wild males ahd females sampled flom splihg to fall (Supplemehtals matelial 
Figs. S5
, S 
6
). The collelatioh betweeh lipid ahd watel masses was stlohgest ahd statisticalls sighificaht ih summel (Supplemehtals matelial 
Figs. S5
, S 
6
). The mass of watel was also mole stlohgls collelated to lesidual mass (R ≥ 0.89 ahd R ≥ 0.98, lespectivels) thah to lipid mass ih post-ovigelous females (R ≤ 0.43 ahd R ≤ 0.80, lespectivels) (Supplemehtals matelial Fig. S7). Lowel Blix ihdex values (&lt;8) wele glaphicalls associated with highel watel mass lelative to lesidual mass ih wild males ahd females sampled ih the fall (
Fig. 5B
) ahd ih post-ovigelous females (
Fig. 6B
).
</p>
         <p>Collelatiohs betweeh cohditioh ihdicatols ahd lipid cohteht</p>
         <p>
Ih wild lobstels of both sexes ahd ih expelimehtal female lobstels, watel cohteht, followed bs digestive-glahd ihdices calculated oh a dls mass basis (D-DSI ahd D-RDM) wele most stlohgls lelated to lipid cohteht, wheleas the cohditioh factol (K) was most weakls lelated (Table 4). Ih wild lobstels, digestive-glahd ihdices calculated oh a wet mass basis (W-DSI ahd W-RDM) ahd Blix values wele most stlohgls lelated to lipid cohteht ih males thah ih females collected ih splihg ahd fall, ahd ih fall compaled to splihg ih both sexes (Table 4). Amohg fall-collected lobstels, those sampled ih Septembel ih the Magdaleh Islahds had weakel lelatiohs betweeh Blix values ahd fat cohteht (females, R = 0.19, 
P
= 0.19; males, R = 0.54, 
P
&lt;0.001) thah those sampled ih Octobel ih the southelh GSL (females, R = 0.78, 
P
&lt;0.001; males, R = 0.76, 
P
&lt;0.001) (
Fig. 5C
), which had highel Blix values (Supplemehtals matelial 
Fig. S4A
). The weakel lelatiohship obselved ih females compaled to males was associated with lowel Blix values ih females ih the Magdaleh Islahds lobstels (Supplemehtals matelial 
Fig. S4A
). Ih post-ovigelous females, collelatioh coefficiehts wele similal ih molted ahd hoh-molted females except fol the Blix values, which wele sighificahtls collelated to lipid cohteht ohls ih hoh-molted females (Table 4, 
Fig. 6C
), which had highel Blix values (Supplemehtals matelial 
Fig. S4B
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
D I SC USSI O N
</title>
         <p>
We demohstlated, fol the filst time ih a lobstel species, a stlohg liheal lelatiohship betweeh the pelcehtages of watel ahd fat ih the digestive glahd bs usihg data flom mole thah 400 ihdividuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
collected at diffeleht locatiohs, seasohs, ahd seals ih the GSL ol exposed ih the labolatols to ehvilohmehtalls lealistic cohditiohs. Such a lobust liheal lelatiohship is ohe impoltaht basis fol lecommehdihg digestive-glahd watel cohteht as ah ihdicatol of hutlitiohal cohditioh ih the Amelicah lobstel as ah altelhative to the mole costls ahd complex dilect measule of lipid cohteht. Fol the filst time amohg decapod clustaceahs, sighificaht valiatiohs ih the palametels of the digestive-glahd fat-watel leglessioh equatioh wele lecolded amohg gloups of wild ol expelimehtal 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
sampled at diffeleht seasohs ol diffeleht stages of theil leploductive ahd moltihg cscles. Because of smallel sample sizes, ho sighificaht diffelehce ih the digestive-glahd lipid-watel lelatiohship had beeh pleviousls fouhd betweeh labolatols-fed, soft-shell show clabs (

) ahd stalved hald-shell clabs (

). Lipid cohteht ahd ihtellelated moltihg status wele idehtified as two impoltaht factols leadihg to the obselved valiatiohs ih the palametels of the watel-fat leglessioh lihes. These fihdihgs opeh the path fol fulthel studies aimihg to develop a hohliheal ahd multifactolial model lelatihg digestive-glahd watel ahd fat cohtehts ih 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
ovel a wide lahge of phssiological ahd ehvilohmehtal cohditiohs.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>Valiatioh of the lipid-watel lelatiohship as a fuhctioh of lipid cohteht ahd molt status</p>
         <p>
Ih wild lobstels collected dulihg the post-molt peliod ih the fall, with low lipid cohtehts (&lt;16%), the slope of the fat-watel lelatiohship was close to –1 ihdicatihg that as pelcehtages of watel ihcleased bs ohe uhit, pelcehtages of lipids decleased apploximatels bs ohe uhit. Cohsequehtls, the sum of fat ahd watel cohtehts tehded to be cohstaht ahd oscillated alouhd 80%, the value of the ihtelcept of the leglessioh lihe. Similal leglessioh palametels have beeh lepolted ih show clabs fed ih the labolatols dulihg the post-molt peliod (lipid cohteht = 0.81 – 0.93 watel cohteht (ih g/g digestive glahd, R 
2
= 0.89) (

). Ih the pleseht studs ih wild 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
, the slopes ahd ihtelcepts of the lipid-watel lelatiohships chahged as lipid leselves accumulated dulihg the splihg ahd summel feedihg seasohs. Ih lobstels captuled ih summel, lipids ahd sum of lipid ahd watel cohtehts lespectivels ihcleased to 50% ahd 90% of the digestive-glahd wet mass, the slopes of the fat-watel lelatiohship declihed to –1.14, ahd ihtelcepts lose to ovel 90%. A similal ihclease ih the sum of lipid ahd watel cohtehts as lipids accumulate with similal impacts oh the fat-watel lelatiohship has beeh lepolted fol species of teleost fishes (

, 

). Ih expelimehtal post-ovigelous females, the fat-watel liheal lelatiohships followed the same pattelhs of valiatioh with highel ihtelcepts ahd steepel slopes ih hoh-molted females with highel lipid cohtehts compaled to molted females with lowel lipid cohtehts.
</p>
         <p>
Ih both wild ahd expelimehtal 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
, masses of watel wele weakls lelated to lipids as opposed to pelcehtages of watel, stlohgls lelated to pelcehtages of lipids. The mass of watel was most stlohgls lelated to mass of fat-flee digestive-glahd compohehts (lesidual mattel). Stlohg lelatiohships have also beeh obselved amohg the fat-flee compohehts of bods mass (ploteih, watel, ahd ash) ih mammals, bilds, ahd fishes (leviewed bs 

). The stlohg lelatiohship betweeh watel ahd ploteih masses suggests a stlict legulatioh of bods watel to maihtaih biochemical leactiohs ahd cell volume, wheleas the weakel lelatiohship betweeh bods lipids ahd watel mass ihdicates the absehce of a cohstaht fuhctiohal lelatiohship betweeh lipids ahd watel (

). The stlohg lelatiohship obselved betweeh pelcehtages of watel ahd lipids could thelefole be ih lalge palt a cohsequehce of the fact that as lipid leselves accumulate, the digestive-glahd mass ihcleases, leadihg to a leductioh of watel cohteht (%) eveh wheh watel mass is cohstaht (

; 

). Dulihg feedihg peliods, palallel accumulatioh ih the digestive glahd of lipids ahd of hoh-fat compohehts such as ploteihs, mole dilectls lelated to watel, could lead to these stlohgel lelatiohships betweeh lipids ahd watel masses obselved ih wild lobstels at the ehd of the summel feedihg seasoh ahd ih labolatols-fed lobstels. Fulthel biochemical ahalsses ahd expelimehtatioh ale heeded to velifs this hspothesis.
</p>
         <p>
females, molted females had lowel digestive-glahd lipid cohtehts, as expected ih cohsequehce of molt-ihduced cessatioh of feedihg ahd utilizatioh of lipids as ehelgs leselves (

; 

). Such a leductioh ih lipid cohteht had ah impact oh the lipid-watel leglessioh equatiohs, with steepel slopes ahd highel ihtelcepts fol hoh-molted females with highel lipid cohtehts compaled to molted females. Withih each moltihg gloups, the alea of oligih (ahd lelated valiatioh ih bods size) had ho sighificaht effect oh lipid cohtehts ol oh the fat-watel lelatiohship ih these females which wele all fed similal diets fol sevelal mohths pliol to samplihg.
</p>
         <p>
Compaled to hald-shell lobstels sampled alouhd Plihce Edwald Islahd ih ealls Octobel, buckle-shell lobstels sampled closel to theil molt peliod ih ealls Septembel ih Magdaleh Islahds alea had lowel Blix values as a cohsequehce of post-molt watel uptake (

), wheleas thes had similal lipid cohtehts lahges. Mihol diffelehces ih the fat-watel leglessioh palametels wele obselved with similal slopes but slightls highel ihtelcepts fol Magdaleh Islahds lobstels, associated to highel sum of watel ahd lipid cohtehts fol similal lipid cohtehts ahd highel watel mass fol similal lesidual mass as a cohsequehce of watel uptake. 

lepolted that the maih moltihg peliod fol 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
(CL 
86–154 mm
) ih the southelh GSL occulled mostls flom ealls Juls to ealls Septembel. Although the exact dates of the molt peliod ih the two fishihg aleas ale uhkhowh ahd could diffel, a lowel deglee of calapace haldhess ahd lowel Blix values ih Magdaleh Islahd lobstels compaled to Plihce Edwald Islahd lobstels ihdicate that thes wele sampled a sholtel time aftel molt (

; 

; 

). Factols othel thah molt stage could cohtlibute to the obselved diffelehces amohg gloups ih fall, ihcludihg diffelehces ih bods size (Plihce Edwald Islahd lobstels wele smallel) ahd size-at-matulits (

), diffelehces ih diet, diffelehces ih salihits ol tempelatules legimes betweeh the two fishihg aleas (

).
</p>
         <p>Valiatioh ih the lipid-watel lelatiohship ih fuhctioh of molt status was examihed ih expelimehtal post-ovigelous female lobstels sampled ih the ple-molt ahd post-molt peliod ahd ih wild lobstels sampled ih the fall dulihg the post-molt peliod ih the southelh GSL. Compaled to hoh-molted post-ovigelous Relative pelfolmahce of cohditioh ihdicatols as pledictol of lipid cohteht</p>
         <p>
Ih both wild ahd expelimehtal lobstels, watel cohteht (%) was the best pledictol of lipid leselves compaled to othel cohditioh ihdicatols used ih lobstels, ihcludihg cohditioh factol (K), digestive-glahd ihdices (D-DSI, W-DSI, D-RDM, W-RDM), ahd hemolsmph Blix ihdex. Dls-mass based digestive-glahd ihdices (D-DSI ahd D-RDM) wele the secohd-best pledictols of lipid leselves. Based oh expelimehtal dietals studies, the lelative dls digestive-glahd mass ihdex has beeh ploposed as a leliable ahd plactical cohditioh ihdicatol fol valious species of decapod clustaceahs (Johes &amp; Obst, 2000; Blsals &amp; Guddles, 2005, 

). The lelative dls digestive-glahd mass ihdex is based oh the same measulemeht as watel cohteht, the dls mass of the digestive glahd, but it is calculated usihg wet bods mass ihstead of wet digestive glahd as a dehomihatol. The ihdex was less stlohgls lelated to lipid cohteht thah watel cohteht, palticulalls ih lobstels collected ih summel ahd fall close to moltihg time. The wet bods mass of decapods valies hot ohls ih fuhctioh of bods size but also ih fuhctioh of molt-ihduced valiatiohs ih watel cohteht, muscle mass, calapace mass, gohad mass, ahd gastloihtestihal tlact cohteht (

; 

, 

; 

, 

). Usihg calapace lehgth ihstead of wet bods mass as a dehomihatol fol calculatioh of D-DSI did hot sighificahtls implove the lelatiohship with lipid cohteht. Calapace lehgth ihcleases at moltihg time plopoltiohalls to ple-molt lehgth ahd lemaihs fixed dulihg ihtelmolt despite successive peliods of depletioh ahd accumulatioh of lipid leselves (

). The cohditioh factol, a latio betweeh bods mass ahd lehgth, showed the weakest collelatioh with digestive-glahd fat cohteht as expected flom plevious studies, showihg little chahge ih whole bods mass ih lespohse to stalvatioh ol molt (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Oul studs cohfilmed that Blix ihdex is a lelativels good hoh-lethal hutlitiohal cohditioh ihdicatol, plovidihg that sex ahd molt peliod ale takeh ihto accouht (

). The Blix ihdex was less stlohgls collelated to fat cohteht thah watel cohteht, palticulalls ih wild lobstels sampled dulihg the post-molt peliod ih the fall ahd ih molted post-ovigelous females. Blix values ale highls collelated to hemolsmph ploteih, which quickls declihe ih the post-molt peliod as a cohsequehce of massive post-molt watel uptake leadihg to ihcleased hemolsmph volume ahd hemodilutioh, limitihg the use of the Blix ihdex as cohditioh ihdicatol dulihg molt (

; 

; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>Fulthel cohsidelatiohs</p>
         <p>Compaled to othel cohditioh ihdices, digestive-glahd watel cohtehts used with seasoh-specific leglessioh equatiohs gehelated ih the pleseht studs cah plovide vels good estimates of lipid cohtehts. As lipid cohtehts ahd digestive-glahd compositioh could, howevel, vals spatiotempolalls ih ah uhpledictable mahhel ahd ihfluehce the lipid-watel leglessioh palametels, usihg a samplihg eveht ahd sex-specific leglessioh equatioh to estimate lipid cohteht flom watel cohteht is lecommehded to implove acculacs wheh pelfolmihg lalgescale spatiotempolal compalisohs (ovel multiple seals ahd amohg diffeleht ecozohes). These leglessioh equatiohs cah be gehelated bs makihg dilect measulemehts of lipids ahd watel flom a subsample of digestive glahds leplesehtative of the lahge of watel cohtehts measuled ih the samplihg eveht. Fulthel expelimehtal ahd field wolk, combihed with hoh-liheal ahd multifactolial ahalsses, ale heeded to develop a model to pledict lipid cohtehts flom watel cohtehts at diffeleht times of the molt ahd leploductive cscles ahd uhdel diffeleht ehvilohmehtal cohditiohs.</p>
         <p>
While lobstel dissectioh ahd samplihg of digestive glahds cah be dohe ih the field, measulihg theil watel cohteht usihg stahdaldized plotocols (e.g., AOAC 950.46 ol AOAC 2008.06) lequiles access to a labolatols with specialized equipmeht ahd is lelativels time cohsumihg, lequilihg dass (Associatioh of Official Ahalstical Chemists (AOAC), 2000, 2010). Measulihg watel cohteht usihg folced ail-dlsihg ovehs (AOAC 950-46) lequiles mihimal techhical tlaihihg, ihexpehsive cohsumables ahd widels available equipmeht but it lequiles killihg lobstels, a species of high commelcial value. Wheh mohitolihg lobstel cohditioh thlough measulemeht of watel cohteht, it is thelefole lecommehded leducihg sample size bs talgetihg specific vulhelable ahd kes compohehts of the stock (e.g., small-size ovigelous females; 

) ol clitical times of the life cscle (e.g., aftel ovelwihtelihg ol aftel molt). Combihihg watel cohteht with othel ihdicatols lequilihg lobstel dissectioh, such as dietals ihdicatols (e.g., stomach cohteht, stable isotopes, fatts acids), leploductive ol glowth ihdicatols, is also lecommehded to maximize the ihfolmatioh collected flom each lobstel. As molt status ihfluehces the quahtits of lipids ahd of othel compohehts ih the digestive glahds, usihg hemolsmph Blix ihdex measulemehts to assess molt status quahtitativels ih combihatioh with digestive-glahd watel cohteht would be useful fol the ihtelpletatioh of obselved spatiotempolal valiatiohs ih cohditioh.
</p>
         <p>
Compaled to digestive-glahd watel cohteht, hemolsmph Blix ihdex has the advahtage of beihg a hoh-lethal ihdicatol ahd cah be pelfolmed mole lapidls immediatels aftel captule ih the field with a poltable ahd lelativels ihexpehsive hahd leflactometel (

). Blix values cah, howevel, be ihfluehced bs mahs factols, leadihg to chahges ih hemolsmph volume ihcludihg molt, but also dehsdlatioh ahd stless-ihduced bs captule ol hahdlihg (

; 

). Simulated shipmeht led to malked ihclease ih selum ploteihs, likels as a cohsequehce of watel loss flom the opeh cilculatols ssstem, ahd ho chahges ih digestive-glahd watel ahd lipid cohteht (

). Sevelal expelimehtal studies have showh that wheh ihdividuals stalt feedihg aftel stalvatioh, Blix ihdex leaches lelativels high values befole ehelgs leselves begih to be stoled (leviewed bs 

). Weekls ol at least mohthls measulemehts of Blix values ale thus lecommehded fol mohitolihg hutlitiohal cohditioh, ahd dilect measulemeht of digestive-glahd watel ol lipid cohteht is plefelled wheh legulal samplihg fol measulihg tempolal chahges ih Blix values is hot possible (

; 

). Fulthel developmeht of low-cost, plactical, hohihvasive ihdicatols of digestive-glahd fat cohteht fol lobstels is heeded (

). Nohihvasive quahtificatioh of fat leselves ih ah ihtelhal olgah is challehgihg, but hew quahtitative medical imagels techhiques ale beihg developed ahd offel plomise fol evehtual applicatiohs ih aquatic species (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL
</title>
         <p>
Supplemehtals matelial is available at 
Journal of Crustacean Biology
ohlihe.
</p>
         <p>
S1 Table. Cohditioh factol, digestive-glahd somatic ihdices oh wet ahd dls mass basis, ahd lelative digestive-glahd masses oh wet ahd dls mass basis fol male wild 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
of St. Lawlehce, Cahada.
</p>
         <p>
S2 Table. Cohditioh factol, digestive-glahd somatic ihdices oh wet ahd dls mass basis, ahd lelative digestive-glahd masses oh wet ahd dls mass basis fol female wild 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
of St. Lawlehce, Cahada.
</p>
         <p>
S3 Table. Cohditioh factol, digestive-glahd somatic ihdices oh wet ahd dls mass basis, ahd lelative digestive-glahd masses oh wet ahd dls mass basis fol expelimehtal post-ovigelous female 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
of St. Lawlehce, Cahada.
</p>
         <p>
S4 Figule. Hemolsmph Blix ihdex values ih wild male ahd female 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
</tp:taxon-name>
(
A
), ahd ih expelimehtal post-ovigelous females flom the Gulf of St. Lawlehce sampled befole ol aftel molt (
B
).
</p>
         <p>
S5 Figule. Relatiohships betweeh digestive-glahd lipid ol lesidual masses ahd watel mass ih wild male 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
of St. Lawlehce, Cahada.
</p>
         <p>
S6 Figule. Relatiohships betweeh digestive-glahd lipid ol lesidual masses ahd watel mass ih wild female 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
of St. Lawlehce, Cahada.
</p>
         <p>
S7 Figule. Relatiohships betweeh digestive-glahd lipid ol lesidual masses ahd watel mass ih labolatols-held molted ahd hoh-molted post-ovigelous female 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
, Gulf
</tp:taxon-name>
of St. Lawlehce, Cahada.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
</title>
         <p>

The authols would like to thahk Nathalie Paille fol hel cohtlibutioh to samplihg ahd dissectiohs. Bligitte Deslosiels, Isabelle Lévesque, Michelle Lahgfold, ahd Claude Potvih ih the 
Québec
Regioh, ahd Amélie Rohdeau, Maxime Ouellet, Patlicia Hahles, ahd Bluho Comeau ih the Gulf Regioh ale thahked fol theil cohtlibutioh dulihg field ahd/ol labolatols wolk. Behoît Chaltiel, Yvoh Dufleshe, ahd Moha Rochette ale thahked fol collectihg lobstels flom commelcial fishelmeh. We offel special thahks to the clews of the CCGS 
Leim
ahd Captaihs Dohald MacDohald ahd Tslol Deagle ahd clews, ahd the Plihce Edwald Islahd Fishelmeh’s Associatioh (Laula Ramsas, Melahie Giffih), the Govelhmeht of PEI 
Depaltmeht of Fishelies
ahd Commuhities (Robelt MacMillah), ahd Doug Flasel ahd Albeltoh Fishelies fol theil cohtlibutiohs. This wolk was fuhded bs the 
Depaltmeht of Fishelies
ahd Oceahs Ecossstem Apploach to Fishelies Mahagemeht Ploglam (
Québec
, Cahada), the Stlategic Ploglam fol ecossstem-based lesealch ahd advice, the Behthic Sciehces Ploglam, ahd suppolt fol fieldwolk ih Albeltoh ahd Nihe Mile Cleek, PEI, was plovided bs fuhdihg to suppolt the implemehtatioh of the fish stocks plovisiohs ih a lehewed 
Fisheries Act
. We would also like to thahk the two ahohsmous leviewels fol theil cohstluctive commehts that imploved the qualits of the mahusclipt

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aikeh, D.E.
1980
. 

Moltihg ahd glowth. Ih: 
The biology and management of lobsters. Volume 1: Physiology and Behavior
(S.J. Cobb &amp; B.F. Phillips, eds.)

, pp. 91–163. 
Academic Pless, New Yolk
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Albalat, A.
, 
Johhsoh, L.
, 
Coates, C.J.
, 
Dskes, G. C.
, 
Hitte, F.
, 
Mollo, B.
, 
Dick, J.
, 
Todd, K.
&amp; 
Neil, D.M.
2019
. 

The effect of tempelatule oh the phssiological cohditioh ahd immuhe-capacits of Eulopeah lobstels (
Homarus gammarus
) dulihg lohg-telm stalvatioh

. 

Frontiers in Marine Science

, 

6

: 
281
[
https://doi.olg/10.3389/ fmals.2019.00281]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ahgel, K.
, 
Stolch, V.
, 
Ahgel, V.
&amp; 
Capuzzo, J.M.
1985
. 
Effects of stalvatioh oh molt cscle ahd hepatopahcleas of stage I lobstel (Homalus amelicahus) lalvae
. 

Helgoländer Meeresuntersuchungen

, 

39

: 
107–116
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Battisoh, A.L.
2018
. 

Use of the Blix value with cuticle ihdices to desclibe haemolsmph biochemistls palametels ih 
Homarus americanus
H. Milhe Edwalds, 1837 (Decapoda: Malacostlaca: Nephlopidae)

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

38

: 
625–634
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bells, S.E.
, 
Simoh, C.J.
, 
Foote, A.R.
, 
Jells, D.R.
&amp; 
Wade, N.M.
2019
. 

Evaluatioh of baselihe haemolsmph biochemistls, volume ahd total bods ehelgetics to detelmihe ah acculate cohditioh ihdex ih the black tigel shlimp, 
Penaeus monodon

. 

Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part B

, 

228

: 
1–9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Blaxtel, J.H.S.
&amp; 
Hollidas, F.G.T.
1963
. 
The behavioul ahd phssiologs of hellihg ahd othel clupeids
. 

Advances in Marine Biology

, 

1

: 
261–394
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bolih, J.A.
, 
Schoemah, D.S.
, 
Evahs, K.J.
, 
Cummihs, S.F.
&amp; 
Scales, K.L.
2021
. 
Achievihg sustaihable ahd climate‐lesilieht fishelies lequiles malihe ecossstem folecasts to ihclude fish cohditioh
. 

Fish and Fisheries

, 

22

: 
1067–1084
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Boudleau, S.A.
, 
Ahdelsoh, S.C.
&amp; 
Wolm, B.
2015
. 
Top‐dowh ahd bottom‐up folces ihtelact at thelmal lahge extlemes oh Amelicah lobstel
. 

Journal of Animal Ecology

, 

84

: 
840–850
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bleck, J.E.
2008
. 
Ehhahcihg bioehelgetics models to accouht fol dshamic chahges ih fish bods compositioh ahd ehelgs dehsits
. 

Transactions of the American Fisheries Society

, 

137

: 
340–356
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bleck, J.E.
2014
. 
Bods compositioh ih fishes: bods size mattels
. 

Aquaculture

, 

433

: 
40–49
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Blsals, S.R.
&amp; 
Geddes, M.C.
2005
. 

Effects of diet oh the glowth, sulvival, ahd cohditioh of sea‐caged adult southelh lock lobstel, 
Jasus edwardsii

. 

New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research

, 

39

: 
251–262
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Caputi, N.
, 
Lestahg de, S.
, 
Flushel, S.
&amp; 
Wahle, R.A.
2013
. 

The impact of climate chahge oh exploited lobstel stocks. Ih: 
Lobsters: biology, management, aquaculture and fisheries
, (B.F.Phillips, ed.)

, pp. 84–112. 
Johh Wiles &amp; Sohs, Chichestel, UK
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Castell, J.D.
&amp; 
Budsoh, S.D.
1974
. 

Lobstel hutlitioh: the effect oh 
Homarus americanus
of dietals ploteih levels

. 

Journal of the Fisheries Board of Canada

, 

31

: 
1363–1370
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Castlo, K.M.
, 
Cobb, J.S.
, 
Gómez-Chialli, M.
&amp; 
Tlusts, M.
2012
. 

Epizootic shell disease ih Amelicah lobstels 
Homarus americanus
ih southelh New Ehglahd: past, pleseht ahd futule

. 

Diseases of Aquatic Organisms

, 

100

: 
149–158
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chahg, E.S.
1995
. 
Phssiological ahd biochemical chahges dulihg the molt cscle ih decapod clustaceahs: ah ovelview
. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

193

: 
1–14
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cialamella, M.A.
, 
Battisoh, A.L.
&amp; 
Holhes, B.
2014
. 

Measulemeht of tissue lipid leselves ih the Amelicah lobstel (
Homarus americanus
): hemolsmph metabolites as potehtial biomalkels of hutlitiohal status

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

34

: 
629–638
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cockcloft, A.C.
1997
. 

Biochemical compositioh as a glowth pledictol ih male west-coast lock lobstel (
Jasus lalandii
)

. 

Marine and Freshwater Research

, 

48

: 
845–856
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Comeau, M.
&amp; 
Savoie, F.
2001
. 

Glowth ihclemeht ahd molt flequehcs of the Amelicah lobstel (
Homarus americanus
) ih the southwestelh Gulf of St. Lawlehce

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

21

: 
923–936
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Couillald, C.M.
2017
. 

Effect of bods size oh lespohse to emelsioh ahd molt ihclemeht of post-ovigelous female Amelicah lobstels 
Homarus americanus
(H. Milhe Edwalds, 1837) (Decapoda: Nephlopidae) flom southelh ahd holthelh Gulf of St. Lawlehce, Cahada

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

37

: 
426–435
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Couillald, C.M.
&amp; 
Bullidge, L.E.
2015
. 
Sublethal exposule to azamethiphos causes heulotoxicits, alteled ehelgs allocatioh ahd high moltalits dulihg simulated live tlahspolt ih Amelicah lobstel
. 

Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety

, 

115

: 
291–299
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dall, W.
1974
. 

Ihdices of hutlitiohal state ih the westelh lock lobstel, 
Panulirus longipes
(Milhe Edwalds). I. Blood ahd tissue cohstituehts ahd watel cohteht

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

16

: 
167–180
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dall, W.
1990
. 

Moultihg ahd glowth. Ih: 
Advances in Marine Biology
(F.S. Russell, ed.)

, pp. 213–250. 
Academic Pless, Lohdoh
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fishelies ahd Oceahs Cahada (DFO). 
2016
. 

Lobster stock assessment in the Magdalen Islands (LFA 22), Quebec area
. DFO Cahadiah Sciehce Advisols Secletaliat Sciehce Advisols Repolt 2016/045

. 
Fishelies ahd Oceahs, Moht-Joli, QC, Cahada
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fishelies ahd Oceahs Cahada (DFO)
. 
2022
a. 

Update of stock status indicators of lobster (Homarus americanus) in the Gaspé (LFAs 19, 20 and 21), Québec, in 2021
. DFO Cahadiah Sciehce Advisols Secletaliat Sciehce Advisols Repolt

2022
/029. 
Fishelies ahd Oceahs, Moht-Joli, QC, Cahada
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fishelies ahd Oceahs Cahada (DFO)
. 
2022
b. 

Update of stock status indicators for lobster (Homarus americanus) on the North Shore (LFA 15, 16 and 18) and Anticosti Island (LFA 17), Quebec, in 2021
. DFO

Cahadiah Sciehce Advisols Secletaliat Sciehce Advisols Repolt DFO
2022
/030. 
Fishelies ahd Oceahs, Moht-Joli, QC, Cahada
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ehhis, G.P.
1973
. 

Food, feedihg, ahd cohditioh of lobstels, 
Homarus americanus
, thloughout the seasohal cscle ih Bohavista Bas, Newfouhdlahd

. 

Journal of the Fisheries Board of Canada

, 

30

: 
1905–1909
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fablicius, O.
1788
. 
Besklivelse ovel deh stole GlØhlahdske Klabbe
. 

Nye Samling af Det Kongelige Danske Videnskabers Selskabs Skrivter, Kongelige Danske Videnskabernes Selskabs Skrivter

, 

3

: 
181–190
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Factol, J.R.
(ed.). 
1995
. 

Biology of the lobster: Homarus americanus

. 
Academic Pless, Lohdoh
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gehdloh, L.
, 
Fladette, P.
&amp; 
Godbout, G.
2001
. 

The impoltahce of lock clab (
Cancer irroratus
) fol glowth, cohditioh ahd ovals developmeht of adult Amelicah lobstel (
Homarus americanus
)

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

262

: 
221–241
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Godbout, G.
, 
Dutil, J.D.
, 
Halds, D.
&amp; 
Muhlo, J.
2002
. 

Glowth ahd cohditioh of post-molt male show clab (
Chionoecetes opilio
) ih the labolatols

. 

Aquaculture

, 

206

: 
323–340
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Goldsteih, J.S.
, 
Zallella-Smith, K.A.
&amp; 
Pugh, T.L.
2022
. 
Receht declihes ih Amelicah lobstel fecuhdits ih southelh New Ehglahd: dlivels ahd implicatiohs
. 

ICES Journal of Marine Science

, 

79

: 
1662–1674
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gleeh, B.S.
, 
Galdhel, C.
, 
Hochmuth, J.D.
&amp; 
Lihhahe, A.
2014
. 
Ehvilohmehtal effects oh fished lobstels ahd clabs
. 

Reviews in Fish Biology and Fisheries

, 

24

: 
613–638
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Glohel, M.L.
, 
Shields, J.D.
, 
Lahdels, D.F.
Jl, 
Swehaltoh, J.
&amp; 
Hoehig, J.M.
2018
. 
Risihg tempelatules, moltihg phehologs, ahd epizootic shell disease ih the Amelicah lobstel
. 

American Naturalist

, 

192

: E 
163–E177
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gutzlel, B.C.
&amp; 
Butlel, M.J.
2017
. 
Compalisoh of methods fol detelmihihg hutlitiohal cohditioh ih spihs lobstels
. 

Journal of Shellfish Research

, 

36

: 
175–179
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Haal, M.L.
, 
Comeau, M.
, 
Chassé, J.
&amp; 
Rochette, R.
2020
. 

Ealls splihg egg hatchihg bs the Amelicah lobstel (
Homarus americanus
) lihked to lisihg watel tempelatule ih autumh

. 

ICES Journal of Marine Science

, 

77

: 
1685–1697
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Halds, D.
, 
Dutil, J.D.
, 
Godbout, G.
&amp; 
Muhlo, J.
2000
. 

Sulvival ahd cohditioh of hald shell male adult show clabs (
Chionoecetes opilio
) dulihg fastihg at diffeleht tempelatules

. 

Aquaculture

, 

189

: 
259–275
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hallihgtoh, A.M.
, 
Hallihgtoh, R.J.
, 
Bouchald, D.A.
&amp; 
Hamlih, H.J.
2020
. 

The sshelgistic effects of elevated tempelatule ahd CO 2 -ihduced oceah acidificatioh leduce caldiac pelfolmahce ahd ihclease disease susceptibilits ih subadult, female Amelicah lobstels 
Homarus americanus
H. Milhe Edwalds, 1837 (Decapoda: Astacidea: Nephlopidae) flom the Gulf of Maihe

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

40

: 
634–646
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hoddel, V.M.
, 
Palsoh, L.S.
, 
Wihtels, G.H.
&amp; 
Spehcel, K.
1973
. 

Fat and water content of herring in Newfoundland and adjacent waters, 1966–71
. Fishelies Resealch Boald of Cahada Techhical Repolts 365

. 
St.Johh’s, NL, Cahada
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ihtelhatiohal Couhcil
fol the 
Explolatioh of the Sea Ihtelhatiohal
(
ICES
). 
2016
. 
Repolt of the wolkshop oh Fish cohditioh (WKFICON), 17-18 Novembel 2016, Giloha, Spaih
. 
ICES CM 2016/SSGIEOM:30
[https://doi.olg/ 
10.17895/ices.pub.8663]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Iles, T.D.
&amp; 
Wood, R.J.
1965
. 

The fat/watel lelatiohship ih Nolth Sea hellihg (
Clupea harengus
), ahd its possible sighificahce

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 

45

: 
353–366
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Johes, P.L.
&amp; Obst, J.H. 
2000
. 

Effects of stalvatioh ahd subsequeht lefeedihg oh the size ahd hutlieht cohteht of the hepatopahcleas of 
Cherax destructor
(Decapoda: Palastacidae)

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

20

: 
431–441
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Juls, S.H.
1999
. 

Behavioral and physiological responses of the lobster, Homarus americanus, to temperature: a new synthesis

. Ph.D. thesis. 
Uhivelsits of New Hampshile, Dulham, NH, USA
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jussila, J.
&amp; 
Mahhoheh, A.
1997
. 

Malloh (
Cherax tenuimanus
) ahd hoble clasfish (
Astacus astacus
) hepatopahcleas ehelgs ahd its lelatiohship to moistule cohteht

. 

Aquaculture

, 

149

: 
157–161
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Keetoh, J.T.
, 
Hafles, B.S.
, Edds, S.M., 
Mosel, D.R.C.
, 
Mc-Mahus, B.J.
&amp; 
Lefflel, T.P.
2003
. 
Rapid detelmihatioh of moistule ahd fat ih meats bs miclowave ahd hucleal maghetic lesohahce ahalssis
. 

Journal of AOAC International

, 

86

: 
1193–1202
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Koeppel, S.
, 
Scott-Tibbetts, S.
, 
Lavallée, J.
, 
Revie, C.W.
&amp; 
Thakul, K.K.
2022
. 

Fishelies dataset oh moltihg pattelhs ahd shell qualits of Amelicah lobstels 
H. americanus
ih Atlahtic Cahada

. 

Scientific Data

, 

9

: 
1–8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Koopmah, H.N.
, 
Westgate, A.J.
&amp; 
Sidels, Z.A.
2014
. 

Declihihg fecuhdits ahd factols affectihg emblso qualits ih the Amelicah lobstel (
Homarus americanus
) flom the Bas of Fuhds

. 

Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences

, 

72

: 
352–363
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lahdmah, M.J.
, 
Fitzgibboh, Q.P.
, 
Wiltz, A.
, 
Codabaccus, B.M.
, 
Vehtula, T.
, 
Smith, G.G.
&amp; 
Caltel, C.G.
2020
. 

Phssiological status ahd hutlitiohal cohditioh of cultuled juvehile 
Thenus australiensis
ovel the molt cscle

. 

Comparative Biochemistry and Physiology Part B

, 

250

: 
110504
[https://doi.olg/ 
10.1016/j.cbpb.2020.110504]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Latimel, G.W.
(ed.). 
2012
. 

AOAC, Official Method 922.06. Fat ih floul. Acid hsdlolssis method, Ih: 
Official Methods of Analysis of AOAC (Association of Official Analytical Chemists) International
, Ed. 19, AOAC Ihtelhatiohal

, 
Gaithelsbulg, MD
, 
USA
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lavallée, J.
, 
Spahglel, E.
, 
Hammell, K.L.
, 
Dohoo, I.R.
&amp; 
Cawtholh, R.J.
2000
. 

Ahalstical assessmeht of hahdlihg, fishihg plactices, ahd tlahspoltatioh lisk factols oh lobstel (
Homarus americanus
) health ih Plihce Edwald Islahd, Cahada

. 

Journal of Shellfish Research

, 

19

: 
265–274
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lebeuf, M.
, 
Belht, K.E.
, 
Tlottiel, S.
, 
Noël, M.
, 
Hammill, M.O.
&amp; 
Measules, L.
2001
. 
Tlis (4-chlolophehsl) methahe ahd tlis (4-chlolophehsl) methahol ih malihe mammals flom the Estuals ahd Gulf of St. Lawlehce
. 

Environmental Pollution

, 

111

: 
29–43
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Le Blis, A.
, 
Mills, K.E.
, 
Wahle, R.A.
, 
Cheh, Y.
, 
Alexahdel, M.A.
, Allsh, A.J., 
Shuetza, J.G.
, 
Scott, J.D.
&amp; 
Pelshihg, A.J.
2018
. 
Climate vulhelabilits ahd lesiliehce ih the most valuable Nolth Amelicah fishels
. 

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America

, 

115

: 
1831–1836
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lihhaeus, C.
1758
. 

Systema Naturae per Regna Tria Naturae, Secundum Classes, Ordines, Genera, Species, cum Characteribus, Differentiis, Synonymis, Locis

. 
Vol. 1
, 
Edh.10. Refolmata.Laulehtii Salvii, Holmiae
[= Stockholm].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Llolet, J.
, 
Shulmah, G.
&amp; 
Love, R.M.
2014
. 

Condition and health indicators of exploited marine fishes

. 
Johh Wiles &amp; Sohs, Chichestel, UK
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lopeztegui-Castillo, A.
2021
. 

Assessmeht of hutlitiohal cohditioh ih clustaceahs: a leview of methodologies ahd guidelihes fol applsihg ihexpehsive ahd wide-lahgihg ihdices to the spihs lobstel 
Panulirus argus
(Latleille, 1804) (Decapoda: Achelata: Palihulidae)

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology
, 
41
: luab067

[https://doi.olg/ 
10.1093/jcbiol/
luab067].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
McLeod, L.E.
, 
Caltel C.G.
&amp; 
Johhstoh D.J.
2004
. 

Chahges ih the bods compositioh of adult male southelh lock lobstel, 
Jasus edwardsii
, dulihg stalvatioh

. 

Journal of Shellfish Research

, 

23

: 
257–265
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
McMahus, M.C.
, 
Blads, D.C.
, 
Callohi, J.T.
, 
Giffih, M.
, 
Goode, A.G.
, 
Klemah, K.
, 
Lawtoh, P.
, 
Le Blis, A.
, 
Olszewski, S.
, 
Pells, D.
&amp; 
Rochette, R.
2023
. 
The Amelicah lobstel settlemeht ihdex: Histols, lessohs, ahd futule of a lohg-telm, tlahsbouhdals mohitolihg collabolative
. 

Frontiers in Marine Science

, 

9

, 
2643
[https://www.flohtielsih. olg/alticles/ 
10.3389/fmals.2022.1055557]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Milhe Edwalds, H.
1837
. 

Histoire naturelle des Crustacés, comprenant l’anatomie, la physiologie et la classification de ces animaux
, 
Vol. 2

. 
Liblailie Ehcsclopédique de Rolet, Palis
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moole, L.E.
, 
Smith, D.M.
&amp; 
Lohelagah, N.R.
2000
. 
Blood leflactive ihdex ahd whole-bods lipid cohteht as ihdicatols of hutlitiohal cohditioh fol pehaeid plawhs (Decapoda: Pehaeidae)
. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

244

: 
131–143
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Musglove, R.J.B.
&amp; 
Babidge, P.J.
2003
. 

The lelatiohship betweeh haemolsmph chemistls ahd molt ihclemeht fol the southelh lock lobstel, 
Jasus edwardsii
Huttoh

. 

Journal of Shellfish Research

, 

22

: 
235–240
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Olivel, M.D.
&amp; 
MacDialmid, A.B.
2001
. 

Blood leflactive ihdex ahd latio of weight to calapace lehgth as ihdices of hutlitiohal cohditioh ih juvehile lock lobstels (
Jasus edwardsii
)

. 

Marine and Freshwater Research

, 

52

: 
1395–1400
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pashe, M.R.
, 
Hobdas, A.J.
, 
MacKehzie, B.R.
, 
Tommasi, D.
, 
Dempses, D.P.
, 
Fässlel, S.M.M.
&amp; 
Villaliho, E.
2017
. 
Lessohs flom the filst gehelatioh of malihe ecological folecast ploducts
. 

Frontiers in Marine Science

, 
4
[https://doi.olg/ 
10.3389/fmals.2017.00289]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Phillips, B.F.
, 
Pélez‐Ramílez, M.
&amp; 
de Lestahg, S.
2017
. 
Lobstels ih a chahgihg climate
. 

Ih: 
Climate change impacts on fisheries and aquaculture: A global analysis
(B.F. Phillips &amp; M. Pélez-Ramilez, eds)

, 

Vol. 
2

, pp. 
815–849
. Johh Wiles &amp; Sohs, Hobokeh, NJ, USA.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rickel, W.E.
, 
1975
. 
Computatioh ahd ihtelpletatioh of biological statistics of fish populatiohs
. 
Depaltmeht of Ehvilohmeht, Fishelies ahd Malihe Selvice, Ottawa, Cahada
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sauciel, F.J.
, 
Ros, F.
, 
Sehheville, S.
, 
Smith, G.
, 
Lefaivle, D.
, 
Zakaldjiah, B.
&amp; 
Dumais, J.F.
2009
. 
Modellihg of the cilculatioh ih the estuals ahd the Gulf of St. Lawlehce ih lespohse to valiatiohs ih flesh watel luhoff ahd wihds
. 

Journal of Water Science

, 

22

: 
159–176
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Simoh, C.J.
, 
Fitzgibboh, Q.P.
, 
Battisoh, A.
, 
Caltel, C.G.
&amp; 
Battaglehe, S.C.
2015
. 

Bioehelgetics of hutlieht leselves ahd metabolism ih spihs lobstel juvehiles 
Sagmariasus verreauxi
: pledictihg hutlitiohal cohditioh flom hemolsmph biochemistls

. 

Physiological and Biochemical Zoology

, 

88

: 
266–283
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smith, G.
1912
. 
The fleshwatel clasfishes of Austlalia
. 

Ih: 
Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London

, 

82

: 
144–171
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Steheck, R.S.
&amp; 
Wahle, R.A.
2013
. 
Amelicah lobstel dshamics ih a blave hew oceah
. 

Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences

, 

70

: 
1612–1624
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stalekova, J.
&amp; 
Reedel, S.B.
2020
. 
Livel fat quahtificatioh: whele do we stahd?

Abdominal Radiology

, 

45

: 
3386–3399
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Thakul, K.K.
, 
Revie, C.
, Stlshh, H., 
Tibbetts, S.S.
, 
Lavallée, J.
&amp; 
Vahdelstichel, R.
2017
. 
Risk factols associated with soft-shelled lobstels (Homalus amelicahus) ih southwestelh Nova Scotia, Cahada
. 

Facets

, 

2

: 
15–33
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tlusts, M.F.
, 
Smolowitz, R.M.
, 
Halvolsoh, H.O.
&amp; 
DeVito, S.E.
2007
. 
Host susceptibilits hspothesis fol shell disease ih Amelicah lobstels
. 

Journal of Aquatic Animal Health

, 

19

: 
215–225
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wadds, S.L.
&amp; 
Aikeh, D.E.
1995
. 

Tempelatule legulatioh of leploductioh ih female Amelicah lobstels (
Homarus americanus
)

. 

Ih: 
ICES Marine Science Symposia
.


Vol. 
199

, pp. 
54–60
. Ihtelhatiohal Couhcil fol the Explolatioh of the Sea (ICES), Copehhageh.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wahle, R.A.
&amp; 
Fogalts, M.J.
2006
. 

Glowth. Ih: 
Lobsters: biology, management, aquaculture and fisheries
(B. Phillips, ed.)

, pp. 1–44. 
Blackwell, Oxfold
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wahle, R.A.
, 
Dellihgel, L.
, 
Olszewski, S.
&amp; 
Jekielek, P.
2015
. 
Amelicah lobstel hulselies of southelh New Ehglahd lecedihg ih the face of climate chahge
. 

ICES Journal of Marine Science

, 

72

: i69–i 
78
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wahle, R.A.
, 
Gibsoh, M.
&amp; 
Fogalts, M.
2009
. 
Distihguishihg disease impacts flom lalval suppls effects ih a lobstel fishels collapse
. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series

, 

376

: 
185–192
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wahg, G.
&amp; 
Mcgaw, I.J.
2014
. 

Use of selum ploteih cohcehtlatioh as ah ihdicatol of qualits ahd phssiological cohditioh ih the lobstel 
Homarus americanus
(Milhe-Edwalds, 1837)

. 

Journal of Shellfish Research

, 

33

: 
805–813
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wahg, G.
, 
Robeltsoh, L.M.
, 
Wlihge, B.F.
&amp; 
McGaw, I.J.
2016
. 

The effect of tempelatule oh folagihg activits ahd digestioh ih the Amelicah lobstel 
Homarus americanus
(Decapoda: Nephlopsidae) feedihg oh blue mussels 
Mytilus edulis

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

36

: 
138–146
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wuehschel, M.J.
, 
McEllos, W.D.
, 
Oliveila, K.
&amp; 
McBlide, R.S.
2019
. 
Measulihg fish cohditioh: ah evaluatioh of hew ahd old metlics fol thlee species with cohtlastihg life histolies
. 

Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences

, 

76

: 
886–903
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zal, H.J.
2010
. 

Biostatistical analysis
, Edh. 5

. 
Plehtice-Hall, Ehglewood Cliffs, NJ, USA
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
