<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of Crustacean Biology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jcbiol/ruad055</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Trophic discrimination factors and stable isotope variability in a captive feeding trial of the southern rock lobster Jasus edwardsii (Hutton, 1875) (Decapoda: Palinuridae) in Tasmania, Australia</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>29</day>
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
(
Hutton, 1875
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Palinuridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
(
Hutton, 1875
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
(
Hutton, 1875
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Centrostephanus rodgersii
(A. Agassiz, 1864)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mytilus galloprovincialis
(Lamarck, 1819)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. galloprovincialis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Centrostephanus rodgersii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sardinops sagax
(Jenyns, 1842)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Haliotis rubra
(Leach, 1814)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Heliocidaris erythrogramma
(Valenciennes, 1846)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lunella undulata
(Lightfoot, 1786)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
(

Guest 
et al.
, 2009

)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sagmariasus verreauxi
(H. 
Milne Edwards, 1851
) (

Day 
et al.
, 2022

)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. verreauxi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Haliotis rubra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Heliocidaris erythrogramma
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lunella undulata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. rodgersii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. rodgersii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Trophic discrimination factors and stable isotope variability in a captive feeding trial of the southern rock lobster 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
(
Hutton, 1875
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Palinuridae</tp:taxon-name>
) in 
Tasmania
, 
Australia
</p>
         <p>
Jennifer E. Smith
1,
, 
Christian Dietz
2,
, 
John Keane
1,
, 
Craig Mundy
1,
, 
Michael Oellermann

1, 
3
,4,

and 
Caleb Gardner
1
</p>
         <p>
1

Institute for Marine and Antarctic Studies, University of 
Tasmania
, Hobart, 
Tasmania
7005, 
Australia
</p>
         <p>
2
Central Science Laboratory
, University of 
Tasmania
, Hobart, 
Tasmania
7005, 
Australia
</p>
         <p>
3

Centre for Marine Environmental Sciences (MARUM), University of 
Bremen
, 

28359 
Bremen
, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
4

Alfred Wegener Institute, Helmholtz Centre for Polar and Marine Research, 27570 Bremerhaven, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>Correspondence: J.Smith; e-mail: je.smith@utas.edu.au</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A B ST R A CT
</title>
         <p>
Trophic discrimination or fractionation factors (TDFs), such as ∆15N and ∆13C, are used in stable isotope mixing models to account for differences between source tissues (diet/prey) and consumer tissues (predator). We aimed firstly to obtain TDF values for a spiny lobster, the southern rock lobster 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
(
Hutton, 1875
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, to better understand lobster diet in the wild and secondly to investigate variability in isotope signature within tissues of individuals and across a temporal scale to test if non-lethal sampling can be used in an ecological context. We conducted an 18-mo captive feeding trial with juvenile lobsters using three diet treatments and analysed dorsal and leg muscle, along with dorsal and leg exoskeleton for 
δ
13
C and 
δ
15
N values. Average TDFs for the three diet treatments were 3.86 ± 0.98‰ (∆13C) and 5.06 ± 0.65‰ (∆15N) for leg muscle, and 4.45 ± 1.04‰ (∆13C) and 4.36 ± 0.6‰ (∆15N) for dorsal muscle. When tested against wild lobsters and prey, these TDFs outperformed multi-taxa TDFs found in the literature. Isotope values from lobster leg muscle were not identical to associated dorsal muscle but the two were highly correlated, indicating that non-lethal sampling is acceptable. Values for exoskeleton isotope were significantly different from muscle, likely due to the exoskeleton not being in a constant state of growth and replacement, unlike the muscle tissue, which constantly incorporates new material. We conclude that our experimentally derived TDFs are suitable for mixing model analysis for 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
and when tested on a wild sample of lobsters they outperformed other TDFs reported in the literature. We show that non-lethal sampling using leg muscle is an appropriate sampling method, since this tissue is highly correlated to the commonly used dorsal muscle. This option for non-lethal sampling enhances the potential to widely sample wild populations or sample during industrial processing without the need to sacrifice whole animals.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
KEY WORDS:
Crustacea
, 
southern rock lobster
, 
spiny lobsters
, 
stable isotope analysis
, 
trophic discrimination factors
(
TDFs
)

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
The use of stable isotope analysis in food-web ecology and trophic interactions is widespread in ecological studies and is increasingly used for aquaculture and diet investigations on marine organisms. To determine the diet of an animal, various stable isotope mixing models (e.g., MixSIAR, simmr, Fruits) can be used to estimate the proportion of consumer diet from a selection of dietary sources (

; 

; 

). Due to isotopic fractionation, stable isotope delta values change as organisms sit further up or down the trophic cascade. To assess this change, Trophic Discrimination Factors (TDF, denoted by ∆) are used, which are defined as the difference in isotopic values between food source and consumer. Here, we describe species-specific TDFs which can be used to assess the diet of a spiny lobster, the southern rock lobster 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
(
Hutton, 1875
)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
Mixing models require a TDF to adequately account for changes in uptake of carbon and nitrogen through the food chain. TDFs can vary significantly and therefore mixing models require a TDF to be specific for each tissue 
type
, species, and isotope (e.g., ∆13C and ∆15N). TDFs for a particular species may be obtained from the literature, but ideally are experimentally determined with controlled captive feeding trials. Approximated TDFs produced from averages across multiple taxa can be used if species-specific TDFs are not available in the literature: 0.4‰ for ∆13C and 3.4‰ for ∆15N (

). The use of non-species-specific TDFs will increase uncertainty in the estimation of consumer diet using mixing models (

), and therefore researchers have been urged to use experimentally derived TDFs for mixing models (e.g., 

; Martínez del 

; 

); 

).
</p>
         <p>
To obtain diet information of a consumer by stable isotope analysis, a tissue sample is required from the consumer and from each of the potential diet sources. Muscle tissue is commonly used for analysis because muscle generally reflects the long-term isotope signature and thus reflects longer term diet of the animal and is less prone to short-term changes in diet (

), unlike, for example, hair or shell tissue. In many cases, the required tissue involves lethal sampling of the individual (

). Non-lethal sampling options for crustaceans, such as carapace, leg, antenna, and faeces samples, however, have been proven to be promising alternatives to muscle tissue, due to high isotopic correlations between tissues in some species (

; 

; 

). Non-lethal sampling provides a useful alternative in situations investigating protected populations or long-term, repetitive-sampling experiments. Removing a single leg rather than a more invasive or whole-animal sample, it provides the opportunity to sample industry caught crustaceans destined for market without compromising sale value, which could allow for large sample sizes.
</p>
         <p>
Stable isotope measurements reflect a long-term temporal scale for dietary uptake. But as tissue is constantly being replaced, and because diet may seasonally change in the wild, the exact stable-isotope turnover rate for a given tissue remains unknown (

; 

; 

). The present work aims to contribute to filling this knowledge gap by determining isotope fractionation and variability in 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Jasus edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
is a generalist predator on rocky reefs in southeastern 
Australia
and 
New Zealand
(

). The size of maturity of this species varies greatly in Tasmania (

), with the current minimum legal size being 
110 mm
carapace length (CL) for males and 
105 mm
/ 
120 mm
CL for females (in southern/northern Tasmania, respectively). Interest in the diet of this predator is currently of high importance due to their perceived potential in providing top-down predatory pressure on a range-extending pest species, the longspined sea urchin 
<tp:taxon-name>
Centrostephanus rodgersii
(A. Agassiz, 1864)
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

). Individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
are used as a management strategy to control the sea urchin in Tasmania (Department of Primary Industries, Parks, Water and Environment, 2018), yet the extent to which the lobster will predate on the sea urchin is uncertain if there are more preferable prey options available (

).
</p>
         <p>
The variability of stable isotopes in 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
tissues and muscle TDF values were determined for juvenile lobsters in 
New Zealand
(

). These TDF values were similar to those provided by 

, but did not provide adequate coverage for mixing models to provide insight on lobster diet in Tasmania (JS, unpublished data). For this reason, we designed our own 18-mo captive experimental feeding trial with 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
using three different diet treatments to determine 1) species-specific TDFs for use in dietary predicting mixing models, 2) tissue variability within individuals to assess whether non-lethal sampling is suitable for stable isotope work, and 3) timescales on which stable isotopes may vary to verify an optimal sampling method.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
METHODS
</title>
         <p>Experimental design</p>
         <p>
An 18-mo controlled captive feeding study was conducted using three groups of juvenile 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
(carapace length 
47–101 mm
). The sampling period started in Australian winter (
June 2020
) and ran through to the second Australian summer (
December 2021
). Prior to the experiment, lobsters were collected as puerulus from the wild (Iron Pot, 
Tasmania
) during the summer of 2017–2018 (

, b). These juveniles had been fed a consistent diet of frozen blue mussels 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mytilus galloprovincialis
(Lamarck, 1819)
</tp:taxon-name>
for over two years. Up to 15 lobsters were kept in three separate treatment tanks (approximately 
1.5 m
diameter × 
1.5 m
depth, ~2,600 litres) at IMAS Taroona laboratories (Hobart, 
Tasmania
) with flowing untreated seawater, which is reflective of the natural environment for lobsters in this region. Different sizes and sex of lobsters were randomly assorted between tanks. Lobsters were held communally (in the three treatment tanks). We provided excess food to make sure all lobsters had access to food until the individuals stopped eating; remains were then removed to maintain water quality and avoid nitrate and nitrite accumulation. There were no unexpected mortalities or cannibalisms during the trials. Each tank was supplied with one of the following: frozen whole blue mussels 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. galloprovincialis
</tp:taxon-name>
(“control/mussel treatment”), frozen whole sea urchin 
<tp:taxon-name>
Centrostephanus rodgersii
</tp:taxon-name>
(“sea urchin treatment”) or frozen whole sardine 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sardinops sagax
(Jenyns, 1842)
</tp:taxon-name>
(“fish treatment”) 2–3 times per week. Wild sea urchins were collected from the 
Tasman
Peninsula by diving at the beginning of the experiment and stored frozen. Mussels were obtained from a commercial farm at Spring Bay, 
Tasmania
(Spring Bay Seafoods), and sardines from a commercial supplier (Ashmores Southern Fish Markets, Hobart, 
Tasmania
). Although the same processors were used to source the mussels and fish throughout, we cannot guarantee these were collected at the same time and so could be a source of isotopic variation. These diets were chosen as proxies for lobster diet in the wild (sea urchins, mussels, remains of dead fish; 

), and to provide wider trophic differentiation as the three species in the diet options feed at different trophic levels and so are likely to have distinct isotopic signatures. We lethally sampled five lobsters for an initial reference sample: muscle from the hind leg, dorsal cephalothorax muscle, and dorsal exoskeleton. Five lobsters from each experimental setup were non-lethally sampled by removing a hind leg (see 

). By removing only hind legs, we ensured no lobster was non-lethally sampled more than once. After 12 mo on the controlled, single-species diet, five lobsters and five prey were sampled for stable isotope analysis. Five random lobsters from each treatment were sacrificed and sampled for dorsal, leg, and exoskeleton tissue. Due to the difficulty of identifying individuals through moults, we did not record whether or not a moult matched a previous/subsequent sample from the same individual. Soft tissue from five individual prey animals from each treatment were also sampled. The trial continued until 18 mo when all remaining lobsters were lethally sampled (sea urchin treatment = 8; fish treatment = 4; control/ mussel treatment = 3). Seasonal moulting allowed opportunistic collection of exoskeleton samples from exuviae during two periods between sampling events (4–6 mo and 8–12 mo). Some lobsters from every diet treatment moulted (
N
= 13), but not all individuals moulted. Individuals of all treatments moulted during the 4–8 mo period (one lobster moulted in each treatment), individuals of only sea urchin (
N
= 6) and fish (
N
= 4) treatments moulted during the 8–12 mo period.
</p>
         <p>Sample preparation</p>
         <p>
We dissected a 
1 cm
3
piece of soft tissue from beneath the leg or dorsal cephalothorax exoskeleton of each lobster, 
1 cm
2
exoskeleton samples were also saved from the leg and dorsal cephalothorax carapace. Soft tissue was sampled from five individuals under each diet species: muscle tissue from the fish and mussels and gonads from sea urchins, as these tissues are what we observed to be consumed by the lobsters. All tissue samples from lobsters and diet species were placed into glass vials and oven-dried at 60 °C to a constant weight. Dry samples were then ground into a homogeneous powder using mortar and pestle. About 
0.5 mg
of sample powder was then weighed and folded into tin capsules for analysis at the Central Science Laboratory, University of 
Tasmania
, Hobart.
</p>
         <p>Stable isotope analysis</p>
         <p>
Carbon and nitrogen stable isotopes were analysed consecutively for each sample using flash combustion isotope ratio mass spectrometry (varioPYRO cube coupled to Isoprime100 mass spectrometer; Elementar, Langenselbold, 
Germany
). The nitrogen produced during combustion was directly fed into the mass spectrometer and measured against a reference gas. Carbon dioxide was trapped in the meantime and released into the mass spectrometer after the nitrogen isotope measurement was completed and the system retuned accordingly. Stable isotope abundances are reported in delta (
δ
) values as the deviations from conventional standards in parts per mil (‰) from equation 1:
</p>
         <p>
δX (%) = (Rsample/Rstandard 
–
1) × 1000)
</p>
         <p>(1)</p>
         <p>
where X = 
13
C or 
15
N and R = ratio 
13
C/ 
12
C or 
15
N/ 

14
N.

δ
13
C, and 
δ
15
N values are reported relative to PDB (Pee Dee Belemnite) and atmospheric air, respectively. We used international reference standards with known isotopic composition (USGS 25, USGS 40, USGS 41, IAEA-N1 and IAEA-N2, NBS 21, USGS 24, and ANU-NAT-76H) to correct for instrumental drift and quality assurance purposes. The analytical performance of the instrumentation, drift correction, and linearity performance were calculated from the repetitive analysis of these standards. Precision was 0.1% for both isotopes. One sample for every source 
type
and the consumer was replicated three time to account for overall precision and homogeneity; error did not exceed 0.33‰ for nitrogen and 0.11‰ for carbon.
</p>
         <p>Calculating TDFs</p>
         <p>
We calculated carbon and nitrogen discrimination factors for each diet group by subtracting the mean 
δ
15
N or 
δ
13
C value of the diet item from the mean 
δ
15
N or 
δ
13
C value of the lobsters in that treatment at 12 mo, following the equation in 

. The distances between the consumer isotope signature and the relative diet-species isotope signature were averaged for the three treatments. Wild lobster isotope signatures were visualised on an isoplot along with average source signatures using no TDFs, TDFs obtained from the literature (

; 

) and our experimentally derived TDFs.
</p>
         <p>Wild sample collection</p>
         <p>
Stable isotope values for wild 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
and potential prey species, collected in 
January 2021
, were included for verification of our experimentally derived TDFs. Thirty-seven lobster individuals (CL 
75–160 mm
), ten of which overlapped in size with our experimental tank lobsters (CL 
75–101 mm
), were collected under permit from the Crayfish Point Research Reserve, Hobart, 
Tasmania
and their dorsal cephalothorax tissue sampled for stable isotope analysis. Five soft-tissue samples from source species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Haliotis rubra
(Leach, 1814)
</tp:taxon-name>
(abalone), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Heliocidaris erythrogramma
(Valenciennes, 1846)
</tp:taxon-name>
(sea urchin), and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lunella undulata
(Lightfoot, 1786)
</tp:taxon-name>
(sea snail) were collected from the same site. All tissue samples were treated as detailed above and underwent the same stable isotope analysis process.
</p>
         <p>Data analysis</p>
         <p>
We used split-plot ANOVAs to compare variability of each isotope (
δ
13
C and 
δ
15
N) between different tissues (dorsal muscle, leg muscle, and exoskeleton) of each lobster. Q-Qplots and Shapiro-Wilk Tests were used to visualise and confirm normality of the data. Linear regression and Pearson’s correlation were performed to determine correlation between isotopes of lobster tissues. Comparisons within tissue 
types
across sampling periods in lobsters from different diet treatments were tested using ANOVA and post-hoc Tukey HSD tests. For lethal samples (initial, 12, and 18 mo), exoskeleton samples are the mean of leg and dorsal samples where both were collected. Exoskeleton for non-lethal samples were only leg samples. Opportunistic moult sample results were analysed separately from those from regular sampling intervals due to unequal and low numbers of replication. All data analysis was conducted using R version 4.1.1 (R 

) in RStudio (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
R E SU LTS
</title>
         <p>Variation between tissues</p>
         <p>
Split-plot ANOVAs showed that 
δ
13
C and 
δ
15
N values were different within individual lobsters between dorsal muscle, leg muscle, and exoskeleton (
δ
13
C F-test 
(2.09, 50.27)
= 189.27, 
P &lt;
0.001, generalized effect size (ges) = 0.79; 
δ
15
N F 
(1.94, 46.5)
= 237.61, 
P &lt;
0.001, ges = 0.71). Pairwise comparisons showed there was no significant difference between dorsal exoskeleton and leg exoskeleton samples (
δ
13
C F 
(24)
= –0.610, 
P
= 1; 
δ
15
N F 
(24)
= –1.63 
P
= 1), so these were not included in the linear modelling (
Table 1
). In all samples tested, lobster leg muscle varied between –18.7 to –16.6‰ in 
δ
13
C and 12.2 to 15.7‰ in 
δ
15
N.

Dorsal muscle varied between –18.2 to –16.4‰ in 
δ
13
C and 11.7 to 14.9 ‰ in 
δ
15
N, and exoskeleton varied between –18 to –12.2‰ in 
δ
13
C and 6.7 to 13.5‰ in 
δ
15
N.

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
There was a strong linear correlation between muscle tissue samples within individuals for both 
δ
13
C and 
δ
15
N (
Fig. 1
). Equations 2 and 3 show the linear relationship between lobster dorsal and leg muscle tissue for 
δ
13
C and 
δ
15
N derived from the linear regression models (
Table 1
). Pearson’s correlation statistic for leg-dorsal muscle tissue was 0.65 for 
δ
13
C and 0.87 for 
δ
15
N; 0.53 for 
δ
13
C and 0.59 for 
δ
15
N for dorsal exoskeleton-tissue.
</p>
         <p>
δ 
13
C: dorsal δ 
13
C = -3.138 + 0.795 × Leg δ 
13
C
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
(2)
</title>
         <p>
δ 
15
N: dorsal δ 
15
N = 3.0433 + 0.7164 × Leg δ 
15
N 
δ
15
N isotope signatures (ANOVA 
δ
13
C F (31,2) = 0.08, 
P
= 0.92; 
δ
15
N F 
(31,2)
= 1.65, 
P
= 0.209). Inclusion of size increased the model AIC values for both 
δ
13
C (AIC 22.7, AIC 
size
26.5) and 
δ
15
N (AIC 27.3, AIC 
size
27.8) and therefore was left out of the final linear model.
</p>
         <p>
Change in isotopic signatures following diet change Overall, mean values of stable isotopes in leg exoskeleton samples were much lower in 
δ
15
N (9.04 ± 1.8) than the leg muscle samples (13.5 ± 0.9) and higher in 
δ
13
C (–14 ± 1.4, muscle: –17.8 ± 0.5), and both tissues showed variability over time during the 18-mo time period (
Fig. 2
).
</p>
         <p>Leg muscle isotope signature change over time</p>
         <p>
There was a significant effect of time period and diet treatment on the isotope signature of lobster leg muscle in the experiment (ANOVA 
δ
13
C F 
(14, 60)
= 10.05, r 
2
= 0.701, 
P &lt;
0.001; ANOVA 
δ
15
N F 
(14,60)
= 25.02, r 
2
= 0.8538, 
P&lt;
0.001).
</p>
         <p>
There was a change in mean isotopic signature for the treatments over time in both 
δ
13
C and 
δ
15
N (
Fig. 2
). After 4 mo, neither of the new diet treatments could be distinguished from the control in 
δ
13
C (Tukey HSD 
P
</p>
         <p>(mussel-urchin)</p>
         <p>
= 0.09, 
P
</p>
         <p>(mussel-fish)</p>
         <p>
= 0.06) or 
δ
15
N (Tukey HSD 
P
(mussel-urchin)
= 0.26, 
P
(mussel-fish)
= 0.99), but lobsters from the sea urchin treatment were significantly higher in 
δ
13
C value than those in the fish treatment (Tukey HSD 
P &lt;
0.001). By 8 mo, lobsters in the sea urchin treatment had isotopic signatures significantly different in 
δ
13
C value from those in the control treatment (Tukey HSD 
P &lt;
0.001) and the fish treatment (Tukey HSD 
P =
0.002); this diet group remained distinct in 
δ
13
C for the rest of the experiment (Tukey HSD 
P
(12 month-mussel) 
&lt;
0.001, 
P
(12 month-fish) = 0.004, 
P
(18 month-mussel)
&lt;
0.001, 
P
(18 month-fish)
= 0.001). 
δ
15
N values for all treatments remained within the range of the control treatment at 4 mo (ANOVA F (2,12) =1.72, 
P
= 0.221) but by 8 mo the lobsters on the sea urchin diet were higher in 
δ
15
N compared to those in the control (Tukey HSD 
P
= 0.004). By 12 mo, the two new diet treatments were both enriched in 
δ
15
N compared to those in the control (Tukey HSD 
P
(mussel-urchin)
= 0.001, 
P
(mussel-fish)
= 0.002). There was a steep rise in the 
δ
15
N across lobsters in all treatments at 18 mo (
Fig. 2
).
</p>
         <p>Exoskeleton isotope signature change over time</p>
         <p>
There was a significant effect of sample period but not treatment on 
δ
13
C isotope value of lobster exoskeleton samples across the whole sampling period (ANOVA F 
(14,59)
= 2.5, 
P
= 0.007). Prior to the 12-mo sampling, treatment had no effect on 
δ
13
C (ANOVA F 4month (2,11) = 0.05, 
P
= 0.951, F 8month(2,12) = 0.66, 
P
= 0.534). At 12 mo, lobsters in the sea urchin treatment had significantly higher exoskeleton 
δ
13
C values than those in the fish treatment (Tukey HSD 
P
= 0.016) and this pattern continued at 18 mo (Tukey HSD 
P =
0.023). There was a significant effect of sample period and treatment and an interaction across the whole experiment (ANOVA F (14, 59) = 23.55, 
P &lt;
0.001) for 
δ
15
N values in lobster exoskeleton. There was no difference between treatments (ANOVA F 
(2,11)
= 0.278, 
P
= 0.763) at 4 mo, but by 8 mo the lobsters in the fish treatment had become significantly enriched in 
δ
15
N compared to the control (Tukey HSD 
P =
0.005), lobsters in the sea urchin and mussel treatments remained similar (Tukey HSD 
P =
0.08). Throughout the first 12 mo, lobsters in the new diet treatments maintained similar 
δ
15
N exoskeleton values, and these were both significantly higher than the control at the 12-mo sampling (Tukey HSD 
P
(mussel-urchin)
&lt;
0.001, 
P
(mussel-fish)
&lt;
0.001). Like 
δ
15
N in the leg muscle samples, there was a steep increase in 
δ
15
N of exoskeleton of lobster in all treatments between 12 and 18 mo (
Fig. 2
).
</p>
         <p>
Opportunistically, we sampled 13 moulted exuviae for exoskeleton analysis between the established sampling periods: one from each treatment during the period of 4-8 mo (
N
= 3) and six from the sea urchin treatment (mean ± SE, 
δ
13
C –12.4 ± 0.2, 
δ
15
N 8.4
± 0.2) and four from the fish treatment (
δ
13
C –12 ± 0.4, 
δ
15
N: 8.4 ± 0.3) during 8–12 mo (
N
= 10).
</p>
         <p>
Calculating a Trophic Discrimination Factor Captive lobsters in different treatments had different mean isotope values from the control treatment (mussel-fed lobsters) after 12 mo. We calculated TDF values sing the mean isotope value at 12 mo from the lobsters and the isotope values from the sources (
Table 2
). Mean ± SD isotope values for the sources were as follows: mussel 
δ
13
C –20.34 ± 0.77, 
δ
15
N 8.02
± 0.39 (
N
= 4); sea urchin 
δ
13
C –21.53 ± 1.74, 
δ
15
N 7.66
± 0.28 (
N
= 5); fish 
δ
13
C –22.28 ± 0.45, 
δ
15
N 9.03
± 0.37 (
N
= 5).
</p>
         <p>Testing the obtained trophic discrimination factors</p>
         <p>
Figure 3
illustrates the comparison of using different TDF values on a population of wild lobsters and diet sources. Sources with the correction for experimentally derived TDFs for both leg muscle and dorsal muscle overlap the consumer population and would therefore be acceptable to use in stable isotope mixing models. Sources corrected for TDFs found in the literature (∆13C 0.4‰ and ∆15N; 3.4‰ and ∆13C 0.84‰ and ∆15 
N 3.28
‰ (

; 

)), improve the fit of the sources from no TDFs at all but do not correct the sources to overlap the consumer population and so would have to be considered inappropriate for use in mixing models.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
</title>
         <p>
By using a controlled experimental feeding trial, we were able to assess tissue variability, changing isotopic signatures over time, and determine species- and tissue-specific trophic discrimination factors for juvenile 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Tasmania
.
</p>
         <p>
The variation in isotope signatures of invertebrates was not assessed by 

, but their study did find tissue 
type
was a significant factor affecting isotope signature in some vertebrates (fishes and birds). We found a large difference in isotope signatures between lobster muscle tissue and exoskeleton and a smaller difference between dorsal and leg muscles. The range of isotope values we collected fall around the mean found in wild 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
(

Guest 
et al.
, 2009

)
</tp:taxon-name>
and within the range seen in another species of rock lobster (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sagmariasus verreauxi
(H. 
Milne Edwards, 1851
) (

Day 
et al.
, 2022

)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The tissue variability we found between the samples of leg and dorsal muscle in 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
is significant but highly correlated, meaning the use of non-lethal leg samples would be warranted with the correction factor provided for 
δ
13
C and 
δ
15
N (equations 2, 3). A similar conclusion was made in the study of another species of rock lobster (
<tp:taxon-name>
S. verreauxi
</tp:taxon-name>
), in which the authors provide a correction formula to use leg tissue isotopic signature to provide information for the lobster (

). We do not recommend using exoskeleton tissue in the same way due to the low correlation and R 
2
values. Further, temporal sampling of exoskeleton indicates that 
δ
13
C does not change with diet change in the same way that the muscle tissue does (
Fig. 2
), likely representing the diet at the time of laying the exoskeleton rather than the recently assimilated diet.
</p>
         <p>
Over the timeline of the 18-mo experiment, we can observe that within 4 mo, change of diet can have a significant impact on the consumer’s isotopic signature (
Fig. 2
). For this reason, the time frame in which samples were collected from the wild must be taken into account in all isotope studies. For example, if season changes prey availability and thus diet, consumer isotope signature could shift seasonally and so if comparability is important to the study, we recommend that samples should be collected within a short time frame (e.g., less than 4 mo apart). The moulted exuviae were enriched in mean 
δ
13
C when compared to non-lethal exoskeleton samples either side of the moult. This could be related to the reabsorption processes which occurs in spiny lobsters prior to moult (

); however, we had insufficient samples to pursue this theory further.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Our experimentally derived TDF values of ∆13C (4.45 ± 1.04) and ∆15N (4.36 ± 0.6) for dorsal muscle and ∆13C (3.86 ± 0.98) and ∆15N (5.06 ± 0.65) for leg muscle are higher than the mean TDFs reported by 

but do fall in the range of TDFs they found within their analysis. These values are also higher than those found by 

in juvenile 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
New Zealand
. The TDFs we supply here are intended for use with 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
in Tasmania but it would be advantageous to test the validity of the TDFs with the same species in other locations and similar species elsewhere as it appears that the geographic location can influence TDFs within the same species. We provide evidence that TDFs are highly efficient at improving the fit of the wild consumer and prey data (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
We used juvenile 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
because particular individuals had been in captivity for two years prior so we could be certain of their feeding history and being juvenile they were more likely to moult and experience a change of exoskeleton during the experiment. We nevertheless ensured the size range of those in our experiments did overlap with ones caught in the wild for testing of the TDF values to demonstrate that the experimental individuals we sampled were comparable. It must be considered that discrimination factors can be influenced by lobster growth in captivity (

) and rapid growth during this life stage could increase the variability of isotope signatures (

). Despite this, when tested for a range of different-size wild lobsters, our TDFs did outperform others from the literature for 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Tasmania
. It was important to the outcomes of this study to test the validity of our TDFs for larger sized lobsters in the field, as these are likely to be targeted for diet analysis due to their potential to predate on the range-extending sea urchin (

).
</p>
         <p>
We found a significant increase in 
δ
15
N across all treatments in both muscle tissue and in the exoskeleton at 18 mo. We are uncertain whether this could be due to the lobster’s life stage, or influence of upstream terrestrial and/or marine farming on the nitrogen in the untreated tank water. Data on salinity from the water source suggests a significant flood event may have occurred in the 4-mo preceding our 18-mo sampling event (Supplementary material 
Fig. S1
). A flood of fresh water, enriched with land-based fertilisers, could provide reason for higher nutrient loading in the tank water, but we did not see similar enrichment in 
δ
15
N in the samples after a different potential flood event earlier in the experiments, so this conclusion is uncertain. Due to timing and resources, we were unable to run the experiment for longer, but trials like this with different life stages of consumer and which run for longer time periods with regular water nutrient monitoring would be worth further investigation. This rapid change in 
δ
15
N further highlights the importance of sampling sources at the same time as consumers to avoid temporal mismatch in unexpected changing conditions. Our diet species (fish and mussels) are also a potential source of isotopic variation due to external sourcing of the product, which could be improved on in future experiments by ensuring homogeneity of the sources. Further, the 
δ
13
C signature of our sea urchin source was highly variable between individuals and so could be reason for unexpected variation in the consumer. In other studies of the same sea urchin species (
<tp:taxon-name>
C. rodgersii
</tp:taxon-name>
), such a strong variation was not seen (JS, unpublished data), implying this variation requires more research as to whether this could be large individual spread/variation or a sampling error. More investigation into the mechanisms behind short-term stable isotope variability in lobsters and variability of signature between individuals of the same species (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. rodgersii
</tp:taxon-name>
) would improve the reliability of stable isotope methods for dietary analysis.
</p>
         <p>
This study has provided a less invasive, non-lethal sampling protocol for 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
in the wild and TDFs to assess lobster diet in relation to its role as a top-down predator of range-extending pest sea urchins in 
Tasmania
. We have provided evidence that non-lethal sampling of leg muscle in 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
can be used in place of lethally collected dorsal muscle for stable isotope analysis. We showed that experimentally derived, species- and tissue-specific TDFs outperform literature based TDFs for use in diet studies and mixing models for 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. edwardsii
</tp:taxon-name>
in the wild or in the laboratory. We recommend time-relevant sampling of stable isotope tissue samples due to the potential for variability in isotope signatures over a temporal scale.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL
</title>
         <p>
Supplementary material is available at 
Journal of Crustacean Biology
online.
</p>
         <p>S1 Figure. Monthly average of water salinity and temperature during experimental trials. All underlying data for this study</p>
         <p>
were published as open access at the PANGAEA data repository (

, b)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ACK N O W LE D G E M E N TS
</title>
         <p>
We acknowledge the 
palawa
, traditional custodians of 
lutruwita
(
Tasmania
), in which this study took place. JS would like to thank Shenae Willis for laboratory assistance. Funding for stable-isotope analysis was provided by the Fisheries Research and Development Corporation (FRDC project 2021-020 “Stable isotopes: a rapid method to determine lobster diet and trace lobster origin?”) MO was supported by the German Research Foundation (DFG) fellowship 326692763 [https://gepris. dfg.de/gepris/projekt/326692763?language=en]. The authors would like to thank the Derwent Estuary Program for providing water quality data. The authors would also like to thank the anonymous reviewers. The contribution by the authors was as follows: conception: JS, JK; Data collection/analysis: JS; writing: JS, CD; review: JS, CD, JK, MO, CM, CG.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Carolan, J.V.
, 
Mazumder, D.
, 
Dimovski, C.
, 
Diocares, R.
&amp; 
Twining, J.
2012
. 

Biokinetics and discrimination factors for δ13C and δ15N in the omnivorous freshwater crustacean, 
Cherax destructor

. 

Marine and Freshwater Research

, 

63

: 
878–886
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Caut, S.
, 
Angulo, E.
&amp; 
Courchamp, F.
2009
. 

Variation in discrimination factors (Δ 
15
N and Δ 
13
C): The effect of diet isotopic values and applications for diet reconstruction

. 

Journal of Applied Ecology

, 

46

: 
443–453
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Day, J.
, 
Knott, N.A.
, 
Swadling, D.
, 
Ayre, D.
, 
Huggett, M.
&amp; 
Gaston, T.
2022
. 

Non‐lethal sampling does not misrepresent trophic level or dietary sources for 
Sagmariasus verreauxi
(eastern rock lobster)

. 

Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry

, 

37

: e 
9435
[
https://doi. org/10.1002/rcm.9435]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Department of Primary Industries
, 
Parks, Water
and Environment (DPIPWE). 
2018
. 

Tasmanian rock lobster fishery: East Coast stock rebuilding strategy 2013-2023

. 
Department of Primary Industries, Parks, Water and Environment, Hobart, Australia
[
https://fishing. tas.gov.au/Documents/East_Coast_Stock_Rebuilding_Strategy_ Sept18.pdf]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fernandes, R.
, 
Millard, A.R.
, 
Brabec, M.
, 
Nadeau, M.-J.
&amp; 
Grootes, P.
2014
. 
Food reconstruction using isotopic transferred signals (FRUITS): A Bayesian model for diet reconstruction
. 

PLoS ONE

, 

9

: e 
87436
[
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0087436]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fry, B.
2006
. 
Introduction
. In: 

Stable isotope ecology

(
Fry, B.
, ed.), pp. 
1– 20
. 
Springer Science, New York
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gardner, C.
, 
Frusher, S.
, 
Barrett, N.
, 
Haddon, M.
&amp; 
Buxton, C.
2006
. 

Spatial variation in size at onset of maturity of female southern rock lobster 
Jasus edwardsii
around Tasmania, Australia

. 

Scientia Marina

, 

70

: 
423–430
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guest, M.
, 
Frusher, S.
, 
Nichols, P.
, 
Johnson, C.
&amp; 
Wheatley, K.
2009
. 

Trophic effects of fishing southern rock lobster 
Jasus edwardsii
shown by combined fatty acid and stable isotope analyses

. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series

, 

388

: 
169–184
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hutton, F.W.
1875
. 
Descriptions of two new species of Crustacea from New Zealand
. 

Annals and Magazine of Natural History

, Series 4, 

15

: 
41–42
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ling, S.D.
, 
Johnson, C.R.
, 
Frusher, S.D.
&amp; 
Ridgway, K.R.
2009
. 
Overfishing reduces resilience of kelp beds to climate-driven catastrophic phase shift
. 

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America

, 

106

: 
22341–22345
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ling, S.D.
&amp; 
Keane, J.P.
2021
. 

Decadal resurvey of long-term lobster experimental sites to inform
Centrostephanus 
control
(AIRF2019_08)

. 
Institute for Marine and Antarctic Studies, University of Tasmania, Hobart, Tasmania, Australia
https://www.imas.utas.edu.au/__data/
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
MacDiarmid, A.B.
, 
Freeman, D.
&amp; 
Kelly, S.
2013
. 
Rock lobster biology and ecology: Contributions to understanding through the Leigh Marine Laboratory 1962
–2012. 

New Zealand Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research

, 

47

: 
313–333
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Madigan, D.J.
, 
Snodgrass, O.E.
, 
Hyde, J.R.
&amp; 
Dewar, H.
2021
. 

Stable isotope turnover rates and fractionation in captive California yellowtail (
Seriola dorsalis
): Insights for application to field studies

. 

Scientific Reports

, 

11

: 
4466
[
https://doi.org/10.1038/ s41598-021-83880-z]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Martínez del 
Rio, C.
, 
Wolf, N.
, 
Carleton, S.A.
&amp; 
Gannes, L.Z.
2009
. 
Isotopic ecology ten years after a call for more laboratory experiments
. 

Biological Reviews

, 

84

: 
91–111
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mazumder, D.
, 
Johansen, M.P.
, 
Fry, B.
&amp; 
Davis, E.
2018
. 

Muscle and carapace tissue–diet isotope discrimination factors for the freshwater crayfish 
Cherax destructor

. 

Marine and Freshwater Research

, 

69

: 
56–65
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Milne Edwards, H.
1851
. 
Observations sur le squelette tégumentaire des crustacés décapodes et sur la morphologie de ces animaux
. 

Annales des Sciences Naturelles

, Série 3, 

16

: 
221–291
, pls. 8–11.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Parnell, A.
&amp; 
Govan, E.
2019
. 

simmr: A stable isotope mixing model
. R package version 0.5

.0.9000 [
https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=simmr]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Post, D.M.
2002
. 
Using stable isotopes to estimate trophic position: Models, methods, and assumptions
. 

Ecology

, 

83

: 
703–718
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
R 
Core Team
. 
2021
. 

R: A language and environment for statistical computing
.

R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna
[
https:// www.R-project.org/]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
RStudio. 
2020
. 

RStudio: Integrated development environment for R
. [computer software]

. 
RStudio, PBC
, 
Boston, MA
, 
USA
[
http://www.rstudio.com/]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smith, J.E.
, 
Dietz, C.
, 
Keane, J.
, 
Mundy, C.
, 
Oellermann, M.
&amp; 
Gardner, C.
2023
a. 

Stable isotope signatures of native prey of Southern Rock Lobster (
Jasus edwardsii) 
and the range-extending sea urchin
Centrostephanus rodgersii

. 
PANGAEA (Data Publisher for Earth &amp; Environmental Science), Hobart, TAS, Australia
[
https://doi.org/10.1594/ PANGAEA.960320]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smith, J.E.
, 
Dietz, C.
, 
Keane, J.
, 
Mundy, C.
, 
Oellermann, M.
&amp; 
Gardner, C.
2023
b. 

Stable isotope signatures of Southern Rock Lobster (
Jasus edwardsii
) following captive feeding with native prey and the range-extending sea urchin
Centrostephanus rodgersii

. 
PANGAEA (Data Publisher for Earth &amp; Environmental Science), Hobart, TAS, Australia
[
https:// doi.org/10.1594/PANGAEA.960317]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smith, J.E.
, 
Keane, J.
, 
Mundy, C.
, 
Gardner, C.
&amp; 
Oellermann, M.
2022
. 
Spiny lobsters prefer native prey over range-extending invasive urchins
. 

ICES Journal of Marine Science

, 

79

: 
1353–1362
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stock, B.C.
&amp; 

Semmens, B. 

X. 
2016


. 
Unifying error structures in commonly used biotracer mixing models
. 

Ecology

, 

97

: 
2562–2569
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stock, B.C.
&amp; 

Semmens, B. 

X. 
2022


. 

MixSIAR GUI user manual. Version 3.1.2

. 
Zenodo,Organisation Européenne pour la Recherche Nucléaire, Geneva, Switzerland
[https://doi.org/ 
doi:10.5281/zenodo.47719]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Suring, E.
&amp; 
Wing, S.R.
2009
. 

Isotopic turnover rate and fractionation in multiple tissues of red rock lobster (
Jasus edwardsii
) and blue cod (
Parapercis colias
): Consequences for ecological studies

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

370

: 
56–63
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wirtz, A.
, 
Mazumder, D.
, 
Carter, C.G.
, 
Codabaccus, M.B.
, 
Fitzgibbon, Q.P.
&amp; 
Smith, G.G.
2022
. 

Application of stable isotope analysis to evaluate the assimilation of protein sources in juvenile slipper lobsters (
Thenus australiensis
)

. 

Aquaculture

, 

560

: 
738570
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2022.738570]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wolf, N.
, 
Carleton, S.A.
&amp; Martínez del 
Rio, C.
2009
. 
Ten years of experimental animal isotopic ecology
. 

Functional Ecology

, 

23

: 
17–26
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zoutendyk, P.
1988
. 

Carbon and nitrogen losses through moulting in the Cape rock lobster 
Jasus lalandii

. 

South African Journal of Zoology

, 

23

: 
173–175
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
