<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of Crustacean Biology</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jcbiol/ruad035</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Beneath the surface: correlates of solitary, paired, and group living in a cryptic burrowing ghost shrimp Trypaea australiensis Dana, 1852 (Decapoda: Axiidea: Calianassidae)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>11</day>
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
Dana, 1852
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
Dana, 1852
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Callianassidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
regalis
(
Duffy, 1996
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Alpheidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hippolytidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Palaemonidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pinnotheridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alpheus bellulus
(
Miya &amp; Miyake, 1969
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. bellulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ascidonia flavomaculata
(
Heller, 1864
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ascidonia miserabilis
(
Holthuis, 1951
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Callianassidae 
Dana, 1852
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
(
Dana, 1852
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Callichirus seilacheri
(
Bott, 1955
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Neotrypaea californiensis
(
Dana, 1854
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Upogebia pugettensis
(
Dana, 1852
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Callianassa japonica
(
Ortmann, 1891
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lepidophthalmus bocourti
(A. 
Milne-Edwards, 1870
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Beneath the surface: correlates of solitary, paired, and group living in a cryptic burrowing ghost shrimp 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
Dana, 1852
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
: Axiidea: Calianassidae)

</p>
         <p>
Renae L. Kirby
and 
Marian Y.L. Wong
</p>
         <p>
School of Earth, Atmospheric and Life Sciences, University of Wollongong, Wollongong, NSW 2522, 
Australia
</p>
         <p>Correspondence:R. L.Kirby; e-mail address: 26rkirby@gmail.com</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A B ST R A CT
</title>
         <p>
Marine organisms, particularly invertebrates, are relatively understudied regarding social structure and behaviour, especially those that are cryptic. While empirically challenging to investigate, these species can provide novel insights into the evolution of sociality given their unique ecology. Our aim was to quantify 
in-situ
the social structure and its underlying correlates in the Australian burrowing shrimp, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
Dana, 1852
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Callianassidae</tp:taxon-name>
). We show that 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibits intraspecific variation in social structure, being most often found in solitary arrangements, frequently in pairs (including homosexual and heterosexual arrangements), and sometimes in groups. The majority of shrimp in pairs and groups were found in heterosexual pairings or groups of 
one male
and multiple females. Variation in social structure was correlated with variation in body size characteristics, seasonality, and site. These findings demonstrate that a wider array of social structures are exhibited by this species than previously expected, but the obvious limitations associated with sampling a cryptic burrowing species 
in situ
mean that further investigations under controlled conditions, including laboratory behavioural manipulations, will be needed to confirm the current findings. The use of resin casts to understand burrow morphology would be important for understanding the causes of intraspecific variation in this and other cryptic species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
KEY WORDS:
behaviour
, 
Crustacea
, 
cryptic species
, 
mating system
, 
sociality
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
Social living has been reported in a wide range of animal taxa, although explanations for why sociality exists are controversial, largely due to its complexity in nature (

). These living arrangements, also termed social structures, can be described as either solitary (an individual arrangement), paired (two individuals living together, either a dyad or reproductive pair) or group forming (

). While these structures suggest a form of permanency (e.g., monogamous pairings or eusocial groups for joint defence and offspring care) (Duffy, 2002; 

; 

; 

; 

), they can also be formed temporarily (e.g., temporary mate guarding) (

; 

). These arrangements can be described as strict (wherein species typically never deviate from their chosen lifestyle) (Duffy, 2002; 

; 

) or facultative (in which a given species can be seen to have several 
types
of social arrangements) (

, 

; 

; 

). Understanding the nature of social associations is important as they can influence individual fitness, but also because they are often linked to or influence the surrounding ecosystem as many species play vital roles in maintaining their habitats, i.e., ecosystem engineers (

; 

). With this in mind, environmental change can severely impact these interactions, leading to extensive consequences for the wider community. For example, impacts on ecosystem engineers could have effects on the surrounding ecosystem as their role has both direct and indirect effects on community composition (

; 

; 

). Gaining an understanding of animal social structures is therefore vital to ensure all species maintain their roles, and to ensure the continued functioning of the ecosystems they reside in.
</p>
         <p>
Marine invertebrates have the potential to exhibit an array of different social structures and can generate novel insights into current theories of social evolution (

; 

; 

; 

). For example, the snapping shrimp 
Synapheus
<tp:taxon-name>
regalis
(
Duffy, 1996
)
</tp:taxon-name>
lives within the canals of sponges (

) and display eusociality, whereby individuals reside in large groups. This results in overlapping generations and a division of labour for defence and offspring care (Duffy, 2002; 

; 

; 

; 

). The group’s reproductive individuals typically consist of 
one queen
and her mate (Duffy, 2002; 

), while the remaining non-breeding group members are allocated to parental care or colony defences (Duffy, 2002; 

; 

). Kinship is thought to be the main factor promoting sociality in species of snapping shrimps, owing to high genetic relatedness between breeders and non-breeders (

; 

; 

). In comparison, many other species of decapods live in pairs with monogamous mating systems (i.e., 
<tp:taxon-name>Alpheidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Hippolytidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Palaemonidae</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>Pinnotheridae</tp:taxon-name>
) (

; 

; 

; 

); for example, the burrowing shrimp 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alpheus bellulus
(
Miya &amp; Miyake, 1969
)
</tp:taxon-name>
only occurs in monogamous pairs as adults with the pair-bond forming early in their life (

; 

; 

, 

). It is believed that 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. bellulus
</tp:taxon-name>
pair bonds form due to the benefits of joint burrow defence and maintenance, and the provision of a readily accessible mate. Finally, certain species of shrimps are solitary, like the ascidian-associated shrimps 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ascidonia flavomaculata
(
Heller, 1864
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ascidonia miserabilis
(
Holthuis, 1951
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, which live solitarily within a branch of the host ascidian due to competition for resources (i.e., shelter and food) (

; 

). Only temporary mating pairs form, whereby males leave the safety of their shelter in search of females, and males subsequently leave once brooded embryos are established, suggesting a temporary mate guarding system within an overall solitary social structure (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
While various studies have investigated the social structure of sponge-dwelling shrimps and other crustaceans, burrowing mud shrimps, otherwise known as callianassid shrimp (
<tp:taxon-name>
Callianassidae 
Dana, 1852
</tp:taxon-name>
) have been somewhat overlooked. Callianassid shrimps typically have elongated, fragile soft bodies that are protected by calcified plates along the dorsal length of their bodies, as well as possessing three sets of pleopods for swimming and two chelipeds (one of which is enlarged) (

). Their highly cryptic lifestyles make detailed quantification of their social structures much more challenging, as their subterranean burrows allow them to hide and otherwise avoid exposure. As a result, relatively little is known about their social and mating associations (

; 

, 

) compared to their reproductive and population biology (

; 

; 

). Social and mating systems have typically been inferred indirectly, establishing a lack of empirical studies that directly quantify mating and social associations (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

). An understanding of the causes and consequences of sociality in these callianassid shrimps is essential as they are important ecosystem engineers that affect the surrounding environment and the biota residing in it (

; 

). Behaviour can influence ecological outcomes (i.e., predator-prey, community assembly, human disturbance, ecosystem engineers), and therefore any change in the behaviour or structure of a species can change the ecosystem as a whole. As a result, we must gain a better understanding of their social and reproductive associations to ensure these roles are continued to maintain a functioning ecosystem.
</p>
         <p>
Australia
is home to an endemic burrowing mud shrimp, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
(
Dana, 1852
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, with populations that span along the east coast from northern 
Queensland
to southern 
Victoria
(

; 

). Several studies have shown that female and male differences are apparent within a given population of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, with males being slightly larger in size compared to females (

; 

; 

, 

). Males are also characterised by an enlarged chela, with the difference in chela size attributed to sex rather than body length (male chela typically larger than that of females) (

; 

; 

; 

). One study of the breeding cycle of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
confirmed discontinuous (seasonal, production one to five broods) reproduction of a population from the 
New South Wales
(NSW) coast of 
Australia
, with ovigerous females appearing only during the warmer months (

). Like other callianassids, 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is an important ecosystem engineer, affecting the water quality during their burrow formation and maintenance, this then impacting the surrounding flora and fauna (

; 

; 

; 

). Furthermore, 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is of great importance to the commercial and recreational fisheries industry, both on a social and economic scale, as a bait source (

; 

). 

showed on average (over one trip), anglers were taking in excess of 200 individuals, while the NSW Department of Primary Industries (DPI) indicated that 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
was moderately fished. DPI then implemented a bag limit for recreational fishermen and a total allowable catch of 
5.1 tonnes
for commercial fisheries, with no discrimination of shrimp sex or size. According to the 2020/2021 stock assessment (

), the fishery for the species is now sustainable. These assessments (which the DPI have acknowledged) have nevertheless potentially underestimated the populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
due to the significant amount of time that has lapsed between survey periods and surveys only being conducted at one location. Without an accurate representation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
populations and the effectiveness of these non-discriminate size/ sex catch limits, such lack of understanding regarding species and population ecology has the potential to affect the structure and persistence of their populations. Therefore, research that is focused on understanding the social structure and reproductive behaviour of the species is vital to ensure proper management of populations. This in turn will sustain fisheries and the optimal functioning of the estuarine mud-flat ecosystems.
</p>
         <p>
We aimed to quantify the social associations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and to investigate, 
in situ
, the correlates of any variation in social associations. There are clear limitations of sampling within a cryptic environment, i.e., individuals residing within burrows may be missed or sampled from neighbouring burrows because of an inability to see the organisms and the burrows. Our study provides a baseline for the potential range of social associations that could be exhibited by this species.
</p>
         <p>
We hypothesised that 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
has the potential of being found in a given burrow as either a solitary individual, as a pair (of either heterosexual or homosexual composition), or as a group of three or more shrimp, given the diverse array of social structures exhibited by other shrimp species (

; 

; 

). Furthermore, we aimed to investigate the correlates of social association in this species. Specifically, we considered a number of key ecological factors (site and season) and morphological features (body size, sex, and sexual maturity). We finally investigated the sexual composition of any pairs and groups observed to infer the 
type
of mating system exhibited by this species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
METHODS
</title>
         <p>Sampling</p>
         <p>

The social structure of the burrowing shrimp 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
was studied between 

September 2018
and 
August 2019

along the southeastern coast of 
New South Wales
, 
Australia
. 
Monthly
sampling was conducted at three estuarine locations including, 
Maianbar
at 
Port Hacking
, 
Shoalhaven Heads Inlet
at 
Shoalhaven Heads
, and 
Garlandtown
on the 
Moruya River
(
Fig. 1
). 
Each
site is characterised by a sandy/muddy substratum, typical of estuarine ecosystems

.
</p>
         <p>
Sampling at each of the three sites was conducted two to three hours before low tide in the mid-low intertidal zone. To collect the shrimp, a typical burrow opening was randomly selected and pumped four to six times with a standard nipper pump (
76 cm
in length, 
5 cm
diameter).As these burrows can have multiple openings (a typical burrow as described by 

, a minimum of one-meter distance between burrows and areas where burrows were less densely orientated were selected to avoid the potential of resampling the same burrow. This methodology has been used effectively in several studies (

; 

; 

; 

; 

, 

). Each shrimp from a burrow was collected and assigned individual burrow and shrimp identification numbers. Shrimp were secured on a board, and scaled photographs of the ventral side of each individual were taken for later verification of sex and size (
Fig 1
). Sex was determined by the presence of the second pair of pleopods, which are absent in males and present in females (

). The carapace length and the propodus of the enlarged cheliped length were measured to the nearest 
0.1mm
using plastic callipers and recorded on waterproof paper. The position (left or right) of the major cheliped was also recorded. After measurements were taken, shrimp were then released back to an adjacent area where they were pumped from and monitored until they had safely burrowed again.
</p>
         <p>Statistical analysis</p>
         <p>
To establish the social structure of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, we first considered whether individuals occurred predominantly in solitary, paired or group associations in burrows. We used SPSS statistical software (

) and investigated whether or not burrow distributions differed significantly from that of a random distribution, using a nonparametric Chi-square goodness-of-fit test, comparing observed with Poisson distributions. A multinomial logistic regression model was conducted to assess whether the social structure was affected by site, seasonality, and morphological factors. The model contained social structure (solitary, paired or group) as a categorical response, categorical predictors of site, season, carapace length (mm) and cheliped length (mm), and burrow ID as a random factor was completed. A reference category was specified with odds ratios used to compare the odds of the response category (social structure) to the odds of each level with the predictor category site, season, carapace length and cheliped length, assuming that all predictor variables are constant.
</p>
         <p>
Sexual
dimorphism was investigated using a simple paired t-test comparing the cheliped length of male and female shrimp. 
Average
cheliped length was also compared between the sexes to establish if sexual dimorphism was present. 
Lastly
, pairs and groups were considered separately to further investigate their composition by sex and sexual maturity (this included all representative samples collected: 225 paired shrimp and 55 groups, rather than the previous analysis with a reduced data set to remove missing values as a result of missing morphological data). 
Summary
tables were generated showing the overall trends for paired and grouped shrimp separately. 
Sexual
maturity was determined for males and females via the values provided by 

, wherein they used REGRANS relative growth models to extrapolate an inflection point (i.e., the point at which relative growth curves of juveniles and adults join) that indicates the size at which sexual maturity starts. 
Each
pair and group were then defined as either adult-only or juveniles present (the latter referring to groups with adults and juveniles as well as juveniles-only groups). 
Sexual
composition was categorised into three main categories for pairs: heterosexual (male/female), homosexual male (male/male), or homosexual female (female/ female) compositions. A chi-square goodness-of-fit test was conducted to determine if there were differences associated between the different sex compositions. 
For
groups, sexual composition was classed as: all same sex, equal males and females, 
one female

and two or more males, 
one male
and two or more females, or 
two males
with 
three females
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
RESULTS
</title>
         <p>Shrimp social structure</p>
         <p>
A total of 1,786 specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
from 1,430 burrows were sampled between 
September 2018
and 
August 2019
at all three sites. After statistical cleaning, removal of samples with missing values and preliminary analysis of the data, 1,708 shrimp from 1,368 burrows were analysed to determine shrimp social structure (
Fig 2
). The chi-square goodness-of-fit test revealed that shrimp were predominantly found in solitary arrangements (80.3% of burrows, 
N
= 1,098), than in pairs (15.7% of burrows, 
N
= 430), then substantially less in groups (4% of burrows, 
N
= 180) (Chi-square goodness-of-fit, Χ 
2
= 791.25, 
P
&lt;0.000).
</p>
         <p>
When considering site, seasonality, and body size effects on the social structure of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
; site and season were found to have the most influence on shrimp social structure. Among sites, shrimp in paired and group associations were more likely to occur at Port Hacking and Moruya compared to Shoalhaven Heads, and solitary shrimp were more likely to occur at Shoalhaven Heads than at Port Hacking and Moruya (
Table 1
, Supplementary material 
Fig. S1
). Social structure was also related to meteorological season (summer, autumn, winter, and spring). Paired shrimp were more likely to occur during the summer and spring months rather than in winter compared to solitary shrimp (
Table 1
, Supplementary material 
Fig. S2
). Specifically, there were 11% more paired shrimp in the spring than in winter and 9.3% more paired than solitary shrimp in summer than in winter relative to solitary shrimp. individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
found within a particular burrow. Analyses considered effects of yearly season, site, carapace length (mm),
</p>
         <p>and cheliped length (mm) on social structure, with a random effect of burrow identification added. Reference category selected for site is</p>
         <p>
Shoalhaven Heads, and the reference category for season is winter. Bold probability values with (*) indicate statistical significance at 
P
&lt;0.05. Odds ratios also indicated that group arrangements were slightly more likely to occur in spring and summer months than winter when compared to paired shrimp. Furthermore, when comparing paired to solitary shrimp, there was no difference between autumn and winter (
Table 1
, Supplementary material 
Fig. S2
). Body size measurements of carapace length and cheliped length showed no significant effect on social structure (
Table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>Sexual dimorphism</p>
         <p>
Of the shrimp that had claws measured, 987 were females and 
721 males
. The enlarged cheliped length ranged from 
1.2 mm
to 
22.1 mm
in females and 
1.2 mm
to 
27.7 mm
in males. The average enlarged cheliped length was statistically different between male and female shrimp, with males having longer cheliped lengths (mean 
13.43mm
), whereas females had smaller chelipeds (mean 
9.70 mm
) (t test = –114.40, 
df
= 1707, 
P
&lt;0.05). There was no statistically significant difference in the mean carapace lengths of females (
11.18 mm
) and males (
11.30 mm
).
</p>
         <p>Sex composition in pairs</p>
         <p>
A total of 225 pairs were collected across the three sites, comprising either male/female pair (
N
= 135), male/male (
N
= 29), or female/ female (
N
= 61) (
Table 2
). The frequency observed for each of the sex compositions differed significantly from the expected frequencies reported (Χ2 = 76.85, 
P
&lt;0.001). Overall, a negative difference between observed and expected frequencies of male/ male and female/female pairings, while heterosexual pairings had a positive difference. Considering sexual maturity, pairs consisted of either 
two juveniles
, 
two adults
, or 
one adult
and 
one juvenile
. The majority of pairs collected consisted of 
two adults
(76%), rather than pairs with 
one juvenile
and 
one adult
(20%), or 
two juveniles
(4%). Trends show that heterosexual pairings occurred at higher frequencies than rather than homosexual pairings regardless of sexual maturity (
Table 2
).
</p>
         <p>Sex composition in groups</p>
         <p>
A total of 55 groups (ranging in size from three to five individuals) were collected across the three field sites comprising either all same sex (either all male or all female), equal numbers of both sexes, 
one female
with multiple males, 
one male
with multiple females or 
two males
with 
three females
(
Fig. 3
, 
Table 3
). There was a trend where more groups consisted of 
one male
and multiple females compared to all other sex compositions except for 
one female
and multiple male groups, with 58.3% of groups exhibiting 
one male
with multiple females. Groups consisting of 
one female
and multiple males contributed approximately 27.1%. Same-sex groups made up a small percentage of the groups sampled (approximately 14.6%). Groups with an even number of males and females contributed 10.4% and groups with 
two males
and 
three females
made up the smallest percentage of 4.2%.
</p>
         <p>
Groups shared similar trends of sex composition regardless of juvenile presence. More groups comprising of all adults were found (74.5%), followed by groups with 
one juvenile
and the rest adults (21.8%). One representative burrow comprising of only juveniles was also collected, showing 
one male
and multiple females present. A burrow that had adults and 
two juveniles
was also collected in a sex composition of 
one female
and multiple males.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Trypaea australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
can occupy burrows either solitarily or forming social groups; i.e., paired or in small groups of up to five individuals. Although the solitary mode was dominant in the population studied, a great proportion of the total shrimp (35.7%) were found forming pairs or other associations within their respective burrows. Shrimp were mostly found as solitary individuals rather than paired or in groups. There was also a variation in the prevalence of different social structures across sites. Shrimp in paired and group associations were more likely to occur at Port Hacking and Moruya than at Shoalhaven Heads.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
When investigating the correlates of social associations, it was found that pairs were more likely to occur during the warmer seasons (i.e., spring and summer) rather than in the winter. Given that 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
typically breeds in warmer months (

), paired shrimp could be occurring for reproductive reasons. Such pairings are likely temporary, given the predominance of solitary shrimp that were obtained. Such transient associations in other callianassid shrimps have been shown in other studies, occurring through the creation of temporary burrow connections by neighbouring shrimp (

; 

), where male shrimp create horizontal burrow connections to neighbouring female burrows (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). Having done so, males then mate with the female before returning to their burrows and closing the burrow connection (

). This behaviour further supports suggestions of temporary pairing for breeding purposes, as opposed to formations of stable monogamous pairs. Similarly, 

study on the Eastern Pacific 
<tp:taxon-name>
Callichirus seilacheri
(
Bott, 1955
)
</tp:taxon-name>
found that heterosexual pairings were short-termed that only 7% of the sampled burrows exhibited heterosexual pairs (much less than expected for socially monogamous species). From our study, 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibited adult-only pairs that were more frequently composed of heterosexual pairings when compared to pairs with juveniles and of similar-size individuals, again suggesting temporary pairing for breeding purposes. The observations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
are nevertheless preliminary, requiring further investigations of burrow interconnection frequency, mating behaviours, and analyses of parentage to verify the mating system in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
as well as in other callianassid species.
</p>
         <p>
If
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
does form temporary pairs, why not form stable monogamous pairs on a permanent basis, as seen in other crustaceans (i.e., 

; 

; 

)? 
Long-term
monogamy is usually the result of the need for biparental care of young, particularly seen in birds (

; 

; 

). 
The
bi-parental care hypothesis is, however, unlikely to apply to callianassid shrimps as their eggs hatch into free-swimming larvae, after which little parental care is needed (

; 

). 
Alternatively
, it has been suggested that resource limitation and distribution could promote long-term monogamy (

; 

; 

). 
As
callianassid species appear unlimited by mudflat habitat and planktonic food resources, it is also unlikely that callianassids will form permanent pairs due to patchy and limited resources. 
If
one considers burrows as the limiting resource, which is possible due to the energetic costs of burrowing and maintenance (

, 

; RLK, unpublished data), the benefits of joint territory defence and maintenance could select for pair-bonding and long-term monogamy instead. 
It
is noteworthy that some pairs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
consisted of 
two females
or 
two males
, although the former was more prevalent. This pairing suggests that other factors, besides reproduction, could explain some instances of pair-formation, whether temporary or permanent in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>

.
</p>
         <p>
Sexual dimorphism could explain the predominance of solitary shrimp in our study, given the average cheliped length for males was found to be statistically larger than for females. As is seen in other callianassid species, individuals with a larger major cheliped (most often males) are typically more likely to protect or infiltrate burrows, and successfully gain access to mates (

; 

; 

). Furthermore, as burrow construction is costly (RLK, unpublished data), the formation of these temporary pairs, and even single-sex pairings, could arise due to the benefits of joint burrow maintenance and construction. The temporary nature of pair forming could be furthered by the maturity composition of the pairings collected, wherein heterosexual pairs were predominant and single-sex pairs were rarely comprised of two sexually mature adults. This sex composition could therefore show a strong competition between adult males, further evident by the lack of burrows shown to be occupied by males together.
</p>
         <p>
While adult-only pairs were more likely to occur as heterosexual or female-female pairs, pairs consisting of an adult and a juvenile exhibited a greater range of sex compositions. Given that adult-juvenile pairs could not be formed for immediate breeding purposes, they could instead be formed to increase the survival of juveniles living under the protection of a larger individual and its burrow. Indeed, burrow cast studies of callianassids have shown that juveniles cohabit with adult shrimp via a smaller burrow branch off the main adult burrow (

; 

; RLK, unpublished data).
</p>
         <p>

In addition, other callianassids typically take 1–1.5 months for larval settlement, and, from settlement, approximately one to two years to reach sexual maturity (

; 

). Cohabiting with a larger adult during this time may enable juveniles to safely grow until they reach sexual maturity and become able to defend their own burrow. We also occasionally found groups during sampling, suggesting a facultative social system. Such groups mostly consisted of 
one male
and multiple females, suggesting that groups may form due to reproductive purposes where males compete to monopolise multiple females. 
Indeed
sexual dimorphism in claw size is present in this species, with males typically having larger cheliped length than females, in support of male-male competition over females (

). 
Furthermore
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
becomes reproductively mature rather quickly, likely due to their short lifespan (

). 
Studies
on other burrowing shrimp species, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neotrypaea californiensis
(
Dana, 1854
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Upogebia pugettensis
(
Dana, 1852
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Callianassa japonica
(
Ortmann, 1891
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, have shown that success rates for viable offspring are much higher in the larger individuals (

; 

). 
From
a reproductive standpoint, it would therefore be more advantageous for males to gain access to larger females for copulation (

). 
If
this indeed occurs on the mudflats, it would explain why larger individuals have been found together in groups, as males will likely prefer access to larger females

.
</p>
         <p>
The limitations imposed by sampling within a cryptic environment, as well as shrimp size and the complexity of the burrows of callianassid species (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

), mean that individuals residing in burrows could simply have not been sampled. This would not only overestimate the proportion of the population apparently associating singly but also underestimate the proportion in social arrangements, i.e., pairs and groups. Additionally, studies have shown that other species of callianassids occurring in pairs (

; 

) occupy different sections within a burrow when individuals are larger in size, while smaller shrimp reside together (

; 

). Meaning that individuals from the same burrow could have been missed during sampling in our study. Juvenile size may have also played a role in sampling bias as sediment turnover from pumps creates low visibility when collecting them. Although each burrow was pumped multiple times, thereby increasing the chances of finding all shrimp present within the burrow, we recognise that some individuals residing within the burrow could simply have escaped sampling.
</p>
         <p>
While the limitations of our study are apparent due to the cryptic nature of the species, our findings do suggest a greater variety of social structures are exhibited by this species than expected. To date, another burrowing shrimp, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lepidophthalmus bocourti
(A. 
Milne-Edwards, 1870
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, has been found to exhibit similar facultative social arrangements (

). Therefore, the current study as well as studies by 

and 

represent the first key insights into burrowing shrimp social structures and provide the foundations for future work into understanding cryptic species associations.
</p>
         <p>
Our study suggests that the social structure in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is adaptive, linked to spatial (i.e., local factors) and temporal (i.e., breeding season) factors. This situation suggests either a facultative social structure or to the result of sampling limitations, a predominantly solitary lifestyle with temporary social interactions. The formation of pairs and groups could reflect either a temporary arrangement for reproductive reasons or possibly joint territorial defence, although further observations and experimental manipulations in controlled settings are required to verify these hypotheses. Social arrangements were also related to a range of factors, including sampling site, seasonality, and cheliped and carapace size, suggesting complex underlying reasons for the expression of different social structures. Future research into the social structure and mating system of the species would greatly benefit from the use of laboratory experiments to quantify behaviour within burrows, particularly between males and females in pairs and groups, as well as genetic analyses to quantify parentage and their mating system. Our study nevertheless provides the first detailed assessment of sociality in a highly cryptic crustacean and provides the necessary foundations for future work unravelling the social structure, behaviour, and mating systems of this and other burrowing species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
SUPPLE M EN TARY M ATERIAL
</title>
         <p>
Supplementary material is available at 
Journal of Crustacean Biology
online.
</p>
         <p>
S1 Figure. The percentages of burrows containing solitary individuals, and pair and group arrangements across sampling sites (
N
= 1,368).
</p>
         <p>
S2 Figure. Percentage of burrows sampled with either a single, paired, or a group of shrimp collected within a given season across all sites (
N
= 1,368).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
</title>
         <p>
We would like to thank the following for help with fieldwork at various times during this project: Charlotte Brown, Kurtis Croucher, Brett Kirby, Katelyn Kirby, Adrian Plummer, and Oskar Sebben. We also like to thank Prof. Marijka Batterham, Statistical Consulting Centre in the National Institute of Applied Statistics Research 
Australia
, for her assistance with some of the statistical analyses in SPSS. A special thank you to Katelyn Kirby for those final proofreads/comments. Thank you also to both anonymous reviewers for your guidance to improve this manuscript. This work was generously funded by the Department of Primary Industries, Recreational Fisheries Trust (Project LS048). RK was also funded by an Australian Government Research Training Program Scholarship. All authors certify that they have no affiliations with or involvement in any organization or entity with any financial interest or non-financial interest in the subject matter or materials discussed in this manuscript. The authors have no competing interests to declare that are relevant to the content of this article. No approval of research ethics committees at the University of Wollongong was required to accomplish the goals of this study, as experimental work was conducted with invertebrate species not regulated by the committee. The authors declare that all necessary approvals for sampling of specimens have been obtained and conducted under a Fisheries 
New South Wales
permit (permit no. F95/269-8.2). The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request. Author contributions: Renae Kirby: study concept and design, data collection, statistical analysis, writing, reviewing and editing; Dr. Marian Wong: study concept and design, supervision, writing, reviewing and editing. All authors consent to participate. All authors and all institutions that provided funding and to which the authors belong consent to the publication of this study.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alves, D.F.R.
, 
Barros-Alves, S.
, 
Almeida, A.C.
, 
Cobo, V.J.
&amp; 
Bauer, R.T.
2021
. 

Mating system of the snapping shrimp 
Synalpheus brevicarpus
(Caridea,Alpheidae) inhabiting sponges 
Dysidea
sp.(Demospongiae)

. 

Biological Bulletin

, 

240

: 
132–143
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baeza, J.A.
&amp; 
Díaz-Valdés, M.
2011
. 

The symbiotic shrimp 
Ascidonia flavomaculata
lives solitarily in the tunicate 
Ascidia

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baeza, J.A.
, 
Simpson, L.
, 
Ambrosio, L.J.
, 
Guéron, R.
&amp; 
Mora, N.
2016
. 
Monogamy in a hyper-symbiotic shrimp
. 

PLoS ONE

, 

11

: e 
0149797
[
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0149797]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Berkenbusch, K.
&amp; 
Rowden, A.A.
2003
. 
Ecosystem engineering: Moving away from ‘just-so’ stories
. 

New Zealand Journal of Ecology

, 

27

: 
283–292
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bilodeau, A.L.
, 
Felder, D.L.
&amp; 
Neigel, J.E.
2005
. 

Multiple paternity in the thalassinidean ghost shrimp, 
Callichirus islagrande
(Crustacea: Decapoda: Callianassidae)

. 

Marine Biology

, 

146

: 
381–385
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bird, F.L.
&amp; 
Poore, G.C.B.
1999
. 

Functional burrow morphology of 
Biffarius arenosus
(Decapoda: Callianassidae) from southern Australia

. 

Marine Biology

, 

134

: 
77–87
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Black, J.M.
2001
. 
Fitness consequences of long-term pair bonds in barnacle geese:Monogamy in the extreme
. 

Behavioral Ecology

, 

12

: 
640–645
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bott, R.
1955

Dekapoden (Crustacea) aus El Salvador. 2. Litorale Dekapoden, ausser 
Uca

. 

Senckenbergiana biologica

, 

36

: 
47–70
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Boltaña, S.
&amp; 
Thiel, M.
2001
. 

Associations between two species of snapping shrimp, 
Alpheus inca
and 
Alpheopsis chilensis
(Decapoda: Caridea: Alpheidae)

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 

81

: 
633–638
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bourke, A.
2011
. 

Principles of social evolution

. 
Oxford University Press, Oxford
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Butler, S.N.
&amp; 
Bird, F.L.
2008
. 

Temporal changes in burrow structure of the thalassinidean ghost shrimps 
Trypaea australiensis
and 
Biffarius arenosus

. 

Journal of Natural History

, 

42

: 
2041–2062
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Candisani, L.C.
, 
Sumida, P.Y.G.
&amp; 
Pires-Vanin, A.M.S.
2001
. 

Burrow morphology and mating behaviour of the thalassinidean shrimp 
Upogebia noronhensis

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 

81

: 
799–803
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chak, S.T.C.
, 
Bauer, R.
&amp; 
Thiel, M.
2015
. 
Social behaviour and recognition in decapod shrimps, with emphasis on the Caridea
. In: 

Social recognition in invertebrates

(
L. Aquiloni
&amp; 
E. Tricarico
, eds.), pp. 
57–84
. 
Springer, Cham, Switzerland
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chick, R.C.
2021
. 

NSW stock status summary 2020/21 – Estuary general fishery (hand gathering) – Ghost nipper (
Trypaea australiensis)

. 
New South Wales Department of Primary Industries, Port Stephens, NSW, Australia
[
https://www.dpi.nsw.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_ file/0011/1294760/stock-status-summary-2020-21-nipper-v2.pdf]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Coelho, V.
, 
Cooper, R.
&amp; 
de Almeida Rodrigues, S.
2000
. 

Burrow morphology and behavior of the mud shrimp 
Upogebia omissa
(Decapoda: Thalassinidea: Upogebiidae)

. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series

, 

200

: 
229–240
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Coleman, F.C.
&amp; 
Williams, S.L.
2002
. 
Overexploiting marine ecosystem engineers: Potential consequences for biodiversity
. 

Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution

, 

17

: 
40–44
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Contessa, L.
&amp; 
Bird, F.L.
2004
. 

The impact of bait-pumping on populations of the ghost shrimp 
Trypaea australiensis
Dana 1852 (Decapoda: Callianassidae)andthesedimentenvironment

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

304

: 
75–97
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Correa, C.
&amp; 
Thiel, M.
2003
. 
Mating systems in caridean shrimp (Decapoda: Caridea) and their evolutionary consequences for sexual dimorphism and reproductive biology
. 

Revista Chilena de Historia Natural

, 

76

: 
187–203
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dana, J.D.
1852
. 
Conspectus crustaceorum, &amp;c. Conspectus of the Crustacea of the exploring expedition under Capt. C. Wilkes, U.S.N. Macroura
. 

Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia

, 

6

: 
10–28
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dana, J.D.
1854
. 
Catalogue and descriptions of Crustacea collected in California by Dr. John L. Le Conte
. 

Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia

, 

7

: 
175–177
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Detto, T.
&amp; 
Backwell, P.R.Y.
2009
. 

Social monogamy in a fiddler crab, 
Uca capricornis

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

29

: 
283–289
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Duffy, J.E.
1996
. 

Synalpheus regalis
, new species, a sponge-dwelling shrimp from the Belize Barrier Reef, with comments on host specificity in 
Synalpheus

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

16

: 
564–573
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Duffy, J.E.
2002
. 
The ecology and evolution of eusociality in sponge dwelling shrimp
. In: 

Genes, behaviour, and evolution in social insects

(
T. Kikuchi
. ed.), pp. 
217–254
. 
University of Hokkaido Press, Sapporo, Japan
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Duffy, J.E.
&amp; 
Macdonald, K.S.
2010
. 
Kin structure, ecology and the evolution of social organization in shrimp: A comparative analysis
. 

Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences

, 

277

: 
575–584
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Duffy, J.E.
&amp; 
Thiel, M.
(eds.). 
2007
. 

Evolutionary ecology of social and sexual systems: Crustaceans as model organisms

. 
Oxford University Press, Oxford
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Duffy, J.E.
, 
Morrison, C.
&amp; 
Macdonald, K.
2002
. 

Colony defense and behavioral differentiation in the eusocial shrimp 
Synalpheus regalis

. 

Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology

, 

51

: 
488–495
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dumbauld, B.R.
, 
Armstrong, D.A.
&amp; 
Feldman, K.
1996
. 

Life-history characteristics of two sympatric thalassinidean shrimps, 
Neotrypaea californiensis
and 
Upogebia pugettensi
s, with implications for oyster culture

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

16

: 
689–708
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dworschak, P.C.
, 
Koller, H.
&amp; 
Abed-Navandi, D.
2006
. 

Burrow structure, burrowing and feeding behaviour of 
Corallianassa longiventris
and 
Pestarella tyrrhena
(Crustacea, Thalassinidea, Callianassidae)

. 

Marine Biology

, 

148

: 
1369–1382
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Emlen, S.T.
&amp; 
Oring, L.W.
1977
. 
Ecology, sexual selection, and the evolution of mating systems
. 

Science

, 

197

: 
215–223
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Felder, D.L.
&amp; 
Lovett, D.L.
1989
. 

Relative growth and sexual maturation in the estuarine ghost shrimp 
Callianassa louisianensis
Schmitt

, 1935. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 

9

: 
540–553
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Griffis, R.
&amp; 
Suchanek, T.
1991
. 
A model of burrow architecture and trophic modes in thalassinidean shrimp (Decapoda: Thalassinidea)
. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series

, 

79

: 
171–183
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hailstone, T.S.
&amp; 
Stephenson, W.
1961
. 

The biology of 
Callianassa
(
Trypaea
) 
australiensis
Dana, 1852 (Crustacea, Thalassinidea)

. 

University of Queensland Papers Department of Zoology

, 

1

: 
259–282
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Heller, C.
1864
. 
Horae dalmatinae. Bericht über eine Reise nach der Ostküste des adriatischen Meeres
. 

Verhandlungen der kaiserlich-königlichen zoologisch-botanischen Gesellschaft in Wien

, 

14

: 
17–64
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hernáez, P.
&amp; 
João, M.C.A.
2018
. 

Social structure, sexual dimorphism and relative growth in the ghost shrimp 
Callichirus seilacheri
(Bott, 1955) (Decapoda, Axiidea, Callianassidae) from the tropical eastern Pacific

. 

Marine Biology Research

, 

14

: 
856–867
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hernáez, P.
, 
Mugnai, R.
, 
Souza-Filho, J.F.
&amp; 
Pinheiro, M.A.A.
2022
. 

Monogamy in the burrowing shrimp 
Axianassa australis
Rodrigues &amp; Shimizu, 1992 (Decapoda, Gebiidea, Axianassidae)

. 

Biological Bulletin

, 

242

: 
87–96
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hernáez, P.
, 
Villegas-Castro,E.
, 
João, M.C.A.
, 
Duarte, R.C.
&amp; 
Rivadeneira, M.M.
2021
. 

Inferring the mating system in the burrowing shrimp 
Lepidophthalmus bocourti
(Decapoda, Axiidea, Callichiridae) from the social structure and sexual dimorphism

. 

Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology

, 
75
: [
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00265-021-03031-2]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Holthuis, L.B.
1951
. 
A general revision of the Palaemonidae (Crustacea Decapoda Natantia) of the Americas. I. The subfamilies Euryrhynchidae and Pontoniinae
. 

Occasional Papers of the Allan Hancock Foundation

, 

11

: 
1–332
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hultgren, K.
, 
Duffy, J.E.
&amp; 
Rubenstein, D.R.
2017
. 
Sociality in shrimps
. In: 

Comparative social evolution

(
D. Rubenstein
&amp; 
P. Abbot
, eds.), pp. 
224–252
. 
Cambridge University Press, Cambridge
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
IBM
. 
2011
. 

IBM SPSS statistics for windows
(Version 20)

. 
IBM, Armonk, NY, USA
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jennions, M.D.
&amp; 
Backwell, P.R.Y.
1996
. 

Residency and size affect fight duration and outcome in the fiddler crab 
Uca annulipes

. 

Biological Journal of the Linnean Society

, 

57

: 
293–306
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jones, C.G.
, 
Lawton, J.H.
&amp; 
Shachak, M.
1994
. 
Organisms as ecosystem engineers
. 

Oikos

, 

69

: 
373–386
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jordan, M.A.
, 
Welsh, D.T.
, 
Dunn, R.J.K.
&amp; 
Teasdale, P.R.
2009
. 

Influence of 
Trypaea australiensis
population density on benthic metabolism and nitrogen dynamics in sandy estuarine sediment: A mesocosm simulation

. 

Journal of Sea Research

, 

61

: 
144–152
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Katrak, G.
&amp; 
Bird, F.L.
2003
. 

Comparative effects of the large bioturbators, 
Trypaea australiensis
and 
Heloecius cordiformis
, on intertidal sediments of Western Port, Victoria, Australia

. 

Marine and Freshwater Research

, 

54

: 
701–708
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kinoshita, K.
, 
Itani, G.
&amp; 
Uchino, T.
2010
. 

Burrow morphology and associated animals of the mud shrimp 
Upogebia yokoyai
(Crustacea: Thalassinidea: Upogebiidae)

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 

90

: 
947–952
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lott, D.
1984
. 
Intraspecific variation in the social systems of wild vertebrates
. 

Behaviour

, 

88

: 
266–325
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lott, D.
1991
. 

Intraspecific variation in the social systems of wild vertebrates

. 
Cambridge University Press, Cambridge
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mariappan, P.
, 
Balasundaram, C.
&amp; 
Schmitz, B.
2000
. 
Decapod crustacean chelipeds: An overview
. 

Journal of Biosciences

, 

25

: 
301–313
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mathews, L.M.
2002
. 
Territorial cooperation and social monogamy: Factors affecting intersexual behaviours in pair-living snapping shrimp
. 

Animal Behaviour

, 

63

: 
767–777
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mathews, L.M.
2003
. 
Tests of the mate-guarding hypothesis for social monogamy:Male snapping shrimp prefer to associate with high-value females
. 

Behavioral Ecology

, 

14

: 
63–67
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
McDermott, J.J.
2005
. 

Biology of the brachyuran crab 
Pinnixa chaetopterana
Stimpson (Decapoda: Pinnotheridae) symbiotic with tubicolous polychaetes along the Atlantic coast of the United States, with additional notes on other polychaete associations

. 

Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington

, 

118

: 
742–764
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
McPhee, D.P.
&amp; 
Skilleter, G.A.
2002
. 

Aspects of the biology of the yabby 
Trypaea australiensis
(Dana) (Decapoda: Thalassinidea) and the potential of burrow counts as an indirect measure of population density

. 

Hydrobiologia

, 

485

: 
133–141
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Milne-Edwards, A.
1870
. 
Révision du genre Callianassa (Leach) et description de plusieurs espèces nouvelles de ce groupe faisant partie de la collection du Muséum
. 

Nouvelles Archives du Muséum d’Histoire Naturelle

, 

6

: 
75–102
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Miya, Y.
&amp; 
Miyake, S.
1969
. 

Description of 
Alpheus bellulus
sp. nov. associated with gobies from Japan (Crustacea, Decapoda, Alpheidae)

. 

Publications from the Seto Marine Biological Laboratory

, 

16

: 
307–314
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moore, J.W.
2006
. 
Animal ecosystem engineers in streams
. 

BioScience

, 

56

: 
237–246
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ortmann, A.
1891
. 
Die Decapoden-Krebse des Strassburger Museums, mit besonderer Berücksichtigung dr von Herrn Dr. Döderlein bei Japan und bei den Liu-Kiu-Inseln gesammelten und z. Z. im Strassburger Museum aufbewahrten Formen. II. Theil. Versuch einer Revision der Gattungen Palaemonsens. strict. und Bithynis
. 

Zoologische Jahrbücher. Abtheilung für Systematik, Geographie und Biologie der Thiere

, 

5

: 
693–750
, pl. 47.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pachelle, P.P.G.
, 
Paiva, S.V.
, 
Oliveira Filho, R.R.
&amp; 
Anker, A.
2012
. 

The ascidian-associated shrimp 
Ascidonia miserabilis
(Caridea: Palaemonidae): first record for Brazil and additional records for the Caribbean Sea

. 

Marine Biodiversity Records

, 

5

: e 
83
[
https://doi. org/10.1017/S1755267212000486]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pillay, D.
2019
. 
Ecosystem engineering by thalassinidean Crustaceans: Response variability, contextual dependencies and perspectives on future research
. 

Diversity

, 

11

: 
64
[
https://doi.org/10.3390/ d11040064]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pillay, D.
&amp; 
Branch, G.
2011
. 
Bioengineering effects of burrowing thalassinidean shrimps on marine soft-bottom ecosystems
. 

Oceanography and Marine Biology: An Annual Review

, 

49

: 
137–192
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rahman, N.
, 
Dunham, D.W.
&amp; 
Govind, C.K.
2003
. 

Social monogamy in the big-clawed snapping shrimp, 
Alpheus heterochelis
: Monogamy in 
Alpheus heterochelis

. 

Ethology

, 

109

: 
457–473
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rotherham, D.
2004
. 

Fisheries biology, ecology and recreational harvesting of ghost shrimp
(
Trypaea australiensis
) 
in south-eastern Australia

. Ph.D. thesis, 
University of Wollongong, Wollongong, NSW, Australia
[
http://ro.uow.edu.au/theses/376]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rotherham, D.
&amp; 
West, R.
2007
. 

Spatial and temporal patterns of abundance and recruitment of ghost shrimp 
Trypaea australiensis
across hierarchical scales in south-eastern Australia

. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series

, 

341

: 
165–175
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rotherham, D.
&amp; 
West, R.J.
2009
. 

Patterns in reproductive dynamics of burrowing ghost shrimp 
Trypaea australiensis
from small to intermediate scales

. 

Marine Biology

, 

156

: 
1277–1287
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rowden, A.A.
&amp; 
Jones, M.B.
1994
. 

A contribution to the biology of the burrowing mud shrimp, 
Callianassa subterranea
(Decapoda: Thalassinidea)

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 

74

: 
623–635
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rubenstein, D.
&amp; 
Abbot, P.
2017
. 

Comparative social evolution

. 
Cambridge University Press, Cambridge
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shimoda, K.
, 
Wardiatno, Y.
, 
Kubo, K.
&amp; 
Tamaki, A.
2005
. 
Intraspecific behaviors and major cheliped sexual dimorphism in three congeneric callianassid shrimp
. 

Marine Biology

, 

146

: 
543–557
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Somiya, R.
&amp; 
Tamaki, A.
2017
. 
Unraveling mating behavior for Axiidea (Crustacea: Decapoda): Burrow-dwelling callianassid shrimp in intertidal sandflat
. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

486

: 
305–313
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stamhuis, E.J.
, 
Reede-Dekker, T.
, 
van Etten, Y.
, 
de Wiljes, J.J.
&amp; 
Videler, J.J.
1996
. 

Behaviour and time allocation of the burrowing shrimp 
Callianassa subterranea
(Decapoda, Thalassinidea)

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

204

: 
225–239
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stamhuis, E.
, 
Schreurs, C.
&amp; 
Videler, J.
1997
. 

Burrow architecture and turbative activity of the thalassinid shrimp 
Callianassa subterranea
from the central North Sea

. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series

, 

151

: 
155–163
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Subramoniam, T.
2017
. 
Emergence of eusociality in aquatic environment: Synalpheid shrimps show the way!

Indian Journal Marine Science

, 

46

: 
1511–1518
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tamaki, A.
, 
Ingole, B.
, 
Ikebe, K.
, 
Muramatsu, K.
, 
Taka, M.
&amp; 
Tanaka, M.
1997
. 

Life history of the ghost shrimp, 
Callianassa japonica
Ortmann (Decapoda: Thalassinidea), on an intertidal sandflat in western Kyushu, Japan

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 

210

: 
223–250
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Teitelbaum, C.S.
, 
Converse, S.J.
&amp; 
Mueller, T.
2017
. 
Birds choose long-term partners years before breeding
. 

Animal Behaviour

, 

134

: 
147–154
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Whiteman, E.A.
&amp; 
Côté, I.M.
2004
. 
Monogamy in marine fishes
. 

Biological Reviews

, 

79

: 
351–375
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wickler,W.
&amp; 
Seibt,U.
1981
. 
Monogamy in Crustacea and man
. 

Zeitschrift Für Tierpsychologie

, 

57

: 
215–234
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wong, M.Y.L.
, 
Munday, P.L.
&amp; 
Jones, G.P.
2005
. 

Habitat patch size, facultative monogamy and sex change in a coral-dwelling fish, 
Caracanthus unipinna

. 

Environmental Biology of Fishes

, 

74

: 
141–150
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yanagisawa, Y.
1984
. 

Studies on the interspecific relationship between gobid fish and snapping shrimp ll. Life history and pair formation of snapping shrimp 
Alpheus bellulus

. 

Publications of the Seto Marine Biological Laboratory

, 

29

: 
93–116
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
