<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Megataxa</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11646/megataxa.10.2.1</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A decade of Biotaxa.org: community-supported online library for taxonomic journals enhanced their publication, access and preservation</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>29</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dumerilia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Montenegrina</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Euscorpius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Folia Parasitologica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ruthenica, Russian Malacological</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sherbornia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Treubia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dumerilia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Montenegrina</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Euscorpius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Folia Parasitologica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ruthenica, Russian Malacological</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sherbornia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Treubia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Megataxa

0 1 0

(
2
)
: 0 4 3 –0 5 2
ISSN 2703-3082 (print edition) h Copyright t t p s: / / w w © w 2023. m a p Magnolia r e s s. c o m Press / m t 
Correspondence MEGATAXA
ISSN 

2703-3090

(online edition) https://doi.org/ 
10.11646/megataxa.10.2.1
http://zoobank.org/ 

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 
0B85164F-07B2-46AD-8CDE-A3F75618BD2B
</p>
         <p>
A decade of Biotaxa.org: community-supported online library for taxonomic journals enhanced their publication, access and preservation
</p>
         <p>
ZHI-QIANG ZHANG
1,2
&amp; 
MARK JOHN COSTELLO
3
</p>
         <p>
1
Manaaki Whenua–Landcare Research, Private Bag 92170, 
Auckland
, 
New Zealand
</p>
         <p>
Ễ 
zhangz@landcareresearch.co.nz; https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4172-0592
</p>
         <p>
2
Centre for Biodiversity and Biosecurity, School of Biological Sciences, the University of 
Auckland
, 
Auckland
1072, 
New Zealand
3
Faculty of Biosciences and Aquaculture, Nord Universitet, BodØ 8049, 
Norway
</p>
         <p>
Ễ 
mark.j.costello@nord.no; https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-0328
</p>
         <p>
*Corresponding author
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Abstract
</title>
         <p>Biotaxa.org is a non-profit international collaboration among professional societies, institutions, publishers, natural history museums and libraries for facilitating the publication, enhancing the access and enabling the preservation of journals in biological taxonomy. Since the start of Biotaxa.org in 2013, 58 journals by 46 publishers from 23 countries have joined this platform and 49 of these journals archived 10,076 issues covering a span of 98 years (1926 to 2023). Most of these journals (41) are for open access. Currently 13 journals are also using Biotaxa.org site for manuscript submission and review. Biotaxa.org has helped small publishers and journals—many of these lack sufficient funding—go online, reduce cost, become more sustainable, remain editorial independent, and/or be archived to fulfil the requirements of the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Key words:
taxonomic publication
, 
archiving
, 
online submission and review
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Despite claims to the contrary, taxonomy is flourishing in some aspects, and it needs to be able to provide the evidence supporting the wonderous biodiversity on Earth, and how humans are extinguishing it (

). A tantalisingly near complete inventory of 2.2 million named species was published last year (

) and 88 % of 1,134 biologists who participated in a survey by Lien 
et al.
(2022) supported a more coordinated and managed global list of all species. About 18,000 new species are named every year, including a few thousand from fossils and about two thousand marine species (

, 

). Popular media share the excitement of new species discoveries, indicating that the public expect scientists to discover species. Indeed, in both the Bible and Quran, “man” was told to name species and tell people their names, while the Sikh holy scriptures estimated 8.4 million may exist (

). The fact that new species discoveries are highly correlated with the number of named species across taxa (

) and are typically found where most known species occur (

), indicates we now have a representative sample of life on Earth.
</p>
         <p>
New species discoveries continue to be made by both amateurs and professionals in hundreds of books and journals (

, 

). While gathering this knowledge is greatly aided for digital publications in the last few decades, and for pre-1923 publications which have been digitised by the Biodiversity Heritage Library, many publications have not been digitised and can be difficult to access. Moreover, a particular challenge for many journals with perhaps only a few issues per year and no full-time staff, has been a lack of access to low cost online publication systems, both with respect to editorial processing of papers submitted for review, and appropriate digital archiving to comply with the requirements of codes of nomenclatures for validity of online-only publication and the new species names therein (

, 

). Biotaxa.org was established in 2013 to address these gaps by forming a collective platform for the electronic publication of journals in the field of taxonomy, including digital archiving back-issues.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
About Biotaxa.org
</title>
         <p>Biotaxa.org is a non-profit international collaboration among professional societies, institutions, publishers, natural history museums and libraries for facilitating the publication, enhancing the access and enabling the preservation of journals in biological taxonomy. Biotaxa. org also provides a publishing platform and online hosting for member publishers. Using Open Journal Systems (OJS), journal editors of participating publishers can have authors submit manuscripts online using a manuscript submission and tracking within OJS, which considerably eases the entire process of online publication, including peer-review and editorial decisions. By aggregating many taxonomic journals in a single cross-searching system, Biotaxa.org defragments the current taxonomic publishing landscape and thus increases the visibility and impact of taxonomic journals.</p>
         <p>Biotaxa.org serves as a third-party digital archive (ICZN-approved and ZooBank-enabled) for taxonomic journals, enabling e-only publication of nomenclatural acts in taxonomic journals and preserving them for future generations. Participating journals may also make their content available through other online systems. Preference is given to journals publishing current content. Biotaxa. org encourages the participation of open-access journals but can also host journals with subscriber access. Biotaxa. org advocates the use of the international standard PDF/A to preserve the fixed content and layout of participating journals.</p>
         <p>Through international collaboration and sharing of resources and expertise, Biotaxa.org reduces duplication of efforts and enables small societies and independent publishers and their journals to benefit from the economy of scale. Biotaxa.org is sustained by member contributions: financial or in-kind, and managed by representatives from member organisations.</p>
         <p>Biotaxa.org is not a publisher; it is a consortium of publishers and functions as a non-profit member-supported organization. Each participating publisher or journal retains its identity and copyright, and is responsible for editorial decisions and policies, subscription policies and processing of current contents and open-access policies (immediate open-access or delayed open-access). For publishers that opt for delayed open access, they must provide Biotaxa.org permanent or irrevocable licence to make the work accessible should they no longer do so before copyright expires.</p>
         <p>Biotaxa.org is currently managed by its co-founders: Mark John Costello and Zhi-Qiang Zhang. It is open to all taxonomic journals or other biodiversity journals related to taxonomy. Publishers who wish to join Biotaxa.org should contact Dr Zhi-Qiang Zhang (to whom a membership form may also be requested). Currently there is no membership fee. Members can contribute in-kind support to Biotaxa.org.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
History of Biotaxa.org
</title>
         <p>
The initial idea behind Biotaxa.org was first envisaged in 2010 during a dialogue between Dr Zhang and Dr Costello (then Chair of the Council for the Society for the Management of Electronic Biodiversity Data) about the need to archive Zootaxa and other journals, and to build linkages between Zootaxa and databases, after Zootaxa became the largest journal in taxonomy. The idea was further developed at “the 3rd Meeting Scientific Publishing in Natural History Institutions” held at the Natural History Museum of 
Denmark
, Copenhagen in 2010. With the support of Ward Appeltans and Hernandez Francisco of The Flanders Marine Institute (VLIZ), OJS was installed on a VLIZ server and tested in 2011. The idea about “developing a non-profit international facility that will integrate cost-efficient online publishing and permanent digital archiving for all taxonomic publications” was formally mentioned in 

. The name Biotaxa was first made public by Zhi-Qiang Zhang in August 2011 during a public seminar at the School of Environment, The University of Auckland. The seminar was followed by discussions with supportive colleagues from the University of Auckland including the Faculty of Science, Centre for eResearch, Library and 
School of Biological Sciences. In
2012, Biotaxa.org went online on a server hosted by the Centre for eResearch at The University of Auckland. In early January 2013, 
Biotaxa.
org formally started with the archiving of the online editions of two journals (

Zootaxa

and 

Phytotaxa

) from its founding member 
Magnolia Press
and another journal (

Systematic
&amp; 
Applied Acarology

) from another founding member (
Systematic
&amp; 
Applied Acarology Society
) in PDF/A.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Growth in its first decade
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Improved access, publication, and preservation
</title>
         <p>
Of the 58 journals, 33 are published both online and in print and 17 are online-only; the remaining eight journals were published in print before but made available online (
Table 1
). Of 41 open access journals (76% of all member journals), 22 are Gold open access and 21 are platinum or diamond open access (no fee charged to author); 11 are hybrid journals and only four are subscription journals (
Table 2
). Except for nine journals, 49 journals archived 10,076 issues covering a span of 98 years (1926 to 2023).
</p>
         <p>OJS comes with manuscript submission and review capability, which was offered to our member journals free of charge. Currently 13 journals are using Biotaxa.org site for manuscript submission and review. This increases the efficiency in editorial processing of papers submitted for review in these journals.</p>
         <p>
Since the start of Biotaxa.org in 2013, 58 journals by 46 publishers from 23 countries have joined (
Table 1
). Just over half of these journals joined during the first two years and the growth in journals, publishers and countries has continued with no signs of reaching a plateau (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
The distribution of journals among countries sees just over half of the countries having one journal and the top three countries accounting for 38% of all the journals (
Fig. 2
). The distribution of journals among publishers is similarly uneven with 93% of the publishers contributing to one journal each but the top publisher from 
New Zealand
alone contributing to 10 journals (or 22% of all the journals) (
Table 1
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
Discussion
</title>
         <p>
The world of scientific publishing has seen the growth of massive online only journals, and merger of publishers into a few who dominate the market and determine the prices that authors and readers pay to publish/read. Because they set the price, and every journal and paper are unique, the market does not saturate, and so competition does not lead to reduced costs to authors or readers, or debates over valuefor-money. This is despite that the bulk of the salaries of authors and other research costs are paid by the taxpayer through government funding, and institutional policies typically require the use of “preferred (discounted) service providers”, obtaining “alternative quotations” and reviews of staffing to reduce costs. This situation means that those authors and readers without institutional funding will publish in either Platinum open-access or subscriber-funded journals (including hybrid journals). This is a significant community for taxonomists, with about 50,000 people describing species in recent decades (

) and an estimated 60 % of people involved in writing new species descriptions not having institutional addresses (

). Hundreds of taxonomists are also collaborating to publish open-access databases on species nomenclature, traits and associated literature (e.g., 

, 

). A parallel initiative to Biotaxa.org, also using OJS and Platinum open-access, is the European Journal of Taxonomy (

). Such efforts, and Biotaxa.org, demonstrate that the taxonomic community is making efforts to coordinate open access and low cost online publications of species descriptions and associated information to advance primary knowledge of life on Earth and aid quality assurance in the use of species names in science and environmental management.
</p>
         <p>
Our overview of the history and development of Biotaxa.org over the last ten years shows that it has helped small publishers and journals—many of these lack sufficient funding—go online, reduce cost, achieve better sustainability, remain editorially independent, and/or be archived to fulfil the requirements of the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature. It is a significant achievement to have over 10,000 issues from 49 journals archived in Biotaxa.org with only voluntary contributions from members. It is known that two of the founding journals (
Zootaxa
and 
Systematic and Applied Acarology)
are among the top-10 journals in the numbers of new taxa published: the former accounts for 26.6% and the latter 0.8% of all new taxa indexed in 
Zoological Record
from 2015 to 2020 (

). It is unknown how many new taxa are included in other journals archived in Biotaxa.org. It will be an interesting future project to find if journals in Biotaxa.org account for over 50% of the new taxa described each year.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>This Biotaxa.org website is hosted by Faculty of Science, The University of Auckland. Technical support is provided by the editorial office of Zootaxa at Magnolia Press. The domain name was initially registered and managed on behalf of Biotaxa.org by the Data Centre of The Flanders Marine Institute and now by the Faculty of Science, The University of Auckland.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bouchet, P.
, 
Bary, S.
, 
Heros, V.
&amp; 
Marani, G.
(
2016
) 
How many species of molluscs are there in the world’s oceans, and who is going to describe them?
In
: 
Strong, H.V.
&amp; 
Bouchet, P.
(Eds.), 

Tropical Deep-Sea Benthos. Vol. 29

. 
Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris
, pp. 9–24.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature
(
1999
) 

International Code of Zoological Nomenclature. Fourth edition

. 
International Trust for Zoological Nomenclature, London
, xxix + 
306 pp.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
...Continued on the next page
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
...Continued on the next page
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
...Continued on the next page
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
...Continued on the next page
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
