<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Annalsofthetransvaalmuseum</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A New Genus And Species Of Syrphidae (Diptera) From South Africa</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>1924</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>SYRPHIDAE</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>DIPTERA</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Achoanus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Asarcina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Achoanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Asarcina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Achoanus hulleyi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Achoanus hulleyi,
n. sp
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Asarcina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asarcina</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Squamae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Scutellum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asarcina</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
A NEW GENUS AND SPECIES OF 
<tp:taxon-name>SYRPHIDAE</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
(
<tp:taxon-name>DIPTERA</tp:taxon-name>
) FROM 
SOUTH AFRICA
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

By 
H. K. MUNRO
, B.Sc., F.E.S.

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
With one Plate
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Achoanus</tp:taxon-name>
,

n.g
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Very like 
AsarcinaI,
particularly the 
ericetorum
group, but may be distinguished by the absence of a well-defined " collar" of hairs on the anterior margin of the dorsum of the thorax. It differs from any form 2. of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Asarcina
</tp:taxon-name>
yet recorded by the following features: 
(a)
enlargement of the upper facettes of the eyes of the male. The upper part of each eye is so inflated anteriorly that, the two organs being contiguous for a considerable length, the frontal triangle is much reduced; 
(b)
by the longer vertical triangle, which is, in the 
type
, three times as long as its base; 
(c)
from known Ethiopian forms, at least, by the third longitudinal vein of the wing being only gently curved downwards, and not making a decided bend into the first posterior cell. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Achoanus
</tp:taxon-name>
resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
Asarcina
</tp:taxon-name>
in the following characters: the frons in the female is narrowed gradually; the buccal cavity is long and narrow; the lateral median sinuosity of the posterior border of the eye is clothed with silvery squamous hairs; the abdomen is flat, margined, yellow and transparent, with transverse black bands; the hypopygium in the male is small and asymmetrical
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Type
of genus: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Achoanus hulleyi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. n
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Achoanus hulleyi,
n. sp
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
~. Length 
13.8 mm
.; head, length, 
2·8 mm
., width, 4' 
3 mm
.; wing, length, II mm.; abdomen, maximum width, 4' 
5 mm
. (
Two specimens
.)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Head:
hemispherical, wider than thorax, face not conically produced, anterior margin of buccal cavity retreating; oral opening long and narrow. 
Face:
saffron yellow, sides paler and clothed with pale yellow hair, golden tomentum above, and white below; 
facial tubercle
cariniform. 
Genae:
black with white tomentum. 
Frons:
tuberculate, small, shining black, clothed on sides and above with long, black hair and rather sparse, golden tomentum. 
Lunule:
yellow. 
Antennae:
approximated at base; first two joints of equal length, rufous and clothed with short black bristles; third joint oval, rufous with a blackish infuscation except on a narrow margin where it meets the second joint; darker above. (The infuscation is less pronounced in the specimen from the Transvaal.) 
Arista:
black, with minute hairs on the proximal thickened two-thirds. 
Proboscis:
short. 
Vertical triangle:
very long and narrow, three times as long as its base; clothed with black hair except on the apex in front of the anterior ocellus. 
Ocelli:
far forward; posterior ocelli at middle of triangle, anterior ocellus half as far again from them as they are from each other. 
Eyes:
bare, inflated anteriorly above; contiguous for a distance one and a half times the length of the vertical triangle and for twice the length of the frontal triangle. Upper facettes greatly enlarged. 
Occiput:
deeply excavated above, so that the posterior dorsal margin of the eyes and vertex forms a sharp edge on which is a row of short yellowish hairs. Laterally, in the posterior median sinuosity of the eye the occiput widens out and is clothed
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

1 
Bezzi, M.
, 

Secondo contributo alia Conoscenza del Genere Asarcilla
,

Ann. Mus. Nat. Hung.
VI
, p. 
495
, 
1908
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
2 A new form of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Asarcina
</tp:taxon-name>
in which the upper facettes of eyes in the male are enlarged is to be
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>described</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>with</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a very thick silvery tomentum and long silvery squamous hairs; the latter extend down to t.he lowest corner of the eye where they merge into the long white hairs on the lower part of the occiput. 
Thorax:
dorsum dull black, shining, clothed with yellow hair which does not form a well-defined collar anteriorly; sides of dorsum and pleura yellowish; clothed with long yellow hair and yellow tomentum as in 

<tp:taxon-name>Asarcina</tp:taxon-name>
. Sterna:

blackish in front and on sides, yellowish behind. 
Legs:
slender, yellow, first two pairs clothed with yellow, last pair with black hair; 
tarsi:
black above. 
Wings:
as long as abdomen and thorax together, hyaline with a slight greyish infuscation, and a few yellowish marks towards the base; stigma yellow; veins brown; third longitudinal vein with only a gentle curve downwards. 

<tp:taxon-name>Squamae</tp:taxon-name>
:

rather small; yellow; margin thickened, inner lobe fringed with short yellow hair, outer with long, yellow, branched hairs. 
Halteres:
pale lemon yellow. 

<tp:taxon-name>Scutellum</tp:taxon-name>
:

yellowish translucent; clothed with black hair above, except at base where it is yellowish; hair yellow beneath. 
Postscutellum:
shining black. 
Abdomen:
ovate, wider than thorax; dorsum saffron yellow, clothed with short black hair except longer yellow hair on basal angles. First segment entirely yellow; on the posterior margins of the second to fourth segments is a rather narrow blackish or very dark brown transverse band; the bands become somewhat broader backwards; on the fifth segment the band is reduced and does not reach the outer margins of the s;gment. The anterior edge of each band is not very clearly defined (in the Transvaal specimen the bands are much narrower; the abdomen is badly discoloured, but as far as may be observed, the band on the second segment seems to be almost absent). 
Hypopygium:
small, spherical, concealed and asymmetrical
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
C(. Length 
14 mm
.; head, len~h, 2' 
7 mm
., width, 
4 mm
.; wing, length, 10' 
5 mm
.; abdomen, maximum Width, 4' 
9 mm
, (
Three specimens
.) Length II mm.; head, length, 2' 
1 mm
., width, 3' 
4 mm
.; wing, length, 
10 mm
.; abdomen, maximum width, 4' 
2 mm
. (
Two specimens
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.)</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
.
) 2009 dated (Publisher grantedbythe licence Gatewayunder ReproducedbySabinet
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The infuscation on the third antennal joint is not as deep as in the male, but in 
two specimens
it is even more so. 
Eyes:
not inflated above. 
Frons:
narrowed gradually; clothed with hair laterally and above, and golden tomentum laterally, leaving a broad shining black, median stripe from the tubercle to the upper shining black portion of the frons. 
Vertex:
black, with azure blue reflections (this is more pronounced in some specimens than others); clothed with black hair. 
Ocelli:
equidistant. 
Occiput:
with a narrow margin visible above, clothed with fine yellowish tomentum. The transverse abdominal bands are blacker, rather wider, and better defined than in the male. 
Ovipositor:
short, yellow. In other respects the female is similar to the male
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Two of the specimens were captured on the farm Stentor, near Kaapmuiden, in the Transvaal, by Mr L. S. Hulley, who, as a· collector, has done much to increase our knowledge of S. MricanDiptera, and it is with no small pleasure that I give his name to this species</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cotypes.
I 
S,
I ~, Stentor, Barberton district, Transvaal, November, 1919 (L. S. HulIey). 1 
S,
Pretoria, January, 1913 and I cJ, 3 繾Ⱐ East London, May, 1923 (author). I 
S
(Barberton) and I C((East London), cotype deposited in the collection of the Transvaal Museum, Pretoria, the remainder being in the author's collection
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Biology.
As far as has been observed by the author, this species frequents the same haunts as do most of the species of 

<tp:taxon-name>Asarcina</tp:taxon-name>
.

Like these, it seems averse t~ bright sunlight, and is found among the undergrowth below trees, hovering in the air, and occasionally resting on leaves or twigs
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Annals</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Transvaal Mus. Vol. X, Pt. 
2
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Plate 1</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
ReproducedbySabinet
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
