<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nauplius</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2358-2936e2022006</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Effects of methyl farnesoate injection on spermatozoa number and reproductive indices in the narrow-clawed crayfish Pontastacus leptodactylus</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>11</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
(Escholtz, 1823)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. leptodactylus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
(Escholtz, 1823)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Neohelice granulata
(Dana, 1851)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oziothelphusa senex senex
(Fabricus, 1798)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Litopenaeus vannamei
(Boone, 1931)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Charybdis feriatus
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Portunus trituberculatus
(Miers, 1876)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. leptodactylus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pontastacus leptodactylus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodctylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
O. senex senex
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pontastacus leptodactylus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium malcolmsonii
(H.Milne Edwards, 1844)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. malcolmsonii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. granulata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P.leptodactylus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Carcinus maenas
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Procambarus clarkii
(Girard, 1852)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
(Milne Edwards, 1837)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nephrops norvegicus
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Panulirus polyphagus
(Herbst, 1793)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Astacus leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ORIGINAL
ARTICLE
</title>
         <p>

Effects of methyl farnesoate injection on spermatozoa number and reproductive indices in the narrow-clawed crayfish 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Mehmet Bal
B
orcid.org/0000-0002-8659-3200
</p>
         <p>
Ayşe Gül Harlıoğlu
B
orcid.org/0000-0001-9478-6419
</p>
         <p>
Fisheries Faculty, Fırat University, 23119, 
Elazığ
, 
Turkey
.
</p>
         <p>
MB
E-mail: mehmet.bal@tkdk.gov.tr
</p>
         <p>
AGH
E-mail: aharlioglu@firat.edu.tr
</p>
         <p>
ZOOBANK
: http://zoobank.org/ 

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 
A9F55966-19AE-4568- B061-903239576A98
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
</title>
         <p>
In this study, the effect of methyl farnesoate (MF) injection on haemolymph MF levels, spermatozoa production and the reproductive indices of gonadosomatic index (GSI), testicular index (TI) and vasosomatic index (VSI)were investigated in males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
(Escholtz, 1823)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Sixty male
<tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
were used for the study. They were housed in a total of twelve tanks in their normal reproductive season in 2018 and were fed 
ad libitum
with a pelleted food. Animals were injected once a week for five consecutive weeks, at doses of 250 (G2), 500 (G3) and 1000 (G4) ng MF 
g-1
of body weight. The doses of the injections, the durations used, and the frequency of administration were determined according to the literature. An increase was observed in gonadosomatic index and spermatozoal number of crayfish injected with 
1000 ng
of MF 
g-1
of body weight when compared to control (G1, no MF injection applied) and other experimental groups. In addition, the present study indicated that G4 crayfish had a higher GSI, TI and VSI than control crayfish. There was no difference in the level of hemolymph MF between control and MF injected crayfish. In conclusion, MF injection is effective for inducing increased gonadasomatic index and spermatozoal number in 

<tp:taxon-name>P. leptodactylus</tp:taxon-name>
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
KEYWORDS
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
            <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
, gonad, gonadosomatic index, male gamete, reproduction

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
In recent decades, astaciculture has gained importance because of high demands from international markets for crayfish (

; 

). The narrow-clawed crayfish 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
(Escholtz, 1823)
</tp:taxon-name>
, a crustacean with a high commercial value, is widely stocked in Eastern Europe and the Middle East and is a species suitable for aquaculture (

; 

; 

). Basic knowledge of gamete biology may help enhance the quality of artificial reproduction in commercial decapod crustaceans such as crayfish (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The regulation of reproduction in decapods is controlled by a variety of different factors such as water temperature (

; 

), photoperiod (

; 

), biogenic amines (

), gonad stimulating hormone, methyl farnesoate (MF), steroid hormones (

), and neuropeptides (

; 

).Control of male reproduction is a key factor in crustacean aquaculture. For example, spermatozoa quality is one of the most inf luential factors and affects reproductive output in crustacean hatcheries (

) and many factors affect spermatozoal production and quality in decapods including broodstock nutrition, water pollution, water temperature, captivity, hormones, neurotransmitters, stress, disease, male age, and size (

).
</p>
         <p>
Methyl farnesoate is a terpenoid hormone that is synthesized by the mandibular organ and is structurally similar to juvenile hormone III of insects. However, it differs in the presence of an epoxide moiety at the terminal end. MF is included in several hormonal processes in crustaceans. There are studies showing that MF induces gonadal development in some decapods (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

). For example, gonadal development of decapods induced by MF has been reported in the estuarine female crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neohelice granulata
(Dana, 1851)
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

) and freshwater crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oziothelphusa senex senex
(Fabricus, 1798)
</tp:taxon-name>
(seeReddy and 

) and 

found that MF has an effect on spermatophore quality in the white shrimp, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Litopenaeus vannamei
(Boone, 1931)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 

reported that MF stimulates moulting and ovarian maturation in the Pacific White Shrimp 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
. Similarly, it has been found that changes in MF levels affect testicular development (

) and MF injection increases spermatozoal production in male decapods (

). The molecular mechanism of MF in testicular development is not clear.Studies have shown that MF induces the expression of vitellogenin in female decapods such as the crucifix crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charybdis feriatus
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Portunus trituberculatus
(Miers, 1876)
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

). Several studies have been carried out to decipher the biology and role of crayfish gametes in reproduction including the fine structure of crayfish immotile spermatozoa (

; 

; 

; 

), spermatozoal capacitation (

; 

; 

; 2016; 

), egg activation and attachment stalk formation (

), annual cycle of spermatozoan production (

), and artificial extrusion of the male gamete for reproduction (Farhadi 
et al.
, 2019). However, the role of hormones such as MF on spermatozoa production in freshwater crayfish is still unknown.
</p>
         <p>
This study aims to evaluate the effect of injection of MF at different doses on spermatozoal production and some associated reproductive parameters such as gonadosomatic index (GSI), testicular index (TI) and vasosomatic index (VSI) in male 

<tp:taxon-name>P. leptodactylus</tp:taxon-name>
.

Changes in the haemolymph MF levels after injection were also evaluated in our study.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
MATERIAL
AND
METHODS
</title>
         <p>
Crayfish and experimental design
</p>
         <p>
Sixty adult
male 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
(mean body weight, 46.7 ± 
3.4 g
; mean carapace length 5.7 ± 
0.2 cm
) were obtained from the 
Keban Dam Lake
(
Elazığ
, 
Turkey
). 
Specimens
were placed in a total of twelve outdoor concrete tanks (2 × 2 × 

1 m

) and exposed to a natural photoperiod in the crayfish reproduction unit of the 
Fisheries Faculty
, 
Fırat University
, 
Elazığ
, 
Turkey
. 
The
crayfish were divided arbitrarily into four groups (15 individuals per group). 
In
each tank, plastic pipes (
20 cm
in length and 
7 cm
in diameter) were supplied as shelters for the crayfish. 
Crayfish
were daily fed (
ad libitum
) with a commercial pellet food (
Manufactured
by 
Gürdal
, 
Kahramanmaraş
, 
Turkey
, containing 35 % crude protein on a dry-weight basis and 3600 kcal/kg gross energy)

.
</p>
         <p>
Water flow was 1.5 l/s per 
1 m
2
in

each tank. During the experiment, dissolved oxygen, pH, and water temperature was measured daily. Ammonia, iron, copper, alkalinity, hardness, calcium and water f low were measured. Methyl farnesoate (trans, trans MF, C 
16
H 
26
O 
2
) was purchased from Echelon (Echelon Biosciences Inc., Salt Lake City, 
USA
) and dissolved in 10 ml of ethanol. This stock solution was kept at -70 °C. Methyl farnesoate injection was performed in three different doses. The stock solution was diluted in 0.85 % NaCl to reach the final concentration. All MF solutions were prepared weekly. Methyl farnesoate injection was not applied to the control group (G1). For G1, 0.02 ml ethanol was diluted to 0.05 ml with saline (physiological solution, 0.85 % salt water). The highest ethanol level was 40 % of the injection volume (20 µl ethanol + 30 µl physiological solution). Male crayfish were injected five times in the second abdominal muscle on days 1, 8, 15, 22, and 29 by means of 1-ml syringes (27 G needle) before mating.
</p>
         <p>
The injection doses and the frequency of administration of the doses were determined according to 

, 

and 

:
</p>
         <p>
G1: 0 ng MF body 
weight-1
(control)
</p>
         <p>
G2: 
250 ng
MF body 
weight-1
</p>
         <p>
G3: 
500 ng
MF body 
weight-1
</p>
         <p>
G4: 
1000 ng
MF body 
weight-1
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Pontastacus leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
usually starts mating and carries spermatozoa in the first week of January in the crayfish reproduction unit of the Fisheries Faculty (

; 

; 

). Therefore, in the normal reproductive season, the first injection was performed on 
1 December 2018
and the last injection was performed on 
29 December 2018
. The second, third and fourth injections were administered on the 8th, 15th, and 22nd days, in one-week intervals. Haemolymph samples were taken from crayfish one week after (
4 January 2018
) the last dose application based on the weekly dosing interval (1 week). In the present study, crayfish started to mate the first week of 
January 2019
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Haemolymph collection
</title>
         <p>
To determine the MF levels in haemolymph, at least 1 ml haemolymph was collected from the heart of the crayfish using a sterile BD PrecisionGlideTM 1 ml syringe (26 G ½; 
0.45 mm
× 
13 mm
).
</p>
         <p>
For MF analysis, haemolymph samples were transferred into tubes in 4 % NaCl and acetonitrile, keeping a (4:5) ratio of water to acetonitrile. Before extraction, 
10 ng
of the nonbiological isomer of MF (cis- trans MF), was added to each tube as an internal standard (

). Water and acetonitrile ratio were maintained at 4:5, v / v. 2 ml of n-hexane was added to this mixture to be homogenized and mixed thoroughly. The mixture was centrifuged at 
750 g
for 10 minutes and the upper hexane phase was transferred separately to a tube. This procedure was repeated three times and the hexane phases were dried under open nitrogen flow and the MF level was measured in a HPLC. A PDA (Photodiode Array) detector was used in the HPLC system. The wavelength was adjusted to 
220 nm
between 190-350 and analyzed by using a Nucleosil 100-5 (5 µm, 250 × 
4.6 mm
; Macherey-Nagel, Dueren, 
Germany
) HPLC column (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Reproductive parameters and spermatozoal counting
</title>
         <p>
At the end of the experiment, the crayfish samples were stored at -20 °C until dissection. Their carapace length and weight were recorded. The whole reproductive system, vasa deferentia and testis, were also weighed. The gonadosomatic index(GSI, %) was calculated as reproductive system weight 
/
body weight × 100, the testicular index (TI, %) was calculated as testis weight 
/
body weight × 100, and the vasosomatic index (VSI, %) was calculated as vasa deferentia weight 
/
body weight × 100) (

). For spermatozoal counting a modified protocol developed by 

was employed. A 
1 cm
section of the distal vas deferens (DVD) was disaggregated in 1 ml of physiological solution for decapods (

). Then, spermatozoa were counted using a Neubauer camera. Spermatozoal count was expressed as spermatozoa/ DVD section (

; 

; Farhadi 
et al.,
2018).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Statistical analyses
</title>
         <p>
The normality and homoscedasticity of the data were examined using the Kolmogorov Smirnov and Levene’s tests. Proportional data (GSI, TI, VSI) were normalized using squareroot arcsin transformation. Data were analyzed statistically using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Duncan’s new multiple range test (SPSS 15.0). Significant differences were based on the 
P
&lt;0.05 level.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
RESULTS
</title>
         <p>
The quality of parameters of the water used in the experiment
</p>
         <p>
Mean dissolved oxygen was 7.1 ± 
0.2 mg
/l; mean ammonia, iron and copper content were less than 
0.001 mg
/l (for each parameter); mean calcium was 40.3 ± 
0.21 mg
/l; mean alkalinity was 182.2 ± 
1.21 mg
CaCO 
3
/l; mean hardness was 34 ± 4 °fH; mean pH was 8.3 ± 0.22 (

). Mean water temperature was 1.58 ± 0.20 °C in 
December 2018
and 1.41 ± 
0.12 in
January 2019
.
</p>
         <p>
Determination of the effect of MF injection on haemolymph MF
</p>
         <p>
Methyl farnesoate injection did not affect haemolymph MF (ANOVA, 
F
3,16
= 0.08, 
P
= 0.97) (
Fig. 1
). Methyl farnesoate levels in the haemolymph were 1.39, 1.41, 1. 38 and 1.39 (ng 
ml-1
) for G1, G2, G3 and G4 respectively (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Effects of MF injection on GSI, TI, VSI, reproductive system, testis, and vasa deferentia weights
</p>
         <p>
No mortality was observed in the present study. The highest weight of the reproductive system was found in the crayfish injected with G4 (
1.54 g
). Although there were no differences between G1 (
1.07 g
), G2 (
1.05 g
), and G3 (
1.13 g
), G4 showed a higher reproductive system weight than other groups (ANOVA, 
F
3,16
= 5.42, 
P
=0.009)(
Fig. 2
). The results revealed that, GSI (%) was 2.27, 2.20, 2.40, and 3.38 for G1 (control), G2, G3 and G4, respectively. GSI was higher (ANOVA, 
F
3,16
= 10.11, 
P
= 0.001) in G4 than other treatments (
Fig. 2
). Testis weight (g) was 0.11, 0.12, 0.10 and 0.21 for G1, G2, G3 and G4, respectively. Testis weight was found to be higher in G4 than other treatments (ANOVA, 
F
3,16
= 14.81, 
P
= 0.000). The findings showed that the TI (%) value determined for the G4 group (0.46) was higher than the control group (0.24), G2 (0.25) and G3 groups (0.22) (ANOVA, 
F
3,16
= 12.96, 
P
= 0.000) (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
Vasa deferentia weight (g) was 0.89, 0.90, 0.96 and 1.25 for G1, G2, G3 and G4, respectively. Vasa deferentia weight was also found to be higher (ANOVA, 
F
3,16
= 3.10, 
P
= 0.046) in G4 compared to the other treatments. While the VSI (%) value was determined as 1.86, 1.89, 2.03 and 2.74 for G1, G2, G3 and G4, respectively. The VSI value was found to be higher (ANOVA, 
F
3,16
= 6.36, 
P
= 0.005) in G4 group than the control group and the other experimental groups (
Fig. 4
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Effect of MF injection on spermatozoal number
</title>
         <p>
There was a no difference in spermatozoal number between the control (G1) (5.6 x 
106
), G2 (5.80 x 
106
) and G3 (7.0 x 
106
) (
Fig. 5
). The highest number of spermatozoa were observed in G4 (8.20 x 
106
) with no differences between G4 and G3. The lowest spermatozoal number (5.6 x 
106
) was in the control group. Spermatozoal number was higher (ANOVA, 
F
3,16
= 3.33, 
P
= 0.046) in G4 than G1 and G2 treatments (
Fig. 5
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
</title>
         <p>
This study has shown that male 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodctylus
</tp:taxon-name>
injected with MF about six weeks prior to their reproductive period significantly increased spermatozoa production, reproductive system weight, GSI, TI and VSI. It was observed that after injection of 
1000 ng
MF body 
weight-1
GSI, TI and VSI of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
were significantly increased as compared to the control. Similar results have also been found by 

on the effects of MF injection on the TI of freshwater crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. senex senex
</tp:taxon-name>
. 

injected animals with MF on days 1,7 and 14 using 
16 ng
/crab and terminated the study on the 21st day.They found MF injection increased testicular weight, diameter, and size in this crab species, and also promoted the growth of testes by increasing the testicular index value, they concluded that MF was effective in stimulating testicular growth in freshwater crabs.
</p>
         <p>

found that MF injection at a 
5 ng
/freshwater shrimp dose significantly increased the TI of male 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium malcolmsonii
(H.Milne Edwards, 1844)
</tp:taxon-name>
. They determined a testicular index value of 
0.33 in
the control group that significantly increased to 0.52 as a result of MF injection. Based on these results, 

argued that MF injection in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. malcolmsonii
</tp:taxon-name>
accelerated gonad development. 

reported that GSI in female crab, 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. granulata
</tp:taxon-name>
was significantly higher in animals fed hormone enriched (17 – hydroxyprogesterone or MF) pellets compared to controls. Also, 

reported that gonad size was increased in different decapod species following application of MF in vivo. In this study, it was determined that the GSI increased with MF injection in male crayfish. These results provide strong evidences that MF is involved in the control of reproduction in decapods.
</p>
         <p>
Similarly, the testicular index of 
0.24 in
the control group significantly increased to 
0.46 in
T 
4 in
the present study. It is thought this increase is due to the accelerating effect of MF on testicular development in decapods. Moreover, 

investigated the effects of environmental factors on testicular development of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Carcinus maenas
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
and found that environmental conditions such as salinity and water temperature affect the development of the testis by raising the MF value of the haemolymph.
</p>
         <p>
Methyl farnesoate is a terpenoid hormone that has crucial roles in reproduction of both females and males (

). The level of this hormone was determined in different decapods in some studies, for example, the MF level of the crayfish 
<tp:taxon-name>
Procambarus clarkii
(Girard, 1852)
</tp:taxon-name>
haemolymph was found to be between 
0.5 ng
/ml and 
3 ng
/ml, (

) and 
1.41 ng
/ml (

). In addition, 

found that the MF value in the American lobster, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Homarus americanus
(Milne Edwards, 1837)
</tp:taxon-name>
hemolymph was 
5 ng
/ml, and 

determined that the MF of Norwegian lobster 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nephrops norvegicus
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
haemolymph in males and females was between 
0.5 to 1 ng
/ml. In the present study, the MF level of haemolymph was 
1.38–1.41 ng
/ml in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>In this study, the hemolymph MF analysis was determined one week after the last injection. The lack of any significant differences in the concentration of MF in the hemolymph of crayfish suggests that the injected MF dosages were converted to spermatozoal production and associated reproductive parameters at the end of the experiment.</p>
         <p>

found that MF injected into shrimp 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
at a doze of 
120 ng
/g resulted in approximately 38 million spermatozoa, while the number of spermatozoa in the control was around 2 million. They also found that injection of juvenile hormone III into 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
did not significantly increase the spermatozoal number compared to the control group. Therefore, 

concluded that MF is the reproductive hormone in 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
, and that they cannot use juvenile hormone III instead of MF.Similarly, in this study, MF application increased spermatozoal count in crayfish.
</p>
         <p>
The effects of hormones on the number of spermatozoa in decapods were investigated by other authors. For example, 

reported that the mean of sperm quantity in male mud spiny lobster, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Panulirus polyphagus
(Herbst, 1793)
</tp:taxon-name>
was increased with17α-hydroxyprogesterone (17α-OHP) and 17α-hydroxypregnenolone (17α-OHPL) treated hormones. As a conclusion, 

recommended that higher doses of 17α-OHP and 17α-OHPL should be tried to observe whether there is any significant effect on sperm quality, quantity and accordingly higher hormone concentration.
</p>
         <p>

injected 17 α-Methyltestosterone into the shrimp 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. vannamei
</tp:taxon-name>
. The number of spermatozoa in the control was 10.9 million, whereas it increased to 32.7 million in treated shrimp with 17 α-Methyltestosterone at a dose of 0.01 pg/g and reported it reached 31.7 million in the shrimp treated with 17 α-Methyltestosterone at a dose of 0.1 pg/g. In our study, a total of 5 MF injections were administered to crayfish once a week before mating. When compared to the control group, the number of spermatozoa obtained from 
1000 ng
MF body 
weight-1
treatment was higher.
</p>
         <p>
Overlap has been reported between proteomic profiles of the freshwater crayfish eggs and spermatozoa (

; 

) and it would be interesting to run future experiments to explore the potential effects of MF elevation on the expression levels of similar proteins in male and female gametes.
</p>
         <p>
This study shows that MF injection can notably increase some reproductive indices in male crayfish such as spermatozoal number, GSI, TI, and VSI of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
. The dose of 
1000 ng
MF body 
weight-1
treatment resulted in an increase in both the number of spermatozoa and the weight of the reproductive system. The results of this study are consistent with the results of other studies on other decapod species (

; 

; 

).Further research should be carried out to determine the effect of MF injection on reproductive endocrine metabolism, gamete composition (
e.g.
, protein and lipid profiles) and histology of different regions of the vas deference to assess changes in quantities and ratios of cell 
types
in male reproductive tracts in crayfish.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
</title>
         <p>
This study was conducted as a part of Mehmet BAL’s masters thesis “Effect of Methyl farnesoate on some Reproductive Efficiency Parameters in Male 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astacus leptodactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
” supported by the Scientific and Technological Research Council of 
TURKEY
, TÜBİTAK (Project No: TOVAG-117O915). The authors of this article are very grateful to TÜBİTAK- TOVAG as this article would not have been possible without this support.The authors are also very grateful to Dr.Ardavan FARHADI for his invaluable assistance in the laboratory and to Prof. Roger Francis Thoma for English grammer corrections to the manuscript. The crayfish in this experiment were treated in agreement with the experimental protocol approved by the Firat University Animal Experimentation Ethics Committee (FUAEEC) operating under the 2006 Turkish code of practice for the care and use of animals for scientific purposes (
July 28, 2017
, Protocol No:2017/90).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ADDITIONAL
INFORMATION
AND
DECLARATIONS
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Disclosure statement
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Abdu, U.
; 
Barki, A.
; 
Karplus, I.
; 
Barel, S.
; 
Takac, P.
; 
Yehezkel, G.
; 
Laufer, H.
and 
Sagi, A.
2001
. 

Physiological effects of methyl farnesoate and pyriproxyfen on wintering female crayfish 
Cherax quadricarinatus

. 

Aquacultur
e

, 
202
: 
163–175
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alfaro, J.
1996
. 

Effect of 17α-Methyltestosterone and 17α-Hydroxyprogesterone on the Quality of White Shrimp 
Penaeus vannamei
Spermatophores

. 

Journal of World Aquaculture Society
,

27
: 
487–492
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alfaro, J.
; 
Zuniga, G.
; 
Garcia, A.
and 
Rojas, E.
2008
. 

Preliminary evaluation of the effect of juvenile hormone III and methyl farnesoate on spermatophore quality of the whiteshrimp, 
Litopenaeus vannamei
Boone, 1931 (Decapoda: Penaeidae)

. 

Revista de Biologia Marina y Oceanografia
,

43
: 
167–171
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alnawafleh, T.
; 
Kim, B.K.
; 
Kang, H.E.
; 
Yoon, T.H.
and 
Kim, H.W.
2014
. 

Stimulation of Molting and Ovarian Maturation by Methyl Farnesoate in the Pacific White Shrimp 
Litopenaeus vannamei
(Boone, 1931)

. 

Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences

, 
17
: 
115–121
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
American Public Health Association
(
APHA
). 
1985
. 
Standard methods for the examination of water and wastewater, 16th edn
. 
Washington, DC: The American Public Health Association
. 
1268p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Borst, D.W.
; 
Laufer, H.
; 
Landau, M.
; 
Chang, E.S.
; 
Hertz, W.A.
; 
Baker, F.C.
and 
Schooley, D.A.
1987
. 
Methyl farnesoate and its role in crustacean reproduction and development
. 

Insect Biochemistry

, 
17
: 
1123–1127
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Borst, D.W.
and 
Tsukimura, B.
1991
. 
Quantification of methyl farnesoate levels in hemolymph by high-performance liquid chromatography
. 

Journal of Chromatography A
,

545
: 
71–78
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chan, S.M.
; 
Mak, A.S.C.
; 
Choi, C.L.
; 
Ma, T.H.T.
; 
Hui, J.H.L.
and 
Tiu, S.H.K.
2005
. 

Vitellogenesis in the red crab, 
Charybdis feriatus
: Contributions from small vitellogenin transcripts (Cf Vg) and farnesoic acid stimulation of Cf Vg expression

. 

Annals of the New York Academy
of 
Sciences

, 
1040
: 
74–79
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Farhadi, A.
and 
Harlıoglu, M.M.
2018
. 

Elevated water temperature impairs gamete production in male narrow-clawed crayfish 
Pontastacus leptodactylus
(Eschscholtz, 1823)

. 

Knowledge and Management
of 
Aquatic Ecosystems

, 
419
: 
40
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Farhadi, A.
and 
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
2019
a. 
Molecular and cellular biology of the crayfish spermatozoon: toward development of artificial reproduction in aquaculture
. 

Reviews in Fisheries Science and Aquaculture

, 
27
: 
198–214
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Farhadi, A.
and 
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
2019
b. 

Photoperiod affects gamete production, and protein and lipid metabolism in male narrow-clawed Crayfish 
Pontastacus leptodactylus
(Eschscholtz, 1823)

. 

Animal Reproduction Science
,

211
: 
106204
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Farhadi, A.
and 
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
2019
c. 

The annual cycle of spermatozoa content in the vas deferens and some reproductive parameters in the narrow-clawed crayfish 
Pontastacus leptodactylus
(Eschscholtz, 1823)

. 

Aquaculture Reports
,

13
: 
100185
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Farhadi, A.
; 
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
and 
Gür, S.
2019
. 

Artificial extrusion of spermatophores for insemination of the narrow-clawed crayfish P 
ontastacus leptodactylus
(Eschscholtz, 1823)

. 

Aquaculture Reports

, 
14
: 
100200
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Farhadi, A.
; 
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
and 
Yılmaz, Ö.
2020
. 

Effect of serotonin injection on the reproductive parameters and haemolymph methyl farnesoate level in the narrow-clawed crayfish 
Pontastacus leptodactylus (
Eschscholtz, 1823)

. 

Aquacultre Research
,

51
: 
155–163
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Farhadi, A.
; 
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
; 
Gür, S.
and 
Acısu, T.C.
2018
. 

Optimization of the incubation time and temperature for spermatozoa extraction in freshwater crayfish 
Pontastacus leptodactylus
(Eschscholtz, 1823)

. 

Animal Reproduction Science

, 
193
: 
153–157
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fatihah, S.N.
; 
Safiah, J.
; 
Abol-Munafi, A.B.
and 
Ikhwanuddin, M.
2014
. 

Effect of 17α-hydroxyprogesterone and 17α-hydroxypregnenolone on sperm quality and sperm quantity in male mud spiny lobster (
Panulirus polyphagus
)

. 

Pakistan Jouurnal of Biological Sciences
,

17
: 
1124–1129
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
2004
. 

The present situation of freshwater crayfish, 
Astacus leptodactylus
(Eschscholtz, 1823) in Turkey

. 

Aquaculture

, 
230
: 
181–187
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
; 
Kutluyer, F.
and 
Gür, S.
2012
. 

An investigation on the sperm number and reproductive parameters of males in wild caught freshwater crayfish (
Astacus leptodactylus,
Eschscholtz)

. 

Animal Biology
,

62
: 
409–418
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
and 
Duran, T.Ç.
2010
. 

The effect of darkness on mating and pleopodal egg production time in a freshwater crayfish, 
Astacus leptodactylus
Eschscholtz

. 

Aquaculture International
,

18
: 
843–849
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
and 
Farhadi, A.
2017
. 
Factors affecting the reproductive efficiency in crayfish: implications for aquaculture
. 

Aquaculture Research
,

48
: 
1983–1997
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
and 
Harlıoğlu, A.G.
2004
. 

The harvest of freshwater crayfish, 
Astacus leptodactylus
(Eschscholtz, 1823) in Turkey

. 

Reviews in Fish Biology and Fisheries

, 
14
: 
415–419
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
; 
Çakmak, M.N.
; 
Köprücü, K.
; 
Aksu, Ö.
; 
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
; 
Mişe, Y.S.
; 
Çakmak, D.T.
; 
Özcan, S.
and 
Gündoğdu, H.
2013
a. 

The effect of dietary n-3 series fatty acids on the number of pleopadal egg and stage 1 juvenile in freshwater crayfish, 
Astacus leptodactylus
Eschscholtz

. 

Aquaculture Research

, 
44
: 
860–868
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
; 
Köprücü, K.
; 
Harlıoğlu, A.G.
; 
Mişe, Y.S.
; 
Çakmak, D.T.
; 
Çakmak, M.N.
; 
Aksu,Ö.
; 
Özcan,S.
; 
Kutluyer, F.
and 
Gündoğdu, H.
2013
b. 

Effect of dietary n-3 series fatty acids on sperm production in the freshwater crayfish, 
Astacus leptodactylus
(Eschscholtz) (Astacidae)

. 

Aquaculture International
,

21
: 
273–282
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
; 
Yonar, M.E.
; 
Harlıoğlu, A.G.
; 
Mişe Y.S.
and 
Farhadi, A.
2018
a. 

Effects of 17β-estradiol injection on the reproductive efficiency of freshwater crayfish, 
Astacus leptodactylus
(Eschscholtz,1823)

. 

Journal of Applied Aquaculture
,

30
: 
197–210
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harlıoğlu, M.M.
; 
Farhadi, A.
and 
Gür, S.
2018
b. 
Determination of sperm quality in decapod crustaceans
. 

Aquaculture
,

490
: 
185–193
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hemalatha, M.
; 
Parameswari, K.
; 
Kishori, B.
; 
Reddy, B.S.
and 
Reddy, P.R.
2016
. 
Methyl Farnesoate induced ovarian maturation in freshwater prawn
, 

Macrobrachium rosenbergii. Journal of Oceanography Marine Resesrch
,

4
: 
142
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kalavathy, Y.
; 
Mamatha, P.
and 
Sreenivasula, R.P.
1999
. 

Methyl farnesoate stimulates testicular growth in the freshwater crab 
Oziotelphusa senex senex fabricius

. 
Naturwissenschaften
, 
86
: 
394–395
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kouba, A.
; 
Kuklina, I.
; 
Niksirat, H.
; 
Machova, J.
and 
Konak, P.
2012
a. 

Tolerance of signal crayfish (
Pacifastacus leniusculus
) to Persteril 36 supports use of peracetic acid in astaciculture

. 

Aquaculture

, 
350
: 
71–74
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kouba, A.
; 
Niksirat, H.
and 
Blaha, M.
2015
. 

Comparative ultrastructure of spermatozoa of the redclaw 
Cherax quadricarinatus
and the yabby 
Cherax destructor
(Decapoda, Parastacidae)

. 

Micron

, 
69
: 
56–61
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kouba, A.
; 
Niksirat, H.
; 
Kuklina, I.
; 
Buric, M.
and 
Kozak, P.
2012
b. 

Ultraviolet light and semi-recirculating systems in artificial incubation of noble crayfish (
Astacus astacus)
eggs: opportunities and limitations

. 

Aquaculture Research
,

44
: 
67–74
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Laufer, H.
; 
Biggers, W.J.
and 
Ahl, J.S.B.
1998
. 

Stimulation of ovarian maturation in the crayfish 
Procambarus clarkii
by methyl farnesoate

. 

General and Comparative Endocrinology
,

111
: 
113–118
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Laufer, H.
; 
Demir, N.
; 
Pan, X.
; 
Stuart, J.D.
and 
Ahl, J.S.
2005
. 

Methyl farnesoate controls adult male morphogenesis in the crayfish, 
Procambarus clarkii

. 
Journal of Insect Physiol ogy
, 
51
: 
379–384
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Leung‐Trujillo, J.K.
and 
Lawrence, A.L.
1985
. 

The effect of eyestalk ablation on spermatophore and sperm quality in 
Penaeus vannamei

. 
Journal of the World Mariculture Society
, 
16
: 
258–266
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, M.
; 
Xie, X.
; 
Tao, T.
; 
Jiang, Q.
; 
Shao, J.
and 
Zhu, D.
2016
. 

Molecular characterization of methoprene-tolerant gene (Met) in the swimming crab 
Portunus trituberculatus
: Its putative role in methyl farnesoate-mediated vitellogenin transcriptional activation

. 

Animal Reproduction Science
,

174
: 
132–142
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Marsden, G.
; 
Hewitt, D.
and 
Boglio, E.
2008
. 
Methyl farnesoate inhibition of late stage ovarian development and fecundity reduction in the black tiger prawn
, 

Penaeus monodon. Aquaculture
,

280
: 
242–246
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Medesani, D.A.
; 
Ferre, L.E.
; 
Canosa, I.S.
; 
Silveyra, G.R.
and 
Rodriguez, E.M.
2015
. 
Induction of vitellogenesis by 17-hydroxyprogesterone and methyl farnesoate during postreproductive period
, in 

the estuarine crab 
Neohelice granulata

. 
Invertebrate Reproduction and Devvelopment
, 
59
: 
104–110
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nagaraju, G.P.C.
and 
Borst, D.W.
2008
. 

Methyl farnesoate couples environmental changes to testicular development in the crab 
Carcinus maenas

. 
Journal of Experimental Biology
, 
211
: 
2773–2778
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nagaraju, G.P.C.
; 
Suraj, N.J.
and 
Reddy, P.S.
2004
. 

Methyl farnesoate stimulates gonad developmentin 
Macrobrachium malcolmsonii
(H. Milne Edwards) (Decapoda, Palaemonidae)

. 

Crustaceana
,

76
: 
1171–1178
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niksirat, H.
and 
Kouba,A.
2016
. 

Subcellular localization of calcium deposits in the noble crayfish 
Astacus astacus
spermatophore: Implications for post-mating spermatophore hardening and spermatozoon maturation

. 

Journal of Morphology
,

277
: 
445–452
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niksirat, H.
; 
Andersson, L.
; 
James, P.
; 
Kauba, A.
and 
Kozak P.
2014
a. 

Proteomic profiling of the signal crayfish 
Pacifastacus leniusculus
egg and spermatophore

. 

Animal Reproduction Science
,

149
: 
335–344
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niksirat, H.
; 
James, P.
; 
Andersson, L.
; 
Kauba, A.
and 
Kozak, P.
2015
a. 

Label-free protein quantification in freshly ejaculated versus post-mating spermatophores of the noble crayfish 
Astacus astacus

. 
Journal of Proteomics
, 
123
: 
70–77
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niksirat, H.
; 
Kouba, A.
and 
Kozak, P.
2014
b. 

Post-mating morphological changes in the spermatozoon and spermatophore wall of the crayfish 
Astacus leptodactylus:
insight into a non-motile spermatozoon

. 

Animal Reproduction Science
,

149
: 
325–334
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niksirat, H.
; 
Kouba, A.
and 
Kozak, P.
2015
b. 

Ultrastructure of egg activation and cortical reaction in the noble crayfish 
Astacus astacus

. 
Micron
, 
68
: 
115–121
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niksirat, H.
; 
Kouba, A.
; 
Psenicka, M.
; 
Kuklina, I.
and 
Kozak, P.
2013
a. 

Ultrastructure of spermatozoa from three genera of crayfish 
Orconectes
, 
Procambarus
and 
Astacus
(Decapoda: Astacoidea): New findings and comparisons

. 

Z 
oologischher Anzeiger-A Journal of Comparative Zoology

, 
252
: 
226–233
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niksirat, H.
; 
Kouba, A.
; 
Rodina, M.
and 
Kozak, P.
2013
b. 

Comparative ultrastructure of the spermatozoa of three crayfish species: 
Austropotamobius torrentium
, 
Pacifastacus leniusculus
and 
Astacus astacus
(Decapoda: Astacidae)

. 

Journal of Morphology
,

27
: 
750–758
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niksirat, H.
Vancová, M.
; 
Andersson, L.
; 
James, P.
; 
Kouba, A.
and 
Kozak, P.
2016
. 

Protein modification in the post-mating spermatophore of the signal crayfish 
Pacifastacus leniusculus:
insight into the tyrosine phosphorylation in a non-motile spermatozoon

. 

Animal Reproduction Science
,

172
: 
123–130
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Raghavan, S.D.A.
and 
Ayanath, A.
2018
. 

Effect of Methyl Farnesoate administration on ovarian growth and maturation in the freshwater crab 
Travancoriana schirnerae

. 

Egyptian Journal of Aquatic Biology and Fisheries
,

22
: 
257–271
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Reddy, B.S.
and 
Reddy, P.R.
2015
. 

Methyl farnesoate induced ovarian vitellogenin syntehsis in freshwater rice field crab 
Oziothelphusa senex senex
Fabricus

. 

Journal of Infertility and Reproducvtive Biology
,

3
: 
237–244
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodríguez, E.M.
; 
Greco, L.S.L.
; 
Medesani, D.A.
; 
Laufer, H.
and 
Fingerman, M.
2002
. 

Effect of methyl farnesoate, alone and in combination with other hormones, on ovarian growth of the red swamp crayfish, 
Procambarus clarkii,
during vitellogenesis

. 

General and Compatative Endocrinolnology
,

125
: 
34–40
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rotllant, G.
; 
Pascual, N.
; 
Sardà, F.
; 
Takac, P.
and 
Laufer, H.
2001
. 
Identification of methyl farnesoate in the hemolymph of the Mediterranean deep-sea species Norway lobster
, 

Nephrops norvegicus. Journal of Crustacean Biology
,

21
: 
328–333
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Swetha, C.H.
; 
Sainath, S.B.
; 
Reddy, P.R.
and 
Reddy, P.S.
2011
. 
Reproductive endocrinology of female crustaceans: perspective and prospective
. 

Journal of Marine Science: Research and Development,
S

3
: 
1–13
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wickins, J.F.
and 
Lee, D.O.C.
2002
. 
Crustacean Farming Ranching and Culture
. 
Oxford, Blackwell Science
, 
464 p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yazicioglu, B.
; 
Reynolds, J.
and 
Kozak, P.
2016
a. 
Different aspects of reproduction strategies in crayfish: A review
. 

Knowledge and Managgement of Aquatic Ecosystems

, 
417
: 
33
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yazicioglu, B.
; 
Hamr, P.
; 
Kozak, P.
; 
Kouba, A.
and 
Niksirat, H.
2016
b. 

Fine structure of the spermatozoon in three species of Cambaridae (Arthropoda: Crustacea: Decapoda) 
Cambarus robustus, Orconectes propinquus
and 
Orconectes rusticus
: a comparative biometrical study

. 

PeerJ

, 
4
: e 
2363
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yazicioglu, B.
; 
Kouba, A.
; 
Kozak, P.
and 
Niksirat, H.
2018
. 
Post-mating spermatophore storage strategies in two species of crayfish: implications for broodstock management
. 

Animal
,

12
: 
554–558
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zaleski, M.A.F.
and 
Tamone, S.L.
2014
. 

Relationship of molting, gonadosomatic index, and methyl farnesoate in male snow crab (
Chionoecetes opilio
) from the eastern Bering Sea

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology
,

34
: 
764–772
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
