<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nauplius</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2358-2936e2022004</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Filling gaps in the biology of the endemic and threatened freshwater shrimp Macrobrachium candango (Caridea: Palaemonidae) through basic morphometric and reproductive approaches</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>21</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Palaemonidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi,Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Palaemonidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium
Spence Bate, 1868
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cryphiops
Dana, 1852
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi, Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cryphiops brasiliensis
Gomes Corrêa, 1973
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium caementarius
(Molina, 1782)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cryphiops caementarius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M.candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Macrobrachium</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi, Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi, Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi, Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi, Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi, Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi, Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez,2021
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium iheringi
(Ortmann, 1897) (

Nogueira 
et al.
, 2019

)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. iheringi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium olfersii
(Wiegmann, 1836)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium brasiliense
(Heller, 1862)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M.brasiliense
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. iheringi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium nattereri
(Heller, 1862)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium totonacum
Mejía, Alves and Hartnoll, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Macrobrachium</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. iheringi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium potiuna
(Müller, 1880)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ORIGINAL
ARTICLE
</title>
         <p>
Caio Santos Nogueira
1
B

orcid.org/0000-0001-8539-0551
</p>
         <p>
Emerson Contreira Mossolin
2
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-0569-9135
</p>
         <p>
Mauro César Lambert Brito Ribeiro
3
B

orcid.org/0000-0003-4798-4919
</p>
         <p>
Fernando Luis Mantelatto
4
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-8497-187X
</p>
         <p>
1

Laboratory of 
Biology of Marine

and Freshwater Shrimp (LABCAM), 
Department of Biological Sciences
, 
Faculty of Sciences
, 
São Paulo State

University (UNESP). Bauru, 
São Paulo
, 
Brazil

.

</p>
         <p>
CSN
E-mail: caiosnogueira@hotmail.com
</p>
         <p>
2

Department of Biological Sciences, Federal University of Catalão (UFCAT). Catalão, 
Goiás
, 
Brazil
.

</p>
         <p>
ECM
E-mail: ecmossolin@yahoo.com.br
</p>
         <p>
3

Cerrado Environmental Studies Center (GEC/DF), IBGE State Unit in the 
Federal District
(UE/DF). 

Brasília, 
Federal District
, 
Brazil

.

</p>
         <p>
MCLBR
E-mail: maurolambert@gmail.com
</p>
         <p>
4
Laboratory of Bioecology
and Crustacean Systematics (LBSC), 
Department of Biology
, 
Faculty of Philosophy
, Sciences and Letters at Ribeirão Preto (FFCLRP), University of 
São Paulo
(USP)

. 

Ribeirão Preto, 
São Paulo
, 
Brazil

.

</p>
         <p>
FLM
E-mail: flmantel@usp.br
</p>
         <p>
ZOOBANK
: http://zoobank.org/ 

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 

906CDFC3 
-DD84-
4 
C
8A-985C-ACFAF4 
E04C
4 
C
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi,Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
is an endemic shrimp species to the Brazilian Central-West region (Brasília, 
Federal District
). The present study aims to analyze the relative growth, morphometry, morphological sexual maturity, and fecundity of this species. Specimens were collected from tributaries of the Paranoá Lake hydrographic basin, Brasília, during sporadic periods between 1983 and 2012. Relative growth was analyzed for different structures (carapace, abdomen, second abdominal pleura, merus, carpus, and propodus). The laterality and heterochely patterns were evaluated based on the dimensions of the propodus length. Fecundity was calculated as the average total number of eggs per female and egg size was measured to obtain the volume. There were differences in relative growth (
p
&lt;0.05) of the structures analyzed between juveniles and adults, and distinct allometric patterns were observed between the life stages, which could reflect the habit of these animals at each developmental stage. No pattern of laterality and heterochely was observed between the chelipeds of the animals analyzed (
p
&gt; 0.05). The lack of laterality may indicate that this species directs energy to the smallest propodus when the largest propodus is injured. Egg volume ranged from 
4.41 to 7.71 mm
3
, and fecundity ranged from 38 to 
61 eggs
, indicating a life cycle with abbreviated larval development. The characteristics presented herein are unprecedented for 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
and present relevant information needed to assess the conservation status of this species, which is currently threatened.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
KEYWORDS
</title>
         <p>
Conservation, fecundity, heterochely, laterality, relative growth
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
Freshwater shrimps present great examples of adaptation to environments that constantly change or f luctuate, as they present a complex set of characters regarding reproduction, behavior, growth and morphology throughout their lifecycles, that are closely linked to habitat and life history (

; 

; 

; 

). Among the most complex aspects of the evolutionary process of this taxon is the embryonic development that can be abbreviated or extended, which directly affects the number and size of eggs that will be incubated (

; Sankoli 
et al
., 1993; 

; 

), and represents a phylogenetic premise in some groups (

).
</p>
         <p>
In 
Brazil
, the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Palaemonidae</tp:taxon-name>
is widely diverse, with species occupying different environments from the coastal region to inland waters in different watersheds (

; 

; 

). Among the genera of this diverse family, the Brazilian species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium
Spence Bate, 1868
</tp:taxon-name>
received special attention during the last decade with regard to updated taxonomy (

; 

; 

; 

), and most recently a taxonomic revision proposed a new nomenclatural and phylogenetic rearrangement in which all the six American species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cryphiops
Dana, 1852
</tp:taxon-name>
were accommodated in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

). Regarding this latter group, the only known species from Brazilian territory is 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
Mantelatto, Pileggi, Pantaleão, Magalhães, Villalobos and Álvarez, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
(originally described as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cryphiops brasiliensis
Gomes Corrêa, 1973
</tp:taxon-name>
), which is endemic to the Paranoá Lake hydrographic basin in Brasília, 
Federal District
(

; 

).
</p>
         <p>

The only information available on this species was registered in its description (

), which addressed its morphological characters and compared them with those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium caementarius
(Molina, 1782)
</tp:taxon-name>
(as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cryphiops caementarius
</tp:taxon-name>
) occurring in coastal areas of 
Chile
. In the same study, some observations about its fecundity were also reported (three ovigerous females incubated between42and 
63eggs
). 
Reports
from local collections and observations indicate that the abundance of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
is naturally low, with a high degree of endemism (

), causing the species to be categorized as threatened according to IUCN criteria. 
Additionally
, their habitats have been affected by anthropogenic actions such as pollution and deforestation (

; 

). 
Shrimps
have an important ecological role within aquatic ecosystems(

),and in the case of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M.candango
</tp:taxon-name>
, which is an endemic species in a region of 
Brazil
, its disappearance from the environment can cause irreversible problems to these ecosystems, influencing the local food chain (

; 

). 
Therefore
, due to this degree of endemism, it is necessary to carry out constant monitoring studies addressing 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
, in order to properly understand its ecological role in the 
Paranoá Lake
ecosystem

.
</p>
         <p>

Faced with this scenario we searched for more information by visiting its 
type
locality (ECM and FLM) to collect new specimens. 
During
these field activities, we were positively surprised to find a considerable collection of lots of this species deposited at the 
Aquatic Crustaceans Collection
of the 
Reserva Ecológica
do IBGE (
Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia
e 
Estatística
), 
Brasília
- 
Federal District
, which serve as the basis for the preparation of this article

.
</p>
         <p>
Thus,considering that knowledge about biological characteristics is fundamental for understanding the life cycle, and necessary for defining conservation strategies, particularly for species with low abundance and endemism, the present study aims to investigate basic aspects (relative growth, morphometry, morphological sexual maturity and fecundity) about the biology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
. In the future this information can be used to assess the conservation status of this species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
MATERIAL
AND
METHODS
</title>
         <p>
Scientific and field collections
</p>
         <p>
The field collection resulted from surveys carried out in 122 lotic stretches of tributaries forming the Paranoá Lake hydrographic basin, collected from 28 sampling points distributed along the four main tributaries of the Paranoá Lake (
Fig. 1
): Riacho Fundo (three sites, including the 
type
locality), Ribeirão do Torto (three sites), Ribeirão Bananal (five sites), and Ribeirão Gama (17 sites, 
11 in
the Taquara stream and six in the Roncador stream), which recorded the species in only 23 % of the sampled locations. The previous collection of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
deposited at the IBGE’s Aquatic Crustaceans Collection consists of 345 lots containing 
932 specimens
. Samplings occurred sporadically between 1983 and 2012, specifically in November/1983; February, April and August/1985; November/1986; February and March/1987; May/1988 to April/1989; July/1989; May/1990; October/1992; September/1998; October/2005; September/2009; and May and July/2012. All collections were performed using trawls (mesh size 
3 mm
).
</p>
         <p>
All
locations where specimens were present in the streams of 
Torto
and 
Bananal
(
Brasilia National Park
), 
Roncador
(IBGE 
Ecological Reserve
) and 
Taquara
(IBGE 
Ecological Reserve
, 
Area of Relevant Ecological Interest Capetinga -Taquara
and 
Ecological Station
of the 
Botanical Garden of Brasilia
) are within conservation units. 
Only
the locations in 
Riacho Fundo
, which includes the 
type
locality, are not within an environmental protection area. 
Only
one lot, with 
one specimen
, was collected in a transition zone between the Milho Cozido stream and the Santa Maria Reservoir (
Ribeirão do Torto
), while all 
other specimens
were captured in lotic environments of the 
Paranoá Lake
tributaries

.
</p>
         <p>
The third author (MCLBR) and his team were responsible for all expeditions. Two permanent licenses issued by SUDEPE (Superintendência do Desenvolvimento Pesca; 1983 to 1989) and IBAMA (Instituto Brasileiro do Meio Ambiente e dos Recursos Naturais Renováveis) in the 
Federal District
(1990 – 2009) allowed the collection of fish and aquatic crustaceans in these respective periods. Those responsible for the Conservation Units also authorized the collections. The surveys carried out in the Brasilia National Park, in 2012, were done in collaboration with CAESB (Companhia de Saneamento Ambiental do 
Distrito Federal
) to prepare the environmental impact study about the Santa Maria Dam construction to renew the environmental license for that enterprise. Therefore, the authorization for scientific activity was issued directly by the ICMBio (Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade), with consent of the Brasilia National Park.
</p>
         <p>After sampling, the material was screened in the field and shrimps were placed in a solution of clove oil and water for five minutes for euthanasia, and later placed in containers with 70 % alcohol and deposited in the scientific collection of the Reserva Ecológica do IBGE.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Laboratory analysis
</title>
         <p>
The sex of shrimps was checked under a stereomicroscope, following a protocol suggested by 

for the genus 

<tp:taxon-name>Macrobrachium</tp:taxon-name>
,

which requires observing the presence (male) or absence (female) of the male appendage on the second pair of pleopods. Subsequently, they were identified to species level according to 

and the length of the following structures were measured with a caliper (
0.01 mm
): carapace (CL), abdomen (AL), merus(ML),carpus (CaL),and propodus (PrL), along with the width of the second abdominal pleura (PW) (
Fig. 2
). The merus, carpus, and propodus selected for analysis constitute the cheliped of the second largest pair of pereopods (independent of the side). All animals used in the analyses presented intact structures.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Relative growth
</title>
         <p>
The comparative analysis of body dimensions was based on the measurements described above. Data normality was verified with the Shapiro-Wilk test (α = 0.05). The non-hierarchical analysis of K-means clustering (

) was used considering the morphometric relationships measured between the groups of males and females (juveniles and adults). This analysis distributes the data set into groups that are previously established by an interactive process, which minimizes the variance between groups. After determining K-means, a discriminant analysis was performed to refine the data for categorization (

). Afterwards, the data was submitted to a covariance analysis (ANCOVA) to test the angular and linear coefficients between the groups defined by the analyzes. This showed whether the data for each relationship fit better to a single equation or whether morphometric relationships should be represented by different linear equations.
</p>
         <p>
In the relative growth analysis, changes in the allometric coefficient were verified in the development of body structures related to the independent variable (CL). Scatter plots were constructed from the data set obtained by measuring body structures and adjusted to the allometric equation y = ax 
b
(

, 

; 

). Subsequently, the data was linearized (log y = log a + b × log x) in which “y” is the structure dimension studied, “x” the carapace length, “a” the intersection of the axis “y” and “b” the allometric coefficient(angular) that represents the slope and angle of the line.The allometric constant “b” was calculated for each morphometric relationship and the null hypothesis (H 
0
: b = 1) was tested with the Student test (α = 95 %). The values of the allometric constant correspond to isometric growth (b = 1), positive allometry (b&gt; 1) or negative allometry (b &lt;1) (

).
</p>
         <p>
Morphological sexual maturity was estimated from the inf lection break of the points resulting from the lines drawn based on the equations of adults and juveniles in the CL x PrL and CL x PW relationships for males and females, respectively. These relationships were chosen because they best reflect the variations that occur during the reproductive phases (juveniles and adults) (

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Laterality and heterochely
</title>
         <p>
The laterality pattern of males and females was investigated using the chi-square test (α = 0.05) (

), based on the propodus length of both chelipeds (right and left) of the second pair of pereopods.
</p>
         <p>
The heterochely analysis was performed based on the final result of the laterality test, using the Kruskal- 
Wallis
test and its Dunn’s post-hoc test (

). In the heterochely test,the largest propodus x smallest propodus (independent of the side) was compared due to the lack of laterality pattern.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Fecundity
</title>
         <p>
Fecundity was obtained from the total number of eggs adhered to pleopods. Therefore, 
15 eggs
were removed from the pleopods of each ovigerous female (OF) and the length and width of eggs were measured under a stereomicroscope to calculate egg volume (

). The egg volume (EV) was calculated as: EV = π * l * h * (h)²; where ‘‘l’’ is the length; ‘’h’’ is width in mm and π = 3.14 (

). The developmental stage of the embryos was classified into two stages, being early (eggs with homogeneous color and lacking visible eye pigmentation) and late (embryos with fully developed eyes) (

). The relationships between CL/PW and CL/number of eggs were investigated using a linear regression. Monthly rainfall data for the years that ovigerous females occurred were obtained from the digital platform HidroWeb of the SNIRH (Sistema Nacional de Informações sobre Recursos Hídricos).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
RESULTS
</title>
         <p>
A total of 262 individuals were analyzed, including 
157 males
(59.9%) and 
105females
(40.1 %). The mean CL for males was16.44 ± 
4.34 mm
, ranging from 
6.8 to 25.2 mm
, and for females was 11.5 ± 
2.86 mm
, ranging from 
4.8 to 17.4 mm
, with a significant difference in mean CL between sexes (Mann-Whitney, 
p
&lt;0.001). To analyze the relative growth of the largest cheliped articles, a total of 166 individuals (
102 males
and 
64 females
) with intact appendages were examined.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Relative growth
</title>
         <p>
The ANCOVA analysis (
Tab.1
) showed that adult male individuals differed statistically (
p
&lt;0.01) from juvenile males in the morphometric relationships related to pleura and chelipeds (CL × PW, CL × PrL, CL × CaL, and CL × ML), however, in the CL × AL morphometric relationship there was no difference between these groups (
p
&gt; 0.05). The same pattern occurred in females, with statistical difference (
p
&lt;0.01) between adult and juvenile females in almost all relationships investigated herein (CL × PW, CL × PrL, CL × CaL, and CL × ML), except for CL × AL (
p
&gt; 0.05, 
Tab. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Significant correlations were observed in all morphometric relationships (
p
&lt;0.01) (
Tab.2
).Since the CL × AL relationship did not differ significantly (ANCOVA, 
p
&gt; 0.05) between the demographic categories (adults and juveniles) of both sexes, these were represented by a single equation obtained through linear regression analysis. For males, a negative allometric growth was observed for the CL × PW and CL× AL relationships. Regarding chelipeds (CL × PrL, CL × CaL, and CL × ML), a positive allometric pattern was observed for adult males. For juvenile males, isometry was observed for CL × PrL and negative allometry was observed for the other relationships (CL × CaL and CL × ML).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
For females (adult and juvenile), negative allometry was observed in the relationship CL × AL, while a negative allometry and an isometry were observed for adults and juveniles, respectively, in the CL × PW relationship. Regarding chelipeds (CL × PrL, CL × CaL, and CL x ML), an allometric pattern was observed between adults and juveniles in all relationships,with negative allometric growth (
Tab.2
).
</p>
         <p>
Based on CL × PrL and CL × PW morphometric relationships, the size of morphological sexual maturity was estimated at 17.6 and 
10.9 mm
CL for males and females, respectively (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Laterality and heterochely
</p>
         <p>
There was no defined laterality pattern in males and females (males: Χ 
2
= 0.35 and 
p
= 0.84; females: Χ 
2
= 0.07 and 
p
= 0.96) and, therefore, individuals may present either right or left propodus as most developed. In males, the right and left propodus were more robust in 52.9 % and 47.1 % cases, respectively. In females this proportion was 48.3 % and 51.7 %, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
Due to the lack of laterality pattern, the heterochely analyses compared the largest propodus × smallest propodus. The average length of the largest and smallest propodus of adult males was 20.03 ± 
5.1 mm
and 16.64 ± 
3.86 mm
, while in juvenile males it was 9.71 ± 
2.25 mm
and 8.73 ± 
2.1 mm
, respectively. The average length of the largest and smallest propodus of adult females was 9.9 ± 
1.48 mm
and 9.2 ± 
1.52 mm
, while in juvenile females it was 7.07 ± 
0.92 mm
and 6.42 ± 
0.9 mm
, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
Heterochely was not found within the demographic categories (adult and juvenile males; adult and juvenile females), 
i.e.
, the length of the largest propodus was not significantly different from the smallest propodus (
p
&gt; 0.05). However, significant differences in the propodus length were observed between all demographic categories, and sexual dimorphism based on propodus length can be characterized in both life stages.The length of the largest and smallest propodus of adult males differed significantly from all other demographic categories (
p
&lt;0.01). The length of the largest propodus of juvenile males and adult females was only significantly different from the propodus (largest and smallest) of juvenile females (
p
&lt;0.01), as well as adult males (see 
Tab.3
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Reproductive aspects
</title>
         <p>
Fifty OF were used with a mean CL of 13.9 ± 
1.08 mm
, ranging from 
12.2 to 15.3 mm
. The average egg volume (EV) was 5.68 ± 
0.93 mm
3
, ranging from 
4.41 to 7.71 mm
3
. The average fecundity was 49 ± 11, ranging from 38 to 
61 eggs
. Among the 15 OF analyzed, only 
two females
incubated embryos in the late stage of development. The average volume of eggs in the early and late stages was 5.63 ± 
0.94 mm
3
and 6.03 ± 
1.13 mm
3
, respectively. There was no correlation between CL and number of eggs (
p
&gt; 0.05), however, there was a positive correlation between PW and number of eggs (
p
&lt;0.05). Based on all individuals sampled, a higher abundance of OF was observed in October/2005, followed by September/2009, January/1989, August/1988 and November/1988 (
Fig. 4a
). In most cases, OF were found in months with a high volume of rainfall, except for August/1988 (
Fig. 4b
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
</title>
         <p>
Forty-nine years after the species was described, detailed information about the morphometry and reproduction of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
was gathered from data collected for a 30-year time period and analyzed for the first time herein, revealing information about aspects of its life history.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Morphometric aspects
</title>
         <p>
The development pattern of PW in males and females was similar, except for juvenile females that presented isometric development. This group of juvenile females has this difference possibly due to the need for the pleura to be well developed until its adult phase, which is when this structure will have the function of expanding the size of the hatchery chamber, allowing these females to hatch more eggs (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). Therefore, this structure develops at the same rate as the carapace during the juvenile phase, but modifies its growth pattern when reaching sexual maturity, which is when the adult female starts to invest more energy in gonadal development (

).
</p>
         <p>
In the morphometric relationships related to the chelipeds of adult and juvenile males, a distinct pattern was found among these groups, where adult males invest more energy than juveniles in the development of the articles of the largest cheliped. During the life stages of shrimps, chelipeds play important roles in feeding and agonistic behaviors (

; 

); thus, the unequal development of this structure between life stages may be related to its different functions (

). Adult individuals require highly developed chelipeds for disputes over females or mating behaviors, on the other hand, juveniles do not dispute sexual partners, possibly this group uses this structure for more general functions such as foraging and for body cleaning (

, 1982; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
For females, the morphometric relationships of the chelipeds showed the same 
type
of development between adults and juveniles (allometrically negative). Again, this result refers to the functional role of these appendages in these categories (

; 

), because females might use chelipeds differently than males and may not require these appendages to be robust.Therefore, they use less energy to develop this structure, justifying the allometric pattern found, in addition, these results reinforce the sexual dimorphism found in the propodus length between males and females.
</p>
         <p>
Analyzing the average length of the largest and smallest propodus between the demographic categories, significant differences were observed between these groups, with sexual dimorphism between adult and juvenile males and females. Sexual dimorphism based on the length of the chelipeds or propodus is a characteristic that has been widely observed in other shrimp species (

; 

; 

; 

; 

), and this unique trait mainly refers to the sexual behavior of these animals, where males use chelipeds to dispute and guard females before and after copulation (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The size of the morphological sexual maturity observed in this study was similar to that observed for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium iheringi
(Ortmann, 1897) (

Nogueira 
et al.
, 2019

)
</tp:taxon-name>
, a species that presents a similar body size variation to that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
. Furthermore, in both species males reach morphological sexual maturity at larger sizes than females, indicating that possibly 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
has the reproductive strategy called “mate guarding” (

), as was suggested for 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. iheringi
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

); a result that is correlated with the occurrence of sexual dimorphism in body size and chelipeds, and with different patterns of allometric development between males and females.
</p>
         <p>
The lack of a laterality pattern seems to be a common feature in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium
species
</tp:taxon-name>
that have heterochely, this was also observed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium olfersii
(Wiegmann, 1836)
</tp:taxon-name>
by 

, and in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium brasiliense
(Heller, 1862)
</tp:taxon-name>
by 

, where the males and females analyzed did not have a constant between which propodus (left or right) would be the most developed. Therefore, it has been suggested that this characteristic (
i.e.
, laterality) may not be genetically predetermined (

). In some decapod crustaceans, such as brachyuran crabs, the lack of a laterality pattern is common (

; 

). These crabs usually use the largest cheliped as a weapon in agonistic contests. If these individuals lose this appendage during these disputes, the other cheliped (the smallest) will become the largest (

). Possibly this also occurs in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
, since these individuals have a major cheliped, this structure can be used as the main weapon during disputes over resources, therefore, this appendage is more likely to be injured or amputated.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Reproductive features
</title>
         <p>
Based on the low fecundity and large volume of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
eggs, it can be inferred that this species has abbreviated larval development, where the embryos develop for a longer time within the egg. After hatching, larvae originate in the final stage of development, leaving few morphological characteristics to be considered juveniles, these characteristics will be developed in two or three larval stages, which precede the juvenile phase (Sankoli 
et al
., 1993; 

). Some species of freshwater shrimps exhibit this characteristic, in which low fecundity along with large eggs is correlated to the 
type
of larval development, as recorded, for instance, for 
<tp:taxon-name>
M.brasiliense
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. iheringi
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium nattereri
(Heller, 1862)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium totonacum
Mejía, Alves and Hartnoll, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

; 

; Mejía- Ortíz 
et al
., 2010, respectively). Molecular analyzes (using mitochondrial16S and COI genes)indicate that these species are phylogenetically close and are part of the same clade with abbreviated larval development (

; 

). Thus, the reproductive and phylogenetic aspects found lead us to infer that 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
presents abbreviated larval development, a condition that should be investigated in the future with the larval description of the species.
</p>
         <p>
The reproductive period in freshwater shrimps can be characterized in two ways: continuous reproduction throughout the year with reproductive peaks at specific times or the reproductive period is seasonal (

). Although we do not have enough evidence to state the 
type
of reproductive period for 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
due to the sampling method used in the capture of individuals, the majority of ovigerous females (93.3 %) were collected when there was an increase in rainfall, and it is known that there is a strong relationship between this abiotic factor and the seasonal reproductive period in some species of 

<tp:taxon-name>Macrobrachium</tp:taxon-name>
.

This 
type
of reproductive period associated with rainfall has already been observed in some other species of freshwater shrimps, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. iheringi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium potiuna
(Müller, 1880)
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

, respectively), which could be an indication that 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
has seasonal reproduction. However, in addition to evidence on the 
type
of larval development, further studies are needed to confirm this hypothesis.
</p>
         <p>
Based on the information obtained in the present study, we can state that 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
presents similarities with other species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
e.g.
, reproductive features such as low fecundity due to abbreviated larval development, along with allometric development patterns. Some characteristics of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. candango
</tp:taxon-name>
categorize it as a species at risk of decreasing its already low natural abundance: endemic, occurring in environments with anthropogenic pressures and low fecundity. Thus,the biological aspects studied herein are important and reinforce the previous recommendation regarding the unrestricted protection of the species (

; 

), including future projects focused on monitoring populations throughout the area of occurrence.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
</title>
         <p>
We express our gratitude to Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq) (304968/2014-5; 302253/2019-0; 471011/2011- 8) and Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do 
Estado de São Paulo
(FAPESP) (Projeto Biota FAPESP – INTERCRUSTA 2018/13685-5; PROTA 
X 2021
/08075-6) for providing research grants to FLM. We give special thanks to IBGE for logistic support and laboratory availability during the visit and field work. The authors also thank Dr. José Wilson Corrêa Rosa (Instituto de Geociências da Universidade de Brasília – UnB) for making the map of occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrobrachium candango
</tp:taxon-name>
. CSN would like to thank the ongoing doctoral scholarship provided by FAPESP (2019/00661-3). ECM would like to thank the students Gabriela S. Ribeiro, Lucas R. Rezende, and Michelle F. Agapito for help with data collection. The species collections were compiled in accordance with current applicable state and federal laws of 
Brazil
. We are grateful for the comments made by anonymous referees and assistant editor Dr. Célio Magalhães during the reviewing process.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Anger, K.
2013
. 

Neotropical 
Macrobrachium
(Caridea: Palaemonidae): on the biology, origin, and radiation of freshwater-invading shrimp

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
33
: 
151−183
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Anger, K.
and 
Moreira, G.S.
1998
. 
Morphometric and reproductive traits of tropical caridean shrimps
. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
18
: 
823−838
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bauer, R.T.
1989
. 
Continuous reproduction and episodic recruitment in nine shrimp species inhabiting a tropical seagrass meadow
. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 
127
: 
175−187
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bauer, R.T.
2004
. 
Remarkable Shrimps: Adaptations and Natural History of the Carideans
. 
Norman, University of Oklahoma Press
, 
316p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bueno, S.L.S.
and 
Rodrigues, S.A.
1995
. 

Abbreviated larval development of the freshwater prawn, 
Macrobrachium iheringi
(Ortmann, 1897) (Decapoda, Palaemonidae), reared in the laboratory

. 

Crustaceana

, 
68
: 
665−686
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Coelho, P.A.
and 
Ramos-Porto, M.
1984
. 
Camarões de água doce do Brasil: distribuição geográfica
. 

Revista brasileira de Zoologia

, 
2
: 
405−410
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Correa, C.
and 
Thiel, M.
2003
. 
Mating systems in caridean shrimp (Decapoda: Caridea) and their evolutionary consequences for sexual dimorphism and reproductive biology
. 

Revista Chilena de Historia Natural

, 
76
: 
187−203
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Daniel, W.W.
1990
. 
Kruskal–Wallis one-way analysis of variance by ranks
. 

Applied Nonparametric Statistics

, 
226−234
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
De Souza, M.L.
and 
Moulton, T.P.
2005
. 
The effects of shrimps on benthic material in a Brazilian island stream
. 

Freshwater Biology
,

50
: 
592−602
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dos Santos, A.
; 
Hayd, L.
and 
Anger, K.
2013
. 

A new species of Macrobrachium Spence Bate, 1868 (Decapoda, Palaemonidae), 
M. pantanalense
, from the Pantanal, Brazil

. 

Zootaxa

, 
3700
: 
534−546
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Franchito, S.H.
; 
Rao, V.B.
; 
Barbieri, P.R.
and 
Santo, C.M.
2008
. 
Rainy-season duration estimated from OLR versus rain gauge data and the 2001 drought in Southeast Brazil
. 

Journal of Applied Meteorology and Climatology

, 
47
: 
1493−1499
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gomes Corrêa, M.M.
1973
. 

Descrição de uma espécie nova do gênero 
Cryphiops
(Decapoda, Natantia, Palaemonidae)

. 

Revista Brasileira de Biologia

, 
33
: 
169−173
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hartnoll, R.G.
1974
. 
Variation in growth pattern between some secondary sexual characters in crabs (Decapoda, Brachyura)
. 

Crustaceana

, 
27
: 
131−136
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hartnoll, R.G.
1978
. 
The determination of relative growth in Crustacea
. 

Crustaceana

, 
34
: 
281−293
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hawkins, S.J.
and 
Hartnoll, R.G.
1982
. 

The influence of barnacle cover on the numbers, growth and behaviour of 
Patella vulgata
on a vertical pier

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
62
: 
855−867
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Holthuis, L.B.
1952
. 
A general revision of the Palaemonidae (Crustacea, Decapoda, Natantia) of the Americas. II. The Subfamily Palaemonidae
. 

Occasional Papers of the Allan Hancock Foundation

, 
12
: 
1–396
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Karplus, I.
and 
Barki, A.
2019
. 

Male morphotypes and alternative mating tactics in freshwater prawns of the genus 
Macrobrachium
: a review

. 

Reviews in Aquaculture

, 
11
: 
925–940
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Koshy, M.
1973
. 

Studies on the sexual dimorphism in the freshwater prawn 
Macrobrachium dayanum
(Henderson, 1893) (Decapoda, Caridea), II

. 

Crustaceana

, 
24
: 
110–118
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Magalhães, C.
1989
. 

The larval development of palaemonid shrimps from the amazon region reared in the laboratory.VI. Abbreviated development of 
Macrobrachium nattereri
(Heller, 1862) (Crustacea, Decapoda)

. 

Amazoniana: Limnologia et Oecologia Regionalis Systematis Fluminis Amazonas

, 
10
: 
379–392
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Magalhães, C.
and 

Walker, 

I. 
1988


. 
Larval development and ecological distribution of Central Amazonian palaemonid shrimps (Decapoda: Caridea)
. 

Crustaceana

, 
55
: 
279–292
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mantelatto, F.L.
and 
Barbosa, L.R.
2005
. 

Population structure and relative growth of freshwater prawn 
Macrobrachium brasiliense
(Decapoda, Palaemonidae) from São Paulo State, Brazil

. 

Acta Limnologica Brasiliensia

, 
17
: 
245–255
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mantelatto, F.L.
; 
Pileggi, L.G.
; 
Magalhães, C.
; 
Carvalho, F.L.
; 
Rocha, S.S.
; 
Mossolin, E.C.
and 
Bueno, S.L.S.
2016
. 
Avaliação dos Camarões Palemonídeos (Decapoda: Palaemonidae). Cap. 20
, p. 
252–267
. In: 
M.A.A. Pinheiro and H. Boos (Org.), Livro Vermelho dos Crustáceos do Brasil: Avaliação 2010
- 2014. 
Porto Alegre, RS, Sociedade Brasileira de Carcinologia – SBC
. 
466 p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mantelatto, F.L.
; 
Pileggi, L.G.
; 
Pantaleão, J.A.F.
; 
Magalhães, C.
; 
Villalobos, J.L.
and 
Alvarez, F.
2021
. 

Multigene phylogeny and taxonomic revision of American shrimps of the genus 
Cryphiops
Dana, 1852 (Decapoda, Palaemonidae) implies a proposal for reversal of precedence with 
Macrobrachium
Spence Bate

, 1868. 

ZooKeys

, 
1047
: 
155–198
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
March, J.G.
; 
Pringle, C.M.
; 
Townsend, M.J.
and 

Wilson, A. 

I. 
2002


. 
Effects of freshwater shrimp assemblages on benthic communities along an altitudinal gradient of a tropical island stream
. 

Freshwater Biology

, 
47
: 
377–390
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mariappan, P.
and 
Balasundaram, C.
1997
. 

Cheliped laterality in freshwater prawn, 
Macrobrachium nobilii
(Henderson and Matthai, 1910)

. 

Current Science

, 
875–877
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mariappan, P.
; 
Balasundaram, C.
and 
Schmitz, B.
2000
. 
Decapod crustacean chelipeds: an overview
. 

Journal of Biosciences

, 
25
: 
301–313
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mattos, L.A.
and 
Oshiro, L.M.Y.
2009
. 

Estrutura populacional de 
Macrobrachium potiuna
(Crustacea, Palaemonidae) no Rio do Moinho, Mangaratiba, Rio de Janeiro, Brasil

. 

Biota Neotropica

, 
9
: 
81–86
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mejia-Ortiz, L.M.
; 
Hartnoll, R.G.
and 
Lopez-Mejia, M.
2010
. 

The abbreviated larval development of 
Macrobrachium totonacum
Mejia, Alvarez &amp; Hartnoll, 2003 (Decapoda, Palaemonidae), reared in the laboratory

. 

Crustaceana

, 
83
: 
1–16
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Melo, G.A.S.
2003
. 
Manual de identificação dos Crustacea Decapoda de água doce do Brasil
. 
São Paulo, Ed. Loyola
, 
429p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mossolin, E.C.
and 
Bueno, S.L.
2003
. 

Relative growth of the second pereiopod in 
Macrobrachium olfersi
(Wiegmann, 1836) (Decapoda, Palaemonidae)

. 

Crustaceana

, 
76
: 
363–376
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nagamine, C.
and 
Knight, A.W.
1980
. 

Development, maturation and function of some sexually dimorphic structures of the Malaysian prawn, 
Macrobrachium rosenbergii
(de Man) (Decapoda, Palaemonidae)

. 

Crustaceana

, 
39
: 
141–152
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nogueira, C.S.
; 
Pantaleão, J.A.F.
; 
Almeida, A.C.
and 
Costa, R.C.
2020
. 

Male morphotypes of the freshwater prawn 
Macrobrachium brasiliense
(Decapoda: Caridea: Palaemonidae)

. 

Invertebrate Biology

, 
139
(
1
): e 
12279
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nogueira, C.S.
; 
Perroca, J.F.
; 
Piantkoski, E.L.
; 
Costa, R.C.
; 
Taddei, F.G.
and 
Fransozo, A.
2019
. 

Relative growth and population dynamics of 
Macrobrachium iheringi
(Decapoda, Palaemonidae)

. 

Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia

, 
59
: e 
20195908
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Odinetz-Collart, O.
and 
Magalhães, C.
1994
. 
Ecological constraints and life history strategies of palaemonid prawns in Amazonia
. 

Internationale Vereinigung für theoretische und angewandte Limnologie

, 
25
: 
2460–2467
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pantaleão, J.A.F.
; 
Gregati, R.A.
; 
Taddei, F.G.
and 
Costa, R.C.
2011
. 

Morphology of the first larval stage of 
Macrobrachium brasiliense
(Heller, 1868) (Caridea: Palaemonidae)

. 

Nauplius

, 
19
: 
79–85
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pantaleão, J.A.F.
; 
Hirose, G.L.
and 
Costa, R.C.
2012
. 

Relative growth, morphological sexual maturity, and size of 
Macrobrachium amazonicum
(Heller 1862) (Crustacea, Decapoda, Palaemonidae) in a population with an entirely freshwater life cycle

. 

Invertebrate Reproduction
&amp; 
Development

, 
56
: 
180–190
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pearson, K.
1900
. 
X. On the criterion that a given system of deviations from the probable in the case of a correlated system of variables is such that it can be reasonably supposed to have arisen from random sampling
. 

The London, Edinburgh, and Dublin Philosophical Magazine and Journal of Science

, 
50
(
302
): 
157–175
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pereira, G.
1997
. 
A cladistic analysis of the freshwater shrimps of the family Palaemonidae (Crustacea, Decapoda, Caridea)
. 

Acta Biologica Venezuelica

, 
17
: 
1–69
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pereira, S.G.A.
and 
Garcia, D.
1995
. 

Larval development of 
Macrobrachium reyesi
(Decapoda: Palaemonidae), with a discussion on the origin of abbreviated development in palaemonids

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
15
: 
117–133
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pescinelli, R.A.
; 
Almeida, A.O.
and 
Costa, R.C.
2018
. 

Population structure, relative growth and morphological sexual maturity of the snapping shrimp 
Alpheus brasileiro
Anker, 2012 (Caridea: Alpheidae) from the south-eastern coast of Brazil

. 

Marine Biology Research

, 
14
: 
610–620
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pileggi, L.G.
and 
Mantelatto, F.L.
2010
. 

Molecular phylogeny of the freshwater prawn genus 
Macrobrachium
(Decapoda, Palaemonidae), with emphasis on the relationships among selected American species

. 

Invertebrate Systematics

, 
24
: 
194–208
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pileggi, L.G.
and 
Mantelatto, F.L.
2012
. 

Taxonomic revision of doubtful Brazilian freshwater shrimp species of genus 
Macrobrachium
(Decapoda, Palaemonidae)

. 

Iheringia, Série Zoologia

, 
102
: 
426–437
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pralon, B.G.N.
and 
Negreiros-Fransozo, M.L.
2006
. 

Population biology of 
Palaemon
(
Palaeander
) 
northropi
Rankin, 1898 (Crustacea, Decapoda, Palaemonidae) in a tropical South American estuary

. 

Acta Limnologica Brasiliensia

, 
18
: 
77–87
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rossi, N.
; 
Magalhães, C.
; 
Mesquita, E.R.
and 
Mantelatto, F.L.
2020
. 

Uncovering a hidden diversity: a new species of freshwater shrimp 
Macrobrachium
(Decapoda: Caridea: Palaemonidae) from Neotropical region (Brazil) revealed by morphological review and mitochondrial genes analyses

. 

Zootaxa

, 
4732
: 
177–195
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sampaio, C.M.S.
; 
Silva, R.R.
; 
Santos, J.A.
and 
Sales, S.P.
2007
. 

Reproductive cycle of 
Macrobrachium amazonicum
females (Crustacea, Palaemonidae)

. 

Brazilian Journal of Biology

, 
67
: 
551–559
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sampedro, M.P.
; 
González-Gurriarán, E.
; 
Freire, J.
and 
Muiño, R.
1999
. 

Morphometry and sexual maturity in the spider crab 
Maja squinado
(Decapoda: Majidae) in Galicia, Spain

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
19
: 
578–592
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sankolli, K.N.
; 
Jalihal,D.R.
and 
Shenoy, S.
1993
. 

Evolution of larval developmental patterns and the process of freshwaterization in the prawn genus 
Macrobrachium
Bate, 1868 (Decapoda, Palaemonidae)

. 

Crustaceana

, 
65
: 
365–376
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Santos, F.M.
; 
Pescinelli, R.A.
; 
Pantaleão, J.A.F.
and 
Costa, R.C.
2018
. 

Relative growth, morphological sexual maturity, heterochely, and handedness in 
Panopeus occidentalis
(Brachyura, Panopeidae)

. 

Invertebrate Reproduction
&amp; 
Development

, 
62
: 
74–81
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smith, L.D.
and 
Palmer, A.R.
1994
. 
Effects of manipulated diet on size and performance of brachyuran crab claws
. 

Science

, 
264
(
5159
): 
710–712
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sokal, R.R.
; 
Rohlf, F.J.
and 
Lahoz-León, M.
1979
. 
Biometría: principios y métodos estadísticos en la investigación biológica
. 
Madrid, Blume
, 
832p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Valenti, W.C.
; 
Lobão, V.L.
and 
Mello, J.T.
1989
. 

Crescimento relativo de 
Macrobrachium acanthurus
(Wiegmann, 1836) (Crustacea, Decapoda, Palaemonidae)

. 

Revista brasileira de Zoologia

, 
6
: 
1–8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wehrtmann, I.S.
1990
. 

Distribution and reproduction of 
Ambidexter panamense
and 
Palaemonetes schmitti
in Pacific Costa Rica (Crustacea, Decapoda)

. 

Revista de Biología Tropical

, 38(
2
A): 
327–329
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zar, J.H.
2010
. 
Biostatistical analysis
. 
Pearson Education Upper Saddie River, New Jersey, USA
, 
944p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
