<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nauplius</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2358-2936e2021001</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Individual growth and mortality of Rhithropanopeus harrisii (Decapoda: Panopeidae) in the estuarine region of Patos Lagoon, Southern Brazil</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>18</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Panopeidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
(Gould, 1841)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
(Gould,1841)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Panopeidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Neohelice granulata
(Dana, 1851)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Callinectes sapidus
Rathbun, 1896
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>R. harrisii</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Genidens genidens
(Cuvier, 1829))
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Netuma barba
Lacepède, 1803
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Netuma planifrons
Higuchi, Reis and Araújo, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Paralichthys orbygnianus
Valenciennes, 1839
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Micropogonias furnieri
Desmarest, 1823
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>R. harrisii</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. furnieri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. furnieri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cyrtograpsus angulatus
Dana, 1851
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. granulata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. sapidus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. furnieri
(
Mendoza-Carranza and Vieira, 2008
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cy. angulatus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>M. furnieri</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. barba
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Callinectes
Stimpson, 1860
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. sapidus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. sapidus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. sapidus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>R. harrisii</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ORIGINAL
ARTICLE
</title>
         <p>
Diego Schuch Rodrigues
1
B

orcid.org/0000-0001-9195-6785
</p>
         <p>
Duane Barros Fonseca
2
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-8085-7156
</p>
         <p>
1
Universidade Federal do Rio Grande, Instituto de Oceanografia, Laboratório
</p>
         <p>
de Crustáceos Decápodes. Rio Grande, 
Rio Grande do Sul
, 
Brazil
</p>
         <p>
DSR
E-mail: docbiooceano@gmail.com
</p>
         <p>
2
Universidade Federal do Rio Grande, Instituto de Ciências Fisiológicas.
</p>
         <p>
Rio Grande, 
Rio Grande do Sul
, 
Brazil
</p>
         <p>
DBF
E-mail: dbf1 
@mac.com
</p>
         <p>
ZOOBANK
: http://zoobank.org/ 

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 

D98C6FE7-65D0-43E2 
- 97C0-10727A
2 
E16D
6

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
</title>
         <p>
The present investigation aimed to estimate the individual growth and mortality of an invasive species found in the estuarine region of Patos Lagoon (Southern 
Brazil
). For 20 months crabs were sampled, and in the laboratory specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
(Gould, 1841)
</tp:taxon-name>
were measured (carapace width, CW, and weight). Carapace width data was utilized for a modal progression analysis and to estimate the individual growth curve (von Bertalanffy growth model), and a size-converted catch curve. Von Bertalanffy parameters estimated were CW 
∞
= 
16.92 mm
and 
k
= 1.28 
year-1
. Maximum longevity was estimated at 3.5 years. Instantaneous total mortality was estimated at 2.17 ± 0.30 
year-1
. It has been suggested that longevity may be explained by a low predation impact on 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
, which, as a consequence, may lead to slow individual growth of this species in the estuarine region of Patos Lagoon.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
KEYWORDS
</title>
         <p>
Crab, longevity, modal progression, population ecology, predation
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
The introduction of non-native species in the environment is a constant threat for terrestrial and marine biodiversity, and an important issue in environmental global change (

). Each river basin has a characteristic faunal composition, with its endemic species bound by natural geographic barriers, and anthropogenic changes have led to losses in biodiversity and the increased likelihood of bio-invasions (

). Crustaceans are understood to be the main group of invasive species on continental and regional scales (Hänf lig 
et al.
, 2011).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
(Gould,1841)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Panopeidae</tp:taxon-name>
) is a native crab from North America (Atlantic Coast), distributed from 
New Brunswick
(
Canada
), through the north of the Gulf of 
Mexico
(Florida, 
USA
), to 
Mexico
, 
Panama
, and 
Venezuela
(

; 

; 

). It is an euryhaline species, in which adults are found in water with salinity from 0.5 to 40 ppt (

). This species is typically cryptic and found under stones and in vegetation, but an association with oyster reefs or debris, muddy and sandy substrates have been also reported (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
is noted to outcompete native species (

) and to spread white spot baculovirus, with potential impacts on aquaculture and commercial harvests (

).
</p>
         <p>
The occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
in the estuarine region of the Patos Lagoon (Southern 
Brazil
) has been reported by 

, with specimens caught from 1982 to 1985 at several locations in the estuary, 
e.g.
, from the breakwater up to 
40 km
into the estuarine region such as “Praia do Barro Duro” (Pelotas City). It is not understood whether the introduction was facilitated by ballast water (

) or by ship fouling (

). This estuarine region is located in the Southwestern Atlantic, on the Subtropical Convergence region and the mouth of the estuary is an access point to the Port of Rio Grande, an important port for Mercosul trading (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
has been established in this estuarine region, and this species has not been reported in any other estuary on the Brazilian coast (

).
</p>
         <p>
For the estuarine region of the Patos Lagoon, only one study on the biology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
is published (

). This paper reported biometric relationships and estimates of the abundance of this species but did not report on individual growth or other population parameters. Invasive species are interesting subjects to study basic processes in population biology, as it is important to understand the life history traits that allow a species to be successfully settled in the environment. Moreover, this basic information can feed demographic models that can be applied for the management of populations of these invaders (

).
</p>
         <p>
The individual growth of an organism is described by its increase in size (or weight) with age. Crustaceans have exoskeletons which must be periodically shed for incremental growth, and this process is called ecdysis. As no hard structures which carry age information are kept, typically, the study of age and growth is carried out using size-based methods such as modal progression analysis (

). Individual growth of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
has been studied in laboratory conditions, using crabs caught from a location in 
Poland
(

). It has been determined that eight to nine ecdyses occur before the adult phase is reached and maximum longevity was estimated at five years (

).
</p>
         <p>
The present investigation aims to estimate the growth curve based on the von Bertalanffy growth model and the total mortality of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
based on samples taken in the estuarine region of the Patos Lagoon.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
MATERIAL
AND
METHODS
</title>
         <p>
Sampling
</p>
         <p>
Samples
were taken from 
July
/2015to 
March
/2017 (20 months). 
Three
rectangular samplers (21.1 × 18.1 × 
15.6 cm
, 6L; 

) were placed at 
Marinheiros Island
(“ 
Ilha dos Marinheiros
”) (
32°02’S
52°19’W
), at a location called Bandeirinhas, Patos Lagoon, southern 
Brazil
(
Fig. 1
). Each sampler was filled with empty shells (bivalves and gastropods) to provide hiding places for the animals

.
</p>
         <p>
A mesh (
7 cm
aperture) was used to cover the sampler to prevent the entrance of large animals. Samplers were submerged (
1 m
deep), attached to a pier by nylon ropes, and laid five meters away from each other along this pier. Every two weeks samplers were emptied by washing the shells in a mesh. All sediment washed from the samplers was put in plastic bags and taken to the laboratory for sorting. The location was chosen based on the fact that it represented a habitat with low anthropogenic impact with regard to pollution and substrate modification. This sampling was part of a broader design to compare abundances of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
in three locations in the estuarine region.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Laboratory analyses
</title>
         <p>
Samples taken to the laboratory were washed and specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
were sorted, sexed, measured and weighed. Species identification was based on 

and 

. The size was measured as carapace width (CW, in mm) between the lateral spines, using a digital calliper (to nearest 
0.1 mm
). Weight was measured in grams. Sex was determined using a stereoscopic microscope.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Individual growth
</title>
         <p>Considering the small monthly sample sizes, some compromise had to be made to estimate the individual growth. Therefore, sexes were combined and animals caught were pooled by season (Summer, Dec–Feb; Autumn, Mar–May; Winter, Jun–Aug; Spring, Sept– Nov). The first pooled sample (Winter/2015) was considered time zero. Subsequently, Spring/2015, Summer/2015, Autumn/2016, Summer/2016 and Summer/2017 were utilized for modal progression analysis (MPA). Due to the small sample sizes, Winter/2016 (n = 17) and Spring/2016 (n = 17) were not utilized for the MPA.</p>
         <p>
Modal groups were determined on CW frequency distributions (
1 mm
bins) using the software PeakFit (SPSS Inc.).Gaussian peaks were then fitted to carapace width frequency distributions by an automated least-squares fitting procedure. Modal values determined in each CW frequency distribution were tentatively linked to visualize the modal progression. Growth curves, based on the von Bertalanffy growth function (VBGF), were estimated for the determined cohorts. Fitting was performed by least-squares minimization. Thereafter, a pooled VBGF was estimated. Maximum longevity (T 
max
) was calculated by the inverted von Bertalanffy equation, using 99 % of the asymptotic size as recommended by 

, and recently supported by investigations on brachyurans (

; 

). Average maximum longevity was estimated by 95 % of the largest animals (Taylor, 1965).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Mortality
</title>
         <p>
To estimate the mortality rate, parameters of individual growth estimated for this population were utilized to convert length to age (
t
). Instantaneous rate of total mortality (Z) was estimated by a size-converted catch curve — ln(N/∆t) = a+bt’ — where the slope of regression (
b
) is the estimate of Z, N is the number of individuals in a given size class, ∆t is the time for the individuals growth through that size class and 
t
is the mean age of the individual in that size class (

). Least-squares regression was utilized, and the significance of the regression assessed by an F-test.
</p>
         <p>
To assess the estimate of the instantaneous rate of total mortality (Z) for 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
, information regarding von Bertalanffy growth parameters 
k
and Z were compiled for 15 species of brachyurans inhabiting estuarine and coastal areas. With this information, a linear regression — least-squares minimization — was fitted to predict Z in relation to 
k
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
RESULTS
</title>
         <p>
A total of 1,082 animals were caught, 
619 females
and 
463 males
. Size range was 
2.4 to 14.3 mm
for females and 
2.5 to 17.9 mm
for males. Average CW of males and females was 8.41 ± 0.16 and 7.00 ± 
0.10 mm
, respectively. On average, females were lighter (0.16 ± 
0.007 g
) than males (0.35 ± 
0.016 g
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Individual growth
</title>
         <p>Two cohorts were followed for the period of study</p>
         <p>
(
Fig. 2
), and the pooled growth curve (
Fig. 3
) resulted
</p>
         <p>
in estimates of CW 
∞
= 
16.92 mm
and 
k
= 1.28 year 
-1
. This curve exhibited a 
12.22 mm
and 
15.61 mm
CW for 1 and 2 year old crabs, respectively. Based on the growth parameters estimated for this pooled growth curve, maximum longevity was estimated as 43 months (approximately 3.5 years). This value could only be reached by a male, as no female is as large as this. For a female, considering the maximum size observed, the maximum longevity estimated is 18 months. Average maximum longevity (pooled data) was estimated at 20 months.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Mortality
</title>
         <p>
The instantaneous rate of total mortality was 0.181 
month-1
(95% confidence limit, 
0.155
– 0.206
), which is equivalent to 2.17 ± 0.30 
year-1
. The regression fitted was significant (F 
calc
= 239.81&gt; F 
crit. 0.05 1,11
= 4.84) (
Fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
The regression fitted to the compilation data was also significant (F 
calc
= 103.33&gt; F 
crit. 0.05 1,29
= 4.19), but the intercept was not different from zero (95 % confidence limits, -0.66 to 1.05, 
p
= 0.65). Therefore, a regression through the origin was fitted, which was also significant (F 
calc
= 105.90&gt; F 
crit. 0.05 1,30
= 4.17) (
Fig. 5
). Using this regression, the regression slope was 2.24 ± 0.22, and the estimate of Z for 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
was 2.89 ± 0.29 
year-1
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
</title>
         <p>
Maximum longevity was estimated at 3.5 years. At first, this estimate could be considered high as larger brachyurans living in the same estuary have lower maximum longevities (
<tp:taxon-name>
Neohelice granulata
(Dana, 1851)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 2 years, maximum CW 38 and 
27.2 mm
for males and females); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Callinectes sapidus
Rathbun, 1896
</tp:taxon-name>
, 3 years, maximum CW 136.30 and 
132.70 mm
for males and females) (

; 

).The average lifespan of brachyurans was estimated at 5.6 years, with a general trend of the largest species having the longest life spans, while the smallest species have lifespans between one and two years (

), which suggests 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
has indeed a longer maximum longevity than expected.
</p>
         <p>
While the estimate of maximum longevity is related to the maximum size, this estimate is also quite dependent on the von Bertalanffy growth rate (
k
). This happens when the growth curve is estimated by size-based methods — which is the situation in most studies of crustacean populations in the wild — and so the von Bertalanffy 
k
shows how fast this growth curve will reach the asymptotic size. Therefore, any bias in von Bertalanffy 
k
estimation directly affects the estimate of maximum longevity.
</p>
         <p>
crit.0.05 1,11
</p>
         <p>
We have estimated a slower growth rate than what has been reported for 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
reared in laboratory conditions. For instance, 

found that it takes two months to reach 8.0 mm CW, at25 ºC. Based on the growth curve estimated in the present investigation, six months are needed for a crab to reach this size in the wild. In another study with animals kept in the laboratory (

), but with temperature regimes simulating natural conditions (highest temperature 22.8 ºC; lowest, 0.9 ºC), a 
5.5 mm
CW is reached at around three months, while in our population this size is reached in five months.
</p>
         <p>
As a size-based method was utilized to study individual growth, the maximum longevity estimate is related to the largest animal found. In the present investigation, the largest animal found measured 
17.9 mm
CW, and the average CW of the1% largest animals was 16.50 ± 
0.18 mm
. Our approach was to use 99 % of the estimated asymptotic CW (16.92 × 0.99 = 
16.75 mm
) — proposed by 

— as the size for T 
max
estimation, as this figure should be somewhat similar to the 1 % largest animals caught, which was the case. Therefore, it seems plausible the use of this CW to estimate T 
max
.
</p>
         <p>
Considering the evolutionary theory of ageing, a high longevity could possibly be explained by low predation (

). A relationship between mortality rate and longevity has been shown elsewhere in a classic paper for teleosts (

). The total mortality of a population can be split into natural mortality processes, such as old age and diseases. Alien species can be resistant to local diseases, and spread them, as is the case for 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
and the white spot baculovirus (

), and therefore this alien species acts as a disease carrier, without being affected by them (

).
</p>
         <p>
Moreover, total mortality is related to extrinsic mortality, which is typically linked to predation. Fish species have been cited as the main predators of 

<tp:taxon-name>R. harrisii</tp:taxon-name>
,

such as catfish, eel and f lounder (

; 

; 

). The ichthyofauna of the estuarine region of Patos Lagoon has approximately 110 species (

), including estuarine resident catfish (
<tp:taxon-name>
Genidens genidens
(Cuvier, 1829))
</tp:taxon-name>
. Other catfish, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Netuma barba
Lacepède, 1803
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Netuma planifrons
Higuchi, Reis and Araújo, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
are anadromous species that migrate to the estuarine region to reproduce. The marine flounder 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paralichthys orbygnianus
Valenciennes, 1839
</tp:taxon-name>
spawns in the sea but has sub-adult life-cycle stages found in these estuarine regions. Anguiliforms (eels) are occasional visitors to the estuarine region. Lastly, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Micropogonias furnieri
Desmarest, 1823
</tp:taxon-name>
is a very abundant marine species that uses estuarine waters as a nursery ground.
</p>
         <p>
There are no reports of natural predators for 

<tp:taxon-name>R. harrisii</tp:taxon-name>
.

For example, a study regarding the natural diet of the white croaker (
<tp:taxon-name>
M. furnieri
</tp:taxon-name>
), one of the most abundant fish species in the estuary, did not report the occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
in the stomach contents (

). While it can be said that 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. furnieri
</tp:taxon-name>
is not a crab eater, as tanaids are the main item in the stomach contents, it is important to point out that other studies have reported a high frequency of occurrence of decapods in stomach contents of this species, including 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cyrtograpsus angulatus
Dana, 1851
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. granulata
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. sapidus
</tp:taxon-name>
. At Chuí Stream — Brazil-Uruguay border — 16% of the occurrence was decapods in the gut contents of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. furnieri
(
Mendoza-Carranza and Vieira, 2008
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and around 40% of occurrence was 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cy. angulatus
</tp:taxon-name>
at 
Rocha
Lagoon, 
Uruguay
(

). Therefore, the absence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
in the stomach contents of 

<tp:taxon-name>M. furnieri</tp:taxon-name>
,

reported for the estuarine region of the Patos Lagoon (

; 

), is noteworthy.
</p>
         <p>
Among the catfish, 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. barba
</tp:taxon-name>
is one the species for which diet has been studied. Pereiopods of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Callinectes
Stimpson, 1860
</tp:taxon-name>
, and polychaetes were found in the stomach contents of juveniles and it is reported that the diet of adults is composed of molluscs and polychaetes (Araujo, 1984, 
op. cit.
in 

). The swimming crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. sapidus
</tp:taxon-name>
is a very abundant brachyuran which uses estuarine regions as nursery grounds. Studies on the natural diet of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. sapidus
</tp:taxon-name>
did not mention 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Therefore, it seems plausible to assume that 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
is under a low predation impact and this would explain the high longevity found, as this species has been caught in the estuarine region since 1982 and no reports of its presence in the diet of fish or crabs are published. While we have to acknowledge it does not provide irrefutable proof of a low predation impact, this hypothesis cannot be ruled out.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
is an established species in the estuarine region of the Patos Lagoon. Another study in the Patos Lagoon (

) reported a larger maximum size for males (
20.4 mm
) and a smaller maximum size for females (
12.7 mm
) than those observed in our study. For marine and estuarine invertebrates it has been suggested that invasions are related to an increase in body size (

). For 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
in the native distribution range (
i.e.
, Cheasapeake Bay, 
USA
), the maximum size of males and females is 
21.3 mm
and 
16 mm
, respectively (

). European non-native populations show larger sizes for males (
26.1 mm
) and females (19.0 mm) (

). Sizes of 
22.9 mm
(males) and 
19.8 mm
(females) were reported in Polish estuarine regions (

). Such a predicted increase in body size has not been observed in Patos Lagoon populations. The reasons why this suggested pattern was not observed are not understood, but it is important to discuss some reasoning.
</p>
         <p>

proposed two biological explanations for this increase in body size in invasive species. One is that resource increases in the new environment lead to a faster growth and therefore larger size. The second is that the absence of natural enemies (
e.g
, predators or parasites) results in larger body sizes. Here we argue against both explanations. It has been previously shown (

) that faster growth rates are typically related (intra and interspecifically) to smaller maximum sizes, not larger. Regarding the second possibility, another interpretation is that the absence of natural enemies could ease the ‘need’ for faster growth, as animals will not be under pressure to grow fast to reach sexual maturity (

). In this case, a low natural mortality could be related to a slower growth rate.
</p>
         <p>
Natural mortality is difficult to observe in populations in the wild, and in the absence of age information it is hard to estimate it (

; 

). In an attempt to circumvent this, several empirical relationships have been proposed (reviewed in 

). However, a difficulty is that these relationships have not been based on data from crustaceans, and most of them are based on teleosts.
</p>
         <p>
For deep-water brachyurans from the Mediterranean, one study (

) has reported a data compilation of von Bertalanffy growth parameters, but no information regarding Z is found. Another compilation (

) reports data for temperate deep-water crabs, in which the attempt to fit Hoenig’s relationship (

) to crab data yields a determination coefficient of 0.30, leading to the conclusion that “a meaningful relationship between M estimates and maximum ages is difficult to be established” (

).
</p>
         <p>
Considering 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
is not subject to fishery, the total mortality found (Z = 2.17 
year-1
) can be considered an estimate of the natural mortality. In the present investigation a promising significant relationship was found between estimates of Z and von Bertalanffy’s 
k
. We are not aware of any similar relationship — for estuarine-coastal brachyurans — in the available literature. The application of this relationship resulted in a predicted instantaneous total mortality (Z = 2.89 
year-1
) which is 25 % higher than that found in the catch-curve analysis. However, considering the upper confidence limit of the catch-curve estimate (2.17 + 0.30 = 2.47), and the lower confidence limit of this estimate (2.89 - 0.29 = 2.60), the estimates are different by only 5 %. Therefore, in light of the information published in the literature, the instantaneous total mortality estimated by size-converted catch curve can be considered quite robust.
</p>
         <p>
A weakness of the study is that no estimation of growth and mortality has been done for the sexes separately. In fact, providing enough animals are caught monthly for a modal progression analysis, it is better to estimate growth curves separately, as differences in size at sexual maturity could affect growth rates. For example, females of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. sapidus
</tp:taxon-name>
were observed to stop growing after maturation (

). However, we have not been able to analyze the sexes separately, as the small sample sizes did not permit it. While aware of these limitations, it is important to note that we found no indication in the literature of possible differences in growth rate or mortality between sexes. In fact, a comprehensive study on 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

) has pointed out that no differences in post-moult body growth were seen between the sexes.
</p>
         <p>
The growth and mortality parameters estimated in the present investigation have important consequences for the understanding of the population dynamics of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
in the estuarine region of the Patos Lagoon. Considering that this species has been found in this region for at least 30 years, this first account of growth and mortality of a population of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. harrisii
</tp:taxon-name>
is important to provide a starting point to assess differences between populations found around this estuarine region; as well as a reference point to study new populations which may be found in the future in other estuarine regions of the South American coastline.
</p>
         <p>
In short, the present investigation has shown, for the first time, the growth curve for an invasive population of 

<tp:taxon-name>R. harrisii</tp:taxon-name>
.

Maximum longevity was estimated at 3.5 years, and from this it is suggested that this species is subject to weak natural predation. The instantaneous mortality rate estimated fits an empirical relationship found for estuarine and coastal brachyurans very well.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
</title>
         <p>DSR and DBF would like to thank Dr. M.A. Rodrigues and Dr. R.A. Barutot for their useful comments on this manuscript. Two anonymous reviewers and the editors improved the English for this paper, which is greatly appreciated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Beverton, R.J.H.
and 
Holt, S.J.
1959
. 
A review of the lifespans and mortality rates of fishes in nature, and their relation to growth and other physiological characteristics
.p. 
142–179
.In: 
C.E.W. Wolstenholme
and 
M.O’Connor
(eds), 
Ciba Foundation Colloquia on Ageing
. 
London, J. and A. Churchill Ltd
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Boyle, J.R.T.
; 
Keith, D.
and 
Pfau, R.
2010
. 

Occurrence, reproduction, and population genetics of the estuarine mud crab, 
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
(Gould) (Decapoda, Panopidae) in Texas freshwater reservoirs

. 

Crustaceana

, 
83
: 
493–505
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Brockerhoff, A.
and 
McLay, C.
2011
. 
Human-Mediated Spread of Alien Crabs
. p. 
27–106
. In: 
B.S. Galil
; 
P.F. Clark
and 
J.T. Carlton
(eds), 
In the Wrong Place - Alien Marine Crustaceans: Distribution, Biology and Impacts
. 
Dordrecht, Springer
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Calliari, L.J.
; 
Garcia, C.A.E.
; 
Niencheski, L.F.
; 
Baumgarten, M.G.
; 
Costa, C.S.B.
; 
Seeliger, U.
; 
Abreu, P.C.
; 
Odebrecht, C.
; 
Montú, M.
; 
Duarte, A.K.
; 
Gloeden, I.M.
; 
Bemvenuti, C.E.
; 
Santos, E.A.
; 
Bianchini, A.
; 
Sinque, C.
; 
Muelbert, J.H.
; 
Vieira, J.P.
; 
Castello, J.P.
; 
Vooren, C.M.
and 
Pinedo, M.C.
1997
. 
Environment and Biota of the Patos Lagoon Estuary
. p. 
13–64
. In: 
U. Seelinger
; 
C. Odebrecht
and 
J.P. Castelo
(eds), 
Subtropical Convergence Environments. The Coast and Sea in the Southwestern Atlantic
. 
Berlin, Heidelberg, Springer
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Company, J.B.
and 
Sardà, F.
2000
. 
Growth parameters of deep-water decapod crustaceans in the Northwestern Mediterranean Sea: a comparative approach
. 

Marine Biology

, 
136
: 
79–90
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Costa, T.
and 
Soares-Gomes, A.
2011
. 

Population dynamics and secondary production of 
Uca rapax
(Brachyura: Ocypodidae) in a tropical coastal lagoon, southeast Brazil

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
31
: 
66–74
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Czerniejewski, P.
2009
. 

Some aspects of population biology of the mud crab, 
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
(Gould, 1841) in the Odra estuary, Poland

. 

International Journal of Oceanological and Hydrobiological Studies

, 
38
: 
49–62
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Diele, K.
and 

Koch, 

V. 
2010


. 

Growth and mortality of the exploited mangrove crab 
Ucides cordatus
(Ucididae) in N-Brazil

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 
395
: 
171–180
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
D’Incao, F.
and 
Fonseca, D.B.
2000
. 
Performance of the von Bertalanffy growth curve in penaeid shrimps: a critical approach
. p. 
733–737
. In: 
J.C. von Vaupel Klein
and 
F.R. Schram
(eds), 
The Biodiversity Crisis and Crustacea: Proceedings of the Fourth International Crustacean Congress
. 
Rotterdam, A.A. Balkema
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
D’Incao, F.
and 
Martins, S.T.S.
1998
. 

Occurrence of 
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
(Gould, 1841) in the Southern Coast of Brazil (Decapoda, Xanthidae)

. 

Nauplius

, 
6
: 
191–194
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
D’Incao, F.
; 
Ruffino, M.L.
; 
Silva, K.G.
; 
Braga, A.C.
and 
Marques, L.H.C.
1993
. 

Crescimento de 
Chasmagnathus granulata
Dana, 1851, em um marisma do estuário da Lagoa dos Patos, RS (Decapoda, Grapsidae)

. 

Revista Brasileira de Biologia

, 
53
: 
637–643
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Figueiredo, G.M.
and 
Vieira, J.P.
2005
. 

Diel feeding, daily food consumption and the predatory impact of whitemouth croaker (
Micropogonias furnieri
) in an estuarine environment

. 

Marine Ecology

, 
26
: 
130–139
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fischer, S.
and 
Wolff, M.
2006
. 

Fisheries assessment of 
Callinectes arcuatus
(Brachyura, Portunidae) in the Gulf of Nicoya, Costa Rica

. 

Fisheries Research

, 
77
: 
301–311
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fowler, A.E.
; 
Forsström, T.
; 
von Numers, M.
and 
Vesakoski, O.
2013
. 

The North American mud crab 
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
(Gould, 1841) in newly colonized Northern Baltic Sea: distribution and ecology

. 

Aquatic Invasion

, 
8
: 
89–96
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gonçalves, G.R.L.
; 
Miazaki, L.F.
; 
Bolla Junior, E.A.
; 
Grabowski, R.C.
; 
Costa, R.C. da
and 
Castilho, A.L.
2020
. 

Growth and longevity of the spider crab 
Libinia ferreirae
(Majoidea, Epialtidae)

. 

Nauplius

, 
28
: e 
2020003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grosholz, E.D.
and 
Ruiz, G.M.
2003
. 
Biological invasions drive size increases in marine and estuarine invertebrates
. 

Ecology Letters

, 
6
: 
700–705
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hamid, A.
and 
Wardiatno, Y.
2015
. 

Population dynamics of the blue swimming crab (
Portunus pelagicus
Linnaeus, 1758) in Lasongko Bay, Central Buton, Indonesia

. 

Aquaculture, Aquarium, Conservation
&amp; 
Legislation

, 
8
: 
729–739
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hänfling, B.
; 
Edwards, F.
and 
Gherardi, F.
2011
. 
Invasive alien Crustacea: dispersal, establishment, impact and control
. 

BioControl

, 
56
: 
573–595
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hayes, K.R.
and 
Sliwa, C.
2003
. 
Identifying potential marine pests—a deductive approach applied to Australia
. 

Marine Pollution Bulletin

, 
46
: 
91–98
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hilborn, R.
and 
Walters, C.J.
1992
. 
Analysis of body and growth data
. p. 
410–433
. In: 
R. Hilborn
and 
C.J. Walters
(eds), 
Quantitative Fisheries Stock Assessment: Choice, Dynamics &amp; Uncertainty
. 
London, Chapman &amp; Hall
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hoenig, J.M.
1983
. 
Empirical use of longevity data to estimate mortality rates
. 

Fishery Bulletin

, 
82
: 
898–903
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hulme, P.E.
2014
. 
Invasive species challenge the global response to emerging diseases
. 

Trends in Parasitology

, 
30
: 
267–270
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kapusta, S.C.
and 
Bemvenuti, C.E.
1998
. 

Atividade nictemeral de alimentação de juvenis de 
Callinectes sapidus
Rathbun, 1895 (Decapoda: Portunidae) numa pradaria de 
Ruppia maritima
L. e num plano não vegetado, numa enseada estuarina da Lagoa dos Patos, R. S., Brasil

. 

Nauplius

, 
6
: 
41–52
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kenchington, T.J.
2013
. 
Natural mortality estimators for information-limited fisheries
. 

Fish and Fisheries

, 
15
: 
533–562
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Keunecke, K.A.
; 
D’Incao, F.
and 
Fonseca, D.B.
2007
. 

Growth and mortality of 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Crustacea: Calappidae) in south-western Brazil

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
87
: 
885–891
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Keunecke, K.A.
; D 
Incao, F.
; 
Moreira, F.N.
; 
Silva Jr, D.R.
and 
Verani, J.R.
2008
. 

Age and growth of 
Callinectes danae
and 
C. ornatus
(Crustacea, Decapoda) in Guanabara Bay, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

. 

Iheringia, Série Zoologia

, 
98
: 
231–235
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kirkwood, T.B.
and 
Austad, S.N.
2000
. 
Why do we age?

Nature

, 
408
: 
233
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Klaoudatos, D.S.
; 
Conides, A.J.
; 
Anastasopoulou, A.
and 
Dulčić, J.
2013
. 

Age, growth, mortality and sex ratio of the inshore population of the edible crab, 
Cancer pagurus
(Linnaeus 1758) in South Wales (UK)

. 

Journal of Applied Ichthyology

, 
29
: 
579–586
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Koch, V.
; 
Wolff, M.
and 
Diele, K.
2005
. 

Comparative population dynamics of four fiddler crabs (Ocypodidae, genus 
Uca
) from a North Brazilian mangrove ecosystem

. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series

, 
291
: 
177–188
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kujawa, S.
1965
. 

Some remarks on the biology of the crab 
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
subsp. 
tridentatus
(Maitland)

. 

Annals Biology Copenhagen

, 
20
: 
103–104
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lee, H.
and 
Hsu, C.
2003
. 

Population biology of the swimming crab 
Portunus sanguinolentus
in the waters off northern Taiwan

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
23
: 
691–699
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Melo, G.A.S.
1999
. 
Manual de identificação dos Crustacea Decapoda do litoral brasileiro: Anomura, Thalassinidea, Palinuridea e Astacidea
. 
São Paulo, FAPESP/Plêiade
, 
551p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mendoza-Carranza, M.
and 
Vieira, J.
2008
. 

Whitemouth croaker 
Micropogonias furnieri
(Desmarest, 1823) feeding strategies across four southern Brazilian estuaries

. 

Aquatic Ecology

, 
42
: 
83–93
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Miazaki, L.F.
; 
Simões, S.M.
; 
Castilho, A.L.
and 
Costa, R.C.
2019
. 

Population dynamics of the crab 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst, 1785) (Decapoda, Aethridae) on the southern coast of São Paulo state, Brazil

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
99
: 
867–878
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mokhtari, M.
; 
Savari, A.
; 
Rezai, H.
; 
Kochanian, P.
and 
Bitaab, A.
2008
. 

Population ecology of fiddler crab, 
Uca lactea annulipes
(Decapoda:Ocypodidae) in Sirik mangrove estuary, Iran

. 

Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Scie
nce

, 
76
: 
273–281
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morgan, S.G.
; 
Goy, J.W.
and 
Costlow, J.D.
1983
. 

Multiple ovipositions from single matings in the Mud Crab 
Rhithropanopeus harrisii

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
3
: 
542–547
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oliveira, A.R.D.
; 
Pinto, T.K.D.O.
; 
Santos, D.P.D.
and 
D’Incao, F.
2006
. 

Dieta natural do siri-azul 
Callinectes sapidus
(Decapoda, Portunidae) na região estuarina da Lagoa dos Patos, Rio Grande, Rio Grande do Sul, Brasil

. 

Iheringia, Série Zoologia

, 
96
: 
305–313
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Olsson, D.
2013
. 

Temporal feeding habits of the whitemouth croaker 
Micropogonias furnieri
in a shallow coastal lagoon (southwestern Atlantic Ocean, Uruguay)

. 

Ciencias Marinas

, 
39
: 
265–276
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pauly, D.
1990
. 
Length-converted catch curves and the seasonal growth of fishes
. 

Fishbyte

, 
8
: 
33–38
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Roche, D.G.
; 
Torchin, M.E.
; 
Leung, B.
and 
Binning, S.A.
2009
. 

Localized invasion of the North American Harris mud crab, 
Rhithropanopeus harrisii

, in 
the Panama Canal: implications for eradication and spread
. 

Biological Invasions

, 
11
: 
983–993
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodrigues, M.A.
and 
D’Incao, F.
2008
. 

Comparação do crescimento entre 
Callinectes sapidus
(Crustacea, Decapoda, Portunidae) coletados em campo e mantidos em condições contoladas

. 

Iheringia, Série Zoologia

, 
98
: 
372–378
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodrigues, M.A.
and 
D’Incao, F.
2015
. 

Abundância e relações biométricas do caranguejo invasor 
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
(Crustacea, Decapoda) no estuário da Lagoa dos Patos, Rio Grande do Sul, Brasil

. 

Boletim do Museu Biologia Mello Leitão

, 
37
: 
219–232
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodríguez, G.
and 
Suárez, H.
2001
. 
Anthropogenic dispersal of decapod crustaceans in aquatic environments
. 

Interciencia

, 
26
: 
282–288
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sakai, A.K.
; 
Allendorf, F.W.
; 
Holt, J.S.
; 
Lodge, D.M.
; 
Molofsky, J.
; 
With, K.A.
; 
Baughman, S.
; 
Cabin, R.J.
; 
Cohen, J.E.
; 
Ellstrand, N.C.
; 
McCauley, D.E.
; 
O’Neil, P.
; 
Parker, I.M.
; 
Thompson, J.N.
and 
Weller, S.G.
2001
. 
The Population Biology of Invasive Species
. 

Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics

, 
32
: 
305– 332
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sara, L.
2011
. 

Study on the size structure and population parameters of mud crab 
Scylla serrata
in Lawele bay, Southeast Sulawesi, Indonesia

. 

Journal of Coastal Development

, 
13
: 
133–147
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sara, L.
; 
Muskita, W.H.
and 
Astuti, O.
2017
. 

Some population parameters of blue swimming crab (
Portunus pelagicus
) in southeast Sulawesi waters, Indonesia

. 

Aquaculture, Aquarium, Conservation
&amp; 
Legislation

, 
10
: 
587–601
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Seeliger, U.
and 
Odebrecht, C.
1997
. 
Introduction and overview
. p. 
1–3
. In: 
U. Seelinger
; 
C. Odebrecht
and 
J.P. Castelo
(eds), 
Subtropical Convergence Environments.The Coast and Sea in the Southwestern Atlantic
. 
Berlin, Heidelberg, Springer
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Simberloff, D.
; 
Martin, J-L.
; 
Genovesi, P.
; 
Maris, V.
; 
Wardle, D.A.
; 
Aronson, J.
; 
Courchamp, F.
; 
Galil, B.
; 
García-Berthou, E.
; 
Pascal, M.
; 
Pyšek, P.
; 
Sousa, R.
; 
Tabacchi, E.
and 
Vilà, M.
2013
. 
Impacts of biological invasions: what’s what and the way forward
. 

Trends in Ecology
&amp; 
Evolution

, 
28
: 
58–66
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smith, S.G.
and 
Chang, E.S.
2007
. 
Molting and growth
. p. 
197– 254
. In: 
V.S. Kennedy
and 
L.E. Cronin
(eds), 

The Blue Crab: 
Callinectes sapidus

. 
College Park, Maryland Sea Grant College, University of Maryland
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stearns, S.C.
1992
. 
The Evolution of Life Histories
. 
Oxford, Oxford University Press
, 
249p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sukumaran, K.K.
and 
Neelakantan, B.
1996
. 

Mortality and stock assessment of two marine portunid crabs, 
Portunus
(
Portunus
) 
sanguinolentus
(Herbst) and 
Portunus
(
Portunus
) 
pelagicus
(Linnaeus) along the southwest coast of India

. 

Indian Journal of Fisheries

, 
43
: 
225–240
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tavares, M.
2011
. 
Alien decapod crustaceans in the Southwestern Atlantic Ocean
. p. 
251–268
. In: 
B.S. Galil
; 
P.F. Clark
and 
J.T. Carlton
(eds), 
In the Wrong Place - Alien Marine Crustaceans: Distribution, Biology and Impacts
. 
Dordrecht, Springer
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Turoboyski, K.
1973
. 

Biology and ecology of the crab 
Rhithropanopeus harrisii
ssp. 
tridentatus

. 

Marine Biology

, 
23
: 
303–313
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vasconcelos, P.P.L.
and 
da Silva Piva, R.
2007
. 
A importância do Mercosul na economia rio-grandina através da movimentação de cargas pelo Porto do Rio Grande
. 

SINERGIA-Revista do Instituto de Ciências Econômicas, Administrativas e Contábeis
11.1

: 
49–56
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
van der Velde, G.
; 
Nagelkerken, I.
; 
Rajagopal, S.
and 
de Vaate, A.B.
2002
. 
Invasions by Alien Species in Inland Freshwater Bodies in Western Europe:The Rhine Delta
.p. 
360–372
.In: 
E. Leppäkoski
; 
S. Gollasch
and 
S. Olenin
(eds), 
Invasive Aquatic Species of Europe. Distribution, Impacts and Management
. 
Dordrecht, Springer
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vetter, E.F.
1988
. 
Estimation of natural mortality in fish stocks: A review
. 

Fisheries Bulletin

, 
86
: 
25–43
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vidhya, V.
; 
Jawahar, P.
; 
Karuppasamy, K.
and 
Srinivasan, A.
2018
. 

Growth and mortality characteristics of 
Charybdis natator
(Herbst, 1794) (Crustacea: Brachyura: Portunidae) along Gulf of Mannar, Southeast coast of India

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of India

, 
60
: 
48–52
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vogt, G.
2019
. 
A compilation of longevity data in decapod crustaceans
. 

Nauplius

, 
27
: e 
2019011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Williams, A.B.
1984
. 
Shrimps, lobsters, and crabs of the Atlantic coast of the Eastern United States, Maine to Florida
. 
Washington DC, Smithsonian Institution
, 
550p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zheng, J.
2005
. 
A review of natural mortality estimation for crab stocks: data-limited for every stock?
p. 
595–612
. In: 
G.H. Kruse
; 
V.F. Gallucci
; 
D.E. Hay
; 
R.I. Perry
; 
R.M. Peterman
; 
T.C. Shirley
; 
P.D. Spencer
; 
B. Wilson
and 
D. Woodby
(eds), 
Fisheries Assessment and Management in Data-Limited Situations
. 
Fairbanks, Alaska Sea Grant, University of Alaska
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
