<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nauplius</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2358-2936e2020003</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Growth and longevity of the spider crab Libinia ferreirae (Majoidea, Epialtidae)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>17</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
Brito Capello, 1871
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Epialtus brasiliensis
(Dana 1852)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lychnorhiza lucerna,
(Haeckel, 1880) (Scyphomedusa)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L.ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
Brito Capello, 1871
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
Brito Capello, 1871
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
Brito Capello, 1871
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>L. ferreirae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia dubia
H. Milne Edwards, 1834
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia emarginata
Leach, 1815
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chionoecetes opilio
(O. Fabricius, 1788)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Maja squinado
(Herbst,1788)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. spinosa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. opilio
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Callinectes sapidus
Rathbun, 1896
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. squinado
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
ORIGINAL
ARTICLE
</p>
         <p>

Growth and longevity of the spider crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae</tp:taxon-name>
)

</p>
         <p>
Geslaine Rafaela Lemos Gonçalves
1
B

orcid.org/0000-0001-7443-6913
</p>
         <p>
Lizandra Fernandes Miazaki
3
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-1678-3228
</p>
         <p>
Eduardo Antonio Bolla Junior
1,2
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-0493-5095
</p>
         <p>
Raphael Cezar Grabowski
1
B

orcid.org/0000-0001-9414-8310
</p>
         <p>
Rogério Caetano da Costa
3
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-1342-7340
</p>
         <p>
Antonio Leão Castilho
1
B

orcid.org/0000-0003-0001-9054
</p>
         <p>
1

Group of 
Studies on Crustacean Biology

, Ecology and Culture (NEBECC), Zoology Department, 

Institute of 
Bioscience of Botucatu

, 
São Paulo State

University. 18618- 970, Botucatu, 
São Paulo
, 
Brazil

.

</p>
         <p>
2

Federal Institute of 
São Paulo
, 

Avaré campus. 18707-150, Avaré, 
São Paulo
Brazil

.

</p>
         <p>
3
Laboratory of Biology
and 
Ecology of Marine
and Freshwater Shrimps (LABCAM), Biological Science Department, 

Faculty of 
Sciences of Bauru

, 
São Paulo State

University. 17033-360, Bauru, 
São Paulo
Brazil

.

</p>
         <p>
ZOOBANK
: http://zoobank.org/ 

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 

0CE2 
C0A
8-001A-4269- B7C2 
-
8AFD930B8121

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
</title>
         <p>
We estimated the growth parameters of the spider crab, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
(age, asymptotic size and growth rate) using the von Bertalanffy growth equation model. We obtained nine cohorts for female carapace asymptotic width (CW 
∞
) = 
64.32 mm
, growth coefficient (
day-1
) (k) = 
0.0027 e
t 
0
= 0.77 days) and seven for males (CW 
∞
= 
81.93 mm
, k= 
0.0021 e
t 
0
= 0.49 days). The longevity for males was higher than that for females, estimated 2,156 days (5.91 years) and 1,706 days (4.68 years), respectively.The growth curves for males and females differed (F = 
34.67 e
p &lt;0.001). Males reached gonadal maturity before morphometric maturity and occurred at 8.8 and 16.6 months of life, respectively. Females reach gonad and morphometric maturity synchronously and this was estimated to occur at about 11.42 months of life. These crabs invest a great amount of energy in growth during a brief period of their development until reaching the terminal moult. This growth strategy would bring less wear to the organism and consequently a greater longevity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
KEYWORDS
</title>
         <p>
Growth, von Bertalanffy, puberty moult, age, symbiotic relationship
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
Due to their hard exoskeleton, crustacean growth is a discontinuous process occurring incrementally. Individuals grow with the production of a new exoskeleton, occurring at each moult (

). This growth is defined as: determinate, where some species enter terminal anecdysis and invest all their energy in reproduction (individuals grow to a certain size and no longer grow for the rest of their lives); and indeterminate growth for the majority, who continue to invest energy in moulting as well as in reproduction (growth occurs during all their life) (

).
</p>
         <p>
In the superfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
, all individuals undergo several moults before the pre-puberty moult for juvenile growth (that may coincide with the onset of gonadal maturity)and terminal for the ultimate moult, preceding the onset of the adult stage. The adult stage is reached after the terminal moult, which marks both gonadal maturity and morphological maturity, 
i.e.
, individuals of both sexes present functional reproductive cells and well-defined secondary sexual morphological characters (

; 

). However, males of some 
<tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
species can reach gonadal maturity during pre-pubertal moulting (the second to last moult before terminal moulting), these crabs have gonad maturity but no morphometric maturity. This may allow opportunistic copulation before going through the last moult (terminal moult and end of growth), where individuals have maturity (gonadal and morphometric), and are able to transfer sperm and guard females (

; 

). In this way, individuals who undergo early gonadal maturity have an altered reproductive role within the species population dynamics. This may lead to selection for an extended pre-puberty intermoult stage (

; 

). The spider crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
Brito Capello, 1871
</tp:taxon-name>
is included in this superfamily, the females of these species reach gonadal and morphometric maturity simultaneously; unlike males, who reach gonadal maturity before morphometric maturity (

).
</p>
         <p>
Because of this growth pattern, spider crabs do not exhibit continuous growth during their lifespan, 
i.e.
, when crabs reach maturity (gonadal, morphometric or functional), they do not present apparent growth, as seen in other brachyurans (

). Whilst investigating gonad development, 

did not observe the production of a new carapace in 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
when removing the calcified carapace from adult crabs, as seen in the study of 

with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epialtus brasiliensis
(Dana 1852)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Thus, adult crab size is set by the number of pre-pubertal moults and depends on factors that may influence its life cycle, such as food availability, survival and gonadal and morphometric maturation (

).
</p>
         <p>
Studies concerning the growth and age of the species are essential to understanding their basic biology, including how fast they grow and how long they can live. Such information is necessary for sustainable fishery management, which aims to preserve animal populations that are accidentally exploited (

). Crustacean age is considered one of the most important biological variables; it enables calculations of growth, mortality rates, productivity and provides valuable information about population dynamics and population size (

). Using equations, one can estimate the growth of an organism, defined by measurements of any structure that may vary in size over time. The 

equation is the most useful mathematical equation that estimates growth parameters, while also considering individual biological processes.
</p>
         <p>
To date, there have been no studies that use the von Bertalanffy model to determine age for 
<tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
crabs. Generally, such studies are carried out using laboratory breeding techniques (

; 

; 

), which may include making observations on the tissues and exoskeleton (

), measuring the proportion of radionucleotide activity of 
228
Th/ 
228
Ra in the exoskeleton (

), or analysing the condition and integrity of the carapace through the degradation of the cheliped or dactyl (

). The lack of studies focusing on growth and age may be associated with the difficulty in fitting growth models, arising from the occurrence of a terminal moult.
</p>
         <p>
The von Bertalanffy growth model is the most commonly used model in studies on crustacean growth; however, this model is normally used to describe the growth during the benthic phase, limiting its applicability to the complete life history of some species (

). Petriella and Boshi (1997) proposed that this model can be adjusted for species that have fast growth, such as Penaeoidea and Sergestoidea shrimps.
</p>
         <p>
The distribution of the spider crab, 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
is restricted to the western Atlantic, from 
Costa Rica
to 
Uruguay
, and inhabits depths up to 
35 m
(

; 

). This species also maintains a symbiotic relationship with the jellyfish, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lychnorhiza lucerna,
(Haeckel, 1880) (Scyphomedusa)
</tp:taxon-name>
. During their larval and juvenile stages, the crabs grow together with the medusa and use the host for protection, transportation and as a food source. When they reach the adult stage, they live in the benthos associated with many organisms attached to their carapace such as anemones, polychaetes, algae among others(

). Thus, these crabs can move on the sea bed camouflaged (Nogueira Jr. and Haddad, 2005; 

). This symbiotic behavior may result in increased survival and individual longevity.
</p>
         <p>
To date, studies on this spider crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
have addressed their larval development (

; 

), symbiotic relationships (Nogueira Jr. and Haddad, 2005; 

; 

; 

), morphology and maturity (

; 

) and distribution (

). However, little is known about the growth of this species. Based on this knowledge, this study aims to estimate the growth parameters, including age (days), asymptotic size, and growth rate for both sexes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
in the Cananéia region, 
São Paulo State
, on the southeastern coast of 
Brazil
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
MATERIAL
AND
METHODS
</title>
         <p>
Biological sampling
</p>
         <p>

Sampling was carried out monthly from 

July 2012

to 

May 2014

at seven pre-established sampling stations, using a shrimp-fishing boat outfitted with double-rig nets. 
Each
trawl lasted for 30 minutes in the 
Estuarine-Lagoon System of Cananéia-Iguape
(≈ 
25º05’S
; ≈ 
47º53’O
) and the adjacent oceanic area

.
</p>
         <p>
Crabswereidentifiedaccordingtothemorphological features noted in the studies carried out by 

and 

. Specimens were sexed based on the shape of the abdomen (an elongated shape for males and an oval shape for females) and the number of pleopods (two pairs of pleopods for males and four pairs for females) (

; 

). Afterwards, the carapace width (CW; the greatest distance between the lateral body edges, disregarding thorns and∕ or tubercles) was measured using a digital calliper (to the nearest 
0.01 mm
) and a stereomicroscope (Zeiss 
®
Stemi SV6) outfitted with an image capturing system (Zeiss 
®
Stemi 2000-C). To analyse animal size data, 95%confidence intervals were obtained using the bootstrap interaction method (R studio version 1.0.153).
</p>
         <p>
Individual growth
</p>
         <p>
We analysed the growth parameters for 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
based on the similarity of the estimated parameters found in 

; 

),to the size and maturity of crabs in real ecosystems. Specimens with CW smaller than 
4 mm
were sexually undifferentiated and were not included in the size class distribution. Growth analyses were performed based on the 

growth model, following the methodology adopted by 

. The modal values were determined in each CW frequency distribution (size classes of 
2 mm
) using the program PeakFit (Automatic Peak Fitting Detection and Fitting, Method I-Residual, no Data Smoothing). The obtained numerical peak values were plotted in a scatter plot (time 
versus
age), from which we analysed the cohorts’ growth rhythm according to each growth model, namely:
</p>
         <p>

model: CW 
t
= CW 
∞
[1 − 
e− k(t−t0
)]; where, for this model: CW 
t
= individual’s carapace width at age 
t
; 
CW
∞
= carapace asymptotic width; 
k
= growth coefficient (
day-1
); t 
0
= theoretical age at size zero.
</p>
         <p>
ThegrowthparametersCW 
∞
,k and t 
0
wereestimated using the Solver tool, available in Microsoft Excel® (in the Microsoft Office® software pack), minimizing the sum of the squared residuals. The obtained modal progression was evaluated based on the similarity observed between the estimated parameters and the sampled biological data, considering its biological coherence. We selected growth curves with estimated asymptotic length values that were similar to the average CW recorded for post-pubertal adults of both sexes (for more details, see 

). Next, we standardized the onset of each curve so that it began at age 0 (von Bertalanffy model). Using the software TableCurve®2d v.5.01 (Systat®), we obtained an average growth curve for each sex, with a 95% confidence interval for mean and prediction interval for each curve. Statistically significant differences between male and female growth curves were tested using an F-test at the p = 0.05 level significance (

).
</p>
         <p>
Age and longevity
</p>
         <p>
Longevity was estimated by inverse 

</p>
         <p>(1938) equation, with modifications suggested by</p>
         <p>

, 
t
0
= 0 and CW/CW∞ = 0.99, while the longevity equation was t = (
t
0
− (1/k) Ln (1 −CW 
t
/CW 
∞
)) (Miaziki 
et al.
, 2019).
</p>
         <p>The age in months when 50% of the males and</p>
         <p>
females of 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
became sexually mature (gonadal
</p>
         <p>and morphometrically)was calculated using the inverse</p>
         <p>
of the growth equation (t = (
t
0
− (1/k) Ln (1 −CW 
t
/ CW 
∞
)) (King, 1995), based on the maturity sizes determined by 

: for males,
</p>
         <p>
35 and 
53 mm
CW for gonad and morphometric
</p>
         <p>
maturity respectively, while for females, 
38 mm
CW
</p>
         <p>
for both maturities.Males of this superfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>become gonadally mature before terminal moult, unlike</p>
         <p>females that reach gonadal maturity and morphometric</p>
         <p>
maturity at the terminal moult (

;
</p>
         <p>

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
RESULTS
</title>
         <p>
Growth and longevity
</p>
         <p>
A total of 

611 
<tp:taxon-name>
L.ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>

were analyzed(CW ranging from 
4.4 to 77.84 mm
). Among them, we identified 
110 immature
females (mean 24.57 ± 
11.01 mm
CW) and 264 mature females (49.09 ± 
5.32 mm
CW). For males, we found 93 (23.48 ± 
11.71 mm
CW) immature individuals and identified 144 (50.20± 
10.13 mm
CW)mature (gonadal and morphometric) individuals. The largest individuals captured measuring 71.64 and 
77.84 mm
CW for females and males, respectively. Our sample size was limited by low crab abundance, however, we used ecological parameters established by 

; 

),and the data was tested for their confidence limits. We have 95% confidence (bootstrap interactions: 100000) that the mean CW for female is somewhere between - 
0.37 mm
lower than for males up to 
4.72 mm
higher than for females.
</p>
         <p>
We identified nine cohorts for females (
Fig. 1
) and seven for males (
Fig. 2
). In most of the months sampled, occurrence of juvenile crabs was common for both sexes. In Sept/ 
Oct 2012
the recruitment increased for both sexes (
Fig. 1
and 
2
). For females, the accentuated peak of abundance occurred during the spring/summer 2012 and summer in Jan/2013 and 2014 (
Fig. 1
). Males were absent only in Mar/13 and Feb/14, and present in the remaining months with greatest abundance in similar periods to females (
Fig. 2
).
</p>
         <p>
Estimated parameters, based on the average growth curves, resulted in CW 
∞
= 
64.32 mm
, 
k
= 0.0027 and 
t
0
= 0.77 days for females and CW 
∞
= 
81.93 mm
, 
k
= 0.0021 and 
t
0
= 0.49 days for males (
Fig. 3
). Estimated age for female was 1.706 days (4.68 years), whereas, males it was 2.156 days (5.91 years).
</p>
         <p>
The growth curves obtained for females and males using the 

model were significantly different (
F
critic
= 2.71, 
F
calculated
= 34,67; 
df
= 87; 
P
&lt;0.001), supporting the notion that a single curve cannot be applied to explain the growth of both sexes.
</p>
         <p>Time taken, in days, to reach gonadal maturity was estimated approximately at 342.7 (11.42 months) and 264.6(8.8 months) for females and males, respectively. Time taken, in days, for males to reach morphometric maturity was 500.33 days (16.6 months). This parameter was not estimated for females, since gonadal and morphometric maturity occur concomitantly.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
</title>
         <p>
The equation of the 

growth model may have its limitations when applied to 
<tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
crabs, such as the crab 

<tp:taxon-name>L. ferreirae</tp:taxon-name>
,

because they have determinate growth. However, with the use of well-established parameters, adjustments can be made to provide accurate results. It is essential to understand the biology and ecology of the species, especially concerning its period of gonadal and morphometric maturity, since the 
<tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
crabs reach their maturity before ceasing growth (during the terminal moulting). This study was based on previous knowledge of reproductive maturity and ecology of 
<tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
studied by 

; 

),in the same region. It is important to use a representative sampling technique that shows the size distribution of crabs in the population, in order to accurately calculate carapace asymptotic width (CW∞). When considering the best growth coefficient (k), a broad literature search is required, especially considering closely related species or organisms in a similar environment. 

reinforce that it is difficult to determine precisely the growth of an individual from birth to death because of changes in their metabolism rates and in the environment in which they live.
</p>
         <p>
In this study, we observed the occurrence of individuals of varying age and size allowing us to determine growth and longevity for both sexes. The highest peaks of juvenile abundance occurred in Sept and Oct / 2012 for both sexes, and Jan / 2014 for females, showing that these crabs prefer spring and summer to breed. Increased temperature conditions accelerate growth; furthermore, these periods support greater food availability (phytoplankton and zooplankton). Thus, warmer temperatures are favorable for the survival of larval and juvenile phases. However, 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
demonstrates continuous reproduction with reproductive peaks in certain seasons as seen in 

.
</p>
         <p>
Juvenile 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
use symbiotic relationships as a camouflage strategy; this allows them to avoid predation and consequentially the loss of appendages or even death. When using jellyfishes while in the juvenile stage, these crabs are less vulnerable in the environment and cease to be part of the food web for countless other animals. Furthermore, as adults, they act as hosts to a wide range of epibiont organisms on their carapace, allowing them to live unnoticed in the environment through the use of this natural camouflage (Nogueira Jr.and Haddad, 2005; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Larger males are likely to have increased mating success and may also provide a protective function during or after copulation (

; 

). Additionally, 

, when studying 
<tp:taxon-name>
Libinia dubia
H. Milne Edwards, 1834
</tp:taxon-name>
, observed that males were larger than females, while for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Libinia emarginata
Leach, 1815
</tp:taxon-name>
, 

observed that males seemed to possess body sizes approximately 15% larger than those observed for females. However, males allocate more energy toward growth and toward developing secondary sexual characteristics (

), tending to take a longer time to reach their morphometric maturity in comparison to females, as shown by 

, with 
<tp:taxon-name>Majoidea</tp:taxon-name>
crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
. This holds true for 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
because they develop well-defined secondary sexual characteristics, such as large chelipeds (

), and take longer to reach the terminal moult.
</p>
         <p>
Large size may be beneficial in females, if they are able to accommodate a higher number of fertilized eggs on the ventral portion of their abdomen during reproduction (

; 

; 

). Females reach their gonadal/ morphometric maturity in the terminal moult; however, their ovarian maturation demands a large amount of energy; therefore, they divide their energy between growth and gonad maturation at the end of the juvenile instar (the penultimate instar before to the pubertal moult). Thus, the posterior moult increment may be strongly compromised (

) given that they preferably invest their energy in oogenesis and in embryo-related care (

).
</p>
         <p>
The different growth and age rate observed for both sexes are strongly influenced by their reproductive traits. Females, for instance, cease their growth when they reach the terminal moult (consequently their morphometric maturity) around 1 year, instead investing their energy in production, breeding and care of fertilized eggs. On the other hand, males may remain in the pre-puberty intermoult stage for a longer period, acting as adolescent males (
i.e.
, possessing mature gonads without mature morphometric features). As observed in this study, males reach gonad maturity before the females, by around 6 months. Many studies have shown that males are able to copulate in pre-puberty(adolescent males) and may thus stay in the pre-puberty intermoult for a long time before attaining the terminal moult; while copulating, they are as successful as they would be if they were morphometrically immature (

; 

; 

; 

). This behavior may explain why they take a longer time to reach morphometric maturity (terminal moult), around 5 months after the females. This is supported by our results whereby males were found to be older before reaching maturity.
</p>
         <p>

estimated the longevity for males of the snow crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chionoecetes opilio
(O. Fabricius, 1788)
</tp:taxon-name>
, found in cold regions, using the capture-recapture method. The authors analyzed the wear of the cheliped and dactyl, carapace conditions and natural changes that occurred along the specimens’ body; they estimated a species longevity of 7.7 years after the terminal moult. On the other hand, using radio-isotopic techniques to study this same species, Saint-Marie 
et al.
(1995) estimated the male longevity at 6 years after the terminal moult, while females would live 4–5 years after the terminal moult. However, 

justified their higher longevity based on the sampled area, given that it is maintained as an ecological preservation area. Also using radio-isotopic techniques, 

divided the longevity of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Maja squinado
(Herbst,1788)
</tp:taxon-name>
into two stages since they present a terminal moult (representing the end of the juvenile growth period, which may last for 2–3 years) and a reproductive stage (after their terminal moult), which may last for 5–6 years.
</p>
         <p>
According to our results, females of 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
reach the puberty moult in approximately 12 months, which is almost the same amount of time proposed for 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. spinosa
</tp:taxon-name>
to reach maturity, according to 

. For males, we determined that the puberty moult occurs at approximately 16 months, highlighting that when they reach the pre-puberty moult, males are already gonadally mature (

). 

, studying males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. opilio
</tp:taxon-name>
, determined that they have 11 life stages prior to their terminal moult. In this case, pre-puberty would occur in 5–6-year-old individuals, and such adolescent males could take up to 5 years to reach the adult stage. However, males reach gonadal maturity prior (in smaller sizes) to females, which provides them with a higher probability of experiencing opportunistic copulations (

; Sampdro 
et al
., 1999). 

state that the intermoult period increases with higher individual size.
</p>
         <p>
The longevity found in this study for 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
males and females was higher than the longevity found with the same estimation methods for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Callinectes sapidus
Rathbun, 1896
</tp:taxon-name>
(3.02 to 3.27 years for males and 3.16 to 3.24 years for females) by 

.This crab experiences reproduction and growth constantly, bringing a high metabolic expense to the individual which naturally shortens its life span. On the other hand, 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
has determined growth, investing energy to grow for a brief period, stops growing in the terminal moult, before allocating energy after this period for reproduction. 

, in a study of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. squinado
</tp:taxon-name>
crab based on radio-isotope techniques, divided the longevity of these individuals into two phases: young growth phase, which lasts 2–3 years, and a reproduction phase (after the change of puberty/terminal moult), which can last 5–6 years. These studies corroborate our results since males live longer than females and also because the longest life period occurs after the terminal moult. However, the different techniques used to estimate the growth and longevity of crustaceans may generate different results, especially when considering population genetics and their environment (

).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Libinia ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
completes its life cycle in the adjacent coastal area to the city of Cananéia, SP. However, this region faces an excessive shrimp-fishing effort, in which 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
is captured as bycatch in all of their developmental stages. When this happens, individuals generally die before being discarded back to the sea, where they are exposed to the same fishing pressure as the target species. The impact of fishing on these crabs can result in population imbalances, since these species take about a year or more to reach reproductive maturity.Thus, numerous crabs are caught in the juvenile phase without having the opportunity to have reproduced. In this way, it is likely that the low abundance of this species in the region, when compared to other Brachyura crabs that reproduce at a younger age, results from the pressure of indirect fishing and bycatch of species that 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
may depend upon in the ecosystem. These fishing practices may lead to population disorders, even for animals with an evolutionary history composed of ecological relationships, as seen for 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. ferreirae
</tp:taxon-name>
. Future studies on this population should consider a large temporal period and are necessary to verify whether the population has been undergoing any 
type
of plasticity due to the influence of fishing activities (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
</title>
         <p>
We thank for Dr. Maria Lucia Negreiros-Fransozo for useful suggestions and comments on early drafts of the manuscript; Richard Little (Language and Academic Support Services, and Charlie Savill, (MSc in Evolutionary and Behavioural Ecology) at the University of Exeter in 
Cornwall
– 
UK
, for assistance with English, and the ‘‘Instituto Brasileiro do Meio Ambiente e dos Recursos Naturais Renováveis’’ (IBAMA) for granting permission to collect the crabs. To the funding agencies: “Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo” (FAPESP) (Biota/FAPESP #2010/50188-8 and Scholarship 2014/13770-1, 2018/01659-0, 2019/00105-3), “Centro de Apoio Profissionalizante Educacional e Social” (CAPES CIMAR) (No. 23038.004310/2014- 85), and to “Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico” (CNPq) (Financial Support # 406006/2012-1, Research Scholarships PQ 303371/2011-0 and 311034/2018-7), for providing financial support during field collections and visiting activities.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Anger, K.
; 
Harms, J.
; 
Montú, M.
and 
Bakker, C.
1989
. 

Growth and respiration during the larval development of a tropical spider crab, 
Libinia ferreira
(Decapoda: Majidae)

. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series

, 
54
: 
43–50
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bakker, C.
; 
Montu, M.
; 
Anger, K.
and 
Harms, J.
1990
. 

Larval development of a tropical spider crab, 
Libinia ferreirae
Brito Capello, 1871 (Decapoda: Majidae), reared in the laboratory

. 

Meeresforschung
,

33
: 
90–103
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Braga, A.A.
; 
Fransozo, A.
; 
Bertini, G.
and 
Fumis, P.B.
2007
. 

Bathymetric distribution and recruitment of the spider crab 
Libinia spinosa
H. Milne Edwards 
1834 in
the Ubatuba and Caraguatatuba regions, northern coast of São Paulo, Brazil (Crustacea, Brachyura, Majoidea, Pisidae)

. 

Senckenbergiana Biologica

, 
87
: 
7–16
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Campana, S.E.
2001
. 
Accuracy, precision and quality control in age determination, including a review of the use and abuse of age validation methods
. 

Journal of Fish Biology

, 
59
: 
197–242
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Castilho, A.L.
; 
Bauer, R.T.
; 
Freire, F.A.M.
; 
Fransozo, V.
; 
Costa, R.C.
; 
Grabowski, R.C.
and 
Fransozo, A.
2015
. 

Lifespan and reproductive dynamics of the commercially important sea bob shrimp 
Xiphopenaeus kroyeri
(Penaeoidea): synthesis of a 5-year study

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
35
: 
30–40
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cerrato, R.M.
1990
. 
Interpretable statistical tests for growth comparisons using parameters in the von Bertalanffy equation
. 

Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences

, 
47
: 
1416– 1426
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Conan, G.Y.
and 
Comeau, M.
1986
. 
Functional maturity and terminal moult of male snow crab
, 

Chionoecetes opilio.Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences
.

43
, 
1710–1719
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
D’Incao, F.
and 
Fonseca, D.B.
1999
. 
Performance of the von Bertalanffy growth curve in penaeid shrimp: a critical approach
. p. 733–737. In: 
J.C. von Kaupel Klein
and 
F.R. Schram
(ed), 
The Biodiversity Crisis and Crustacean. Proceedings of the Fourth International Crustacean Congress, Amsterdam, Netherlands
, 
20–24 July 1998
, vol. 2. 
Crustacean Issues, 12. Rotterdam, A.A. Balkema
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
De Goursey, R.E.
and 
Auster, P.J.
1992
. 

A mating aggregation of the spider crab (
Libinia emarginata
)

. 

Journal of Northwest Atlantic Fishery Science

, 
13
: 
77–82
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Duran, J.
; 
Palmer, M.
and 
Pastor, E.
2013
. 

Growing reared spider crabs (
Maja squinado
) to sexual maturity: The first empirical data and a predictive growth model

. 

Aquaculture
,

409
: 
78–87
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elner, R.W.
and 
Beninger, P.G.
1995
. 

Multiple reproductive strategies in snow crab, 
Chionoecetes opilio
: physiological pathways and behavioral plasticity

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 
193
: 
93–112
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ferreira, L.S.
and 
F. D’Incao
. 
2008
. 

Crescimento de 
Callinectes sapidus
(Crustacea, Decapoda, Portunidae) no estuário da laguna dos Patos, Rio Grande do Sul, Brasil

. 

Iheringia, Série Zoologia

, 
98
: 
70–77
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fonseca, D.B.
; 
Sainte-Marie, B.
and 
Hazel, F.
2008
. 

Longevity and change in shell condition of adult male snow crab 
Chionoecetes opilio
inferred from dactyl wear and mark-recapture data

. 

Transactions of the American Fisheries Society
,

137
: 
1029–1043
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fonseca, D.B.
and 
D’Incao, F.
2003
. 

Growth and reproductive parameters of 
Kalliapseudes schubartii
in the estuarine region of the Lagoa dos Patos (southern Brazil)

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
83
: 
931–935
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Garcia,S.
and 
Le Reste, L.
1981
. 
Life cycles, dynamics, exploitation and management of coastal penaeid shrimp stocks
. 

FAO Fisheries and Aquaculture Technical Papers

, 
203
: 
1–215
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ghalambor, C.K.
; 
McKay, J.K.
; 
Carroll, S.P.
and 
Reznick, D.N.
2007
. 
Adaptive versus non-adaptive phenotypic plasticity and the potential for contemporary adaptation in new environments
. 

Functional Ecology

, 
21
: 
394–407
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gonçalves, G.R.L.
; 
Wolf, M.R.
; 
Costa, R.C.
and 
Castilho, A.L.
2016
. 
Decapod crustacean associations with scyphozoan jellyfish (Rhizostomeae: Pelagiidae) in the Southeastern Brazilian coast
. 

Symbiosis

3
: 
93–198
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gonçalves, G.R.L.
; 
Bolla Jr, E.A.
; 
Negreiros-Fransozo, M.L.
and 
Castilho, A.L.
2017
a. 

Morphometric and gonadal maturity of the spider crab 
Libinia ferreirae
Brito Capello, 1871 (Decapoda: Majoidea: Epialtidae) at Southeastern Brazilian coast

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
97
: 
289–295
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gonçalves, G.R.L.
; 
Grabowski, R.C.
; 
Bochini, G.L.
; 
Costa, R.C.
and 
Castilho, A.L.
2017
b. 

Ecology of the spider crab 
Libinia ferreirae
(Brachyura: Majoidea): ontogenetic shifts in habitat use

. 

Hydrobiologia

, 
795
: 
313–325
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gonzalez-Gurriaran, E.
; 
Freire, J.
; 
Parapar, J.
; 
Sampedro, M.P.
and 
Urcera, M.
1995
. 

Growth at molt and molting seasonality of the spider crab, 
Maja squinado
(Herbst) (Decapoda: Majidae) in experimental conditions: implications for juvenile life history

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology

, 
189
: 
183–203
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hartnoll, R.G.
1963
. 
The biology of Manx spider crabs
. 

Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London

, 
141
: 
423–496
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hartnoll, R.G.
1969
. 
Mating in the Brachyura
. 

Crustaceana
,

16
: 
161–181
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hartnoll, R.G.
1982
. 
Growth
. p. 
111–196
. In: 
D.E. Bliss
(ed), 
The Biology of Crustacea: Embryology, Morphology and Genetics
. 
New York, Academic Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hartnoll, R.G.
and 
Bryant, A.D.
2001
. 

Growth to maturity of juveniles of the spider crabs 
Hyas coarctatus
Leach and 
Inachus dorsettensis
(Pennant) (Brachyura: Majidae)

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology
,

263
: 
143–158
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hartnoll, R.G.
; 
Bryant, A.D.
and 
Gould, P.
1993
. 
Size distribution in spider crab populations spatial and temporal variation
. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
13
: 
647–655
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hébert, M.
; 
Benhalima, K.
; 
Miron, G.
and 
Moriyasu, M.
2002
. 

Molting and growth of male snowcrab, 
Chionoecetes opilio
(O. Fabricius, 1788) (Crustacea: Majidae) in the southern Gulf of St. Lawrence

. 

Crustaceana

, 
75
: 
671–702
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hultgren, K.
and 
Stachowicz, J.
2011
. 
Camouflage in decorator crabs
. p. 
214–238
. In: 
M. Stevens
and 
S. Merilaita
(eds), 
Animal Camouflage:Mechanisms and Function
. 
Cambridge, Cambridge University Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ingle, R.W.
1977
. 

The larval and post-larval development of the scorpion spider crab, 
Inachus dorsettensis
(Pennant) (family: Majidae), reared in the laboratory

. 

Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History), Zoology
,

30
: 
329–348
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Laufer, H.
and 
Ahl, J.S.B.
1995
. 

Mating behaviour and methyl farnesoate levels in male morphotypes of the spider crab 
Libinia emarginata
(Leach)

. 

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology
,

193
: 
15–20
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Le Foll, D.
1993
. 

Biologie et exploitation de l’araignée de mer 
Maja squinado
(Herbst) en manche ouest

. 
Université de Bretagne Occidentale, Brest
, Ph.D. thesis. 
517p.
[Unpublished].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Le Foll, D.
; 
Brichet, E.
; 
Reyss, J.L.
; 
Lalou, C.
and 
Latrouite, D.
1989
. 

Age determination of the Spider crab 
Maja squinado
and the European lobster 
Homarus gammarus
by 
228
Th/ 
228
Ra chronology: possible extension to others crustaceans

. 

Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences
,

46
: 
720–724
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
McLay,C.L.
2015
. 
Moulting and growth in Brachyura
.p. 
245–316
. In: 
P. Castro
; 
P.J.F. Davie
; 
D. Guinot
; 
F.R. Schram
. and 
J.C. von Vaupel Klein
(eds), 
The Crustacea, treatise on Zoology — Anatomy, Taxonomy, Biology, Volume 9
. 
Leiden, Brill
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Melo, G.A.S.
1996
. 
Manual de Identificação dos Brachyura (Caranguejos e Siris) do Litoral Brasileiro
. 
São Paulo, Ed. Plêiade
. 
604p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Miazaki, L.F.
; 
Simões, S. M.
; 
Castilho, A. L.
and 
Costa, R.C.
2019
. 

Population dynamics of the crab 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst, 1785) (Decapoda, Aethridae) on the southern coast of São Paulo state, Brazil

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
99
: 
867–878
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Miller, R.J.
and 
Watson, J.
1976
. 

Growth per molt and limb regeneration in the spider crab, 
Chionoecetes opilio

. 

Journal of the Fisheries Research Board of Canada

, 
33
: 
1644–1649
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nogueira Jr, M.
and 
Haddad, M.A.
2005
. 

Lychnorhiza lucerna
(Scyphozoa, Rhizostomeae) and 
Libinia ferreirae
Brito Capello (Brachyura, Majidae) association in southern Brazil

. 

Revista brasileira de Zoologia

, 
22
: 
908–912
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
O’Brien, S.B.
; 
Landau, M.
and 
Able, K.W.
1999
. 

Sex ratios of two species of spider crabs, 
Libinia dubia
H. Milne Edwards, 1834 and 
L. emarginata
Leach, 1815: in the area of Great Bay, New Jersey

. 

Crustaceana

, 
72
, 
187–192
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Petriella, A.M.
and 
Boschi, E.E.
1997
. 
Crecimiento en crustáceos decápodos: Resultados de investigaciones realizadas en Argentina
. 

Investigaciones Marinas

, 
25
: 
135–157
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sainte-Marie, B.
; 
Raymond, S.
and 
Brêthes, J.C.
1995
. 

Growth and maturation of the benthic stages of male snow crab, 
Chionoecetes opilio
(Brachyura: Majidae)

. 

Canadian Journal of Fisheries and Aquatic Sciences

, 
52
: 
903–924
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sal Moyano, M.
and 
Gavio, M.A.
2012
. 

Comparison of mating behavior and copulation in male morphotypes of the spider crab 
Libinia spinosa
(Brachyura:Majoidea:Epialtidae)

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology
,

32
: 
31–38
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sal Moyano, M.P.
; 
Gavio, M.A.
and 
Maggi, M.D.
2011
. 

Morphometric and gonad maturity of the spider crab 
Libinia spinosa
(Crustacea: Brachyura: Majoidea: Epialtidae) in Argentina

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
91
: 
837–844
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sampedro, M.P.
; 
González-Gurriarán, E.
; 
Freire, J.
and 
Muíño, R.
1999
. 

Morphometry and sexual maturity in the spider crab 
Maja squinado
(Decapoda: Majidae) in Galicia

, 

Spain, 
Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
19
: 
578–592
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tavares, M.
and 
Santana, W.
2012
. 

On the morphological differentiation between 
Libinia spinosa
and 
L. ferreirae
(Crustacea: Brachyura: Majoidea: Epialtidae)

. 

Zoologia
,

29
: 
577–588
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Teixeira, G.M.
; 
Fransozo, V.
; 
Castilho, A.L.
; 
da Costa, R.C.
and 
de Morais Freire, F.A.
2008
. 

Size distribution and sex ratio in the spider crab 
Epialtus brasiliensis
(Dana 1852) associated with seaweed on a rocky shore in southeastern Brazil (Crustacea, Decapoda, Brachyura, Majoidea, Epialtidae)

. 

Senckenbergiana biologica

, 
169–175
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Urban, H.J.
2002
. 
Modeling growth of different developmental stages in bivalves
. 

Marine Ecology Progress Series
,

238
: 
109–114
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Varisco, M.
and 
Vinuesa, J.
2011
. 

Reproductive biology of the spider 
crab Leucippa pentagona
(Decapoda: Epialtidae)

, in 
Bustamante Bay, Argentina
. 

Latin American Journal of Aquatic Research

, 
39
: 
471–480
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
von Bertalanffy, L.
1938
. 
A quantitative theory of organic growth
. 

Human Biology

, 
10
: 
181–213
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Winter, V.C.
and 
Masunari, S.
2006
. 

Macroepizoismo em 
Libinia ferreirae
(Crustacea, Brachyura, Majidae)

. 

Iheringia, Série Zoologia

, 
96
: 
135–140
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
