<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nauplius</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2358-2936e2020008</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Population structure of Hepatus pudibundus (Decapoda: Aethridae) off the coast of Sergipe State, northeastern Brazil</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>23</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aethridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst, 1785)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aethridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Leptuca uruguayensis
(Nobili, 1901)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aethridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xiphopenaeus kroyeri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Callinectes ornatus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ORIGINAL
ARTICLE
</title>
         <p>
BRAZILIAN
CRUSTACEAN
SOCIETY
</p>
         <p>
Josafá Reis-Júnior
1
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-0791-2673
</p>
         <p>
Kátia Meirelles Felizola Freire
2
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-6190-3532
</p>
         <p>
Leonardo Cruz da Rosa
3
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-4263-332X
</p>
         <p>
Thaiza Maria Rezende da Rocha Barreto
4
B

orcid.org/0000-0002-8085-9901
</p>
         <p>
1
Programa de Pós-graduação em Biometria e Estatística Aplicada (PPGBEA),
</p>
         <p>
Universidade Federal Rural de 
Pernambuco
(UFRPE). 

Recife, 
Pernambuco
, 
Brazil

.
</p>
         <p>
JRJ
E-mail: josafajunior13@hotmail.com
</p>
         <p>
2

Laboratório de Ecologia Pesqueira (LEP), Departamento de Engenharia de Pesca e Aquicultura (DEPAQ), Universidade Federal de Sergipe (UFS), 
São Cristóvão
, 
Sergipe
, 
Brazil
.

</p>
         <p>
KMFF
E-mail: kmffreire2018@gmail.com
</p>
         <p>
3

Laboratório de Ecologia Bentônica (LEB), DEPAQ, Universidade Federal de Sergipe (UFS), 
São Cristóvão
, 
Sergipe
, 
Brazil
.

</p>
         <p>
LCR
E-mail: leonardo.rosa@rocketmail.com
</p>
         <p>
4

Laboratório de Ciências da Pesca, Instituto do Mar, Universidade Federal de 

São 

Paulo, Campus Baixada Santista, Santos, 
São Paulo
, 
Brazil
.

</p>
         <p>
TMRRB
E-mail: barreto.thaiza@gmail.com
</p>
         <p>
ZOOBANK
: http://zoobank.org/ 

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 

6E806DDE-E6F7-45EA-81A4 
-CE
9EC814D906

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT
</title>
         <p>
Shrimp trawling is an important socioeconomic activity but catches a large number of non-target species, including 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
. This study aimed at assessing the population structure of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
, analyzing its sex ratio, length distribution, size at first morphological maturity and biometric relationships, and identifying latitudinal patterns. Four samples of 
6 kg
(shrimps plus by-catch) were monthly collected in March/2015– May/ 
2016 in
Pirambu, 
Sergipe
. Carapace width (CW) and length (LC), and total weight (TW, g) were measured. Sex and stage of morphological maturity were defined. A total of 240 individuals was collected from all samples and the sex ratio did not differ from 1:1. This was observed in low latitudes, but females dominated in higher latitudes. The carapace width was 
20.8–60.1 mm
for females and 
19.1–60.8 mm
CW for males. Larger sizes were observed in higher latitudes. The estimated carapace widthlength relationships for females and males were not significantly different (CL=0.6764+0.7390∙CW; sex grouped). The estimated weight-length relationship was TW=0.0004∙CW 
2.8568
for females and TW=0.0001∙CW 
3.1225
for males. When compared with previous studies carried out throughout the Brazilian coast, slope values (
b
) for weight-length relationships were higher for males. The length at first morphological maturity for females and males was 28.9 and 
29.6 mm
, respectively, the lowest ever recorded for this species, reflecting the occurrence of smaller sizes in lower latitudes. These results are the first obtained for northeastern 
Brazil
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
KEYWORDS
</title>
         <p>
Brachyura, biometric relationships, allometric growth, morphological maturation, latitudinal variation
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION
</title>
         <p>
Bottom shrimp trawling in 
Brazil
is an important socio-economic activity, which was responsible for catches of approximately 38.7 thousand tonnes of marine shrimps in 2011 off Brazilian waters (MPA, 2011). In the state of 
Sergipe
, shrimp catches amounted to approximately 1.3 thousand tonnes in 2014 (

). However, bottom shrimp trawlers are considered predatory, especially due to the low selectivity leading to high catches of non-target species that end up discarded. This causes a serious environmental problem, as many of these species may be ecologically important in the food chain (

) or may be juveniles of commercially important species (

), even though they do not have economic importance (

; 

). FAO data indicate that 1,865 thousand tonnes of by-catch are discarded in relation to 1,126 thousand tonnes of shrimps landed in the world (1992–2001 period), with an average discard rate of 62% (

). Discarded by-catch includes several species of fish, crustaceans, mollusks, cnidarians, and echinoderms of no commercial importance (

), which under continuous fishing pressure are subject to several environmental problems (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
In surveys conducted along the Brazilian coast, many species are caught as by-catch in shrimp fisheries: 216 species off 
Santa Catarina
(

), 258 species off 
São Paulo
(

), 77 species off 
Espírito Santo
(

), and 79 species of only crustaceans between 
Sergipe
and 
Alagoas
(Santos 
et al.
, 2016). In these studies, the presence of brachyuran crabs is significant, indicating this group is widely distributed along the Brazilian coast and has been probably impacted by shrimp trawlers. One of the brachyurans with the highest catch rates is the flecked box crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst, 1785)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Severino-Rodrigues 
et al.
, 2002; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
belongs to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Aethridae</tp:taxon-name>
and occurs in the Western Atlantic Ocean, from 
Georgia
(
USA
) to 
Rio Grande do Sul
(
Brazil
), on muddy or sandy areas with biodetritus and up to 
160 m
depth (

). Some of the studies for this species off the southeastern-southern regions in 
Brazil
reported its presence as by-catch and/or analysed the population structure and length at first maturity (

; 

; 

; 

), population dynamics (Sardá 
et al.
, 2013; 

), reproductive cycle (

), natural feeding habits (

), distribution, abundance and reproductive biology (

; 

; 

; 

), and morphological and morphometric analyses (

; Marochi 
et al.
, 2016). 

assessed the mortality of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
caused by shrimp trawlers and concluded this species is overexploited off 
Rio de Janeiro
and 
São Paulo
. These individuals are also subject to the effects of anthropogenic pollution, as evidenced by 

. Their research observed the contamination and bioaccumulation of persistent organic pollutants in 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
. These studies are important for the assessment of the species caught, even as by-catch, and give support to management plans for local communities (

; 

). All these studies were conducted along the coast of the southeastern and southern regions in 
Brazil
and thus the absence of information for northeastern 
Brazil
is evident.
</p>
         <p>
Considering the absence of information for northeastern 
Brazil
, this study was conducted aiming at analysing the population structure (sex ratio, length distribution and size at first morphological maturity) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
caught as by-catch by shrimp trawlers off the state of 
Sergipe
and its biometric relationships. Finally, the existence of latitudinal patterns in the population structure and biometric relationships was assessed based on the information available in the literature
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
MATERIALS
AND
METHODS
</title>
         <p>
Sampling and processing
</p>
         <p>

Samples of approximately 
6 kg
each on average were collected monthly from 

March 2015

to 

May 2016

from four shrimp bottom trawlers (one sample per boat). All trawlers were 

8.5 to 15 m

long, operated with double nets, and were based in the municipality of 
Pirambu
, in the state of 
Sergipe
(
10°44’16”S
36°51’22”W
to 
11°31’09”S
37°30’42”W
), northeastern 
Brazil
(
Fig. 1
). 
All
samples were obtained before any sorting by fishermen and thus included both shrimps and by-catch (fish, crustaceans, mollusks, and others). 
Samples
were stored in ice and later kept frozen in the 
Laboratório de Ecologia Pesqueira
at the 
Universidade Federal
de 
Sergipe
(LEP/UFS) for future analysis

.
</p>
         <p>
All individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
present in the samples were separated and identified according to 

. Each specimen was weighed (total weight, TW, g) using a BEL Engineering® scale (precision: 
0.0001 g
) and measured (carapace length- CL and width-CW, both in mm) with a Precision Gold® digital calliper (precision: 
0.01 mm
). All individuals were sexed based on the shape of the abdomen (oval for females and elongated or triangular for males) (

; 

). The definition of morphological maturity was based on the macroscopic observation of the adherence of the abdomen to the thoracic sternites: immature and mature individuals have attached and non-attached abdomens, respectively (

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Statistical analyses
</title>
         <p>
A chi-square test (Χ²) with the Yates correction for continuity was applied to test if the overall sex ratio (M:F) differed from 1:1 (Zar, 2010). All individuals measured were divided into size classes of 
5 mm
CW, following Sturges (1926). The normality and homogeneity of the quantitative variables were tested by the Kolmogorov-Smirnov and Bartlet tests, respectively. A Student t-test with difference of variances was used to compare the mean carapace width (CW) and total weight (TW) between females and males (Zar, 2010). Maximum values of carapace width (CW 
max
) from different studies were obtained from the literature and compared to this study in order to test the hypothesis of increasing sizes in higher latitude using a linear regression. Relationships between carapace length and width were fitted using a linear model (CL= 
a
+ 
b
∙CW), and relationships between total weight and carapace width using a power model (TW= 
a
∙CW 

b

) for females and males, separately. The significance of the regressions was tested using an ANOVA for regression and differences between sexes were tested using the confidence intervals for the intercept (
a
) and slope (
b
) (Zar, 2010). The hypothesis of isometry was tested for the carapace length-width (
b
=1) and total weight-carapace length (
b
=3) relationships using a Student t-test (

; Zar, 2010). All tests were performed using a significance level of 5%.
</p>
         <p>
Length at first morphological maturity (CW 
m
) was estimated using a logistic curve fitted to the percentage of mature individuals (% mature) and carapace width (CW)for females and males,separately:%mature=100/ [1+exp(
a
+ 
b
∙CW)] (Sparre and Venema, 1998). Parameters ‘ 
a
’ and ‘ 
b
’ were estimated using a nonlinear method (SOLVER in Microsoft Excel).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Latitudinal pattern
</title>
         <p>
All data related to population structure and biometric relationships were compared to the literature available, considering the latitude where each study was conducted. CW 
max
was plotted against latitude to verify changes with latitude. Finally, CW 
m
/CW 
max
for each study was calculated to check if it is constant or also varies with latitude.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
RESULTS
</title>
         <p>
Population structure and biometric analysis
</p>
         <p>
A total of 
240 specimens
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
has collected and analysed: 
128 females
(
11 immature
and 117 mature) and 
111 males
(
28 immature
and 83 mature). The overall sex ratio was not statistically different from 1:1 (Chi-square test, Χ²=0.94, 
p
=0.33). Quantitative variables were normal (Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, 
p
&gt;0.05) and with different variances between the sexes (Bartlet test, 
p
&lt;0.05). The carapace width ranged from 
20.8 to 42.6 mm
for immature females and from 25.0 to 
60.1 mm
for mature females (
Fig. 2A
). The carapace width ranged from 19.1 to 46.0 mm for immature males and from 
25.8 to 60.9 mm
for mature males (
Fig. 2B
). The mean carapace width for females (41.4± 
7.8 mm
) was not statistically different from males (39.3± 
9.5 mm
) (t-test, t=1.86, 
p
=0.06). The total weight ranged from 
2.5 to 17.6 g
for immature females and from 
3.8 to 47.8 g
for mature females. The total weight ranged from 
0.9 to 20.8 mm
for immature males and from 
3.9 to 57.6 mm
for mature males. Similarly, the mean total weight for females (16.0± 
8.5 g
) was not statistically different from males (15.3±11.0 g) (t=0.54, 
p
=0.59).
</p>
         <p>
The relationships estimated between carapace length and width for females and males were not statistically different (
Tab.1
). Thus, a single relationship was estimated for both sexes: CL=0.6764+0.7390∙CW (
Fig. 3
), indicating a negative allometry in the growth of the carapace length (
b
&lt;1, t=43.45, 
p
&lt;0.05). The relationships between total weight and carapace width were TW=0.0004∙CW 
2.8568
and TW=0.0001∙CW 
3.1225
for females and males, respectively (
Fig. 4
). Significant difference was observed in the relationships estimated for females and males, indicating a negative allometry for females (
b
&lt;3, t=3.23, 
p
&lt;0.05) and a positive allometry for males (
b
&gt;3, t=2.44, 
p
&lt;0.05) (
Tab.1
).
</p>
         <p>
The length at first morphological maturity (CW 
m
) for females and males was 28.9 and 
29.6 mm
, respectively (
Fig. 5
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Latitudinal pattern
</title>
         <p>
The northernmost studies (
Sergipe
and 

Rio de 
Janeiro) indicated an equal proportion of females
</p>
         <p>and males, and changed to predominance of females</p>
         <p>
in higher latitudes. 
Table 2
presents the coefficients
</p>
         <p>
(
a
: intercept and 
b
: slope) of the weight-width
</p>
         <p>
relationships for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
along the
</p>
         <p>Brazilian coast. The weight-width relationships</p>
         <p>did not indicate any latitudinal pattern but higher</p>
         <p>
values of 
b
for males were evident throughout the
</p>
         <p>
Brazilian coast (
Tab. 2
). The maximum carapace
</p>
         <p>
width (CW 
max
) increases significantly with latitude: CW 
max
=1.1074∙Lat+41.406 for females (r²=0.676, F=16.7, 
p
&lt;0.01) and CW 
max
=1.1630∙Lat+49.763 for males (r²=0.738, F=22.6, 
p
&lt;0.01) (
Fig. 6
). CW 
m
was the smallest estimated for the Brazilian coast, but it is
</p>
         <p>
directly related to CW 
max
, as evidencied by the CW 
m
/ CW 
max
(
Tab.3
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

CL = carapace length; CW = carapace width; TW = total weight; 
a
= intercept; 
b
= slope or power; CI = confidence interval; r 
2
= coefficient of determination; n = sample size; F = Fisher’s F for ANOVA regression; *indicates statistically significant results, p&lt;0.05.

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
*Values of 
a
obtained using anti-log, as original references used log-transformed data.
</p>
         <p>
**Values of 
a
transformed as the original source estimated the weight-length relationship using width in cm. Mean bottom water temperature values found for the same region in other studies: 
a

; 
b

, approximate graphical values; 
c
Sardá 
et al.
(2013).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
DISCUSSION
</title>
         <p>
The number of females and males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hepatus pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
was not statistically different in 
Sergipe
compared to what was observed in 
Rio de Janeiro
(

) and 
Santa Catarina
(Sardá 
et al
., 2013). Nevertheless, several studies indicated predominance of females (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

), all of them in high latitude. Fisher’s theory (1930) postulates that a sex ratio of 1:1 is expected in dioecious species, as observed in this study. Differences in number of females and males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
along the Brazilian coast suggests that factors such as migration, growth and mortality exert differential control over each sex (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Mean carapace width and mean total weight were not statistically different between females and males. 

also found no difference off 
São Paulo
. However, studies conducted in 
Rio de Janeiro
(

; 

), 
São Paulo
(

; 

), and 
Santa Catarina
(Sardá 
et al.
, 2013) indicated larger mean carapace width for males than females. Overall, male brachyurans are larger than females (

), which may be related to different foraging behaviour and reproductive strategies. Thus, the development process favours larger males with better reproductive success; on the other hand, females invest more in reproduction after first maturity, with less investment into growth (

; 

; Marochi 
et al.
, 2016).
</p>
         <p>
In this study, no difference in mean size for males and females was observed, and factors such as different patterns of migration, food foraging, sexual behavior, and reproductive strategy may influence the dispersion of these individuals (

; Sardá 
et al.
, 2013; 

), and consequently the differential capture of size classes of specimens by fishing gear. The absence of crabs smaller than 
19 mm
CW may have been influenced by segregation and different spatial distribution between immature and mature crabs (

; Watanabe 
et al.
, 2014), and by the selectivity of the mesh size used (
21 mm
, JRJ and KMFF, personal observation).
</p>
         <p>
Data compiled for maximum carapace width of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
along the Brazilian coast showed an increase in width (and hence length) with latitude (
Fig. 6
). The largest individuals found in the literature were a male with 
96.7 mm
CW off 
Santa Catarina
(Sardá 
et al.
, 2013) and a female 
81.4 mm
CW long off 
São Paulo
(

), in southern and southeastern 
Brazil
, respectively. The smallest CW 
max
values found were 
54.4 mm
for females off 
Bahia
(

) and 
60.8 mm
for males off 
Sergipe
(present study), both in northeastern 
Brazil
. Santos 
et al
. (2016) found a CW 
max
of 
62.6 mm
for grouped sexes off the Alagoas-Sergipe states (original values of CL converted to CW using the linear equation CL×CW presented at 
Tab.1
), corroborating with the values found in the present study. This latitudinal variation of length is called Bergmann’s Rule, which states that individuals of a certain species reaching larger corporal length tend to live in higher latitudes (

).
</p>
         <p>
One of the main factors affecting species body size is temperature, which controls metabolism and growth (

). 

found latitudinal difference for crustaceans along the coast of North America and considered temperature as the main cause for this difference. 

described a similar latitudinal pattern for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leptuca uruguayensis
(Nobili, 1901)
</tp:taxon-name>
, where the largest individuals were found in 
Argentina
(36ºS) when compared with individuals from 
Brazil
(23ºS). In fact, the southeastern and southern regions of 
Brazil
are characterized by lower seawater temperature (

) when compared with the northeastern region (Heileman, 2009) (see 
Tab.3
). Warmer waters have a lower amount of dissolved oxygen, and organisms have to adjust their metabolism to balance out oxygen availability and consumption. As a consequence, individuals reach smaller body size (

). Conversely, invertebrates (crabs and others) inhabiting cold waters enjoy a larger amount of dissolved oxygen and if their enzymatic and metabolic systems are not affected by the low temperature, they will reach larger body size (

). Other factors such as food availability and fishing pressure may also influence the maximum observed size (

).
</p>
         <p>
The relationship between carapace width and length showed a pattern of negative allometry (
b
&lt;1) for both sexes, indicating that carapace length grows relatively less than expected in relation to carapace width. Sardá 
et al.
(2013) found a negative allometry for this relationship for 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
off 
Santa Catarina
, even though there was significant difference between sexes. On the other hand, 

found isometric growth (
b
=1) off 
São Paulo
. The relationship between total weight and carapace length indicated differences in allometry between sexes: negative for females and positive for males. Thus, males grow more in weight than would be expected for their increase in length than females. Several other studies analysed this allometric difference in weight between sexes for 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
, and in general, males present larger 
b
values (
Tab.2
). Some authors attribute negative allometry on weight for females to reproductive factors, as females direct a large part of their energy to reproductive activities after maturity is reached, reducing investments in body growth (

). Some authors, on the other hand, do not agree with this point of view (see, 
e.g
., 

). Positive allometry in males may be related to the need to maximize size and biomass to improve food search capabilities and territorial defence (Sardá 
et al.
, 2013). Moreover, this may be related to much larger chelar propodus developed in males after maturity (Marochi 
et al.
, 2016), common in brachyurans (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Length at first morphological maturity was similar for females and males (around 
29 mm
CW), as found off other states in 
Brazil
. In general, females begin to reproduce when reaching 40-62% of the maximum carapace length and males around 43-54% of CW 
max
(
Tab.3
). The largest CW 
m
recorded along the Brazilian coast was found by 

for females (36.0 mm CW, 
Santa Catarina
, southern region) and by 

for males (38.0 mm CW, 
São Paulo
, southeastern region). The CW 
m
estimated in the present study for 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
were the smallest ever registered along the Brazilian coast (
Tab.3
). Yet, this may also reflect the fact that individuals reach smaller sizes in lower latitudes, evidenced by the similarity in CW 
m
/CW 
max
observed along the coast (50% on average).
</p>
         <p>
The population parameters estimated here for 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pudibundus
</tp:taxon-name>
for the first time in 
Sergipe
, northeastern 
Brazil
, differ, in some cases, from studies carried out off southeastern-southern 
Brazil
, mainly due to latitudinal differences directly associated to temperature. We suggest that new studies are conducted along the Brazilian coast to better understand latitudinal patterns related to population structure and biometric relationships, especially in northeastern 
Brazil
. As these communities are also impacted by high fishing effort, the information presented here represent an initial step towards sustainable management of the environment.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
</title>
         <p>
This study was supported by Projeto de Monitoramento Participativo de Desembarque Pesqueiro (PMPDP) and Fundação de Apoio à Pesquisa e Extensão de 
Sergipe
(FAPESE) (Grant numbers 2600.0094374.14.4 and 2600.0099827.15.4). The authors are grateful to Maria Morais and fishermen from Pirambu (
Sergipe
) for the collection of samples used in this study, to Aline Alves dos Santos Dias and Ana Claudia Gaspar for helping with sample processing, to Robson Rosa for the map of the study area, and to two anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments on the first version of our manuscript.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Almeida, A.O.
; 
Coelho, P.A.
; 
Santos, J.T.A.
and 
Ferraz, N.R.
2007
. 
Crustáceos estomatópodos e decápodos da costa de Ilhéus, Bahia, Brasil
. 

Atlântica

, 
29
: 
5–20
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Araújo, A.R.R.
; 
Barbosa, J.M.
; 
Santos, J.P.
; 
Carvalho, B.L.F.
; 
Garciov-Filho, E.B.
; 
Deda, M.S.
; 
Silva, C.O.
and 
Chammas, M.A.
2016
. 
Boletim estatístico da pesca nos litorais de Sergipe e extremo norte da Bahia, Ano 2014
. 
São Cristóvão, Universidade Federal de Sergipe
, 
82p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Blackburn, T.M.
; 
Gaston, K.J.
and 
Loder, N.
1999
. 
Geographic gradients in body size: a clarification of Bergmann’s rule
. 

Diversity and Distributions

, 
5
: 
165–174
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Branco, J.O.
; 
Freitas-Júnior, F.
and 
Christoffersen, M.L.
2015
. 
By-catch fauna of seabob shrimp trawl fisheries from Santa Catarina State, southern Brazil
. 

Biota Neotropica

, 
15
: 
1–14
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Branco, J.O.
and 
Verani, J.R.
2006
. 
Pesca do camarão sete-barbas e sua fauna acompanhante, na Armação do Itapocoroy, Penha, SC
. p. 
153–170
. In: 
J.O. Branco
and 
A.W.C. Marenzi
(eds), 
Bases ecológicas para um desenvolvimento sustentável: estudos de caso em Penha, SC
. 
Itajaí, Editora da UNIVALI
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bueno, F.A.
; 
Severino-Rodrigues, E.
; 
Santos, J.L.
and Reis- 
Santos, P.
2009
. 

Crescimento relativo e tamanho de primeira maturação em 
Hepatus pudibundus
capturado pela pesca do camarão sete-barbas na Praia do Perequê, Guarujá, SP, Brasil

. 

Revista Ceciliana

, 
1
: 
3–38
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Costa, R.C.
; 
Carvalho-Batista, A.
; 
Herrera, D.R.
; 
Pantaleão, J.A.F.
; 
Teodoro, S.S.A.
and 
Davanso, T.M.
2016
. 

Carcinofauna acompanhante da pesca do camarão-sete-barbas 
Xiphopenaeus kroyeri
em Macaé, Rio de Janeiro, sudeste brasileiro

. 

Boletim do Instituto de Pesca

, 
42
: 
611–624
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Crowder, L.B.
and 
Murawski, S.A.
1998
. 
Fisheries by-catch: implications for management
. 

Fisheries

, 
23
: 
8–17
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fisher, R.A.
1930
. 
The genetical theory of natural selection
. 
Oxford, Clarendon Press
, 
308p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fracasso, H.A.A.
and 
Branco, J.O.
2005
. 

Estrutura populacional de 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst) (Crustacea, Decapoda) na Armação do Itapocory, Penha, Santa Catarina, Brasil

. 

Revista brasileira de Zoologia

, 
22
: 
342–348
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Freire, K.M.F.
and 
Pauly, D.
2010
. 
Fishing down Brazilian marine food webs, with emphasis on the East Brazil Large Marine Ecosystem
. 

Fisheries Research

, 
105
: 
57–62
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Froese, R.
2006
. 
Cube law, condition factor and weight-length relationships: history, meta-analysis and recommendations
. 

Journal of Applied Ichthyology

, 
22
: 
241–253
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Furlan, M.
; 
Castilho, A.L.
; 
Fernandes-Góes, L.C.
; 
Fransozo, V.
; 
Bertini, G.
and 
Costa, R.C.
2013
. 
Effect of environmental factors on the abundance of decapod crustaceans from soft bottoms off southeastern Brazil
. 

Anais da Academia Brasileira de Ciências

, 
85
: 
1345–1356
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Graça-Lopes, R.
; 
Tomás, A.R.G.
; 
Tutui, S.L.S.
; 
Severino-Rodrigues, E.
and 
Puzzi, A.
2002
. 
Fauna acompanhante da pesca camaroneira no litoral do estado de São Paulo, Brasil
. 

Boletim do Instituto de Pesca

, 
28
: 
173–188
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Haley, S.R.
1979
. 

Sex ratio as a function of size in 
Hippa pacifica
Dana (Crustacea, Anomura, Hippidae): a test of the sex reversal and differential growth rate hypothesis

. 

The American Naturalist

, 
113
: 
391–397
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hall, M.
; 
Alverson, D.L.
and 

Metuzals, K. 

I. 
2000


. 
By-catch: problems and solutions
. 

Marine Pollution Bulletin

, 
41
: 
204– 219
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hartnoll, R.G.
1974
. 
Variation in growth pattern between some secondary sexual characters in crabs (Decapoda Brachyura)
. 

Crustaceana

, 
27
: 
131–136
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hartnoll, R.G.
1978
. 
The determination of relative growth in Crustacea
. 

Crustaceana

, 
34
: 
281–293
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Heileman, S.
and 
Gasalla, M.
2009
. 
XVI-54 South Brazil Shelf: LME
#15. p. 
723–734
. In: 
K. Sherman
and 
G. Hempel
(eds), 
The UNEP Large Marine Ecosystems Report: a perspective on changing conditions in LMEs of the world’s regional seas
. 
Nairobi, UNEP Regional Seas Report and Studies No
. 182.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Heileman, S.
2009
. 
XVI-53 East Brazil Shelf: LME
#16. p. 
711–721
. In: 
K. Sherman
and 
G. Hempel
(eds), 
The UNEP Large Marine Ecosystems Report: a perspective on changing conditions in LMEs of the world’s regional seas
. 
Nairobi, UNEP Regional Seas Report and Studies No
. 182.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hines, A.H.
1989
. 
Geographic variation in size at maturity in brachyuran crabs
. 

Bulletin of Marine Science

, 
45
: 
356–368
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hines, A.H.
; 
Wolcott, T.G.
; 
González-Gurriarán, E.
; González- 
Ecalante, J.L.
and 
Freire, J.
1995
. 

Movement patterns and migrations in crabs: Telemetry of juvenile and adult behavior in 
Callinectes sapidus
and 
Maja squinado

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
75
: 
27–42
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hirose, G.
L; 
Fransozo, V.
; 
Tropea, C.
; 
Lopez-Greco, L.S.
and 
Negreiros-Fransozo, M.L.
2012
. 

Comparison of body size, relative growth and size at onset sexual maturity of 
Uca uruguayensis
(Crustacea: Decapoda: Ocypodidae) from different latitudes in the southwestern Atlantic

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
93
: 
781–788
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kelleher, K.
2005
. 
Discards in the world’s marine fisheries: an update
. 
Rome, FAO (Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations)
, 
131p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Keunecke, K.A.
; 
D’Incao, F.
and 
Fonseca, D.B.
2007
. 

Growth and mortality of 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Crustacea: Calappidae) in south-western Brazil

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
87
: 
885–891
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
King, M.
2007
. 
Fisheries biology, assessment and management. Second edition
. 
Oxford, Blackwell Publishing
, 
382p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Klôh, A.S.
and 
Di Beneditto, A.P.M.
2010
. 

Estrutura populacional do siri-baú, 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst 1785) no norte do Estado do Rio de Janeiro, sudeste do Brasil

. 

Biota Neotropica

, 
10
: 
463–467
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lima, P.A.
; 
Bertini, G.
; 
Fransozo, V.
; 
Gragati, R.A.
; 
Fernandes-Góes, L.C.
and 
Castilho, A.L.
2014
b. 

Reproductive biology of 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Crustacea: Brachyura), the most abundant crab on the southeastern Brazilian coast

. 

Biologia

, 
69
: 
219–227
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lima, P.A.
; 
Fransozo, V.
; 
Andrade, L.S.
; 
Almeida, A.C.
; 
Furlan, M.
and 
Fransozo, A.
2014
a. 

Distribution and population structure of the flecked box crab 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Decapoda, Brachyura) in the western South Atlantic

. 

Marine Biology Research

, 
10
: 
589–600
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Magalhães, C.A.
; 
Taniguchi, S.
; 
Cascaes, M.J.
and 
Montone, R.C.
2012
. 

PCBs, PBDEs and organochlorine pesticides in crabs 
Hepatus pudibundus
and 
Callinectes danae
from Santos Bay, State of São Paulo, Brazil

. 

Marine Pollution Bulletin

, 
64
: 
662–667
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mantelatto, F.L.
; 
Bernardo, C.H.
; 
Silva, T.E.
; 
Bernardes, V.P.
; 
Cobo, V.J.
and 
Fransozo, A.
2016
. 

Composição e distribuição de crustáceos decápodes associados à pesca do camarão-sete-barbas 
Xiphopenaeus kroyeri
(Heller, 1862) no litoral norte do estado de São Paulo

. 

Boletim do Instituto de Pesca

, 
42
: 
307–326
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mantelatto, F.L.M.
; 
Fransozo, A.
and 
Negreiros-Fransozo, M.L.
1995
a. 

Population structure of 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Decapoda: Calappidae) in Fortaleza Bay, Brazil

. 

Revista de Biologia Tropical

, 
43
: 
265–270
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mantelatto, F.L.M.
; 
Fransozo, A.
and 
Negreiros-Fransozo, M.L.
1995
b. 

Distribuição do caranguejo 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst, 1785) (Crustacea, Decapoda, Brachyura) na Enseada da Fortaleza, Ubatuba (SP), Brasil

. 

Boletim do Instituto Oceanográfico

, 
43
: 
51–61
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mantelatto, F.L.M.
and 
Fransozo, A.
1992
. 

Relação peso/largura da carapaça do caranguejo 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst, 1785) (Crustacea, Decapoda, Calappidae) na região de Ubatuba, SP, Brasil

. 

Arquivos de Biologia e Tecnologia

, 
35
: 
719–724
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mantelatto, F.L.M.
and 
Fransozo, A.
1994
. 

Crescimento relativo e dimorfismo sexual em 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst, 1785) (Decapoda, Brachyura) no litoral norte paulista

. 

Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia

, 
39
: 
33–48
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mantelatto, F.L.M.
and 
Petracco, M.
1997
. 

Natural diet of the crab 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Brachyura: Calappidae) in Fortaleza Bay, Ubatuba (SP), Brazil

. 

Journal of Crustacean Biology

, 
17
: 
440–446
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Marochi, M.Z.
and 
Masurani, S.
2016
. 
Ecomorphology of crabs and swimming crabs (Crustacea Decapoda Brachyura) from coastal ecosystems
. 

Brazilian Journal of Oceanography

, 
64
: 
137–148
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Marochi, M.Z.
; 
Trevisan, A.
; 
Gomes, F.B.
and 
Masurani, S.
2016
. 

Dimorfismo sexual em 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Crustacea, Decapoda, Brachyura)

. 

Iheringia, Série Zoologia

, 
106
: e 
2016003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Melo, G.A.S.
1996
. 
Manual de identificação dos Brachyura (caranguejos e siris) do litoral brasileiro
. 
São Paulo, Plêiade
, 
604p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Miazaki, L.F.
; 
Simões, S.M.
; 
Castilho, A.L.
and 
Costa, R.C.
2018
. 

Population dynamics of the crab 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst, 1785) (Decapoda, Aethridae) on the southern coast of São Paulo state, Brazil

. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
99
: 
867–878
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ministério da Pesca
e Aquicultura (MPA). 
2011
. 
Boletim Estatístico da Pesca e Aquicultura
– 2011. 
Brasil (Brasília/ DF)
. Available at 
http://www.icmbio.gov.br/cepsul/images/ stories/biblioteca/download/estatistica/est_2011_bol__ bra.pdf
Accessed on 

10 June 2019

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Muto, E.Y.
; 
Corbisier, T.N.
; 
Coelho, L.I.
; 
Arantes, L.P.L.
; 
Chalom, A.
and 
Soares, L.H.
2014
. 
Trophic groups of demersal fish of Santos Bay and adjacent continental shelf, São Paulo State, Brazil: temporal and spatial comparisons
. 

Brazilian Journal of Oceanography

, 
62
: 
89–102
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pauly, D.
2010
. 
Gasping fish and panting squids: Oxygen, temperature and the growth of water-breathing animals
. 
Excellence in Ecology 22. Oldendorf/Luhe, International Ecology Institute
, 
216p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pauly, D.
2019
. 
Métodos para avaliação de recursos pesqueiros
. 
São Paulo, Editora da Universidade de São Paulo
, 
256p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pauly, D.
and 
Cheung, W.W.L.
2018
. 
Sound physiological knowledge and principles in modeling shrinking of fishes under climate change
. 

Global Change Biology

, 
24
: 
15–26
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pinheiro, H.T.
and 
Martins, A.S.
2009
. 
Estudo comparativo da captura artesanal do camarão sete barbas e sua fauna acompanhante em duas áreas de pesca do litoral do estado do Espírito Santo, Brasil
. 

Boletim do Instituto de Pesca

, 
35
: 
215–225
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pinheiro, M.
and 
Boss, H.
2016
. 
Livro vermelho dos crustáceos do Brasil: Avaliação 2010
-2014. 
Porto Alegre, Sociedade Brasileira de Carcinologia
, 
466p.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Reigada, A.L.D.
and 
Negreiros-Fransozo,M.L.
2000
. 

Reproductive cycle of 
Hepatus pudibundus
(Herbst, 1785) (Crustacea, Decapoda, Calappidae) in Ubatuba, SP, Brazil

. 

Revista Brasileira de Biologia

, 
60
: 
483–491
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodrigues-Filho, J.L.
; 
Couto, E.C.G.
; 
Barbieri, E.
and 
Branco, J.O.
2016
. 

Ciclos sazonais da carcinofauna capturada na pesca do camarão-sete-barbas, 
Xiphopenaeus kroyeri
no litoral de Santa Catarina

. 

Boletim do Instituto de Pesca

, 
42
: 
648–661
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Santos, R.C.
; 
Silva, S.L.R.
; 
Costa, R.C.
; 
Davanso, T.M.
and 
Hirose, G.L.
2017
. 
Evaluation of the management plan for penaeid shrimps in the continental shelf of Sergipe, Brazil
. 

Boletim do Instituto de Pesca

, 
43
: 
308–321
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
