<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>NeoBiota</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/neobiota.91.109251</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Effect of residence time on trait evolution in invasive plants: review and meta-analysis</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>22</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Impatiens glandulifera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sapium sebiferum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Butomus umbellatus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lonicera japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Plantago lanceolata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia artemisiifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Reynoutria japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Senecio inaequidens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gladiolus gueinzii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alliaria petiolata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Solidago canadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lonicera japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mikania micrantha
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Impatiens glandulifera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Senecio inaequidens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mikania micrantha
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lonicera japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rubus alceifolius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Senecio madagascariensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lonicera japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mikania micrantha
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mikania micrantha
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alliaria petiolata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Spartina alterniflora
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Harmonia axyridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Senecio inaequidens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Senecio inaequidens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Persicaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Solidago canadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Verbascum thapsus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alliaria petiolata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Brassicaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Reynoutria japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Plantago lanceolata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="﻿introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Introduction
</p>
         <p>
A main interest in the study of plant invasion is the characterisation of traits associated with invasive success, such as high growth rate, competitive ability and phenotypic plasticity and the processes governing the prevalence of these traits in introduced compared to native ranges (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

). While traits that determine invasiveness could be pre-selected for invasion (

), the success of invasive species has often been attributed to rapid post-introduction evolution, due to novel selection pressures at the introduced range, such as release from native enemies and co-evolved competitors (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

). Such trait evolution in invasive plants has been examined in ample studies that provided support for evolutionary shifts between native and introduced ranges in traits such as defence, growth, fecundity, competitive ability, allelopathy and phenotypic plasticity (see meta-analyses: 

; 

; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
In addition to trait divergence between the native and introduced ranges, evolutionary shifts in invasion-promoting traits can take place within the introduced range over time, due to varying selection pressures that might come into play at different invasion stages (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). For example, while populations at the invasion front can experience release from enemies or co-evolved competitors, this selection pressure is likely to attenuate over time in fully-established populations, where herbivores and pathogens could become increasingly accustomed to the invasive plant (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

) and intraspecific competition could intensify (

). Such changes in selection pressures might, in turn, lead to divergence in invasion-promoting traits along gradients of invasion history, with attributes that facilitate greater invasion potential in populations at the invasion front, compared to core populations.
</p>
         <p>
Compared to the evolution of invasive plants between their native and introduced ranges, fewer studies have looked at potential evolutionary shifts within the introduced range. However, studying the idea that invasive plants might undergo rapid selection with time since their introduction might provide a unique model system to explore fundamental questions related to adaptive divergence in plant traits. Moreover, if the adaptive advantage of invasion-promoting traits might decline in more established populations with a long invasion history, this might lead to changes in the effect of such invasive plants on local communities (

; 

; 

; 

). Hence, knowledge on the potential evolution of invasive populations at different invasion stages might also be valuable for predicting the long-term effects of invasive plants and evaluating alternative management practices (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Studying the evolution of invasion-promoting traits with time since introduction presents a challenge, as knowledge on population ages and residence times might not be readily available. However, despite these difficulties, an increasing number of studies have recently focused on exploring changes in invasion-promoting traits of invasive plants over time (Suppl. material 1: fig. S1). Here, we first present a review of the proposed hypotheses regarding the selection pressures and evolution of trait divergence along gradients of invasion history and the studies that examined them. In addition, we present the results of a meta-analysis aimed at providing a more general overview of current knowledge on trait evolution with time since introduction. In both the review and meta-analysis, the chosen species were defined as 
"invasive"
according to the definition of the CBD, i.e. alien species that threaten ecosystems, habitats or species (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿review of trait evolution with invasion history">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Review of trait evolution with invasion history</p>
         <p>Approaches for studying trait divergence in invasive species over time</p>
         <p>
Two main approaches have been employed to study changes in invasion-promoting traits over invasion-history gradients, with advantages and drawbacks to both. In the first approach, plant traits are compared amongst different invasive species with varying residence time within a region (e.g. 

; 

; 

; 

). Such an interspecific approach can provide a generalised overview across multiple species and requires only general knowledge on residence time of species within a region, such as the earliest report of introduction time (e.g. at the country level). However, results of multi-species experiments might be confounded due to historic biases in the types of introductions (

) or due to discrepancies between the time of introduction to certain regions and the age of the sampled populations (but see 

). In the second approach, plant traits are compared within a species across different populations along gradients of invasion history (e.g. 

; 

; 

). This intraspecific approach requires knowledge on population age (a chronosequence approach) or the identity of source populations and invasion trajectories (i.e. distance to source populations), as well as information on the possibility of multiple introductions. Regardless of the approach used, the study of divergence in invasion-promoting traits is best examined in controlled common garden experiments, which expose plants with varying invasion histories to the same environmental conditions. Such studies can reveal inherent variations in trait levels and exclude variations due to plastic responses to field conditions at different sites.
</p>
         <p>
Two additional approaches should be noted due to the alternative advantages they offer to the study of trait evolution along invasion-history gradients. The first approach is the use of herbaria collections, which can provide historical samples of invasive plants (reviewed in: 

; 

). Such collections can be compared at the intraspecific level to identify divergence over time since introduction in physiological and morphological traits, such as herbivore defence compounds or plant size (

; 

). Herbaria records can, thus, be an important tool in the study of invasion history. The second approach is the use of selection gradients (

) on invasion-promoting traits, which are measured in the field in introduced populations with different invasion histories. Such field measurements of selection can provide important knowledge on the adaptive relevance of a focal trait in different populations along invasion gradients, but, to date, it has mainly been applied to study variations between native and introduced populations (e.g. 

; 

; 

). However, as for other studies using field-collected measurements or samples, both approaches cannot exclude plastic responses to field conditions as an explanation for trait variation rather than evolutionary change (excluding herbaria studies that examine the genetic makeup of plants: 

).
</p>
         <p>The following sections provide a review of the hypotheses suggested to explain the effect of time on the evolution of different invasion-promoting traits, including defence, growth, competitive ability and dispersal ability, focusing on studies that examined them under common garden conditions.</p>
         <p>Divergence in traits associated with defence</p>
         <p>
One of the most well-studied hypotheses to explain the success of invasive plants is the evolution of increased competitive ability hypothesis (EICA) (

). This hypothesis proposes that plants in their introduced range experience reduced damage by natural enemies, such as pathogens and specialist herbivores, which selects for reduced allocation to defence traits and a consequent increase in resources available for growth and competitive ability (

; 

). Alternatively, the shifting defence hypothesis (SDH) proposes that the loss of specialist enemies at the introduced range can result in an evolutionary shift from investment in defence against specialists (digestibility reducers such as trichomes and tannins) to defence against generalists (toxins such as glucosinolates and alkaloids) (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Both the EICA and the SDH assume that invasive plants experience release from their specialist enemies at the introduced range. This attenuating selection pressure is not likely to change with time since introduction, except due to the unintentional introduction of specialist herbivores or pathogens (e.g. 

; 

) or their use as biocontrol agents (

). Nevertheless, several studies have shown that enemy pressure on invasive plants increases over time. In particular, more established populations have been shown to experience greater colonisation rates and attacks from local herbivores (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; but see 

), increased pathogen accumulation (

; 

; 

; 

) and increased negative soil feedback (

). These results imply that compared to range-edge populations, older populations might incur greater attacks even from generalist enemies. Such increased enemy load could be attributed to increases in the density and abundance of invasive plants in older populations, which could increase their attraction as hosts (

).
</p>
         <p>
Increased enemy pressure with time since introduction might re-select for increased allocation to defence traits in plants and particularly against generalist herbivores (Fig. 
1
). However, we are aware of only three studies to date that examined divergence in defence-related traits along invasion history gradients under common garden conditions. 

found that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Impatiens glandulifera
</tp:taxon-name>
plants from younger populations within the invasive range have reduced herbivore resistance against a generalist herbivore, coupled with reduced production of secondary defence compounds, to an extent similar to those of native populations. In contrast, 

found no effect of population age on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sapium sebiferum
</tp:taxon-name>
survival in common gardens exposed to local herbivores, even though herbivory levels increased in older populations. Similarly, 

found no effect of population age on herbivore defence against a generalist herbivore in the invasive plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Butomus umbellatus
</tp:taxon-name>
. Additional studies are, therefore, required to provide a general understanding of the effect of invasion history on the evolution of enemy defence in invasive plants. Moreover, such future studies should compare their relative allocation to defence against specialist vs. generalist enemies across populations with different invasion histories.
</p>
         <p>Divergence in growth traits</p>
         <p>
Invasive plants are commonly associated with increases in growth rate and size at their introduced compared to native range (

; 

). While such increases in growth-related traits can be a result of plastic responses to the environment, they might also be attributed to evolutionary change. The latter idea was proposed in the EICA hypothesis, which predicts that, due to an allocation trade-off, the decrease in defence experienced by plants at the introduced range is likely to result in an evolutionary increased allocation to traits related to growth (

; 

; 

). The same defence-growth trade-off might govern the evolution of growth traits within the introduced range of invasive plants. Specifically, if as suggested above, older and more established populations incur more enemy pressure that selects for increased investment in defence, these populations are also predicted to evolve decreased allocation to growth (Fig. 
1
).
</p>
         <p>
We found seven common garden studies that explicitly investigated the effect of invasion history on the evolution of plant growth and their results provide contrasting patterns. 

and 

provide support for the hypothesised negative effect of invasion history on plant size in studies on the invasive plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lonicera japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
, where plants from core populations within the introduced range were smaller than their conspecifics from edge populations. In contrast, 

found that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Plantago lanceolata
</tp:taxon-name>
plants from populations with a long invasion history were larger and more fecund compared to populations at the invasion front and similar results were shown by 

in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia artemisiifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
and 

in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Reynoutria japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
. Finally, 

found no effect of population age on biomass production of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Senecio inaequidens
</tp:taxon-name>
and 

similarly found no effect of distance to source population on the height of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gladiolus gueinzii
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
A lack of consistent results regarding the effect of invasion history on plant size might reflect the variety of selection pressures that likely act on such a fundamental life-history trait. For example, local climate across elevational and latitudinal gradients, as well as levels of primary productivity, might also change along invasion routes and exert strong selection on plant size and growth rate (

; 

). Thus, although the defence-growth trade-off might be key to the invasive success of many plant species, other factors can contribute to divergence in growth traits within the introduced range.
</p>
         <p>Divergence in traits associated with competitive ability</p>
         <p>Two hypotheses were suggested to account for the evolution of competitive ability in invasive plants and can be similarly applied for divergence in competitive ability within the introduced range. First, as suggested above and following the premise of the EICA hypothesis, older populations are predicted to undergo selection for increased defence associated with decreased allocation to growth and plant size. This decrease in size is, therefore, likely to be manifested in reduced competitive ability via resource competition in older and more established populations. In contrast, populations at the invasion front are predicted to undergo selection for decreased defence and increased size and competitive ability.</p>
         <p>
The second hypothesis suggested to explain the evolution of increased competitive ability in invasive plants is the novel weapons hypothesis (NWH: 

; 

). The NWH suggests that the production of toxic allelochemicals should be selected for in introduced populations due to its enhanced negative effects on 
naive
native competitors compared to co-evolved ones at the native range (

; 

; 

). Hence, this hypothesis proposes increased selection for competitive ability via interference competition in introduced populations. As for plant size and its derived competitive ability, the adaptive advantage of allelopathy might also decline with time since introduction, due to three selection pressures. First, the above-suggested need for increased production of defence compounds in older populations, might favour decreased production of allelochemicals due to a trade-off between these secondary compounds (

; 

). Secondly, in older and more established populations, plants might experience a shift from competition with heterospecific to conspecific neighbours, which are usually unaffected by conspecific allelochemicals (

). Thirdly, with time since introduction, co-occurring native species or their mutualist soil biota might also evolve resistance to the novel allelochemicals of the invasive plants (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Competitive ability can be attributed to two components that were suggested to be associated with different traits (

, 

). Competitive effect, which is the ability to suppress neighbours, can be attributed to rapid resource acquisition and growth or to allelopathy; while competitive response, which is the ability to withstand competition, can be attributed to tolerance of low resource levels or to neighbour avoidance (

; 

). Thus, the two aforementioned hypotheses regarding the evolution of decreased competitive ability with time since introduction via allocation to plant size or allelopathy, are mostly related to competitive effect (Fig. 
1
). In contrast, competitive response might be either not affected by these processes or even increase, if lower growth rate and smaller size correlate with stress tolerance (Fig. 
1
).
</p>
         <p>
Changes in competitive ability at the introduced range over time were examined in several studies. Some of these studies used an interspecific approach and examined the competitive effect of multiple invasive species with different residence times, using either common garden experiments (

; 

) or a meta-analysis approach (

) and their results reveal different patterns. For example, 

used a common garden experiment to study the competitive effect of 47 non-native 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
species on native plants and found that species with longer residence time had stronger competitive effects. However, this study referred to plants of varying non-native status rather than strictly invasive species and the variation in their competitive effect was better explained by this status (casual vs. established neophytes, archaeophytes or native species). In contrast, 

performed a meta-analysis of studies that examined the competitive effect of 36 invasive species with a known residence time at the collection sites and found that competitive effect of the plants decreases with time since introduction. The results of this study provide compelling evidence for temporal shifts in the evolution of competitive ability, because they are based on introduction time of the studied population rather than the entire invaded region. However, such an interspecific approach might be confounded due to variations in competitive ability amongst species, which can be avoided by comparing competitive ability of conspecifics with different residence time.
</p>
         <p>
A few common garden studies used an intraspecific approach and explored divergence in competitive ability amongst populations of the same species across invasion gradients. While some of these studies have attributed competitive ability to growth traits, such as plant height and biomass (see "Divergence in growth traits" above), we found only six studies that have explicitly examined divergence in competitive ability and all compared competitive effects on the performance of neighbours or the production of allelochemicals. 

and 

provide support to the predicted decrease in competitive effect with invasion age, showing that the production of allelochemicals in invasive 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alliaria petiolata
</tp:taxon-name>
declines in older populations. Similarly, 

found that invasive 
<tp:taxon-name>
Solidago canadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
plants from older populations had a lower competitive effect on native species and a greater competitive response to them, although these interactions depended on plant-soil feedbacks, suggesting that soil biota has an important role in these interactions. 

also found a reduced competitive effect in older 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lonicera japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
populations under competition with conspecifics. In contrast, 

found that the competitive effect of the invasive vine 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mikania micrantha
</tp:taxon-name>
in intraspecific competition is higher in more established core populations, while 

found no effect of population age on allelopathic ability of invasive 
<tp:taxon-name>
Impatiens glandulifera
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The lack of consistent results for the effect of invasion history on the competitive ability of the studied plants might be attributed to variations in competitive environments experienced by these plants. For example, as suggested above, invasive plants often experience a shift from inter- to intraspecific competition with time since introduction, which could select for different competitive strategies. Indeed, in this review, the three studies whose results support the predicted decrease in competitive effect used heterospecific neighbours, while a study that employed conspecific competitors found the opposite trend (

). Further studies are, therefore, needed to differentiate between the effect of invasion history on inter- vs. intraspecific competitive ability.
</p>
         <p>Divergence in dispersal ability</p>
         <p>
As for other invasion-promoting traits, evolution of traits related to dispersal ability might also take place between different invasion stages within the introduced range. The most common hypothesis in this regard proposes that, during range expansion, higher dispersal ability is likely to be selected for in individuals arriving at the invasion front compared to core populations (

; 

) (Fig. 
1
).
</p>
         <p>
The notion that dispersal ability should be selected for at range edges of invasive species has been suggested in several theoretical models (

; 

; 

) and supported by several studies on invasive animal species (e.g. 

; 

; 

; 

). However, evolutionary shifts in dispersal ability at range edges of invasive plants have been relatively less studied, of which we are aware of only two studies that were conducted with seeds collected from plants grown under common garden conditions. These studies, by 

and 

, provide support for increased dispersal ability (i.e. increased investment in seed pappus) at the invasion front of the invasive plants 
<tp:taxon-name>
Senecio inaequidens
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mikania micrantha
</tp:taxon-name>
, respectively. A few additional studies examined dispersal ability in seeds that were collected directly from field populations and not from plants growing under common garden conditions, showing similar results (

; 

; but see 

).
</p>
         <p>In summary, accumulating evidence provides support for different ways in which invasion-promoting traits such as defence, growth, competitive ability and dispersal might evolve in the introduced range over time. However, our review of the studies did not reveal consistent directions in divergence for most of the studied traits, which could be attributed to other selection pressures that might vary along invasion gradients. Moreover, existing studies that have explicitly explored trait divergence along gradients of invasion history are still very few, ranging from two to seven studies per trait, thus precluding our ability to reach generalised conclusions and highlighting the need for further studies on the subject. The aim of the following meta-analysis is to provide a more general overview on the subject.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿meta-analysis of trait divergence with invasion history">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Meta-analysis of trait divergence with invasion history</p>
         <p>Studies that examine divergence in plant characteristics with residence time often vary in the specific traits and the methodology used to measure them, as well as the way residence time is evaluated and compared across populations. For example, different studies used either time of introduction or distance from core population(s) to estimate chronosequence effects. Therefore, to provide a more general overview of current knowledge on trait divergence with time, we employed a meta-analysis approach that synthesises published literature on the subject. However, as apparent from the literature review above, only very few studies compared trait variations of invasive populations across invasion gradients and even fewer compared these traits under common garden conditions, rendering the data insufficient from which to draw conclusions. To tackle this issue, we employed an additional approach in our meta-analysis, whereby we analysed data from common garden experiments that measured invasion-promoting traits across several populations and used information on the age of these populations from additional sources.</p>
         <p>
Using the two approaches, we asked whether invasion-promoting traits, including herbivore defence (in general or against generalist or specialist species if known), plant growth, competitive ability (effect and response) and dispersal ability, change with residence time across populations of the same invasive plant species. In addition, we asked whether such an overall change has a similar direction within or across traits, corresponding to the predictions outlined above, including an increase in defence, particularly against generalist herbivores; and a decrease in growth, competitive ability, particularly competitive effect, and dispersal ability (Fig. 
1
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Methods</p>
         <p>Literature search</p>
         <p>To test for directional changes in the different traits along the invasion-history gradient, we used two literature review procedures. In the first procedure, we searched for studies explicitly investigating divergence in plant characteristics along invasion gradients at the introduced range, which included information on population ages. The literature was searched using two databases, Web of Science Core Collection (WOS) and Google Scholar. We first screened the literature in WOS (last accessed on 17 January 2023), using the search terms (chronosequence OR time-since-introduction OR invasion-history OR residence-time OR range-expansion OR colonization-history OR introduction-history) AND (plant*) AND (invasi*). We then complemented our search and screened the literature in Google Scholar (last accessed on 6 July 2022), using similar search terms.</p>
         <p>Papers selected for the analysis had to meet the following criteria: (1) the study aimed to test the relationship between residence time of an invasive plant and at least one of the following traits: defence against herbivores (measured as, for example, the inverse of leaf damage or herbivore mass following feeding or the production of defence metabolites), plant growth (e.g. plant biomass or height), competitive effect (e.g. effects on the performance of native species or allelopathy), competitive response (e.g. performance of the invasive species under competition with native species) and dispersal ability (e.g. the ratio between the size of dispersal structures such as wing or pappus and seed mass); (2) a gradient of invasion history was explicitly reported in the paper, either as differences in time (generally in years, although papers that reported residence times at large geographical scales, such as country were not included) or as a distance from source to expanding populations; (3) the study reported the results of controlled experiments under common garden conditions, thus ensuring that variations amongst populations in the studied traits are the result of genetic differentiations rather than plastic responses to environmental conditions at the site. A total of 24 cases from 19 papers were included after meeting these criteria.</p>
         <p>We carefully checked whether species were defined as invasive (rather than, for instance, alien or naturalised), based on the terminology given in the specific studies as well as in the CABI compendium digital library, invasive species section (https://www.cabidigitallibrary.org/product/qi). Moreover, in several cases, in which naturalised vs. invasive ranges of introduced species were compared, only the invasive range was used in our analysis.</p>
         <p>In the second literature review procedure, we searched for studies investigating variation in characteristics of invasive plants across populations under common garden conditions, but that did not explicitly include data on invasion history. Instead, these data were extracted from additional sources. The literature was searched using the Web of Science Core Collection (WOS) (last accessed on 18 January 2023), using the search terms (common garden OR greenhouse) AND (population OR accession) AND (plant*) AND (invasi*). Data on the location of the collection sites used in the different studies were extracted when possible. Invasion history of the populations was obtained when possible from additional papers that studied the same populations. For other cases, this information was extracted from additional sources such as the Global Biodiversity Information Facility database (https://www.gbif.org/) and CABI compendium digital library- invasive species section. Such information was extracted only for the same locations or for nearby locations at the scale of kilometres. In cases where information on the age of certain populations was missing, such populations were excluded from the analyses. Moreover, when information was given in the literature on the location of the first introduction of the invasive plant (given mostly at the local scale, for example, city), this location was used to estimate the distance from the source population with Google Earth Pro. In such cases, distance to source population was used instead of population age in the analysis. Papers selected for the analysis had to meet similar criteria as in the first literature review procedure, with the exception that information on population ages was not provided, but could be extracted from external sources, following which a gradient of invasion history was used to compare across sites.</p>
         <p>Using the two literature review procedures, a total of 79 cases from 62 papers were included after meeting our inclusion criteria in the final dataset of the meta-analysis (see Suppl. material 1: fig. S2 for more details on paper screening and selection process).</p>
         <p>Data analysis</p>
         <p>Data on the relationship between invasion history (population age or distance from source population) and the studied traits were extracted for each of the selected study cases. When source data were not available, the data were extracted from figures using the software GetData Graph Digitizer ver. 2.26 (http://getdata-graph-digitizer.com). In studies where several treatments were applied (e.g. water or nutrients addition or different disturbance levels), only a subset of the data, representing standardised controlled conditions, was used, such as high water availability (see Suppl. material 1: table S1 for details on specific studies).</p>
         <p>As considerable variation could be found amongst studies in the ranges of ages or distances across the studies populations, both the invasion history and measured trait data were first transformed using z-standardisation (standardised by subtracting the mean from each value and dividing by the standard deviation). A linear regression was then performed between the measured trait values and population age/distance. The standardised slope of the regression (β) was taken as the estimated effect size and the variance of the estimate of the standardised slope (SE squared) was taken as the estimated sampling variance (see Suppl. material 1: table S1). When other geographic variables were provided for the populations, such as elevation or mean annual temperature, the estimated standardised slope and variance were generated using linear model or linear mixed model analyses, with these variables as covariates (see Suppl. material 1: table S1).</p>
         <p>
The effect of invasion history on overall trait divergence (regardless of its direction) was examined with the absolute value of the estimated standardised slope (|β|), while the effect on directional changes in traits was examined with the standardised slope (β) as an effect size. For both meta-analyses, a random-effects model was used in order to combine the estimated effect sizes from the different studies. Such random-effects models allow for both variation of effect sizes amongst studies and sampling variation within studies (

). In order to estimate model parameters, a Restricted Maximum Likelihood (REML) approach was used. In order to determine means and confidence intervals for the different trait categories, trait category was used as a moderator in the models. As some studies used the same invasive plant species or different traits were sometimes measured in the same study (see Suppl. material 1: table S1), study as well as species identity were also included as random factors in the models. Effect sizes were considered significant if the 95% confidence intervals did not overlap zero. Meta-analyses were performed using the METAFOR package v.4.4 (

) in R-Studio v.2023.9.1.494 (

) and R (

).
</p>
         <p>Effects of type of study and origin of information on effect sizes</p>
         <p>
Study cases selected for the meta-analyses included information on invasion history data extracted from different sources, i.e. reported in papers (n = 36 cases) or estimated from external databases (n = 43). In addition, invasion history was measured in two ways, i.e. residence time (n = 65) or distance from source populations (n = 14) (Suppl. material 1: table S1). A meta-regression model was, therefore, conducted to assess the effect of these moderators on the magnitude of effect sizes. Here, a random-effects meta-regression was performed, in which data origin and type of study were served as moderators, study as well as species identity were included as random factors and an REML approach was employed to estimate model parameters. To interpret the significance of the chosen moderators, Qm statistics was used to test the extent of heterogeneity explained by the moderators. The meta-regression was performed using the METAFOR package v.4.4 (

) in R-Studio v.2023.09.1.494 (

) and R (

).
</p>
         <p>Publication bias analysis</p>
         <p>
The magnitude and significance of effect sizes may affect the publication and/or visibility rates of studies (e.g. based on the impact factor of journals) (

). To test for a possible publication bias in cases where the overall effect sizes in our meta-analyses were found to be significant, several approaches were used. First, we tested for temporal publication bias, examining a potential correlation between effect sizes and publication year. Additionally, we checked for a potential correlation between effect sizes and the 
journal's
impact factor at the year of publication. We also tested for the possibility that differences in age and distance ranges amongst studies could influence effect sizes. To that end, an LMM analysis was used, in which publication year, 
journal's
impact factor and age/distance ranges per study served as the independent variables and study identity and the invasive plant species served as random factors. Finally, we estimated the fail-safe numbers using the Rosenberg method (

), which indicates the number of additional studies with effect size of 0 needed to reduce the significance level of the observed average effect size to 
α
= 0.05. This analysis was conducted using the Fail-Safe Number Calculator software (https://www.rosenberglab.net/Rosenberg2005FailSafe.html). Statistical analyses, unless indicated otherwise, were performed using JMP Pro 17.1 (SAS Inst. Inc.).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Meta-analysis results</p>
         <p>
A total of 79 observations from 62 studies were included in our meta-analysis after meeting our criteria (Suppl. material 1: table S1). Population age in these studies ranges between 0 and 230 years and distance from source to peripheral populations ranges between 0 and 1000 km (Suppl. material 1: table S1). Overall, invasive species exhibited divergence in the studied traits over time, when averaged across traits (
p
&lt;0.001, Fig. 
2A
). This overall change is also shown for traits related to defence (
p
&lt;0.001) and defence against generalists (
p
&lt;0.007), growth (
p
&lt;0.001), dispersal ability (
p
= 0.023), overall competitive ability (
p
&lt;0.001) and competitive effect (
p
&lt;0.001), but not for defence against specialists (
p
= 0.146) or competitive response (
p
= 0.363) (Fig. 
2A
).
</p>
         <p>
In contrast to the overall trait divergence, the direction of change was not affected by residence time for most trait categories, including overall defence (
p
= 0.135), competitive ability (
p
= 0.95) or dispersal ability (
p
= 0.105) (Fig. 
2B
). However, plant growth increased with residence time (estimated slope 
+/-
SE = 0.187 
+/-
0.057; 
p
= 0.001; Fig. 
2B
).
</p>
         <p>Effects of type of study and origin of information on effect sizes</p>
         <p>
The meta-regression results indicate no significant effect of the two moderators on absolute effect sizes (QM = 3.193, 
p
= 0.203, residual heterogeneity QE = 162.94, 
p
&lt;0.001). Specifically, there were no significant differences in absolute effect size between the two types of study (residence time: mean 
+/-
SE = 0.272 
+/-
0.041; distance: mean 
+/-
SE = 0.334 
+/-
0.084, 
p
= 0.48; Suppl. material 1: fig. S3). Yet, a non-significant trend was found for the origin of data, according to which absolute effect size values of data reported in papers was slightly higher than data estimated using external databases (reported in papers: mean 
+/-
SE = 0.369 
+/-
0.085; estimated from external sources: mean 
+/-
SE = 0.247 
+/-
0.097, 
p
= 0.075; Suppl. material 1: fig. S3).
</p>
         <p>Publication bias</p>
         <p>
The chosen studies were published between the years 1994-2022. When testing for temporal bias, publication year had no effect on absolute effect size (LMM results: slope 
+/-
SE = 0.0038 
+/-
0.0058, 
p
= 0.51). Nevertheless, a significant effect of the 
journal's
impact factor was found on absolute effect size, according to which studies with 
lower
absolute effect sizes were published in higher impact journals (LMM results: slope 
+/-
SE = -0.039 
+/-
0.017, 
p
= 0.039; Suppl. material 1: fig. S4A). Moreover, a positive correlation was found between the 
journal's
impact factor and the 
study's
total sample size (
Pearson's
correlation (log-log scale): r = 0.539, 
p
&lt;0.001; Suppl. material 1: fig. S4B). In addition, when time/distance ranges per study was considered, no significant effect of differences in ranges on absolute effect size was observed (LMM results (log range): slope (
+/-
SE) = 0.036 
+/-
0.076, 
p
= 0.63). Finally, the estimated 
Rosenberg's
fail-safe number (i.e. additional number of studies with an average effect size of 0 needed to reduce the significance level of the observed average effect size to 
α
= 0.05) was 4767, suggesting our results of overall absolute effect size are robust against possible publication bias.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿discussion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Discussion</p>
         <p>Our meta-analysis results reveal overall divergence in invasion-promoting traits with residence time. This divergence was exhibited for all traits, except for competitive response and defence against specialists, which could be attributed to the lower sample sizes of studies that examined these traits in the meta-analysis. However, both our review and meta-analysis results show that, for most studied traits, their divergence lacks a consistent direction.</p>
         <p>
The only trait for which our meta-analysis revealed a directional shift was plant growth. However, in contrast with our prediction, growth-related traits, such as height and vegetative biomass, increased over time. Invasive plants in older and more established populations were predicted to undergo selection for decreased allocation to growth and competitive ability compared to populations at the invasion front, due an increase in herbivore and pathogen pressure and an allocation trade-off with defence traits. However, of the seven studies explored in our review, only two studies, conducted with the same species (
<tp:taxon-name>
Lonicera japonica
</tp:taxon-name>
), provide support for this prediction (

; 

). An increased allocation to size in older and more established populations might be driven by increased competition pressure. Specifically, plants in these populations might experience shifts from interspecific competition with diverse neighbours to intraspecific competition with neighbours of similar resource requirements (

; 

), which might be stronger and require greater allocation to growth (

). However, the increase in growth with residence time did not translate to increased competitive ability in the meta-analysis results, which might be attributed to the fact that most invasion history studies tested for inter- rather than intraspecific competition (but see 

; 

). Studies that compare competitive ability with heterospecific vs. conspecific neighbours across invasion history gradients are, thus, needed to examine this hypothesis.
</p>
         <p>
The lack of significant consistent directional divergence in most of the traits tested in our meta-analysis could be attributed to varying selection pressures that might be context-dependent and vary with habitat type and resilience of the native communities. Moreover, some gradients of invasion history might take place along geographical gradients, where variation in invasion history could be confounded with other factors, such as changes in ambient temperatures, season length and primary productivity across sites, which could affect the observed patterns (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

). Several studies have shown that local climates can play an important role in the rapid adaptation of invasive plants and their range expansion (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). For example, 

analysed data from experiments that examined trait divergence of invasive plant species from native and introduced populations and showed that such divergence is highly affected by geographic clines. While we incorporated climatic factors in the analyses whenever available, this was not the case for most of the chosen studies. If such climatic variables can result in divergence in invasion-promoting traits, they may confound divergence due to invasion history. In addition, the evolution of invasive populations might be affected by additional factors whose strength might change with time. For example, as suggested above, while selection pressures that promote greater plant size and competitive ability, such as enemy release, could attenuate with time since introduction, strong competitive ability might still be selected for in older populations if the effect of intraspecific competition is much stronger than that of native heterospecifics.
</p>
         <p>
In addition to different context-dependent selection pressures, the lack of consistent directional change with time since introduction can be attributed to neutral non-adaptive evolutionary processes that might have taken place within the introduced range of some invasive species, such as founder effects and genetic drift. For example, multiple introductions could involve different samplings from the native range, resulting in repeated founder effects of populations with different invasion histories (

; 

; 

; 

). Similarly, successive founder events along invasion routes can result in non-adaptive (or even mal-adaptive) differentiation (

; 

). In order to discern between evolution due to selection vs. neutral processes along gradients of invasion history, further studies should, therefore, use genetic information of these populations and/or employ reciprocal transplant experiments that test for local adaptations along such gradients (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Another explanation for a lack of directional effects of residence time found in this meta-analysis is that, unlike our predictions, trait evolution might follow a non-linear trajectory. For example, recently established populations at the invasion front might exhibit initial lags in their responses to selection pressures if they are derived from different source populations of different ages or due to factors such as small population sizes. Moreover, evolution of core populations might decelerate if the intensity of selective pressures they experience, such as herbivore load, attenuate with time (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Finally, the lack of a clear directional change might result from the small number of studies on the subject in some of the categories. This is particularly true for traits related to dispersal ability for which we were able to find only three studies that compared dispersal ability across different populations in the introduced range that used common garden experiments. Several other studies have examined the effect of residence time on dispersal ability under field conditions, providing support for such divergence (

; 

). However, additional studies that incorporate the effect of residence time on this trait under common garden conditions could provide valuable information and expand the empirical basis and knowledge on its impact on the evolution of invasive plants.
</p>
         <p>
In this review and meta-analysis, we looked at four main categories of invasion-promoting traits for which temporal changes are predicted within the introduced range, including defence, growth, competitive ability and dispersal ability. Yet, additional traits that could contribute to the invasive success of plants might be affected by time since introduction. For example, phenotypic plasticity has been suggested to evolve at the introduced range and facilitate plant invasion in varying habitats and climates (

; 

). Similarly, selection pressures that might favour phenotypic plasticity are likely to be stronger at the invasion front, where invasive plants encounter novel environmental conditions (

; 

). However, while several studies have examined changes in plasticity in response to range shifts (

), only very few looked at such changes in plasticity along gradients of invasion history (

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿conclusions">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Conclusions</p>
         <p>Adding a temporal dimension to studies on traits of invasive plants is challenging because it entails knowledge on the timing of population establishment or distance to known core populations. However, the potential for rapid evolution of invasive plants within their introduced range across different invasion stages provides a unique opportunity to study fundamental questions related to adaptive divergence in plant traits. Here, we reviewed several hypotheses regarding divergence in invasion-promoting traits, which propose that the effect of varying selection pressures might attenuate with time since introduction. However, while our meta-analysis results reveal a general indication for the evolution of invasive plants with residence time, they do not provide support for a consistent directional divergence, except for growth. Here and in contrast with our prediction, growth parameters were found to increase with invasion history, which might reflect greater competition pressure in these populations.</p>
         <p>The general temporal effect found in this study highlights the need to take into account the potential confounding effect of population age when sampling populations to explore attributes of invasive plants (e.g. comparing trait evolution between native and invasive ranges) and particularly when evaluating the long-term effects of invasive plants on native communities and ecosystems. Moreover, the increased size of invasive plants in older populations found in this study, suggests that, although some selection pressures that drive the evolution of invasiveness, such as enemy release, can decrease with time, their dominance and effects on the native communities and ecosystems in the introduced range might not attenuate. Studies that further explore both trait divergence and community effects across invasion routes in the introduced range will be crucial for understanding the long-term dynamics between invasive plants and their recipient native communities.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>We are grateful to Maud Bernard-Verdier, Robert Colautti, Wayne Dawson and several anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments and suggestions on earlier versions of this manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Abhilasha, D
, 
Quintana, N
, 
Vivanco, J
, 
Joshi, J
, 
2008
. 
Do allelopathic compounds in invasive Solidago canadensis sl restrain the native European flora? Journal of Ecology 96(5): 993-1001.
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2745.2008.01413.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Agrawal, AA
, 
Lau, JA
, 

Hambaeck
, PA

, 
2006
. 
Community heterogeneity and the evolution of interactions between plants and insect herbivores.
The Quarterly Review of Biology
81
(
4
): 
349 - 376
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1086/511529
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Amsellem, L
, 
Noyer, J-L
, 
Le Bourgeois, T
, 
Hossaert-Mckey, M
, 
2000
. 

Comparison of genetic diversity of the invasive weed 

Rubus alceifolius

Poir.(
Rosaceae
) in its native range and in areas of introduction, using amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) markers.

Molecular Ecology
9
(
4
): 
443 - 455
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-294x.2000.00876.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baker, HG
, 
1965
. 
Characteristics and modes of origin of weeds. The Genetics of colonizing species: Proceedings of the first international union of biological sciences symposia on general biology. Academic Press, 147-172.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bartle, K
, 
Moles, AT
, 
Bonser, SP
, 
2013
. 

No evidence for rapid evolution of seed dispersal ability in range edge populations of the invasive species 

Senecio madagascariensis

.

Austral Ecology
38
(
8
): 
915 - 920
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/aec.12032
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Blossey, B
, 
Notzold, R
, 
1995
. 
Evolution of increased competitive ability in invasive nonindigenous plants: A hypothesis.
Journal of Ecology
83
(
5
): 
887 - 889
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.2307/2261425
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Blumenthal, DM
, 
Hufbauer, RA
, 
2007
. 
Increased plant size in exotic populations: A common-garden test with 14 invasive species.
Ecology
88
(
11
): 
2758 - 2765
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1890/06-2115.1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bossdorf, O
, 
Auge, H
, 
Lafuma, L
, 
Rogers, WE
, 
Siemann, E
, 
Prati, D
, 
2005
. 
Phenotypic and genetic differentiation between native and introduced plant populations.
Oecologia
144
(
1
): 
1 - 11
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-005-0070-z
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Braendle
, M

, 

Kuehn
, I

, 
Klotz, S
, 
Belle, C
, 
Brandl, R
, 
2008
. 
Species richness of herbivores on exotic host plants increases with time since introduction of the host.
Diversity &amp; Distributions
14
(
6
): 
905 - 912
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1472-4642.2008.00511.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bucharova, A
, 
Van Kleunen, M
, 
2009
. 
Introduction history and species characteristics partly explain naturalization success of North American woody species in Europe.
Journal of Ecology
97
(
2
): 
230 - 238
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2745.2008.01469.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Buswell, JM
, 
Moles, AT
, 
Hartley, S
, 
2011
. 
Is rapid evolution common in introduced plant species? Journal of Ecology 99(1): 214-224.
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2745.2010.01759.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cahill, Jr JF
, 
Kembel, SW
, 
Gustafson, DJ
, 
2005
. 

Differential genetic influences on competitive effect and response in 

Arabidopsis thaliana

.

Journal of Ecology
93
(
5
): 
958 - 967
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2745.2005.01013.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Callaway, RM
, 
Aschehoug, ET
, 
2000
. 
Invasive plants versus their new and old neighbors: A mechanism for exotic invasion.
Science
290
(
5491
): 
521 - 523
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1126/science.290.5491.521
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Callaway, RM
, 
Ridenour, WM
, 
2004
. 
Novel weapons: Invasive success and the evolution of increased competitive ability. Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment 2(8): 436-443.
https://doi.org/10.1890/1540-9295(2004)002[0436:NWISAT]2.0.CO;2
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Callaway, RM
, 
Ridenour, WM
, 
Laboski, T
, 
Weir, T
, 
Vivanco, JM
, 
2005
. 
Natural selection for resistance to the allelopathic effects of invasive plants.
Journal of Ecology
93
(
3
): 
576 - 583
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2745.2005.00994.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Carpenter, D
, 
Cappuccino, N
, 
2005
. 
Herbivory, time since introduction and the invasiveness of exotic plants.
Journal of Ecology
93
(
2
): 
315 - 321
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2745.2005.00973.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>CBD (2000) Decision V/8. Alien species that threaten ecosystems, habitats or species. UNEP/CBD/COP/5/8. Secretariat of the Convention on Biological Diversity Nairobi, Kenya.</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Colautti, RI
, 
Barrett, SC
, 
2013
. 
Rapid adaptation to climate facilitates range expansion of an invasive plant.
Science
342
(
6156
): 
364 - 366
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1242121
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Colautti, RI
, 
Lau, JA
, 
2016
. 
Contemporary evolution during invasion: evidence for differentiation, natural selection, and local adaptation.
In: 
Barrett, SCH
, 
Colautti, RI
, 
Dlugosch, KM
, 
Rieseberg, LH
, Eds., 
Invasion Genetics: The Baker and Stebbins Legacy.
John Wiley &amp; Sons
: 
101 - 121
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119072799.ch6
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Colautti, RI
, 
Maron, JL
, 
Barrett, SC
, 
2009
. 
Common garden comparisons of native and introduced plant populations: Latitudinal clines can obscure evolutionary inferences.
Evolutionary Applications
2
(
2
): 
187 - 199
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1752-4571.2008.00053.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Colautti, RI
, 
Eckert, CG
, 
Barrett, SC
, 
2010
. 
Evolutionary constraints on adaptive evolution during range expansion in an invasive plant. Proceedings.
Biological Sciences
277
(
1689
): 
1799 - 1806
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2009.2231
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Colomer-Ventura, F
, 

Martinez-Vilalta
, J

, 
Zuccarini, P
, 

Escola
, A

, 
Armengot, L
, 
Castells, E
, 
2015
. 
Contemporary evolution of an invasive plant is associated with climate but not with herbivory.
Functional Ecology
29
(
11
): 
1475 - 1485
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2435.12463
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Crystal-Ornelas, R
, 
Lockwood, JL
, 
2020
. 
Cumulative meta-analysis identifies declining but negative impacts of invasive species on richness after 20 yr. Ecology 101(8): e03082.
https://doi.org/10.1002/ecy.3082
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Davidson, AM
, 
Jennions, M
, 
Nicotra, AB
, 
2011
. 
Do invasive species show higher phenotypic plasticity than native species and, if so, is it adaptive? A meta-analysis.
Ecology Letters
14
(
4
): 
419 - 431
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1461-0248.2011.01596.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Diez, JM
, 
Dickie, I
, 
Edwards, G
, 
Hulme, PE
, 
Sullivan, JJ
, 
Duncan, RP
, 
2010
. 
Negative soil feedbacks accumulate over time for non-native plant species.
Ecology Letters
13
(
7
): 
803 - 809
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1461-0248.2010.01474.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dlugosch, KM
, 
Parker, IM
, 
2008
. 
Founding events in species invasions: Genetic variation, adaptive evolution, and the role of multiple introductions.
Molecular Ecology
17
(
1
): 
431 - 449
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2007.03538.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Dostal
, P

, 

Muellerova
, J

, 

Pysek
, P

, 
Pergl, J
, 

Klinerova
, T

, 
2013
. 
The impact of an invasive plant changes over time.
Ecology Letters
16
(
10
): 
1277 - 1284
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/ele.12166
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Evans, GA
, 
Kilkenny, FF
, 
Galloway, LF
, 
2013
. 

Evolution of competitive ability within 

Lonicera japonica

's invaded range.

International Journal of Plant Sciences
174
(
5
): 
740 - 748
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1086/669928
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Felker-Quinn, E
, 
Schweitzer, JA
, 
Bailey, JK
, 
2013
. 
Meta-analysis reveals evolution in invasive plant species but little support for Evolution of Increased Competitive Ability (EICA).
Ecology and Evolution
3
(
3
): 
739 - 751
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.488
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fenesi, A
, 

Botta-Dukat
, Z

, 
2012
. 
Phenotypic divergences induced by different residence time in invasive common ragweeds.
Journal of Plant Ecology
5
(
2
): 
174 - 181
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1093/jpe/rtr022
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Flory, SL
, 
Clay, K
, 
2013
. 
Pathogen accumulation and long-term dynamics of plant invasions.
Journal of Ecology
101
(
3
): 
607 - 613
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.12078
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Franks, SJ
, 
Pratt, PD
, 
Dray, FA
, 
Simms, EL
, 
2008
. 
Selection on herbivory resistance and growth rate in an invasive plant.
American Naturalist
171
(
5
): 
678 - 691
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1086/587078
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Goldberg, DE
, 
1990
. 
Components of resource competition in plant communities.
In: 
Grace, JB
, 
Tilman, D
, Eds., 
Perspectives on plant competition.
Academic Press
: 
27 - 49
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-294452-9.50007-2
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Goldberg, DE
, 
1996
. 
Competitive ability: definitions, contingency and correlated traits.
Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London, Series B: Biological Sciences
351
(
1345
): 
1377 - 1385
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.1996.0121
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Goldberg, DE
, 
Landa, K
, 
1991
. 
Competitive effect and response: hierarchies and correlated traits in the early stages of competition.
Journal of Ecology
79
(
4
): 
1013 - 1030
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.2307/2261095
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gruntman, M
, 
Segev, U
, 
Glauser, G
, 

Tielboerger
, K

, 
2017
. 
Evolution of plant defences along an invasion chronosequence: Defence is lost due to enemy release-but not forever.
Journal of Ecology
105
(
1
): 
255 - 264
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.12660
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Haider, S
, 
Palm, S
, 
Bruelheide, H
, 
de Villemereuil, P
, 
Menzel, A
, 
Lachmuth, S
, 
2022
. 
Disturbance and indirect effects of climate warming support a plant invader in mountains. Oikos 2022(4): e08783.
https://doi.org/10.1111/oik.08783
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hargreaves, AL
, 
Eckert, CG
, 
2014
. 
Evolution of dispersal and mating systems along geographic gradients: Implications for shifting ranges.
Functional Ecology
28
(
1
): 
5 - 21
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2435.12170
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harms, NE
, 
Walter, DJ
, 
2021
. 
Influence of Butomus umbellatus L. lineage and age on leaf chemistry and performance of a generalist caterpillar. Aquatic Botany 172: 103391.
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquabot.2021.103391
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harvey, KJ
, 
Nipperess, DA
, 
Britton, DR
, 
Hughes, L
, 
2013
. 
Does time since introduction influence enemy release of an invasive weed? Oecologia 173(2): 493-506.
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-013-2633-8
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hawkes, CV
, 
2007
. 
Are invaders moving targets? The generality and persistence of advantages in size, reproduction, and enemy release in invasive plant species with time since introduction.
American Naturalist
170
(
6
): 
832 - 843
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1086/522842
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hierro, JL
, 

Eren, 
Oe

, 
Montesinos, D
, 
Andonian, K
, 
Kethsuriani, L
, 

Oezcan
, R

, 
Diaconu, A
, 

Toeroek
, K

, 
Cavieres, L
, 
French, K
, 
2020
. 
Increments in weed seed size track global range expansion and contribute to colonization in a non-native region.
Biological Invasions
22
(
3
): 
969 - 982
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10530-019-02137-z
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hodgins, KA
, 
Bock, DG
, 
Rieseberg, LH
, 
2018
. 
Trait evolution in invasive species.
Annual Plant Reviews
1
: 
459 - 496
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119312994.apr0643
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, F
, 
Peng, S
, 
2016
. 

Intraspecific competitive ability declines towards the edge of the expanding range of the invasive vine 

Mikania micrantha

.

Oecologia
181
(
1
): 
115 - 123
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-015-3526-9
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, F
, 
Peng, S
, 
Chen, B
, 
Liao, H
, 
Huang, Q
, 
Lin, Z
, 
Liu, G
, 
2015
. 

Rapid evolution of dispersal-related traits during range expansion of an invasive vine 

Mikania micrantha

.

Oikos
124
(
8
): 
1023 - 1030
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/oik.01820
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, F
, 
Huang, Q
, 
Gan, X
, 
Zhang, W
, 
Guo, Y
, 
Huang, Y
, 
2021
. 
Shift in competitive ability mediated by soil biota in an invasive plant.
Ecology and Evolution
11
(
23
): 
16693 - 16703
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.8287
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hughes, CL
, 
Hill, JK
, 
Dytham, C
, 
2003
. 
Evolutionary trade-offs between reproduction and dispersal in populations at expanding range boundaries. Proceedings of the Royal Society B, Biological Sciences 270: S147-S150.
https://doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2003.0049
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hulme, PE
, 
Bernard-Verdier, M
, 
2018
. 
Comparing traits of native and alien plants: Can we do better? Functional Ecology 32(1): 117-125.
https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2435.12982
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Iacarella, JC
, 
Mankiewicz, PS
, 
Ricciardi, A
, 
2015
. 
Negative competitive effects of invasive plants change with time since invasion.
Ecosphere
6
(
7
): 
1 - 14
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1890/ES15-00147.1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Inderjit,
, 
Wardle, DA
, 
Karban, R
, 
Callaway, RM
, 
2011
. 
The ecosystem and evolutionary contexts of allelopathy.
Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution
26
: 
655 - 662
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tree.2011.08.003
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Irimia, RE
, 
Lopes, SM
, 
Sotes, G
, 
Cavieres, LA
, 

Eren, 
Oe

, 
Lortie, CJ
, 
French, K
, 
Hierro, JL
, 
Rosche, C
, 
Callaway, RM
, 
Pinho e Melo, TMVD
, 
Montesinos, D
, 
2019
. 
Biogeographic differences in the allelopathy of leaf surface extracts of an invasive weed.
Biological Invasions
21
(
10
): 
3151 - 3168
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10530-019-02038-1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Joshi, J
, 
Vrieling, K
, 
2005
. 
The enemy release and EICA hypothesis revisited: Incorporating the fundamental difference between specialist and generalist herbivores.
Ecology Letters
8
(
7
): 
704 - 714
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1461-0248.2005.00769.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Keane, RM
, 
Crawley, MJ
, 
2002
. 
Exotic plant invasions and the enemy release hypothesis.
Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution
17
(
4
): 
164 - 170
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0169-5347(02)02499-0
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Keller, SR
, 
Sowell, DR
, 
Neiman, M
, 
Wolfe, LM
, 
Taylor, DR
, 
2009
. 
Adaptation and colonization history affect the evolution of clines in two introduced species.
The New Phytologist
183
(
3
): 
678 - 690
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02892.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kilkenny, FF
, 
Galloway, LF
, 
2013
. 
Adaptive divergence at the margin of an invaded range.
Evolution; International Journal of Organic Evolution
67
(
3
): 
722 - 731
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1558-5646.2012.01829.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kliber, A
, 
Eckert, CG
, 
2005
. 
Interaction between fournder effect and selection during biological invasion in an aquatic plant.
Evolution; International Journal of Organic Evolution
59
(
9
): 
1900 - 1913
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.0014-3820.2005.tb01060.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Koricheva, J
, 
Hayes, D
, 
2018
. 
The relative importance of plant intraspecific diversity in structuring arthropod communities: A meta-analysis.
Functional Ecology
32
(
7
): 
1704 - 1717
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2435.13062
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Koricheva, J
, 
Gurevitch, J
, 
Mengersen, K
, 
2013
. 
Handbook of meta-analysis in ecology and evolution.
Princeton University Press, Princeton and Oxford
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1515/9781400846184
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Kuehn
, P

, 
Ratier Backes, A
, 

Roemermann
, C

, 
Bruelheide, H
, 
Haider, S
, 
2021
. 
Contrasting patterns of intraspecific trait variability in native and non-native plant species along an elevational gradient on Tenerife, Canary Islands.
Annals of Botany
127
(
4
): 
565 - 576
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcaa067
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lande, R
, 
Arnold, SJ
, 
1983
. 
The measurement of selection on correlated characters.
Evolution; International Journal of Organic Evolution
37
(
6
): 
1210 - 1226
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.2307/2408842
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lang, PL
, 
Willems, FM
, 
Scheepens, J
, 
Burbano, HA
, 
Bossdorf, O
, 
2019
. 
Using herbaria to study global environmental change.
The New Phytologist
221
(
1
): 
110 - 122
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.15401
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lankau, RA
, 
2011
. 

Resistance and recovery of soil microbial communities in the face of 

Alliaria petiolata

invasions.

The New Phytologist
189
(
2
): 
536 - 548
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03481.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lankau, RA
, 
2012
. 
Interpopulation variation in allelopathic traits informs restoration of invaded landscapes.
Evolutionary Applications
5
(
3
): 
270 - 282
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1752-4571.2011.00218.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lankau, RA
, 
Nuzzo, V
, 
Spyreas, G
, 
Davis, AS
, 
2009
. 
Evolutionary limits ameliorate the negative impact of an invasive plant.
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America
106
(
36
): 
15362 - 15367
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0905446106
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, W
, 
Strong, DR
, 
Pennings, SC
, 
Zhang, Y
, 
2017
. 

Provenance-by-environment interaction of reproductive traits in the invasion of 

Spartina alterniflora

in China.

Ecology
98
(
6
): 
1591 - 1599
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ecy.1815
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lombaert, E
, 
Estoup, A
, 
Facon, B
, 
Joubard, B
, 

Gregoire
, JC

, 
Jannin, A
, 
Blin, A
, 
Guillemaud, T
, 
2014
. 

Rapid increase in dispersal during range expansion in the invasive ladybird 

Harmonia axyridis

.

Journal of Evolutionary Biology
27
(
3
): 
508 - 517
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jeb.12316
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Matesanz, S
, 
Gianoli, E
, 
Valladares, F
, 
2010
. 
Global change and the evolution of phenotypic plasticity in plants.
Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences
1206
(
1
): 
35 - 55
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05704.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Meineke, EK
, 
Davis, CC
, 
Davies, TJ
, 
2018
. 
The unrealized potential of herbaria for global change biology.
Ecological Monographs
88
(
4
): 
505 - 525
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ecm.1307
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mitchell, CE
, 
Blumenthal, D
, 

Jarosik
, V

, 
Puckett, EE
, 

Pysek
, P

, 
2010
. 

Controls on pathogen species richness in 
plants'
introduced and native ranges: Roles of residence time, range size and host traits.

Ecology Letters
13
(
12
): 
1525 - 1535
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1461-0248.2010.01543.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Monty, A
, 
Mahy, G
, 
2009
. 

Clinal differentiation during invasion: 

Senecio inaequidens

(
Asteraceae
) along altitudinal gradients in Europe.

Oecologia
159
(
2
): 
305 - 315
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-008-1228-2
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Monty, A
, 
Mahy, G
, 
2010
. 

Evolution of dispersal traits along an invasion route in the wind-dispersed 

Senecio inaequidens

(
Asteraceae
).

Oikos
119
(
10
): 
1563 - 1570
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0706.2010.17769.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moran, EV
, 
Alexander, JM
, 
2014
. 
Evolutionary responses to global change: Lessons from invasive species.
Ecology Letters
17
(
5
): 
637 - 649
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/ele.12262
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Mueller-Schaerer
, H

, 
Schaffner, U
, 
Steinger, T
, 
2004
. 
Evolution in invasive plants: Implications for biological control.
Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution
19
(
8
): 
417 - 422
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tree.2004.05.010
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

O'Donnell
, KL

, 
Pigliucci, M
, 
2010
. 

Selection dynamics in native and introduced 

Persicaria

species.

International Journal of Plant Sciences
171
(
5
): 
519 - 528
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1086/652012
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ochocki, BM
, 
Miller, TE
, 
2017
. 
Rapid evolution of dispersal ability makes biological invasions faster and more variable.
Nature Communications
8
(
1
): 
1 - 8
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms14315
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oduor, AM
, 
Adomako, MO
, 
Yuan, Y
, 
Li, JM
, 
2022
. 

Older populations of the invader 

Solidago canadensis

exhibit stronger positive plant-soil feedbacks and competitive ability in China.

American Journal of Botany
109
(
8
): 
1230 - 1241
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ajb2.16034
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Parker, IM
, 
Rodriguez, J
, 
Loik, ME
, 
2003
. 

An evolutionary approach to understanding the biology of invasions: Local adaptation and general-purpose genotypes in the weed 

Verbascum thapsus

.

Conservation Biology
17
(
1
): 
59 - 72
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1523-1739.2003.02019.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Phillips, BL
, 
Brown, GP
, 
Webb, JK
, 
Shine, R
, 
2006
. 
Invasion and the evolution of speed in toads.
Nature
439
(
7078
): 
803 - 803
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1038/439803a
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Phillips, BL
, 
Brown, GP
, 
Travis, JM
, 
Shine, R
, 
2008
. 

Reid's
paradox revisited: The evolution of dispersal kernels during range expansion. American Naturalist 172(S1): S34-S48.

https://doi.org/10.1086/588255
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
2023
.. 
http://www.posit.co/
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Prati, D
, 
Bossdorf, O
, 
2004
. 

Allelopathic inhibition of germination by 

Alliaria petiolata

(
Brassicaceae
).

American Journal of Botany
91
(
2
): 
285 - 288
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.3732/ajb.91.2.285
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Prentis, PJ
, 
Wilson, JR
, 
Dormontt, EE
, 
Richardson, DM
, 
Lowe, AJ
, 
2008
. 
Adaptive evolution in invasive species.
Trends in Plant Science
13
(
6
): 
288 - 294
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2008.03.004
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Pysek
, P

, 
Richardson, DM
, 
2008
. 
Traits associated with invasiveness in alien plants: Where do we stand?
In: 
Nentwig, W
, Ed., 
Biological Invasions.
Springer, Berlin
: 
97 - 125
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-540-36920-2_7
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Pysek
, P

, 
Manceur, AM
, 
Alba, C
, 
McGregor, KF
, 
Pergl, J
, 

Stajerova
, K

, 

Chytry
, M

, 
Danihelka, J
, 
Kartesz, J
, 

Klimesova
, J

, 

Lucanova
, M

, 

Moravcova
, L

, 
Nishino, M
, 

Sadlo
, J

, 
Suda, J
, 

Tichy
, L

, 

Kuehn
, I

, 
2015
. 
Naturalization of central European plants in North America: Species traits, habitats, propagule pressure, residence time.
Ecology
96
(
3
): 
762 - 774
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1890/14-1005.1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
2023
.. 
https://www.R-project.org/
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Richards, CL
, 
Bossdorf, O
, 
Muth, NZ
, 
Gurevitch, J
, 
Pigliucci, M
, 
2006
. 
Jack of all trades, master of some? On the role of phenotypic plasticity in plant invasions.
Ecology Letters
9
(
8
): 
981 - 993
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1461-0248.2006.00950.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Robinson, D
, 
Bogdanova, T
, 
Cohen, O
, 
Gruntman, M
, 
2023
. 
Trade-off between dispersal traits in a heterocarpic plant across its invasion route. American Journal of Botany 110(7): e16192.
https://doi.org/10.1002/ajb2.16192
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rosenberg, MS
, 
2005
. 
The file-drawer problem revisited: A general weighted method for calculating fail-safe numbers in meta-analysis.
Evolution; International Journal of Organic Evolution
59
(
2
): 
464 - 468
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.0014-3820.2005.tb01004.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rotter, MC
, 
Holeski, LM
, 
2018
. 
A meta-analysis of the evolution of increased competitive ability hypothesis: Genetic-based trait variation and herbivory resistance trade-offs.
Biological Invasions
20
(
9
): 
2647 - 2660
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10530-018-1724-1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sakai, AK
, 
Allendorf, FW
, 
Holt, JS
, 
Lodge, DM
, 
Molofsky, J
, 
With, KA
, 
Baughman, S
, 
Cabin, RJ
, 
Cohen, JE
, 
Ellstrand, NC
, 
McCauley, DE
, 

O'Neil
, P

, 
Parker, IM
, 
Thompson, JN
, 
Weller, SG
, 
2001
. 
The population biology of invasive species.
Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics
32
(
1
): 
305 - 332
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.32.081501.114037
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schlaepfer, DR
, 

Glaettli
, M

, 
Fischer, M
, 
van Kleunen, M
, 
2010
. 
A multi-species experiment in their native range indicates pre-adaptation of invasive alien plant species.
The New Phytologist
185
(
4
): 
1087 - 1099
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03114.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schultheis, EH
, 
Berardi, AE
, 
Lau, JA
, 
2015
. 
No release for the wicked: Enemy release is dynamic and not associated with invasiveness.
Ecology
96
(
9
): 
2446 - 2457
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1890/14-2158.1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sheppard, CS
, 
Brendel, MR
, 
2021
. 
Competitive ability of native and alien plants: Effects of residence time and invasion status.
NeoBiota
65
: 
47 - 69
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.3897/neobiota.65.63179
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sheppard, CS
, 
Schurr, FM
, 
2019
. 
Biotic resistance or introduction bias? Immigrant plant performance decreases with residence times over millennia.
Global Ecology and Biogeography
28
(
2
): 
222 - 237
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/geb.12844
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Siemann, E
, 
Rogers, WE
, 
Dewalt, SJ
, 
2006
. 
Rapid adaptation of insect herbivores to an invasive plant.
Proceedings of the Royal Society B, Biological Sciences
273
(
1602
): 
2763 - 2769
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2006.3644
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stastny, M
, 
Sargent, R
, 
2017
. 
Evidence for rapid evolutionary change in an invasive plant in response to biological control.
Journal of Evolutionary Biology
30
(
5
): 
1042 - 1052
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jeb.13078
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Strayer, DL
, 
Eviner, VT
, 
Jeschke, JM
, 
Pace, ML
, 
2006
. 
Understanding the long-term effects of species invasions.
Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution
21
(
11
): 
645 - 651
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tree.2006.07.007
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tabassum, S
, 
Leishman, MR
, 
2018
. 
Have your cake and eat it too: Greater dispersal ability and faster germination towards range edges of an invasive plant species in eastern Australia.
Biological Invasions
20
(
5
): 
1199 - 1210
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10530-017-1620-0
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Thebaud
, C

, 
Simberloff, D
, 
2001
. 
Are plants really larger in their introduced ranges? American Naturalist 157(2): 231-236.
https://doi.org/10.1086/318635
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Travis, JM
, 
Dytham, C
, 
2002
. 
Dispersal evolution during invasions.
Evolutionary Ecology Research
4
: 
1119 - 1129
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Travis, JM
, 
Mustin, K
, 
Benton, TG
, 
Dytham, C
, 
2009
. 
Accelerating invasion rates result from the evolution of density-dependent dispersal.
Journal of Theoretical Biology
259
(
1
): 
151 - 158
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2009.03.008
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
van Boheemen, LA
, 
Atwater, DZ
, 
Hodgins, KA
, 
2019
. 
Rapid and repeated local adaptation to climate in an invasive plant.
The New Phytologist
222
(
1
): 
614 - 627
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.15564
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Van Kleunen, M
, 
Weber, E
, 
Fischer, M
, 
2010
. 
A meta-analysis of trait differences between invasive and non-invasive plant species.
Ecology Letters
13
(
2
): 
235 - 245
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1461-0248.2009.01418.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vandepitte, K
, 
De Meyer, T
, 
Helsen, K
, 
Van Acker, K
, 

Roldan-Ruiz
, I

, 
Mergeay, J
, 
Honnay, O
, 
2014
. 
Rapid genetic adaptation precedes the spread of an exotic plant species.
Molecular Ecology
23
(
9
): 
2157 - 2164
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.12683
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
VanWallendael, A
, 
Hamann, E
, 
Franks, SJ
, 
2018
. 

Evidence for plasticity, but not local adaptation, in invasive Japanese knotweed (

Reynoutria japonica

) in North America.

Evolutionary Ecology
32
(
4
): 
395 - 410
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10682-018-9942-7
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Viechtbauer, W
, 
2010
. 
Conducting meta-analyses in R with the metafor package.
Journal of Statistical Software
36
(
3
): 
1 - 48
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v036.i03
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vila, M
, 
Weiner, J
, 
2004
. 
Are invasive plant species better competitors than native plant species? Evidence from pair-wise experiments.
Oikos
105
(
2
): 
229 - 238
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.0030-1299.2004.12682.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wan, JS
, 
Fazlioglu, F
, 
Bonser, SP
, 
2018
. 

Loss of plasticity in life-history strategy associated with secondary invasion into stressful environments in invasive narrowleaf plantain (

Plantago lanceolata

L.).

Austral Ecology
43
(
7
): 
752 - 762
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/aec.12599
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wan, J
, 
Huang, B
, 
Yu, H
, 
Peng, S
, 
2019
. 
Reassociation of an invasive plant with its specialist herbivore provides a test of the shifting defence hypothesis.
Journal of Ecology
107
(
1
): 
361 - 371
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2745.13019
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wilson, JR
, 
Richardson, DM
, 
Rouget, M
, 

Proches
, 
S

, 
Amis, MA
, 
Henderson, L
, 
Thuiller, W
, 
2007
. 
Residence time and potential range: Crucial considerations in modelling plant invasions.
Diversity &amp; Distributions
13
(
1
): 
11 - 22
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1366-9516.2006.00302.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zangerl, AR
, 
Berenbaum, MR
, 
2005
. 
Increase in toxicity of an invasive weed after reassociation with its coevolved herbivore.
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America
102
(
43
): 
15529 - 15532
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0507805102
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, Z
, 
Pan, X
, 
Blumenthal, D
, 
Van Kleunen, M
, 
Liu, M
, 
Li, B
, 
2018
. 
Contrasting effects of specialist and generalist herbivores on resistance evolution in invasive plants.
Ecology
99
(
4
): 
866 - 875
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ecy.2155
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Supplementary materials</p>
         <p>Supplementary material 1 Supplementary information Data type</p>
         <p>docx</p>
         <p>Explanation note</p>
         <p>
fig. S1.
Temporal trends (between 1977-2022) in studies focusing on exploring variation in invasion-promoting traits of invasive plants over time. Data was extracted after searching the Web of Science Core Collection database using the search terms (chronosequence OR time-since-introduction OR invasion-history OR residence-time OR range-expansion OR colonization-history OR introduction-history) and plant* and invasi* and (biomass OR defense OR competiti* OR dispersal OR allelopathy OR herbivor* OR plant-height). The smooth curve (indicated in blue) was added for visual interpretation. 
fig. S2.
Schematic representation of the two literature searches used in the meta-analysis, using both Web of Science and Google Scholar databases. 
fig. S3.
Meta regression results for the effects of the different moderators on mean absolute effect sizes (|β| 
+/-
95% confidence intervals; 0 ≤ |β| ≤ 1). Moderators include the origin of information (invasion history data reported in papers vs. estimated using external databases) and type of invasion history measurement (residence time vs. distance). Sample sizes (number of cases) are indicated in parentheses. 
fig. S4.
Correlations between (A) absolute effect size of the different studies and the impact factor of the journal at time of publication or between (B) 
journal's
impact factor and total sample size per study. Dashed lines indicate significant negative correlations (r = - 0.357, p = 0.0017, n = 75 and r = 0.539, p &lt;0.001, n = 75, respectively). 
table S1.
Information on the invasive species, variables and factors used for the meta-analysis, as well as the respective effect sizes and variances.
</p>
         <p>This dataset is made available under the Open Database License (http://opendatacommons.org/licenses/odbl/1.0/). The Open Database License (ODbL) is a license agreement intended to allow users to freely share, modify, and use this Dataset while maintaining this same freedom for others, provided that the original source and author(s) are credited.</p>
         <p>Michal Gruntman, Udi Segev</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
