<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nota Lepidopterologica</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/nl.47.118555</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The date of publication of A. Guenée’s Geometridae et Uranides, Histoire Naturelle des Insectes. Species Général des Lépidoptères</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>27</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agathia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aplodes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Almodes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ceratonyx
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bombycodes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Heterocera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Brephinae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="﻿introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Introduction
</p>
         <p>
Two important works in the taxonomy of 
<tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
are volumes 9 and 10 of the "Histoire Naturelle des Insectes. Species 
General
des 
Lepidopteres"
, written by Achille 
Guenee
(1809-1880) under the joint editorship of J.B.A.D. Boisduval and A. 
Guenee
. Both volumes of the text are imprinted with the date 1857, although the 
"Atlas"
(plates) bears the imprint 1858. There has been inconsistency in the literature as to whether the actual date of publication for the text should be 1857 or 1858, and the purpose of this short paper is to clarify the matter and present evidence for what we trust will establish the date that should be accepted - dates being of particular importance in taxonomy.
</p>
         <p>
Examples of conflicting date usage may be illustrated in works by two key researchers on 
<tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
: L.B. Prout (

, 

, 

) referred to 
Guenee
1858, whereas D.S. Fletcher, in his influential work on the generic names of 
<tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
(

), cited 1857 for the text, but 1858 for the 
"Atlas"
(plates).
</p>
         <p>
Later, 

adopted the date 
"Guenee
[1858]", the square brackets indicating that the date was established from sources other than the date imprinted on the publication. No explanation was given for the adoption of the date. 

cited the work as 
"Guenee
, A., [1858]" in the references, but "1857 ff" in his list of key works to 
<tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
in the introduction to his volume. 

used 
"Guenee
, 1858" in their paper announcing the launch of an online global taxonomic facility of 
<tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
, but adopted the use of parentheses (square brackets) around the date of the associated online database, i.e., 
"Guenee
, [1858]" (https://geometroidea.smns-bw.org/geometridae/Catalogue/).
</p>
         <p>
That confusion about the dates remains, may also be observed in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
component of the online database provided by the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF Secretariat, accessed 13 August 2022). While some generic names are cited in Volume 9 as 
Guenee
(1857) (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agathia
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aplodes
</tp:taxon-name>
), others in the same volume are listed as 
Guenee
(1858) (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Almodes
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratonyx
</tp:taxon-name>
). And while the date of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bombycodes
</tp:taxon-name>
Guenee
, published in Volume 10, is given as 1857, the type species, described in the original two pages later, is dated 1858. There are many other examples in the database of the two dates being used.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿discussion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Discussion</p>
         <p>
We consider that important evidence for accepting the date of 1858 for 
Guenee's
volumes 9 (
Guenee
[1858a]) and 10 (
Guenee
[1858b]) is to be found in the Bibliographie de la France, where the full reference to 
Guenee
volume 9 is provided on page 17 (Bibliographie de la France 1858: 17, entry no. 338). Dates of publications are not given for individual entries in the Bibliographie, but rather entries are listed collectively under the date of the respective number of this publication, in this case Volume (
"Tome"
) 2, No. 2, which is dated 8 January 1858 (

: 13). The full reference to 
Guenee's
volume 10 is on page 153 (

: 153, entry no. 2877), in Volume 2, No. 12, dated 20 March 1858.
</p>
         <p>
The validity of the date of 1858 was explored by R.B. Williams in a paper primarily aimed at establishing the dates of the parts and consolidated volumes of H.T. 
Stainton's
"A Manual of British Butterflies and Moths" (

). Citing the Bibliographie de la France, Williams noted (pp. 94, 95), as we have done above, that volume 9 (
"Tome"
I) of 
Guenee's
work was published between 2 and 8 January 1858 and volume 10 (
"Tome"
II) between 13 and 19 March 1858 (given as 20 March 1858 in Bibliographie de la France). Importantly, he demonstrated that Stainton had awaited publication of 
Guenee's
volumes, of which he had seen some proofs earlier, and had delayed the publication of his own work on 
<tp:taxon-name>Geometridae</tp:taxon-name>
for a few months to benefit from their content. The explanation for the imprinted date of 1857 was explained cogently by Williams, who cited a published note by Stainton stating that he had seen some of the proofs in April 1857. (We have sourced this note and see that Stainton had indeed viewed proofs during a visit to 
Guenee
in France, and was given to understand at that time that publication would take place in September (

).) 
Stainton's
own publication (in 1858) occurred shortly after 
Guenee's
. (See 

: 91, 95.) Williams concluded by accepting the date of 1858 for both volumes 9 and 10.
</p>
         <p>
We have investigated further and found what we consider to be compelling evidence for a publication date of 1858 in the form of an article from The 
Entomologist's
Weekly Intelligencer (

), dated Saturday, January 9, 1858. This piece, assuredly written by Stainton, expressed considerable frustration and exasperation with the several delays in the expected publication of 
Guenee's
work. Stainton continued to hold back his own publication to await 
Guenee's
results and was in close touch with him. In this rather pointed article, September 1857 was stated as the new intended date of publication. However:
</p>
         <p>
"...

first, it was to have been out in September; then, after repeated correspondence on our part, M. 
Guenee
, who really appears to have exerted himself immensely to accommodate us, wrote that the volume would be published before the end of November ...

"
</p>
         <p>But the work did not appear in November and the article continues:</p>
         <p>
"...

and nay, more, that December is also gone, and did we not receive a positive assurance that the volume would be published on the 20th of December? And did not "our own correspondent [Stainton]," calling there on that day, learn to his regret "that M. 
Guenee's
volume would appear in the course of January

" 
..."
</p>
         <p>
Guenee's
work (volume 9) was at last received in January 1858, a note at the end of the article stating:
</p>
         <p>
" 
Since the above was in type, we are happy to announce that we
have received 

the first volume of M 
Guenee's

Geometrae 
..."
</p>
         <p>
In the previous issue of the Intelligencer (No. 66, 2 January 1858) there was no mention of 
Guenee's
first volume (volume 9) having been received. And we note further that the article in the issue of 9 January fits the citation in the Bibliographie de la France dated 8 January 1858. 
Guenee's
second volume (volume 10) appeared somewhat later, as noted above. It was still awaited on 3 February 1858 (

). Stainton had received a copy by 23 February 1858 (

), although whether this was an advance copy, given 
Stainton's
pressure on 
Guenee
, or the published version remains uncertain.
</p>
         <p>
We are conscious that 
Guenee
informed Stainton in a letter dated September 26, 1857 (
Guenee
in 

) that volume 9 had been printed, but he made it clear that it was not yet published and that he too was awaiting publication. There is a well-established distinction between the date when a work is printed and the date that it is published. The meaning of 
'printing'
is self-evident. But publication requires that a work must be available to the public (derived from the Latin 
publicationem
- a making public) and obtainable, i.e., available for distribution. Indeed, Article 8 of the 

("What constitutes published work") requires that a work "must be issued for the purpose of providing a public and permanent scientific record"; that "it must be obtainable, when first issued, free of charge or by purchase"; and "it must have been produced in an edition containing simultaneously obtainable copies by a method that assures numerous identical and durable copies
..."
. 
Guenee
himself made a distinction between printing and publication in this instance. He stated in his letter that "My first volume [i.e., volume 9] is printed, and the plates are all ready, but the publisher will only bring out the volumes both together." 
Guenee
wrote that he could not enlighten Stainton on the precise date of publication of his two volumes: "I have lately written [to the publisher] to complain of this dawdling, and I hope he will hasten the publication; that depends entirely on him."
</p>
         <p>
In essence, therefore, we argue that it is fair to assume that the most reliable source of information comes from 
Guenee
himself - that is from a combination of his letter to Stainton, and what he imparted to Stainton when he visited 
Guenee
on 20 December 1857, namely that the work would be published in January of 1858.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿conclusion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Conclusion</p>
         <p>
While sensitive to the contrary opinion, we find no firm evidence for accepting the year 1857, and the counter-evidence from Anonymous [Stainton] (1858) seems highly persuasive. We conclude that [1858] should be accepted as the valid date, being also guided by Article 21 of the International Code of Zoological Nomenclature (

) and the requirements of what constitutes published work. We consider that the weight of evidence lies firmly in favour of [1858]. As such, we note that in such a circumstance (following Article 21.4) 
"...
the earliest day on which the work is demonstrated to be in existence as a published work [our emphasis] is to be adopted.". For the reasons given above, we consider that the earliest date of 
Guenee's
publication would be between 2 and 8 January 1858.
</p>
         <p>
We trust that our argumentation will establish the accepted date to be [1858]. In so doing, we hope to remove the uncertainty among geometrid taxonomists about which date to apply to 
Guenee's
much cited publications.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿a note on citation style">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>A note on citation style</p>
         <p>
In versions of the ICZN prior to the Fourth Edition it was recommended that when the actual date of publication differs from the date specified in the work (the imprint date), the actual date should be cited in square brackets. Under Recommendation 22A.2.2 of the Fourth Edition of the Code (

), however, it is stated simply that the actual date of publication should be cited - there is no mention of square brackets. The option of using square brackets is explained in Recommendation 22A.2.3, which proposes placing the imprinted date in parentheses, the precise opposite of the earlier practice, which is certain to result in confusion. We have, therefore, opted to use the well-tested and peer-reviewed approach of using square brackets for 
Guenee
[1858a, b] to make it perfectly clear to readers and applicants of future taxonomy that the date we have established is determined from external evidence.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>
For discussion and suggestions, we thank Axel Hausmann (Zoologische Staatssammlung, Munich), Ian Kitching (Natural History Museum, London), Pasi Sihvonen (Finnish Museum of Natural History, Helsinki) and Manfred Sommerer (Munich). Our thanks are extended to 
Joel
Minet (
Museum
National 
d'Histoire
Naturelle, Paris) for his thoughts and for sending us further references and documents. We are also grateful to Alberto Zilli (Natural History Museum, London) for his valued and challenging discussions, which encouraged us to dig deeper. We thank three referees for their thoughtful and valuable comments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1858
.. 
https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/206537#page/119/mode/1up
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1858a
.. 
https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k867031/f164.item
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1858b
.. 
https://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k867031/f300.item
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fletcher, DS
, 
1979
. 
Geometroidea. In: Nye IWB (Ed.) The Generic Names of Moths of the World 3, Trustees of the British Museum (Natural History), London, [xx +] 243 pp.
https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.119424
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
2022
.. 
https://doi.org/10.15468/39omei
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guenee
A [1858a] Uranides et 
Phalenites
, I. Vol. 9 In: Boisduval JBAD, 
Guenee
A (Eds) Histoire Naturelle des Insectes: Species 
General
des 
Lepidopteres
. 
"1857"
. Librairie 
Encyclopedique
de Roret, Paris, [i-lvi,] 1-515.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guenee
A [1858b] Uranides et 
Phalenites
, II. Vol. 10 In: Boisduval JBAD de, 
Guenee
A (Eds) Histoire Naturelle des Insectes: Species 
General
des 
Lepidopteres
. 
"1857"
. Librairie 
Encyclopedique
de Roret, Paris, 1-584.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hausmann, A
, 
2001
. 
Introduction. Archiearinae, Orthostixinae, Desmobathrinae, Alsophilinae, Geometrinae. In: Hausmann A (Ed.) The Geometrid Moths of Europe, vol. 1.
Apollo Books, Stenstrup
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1999
.. 
https://code.iczn.org/?frame=1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Parsons, MS
, 
Scoble, MJ
, 
Honey, MR
, 
Pitkin, LM
, 
Pitkin, BR
, 
1999
. 
The Catalogue. In: Scoble MJ (Ed.) Geometrid Moths of the World: a Catalogue (Lepidoptera: Geometridae) (2 volumes). CSIRO Publishing, Collingwood, [xxv] + 1016 pp.
https://doi.org/10.1071/9780643101050
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Prout, LB
, 
1910a
. 

Lepidoptera
Heterocera
, Fam. 
Geometridae
, Subfam. 
Brephinae
. In: Wytsman P (Ed.

) Genera Insectorum
103
: 
1 - 16
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Prout, LB
, 
1910b
. 
LepidopteraHeterocera, Fam. Geometridae, Subfam. Oenochrominae. 104. In: Wytsman P (Ed.) Genera Insectorum 104: 1-120. [2 pls].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Prout, LB
, 
1912
. 
Lepidoptera, Fam. Geometridae, Subfam. Hemitheinae. In: Wytsman P (Ed.) Genera Insectorum 129: 1-274. [5 pls].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rajaei, H
, 
Hausmann, A
, 
Scoble, M
, 
Wanke, D
, 
Plotkin, D
, 
Brehm, G
, 
Murillo-Ramos, L
, 
Sihvonen, P
, 
2022
. 

An online taxonomic facility of 
Geometridae
(
Lepidoptera
), with an overview of global species richness and systematics.

Integrative Systematics
5
(
2
): 
145 - 192
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.18476/2022.577933
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stainton, HT
, 
1857a
. 

A visit to Chateaudun. The 
Entomologist's
Weekly Intelligencer 2(No. 31): 37. https://

www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/206514#page/43/mode/1up
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stainton, HT
, 
1857b
. 

Guenee's
Geometrae. The 
Entomologist's
Weekly Intelligencer 3(No. 55): 22-23.

https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/206537#page/28/mode/1up
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stainton, HT
, 
1858a
. 

Arrangement of the Geometrae. The 
Entomologist's
Weekly Intelligencer 3(No. 72): 157-158.

https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/206537#page/164/mode/1up
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stainton, HT
, 
1858b
. 

Problems in Geometrae No. IV. The 
Entomologist's
Weekly Intelligencer 3(No. 75): 180-181.

https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/206537#page/186/mode/1up
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Williams, RB
, 
2019
. 

Bibliographical descriptions and dating of the original parts and consolidated volumes of H. T. 
Stainton's
A Manual of British Butterflies and Moths, with dating and combined order of precedence of some relevant contemporaneous literature.

Zoological Bibliography
6
(
6
): 
55 - 102
, 
https://www.avespress.com/uploads/texteditor/ZB_6_6_PDFA.pdf
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
