<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytotaxa</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11646/phytotaxa.637.3.10</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>INDIARA NUNES MESQUITA FERREIRA, DANIELLE DE OLIVEIRA DINIZ, FERNANDA GOMES FERREIRA &amp; FÁBIO VENTUROLI (2024) A new species of Oxandra (Annonaceae) from the Brazilian Cerrado. Phytotaxa 636 (3): 246-251</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>22</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group/>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
INDIARA NUNES MESQUITA FERREIRA
, 
DANIELLE DE

OLIVEIRA DINIZ, FERNANDA GOMES FERREIRA &amp; FÁBIO VENTUROLI (
2024
)


A new species of 
Oxandra
(Annonaceae) from the Brazilian Cerrado. 
Phytotaxa
636
(
3
): 
246–251
</p>
         <p>
Please note the 
Acknowledgements
on page 6:
</p>
         <p>We thank the Coordenação de aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES) agency, which provided a scholarship grant for the first author. We would also like to thank the Serviço Florestal brasileiro, Legado Verdes do Cerrado, Universidade Federal de Goiás and Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FaO) for project financing. We are grateful to Carlos de Morais Gomes for assistance and support during botanical collections. Contributions from reviewers are greatly appreciated.</p>
         <p>Should read:</p>
         <p>We thank the Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES) agency, which provided a scholarship grant for the first author. We would also like to thank the Serviço Florestal Brasileiro, Legado Verdes do Cerrado, Inventário Florestal Nacional, Universidade Federal de Goiás and Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FaO) for project financing. We are grateful to Carlos de Morais Gomes for assistance and support during botanical collections. Contributions from reviewers are greatly appreciated.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
