<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Soil Organisms</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25674/so94iss1id178</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Global monitoring of soil animal communities using a common methodology</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Enchytraeidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Diplura
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Araneae, Thysanoptera, Sternorrhyncha</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Blattidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Corydiidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Formicidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Coleoptera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cantharidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Elateridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Staphylinidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Curculionidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Scarabaeidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Tenebrionidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Silphidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera, Diptera, Dermaptera, Thysanoptera. Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Araneae, Opiliones, Amblypygi, Uropygi, Solifugae, Scorpiones.</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>CALL FOR COLLABORATION</p>
         <p>
Global monitoring of soil animal communities using a common methodology
</p>
         <p>
Anton M. Potapov
1,2
*, 
Xin Sun
3
*, 
Andrew D. Barnes
4
, 
Maria J. I. Briones
5
,

</p>
         <p>
George G. Brown
6,7
, 
Erin K. Cameron
8
, 
Chih-Han Chang
9,10
, 
Jérôme Cortet
11
,

</p>
         <p>
Nico Eisenhauer
12,13
, 
André L.C. Franco
14
, 
Saori Fujii
15
, 
Stefan Geisen
16
,

</p>
         <p>
Konstantin B. Gongalsky
2
, 
Carlos Guerra
12,17
, 
Jari Haimi
18
, 
I. Tanya Handa
19
,

</p>
         <p>
Charlene Janion-Scheepers
20,21
, 
Kamil Karaban
22
, 
Zoë Lindo
23
, 
Jérôme Mathieu
24
,

</p>
         <p>
María Laura Moreno
25,26
, 
Maka Murvanidze
27
, 
Uffe N. Nielsen
28
, 
Stefan Scheu
1
,

</p>
         <p>
Olaf Schmidt
29
, 
Clement Schneider
30
, 
Julia Seeber
31,32
, 
Maria A. Tsiafouli
33
, 
Jiri Tuma
34
, 
Alexei V. Tiunov
2
, 
Andrey S. Zaitsev
2,
Frank Ashwood 
35
, 
Mac Callaham
36
and 
Diana H. Wall
37
</p>
         <p>
1

JOhann Friedrich BlUmenbach InstitUte OF ZOOlOgy and AnthrOpOlOgy, University OF Göttingen, Göttingen, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
2

A.N. SevertsOv InstitUte OF EcOlOgy and EvOlUtiOn, RUssian Academy OF Sciences, 
MOscOw
, 
RUssia
</p>
         <p>
3

Key LabOratOry OF Urban EnvirOnment and Health, InstitUte OF Urban EnvirOnment Chinese Academy OF Sciences, 361021, Xiamen, 
China
</p>
         <p>
4

SchOOl OF Science, University OF 
WaikatO
, HamiltOn, 
New Zealand
</p>
         <p>
5

DepartamentO de EcOlOgÍa y BiOlOgÍa Animal, Universidad de VigO, 36310 VigO, 
Spain
</p>
         <p>
6

Embrapa FOrestry, Estrada da Ribeira Km. 111, COlOmbO, 
PR
, 
Brazil
, 83411-000

</p>
         <p>
7

SOils Department, Universidade Federal dO 
Paraná
, 

RUa dOs FUnciOnáriOs 1540, CUritiba, 
PR
, 
Brazil

, 80035-050

</p>
         <p>
8

Department OF EnvirOnmental Science, Saint Mary’s University, HaliFax, 
NOva ScOtia
, 
Canada
</p>
         <p>
9

Department OF LiFe Science, NatiOnal 
Taiwan
University, 
Taipei
, 
Taiwan
</p>
         <p>
10

InstitUte OF EcOlOgy and EvOlUtiOnary BiOlOgy, NatiOnal 
Taiwan
University, 
Taipei
, 
Taiwan
</p>
         <p>
11
CEFE, UMR 5175, Université PaUl-Valéry MOntpellier 3, Université de MOntpellier, EPHE, IRD, rOUte de Mende,
</p>
         <p>34000 MOntpellier</p>
         <p>
12

German Centre FOr Integrative BiOdiversity Research (iDiv), Halle-Jena-Leipzig, PUschstr. 4, 04103 Leipzig, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
13

InstitUte OF BiOlOgy, Leipzig University, PUschstr. 4, 04103 Leipzig, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
14

Department OF BiOlOgy, 
COlOradO State
University, FOrt COllins, CO 80523-1036, 
USA
</p>
         <p>
15
Department OF FOrest EntOmOlOgy, FOrestry and FOrest PrOdUcts Research InstitUte, 1 MatsUnOsatO, TsUkUba,
</p>
         <p>
Ibaraki
, 305-8687, 
Japan
</p>
         <p>
16
LabOratOry OF NematOlOgy, Department OF Plant Sciences, Wageningen University &amp; Research, 6700 ES Wageningen,
</p>
         <p>
The Netherlands
</p>
         <p>
17
InstitUte OF BiOlOgy, Martin LUther University Halle Wittenberg, Halle (Saale), 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
18
Department OF BiOlOgical and EnvirOnmental Science, University OF Jyväskylä, 
Finland
</p>
         <p>
19
Département des sciences biOlOgiQUes, Université dU 
QUébec
à MOntréal, CP. 8888, sUccUrsale Centre-Ville, MOntréal QC,
</p>
         <p>
H3C 3P8, 
Canada
</p>
         <p>
20
Department OF BiOlOgical Sciences, University OF 
Cape
TOwn, ROndebOsch, 7700, 
SOUth AFrica
</p>
         <p>
21
IzikO MUseUms OF 
SOUth AFrica
, 
Cape
TOwn, 8000, 
SOUth AFrica
</p>
         <p>
22
InstitUte OF BiOlOgical Sciences, Cardinal SteFan Wyszynski University in Warsaw, WOycickiegO 1/ 3, 01-938 Warsaw, 
POland
</p>
         <p>
23
University OF Western
OntariO

, 

Department OF
BiOlOgy, LOndOn, 
OntariO
, 
Canada
</p>
         <p>
24
InstitUt d’EcOlOgie et des Sciences de l’EnvirOnnement de Paris, SOrbOnne Université, CNRS, UPEC, Paris 7, INRA, IRD,
</p>
         <p>
F-75005 Paris, 
France
</p>
         <p>
25
Centro de Investigaciones EntomolÓgicas
de 
CÓrdoba

, 

F.C.
E.F.yN., Universidad Nacional de 
CÓrdoba

, 

Av. Vélez Sarsfield
1611 (X5016GCA), 
CÓrdOba
, 
Argentina
</p>
         <p>
26
InstitUto MUltidisciplinario 
de Biología Vegetal
(CONICET-Universidad Nacional de 
CÓrdoba
), 
Av. Vélez Sarsfield
1611-(X5016GCA), 
FacUltad de Ciencias Exactas
FÍsicas y NatUrales, Universidad NaciOnal de 
CÓrdOba
, 
Argentina
</p>
         <p>
27
I. Javakhishvili
Tbilisi State
University, I
. Chavchavadze ave. 1, 0179 
Tbilisi
, 
GeOrgia
</p>
         <p>
28
HawkesbUry InstitUte FOr the EnvirOnment, Western Sydney University, LOcked Bag 1797, NSW, Penrith, 2751, 
AUstralia
</p>
         <p>
29
UCD School of AgricUltUre and Food Science, and UCD Earth InstitUte, University College 
DUblin
, Belfield, 
DUblin
4, 
Ireland
</p>
         <p>
30
Department OF SOil ZOOlOgy, Senckenberg SOciety FOr NatUre Research, Am MUseUm 1, 02826 Görlitz, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
31
InstitUte For Alpine Environment, EUrac Research, DrUsUsallee 1, 39100 Bozen, 
Italy
</p>
         <p>
32
Department oF Ecology, University oF InnsbrUck, Technikerstrasse 25, 6020 InnsbrUck, 
AUstria
</p>
         <p>
33
Department oF Ecology, School oF Biology, Aristotle University, 54124 Thessaloniki, 
Greece
</p>
         <p>
34
BiOLOGy Centre OF the Czech Academy OF ScienceS, InStitUte OF SOiL BiOLOGy, Na Sádkách 7, 370 05, ČeSké BUděJOVice, 
Czech RepUblic
</p>
         <p>
35
Forest Research, Northern Research Station, Roslin, 
Midlothian
, Scotland EH25 9SY, 
United Kingdom
</p>
         <p>
36
USDA Forest Service, SoUthern Research Station, 30602 Athens, GA, 
USA
</p>
         <p>
37
School oF Global Environmental
SUstainability and 
Department oF Biology
, 
Colorado State
University, 
Fort Collins

,
</p>
         <p>
CO 80523-1036, 
USA
</p>
         <p>* Corresponing aUthors, Email: potapov.msU@gmail.com, xsUn@iUe.ac.cn</p>
         <p>
Received 
18 FebrUary 2022
| Accepted 
29 March 2022
</p>
         <p>
Published online at www.soil-organisms.de 

1 April 
2022

| Printed version 
15 April 2022
</p>
         <p>
DOI 
10.25674/so94iss1id178
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Abstract
</title>
         <p>Here we introduce the Soil BON Foodweb Team, a cross-continental collaborative network that aims to monitor soil animal communities and food webs using consistent methodology at a global scale. Soil animals support vital soil processes via soil structure modification, consumption of dead organic matter, and interactions with microbial and plant communities. Soil animal effects on ecosystem functions have been demonstrated by correlative analyses as well as in laboratory and field experiments, but these studies typically focus on selected animal groups or species at one or few sites with limited variation in environmental conditions. The lack of comprehensive harmonised large-scale soil animal community data including microfauna, mesofauna, and macrofauna, in conjunction with related soil functions, microbial communities, and vegetation, limits our understanding of biological interactions in soil systems and how these interactions affect ecosystem functioning. To provide such data, the Soil BON Foodweb Team invites researchers worldwide to use a common methodology to address six long-term goals: (1) to collect globally representative harmonised data on soil micro-, meso-, and macrofauna communities, (2) to describe key environmental drivers of soil animal communities and food webs, (3) to assess the efficiency of conservation approaches for the protection of soil animal communities, (4) to describe soil food webs and their association with soil functioning globally, (5) to establish a global research network for soil biodiversity monitoring and collaborative projects in related topics, (6) to reinforce local collaboration networks and expertise and support capacity building for soil animal research around the world. In this paper, we describe the vision of the global research network and the common sampling protocol to assess soil animal communities and advocate for the use of standard methodologies across observational and experimental soil animal studies. We will use this protocol to conduct soil animal assessments and reconstruct soil food webs at sites associated with the global soil biodiversity monitoring network, Soil BON, allowing us to assess linkages among soil biodiversity, vegetation, soil physico-chemical properties, climate, and ecosystem functions. In the present paper, we call for researchers especially from countries and ecoregions that remain underrepresented in the majority of soil biodiversity assessments to join us. Together we will be able to provide science-based evidence to support soil biodiversity conservation and functioning of terrestrial ecosystems.</p>
         <p>
Keywords
Biogeography
| 
ecosystem FUnctioning
| 
macroecology
| 
soil FaUna
| 
soil biodiversity
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Soil animals are an essential component of virtually all terrestrial ecosystems (

, 

). They support ecosystem functions by directly contributing to decomposition and nutrient cycling, and indirectly through engineering activities, as well as by influencing microbial communities and plant growth (

, 

, 

, 

). In exclusion experiments, the presence of soil animals can enhance aboveground plant productivity by up to 70%, depending on the vegetation 
type
(

, 

, 

), or facilitate litter decomposition by up to 50 %, depending on climatic conditions (

). These effects largely emerge from biological interactions within and among functional groups of soil animals, microbes, and plants (

, 

, 

). Local variations in animal communities may sum up to considerable effects on ecosystem processes at the biosphere level (

, 

). There have been several calls to include explicitly soil animal effects in global biogeochemical (

, 

, 

) and soil erosion models (

), but the required large-scale comprehensive community data to validate these animal-based models are lacking.
</p>
         <p>
The most comprehensive overview on the contribution of soil animal communities to ecosystem functioning comes from the International Biological Programme and dates back to the 1980s (

, 

). However, the observational data compiled at that time was not linked to soil properties and functions in a spatially-explicit way, which limited their use for biogeochemical modelling and for a broader ecosystem level understanding. Several recent studies have collected global spatially-explicit data and extrapolated global distributions of earthworms (

) and nematodes (

), while syntheses on springtails (#GlobalCollembola) (

, Potapov et al. 2022) and soil macrofauna (GlobalSOilMacrofauna) (Lavelle et al. 
under review
) are in progress. These studies showed that the distribution of the local diversity of soil animals differs strongly from that of aboveground organisms (

, 

) due to their contrasting responses to environmental drivers (

).
</p>
         <p>
To date, global assessments of soil micro-, meso- and macrofauna have been done independently by different expert communities and using different methodologies. This limits our understanding of relationships among key functional groups of soil organisms and prevents us from global upscaling of soil communities and food webs they form. A comprehensive community-level assessment will make it possible to reconstruct soil food webs and infer energy fluxes to describe biotic controls, trophic functioning, and stability patterns of soil biodiversity. Food webs is a particularly powerful approach to link soil biodiversity to both ecosystem functioning and environmental drivers (

, 

). Existing global extrapolations of soil biodiversity remain poorly linked to soil functions with only 0.3% of soil ecological studies simultaneously assessing soil biodiversity and functions (

). This important knowledge gap makes a robust quantification of soil animal contribution to biosphere functioning impossible and hampers projections of soil functioning under future global change scenarios (

). Furthermore, gaps in knowledge of soil animal distribution and diversity, especially of tropical soil animal communities, severely limits our understanding of human impact on soil animals and the design of appropriate conservation strategies (

, Geisen et al. 2019, 

). These knowledge gaps call for a comprehensive soil animal biodiversity assessment at a global scale using a common methodology (Geisen et al. 2019, 

, 

), which is achievable only through a major joint effort.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A standardised soil animal monitoring at the global scale
</title>
         <p>
The Soil Biodiversity Observation Network (Soil BON) was launched in 2018 as a part of The Group on Earth Observations Biodiversity Observation Network (GEO BON), a United Nations initiative that aims to monitor Earth’s biodiversity (

, 

). Soil BON is a collaborative network supported by the Global Soil Biodiversity Initiative (GSBI) that focuses on soil biodiversity (

) and at present includes research teams across 80+ countries. Local teams will collect soil samples at approximately 1,000 sites across all continents, except 
Antarctica
, for the first time in 2022. Additional sampling is planned every three years to establish long-term global-scale monitoring of soil biodiversity. The resulting soil samples will be shipped to a central hub (German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research, iDiv, Leipzig, 
Germany
) to perform measurements of soil properties (water holding capacity, stoichiometry of nutrients, pH, root characteristics), microbiome (eDNA sequencing of prokaryotes, fungi, protists), and functions (soil respiration, substrate-induced respiration, microbial biomass, enzymatic activity, litter decomposition, soil aggregate stability). The sampling also includes nematodes from topsoil. However, this approach is not well-suited to assess in full soil animal communities due to the large amount of material that needs to be transported (kilograms of soil per site), and the high mortality of soil animals (particularly macrofauna) in long-term stored and shipped soil samples. Hence, it is important that soil animals are collected, extracted, and assessed immediately after sampling with limited disturbance to samples.
</p>
         <p>
Here, we introduce the Soil BON Foodweb Team (SBF Team), an extension of Soil BON that focuses on the assessment of soil animal communities (
Fig. 1a
). We aim at producing new harmonised global data on densities and biomasses of all major taxonomic groups of soil invertebrates across micro-, meso-, and macrofauna, and thus expand the scope of the Soil BON initiative by linking soil biodiversity to ecosystem level processes through a soil food web perspective. This effort widens the core Soil BON network by involving local research communities of soil zoologists and taxonomists and applying additional sampling approaches. Instead of having a central hub, we will coordinate local researchers and facilities to form a complementary global network aiming at six main long-term goals:
</p>
         <p>
1. To deliver 
open, comprehensive, and globally representative methods and harmonised datasets
</p>
         <p>on soil micro-, meso-, and macrofauna in conjunction with soil functions.</p>
         <p>
2. To explore effects of 
climate, land use, and other environmental variables
on soil animal
</p>
         <p>communities, soil food web structure, resistance, and resilience.</p>
         <p>
3. To assess the efficiency of current 
nature conservation
approaches in protecting soil animal
</p>
         <p>communities.</p>
         <p>
4. To relate soil animal communities and food webs with 
soil functioning
across climates, soils, and land use 
types
.
</p>
         <p>
5. To establish a 
global soil fauna expert network
for soil biodiversity monitoring and other collaborative projects.
</p>
         <p>
6. To reinforce local collaboration networks and 
local expertise
in soil animal ecology and taxonomy.
</p>
         <p>
Our initial objective is to sample at least 240 out of the planned ~1,000 Soil BON sites in 2022. Soil animal data will be linked to the core Soil BON network data on climate, land use, soil parameters, microorganisms, and functions via common sampling sites and similar sampling periods. Therefore, 
this is the first initiative linking quantitative soil animal data across the size spectrum to a range of
</p>
         <p>
soil functions worldwide
. The 
Global coordination team
</p>
         <p>
includes the 
Central team
which is responsible for data acquisition and storage, the co-Chairs of Soil BON, and the 
National coordinators
who communicate with the local survey networks (
Fig. 1c
). The extended network includes 
Field teams
and 
Local hubs
, i.e. research teams that have expertise in soil animal ecology and perform soil sampling and animal extraction. All these roles are not mutually exclusive (e.g. a person can be involved in the 
Global coordination team
, but also form a 
Local hub
and a 
Field team
). To date, research teams from 25 countries have volunteered to join the Team, partly covering also less explored regions such as Africa, South America, Asia, and 
Russia
. This paper is a call for soil animal ecologists from around the world to join the SBF Team. Priority will be given to research teams from undersampled countries and ecoregions; at present, these include mainly countries in Africa, Asia, South America, and the Middle East (
Fig. 1b
). To participate as a 
Field team
, expertise in soil zoology, basic equipment for the field work (Supplementary protocol S1), and possibility to collect soil animals from several sampling sites with standardised methods is needed. To establish a 
Local hub
, a laboratory equipped with wet and/ or dry extractors is needed. This equipment can be also built with little monetary costs and guidelines will be provided by the Team participants (

, 

, 

). 
National coordinators
will help establish, support, and coordinate local collaboration networks of 
Field teams
and 
Local hubs
. The current list of 
National coordinators
, sampling video, and extraction guidelines will be available from the web page of the SBF Team (www.soilbonfoodweb.org). All material and data contributors and national coordinators are invited to join collaborative publications, workshops, and add-on projects of the SBF Team and synthesis publications of the Soil BON consortium including their data. Below, we describe our sampling protocol, data acquisition and storage strategies.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A common methodology
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Target variables
</title>
         <p>
Our initiative and methodologies have been designed to be as 
comprehensive
as possible and cover all key functional groups of soil micro-, meso- and macrofauna, to be 
globally representative
, with significant coverage across continents, different countries, and environmental conditions, and to be 
inclusive
for research groups and countries with limited facilities (

). This is a bold and challenging task that demands low-cost and labour-efficient approaches. To ensure feasibility, at the initial stage we will focus on biomass of taxonomic and functional groups, rather than at species level. The latter implies a need for taxonomic expertise in all major soil invertebrate groups which is limiting particularly in tropical regions, where a large proportion of the individuals collected are singletons, and where many species are unknown/undescribed (

, 

, 

, 

). Nevertheless, building taxonomic expert capacities locally is one of the long-term goals of the SBF Team (see our aims above). Our methodologies are designed to represent well all major functional groups of soil animals while being feasible for implementation across the globe. Additional methodologies that improve representation of specific functional groups (e.g. very large or spatially-aggregated macrofauna) are considered for add-on projects in the future.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Site selection, sampling size and time
</title>
         <p>
Site selection is linked to the Soil BON core design, where soil parameters, functions, and microbial communities are assessed. Therefore, sampling sites for animal assessment are chosen from a pre-selected set of sites in communication with researchers involved in the core Soil BON network. The core design includes sites outside and inside areas that have a ‘protection’ status (e.g. nature conservation reserves) in each country to evaluate the effect of present conservation strategies on soil biota (

). The sampling of soil animals should be done at least on two sites by each 
Field team
(e.g. one site inside and one outside of a protected area within the same geographical region and habitat 
type
), but ideally cover more ecosystems and geographic areas. The final site selection is designed by 
National coordinators
to identify priority ecosystems that cover wide environmental gradients (

). At the initial stage, we target to sample at least 240 sites (120 pairs) globally, which will be sufficient for general analyses (

). For all sites we collect information on the sampling date, person, location, vegetation characteristics, and history. The sampling is done at the peak vegetation biomass season according to the Soil BON approach (

). A 3-month window will be provided for each site and these time frames will vary across sites. At each site, soil animals are assessed at five sampling points (within a 30 x 
30 m
area) to account for within-site variation as the recommended minimum for large soil animals, whose spatial distribution is commonly heterogeneous (
Fig. 2
) (

, 

). All samples will be processed separately, making it possible to assess local beta-diversity. Animal sorting will be done outside sampling sites to minimise disturbance.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Field sampling methods
</title>
         <p>
Selected methods
. We will use a combination of sampling methods to comprehensively represent soil animal communities, including micro-, meso-, and macrofauna (
Fig. 3
; Geisen et al. 2019, 

). Microfauna and enchytraeids will be collected using wet extractions (Baermann funnels; 

, 

), microarthropods using dry extraction (e.g. Berlese-like; 

), and macrofauna using hand-sorting (

, 

; details are given below). We have chosen these sampling methods as the most commonly used for the corresponding animal size groups and are straightforward enough to be used even by researchers with basic experience in soil animal ecology. These methods provide area-based estimations of biomass and density which is necessary for data comparability and calculations of energy fluxes and functional impacts of soil animals (

). For the latter reason, pitfall traps are not included in the main methods, but suggested as an auxiliary method (Supplementary protocol S1). We will also take pictures of topsoil profiles and sampling sites to collect environmental data (
Fig. 3
, Supplementary protocol S1).
</p>
         <p>
Sample areas
. We follow a common 19. 
6 cm
2
sample area for microarthropods, i.e. soil corer of 
5 cm
diameter (also used in the core Soil BON network sampling). We use the same sample area for microfauna and enchytraeids, but the sample is divided in two equal parts at 
Local hubs
(see below). A 
625 cm
2
sample area is used for macrofauna (soil monoliths 25 x 
25 cm
). Although a larger sample area would better represent large-sized actively-moving animals and social insects, we have to limit collection efforts to make the sampling of many sites feasible and thus make the initiative more inclusive for research teams and globally representative.
</p>
         <p>
Sample depth
. We sample the entire fresh litter layer (OL horizon, unfragmented litter) together with the first 
10 cm
of the underlying substrate (‘soil’, here referring to OF, OH, A, and sometimes top B horizons). Animals from litter and soil layers are collected and processed together to maximise efficiency and avoid data mismatch due to ambiguities in the definition of ‘litter’ (
Fig. 4
). Our assessment will focus on animals and processes in top soil and will miss deep-living soil animals (e.g., some endogeic earthworms; Lavelle 1988, 

), especially in soils with well-developed organic horizons (

, 

, 

). We also acknowledge that other special soil habitats such as suspended soils, subsoils and subterranean soils will not be included in this effort (see 

Fig. 
1 in

). This would allow the application of a single standard protocol and increase the number of sites to make the analysis globally representative. Furthermore, we plan to address the issue of undersampling of deep-living soil fauna by (1) performing sampling of deeper soil layers as an add-on project (Supplementary protocol S1), and (2) modelling the vertical distributions of different animal groups depending on the soil 
type
based on existing data (

, 

, 

, Lavelle et al. 
under review
). The uniform sampling depth is used for all samples to make the energy flux calculations comparable across size classes. To correctly measure the sampling depth, we strongly encourage soil zoologists to become familiar with the recent HUMUSICA publications to define the diagnostic horizons (

, Zanella et al. 2018b).
</p>
         <p>
Macrofauna collection.
Large invertebrates (&gt; 
3 mm
in body length) including earthworms are picked up by hand from litter and soil, generally following the Tropical Soil Biology and Fertility method (TSBF; 

). We excavate soil monoliths 25 x 
25 cm
to a 
10 cm
depth and animals are hand sorted either in the field or brought to a laboratory. All social insects (ants, termites) regardless their size and all other animals belonging to the size class between 3 and 
30 mm
and not belonging to taxa of microarthropods (mites, pseudoscorpions, symphylans, diplurans, pauropods etc.) (

) are collected and stored in 96% alcohol. Hand-sorting of macrofauna is preferred over dry extraction, because it has better compatibility with other existing global-scale initiatives (Lavelle et al. 
under revision
), is conventionally used to collect earthworms, and catches less mobile animals like gastropods and insect larvae (

). Besides, large amounts of material do not have to be transported to the laboratory, which is hard for remote sites and may be disruptive.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Animal extraction: Local hubs
</title>
         <p>
Animal extractions are done at 
Local hubs
to improve consistency of extractions across sites and make possible participation of research teams without extraction equipment. We distinguished 
Wet extraction hubs
that are equipped with Baermann funnels or other wet extraction equipment and 
Dry extraction hubs
that are equipped with dry Berlese, Tullgren, or high-gradient extractors. These 
two types
of hubs could (but do not have to) be at different locations and coordinated by different research teams. Each hub is expected to do extractions and animal imaging from 4-10 sites in the sampling year (i.e., 20-50 soil samples). 
Local hubs
can receive central support from the SBF Team (e.g. imaging equipment), their coordinators are closely engaged in the planning of sampling and add-on projects together with 
National coordinators
, and have priority to lead regional-scale synthesis studies. The global assessment in the framework of the SBF Team can be combined with ongoing regional and local-scale projects or monitoring activities as long as the sites are registered in Soil BON and the common sampling protocol is used. 
Local hubs
are also responsible for organising mid-term (at least 5 years) storage of samples, but are 
not
expected to do field sampling (unless research teams form both a 
Local hub
and a 
Field team
), animal sorting and identification (the latter is done by the 
Central team
from the images at iDiv, Leipzig). A collaboration with museums for long-term sample storage is encouraged. We also will provide detailed manuals and protocols of the extraction equipment and process on our web page (www.soilbonfoodweb.org).
</p>
         <p>
Nematode and enchytraeid extraction.
These two groups are extracted separately using wet extractors. For both groups, we recommend Baermann funnels as the most commonly used and more accessible method in comparison to e.g. Oostenbrink elutriator (

). Nematodes together with other microfauna are extracted through milk filters to produce clean samples. We will generally follow a recent protocol for large-scale nematode assessments to improve extraction efficiency (

). Formalin will be used as a storage agent to allow for potential future identifications. Enchytraeids are extracted separately through a 0. 
5 mm
mesh (ISO 23611-3 2019) and stored in ~96% ethanol to make the material suitable for potential genetic analyses.
</p>
         <p>
Microarthropod extraction.
To extract microarthropods, we recommend light bulb-equipped Tullgren/Berlese funnels (

, 

) or Macfadyen/Kempson high-gradient extractors (

, 

). These different extractor 
types
provide a fair representation of community composition and biomass of microarthropods and, despite in some cases favouring different groups, yield comparable results (

, 

, 

). The extraction is done through a 
2 mm
mesh to exclude large macrofauna, and ~96% ethanol is used as the collection and storage solution to make the material suitable for potential genetic analyses. Since each laboratory is equipped with slightly different extractors, we will provide detailed protocols on both wet and dry extraction procedures to participants and openly distribute in via www.soilbonfoodweb.org.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Animal identification
</title>
         <p>
Soil communities will be characterised at each sampling site based on the list of taxonomic and functional groups with data on their abundance, individual body masses, and total biomasses (the tentative list of target groups is given in 
Table 1
). On the one hand, a taxonomic grouping should be detailed enough to make functional inferences as well as a food web reconstruction possible (

, 

, 

, 

). On the other hand, the grouping should be generic enough to include all major taxa and regions and easy enough to allow the sorting by a general soil ecologist from a mixed community image, i.e. under a low magnification microscope. In most cases, we follow a taxonomic classification, because it allows for unambiguous
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Earthworms. 
Gastropoda
: snails, slugs. 
Orthoptera
: Ensifera, Caelifera. Cockroaches (
<tp:taxon-name>Blattidae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Corydiidae</tp:taxon-name>
), Isoptera, 
<tp:taxon-name>Formicidae</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Hemiptera
: Auchenorrhyncha, Sternorrhyncha, Heteroptera herbivores, Heteroptera predators. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Coleoptera
</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Carabidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cantharidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Elateridae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Staphylinidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Curculionidae</tp:taxon-name>
,
</p>
         <p>
Hand sorting 
<tp:taxon-name>Scarabaeidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tenebrionidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Silphidae</tp:taxon-name>
, other beetle families. Psocoptera, 
<tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera, Diptera, Dermaptera, Thysanoptera. Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
(only large epigeic species), other insect groups. 
Chilopoda
: Geophilomorpha, Lithobiomorpha and Scolopendromorpha. Diplopoda. Isopoda, other crustaceans. 
<tp:taxon-name>Araneae, Opiliones, Amblypygi, Uropygi, Solifugae, Scorpiones.</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
grouping of animals and because functional roles and trophic niches of soil animals are in general related to their taxonomic position (

, 

). In several functionally diverse groups, such as mites, flies, ants, and termites, a broad taxonomic resolution may lead to information loss (

, 

, 

, 

), but more detailed identification is constrained by the absence of appropriate taxonomic expertise across many regions. We are planning to approach these limitations in the follow-up molecular and taxonomic projects by establishing thematic collaborative networks. For instance, nematodes are planned to be sorted to trophic groups (
Table 1
) in collaboration with experts. In perspective, linking the global assessment of soil biodiversity with networks of taxonomic experts and organisation of taxonomic training programmes would allow for a great progress in the understanding of global soil biodiversity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Animal identification and measurement
</title>
         <p>
Animal sorting and identification is probably the most difficult and laborious part of soil animal assessments. Rapidly developing metabarcoding and metagenomic approaches are often seen as an alternative to visual identification (

, 

), however, they have strong limitations in the light of our aims: (1) large-scale assessments using these approaches are expensive and require complex local facilities, thus are not inclusive for research teams/regions with limited resources, (2) mass-sequencing methods are non-quantitative due to extraction and amplification biases (

, 

), (3) due to a limited trait data availability, it is not possible to extract body sizes for all soil invertebrate taxa based on genetic sequences and thus reliably calculate energy fluxes, (4) barcode libraries are absent for vast majority of soil invertebrate species to match phylogenetic positions with traits such as body size.
</p>
         <p>
As an alternative high-throughput approach, we adopt image analyses of mixed invertebrate community samples (

). Image analysis is based on visual animal identification and allows for direct body size estimations which can be used to estimate biomasses and energy fluxes. To acquire high resolution photographs, we will use a recently tested imaging pipeline for soil communities using a flatbed scanner (Potapov et al. 
unpublished data
). This approach lowers the costs of imaging equipment to max 350 USD, thus being inclusive for teams with limited resources (
Fig. 5
). The imaging is done at 
Local hubs
and all images are stored on central servers at iDiv, Leipzig.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Data acquisition
</title>
         <p>
High-resolution pictures will be processed by the 
Central team
using manual image annotations to develop a computer-vision pipeline based on deep learning algorithms (RCNN) (

, Sys et al. 
under review
). Preliminary tests on a community of 10 springtail and two mite species showed a detection rate of 77% with identification accuracy of 90% at the species level. We expect improvement of the two metrics with further developments of the training library and at a coarser taxonomic resolution. Manual annotations will be used at the initial stages and then deep learning algorithms will be applied to streamline the identification and measurement processes. With this approach, all individuals of micro-, meso-, and macrofauna will be identified to the group level (
Table 1
) and body dimensions will be measured. Individual body sizes will be converted to body masses and total community biomass using allometric equations (

, 

, 

, 

). With development of a training image library, scanning and image analysis are expected to speed up group-level identification and body size estimations of soil invertebrates and considerably reduce workload of 
Local hubs
. Our methodology can be applied by most soil ecology laboratories across the globe and will produce reliable and comparable data on density, biomass, and size distributions of all key functional groups of soil micro-, meso- and macrofauna found in the topsoil. All images and collected data will be centrally stored and accessible for the data providers who will have priority of analysing and publishing these data. Collected data and developed machine learning algorithms will be made openly available through public online platforms upon publication for the use of the research community.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Future prospects
</title>
         <p>
Data collected by the SBF Team will be linked to the data on soil, vegetation, climatic, and microbial parameters generated by ongoing work at respective Soil BON sites, and relationships between soil animals and ecosystem functioning and their responses to environmental factors and human activities will be assessed. We will also compare soil animal communities inside and outside of the protected areas worldwide to evaluate the effect of current conservation practices on soil animal communities. To analyse the animal data, we will use different approaches, such as path analysis (

), geospatial modelling (

), food-web reconstruction and modelling (

, 

), and energy flux approaches (

, 

). We also plan to link collected animal data with multiple functional traits to assess global variation in the functional diversity of soil animal communities (

, 

) and work on integration of our results in suggested animal-based biogeochemical models (

, 

, 

). Finally, any SBF Team participant can propose further ideas of how to use the collected data to the 
Global coordination team
and test his/her/their hypotheses.
</p>
         <p>
The developed protocol can be used beyond the SBF Team in any other compatible observational or experimental study that aims to accumulate standard and comprehensive data on soil animal communities across environmental and biotic gradients. To ensure the long-term data safety, compatibility, and accessibility, common databases on community images and animal counts will be established. We intend to upload collected data to Edaphobase (

) which will make it publicly available directly and through the linked Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF; 

). To ensure the safety of collected materials, all animals will be stored in ~96% ethanol in the freezer for at least five years after the sampling, and this period is likely to be prolonged. These storage conditions will allow us to run potential add-on projects on biodiversityrelated questions, such as metabarcoding of soil animal communities and taxonomic identification of selected animal groups. Established collaborative networks at the global and regional scales will serve as the coordination basis for such add-on projects, facilitating soil animal ecology and providing science-based evidence to policymakers to support soil biodiversity conservation and functioning of the terrestrial biosphere.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
AP and SS acknowledge support of the German Research Foundation (DFG–SFB 990, 192626868 – collaborative German - Indonesian research project CRC990 - EFForTS). NE acknowledges support of iDiv funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG– FZT 118, 202548816). NE acknowledges funding by the by the DFG (Ei 862/29-1 and Ei 862/31-1) and European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union‘s Horizon 2020 research and innovation program (grant agreement no. 677232). GGB acknowledges support of CNPq (Process 310690/2017-0). XS acknowledges support of the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(No. 42021005, 41571052), and the National Science and Technology Fundamental Resources Investigation Program of 
China
(No. 2018FY100303). We thank all anonymous ‘Where is the litter?’ poll participants.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Supplementary materials
</title>
         <p>Protocol S1 describing field sampling; as supplementary file to this article on www.soil-organisms.org.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Anderson, J. M.
&amp; 
J. S. I. Ingram
(
1993
): 
Tropical Soil Biology and Fertility: A Handbook of Methods. – C.A.B. International, Wallingford, Oxfordshire
, 
England
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Andrassy, I.
(
1956
): 
Die rauminhalts-und gewichtsbestimmung der fadenwürmer (Nematoden)
.– 
Acta Zoologica Hungarica

2

: 
1–5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
André, H. M.
, 
X. Ducarme
&amp; 
P. Lebrun
(
2002
): 
Soil biodiversity: myth, reality or conning?
– 
Oikos

96

: 
3–24
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bardgett, R. D.
, &amp; 
W. H. van der Putten
(
2014
): 
Belowground biodiversity and ecosystem functioning
. – 
Nature

515

: 
505–511
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Barnes, A. D.
, 
M. Jochum
, 
J. S. Lefcheck
, 
N. Eisenhauer
, 
C. Scherber
, 
M. I. O’Connor
, 
P. de Ruiter
&amp; 
U. Brose
(
2018
): 
Energy Flux: The Link between Multitrophic Biodiversity and Ecosystem Functioning
. – 
Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution

33

: 
186–197
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Barnes, A. D.
, 
M. Jochum
, 
S. Mumme
, 
N. F. Haneda
, 
A. Farajallah
, 
T. H. Widarto
&amp; 
U. Brose
(
2014
): 
Consequences of tropical land use for multitrophic biodiversity and ecosystem functioning
. – 
Nature Communications

5

: 
5351
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bignell, D. E.
(
2009
): 
Towards a universal sampling protocol for soil biotas in the humid tropics
. – 
Pesquisa Agropecuaria Brasileira

44

: 
825–834
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bonkowski, M.
, 
C. Villenave
&amp; 
B. Griffiths
(
2009
): 
Rhizosphere fauna: the functional and structural diversity of intimate interactions of soil fauna with plant roots
. – 
Plant and Soil

321

: 
213–233
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Briones, M. J. I.
(
2014
): 
Soil fauna and soil functions: a jigsaw puzzle
. – 
Frontiers in Environmental Science

2

[
https://doi. org/10.3389/fenvs.2014.00007]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Brousseau, P.-M.
, 
D. Gravel
&amp; 
I. T. Handa
(
2018
): 
On the development of a predictive functional trait approach for studying terrestrial arthropods
. – 
The Journal of Animal Ecology

87

: 
1209–1220
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Brussaard, L.
(
1998
): 
Soil fauna, guilds, functional groups and ecosystem processes
. – 
Applied Soil Ecology: A Section of Agriculture, Ecosystems &amp; Environment

9

: 
123–135
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Buchkowski, R. W.
, &amp; 
Z. Lindo
(
2021
): 
Stoichiometric and structural uncertainty in soil food web models
. – 
Functional Ecology
35
(
1
): 
288–300
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Burkhardt, U.
, 
D. J. Russell
, 
P. Decker
, 
M. Döhler
, 
H. Höfer
, 
S. Lesch
, 
S. Rick
, 
J. Römbke
, 
C. Trog
, 
J. Vorwald
&amp; et al. (
2014
): 
The Edaphobase project of GBIF-Germany—A new online soil-zoological data warehouse
. – 
Applied Soil Ecology

83

: 
3–12
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cameron, E. K.
, 
I. S. Martins
, 
P. Lavelle
, 
J. Mathieu
, 
L. Tedersoo
, 
M. Bahram
, 
F. Gottschall
, 
C. A. Guerra
, 
J. Hines
, 
G. Patoine
&amp; et al. (
2019
): 
Global mismatches in aboveground and belowground biodiversity
. – 
Conservation Biology

33

: 
1187–1192
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cardoso, P.
, 
S. Pekár
, 
R. Jocqué
&amp; 
J. A. Coddington
(
2011
): 
Global patterns of guild composition and functional diversity of spiders
. – 
PloS One

6

: e 
21710
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cesarz, S.
, 
A. E. Schulz
, 
R. Beugnon
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2019
): 
Testing soil nematode extraction efficiency using different variations of the Baermann-funnel method
. – 
Soil Organisms

91

: 
61–72
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chertov, O.
, 
A. Komarov
, 
C. Shaw
, 
S. Bykhovets
, 
P. Frolov
, 
V. Shanin
, 
P. Grabarnik
, 
I. Priputina
, 
E. Zubkova
&amp; 
M. Shashkov
(
2017
): 
Romul_Hum—A model of soil organic matter formation coupling with soil biota activity. II. Parameterisation of the soil food web biota activity
. – 
Ecological Modelling

345

: 
125–139
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Coulibaly, S. F. M.
, 
B. R. Winck
, 
M. Akpa-Vinceslas
, 
L. Mignot
, 
M. Legras
, 
F. Forey
&amp; 
M. Chauvat
(
2019
): 
Functional assemblages of Collembola determine soil microbial communities and associated functions
. – 
Frontiers of Environmental Science

7

[
https://doi.org/10.3389/ fenvs.2019.00052]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Deckmyn, G.
, 
O. Flores
, 
M. Mayer
, 
X. Domene
, 
A. Schnepf
, 
K. Kuka
, 
K. Van Looy
, 
D. P. Rasse
, 
M. J. I. Briones
, 
S. Barot
&amp; et al. (
2020
): 
KEYLINK: towards a more integrative soil representation for inclusion in ecosystem scale models. I. review and model concept
. – 
PeerJ

8

: e 
9750
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
De Goede, R. G. M.
&amp; 
B. Verschoor
(
2000
): 
The nematode extraction efficiency of the Oostenbrink elutriator-cottonwool filter method with special reference to nematode body size and life strategy
. – 
Nematology

2

: 
325–342
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
de Vries, F. T.
, 
E. Thebault
, 
M. Liiri
, 
K. Birkhofer
, 
M. A. Tsiafouli
, 
L. Bjornlund
, 
H. B. Jorgensen
, 
M. V. Brady
, 
S. Christensen
, 
P. C. de Ruiter
&amp; et al. (
2013
): 
Soil food web properties explain ecosystem services across European land use systems
. – 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America

110

: 
14296–14301
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Delgado-Baquerizo, M.
, 
P. B. Reich
, 
C. Trivedi
, 
D. J. Eldridge
, 
S. Abades
, 
F. D. Alfaro
, 
F. Bastida
, 
A. A. Berhe
, 
N. A. Cutler
, 
A. Gallardo
&amp; et al. (
2020
): 
Multiple elements of soil biodiversity drive ecosystem functions across biomes
. – 
Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution

4

: 
210–220
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Demetrio, W. C.
, 
A. C. Conrado
, 
A. N. S. Acioli
, 
A. C. Ferreira
, 
M. L. C. Bartz
, 
S. W. James
, 
E. da Silva
, 
L. S. Maia
, 
G. C. Martins
, 
R. S. Macedo
&amp; et al. (
2021
): 
A “Dirty” Footprint: Macroinvertebrate diversity in Amazonian Anthropic Soils
. – 
Global Change Biology

27

: 
4575–4591
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dopheide, A.
, 
D. Xie
, 
T. R. Buckley
, 
A. J. Drummond
&amp; 
R. D. Newcomb
(
2019
): 
Impacts of DNA extraction and PCR on DNA metabarcoding estimates of soil biodiversity
. – 
Methods in Ecology and Evolution

10

: 
120–133
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Edwards, C. A.
(
1991
): 
The assessment of populations of soil-inhabiting invertebrates
. – 
Agriculture, Ecosystems &amp; Environment

34

: 
145–176
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eggleton, P.
&amp; 
I. Tayasu
(
2001
): 
Feeding groups, lifetypes and the global ecology of termites
. – 
Ecological Research

16

: 
941–960
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ehnes, R. B.
, 
B. C. Rall
&amp; 
U. Brose
(
2011
): 
Phylogenetic grouping, curvature and metabolic scaling in terrestrial invertebrates
. – 
Ecology Letters

14

: 
993–1000
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
Bonn,A.
, &amp;A 
Guerra, C.
(
2019
): 
Recognizing the quiet extinction of invertebrates
. 
–– Nature Communications

10

: 
50
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
M.A. Bowker
, 
J. B. Grace
&amp; 
J. R. Powell
(
2015
): 
From patterns to causal understanding: Structural equation modeling (SEM) in soil ecology
. – 
Pedobiologia

58

: 
65–72
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
F. Buscot
, 
A. Heintz-Buschart
, 
S. D. Jurburg
, 
K. Küsel
, 
J. Sikorski
, 
H.-J. Vogel
&amp; 
C. A. Guerra
(
2021
): 
The multidimensionality of soil macroecology
. – 
Global Ecology and Biogeography

30

: 
4–10
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fierer, N.
, 
M. S. Strickland
, 
D. Liptzin
, 
M. A. Bradford
&amp; 
C. C. Cleveland
(
2009
): 
Global patterns in belowground communities
. – 
Ecology Letters

12

: 
1238–1249
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Filser, J.
, 
J. H. Faber
, 
A. V. Tiunov
, 
L. Brussaard
, 
J. Frouz
, 
G. De Deyn
, 
A. V. Uvarov
, 
M. P. Berg
, P. 
Lavelle, M.
Loreau
&amp; et al. (
2016
): 
Soil fauna: key to new carbon models
. – 
Soil

2

: 
565–582
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Flores, O.
, 
G. Deckmyn
, 
J. Curiel Yuste
, 
M. Javaux
, 
A. Uvarov
, 
S. van der Linde
, 
B. De Vos
, 
H. Vereecken
, 
J. Jiménez
, 
O. Vinduskova
&amp; 
A. Schnepf
(
2021
): 
KEYLINK: towards a more integrative soil representation for inclusion in ecosystem scale models-II: model description, implementation and testing
. – 
PeerJ

9

: e 
10707
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frouz, J.
(
1999
): 
Use of soil dwelling Diptera (Insecta, Diptera) as bioindicators: a review of ecological requirements and response to disturbance
. – 
Agriculture, Ecosystems &amp; Environment

74

: 
167–186
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
García-Palacios, P.
, 
F. T. Maestre
, 
J. Kattge
&amp; 
D. H. Wall
(
2013
): 
Climate and litter quality differently modulate the effects of soil fauna on litter decomposition across biomes
. – 
Ecology Letters

16

: 
1045–1053
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Geisen, S.
, 
M. J. I. Briones
, 
H. Gan
, 
V. M. Behan-Pelletier
, 
V.-P. Friman
, 
G. A. de Groot
, 
S. E. Hannula
, 
Z. Lindo
, 
L. Philippot
, 
A. V. Tiunov
&amp; 
D. H. Wall
(
2019
): 
A methodological framework to embrace soil biodiversity
. – 
Soil Biology &amp; Biochemistry

136

: 
107536
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Geisen, S.
, 
D. H. Wall
&amp; 
W. H. van der Putten
(
2019
): 
Challenges and Opportunities for Soil Biodiversity in the Anthropocene
. – 
Current Biology

29

: R 
1036–R1044
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gongalsky, K. B.
(
2021
): 
Soil macrofauna: Study problems and perspectives
. – 
Soil Biology &amp; Biochemistry

159

: 
108281
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guerra, C. A.
, 
R. D. Bardgett
, 
L. Caon
, 
T. W. Crowther
, 
M. Delgado-Baquerizo
, 
L. Montanarella
, 
L. M. Navarro
, 
A. Orgiazzi
, 
B. K. Singh
, 
L. Tedersoo
&amp; et al. (
2021
a): 
Tracking, targeting, and conserving soil biodiversity
. – 
Science

371

: 
239–241
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guerra, C. A.
, 
M.Delgado-Baquerizo
, 
E.Duarte
, 
O. Marigliano
, 
C. Görgen
, 
F. T. Maestre
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2021
b): 
Global projections of the soil microbiome in the Anthropocene
. – 
Global Ecology and Biogeography

30

: 
987–999
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guerra, C. A.
, 
A. Heintz-Buschart
, 
J. Sikorski
, 
A. Chatzinotas
, 
N. Guerrero-Ramírez
, 
S. Cesarz
, 
L. Beaumelle
, 
M. C. Rillig
, 
F. T. Maestre
, 
M. Delgado-Baquerizo
, 
F. Buscot
&amp; et al. (
2020
): 
Blind spots in global soil biodiversity and ecosystem function research
. – 
Nature Communications

11

: 
3870
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guerra, C. A.
, 
D. H. Wall
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2021
c): 
Unearthing soil ecological observations
. – 
Soil Organisms

93

: 
79–81
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Handa, I. T.
, 
R. Aerts
, 
F. Berendse
, 
M. P. Berg
, 
A. Bruder
, 
O. Butenschoen
, 
E. Chauvet
, 
M. O. Gessner
, 
J. Jabiol
, 
M. Makkonen
&amp; et al. (
2014
): 
Consequences of biodiversity loss for litter decomposition across biomes
. – 
Nature

509

: 
218–221
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hassall, M.
, 
S. Adl
, 
M. Berg
, 
B. Griffiths
&amp; 
S. Scheu
(
2006
): 
Soil fauna–microbe interactions: towards a conceptual framework for research
. – 
European Journal of Soil Biology

42

: 
54–60
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Heberling, J. M.
, 
J. T. Miller
, 
D. Noesgaard
, 
S. Weingart
&amp; 
D. Schigel
(
2021
): 
Data integration enables global biodiversity synthesis
. – 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America

118

: e 
2018093118
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huhta, V.
(
2007
): 
The role of soil fauna in ecosystems: A historical review
. – 
Pedobiologia

50

: 
489–495
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ISO
23611-3 (
2019
): 
Soil quality - sampling of soil invertebrates. Part 3
, 
Sampling and extraction of enchytraeids
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jiménez, J. J.
&amp; 
T. Decaëns
(
2000
): ‘ 
Vertical Distribution of Earthworms in Grassland Soils of the Colombian Llanos’
. – 
Biology and Fertility of Soils

32

: 
463–73
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jochum, M.
, 
A. D. Barnes
, 
U. Brose
, 
B. Gauzens
, 
M. Sünnemann
, 
Amyntas
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2021
): 
For flux’s sake: General considerations for energy-flux calculations in ecological communities
. – 
Ecology and Evolution

11

: 
12948–12969
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jochum, M.
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2022
): 
Out of the dark: Using energy flux to connect above‐ and belowground communities and ecosystem functioning
. – 
European Journal of Soil Science

73

: e 
13154
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kempson, D.
, 
M. Lloyd
&amp; 
R. Ghelardi
(
1963
): 
A new extractor for woodland litter
. – 
Pedobiologia

3

: 
1–21
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
King, J. R.
(
2016
): 
Where do eusocial insects fit into soil food webs?
– 
Soil Biology &amp; Biochemistry

102

: 
55–62
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lavelle, P.
, 
T. Decaëns
, 
M. Aubert
, 
S. Barot
, 
M. F. Blouin
, 
F. Bureau
, 
P. Margerie
, 
P. Mora
&amp; 
J.-P. Rossi
(
2006
): 
Soil invertebrates and ecosystem services
. – 
European Journal of Soil Biology

42

: 
3–15
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, M.
, 
L. J. Clarke
, 
S. C. Baker
, 
G. J. Jordan
&amp; 
C. P. Burridge
(
2020
): 
A practical guide to DNA metabarcoding for entomological ecologists
. – 
Ecological Entomology

45

: 
373– 385
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Macfadyen, A.
(
1961
): 
Improved funnel-type extractors for soil arthropods
. – 
The Journal of Animal Ecology
30
(
1
): 
171–184
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maestre, F. T.
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2019
): 
Recommendations for establishing global collaborative networks in soil ecology
. – 
Soil Organisms

91

: 
73–85
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moreira, F. M. S.
, 
E. Jeroen Huising
&amp; 
D. E. Bignell
(
2012
): 
A Handbook of Tropical Soil Biology: Sampling and Characterization of Below-ground Biodiversity. Routledge, Milton Park, Abingdon
, 
Oxfordshire
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Newton, J. S.
, &amp; 
H. Proctor
(
2013
): 
A fresh look at weightestimation models for soil mites (Acari)
. – 
International Journal of Acarology

39

: 
72–85
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niva, C. C.
, 
R. M. Cezar
, 
P. M. Fonseca
, 
M. R. G. Zagatto
, 
E. M. Oliveira
, 
E. F. Bush
, 
L. A. Clasen
&amp; 
G. G. Brown
(
2015
): 
Enchytraeid abundance in Araucaria Mixed Forest determined by cold and hot wet extraction
. – 
Brazilian Journal of Biology

75

: 
169–175
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oliverio, A. M.
, 
H. Gan
, 
K. Wickings
&amp; 
N. Fierer
(
2018
): 
A DNA metabarcoding approach to characterize soil arthropod communities
. – 
Soil Biology &amp; Biochemistry

125

: 
37–43
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Orgiazzi, A.
&amp; 
P. Panagos
(
2018
): 
Soil biodiversity and soil erosion: It is time to get married
. – 
Global Ecology and Biogeography

27

: 
1155–1167
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pereira-da-Conceicoa, L.
, 
V. Elbrecht
, 
A. Hall
, 
A. Briscoe
, 
H. Barber-James
&amp; 
B. Price
(
2021
): 
Metabarcoding unsorted kick‐samples facilitates macroinvertebrate‐based biomonitoring with increased taxonomic resolution, while outperforming environmental DNA
. – 
Environmental DNA

3

: 
353–371
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Petersen, H.
(
1975
): 
Estimation of dry weight, fresh weight, and calorific content of various Collembolan species
. – 
Pedobiologia

15

: 
222–243
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Petersen, H.
&amp; 
M. Luxton
(
1982
): 
A comparative analysis of soil fauna populations and their role in decomposition processes
. – 
Oikos

39

: 
288–388
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pey, B.
, 
J. Nahmani
, 
A. Auclerc
, 
Y. Capowiez
, 
D. Cluzeau
, 
J. Cortet
, 
T. Decaëns
, 
L. Deharveng
, 
F. Dubs
, 
S. Joimel
&amp; et al. (
2014
): 
Current use of and future needs for soil invertebrate functional traits in community ecology
. – 
Basic and Applied Ecology

15

: 
194–206
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Phillips, H. R. P.
, 
C. A. Guerra
, 
M. L. C. Bartz
, 
M. J. I. Briones
, 
G. Brown
, 
T. W. Crowther
, 
O. Ferlian
, 
K. B. Gongalsky
, 
J. van den Hoogen
, 
J. Krebs
&amp; et al. (
2019
): 
Global distribution of earthworm diversity
. – 
Science

366

: 
480–485
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Potapov, A.
(
2021
): 
Multifunctionality of belowground food webs: resource
, 
size and spatial energy channels. – bioRxiv
[
https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.06.06.447267]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Potapov, A.
, 
B. Bellini
, 
S. Chown
, 
L. Deharveng
, 
F. Janssens
, 
Ľ. Kováč
, 
N. Kuznetsova
, 
J.-F. Ponge
, 
M. Potapov
, 
P. Querner
&amp; et al. (
2020
a): 
Towards a global synthesis of Collembola knowledge – challenges and potential solutions
. – 
Soil Organisms

92

: 
161–188
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Potapov, A. M.
, 
N. Dupérré
, 
M. Jochum
, 
K. Dreczko
, 
B. Klarner
, 
A. D. Barnes
, 
V. Krashevska
, 
K. Rembold
, 
H. Kreft
, 
U. Brose
&amp; et al. (
2020
b): 
Functional losses in ground spider communities due to habitat structure degradation under tropical land-use change
. – 
Ecology

101

: e 
02957
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Potapov, A. M.
, 
A. A. Goncharov
, 
E. E. Semenina
, 
A. Y. Korotkevich
, 
S. M. Tsurikov
, 
O. L. Rozanova
, 
A. E. Anichkin
, 
A. G. Zuev
, 
E. S. Samoylova
, 
I. I. Semenyuk
&amp; et al. (
2017
): 
Arthropods in the subsoil: Abundance and vertical distribution as related to soil organic matter, microbial biomass and plant roots
. – 
European Journal of Soil Biology

82

: 
88–97
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Potapov, A. M.
, 
C. A. Guerra
, 
J. van den Hoogen
, 
A. Babenko
, 
B. C. Bellini
, 
M. P. Berg
, 
S. L. Chown
, L., Deharveng, 
L.Kovac
, 
N.A.Kuznetsova
&amp; et al.(
2022
): 
Globally invariant metabolism but density-diversity mismatch in springtails
. – 
bioRxiv
[
https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.01.07.475345]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Potapov, A. M.
, 
S. Scheu
&amp; 
A. V. Tiunov
(
2019
): 
Trophic consistency of supraspecific taxa in below-ground invertebrate communities: Comparison across lineages and taxonomic ranks
. – 
Functional Ecology

33

: 
1172–1183
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rossi, J.-P.
, 
J. Mathieu
, 
M. Cooper
&amp; 
M. Grimaldi
(
2006
): 
Soil macrofaunal biodiversity in Amazonian pastures: Matching sampling with patterns
. – 
Soil Biology &amp; Biochemistry

38

: 
2178–2187
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ruiz, N.
, 
J. Mathieu
, 
L. Célini
, 
C. Rollard
, 
G. Hommay
, 
E. Iorio
&amp; 
P. Lavelle
(
2011
): 
IBQS: A synthetic index of soil quality based on soil macro-invertebrate communities
. – 
Soil Biology &amp; Biochemistry

43

: 
2032–2045
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sackett, T. E.
, 
A. T. Classen
&amp; 
N. J. Sanders
(
2010
): 
Linking soil food web structure to above- and belowground ecosystem processes: a meta-analysis
. – 
Oikos

119

: 
1984–1992
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schneider, K.
, 
S. Migge
, 
R. A. Norton
, 
S. Scheu
, 
R. Langel
, 
A. Reineking
&amp; 
M. Maraun
(
2004
): 
Trophic niche differentiation in soil microarthropods (Oribatida, Acari): evidence from stable isotope ratios (15N/14N)
. – 
Soil Biology &amp; Biochemistry

36

: 
1769–1774
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schneider, S.
, 
G. W. Taylor
, 
S. C. Kremer
, 
P. Burgess
, 
J. McGroarty
, 
K. Mitsui
, 
A. Zhuang
, 
J. R. deWaard
&amp; 
J. M. Fryxell
(
2021
): 
Bulk arthropod abundance, biomass and diversity estimation using deep learning for computer vision
. – 
Methods in Ecology and Evolution
[
https://doi. org/10.1111/2041-210X.13769]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Scholes, R. J.
, 
G. M. Mace
, 
W. Turner
, 
G. N. Geller
, 
N. Jurgens
, 
A. Larigauderie
, 
D. Muchoney
, 
B. A. Walther
&amp; 
H. A. Mooney
(
2008
): 
Toward a global biodiversity observing system
. – 
Science

321

: 
1044–1045
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Seibold, S.
, 
W. Rammer
, 
T. Hothorn
, 
R. Seidl
, 
M. D. Ulyshen
, 
J. Lorz
, 
M. W. Cadotte
, 
D. B. Lindenmayer
, 
Y. P. Adhikari
, 
R. Aragón
&amp; et al. (
2021
): 
The contribution of insects to global forest deadwood decomposition
. – 
Nature

597

: 
77–81
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sohlström, E. H.
, 
L. Marian
, 
A. D. Barnes
, 
N. F. Haneda
, 
S. Scheu
, 
B. C. Rall
, 
U. Brose
&amp; 
M. Jochum
(
2018
): 
Applying generalized allometric regressions to predict live body mass of tropical and temperate arthropods
. – 
Ecology and Evolution

8

: 
12737–12749
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Soong, J. L.
&amp; 
U. N. Nielsen
(
2016
): 
The role of microarthropods in emerging models of soil organic matter
. – 
Soil Biology &amp; Biochemistry

102

: 
37–39
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Trap, J.
, 
M. Bonkowski
, 
C. Plassard
, 
C. Villenave
&amp; 
E. Blanchart
(
2016
): 
Ecological importance of soil bacterivores for ecosystem functions
. – 
Plant and Soil

398

: 
1–24
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tullgren, A.
(
1917
): En 
enkel apparat for automatiskt vittjande av sallgods
. – 
Entomologisk Tidskrift

38

: 
97–100
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
van den Hoogen, J.
, 
S. Geisen
, 
D. Routh
, 
H. Ferris
, 
W. Traunspurger
, 
D. A. Wardle
, 
R. G. M. de Goede
, 
B. J. Adams
, 
W. Ahmad
, 
W. S. Andriuzzi
&amp; et al. (
2019
): 
Soil nematode abundance and functional group composition at a global scale
. – 
Nature

572

: 
194–198
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
van den Hoogen, J.
, 
N. Robmann
, 
D. Routh
, 
T. Lauber
, 
N. van Tiel
, 
O. Danylo
&amp; 
T. W. Crowther
(
2021
): 
A geospatial mapping pipeline for ecologists
. – 
bioRxiv
[
https://doi. org/10.1101/2021.07.07.451145]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
van Groenigen, J. W.
, 
I. M. Lubbers
, 
H. M. J. Vos
, 
G. G. Brown
, 
G. B. De Deyn
&amp; 
K. J. van Groenigen
(
2014
): 
Earthworms increase plant production: a meta-analysis
. – 
Scientific Reports

4

: 
6365
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
White, H. J.
, 
L. León-Sánchez
, 
V. J. Burton
, 
E. K. Cameron
, 
T. Caruso
, 
L. Cunha
, 
T. Dirilgen
, 
S. D. Jurburg
, 
R. Kelly
, 
D. Kumaresan
&amp; et al. (
2020
): 
Methods and approaches to advance soil macroecology
. – 
Global Ecology and Biogeography

29

: 
1674–1690
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zanella, A.
, 
J.-F. Ponge
, 
J.-M. Gobat
, 
J. Juilleret
, 
M. Blouin
, 
M. Aubert
, 
O. Chertov
&amp; 
J. L. Rubio
(
2018
a): 
Humusica 1
, article 1: 
Essential bases – Vocabulary. – Applied Soil Ecology

122

: 
10–21
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zanella, A.
, 
J.-F. Ponge
, 
B. Jabiol
, 
G. Sartori
, 
E. Kolb
, 
J.-M. Gobat
, 
R.-C. L. Bayon
, 
M. Aubert
, 
R. D. Waal
, 
B. Van Delft
, 
A. Vacca
&amp; et al. (
2018
b): 
Humusica 1
, article 4: 
Terrestrial humus systems and forms — Specific terms and diagnostic horizons. – Applied Soil Ecology

122

: 
56–74
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
