<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Soil Organisms</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25674/eG3x</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Conservation of ant material for natural history collections (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2018</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Formicidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>

CHtHONOLASIUS

</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dinoponera australis
Borgmeier, 1937
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Discothyrea sexarticulata
Borgmeier, 1954
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Formica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lasius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Myrmica hirsuta
Elmes, 1978
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Formica uralensis
Ruzsky, 1895
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camponotus
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chthonolasius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chthonolasius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chthonolasius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tetramorium caespitum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Myrmica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lasius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Formica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Myrmica
(
Radchenko &amp; Elmes 2010
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tapinoma
(
Seifert et al. 2017
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camponotus vagus
(Scopoli, 1763)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Formicoxenus nitidulus
(Nylander, 1846)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lasius nitidigaster
Seifert, 1996
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lasius niger
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Formica sanguinea
Latreille, 1798
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Formica sanguinea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Polyrhachis dives
(Smith, 1857)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Solenopsis
Westwood, 1840
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Solenopsis
Westwood, 1840
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Chthonolasius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Alexander Prosche
</title>
         <p>

Conservation of ant material for natural history collections (
<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Formicidae</tp:taxon-name>
)

</p>
         <p>
Internationales HochschUlinstitUt - TU Dresden, Markt 23, 02763 ZittaU, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>E-mail: prosche90@web.de</p>
         <p>
Received 
23 JUne 2018
| Accepted 
16 JUly 2018
</p>
         <p>
Published online at www.soil-organisms.de 


1 AUGUst 
2018

| Printed version 
15 AUGUst 2018
</p>
         <p>
DOI 
10.25674/eG3x-w
721
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Abstract
</title>
         <p>Correct sampling and preparation of living material build up the heart of all natural history collections. Ideally, the samples outlive their collectors and preparators for centuries. This article gives advice on correct and durable storage of either mounted or ethanol stored material as well as on correct sampling during field work. Furthermore, the advantages and disadvantages of a number of the most common ant preparation techniques for inner and outer body characters are presented, compared, and illustrated. This can either mean a decision between a basket shape arrangement, a preparation according to Wilson, or a preparation in standing position if the whole individual and its morphology is of interest. Dissection methods to obtain information on inner organs involved in pheromonal communication or indicating reproductive status and age are described.</p>
         <p>
Keywords
ants
| 
preparation techniQUes
| 
<tp:taxon-name>
CHtHONOLASIUS
</tp:taxon-name>
| 
ethanol storaGe
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The preparation of insect material can be dated back to antique and medieval times when insects – mainly colorful beetles and butterflies – were collected and conserved for appreciation of beauty or artistic design (

, 

). In the early seventeenth century, entomology was founded as scientific discipline. Collection became the decisive instrument of documentation and comparison. Famous scientists and collectors, such as Charles Darwin or Alfred Russel Wallace increased the amount of material tremendously and influenced nomenclature until the present times (

). These classical materials are conserved until now and have a high value and importance for evolutionists and taxonomists.
</p>
         <p>In the nineteenth century the collection of insects became popular for the educated middle class, especially the collection of lepidopterans. Later, these collections usually were donated to natural history museums and increased the information about distribution and rarity. Some taxa were more popular than others resulting in nearly continuous information flow for beetles and butterflies and a lack of information for less eye-catching beautiful groups through the decades.</p>
         <p>This article deals with the preparation of ants, which belong to the aculeate hymenopterans. These mostly have a strongly sclerotized exoskeleton, which allows preparation without any pretreatment.</p>
         <p>
Ants can strikingly differ in their respective size (
Fig. 1
), which requires different modes of preparation. The systematic and scientific collection of ant material started more than 250 years ago when Carl Linnaeus named the first ants and provided their first taxonomic system (

, 

). Later, taxonomists, such as Carlo Emery (1848–1925) and Auguste-Henri Forel (1848–1931), described many new taxa, substantially extending the number of 
type
specimens (

, 

). There are different methods of preparation, which have advantages and disadvantages regarding stability and visibility of characters. The present study aims at a brief summary of the most common techniques for preparation of ant material. This includes the preparation of whole and intact ant bodies as well as the preparation of inner organs, such as wing-musculature or reproductive organs, which provide valuable information about reproductive capabilities.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Collecting and general storage
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1 Collecting of ant material
</title>
         <p>
The preparation of ant material starts with a correct sampling. For the field work a short, stable knife is a proper tool to access small nests in bark, rotten logs, nuts, acorns or snail shells. For opening harder material – such as living wood – a small camping ax is an applicable tool. In order to lift stones partially sunken into soil, a robust, modified screwdriver is most effective, the tip of which is bent rectangularly within the plane of the apical flattening, about 
2–3 cm
from the tip. Furthermore, a hand shovel is a good tool for work in loose soil substrates (

). Ant material is usually collected using an aspirator to catch several individuals or a whole nest community. In the latter case, information about colony size, number of gynes, number of eggs, larvae, and pupae or the occurrence of social parasites can be obtained. The collected ants can be killed using a screw cup jar with a sponge containing cyanide or ethyl-acetate. This allows – mainly important for ants living in loose soil or sand – a more easy separation from soil particles after sampling with an aspirator. As another possibility the collected ants can be put directly into high concentrations of ethanol (70– 99 %). Fast killing and a proper conservation is done with ethanol in a single process. Compared to 70–75 % ethanol which is frequently recommended as storage medium for insects, the higher concentration shows considerable advantages for mounting. Preparation from 70 % causes difficulties in appropriate adjustment and positioning of body parts. After they are brought in a desired position, they try to return into their original position when released. This feature often lasts for many hours – depending on the ant size – thus requires fixation until the glue has dried and leads to a high time expenditure (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2 Long-term storage
</title>
         <p>
In general, ants are either stored in ethanol, ethanolglycerol mixtures, or as dried mounted specimens in insect boxes. As the preparation of the collected ant material needs a high amount of time, sampling and preparation may be separated by a longer period of time. Thus, the storage and conservation liquid used are highly relevant for the results of later scientific work. Ethanol conserves via dehydrating the material, which usually, due to the strongly sclerotized exoskeleton, has only a small impact on the body shape of ants. The wet material has to be stored continuously in pure undenatured ethanol (99 %+) to conserve the DNA for several years (

) as well as outer body parts for decades. Due to dehydration and the resulting water intake, solvents should be changed regularly to inhibit denaturation of DNA. Best conservation of outer body is given by using 10 % glycerol in ethanol. Glycerol does not evaporate, is hygroscopic and thus prevents desiccation of the material even if it is stored for long time periods. On the other hand, the main disadvantage of this method is the formation of a glycerol layer on the cuticle causing a sticking-together of pubescence hairs or masking of important micro-structures of cuticle and pilosity. This layer has to be removed by one or two washing steps. One unwelcome effect of ethanol is the strong bleaching effect leading to a loss of pigmentation after several years or, on rare occasions, it also leads to the opposite effect in converging reddish ants into blackish ants. Thus, the samples should be stored preferably in a cool and dark place in order to prevent additional bleaching by (sun-) light and evaporation of solvent. Formaldehyde or its ethanol dilutions also show high bleaching effects and an irreversible hardening of joints (

). Additionally, due to the widely discussed issue of a potential risk for health, the use of formaldehyde should be avoided as far as possible (

). Plant material, soil particles, and other remnants of sampling should be removed. The latter may have an impact on the acidity of the storage liquid or may cause discolorations (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>Ethanol collections are classically stored using glass tubes, which are closed by some cotton wool and placed in a second container filled with ethanol. This method has the benefit of an easy and fast refill, but leads to high searching effort if a single tube is of interest. Another option is the storage in plastic tubes with some sealing ring containing lids. These tubes do not necessarily need a second container and can thus be more easily stored in a numerical order. An additional digital file providing information on each number is an important step for wellarranged collections. Many of the sealing rings, however, do not fully ensure a tight closing, which may lead to a complete desiccation of the material after a longer period of time. The possibly best way of storage would be tightly closing borosilicate glasses, which inhibit chemical processes and interactions harming the conserved material – mainly triggered by sodium-ions from normal glassware or by oxygen from not tight closing lids. The development of tight closing and cheap borosilicate glass tubes allowing storage without any outer container would be a revolution in collections. Theoretically, it would be possible to produce such glass tubes, but the high production costs presently seem to prevent the marketing of such systems.</p>
         <p>
Mounted specimens can be stored for an infinite time, but may still be destroyed by external factors such as moisture or pests. Thus, the collection room should have a low air moisture and low to moderate temperature to inhibit pest species as well as possible. For the control of pest organisms, pesticides – for example ‘Vandal Mottenschutz’ – are commonly in use, but should be avoided as far as possible due to potential health hazard. The material is best stored in tightly closed insect boxes of acid and formaldehyde free wood to properly protect the material (

). The insect pins should be corrosion-free and all labels and cardboards made of acid-free paper. Depending on the body-size, up to 
six specimens
or morphospecies of one nest sample can be mounted together on the same pin – this may include males, gynes, or different worker castes that were found in the same (nest-) sample (

). 
One specimen
on one pin would lead to a much faster exhaustion of available collection space.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2.1 Appropriate labeling
</title>
         <p>

Correct labeling is essential in a scientific collection. Each sample tube or needle with mounted specimens has to carry at least two labels: The first label with information on sampling date, locality, and collector as well as a second label which includes the species name, the name of the determinator and, ideally, the year of determination. Without information on the exact locality and sampling date the prepared material can be considered scientifically worthless. The second label is in case of 
type
material of taxonomically high importance. The labels should be made out of acid-free, fine card stock or thick paper. A non-neutral pH of the material would cause deterioration within 40–50 years, resulting in brittleness or, in the worst case, detachment from the pin. Especially in geographic regions with a high level of air humidity the latter process is accelerated dramatically. 
India
ink that is preferably used for writing labels has been a timeproven standard for centuries. The use of laser printers is basically an excellent modern option but the long-term stability of the printed information has to be considered for which there is little experience. A printed label – using a font without serifs – seems to be most suitable to ensure readability. Printed labels should have, for size relations commonly observed in ants, a font size of four to five points and a general cardboard size of 
7–10 mm
width and 
15–20 mm
length. This label size is compromising between a high amount of information and efficiency of space in insect boxes. An even number of written lines on the labels is recommendable not to obliterate important data by the pin itself. A right-alignment of letters could be a possible solution. Nevertheless, the labels should be consistently oriented – readable from the same direction in dependence of left or right handedness – parallel to the mounted specimens and should ideally not exceed two or three in number (

). In addition, the labels may also serve as spacers towards 
other specimens
or insect box walls in order to protect the pinned specimens

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Preparation of material
</title>
         <p>
The preparation is often a compromise between stability and the best visualization of a maximum of characters. Especially for morphometrics, the lateral view on both sides and also on slightly hidden parts – for example the gula, the ventral or the inner side of the tibia – should be possible. For preparation of workers and gynes, the main focus is set on non-genital characters, whereas the copulatory organs are accessorily most important in males (

, 

, 

). Furthermore, wing venation can be used in gynes and males for determination purposes but is of less interest from an alpha-taxonomic point of view (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1 Preparation techniques for workers and gynes
</title>
         <p>
Workers and gynes (
Fig. 2
, 
3
) can be prepared by using basically the same techniques. The main arguments for or against the use of a particular preparation technique refer to the respective size of the ant, the location of taxonomically important characters and the amount of individual previous practice. In case of alate gynes, wing preparation is best done by cutting the front- and hindwings at the base and gluing them flat on the same or another cardboard to allow the best evaluation of wing parameters (

, 

). For the workers (major, etc.) the following preparation techniques are frequently in use.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1.1 Pinning
</title>
         <p>
The first classical mode of preparation was to put a thin insect needle directly through the middle of the mesosoma. This method was and is mainly done with very large species, the main advantage being the low time needed for preparation. However, the high fragility of the dried ant material in connection with the bending property of the needle all too easily leads to destruction (

, 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1.2 Several ants on one plate
</title>
         <p>Another frequently seen method is to put some watersoluble glue on a cardboard and – depending on the respective size of the specimens – to fix one to eight ants on one cardboard. This method saves material, time and space, but the free view on many characters of the ant is blocked or these are masked by the glue. Accordingly, this mode of preparation is not recommended. Nevertheless, it is possible, even after a long period of time, to re-prepare the dried ants in another position.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1.3 Standing position
</title>
         <p>
In general, the standing positioning (
Fig. 2
, 
3
) is highly recommendable for nearly all kinds of ants. The specimen is glued on its tarsae in a standing position on a paper plate. The fore-legs are orientated frontwards whereas the middle and hind-legs are directed backwards – aiming for a natural position of the legs. The mesosoma is uplifted to give an unrestricted view on the mesosoma as well as on the waist segments. The scapes are bent to the front and the antennae are glued parallel to the front-tarsae on the paper plate (
Fig. 3
). This technique ensures the highest stability with additional protection of the antennae. The latter benefit from their fixed position for measurement purposes. Additionally, characteristics of the legs are easily accessible – this is especially important, in the Central European fauna, for the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>
Formica
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lasius
</tp:taxon-name>
(

, 

). One disadvantage of this preparation mode is the rather large preparation time needed. In very large ants, where the relation between material stability of dried appendages and body mass becomes low, this mode of preparation bears the risk that the whole specimen may break off from the cardboard caused by percussions during mail transport as it is with the Wilson preparation. Furthermore, when very large ants are prepared from ethanol, the strong mechanical resilience of the stiff body parts may cause difficulties in adjustment of body parts – but this disadvantage applies to any mode of mounting (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1.4 Preparation according to Wilson
</title>
         <p>
The preparation method most commonly used is the so-called Wilson-preparation (
Fig. 4
). In this preparation 
type
, the legs are bent in a ventral position using a fine forceps or a curved needle. The ant is glued between its second and third coxae on the tip of a triangular cardboard – according to the usual standard with the specimen‘s head pointing to the left when viewing the cardboard lengthwise from the pin side. After allowing the glue to dry, the legs and antennae should be adjusted in a position appropriate for measurement. The size of the triangular paper plate can be chosen variably with regard to the specific size and weight of the prepared specimen (

, 

, 

). For improved stability it is recommended to use a thicker cardboard with a broader tip for large species such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Camponotus
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
This 
type
of preparation has the advantage of a free view from nearly all angles, especially for characters belonging to ventrally situated mouth parts. One disadvantage is the obstructed view when looking from the cardboard/pin side. Thus, this preparation mode is not appreciated by taxonomists who apply morphometric determination and need a bilateral recording of characters. Furthermore, these investigators do not like the crosswise and more eccentric position of the specimen relative to the pin‘s center of rotation, which makes the handling and adjustment of the specimen more difficult during measuring processes with x-y-z stages. Another disadvantage is the higher risk of damaging the specimen already in weak collisions and of breaking off especially specimens with a larger body mass from the cardboard (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1.5 Mounting with basket-shape arrangement of legs
</title>
         <p>
A technique currently used by some taxonomists who apply morphometric determination is a mounting method where the legs of the ant are bent basket-like on its ventral side and then glued with its metatarsae and tarsae on the tip of a triangular cardboard – parallel to its longitudinal axis (

). The antennae are bent downwards until they form a right angle to the middle axis of the head capsule. The big advantage of this method is the elevated position of head, mesosoma, and gaster relative to the cardboard and that the legs do not obscure the investigation of most characters placed on these body parts. Sometimes, a combination with other modes of preparation – for example according to Wilson – improves the view on ventral characters, which can have benefit for photography purposes (
Fig. 5
). The higher position of the ant as well as the free view from nearly all angles may highlight important characters. The only disadvantage compared to the other methods is the limited view on the legs. Accordingly, basket-shape preparation is clearly preferable only for those ant groups, in which, according to current knowledge, investigation of metatarsal and tibial characters has low taxonomic importance (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

3.1.6 Preparation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chthonolasius
</tp:taxon-name>
workers

</title>
         <p>
Special, taxon-specific, preparation techniques may be necessary for proper character investigation of some ant taxa. For instance, in workers and gynes of the subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chthonolasius
</tp:taxon-name>
an unrestricted antero-caudal view on the petiole is desired for taxonomical measurement and determination. Here, the junction between petiole and mesosoma is cut and the severed body part is glued by the gaster tip on the same cardboard in some distance from the mesosoma in a position allowing a free view on the full area of petiole (
Fig. 6
). The front body is prepared in standing position near to the tip of the cardboard. Compared to the other methods, this preparation is more time-consuming and it needs some experience and practice to prevent the surfaces from being stained by leaking body fluids when the specimens are prepared from liquid storage.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.2 Preparation of males
</title>
         <p>
Preparation of males often requires special treatment of the genitalia which are placed at the end of the abdomen. There are three different approaches of preparation. Firstly, males can be prepared after Wilson, which allows a proper view on the abdomen from all angles. In the second method, only the genital is cut off and is glued with its parts remaining in situ on the margin of the same paper plate. The rest of the specimen is prepared in standing position. This method allows a view on the genital from dorsal, ventral and caudal but needs some caution to prevent destruction or deformation of the genital structures. In a third method, the gaster can be cut off entirely – similar to the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chthonolasius
</tp:taxon-name>
workers – and is afterwards fixed in upright position (
Fig. 7
). This method is easier to perform, but it often leads to a less optimal result because the bending of the gaster may disturb the ventral view on the genital. All three methods provide a sufficient view on all parts of the body and on the genital in an in-situ position. Thorough investigation of shape and structure of the different elements or parts of the genitalia requires dissection after maceration and preparation of slides for transmitted-light microscopy (

, 

). The value of male genitalia for species separation is, according to present knowledge, significant in rather few ant groups (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tetramorium caespitum
</tp:taxon-name>
complex, 

, 

). In several genera such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Myrmica
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lasius
</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>
Formica
</tp:taxon-name>
, species are much better separable by somatic characters of workers than by genital characters of males (

, 

, 1992, 

; Seifert. &amp; Galkowski 2016; 

). Furthermore, males are available only for a short period of the year and show higher variation due to their haploid genome (

). All these difficulties can explain that existing systems for male determination down to the species level are frequently unreliable and that keys for males are rarely provided (

). Nevertheless, characters of males may be of significant use in the delimitation of groups of closely related species within genera such as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Myrmica
(
Radchenko &amp; Elmes 2010
)
</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tapinoma
(
Seifert et al. 2017
)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.3 Preparation and dissection of inner organs and musculature
</title>
         <p>
In addition to preservation of exocuticulary characteristics, sectioning and conservation of organs and musculature provides scientific important information – age, dispersal abilities, reproductive capability, etc. There are several commonly used techniques for the different body parts. Usually, a dish with dark colored paraffin wax is filled with 70 % ethanol up to a height of approximately 
5 mm
. Insect needles of appropriate thickness can be used to fixate material if necessary. The main disadvantage of sectioning is the destruction of material, which is then no more available for later mounting and taxonomic processing.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.3.1 Preparation of wing musculature
</title>
         <p>
Hymenopterans, in general, have indirect wing musculature which is characterized by dorso-ventral muscle strands for each wing. Another thick strand of muscles is located in the middle of the thorax in parallel orientation to the body axis. After the nuptial flight, the wings are dropped and the musculature is increasingly replaced by fat tissue (

, 

, 

). Thus, the measurement of body fat is a proper technique for age determination of gynes (

). In order to give access to the musculature, the thorax of the fresh gyne is laterally cut underneath the wing insertions and subsequently spread using fine forceps (
Fig. 8
). The amount of musculature gives information about the dispersal tactic – for example rather small musculature in combination with small wings (brachypterous gynes) may hint to short distance dispersal and vice versa (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.3.2 Preparation of the reproductive organs
</title>
         <p>
The preparation of the reproductive organs (
Fig. 9
) – mainly with a focus on the spermatheca – provides valuable information about the reproductive capabilities of gynes or sometimes workers (

, 

). Furthermore, the relation between the number of ovarioles and the amount of sperm in the spermatheca allows estimations of the respective egg production capability (

). In the first step of preparation the end of the gaster is cut and the sclerotized abdominal rings are removed. Afterwards, the digestive tract can be spread and fixed with insect needles. The ovarioles and spermatheca, which are wrapped by other organs are separated using some fine needles and can be cut off for further investigations (

, 

). The spermatheca can, afterwards, be put on a slide for microscopic investigation (
Fig. 10
). The section of the reproductive organs provides good information but needs a lot of previous practice. Furthermore, it is of benefit to use fresh material for preparation since ethanol storage dehydrates the tissue, alters the typical shape, and leads to higher fragility of the tissue.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.3.3 Preparation of (poison) glands
</title>
         <p>
It is of high scientific value to understand the communication of the eusocial insects, for example in the two very important taxa ants and bees (

). Thus, the compounds which are produced in the numerous glands (
Fig. 11
) have to be characterized and studied (

, 

). Furthermore, the hormones as well as the poisons and repellents – for example citronellal – can be of potential interest for pharmaceutical and biotechnological purposes (

). Sectioning and following extraction of special glands as well as milking (
Fig. 12
) is a common technique for understanding the produced chemicals. For the extraction of the poison and Dufour’s gland, the gaster is carefully cut at the anus and all sclerotized parts are removed. The inner organs are spread and the glands are separated. For a proper investigation of the produced compounds it is essential to use fresh material which has not been killed and stored in ethanol. The ethanol would strongly wash out and dilute the compounds. Furthermore, the dissection is easier to be performed in fresh material – for similar reasons as described in the preparation of reproductive organs. An appropriate killing method for this purpose is the use of cyanide jars.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
This article presented a comparing, descriptive, and illustrated summary of the most common techniques of ant preparation. It can be seen as a guideline for amateurs as well as for professionals with the goal of conserving natural history of ants in a proper way. In a scientific collection all kinds of preparations can be found due to the different preferences of the respective scientist. The individual previous knowledge on genus specific characters is also of high importance. Only myrmecologists who dealt with, for example 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chthonolasius
</tp:taxon-name>
workers or persons who gained information from taxonomic papers would know the importance of the specific preparation and cutting technique. This lack of information may lead to inappropriate preparations which need to be reprepared to have the full scientific use. The first methods of conservations, for example pinning of ant material, led to destruction or strong change of morphology. Such material – often being of outstanding value – is hard to re-prepare without risking further damage and lacks valuable morphologic information.
</p>
         <p>
Within
the last years, collections received attention due to their new developed function of being genetic archives (

, 

). 
The
next generation sequencing accesses whole genomes of collection material – thus also ant species. 
This
allows studies on old ant material with taxonomic or population genetic purpose and might make collections and prepared ant material more valuable than ever. 
The
access to 
type
material can be, depending on its location, difficult or impossible. A sequencing of all 
type
material with subsequent free use databases would represent an ideal goal of DNA taxonomy but will remain a very incomplete story as extraction of DNA from primary 
types
of smallbodied, weakly sclerotized insects is often not possible without causing deformation of cuticle and concealing of very delicate surface structures

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Acknowledgment
</title>
         <p>Preeminently, I want to thank Bernhard Seifert for an outstanding guidance and assistance. His 39 years of theoretical and practical experience as well as studying the ant collection built up by him were of great help to write this article. Furthermore, special thanks to Willi Xylander for his support and the idea for the creation of this article which based on a seminar paper for the module ‘Museums and collections’ within the master program ‘Biodiversity and Collection Management’. Finally, I want to thank Sandra Avant, Alfred Buschinger, Eduardo Fox, Guilherme Ide and Roland Schultz who kindly provided outstanding pictures of ants, ant sections or ant handling.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
6. References
</title>
         <p>
Agosti, D.
(
1989
): 

Versuch einer phylogenetischen Wertung der Merkmale der Formicini (Hymenoptera, Formicidae), Revision der 
Formica exsecta
-Gruppe und Liste der Formicidae Europas

. – PhD Thesis, 
ETH Zurich
: 
278 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Agosti, D.
, 
J. D. Majer
, 
L. E. Alonso
&amp; 
T. Schultz
(
2000
): 
Standard methods for measuring and monitoring biodiversity
– 
Smithsonian Institution, Washington DC
: 
280 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Berman, M.
, 
C. M. Austin
&amp; 
A. D. Miller
(
2014
): 

Characterisation of the complete mitochondrial genome and 13 microsatellite loci through next-generation sequencing for the New Caledonian spider-ant 
Leptomyrmex pallens

– 
Molecular biology reports
41

: 
1179–1187
.

</p>
         <p>
Berry, A.
(
2008
): 
Ardent beetle-hunters: natural history, collecting, and the theory of evolution
– 
Natural Selection and Beyond: The Intellectual Legacy of Alfred Russel Wallace
: 
47–65
.

</p>
         <p>
Billen, J.
&amp; 
A. Buschinger
(
2000
): 

Morphology and ultrastructure of a specialized bacterial pouch in the digestive tract of 
Tetraponera
ants (Formicidae, Pseudomyrmecinae)

– 
Arthropod Structure &amp; Development
29

: 
259–266
.

</p>
         <p>
Clausen, R.
(
1938
): 
Untersuchungen über den männlichen Copulationsapparat der Ameisen, speziell der Formicinae
– 
Mitteilungen der Schweizer Entomologischen Gesellschaft
17

: 
233–348
.

</p>
         <p>
Emery, C.
(
1911
): 
Formicidae
– 
Nova Guinea
9

: 
249–259
.

</p>
         <p>
Forbes, J.
&amp; 
D. Do-Van-Quy
(
1965
): 

The anatomy and histology of the male reproductive system of the legionary ant, 
Neivamyrmex harrisi
(Haldeman)(Hymenoptera: Formicidae)

– 
Journal of the New York Entomological Society
73

: 
95–111
.

</p>
         <p>
Forel, A.
(
1901
): 

Formiciden des Naturhistorischen Museums zu Hamburg. Neue 
Calyptomyrmex
-, 
Dacryon
-, 
Podomyrma
-, und 
Echinopla
-Arten

. – 
Mitteilungen aus dem Naturhistorischen Museum in Hamburg
18

: 
43–82
.

</p>
         <p>
Gotwald, W. H.
&amp; 
A. W. Burdette
(
1981
): 
Morphology of the male internal reproductive system in army ants: phylogenetic implications (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)
– 
Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington
83

: 
72–92
.

</p>
         <p>
Graser, K.
(
1959
): 
Über das Sammeln und Präparieren von Ameisen
– 
Entomologische Nachrichten und Berichte
3

: 
15–19
.

</p>
         <p>
Harpaz, I.
(
1973
): 
Early entomology in the Middle East. History of entomology
– 
Bulletin of the Entomological Society of America
20

: 
71–73
.

</p>
         <p>
Hatchfield, P. B.
&amp; 
J. M. Carpenter
(
1986
): 
The problem of formaldehyde in museum collections
– 
Museum Management and Curatorship
5

: 
183–188
.

</p>
         <p>
Heinze J.
, 
A. Schrempf
, 
B. Seifert
&amp; 
A. Tinaut
(
2002
): 

Queen morphology and dispersal tactics in the ant, 
Cardiocondyla batesii

– 
Insectes sociaux
49

: 
129–132
.

</p>
         <p>
Hölldobler B.
&amp; 
H. Engel
(
1978
): 
Tergal and sternal glands in ants
– 
Psyche
85

: 
285–330
.

</p>
         <p>
Hölldobler, B.
&amp; 
H. Engel-Siegel
(
1984
): 
On the metapleural gland of ants
– 
Psyche
91

: 
201–224
.

</p>
         <p>
Hölldobler B.
&amp; 
E.O. Wilson
(
1990
): 
The ants
— 
Havard University Press
: 
746 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Holliday, M.
(
1903
): 
A study of some ergatogynic ants
– 
Zoologische Jahrbücher Abteilung für Systematik
19

: 
293–328
.

</p>
         <p>
Jones, R. G.
, 
W. L. Davis
, 
A. C. Hung
&amp; 
S. B. Vinson
(
1978
): 

Insemination-induced histolysis of the flight musculature in fire ants (
Solenopsis
spp.): An ultrastructural study

– 
Developmental Dynamics
151

: 
603–610
.

</p>
         <p>
Keller, L.
&amp; 
L. Passera
(
1989
): 
Size and fat content of gynes in relation to the mode of colony founding in ants (Hymenoptera; Formicidae)
– 
Oecologia
80

: 
236–240
.

</p>
         <p>
Kulmuni, J.
, 
B. Seifert
&amp; 
P. Pamilo
(
2010
): 
Segregation distortion causes large-scale differences between male and female genomes in hybrid ants
– 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
107

: 
7371–7376
.

</p>
         <p>
Klingenberg, C.
&amp; 
B. H. Dietz
(
2004
): 
Ameisenflügel: morphologisches Merkmal zur Gattungsbestimmung von drei neotropischen Triben mit Vorschlägen zur Nomenklatur
– 
Beiträge der Hymenopterologen-Tagung, Stuttgart
1–3
.

</p>
         <p>
Koch, M.
(Hrsg) (
1956
): 
Präparation von Insekten: sachgemässe Anleitung für Wissenschaftler und Liebhaber
– 
Neumann Verlag, Radebeul
: 
119pp.
</p>
         <p>
Larson, J. L.
(
1968
): 
The species concept of Linnaeus
– 
Isis
59

: 
291–299
.

</p>
         <p>
Lohaus, R.
&amp; 
Y. Van de Peer
(
2016
): 
Of dups and dinos: evolution at the K/Pg boundary
– 
Current opinion in plant biology
30

: 
62–69
.

</p>
         <p>
Morge, G.
(
1973
): 
Entomology in the western world in antiquity and in medieval times. History of entomology
– 
Bulletin of the Entomological Society of America
20

: 
71–73
.

</p>
         <p>
Peeters C.
&amp; 
S. Higashi
(
1989
): 

Reproductive dominance controlled by mutilation in the queenless ant 
Diacamma australe

– 
Naturwissenschaften
76

: 
177–180
.

</p>
         <p>
Post, R. J.
, 
P. K. Flook
&amp; 
A. L. Millest
(
1993
): 
Methods for the preservation of insects for DNA studies
– 
Biochemical systematics and ecology
21

: 
85–92
.

</p>
         <p>
Poulsen, M.
, 
A. N. Bot
, 
M. G. Nielsen
&amp; 
J. J. Boomsma
(
2002
): 
Experimental evidence for the costs and hygienic significance of the antibiotic metapleural gland secretion in leaf-cutting ants
– 
Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology
52

: 
151–157
.

</p>
         <p>
Radchenko, A.
&amp; 
G. W. Elmes
(
2010
): 

Myrmica
ants (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) of the old world

– 
Natura Optima Dux Foundation, Warsaw
: 
789 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Schlick-Steiner, B. C.
, 
F. M. Steiner
, 
K. Moder
, 
B. Seifert
, 
M. Sanetra
, 
E. Dyreson
, 
C. Stauffer
&amp; 
E. Christian
(
2006
): 

A multidisciplinary approach reveals cryptic diversity in Western Palearctic 
Tetramorium
ants (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)

– 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution
40

: 
259–273
.

</p>
         <p>
Schwarz, M.
(
2014
): 
Bienen, Wespen und Ameisen – eine Übersicht über heimische Hautflügler (Hymenoptera) sowie praktische Tipps für angehende Hymenopterologen
– 
Entomologica Austriaca
21

: 
153–207
.

</p>
         <p>
Seifert, B.
(
1988
a): 

A revision of the European species of the ant subgenus 
Chthonolasius
(Insecta, Hymenoptera, Formicidae)

– 
Entomologische Abhandlungen des Museums für Tierkunde Dresden
51

: 
143–180
.

</p>
         <p>
Seifert, B.
(
1988
b): 

A taxonomic revision of the 
Myrmica
species of Europe, Asia Minor, and Caucasus (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)

– 
Abhandlungen und Berichte des Naturkundemuseums Görlitz
62

: 
1–75
.

</p>
         <p>
Seifert, B.
(
1992
): 

A taxonomic revision of the Palaearctic members of the ant subgenus 
Lasius
s. str. (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)

– 
Abhandlungen und Berichte des Naturkundemuseums Görlitz
66

: 
1–67
.

</p>
         <p>
Seifert, B.
(
2000
): 

A taxonomic revision of the ant subgenus 
Coptoformica
Mueller, 1923 (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)

– 
Zoosystema Paris
22

: 
517–568
.

</p>
         <p>
Seifert, B.
(
2007
): 
Die Ameisen Mittel- und Nordeuropas – Lutra Verlag- und Vertriebsgesellschaft
, 
Tauer
: 
368 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Seifert, B.
(
2018
): 
The ants of Central and North Europe. Lutra Verlag- und Vertriebsgesellschaft
, 
Tauer
: in press.

</p>
         <p>
Seifert, B.
, 
D. D’Eustacchio
, 
B. Kaufmann
, 
M. Centorame
&amp; 
M. Modica
(
2017
): 

Four species within the supercolonial ants of the 
Tapinoma nigerrimum
complex revealed by integrative taxonomy (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)

– 
Myrmecological News
24

: 
123–144
.

</p>
         <p>
Seifert, B.
&amp; 
C. Galkowski
(
2016
): 

The Westpalaearctic 
Lasius paralienus
complex (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) contains three species

– 
Zootaxa
4132

: 
44–58
.

</p>
         <p>
Smithers, C. N.
(
1981
): 
Handbook of Insect Collecting: Collection, Preparation, Preservation and Storage – Reed
, 
Cornell University
: 
120 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Stearn, W.T.
(
1959
): 
The background of Linnaeus’s contributions to the nomenclature and methods of systematic biology
– 
Systematic Zoology
8

: 
4–22
.

</p>
         <p>
Stephenson, A. B.
&amp; 
J. L. Riley
(
1995
): 
Fixation and preservation of museum marine collections using formaldehyde/ glutaraldehyde mixes
– 
Collection Forum
11

: 
58–68
.

</p>
         <p>
Tschinkel, W. R.
(
1987
): 
Relationship between ovariole number and spermathecal sperm count in ant queens: a new allometry
– 
Annals of the Entomological Society of America
80

: 
208– 211
.

</p>
         <p>
Wagner, D.
&amp; 
D. M. Gordon
(
1999
): 
Colony age, neighborhood density and reproductive potential in harvester ants
– 
Oecologia
119

: 
175–182
.

</p>
         <p>
Wagner, H. C.
, 
W. Arthofer
, 
B. Seifert
, 
C. Muster
, 
F. M. Steiner
&amp; 
B. C. Schlick-Steiner
(
2017
): 

Light at the end of the tunnel: Integrative taxonomy delimits cryptic species in the 
Tetramorium caespitum
complex (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)

– 
Myrmecological News
25

: 
95–129
.

</p>
         <p>
Wheeler D. E.
&amp; 
P. H. Krutzsch
(
1992
): 

Internal Reproductive System in Adult Males of the Genus 
Camponotus
(Hymenoptera: Formicidae: Formicinae)

– 
Journal of Morphology
211

: 
307–317
.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
