<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Soil Organisms</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25674/so92iss2pp109</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Addition of polyester in soil affects litter decomposition rates but not microarthropod communities</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eisenia andrei
Bouche, 1972
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Plantago lanceolata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Plantago lanceolata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata, Prostigmata, Astigmata, Acari</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tectocepheus velatus
(Michael, 1880)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oppiella nova
(Oudemans, 1902)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Moritzoppia unicarinata
(Paoli, 1908)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Suctobelbella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Scheloribates
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoribates
cf. 
novus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eupelops
cf. 
curtipilus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Suctobelbella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Moritzoppia unicarinata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oppiella nova
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Scheloribates
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
F. candida
Willem 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
F. candida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
F. candida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
F. candida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hypoaspis aculeifer
(Canestrini)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Damaeus exspinosus
Wang &amp; Norton, 1989
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tectocepheus velatus
(Michael, 1880)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oppiella nova
(Oudemans, 1902)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Moritzoppia unicarinata
(Paoli, 1908)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Suctobelbella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Scheloribates
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoribates
cf. 
novus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eupelops
cf. 
curtipilus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Addition of polyester in soil affects litter decomposition rates but not microarthropod communities
</p>
         <p>
Carlos Barreto
1,2,
*, 
Matthias C. Rillig
2,3
and 
Zoë Lindo
1
</p>
         <p>
1
Department of Biology
, 
The University of Western
Ontario

, 

1151 
Richmond Street, N
6A 3K7 
London
, 
Ontario
, 
Canada
2
Freie Universität 
Berlin
, 

InstitUt
für 
Biologie
, 
Plant Ecology
, Altensteinstrasse 6, 14195 
Berlin
, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
3

Berlin-BrandenbUrg InstitUte of Advanced Biodiversity Research (BBIB), Königin-LUise-Str. 2-4, 14195 
Berlin
, 
Germany
* Corresponding aUthor: cbarreto@UWo.ca

</p>
         <p>
Received 
23 April 2020
| Accepted 
30 JUne 2020
</p>
         <p>
Published online at www.soil-organisms.de 


1 AUgUst 
2020

| Printed version 
15 AUgUst 2020
</p>
         <p>
DOI 
10.25674/so92iss2pp109
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Abstract
</title>
         <p>
Microplastics are defined as plastic particles that are &lt;
5mm
. Manufactured in the production of many commercial products, microplastics have become an environmental threat for many organisms. Microplastics can be highly abundant in soil, and given their size, can interact with soil microarthropods. But how microplastics affect soil-dwelling organisms (mites and collembolans) and their role in ecosystem services such as decomposition is largely unknown. We studied the effects of polypropylene and polyester microfibers of two different lengths (
2–3mm
and 
5–6mm
) on microarthropod communities and decomposition rates in a sandy soil. Microplastic addition showed no effects on soil microarthropod communities for the groups Oribatida (abundance and species richness), Prostigmata, Astigmata and 
<tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
, nor other invertebrates present in the soil samples (abundance), and no significant differences were found on feeding rates measured by bait-lamina sticks. Permanova results for microarthropod community structure among treatments were not significant, although non-metric multidimensional scaling analysis (NMDS) found that communities were less similar to one another in polypropylene addition treatments compared to polyester addition and to control treatments. However, the addition of microplastics in the soil did affect litter decomposition rates for litterbags on the soil surface; higher mass loss (i.e. decomposition) was found in polyester treatments compared to control and polypropylene treatments, regardless of the length of the fibers. This study is the first to test the effects of microplastics on soil microarthropod communities, and we find no direct negative effects of microplastic addition.
</p>
         <p>
Keywords
microplastics
| 
litterbags
| 
bait-lamina-test strip
| 
Acari
| 
soil organisms
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
With the fate of globalization and a consequent increase on the dependence of society on plastics, this material can be found virtually everywhere, from fresh waters (

) and marine environments (

), to soils (

) and air (

). Different 
types
of plastics are used in a vast array of products due to their durability, lightness, stability, and low cost (

). Despite their benefits, plastic pollution is an environmental issue worldwide, and numbers are quite impressive, with more than 240 million tons of plastic estimated to be used annually (

). In just a few years, the production of plastics has spiked to 380 million tons and the total amount produced until the year 2015 has been estimated to exceed 8300 million tons (

). Same authors estimated the global plastic waste to be 6300 million tons between 1950 and 2015, from which 79 % has accumulated in landfills and other environmental compartments, rendering plastics a major environmental issue.
</p>
         <p>
The term microplastics was first coined by 

for the microscopic pieces of plastics found in European waters. Since then, its definition has changed (

, 

, 

, 

), but the most common iteration of microplastics is by 

, that considers microplastics as plastic particles smaller than 
5mm
. Several studies have adopted this definition (e.g. 

, 

, 

), even though the concept of microplastics is subject to intense discussion (see 

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
During the past 50 years, the effects of microplastics have been extensively studied in aquatic systems, with the first pieces of evidence of pollution by plastics dating back to the 70’s (see 

, 

). Studies on microplastics have largely investigated their effects on marine organisms and the possibility of transfer through the food chain (

, 

, 

), with potentially serious consequences to life on land as well. Furthermore, microplastic contamination on land is suggested to be 4-23-fold larger than in the ocean (

,b). Among organisms that live in soil, specific groups like earthworms have been studied in depth (see 

, 

, 

, 

, 

, 

), while other groups like microarthropods such as oribatid mites (Acari: Oribatida) and springtails (
<tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
) have not (but see 

, and 

, Ju et al. 2019, 

, 

, respectively). The consequences of microplastic contamination in soil systems on soil organisms are yet not well understood, but inhibition of growth, increased mortality, and detachment or atrophy of the gut epithelium have been observed in the earthworm 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eisenia andrei
Bouche, 1972
</tp:taxon-name>
(

).
</p>
         <p>
Microplastics may cause changes within the soil food web as they can be small enough to potentially be ingested by microarthropods, which may lead to accumulation in different trophic levels (

) with potentially cascading consequences at the ecosystem level, for instance, through altering nutrient cycles, carbon storage and decomposition rates. Other potential negative effects of microplastics on soil microarthropods are determined through changes in soil properties (

). Alternatively, it is possible that microplastics impact soil organisms directly through sorbing pollutants on their surfaces, which makes them toxic (

).
</p>
         <p>
Since 

, increasing evidence has shown that microplastics are ubiquitous in soils and are largely influenced by anthropogenic activities including the application of biosolids and mulching with plastic films in agriculture (

), domestic sewage (

), fertilizers (

), tire abrasion (

), and atmospheric particles transported over long distances (

). With a multitude of paths for soil pollution by microplastics, many species that depend on soils for their survival are under potential threat (

).
</p>
         <p>
The persistence of microplastic pollution in soil systems might qualify these particles to be drivers of environmental change, since they affect soil bulk density, water holding capacity, soil aggregate formation, soil porosity and soil structure (

, Lehmann et al. 2019), increase soil water evaporation (

), besides serving as vectors for metal exposure in soils (

). Considering that soil fauna is exposed to these changes in soils, and at the same time, are involved in ecosystem processes, like decomposition, that occur in soil systems, it is important to investigate the impacts of microplastics on microarthropod communities. Here, we used polyester and polypropylene microfibers in two different lengths each added to meadow soil in a microcosm experiment to determine whether microplastic addition have effects on litter decomposition rates, soil fauna feeding rates, and soil microarthropod community structure.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Materials and methods
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Study site
</title>
         <p>

The test soil used in this microcosm experiment was a loamy sand soil collected in a meadow at Freie Universität 
Berlin
– 
Institute of Biology
(
52.45°N
, 
13.30°W
; 
Berlin
, 
Germany
) inJune 2019.Berlinhasamoderatelycontinental climate (Cfb in the Köppen Climate Classification), with mean annual temperature of 9.1°C and a precipitation of 
570 mm
(climate-data.org 2019)

.
</p>
         <p>
Soil (an Albic Luvisol, including the litter layer) was collected manually using shovel and hand trowel to sample the top 
10cm
of a 1× 
0.5m
plot. Roots thicker than 
1cm
and aboveground vegetation were removed. After collection, the soil was kept at ambient temperature for 24 hours until the microcosms were prepared and established. Leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Plantago lanceolata
</tp:taxon-name>
L. were handpicked from the same location to be used as substrate in litterbags, since this is a very common species in our site. Leaves were dried in the oven at 60ºC for 72 hours.
</p>
         <p>
Before the microcosms were established, in order to characterize the soil and the litter used in the litterbags, we homogenized both soil and litter samples, separately, using a mixer mill for three minutes (Retsch MM400). Carbon (C) and nitrogen (N) contents from the initial homogenized soil and litter samples (six soil and six litter samples) were analyzed using a combustion autoanalyzer (EuroVector EA3000 Elemental Analyzer) to determine carbon and nitrogen contents. Soil samples had on average 
0.2g
N / 
100g
soil dw, 60°C and 
3.39g
C / 
100g
soil dw, 60 °C and litter samples had 
1.33g
/ 
100g
N and 
44.12g
/ 
100g
C. Moisture content of initial soil was measured as the difference in mass of the soil samples prior to and following samples were put in the oven at 60ºC for 72 hours; this was on average 12.1 % dry weight (dw). The pH from six soil samples was measured in a weak solution of calcium chloride (0.01 M CaCl 
2
) and this was on average 6.81.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Experimental design
</title>
         <p>
Soil
from the meadow was homogenized by hand and used to fill 50 microcosms [
100.01g
± 
0.005g
SE wet weight (ww)] in 550ml mason jars that were placed in a climate chamber at 24°C in the dark during four weeks at the 
Institut
für 
Biologie
, 
Plant Ecology
at 
Freie Universität
Berlin
. 
All
microcosms had a rectangular hole (2.5 × 
1 cm
) with a small piece of foam inserted in the lid to allow air exchange and prevent organisms from leaving the system. 
Two
different 
types
of microfiber plastics cut to two different lengths were considered as treatments, making a nested statistical experimental design (i.e. the two different lengths were nested within each of two different plastic 
types
). 
The
microfibers were created by manually by cutting 100 % polyester (PE) white ‘ 
Paraloc Rope’
(product number 8442173, Mamutec), and 100 % polypropylene (PP) orange ‘ 
Paraloc Rope’
(product number 8442202, Mamutec) to a length of either 
2–3mm
or 
5–6mm
; the average diameter of fibers was 22.92 ± 0.17 μm for PE and 33.33 ± 0.07 μm for PP fibers. 
Fibers
were manually separated before mixing into the soil to help achieve an equal distribution. 
The
amount of microplastics added was 0.4 % of the soil dry weight (

0.351
–0.352
g

) mixed over a period of 90 seconds; each microplastic 
type
was added separately. We also manually mixed the soil in control microcosms to create the same disturbance applied to the microplastic addition treatments. The amount of microplastics added is based on 

and corresponded to the maximum amount of linear microplastic fiber addition that caused minor changes in soil volume in that study

.
</p>
         <p>
Each
microcosm also contained one bait-lamina test strip with bait substrate (
Terra Protecta
GmbH, 
Berlin
, 
Germany
) that was vertically inserted in the soil at the start of the experiment, and one litterbag (
5cm
× 
5cm
with 
1mm
mesh, average weight 
0.3g
) containing oven-dried leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Plantago lanceolata
</tp:taxon-name>
L. that was placed on the top layer of the soil inside each jar. 
Soil
moisture content was maintained in the microcosms gravimetrically during the experiment with deionised H 
2
O added equal to the weight lost during each week, meaning that water content was kept at the level of sampling. 
The
experiment was built as a nested design with 10 replicates per treatment (n=10 for fiber-less control and n=10 for each of the four plastic addition treatments, i.e. two lengths for each fibre 
type
). Microcosm setup sequence and jar location in the climate chamber were randomized, and the experiment lasted four weeks

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Variables measured
</title>
         <p>Decomposition rates were measured by mass loss from the litterbags (on soil surface) using the following</p>
         <p>
equation: 
initial dry weight (g) – final dry weight (g)
</p>
         <p>
Mass loss =
x 100 
initial dry weight (g)
</p>
         <p>
Feeding activity of microbial and microarthropod communities was measured as a proxy for biological activity with bait-lamina tests (

) (in soil profile) following the equation:
</p>
         <p>
number of holes with entirely consumed bait Feeding rate =
</p>
         <p>
total number of holes inserted in soil
</p>
         <p>
Soil fauna were extracted from the soil using a modified MacFadyen apparatus into 75 % EtOH at the end of the experiment. The MacFadyen apparatus extracts fauna from soils by creating a temperature/moisture gradient, inducing the soil fauna to actively move lower into the soil profile, and where the bottom of the sample container is mesh, allowing the fauna to pass through and into the EtOH collection. The temperature/moisture gradient was established by increasing the temperature of the extraction chamber in +3°C increments from 30°C to 50°C over a period of one week. Microarthropods collected in EtOH were sorted into major taxonomic groups and counted under a dissecting microscope. As the dominant group, oribatid mites (Acari: Oribatida) were identified to the species level, where possible using descriptions from (

, 

, 

, 

). Representative oribatid mite specimens were slide mounted using Hoyer’s medium for the identification process under 200-600× magnification.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Statistics
</title>
         <p>
All analyzes were conducted in R using RStudio (version 1.1.463) and results were considered significant at P&lt;0.05. Because the experimental design was nested, and in order to account for microfiber length effects, we initially tested the effects of microplastic 
type
(polyester and polypropylene) and microfiber length (
2–3mm
and 
5–6mm
) on Oribatida richness, decomposition rates (as measured by mass loss) and feeding activity (measured as consumed substrate in bait-lamina) using a nested ANOVA. As no significant effects of fiber length (Oribatida richness F 
2,45
= 0.345, P= 0.71, decomposition rates F 
2,45
= 3.115, P= 0.06, and feeding activity F 
2,45
= 0.671, P = 0.51) were detected, we grouped treatments by plastic 
type
only (i.e. control, polyester, polypropylene). Oribatida richness, decomposition rates, and feeding activity were then analyzed for differences between plastic treatments using a one-way 
type
II ANOVA (control, polypropylene, polyester treatments) to account for the unbalanced design. Tukey HSD post-hoc test was applied where applicable.
</p>
         <p>
To further evaluate the total number of Oribatida (adults + immatures), and the abundance of immature Oribatida, adult Oribatida, 
<tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata, Prostigmata, Astigmata, Acari</tp:taxon-name>
(all mites together), ‘other’ invertebrates, as well as total microarthropod abundance based on treatments (plastic 
type
, microfiber length) (all standardized by # ind. 
g-1
dw), we used the package ‘mvabund’ (

) to create univariate generalized models. It returns a table summarising the statistical significance of a fitted manyglm model (

). This package allows us to overcome the statistical issues that occur with a high number of zeros (

), which is a common feature in ecological community data (i.e. not all species will occur in all samples). The models were conducted using the {anova.manyglm} function assuming a negative binomial distribution, resampled 999 times (

) to test whether there is significant treatment effect.
</p>
         <p>
Microarthropod community composition was assessed using nonmetric multidimensional scaling (NMDS) (

) with PERMANOVA to compare community structure among treatments (in this case, plastic addition and microfiber length). To further describe the oribatid mite community, we ran correspondence analysis (CA), an ordination technique that plots species in multivariate space and allows inferences about how much of the variation in the dataset can be explained by treatments (

). In the CA plot, the closer the samples are to one another, the more similar they are in terms of their residuals. The same applies to species with other species in ordination space. Comparisons between samples and species are based on the angle between the lines from the origin to the location of a sample and of a species; the smaller the angle, the higher the association (0 to 90 degrees).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Results
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Decomposition and feeding rates
</title>
         <p>
Microplastic 
type
had a significant effect on the rate of decomposition measured as percent mass loss in litterbags (F 
2,47
= 4.83, P = 0.01), with the highest mass loss observed in polyester-addition (
0.11g
lost on average), followed by polypropylene-addition (
0.09g
lost on average) and control (
0.08g
lost on average) (Tukey HSD, P = 0.02) (
Figure 1
). Microplastic addition (F 
2,47
= 0.40, P = 0.67) showed no significant effect on feeding activity in the soil profile measured as the number of consumed baits in a bait-lamina. The soil microarthropod community exhibited very low feeding activity assessed in bait-laminas, with only nine of the 50 laminas having baits entirely eaten, with an average 1.4 baits/lamina consumed.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Microcosm microarthropod diversity
</title>
         <p>
We identified eight species of oribatid mites at the end of the experiment: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tectocepheus velatus
(Michael, 1880)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oppiella nova
(Oudemans, 1902)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Moritzoppia unicarinata
(Paoli, 1908)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Suctobelbella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scheloribates
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
nr. 
laevigatus
, 
Minuthozetes semirufus
(C.L. Koch, 1841), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichoribates
cf. 
novus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eupelops
cf. 
curtipilus
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Table S1
). Oribatida species richness was not significantly affected by microplastic addition (F 
2,47
= 1.53, P = 0.22).
</p>
         <p>
In total, 2663 oribatid mite specimens were collected, of which 1454 were immatures. Oribatid mites were the most abundant group across all treatments; their total abundance, including immatures, represented 86 % in control, 90% in polypropylene 
2–3mm
, 94 % in polyester 
2–3mm
, 88 % in polypropylene 
5–6mm
and 90 % of total abundance in polyester 
5–6mm
microcosms. The abundance of all individuals of oribatid mite (adults and immatures together) was not significantly affected by microplastic addition (LRT = 37.79, P = 0.47) or microfiber length (LRT = 54.15, P = 0.28) based on the mvabund analysis. The abundance of immatures did not significantly differ with plastic addition (LRT = 6.36, P = 0.58) or microfiber length (LRT = 14.98, P = 0.22). Microplastic addition (LRT = 31.42, P = 0.46) and microfiber length (LRT = 39.17, P = 0.36) did not have any significant effect on the abundance of adult oribatid mites.
</p>
         <p>
Microplastic addition had no significant effects on 
<tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
abundance (LRT = 9.57, P = 0.30), 
<tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata</tp:taxon-name>
abundance (LRT = 20.04, P = 0.13), Prostigmataabundance(LRT= 7.61,P= 0.11),Astigmata abundance (LRT = 2.34, P = 0.50), Acari abundance (LRT = 67.78, P = 0.36), other invertebrates abundance (LRT = 23.14, P = 0.24) and total microarthropod abundance (LRT = 100.5, P = 0.37).
</p>
         <p>
In addition, microfiber length did not have significant effects on 
<tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
abundance (LRT = 8.10, P = 0.41), 
<tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata</tp:taxon-name>
abundance (LRT = 23.17, P = 0.06), Prostigmataabundance(LRT= 4.67,P= 0.38),Astigmata abundance (LRT = 6.02, P = 0.13), Acari abundance (LRT = 88.03, P = 0.18), other invertebrates abundance (LRT = 28.22, P = 0.08) and total microarthropod abundance (LRT = 124.3, P = 0.15).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Community composition
</title>
         <p>
PERMANOVA results were not significant for the effect of microplastic addition (F 
2,47
= 1.11, P = 0.31) on microarthropod communities, although the NMDS
</p>
         <p>
plot demonstrates communities were less similar in polypropylene addition treatments compared to polyester addition and control treatments (
Figure 2A
). Permanova results were not significant for different lengths of plastic microfiber addition on microarthropod communities either (F 
2,47
= 0.60, P = 0.81), and no specific patterns can be seen in the NMDS plots (
Figure 2B
). In the correspondence analysis we conserved the first two axes, which explained, respectively 34.5 % and 18.8 % of the variance in microarthropod communities (
Figure S1
). Most species of oribatids had relatively similar residuals, and thus were grouped near the origin of the plot. However, three oribatid species were plotted away from the origin; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Suctobelbella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
was a singleton present in a polypropylene- 
5mm
sample, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Moritzoppia unicarinata
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oppiella nova
</tp:taxon-name>
were present in all the treatments, but in low abundance; 38 and 7 individuals, respectively. Neither any particular pattern of similarity or high association between species and treatments could be detected; the samples seemed to be randomly plotted due to the dominance in oribatid mite communities by two species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scheloribates
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
nr. 
laevigatus
and 
Minuthozetes semirufus
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Effects of microplastics on decomposition
</title>
         <p>
Aboveground and belowground systems are linked by the input of detritus to soils, where it is decomposed by primary decomposers (fungi and bacteria) and secondary decomposers (microarthropods, mostly oribatid mites and collembolans). In addition to the decomposers’ activity, abiotic factors such as temperature, moisture, and litter quality (chemical composition) are well known to affect decomposition rates (

). Our study demonstrates that microplastics are potentially another abiotic factor that might affect decomposition rates in soil systems with an increase in decomposition rates seen in litterbags in polyester-addition treatments, compared to polypropylene-addition and control treatments. Although not assessed here, polyester fibers have been shown to decrease soil bulk density and microbial activity and increase water holding capacity (

), besides reducing soil aggregate stability (

). In our study, litterbags were placed on the top of soil, thus also in contact with microplastic fibers. The mechanism underlying the increase in litter decomposition remains unknown.
</p>
         <p>
The few studies that have previously addressed the effects of microplastics on decomposition suggest that ratesmaybeaffectedthroughchangesinmicroarthropod gut microbiomes. For instance, 

found that commercial polyvinyl chloride (PVC) particles in soil significantly increased gut microbe alpha-diversity in 
<tp:taxon-name>
F. candida
Willem 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
, whereas 

demonstrated that polyethylene beads, instead, decreased gut microbe alpha-diversity in the same species. Changes in gut microbial communities can favour or impair species that are primary decomposers, ultimately affecting decomposition rates.
</p>
         <p>
However, considering that microplastics can be carbon sources to microbial communities in soils (

), they may contribute to a ‘priming’ effect (

), and therefore differences in microplastic decomposition rates may be a result of increased microbial activity through microbial growth. That said, as we did not measure the degradation of the microfibers, this would need further study to substantiate this hypothesis. Nonetheless, supporting this hypothesis, 

using a soil incubation experiment addressing the effect of biodegradable microplastics on soil functions and microbial communities, concluded that polylactic acid microplastics (a 
type
of polyester) could induce the ‘priming’ effect as a carbon source, which could potentially alter the nutrient content, for example, inorganic nitrogen and dissolved organic carbon. Polyesters are polymers with the monomer units linked by an ester group (–COO–) (

), which is easier to degrade than polypropylene, a thermoplastic polymer with a carbon-carbon backbone (C 
3
H 
5
) 

n

. Polyesters undergo hydrolysis, a relatively easier chemical reaction compared to the oxidation reactions involved in the degradation of polypropylene. Nonetheless, polypropylene also has been shown to be degraded by isolated soil microbial communities (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Effects of microplastics on microarthropods
</title>
         <p>

In our study, the addition of polyester and polypropylene microfibers did not contribute to differences in abundance of all microarthropods analysed individually (major taxonomic groups) or in totality. To the best of our knowledge and as this was one the first experiments using this 
type
of soil, plastics, and assessing microarthropod community responses, it is uncertain whether our study captured a short, long, or an ideal-duration for obtaining experimental results. 
Polyester
fibers have been found to have weak negative effects on soil invertebrates (isopod, collembolan, enchytraeid and oribatid mite) in a short-term laboratory assay (

). 
Althogh
this study also used polyester fibers, it differs from ours in the soil used (
Lufa
2.2 (
Lufa Speyer
, 
Germany
) compared to our loamy sand soil collected in 
Berlin
), microplastic concentration (0.02, 0.06, 0.17, 0.5 and 1.5 % ww compared to 0.4 % dw in ours), microarthropod communities (four species compared to our natural communities), fiber length (
12 mm
– 
2.87 mm
4–24 mm
compared to 
2–3 mm
and 
5–6 mm
here) and finally the effects investigated (reproduction, mortality, energy reserves, ingestion compared to feeding rates and changes community structure here)

.
</p>
         <p>
Microplastics have the ability to adsorb toxic substances like heavy metals (

, 

) on their surface, which may pose a threat to soil biota. Here, we used commercial microplastics that were recently bought and thus we did not expect the particles to carry other substances on their surface. Therefore, any potential direct negative effects of microplastic addition associated with toxins would not have been detected in our study.
</p>
         <p>
The microplastic concentration used here is in line with other studies on soil fauna, although most previous studies have looked at macrofauna (invertebrates&gt; 
2mm
) rather than microarthropods (

, 

, 

). The concentration of 0.4 % dw microplastic addition was previously seen to have direct effects on soil physical properties and microbial activity (

), both with potential negative consequences to microarthropod communities. Nonetheless, we did not detect significant differences in microarthropod abundance or Oribatida richness when microplastics were added to the microcosms. In a short-term study, 

found that significantly more individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
F. candida
</tp:taxon-name>
chose to live in soil without addition of polyethylene beads, and that collembolan reproduction was inhibited in relatively low concentrations of microplastics [0.1 % in dry soil (w/w)]. Regarding ingestion of microplastics in our study, although assessing it was not our goal, 85 % of the oribatid individuals were bigger than 
6mm
(the longest length treatment), which leaves open the question whether these oribatid mites could ingest microfibers, as seen in 

for smaller particles detected in 
<tp:taxon-name>Collembola</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
Microarthropods are essential to ecosystem services in soil systems. For instance, the feeding behaviour of collembolans (and most oribatid mites) promotes decomposition of organic matter and nutrient cycling in soils through feeding on fungi and bacteria (

). Although considered the best method to reflect soil animal and microbial feeding activity (

, 

), in our study, bait-lamina strips showed no differences in feeding rates with the addition of polyester or polypropylene. Nonetheless, 

detected increases in feeding rates with increases in earthworm density, but found no significant differences when exposed to collembolans and mites without earthworms. It is possible we did not detect responses because in our samples most of the fauna were microarthropods (mesofauna), with only a few macrofauna individuals (i.e. 43 earthworms total, most were juvenile). Bait strips could have fed upon steadily, but not enough to affect the entire bait substrate. As such, we consider the results of our bait lamina strips as underestimations of feeding.
</p>
         <p>
The fact that little is known regarding the effects of microplastics in soil microarthropods is concerning because the few results available [e.g., 

for 
<tp:taxon-name>
F. candida
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 

for 
<tp:taxon-name>
F. candida
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hypoaspis aculeifer
(Canestrini)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Mesostigmata</tp:taxon-name>
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Damaeus exspinosus
Wang &amp; Norton, 1989
</tp:taxon-name>
(Oribatida)] suggest that the movement of microarthropods in soils may influence the exposure of other soil biota to microplastics and change the physical properties of soils (see 

, Lehmann et al. 2019, 

) with unknown and potentially greater consequences at the ecosystem level. Even though in our study we detected no strong direct effects of microplastics on soil microarthropod communities, the movement of particles can rather impose a greater threat to ecosystem processes like decomposition.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
We detected effects of polyester addition in litter decomposition rates, but no direct effects of plastic addition on soil microarthropod communities. Although results are still conflicting in microplastic studies in soil systems, and it is difficult to directly compare our results due to differences in methodology and low number of studies, it is important to consider microplastics as a factor of global change that could affect soil biota and ecosystem process rates (

), since they persist and accumulate in soils (

). For example, 

points to the need of considering potential evolutionary implications of the presence of microplastics in soils, including changes in soil structure, alteration of host availability or function (host microbiome), toxic effects, and plastic particles themselves becoming a carbon resource and providing novel surfaces where heavy metals could adhere. With microplastics potentially being an issue in urban environments (e.g. our site) and due to their wide distribution, this topic may also deserve attention of policy makers and regulatory bodies (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
The authors thank Dr. Anika Lehmann, Dr. Eva Leifheit, Dr. 
India
Mansour and Dr. Moisés Sosa Hernández and for helping with experiment setup, and Sabine Buchert for helping with logistics (all above at Freie Universität). We thank Dr. Elizabeth Gillies (Western University) for helping with the chemistry involved in polymers. This research was funded by grants to CB by Mitacs 
Canada
(IT13825 GRA) and Science International Engagement Fund Award by Western University. MCR acknowledges support from an ERC Advanced Grant (694368).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
6. References
</title>
         <p>
Andrady, A. L.
(
2011
): 
Microplastics in the marine environment
. – 
Marine Pollution Bulletin
62

: 
1596−1605
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2011.05.030]
.

</p>
         <p>
Arthur, C.
, 
J. Baker
&amp; 
H. Bamford
(eds) (
2009
): 
Proceedings of the International Research Workshop on the occurrence, effects, and fate of microplastic marine debris. – NOAA Technical Memorandum NOS-OR&amp;R-30
, 
Tacoma, WA
, 
USA
: 
530 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Bayartogtokh, B.
&amp; 
H. Schatz
. (
2008
): 

Trichoribates
and 
Jugatala
(Acari: Oribatida: Ceratozetidae) from the Central and Southern Alps, with notes on their distribution

. – 
Zootaxa
35

: 
1−35
[

https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa. 
1948.1.1
]

.

</p>
         <p>
Bergami, E.
, 
Rota, E.
, 
Caruso, T.
, 
Birarda, G.
, 
Vaccari, L.
, &amp; 
Corsi, I.
(
2020
). 

Plastics everywhere: first evidence of polystyrene fragments inside the common Antarctic collembolan 
Cryptopygus antarcticus

. 
Biology Letters
, 
16
, 
20200093
https://doi.org/ 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2020.0093
</p>
         <p>
Bergmann, M.
, 
S. Mützel
., 
S. Primpke
., 
M. B.Tekman
., 
J.Trachsel
. &amp; 
G. Gerdts
. (
2019
): 
White and wonderful? Microplastics prevail in snow from the Alps to the Arctic
. – 

Science Advances 
5
: eaax

1157
[
https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aax1157]
.

</p>
         <p>
Bradford, M. A.
, 
B. Berg
, 
D. S. Maynard
, 
W. R. Wieder
&amp; 
S. A. Wood
(
2016
): 
Understanding the dominant controls on litter decomposition
. – 
Journal of Ecology
104

: 
229−238
[
https://doi. org/10.1111/1365-2745.12507]
.

</p>
         <p>
Buchanan, J. B.
(
1971
): 
Pollution by synthetic: fibres oiled birds in Holland
. – 
Marine Pollution Bulletin
2

: 
23
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/0025-326X(71)90136-6]
.

</p>
         <p>
Cacciari, I.
, 
P. Quatrini
, 
G. Zirletta
, 
E. Mincione
, 
V. Vinciguerra
, 
P. Lupattelli
&amp; 
G. G. Sermanni
(
1993
): 
Isotactic polypropylene biodegradation by a microbial community: physicochemical characterization of metabolites produced
. – 
Applied and Environmental Microbiology
59

: 
3695−3700
[
https://doi. org/10.1128/aem.59.11.3695-3700.1993]
.

</p>
         <p>
Cao, D.
, 
X. Wang
, 
X. Luo
, 
G. Liu
&amp; 
H. Zheng
(
2017
): 
Effects of polystyrene microplastics on the fitness of earthworms in an agricultural soil
. – 
IOP Conference Series: Earth and Environmental Science
61

: 012148 [
https://doi. org/10.1088/1755-1315/61/1/012148]
.

</p>
         <p>
Chen, H.
, 
Y. Wang
, 
X. Sun
, 
Y. Peng
&amp; 
L. Xiao
(
2020
): 
Mixing effect of polylactic acid microplastic and straw residue on soil property and ecological function
. – 
Chemosphere
243

: [
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2019.125271]
.

</p>
         <p>
Clarke, K. R.
(
1993
): 
Non‐parametric multivariate analyses of changes in community structure
.– 
Australian Journal of Ecology
18

: 
117−143
[
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1442-9993.1993. tb00438.x]
.

</p>
         <p>
Cole, M.
, 
P. Lindeque
, 
C. Halsband
&amp; 
T. S. Galloway
(
2011
): 
Microplastics as contaminants in the marine environment: a review
. – 
Marine Pollution Bulletin
62

: 
2588–2597
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2011.09.025]
.

</p>
         <p>
Colton, J. B.
, 
F. D. Knapp
&amp; 
B. R. Burns
(
1974
): 
Plastic particles in surface waters of the Northwestern Atlantic
. – 
Science
185

: 
491–497
.

</p>
         <p>
de Souza Machado,A.A.
, 
C.W.Lau
, 
J.Till
, 
W.Kloas
, 
A.Lehmann
, 
R. Becker
&amp; 
M. C. Rillig
(
2018
b): 
Impacts of microplastics on the soil biophysical environment
. – 
Environmental Science and Technology
52

: 
9656−9665
[
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. est.8b02212]
.

</p>
         <p>
de Souza Machado, A. A.
, 
W. Kloas
, 
C. Zarfl
, 
S. Hempel
&amp; 
M. C. Rillig
(
2018
a): 
Microplastics as an emerging threat to terrestrial ecosystems
. – 
Global Change Biology
24

: 
1405–1416
[
https:// doi.org/10.1111/gcb.14020]
.

</p>
         <p>
Deville, J. C.
&amp; 
G. Saporta
(
1983
): 
Correspondence analysis, with an extension towards nominal time series
. – 
Journal of Econometrics
22

: 
169−189
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/0304- 4076(83)90098-2]
.

</p>
         <p>
Dioses-Salinas, D. C.
, 
C. I. Pizarro-Ortega
. &amp; 
G. E. De-la-Torre
. (
2020
): 
A methodological approach of the current literature on microplastic contamination in terrestrial environments: Current knowledge and baseline considerations
. – 
The Science of the Total Environment
730

: 
139164
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. scitotenv.2020.139164]
.

</p>
         <p>
Dris, R.
, 
J. Gasperi
, 
M. Saad
, 
C. Mirande
&amp; 
B. Tassin
(
2016
): 
Synthetic fibers in atmospheric fallout: a source of microplastics in the environment?
– 
Marine Pollution Bulletin
104

: 
290–293
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2016.01.006]
.

</p>
         <p>
Duis, K.
&amp; 
A. Coors
(
2016
): 
Microplastics in the aquatic and terrestrial environment: sources (with a specific focus on personal care products), fate and effects
. – 
Environmental Sciences Europe
28

: 
1–25
[
https://doi.org/10.1186/s12302- 015-0069-y]
.

</p>
         <p>
Frias, J. P. G. L.
&amp; 
R. Nash
(
2019
): 
Microplastics: finding a consensus on the definition
. – 
Marine Pollution Bulletin
138

: 
145–147
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2018.11.022]
.

</p>
         <p>
Gaylor, M. O.
, 
E. Harvey
&amp; 
R. C. Hale
(
2013
): 

Polybrominated diphenyl ether (PBDE) accumulation by earthworms (
Eisenia fetida
) exposed to biosolids-, polyurethane foam microparticle-, and penta-BDE-amended soils

. – 
Environmental Science and Technology
47

: 
13831–13839
[
https://doi.org/10.1021/ es403750a]
.

</p>
         <p>
GESAMP

(
2015
): 
Sources, fate and effects of microplastics in the marine environment: a global assessment
. 
London, UK
: 
96 pp.
</p>
         <p>
GESAMP
(
2016
): 
Sources, fate and effects of microplastics in the marine environment: part 2 of a global assessment
. – 
International Maritime Organization
, 
London, UK
: 
220 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Geyer, R.
, 
J. R. Jambeck
. &amp; 
K. L. Law
. (
2017
): 
Production, use, and fate of all plastics ever made
. – 
Science Advances
3

: 
25−29
. [
https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.1700782]
.

</p>
         <p>
Gooch, J. W.
(
2007
): 
P
. – In: 
Encyclopedic dictionary of polymers
. – 
Springer US
, 
New York, NY
: 
742
.

</p>
         <p>
Hartmann, N. B.
, 
T. Hüffer
, 
R. C. Thompson
, 
M. Hassellöv
, 
A. Verschoor
, 
A. E. Daugaard
, 
S. Rist
, 
T. Karlsson
, 
N. Brennholt
, 
M. Cole
, 
M. P. Herrling
, 
M. C. Hess
, 
N. P. Ivleva
, 
A. L. Lusher
&amp; 
M. Wagner
(
2019
): 
Are we speaking the same language? Recommendations for a definition and categorization framework for plastic debris
. – 
Environmental Science and Technology
53

: 
1039−1047
[
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. est.8b05297]
.

</p>
         <p>
Helling, B.
, 
G. Pfeiff
&amp; 
O. Larink
(
1998
): 
A comparison of feeding activity of collembolan and enchytraeid in laboratory studies using the bait-lamina test
. – 
Applied Soil Ecology
7

: 
207−212
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0929-1393(97)00065-6]
.

</p>
         <p>
Hodson, M. E.
, 
C.A. Duffus-Hodson
, 
A. Clark
, M.T. Prendergast- Miller &amp; 
K. L.Thorpe
(
2017
): 
Plastic bag derived-microplastics as a vector for metal exposure in terrestrial invertebrates
. – 
Environmental Science and Technology
51

: 
4714−4721
[
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.7b00635]
.

</p>
         <p>
Horton, A. A.
, 
A. Walton
., 
D. J. Spurgeon
., 
E. Lahive
. &amp; 
C. Svendsen
. (
2017
): 
Microplastics in freshwater and terrestrial environments: Evaluating the current understanding to identify the knowledge gaps and future research priorities
. – 
Science of the Total Environment
586

: 
127−141
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. scitotenv.2017.01.190]
.

</p>
         <p>
Huerta Lwanga, E.
, 
B. Thapa
., 
X. Yang
., 
H. Gertsen
., 
T. Salánki
., 
V. Geissen
. &amp; 
P. Garbeva
. (
2018
): 
Decay of low-density polyethylene by bacteria extracted from earthworm’s guts: A potential for soil restoration
. – 
Science of the Total Environment
624

: 
753−757
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. scitotenv.2017.12.144]
.

</p>
         <p>
Huerta Lwanga, E.
, 
H. Gertsen
, 
H. Gooren
, 
P. Peters
, 
T. Salánki
, 
M. van der Ploeg
, 
E. Besseling
, 
A. A. Koelmans
&amp; 
V. Geissen
(
2016
): 

Microplastics in the terrestrial ecosystem: implications for 
Lumbricus terrestris
(Oligochaeta, Lumbricidae)

. – 
Environmental Science and Technology
50

: 
2685−2691
[
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.5b05478]
.

</p>
         <p>
Huerta Lwanga, E.
, 
J. Mendoza Vega
, 
V. Ku Quej
, J. de los 
A. Chi
, 
L. Sanchez
del Cid, 
C. Chi
, 
G. Escalona Segura
, 
H. Gertsen
, 
T. Salánki
, 
M. van der Ploeg
, 
A. A. Koelmans
&amp; 
V. Geissen
(
2017
): 
Field evidence for transfer of plastic debris along a terrestrial food chain
. – 
Scientific Reports
7

: 
1−7
[
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-14588-2]
.

</p>
         <p>
Ivar do Sul, J. A.
&amp; 
M. F. Costa
(
2014
): 
The present and future of microplastic pollution in the marine environment
. – 
Environmental Pollution
185

: 
352–364
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.envpol.2013.10.036]
.

</p>
         <p>
Ju, H.
, 
D. Zhu
&amp; 
M. Qiao
(
2019
): 

Effects of polyethylene microplastics on the gut microbial community, reproduction and avoidance behaviors of the soil springtail, 
Folsomia candida

. – 
Environmental Pollution
247

: 
890−897
[
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2019.01.097]
.

</p>
         <p>
Kim, S. W.
&amp; 
Y. An
(
2019
): 
Soil microplastics inhibit the movement of springtail species
. – 
Environment International
126

: 
699−706
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2019.02.067]
.

</p>
         <p>
Kooi, M.
&amp; 
A. A. Koelmans
(
2019
): 
Simplifying microplastic via continuous probability distributions for size, shape, and density
. – 
Environmental Science and Technology Letters
6

: 
551−557
[
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.estlett.9b00379]
.

</p>
         <p>
Krantz, G. W.
&amp; 
D. E. Walter
. (
2009
): 
A manual of acaroloy. 3rd edn
. – 
Texas Tech University Press, Lubbock, Texas
: 
816 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Kratz, W.
(
1998
): 
The bait-lamina test: general aspects, applications and perspectives
. – 
Environmental Science and Pollution Research
5

: 
94−96
[
https://doi.org/10.1007/ BF02986394]
.

</p>
         <p>
Lehmann, A.
, 
K. Fitschen
&amp; 
M. C. Rillig
(
2019
): 
Abiotic and biotic factors influencing the effect of microplastic on soil aggregation
. – 
Soil Systems
3

: 
21
[
https://doi.org/10.3390/ soilsystems3010021]
.

</p>
         <p>
Maass, S.
, 
D. Daphi
, 
A. Lehmann
&amp; 
M. C. Rillig
(
2017
): 
Transport of microplastics by two collembolan species
. – 
Environmental Pollution
225

: 
456−459
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.envpol.2017.03.009]
.

</p>
         <p>
Mason, S.
(
2019
): 
Plastics, Plastics Everywhere
. – 
American Scientist
107

: 
284
[
https://doi.org/10.1511/2019.107.5.284]
.

</p>
         <p>
Mason,S.A.
, 
D. Garneau
, 
R. Sutton
, 
Y.Chu
, 
K. Ehmann
, 
J. Barnes
, 
P. Fink
, 
D. Papazissimos
&amp; 
D. L. Rogers
(
2016
): 
Microplastic pollution is widely detected in US municipal wastewater treatment plant effluent
. – 
Environmental Pollution
218

: 
1045−1054
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2016.08.056]
.

</p>
         <p>
Nizzetto, L.
, 
M. Futter
&amp; 
S. Langaas
(
2016
a): 
Are agricultural soils dumps for microplastics of urban origin?
– 
Environmental Science and Technology
50

: 
10777−10779
[
https://doi. org/10.1021/acs.est.6b04140]
.

</p>
         <p>
Nizzetto, L.
, 
S. Langaas
. &amp; 
M. Futter
. (
2016
b): 
Do microplastics spill on to farm soils?
– 
Nature
537

: 
488
</p>
         <p>
Potapov, A. A.
, 
E. E. Semenina
, 
A. Y. Korotkevich
, 
N. A. Kuznetsova
&amp; 
A. V. Tiunov
(
2016
): 
Connecting taxonomy and ecology: trophic niches of collembolans as related to taxonomic identity and life forms
. – 
Soil Biology and Biochemistry
101

: 
20−31
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.soilbio.2016.07.002]
.

</p>
         <p>
Rillig M. C.
&amp; 
A. Lehmann
(
2020
): 
Microplastic in terrestrial ecosystems
. 
Science
368

: 
1430−1431
.

</p>
         <p>
Rillig, M. C.
(
2012
): 
Microplastic in terrestrial ecosystems and the soil?
– 
Environmental Science and Technology
46

: 
6453−6454
[
https://doi.org/10.1021/es302011r]
.

</p>
         <p>
Rillig, M. C.
, 
A. A. de Souza Machado
, 
A. Lehmann
&amp; 
U. Klümper
(
2019
): 
Evolutionary implications of microplastics for soil biota
. – 
Environmental Chemistry
16

: 
3−7
[
https://doi. org/10.1071/EN18118]
.

</p>
         <p>
Rillig, M. C.
, 
L. Ziersch
&amp; 
S. Hempel
(
2017
): 
Microplastic transport in soil by earthworms
. – 
Scientific Reports
7

: 
1−6
[
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-01594-7]
.

</p>
         <p>
Rodriguez-Seijo, A.
, 
J. Lourenço
, 
T. A. P. Rocha-Santos
, 
J. da Costa
, 
A. C. Duarte
, 
H. Vala
&amp; 
R. Pereira
(
2017
): 

Histopathological and molecular effects of microplastics in 
Eisenia andrei
Bouché

. – 
Environmental Pollution
220

: 
495−503
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2016.09.092]
.

</p>
         <p>
Rodríguez-Seijo, A.
, 
J. P. da Costa
, 
T. Rocha-Santos
, 
A. C. Duarte
&amp; 
R. Pereira
(
2018
): 

Oxidative stress, energy metabolism and molecular responses of earthworms (
Eisenia fetida
) exposed to low-density polyethylene microplastics

. – 
Environmental Science and Pollution Research
25

: 
33599−33610
[
https://doi. org/10.1007/s11356-018-3317-z]
.

</p>
         <p>
Selonen, S.
, 
A. Dolar
, 
A. Jemec Kokalj
, 
T. Skalar
, 
L. Parramon Dolcet
, 
R. Hurley
&amp; 
C. A. M. van Gestel
(
2020
): 
Exploring the impacts of plastics in soil – the effects of polyester textile fibers on soil invertebrates
. – 
Science of the Total Environment
700

: 
134451
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.134451]
.

</p>
         <p>
Seniczak, A.
, 
S. Seniczak
. &amp; 
S. Kaczmarek
. (
2015
): 

Morphology, distribution and ecology of 
Eupelops curtipilus
and 
Eupelops plicatus
(Acari, Oribatida, Phenopelopidae)

. – 
International Journal of Acarology
41

: 
77−95
[
https://doi.org/10.1080/0164 7954.2014.986523]
.

</p>
         <p>
Shen, M.
, 
B. Song
., 
G. Zeng
., 
Y. Zhang
., 
W. Huang
., 
X. Wen
. &amp; 
W.Tang
.(
2020
): 
Arebiodegradableplasticsapromisingsolution to solve the global plastic pollution?
– 
Environmental Pollution
263

: 
114469
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2020.114469]
.

</p>
         <p>
Thompson, R. C.
, 
C. J. Moore
., F. S. vom Saal. &amp; 
S. H. Swan
. (
2009
): 
Plastics, the environment and human health: Current consensus and future trends
. – 
Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences
364

: 
2153−2166
[
https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2009.0053]
.

</p>
         <p>
Thompson, R. C.
, 
Y. Olsen
, 
R. P. Mitchell
, 
A. Davis
, 
S. J. Rowland
, 
A. W. G. John
, 
D. McGonigle
&amp; 
A. E. Russel
(
2004
): 
Lost at sea: where is all the plastic?
– 
Science
304

: 
838
[

https:// doi.org/10.1210/jcem- 
10-10-1361
]

.

</p>
         <p>
van Gestel, C. A. M.
, 
M. Kruidenier
&amp; 
M. P. Berg
(
2003
): 
Suitability of wheat straw decomposition, cotton strip degradation and bait-lamina feeding tests to determine soil invertebrate activity
. – 
Biology and Fertility of Soils
37
: 
115– 123
[
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00374-002-0575-0]
.

</p>
         <p>
Wagner, S.
, 
T. Hüffer
, 
P. Klöckner
, 
M. Wehrhahn
, 
T. Hofmann
&amp; 
T. Reemtsma
(
2018
): 
Tire wear particles in the aquatic environment − a review on generation, analysis, occurrence, fate and effects
. – 
Water Research
139

: 
83−100
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.watres.2018.03.051]
.

</p>
         <p>
Wan, Y.
, 
C. Wu
, 
Q. Xue
&amp; 
X. Hui
(
2019
): 
Effects of plastic contamination on water evaporation and desiccation cracking in soil
. – 
Science of the Total Environment
654

: 
576−582
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.11.123]
.

</p>
         <p>
Wang, Y.
, 
U. Naumann
, 
S. T. Wright
&amp; 
D. I. Warton
(
2012
): 
mvabund − an R package for model-based analysis of multivariate abundance data
. – 
Methods in Ecology and Evolution
3

: 
471−474
[
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.2041- 210X.2012.00190.x]
.

</p>
         <p>
Warton, D. I.
(
2011
): 
Regularized sandwich estimators for analysis of high-dimensional data using generalized estimating equations
. – 
Biometrics
67

: 
116−123
[
https://doi.org/10.1111/ j.1541-0420.2010.01438.x]
.

</p>
         <p>
Weigmann, G.
(
2006
): 
Hornmilben (Oribatida) — Die Tierwelt Deutschlands, Teil 76
. – 
Goecke &amp; Evers
, 
520 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Wright, S. L.
, 
R. C. Thompson
&amp; 
T. S. Galloway
(
2013
): 
The physical impacts of microplastics on marine organisms: a review
. – 
Environmental Pollution
178

: 
483−492
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.envpol.2013.02.031]
.

</p>
         <p>
Zhu, D.
, 
Q. Bi
, 
Q. Xiang
, 
Q. Chen
, 
P. Christie
, 
X. Ke
, 
L. Wu
&amp; 
Y. Zhu
(
2018
a): 

Trophic predator-prey relationships promote transport of microplastics compared with the single 
Hypoaspis aculeifer
and 
Folsomia candida

. – 
Environmental Pollution
235

: 
150−154
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2017.12.058]
.

</p>
         <p>
Zhu, D.
, 
Q. L. Chen
, 
X. L. An
, 
X. R. Yang
, 
P. Christie
, 
X. Ke
, 
L. H. Wu
&amp; 
Y. G. Zhu
(
2018
b): 
Exposure of soil collembolans to microplastics perturbs their gut microbiota and alters their isotopic composition
. – 
Soil Biology and Biochemistry
116

: 
302−310
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.soilbio.2017.10.027]
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Supplementary Informations 
Table S1
and 
Figure S1
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
