<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Soil Organisms</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25674/so93iss1pp1</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Biodiversity in agricultural used soils: Threats and options for its conservation in Germany and Europe</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group/>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
AGENCY REPORT
</title>
         <p>

Biodiversity in agricultural used soils: Threats and options for its conservation in 
Germany
and Europe

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Moritz Nabel
*, 
Christian Selig
, 
Johanna Gundlach
, Henrike von der Decken and 
Manfred Klein
</title>
         <p>
German FederaL Agency for NatUre Conservation (BfN), Konstantinstr. 110, 53179 Bonn, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>* Corresponing aUthor, EmaiL: moritz.nabeL@bfn.de</p>
         <p>
Received 
23 FebrUary 2021
| Accepted 
18 March 2021
</p>
         <p>
Published online at www.soil-organisms.de 


1 ApriL 
2021

| Printed version 
15 ApriL 2021
</p>
         <p>
DOI 
10.25674/so93iss1pp1
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Abstract
</title>
         <p>Agriculture and soil biodiversity are highly interdependent. Agriculture strongly depends on essential ecosystem services of an active and diverse soil life, leading to soil fertility. Fertile soil is the basis for the cultivation of vital, robust and productive crops. However, today’s intensive agriculture partly aims at replacing certain natural ecosystem services by intense agricultural practices and the use of agrochemicals. Even more, these intensive practices including intense mechanical soil tillage, pollution from contaminated fertilizers and pesticides pose direct threats to soil biodiversity. Although the biggest share of soil biodiversity has not yet been taxonomically recorded, there is evidence of a decline in soil biodiversity.</p>
         <p>There are many opportunities in agriculture to support an active and diverse soil life and profit from its related ecosystem services. Here we present a set of actions to promote soil biodiversity in agricultural used soils including measures from integrated pest and nutrient management, conservation soil cultivation and agricultural diversification. All these actions show synergies for a transition of agricultural productions systems to a more sustainable and climate change smart production. This transition process needs to be understood as a process relevant to society as a whole. Therefore, extra efforts cannot be borne by farmers alone, but adequate subsidies with a clear focus on soil biodiversity need to be implemented in agricultural policies on national and international level. At international level the 15th Conference of the Parties of the Convention on Biodiversity (CBD COP15) can set the frame for the future of soil biodiversity. On European and national level, the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) and its implementation via the national strategic plans will be key for a transition to a soil biodiversity promoting agricultural production. Investments in research and development help to continuously develop measures and legal frameworks and to invest in effective soil protection in the long term.</p>
         <p>
Keywords
SoiL Biodiversity
| 
AgricULtUre
| 
Threats
| 
Conservation
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Soils, especially in temperate climate zones, are host to a variety of organisms that exceeds the biological diversity above ground (

). About 90 % of all living organisms are bound to soils in different ways throughout their live-cycles and are part of food webs that closely link above- and belowground biodiversity (

). Further, soil organisms provide a wide range of ecosystem services that make them ecosystem engineers. These ecosystem services include the processing of detritus by shredding, decomposing and mineralizing, the creation of a resilient soil matrix as well as the natural regulation of pathogens and pests (

). With all these activities, soil organisms create the basis for a diverse and vital life below- and above ground: a fertile soil (

). Fertile soils are distinguished by a well aerated structure, good water infiltration and retention, stable humus aggregation, nutrient retention and availability and a wide range of further parameters. Also, humans strongly depend on fertile soil as valuable and non-regenerative resource as it is the basis of all agricultural activities.
</p>
         <p>
The United Nations’ Food and Agricultural Organisation (FAO) directly related the ecosystem services of soil biodiversity to six of the 17 United Nations’ (UN) Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs, 
Fig. 1
) (

).
</p>
         <p>
Even though life below ground is so far only known and understood to a marginal extent, the loss of soil biodiversity is documented on an international (

), European (

), and national level (

) to be as prominent and dramatic as it is documented for above ground biodiversity. Soil biodiversity related ecosystem services are therefore threatened. The consequences for ecosystems and agriculture are severe and will oppose the fulfilment of the SDGs (

).
</p>
         <p>
Therefore, the conservation and promotion of soil biodiversity is receiving increasing attention. At an international level the Convention on Biodiversity (CBD) intends to adopt a draft plan of action for soil biodiversity at its next conference of the parties (COP15) (

). At European level soil and soil biodiversity related aspects are included into the Biodiversity Strategy for 2030 (

) and the Farm to Fork Strategy (

) of the European Union (EU). For 
Germany
with about 50% of the terrestrial area under agricultural use, the Federal Agency for Nature Conservation (BfN) compiled a report on soil biodiversity including actions to conserve and promote soil biodiversity especially in soils under agricultural practice (

).
</p>
         <p>
Agriculture strongly depends on soil biodiversity related ecosystem services including the maintenance and promotion of soil fertility. On the other hand, intensive agriculture is one of the major threats to soil biodiversity (

). Many of the agricultural practices that threaten soil biodiversity mimic the natural ecosystem services provided by soil organisms. Even though many different factors like soil sealing and different sources of soil pollution are responsible for the decline in soil biodiversity (

, 

), we will focus only on agricultural aspects in this article. We will exhibit how agricultural practices and policies endanger soil biodiversity and which agricultural actions would be suitable to conserve and promote the diversity of organisms in agricultural soils. Here, the proposed actions are beneficial for soil organisms, soil fertility and therefore also for farmers themselves. We want to open a win-win situation and show a common path for nature conservation and agriculture. In line with the SDGs, the presented measures are suitable to adapt agricultural practices to climate change and increase food security as well as ecosystem resilience.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Threats to soil biodiversity
</title>
         <p>
Even though soil biodiversity and its ecosystem services receive increasing attention, large parts still remain hidden underground. Estimations assume 75 % of earth worm -, 50 % of ant – and 50 % of all mite species are not yet taxonomically recorded. For soil fungi species (6 % are described) and soil microorganisms (1 % are discovered) the lack in knowledge is even bigger (

, 

, 

, 

). However, already today it is obvious that the state of soil biodiversity shows the same negative trend which is well documented for above ground biodiversity over the past decades (

, 

). For 
Germany
, the nationwide red lists document that 37 % of earth worm-, 22% of isopod-, 24 % of millipede-, 35 % of ground beetle- and 25 % of fungi species are endangered (BfN 2011, BfN 2016a, BfN 2016b). Also, 28 % of vascular plants, whose roots and diaspora represent an important part of soil biodiversity, are endangered (BfN 2018). It should be emphasized that species adapted to agricultural areas are particularly affected (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
The reasons for this decline are manifold. For the agricultural sector, they can be narrowed down to the ongoing intensification in the past decades. In the process of intensification, many ecosystem services provided by soil biodiversity were replaced by chemical and mechanical treatments of agricultural soils and crops (

). The care and maintenance of an active and diverse soil life and its positive effect on soil fertility faded into the background. The related losses in soil fertility were partly compensated by progress in plant breeding and developments of synthetic fertilizers and pesticides. However, this intensive agriculture, depending on high input of agrochemicals and heavy machinery, comes at high ecological costs (

). In the following sections, major aspects of intensive agriculture are analysed on their influence on soil biodiversity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1 Chemical Threats
</title>
         <p>
Agricultural soils and their related soil organisms, especially under intensive agricultural production, are exposed to diffuse substance discharges (

). Residues of multiple pesticides and contaminations from fertilizers accumulate in soils over time (

). Even though levels of individual substances might not exceed critical levels, their combination can cause cross reactions (

).
</p>
         <p>
Most of the applied pesticides on agricultural soils are not selective to the target organism of the substance but have a broad spectrum, thus affecting many non-target species (FAO &amp; ITPS 2017, 

). Lethal and sub lethal effects on soil organisms can be the consequence and weaken the populations of soil organisms in the long term. So far, these effects are not taken into consideration within the European procedures for authorising plant protection products (EASAC &amp; Leopoldina 
April 2015
). Soil organisms are responsible for the degradation of pesticide residues and other harmful organic substances. However, metabolites that are intermediate products of this degradation process can still be toxic and pose a risk to soil organisms (

). Accordingly, herbicides, fungicides and insecticides are related to shifts in distribution or changes in species assemblage of 80 %, 87 % and 95 %, respectively (

).
</p>
         <p>
Today, 74 % of the global nitrogen fertilization is derived synthetically thus enriching the global nitrogen cycles causing eutrophication of ecosystems including soils. Plant biomass from ecosystems affected by eutrophication has a closer ratio between Carbon and Nitrogen and thus a lower content of stable Carbon structures like hemicelluloses or lignin. A decline in abundance and diversity of organisms, specialised to the degradation of such substances is a consequence (

).
</p>
         <p>
On the other side, the abundance of organisms specialised on the degradation of easily degradable plant materials is increased. In the long term the humus- and carbon content of soils decreases, affecting the basis of all soil organisms (

). Further, plants in ecosystems affected by eutrophication do not depend on symbioses with mycorrhiza or rhizobia anymore. Therefore the release of exudates from roots is minimised or even stopped with far reaching consequences for all organisms in the rhizosphere (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
Sulphur emissions were a major source for acidification of soils in the past. Today, mainly Nitrogen emissions are responsible for soil acidification. Acidification of soils has direct influence on the ratio of fungi and bacteria und thus can influence nutrient availability for plants, directly and indirectly (

).
</p>
         <p>
Mineral and organic fertilizers can be contaminated with heavy metals or organic pollutants harmful to soil organisms. Mineral fertilizers like potassium or sulphur, depending on their origin, can be a source of heavy metals that accumulate in agricultural used soils over long periods (

). Organic fertilizers like sludge or manures can contain residues and metabolites of veterinary drugs and antibiotics that are commonly used in intense livestock production systems (

, 

). Already in the short run antibiotics can create a selective advantage for resistant organisms (

: e1002158). In the long term, these resistant organisms can cause health issues also for humans (

). Antiparasitic agents often are used as preemptive measures to avoid infection of grazers. These agents pass the gastrointestinal tract of animals and remain in the dung on pastures. Usually, dung represents a valuable food source and habitat for soil organisms. However, the antiparasitic agents make contaminated dung unavailable for soil organisms or harms them directly (

).
</p>
         <p>
New emerging pollutants of soils are micro- and nano plastic particles. Even though their impact on physical and chemical traits in soils has already been proven (

), the extend of the direct impact on soil organisms is still being investigated (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Physical Threats
</title>
         <p>
Of all mechanical forms of tillage, plowing has the most serious influence on soil biodiversity since the topmost soil layer that is enriched with living and organic material, is shifted to a depth where many organisms can no longer work effectively. In addition, passages and pores are destroyed (

). Earthworms in particular are often directly affected (

) when they are injured by the plow and moved to the soil surface, where they are easy prey for birds and other predators (

). In general, the macro and mesofauna are particularly affected by mechanical interventions in the soil structure, leading to the fact that the soil life on arable soils is less diverse and mainly consists of microorganisms (

). However, fungi, which can form widely branched networks of fungal hyphae in the soil, are also affected by the mechanical interference. Consequently, in arable soils the symbiosis of cultivated plants with mycorrhizal fungi is also permanently disturbed (

).
</p>
         <p>
Intensive tillage also destroys the natural soil structure and increases the vulnerability to soil compaction. In the EU, 35 % of agricultural soils show significant compaction damage (

). Compacted soils offer larger soil organisms such as arthropods or worms only a limited habitat, since the energy expenditure for locomotion in compacted soil becomes too great. Another consequence is an increased vulnerability to erosion and waterlogging, which disrupts an adequate oxygen supply for soil life. Since the topsoil is particularly rich in organic material and thus essential for soil life, it holds the highest species density (

). A disturbed soil structure in combination with increased surface runoff cause an erosion of this biodiversity-rich topsoil by wind and rain. In Europe, 45 % of the soils have already lost a significant amount of organic matter in the topsoil (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Other Threats
</title>
         <p>
Today, agricultural land is used for various reasons, which leads to a further intensification of land management. In 
Germany
, for example, 56 hectares are sealed daily for transport and settlement areas, although the demand for agricultural products is constantly increasing (

). The pressure on agricultural land is particularly high in regions where animal husbandry and biogas use meet. In the EU, 60 % of the grain harvest ends up in a trough instead of directly on the plate (

). The growing bioeconomy leads to an increasing use of agricultural land for the production of industrial raw materials or bioenergy fuels. The growing pressure on land results in massive changes in both land use and environment and nature. For example, 83 % of extensive grassland habitats in 
Germany
are severely endangered (

). This not only has fatal effects on biodiversity aboveground: 47 % of individuals in the soil are lost when extensive grassland is converted to arable land and the biomass of soil life drops by 37 % (

).
</p>
         <p>
The EU’s Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) has a major impact on the way land is managed. Currently, EU agricultural subsidies are paid per hectare of land. Yieldoriented and often non-agricultural investors benefit particularly from this. This means that a large part of the money is passed on indirectly to landowners. Structural weakness and social instability in agricultural companies often lead to land and companies sales in the course of generation change and end in high concentrations of ownership of land by locally and supra-regionally organized holding structures (

). In the period from 2009 to 2019, the prices for arable land and grassland increased by a factor of 2.3 (

). Such misguided developments currently make it difficult for farmers to invest in long-term farm planning that is oriented toward soil life and soil fertility.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Actions to conserve and promote soil biodiversity
</title>
         <p>
In the political discussion about the transition to a more sustainable agricultural practice, promoting biodiversity in agricultural areas is an increasing issue (

, 

, 

). Despite the fact that many measures for above ground biodiversity have beneficial synergetic effects for soil ecology, targeted measures for soil conservation and fertility remain to be implemented. The FAO proposals for a conservation agriculture, which includes integrated crop management (ICM) and integrated pest management (IPM), can be considered as overarching guidelines for transition pathways to agricultural systems that serve both food production and (soil) biodiversity (

, 

, 

, 

). As the FAOs main concern is food security, for the sole purpose of nature conservation more strict soil protection measures are conceivable. In the case of agricultural production systems, the transition to sustainability, where biodiversity is a production goal that serves profitability, has to be accompanied by targeted financial support for farmers (

). To be sustainable, financial support has to be measurable and it must support the protection or deliverance of public goods (

). The increase in soil organic matter, for example, is measurable, and the protection of fertile soils is a public good. Nevertheless do farmers need to be actively involved in the process of transition as they are the main stakeholders (

). The core elements of conservation agriculture, with a focus on soil biodiversity, are outlined in the following sections.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1 Conservation Agriculture
</title>
         <p>
Soil, along with its diversity of living organisms, needs to be understood as the essential basis of all sustainable land cultivation activities. The FAO sets soil fertility as the central element of its concept of conservation agriculture (

). The concept builds on the three main key elements conservation soil cultivation, permanent ground cover and agricultural diversification, but also expands to integrated pest management (IPM) and integrated nutrient management (INM) (

).
</p>
         <p>3.1.1 Conservation soil cultivation</p>
         <p>
In order to disturb the soil habitat as little as possible, conservation soil cultivation aims at preserving the natural soil horizons and especially conserving the topsoil, rich in organic matter (

, 

). At the same time, soil organisms experience only little mechanical disturbance and are not translocated to deeper soil layers. The soil matrix with pores and subterranean tunnels remains in good condition, including a wide range of microhabitats for soil organisms (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
An already well established method is direct seeding. However, in most cases it solely depends on broadspectrum herbicides for weed control with far reaching negative effects on the biodiversity of agricultural ecosystems (

, 

). Negative effects of herbicides, especially of glyphosates, on belowground biodiversity have been shown in the past (

). Here, mulch drilling systems might offer an alternative, reducing the dependency on broad herbicides. The mulch covers the soil surface and thus suppresses weed germination, provides cover and a nutritional basis for a wide range of soil organisms (

).
</p>
         <p>
In case high weed -, pest - or disease pressure demand for tillage, this practice should be accompanied by immediate organic fertilization to enrich the topsoil with organic matter and allow for a fast and successful repopulation with an active and diverse soil life (

).
</p>
         <p>3.1.2 Permanent ground cover</p>
         <p>
Catch crops are widely implemented in today’s agriculture to protect soils from erosion and nutrient leaching outside the vegetation period. They provide shelter and food for a variety of organisms in periods between harvest and seeding of new crops and enrich the topsoil with organic matter (

, 

). As a method of IPM, catch crops also supress the emergence of unwanted weeds (

). The long term effects of catch crops on soil conservation also increases the income potential of the fields as soil fertility and crop yield are positively affected (

). To achieve the greatest positive effect, catch crop mixtures have to be composed of diverse and regional species as these support the greatest variety of species below and above ground (

). Nurse crops, which are sown together with the main crop but are not harvested, suppress unwanted weeds during the vegetation period. They remain on the field after the main crop is harvested and later serve the same purpose as catch crops.
</p>
         <p>3.1.3 Agricultural diversification</p>
         <p>
Crop rotation is the succession of different crops in consecutive years. Planting the same crop every year on the same field promotes the spread of adapted weeds, pathogens and other pests. The application of a crop rotation is therefore a method of IPM. A diverse (many different crops) and wide (long period until the crop sequence repeats) crop rotation is beneficial to soil biodiversity (

). Multicropping combines two or more different crops on the same area at the same time and provides a higher resource use efficiency (

). It enhances the diversity of crops and soil biodiversity as each crop offers a microhabitat for a specialized community of soil organisms in its rhizosphere (

). In agroforestry, annual crops are planted between perennial plants, such as trees or shrubs, which can be used for energy production. In terms of soil conservation, these systems provide disturbed and undisturbed soils on a small scale combined with a relatively diverse plant community (

). In other multi cropping systems, perennial wild flowers are used for biogas production or a mixture of grass and clover is used for cattle fodder (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
Beside measures to increase soil cover and diversification directly on the cultivated area, the context of the agricultural landscape should also be taken into account (

). Trees, shrubs and hedges as well as waysides strips offer habitats that remain undisturbed over long periods and thus can serve as refuge. Further, the deep reaching root systems of the perennial vegetation reaches deeper water reservoirs. Via hydraulic lift, part of this humidity can be accessible to soil organisms helping them to survive longer drought periods (

). As soil organisms for the most part are not very mobile, landscape elements need to be well connected and the shape and size of arable fields should be capped. Only in this way, a successful repopulation of agricultural area from perennial landscape elements can be achieved.
</p>
         <p>3.1.4 Integrated Nutrient Management (INM)</p>
         <p>
Fertilization should aim to increase soil fertility and thus allow for the cultivation of vital and robust crops (

). Accordingly, fertilizer formulations should apply individual nutrients in well balanced ratios and should not contain any contaminations. A sufficient supply with organic matter via organic fertilizers is essential to sustain an active and divers soil life and can increase soil fertility in the long term. Consequently, organic fertilizers should be the basis of all fertilization planning. In 
Germany
, organic fertilizers are not homogenously distributed as livestock production is concentrated in regional hotspots. A link between area and livestock production could dissolve these hotspots and support an even distribution of organic fertilizers, promoting circular economy and closed nutrient loops (

). Where organic fertilization via sludge or manure may not be an option, phosphor mobilizing and nitrogen fixing crops should be integral component of fertilization and crop rotation (

). Mineral fertilizers should only be used to close gaps in demand of fertilizers and secure a balanced nutrient ratio. Nutrient surpluses need to be excluded at any time to avoid eutrophication and ground- and freshwater contamination. To compensate for possible acidifying effects of nitrogen fertilizers, moderate liming can be an option to sustain the pH level of agricultural used soils.
</p>
         <p>3.1.5 Integrated Pest Management (IPM)</p>
         <p>
In the toolbox of crop protection methods, chemical products can have non-target effects and pose a threat to biodiversity and functionality of agricultural soils (

). Since 2009, the principles of IPM are implemented in European law. IPM includes all methods that are suited to control for unwanted weeds, pathogens and animals. The fundamentals of IPM consider chemical crop protection as the last option, after all other techniques, such as soil cultivation, crop rotation and biological pest control had been implemented (

). Also, IPM requires the use of damage thresholds for each application. Using these thresholds properly requires the inclusion of external costs, for example for the contamination of water and the loss of ecosystem services through non-target species. If species get affected by an unavoidable pest control method, the restoration of their population has to be ensured. This can be acquired by the provisioning of areas of refuge which are ecologically valuable and from which treated areas can be repopulated (

). Despite its significance to protect biodiversity, to this day there is no consistent application of IPM in day to day practice (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.2 Research and development
</title>
         <p>
Soil organisms are one of the least considered organism groups in research, resulting in knowledge gaps about the mode of life and population development for a large number of species (BfN 2011, BfN 2016a, BfN 2016b, BfN 2018). Thus, there is a risk that species will decline sharply or even become extinct before they and their significance for the respective ecosystem have been adequately explored. The consequences for ecosystems are unpredictable. To close the gaps in knowledge and expand research and development in the field of soil biodiversity is therefore pressing (

, 

). In addition to the further development of methodological standards for recording biodiversity and the associated ecosystem services, new methodological approaches such as metabarcoding and eDNA should be used increasingly in order to be able to characterize the undiscovered mass of soil life more comprehensively and to develop suitable 
types
of indicators (

, 

). An expansion of applied research is equally important in order to put promising approaches for the protection of soil biodiversity into practice. ‘Living labs’ could initiate collaboration between civil society, land users and science. This can promote long-term cooperation and model regions with innovative approaches, for example arable farming systems that promote soil life and agricultural technology. However, an important requirement for many research approaches is the training of a sufficient number of professionals to become species experts. An example of this is the EU call for tenders concluded in 
February 2021
for raising the taxonomic capacity in EU Member States with regard to pollinating insects as part of the preparatory implementation of the EU Pollinator Monitoring Scheme (EU-PoMS) (

). Similar initiatives for the generation of knowledge are also desirable for the protection of soil life.
</p>
         <p>
Furthermore, in agricultural training, vocational and technical schools as well as universities and technical colleges, an emphasis should be put on soil life and its great importance for soil fertility. Just as important is that farm advisory services focus more on the aspect of soil biodiversity and soil fertility. This requires targeted training and further education of appropriate advisors. So far, the general public hardly knows about life in the soil. Citizen science projects and innovative educational formats can involve the public, raise awareness and at the same time help to increase knowledge about the species in the soil (

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>The importance of soil must be placed much more strongly than before in the centre of social and technical discussions in order to be acknowledged by politicians and to generate appropriate research funding.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.3 Agricultural policies: subsidies, marked regulations
</title>
         <p>
The EU’s biodiversity strategy for 2030 intends to ensure that soil protection is also implemented within the framework of the EU’s Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) (

). The CAP is currently the most harmonized legal framework for soil protection at EU level (

). It also is the most influential and currently the financially best equipped funding instrument to protect agricultural soils. Furthermore, it is the most important funding instrument for biodiversity in the agricultural landscape. However, with regard to financial resources, measures and regulations for the protection and promotion of soil biodiversity, the contribution of the CAP has so far been marginal at best (

, 

). There is an urgent need for a paradigm shift in the CAP, which has to consistently recognize and promote environmental and nature conservation as public services. CAP instruments and measures must go beyond the merely protection of soils against material inputs and erosion. They must explicitly acknowledge the soil as a medium itself and focus on its protection accordingly (

). Consequentially, the protection and promotion of soil biodiversity in agricultural soils must become a priority under the CAP in order to preserve many ecosystem services that are also important for production. This applies equally to the first and second pillar of the current policy model of the CAP.
</p>
         <p>
The CAP regulations coming into effect in 2023 do not yet provide for any special protection for soil biodiversity. However, the development of the national CAP strategic plan provides leeway in the selection of more detailed options. This opportunity must be used to achieve the environmental goals set by the new CAP regulation itself and by the European Green Deal and its strategies (

, 

). Thus, regarding the conditionality of the first pillar, standards for ‘Good Agricultural and Ecological Condition’ (GAEC) with special consideration of soil life must be a prerequisite for all farms that receive direct payments. The maintenance of permanent grassland at a high level should be ensured by GAEC standards, also outside of Natura 2000 areas and the plowing of grassland for purely administrative reasons has to be prevented. Furthermore, the restoration and new establishment of melioration measures on organic soils must be prohibited. To maintain the soil structure, further standards need to aim at an effective erosion protection. To benefit soil organisms even more, a year-round surface cover, e.g. via cover crops, as well as effective crop rotations have to be ensured. Crop rotations should include at least five different 
types
of crops. Finally, it is necessary to establish non-productive areas on at least 10 % of all agricultural land as habitats for organisms above and below ground.
</p>
         <p>
Concerning the new eco-schemes of the first pillar of the CAP, farmers must be offered ecologically effective and financially attractive measures. They have to be beneficial for the biological diversity in soils on arable land and grasslands. To achieve this, measures can promote an expansion of the proportion of non-productive areas beyond the GAEC requirements, including hedges and field trees, or the creation of preferably perennial areas or strip elements (e.g. flower strips and fallows) on arable land and grassland, with reduced or no use of fertilizer and no chemical pesticides. Perennial elements are likely to have a particularly high ecological value due to the pause of tillage and thus should be preferred (

, 

). Moreover, Eco-Schemes should be used to promote organic agriculture.
</p>
         <p>Agri-environmental and climate measures (AECM) of the second pillar which specifically aim at promoting soil life must be developed and integrated into the funding programs. If possible, they should be co-financed through national funding guidelines in order to enable nationwide implementation. Appropriate measures can also create synergies for climate protection by increasing the soil’s binding capacity of the climate gas carbon dioxide.</p>
         <p>In line with the cross-sectional goal of the new CAP to ‘promote knowledge, innovation and digitization in agriculture’, the second pillar of the CAP should provide funding for farm advisory services that consider the protection of soil as a habitat for a large number of organisms. Also, investment programs for an enhanced knowledge and acquisition of conservational tillage technology on farms should be implemented.</p>
         <p>
In addition to immediate support for farmers, applied research in soil biodiversity must be expanded and appropriately financed (

). The existing knowledge gaps on species living in the soil and their functions in the ecosystem have to be closed (

), for example by using the ‘living labs’ approach as a cooperation between science and civil society.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Conclusion and Outlook
</title>
         <p>Agriculture and soil biodiversity are highly interdependent.Soil organisms provide essential ecosystem services, including increased soil fertility. Appropriate agricultural management is well suited to promote an active and diverse soil life and the related ecosystem services. The conservation and the sustainable use of soil biodiversity have to be a prerequisite for a transformation to sustainable and climate resilient farming systems of the future.Accordingly, the promotion of an active and diverse soil life should be understood as a common goal, both for agriculture and nature conservation. This is a mission for all of society and cannot be borne by farmers alone. They depend on subsidies for farming practices which clearly promote soil biodiversity. Also, consumers should support the transition to a more sustainable agriculture by favouring appropriate agricultural products. On an international level, CBD COP15 has the chance to adopt an action plan for the conservation and the sustainable use of soil biodiversity and encourage national governments to increase their soil life related legislations. On European level, an ambitious implementation of the EU’s Farm to Fork - and Biodiversity Strategy supported by the CAP regulations inter alia can serve the same purpose. On the German national level, the national implementation within the strategic plan of the CAP offers the opportunity to support farmers in their efforts for a more sustainable and soil life promoting cultivation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>We thank Ursula Nigmann, Sandra Balzer, Detlev Metzing, Daniel Wolf and Oliver Hendrischke as well as the anonymous reviewer for providing their valuable comments and expertise improving the quality of this manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
6. References
</title>
         <p>
Albrecht, M.
, 
D. Kleijn
, 
N. M. Williams
, 
M. Tschumi
, 
B. R. Blaauw
, 
R. Bommarco
, 
A. J. Campbell
, 
M. Dainese
, 
F. A. Drummond
, 
M. H. Entlinget
al. (
2020
): 
The effectiveness of flower strips and hedgerows on pest control, pollination services and crop yield: a quantitative synthesis
. – 
Ecology letters
23

(
10
): 
1488–1498
.

</p>
         <p>
Amossé, C.
, 
M.-H. Jeuffroy
, 
F. Celette
&amp; 
C. David
(
2013
): 
Relay-intercropped forage legumes help to control weeds in organic grain production
. – 
European Journal of Agronomy
49

: 
158–167
.

</p>
         <p>
Barrios, E.
(
2007
): 
Soil biota, ecosystem services and land productivity
. – 
Ecological Economics
64

(
2
): 
269–285
.

</p>
         <p>
Beaumelle, L.
, 
L.Thouvenot
, 
J. Hines
, 
M. Jochum
, 
N. Eisenhauer
&amp; 
H. R. P. Phillips
(
2021
): 
Soil fauna diversity and chemical stressors: a review of knowledge gaps and roadmap for future research
. – 
Ecography
.

</p>
         <p>
Bender, S. F.
, 
C. Wagg
&amp; 
M. G. A. van der Heijden
(
2016
): 
An Underground Revolution: Biodiversity and Soil Ecological Engineering for Agricultural Sustainability
. – 
Trends in ecology &amp; evolution
31

(
6
): 
440–452
.

</p>
         <p>

BfN (
2011
): 
Rote Liste gefährdeter Tiere, Pflanzen und Pilze Deutschlands
- 
Wirbellose Tiere (Teil 1)
, Vol. 
70
, 
3
. – Bundesamt für Naturschutz, Bonn-Bad Godesberg.

</p>
         <p>

BfN (
2016
a): 
Rote Liste
gefährdeter Tiere, Pflanzen und Pilze Deutschlands - 
Grosspilze, Vol. 70
: 
440 pp.
</p>
         <p>

BfN (
2016
b): 
Rote Liste gefährdeter Tiere, Pflanzen und Pilze Deutschlands
- 
Wirbellose Tiere (Teil 2)
, Vol. 
70
, 
4
. – Bundesamt für Naturschutz; BfN-Schriftenvertrieb Leserservice im Landwirtschaftsverlag GmbH, Bonn-Bad Godesberg, Münster.

</p>
         <p>
BfN
(
2017
): 
BfN Agrar-Report
. 
Biologische Vilefalt in der Agrarlandschaft Vol
. 1.

</p>
         <p>

BfN (
2018
): 
Rote Liste
gefährdeter Tiere, Pflanzen und Pilze Deutschlands - Pflanzen, Band 70,7. – Bundesamt für Naturschutz, 
Bonn-Bad Godesberg
.

</p>
         <p>
BMU
(
2019
): 
Aktionsprogramm Insektenschutz
. 
Gemeinsam wirksam gegen das Insektensterben
.

</p>
         <p>
Bonilla, I.
&amp; 
L. Bolaños
(
2009
): 
Mineral Nutrition for Legume- Rhizobia Symbiosis: B, Ca, N, P, S, K, Fe, Mo, Co, and Ni: A Review
. – In: 
Lichtfouse, E.
(ed): 
Organic Farming, Pest Control and Remediation of Soil Pollutants. Organic farming, pest control and remediation of soil pollutants
. – 
Springer Netherlands, Dordrecht
: 
253–274
.

</p>
         <p>
Boutin, C.
, 
K. L. Aya
, 
D. Carpenter
, 
P. J. Thomas
&amp; 
O. Rowland
(
2012
): 
Phytotoxicity testing for herbicide regulation: shortcomings in relation to biodiversity and ecosystem services in agrarian systems
. – 
Science of The Total Environment
415

: 
79–92
.

</p>
         <p>
Briones, M. J. I.
&amp; 
O. Schmidt
(
2017
): 
Conventional tillage decreases the abundance and biomass of earthworms and alters their community structure in a global meta-analysis
. – 
Global change biology
23

(
10
): 
4396–4419
.

</p>
         <p>
CBD Executive Secretary
(
2020
): 
CBD SBSTTA 24, Item 7, Biodiversity and Agriculture
. 
Review of the international initiative for the conservation and sustainable use of soil biodiversity and updated plan of action
.

</p>
         <p>
Chauhan, B. S.
, 
G. S. Gill
&amp; 
C. Preston
(
2006
): 
Tillage system effects on weed ecology, herbicide activity and persistence: a review
. – 
Australian Journal of Experimental Agriculture
46

(
12
): 
1557–1570
.

</p>
         <p>
Collette, L.
(
2011
): 
Save and grow. A policymaker’s guide to the sustainable intensification of smallholder crop production
. – 
FAO, Rome
: 
102 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Corsi, S.
(
2019
): 
Conservation Agriculture
. 
Training guide for extension agents and farmers in Eastern Europe and Central Asia
.

</p>
         <p>
Courvoisier, T. J.
(
2018
): 
Opportunities for soil sustainability in Europe, Vol. 36
. – 
EASAC Secretariat Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher Leopoldina, Halle (Saale)
: 
41 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Destatis
(
2019
): 
Teures Acker- und Weideland: Kaufwerte für Agrarland erhöhen sich seit 2009 auf das 2,3-Fache
. – 
Wiesbaden
.

</p>
         <p>
Díaz, S.
, 
J. Settele
&amp; 
E. Brondízio
(
2019
): 
Summary for policymakers of the global assessment report on biodiversity and ecosystem services of the Intergovernmental Science- Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services
. 
ADVANCE UNEDITED VERSION
.

</p>
         <p>
Dybzinski, R.
, 
J. E. Fargione
, 
D. R. Zak
, 
D. Fornara
&amp; 
D. Tilman
(
2008
): 
Soil fertility increases with plant species diversity in a long-term biodiversity experiment
. – 
Oecologia
158

(
1
): 
85–93
.

</p>
         <p>

EASAC &amp; Leopoldina (

April 
2015

): 
Ecosystem services, agriculture and neonicotinoids, Vol. 26
. – 
EASAC Secretariat Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher Leopoldina
, 
Halle (Saale)
: 
53 pp.
</p>
         <p>
EC
(
2020
a): 
EU Biodiversity Strategy
for 2030. 
Bringing nature back into our lives
.

</p>
         <p>
EC
(
2020
b): 
Farm to Fork Strategy
. 
For a fair, healthy and Environmentally-friendly food system
.

</p>
         <p>
ECA
(
2020
): 
Sustainable use of plant protection products: limited progress in measuring and reducing risks
.

</p>
         <p>
FAO
(
2014
): 
The international code of conduct on pesticide management. IOMC
, 
The Inter-Organization Programme For The Sound Management of Chemicals
, [
4
. version]. – Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, Rome: VIII, 
37
S.

</p>
         <p>
FAO
(
2017
): 
Voluntary guidelines for sustainable soil management
. 
Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations
.

</p>
         <p>
FAO
(
2020
): 
State of knowledge of soil biodiversity. Status, challenges and potentialities: report 2020
. – 
FAO, Rome, Italy
: 
585 pp.
</p>
         <p>
FAO &amp; ITPS
(
2017
): 
Global
assessment of the impact of plant protection products on soil functions and soil ecosystem
.

</p>
         <p>
Finck, P.
, 
S. Heinze
, 
U. Raths
&amp; 
Riecken, U.
&amp; 
Ssymank,A.
(eds) (
2017
): 
Rote Liste der gefährdeten Biotoptypen Deutschlands
. 
Dritte fortgeschriebene Fassung 2017, Vol. 156
: 
637 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Gabor, V., A.
Timus, C.
Mariam, A.
Gayane, T.
Vardan, H.
Zsuzsanna, V.
Andrea
&amp; 
N. Avetik

(
2017
): 
Integrated pest management. of major pests and diseases in eastern Europe and the Caucasus
.

</p>
         <p>
Gabriel, J. L.
, 
A. Garrido
&amp; 
M. Quemada
(
2013
): 
Cover crops effect on farm benefits and nitrate leaching: Linking economic and environmental analysis
. – 
Agricultural Systems
121

: 
23– 32
.

</p>
         <p>
Ganser, D.
, 
E. Knop
&amp; 
M. Albrecht
(
2019
): 
Sown wildflower strips as overwintering habitat for arthropods: Effective measure or ecological trap? – Agriculture
, 
Ecosystems &amp; Environment
275

: 
123–131
.

</p>
         <p>
Gardi, C.
, 
L. Montanarella
, 
D.Arrouays
, 
A. Bispo
, 
P. Lemanceau
, 
C. Jolivet
, 
C. Mulder
, 
L. Ranjard
, 
J. Römbke
, 
M. Rutgers
&amp; 
C. Menta
(
2009
): 
Soil biodiversity monitoring in Europe: ongoing activities and challenges
. – 
European Journal of Soil Science
60

(
5
): 
807–819
.

</p>
         <p>
GFG
(
2016
): 
Deutsche Nachhaltigkeitsstrategie
. 
Kabinettbeschluss vom
11. Januar 2017
.

</p>
         <p>
Giller, K. E.
, M. H. 
Beare, P.
Lavelle, A.-M.
Izac &amp; M. J. SWIFT (
1997
): 
Agricultural intensification, soil biodiversity and agroecosystem function
. – 
Applied Soil Ecology
6

(
1
): 
3–16
.

</p>
         <p>
Gryndler,M.
, 
J. Larsen
, 
H. Hršelová
, 
V.Řezáčová
, 
H. Gryndlerová
&amp; 
J. Kubát
(
2006
): 
Organic and mineral fertilization, respectively, increase and decrease the development of external mycelium of arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi in a long-term field experiment
. – 
Mycorrhiza
16

(
3
): 
159–166
.

</p>
         <p>
Guerra, C. A.
, 
A. Heintz-Buschart
, 
J. Sikorski
, 
A. Chatzinotas
, 
N. Guerrero-Ramírez
, 
S. Cesarz
, 
L. Beaumelle
, 
M. C. Rillig
, 
F. T. Maestre
, 
M. Delgado-Baquerizo
, 
F. Buscot
, 
J. Overmann
, 
G. Patoine
, 
H. R. P. Phillips
, 
M. Winter
, 
T. Wubet
, 
K. Küsel
, 
R. D. Bardgett
, 
E. K. Cameron
, 
D. Cowan
, 
T. Grebenc
, 
C. Marín
, 
A. Orgiazzi
, 
B. K. Singh
, 
D. H. Wall
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2020
): 
Blind spots in global soil biodiversity and ecosystem function research
. – 
Nature communications
11

(
1
): 
3870
.

</p>
         <p>
Gullberg, E.
, 
S. Cao
, 
O. G. Berg
, 
C. Ilbäck
, 
L. Sandegren
, 
D. Hughes
&amp; 
D. I. Andersson
(
2011
): 
Selection of resistant bacteria at very low antibiotic concentrations
. – 
PLoS pathogens
7

(
7
): e 
1002158
.

</p>
         <p>
Hansen, S.
&amp; 
F. Engelstad
(
1999
): 
Earthworm populations in a cool and wet district as affected by tractor traffic and fertilisation
. – 
Applied Soil Ecology
13

(
3
): 
237–250
.

</p>
         <p>
Horton, J. L.
&amp; 
S. C. Hart
(
1998
): 
Hydraulic lift: a potentially important ecosystem process
. – 
Trends in ecology &amp; evolution
13

(
6
): 
232–235
.

</p>
         <p>
IASS, BUND
&amp; 
Le Monde
diplomatique (
2015
): 
Soil Atlas. Daten und Fakten über Acker
, 
Land und Erde
.

</p>
         <p>
Kassam, A.
, 
T. Friedrich
, 
F. Shaxson
&amp; 
J. Pretty
(
2009
): 
The spread of Conservation Agriculture: justification, sustainability and uptake
. – 
International Journal of Agricultural Sustainability
7

(
4
): 
292–320
.

</p>
         <p>
KBU
(
2013
): 
12 notwendige Schritte auf dem Weg zum Schutz fruchtbarer Böden und zur Reduzierung des Flächenverbrauchs. Ergebnisse der KBU-Veranstaltung
„ 
Wie viel Boden brauchen wir
?“.

</p>
         <p>
KBU
(
2020
): 
Boden und Biodiversität
. 
Forderungen an die Politik
.

</p>
         <p>
Kladivko, E. J.
(
2001
): 
Tillage systems and soil ecology
. – 
Soil and Tillage Research
61

(1- 
2
): 
61–76
.

</p>
         <p>
Kremer, R. J.
(
2018
): 
Pesticide use and biodiversity in soils
. – In: 
Reicosky, D.
(ed): 
Managing soil health for sustainable agriculture
Volume 2. – 
Burleigh Dodds Science Publishing
: 
247–263
.

</p>
         <p>
Laschewski, L.
&amp; 
A. Tietz
(
2020
): 
Auswirkungen überregional aktiver Investoren in der Landwirtschaft auf ländliche Räume. Ergebnisse aus zwei Fallstudien
. – 
Thünen Report
Vol. 
80
.

</p>
         <p>
Mathews, J.
, 
F. Glante
, 
M. Berger
, 
G. Broll
, 
U. Eser
, A. Faensen- Thiebes, 
N. Feldwisch
, 
W. König
, 
N. Patzel
, 
R. Sommer
&amp; 
W. E. R. Xylander
(
2020
): 
Soil and biodiversity – Demands on politics
. – 
Soil Organisms
92

(
2
): 
95–98
.

</p>
         <p>
Meyer, S.
, 
E. Bergmeier
, 
T. Becker
, 
K. Wesche
, 
B. Krause
&amp; 
C. Leuschner
(
2015
): 
Detecting long-term losses at the plant community level - arable fields in Germany revisited
. – 
Applied Vegetation Science
18

(
3
): 
432–442
.

</p>
         <p>
Nabel, M.
, 
S. D. Schrey
, 
H. Poorter
, 
R. Koller
&amp; 
N. D. Jablonowski
(
2017
): 
Effects of digestate fertilization on Sida hermaphrodita: Boosting biomass yields on marginal soils by increasing soil fertility
. – 
Biomass and Bioenergy
107

: 
207–213
.

</p>
         <p>
Nabel, M.
, 
C. Selig
, 
R. Grunewald
&amp; 
G. Stolpe
(
2018
): 
11 Punkte für einen gemeinsamen Weg zu mehr Biodiversität im Ackerbau. Ergebnisse der interdisziplinären Tagung „Naturschutz und Landwirtschaft im Dialog
– 
Biodiversität im Ackerbau
“.

</p>
         <p>
Nabel, M.
, 
S. Selig
, 
J. Gundlach
, H. v.d. Decken, 
M. Klein
&amp; 
B. Jessel
(
2021
): 
BfN Bodenreport. Vielfältiges Bodenleben
- 
Grundlage für Naturschutz und nachhaltige Landwirtschaft
.

</p>
         <p>
Orgiazzi, A.
, 
R. D. Bardgett
&amp; 
E. Barrios
(eds) (
2016
): 
Global soil biodiversity atlas. Supporting the
EU Biodiversity Strategy
and the Global Soil Biodiversity Initiative: preserving soil organism through sustainable land management practices and environmental policies for the protection and enhancement of ecosystem services. 
Global soil biodiversity initiative
: 
11176 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Osterburg, B.
(
1996
): 
Schutz landwirtschaftlicher Böden vor Überdüngung
. – In: 
Blume, H.-P.
, 
P. Felix-Henningsen
, 
H.-G. Frede
, 
G. Guggenberger
, 
R. Horn
, 
K. Stahr
&amp; 
W. R. Fischer
(eds): 
Handbuch der Bodenkunde
. – 
Wiley-VCH; Ecomed anfangs, Weinheim, Landsberg
: 
1–28
.

</p>
         <p>
Pe’er, G.
, 
A. Bonn
, 
H. Bruelheide
, 
P. Dieker
, 
N. Eisenhauer
, 
P. H. Feindt
, 
G. Hagedorn
, 
B. Hansjürgens
, 
I. Herzon
, 
Â. Lomba
, 
E. Marquard
&amp; et al. (
2020
): 
Action needed for the EU Common Agricultural Policy to address sustainability challenges
. – 
People and nature (Hoboken, N.J.)
2

(
2
): 
305– 316
.

</p>
         <p>
Pe’er, G.
, 
Y. Zinngrebe
, 
F. Moreira
, 
C. Sirami
, 
S. Schindler
, 
R. Müller
, 
V. Bontzorlos
, 
D. Clough
, 
P. Bezák
, 
A. Bonn
, 
B. Hansjürgens
, 
A. Lomba
, 
S. Möckel
, 
G. Passoni
, 
C. Schleyer
, 
J. Schmidt
&amp; 
S. Lakner
(
2019
): 
A greener path for the EU Common Agricultural Policy
. – 
Science (New York, N.Y.)
365

(
6452
): 
449–451
.

</p>
         <p>
Pettibone, L.
, 
B. Blättel-Mink
, 
B. Balázs
, 
A. Di Giulio
, 
C. Göbel
, 
K. Heubach
, 
D. Hummel
, 
J. Lundershausen
, 
A. Lux
&amp; 
T. Potthast
(
2018
): 
Transdisciplinary sustainability research and citizen science: Options for mutual learning
. – 
GAIA- Ecological Perspectives for Science and Society
27

(
2
): 
222–225
.

</p>
         <p>
Phillips, H. R. P.
, 
E. K. Cameron
, 
O. Ferlian
, 
M. Türke
, 
M. Winter
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2017
): 
Red list of a black box
. – 
Nature ecology &amp; evolution
1

(
4
): 
1
.

</p>
         <p>
Pimentel, D.
&amp; 
N. Kounang
(
1998
): 
Ecology of Soil Erosion in Ecosystems
. – 
Ecosystems
1

(
5
): 
416–426
.

</p>
         <p>
Pisa, L.
, 
D. Goulson
, 
E.-C. Yang
, 
D. Gibbons
, 
F. Sánchez-Bayo
, 
E. Mitchell
, 
A. Aebi
, 
J. van der Sluijs
, 
C. J. K. MacQuarrie
, 
C. Giorio
&amp; et al. (
2017
): 
An update of the Worldwide Integrated Assessment (WIA) on systemic insecticides. Part 2: impacts on organisms and ecosystems
. – 
Environmental science and pollution research international
.

</p>
         <p>
Potts, S. G.
, 
J. Dauber
, 
A. Hochkirch
, 
B. Oteman
, 
D. B. Roy
, 
K. Ahrné
, 
K. Biesmeijer
, 
T. D. Breeze
, 
C. Carvell
, 
C. Ferreira
, 
Ú. FitzPatrick
, 
N. Isaac
, 
M. Kuussaari
, 
T. Ljubomirov
, 
J. Maes
, 
H. Ngo
, 
A. Pardo
, 
C. Polce
, 
M. Quaranta
, 
J. Settele
, 
M. Sorg
, 
C. Stefanescu
&amp; 
A. Vujic
(
2021
): 
Proposal for an EU Pollinator Monitoring Scheme
. – 
EUR 30416 EN
.

</p>
         <p>
Puglisi, E.
(
2012
): 
Response of microbial organisms (aquatic and terrestrial) to pesticides
.– 
EFSA Supporting Publications
9

(
11
): 
62
.

</p>
         <p>
Rigueiro-Rodríguez, A.
, 
E. Fernández-Núñez
, P. González- Hernández, 
J. H. McAdam
&amp; 
M. R. Mosquera-Losada
(
2009
): 
Agroforestry Systems in Europe: Productive, Ecological and Social Perspectives
. – In: 
Rigueiro Rodríguez, A.
, 
J. H. McAdam
&amp; 
M. R. Mosquera-Losada
(eds): 
Agroforestry in Europe. Current status and future prospects
. – 
Springer, Dordrecht
: 
43–65
.

</p>
         <p>
Rillig, M. C.
, 
A. Lehmann
, 
J. Lehmann
, 
T. Camenzind
&amp; 
C. Rauh
(
2018
): 
Soil Biodiversity Effects from Field to Fork
. – 
Trends in plant science
23

(
1
): 
17–24
.

</p>
         <p>
Ringselle, B.
, 
G. Bergkvist
, 
H. Aronsson
&amp; 
L. Andersson
(
2015
): 
Under-sown cover crops and post-harvest mowing as measures to control Elymus repens
. – 
Weed Research
55

(
3
): 
309–319
.

</p>
         <p>
Schneider, C.
&amp; 
L. Köder
(
2019
): 
Bodenschutz in der Gemeinsamen Agrarpolitik der EU (GAP) Jg
.24.

</p>
         <p>
Schoof, N.
, 
R. Luick
, 
A. Ackermann
, 
S. Baum
, 
H. Böhmer
, 
N. Röder
, 
S.Rudolph
, 
T.Schmidt
, 
Hötker,Hermann
&amp; 
H.Jeromin
(
2019
): 
Auswirkungen der neuen Rahmenbedingungen der Gemeinsamen Agrarpoilitik auf die Grünland-bezogene Biodiversität
. 
BfN-Skript
540
.

</p>
         <p>
Schweppe-Kraft, B.
, 
K. Schlegelmilch
&amp; 
L. Berger
(
2019
): 
Subventionsbericht 2019. Abbau naturschädigender Subventionen und Kompensationszahlungen auf stoffliche Belastungen. Ökonomische Instrumente zum Schutz der biologischen Vielfalt
. 
BfN-Positionspapier
.

</p>
         <p>
Sengupta, A.
&amp; 
W. A. Dick
(
2015
): 
Bacterial community diversity in soil under two tillage practices as determined by pyrosequencing
. – 
Microbial ecology
70

(
3
): 
853–859
.

</p>
         <p>
Souza Machado, A. A. de
, 
W. Kloas
, 
C. Zarfl
, 
S. Hempel
&amp; 
M. C. Rillig
(
2018
): 
Microplastics as an emerging threat to terrestrial ecosystems
. – 
Global change biology
24

(
4
): 
1405–1416
.

</p>
         <p>
Sparling, D. W.
&amp; 
G. Fellers
(
2007
): 
Comparative toxicity of chlorpyrifos, diazinon, malathion and their oxon derivatives to larval Rana boylii
. – 
Environmental pollution (Barking, Essex: 1987)
147

(
3
): 
535–539
.

</p>
         <p>
Tiemann, L. K.
, 
A. S. Grandy
, 
E. E. Atkinson
, E. Marin- Spiotta &amp; 
M. D. McDaniel
(
2015
): 
Crop rotational diversity enhances belowground communities and functions in an agroecosystem
. – 
Ecology letters
18

(
8
): 
761–771
.

</p>
         <p>
Tsiafouli, M. A.
, 
E. Thébault
, 
S. P. Sgardelis
, 
P. C. de Ruiter
, 
W. H. van der Putten
, 
K. Birkhofer
, 
L. Hemerik
, 
F. T. de Vries
, 
R. D. Bardgett
, 
M. V. Brady
&amp; et al. (
2015
): 
Intensive agriculture reduces soil biodiversity across Europe
. – 
Global change biology
21

(
2
): 
973–985
.

</p>
         <p>
UBA
(
2015
): 
Bodenzustand in Deutschland
. 
Zum „internationalen Jahr des Bodens
“.

</p>
         <p>
van Eekeren, N.
, 
D. van Liere
, 
F. de Vries
, 
M. Rutgers
, 
R. de Goede
&amp; 
L. Brussaard
(
2009
): 
A mixture of grass and clover combines the positive effects of both plant species on selected soil biota
. – 
Applied Soil Ecology
42

(
3
): 
254–263
.

</p>
         <p>
Wardle, D. A.
, 
R. D. Bardgett
, 
J. N. Klironomos
, 
H. Setälä
, 
W. H. van der Putten
&amp; 
D. H. Wall
(
2004
): 
Ecological linkages between aboveground and belowground biota
. – 
Science (New York, N.Y.)
304

(
5677
): 
1629–1633
.

</p>
         <p>
WBB
(
2002
): 
Ohne Boden bodenlos
. 
Eine Denkschrift zum Boden-Bewusstsein
.

</p>
         <p>
Wezel, A.
, 
M. Casagrande
, 
F. Celette
, 
J.-F. Vian
, 
A. Ferrer
&amp; 
J. Peigné
(
2014
): 
Agroecological practices for sustainable agriculture. A review
. – 
Agronomy for Sustainable Development
34

(
1
): 
1–20
.

</p>
         <p>
Xylander, W. E. R.
(
2020
): 
Society´ s awareness for protection of soils, its biodiversity and function in 2030–We need a more intrinsic approach
. – 
Soil Organisms
92

(
3
): 
203–212
.

</p>
         <p>
Xylander, W. E. R.
&amp; 
H. Zumkowski-Xylander
(
2018
): 
Increasing awareness for soil biodiversity and protection: The international touring exhibition ‘The Thin Skin of the Earth’
. – 
Soil Organisms
90

(
2
): 
79–94
.

</p>
         <p>
Yin, R.
, 
J. Siebert
, 
N. Eisenhauer
&amp; 
M. Schädler
(
2020
): 
Climate change and intensive land use reduce soil animal biomass via dissimilar pathways
. – 
eLife
9

.

</p>
         <p>
Zaller, J. G.
, 
F. Heigl
, 
L. Ruess
&amp; 
A. Grabmaier
(
2014
): 
Glyphosate herbicide affects belowground interactions between earthworms and symbiotic mycorrhizal fungi in a model ecosystem
. – 
Scientific reports
4

(
1
): 
1–8
.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
