<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Soil Organisms</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25674/so91200</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>SOIL ORGANISMS - an international open access journal on the taxonomic and functional biodiversity in the soil</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group/>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
SOIL ORGANISMS – an international open access journal on the taxonomic and functional biodiversity in the soil
</p>
         <p>
Nico Eisenhauer
1,2,
* &amp; 
Willi E.R. Xylander
3,4,
*

</p>
         <p>
1
GerMan Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research (iDiv) Halle-Jena-Leipzig, DeUtscher Platz 5e, 04103 Leipzig, 
GerMany
</p>
         <p>
2

InstitUte of Biology, Leipzig University, DeUtscher Platz 5e, 04103 Leipzig, 
GerMany
</p>
         <p>
3

Senckenberg MUseUM of NatUral History Görlitz, Postfach 300 154, 02806 Görlitz, 
GerMany
</p>
         <p>
4

Internationales HochschUlinstitUt ZittaU, TU Dresden, Markt 23, 02763 ZittaU, 
GerMany
</p>
         <p>* Corresponding aUthors: nico.eisenhaUer@idiv.de; willi.xylander@senckenberg.de</p>
         <p>
DOI 
10.25674/so91200
</p>
         <p>
Biodiversity change
and
</p>
         <p>the identification of the</p>
         <p>underlying drivers are in</p>
         <p>the focus of ecological</p>
         <p>research and public and</p>
         <p>political debate (IPBES</p>
         <p>2019). Soil biodiversity</p>
         <p>has thus far rarely entered</p>
         <p>this discussion and</p>
         <p>
analyses (

</p>
         <p>2018), and substantial</p>
         <p>gaps in soil biodiversity</p>
         <p>and function data exist</p>
         <p>
(

).
</p>
         <p>Furthermore, we know</p>
         <p>exceptionally little about</p>
         <p>temporal changes in soil</p>
         <p>
biodiversity (

</p>
         <p>
2017), although soil biodiversity is thought to be essential for critical ecosystem functions and services (

, Wall et al. 2015) but threatened by anthropogenic impacts (

). At the same time, taxonomic expertise of soil biodiversity may be at risk, while novel molecular information still needs to be linked to species and functions (

). At this time of major changes in earth’s biodiversity (e. g. 

, 

, Ceballos et al. 2016, 

, IPBES 2019), and repeated calls to assess soil biological responses to anthropogenic environmental change (e. g., 

, 

), we believe that an 
open access
journal on taxonomy and functional biodiversity in the soil is particularly relevant to address some of the major knowledge gaps that limit management and political decisions (

). Notably, in order to
</p>
         <p>provide an independent</p>
         <p>picture of the drivers</p>
         <p>and consequences of soil</p>
         <p>biodiversity, publication</p>
         <p>decisions have to be based</p>
         <p>
on the 
scientific soundness
</p>
         <p>of the work, rather than</p>
         <p>by potential impact and</p>
         <p>significance of effects. At</p>
         <p>SOIL ORGANISMS, we</p>
         <p>thus encourage submission</p>
         <p>of well-designed studies</p>
         <p>with neutral/non-significant</p>
         <p>
effects to 
combat
</p>
         <p>
the publication bias
.
</p>
         <p>Subsequent syntheses and</p>
         <p>meta-analyses can only be</p>
         <p>as good as the quality of</p>
         <p>
the data they are based on. As open access journals often have publication charges, this might select against publication of work from regions of the world with lower levels of research funds; very often, these are the areas of the globe where our information on (soil) biodiversity is particularly low (

). This is why SOIL ORGANISMS is proud to offer open access publication of scientifically sound work 
without any charges for publication and download
. Soil biodiversity research needs to 
integrate expertise
from a broad range of scientists from biogeographical, taxonomic, innovative methodological and experimental approaches to modern morphometric, molecular, modelbased, and statistical tools as well as the complete variety of organisms from soil macro-, meso-, and microfauna to fungi, algae, and bacteria. We note the loss of taxonomic expertise (e. g. 

, 

</p>
         <p>
2011, 

), which is particularly alarming in a field of research where &lt;10 % of the species have been described (Phillipsetal.2017).Thus, SOIL ORGANISMS wants to provide a forum where organismic researchers in the widest sense can publish their research and gain scientific visibility as well as response from their specific community and beyond.
</p>
         <p>
At SOIL ORGANISMS, we follow and foster the principles of 
open science:
our papers are open access, we encourage the authors to make their data and statistical code publicly available, and recommend the publication of digital supplementary material, for which we provide specific DOIs for, e. g., relevant raw data, photos or videos, distribution maps, and omics data. Thus, valuable research data are accessible to the scientific community to initiate further exchange and use in research, teaching, and application.
</p>
         <p>
Future paper formats:
The majority (and normal format) of publications in SOIL ORGANISMS is the “ResearchArticle”, which is reviewed by two international peers. As in the past, we are, furthermore, planning to publish “Invited Reviews” which reflect a broader field and is summarized by an international expert (e. g. 

). As new formats, we plan “Editors’ Highlights” and “Invited Comments”, which consider most recent, important trends in organismic soil biology, taxonomy, and ecology, but also e. g. focusing or commenting on conservational legislation or funding politics. Also identification keys on larger taxa of soil fauna may to be submitted and published either within the journal or as supplements (e. g. 

, 

, 

). Finally, special issues on focal topics will allow to comprehensively cover certain topics of particular relevance.
</p>
         <p>
Our 
international and diverse editorial board
has been enriched within the last months to draw contributions from regions across the globe, comprehending a wide range of taxa, various scientific fields and approaches and from all status groups. We aim to offer a 
rapid and constructive review process
with clear editorial recommendations to help the authors to not be stuck with multiple contradictory reviews and/or uncertainty which are the most critical issues to address in a revision. To limit any kind of discrimination, we offer a 
double-blind reviewing process
. To 
reduce formatting burdens
, we only request the authors to format their manuscript according to the journal’s guidelines after accepting the manuscript. Nevertheless, some basic rules on paper formatting (common structure of scientific papers) should be followed.
</p>
         <p>
Perspective
: Within the next 10 years, our goal is that SOIL ORGANISMS will become an internationally wellestablished and recognized scientific outlet that serves
</p>
         <p>The Editors-in-Chief of SOIL ORGANISMS: Prof. Dr. Willi Xylander (Görlitz) and Prof. Dr. Nico Eisenhauer (Leipzig).</p>
         <p>
as a worldwide forum for soil organismic and functional biodiversity researchers by integrating soil microbiology, soil zoology, and soil science. Moreover, given its strong history in soil organismic research, we hope that the journal will be considered as a repository for essential soil biological knowledge. We strongly believe that our approach to 
fair open access publishing
will serve as a role model, not only for soil ecology but for scientific publishing in general.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>Nico Eisenhauer acknowledges support by the German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research Halle–Jena–Leipzig, funded by the German Research Foundation (FZT 118) and funding by the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no. 677232).</p>
         <p>Willi Xylander would like to thank his colleagues from the Department of Soil Zoology of SMNG for comments on earlier versions of the manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bardgett, R. D.
&amp; 
van der Putten, W. H.
Belowground biodiversity and ecosystem functioning
. – 
Nature

515

: 
505–511
(
2014
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bingemer, J.
&amp; 
K. Hohberg
(
2017
): 
An illustrated identification key to the eutardigrade species (Tardigrada, Eutardigrada) presently known from European soils
. – 
Soil Organisms

89

(
3
): 
127–149
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cameron, E. K.
, 
I. S. Martins
, 
P. Lavelle
, 
J. Mathieu
, 
L. Tedersoo
, 
M. Bahram
&amp; 
J. Siebert
(
2019
): 
Global mismatches in aboveground and belowground biodiversity
. – 
Conservation Biology
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cameron, E. K.
, 
I. S. Martins
, 
P. Lavelle
, 
J. Mathieu
, 
L. Tedersoo
, 
F. Gottschall
&amp; 
M. Winter
(
2018
): 
Global gaps in soil biodiversity data
. – 
Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution

2

(
7
): 
1042
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ceballos, G.
, 
P. R. Ehrlich
, 
A. D. Barnosky
, 
A. García
, 
R. M. Pringle
&amp; 
T. M. Palmer
(
2015
): 
Accelerated modern human–induced species losses: Entering the sixth mass extinction
. 
Science Advances

1

(
5
): e 
1400253
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Díaz, S.
, 
J. Settele
&amp; 
E. Brondízio
(
2019
): 
Summary for policymakers of the global assessment report on biodiversity and ecosystem services of the Intergovernmental Science-Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services
. – 
Intergovernmental Science-Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services (IPBES)
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dornelas, M.
, 
N. J. Gotelli
, 
B. McGill
, 
H. Shimadzu
, 
F. Moyes
, 
C. Sievers
&amp; 
A. E. Magurran
(
2014
): 
Assemblage time series reveal biodiversity change but not systematic loss
. – 
Science

344

(
6181
): 
296–299
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
A. A. Bonn
&amp; 
C. Guerra
(
2019
): 
Recognizing the quiet extinction of invertebrates
.– 
Nature Communications

10

: 
50
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Geiger, M. F.
, 
J. J. Astrin
, 
T. Borsch
, 
U. Burkhardt
, 
P. Grobe
, 
R. Hand
, 
A. Hausmann
, 
K. Hohberg
, 
L. Krogmann
, 
M. Lutz
, 
C. Monje
, 
B. Misof
, 
J. Morinière
, 
K. Müller
, 
S. Pietsch
, 
D. Quandt
, 
B. Rulik
, 
M. Scholler
, 
W.Traunspurger
, 
G. Haszprunar
&amp; 
W. Wägele
(
2016
): 
How to tackle the molecular species inventory for an industrialized nation – lessons from the first phase of the German Barcode of Life initiative GBOL (2012-2015)
. – 
Genome

59

: 
661–670
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hopkins, G. W.
&amp; 
R. P. Freckleton
(
2002
): 
Declines in the number of amateur and professional taxonomists: implications for conservation
. – 
Animal Conservation

5

: 
245–249
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jordana, R.
(
2012
): 
Synopses of Palaeartic Collembola. Capbryinae &amp; Entomobryini
. – 
Soil Organisms

84

(
1
): 
1–390
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maxwell, S. L.
, 
R. A. Fuller
, 
T. M. Brooks
&amp; 
J. E. Watson
(
2016
) 
J. Biodiversity: The ravages of guns, nets and bulldozers
. – 
Nature News

536

(
7615
): 
143
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Newbold, T.
, 
L. N. Hudson
, 
S. L. Hill
, 
S. Contu
, 
I. Lysenko
, 
R. A. Senior
&amp; 
J. Day
(
2015
): 
Global effects of land use on local terrestrial biodiversity
. – 
Nature

520

(
7545
): 
45
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Phillips, H. R.
, 
E. K. Cameron
, 
O. Ferlian
, 
M. Türke
, 
M.Winter
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2017
): 
Red list of a black box
. – 
Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution

1

(
4
): 0103.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schmelz, R.
&amp; 
R. Collado
(
2010
): 
A guide to European terrestrial and freshwater species of Enchytraeidae (Oligochaeta)
. – 
Soil Organisms

82

(
1
): 
1–176
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sikorski, J.
(
2015
): 
The prokaryotic biology of soil
. – 
Soil Organisms

87

(
1
): 
1–28
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Veresoglou, S. D.
, 
J. M. Halley
&amp; 
M. C. Rillig
(
2015
): 
Extinction risk of soil biota
. – 
Nature Communications

6

: 
8862
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wägele, H.
, 
A. Klussmann-Kolb
, 
M. Kuhlmann
, 
G. Haszprunar
, 
D. Lindberg
, 
A. Koch
&amp; 
J.W. Wägele
(
2011
): 
The taxonomist – an endangered race. A practical proposal for its survival
. – 
Frontiers in Zoology

8

: 
25
[
doi:10.1186/1742-9994-8-25]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wheeler, Q.
(
2014
): 
Are reports of the death of taxonomy an exaggeration?
– 
New Phytologist

201

: 
370–371
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
