<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Soil Organisms</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25674/so93iss1pp59</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The TeaComposition initiative: Unleashing the power of international collaboration to understand litter decomposition</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelia sinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
CALL FOR COLLABORATION
</title>
         <p>
The TeaComposition initiative: Unleashing the power of international collaboration to understand litter decomposition
</p>
         <p>
Ika Djukic
1
*, 
Sebastian Kepfer-Rojas
2
, 
Inger Kappel Schmidt
2
, 
Klaus Steenberg Larsen
2
, 
Claus Beier
2
, 
Björn Berg
3,4
, 
Kris Verheyen
5
, 
Stacey M. Trevathan-Tackett
6
,

</p>
         <p>
Peter I. Macreadie
6
, 
Michael Bierbaumer
7
, 
Guillaume Patoine
8,9
, 
Nico Eisenhauer
8,9
,

</p>
         <p>
Carlos A. Guerra
8,9
, 
Fernando T. Maestre
10,11
, 
Frank Hagedorn
1
, 
Alessandro Oggioni
12
, 
Caterina Bergami
13
, 
Barbara Magagna
14
, 
TaeOh Kwon
15
, 
Hideaki Shibata
15
&amp; TeaComposition initiative

</p>
         <p>
1

Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research WSL, Birmensdorf, 
Switzerland
</p>
         <p>
2

Department of Geosciences and Natural Resource Management, University of Copenhagen, 
Denmark
</p>
         <p>
3

Department of 
Forest
Sciences, University of Helsinki, 
Finland
</p>
         <p>
4

Section of Biology, University of Gävle, 
Sweden
</p>
         <p>
5
Forest &amp; 

Nature Lab, Department of Forest and Water Management, Ghent University, 
Belgium
</p>
         <p>
6

Centre for Integrative Ecology, School of Life and Environmental Sciences, Deakin University, 
Australia
</p>
         <p>
7

Reichergasse 48, 3411 Klosterneuburg-Weidling, 
Austria
</p>
         <p>
8

German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research (iDiv) Halle-Jena-Leipzig, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
9

Institute of Biology, Leipzig University, Leipzig, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
10
Departamento de BiologÍa y GeologÍa, FÍsica y QuÍmica Inorgánica, Escuela Superior de Ciencias Experimentales y TecnologÍa,
</p>
         <p>
Universidad Rey Juan Carlos, MÓstoles, 
Spain
</p>
         <p>
11
Departamento de EcologÍa and Instituto Multidisciplinar para el Estudio del Medio “RamÓn Margalef, Universidad de Alicante,
</p>
         <p>
Alicante, 
Spain
</p>
         <p>
12

Institute for Electromagnetic Sensing of the Environment (CNR-IREA), Milano, 
Italy
</p>
         <p>
13

Institute of Marine Sciences (CNR-ISMAR), Bologna, 
Italy
</p>
         <p>
14

Environment Agency 
Austria
, Ecosystem Research and Environmental Information Management, 
Vienna
, 
Austria
</p>
         <p>
15

Field Science Center for Northern Biosphere, 
Hokkaido
University, 
Japan
</p>
         <p>* Corresponing author, Email: ika.djukic@umweltbundesamt.at</p>
         <p>
Received 
2 February 2021
| Accepted 
17 March 2021
</p>
         <p>
Published online at www.soil-organisms.de 
1 April 2021
| Printed version 
15 April 2021
</p>
         <p>
DOI 
10.25674/so93iss1pp59
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Abstract
</title>
         <p>Collected harmonized data on global litter decomposition are of great relevance for scientists, policymakers, and for education of the next generation of researchers and environmental managers. Here we describe the TeaComposition initiative, a global and open research collaborative network to study organic matter decomposition in a standardized way allowing comparison of decomposition rate and carbon turnover across global and regional gradients of ecosystems, climate, soils etc. The TeaComposition initiative today involves 570 terrestrial and 300 aquatic ecosystems from nine biomes worldwide. Further, we describe how to get involved in the TeaComposition initiative by (a) implementing the standard protocol within your study site, (b) joining task forces in data analyses, syntheses and modelling efforts, (c) using collected data and samples for further analyses through joint projects, (d) using collected data for graduate seminars, and (e) strengthening synergies between biogeochemical research and a wide range of stakeholders. These collaborative efforts within/emerging from the TeaComposition initiative, thereby, will leverage our understanding on litter decomposition at the global scale and strengthen global collaborations essential for addressing grand scientific challenges in a rapidly changing world.</p>
         <p>
Keywords
LitteR deCOMPOSitiON
| 
tea baGS
| 
haRMONized data
| 
TeaCOMPOSitiON iNitiative
| 
NetWORkiNG NetWORkS
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Challenges in global studies
</title>
         <p>
Ecosystems are under pressure from a multitude of stressors, most notably climate and land-use change (e.g., IPCC 2019, 

). Prediction of system responses to these global change drivers are challenged by the extremely complex nature of ecosystems, the strong interlinkage of processes, the interactions among drivers and the interactions with natural or human-induced disturbances and management practices (e.g. 

, 

). In recent decades, many studies have been conducted aiming to unravel these complexities through observations and experiments combined with modelling (e.g. 

), and multiple studies and meta-analyses have aimed to synthesize and generalize our understanding across scales (e.g. 

, 

). Our general understanding of ecosystem processes and functions at the global scale is, however, challenged by the relatively small spatial scale and short-term nature of most studies, as well as by the lack of common methods and standards for conducting cross-site comparisons. This strongly limits our ability to synthesize studies globally and the capacity to adequately inform decision makers about the impacts of global change drivers on fundamental ecosystem processes.
</p>
         <p>
Designing and implementing coordinated and low-cost field studies easily applicable at multiple sites across the globe is a way to integrate ecosystem research towards a common goal (

). In recent years, we have seen an increasing demand for coordinated observational and experimental ecosystem studies (

) and a plea for common methodologies, metrics and standards (e.g. 

, 

). Global coordinated research networks (e.g. 

, 

), are already providing unique insights and generalities regarding ecosystem functioning and responses to global change drivers (e.g. 

, 

, 

), and hold great promise to advance our understanding of planetary responses to such drivers.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Leaf litter decomposition
</title>
         <p>
Decomposition of organic matter is a fundamental process in ecosystems, releasing CO 
2
and 
CH
4
from decaying organic materials back to the atmosphere and transferring carbon and nutrients from the biosphere to the soil and aquatic ecosystems (

). Plant litter decomposition is regulated by a complex interplay of factors, including the composition and activity of soil biota, abiotic conditions (e.g. moisture, temperature, oxygen availability), plant diversity, and the intrinsic chemical composition of litter materials (e.g. 

). Plant litter decomposition, therefore, plays a significant role in the feedback between the biosphere and the atmosphere (e.g. 

), but at the same time, we still face major unknowns in our general understanding of this process such as the controls on carbon stability and atmospheric feedback.
</p>
         <p>
Litter decomposition can be studied by direct 
in-situ
respiration measurements of soil respiration (Singh &amp; Gupta 1997). Such studies provide in-depth processbased data, linking short-term dynamics and controlling drivers, but they are costly and upscaling is significantly challenging because of the small spatial (plot) and temporal (few years) scales of the measurements (

). Alternatively, litter decomposition can be studied by direct incubation of litter in the field and subsequent measurement of the carbon (and nutrient) loss over time. Such studies provide very useful integrated measures of decomposition, with incubation periods spanning from months to 10 years (e.g. Long-term Intersite Decomposition Experiment (LIDET), the Canadian Intersite Decomposition Experiment (CIDET). However, these are most often conducted based on site specific litters, and methodologies and comparison of similar data across different experiments and sites still poses a major challenge due to the lack of common protocols and standard matrices. To overcome these limitations, the Tea Bag Index (TBI) method has been developed (

). This approach is based on the 
in-situ
incubation of 
two types
of tea: Rooibos tea characterized by a slow decomposition rate and Green tea characterized by a higher decomposition rate. The advantage of this approach is that commercially available tea bags constitute a pre-made ‘litterbag’. Hence, any variation related to user differences in preparation and associated workload are marginal. In addition, tea bags are filled with the tea leaves and resemble thus more natural litter than the commonly used cotton strips (

). Limitation of the tea bags is primarily related to the mesh size (0.25) that excludes the larger soil fauna (

), which are of significant importance in most environments (

). In the TBI approach the litter bags are incubated for 90 days, and thus it provides valuable insights into short-term dynamics of plant litter decomposition (

, 

). Yet, extrapolating from short-term to long-term decomposition rates is still challenging due to the fact that the quality of litter changes with progressing decomposition and therewith it’s controlling factors (

). Repeated observations over time, such as those proposed by the TeaComposition initiative we describe below, are thus essential for improving our understanding of temporal dynamics of the decay process of plant litter.
</p>
         <p>
The 
TeaComposition initiative
is a global and collaborative litter decomposition study aiming to estimate short- to long-term plant litter decomposition rates by using standard protocols and litter materials (
Fig. 1A
). The standardized protocol ensures: (i) use of the same batch of tea bags assuring the same substrate quality for all sites, (ii) harmonized start of the decomposition at the same season at the year for northern and southern hemisphere, (iii) comparable incubation depth at the upper 
5 cm
of the soil relevant for litter decomposition, and (iv) standardized incubation times with the sampling points after 3, 12, 24, and 36 months.
</p>
         <p>
TeaComposition is being successfully developed across nine biomes, including 570 terrestrial and 300 aquatic sites worldwide (
Fig. 1B, C
). More than&gt;80,000 tea bags have been deployed by volunteers from academia, government bodies, scientific institutes, and citizen scientists through an online coordinated effort. The results comparing the early stage of decomposition after three months of incubation have demonstrated the strong potential of the approach (

), and further research is ongoing in capturing the long-term dynamics and in analyzing the role of soil biodiversity, environmental factors, and litter chemistry in further depth.
</p>
         <p>
The value and importance of comparable and feasible methods to inform about decomposition and carbon turnover related to climate and global changes is clear from the involvement in TeaComposition of multiple experimental and global research networks such as TreeDivNet (https://treedivnet.ugent.be/), TERENO (https://www.tereno.net/), DIRT (https://dirtnet. wordpress.com/), ILTER (https://www.ilter.network/), GLORIA (https://gloria.ac.at/home) and INTERACT (https://eu-interact.org/). Such global implementations make the quantification of litter carbon turnover possible at a high resolution, both temporally and spatially, capitalizing on local data to elucidate the abiotic and biotic drivers of decomposition processes. TeaComposition hereby plays an important and inclusive role linking different networks of terrestrial ecological studies. In recent years, the TeaComposition initiative has expanded to also include aquatic ecosystems in the framework of the ‘ 

TeaComposition H 
2
O

’ initiative (https://www. bluecarbonlab.org/teacomposition-h2o/). Together, these TeaComposition initiatives provide a unique platform and common metric-important for crosscutting conceptual ecological comparison and understanding of the abiotic (e.g., temperature, precipitation, elevation) and biotic (microbial activity, litter quality) factors involved in the control global litter carbon turnover.
</p>
         <p>
Data handling and policy is following the FAIR principles (

). Data on litter decomposition and ancillary environmental data collected at the sites or gathered from existing global databases will be stored in a dynamic data repository. The data will be made available as data descriptors following the publication of scientific articles according to the milestones of the initiative, thus providing full accessibility to external users. Similarly, metadata of collected samples will be freely accessible within the TeaComposition sample catalogue (Catalogue of samples - http://get-it.it/objects/samples/TeaBag/_site/ index.html; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The data allow not only global cross-site comparison and large-scale trend analyses, but also the comparison of locally collected data with global, freely accessible datasets from the TeaComposition initiative. Further, data from the TeaComposition initiative have the potential to be used for teaching purposes in schools as has already been done for graduate seminars (e.g. Phyton course at Columbia University) or to extend research questions (

). If you wish to use data or samples, a storyline should be submitted to the corresponding author for a general review.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Perspectives
</title>
         <p>Policy support &amp; addressing data gaps</p>
         <p>
Leaf litter decomposition is of significant relevance for developing forecasts on soil carbon and nitrogen dynamics and stocks under different climate, land-use, and policy scenarios (
Fig. 1D
). The TeaComposition initiative provides a unique opportunity to collect harmonized and comparable data of different climatic zones, land-use 
types
, drivers, and management practices at all scales for informing and calibrating carbon models. This is essential for the up-scaling of consequences of environmental changes for ecosystem functioning, carbon storage capacity and contribution to greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions, relevant for national GHG inventories and IPCC reporting. The tea bag approach, however, provides information about the potential decomposition rates in a given ecosystem. In order to provide a link between the potential (i.e. based on standardized tea litter) and actual (i.e. based on local litter) decomposition rates, simultaneous incubation or data of native litter would be needed (

). In addition, information on the role of soil fauna in decomposition process is required in order to provide true unbiased results for global understanding of litter decomposition rates and their impact on carbon and nutrient cycling (

, 

). Therefore, further efforts to harmonize and apply worldwide a complementary method that includes larger fauna are important and we would welcome collaborations with the partners collecting data on the litter decomposing biota.
</p>
         <p>
Globally, environmental data are latitudinally skewed with more studies in the Northern than Southern Hemisphere (e.g. 

), due to regional differences in research effort and investment (

). This will potentially result in a biased process understanding since ecological processes and their underlying drivers are highly ecosystem-dependent. Applying cost-effective methodologies using standardized protocols across sites such as theTeaComposition initiative therefore provides a means to overcome such data gaps, and contribute to improving ecological literacy for ecosystem research and environmental policy formation (

). The TeaComposition initiative particularly encourages institutions, communities, or individuals from underrepresented areas to participate (
Fig. 1C
). Interested collaborators are asked to express their interest by contacting the corresponding author. The amount of work for each site is restricted to installation and collection of the tea bags (corresponds to 10 workdays over the period of three years). Anyone who contributes data will be offered co-authorship for the core papers of the initiative.
</p>
         <p>Networking Networks</p>
         <p>
Effects of global change on ecosystems will occur across large spatial scales, and new meta-networks will be instrumental for data and analytical sharing beyond site-based research (e.g. Rastetter et al. 2011, 

). The TeaComposition initiative has established collaboration among multiple networks, teams, and researchers working in multiple fields, such as add-on studies focusing on soil microbial biomass and diversity, aggregate stability, nutrient availability assessments, and soil microbial diversity (

, 

) (
Fig. 1D
). By doing so, the TeaComposition initiative aims to become a unique source for standardized cross-site procedures and information and an example of a comprehensive overview of existing research activities, reducing duplication of efforts and closing data gaps thereby (
Fig. 1D
). As an inclusive network, TeaComposition works to support the sustainable development goals, which requires significant cross-disciplinary and collaborative networks across many research fields and directions. Therefore, we encourage colleagues, scientists as well as non-scientists, worldwide to join TeaComposition and/or to propose further collaborative research within other fields to unleash the power of scientific collaboration to tackle grand scientific challenges (e.g. carbon feedbacks in the climate systems, factors affecting biological diversity and ecosystem functioning).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
This work was performed within the TeaComposition and TeaComposition H 
2
O initiatives, carried by 290 institutions worldwide. We thank to UNILEVER for sponsoring the Lipton tea bags. The initiative is supported by the following grants: ILTER Initiative Grants, ClimMani Short-Term Scientific Missions Grants, INTERACT Remote Transnational Access and an Alfred Deakin Postdoctoral Research Fellowship. Nico Eisenhauer gratefully acknowledges the support of iDiv funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG– FZT 118, 202548816). ST-T was supported by the ARC DE210101029 and Deakin University’s ADPR Fellowship. Fernando T. Maestre acknowledges support from the European Research Council (ERC Grant agreement 647038 [BIODESERT]) and Generalitat Valenciana (CIDEGENT/2018/041).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aguilar-Cruz, Y.
, 
J. G. García-Franco
&amp; 
G. Zotz
(
2020
): 
Microsites and early litter decomposition patterns in the soil and forest canopy at regional scale
. – 
Biogeochemistry
: 
1–16
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Berg, B.
(
2014
): 
Decomposition patterns for foliar litter–a theory for influencing factors
. – 
Soil Biology and Biochemistry

78

: 
222–232
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Berg, B.
&amp; 
C. McClaugherty
(
2020
): 
Plant litter: decomposition
, 
humus formation, carbon sequestration (Springer, Heidelberg, 2020)
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Borer, E. T.
, 
W. S. Harpole
, 
P. B. Adler
, 
C. A. Arnillas
, 
M. N. Bugalho
, 
M. W. Cadotte
, 
M. C. Caldeira
, 
S. Campana
, 
C. R. Dickman
, 
T. L. Dickson
&amp; et al. (
2020
): 
Nutrients cause grassland biomass to outpace herbivory
. – 
Nature communications

11

(
1
): 
6036
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bradford, M. A.
, 
G. M. Tordoff
, 
T. Eggers
, 
T. H. Jones
&amp; 
J. E. Newington
(
2002
): 
Microbiota, fauna, and mesh size interactions in litter decomposition
. – 
Oikos

99

(
2
): 
317–323
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Delgado-Baquerizo, M.
, 
F. T. Maestre
, 
A. Gallardo
, 
M. A. Bowker
, 
M.D.Wallenstein
, 
J. L.Quero
, 
V. Ochoa
, 
B. Gozalo
, 
M. García-Gómez
, 
S. Soliveres
, 
P. García-Palacios
&amp; et al. (
2013
): 
Decoupling of soil nutrient cycles as a function of aridity in global drylands
. – 
Nature

502

(
7473
): 
672–675
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Didion, M.
, 
A. Repo
, 
J. Liski
, 
M. Forsius
, 
M. Bierbaumer
&amp; 
I. Djukic
(
2016
): 
Towards Harmonizing Leavs Litter Decomposition Studies Using Standard Tea Bags—A Field Study and Model Application
. – 
Forests

7

(
8
): 
167
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dietzen, C. A.
, 
K. S. Larsen
, 
P. L. Ambus
, 
A. Michelsen
, 
M. F. Arndal
, 
C. Beier
, 
S. Reinsch
&amp; 
I. K. Schmidt
(
2019
): 
Accumulation of soil carbon under elevated CO2 unaffected by warming and drought
. – 
Global Change Biology

25

: 
2970– 2977
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Djukic, I.
, 
S. Kepfer-Rojas, I.
K. Schmidt
, K. S. 
Larsen, C.
Beier, B.
Berg, K.
Verheyen, A.
Caliman, A.
Paquette, A.
Gutiérrez- Girón &amp; et al. (
2018
): 
Early stage litter decomposition across biomes
. – 

Science of the Total Environment 
628

- 
629
: 
1369– 1394
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eggleton, P.
, 
H. Griffiths
, 
L. Ashton
, 
S. Law
, 
T. A. Evans
&amp; 
K. Parr
(
2020
): 
Not our cup of tea: the Tea Bag Index (Kueskamp et al. 2013) for assessing decomposition is problematic in most environments, due to macrofauna
. – 
Authorea Preprints
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
García‐Palacios, P.
, 
F. T. Maestre
, 
J. Kattge
&amp; 
D. H. Wall
(
2013
): 
Climate and litter quality differently modulate the effects of soil fauna on litter decomposition across biomes
. – 
Ecology letters

16

(
8
): 
1045–1053
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guerra, C. A.
, 
A. Heintz-Buschart
, 
J. Sikorski
, 
A. Chatzinotas
, 
N. Guerrero-Ramírez
, 
S. Cesarz
, 
L. Beaumelle
, 
M. C. Rillig
, 
F. T. Maestre
, 
M. Delgado-Baquerizo
&amp; et al. (
2020
): 
Blind spots in global soil biodiversity and ecosystem function research
. – 
Nature communications

11

(
1
): 
1–13
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guerra, C. A.
, 
R. D. Bardgett
, 
L. Caon
, 
T. W. Crowther
, 
M. Delgado-Baquerizo
, 
L. Montanarella
, 
L. M. Navarro
, 
A. Orgiazzi
, 
B. K. Singh
, 
L. Tedersoo
&amp; et al. (
2021
): 
Tracking, targeting, and conserving soil biodiversity: A monitoring and indicator system can inform policy
. – 
Science

371

(
6526
): 
239–241
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Halbritter, A. H.
, 
H. J. De Boeck
, 
A. E. Eycott
, 
D. A. Robinson
, 
S. Vicca
, 
B. Berauer
, 
C. T. Christiansen
, 
M. Estiarte
, 
J. M. Grünzweig
, 
R. Gya
&amp; et al. (
2020
): 
The handbook for standardized field and laboratory measurements in terrestrial climate change experiments and observational studies (ClimEx)
. – 
Methods in Ecology and Evolution

11

: 
22–37
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Heintz-Buschart, A.
, 
C. Guerra
, 
I. Djukic
, 
S. Cesarz
, 
A. Chatzinotas
, 
G. Patoine
, 
J. Sikorski
, 
F. Buscot
, 
K. Küsel
, 
C. E. Wegner
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2020
): 
Microbial diversityecosystem function relationships across environmental gradients
. – 
Research Ideas and Outcomes

6

: e 
52217
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
IPCC
(
2019
). 
Climate Change and Land: an IPCC special report on climate change, desertification, land degradation, sustainable land management, food security, and greenhouse gas fluxes in terrestrial ecosystems
[
P. R. Shukla
, 
J. Skea
, 
E. Calvo Buendia
, 
V. Masson-Delmotte
, 
H.-O. Pörtner
, 
D. C. Roberts
, 
P. Zhai
, 
R. Slade
, 
S. Connors
, 
R. van Diemen
&amp; et al. (eds)].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
IPBES
(
2019
): 
Global assessment report of the Intergovernmental Science-Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services. S. Díaz, J. Settele, E. Brondízio and H. T. Ngo. – Bonn, Germany
, 
IPBES Secretariat: 1753
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Keuskamp, J. A.
, 
B. J. Dingemans
, 
T. Lehtinen
, 
J. M. Sarneel
&amp; 
M. M. Hefting
(
2013
): 
Tea Bag Index: a novel approach to collect uniform decomposition data across ecosystems
. – 
Methods in Ecology and Evolution

4

(
11
): 
1070–1075
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Luo, Y.
, 
J. Melillo
, 
S. Niu
, 
C. Beier
, 
J. Clark
, 
A. Classen
, 
E. Davidson
, 
J. S. Dukes
, 
R. D. Evans
, 
C. Field
, 
C. I. Czimczik
&amp; et al. (
2011
): 
Coordinated Approaches to Quantify Long-Term Ecosystem dynamics in Response to Global Change
. – 
Global Change Biology

17

: 
843–854
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maestre, F. T.
, 
J. L. Quero
, 
N. J. Gotelli
, 
A. Escudero
, 
V. Ochoa
, 
M. Delgado-Baquerizo
, 
M. García-Gómez
, 
M. A. Bowker
, 
S. Soliveres
, 
C. Escolar
&amp; et al. (
2012
): 
Plant species richness and ecosystem multifunctionality in global drylands
. – 
Science

335

(
6065
): 
214–218
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maestre, F. T.
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2019
): 
Recommendations for establishing global collaborative networks in soil ecology
. – 
Soil organisms

91

(
3
): 
73–85
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mirtl, M.
, 
T. E. Borer
, 
I. Djukic
, 
M. Forsius
, 
H. Haubold
, 
W. Hugo
, 
J. Jourdan
, 
D. Lindenmayer
, 
W. H. McDowell
, 
H. Muraoka
&amp; et al. (
2018
): 
Genesis, goals and achievements of long-term ecological research at the global scale: a critical review of ILTER and future directions
. – 
Science of the total Environment

626

: 
1439–1462
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moore, T. R.
, 
J. A. Trofymow
, 
C. E. Prescott
, 
B. D. Titus
&amp; 
CIDET Working Group
(
2017
): 
Can short-term litter-bag measurements predict long-term decomposition in northern forests?
– 
Plant and soil
416
(1- 
2
): 
419–426
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ogden, L. E.
(
2017
). 
Brewing big data: the tea-bag index
. – 
BioScience

67

(
7
): 
680–680
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oggioni, A.
&amp; 
C. Bergami
(
2021
). 
oggioniale/ TeaCompositionCatalogue: First release of tea composition catalogue (Version v1.0)
. 
Zenodo
[
http://doi.org/10.5281/ zenodo.4638828]
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rillig, M. C.
, 
M. Ryo
, 
A. Lehmann
, 
C. A. Aguilar-Trigueros
, 
S. Buchert
, 
A. Wulf
, 
A. Iwasaki
, 
J. Roy
&amp; 
G. Yang
(
2019
): 
The role of multiple global change factors in driving soil functions and microbial biodiversity
. – 
Science

366

(
6467
): 
886–890
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singh, J. S.
&amp; 
S. R. Gupta
(
1977
): 
Plant decomposition and soil respiration in terrestrial ecosystems
. – 
The botanical review

43

(
4
): 
449–528
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Song, J.
, 
S. Wan
, 
S. Piao
, 
A. Knapp
, 
A. Classen
, 
S. Vicca
, 
P. Ciais
, 
M. Hovenden
, 
S. Leuzinger
, 
C. Beier
&amp; et al. (
2019
): 
A meta-analysis of 1119 manipulative experiments on terrestrial carbon-cycling responses to global change
. – 
Nature Ecology and Evolution
: 
1309–1320
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Spiegel, H.
, 
T. Mosleitner
, 
T. Sandén
&amp; 
J.G.Zaller
(
2018
): 
Effects of two decades of organic and mineral fertilization of arable crops on earthworms and standardized litter decomposition. Die Bodenkultur
. – 
Journal of Land Management, Food and Environment

69

(
1
): 
17–28
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tiegs, S. D.
, 
S. D. Langhans
, 
K.Tockner
&amp; 
M. O. Gessner
(
2007
). 
Cotton strips as a leaf surrogate to measure decomposition in river floodplain habitats
. – 
Journal of the North American Benthological Society

26

(
1
), 
70–77
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Van Groenigen, K. J.
, 
X. Qi
, 
C. W. Osenberg
, 
Y. Luo
&amp; 
B. A. Hungate
(
2014
): 
Faster decomposition under increased atmospheric CO2 limits soil carbon storage
. – 
Science
1249534
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vicca, S
, 
M. Bahn
, 
M. Estiarte
, 
E. E. van Loon
, 
R. Vargas
, 
G. Alberti
, 
P. Ambus
, 
M. A. Arain
, 
C. Beier
, 
L. Bentley
&amp; et al. (
2014
): 
Can current moisture responses predict soil CO 2 efflux under altered precipitation regimes? A synthesis of manipulation experiments
. – 
Biogeosciences

11

: 
2991–3013
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wilkinson, M. D.
, 
M. Dumontier
, 
I. J. Aalbersberg
, 
G. Appleton
, 
M. Axton
, 
A. Baak
, 
N. Blomberg
, 
J.-W. Boiten
, 
L. B. da Silva Santos
, 
P. E. Bourne
&amp; et al. (
2016
): 
The FAIR Guiding Principles for scientific data management and stewardship
. – 
Scientific data

3

(
1
): 
1–9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
