<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Soil Organisms</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25674/so94iss1id174</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Climate-change effects on the sex ratio of free-living soil nematodes - perspective and prospect</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Heterodera schachtii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Scottnema lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
Snow
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
Sex
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>PERSPECTIVE PAPER</p>
         <p>
Carla Klusmann
1,2
, 
Simone Cesarz
1,2
, 
Marcel Ciobanu
3
, 
Olga Ferlian
1,2
, 
Malte Jochum
1,2
, 
Martin Schädler
4,1
, 
Stefan Scheu
5,6
, 
Marie Sünnemann
1,2
, 
Diana H. Wall
7
and

</p>
         <p>
Nico Eisenhauer
1,2,
*

</p>
         <p>
1

German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research (iDiv) Halle-Jena-Leipzig, PUschstrasse 4, 04103 Leipzig, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
2

InstitUte of Biology, Leipzig University, PUschstrasse 4, 04103 Leipzig, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
3
InstitUte of Biological Research, Branch of the National InstitUte of Research and Development for Biological Sciences,
</p>
         <p>
Str. RepUblicii Nr. 48, 400015, 
ClUJ-Napoca
, 
Romania
</p>
         <p>
4
Department of CommUnity Ecology, Helmholtz-Centre for Environmental Research – UFZ,
</p>
         <p>
Theodor-Lieser-Str. 4, 06120 Halle, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
5

J.F. BlUmenbach InstitUte of Zoology and Anthropology, University of Göttingen, Untere Karspüle 2, 37073 Göttingen, 
Germany
6

Centre of Biodiversity and SUstainable Land Use, Büsgenweg 1, 37077 Göttingen, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
7
School of Global Environmental
SUstainability and 
Department of Biology
, 
Colorado State
University,

</p>
         <p>
Fort Collins, CO 80523-1036 
USA
</p>
         <p>* Corresponing aUthor, Email: nico.eisenhaUer@idiv.de</p>
         <p>
Received 
7 December 2021
| Accepted 
29 March 2022
</p>
         <p>
Published online at www.soil-organisms.de 


1 April 
2022

| Printed version 
15 April 2022
</p>
         <p>
DOI 
10.25674/so94iss1id174
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Abstract
</title>
         <p>Human-induced global environmental change is predicted to alter the stability and functioning of ecosystems worldwide. Most research in recent decades has focused on studying climate-change effects on aboveground systems, causing a poor understanding of belowground responses. However, gaining knowledge on environmental-change effects on soil biota is of crucial importance, as soil-ecosystem services are indispensable for human well-being and contribute fundamentally to the functioning of terrestrial ecosystems. Nematode communities play a central role in various soil ecosystem processes and are therefore commonly used as biological indicators to assess soil conditions and soil health. While causing overall shifts in community composition patterns, which are most often examined, climate change might also alter nematode population dynamics and the sex ratio (number of males per female). Previous studies on plant-parasitic nematode species suggest that changes to unfavorable environmental conditions trigger reduced development of females and favor sexual rather than parthenogenetic reproduction. Therefore, we are presenting the working hypothesis that predicted climate change causing reduced resource availability and enhanced environmental stress will lead to an increased proportion of males in soil nematode communities. Our systematic literature review revealed that climate- and environmental change effects on the sex ratio of free-living soil nematode populations are inconsistent, but heavily understudied. Data on sex ratios have been treated mostly as additional information, presented without any underlying theory and hypotheses, as well as limited discussion. In this perspective paper, we thus propose that future studies should include clear hypotheses and test if the sex ratio of free-living nematodes increases with climate change due to more stressful environmental conditions and low resource availability. Furthermore, we conclude that experimental studies investigating the specific roles of male and female nematodes are needed to better predict the implications of a changing climate on soil ecosystem functioning.</p>
         <p>
Keywords
Climate change
| 
hUman impact
| 
nematode sex ratio
| 
soil biodiversity
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
As a consequence of anthropogenic activities in the recent decades, natural ecosystems across the globe are now facing a variety of rapidly accumulating environmental challenges, such as increases in atmospheric CO 
2
concentrations, rising temperatures, and biodiversity change (

). However, the majority of research on global-change consequences for ecosystems has focused on aboveground flora and fauna rather than on belowground systems resulting in a limited understanding of soil-biodiversity changes (

, 

). Understanding environmental change effects on soil biota is highly important though, as soil organisms make up ~25% of all species on earth and provide a large set of fundamental soil ecosystem services, such as carbon sequestration, maintenance of soil properties, and the support of biogeochemical cycles (

, 

). Some of these, for example climate regulation, are indispensable for human well-being. Furthermore, soil biodiversity is directly linked to the functioning of both, above- and belowground systems, and plays a key role in mediating the impact of future environmental change on global terrestrial ecosystems (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
Some of the most important threats to soil biodiversity are the loss of plant biodiversity, invasion of exotic species, environmental pollution, land-use intensification, and extreme climatic events (

, 

). Recent studies show that the magnitude of threat imposed by a global change driver or the interaction of several drivers depends on the focal group of organisms (

, 

). For instance, 

demonstrated positive effects of increased levels of CO 
2
on soil microfauna and -flora, but negative effects on soil mesofauna. Despite this variability of responses, recent studies highlighted the dominant role of climate (change) effects on different groups of soil organisms (

, 

, 

). Most studies investigating global-change effects on soil communities focused on a relatively confined set of changes in community properties such as total abundance, biomass, functional community composition, or biodiversity indices. However, changes in such broad and integrated biodiversity indices can only be understood if there is knowledge about the climate change-induced shifts in community composition, biotic interactions, and population densities (

).
</p>
         <p>
Soil-nematode communities are often used as a biological indicator for the assessment of soil health and ecosystem functioning. Their community composition and their central role in soil energy fluxes and cycling of organic matter allow drawing conclusions regarding the state of the soil ecosystem compartment (

, 

). Nematodes are ubiquitous and very abundant animals, accounting for approximately 80% of all metazoans on earth (

) and an estimated global biomass of 0.02 Gt carbon (

). They play a central role in soil food webs and are functionally very diverse, including herbivores, bacterivores, fungivores, carnivores, and omnivores. Thus, soil nematodes take an active part in various ecosystem processes like root herbivory, nutrient cycling, and decomposition. Prior to seeing climate change drivers causing shifts in nematode abundance or taxonomic diversity, as analyzed by most previous studies, more subtle alterations within a population may occur, such as behavioral changes (

, 

) and changes of the sex ratio (

, 

). For example, environmental changes might influence sex ratios (

, 

, 

). Changes in nematode sex ratios have significant ecosystem implications. For instance, studies on the plant-parasitic nematode 
<tp:taxon-name>
Heterodera schachtii
</tp:taxon-name>
have shown that, on average, females require 29 times more food compared to males due to the extended sedentary phase which is required for reproduction (

). Generally, plant-parasitic species with sedentary females, such as root-knot nematodes and cyst nematodes, are among the most detrimental agricultural pests (

). Thus, it may be assumed that nematode effects on a given ecosystem will depend on their sex ratio; for example, crop damage is suggested to be much higher when there are more females, as they require a lot of energy for reproduction (

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
Generally, changes in sex ratios might be due to females producing eggs of an unbalanced sex ratio, i.e. due to changes in the primary sex ratio. Further, unbalanced mortality of females and males, i.e., changes in the secondary sex ratio, may contribute to shifts in the sex ratios of populations (

). It is important to note that nematodes may reproduce via different modes including facultative as well as obligatory amphimixis, meiotic as well as mitotic parthenogenesis, and hermaphroditism (

). Therefore, shifts in sex ratios towards females might be due to an increased number of females reproducing via parthenogenesis or being able to self-fertilize their eggs. Mechanisms responsible for variation in primary sex ratios are manifold and include infections of females by bacterial endosymbionts or changes in environmental factors experienced by females (

, 

). Each of these mechanisms as well as changes in secondary sex ratios likely contribute to variation in sex ratios in nematode populations (

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
Overall, the majority of studies on the influence of environmental factors on sex determination and sex ratio of nematodes are lab studies which focused on plant and insect parasitic species (

, 

, 

). First experiments already showed that not only genetic but also environmental factors can influence sex determination (

). One of the most-commonly studied environmental drivers tested in experiments is the availability of resources. Taken together, these studies show that nutrient deficiencies and manipulated concentrations of missing or strongly reduced essential minerals exclusively caused an enhanced proportion of males (

, 

, 

, 

). Moreover, 

and 

concluded that the sex ratio was most dependent on the source of nutrition and its availability compared to other possible influencing factors, such as temperature or intensity of infection by parasitic nematodes. With the exception of an aquatic study by 

, who found an increasing ratio of periphytic male nematodes to females (sex ratio) with ameliorated conditions (trophic state of the lake), studies on resource gradients, such as lake depth (

), also showed that the fraction of females was reduced when resources were scarce. These findings fit with resource-based theories on the evolution of sex predicting that parthenogenetic reproduction is favored if resources are plentiful (

, 

). As most studies looked at parasitic species, ecological parameters such as nematode population density and therefore competition were often examined as additional, not focal, drivers. Nevertheless, the findings show that the higher the population density in a host, or the intensity of infection, the higher the percentage of developed males (

, 

, 

). As elevated population densities often coincide with increased competition for resources, these findings also support the conclusion that resource shortage might generally increase the proportion of males over females, which likely is related to reduced parthenogenetic reproduction if resources become limiting (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
Experiments that solely studied the effect of temperature on nematode sex ratios found that higher temperatures, representing a sudden environmental stress in those contexts, led to higher relative numbers of males (

, 

, 

). These results suggest that, analogous to resource-related drivers, overall stressful conditions have a ‘masculinizing’ effect on nematode populations. As suggested by 

, stressful conditions might be associated with resource shortage favoring sexual over parthenogenetic reproduction. Other, less-frequently studied drivers include elevated CO 
2
(

), age of host plant, immune response, and resistance (

), biodiversity (

), size of the host animal (

), and succession (

). Due to the low number of studies, however, general conclusions are hard to draw. Nevertheless, except for a few cases, studies from 1929 to 2020 overall agree that unfavorable conditions increase the proportion of males relative to females (further described as sex ratio). As a consequence, a high percentage of males was even supposed to demonstrate unfavorable conditions for nematode populations (

). Thus, the questions arise if similar patterns can be found in free-living nematodes and which underlying mechanisms are driving a shift towards male-dominated communities under adverse conditions.
</p>
         <p>
Due to lower investment in reproduction, the development of male nematodes requires fewer resources than that of females. By shifting the sex ratio towards the less resource-consuming males, the few juveniles developing into high resource-demanding females may have a higher probability of surviving (

). Similarly, reducing the female population when food is scarce may also reduce competition for available nutrients, as males are able to survive longer without them (

). Additionally, producing more males ensures an increased heterogeneity of the population, as sexual reproduction increases genetic diversity (

, 

, 

). Being highly genetically variable improves the ability to withstand adverse environmental conditions due to a rich portfolio of responses and the production of progeny with possible superior fitness (

). Lastly, plant-parasitic female nematodes are often sedentary, while the male nematodes are fully mobile, which allows them to leave areas of adverse conditions and still guarantee the persistence of the gene pool and/or fitness of the population (

, 

). However, it remains to be explored which sex ratio ensures highest genetic diversity under different environmental conditions.
</p>
         <p>
Soil-ecological studies on the consequences of increased proportions of females are rare, although parthenogenetic reproduction is very widespread in soil (

, 

, 

, 

). Since it is known that resource consumption is higher for females and that there are further morphological and behavioral differences between males and females, a population shift towards females is very likely to influence nematode consumers and prey, soil nutrient cycles, and thereby alter relevant ecosystem functions. Thus, the consequences for food-web dynamics and related ecosystem services are still unknown, even though those questions are of fundamental importance when trying to predict ecosystem-scale consequences of climate change. Moreover, we currently lack a systematic and comprehensive synthesis of the available literature on climate-change effects on free-living soil nematode sex ratios. Taking existing studies on parasitic nematodes and other taxa into account (

, 

, 

), we introduce the working hypothesis that climate change leads to a higher proportion of males in soil-nematode communities, if it coincides with increased environmental stress. To address this research question and to inspire future studies, we performed a systematic literature search and compiled the available literature on climate-change effects on free-living soil nematodes. We discuss the ecological implications of this work and outline future research directions as well as prospects.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Methods
</title>
         <p>
We ran a Web of Science Core Collection search on 
March 30th, 2020
, using the following search string: nematod* AND ‘climat* change’ OR drought OR temperature* OR warming OR heat* OR precipitation* OR rain* OR flood* OR irrigation OR moisture OR watering OR fire OR ‘carbon dioxide’ OR CO2 OR ‘global change’ OR ‘environmental change’ OR disturbance* OR stress*. This search delivered 13,964 results. We screened the titles for keywords and phrases and also the abstract, when additional information was needed. Based on this initial screening, we selected 53 papers that we then studied in more depth. After thoroughly reading and removing studies that did not focus on soil nematodes or on environmental influences, or that did not report sex ratios, we were left with four studies that matched the scope of the present paper. From these, we derived information on the different study characteristics (location, 
type
of biological system), environmental drivers (temperature, moisture, diversity), and soil nematode responses (population density, number of males per female, sex ratio change) which are displayed in Table 1. Moreover, we added unpublished data from four of our own experiments (Table 1). Due to the paucity of climate change studies on the sex ratio of soil nematodes, we also considered additional studies with variation in soil resource availability and stress (e.g. plant diversity experiments). This resulted in a total of eight studies being considered in the following section. All of these studies used common soil nematode extraction methods and identification protocols.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>Notably, none of the studies examining the effects of environmental drivers on nematodes focused explicitly on the community’s sex ratio, but they provided this information in addition to more common nematode community and diversity response variables. In the majority of studies, the focus of analysis was on changes in abundance of adults and juveniles and life cycle parameters such as mortality and number of juveniles per female. This finding is supported by the observation that none of the studies presented clear hypotheses on expected sex ratio responses to the environmental drivers studied. The paucity of studies on soil nematodes’ sex ratios did not allow us to analyze the extracted data in a more quantitative way (i.e., in a meta-analysis), yet we reviewed the available information qualitatively. As mentioned above, we may see changes in the sex ratio due to switching reproduction modes. However, unless stated otherwise, the information on the species’ reproduction mode and their ability to switch modes are not available from the literature. Therefore, we do not address these differences in the following and focus solely on the overall change in sex ratio. Nevertheless, such information will be critical to assess in future research.</p>
         <p>

Three out of eight experiments included in our review were conducted in the McMurdo Dry Valleys. These hyper-arid deserts in the Antarctic are known to be some of the coldest on Earth and comprise only a very low number of plant and animal species. In this region, the most dominant microfauna species in soils is the microbivorous-feeding nematode 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scottnema lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
. This species reproduces exclusively sexually and has a relatively long life cycle (218 days at 10°C, 

). It has not yet been reported if 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
switches its mode of reproduction. For field populations, a proportion of 63 % females is reported on the McMurdo LTER website (SD = 0.24, 
n
= 27; 
Weicht
&amp; 
Moorhead
2004). This nematode species is adapted to dry soil conditions with soil moisture ranging from 0.9–2.9% (

, 

) and has only been reported from 
Antarctica
(

). Accordingly, it was found to be the most abundant and most widely distributed nematode species in the driest soils. With increasing soil moisture, for example near streams and lakes, its abundance decreases significantly, while the occurrence of other taxa was not impacted (

, 

). Both the McMurdo Dry Valleys ecosystem and the well-adapted nematode species are extreme in their characteristics. Therefore, insights based 

on 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>

might not be representative for soil nematodes of other biomes/regions. However, due to the limited number of existing studies on climate change effects on soil nematodes and the qualitative character of our perspective paper, we decided to include all three experiments in our synthesis, despite the overrepresentation of the species and the ecosystem 
type

.
</p>
         <p>
As snowfall patterns and snow water contents are expected to be altered under the influence of climate change (

, 

), Ayres et al. (2010) tested the effect of increased snow accumulation on soil-nematode communities. A snow-fence set-up caused an increased accumulation of snow (+200%) over five years which resulted in increased soil moisture of approximately 5–9 % and decreased soil pH. Year (date) had a significant effect on the sex ratio of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
(Table 1, P &lt;0.001) which was 0.9 males per female at the beginning of the experiment (year 1). The second year after the experiment’s establishment was the year with the highest soil moisture and was followed by the year with the highest ratio of males to females (1.5). In summary, the ratio of males to females increased as soil moisture increased. These examinations support our overarching hypothesis: for the nematode 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
, which is specifically adapted to dry soils, moist habitat conditions may represent adverse environmental conditions, and, accordingly, the ratio of males to females increased as a response to increasing soil moisture. It is important to note that the life cycle of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
spans several years under the extremely low temperatures and that changes in abundance and primary sex ratio do not appear immediately. This could explain why a relative increase in males is not reported for the year with the highest soil moisture (year 2) but the year after. Furthermore, the shift in the sex ratio might have occurred due to higher mortality in females than in males, i.e. due to changes in the secondary sex ratio.
</p>
         <p>
In a second study from the McMurdo Dry Valleys, 

examined the consequences of predicted future warming for polar regions on soil-nematode populations. It is assumed that estimated increases in temperature enhance snow and glacial melt which leads to an overall increase in soil moisture and higher stream discharges (

, 

). 

experimentally increased soil surface temperature in the austral summer (+2°C between December and February) as well as soil-water content once in December (+12.7 L/m 
2
). The warming treatment reduced the nematode population significantly by 42 % compared to the control. However, there was no significant difference between treatments regarding the sex ratio (Tab. 1). At one site (Lake Bonney), a natural flooding event occurred shortly after sampling in the summer of 2001/2002. As a result of the natural flooding, the abundance and sex ratio of soil nematodes decreased in 2002/2003 (the latter by 42 %) resulting in a reduced number of males per female. In the years after the flood, the sex ratio increased again and reached its initial value. Especially because the flood occurred naturally and not experimentally, the results of this study are likely to be representative of climate-change consequences and climate-extreme effects on nematode communities. However, additional confounding factors such as reduced nutrient availability and physical disturbance might also have contributed to the observed differences further stressing the need for controlled experiments. At the two other sites, neither treatment nor year had a significant influence on the sex ratio.
</p>
         <p>
The third McMurdo Dry Valley study, 

, tested climate-change effects indirectly. The aim was to identify nematode-population dynamics across temporal and spatial scales and to connect these to different environmental conditions. Along an elevational transect, plots were established at three altitudinal levels (low, medium, and high) which differed in their soil-moisture contents, as increasing soil moisture is also predicted to be a consequence of future climate warming in 
Antarctica
(

, 

) with negative impacts on the local biodiversity (

). Soil moisture decreased with elevation, indicating that the environmental conditions for the highly-abundant nematode 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lindsayae
</tp:taxon-name>
were most adverse at the lowest sites and most favorable at the highest. Consistently, nematode abundances correlated positively with dryness. However, elevation had no significant effect on the sex ratio, while sampling year did (Tab. 1, statistics unavailable). There were significantly more males per female in year six than in years one and three. Since the low-elevation habitat with its high soil-moisture content was the least favorable one for nematodes, we expected the sex ratio to be greatest at the low sites. This was only the case in the last year of sampling. Years one and three showed opposite trends. During these years, there were most males per female at the sites with suitable conditions and least males under adverse conditions. Thus, the data of year six are the only ones which match our hypothesis.
</p>
         <p>

conducted a study to investigate changes in the nematode communities along a gradient of environmental conditions using five successional stages at a sand dune. The stages went from beach and fore dune 
Table 1.
List of studies considered. The reader should note that due to a paucity of climate change studies on the sex ratio of soil nematodes, we also considered additional studies with variation in soil resource availability and stress (e.g. plant diversity experiments). Experimental details are described in the Results and discussion section. Statistically significant factors are indicated by bold numbers. The reference to which sex-ratio change was calculated when an environmental gradient existed is indicated as control (ctrl.). The colors indicate environmental conditions:● = favorable, ● = medium, ● = unfavorable.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
over yellow and grey dune to dune heath, beach being the earliest and dune heath being the latest successional stage. Both salinity and soil moisture decreased with increasing successional stage and, thus, with distance from the beach. In contrast, organic carbon content in the soil increased with successional stage. Conditions for nematode communities thus were more stressful at early than at the later successional stages, as high salinity and moisture as well as lack of dietary substrate are major threats to nematode populations. This is supported by changes in nematode abundance, which increased along the environmental gradient of successional stages reaching 1,143 ind./kg soil at the beach and 7,667 ind./kg soil at the dune heath. In agreement with our hypothesis, the nematode sex ratio was significantly greater at the early (1.0 and 1.02 at the beach and fore dune, respectively) than at the later stages (0.1 and 0.05 at the grey dune and dune heath, respectively) (Tab. 1, P &lt;0.001). It correlated positively with pH (P &lt;0.01) and negatively with organic matter content (P &lt;0.01). 

argued that the male-dominated population at the beach is likely due to the combination of a stressed and resource-limited environment.
</p>
         <p>
Due
to the lack of studies on environmental-change effects on nematodes that also include sex ratio data, we decided to integrate additional unpublished data that we had access to. 
From
these datasets, we extracted the information on sex ratios. 
As
we were unable to focus on species composition, we cannot make any inferences on changing reproduction modes of nematodes from the following experiments. 
For
instance, we had detailed soil nematode data from the 
Global Change Experimental Facility
(GCEF), 
Bad Lauchstädt
, 
Germany
, from 2019 (i.e., 5 years after the establishment of the experiment; 

). 
In
this experiment, the effects of a future climate scenario on five different agricultural land-use 
types
were tested, while nematode data were only available for four land-use 
types
(

). The future climate consisted of a reduction in summer precipitation (-20 %), an increase in spring and fall precipitation (each +10 %), and a mean temperature increase of +0.6°C (

). Ambient and future climate scenarios were crossed with different land-use 
types
: intensively-used grassland (meadow), extensively-used grassland (meadow), conventional agriculture, and organic agriculture (extensively-used sheep pasture was not included in the nematode study). In three out of four cases (organic agriculture, extensively-used meadow, intensively-used meadow), the future climate scenario increased soil-nematode abundances. The sex ratio, however, did not respond significantly to the climate-change treatments (Tab. 1). In two of the land-use 
types
(organic farming, intensively-used meadow), the sex ratio was slightly increased, while in the other two (conventional farming, extensively-used meadow), it decreased. Given these opposing, non-significant trends, future long-term studies should explore if land-use intensity modulates soil nematode community responses to climate change (

)

.
</p>
         <p>
The EcoWorm project examines the effects of earthworm invasion on native forest ecosystems in northern North America (

). The invasion of non-native species is a common global-change driver and often causes local biodiversity change and loss (

, 

). Earlier studies on ecosystem consequences of non-native earthworm invasion have shown that these invasive ecosystem engineers cause adverse environmental conditions for other soil organisms (

) and decrease soil biodiversity (

). In 2016 and 2017, nematodes were collected from three Canadian forests and one 
US
forest. In each forest, ten plots were sampled in an area without (or with few) invasive earthworms and ten plots in an area with many earthworms (

). Soil nematode abundances showed a clear response to the invasion of earthworms. In three out of the four invaded forests, the abundance was reduced by at least -50 % compared to low-invaded forest areas (

). However, the response of the soil nematode sex ratio was less clear. Similar to abundance, we expected a more malebiased sex ratio in the earthworm-invaded forest areas, as the conditions in the invaded areas were less favorable for nematodes (

). Contrary to these expectations, nematode sex ratios generally did not change significantly and there was only one site where it declined in trend indicating more favorable conditions for females (Tab. 1).
</p>
         <p>

The MyDiv Experiment, set up in 2015, investigates the impact of different mycorrhizal 
types
on tree diversityecosystem functioning relationships (

). 
It
is located in 
Bad Lauchstädt
, 
Germany
. 
The
species pool of the 
MyDiv Experiment
contains ten deciduous tree species that are native to 
Central Europe
, with five species only associating with ectomycorrhizal (EM) fungi and five species only associating with arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi (

). 
Tree
species were planted in monoculture, two-, and four-species mixtures. 
Further
, these tree-diversity levels were established for AM trees only, EM trees only, and there were two-, and four-species mixtures of AM and EM trees. 
As
biodiversity generally increases ecosystem functioning and stability (

, 

, 

), biologically-diverse systems may be considered more favorable for soil communities than monocultures (

, 

). 
Therefore
, we expected the relative number of nematode females to increase along the tree-diversity gradient. 
First
data from 2019 support this expectation. 
Nematode
abundance increased from monocultures to four-species mixtures and in parallel the ratio of males to females declined (Tab. 1; unpubl. data). 
Even
though these results were statistically non-significant, the trend suggests that plant diversity might ameliorate environmental conditions for soil organisms (

, 

) and this is associated with an increased fraction of females in nematode communities. 
As
plant-diversity effects on ecosystem functions (

, 

) and soil communities (

, 

) may increase over time, long-term effects of plant diversity on nematode sex ratios need further attention

.
</p>
         <p>
The Jena Experiment located in the Saale river valley close to the city of Jena, 
Germany
, was established in 2002 to study the effects of plant diversity on ecosystem processes with the focus on element cycling and trophic interactions (

). In 82 plots, 60 mesophilic grassland species which are typical for Central European meadows are grown in 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, and 60 species mixtures comprising four functional plant groups (grasses, legumes, small forbs, and tall forbs). To account for changes in soil structure and texture on the 10-ha field site, the experiment was set up in a randomized block design, with the blocks accounting for different distances from the Saale river (

). Beginning in 2008, an experiment was set up in subplots to simulate summer drought conditions for approximately 4.5 weeks by excluding natural rainfall (

). The rain exclusion plots were equipped with rainout shelters; control plots also were equipped with shelters but received ambient rainwater (

). In 2013, a natural flood occurred at the site of the Jena Experiment lasting three weeks from May 30th to June 24th. The drought treatment started three months after the beginning of the flood when water had fully retreated from the plots. In 
September 2013
, the drought treatment caused a 41 % reduction in precipitation in comparison to the control treatment. While the soil-water content in the ambient (‘control’) subplot was 18 %, the drought subplots’ soil-water content was reduced to 8 %. We expected nematode sex ratios to be higher under simulated drought than under ambient conditions. Contrasting these expectations, data from 
September 2013
did not show any clear trend with the differences generally being not significant (Tab. 1). In trend, the sex ratio was higher in the drought thanintheambienttreatmentinmonoculturesand 4 species mixtures, whereas the opposite was true for the 16 and 60 species mixtures. With increasing plant-species richness, soil-aggregate stability associated with water infiltration (

) and top-soil water content increases (

), suggesting that unfavorable abiotic conditions caused by drought may be ameliorated in high-diversity plots (

, 

). Accordingly, 

found that high-diversity plant communities buffered negative effects of the prior flood on soil-nematode communities. Hence, stressful conditions imposed by the drought may have been reduced in the 16 and 60 species mixtures explaining why nematode sex ratios were not higher in the drought than in the control treatment.
</p>
         <p>
Five months after the flooding, in 
November 2013
, differences in soil-water content between drought and ambient subplots did not differ anymore, which is why we only analyzed nematodes of the control treatment for potential plant-diversity effects. As in the MyDiv Experiment, we expected nematode sex ratios to decrease with plant-species richness as high plant diversity is likely to be associated with more-favorable conditions for nematodes. In contrast to these expectations, the sex ratio was lowest in monocultures and highest in the 16 species mixtures, but these differences were not significant (Tab. 1). In future studies on nematode sex ratios, it may be important to differentiate the trophic guilds of nematodes, as plant diversity may have dissimilar effects on the functional composition of nematode communities, with higher abundances of plant-feeding nematodes in species-poor plant communities, but higher abundances of microbivorous nematodes, predators and omnivores at high plant diversity (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Conclusions and perspectives
</title>
         <p>
While searching for studies that met the criteria for inclusion in our review, we made several observations that are critical for future research on nematode sex ratio change in response to global-change drivers. First, we found that there are almost no replicated studies investigating environmental drivers of nematode sex ratios. Similarly, the drivers investigated typically were not related to climate-change factors, but included other stressors or environmental gradients. Most studies focused on plant-parasitic nematodes, while almost no data is available for free-living soil nematodes (but see 

; Tab. 1). Furthermore, most studies focused on nematode abundance, diversity, or functional/ trophic group composition, but not on nematode sex ratios. Even if data on sex ratios were provided, they usually were treated as additional information presented without underlying theory and hypotheses, without any reference to the several potential underlying mechanisms outlined in our introduction, as well as limited discussion (

). We propose that future studies should include clear hypotheses and test if the sex ratio of free-living nematodes increases with climate change due to more stressful environmental conditions and low resource availability (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>Besides their different resource needs, little is known about differences in the ecological roles of free-living male and female nematodes. Therefore, consequences of potential shifts in nematode sex ratios under future climate change conditions remain unknown, i.e., their consequences for ecosystem processes and services are unclear. To address this knowledge gap, experimental studies are needed that manipulate the sex ratio of free-living nematodes under climate-change conditions and explore the ecosystem consequences for decomposition, nutrient cycling, and plant growth. Understanding the climate-change driven consequences of shifts in nematode sex ratios is expected to improve predictions on how climate change affects belowground processes and their consequences for the aboveground world.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>

We acknowledge support of iDiv funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG– FZT 118, 202548816). OF, MJ, and NE gratefully acknowledge funding by the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation program (grant agreement no. 677232). The Jena Experiment is funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG; FOR 456, FOR 1451, FOR 5000). The GCEF is a large investment of the Helmholtz Association, funded by the 
Federal Ministry of Education
and Research, the 
State Ministry of Science
and Economy of 
Saxony-Anhalt

and the State Ministry for Higher Education, Research and the Arts of 
Saxony
.
</p>
         <p>
6. References
</p>
         <p>
Adams, B. J.
, 
D. H. Wall
, 
U. Gozel
, 
A. R. Dillman
, 
J. M. Chaston
&amp; 
I. D. Hogg
(
2007
): 

The southernmost worm, 
Scottnema lindsayae
(Nematoda): Diversity, dispersal and ecological stability

. – 
Polar Biology
30

: 
809–815
[
https://doi. org/10.1007/s00300-006-0241-3]
.

</p>
         <p>
Andriuzzi, W. S.
&amp; 
D. H. Wall
(
2018
). 
Soil biological responses to, and feedbacks on, trophic rewilding. Philosophical
– 
Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences
, 

373

: 
20170448
[
https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2017.0448]
.

</p>
         <p>
Anjam, M. S.
, 
S. J. Shah
, 
C. Matera
, 
E. Różańska
, 
M. Sobczak
, 
S. Siddique
&amp; 
F. M. W. Grundler
(
2020
): 

Host factors influence the sex of nematodes parasitizing roots of 
Arabidopsis thaliana

. – 
Plant, Cell &amp; Environment
43

: 
1160–1174
[
https:// doi.org/10.1111/pce.13728]
.

</p>
         <p>
Anwer, M. A.
, 
M. S. Anjam
, 
S. J. Shah
, 
M. S. Hasan
, 
A. A. Naz
, 
F. M. W. Grundler
&amp; 
S. Siddique
(
2018
): 
Genome-wide association study uncovers a novel QTL allele of AtS40-3 that affects the sex ratio of cyst nematodes in Arabidopsis
. – 
Journal of Experimental Botany
69

: 
1805–1814
[
https://doi. org/10.1093/jxb/ery019]
.

</p>
         <p>
Austin, B. U. R. T.
, 
R. Trivers
&amp; 
A. Burt
(
2009
): 
Genes in conflict: the biology of selfish genetic elements
. – 
Harvard University Press
.

</p>
         <p>
Ayres, E.
, 
D. H. Wall
, 
B. J. Adams
, 
J. E. Barrett
&amp; 
R. A.Virginia
(
2007
): 
Unique Similarity of Faunal Communities across Aquatic–Terrestrial Interfaces in a Polar Desert Ecosystem: Soil–Sediment Boundaries and Faunal Community
. – 
Ecosystems
10

: 
523–535
[
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10021- 007-9035-x]
.

</p>
         <p>
Bamforth, S. S.
, 
D. H. Wall
&amp; 
R.A. Virginia
(
2005
): 
Distribution and diversity of soil protozoa in the McMurdo Dry Valleys of Antarctica
. – 
Polar Biology
28

: 
756–762
[
https://doi. org/10.1007/s00300-005-0006-4]
.

</p>
         <p>
Bardgett, R. D.
&amp; 
W. H. van der Putten
(
2014
): 
Belowground biodiversity and ecosystem functioning
. – 
Nature
515

: 
505–511
[
https://doi.org/10.1038/nature13855]
.

</p>
         <p>
Barnett, T. P.
, 
J. C. Adam
&amp; 
D. P. Lettenmaier
(
2005
): 
Potential impacts of a warming climate on water availability in snowdominated regions
. – 
Nature
438

: 
303–309
[
https://doi. org/10.1038/nature04141]
.

</p>
         <p>
Bar-On, Y. M.
, 
R. Phillips
&amp; 
R. Milo
(
2018
): 
The biomass distribution on Earth
. – 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
115

: 
6506–6511
.

</p>
         <p>
Barrett, J. E.
, 
R. A. Virginia
, 
D. H. Wall
&amp; 
B. J. Adams
(
2008
): 
Decline in a dominant invertebrate species contributes to altered carbon cycling in a low-diversity soil ecosystem: CLIMATE-INDUCED DECLINE OF AN INVERTEBRATE SPECIES
. – 
Global Change Biology
14

: 
1734–1744
[
https:// doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2486.2008.01611.x]
.

</p>
         <p>
Bird, A. F.
(
1971
): 
Specialized adaptations of nematodes to parasitism
. p. 
47
. – In: 
B. M. Zuckerman
, 
W. F. Mai
&amp; 
R. A. Rohde
(eds): 
Plant Parasitic Nematodes. Volume II
. – 
Academic Press, New York
.

</p>
         <p>
Bird, D. M.
, 
V. M. Williamson
, 
P. Abad
, 
J. McCarter
, 
E. G. J. Danchin
, 
P. Castagnone-Sereno
&amp; 
C. H. Opperman
(
2009
): 
The genomes of root-knot nematodes
. – 
Annual Review of Phytopathology
47

: 
333–351
[
https://doi. org/10.1146/annurev-phyto-080508-081839]
.

</p>
         <p>
Blankinship, J. C.
, 
P. A. Niklaus
&amp; 
B. A. Hungate
(
2011
): 
A meta-analysis of responses of soil biota to global change
. 
2 Oecologia
165

: 
553–565
[
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442- 011-1909-0]
.

</p>
         <p>
Boström, S.
, 
O. Holovachov
&amp; 
S. A. Nadler
(
2011
): 
Description of Scottnema lindsayae Timm, 1971 (Rhabditida: Cephalobidae) from Taylor Valley, Antarctica and its phylogenetic relationship
. – 
Polar Biology
34

: 
1–12
[
https:// doi.org/10.1007/s00300-010-0850-8]
.

</p>
         <p>
Bürger, R.
(
1999
). 
Evolution of genetic variability and the advantage of sex and recombination in changing environments
. – 
Genetics
153
: 
1055–1069
</p>
         <p>
Cameron, E. K.
, 
I. S. Martins
, 
P. Lavelle
, 
J. Mathieu
, 
L. Tedersoo
, 
M. Bahram
, 
F. Gottschall
, 
C. A. Guerra
, 
J. Hines
, 
G. Patoine
&amp; et al. (
2019
): 
Global mismatches in aboveground and belowground biodiversity
. – 
Conservation Biology
33

: 
1187–1192
[
https://doi.org/10.1111/cobi.13311]
.

</p>
         <p>
Castagnone‐Sereno, P.
&amp; 
E. G. J. Danchin
(
2014
): 
Parasitic success without sex–the nematode experience
. – 
Journal of Evolutionary Biology
27

: 
1323–1333
.

</p>
         <p>
Cesarz, S.
, 
M. Ciobanu
, 
A. J. Wright
, 
A. Ebeling
, 
A. Vogel
, 
W. W.Weisser
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2017
): 
Plant species richness sustains higher trophic levels of soil nematode communities after consecutive environmental perturbations
. – 
Oecologia
184

: 
715–728
[
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-017-3893-5]
.

</p>
         <p>
Chahartaghi, M.
, 
M. Maraun
, 
S. Scheu
&amp; 
K. Domes
(
2009
): 
Resource depletion and colonization: a comparison between parthenogenetic and sexual Collembola species
. – 
Pedobiologia
52

: 
181–189
.

</p>
         <p>
Christie, J. R.
(
1929
): 
Some observations on sex in the Mermithidae
. – 
Journal of Experimental Zoology
53

: 
59–76
[
https://doi.org/10.1002/jez.1400530106]
.

</p>
         <p>
Cohen, J. M.
, 
M. J. Lajeunesse
&amp; 
J. R. Rohr
(
2018
): 
A global synthesis of animal phenological responses to climate change
. – 
Nature Climate Change
8

: 
224–228
[
https://doi. org/10.1038/s41558-018-0067-3]
.

</p>
         <p>
Cryan, W. S.
&amp; 
E. L. Hansen
(
1966
): 

Variation in Sex Ratio of 
Panagrellus redivivus
in Response To Nutritional and Heat Stress

. – 
Nematologica
12
: 
355–358
[
https://doi. org/10.1163/187529266X00824]
.

</p>
         <p>
Delgado-Baquerizo, M.
, 
C. A. Guerra
, 
C. Cano-Díaz
, 
E. Egidi
, 
J.-T. Wang
, 
N. Eisenhauer
, 
B. K. Singh
&amp; 
F. T. Maestre
(
2020
): 
The proportion of soil-borne pathogens increases with warming at the global scale
. – 
Nature Climate Change
10
: 
550–554
[
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-020-0759-3]
.

</p>
         <p>
Duffy, J. E.
, 
Godwin, C. M.
, &amp; 
Cardinale, B. J.
(
2017
). 
Biodiversity effects in the wild are common and as strong as key drivers of productivity
. 
Nature
549

: 
261–264
[
https://doi. org/10.1038/nature23886]
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
S. Partsch
, 
D. Parkinson
&amp; 
S. Scheu
(
2007
): 
Invasion of a deciduous forest by earthworms: Changes in soil chemistry, microflora, microarthropods and vegetation
. – 
Soil Biology and Biochemistry
39

: 
1099–1110
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.soilbio.2006.12.019]
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
O. Ferlian
, 
D. Craven
, 
J. Hines
&amp; 
M. Jochum
(
2019
): 
Ecosystem responses to exotic earthworm invasion in northern North American forests
. – 
Research Ideas and Outcomes
5

: e 
34564
[
https://doi.org/10.3897/rio.5.e34564]
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
V. D. Migunova
, 
M. Ackermann
, 
L. Ruess
&amp; 
S. Scheu
(
2011
): 
Changes in plant species richness induce functional shifts in soil nematode communities in experimental grassland
. – 
Plos one
6

: e 
24087
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
S. Herrmann
, 
J. Hines
, 
F. Buscot
, 
J. Siebert
&amp; 
M. P. Thakur
(
2018
): 
The Dark Side of Animal Phenology
. 
Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution
33

: 
898–901
[
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.tree.2018.09.010]
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
T. Dobies
, 
S. Cesarz
, 
S. E. Hobbie
, 
R. J. Meyer
, 
K. Worm
&amp; 
P. B. Reich
(
2013
): 

Plant diversity effects on soil food webs are stronger than those of elevated CO 
2
and N deposition in a long-term grassland experiment

. – 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
110

: 
6889–6894
[
https:// doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1217382110]
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
F. Buscot
, 
A. Heintz‐Buschart
, 
S. D. Jurburg
, 
K. Küsel
, 
J. Sikorski
, 
H. Vogel
&amp; 
C. A. Guerra
(
2020
): 
The multidimensionality of soil macroecology
. – 
Global Ecology and Biogeography
30

: 
4–10
[
https://doi.org/10.1111/ geb.13211]
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
H. Bessler
, 
C. Engels
, 
G. Gleixner
, 
M. Habekost
, 
A. Milcu
, 
S. Partsch
, 
A. C. W. Sabais
, 
C. Scherber
, 
S. Steinbeiss
&amp; et al. (
2010
): 
Plant diversity effects on soil microorganisms support the singular hypothesis
. – 
Ecology
91

: 
485–496
[
https://doi.org/10.1890/08-2338.1]
.

</p>
         <p>
Ellenby, C.
(
1954
): 
Environmental determination of the sex ratio of a plant parasitic nematode
. – 
Nature
174

: 
1016–1017
.

</p>
         <p>
Ferlian, O.
, 
S. Cesarz
, 
D. Craven
, 
J. Hines
, 
K. E. Barry
, 
H. Bruelheide
, 
F. Buscot
, 
S. Haider
, 
H. Heklau
, 
S. Herrmann
&amp; et al. (
2018
a): 
Mycorrhiza in tree diversity–ecosystem function relationships: Conceptual framework and experimental implementation
. – 
Ecosphere
9

[
https://doi. org/10.1002/ecs2.2226]
.

</p>
         <p>
Ferlian, O.
, 
N. Eisenhauer
, 
M. Aguirrebengoa
, 
M. Camara
, 
I. Ramirez‐Rojas
, 
F. Santos
, 
K. Tanalgo
&amp; 
M. P. Thakur
(
2018
b): 
Invasive earthworms erode soil biodiversity: A meta‐analysis
. – 
Journal of Animal Ecology
87

: 
162–172
[
https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2656.12746]
.

</p>
         <p>
Ferris, H.
, 
T. Bongers
&amp; 
R. G. M. de Goede
(
2001
): 
A framework for soil food web diagnostics: Extension of the nematode faunal analysis concept
. – 
Applied Soil Ecology
18

: 
13–29
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0929-1393(01)00152-4]
.

</p>
         <p>
Foreman, C. M.
, 
C. F. Wolf
&amp; 
J. C. Priscu
(
2004
): 
Impact of Episodic Warming Events on the Physical, Chemical and Biological Relationships of Lakes in the McMurdo Dry Valleys, Antarctica
. – 
Aquatic Geochemistry
10

: 
239–268
.

</p>
         <p>
Freckman, D. W.
&amp; 
E. P. Caswell
(
1985
): 
The Ecology of Nematodes in Agroecosystems
. – 
Annual Review of Phytopathology
23

: 
275–296
.

</p>
         <p>
George, P. B. L.
, 
D. Lallias
, 
S. Creer
, 
F. M. Seaton
, 
J. G. Kenny
, 
R. M. Eccles
, 
R. I. Griffiths
, 
I. Lebron
, 
B. A. Emmett
, 
D.A. Robinson
&amp; 
D. L. Jones
(
2019
): 
Divergent national-scale trends of microbial and animal biodiversity revealed across diverse temperate soil ecosystems
. – 
Nature Communications
10

: 
1107
[
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-019-09031-1]
.

</p>
         <p>
Golestaninasab, M.
, 
M. Malek
, 
B. Jalali
&amp; 
I. Mobedi
(
2012
): 

Variation in the sex ratio of 
Rhabdochona fortunatowi
(Spirurida: Rhabdochonidae) in 
Capoeta capoeta gracilis
(Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae), relative to levels of infection, host size and temperature

. – 
Journal of Helminthology
86

: 
41–45
[
https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022149X11000010]
.

</p>
         <p>
Grundler, F.
, 
M. Betka
&amp; 
U. Wyss
(
1991
): 

Influence of changes in the nurse cell system (syncytium) on sex determination and development of the cyst nematode 
Heterodera schachtii
: Total amounts of proteins and amino acids

. – 
Phytopathology
81

: 
70–74
[
https://doi.org/10.1094/Phyto-81-70]
.

</p>
         <p>
Guerrero-Ramírez, N. R.
, 
D. Craven
, 
P. B. Reich
, 
J. J. Ewel
, 
F. Isbell
, 
J. Koricheva
, 
J. A. Parrotta
, 
H. Auge
, 
H. E. Erickson
, 
D. I. Forrester
&amp; et al. (
2017
): 
Diversity-dependent temporal divergence of ecosystem functioning in experimental ecosystems
. – 
Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution
1

: 
1639–1642
[
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-017-0325-1]
.

</p>
         <p>
Hansen, E. L.
, 
E. J. Buecher
&amp; 
E. A. Yarwood
(
1972
): 

Sex differentiation of 
Aphelenchus avenae
in axenic culture

. – 
Nematologica
18

: 
253–260
[
https://doi. org/10.1163/187529272X00485]
.

</p>
         <p>
Hardy, I. C. W.
(
2002
): 
Sex Ratios: Concepts and Research Methods
– 
Cambridge University Press
: 
424 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Heethoff, M.
, 
R. A. Norton
, 
S. Scheu
&amp; 
M. Maraun
(
2009
): 
Parthenogenesis in oribatid mites (Acari, Oribatida): evolution without sex
. – In: 
Lost Sex
. – 
Springer, Dordrecht
: 
241–257
.

</p>
         <p>
IPCC
(
2021
): 
Climate Change 2021: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Sixth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change
. – 
Cambridge University Press
.

</p>
         <p>
IPBES
(
2019
): 
Global assessment report on biodiversity and ecosystem services of the Intergovernmental Science- Policy – Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services. IPBES secretariat, Bonn
, 
Germany
: 
1148 pp.
[
https://doi. org/10.5281/zenodo.3831673]
.

</p>
         <p>
Isbell, F.
, 
A. Gonzalez
, 
M. Loreau
, 
J. Cowles
, 
S. Díaz
, 
A. Hector
, 
G. M. Mace
, 
D. A. Wardle
, 
M. I. O’Connor
, 
J. E. Duffy
, 
L. A. Turnbull
, 
P. L. Thompson
&amp; 
A. Larigauderie
(
2017
): 
Linking the influence and dependence of people on biodiversity across scales
. – 
Nature
546

: 
65–72
[
https://doi. org/10.1038/nature22899]
.

</p>
         <p>
Kahel-Raifer, H.
&amp; 
I. Glazer
(
2000
): 

Environmental factors affecting sexual differentiation in the entomopathogenic nematode 
Heterorhabditis bacteriophora

. – 
Journal of Experimental Zoology
287

: 
158–166
.

</p>
         <p>
Kapranas, A.
, 
B. Malone
, 
S. Quinn
, 
L. Mc Namara
, 
C. D. Williams
, 
P. O’Tuama
, 
A. Peters
&amp; 
C. T. Griffin
(
2017
): 

Efficacy of entomopathogenic nematodes for control of large pine weevil, 
Hylobius abietis
: Effects of soil type, pest density and spatial distribution

. – 
Journal of Pest Science
90

: 
495–505
[
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10340-016-0823-y]
.

</p>
         <p>
Jochum, M.
, 
O. Ferlian
, 
M. P. Thakur
, 
M. Ciobanu
, 
B. Klarner
, 
J.-A. Salamon
, 
L. E. Frelich
, 
E. A. Johnson
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2021
): 
Earthworm invasion causes declines across soil fauna size classes and biodiversity facets in northern North American forests
. – 
Oikos
130

: 
766–780
.

</p>
         <p>
Jones, J. T.
, 
A. Haegeman
, 
E. G. J. Danchin
, 
H. S. Gaur
, 
J. Helder
, 
M. G. K. Jones
, 
T. Kikuchi
, 
R. Manzanilla-López
, 
J. E. Palomares-Rius
, 
W. M. L. Wesemael
&amp; 
R. N. Perry
(
2013
): 
Top 10 plant-parasitic nematodes in molecular plant pathology
. – 
Molecular Plant Pathology
14

: 
946–961
[
https:// doi.org/10.1111/mpp.12057]
.

</p>
         <p>
Lange, M.
, 
M. Habekost
, 
N. Eisenhauer
, 
C. Roscher
, 
H. Bessler
, 
C. Engels
, 
Y. Oelmann
, 
S. Scheu
, 
W. Wilcke
, 
E.-D. Schulze
&amp; 
G. Gleixner
(
2014
): 
Biotic and Abiotic Properties Mediating Plant Diversity Effects on Soil Microbial Communities in an Experimental Grassland
. – 
PLoS ONE
9

: e 
96182
[
https://doi. org/10.1371/journal.pone.0096182]
.

</p>
         <p>
Laughlin, C.W.
, 
A. S. Williams
&amp; 
J. A.Fox
(
1969
): 

The Influence of Temperature on Development and Sex Differentiation of 
Meloidogyne graminis

. – 
Journal of Nematology
1

: 
212–215
.

</p>
         <p>
Lyons, W. B.
, 
K. A. Welch
, 
A. E.Carey
, 
P. T. Doran
, 
D. H. Wall
, 
R. A.Virginia
, 
A. G. Fountain
, 
B. M. Csathó
&amp; 
C. M. Tremper
(
2005
): 
Groundwater seeps in Taylor Valley Antarctica: An example of a subsurface melt event
. – 
Annals of Glaciology
40

: 
200–206
[
https://doi.org/10.3189/ 172756405781813609]
.

</p>
         <p>
Maynard Smith, J.
(
1978
): 
The evolution of sex
. – 
Cambridge University Press
.

</p>
         <p>
McClure, M. A.
&amp; 
D. R. Viglierchio
(
1966
): 

The Influenceof host nutrition and intensity of infection on the sex ratio and development of 
Meloidogyne incognita
in sterile agar cultures of excised cucumber roots

. – 
Nematologica
12

: 
248–258
.

</p>
         <p>
McSorley,R.
(
2003
): 
Adaptations of nematodes to environmental extremes
. – 
Florida Entomologist
86

: 
138–142
.

</p>
         <p>
Michiels, I. C.
&amp; 
W. Traunspurger
(
2005
): 
Benthic community patterns and the composition of feeding types and reproductive modes in freshwater nematodes
. – 
Nematology
7

: 
21–36
[
https://doi.org/10.1163/1568541054192234]
.

</p>
         <p>
Moens, T.
, 
A. Vierstraete
&amp; 
M. Vincx
(
1996
): 
Life Strategies in Two Bacterivorous Marine Nematodes: Preliminary Results
. – 
Marine Ecology
17

: 
509–518
[
https://doi. org/10.1111/j.1439-0485.1996.tb00524.x]
.

</p>
         <p>
Morran, L. T.
, 
B. J. Cappy
, 
J. L. Anderson
&amp; 
P. C. Phillips
(
2009
): 

Sexual partners for the stressed: facultative outcrossing in the self‐fertilizing nematode 
Caenorhabditis elegans

. – 
Evolution: International Journal of Organic Evolution
63

: 
1473–1482
.

</p>
         <p>
Mote, P. W.
, 
A. F. Hamlet
, 
M. P. Clark
&amp; 
D. P. Lettenmaier
(
2005
): 
Declining mountain snowpack in Western North America
. – 
Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society
86

: 
39–50
[
https://doi.org/10.1175/BAMS-86-1-39]
.

</p>
         <p>
Mulder, C. P. H.
, 
D. D. Uliassi
&amp; 
D. F. Doak
(
2001
): 
Physical stress and diversity-productivity relationships: The role of positive interactions
. – 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
98

: 
6704–6708
[
https://doi.org/10.1073/ pnas.111055298]
.

</p>
         <p>
Müller, J.
, 
K. Rehbock
&amp; 
U. Wyss
(
1981
): 

Growth of 
Heterodera schachtii
with remarks on amounts of food consumed

. – 
Revue de Nematologie
4

: 
227–234
.

</p>
         <p>
Murphy, G. E. P.
&amp; 
T. N. Romanuk
(
2014
): 
A meta‐analysis of declines in local species richness from human disturbances
. 
Ecology and Evolution
4

: 
91–103
[
https://doi.org/10.1002/ ece3.909]
.

</p>
         <p>
Neher, D. A.
(
2001
): 
Role of nematodes on soil health and their use as indicators
. – 
Journal of Nematology
33

: 
161–168
.

</p>
         <p>
Orgiazzi, A.
, 
R. D. Bardgett
&amp; 
E. Barrios
(
2016
): 
Global soil biodiversity atlas
. – 
European Commission; CABDirect
.

</p>
         <p>
Overhoff, A.
, 
D. W. Freckman
&amp; 
R. A. Virginia
(
1993
): 
Life cycle of the microbivorous Antarctic Dry Valley nematode Scottnema lindsayae (Timm 1971)
: – 
Polar Biology
13

: 
151– 156
[
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00238924]
.

</p>
         <p>
Pen-Mouratov, S.
, 
N. Shukurov
, 
J. Yu
, 
S. Rakhmonkulova
, 
O. Kodirov
, 
G. Barness
, 
M. Kersten
&amp; 
Y. Steinberger
(
2014
): 
Successive development of soil ecosystems at abandoned coal-ash landfills
. – 
Ecotoxicology
23

: 
880–897
[
https://doi. org/10.1007/s10646-014-1227-5]
.

</p>
         <p>
Pérès, G.
, 
D. Cluzeau
, 
S. Menasseri
, 
J. F. Soussana
, 
H. Bessler
, 
C. Engels
, 
M. Habekost
, 
G. Gleixner
, 
A. Weigelt
, 
W. W. Weisser
, 
S. Scheu
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2013
): 
Mechanisms linking plant community properties to soil aggregate stability in an experimental grassland plant diversity gradient
. – 
Plant and Soil
373

: 
285–299
[
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11104-013- 1791-0]
.

</p>
         <p>
Phillips, H. R. P.
, 
C. A. Guerra
, 
M. L. C. Bartz
, 
M. J. I. Briones
, 
G. Brown
, 
T. W. Crowther
, 
O. Ferlian
, 
K. B. Gongalsky
, 
J. van den Hoogen
, 
J. Krebs
&amp; et al. (
2019
): 
Global distribution of earthworm diversity
. – 
Science
366

: 
480–485
[
https://doi. org/10.1126/science.aax4851
</p>
         <p>
Porazinska, D. L.
, 
D. H. Wall
&amp; 
R. A. Virginia
(
2002
): 
Population Age Structure of Nematodes in the Antarctic Dry Valleys: Perspectives on Time, Space, and Habitat Suitability
. – 
Arctic, Antarctic, and Alpine Research
34

: 
159–168
[
https:// doi.org/10.1080/15230430.2002.12003480]
.

</p>
         <p>
Reich, P. B.
, 
D. Tilman
, 
F. Isbell
, 
K. Mueller
, 
S. E. Hobbie
, 
D. F. B. Flynn
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2012
): 
Impacts of Biodiversity Loss Escalate Through Time as Redundancy Fades
. – 
Science
336

: 
589–592
[
https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1217909
</p>
         <p>
Roscher, C.
, 
J. Schumacher
, 
J. Baade
, 
W. Wilcke
, 
G. Gleixner
, 
W. W. Weisser
, 
B. Schmid
&amp; 
E.-D. Schulze
(
2004
): 
The role of biodiversity for element cycling and trophic interactions: An experimental approach in a grassland community
. – 
Basic and Applied Ecology
5

: 
107–121
[
https://doi.org/10.1078/1439- 1791-00216
</p>
         <p>
Schädler, M.
, 
F. Buscot
, 
S. Klotz
, 
T. Teitz
, 
W. Durka
, 
J. Bumberger
, 
I. Merbach
, 
S. G. Michalski
, 
K. Kirsch
, 
P. Remmler
, 
E. Schulz
&amp; 
H. Auge
(
2019
): 
Investigating the consequences of climate change under different land-use regimes: a novel experimental infrastructure
. – 
Ecosphere
10

: e 
02635
.

</p>
         <p>
Scherber, C.
, 
N. Eisenhauer
, 
W. W. Weisser
, 
B. Schmid
, 
W. Voigt
, 
M. Fischer
, 
E.-D. Schulze
, 
C. Roscher
, 
A. Weigelt
, 
E. Allan
&amp; et al. (
2010
): 
Bottom-up effects of plant diversity on multitrophic interactions in a biodiversity experiment
. – 
Nature
468

: 
553–556
[
https://doi.org/10.1038/nature09492
</p>
         <p>
Scheu, S.
&amp; 
B. Drossel
(
2007
): 
Sexual reproduction prevails in a world of structured resources in short supply
. – 
Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences
274

: 
1225–1231
[
https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2007.0040]
.

</p>
         <p>
Schroeder, F.
, 
L. Peters
&amp; 
W. Traunspurger
(
2013
): 
Nematodes in the periphyton of lakes: Variations in diversity, species composition, age structure, and sex ratio
. – 
International Review of Hydrobiology
98

: 
322–333
[
https://doi. org/10.1002/iroh.201301652]
.

</p>
         <p>
Schwanz, L.E.
&amp; 
A.Georges
(
2021
): 
SexualDevelopmentand the Environment: Conclusions from 40 Years of Theory
. – 
Sexual Development
15

: 
7–22
[
https://doi.org/10.1159/000515221]
.

</p>
         <p>
Siebert, J.
, 
M. Ciobanu
, 
M. Schädler
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2020
): 
Climate change and land use induce functional shifts in soil nematode communities
. – 
Oecologia
192
: 
281–294
[
https:// doi.org/10.1007/s00442-019-04560-4]
.

</p>
         <p>
Simmons, B. L.
, 
D. H. Wall
, 
B. J. Adams
, 
E. Ayres
, 
J. E. Barrett
&amp; 
R. A. Virginia
(
2009
): 
Long-term experimental warming reduces soil nematode populations in the McMurdo Dry Valleys, Antarctica
. – 
Soil Biology and Biochemistry
41

: 
2052–2060
[
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.soilbio.2009.07.009]
.

</p>
         <p>
Singh, S. K.
, 
M. Hodda
, 
G. J. Ash
&amp; 
N. C. Banks
(
2013
): 
Plant-parasitic nematodes as invasive species: Characteristics, uncertainty and biosecurity implications
. – 
Annals of Applied Biology
28
.

</p>
         <p>
Song, Y.
, 
B. Drossel
&amp; 
S. Scheu
(
2011
): 
Tangled Bank dismissed too early
. – 
Oikos
120

: 
1601–1607
.

</p>
         <p>
Spaak, J. W.
, 
J. M. Baert
, 
D. J. Baird
, 
N. Eisenhauer
, 
L. Maltby
, 
F. Pomati
, 
V. Radchuk
, 
J. R. Rohr
, 
P. J. Van den Brink
&amp; 
F. De Laender
(
2017
): 
Shifts of community composition and population density substantially affect ecosystem function despite invariant richness
. – 
Ecology Letters
20

: 
1315–1324
[
https://doi.org/10.1111/ele.12828]
.

</p>
         <p>
Stearns, S. C.
&amp; 
R. F. Hoekstra
(
2005
): 
Evolution, an introduction
. – 
Oxford University Press
.

</p>
         <p>
Thakur, M. P.
, 
A. Milcu
, 
P. Manning
, 
P. A. Niklaus
, 
C. Roscher
, 
S. Power
, 
P. B. Reich
, 
S. Scheu
, 
D. Tilman
, 
F. Ai
&amp; et al. (
2015
): 
Plant diversity drives soil microbial biomass carbon in grasslands irrespective of global environmental change factors
. – 
Global Change Biology
21

: 
4076–4085
[
https:// doi.org/10.1111/gcb.13011]
.

</p>
         <p>
Thomas, C. G.
, 
G. C. Woodruff
&amp; 
E. S. Haag
(
2012
): 

Causes and consequences of the evolution of reproductive mode in 
Caenorhabditis
nematodes

. – 
Trends in Genetics
28

: 
213–220
.

</p>
         <p>
Tilman, D.
, 
F. Isbell
&amp; 
J. M. Cowles
(
2014
). 
Biodiversity and Ecosystem Functioning. Annual Review of Ecology
, 
Evolution, and Systematics
45

: 
471–493
[
https://doi. org/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-120213-091917]
.

</p>
         <p>
Traunspurger, W.
(
1998
): 

Distribution and Sex Ratio of 
Ethmolaimus pratensis
De Man, 1880 (Nematoda, Chromadorida) in an Oligotrophic Lake

. – 
Nematologica
44

: 
391–408
[
https://doi.org/10.1163/005525998X00061]
.

</p>
         <p>
Treonis, A. M.
, 
D. H. Wall
&amp; 
R. A. Virginia
(
1999
): 
Invertebrate Biodiversity in Antarctic Dry Valley Soils and Sediments
. – 
Ecosystems
2

: 
482–492
.

</p>
         <p>
Triantaphyllou, A. C.
(
1960
): 

Sex determination in 
Meloidogyne incognita
Chitwood, 1949 and intersexuality in 
M. javanica
(Treub, 1985) Chitwood

, 1949. – 
Annales de l’Institut Phytopathologique Benaki
3

: 
12–31
.

</p>
         <p>
Triantaphyllou, A. C.
&amp; 
H. Hirschmann
(
1964
): 
Reproduction in Plant and Soil Nematodes
. – 
Annual Review of Phytopathology
2

: 
57–80
[
https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev. py.02.090164.000421]
.

</p>
         <p>
Triantaphyllou, A. C.
(
1973
): 
Environmental Sex Differentiation of Nematodes in Relation to Pest Management
. – 
Annual Review of Phytopathology
11

: 
441–462
[
https://doi. org/10.1146/annurev.py.11.090173.002301]
.

</p>
         <p>
Trudgill, D. L.
(
1967
): 

The Effect of Environment On Sex Determination in 
Heterodera rostochiensis

. – 
Nematologica
13

: 
263–272
[
https://doi.org/10.1163/187529267X00120
</p>
         <p>
Tyler, J.
(
1933
): 
Development of the root-knot nematode as affected by temperature
. – 
Hilgardia
7

: 
389–415
[
https://doi. org/10.3733/hilg.v07n10p389]
.

</p>
         <p>
van den Hoogen, J.
, 
S. Geisen
, 
D. Routh
, 
H. Ferris
, 
W. Traunspurger
, 
D. A. Wardle
, 
R. G. M. de Goede
, 
B. J. Adams
, 
W. Ahmad
, 
W. S. Andriuzzi
&amp; et al. (
2019
): 
Soil nematode abundance and functional group composition at a global scale
. – 
Nature
572

: 
194–198
[
https://doi.org/10.1038/ s41586-019-1418-6]
.

</p>
         <p>
Veresoglou, S. D.
, 
J. M. Halley
&amp; 
M. C. Rillig
(
2015
): 
Extinction risk of soil biota
. – 
Nature Communications
6

: 
8862
[
https:// doi.org/10.1038/ncomms9862
</p>
         <p>
Vogel, A.
, 
N. Eisenhauer
, 
A. Weigelt
&amp; 
M. Scherer-Lorenzen
(
2013
): 
Plant diversity does not buffer drought effects on early-stage litter mass loss rates and microbial properties
. – 
Global Change Biology
19

: 
2795–2803
[
https://doi. org/10.1111/gcb.12225]
.

</p>
         <p>
Wagg, C.
, 
S. F. Bender
, 
F. Widmer
&amp; 
M. G. A. van der Heijden
(
2014
): 
Soil biodiversity and soil community composition determine ecosystem multifunctionality
. – 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
111

: 
5266–5270
[
https://doi. org/10.1073/pnas.1320054111]
.

</p>
         <p>
Wall, D. H.
(
2007
): 
Global change tipping points: Above- and below-ground biotic interactions in a low diversity ecosystem
. – 
Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences
362

: 
2291–2306
[
https://doi.org/10.1098/ rstb.2006.1950]
.

</p>
         <p>
Wall, J. W.
, 
K. R. Skene
&amp; 
R. Neilson
(
2002
): 
Nematode community and trophic structure along a sand dune succession
. – 
Biology and Fertility of Soils
35

: 
293–301
.

</p>
         <p>
Wall, D. H.
, 
R. D. Bardgett
, 
V. Behan-Pelletier
, 
J. E. Herrick
, 
T. H. Jones
, 
K. Ritz
, 
J. Six
, 
D. R. Strong
&amp; 
W. van der Putten
(
2012
): 
Soil ecology and ecosystem services
. – 
Oxford University Press
.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
