<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Soil Organisms</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25674/so92iss2pp99</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Effects of steam sterilization on soil abiotic and biotic properties</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cephalobus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aporcelaimellus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aglenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hoplotylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pratylenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cephalobus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pratylenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Acrobeloides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cephalobus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucephalobus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aphelenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tylencholaimus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eudorylaimus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Thornia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aporcelaimellus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aglenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Boleodorus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Paratylenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tylenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bitylenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Helicotylenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hoplotylus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pratylenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Effects of steam sterilization on soil abiotic and biotic properties
</p>
         <p>
Peter Dietrich
1,2,
*, 
Simone Cesarz
2,3
, 
Nico Eisenhauer
2,3
and 
Christiane Roscher
1,2
</p>
         <p>
1
UFZ, Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research, Physiological Diversity, Permoserstrasse 15, 04318 Leipzig, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
2
German Centre of Integrative Biodiversity Research (iDiv) Halle-Jena-Leipzig, Deutscher Platz 5e, 04103 Leipzig, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
3
Institute of Biology, Leipzig University, Deutscher Platz 5e, 04103 Leipzig, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>* Corresponding author, e-mail: peter.dietrich@idiv.de</p>
         <p>
Received 
5 March 2020
| Accepted 
16 June 2020
</p>
         <p>
Published online at www.soil-organisms.de 


1 August 
2020

| Printed version 
15 August 2020
</p>
         <p>
DOI 
10.25674/so92iss2pp99
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Abstract
</title>
         <p>
Experiments under natural conditions are becoming increasingly important to investigate the impacts of global change on biodiversity and ecosystem functioning, but field experiments are not always feasible. Climate or biodiversity chamber experiments can be an alternative, which, however, require large amounts of soil substrate. If only low amounts of target soil are available, high quantities of background soil must be sterilized and inoculated with target soil. One of the commonly used methods to sterilize large amounts of background soil is steam sterilization, because it is simple, fast and cheap. However, there is a lack of knowledge, whether steam sterilization is an effective method to completely eliminate all organisms in the soil (in particular heat-resistant organisms) as well as if and how it alters soil abiotic conditions like nutrient concentrations. Therefore, we tested which organisms survived the sterilization treatment and if the effectiveness can be improved by repeated steam sterilization. Additionally, we checked whether steam sterilization changes soil pH, carbon and nutrient concentrations, and whether this is strengthened by a double sterilization treatment. To study this, we steam-sterilized 
2 m
3
sand-soil mix (1:4) for 150 min, stored it for 12 days at ambient temperature (for the germination of heat-resistant organisms) and repeated the sterilization procedure. We found a 27 % reduction in microbial biomass carbon after the first sterilization treatment and a 51 % reduction after the second sterilization treatment compared to untreated soil. Nematodes were almost completely eliminated (97 % after second treatment), while rotifers largely remained unchanged. Soil pH and plant-available phosphorus concentration increased after the first sterilization treatment (pH: from 7.44 to 7.79; phosphorus: +28 %). Phosphorus concentration increased further after the second sterilization treatment (+53 % compared to untreated soil), while pH remained unchanged (7.77). Plant-available potassium and total carbon concentrations decreased after the first treatment (potassium: -19 %; carbon: -5 %), while total carbon further decreased (-8 % compared to untreated soil) and potassium remained unchanged after the second treatment. Taken together, our study highlights that (single and double) steam-sterilization treatments were only partially effective, i.e. non-complete elimination of soil organisms, and additionally influenced soil properties. Nevertheless, steam sterilization is a fast and cost-effective alternative to other sterilization methods, especially when large amounts of soil substrate are needed. Therefore, if so, we recommend to use steam sterilization, but to sterilize the soil twice to significantly reduce the number of soil organisms, and further consider potential side effects, such as an increase in plant-available phosphorous concentration.
</p>
         <p>
Keywords
microbial biomass
| 
nematodes
| 
plant-available phosphorus
| 
plant-available potassium
| 
soil biodiversity
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
There is a rising need for experiments under controlled environmental conditions studying the effect of global change on above- and belowground organisms and on their interactions (

, 

, 

). Such experiments should be performed under natural field conditions as far as possible (

), but this is not always feasible (e.g. when investigating the impact of increased atmospheric CO 
2
concentration) or preliminary or partial experiments are necessary. In such cases, the field studies can be prepared or supplemented with greenhouse, climate chamber or biodiversity chamber experiments (

, 

). These experiments require large amounts of soil substrate, which is prepared by inoculating sterilized soil (= background soil) with target soil, if only low amounts of target soil are available, e.g. due to small size of research plots, long-distance transport or nature conservation requirements. Common sterilization methods to produce background soil are autoclaving, gamma- or steam sterilization (

, 

). The latter one is often used when high quantities of soil substrate are needed, because it is fast and cheap, compared to the other two methods. Thereby, hot water steam flows across the soil with the aim of eliminating all viable organisms (soil biota, plant seeds, etc.), but there is a risk that heat-resistant organisms might survive (

). Furthermore, it is well known that sterilization can lead to nutrient flushes (

, 

, 

), which could influence the outcome of the experiment. Despite this knowledge, there is a lack of experiments exploring the efficiency of steam sterilization in eliminating soil biota (in particular heat-resistant organisms) and evaluating its influence on soil properties.
</p>
         <p>
We tested in this study whether the effectiveness of steam sterilization can be improved by repeated sterilization. We steam-sterilized soil for 150 min at ~80°C and then stored the substrate for 12 days at ambient temperature. This incubation was intended to lead to the germination of heat-resistant spores of protozoa, bacteria and fungi and hatching of nematodes from resistant eggs (

). The second sterilization treatment (same sterilization procedure) was then performed to eliminate the germinated/remaining soil biota (

). To evaluate the effectiveness of single and double steam-sterilization treatments, we investigated soil microbial properties (microbial biomass, microbial basal respiration, microbial community composition) as well as abundance of nematodes and rotifers before and after the treatments. Furthermore, we tested whether single steam sterilization causes nutrient flushes (soil total nitrogen, plant-available phosphorus and potassium) or changes in soil properties (soil carbon, soil pH, soil water content), and if so, whether this is strengthened by a double steam-sterilization treatment.
</p>
         <p>We hypothesized, that (1) the abundance and activity of viable organisms is partly reduced after the first steam-sterilization treatment and completely reduced after second sterilization treatment. Furthermore, we expected (2) a gradual increase in soil carbon, nutrient concentrations and soil water content with each sterilization treatment, while soil pH is not significantly affected.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Materials and methods
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Sterilization of background soil
</title>
         <p>

In 

May 2017

, soil substrate (

1.6 m
3
) for the steam sterilization was collected from a biodiversity experiment (
Jena Experiment
) in 
Jena
(
Thuringia
, 
Germany
, 
50° 55′N
, 
11° 35′E
, 

130 m
a.s.l.

) nearby the 
river Saale. The
soil of the study site is a 
Eutric Fluvisol
which ranges from sandy loam to silty clay with increasing distance to the river (sand content: 40–7 %; silt: 44–69 %; clay: 16–24 %; 

). 
Before
the establishment of the biodiversity experiment in 2002, the site was used as arable land for about 40 years and heavily fertilized (

). 
We
used a mix of excavated soil material from different experimental plots for this study, which was stored for several years outside at the experimental area. 
The
soil substrate was transported to the 
Helmholtz
research station 
Bad Lauchstädt
(Saxony- 
Anhalt
), sieved to 
10 mm
and mixed with 

0.4 m
3
quartz sand (
0.25–0.5 mm
grain size, WF 33, 
Quarzwerke
GmbH, 
Walbeck
, 
Germany
). 
After
mixing, we took a soil sample (around 
200 g
), which was stored in a fridge (4°C) until further processing (untreated soil with 20 % sand = sample A)

.
</p>
         <p>
On
29 June 2017

, the soil-sand mix was steam-sterilized for 150 minutes at ~80°C (= single steam-sterilization treatment) using a modified tipping trailer (EDK 36, 
Münz Fahrzeugbau
GmbH &amp; 
Co KG
, 
Pliezhausen
, 
Germany
) with a steam boiler (S 250, Möschle-Seifert- 
Dämpftechnik AG
, 
Durbach
, 
Germany
) equipped with an oil burner (WL 30 Z, 
Max Weishaupt
GmbH, 
Schwendi
, 
Germany
) and an insulating plastic cover to retain the heat (
Fig. 1
). 
After
cooling down, the substrate was stored in four closeable plastic boxes (each of 

0.6 m
3
size). Four soil samples (around 
50 g
from each box) were taken, pooled and stored in a fridge (4°C; immediately after the first sterilization = sample B). The soil substrate was let rest for 12 days at ambient temperature to allow heat-resistant permanent states of soil biota to germinate. On 

11 July 2017

, i.e. 12 days later, the soil was steam-sterilized a second time using the same procedure as before (= double steam-sterilization treatment). The soil was again stored in the plastic boxes, which were sterilized with a potassium hypochlorite solution (

Eau 
de Javel

: 
2.6 g
KClO to 100 ml water; 1:1) before filling. After the second steam-sterilization treatment as well as after two additional weeks of storage in the boxes at ambient temperature, four soil samples per box were taken (
50 g
each), pooled per treatment (immediately after second sterilization (= sample C) and two weeks after second sterilization (= sample D)) and stored in the fridge (4°C). Microbial community composition was analyzed via phospholipid fatty acid analysis (PLFA); therefore, 
25 g
soil per sample (samples A–D) were frozen at -80°C until further processing

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Soil biota
</title>
         <p>
To determine community composition and activity of soil biota before as well as after first and second steam sterilization, we used soil samples of A, B, C and D. All samples (A–D) were replicated five times with the exception of PLFA analysis (three replicates per sample). For analyses of soil microbial properties, the soil was sieved at 
2 mm
. Basal respiration (BAS) characterizing soil microbial activity and soil microbial biomass carbon (C 
mic
) as important soil ecosystem functions (Eisenhauer et al. 2018) were measured after 

using an O 
2
-microcompensation apparatus. Furthermore, determination of the soil microbial community was done via phospholipid fatty acid analysis (PLFA) following the protocol of 

. For analyses of free-living nematodes and rotifers, the soil was sieved to 
4 mm
. Animals were extracted with a modified Baermann method (

) using 
25 g
soil per funnel (

). After extraction, soil samples were dried at 50°C for 48 h and weighed. Animals were counted per sample under the microscope using 400x magnification (DMI4000 B, Leica, Wetzlar, 
Germany
), and 50 nematode individuals extracted from untreated soil and all nematodes extracted from soil samples after sterilization were identified to genus level and assigned to trophic groups (

, 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Soil characteristics
</title>
         <p>
Soil characteristics before and after treatments were determined from soil samples of A, B and C. All samples (A–C) were replicated five times. Samples were air dried and sieved to 
2 mm
. Plant and animal residuals were removed using tweezers. Soil pH of the samples was determined in a 0.01 M calcium chloride suspension (pH Meter 766, Knick, 
Berlin
, 
Germany
). To determine total soil carbon concentrations and nitrogen concentrations, samples were ground to a fine powder with a mixer mill (MM2000, Retsch, Haan, 
Germany
) and analyzed with an elemental analyzer (Vario EL Element Analyzer, Elementar, Hanau, 
Germany
). Concentrations of soil carbonate were determined volumetrically with a calcimeter according to Scheibler. Soil organic carbon concentrations were calculated as the difference between total soil carbon concentrations and carbonate concentrations. For measurement of plant-available phosphorus concentrations of the samples, soil was extracted with 0.5 M sodium hydrogen carbonate solution (pH 8.5) according to Olsen P method (

) and afterwards analyzed with a plate reader (Varioskan LUX, Thermo Electron LED GmbH, Osterode am Harz, 
Germany
) using the phosphomolybdate blue method (

). To determine plant-available potassium concentrations, soil samples extracted with 1 M calcium-acetate-lactate were analyzed with an inductively-coupled plasma optical emission spectrometer (ICP-OES, SPECTRO ARCOS, SPECTRO Analytical Instruments GmbH, Kleve, 
Germany
). Soil water content was calculated as the difference of fresh and dried (50°C for 48 h) weight of soil samples used for nematode extraction.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Statistical analysis
</title>
         <p>
Differences in soil biota (BAS, C 
mic
, nematodes, rotifers) and soil characteristics (pH, total nitrogen, total carbon, organic carbon, phosphorus, potassium concentrations, soil water content) among soil treatments (factor with four levels for soil biota: A–D; factor with three levels for soil characteristics: A–C) were tested using analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Tukey’s HSD test. Additionally, we used a standardized principal component analysis (PCA) to visualize PLFA results. For all calculations, we used the statistical software R (version 3.6.1, R Development Core Team, http://www.Rproject.org) including 
ggplot2
(

) and 
ggfortify
(

) for PCA.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Results
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Soil biota
</title>
         <p>
Soil biota significantly changed after steam sterilization (
Tab. 1
). Microbial biomass carbon (C 
mic
) was reduced to 73 % (as measured by the mean) after the first steam-sterilization treatment and to 49 % after the second steam-sterilization treatment compared to untreated soil (
Tab. 1
; 
Fig. 2a
). After two-weeks storage, microbial biomass carbon was totally reduced to 41 % of the original value before sterilization (
Fig. 2a
). Basal respiration (BAS) was significantly increased after the first sterilization, but decreased continuously after the following treatments to a level equal to natural soil (
Fig. 2b
). Nematodes were completely reduced after the first sterilization (N = 0), but recolonized the soil afterwards (
Fig. 2c
). In the sterilized soil samples (B–D; N=15), we found in total 10 nematodes. All were juveniles and belonged to five different genera: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cephalobus
</tp:taxon-name>
(bacterial feeders), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aporcelaimellus
</tp:taxon-name>
(omnivores), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aglenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hoplotylus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pratylenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
(all three genera are plant feeders; 
Tab. 2
). Abundance of rotifers was not significantly changed in response to sterilization (
Fig. 2d
). PCA of PLFA showed that the concentrations of most fatty acids decreased with each steam-sterilization event, with the exception of a15:0 (gram-positive bacteria), which showed a strong increase after steam-sterilization treatments (
Tab. 3
; 
Fig. 3
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Soil characteristics
</title>
         <p>
We found significant differences between untreated soil and soil after the first and second sterilization treatment, respectively (
Tab. 1
). Soil pH, soil water content and plant-available phosphorus concentration increased after first steam-sterilization treatment (pH: from 7.44 to 7.78; water: +3 %; phosphorus: +28%; 
Tab. 1
; 
Fig. 4a, b, c
). After second steam-sterilization treatment, soil pH remained unchanged (7.76),whilesoilwatercontentandphosphorusconcentration further increased by 19 %, respectively, compared to single sterilized soil (
Fig. 4a, b, c
). Plant-available potassium and total carbon concentrations decreased after the first steam-sterilization treatment (potassium: -19 %; total carbon: -5%; 
Tab. 1
; 
Fig. 4d, e
). After the second sterilization treatment, total carbon concentration further decreased (-3 % compared to single sterilized soil), while potassium concentration remained unchanged (
Fig. 4d, e
). Soil organic carbon and total nitrogen concentrations did not differ among the treatments (
Tab. 1
; 
Fig. 4f
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Discussion
</title>
         <p>
Single steam-sterilization treatment reduced the abundance of soil biota; however, the effectiveness was lower than expected. Although nematodes were completely eliminated, soil microbial biomass carbon was only reduced to 73 % compared to untreated soil, and the number of rotifers was unchanged. Moreover, basal respiration of microorganisms strongly increased after the first sterilization treatment, which may have been caused by increased soil moisture due to steam condensing and phosphorus flush stimulating microbial activity of the surviving individuals. In general, the results show that a single steam-sterilization event is not sufficient to significantly reduce the number of soil microorganisms in background soil. The second steam-sterilization treatment showed a stronger reduction of soil biota: soil microbial biomass was reduced to 49 % compared to untreated soil, and basal respiration was significantly lower than after the first sterilization treatment (although soil water content and phosphorus concentration further increased). Nevertheless, the abundance of rotifers was still high and nematodes recolonized the soil after the second steam-sterilization treatment, which was possibly due to individuals which survived as eggs. Although we also expected nematodes to survive as dauer larvae, nematodes forming these resting stages (cp1) were not found in the present study. Higher numbers of nematodes after steam sterilization were observed in a study by 

indicating that especially bacterial feeding nematodes strongly increased after an initial strong reduction due to steam sterilization. At day 73 after sterilization, the number of bacterial-feeding nematodes was significantly higher than in the non-treated soil in their study. We also detected bacterial-feeding nematodes in our study (two individuals of the genus 

<tp:taxon-name>Cephalobus</tp:taxon-name>
,

a common genus in soil), which survived the double steam-sterilization treatment. Moreover, six out of the 10 nematodes were plant feeders (four of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pratylenchus
</tp:taxon-name>
), while number of antagonists, such as omnivorous nematodes, were small in sterilized soil. Using this background soil for a plant experiment without further inoculation of soil biota, including predators, could lead to a reduced growth of plants due to an accumulation of plant feeders as shown in 

.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
The PCA showed similar results for microorganisms: the abundance of most microorganisms gradually decreased with every sterilization event, but some gram-positive bacteria benefitted from steam sterilization. This abundance increase of gram-positive bacteria after steam sterilization was also shown in the study by 

. Our results indicate that the steam-sterilization treatment reduces a large range of soil biota, but also that specific species are still alive in background soil (and even benefitted from sterilization). Thus, steam sterilization can reduce soil biota but the subsequent community will be likely dominated by stress resistant organisms and fast-growing opportunistic species. After two-week storage of soil in plastic boxes, we found a small increase in the number of nematodes, but also a further decline in microbial biomass carbon and basal respiration. Therefore, longer storage of soil after steam sterilization may be recommendable, if nematodes are not problematic for the subsequent experiment.
</p>
         <p>
Moreover, our results indicate that steam sterilization has a significant impact on abiotic soil properties. Double sterilization treatment increased plant-available phosphorus concentration by 53 % compared to untreated soil. This is in line with other studies showing that heating of soil can cause a flush in plant-available phosphorus (

, 

). However, it should be noted that the soil we used was rich in calcium carbonate and had high pH, which can cause a reduced availability of plant-available phosphorus for plants (

). Due to sterilization, phosphorus retention could be relaxed leading to a higher concentration of plant-available phosphorus, which is in line with a study by 

. Furthermore, our study shows that soil pH changed from 7.44 to 7.77 after double steam sterilization, possibly due to the release of bases from the organic matter. This increase in pH was also shown in a previous study (

). Soil pH is an important soil property influencing growth rates and diversity of soil biota (

, 

) and nutrient availability for plants (

); however, the increase in pH was small, which probably has no influence on the subsequent experiment.
</p>
         <p>
Contrary to our expectations, plant-available potassium and soil total carbon concentrations decreased after steam-sterilization treatment. Plant-available potassium in soils is to the large extent held by negative charges on clay particles (

), while the binding capacity can differ depending on 
type
, structure and particle size of phyllosilicates, and amount of complexing organic acids and inorganic cations (

). Heating of soil possibly changed the structure of silicates or the quantity of specific soil chemicals, which may have affected the binding capacity and thus the availability of potassium. Furthermore, the decrease of soil total carbon could be explained by the fact that carbon turned into gas due to high heat and evaporated, because the steaming system was not completely closed.
</p>
         <p>
Our study shows that steam sterilization changed abiotic and biotic soil properties of background soil, which is in line with studies on the effects of autoclaving (

, 

, 

).Regarding the efficiency of steam sterilization, we recommend to perform double steam-sterilization treatments to reduce soil biota in background soil under 50 %. Regarding soil properties, our results indicate that it does not matter whether the soil is sterilized once or twice, because soil properties are influenced already after the first sterilization event. Only plant-available phosphorus concentration and soil water content increased even further after the second sterilization event in our study. Nevertheless, repeating the steam-sterilization treatment depends on the soil properties, and aim and design of the subsequent experiment (

). For instance, for experiments studying plant-mycorrhizal interactions, it may be better to sterilize the soil only once, because mycorrhizae are not very heat-resistant (

) and phosphorus flush would be lower.
</p>
         <p>In conclusion, our study highlights that steam sterilization eliminated many soil organisms, but also that a few groups of organisms survived and propagated. Furthermore, steam sterilization caused an increase in phosphorus and soil pH as well as a decrease in potassium, already after the first sterilization treatment. Nevertheless, steam sterilization is a fast and cost-effective alternative to other sterilization methods, especially when large amounts of soil substrate are needed. Therefore, we recommend to run steam sterilization, but to sterilize soil twice, and to consider potential side effects, such as the accumulation of specific soil organisms or the change in plant-available phosphorus and potassium concentrations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>We thank the technicians of the experimental research station Bad Lauchstädt for the transport of soil from Jena to Bad Lauchstädt and preparation of background soil. Furthermore, we are grateful to Petra Hoffmann, Konstantin Albrecht, Laura Bergmann, Alfred Lochner and Lika Kudrjasova for measurements in the laboratory. We also thank Volker Grimm (UFZ) and three anonymous reviewers for helpful comments on earlier versions of this paper. The Jena Experiment is funded by the German Research Foundation (FOR 1451). Further support was provided by the German Centre for Integrative Biodiversity Research (iDiv) Halle-Jena-Leipzig, funded by the German Research Foundation (FZT 118), and by the Heinrich-Böll-Foundation (PhD scholarship).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
6. References
</title>
         <p>
Bååth, E.
&amp; 
K. Arnebrant
(
1994
): 
Growth rate and response of bacterial communities to pH in limed and ash treated forest soils
. – 
Soil Biology and Biochemistry
26

: 
995–1001
.

</p>
         <p>
Berns, A.
, 
H. Philipp
, 
H. D. Narres
, 
P. Burauel
, 
H. Vereecken
&amp; 
W. Tappe
(
2008
): 
Effect of gamma‐sterilization and autoclaving on soil organic matter structure as studied by solid state NMR, UV and fluorescence spectroscopy
. – 
European Journal of Soil Science
59

: 
540–550
.

</p>
         <p>
Blankinship, J. C.
, 
P. A. Niklaus
&amp; 
B. A. Hungate
(
2011
): 
A meta-analysis of responses of soil biota to global change
. – 
Oecologia
165

: 
553–565
.

</p>
         <p>
Blume, H.-P.
, 
H. W. Brümmer
, 
R. Horn
, 
E. Kandeler, I.
Kögel- Knabner, 
R. Kretzschmar
, 
K. Stahr
&amp; 
B.-M. Wilke
(
2016
): 
Scheffer/Schachtschabel: Lehrbuch der Bodenkunde, Vol. 16
. – 
Springer-Verlag
: 
569 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Bongers, T.
(
1988
): 
De nematoden van Nederland: een identificatietabel voor de in Nederland aangetroffen zoetwater-en bodembewonende nematoden
. – 
Stichting Uitgeverij Koninklijke Nederlandse Natuurhistorische Vereniging
: 
408 pp.
</p>
         <p>
Cesarz, S.
, 
A. E. Schulz
, 
R. Beugnon
&amp; 
N. Eisenhauer
(
2019
): 
Testing soil nematode extraction efficiency using different variations of the Baermann-funnel method
. – 
Soil Organisms
91

: 
61–72
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenhauer, N.
&amp; 
M. Türke
(
2018
): 
From climate chambers to biodiversity chambers
. – 
Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment
16

: 
136–137
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenhauer, N.
, 
J. Hines
, 
F. Isbell
, 
F. Van der Plas
, 
S. E. Hobbie
, 
C. E. Kazanski
, 
A. Lehmann
, 
M. Liu
, 
A. Lochner
&amp; 
M. C. Rillig
(
2018
): 
Plant diversity maintains multiple soil functions in future environments
. – 
ELife
7
: e 
41228
.

</p>
         <p>
Endlweber, K.
&amp; 
S. Scheu
(
2006
): 
Establishing arbuscular mycorrhiza-free soil: a comparison of six methods and their effects on nutrient mobilization
. – 
Applied Soil Ecology
34

: 
276–279
.

</p>
         <p>
Frostegård, Å.
, 
A. Tunlid
&amp; 
E. Bååth
(
1991
): 
Microbial biomass measured as total lipid phosphate in soils of different organic content
. – 
Journal of Microbiological Methods
14

: 
151–163
.

</p>
         <p>
McCauley, A.
, 
C. Jones
&amp; 
J. Jacobsen
(
2009
): 
Soil pH and organic matter
. – 
Nutrient management module
8

: 
1–12
.

</p>
         <p>
McSorley, R.
, 
K. Wang
, 
N. Kokalis-Burelle
&amp; 
G. Church
(
2006
): 
Effects of soil type and steam on nematode biological control potential of the rhizosphere community
. – 
Nematropica
36

: 
197–214
.

</p>
         <p>
Murphy, J.
&amp; 
J. P. Riley
(
1962
): 
A modified single solution method for the determination of phosphate in natural waters
. – 
Analytica chimica acta
27

: 
31–36
.

</p>
         <p>
Naeem, S.
, 
L. J. Thompson
, 
S. P. Lawler
, 
J. H. Lawton
&amp; 
R. M. Woodfin
(
1994
): 
Declining biodiversity can alter the performance of ecosystems
. – 
Nature
368

: 
734–737
.

</p>
         <p>
Olsen, S. R.
(
1954
) 
Estimation of available phosphorus in soils by extraction with sodium bicarbonate
. – 
US Department of Agriculture
.

</p>
         <p>
Roscher, C.
, 
J. Schumacher
, 
J. Baade
, 
W. Wilcke
, 
G. Gleixner
, 
W. W. Weisser
, 
B. Schmid
&amp; 
E.-D. Schulze
(
2004
): 
The role of biodiversity for element cycling and trophic interactions: an experimental approach in a grassland community
. – 
Basic and Applied Ecology
5

: 
107–121
.

</p>
         <p>
Ruess, L.
(
1995
): 
Studies on the nematode fauna of an acid forest soil: spatial distribution and extraction
. – 
Nematologica
41

: 
229–239
.

</p>
         <p>
Scheu, S.
(
1992
): 
Automated measurement of the respiratory response of soil microcompartments: active microbial biomass in earthworm faeces
. – 
Soil Biology and Biochemistry
24

: 
1113–1118
.

</p>
         <p>
Serrasolses, I., J.
Romanyà
&amp; 
P. Khanna
(
2008
): 
Effects of heating and autoclaving on sorption and desorption of phosphorus in some forest soils
. – 
Biology and Fertility of Soils
44

: 
1063–1072
.

</p>
         <p>
Sharpley, A. N.
(
1989
): 
Relationship between soil potassium forms and mineralogy
. – 
Soil Science Society of America Journal
53

: 
1023–1028
.

</p>
         <p>
Singh, B.
&amp; 
K. W. T. Goulding
(
1997
): 
Changes with time in the potassium content and phyllosilicates in the soil of the Broadbalk continuous wheat experiment at Rothamsted
. – 
European Journal of Soil Science
48

: 
651–659
.

</p>
         <p>
Skipper, H. D.
&amp; 
D. T. Westermann
(
1973
): 
Comparative effects of propylene oxide, sodium azide, and autoclaving on selected soil properties
. – 
Soil Biology and Biochemistry
5

: 
409–414
.

</p>
         <p>
Tanaka, S.
, 
T. Kobayashi
, 
K. Iwasaki
, 
S. Yamane
, 
K. Maeda
&amp; 
K. Sakurai
(
2003
): 
Properties and metabolic diversity of microbial communities in soils treated with steam sterilization compared with methyl bromide and chloropicrin fumigations
. – 
Soil science and plant nutrition
49

: 
603–610
.

</p>
         <p>
Tang, Y.
, 
Horikoshi, M.
&amp; 
Li, W.
(
2016
): 
ggfortify: unified interface to visualize statistical results of popular R packages
. – 
The R Journal
8

: 
478–489
.

</p>
         <p>
Trevors, J.
(
1996
): 
Sterilization and inhibition of microbial activity in soil
. – 
Journal of Microbiological Methods
26

: 
53–59
.

</p>
         <p>
Van der Heijden, M. G.
, 
R. D. Bardgett
&amp; 
N.M. Van Straalen
(
2008
): 
The unseen majority: soil microorganisms as drivers of plant diversity and productivity in terrestrial ecosystems
. – 
Ecology Letters
11

: 
296–310
.

</p>
         <p>
Van der Putten, W. H.
, 
R. D. Bardgett
, 
J. D. Bever
, 
T. M. Bezemer
, 
B. B. Casper
, 
T. Fukami
, 
P. Kardol
, 
J. N. Klironomos
, 
A. Kulmatiski
&amp; 
J. A. Schweitzer
(
2013
): 
Plant– soil feedbacks: the past, the present and future challenges
. – 
Journal of Ecology
101

: 
265–276
.

</p>
         <p>
Van der Putten, W. H.
, 
M. A. Bradford
, 
E. Pernilla Brinkman
, 
T. F. van de Voorde
&amp; 
G. F. Veen
(
2016
): 
Where, when and how plant–soil feedback matters in a changing world
. – 
Functional Ecology
30

: 
1109–1121
.

</p>
         <p>
Wickham, H.
, 
W. Chang
&amp; 
M. H. Wickham
(
2016
): 
Package ‘ggplot2
’. – 

Create Elegant Data Visualisations using the Grammar of Graphics Version 
2

: 
1–189
.

</p>
         <p>
Williams-Linera, G.
&amp; 
J. J. Ewel
(
1984
): 
Effect of autoclave sterilization of a tropical andept on seed germination and seedling growth
. – 
Plant and Soil
82

: 
263–268
.

</p>
         <p>
Yeates, G. W.
, 
T. Bongers
, 
R. De Goede
, 
D. W. Freckman
&amp; 
S. Georgieva
(
1993
): 
Feeding habits in soil nematode families and genera—an outline for soil ecologists
. – 
Journal of nematology
25

: 
315
.

</p>
         <p>
Zhalnina, K.
, 
R. Dias
, 
P. D. de Quadros
, 
A. Davis-Richardson
, 
F. A. Camargo
, 
I. M. Clark
, 
S. P. McGrath
, 
P. R. Hirsch
&amp; 
E. W. Triplett
(
2015
): 
Soil pH determines microbial diversity and composition in the park grass experiment
. – 
Microbial ecology
69

: 
395–406
.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
