<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Vegetation Classification and Survey</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/VCS.103154</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Proposal (36) to conserve the name Philonotidion seriatae Hinterlang 1992 for the species-poor, bryophyte-dominated, non-calcareous arctic-alpine spring vegetation of Europe</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group/>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="﻿">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
The
syntaxonomic classification of non-calcareous spring vegetation in Europe has evolved from the concept of a single alliance, 
Cardamino-Montion
, to the concept of ecologically and floristically more homogeneous units. This may lead to the misuse of some old names.
</p>
         <p>
Cardamino-Montion

is the oldest alliance name for spring vegetation in Europe. The holotype of this name is the association 
Bryetum schleicheri
, published on page 128 in 

, which is the only element published under the alliance name in the table on page 129. In this table, the alternative name "Assoziation von 
Bryum Schleicheri
und 
Montia rivularis
" (recte: 
Montio fontanae-Bryetum schleicheri

nom. corr. et invers.) is used for the same association. The latter name must be corrected (Art. 44; 

) because 
Montia rivularis
is a younger synonym of 
M. fontana
(see the Euro+Med PlantBase). Moreover, as 
Bryum schleicheri
has a higher cover than 
Montia fontana
in 6 out of 7 
releves
(and equal cover in the remaining one), the name must also be inverted (Art. 42). The lectotype of the association, selected by 

, is 
releve
2 in Table 
1
of the Braun-Blanquet article (

).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
The association 
Bryetum schleicheri

represents the vegetation of open subalpine springs on non-calcareous bedrock. Its 
releves
were sampled at high elevations (1350-1610 m a.s.l.) in the Massif Central, as specified in a subsequent article (

). 
Bryum schleicheri
(
Ptychostomum schleicheri
in the Euro+Med PlantBase), the dominant taxon in the original diagnosis (

, 

), is a circumpolar species with an arctic-alpine distribution. 
Saxifraga stellaris
, another predominantly arctic-alpine species that only rarely descends to the montane belt, is the second most abundant species listed among the faithful (
treue
) character species. 
Sagina linnaei
(
S. saginoides
) and 
Epilobium nutans
are listed as two other faithful character species with optimum distribution in arctic-alpine areas. The arctic-alpine character of the 
Bryetum schleicheri
association (

, 

) is further underlined by the firm (
feste
) character species 
Philonotis seriata
, which co-dominated the moss layer. 
Montia fontana
, reported as a firm (
feste
) character species, occurred in all seven 
releves
, but with low abundance (+ in five cases; 1 in two cases). In contrast to the other species mentioned, this taxon has its distributional optimum at lower elevations, where it often dominates, whereas it only rarely occurs in vegetation where arctic-alpine taxa prevail. Besides the type association, 

included within the alliance the association 
Cardaminetum amarae subatlanticum
, which was documented with only one 
releve
, again from the high elevations of the Massif Central (Mt Puy Mary, 1350 m a.s.l.).
</p>
         <p>
As knowledge of the variability of non-calcareous spring vegetation in Europe increased, new alliances were identified. 

described the 
Mniobryo-Epilobion hornemannii
alliance, another bryophyte-dominated non-calcareous vegetation with many similarities to 
Bryetum schleicheri
(e.g. the dominance of 
Philonotis seriata
and 
Saxifraga stellaris
).
</p>
         <p>

divided 
Braun-Blanquet's
Cardamino-Montion
into two alliances: 
Cardaminion amarae
(shaded springs) and 
Montion
(open springs). The latter is a superfluous name (Art. 29c), since its diagnosis contains the 
Bryetum schleicheri

" (recte: 1925), which is the nomenclatural type of 
Cardamino-Montion

. Shaded forest springs were then distinguished from non-forest springs at the alliance level in most subsequent vegetation surveys. 

classified them as the 
Caricion remotae
Kaestner
1941 alliance (the oldest valid name).
</p>
         <p>
The separation of spring vegetation with arctic-alpine species, dominated by mosses, from colline to montane spring vegetation, dominated by 
Montia fontana
and other vascular plants, was introduced in the synthesis of Czechoslovak spring vegetation by 

. He reported the 
Cardamino-Montion
alliance from the montane zone in the westernmost part of Czechoslovakia, where the arctic-alpine character species of the type association do not occur. For the alpine zone, he described two new alliances: a productive, herb-dominated one (
Cratoneuro filicini-Calthion laetae

) and a moss-rich one with low productivity, characterized by 
Philonotis seriata
and 
Diobelonella palustris
(syn.: 
Anisothecium squarrosum
, 
Dichodontium palustre
, 
Dicranella palustris
). Due to obvious differences compared to the 
Cardamino-Montion
(e.g., the presence of 
Allium schoenoprasum
, 
Bartsia alpina
, 
Swertia perennis
, and 
Pedicularis sudetic
a, and the absence of 
Saxifraga stellaris
, 
Sagina saginoides
, 
Sedum villosum
, and 
Montia fontana
), 

described this vegetation as 
Swertio perennis-Anisothecion squarrosi

.
</p>
         <p>
Later, 

described another new alliance for bryophyte-dominated arctic-alpine spring vegetation, 
Philonotidion seriatae
, which contains 
Philonotis seriata
, 
Bryum schleicheri
and 
Saxifraga stellaris
as in 
Braun-Blanquet's
original description of 
Cardamino-Montion
. Nevertheless, he retained the name 
Cardamino-Montion
for springs with 
Montia fontana
s.l., including 
Braun-Blanquet's
subalpine association.
</p>
         <p>
Consistent differentiation between bryophyte-dominated arctic-alpine spring vegetation and herb-rich montane spring vegetation with 
Montia fontana
agg. began with the first Europe-wide synthesis of spring vegetation by 

. In this study, the vegetation of low-elevation (mostly colline and submontane) springs with 
Montia fontana
was described as the new alliance 
Epilobio nutantis-Montion
Zechmeister in Zechmeister et Mucina 1994. The same solution was adopted in many subsequent studies, and finally also in the European vegetation checklist by 

. The name 
Philonotidion seriatae

was placed there, for unspecified reasons, as a synonym of 
Swertio perennis-Anisothecion squarrosi

instead of 
Cardamino-Montion
, with which it shares more diagnostic species.
</p>
         <p>
Recently, 

conducted a new pan-European synthesis of spring vegetation based on original 
releve
data classified using both unsupervised and supervised methods. This study identified vegetation types that consistently formed distinct clusters in numerical analyses (unsupervised classifications) and were reproducible by formal definitions (supervised classifications). In most cases, these vegetation types corresponded to each the above-mentioned alliances, with one exception: the 
releves
corresponding to the type associations of 
Cardamino-Montion
and 
Philonotidion seriatae
fell into one group in all cases, even when a fine classification with many clusters was performed. 

selected the name 
Philonotidion seriatae

for this vegetation, arguing that the name 
Cardamino-Montion
was often used for different vegetation types in the past (herb-dominated colline to montane 
Montia
springs and even shaded low-elevation springs), making it a source of misunderstanding among vegetation scientists and thus a 
nomen ambiguum
.
</p>
         <p>
Table 
1
shows how the name 
Cardamino-Montion
has been used for very different vegetation types corresponding to different currently distinguished alliances and even orders. Although it is not possible to prove that most of these uses excluded the type of this alliance, i.e. the open arctic-alpine vegetation of the 
Bryo schleicheri-Montietum rivularis
association, it is obvious that different authors understand the name differently. Throughout the history of phytosociology, classification concepts evolved from a single broad alliance 
Cardamino-Montion
towards smaller, ecologically and floristically more homogeneous units at the alliance level. The two name-giving taxa of 
Cardamino-Montion
, both of which actually involve subordinate taxa with different ecological requirements, do not characterize the vegetation corresponding to the type and are instead characteristic of other currently distinguished alliances: C 
ardamine amara
s.l. of 
Caricion remotae
and 
Cratoneuro-Calthion laetae
, and 
Montia fontana
s.l. of 
Epilobio nutantis-Montion
. Applying the rules strictly and maintaining the oldest name 
Cardamino-Montion
would be a constant source of error. We would then have to use two similar, counter-intuitive names: 
Cardamino-Montion
for arctic-alpine springs (although the name-giving taxa occur mainly in montane springs) and 
Epilobio nutantis-Montion
for montane springs (although the name-giving taxon, 
Epilobium nutans
, occurs mainly in arctic-alpine springs). Therefore, it is likely that the name 
Cardamino-Montion
would gradually become ambiguous.
</p>
         <p>
For these reasons, we propose conserving the name 
Philonotidion seriatae

against the names 
Cardamino-Montion

, 
Cardamino-Montion

, and 
Montion

. The latter three alliances share a nomenclatural type which is different from the type of 
Philonotidion seriatae
. The type of 
Philonotidion seriatae
is 
Cratoneuro-Philonotidetum

. The lectotype of this association, selected by 

, is 
releve
11 in table 10 in 
Geissler's
article (

).
</p>
         <p>
In addition, we propose conserving the name 
Philonotidion seriatae

against the name 
Mniobryo-Epilobion hornemannii

. This will prevent the name 
Mniobryo-Epilobion hornemannii

from being used for a broader alliance containing the nomenclatural types of 
Cardamino-Montion
, 
Philonotidion seriatae
, and 
Mniobryo-Epilobion hornemannii
, since 
Epilobium hornemanii
does not occur in most of the distribution range of such a hypothetical alliance.
</p>
         <p>
We acknowledge that classification systems combining associations to alliances differently than was done in the studies by 

, 

, and 

may appear in the future. If our proposal is accepted, then the name 
Philonotidion seriatae

should be used for all species-poor, bryophyte-dominated, non-calcareous spring vegetation types. The name, however, would exclude 
Cratoneuro filicini-Calthion laetae

, which is productive, herb-dominated, and partly transitional to 
Cardamino-Chrysosplenietalia

or even 
Mulgedio-Aconitetea
. It would also exclude 
Swertio perennis-Anisothecion squarrosi

, which is also rich in herbs and partly transitional to 
Scheuchzerio-Caricetea nigrae
. Any hypothetical alliance comprising the latter two herb-rich alliances should therefore be named either 
Cratoneuro filicini-Calthion laetae

or 
Swertio perennis-Anisothecion squarrosi

, depending on its content. We consider these names more suitable for such hypothetical alliances than 
Philonotidion seriatae
, as they both contain taxa from the highest vegetation stratum (herb layer in this case). Finally, a hypothetical alliance combining all non-calcareous springs (regardless of shading and climate, i.e. comprising two currently recognized orders) would be named 
Caricion remotae
Kaestner
1941.
</p>
         <p>
Should our proposal be accepted, the name 
Cardamino-Montion
would remain available for a hypothetical alliance that excludes the type of 
Philonotidion seriatae
; e.g. an alliance comprising non-calcareous springs regardless of elevation, but excluding vegetation extremely poor in vascular plants or without 
Montia fontana
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿author contributions">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Author contributions</p>
         <p>M.H. led the writing, while all authors conceived the idea and critically revised the manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>This proposal was prepared with the support of the Czech Science Foundation (project EXPRO CEVS no. 19-28491X). PH was partially supported by the long-term developmental project of the Czech Academy of Sciences (RVO 67985939). We are grateful to anonymous reviewers and the editors (W. Willner, H. Seiler) for valuable comments on earlier versions of the proposal.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bardat, J
, 
Bioret, F
, 
Botineau, M
, 
Boullet, V
, 
Delpech, R
, 

Gehu
, J-M

, 
Haury, J
, 
Lacoste, A
, 
Rameau, J-C
, 
Touffet, J
, 
2004
. 

Prodrome des 
vegetations
de France. Museum national 
d'histoire
naturelle, Paris, FR.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Borhidi, A
, 
Kevey, B
, 
Lendvai, G
, 
2012
. 

Plant communities of Hungary. 
Akademiai
Kiado
, Budapest, HU.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Braun-Blanquet, J
, 
1925
. 
Zur Wertung der Gesellschaftstreue in der Pflanzensoziologie.

Vierteljahrsschrift der Naturforschenden Gesellschaft in 
Zuerich

70
: 
122 - 149
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Braun-Blanquet, J
, 
1926
. 
Etudes phytosociologiques en Auvergne.
Arvernia
2
: 
29 - 48
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Bueker
, R

, 
1942
. 

Beitraege
zur Vegetationskunde des 
suedwestfaelischen
Berglandes. Beihefte zum Botanischen Centralblatt 56B: 452-558.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Coldea, G
, 
1997
. 

(1997) Les associations 
vegetales
de Roumanie. Tome 1. Les associations 
herbacees
naturelles. Presses Universitaires de Cluj, Cluj-Napoca, RO.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Diekmann, M
, 
1997
. 
The differentiation of alliances in South Sweden.
Folia Geobotanica
32
: 
193 - 205
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02803740
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Dierssen
, K

, 
1996
. 
Vegetation Nordeuropas. Ulmer, Stuttgart, DE.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Dierssen
, K

, 

Dierssen
, B

, 
2005
. 
Studies on the vegetation of fens, springs and snow fields in West Greenland.
Phytocoenologia
35
: 
849 - 885
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1127/0340-269X/2005/0035-0849
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ellenberg, H
, 
Leuschner, C
, 
2010
. 

Vegetation Mitteleuropas mit den Alpen: in 
oekologischer
, dynamischer und historischer Sicht. Ulmer, Stuttgart, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Geissler, P
, 
1976
. 

Zur Vegetation alpiner 
Fliessgewaesser
. 
Pflanzensoziologisch-oekologische
Untersuchungen hygrophiler Moosgesellschaften in den 
oestlichen
Schweizer Alpen.


Beitraege
zur Kryptogamenflora der Schweiz

14
: 
1 - 52
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Hadac
, E

, 
1983
. 
A survey of plant communities of springs and mountain brooks in Czechoslovakia.
Folia Geobotanica et Phytotaxonomica
18
: 
339 - 361
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02857260
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hinterlang, D
, 
1992
. 

Vegetationsoekologie
der Weichwasserquellgesellschaften 
zentraleuropaeischer
Mittelgebirge.

Crunoecia
1
: 
1 - 117
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hinterlang, D
, 
2017
. 

Synopsis der Pflanzengesellschaften Deutschlands, Heft 12: Montio-Cardaminetea (C6) Quell- und Waldsumpfgesellschaften. Floristisch-soziologische Arbeitsgemeinschaft, 
Goettingen
, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Laiviņs
, M

, 
1998
. 

Latvijas ziedaugu un 
paparzaugu
sabiedrību
augstakie
sintaksoni.

Acta Universitatis Latviensis
613
: 
7 - 22
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lawesson, JE
, 
2004
. 
A tentative annotated checklist of Danish syntaxa.
Folia Geobotanica
39
: 
73 - 95
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02803265
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lebrun, J
, 
Noirfalise, A
, 
Heinemann, P
, 
Vanden, Berghen C
, 
1949
. 

Les associations 
vegetales
de Belgique.


Bulletin de la 
Societe
Royale de Botanique de Belgique

82
: 
105 - 199
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maas, FM
, 
1959
. 
Bronnen, bronbeken en bronbossen van Nederland, in het bijzonder die van de Veluwezoom.
Mededelingen van de Landbouwhogeschool Wageningen
59
: 
1 - 166
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Matuszkiewicz, W
, 
2007
. 

Przewodnik do oznaczania zbiorowisk 
roslinnych
Polski. Wydawnictwo Naukowe PWN, Warszawa, PL.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mertz, P
, 
2000
. 
Plant communities in Central Europe and the Alps. Recognition, determination, evaluation: a handbook for practical vegetation science. Ecomed Verlagsgesellschaft, Landsberg am Lech, DE.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mucina, L
, 

Bueltmann
, H

, 
Dierssen, K
, 
Theurillat, J-P
, 
Raus, T
, 

Carni
, A

, 

Sumberova
, K

, 
Willner, W
, 
Dengler, J
, 

Tichy
, L

, 
2016
. 
Vegetation of Europe: hierarchical floristic classification system of vascular plant, bryophyte, lichen, and algal communities. Applied Vegetation Science 19(Suppl. 1): 3-264.
https://doi.org/10.1111/avsc.12257
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nordhagen, R
, 
1943
. 
Sikilsdalen og Norges fjellbeiter. En plantesosiologisk monografi [Sikilsdalen and Norwegian mountain pastures: a plant sociological monograph].
Bergens Museums Skrifter
22
: 
1 - 607
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oberdorfer, E
, 
1957
. 

Sueddeutsche
Pflanzengesellschaften. Fischer, Jena, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oberdorfer, E
, 
2001
. 
Pflanzensoziologische Exkursionsflora. 8th ed. Ulmer, Stuttgart, DE.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Passarge, H
, 
1999
. 

Pflanzengesellschaften Nordostdeutschlands II. Helocyperosa und Caespitosa. 
Gebrueder
Borntraeger Verlagbuchhandlung, Berlin, Stuttgart, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Peterka, T
, 

Hajkova
, P

, 

Jirousek
, M

, 
Hinterlang, D
, 

Chytry
, M

, 
Aunina, L
, 
Deme, J
, 
Lyons, M
, 
Seiler, H
, 

Hajek
, M

, 
2023
. 
Formalised classification of the class Montio-Cardaminetea in Europe: towards a consistent typology of spring vegetation.
Preslia
95
: 
347 - 383
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.23855/preslia.2023.347
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Ranđelovic
, VN

, 

Zlatkovic
, BK

, 
2010
. 

Flora i vegetacija Vlasinske visoravni. Univerzitet u 
Nisu
, 
Nis
, RS.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Ratiu
, O

, 
Gergely, I
, 

Suteu
, 
S

, 
Marvu, A
, 
1983
. 

Flora 
si
unitătile
fitosintaxonomice de pe Valea Iadului (Jud. Nihor). 
Importanăa
economică
si
stiintifică
. Caracterizarea lor 
ecologică
II. 
Vegetatia
1 [Flora and phytosyntaxonomic units of Valea Iadului valley (distr. Nihor). Economic and scientific importance. Ecological characterization II. Vegetation 1].


Contributii
Botanicae

18
: 
69 - 97
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Redzic
, S

, 
2007
. 
Syntaxonomic diversity as an indicator of ecological diversity - case study Vranica Mts in the Central Bosnia.
Biologia
62
: 
173 - 184
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.2478/s11756-007-0026-3
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Redzic
, S

, 

Bulic
, Z

, 

Hadziablahovic
, S

, 
2011
. 
High mountain vegetation of Dinarides (W. Balkan).
Glasnik Republičkog zavoda za zaštitu prirode i Prirodnjačkog muzeja u Podgorici
31
(
32
): 
7 - 46
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rennwald, E
, 
2000
. 
Verzeichnis der Pflanzengesellschaften Deutschlands mit Synonymen und Formationseinteilung.

Schriftenreihe 
fuer
Vegetationskunde

35
: 
121 - 391
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Rivas-Martinez
, S

, 

Fernandez-Gonzalez
, F

, 
Loidi, J
, 

Lousa
, M

, 
Penas, A
, 
2001
. 
Syntaxonomical checklist of vascular plant communities of Spain and Portugal to association level.
Itinera Geobotanica
14
: 
5 - 341
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Schaminee
, JHJ

, 
Weeda, EJ
, 
Westhoff, V
, 
1995
. 
(1995) De vegetatie van Nederland. Deel 2. Plantengemeenschappen van wateren, moerassen en natte heiden. Opulus Press, Uppsala, SE.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schaminée, JHJ
, 
Haveman, R
, 
Hommel, PWFM
, 
Janssen, JAM
, 
de, Ronde I
, 
Schipper, PC
, 
Weeda, EJ
, 
van, Dort KW
, 
Bal, D
, 
2017
. 
Revisie vegetatie van Nederland. Westerlaan Publisher, Lichtenvoorde, NL.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Siebum, MB
, 

Schaminee
, JHJ

, 
Weeda, EJ
, 
1995
. 
Montio-Cardaminetea.
In: 

Schaminee
, JHJ

, 
Weeda, EJ
, 
Westhoff, V
, Eds., 
De Vegetatie van Nederland.
Deel 2. Plantengemeenschappen van wateren, moerassen en natte heiden. Opulus Press, Uppsala, SE
: 
139 - 160
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Soo
, R

, 
1949
. 

Les associations 
vegetales
de la Moyenne-Transylvanie. II. Les associations des marais, des prairies et des steppes.

Acta Geobotanica Hungarica
6
: 
3 - 107
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Theurillat, J-P
, 
Willner, W
, 

Fernandez-Gonzalez
, F

, 

Bueltmann
, H

, 

Carni
, A

, 
Gigante, D
, 
Mucina, L
, 
Weber, H
, 
2021
. 
International Code of Phytosociological Nomenclature. 4th edition. Applied Vegetation Science 24: e12491.
https://doi.org/10.1111/avsc.12491
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tomaselli, M
, 
Spitale, D
, 
Petraglia, A
, 
2011
. 
Phytosociological and ecological study of springs in Trentino (south-eastern Alps, Italy). Journal of Limnology 70(Suppl. 1): 23-53.
https://doi.org/10.4081/jlimnol.2011.s1.23
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Tuexen
, R

, 
1937
. 
Die Pflanzengesellschaften Nordwestdeutschlands.
Mitteilungen der Floristisch-soziologischen Arbeitsgemeinschaft in Niedersachsen
3
: 
1 - 170
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zechmeister, H
, 
Mucina, L
, 
1994
. 

Vegetation of European springs: High-rank syntaxa of the 
Montio
- 
Cardaminetea
.

Journal of Vegetation Science
5
: 
385 - 402
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.2307/3235862
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿e-mail and orcid">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>E-mail and ORCID</p>
         <p>

Michal 
Hajek

(Corresponding author, hajek@sci.muni.cz), ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5201-2682
</p>
         <p>
Tomas
Peterka

(peterkatomasek@seznam.cz), ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5488-8365
</p>
         <p>

Petra 
Hajkova

(buriana@sci.muni.cz), ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1434-7825
</p>
         <p>
Dirk Hinterlang
(dirk.hinterlang@lanuv.nrw.de), ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5434-1228
</p>
         <p>
Harald Zechmeister
(harald.zechmeister@univie.ac.at), ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6578-7244
</p>
         <p>

Milan 
Chytry

(chytry@sci.muni.cz), ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8122-3075
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
