<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Vegetation Classification and Survey</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/VCS.117703</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>How to classify forests? A case study from Central Europe</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group/>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="﻿introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Introduction
</p>
         <p>
The classes of the Braun-Blanquet system correspond to major floristic, biogeographical and ecological units (

; 

). For European zonal forests, these are the 
Quercetea ilicis
(mediterranean evergreen), 
Quercetea pubescentis
(submediterranean deciduous), 
Quercetea robori-petraeae
and 
Carpino-Fagetea
(temperate deciduous), 
Vaccinio-Piceetea
(boreal and temperate montane-subalpine coniferous) and 
Betulo-Alnetea viridis
(subarctic-subalpine deciduous) (Figure 
1
). Azonal forests can be arranged into two groups: 
Erico-Pinetea
, 
Pyrolo-Pinetea
and 
Junipero-Pinetea
include coniferous forests on very dry sites, while 
Salicetea purpureae
, 
Alno-Populetea
and 
Alnetea glutinosae
are wetland forests. Finally, the 
Crataego-Prunetea
, 
Franguletea
and 
Robinietea
comprise seral woodland and tall-scrub (

). These classes can be incorporated into a global formation system, enabling broad-scale comparisons among continents (

).
</p>
         <p>
For most of the 20th century, the correspondence between classes and formations was much weaker because some classes (
Vaccinio-Piceetea
, 
Betulo-Adenostyletea
, 
Epilobietea
) included both forest and non-forest vegetation (e.g., 

). Splitting these physiognomically heterogeneous classes has been identified as one of the megatrends in phytosociology during the last 50 years (

; 

). However, many uncertainties and inconsistencies still linger within the classes, blurring the biogeographical and ecological correspondences outlined above. For instance, the EuroVegChecklist (EVC, 

) classifies Western Caucasian 
Pinus brutia
forests (
Campanulo sibiricae-Pinion brutiae
) in the 
Quercetea pubescentis
while the 
Pinus brutia
forests of the Eastern Mediterranean are included in the 
Quercetea ilicis
(but see 

for a different solution). Boreal-subarctic birch woods on nutrient-poor podzolic soils (
Empetro hermaphroditi-Betulion pumilae
) are included in the 
Vaccinio-Piceetea
, those on nutrient-rich soils (
Geranio sylvatici-Betulion pumilae
) in the 
Betulo-Alnetea viridis
. Temperate pine forests on acidic soils (
Dicrano-Pinion sylvestris
) are classified within the 
Vaccinio-Piceetea
by the EVC, whereas 

assign them to the 
Erico-Pinetea
. Acidophytic beech forests are placed in the 
Carpino-Fagetea
by some authors, but in the 
Quercetea robori-petraeae
by others (

; see also remark 
fag03
in 

, p. 35). High montane acidophytic beech forests of Central Europe (
Calamagrostio villosae-Fagetum
) were even assigned to the 
Vaccinio-Piceetea
in 

. Temperate 
Abies alba
forests are either considered as part of the 
Carpino-Fagetea
(e.g., 

), or as part of the 
Vaccinio-Piceetea
(e.g., 

; 

), whereas some authors split them between the two classes (

).
</p>
         <p>
All these examples have one question in common: Should one give higher weight to the tree layer or the herb layer composition when classifying forests? Floristic similarity is the main criterion in the Braun-Blanquet approach (

). However, floristic similarity of the tree layer might suggest a different grouping than floristic similarity of the herb layer. As the European tree flora is rather poor in species compared to other continents (

), overall similarity is usually driven by the herb layer. Thus, following a purely floristic approach, communities dominated by the same tree species may end up in different classes, orders or alliances (

). Because such units are often very heterogenous in terms of physiognomy and at odds with broad-scale formations and biogeographical units, most authors consciously or unconsciously give higher weight to the tree species composition in at least some cases. However, in the absence of a general rule, these decisions are mostly subjective and arbitrary, resulting in a low stability of the forest classification in Europe.
</p>
         <p>
Similar problems arise from the shrub layer, especially for communities without a tree layer. In the past, shrub communities were either joined with forests or with herb vegetation: The 
Prunetalia spinosae
were part of the 
Querco-Fagetea
, the 
Sambucetalia racemosae
part of the 
Epilobietea angustifolii
, the 
Betulo-Alnetea viridis
included in the 
Betulo-Adenostyletea
etc. (

; 

). Whether shrub communities should be separated from forests on a high syntaxonomic level is still a controversial issue (e.g., 

). Indeed, while the classes 
Crataego-Prunetea
and 
Betulo-Alnetea viridis
have been widely accepted in recent decades, they still include communities dominated by either shrubs or trees (see 

). The distinction between trees and tall shrubs is not always straightforward as many woody species have a rather high phenotypic plasticity. For instance, 
Fagus sylvatica
often has a prostrate growth form at its upper elevational limit (

), 
Quercus pubescens
may be less than 4 m tall on dry sites with shallow soils (

), while 
Corylus avellana
can achieve 10 m in height despite having a shrubby branching pattern (

). Therefore, 
a priori
separation of forests and tall scrub is inevitably at odds with the floristic principle (see also 

).
</p>
         <p>
Interestingly, the traditional classification of tall shrub vegetation is almost exclusively based on the species composition of the shrub layer (

; 

; 

). Herbs and grasses are often confined to the fringes and gaps of the scrub while the dense interior is almost completely devoid of a herb layer (

). Therefore, non-woody species in 
releves
mainly reflect the neighbouring fringe and grassland vegetation, which belongs to a different successional stage, and their presence is strongly dependent on the delimitation of the sampling plot. Since the classification of scrub communities should reflect the ecological and biogeographical properties of the dominant shrubs rather than those of adjacent herbs and grasses, it makes sense to ignore the latter in the delimitation of higher syntaxa.
</p>
         <p>
In an effort to increase the consistency of the Central European forest classification, 

adopted an approach for the definition of higher forest syntaxa that was similar to that of tall shrub vegetation; that is, they suggested that the upper units of the system should be primarily based on the species composition of the tree layer, whereas the lower ones should be primarily based on the understorey composition (

). Depending on the ecological amplitude of the dominant trees, the switch between over- and understorey was done at different hierarchical levels (e.g., between order and alliance for spruce forests, and between alliance and suballiance for most deciduous forests). However, the principle was not rigorously applied using numerical methods.
</p>
         <p>In the present study, I investigate whether a classification of Central European forests based solely on the woody species of the shrub and tree layer leads to units similar to the traditional Braun-Blanquet system or to something completely different.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿study area">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Study area</p>
         <p>
The plot records (
releves
) used in this study are from Austria (Central Europe) and adjacent regions in the SE Alps and NW Dinaric mountains (Figure 
2
). Austria covers most of the Eastern Alps and their foreland, the western part of the Pannonian Basin and the SE part of the Bohemian Massif. The elevation of the plots ranges from 120 m a.s.l. in Eastern Austria to the highest forests in the Alps at ca. 2300 m a.s.l. Annual precipitation ranges from 500 mm to 2000 mm (in the SE Alps locally up to 3000 mm). The mean annual temperature ranges from 1-2°C at the treeline to 10°C in the Pannonian lowland.
</p>
         <p>
Due to the large climatic gradient Austria has a large variety of forest types, and forests cover 46% of the country (ca. 3.88 million hectares). Lowland forests are mostly deciduous, and oaks (
Quercus
spp.), hornbeam (
Carpinus betulus
), beech (
Fagus sylvatica
) and ash (
Fraxinus excelsior
) are dominant trees. The outer ranges of the Alps are occupied by mixed forests composed predominantly of beech and fir (
Abies alba
). The inner parts of the Alps, which have a strongly continental climate, and the whole subalpine belt are covered by coniferous forests with spruce (
Picea abies
), larch (
Larix decidua
), and Arolla pine (
Pinus cembra
) as dominants. The upper subalpine belt is often dominated by 
Pinus mugo
krummholz (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Methods</p>
         <p>Dataset preparation</p>
         <p>
Initially, all 
releves
of forest and shrub communities were selected from the Austrian Vegetation Database (GIVD-ID EU-AT-001; 

). Spruce and pine plantations and stands with a cover of non-native woody species&gt; 5% were excluded from the dataset. Also excluded were forest 
releves
where the cover of trees was not estimated separately for the tree and herb layer, 
releves
with a cover of woody species determined only at the genus level&gt; 5%, and 
releves
dominated by (&gt;25%) low shrubs [i.e., shrub species not exceeding 2 m, including all 
Rubus
species]. The 2 m threshold was chosen following the definition of the forest and woodland formation class (

). Finally, 
releves
with a total cover of trees and tall shrubs &lt;15% were omitted. This resulted in a dataset of 23,681 
releves
, with 22,588 plots from Austria and 1,093 plots from neighbouring countries (Figure 
2
).
</p>
         <p>
Only native tree and tall shrub species in the shrub and tree layer were used in the classification while all other taxa (including records of woody species in the herb layer and taxa determined only at the genus level) were omitted. The omission of non-native trees and shrubs follows the consideration that the syntaxonomic system of European forest and shrub communities should be based on the native species (though syntaxa for communities dominated by non-native species might be added in a second step). Records of native tree and tall shrub species in different layers were merged using the algorithm published by 

. Altogether, 111 taxa were kept in the final dataset. All data handling was done with JUICE 7.1 (

).
</p>
         <p>Numerical classification</p>
         <p>
The matrix of 23,681 
releves
and 111 taxa was classified using the original TWINSPAN algorithm (

). Parameter settings were three pseudospecies cutlevels (0%, 5%, 25%), six levels of division and a minimum group size for division of two. For species sorting and interpretation, the diagnostic value of woody species for phytosociological classes according to 

was used. If a species was given as diagnostic for two or more classes occurring in Central Europe, the diagnostic value according to 

was followed. Within each class, species were sorted by decreasing phi coefficient (

; 

) using a threshold of 0.3. The phi coefficient was calculated assuming equal group size, and positive phi values were only accepted if the difference in species constancy between the target unit and the rest of the data set was significant according to 
Fisher's
exact test at p &lt;0.05.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿results">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Results</p>
         <p>
The TWINSPAN classification resulted in 63 clusters (one division failed because the minimum group size was not reached). With a few exceptions, lowland forests and scrubs were separated from those at higher elevations at the first level of division. At the second division level, lowland communities were further divided along a moisture gradient, and montane communities were separated from subalpine ones (Table 
1
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Specifically, the TWINSPAN clusters corresponded to the following vegetation types (numbers in brackets refer to the column number in Table 
1
and Suppl. material 1, syntaxa follow the EVC system; the clusters are numbered from 1 to 64 to show the full TWINSPAN hierarchy; note that there is no cluster 48 because the corresponding level 6 division failed):
</p>
         <p>
1-8 (1): nutrient-rich willow carrs with 
Salix cinerea
(
Salicion cinereae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
9-12 (2): submontane and montane alluvial willow scrub (
Salicion eleagno-daphnoidis
)
</p>
         <p>
13 (3): alluvial forests with 
Salix alba
(
Salicion albae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
14 (4): alluvial forests with 
Salix fragilis
(
Salicion albae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
15-16 (5): lowland alluvial scrub with 
Salix triandra
(
Salicion triandrae
)
</p>
         <p>
17-20 (6): swamp forests with 
Alnus glutinosa
(
Alnion glutinosae
)
</p>
         <p>
21 (7): alluvial forests with 
Populus alba
(
Alnion incanae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
22 (8): alluvial forests with 
Alnus incana
(
Alnion incanae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
23 (9): alluvial forests with 
Alnus glutinosa
(
Alnion incanae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
24 (10): sycamore forests (
Tilio-Acerion
)
</p>
         <p>
25 (11): moist oak-hornbeam forests with 
Quercus robur
(
Carpinion betuli
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
26 (12): lime forests and mesic oak-hornbeam forests with 
Fraxinus excelsior
(
Melico-Tilion platyphylli
, 
Carpinion betuli
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
27 (13): mesic and dry oak-hornbeam forests with 
Quercus petraea
(
Carpinion betuli
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
28 (14): acidophytic oak forests with 
Quercus petraea
(
Agrostio-Quercion petraeae
)
</p>
         <p>
29 (15): thermophilous oak forests on deeper soils (
Quercion petraeae
, 
Quercion pubescenti-petraeae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
30 (16): thermophilous oak forests on shallow soils with 
Quercus pubescens
(
Quercion pubescenti-petraeae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
31 (17): thermophilous seral scrub (
Berberidion vulgaris
, 
Urtico-Crataegion
)
</p>
         <p>
32 (18): lowland alluvial hardwood forests (
Fraxino-Quercion roboris
)
</p>
         <p>
33-36 (19): beech forests (
Fagetalia sylvaticae
, 
Luzulo-Fagetalia sylvaticae
)
</p>
         <p>
37-38 (20): spruce forests (
Piceetalia excelsae
, 
Athyrio filicis-feminae-Piceetalia
)
</p>
         <p>
39-40 (21): montane elder scrub in forest clearings (
Sambuco-Salicion capreae
)
</p>
         <p>
41 (22): 
Pinus sylvestris
forests (
Erico carneae-Pinion
, 
Dicrano-Pinion sylvestris
, 
Vaccinio uliginosi-Pinion sylvestris
)
</p>
         <p>
42 (23): 
Pinus nigra
forests (
Erico-Fraxinion orni
)
</p>
         <p>
43-44 (24): dry calcareous 
Ostrya carpinifolia
forests on shallow soils (
Fraxino orni-Ostryion
)
</p>
         <p>
45-47 (25): nutrient-poor willow carrs with 
Salix aurita
(
Salicion cinereae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
49-52 (26): subalpine krummholz with 
Pinus mugo
(
Pinion mugo
, 
Erico-Pinion mugo
)
</p>
         <p>
53-54 (27): subalpine 
Larix decidua
woodland (
Piceion excelsae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
55-56 (28): subalpine 
Pinus cembra
woodland (
Piceion excelsae
p.p.)
</p>
         <p>
57-64 (29): subalpine green alder scrub (
Alnion viridis
)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿discussion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Discussion</p>
         <p>Syntaxonomy</p>
         <p>
The TWINSPAN classification revealed elevation (i.e., climate) as the main floristic gradient in the data set. Within lowland communities, soil moisture was the dominant factor. Interestingly, the higher units of the Braun-Blanquet system were mostly well reproduced, with clusters 1-8 corresponding to the 
Franguletea
, clusters 9-16 to the 
Salicetea purpureae
, clusters 17-20 to the 
Alnetea glutinosae
, clusters 21-23 to the 
Alno-Populetea
, clusters 24-27 to the 
Carpino-Fagetea
and so on. Notable exceptions are the classes 
Quercetea pubescentis
, 
Quercetea robori-petraeae
and 
Crataego-Prunetea
, which were all intermingled with the 
Carpino-Fagetea
. This could be interpreted as support for the more traditional concept of a broadly defined class 
Querco-Fagetea
(e.g., 

; 

). However, because the 
Quercetea pubescentis
and 
Quercetea robori-petraeae
have their main distribution outside the study area, this question will not be further discussed in the present paper. The strange position of the 
Fraxino orni-Ostryion
in the TWINSPAN table reflects the fact that 
Ostrya carpinifolia
forests reach their northern distribution limit in the study area, where they are confined to dry, calcareous sites similar to those of pine forests. Indeed, 

classified these communities within the class 
Erico-Pinetea
. Alluvial hardwood forests (
Fraxino-Quercion roboris
) were widely separated from the 
Alnus
and 
Populus
woods of the 
Alnion incanae
, which suggests keeping them in the class 
Carpino-Fagetea
. Lime forests (
Melico-Tilion platyphylli
) were grouped together with oak-hornbeam forests (
Carpinion betuli
). 
Abies alba
forests were not reproduced as a separate cluster, but mostly included in beech forests, supporting the concept of 

. The position of subalpine 
Larix decidua
and 
Pinus cembra
woodland seems at odds with the EVC system, but it fits well with the classification in 

, where both units were included in a broadly defined 
Pinion mugo
.
</p>
         <p>
On the whole, the traditional Braun-Blanquet system of forests seems to have given more weight to the tree species combination than is generally acknowledged in textbooks. As expected, the syntaxonomic rank of the TWINSPAN clusters varies vastly, from a single association (e.g., cluster 13: 
Salicetum albae
) to a group of classes (cluster 41: 
Pinus sylvestris
forests). This reflects the different ecological amplitude of the dominant species. In most cases, however, the woody species combination seems most suitable for the definition of orders and alliances. Some ecological gradients (e.g., calcareous versus acidic soils) are only visible in the herb layer (including dwarf shrubs) and are therefore not reflected in the table.
</p>
         <p>What do we expect from a good forest classification?</p>
         <p>

suggested three criteria for a 
"good"
phytosociological class: (1) biogeographical-evolutionary criterion: common origin and evolution, (2) floristic criterion: common set of characteristic species, and (3) application criterion: coherence in the presentation. For the third criterion, he noted that "it is very difficult to argue, in a teaching context, that forests dominated by the same species belong to different classes". Obviously, the second and third criterion can only be simultaneously fulfilled if the class is floristically defined by the species of the dominant layer. In this way, most European tree species become character species on some hierarchical level while in many traditional systems they are only treated as companion species.
</p>
         <p>
We might complement 
Loidi's
criteria by four general properties that users might reasonably expect from a good forest classification: (a) The upper levels of the hierarchy are more easily recognizable than the lower levels. (b) The upper level units are more stable over time in terms of vegetation history. (c) The factors shaping global vegetation patters are reflected on the upper levels, while the factors responsible for regional and local patterns are reflected on the lower levels. (d) The upper levels are consistent with global formation and biome classifications.
</p>
         <p>
As shown above, the higher levels of the phytosociological forest system can basically be defined by taking only the tall shrub and tree layer into account. However, this has never been formulated as a rule, and all past and current classifications suffer from arbitrary weighting of the layers, leading to inconsistencies and blurring the main biogeographical patterns within European forests. The distribution of European tree species is mainly controlled by broad climatic gradients as well as differences in soil moisture (Table 
1
) - the same ecological factors that are reflected in global biome and formation systems (

; 

; 

). Differences in calcium content, on the other hand, have a more regional significance, and are mostly visible in the herb layer composition (

). It is therefore advisable to reflect the latter on lower hierarchical levels, e.g., by uniting basiphytic and acidophytic beech forests in the same class or even order (

; 

; 

; 

), or by transferring temperate dry 
Pinus sylvestris
forests on acidic bedrock (alliance 
Dicrano-Pinion
) from the 
Vaccinio-Piceetea
to the 
Erico-Pinetea
- a solution that is also supported by numerous common understorey species (

). However, given the extremely broad amplitude of 
Pinus sylvestris
, it is also justified to classify the forests dominated by this species in at least two different classes, 
Erico-Pinetea
(temperate dry pine forests, including the 
Erico-Pinion
, 
Dicrano-Pinion
, 
Ononido-Pinion
and other alliances) and 
Vaccinio uliginosi-Pinetea
(boreal and temperate wet pine forests, including the 
Vaccinio uliginosi-Pinion
and 
Cladonio stellaris-Pinion
; see 

). Submediterranean pine forests dominated by 
Pinus nigra
should probably be placed in a separate class.
</p>
         <p>
Understorey species may have markedly different biogeographical histories than the tree species they are currently associated with (

; 

). Thus, we can assume that vegetation units defined by tree species have been more stable over time than syntaxa defined by species from different layers. In fact, vegetation units solely defined by understorey species can be completely independent of the tree layer and even exist outside the forest. A classic example is 
Braun-Blanquet's
Rhododendro-Vaccinion
(

), which comprised both coniferous forests and treeless dwarf shrub heaths. Carrying this idea to extremes, 

proposed to independently classify the herb, shrub and tree layers (see also 

). While agreeing with these authors on the basic problem, I suggest a different and less radical solution: By using the tree and (tall-)shrub layer for defining the upper levels and the herb and cryptogam layer for defining the lower levels of the system, the basic units (i.e., the associations) represent the whole forest community. At the same time, over- and understorey composition are not mixed in an arbitrary and often confusing manner for the definition of the higher units as in most traditional systems. However, it must be emphasised that 
"upper"
and 
"lower"
level is meant in a purely relative sense here. The lowest appropriate rank to be defined by the tree and tall shrub layer depends both on the ecological amplitude of the resulting units and the floristic heterogeneity of the herb and cryptogam layer within these units; thus, it may vary from association or suballiance (though this will be uncommon) to a group of classes (see examples above).
</p>
         <p>
Previous proposals have suggested separating forests and tall-scrub on the one hand and non-woody vegetation (including dwarf-shrub heaths) on the other hand as two 
a-priori
structural types in syntaxonomy (

; 

). If trees and tall-shrubs are used to define the classes of woody vegetation, this separation becomes a natural component of the floristic classification, without a sudden change of criteria. At the same time, phytosociological classes defined by the combination of woody species can be easily fitted into a global formation system (

) as well as in most biome systems (

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿data availability">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Data availability</p>
         <p>
The 
releves
used in this study are available upon request from the Austrian Vegetation Database (GIVD-ID EU-AT-001) managed by the author of this paper and from the European Vegetation Archive (https://euroveg.org/eva-database/).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>I thank Don Faber-Langendoen, Jim Martin and two anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments on previous versions of the manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bergmeier, E
, 

Haerdtle
, W

, 
Mierwald, U
, 
Nowak, B
, 
Peppler, C
, 
Flintrop, T
, 
1990
. 

Vorschlaege
zur syntaxonomischen Arbeitsweise in der Pflanzensoziologie.

Kieler Notizen zur Pflanzenkunde in Schleswig-Holstein und Hamburg
20
: 
92 - 103
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bohn, U
, 
Gollub, G
, 
Hettwer, C
, 
2000
. 

Karte der 
natuerlichen
Vegetation Europas. Map of the natural vegetation of Europe. Bundesamt 
fuer
Naturschutz, Bonn-Bad Godesberg, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bonari, G
, 

Fernandez-Gonzalez
, F

, 

Coban
, S

, 
Monteiro-Henriques, T
, 
Bergmeier, E
, 
Didukh, YP
, 
Xystrakis, F
, 
Angiolini, C
, 

Chytry
, K

, 

Chytry
, M

, 
2021
. 
Classification of the Mediterranean lowland to submontane pine forest vegetation. Applied Vegetation Science 24: e12544.
https://doi.org/10.1111/avsc.12544
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Braun-Blanquet, J
, 
Sissingh, G
, 
Vlieger, J
, 
1939
. 

Klasse der Vaccinio-Piceetea [Prodromus der Pflanzengesellschaften 6]. 
Comite
International du Prodrome Phytosociologique, Montpellier, FR.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Chytry
, M

, 
2013
. 

Vegetace 
Ceske
republiky 4. 
Lesni
a 
krovinna
vegetace [Vegetation of the Czech Republic 4. Forest and scrub vegetation]. Academia, Praha, CZ.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Chytry
, M

, 

Tichy
, L

, 
Holt, J
, 

Botta-Dukat
, J

, 
2002
. 
Determination of diagnostic species with statistical fidelity measures.
Journal of Vegetation Science
13
: 
79 - 90
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1654-1103.2002.tb02025.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dengler, J
, 
Berg, C
, 
Jansen, F
, 
2005
. 
New ideas for modern phytosociological monographs.
Annali di Botanica
5
: 
193 - 210
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ermakov, N
, 
Morozova, O
, 
2011
. 
Syntaxonomical survey of boreal oligotrophic pine forests in northern Europe and Western Siberia.
Applied Vegetation Science
14
: 
524 - 536
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1654-109X.2011.01155.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Faber-Langendoen, D
, 
Keeler-Wolf, T
, 
Meidinger, D
, 
Josse, C
, 
Weakley, A
, 
Tart, D
, 
Navarro, G
, 
Hoagland, B
, 
Ponomarenko, S
, 
Helmer, E
, 
2016
. 
Classification and description of world formation types. U.S.
Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station [General Technical Report RMRS-GTR-346], Fort Collins, CO, US
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.2737/RMRS-GTR-346
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fischer, HS
, 
2015
. 
On the combination of species cover values from different vegetation layers.
Applied Vegetation Science
18
: 
169 - 170
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/avsc.12130
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fischer, MA
, 
Oswald, K
, 
Adler, W
, 
2008
. 

Exkursionsflora 
fuer
Oesterreich
, Liechtenstein und 
Suedtirol
. 3. Auflage. Biologiezentrum der 
Oberoesterreichischen
Landesmuseen, Linz, AT.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gillet, F
, 
1988
. 

L'approche
synusiale 
integree
des phytoeoenoses 
forestieres
. Application aux 
forets
du Jura.

Colloques Phytosociologiques
14
: 
81 - 92
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gillet, F
, 
Julve, P
, 
2018
. 
The integrated synusial approach to vegetation classification and analysis.
Phytocoenologia
48
: 
141 - 152
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1127/phyto/2017/0164
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grabherr, G
, 
Reiter, K
, 
Willner, W
, 
2003
. 
Towards objectivity in vegetation classification: the example of the Austrian forests.
Plant Ecology
169
: 
21 - 34
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1026280428467
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guarino, R
, 
Willner, W
, 
Pignatti, S
, 
Attorre, F
, 
Loidi, JJ
, 
2018
. 
Spatio-temporal variations in the application of the Braun-Blanquet approach in Europe.
Phytocoenologia
48
: 
239 - 250
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1127/phyto/2017/0181
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hill, M
, 
1979
. 
TWINSPAN - A FORTRAN program for arranging multivariate data in an ordered two-way table by classification of the individuals and attributes. Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, US.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jakucs, P
, 
1961
. 

Die 
phytozoenologischen
Verhaeltnisse
der 
Flaumeichen-Buschwaelder
Suedostmitteleuropas
. 
Akademiai
Kiado
, Budapest, HU.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Keith, DA
, 
Ferrer-Paris, JR
, 
Nicholson, E
, 
Bishop, MJ
, 
Polidoro, BA
, 
Ramirez-Llodra, E
, 
Tozer, MG
, 
Nel, JL
, 
Mac, Nally R
, 
Kingsford, RT
, 
2022
. 

A function-based typology for 
Earth's
ecosystems.

Nature
610
: 
513 - 518
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-05318-4
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Leuschner, C
, 
Ellenberg, H
, 
2017
. 
Ecology of Central European Forests. Vegetation Ecology of Central Europe, Volume I. Springer, Cham, CH.
https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-43042-3
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Loidi, J
, 
2020
. 
The concept of vegetation class and order in phytosociological syntaxonomy.
Vegetation Classification and Survey
1
: 
163 - 167
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.3897/VCS/2020/59977
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Loidi, J
, 

Navarro-Sanchez
, G

, 
Vynokurov, D
, 
2022
. 

Climatic definitions of the 
world's
terrestrial biomes.

Vegetation Classification and Survey
3
: 
231 - 271
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.3897/VCS.86102
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mayer, H
, 
1974
. 

Waelder
des Ostalpenraumes. Gustav Fischer, Stuttgart, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moor, M
, 
1978
. 

Die Klasse der 
Eschen-Buchenwaelder
(
Fraxino-Fagetea
).

Phytocoenologia
4
: 
433 - 445
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1127/phyto/4/1978/433
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mucina, L
, 
2019
. 
Biome: evolution of a crucial ecological and biogeographical concept.
New Phytologist
222
: 
97 - 114
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.15609
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mucina, L
, 
Grabherr, G
, 

Wallnoefer
, S [Eds]

, 
1993
. 

Die Pflanzengesellschaften 
Oesterreichs
, Teil III: 
Waelder
und 
Gebuesche
. Gustav Fischer, Jena, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mucina, L
, 

Bueltmann
, H

, 

Dierssen
, K

, 
Theurillat, J-P
, 
Raus, T
, 

Carni
, A

, 

Sumberova
, K

, 
Willner, W
, 
Dengler, J
, 

Tichy
, L

, 
2016
. 
Vegetation of Europe: Hierarchical floristic classification system of vascular plant, bryophyte, lichen, and algal communities. Applied Vegetation Science 19(Suppl. 1): 3-264.
https://doi.org/10.1111/avsc.12257
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oberdorfer, E
, 
1957
. 

Sueddeutsche
Pflanzengesellschaften. Gustav Fischer, Jena, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oberdorfer, E
, 
1992
. 

Sueddeutsche
Pflanzengesellschaften, 2. Auflage, Teil IV, 
Waelder
und 
Gebuesche
. Gustav Fischer, Jena, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pignatti, S
, 
Oberdorfer, E
, 

Schaminee
, JHJ

, 
Westhoff, V
, 
1995
. 
On the concept of vegetation class in phytosociology.
Journal of Vegetation Science
6
: 
143 - 152
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.2307/3236265
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Schuett
, P

, 
Lang, UM
, 
2014
. 

Corylus avellana. In: Roloff A, Weisgerber H, Lang UM, Stimm B (Eds) 
Enzyklopaedie
der 
Holzgewaechse
: Handbuch und Atlas der Dendrologie. Wiley-VCH, Weinheim, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Tichy
, L

, 
2002
. 

JUICE, software for vegetation 
classiﬁcation
.

Journal of Vegetation Science
13
: 
451 - 453
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1654-1103.2002.tb02069.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Tichy
, L

, 

Chytry
, M

, 
2006
. 
Statistical determination of diagnostic species for site groups of unequal size.
Journal of Vegetation Science
17
: 
809 - 818
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1654-1103.2006.tb02504.x
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Tuexen
, R

, 
1952
. 

Hecken und 
Gebuesche
.

Mitteilungen der Geographischen Gesellschaft in Hamburg
50
: 
85 - 117
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Walter, H
, 
1976
. 

Die 
oekologischen
Systeme der Erde. Prinzipien ihrer Gliederung mit Beispielen. Gustav Fischer, Stuttgart, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Weber, HE
, 
1997
. 

Hecken und 
Gebuesche
in den Kulturlandschaften Europas. Pflanzensoziologische Dokumentation als Basis 
fuer
Schutzmassnahmen
.


Berichte der 
Reinhold-Tuexen-Gesellschaft

9
: 
75 - 106
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Weber, HE
, 
1999
. 

Rhamno-Prunetea (H2A). Schlehen- und 
Traubenholunder-Gebuesche
. In: Dierschke H (Ed.) Synopsis der Pflanzengesellschaften Deutschlands 5. 
Goettingen
, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Westhoff, V
, 
van, der Maarel E
, 
1978
. 
The Braun-Blanquet Approach.
In: 
Whittaker, RH
, Ed., 
Classification of Plant Communities.
Dr. W. Junk, The Hague, NL
: 
287 - 399
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-009-9183-5_9
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Willner, W
, 
2002
. 

Syntaxonomische Revision der 
suedmitteleuropaeischen
Buchenwaelder
.

Phytocoenologia
32
: 
337 - 453
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1127/0340-269X/2002/0032-0337
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Willner, W
, 
2017
. 
Classification of the Austrian forest and shrub communities: concepts, methods and experiences.
Documents Phytosociologiques
6
: 
44 - 50
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Willner, W
, 
Grabherr, G
, 
2007
. 

Die 
Waelder
und 
Gebuesche
Oesterreichs
. Ein Bestimmungswerk mit Tabellen. Spektrum Akademischer Verlag, Heidelberg, DE.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Willner, W
, 
Faber-Langendoen, D
, 
2021
. 
Braun-Blanquet meets EcoVeg: a formation and division level classification of European phytosociological units.
Vegetation Classification and Survey
2
: 
275 - 291
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.3897/VCS/2021/71299
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Willner, W
, 
Berg, C
, 
Heiselmayer, P
, 
2012
. 

Austrian Vegetation Database. In: Dengler J, Oldeland J, Jansen F, 
Chytry
M, Ewald J, Finckh M, 
Gloeckler
F, Lopez-Gonzalez G, Peet RK, 
Schaminee
JHJ (Eds) Vegetation databases for the 21st century. Biodiversity &amp; Ecology 4: 333.

https://doi.org/10.7809/b-e.00125
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Willner, W
, 

Jimenez-Alfaro
, B

, 
Agrillo, E
, 
Biurrun, I
, 
Campos, JA
, 

Carni
, A

, 
Casella, L
, 
Csiky, J
, 

Custerevska
, R

, 

Chytry
, M

, 
2017
. 
Classification of European beech forests: a Gordian Knot? Applied Vegetation Science 20: 494-512.
https://doi.org/10.1111/avsc.12299
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Willner, W
, 
Wessely, J
, 
Gattringer, A
, 
Moser, D
, 

Zaveska
, E

, 
Dullinger, S
, 

Schoenswetter
, P

, 

Huelber
, K

, 
2023
. 
Postglacial range formation of temperate forest understorey herbs - insights from a spatiotemporally explicit modelling approach.
Global Ecology and Biogeography
32
: 
1046 - 1058
, DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.1111/geb.13677
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Zaveska
, E

, 
Kirschner, P
, 
Frajman, B
, 
Wessely, J
, 
Willner, W
, 
Gattringer, A
, 

Huelber
, K

, 

Lazic
, D

, 

Dobes
, C

, 

Schoenswetter
, P

, 
2021
. 
Evidence for glacial refugia of the forest understorey species Helleborus niger (Ranunculaceae) in the southern as well as in the northern Limestone Alps. Frontiers in Plant Science 12: 683043.
https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2021.683043
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿e-mail and orcid">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>E-mail and ORCID</p>
         <p>
Wolfgang Willner
(Corresponding author, wolfgang.willner@univie.ac.at), ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1591-8386
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Supplementary materials</p>Supplementary material 1 Full synoptic table</sec>
   </body>
</article>
