<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Zoodiversity</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15407/zoo2024.01.79</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Biometric Analysis Of Fish Remains From Palaeolake Boltysh (Ukraine)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2024</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gonorynchidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Umbridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus avitus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>

Notogoneus

, 

Boltyshia

</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
Sytchevskaya, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus avitus
Sytchevskaya, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tretoperca vestita
Sytchevskaya, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amiidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gonorynchidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Umbridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Percichthyidae (
Dykan et al., 2018
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tretoperca vestita
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus avitus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
Sytchevskaya, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
avitus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
Sytchevskaya, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus avitus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>

Notogoneus gracilis
Sytchevskaya, 1986

: 
26
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>

Thaumaturus avitus
Sytchevskaya, 1986

: 
7
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>UDC 567.5+591.4(477.65)</p>
         <p>

BIOMETRIC ANALYSIS OF FISH REMAINS FROM PALAEOLAKE BOLTYSH (
UKRAINE
)

</p>
         <p>
A. Dubikovska
1,
*&amp; 
О. Kovalchuk
1,2,3
</p>
         <p>
1
Department of Biology and Biology Teaching Methodology, Faculty of Natural Sciences and Geography,
</p>
         <p>

A. S. Makarenko 
Sumy State
Pedagogical University, 87 Romenska St., 

Sumy
, 40002 
Ukraine
</p>
         <p>
2

Department of Palaeontology, National Museum of Natural History, NAS of 
Ukraine
, 15 B. 
Khmelnytskyi
St., 
Kyiv
01054 
Ukraine
</p>
         <p>
3

Department of Palaeozoology, Faculty of Biological Sciences, University of Wrocław, 21 Sienkiewicza St., Wrocław 50-335, 
Poland
</p>
         <p>
*Corresponding author:
</p>
         <p>
E-mail: oakovska@gmail.com
</p>
         <p>A. Dubikovska (https://orcid.org/0009-0001-7191-0090)</p>
         <p>O. Kovalchuk (https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9545-208X)</p>
         <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 
CD4FADC4-1882-4919-AFA7-68D060EE0DCC
</p>
         <p>

Biometric Analysis of Fish Remains from Palaeolake Boltysh (
Ukraine
). Dubikovska, A. &amp; Koval-chuk, О.

— The results of the study of the meristic and morphometric characters of complete and fragmentary skeletons of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Gonorynchidae</tp:taxon-name>
) and 
Boltyshia brevicauda
(
<tp:taxon-name>Umbridae</tp:taxon-name>
) recovered from Paleocene–Eocene lacustrine deposits of the Boltysh impact structure are presented in the paper. Some of the specimens previously assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus avitus
</tp:taxon-name>
were re-identified as 
Boltyshia brevicauda
. The meristic characters of the specimens considered are stable in both species and refer to those in the respective 
type
series. A previously unknown caudal fin formula (I 6–6 I) is observed in several specimens of 
Boltyshia brevicauda
. The latter species is characterised by more variable meristic characters compared to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
Key words: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus

, 

Boltyshia
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
meristic traits
, 
metric traits
, 
squamation
.
</p>
         <p>
© Publisher Publishing House "Akademperiodyka" of the NAS of 
Ukraine
, 2024. The article is published under an open access license CC BY-NC-ND (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The Boltysh (Bovtyshka) impact structure was formed 65.59 ± 0.64 Ma (roughly at the Cretaceous–Paleogene boundary) in the central part of the modern territory of 
Ukraine
(

, 

; 

; 

). Considering the meteoric origin of the crater and the features of the lake that existed within its borders for a long time (

; 

; 

), Boltysh represents a unique locality yielding numerous remains of Paleocene–Eocene vertebrates, mostly of endemic taxa (

, 

; 

; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The species composition of bony fishes from palaeolake Boltysh is generally well known. A series of imprints obtained from boreholes was assigned to a number of taxa (Amiinae gen. et sp. indet., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
Sytchevskaya, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus avitus
Sytchevskaya, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Boltyshia brevicauda

, 
Boltyshia truncata

, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tretoperca vestita
Sytchevskaya, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
) representing five families: 
<tp:taxon-name>Amiidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Gonorynchidae</tp:taxon-name>
, Thaumaturidae, 
<tp:taxon-name>Umbridae</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Percichthyidae (
Dykan et al., 2018
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. These fishes inhabited a lake that had occasional water exchange with the Tethys Ocean (

; 

). Their remains are likely to have been transported at some distance prior to burial in an oxygenfree environment.
</p>
         <p>
A number of fish specimens from Boltysh are stored in the collection of the Department of Palaeontology of the National Museum of Natural History, National Academy of Sciences of 
Ukraine
(
Kyiv
). This is valuable material as it includes both complete and near-complete fish skeletons with imprints of internal organs. Preliminary species identification of the specimens from this sample was carried out at the macromorphological level. The data on meristic and morphometric characters for most fish species from the Boltysh locality are rather limited or incomplete, while those provided by 

, 

) in most cases represent the relative values of particular morphometric characters, expressed in percentages (e. g., the ratio of orbital diameter to head length). It is rather problematic to use such data without having information about the linear values of the respective measurements because the original linear values can’t be derived from ratios themselves. Some meristic characters mentioned in diagnoses (e. g., the number of dorsal and ventral fin rays, the number of precaudal vertebrae in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Boltyshia
) are the same or strongly overlap, and in this case the use of morphometric characters allows additionally clarifying the species identification for some problematic specimens. The study of a series of specimens is also important for the estimation of the range of intraspecific variability since the accuracy of results strongly depends on the sample size, as well as for further clarification of patterns of morphological disparity between discrete faunas.
</p>
         <p>
The aim of this paper is to present a revised list of taxonomic composition of fish remains recovered from Boltysh and to carry out a biometric analysis of a series of fish remains belonging to the species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Boltyshia brevicauda
endemic to Palaeolake Boltysh, comparing them with the respective data of the 
type
series.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Material and Methods
</title>
         <p>
The studied sample consists of 91 fish imprints, some of which represent complete specimens while others are fragmentary, obtained from a depth of 307.0– 
434.5 m
. These specimens were recovered during core drilling within the Boltysh impact structure in the vicinity of the village of Bovtyshka in 
Kirovohrad Oblast
, central 
Ukraine
. Fragmentary specimens (including various combinations of body parts with fins, heads, or tails) are much more numerous, while only 
Boltyshia brevicauda
is represented by 10 complete skeletons, which provided comprehensive results for this species compared to other taxa from the sample. Original data (

) were used to identify the species affiliation of the specimens, and all available characters were subjected to morphometric and meristic analysis. In order to minimize error in meristic variables, counts were carried out twice: once from the anterior and once from the posterior end of the body, following the methodologies of 

and of 

. Morphometric measurements follow 

, 

) methods; they were taken in three repetitions with digital calipers, with an accuracy of 
0.01 mm
.
</p>
         <p>
The following parameters were measured in the specimens from Boltysh: standard length; preorbital length; orbital diameter; postorbital length; head length; head depth; length of the lower jaw; maximum and minimum body depth; predorsal, preventral, preanal, pectoroventral and ventroanal length; dorsal and anal fin base length, and caudal peduncle length. Calculations were carried out in MS Excel 2010. Photographs of the specimens were taken with a Canon PowerShot SX530 HS camera; microphotographs of scales were made using a ZOOM MICROmed trinocular microscope, equipped with a SL-CMOS/CCD microscope camera and Tsview 7 modular software. Abbreviations used: HL —head length; NMNHU-P Pi — Department of Palaeontology, National Museum of Natural History, National Academy of Sciences of 
Ukraine
(collection Pisces); PIN — Borissiak Palaeontological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences; SD — standard deviation; SL — standard length; TL —total length.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results
</title>
         <p>Species composition</p>
         <p>An updated species list of fish specimens recovered from the Boltysh locality (with the information on the depth from which the respective samples were collected as well as borehole numbers) is presented in the Appendix.</p>
         <p>
The Boltysh assemblage is taxonomically similar to those known from Paleocene and Eocene localities elsewhere in Europe: Menat and Montmartre in 
France
, Messel, Eckfeld and Geiseltal in 
Germany
, and Kučlín in the 
Czech Republic
(

; 

; 

, 

; 

; 

; 

). 
Boltyshia brevicauda
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
are the most abundant taxa in the Boltysh assemblage (
figs 1
, 
2
), being represented by specimens in different states of preservation; other taxa are relatively rare. The smallest number of imprints obtained from Boltysh represent an undetermined amiine fish, 
Boltyshia truncata
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tretoperca vestita
</tp:taxon-name>
. The preservation of two other imprints is extremely poor and thus they remain undetermined.
</p>
         <p>

pointed out the presence of ten complete and fragmentary specimens identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus avitus
</tp:taxon-name>
in the NMNHU-P collection. During our study, these imprints were revised and reassigned to 
Boltyshia brevicauda
, based on both meristic and morphometric parameters.
</p>
         <p>Meristic characters</p>
         <p>
The meristic characters of the specimens in the sample are quite stable and species-specific (see 

for more details). The meristic characters collected include the number of precaudal and caudal vertebrae as well as the number of rays in paired and unpaired fins (
table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
The total number of vertebrae in the specimens considered refers to those in the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Boltyshia brevicauda
(

). It is impossible to accurately count the number of precaudal vertebrae in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
due to poor preservation of the specimens, which prevents the unambiguous identification of the first caudal centrum.
</p>
         <p>
The numbers of dorsal and ventral fin rays in the imprints of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Boltyshia brevicauda
fall within the ranges of those seen in their respective 
type
series. The same was observed with regards to the number of anal fin rays of 
B. brevicauda
, while this character in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
coincides with only one of the values within the interval determined in 

.
</p>
         <p>
The number of pectoral fin rays in specimens of the two studied species is identical to those from their respective 
type
series. The caudal fin formula of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
is also equal to that originally established for this species (

). The caudal fin formula of 
Boltyshia brevicauda
appears to be the most variable species-specific character: the most frequent formula in the sample is I 7–6 I (
7 specimens
), although it does not correspond to the formula indicated for the species in 

, 

). 
Three specimens
of 
B. brevicauda
from the NMNHU-P (Pi 320, Pi 333, and Pi 344) have a previously unknown caudal fin formula of I 6-6 I.
</p>
         <p>
The most stable (i. e., least variable) meristic characters in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
are the number of rays in dorsal, ventral, and caudal fins (II 9, I 6, and I 8–9 I, respectively). All meristic characters of 
Boltyshia brevicauda
are characterised by a certain range of variability (
table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>Total number of vertebrae 45–47 45–47 33–36 33–36 29 36–39 Abdominal vertebrae? 33 18–20 18–20 15 18</p>
         <p>Dorsal fin rays II 9 II 9 11–13 11–13 II 11 12</p>
         <p>Anal fin rays II 6 II 6–7 8–12 8–12 I 9 16–17 Pectoral fin rays 10–11 10–11 15–20 15–20 19 11 Ventral fin rays I 6 I 6 8–10 8–10 9 7–8 Caudal fin rays I 8-9 I I 8-9 I I 7-6 I** I 6–8-7–8 I 15 I 8-8 I</p>
         <p>
* Data presented after 

. ** Other variants of the caudal fin-rays formula for this sample are the following: I 6–7 I; I 6–6 I.
</p>
         <p>Morphometric characters</p>
         <p>
Morphometric characters of fishes are more variable than meristic ones because they change during ontogeny and under the influence of environmental factors (

; 

; 

). Values of the 16 morphometric characters were analysed, mean values and standard deviations were calculated along with the ratio of head measurements and standard length wherever possible. This is the first time that most of these morphometric data are presented for the studied species.
</p>
         <p>
The state of preservation of the specimens assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
does not make it possible to estimate the ratio of individual measurements to standard length. In addition, it was not possible to measure their preventral and ventroanal length. Several characters (e. g., length of the lower jaw, predorsal and preanal length, dorsal and anal fin base length, caudal peduncle length) can only be estimated in some specimens. However, it was possible to measure other parameters, in particular preorbital length, orbital diameter, postorbital length, head depth, as well as the ratio of the length of the lower jaw to the head length (
table 2
). All of the obtained data complement and expand the ranges established based on the study of the 
type
series, except for the length of the lower jaw (

).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
The least variable characters in the studied sample of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
are postorbital and pectoroventral length (SD &lt;1), orbital diameter, minimum body depth, and caudal peduncle height (SD &lt;2). In 
Boltyshia brevicauda
(
table 3
), the least variable morphometric parameters are preorbital length, orbital diameter, minimum body depth, dorsal and anal fin base length (SD &lt;2). Information about these is presented for the first time here, because these characters are missing from the original description of the species. The expansion of the ranges of relative body parameters can be explained by the presence of individuals representing different ecomorphs 
sensu

, 

) in the studied sample.
</p>
         <p>S q u a m a t i o n</p>
         <p>
Cycloid scales of 
Boltyshia brevicauda
(
fig. 3
, A, B) are thin, densely placed, and cover the entire body, head, and proximal parts of the caudal fin rays. Their basal edge is uneven and sinuous. The focus is located in the center or shifted towards the basal edge. Thin sclerites converge near the basal edge and widely diverge in the apical part. The arrangement of the scales is tile-like, individual scales overlapping to some extent, with their lateral edges forming parallel lines on dorsal and ventral sides of the body, as well as near the caudal fin in some individuals. Small ctenoid scales of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
(
fig. 3
, C) bear three to five cteni on their rounded apical edge.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
Discussion
</title>
         <p>
The study of intraspecific variation in fossil species requires the presence of large and well-preserved samples with a clear stratigraphic context in order to minimize sampling bias and avoid taxon oversplitting (e. g., 

; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Although the series of fish imprints from Boltysh in the NMNHU-P collection is less numerous than the material analysed by 

, its study largely contributes to the understanding of the morphological variation of these endemic fish taxa, including the clarification of species-specific and diagnostically important parameters. The absolute values of the morphometric characters, presented here for the first time, additionally allow the determination of their variability among the several complete imprints in the studied sample representing each species. All ranges of values that could be determined for both species considered were compared to those of the 
type
series. This material also allows more precise species identification and comparison with fish remains originating from other deposits of the same age.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
is characterised by several stable meristic characters, in particular the number of dorsal, ventral and caudal fin rays, and the number of precaudal vertebrae (n = 33); however, it is impossible to confirm the latter due to poor preservation of most imprints in the studied sample. A total of 
26 specimens
in the NMNHU-P collection were identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notogoneus gracilis
</tp:taxon-name>
; they differ from the other species of this genus by morphology and biometric parameters (e. g., 

; Grande et al., 2022).
</p>
         <p>
In 
Boltyshia brevicauda
, all meristic traits are variable among the examined specimens, although our counts fall within the previously defined ranges (

, 

). The most variable fin formula in this species is that of the caudal fin. Some meristic characters of 
B. brevicauda
— the number of dorsal, ventral and caudal fin rays, the number of precaudal vertebrae — are similar to or overlap with those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus avitus
</tp:taxon-name>
, which may cause difficulties during the identification of incomplete fish imprints. Because of this, a special attention should be taken for the correct differentiation of the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumaturus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Boltyshia
when using the number of anal and pectoral fin rays, the structure of the caudal fin skeleton, or the morphology and placement of scales.
</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgements
</p>
         <p>
The research was carried out as part of a master’s research project of AD. The research of OK was supported by the individual grant ‘The role of particular fish groups in the functioning of late Mesozoic and Cenozoic ecosystems of Eastern Europe’ (0123U102984) from the National Academy of Sciences of 
Ukraine
. We are sincerely thankful to J. Divay (Royal Tyrrell Museum of Palaeontology, Drumheller, 
Canada
), N. Dykan (Institute of Geological Sciences, National Academy of Sciences of 
Ukraine
), T. Grande (Loyola University Chicago, 
USA
), and N. Trif (Brukenthal National Museum, 
Romania
) for their useful comments and advice. We also wish to thank T. Přikryl (Institute of Geology of the Czech Academy of Sciences) for consultations, and Z. Barkaszi (National Museum of Natural History, National Academy of Sciences of 
Ukraine
) for proofreading the manuscript.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Barton, D. G.
&amp; 
Wilson, M. V. H.
1999
. 
Microstratigraphic study of meristic variation in an Eocene fish from a 10 000-year varved interval at Horsefly, British Columbia
. 

Canadian Journal of Earth Science

, 

36

(
12
), 
2059–2072
, 
https://doi.org/10.1139/e99-085
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Behrensmeyer, A. K.
1982
. 
Time resolution in fluvial vertebrate assemblages
. 

Paleobiology

, 

8

(
3
), 
211–227
, 
https://doi.org/10.1017/S0094837300006941
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Böhme, M.
&amp; 
Ilg, A.
2003
. 
fosFARbase
, 
www.wahre-staerke.com/(2023-10-28)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bookstein, F. L.
, 
Gingerich, P. D.
&amp; 
Kluge, A. G.
1978
. 
Hierarchical linear modelling of the tempo and mode of evolution
. 

Paleobiology

, 

4

(
2
), 
120–134
, 
https://doi.org/10.1017/S0094837300005807
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cavagnetto, C.
&amp; 
Gaudant, J.
2000
. 
A palynoflora of Palaeocene age from the fossiliferous sapropels of the Boltyshka depression, Central Ukraine
. 

Newsletters in Stratigraphy

, 

38

, 
39–56
, https://doi.org/- 
10.1127/nos/38/2000/39
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Divay, J. D.
, 
Brinkman, D. B.
&amp; 
Neuman, A. G.
2020
. 

Late Cretaceous 
Notogoneus
from microvertebrate assemblages of the Dinosaur Park Formation, Campanian of southern Alberta, Canada, and insight into the ecology and evolution of early gonorynchids

. 

Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology

, 

39

(
5
), 
https://doi.org/10.1080/02724634.2019.1699801
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dubikovska, A.
&amp; 
Kovalchuk, O.
2022
. 
The history of the study of Paleogene fauna of Bovtyshka locality
. 
In
: 
Kornus, A. O.
, 
Mironets, L. P.
, 
Babenko, O. M.
, 
Kornus, O. G.
&amp; 
Lytvynenko, Yu. I.
, eds. 

Educational and scientific dimensions of natural sciences
: Proceedings of the Third All-Ukrainian scientific conference (November 09, 2022)

. 
A. S. Makarenko Sumy State Pedagogical University, Sumy
, 
92–95
[Ukrainian].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dykan, K. V.
&amp; 
Dykan, N. I.
2020
. 
Boltysh astrobleme (impact structure): Where? When? As?

Reports of the National Academy of Sciences of Ukraine

, 

2

, 
52–57
, 
https://doi.org/10.15407/dopovidi2020.02.052
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dykan, N.
, 
Kovalchuk, O.
, 
Dykan, K.
, 
Gurov, E.
, 
Dašková, J.
&amp; 
Přikryl, T.
2018
. 
New data on Paleocene–Eocene fauna (gastropods, ostracods, fishes) and palynoflora of the Boltysh impact structure (Ukraine) with biostatigraphical and paleoecological inferences
. 

Neues Jahrbuch für Geologie und Paläontologie Abhandlungen

, 

287

(
2
), 
213–239
, 
https://doi.org/10.1127/njgpa/2018/0714
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ebinghaus, A.
, 
Jolley, D. W.
, 
Andrews, S. D.
&amp; 
Kemp, D. B.
2017
. 
Lake sedimentological and ecological response to hyperthermals: Boltysh impact crater, Ukraine
. 

Sedimentology

, 

64

(
6
), 
1465–1487
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/sed.12360
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elder, R. L.
&amp; 
Smith, G. R.
1988
. 
Fish taphonomy and environmental inference in paleolimnology
. 

Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology

, 

62

, 
577–592
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frey, L.
, 
Maxwell, E. E.
&amp; 
Sánchez-Villagra, M. R.
2016
. 
Intraspecific variation in fossil vertebrate populations: Fossil killifishes (Actinopterygii: Cyprinodontiformes) from the Oligocene of Central Europe
. 

Palaeontologia Electronica

, 

19

.2.14A, 
1–27
, 
https://doi.org/10.26879/628
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gaudant, J.
1979
. 
Mise au point sur l’ichthyofaune paleocene de Menat (Puy-de-Dome)
. 

Comptes Rendus Hebdomadaires des Seances de L’academie des Sciences
, Serie D

, 

28819

, 
1461–1464
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gaudant, J.
1981
. 
Nouvelles recherches sur l’ichthyofaune des gypses et des marnes supragypseuses (Eocène supérieur) des environs de Paris
. 

Bulletin du Bureau de Recherches Geologiques et Minieres
, sect. IV

, 

2

(
1
), 
57–75
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gaudant, J.
2012
. 
An attempt at the palaeontological history of the European mudminnows (Pisces, Teleostei, Umbridae)
. 

Neues Jahrbuch für Geologie und Paläontologie Abhandlungen

, 

263

(
2
), 
93–109
, 
https://doi.org/10.1127/0077-7749/2012/0214
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gilmour, I.
, 
Gilmour, M.
, 
Jolley, D.
, 
Kelley, S.
, 
Kemp, D.
, 
Daly, R.
&amp; 
Watson, J.
2013
. 
A high-resolution nonmarine record of an early Danian hyperthermal event, Boltysh crater, Ukraine
. 

Geology

, 

41

(
7
), 
783–786
, 
https://doi.org/10.1130/G34292.1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gilmour, I.
, 
Jolley, D.
, 
Kemp, D.
, 
Kelley, S.
, 
Gilmour, M.
, 
Daly, R.
&amp; 
Widdowson, M.
2014
. 
The early Danian hyperthermal event at Boltysh (Ukraine); relation to Cretaceous–Paleogene boundary events
. 

Special Papers – Geological Society of America

, 

505

, 
133–146
, 
https://doi.org/10.1130/2014.2505(06)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grande, T. C.
, 
Wilson, M. V. H.
, 
Reyes, A. V.
, 
Buryak, S. D.
, 
Wolfe, A. P.
&amp; 
Siver, P. A.
2020
. 

A new, Late Cretaceous gonorynchiform fish in the genus † 
Notogoneus
from drill core of crater-lake deposits in a kimberlite maar, Northwest Territories, Canada

. 

Cretaceous Research

, 

135

, 
105176
, 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cretres.2022.105176
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gurov, E. P.
, 
Kelley, S. P.
, 
Koeberl, C.
&amp; 
Dykan, N.
2006
. 
Sediments and impact rock filling the Boltysh impact crater
. 
In
: 
Coccel, C.
, 
Koeberl, C.
, 
Gilmour, I.
, eds. 

Biological Processes Associated with Impact Events

. 
Springer, Berlin
, 
335–358
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jerzmańska, A.
1977
. 
The freshwater fishes from the Middle Eocene of Geiseltal
. 

Martin-Luther-Universität Halle-Wittenberg, Wissenschaftliche Beiträge

, 

1977

(
2
), 
41–65
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Micklich, N.
&amp; 
Klappert, G.
2004
. 
Character variation in some Messel fishes
, 
In
: 
Arratia, G.
, 
Tintori, A.
, eds. 

Mesozoic Fishes 3 – Systematics, Paleoenvironments and Biodiversity

. 
Verlag Dr. Friedrich Pfeil, München, Germany
, 
137–163
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pickersgill, A. E.
, 
Mark, D. F.
, 
Lee, M. R.
, 
Kelley, S. P.
&amp; 
Jolley, D. W.
2021
. 
The Boltysh impact structure: An early Danian impact event during recovery from the K-Pg mass extinction
. 

Science Advances

, 

7

(
25
), eabe6530, 
https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.abe6530
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Skutschas, P. P.
&amp; 
Gubin, Y. M.
2012
. 
A new salamander from the late Paleocene–early Eocene of Ukraine
. 

Acta Palaeontologica Polonica

, 

57

(
1
), 
135–148
, 
http://dx.doi.org/10.4202/app.2010.0101
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smith, G. R.
, 
Stearley, R. F.
&amp; 
Badgley, C. E.
1988
. 
Taphonomic bias in fish diversity from Cenozoic floodplain environments
. 

Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology

, 

63

(1– 
3
), 
263–273
, 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-0182(88)90099-5
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sytchevskaya, E. K.
1976
. 
The fossil esocoid fishes of the USSR and Mongolia
. 

Transactions of the Palaeontological Institute of the Academy of Sciences of USSR

, 

156

, 
1–116
[In Russian].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sytchevskaya, E. K.
1986
. 
Palaeogene freshwater fish fauna of the USSR and Mongolia
. 

Transactions of the Joint Soviet-Mongolian Paleontological Expedition

, 

29

, 
1–158
[In Russian].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sytchevskaya, E. K.
&amp; 
Daniltshenko, P. G.
1975
. 
A new genus of the family Palaeoesocidae from the Lower Paleogene of Ukraine
. 
In
: 
Shimansky, V. N.
&amp; 
Soloviov, A. N.
, eds. 

Razvitie i smena organicheskogo mira na rubezhe mezozoya i kainozoya
[Development and changes of organic world at the Mesozoic–Cenozoic boundary]

. 
Nauka, Moscow
, 
117–125
[In Russian].
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Voigt, E.
1934
. 
Die Fische der mitteleozänen Braunkohle des Geiseltales
. 

Nova Acta Leopoldina, Neue Folge

, 

2

(1– 
2
), 
21–146
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
