<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Zoodiversity</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15407/zoo2023.06.521</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Seasonal Variation (Winter Vs. Summer) Crustacean Fauna Of The Oualidia Lagoon, Morocco</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
(Fabricius, 1787)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tanais dulongii
(Audouin, 1826)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Apseudes
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eurydice pulchra
Leach, 1815
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Melita palmata
(Montagu, 1804)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Caprella liparotensis
Haller, 1879
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ampithoe
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gammaridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cyathura carinata
(KrØyer, 1847)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Idotea balthica
(Pallas, 1772)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eurydice pulchra
(Leach, 1815)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
(Fabricius, 1787)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tanais dulongii
(Audouin, 1826)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Apseudes
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Palaemon elegans
(Rathke, 1837)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pagurus bernhardus
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Carcinus maenas
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Balanus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tanais dulongi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeroma</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eurydice pulchra</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cyathura carinata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Balanus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corophium sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Idotea balthica</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Tanais dulongi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Melita palmata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeroma serratum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pagurus bernhardus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Carcinus maenas</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Apseudes
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Caprella liparotensis, Cumacea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ampithoe sp.</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeroma serratum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Tanais dulongi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Idotea balthica</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cyathura carinata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pagurus bernhardus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tanais dulongii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Apseudes
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eurydice pulchra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Melita palmata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Corophium acherusicum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cyathura carinata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma hookeri
(
Chaouti &amp; Bayed, 2005
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gammarus aequicauda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Idotea chelipes</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma hookeri
(
Casagranda et al., 2006
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cyathura carinata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lekanesphaera rugicauda
Touhami et al., 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>UDC 595.3(64)</p>
         <p>

SEASONAL VARIATION (WINTER VS. SUMMER) CRUSTACEAN FAUNA OF THE OUALIDIA LAGOON, 
MOROCCO
</p>
         <p>
F. El Asri
* 
1, 4
, 
A. Errhif
1
, 
M. N. Tamsouri
2
, 
M. Maanan
3
, 
H. Zidane
4
</p>
         <p>
1

Health and Environment Laboratory, Faculty of Sciences Ain Chock, University Hassan II, B.P. 5366 Maârif, 20100 Casablanca, 
Morocco
</p>
         <p>
2

Specialized Center in Zootechnics and Marine Aquaculture Engineering, National Institute of Fisheries Research, BP. 31, 93200 M'diq, 
Morocco
</p>
         <p>
3

Geolittomer Laboratory, UMR 6554 LETG, University of Nantes, Nantes, 
France
</p>
         <p>
4

Prospection of Littoral Resources Laboratory, National Institute for Fisheries Research (INRH). Road Sidi Abderrahmane Club Equestre Ould Jmel – Casablanca, 
Morocco
</p>
         <p>
*Corresponding author
</p>
         <p>
E-mail: fatimaelasri25@gmail.com

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 
F8C5A2E2-4968-4490-9C9E-D9ED6E4F3986
</p>
         <p>

Seasonal Variation (Winter vs. Summer) Crustacean Fauna of the Oualidia Lagoon, 
Morocco
. El Asri, F., Errhif, A., Tamsouri, M. N., Maanan, M., Zidane, H.

— The Oualidia lagoon on the Atlantic coast of Morocco provides important ecosystem services such as aquaculture, fisheries, tourism and high ecological and biological productivity. This is the first study to describe the spatio-temporal distribution of the crustacean community and potential controlling factors in the coastal waters of the Oualidia lagoon. Crustaceans were sampled with a Van Veen grab during two surveys in winter and summer 2013, and taxonomic composition and diversity were determined at 43 sampling sites. Of the eighteen crustacean taxa recorded, fifteen were new to Oualidia Lagoon. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
was the most abundant species in both seasons. Organic matter and chlorophyll a content were higher, temperature and salinity were lower in winter than in summer. The structure of the crustacean assemblages was characterised by the formation of two main clusters, organised according to a downstream gradient. Canonical Correspondence Analysis (CCA) showed that granulometry, organic matter and salinity strongly influenced the distribution pattern of crustaceans in the lagoon.
</p>
         <p>
Key words: 
Coastal lagoon
, 
Oualidia lagoon
, 
Atlantic coast
, 
temporal distribution
, 
crustacean assemblage
, 

Morocco

.
</p>
         <p>
© Publisher Publishing House "Akademperiodyka" of the NAS of 
Ukraine
, 2023. The article is published under an open access license CC BY-NC-ND (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Coastal zones represent the natural interface between land and sea and are valuable ecosystems due to their remarkable productivity and diversity (

), despite their relatively small contribution to the global marine area. These ecosystems are inherently fragile and their ecological balance can change rapidly under the influence of natural or anthropogenic factors (

; 

, 

, 

, 2015; 

; 

, 2017).
</p>
         <p>
Macroinvertebrates are widely used as indicators of coastal environmental status. Crustaceans are a key group and play an important role in maintaining the functioning of marine benthic ecosystems (

) and are an important source of food for human consumption. In addition, the crustacean fauna is ecologically very sensitive to pollution, making it a good bioindicator of natural or disturbed environmental conditions (

).
</p>
         <p>
The Oualidia lagoon is one of the most important lagoon systems in 
Morocco
. It is a RAMSAR wetland of international interest and the most important wintering area for migratory birds in 
Morocco
.
</p>
         <p>
Despite its interest, the studies on the Oualidia lagoon have mainly focused on oceanography (

; Hilmi et al. 2005; Damsiri et al., 2014; 

) and wholesomeness (

; Zourarah et al., 2007; 

). Few studies have focused on benthic biodiversity (

; 

, 

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>The novelty of this study is the first examination of crustaceans inhabiting the Oualidia lagoon to provide an overview of the spatio-temporal biodiversity of crustaceans, with particular emphasis on their distribution patterns and community structure, and their relationships with the main environmental variables.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Material and Methods
</title>
         <p>Study area</p>
         <p>

The Oualidia lagoon, 
34°47' N
‒ 
6°13' W
and 
34°52' N
‒ 
6°14' W
, is located on the 
Atlantic
coast of 
Morocco
(
fig. 1
). 
The
lagoon is 
7 km
long and approximately 
1 km
wide. 
It
extends along a north-south depression bounded by a continental cliff and a coastal dune ridge. 
Water
exchange with the ocean occurs through a large inlet about 

150 m

wide with a shallower, narrower inlet (~ 

50 m

wide) that is also active during spring tides. 
The
morphology of the lagoon is characterised by lateral channels connected to a meandering main channel with an average depth of 

2 m

and a maximum depth (during high tide) that does not exceed 

5 m

(

). Flood tides inundate much of 75 % (
2.25 km
²) of the lagoon surface, bringing saline water into the inner lagoon region and into a saline marsh beyond the inner dam (
fig. 1
)

.
</p>
         <p>Sampling and data analysis</p>
         <p>
Forty-three stations (
fig. 1
) were sampled in winter (March, 2013) and summer (
July 2013
). All samples (two replicates per station) were collected using a Van Veen grab (
0.125 m
2
surface area). Material retained on the mesh (
1 mm
pore size) was transferred to containers and fixed in a 10 % formalin solution. An additional sediment sample was collected for analysis of grain size, and organic matter and chlorophyll a content. The grain size of the sediment collected at each sampling site was analysed using a laser a laser granulometer (Malvern, Mastersizer) at the LETG (UMR 6554, University of Nantes) and expressed as mean grain size, in µm. The percentage of organic matter (OM, %) of the sediment was obtained as the weight losses of dried samples (24 h, 60 °C) after ignition (4h, 450 °C). Chlorophyll a content (chl-a, mg/m²) was determined according to the Lorenzen method (Holm-Hansen 
et al
., 1965). Crustaceans were sorted under a binocular microscope and identified to species level, whenever possible. To analyse the structure of the assemblages, the following indices were calculated: (1) species richness (S: number of species per sample); (2) species abundance (N: individuals/m²); (3) diversity as indicated by the Shannon index (H′, log 
2
basis) (

); and the evenness index (J′) (

). To separate the stations into homogeneous groups, Hierarchical Ascending Classification (HAC) analyses were applied to the sampling stations, based on Euclidean distance and the Wards method using log10(x + 1) to limit the influence of the most dominant taxa. Wilcoxon tests were used to determine the significance (P = 0.05) of the difference between seasons. All these analyses were performed using STATISTICA version 8 for Windows. Canonical Correspondence Analyses (CCA) were performed using the free software package PAST 3.0 to analyse the relationships between environmental variables and crustacean assemblages. Environmental variables and crustacean densities were log10(x+1) transformed prior to analysis.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results
</title>
         <p>Crustacean community structure</p>
         <p>
8721 crustaceans specimens belonging to 18 taxa were collected during this study (
table 1
). Among them, 440 individuals from 17 taxa occurred in winter and 8,281 from 13 taxa in summer. The most abundant taxa in winter were 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
(Fabricius, 1787)
</tp:taxon-name>
(23.6 %), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tanais dulongii
(Audouin, 1826)
</tp:taxon-name>
(28.2 %), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Apseudes
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(9.5 %) 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eurydice pulchra
Leach, 1815
</tp:taxon-name>
(10.2 %). The first one were also dominant in summer (53.7 %) followed by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(34.5 %).Crustaceans densities were significantly higher (
p
&lt;0.05) in summer (0 to 1800 individuals/m²) than in winter (0 to 104 individuals/m²)(
fig. 2
, A). The number of taxa ranged from 0 to
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
10 (winter) or 5 (summer). However, there were non-significant differences (
p
˃ 0.05) (
fig. 2
, B). The Shannon diversity was similar in winter (0‒ 2.8 bits) than in summer (0‒2.1 bits) (
p
˃ 0.05) (
fig. 2
, C) and, similarly, there were non-significant differences in evenness between both seasons (
p
˃ 0.05) (
fig. 2
, D). Two station clusters were obtained both during winter and summer in the Hierarchical Ascending Classification analyses. Group 
1 in
winter (fig. 3, A) included stations mainly from the inner region of the lagoon, characterized by having sediments mainly composed by silt and clay in different proportions, high temperatures and OM and a low average crustaceans density (10.5 individuals/m²). The dominant taxa was 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
, followed by Ostracoda. Group 2 consisted of 11 stations mainly close to the lagoon opening, with predominantly sandy sediments, low temperatures and organic matter, and a relatively low average density (24.7 individuals/m 
2)
. The dominant taxa was 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tanais dulongi
</tp:taxon-name>
. During summer (fig. 3, B), group 1 included stations, mainly located in the inner region of the lagoon, characterized by having relatively high temperatures, high organic matter, clay and silty clay sediments and a high average density (491.4 individuals/m 
2
). The dominant species were 

<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeroma</tp:taxon-name>
serra-

</p>
         <p>
Fig. 3. Dendrogram showing the groups of stations formed by Cluster analysis for the 378 study area; 
tum
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
Group 2 included sta-
</p>
         <p>A — winter, B — summer; Gr 1— group 1; Gr 2 — tions located mostly near the lagoon opening,</p>
         <p>group 2. characterized by having low temperatures,</p>
         <p>
organic matter, very low chlorophyll a, a high percentage of sand, and the lowest recorded average density (93.4 individuals/m²). The dominant taxa was 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>R e l a t i o n s h i p s b e t w e e n t h e d e s c r i p t o r s o f t h e c r u s t a c e a n s a s s e m b l a g e s and the environmental variables</p>
         <p>
In winter, the first two CCA axes accounted for 81.07 % of the observed variance. The taxa composition was mainly related to salinity, OM and granulometry (
fig. 4
, A). In summer, the first two CCA axes accounted for 87.91 % of the relationships, with the most influencing environmental variables being salinity (
fig. 4
, B).
</p>
         <p>
In winter, the projections of the taxa on the environmental parameters vectors (
fig. 4
, B) showed the positive correlations of 

<tp:taxon-name>Eurydice pulchra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyathura carinata</tp:taxon-name>
,

<tp:taxon-name>
Balanus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corophium sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
with granulometry. In turn, the other taxa like 

<tp:taxon-name>Idotea balthica</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tanais dulongi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Melita palmata</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeroma serratum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pagurus bernhardus</tp:taxon-name>

were positively correlated with salinity, organic matter, chlorophyll a and temperature. As for the stations, they are left-right oriented for axis 1, which corresponds to a downstream-upstream gradient. Accordingly, downstream stations (e. g., 29, 31, 34, 35, 36, 37, 38) were characterized by larger grain sizes and high salinity, whereas the upstream stations (e. g., 4, 8, 9, 11, 12, 15, 16) were characterized by high temperature and organic matter.
</p>
         <p>
In summer, the projections of the taxa on the environmental parameters vectors (
fig. 4
, B) showed the positive correlations of 

<tp:taxon-name>Carcinus maenas</tp:taxon-name>
,

<tp:taxon-name>
Apseudes
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Caprella liparotensis, Cumacea</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Ampithoe sp.</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeroma serratum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tanais dulongi</tp:taxon-name>

with granulometry, chlorophyll a and salinity. In turn, 

Melita palmate, 
<tp:taxon-name>Idotea balthica</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyathura carinata</tp:taxon-name>
,

<tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Pagurus bernhardus
</tp:taxon-name>
were positively correlated with organic matter and temperature. As for the stations, they are left-right oriented for axis 2, which corresponds to a downstream-upstream gradient. Accordingly, downstream stations (27, 28, 29, 31, 36, 37, 38, 39, 40, 41) were characterized by larger grain sizes, high salinity and chlorophyll a, whereas the upstream stations (1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 10) were characterised by high organic matter and temperature.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
Discussion
</title>
         <p>This study is the first inventory of all the crustacean taxa found in the Oualidia lagoon in two seasons, winter and summer. In addition, it identifies the main environmental variables that explain the spatial and temporal variations of the crustacean community structure in the study area.</p>
         <p>
The present study provides the current baseline of crustacean distribution, abundance, and diversity within the Oualidia lagoon. The 18 taxa recorded is within the range of values obtained in other lagoons: Aby lagoon (20 species) (

); Khnifiss lagoon (15 species) (

); Smir lagoon (13 species) (

); Merja Zerga lagoon (13 species) (

); Epe lagoon (11 species) (

). The number of species reported in this study is almost higher than those reported by 

. These differences in the structure and diversity of the crustaceans assemblages may likely be explained by the increasing levels of organic matter in the sediment, which may also be related with the changes in the hydrodynamics of the lagoon due to the construction of a pit upstream.
</p>
         <p>
The most abundant taxa in winter were 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
(23.6 %), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tanais dulongii
</tp:taxon-name>
(28.2 %), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Apseudes
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(9.5 %) 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eurydice pulchra
</tp:taxon-name>
(10.2 %). The first one were also dominant in summer (53.7 %) followed by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corophium
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(34.5 %). The first one 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
was also the most abundant specie in Boughrara Lagoon (

). This pattern of dominance differs completely with that reported in the Smir lagoon, where the most representative species were 

<tp:taxon-name>Melita palmata</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Corophium acherusicum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyathura carinata</tp:taxon-name>

and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma hookeri
(
Chaouti &amp; Bayed, 2005
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. The Ichkeul lagoon was dominated by 

<tp:taxon-name>Gammarus aequicauda</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Idotea chelipes</tp:taxon-name>

and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma hookeri
(
Casagranda et al., 2006
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. The Merja Zerga lagoon was dominated by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cyathura carinata
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lekanesphaera rugicauda
Touhami et al., 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
). Coastal lagoons are highly variable in terms of environmental conditions, not only between their different areas, but also seasonally. This may certainly contribute to explain the reported changes in composition and dominance of the assemblages inhabiting different lagoons, but also to drastic changes in the species composition through time, particularly if there are associated changes in anthropogenic pressures (Hernandez-Guevara et al., 2008). These changes, however, are not only related to the ability of the species to respond to the environmental changes, but may also result from the existing biological interactions such as competition or predation, or may depend on intrinsic characteristics of the species (Artemis et al., 2006).
</p>
         <p>
The particular combination of geological, hydrographical and environmental characteristics of the Oaulidia lagoon generates a macrofaunal structure characterized by three assemblages that can be clearly distinguished in the HAC (fig. 3, A, B) showing a spatial organization along an inner-to-outer lagoon gradient, in a similar way as previously reported for other lagoons (e. g. 

)
</p>
         <p>
The diversity, distribution and structure of crustacean assemblages are strongly influenced by environmental parameters (Carrasco and Carbajal 1998; Simboura et al., 2000; Labrune et al., 2007; 

), with particular relevance in the case of sediment characteristics and organic matter (Glémarec, 1973; Martin et al., 2000; Barbosa et al., 2010; Martins et al., 2013).The spatial structure of the crustacean community in the Oualidia lagoon seemed to be determined by the combined influence of granulometry, temperature and salinity, which also seems to be a common trend in lagoon systems (

). However, the environmental factors controlling species distributions may vary from one parallic environment to another. For example, in Smir lagoon (

), vegetation and grain size were reported as the main factors influencing species structure, while in Sacca di Goro (

), dissolved oxygen, temperature and salinity were the main factors, and in Monolimni lagoon (

), temperature and depth.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
In conclusion, this study analysed the diversity, distribution and relationship with environmental factors of crustaceans in the Oualidia lagoon. The results of the present work showed that the Oualidia lagoon, despite its relatively small size, supports rather diverse crustacean assemblages compared to the taxonomic list of other lagoons. A total of 8721 crustacean individuals belonging to 18 taxa were collected from Oualidia lagoon. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaeroma serratum
</tp:taxon-name>
was the most abundant taxon. Cluster analysis showed two communities from downstream to upstream in both seasons. According to canonical correspondence analysis, granulometry, organic matter and salinity are the most frequently reported factors determining the distribution and composition of crustaceans in the Oualidia lagoon. Our results provide useful insights for future coastal management monitoring programmes in the Oualidia lagoon. Therefore, further investigations are needed to see the whole picture of the biodiversity status of macroinvertebrates in the Oualidia lagoon, and to monitor the health of the ecosystem, it would be very interesting to study the seasonal variability of the zoobenthic community in the lagoon and its relationship with environmental parameters.
</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgements
</p>
         <p>We are deeply grateful to all INRH-Oualidia staff for their personal quality and help with the sampling.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Affian, K.
, 
Robin, M.
, 
Maanan, M.
, 
Digbehi, B.
, 
Djagoua, E. V.
&amp; 
Kouamé, F.
2009
. 
Heavy metal and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in Ebrié lagoon sediments, Côte d'Ivoire
. 

Environmental Monitoring and Assessment

, 

159

(1– 
4
), 
531– 541
. doi: 
10.1007/s10661-0080649-z
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Archambault, P.
&amp; 
Bourget, E.
1996
. 
Scales of coastal heterogeneity and benthic intertidal species richness, diversity and abundance
. 

Mar Ecol Prog Ser

, 
136
, 
111–121
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bellucci, L. G.
, 
Frignani, M.
, 
Paolucci, D.
&amp; 
Ravanelli, M.
2002
. 
Distribution of heavy metals in sediments of the Venice Lagoon: the role of the industrial area
. 

Science of the Total Environment

, 
295
, 
35–49
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bennouna, A.
, 
Assobhei, O.
, 
Berland, B.
&amp; 
El Attar, J.
2000
. 
Étude des populations phytoplanctoniques de la lagune de Oualidia (Maroc); dinoflagellés potentiellement nuisibles
. 

Marine life Institut océanographique Paul Ricard
,

10
, 
3–18
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cacabelos, E.
, 
Lourido, A.
&amp; 
Troncoso, J. S.
2010
. 
Composition and distribution of subtidal and intertidal crustacean assemblages in soft-bottoms of the Ria de Vigo (NW Spain)
. 

Scient Mar

, 

74

(
3
), 
455–464
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Carruesco, C.
1989
. 

Genèse et évolution de trois lagunes du littoral atlantique depuis l'holocène: Oualidia, Moulay Bou Salham (Maroc) et Arcachon (France)

. 
Thèse de doctorat.
Université de Bordeaux 
I
, 
1‒485
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Casagranda, C.
, 
Dridi, M. S.
&amp; 
Boudouresque, C. F.
2006
. 
Abundance, population structure and production of macro-invertebrate shredders in a Mediterranean brackish lagoon, Lake Ichkeul, Tunisia
. 

Estuar. Coast. Shelf Sci
.

, 
66
, 
437‒446
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chaouti, A.
&amp; 
Bayed, A.
2008
. 
Spatial patterns of soft-bottom macro-invertebrates and relationships with environmental conditions in a north African coastal lagoon (Smir lagoon, Morocco)
. 

Vie Milieu
,

58
, 
25–35
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chaouti, A.
&amp; 
Bayed, A.
2005
. 
Diversité taxonomique et structure de la macrofaune benthique des substrats meubles de la lagune de Smir
. 

Travaux de l'Institut Scientifique

, 
4
, 
33–42
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chbicheb, A.
1996
. 
Organisation biogéologique d'un bassin paralique: la lagune d'Oualidia (côte atlantique marocaine). Thèse de Doctorat
. 
Université de Nantes, Nantes (France)
, 
1–167
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
El Asri, F.
, 
Zidane, H.
, 
Errhif, A.
, 
Tamsouri, M. N.
, 
Maanan, M.
, 
Malouli Idrissi, M.
&amp; 
Martin, D.
2017
. 
Polychaete diversity and assemblage structure in the Oualidia lagoon, Moroccan Atlantic coast
. 

Journal of the Marine Biological Association of the United Kingdom

, 
1–10
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
El Asri, F.
, 
Zidane, H.
, 
Maanan, M.
, 
Tamsouri, M. N.
&amp; 
Errhif, A.
2015
. 
Taxonomic diversity and structure of the molluscan fauna in Oualidia lagoon (Moroccan Atlantic coast)
. 

Environmental Monitoring and Assessment
,

187
, 
1–10
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
El Asri, F.
, 
Martin, D.
, 
Errhif, A.
, 
Tamsouri, M. N.
, 
Maanan, M.
&amp; 
Zidane, H.
2020
. 
Community Structure and Spatail Patterns of Soft-Bottom Macrozoobenthos in Oualidia lagoon, Moroccan Atlantic
. 

Thalassas: An International Journal of Marine Sciences

. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s41208-020-00263-3
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
El Asri,F.
, 
Errhif,A.
, 
Tamsouri, M.N.
, 
Martin,D.
, 
Maanan, M.
&amp; 
Zidane,H.
2022
. 
Analysis of the structural characteristics and spatial organization of macrobenthic fauna in Oualidia lagoon, Morocco
. 

Applied Water Science
,

12
: 
96
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1007/s13201-022-01629-z
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hassou, N.
, 
Maanan, M.
, 
Hennani, M.
, 
Zourarah, B.
&amp; 
Assobhei, O.
2014
. 
Spatial and temporal variation of faecal pollution indicators (Escherichia coli and faecal streptococci) and physico-chemical parameters at the Oualidia lagoon and its watershed (Morocco)
. 

International Journal of Current Microbiology and Applied Sciences
,

3
, 
675–94
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hendrickx, M. E.
1995
. 
Checklist of brachyuran crabs (Crustacea: Decapoda) from the eastern tropical
. 

Pacific. Bull. de lnst. Royal des Sci. Nat. de Bel. Bio
.

, 
65
, 
125–150
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kevrekidis, T.
2004
. 
Seasonal variation of the macrozoobenthic community structure at low salinities in a Mediterranean Lagoon (Monolimni Lagoon, Northern Aegean)
. 

International Review of Hydrobiology
,

89
, 
407–425
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Khedhri, I.
, 
Afli, A.
&amp; 
Aleya, L.
2016
. 
Structuring factors of the spatio-temporal variability of macrozoobenthos assemblages in a southern Mediterranean lagoon: How useful for bioindication is a multi-biotic indices approach?

Mar Pollut Bull

, 
114
, 
515–527
. 
doi: 10.1016/j.marpolbul.2016.10.023
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Koaudio, K. N.
, 
Diomandé, D.
, 
Ouattara, A.
, 
Koné, Y. J. M.
&amp; 
Gourène, G.
2008
. 
Taxonomic diversity and structure of benthic macroinvertebrates in Aby Lagoon (Ivory Coast, West Africa)
. 

Pakistan Journal of Biological Science

, 
11
, 
2224–2230
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lefrere, L.
, 
Ouassas, M.
, 
Guillois, B.
, 
Gillet, P.
&amp; 
Moukrim, A.
2015
. 
Macrobenthic community structure of soft-bottom sediments in the Khnifiss lagoon, South of Morocco
. 

Journal of Materials and Environmental Science

, 

6

(
11
), 
3226–3235
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maanan, M.
, 
Ruiz-Fernandez, A. C.
, 
Maanan, M.
, 
Fattal, P.
, 
Zourarah, B.
&amp; 
Sahabi, M.
2014
. 
A long-term record of land use change impacts on sediments in Oualidia lagoon, Morocco
. 

International Journal of Sediment Research
,

29
, 
1–10
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maanan, M.
, 
Saddik, M.
, 
Maanan, M.
&amp; 
Chaibi, M.
2015
. 
Environmental and ecological risk assessment of heavy metals in sediments of Nador lagoon, Morocco
. 

Ecological Indicators
,

48
, 
616–626
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mistri, M.
, 
Rossi, R.
&amp; 
Fano, E. A.
2001
. 
Structure and secondary production of a soft bottom macrobenthic community in a brackish lagoon (Sacca di Goro, north-eastern Italy) Estuarine
. 

Coastal and Shelf Science

, 
52
, 
605–616
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pearson, T. H.
&amp; 
Rosenberg, R.
1978
. 
Macrobenthic succession in relation to organic enrichment and pollution of the marine environment
. 

Oceanography and Marine Biology: An Annual Review

, 
16
, 
229–311
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pielou, E. C.
1966
. 
Shannon's Formula as a Measure of Specific Diversity: Its Use and measure
. 

American Naturalist
,

100
, 
463–5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shannon, C. E.
1948
. 
A mathematical theory of communication
. 

Bell System Technical Journal

, 
27
, 
379–423
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Touhami, F.
, 
Bazairi, H.
, 
Badaoui, B.
, 
Bouarour, O.
&amp; 
Benhoussa, A.
2017
. 
Merja Zerga lagoon: study of the functional structure and bioassessment of the ecological quality of benthic communities
. 

Journal of Materials and Environmental Sciences

, 

8

(
12
), 
4591–4599
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Uwadiae, R. E.
2009
. 
Response of benthic macroinvertebrate community to salinity gradient in a sandwiched coastal lagoon
. 

Report and Opinion

, 
1
, 
45–55
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Uwadiae, R. E.
2010
. 
An inventory of the benthic macrofauna of Epe Lagoon, Southwest Nigeria
. 

Journal of Scientific Research and Development
,

12
(
1
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Uwadiae, R.E.
2013
. 
Spatial patterns in diversity and distribution of benthic molluscs in a weak tidal tropical lagoon
. 

International Journal of Marine Science

, 
3
(
14
), 
111–120
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zidane, H.
, 
Maanan, M.
, 
Mouradi, A.
, 
Maanan, M.
, 
El Barjy, M.
, 
Zourarah, B.
&amp; 
Blais, J. F.
2017
. 
Environmental and ecological risk of heavy metals in the marine sediment from Dakhla Bay, Morocco
. 

Environ Sci Poll Res

, 
24
, 
7970–7981
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zidane, H.
, 
Orbi, A.
, 
Mouradi, A.
, 
Zidane, F.
&amp; 
Blais, J. F.
2008
. 
Structure hydrologique et édaphique d'un site ostréicole: Duna Blanca (la baie de Dakhla sud du Maroc)
. 

Environmental Technology
,

29
, 
1031–1042
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
