<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Zoodiversity</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15407/zoo2023.06.563</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Protected Waterbird Species On The Azov-Black Sea Coast In The Winter Seasons 2009-2022</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>v.kostiushyn</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tadorna ferruginea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bucephala clangula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Branta ruficollis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mergus serrator
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Netta rufina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tadorna ferruginea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bucephala clangula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Branta ruficollis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mergus serrator
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Netta rufina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phalacrocorax pygmaeus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Numenius arquata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Haliaeetus albicilla
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Anas strepera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Grus grus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pelecanus crispus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cygnus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Larus ichthyaetus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aythya nyroca
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oxyura leucocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Somateria mollissima
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Haematopus ostralegus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Podiceps auritus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Podiceps grisegena
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Charadrius hiaticulа
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Numenius</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Recurvirostra avosetta
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Platalea leucorodia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Charadrius alexandrinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Numenius phaeopus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pelecanus onocrotalus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phalacrocorax aristotelis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ardeola ralloides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tadorna ferruginea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bucephala clangula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Branta ruficollis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mergus serrator
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Netta rufina</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Podiceps auritus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Podiceps grisegena
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pelecanus onocrotalus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pelecanus crispus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phalacrocorax pygmaeus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Platalea leucorodia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Branta ruficollis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cygnus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tadorna ferruginea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Anas strepera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Netta rufina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aythya nyroca
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bucephala clangula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Somateria mollissima
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oxyura leucocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mergus serrator
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Haliaeetus albicilla
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Grus grus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Charadrius hiaticulа
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Charadrius alexandrinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Recurvirostra avosetta
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Haematopus ostralegus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Numenius arquata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Numenius phaeopus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Numenius
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Larus ichthyaetus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tadorna ferruginea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bucephala clangula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Branta ruficollis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mergus serrator
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Netta rufina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>UDC 598.2:591.524/.525(262.54+262.5)</p>
         <p>
PROTECTED WATERBIRD SPECIES ON THE AZOV-BLACK SEA COAST IN THE WINTER SEASONS 2009‒2022
</p>
         <p>
V. A. Kostiushyn
&amp; 
Yu. O. Andryushchenko
</p>
         <p>

Schmalhausen Institute of Zoology NAS of 
Ukraine
,

</p>
         <p>

vul. B. Khmelnytskogo, 15, 
Kyiv
, 01054 
Ukraine
</p>
         <p>
*Corresponding author
</p>
         <p>

E-mail: 
<tp:taxon-name>v.kostiushyn</tp:taxon-name>
@gmail.com

</p>
         <p>V. A. Kostiushyn (https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5975-8508)</p>
         <p>Yu. O. Andryushchenko (https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7731-1734)</p>
         <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 
DCACADEB-9913-4408-9BBE-9A0758709F9C
</p>
         <p>
Protected Waterbird Species on the Azov-Black Sea Coast in the Winter Seasons 2009–2022. Kostiushyn, V. A. &amp; Andryushchenko, Yu. O. —
The article presents data on waterbirds from the Red Data Book of 
Ukraine
wintering in the Azov-Black Sea coastal wetlands during 2009‒2022. A total of 27 protected waterbird species were recorded during the International Waterbird Census. The average number of protected birds was 13,631 + 2,828 ind., the maximum — 35,768 ind. Detailed information on species composition and bird numbers is given for 14 wetlands, the most valuable for waterbirds.
</p>
         <p>
Key words: 
Azov-Black Sea coast
, 

Ukraine

, 
water birds
, 
winter counts
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Full-scale monitoring of wintering waterbirds through the International Waterbird Census (IWC) began in the late 1980s, and covered all the key wetlands of the Azov-Black Sea region of 
Ukraine
from the Krivaya Spit on the Azov Sea to the Danube Delta.
</p>
         <p>
The IWC in 
Ukraine
is based entirely on the voluntary participation of a large number of ornithologists working in research institutes, universities and protected areas.
</p>
         <p>
A significant proportion of the birds counted are species included in the Red Data Book of 
Ukraine
(RDB). Considering that the latest 3rd edition of the RDB was published in 2009 (

), the purpose of this publication is to summarise all data on protected species collected during the winters 2009–2022.
</p>
         <p>To summarise the census data, the list of protected species approved for the 4th edition of the RDB in 2021 was used.</p>
         <p>
© Publisher Publishing House "Akademperiodyka" of the NAS of 
Ukraine
, 2023. The article is published under an open access license CC BY-NC-ND (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Material and Methodology
</title>
         <p>The IWC according to the generally accepted methodology is carried out in January, but some small data collected in December or in February have also been used for this publication.</p>
         <p>
The results of the waterbird counts are regularly published mainly in the ROM Bulletin and some other publications (Results…, 2011, 2017, 2023; 

). Therefore, this paper is based on an analysis of information sources, all of which were prepared and published with the participation of the authors of this publication.
</p>
         <p>Small and medium-sized wetlands generally were fully covered by counts, while large water bodies were only partially covered.</p>
         <p>
In total 55 wetlands or parts of large water bodies were covered by counts in 2009–2022 (
fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
The number of wetlands or their parts covered by the counts varied from year to year, reaching a maximum of 
28 in
one winter season. The counts on key wetlands of the region were carried out quite regularly, but for small water bodies the degree of irregularity was quite high. The ratio of water bodies to the number of years they were counted is shown in 
fig. 2
.
</p>
         <p>It should be noted that in some waterbodies, two or, more rarely, three counts were carried out in the same winter by different teams of researchers. In such cases, we have combined the count data by selecting the maximum values for each of the species recorded. In a few cases we have also combined data from the same count in different parts of the same large wetland.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>Total number of birds</p>
         <p>
For the period 2009‒2022, a total of 2,565,677 waterbirds were counted, of which 190,838, or 7.44 %, were protected birds of the 27 Endangered, Vulnerable and Rare species listed in the Red Data Book (
table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
The number of recorded birds of protected species varied considerably from year to year — from 836 to 35,768 ind. (
fig. 3
). Such dynamics are the result of the several factors — the coverage of wetlands by surveys, the number of repeated counts on some wetlands, as well as weather conditions. Analysis of the contribution of each of these factors to changes in bird numbers is a separate issue, which we do not consider in this article. The average number of birds recorded over the period analysed was 13,631 + 2,828 ind.
</p>
         <p>Red Data Book categories* Species number Amount of birds, ind. Percentage, %</p>
         <p>Endangered (E) 8 4,026 2.11</p>
         <p>Vulnerable (V) 10 115,798 60.68</p>
         <p>Rare (R) 9 71,014 37.21</p>
         <p>Number of the bird species</p>
         <p>All protected species recorded during the IWC can be divided into three groups: numerous (average number at the level of thousands individuals), common (average number from tens to several hundreds) and small number (a few individuals) (table 2).</p>
         <p>
If the species are ranked according to the number of recorded birds, then 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tadorna ferruginea
</tp:taxon-name>
was the most numerous among the RDB species — 29.42 % of the total number of waterbirds counted in 2018–2022, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bucephala clangula
</tp:taxon-name>
— 27.93 % and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Branta ruficollis
</tp:taxon-name>
— 21.36 %, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mergus serrator
</tp:taxon-name>
— 9.73 %, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Netta rufina
</tp:taxon-name>
— 8.21 %.
</p>
         <p>
The number of single species, as a total number of birds, also significantly varied over the years. To illustrate this we used data for the most numerous species (
fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>Importance of individual wetlands for wintering water birds</p>
         <p>
To evaluate the role of the most important water bodies for wintering protected bird species it was calculated the average number of birds for each of them. As a result, out of 55 wetlands (or their parts in the case of large waterbodies), were selected 14 wetlands, in which of each an average number of protected birds exceeded 100 ind. (
fig. 5
). Undoubtedly, that in the case of using for analysis of the maximum recorded number of birds, the picture would be somewhat different. However, in our opinion, the use of average values gives a more correct estimate importance of the wetlands, since characterises the role of them for the entire observation period.
</p>
         <p>
Average bird abundance characterises only one aspect of the importance of a particular wetland for protected bird species and its high value may be the result of a high abundance of just one or a few species. That is why we also ranked the wetlands using the Shannon index (H), which takes into account both the abundance of birds and richness of the species composition (
fig. 6
).
</p>
         <p>In accordance to this index the most valuable wetlands for RDB waterbirds are Danube Delta (1.16), Northern part of Karkinitskii Bay (1.08) and Dzarylgachskii Bay (1.06). Close to them are Shagany &amp; Alibei &amp; Burnas limans. Tendrovskii Bay and Northern part of Central Sivash.</p>
         <p>
An assessment of the similarity of wetlands was also made based on the species composition and number of wintering birds on them. Similarity was calculated using Bray- Curtis index and clustering was done using algorithm UPGMA. As seen in the 
figure 7
the analyzed wetlands are divided into 2 large groups. The first one includes Donuzlav Lake (6), Northern part of Karkinitskii Bay (7), Bolshoi Chapelskii Pod (8), Western Sivash (9), Northern part of Central Sivash (10) and Northern part of Eastern Sivash (11), which are located close to each other and in the central part of the studied region. The biggest similarity within the group we can see for 10 and 11, which have similar ecological conditions (hallow saline lagoon) and are parts of one big waterbody separated by dam. Bolshoi Chapelskii Pod (8) is closely located to them, but has different biotopes — this is big inland depression temporary wet. 6, 7 and 9 another subgroup closely located wetlands, but environmental characteristics of Western Sivash (9), are quite different from others since that last one is a hypersalty wetland. The second big cluster of wetlands includes wetlands from different parts of the region: western — from Danube delta to Dzharylgach island and eastern — wetlands of Azov sea coast. Here is the general picture is more complicated for explanation. If in first group majority of wetlands are not only close to each other geographically, but, excluding 6 and 7, are closed waterbodies, not linked with the sea or have very small connection to it, then the second group is mainly (3, 4, 5, 12, 13, 14) are big marine bays. Exclusion in this group is Shagany &amp; Alibei &amp; Burnas limans (2), which are shallow water bodies separated from the Black Sea by long sandy spit. That is why 2 have low similarity with other wetlands in the group. Another situation with the Danube Delta (1), which, at first glance, has unexpectedly big similarity with Berdianskaya Spit &amp; Bay (13). We suppose that there are two reasons of this. First, bird counts cover in fact not totally the Danube Delta, but only its shallow part bordering with the sea. Second, counting area of 13 includes not only part of Berdianskiy Bay of Azov Sea, but also quite big part of the delta of Berda River. Thus, counting areas 1 and 13 have some similarities in biotopes.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>More detail information on protected waterbird species in 14 the most important wetlands for them is presented in the table 3.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
As a result of the International Waterbird Census 2009–2022 it was shown that during winter season wetlands at Azov-Black Sea coast are used by 27 Red Data Book species of 
Ukraine
. The average number of protected birds was 13,631 + 2,828 ind., with maximum — 35,768 ind. The most abundant species are 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tadorna ferruginea
</tp:taxon-name>
(29.42 % of the total amount), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bucephala clangula
</tp:taxon-name>
(27.93 %), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Branta ruficollis
</tp:taxon-name>
(21.36 %), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mergus serrator
</tp:taxon-name>
(9.73 %) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Netta rufina
</tp:taxon-name>
(8.21 %). In general, the most important wetlands for protected water birds in the region are the Danube Delta, Tuzlovskie limans (Shagany &amp; Alibei &amp; Burnas), Yagorlytskii Bay, Tendrovskii Bay, Dzarylgachskii Bay, Northern part of Karkinitskii Bay and Sivash. This general assessment should be followed by an analysis of the spatial distribution of individual species and their coverage by protected areas.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Akimov, I. A.
, ed. 
2009
. 

The Red Data Book of Ukraine
. 
Animals
. Globalconsulting

, 
Kyiv
, 
1–600
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kostiushyn, V.
, 
Andryuschenko, Yu.
, 
Goradze, I.
, 
Abuladze, A.
, 
Mamuchadze, J.
&amp; 
Erciyas, K.
2011
. 
Wintering Waterbird Census in the Azov-Black Sea Coastal Wetlands of Ukraine. Georgia and Turkey
. 

Wetlands International Black Sea programme

, 
1–130
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Results of midwinter counts of waterbirds of 2005
, 
2007–2010 in
the Azov-Black Sea region of Ukraine. 
2011
. 
Winter
seasons
2005
, 
2007–2010
: Azov-Black Sea region of Ukraine. 
ROM Bulletin
, (7), 1–64.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Results
of the regional ornithological monitoring. 
2017
. 
Winter seasons 2011
–2017. 

Bulletin ROM

, (
11
), 
1–100
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Results
of the regional ornithological monitoring. 
2023
. 
Winter seasons 2018
–2022. 

Bulletin ROM

, (
16
), 
1–72
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
