<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../../TaxPub/tax-treatment-NS0-v1.dtd">
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id>https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.649</journal-id>
            <issn>2118-9773</issn>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>A new species of Cryptomonas (Cryptophyceae) from the Western Urals
                    (Russia)</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <pub-date>
                <year>2020</year>
            </pub-date>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec sec-type="multiple">
            <title>DUMMY HEADING</title>
            <p>A new species of <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas</tp:taxon-name> (
                    <tp:taxon-name>Cryptophyceae</tp:taxon-name> ) from the Western Urals ( Russia ) </p>
            <p> Nikita A . MARTYNENKO 1,* , Evgeniy S. GUSEV2 , Pavel V. KULIZIN3 , Elena E . GUSEVA
                4 , Kevin McCARTNEY5 &amp; Maxim S. KULIKOVSKIY6</p>
            <p>1,2,4,6 K. А . Timiryazev Institute of Plant Physiology RAS, IPP RAS, 35
                Botanicheskaya Street, Moscow , 127276 Russia . </p>
            <p>3 Lobachevsky State University of Nizhniy Novgorod , Gagarina Prosp., 23, 603950
                Nizhniy Novgorod , Russia . </p>
            <p>5 University of Maine at Presque Isle, Department of Environmental Science and
                Sustainability, 181 Main Street, Presque Isle, 04769 U.S.A.</p>
            <p>* Corresponding author: nikita-martynenko@yandex.ru2 Email: algogus@yandex.ru3 Email:
                kulizinpavel@yandex.ru4 Email: mielenagus@yandex.ru5 Email:
                kevin.mccartney@maine.edu6 Email: max-kulikovsky@yandex.ru</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="abstract">
            <title>Abstract</title>
            <p>Abstract.A new species, <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis Martynenko, Gusev,
                    Kulizin &amp; Guseva </tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> , is described
                from western slopes of the Ural Mountains ( Russia ) based on morphological and
                molecular data. Phylogenetic relationships inferred from nuclear SSU and LSU rDNA
                sequences show that the new species forms a clade with <tp:taxon-name>C.
                    tetrapyrenoidosa Skuja emend. Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian. Comparison
                </tp:taxon-name> of secondary structures of nuclear rDNA ITS 2, including analysis
                of Compensatory Base Changes (CBC), confirms the separation between
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> and
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> . Cell morphology and sizes
                of <tp:taxon-name>C. uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> are very similar
                to <tp:taxon-name>C. tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>C.
                    pyrenoidifera</tp:taxon-name> , and <tp:taxon-name>C. uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> may thus
                represent a species that can only be reliably identified using molecular data. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="key_words">
            <title>Key Words</title>
            <p>Keywords.<tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas</tp:taxon-name> , new species, SSU rDNA, LSU and
                ITS 2 rDNA markers, nuclear ITS 2 secondary structure, Compensatory Base Changes
                approach, Urals. </p>
            <p> Martynenko N . A ., Gusev E .S., Kulizin P.V., Guseva E . E ., McCartney K. &amp;
                Kulikovskiy M.S. 2020. A new species of <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas</tp:taxon-name> (
                    <tp:taxon-name>Cryptophyceae</tp:taxon-name> ) from the Western Urals ( Russia
                ). European Journal of Taxonomy 649: 1–12. https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.649 </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>Cryptophytes (also known as cryptomonads) are mostly photoautotrophic, unicellular,
                biflagellate, softbodied protists distributed in diverse freshwater, brackish, and
                marine habitats. They are characterized by a number of morphological and
                ultrastructural features, including a distinct cellular asymmetry, presence of
                extrusive organelles (termed ejectosomes), cell-covering from organic compounds
                (termed</p>
            <p>periplast), and a remnant nucleus of endosymbiotic origin in close association with
                the plastids (Hoef- Emden &amp; Archibald 2016).</p>
            <p> Recent research has shown that even in well-sampled geographical regions and
                habitats, the true diversity of cryptomonads is often unknown (Hoef-Emden 2007; Lane
                &amp; Archibald 2008 ; Shalchian-Tabrizi et al. 2008 ; Choi et al. 2013 ).
                    <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas Ehrenb. </tp:taxon-name> ( Ehrenberg 1831 ) is a
                diverse genus of cryptophytes, with about 70 morphospecies currently accepted (
                Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian 2003 ). Species in the genus are restricted to
                freshwater, contain chloroplasts with the biliprotein phycoerythrin 566 or
                leucoplasts, and are characterized by a dimorphic life cycle ( Hoef-Emden &amp;
                Melkonian 2003 ). Species display two alternative cell morphotypes, which are
                related to the life cycle: 1) cryptomorph with an inner periplast composed of
                hexagonal to polygonal organic plates and a non-keeled posteriorly directed
                microtubular flagellar root, and 2) campylomorph with a sheet-like inner organic
                periplast component and keeled rhizostyle ( Hill 1991 ; Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian
                2003 ). </p>
            <p> Molecular phylogenetic analyses based on nuclear and nucleomorph ribosomal RNA gene
                sequences demonstrated inconsistencies with traditional
                    <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas</tp:taxon-name> taxonomy based on cell morphology
                studies by light microscopy (LM). Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian (2003) revised the
                genus by combining phylogenetic analyses with morphological data, emended several
                species by including molecular data, and described two new species. DNA sequences of
                additional strains resulted in emendation of five species including one new
                combination (Hoef-Emden 2007). Identification of most
                    <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas</tp:taxon-name> species may be possible only with
                molecular data. A total of 14 <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas</tp:taxon-name> species can
                now be identified by nuclear ITS 2/partial LSU rDNA or by nucleomorph SSU rDNA
                sequences in molecular ecological surveys ( Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian 2003 ;
                Hoef-Emden 2007). It is worth mentioning that these taxa are phylogenetic species,
                which may not correspond to biological species limits. </p>
            <p> Cryptomonads from some freshwater habitats in Russia have been studied
                morphologically, but molecular data is currently lacking. Data on taxonomic
                composition and ecology of this group are available mainly from phytoplankton
                studies. <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas marssonii Skuja </tp:taxon-name> ,
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. ovata Ehrenb. </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>C. erosa
                    Ehrenb. </tp:taxon-name> have been reported from the Urals based on
                morphological data ( Tretyakova et al. 1988 ; Tretyakova </p>
            <p> 1989; Belyaeva 2013 , 2015 ). A new species of
                    <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas</tp:taxon-name> from Russia is here described based
                on combination of morphological and molecular data. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
            <title>Material and methods</title>
            <p>Study area</p>
            <p> Samples were collected from an unnamed small lake in the Usolka River flood plain,
                located in Solikamsk town, Permskiy Krai, Russia ( 59°38′59″ N , 56°44′57″ E , ).
                Permskiy Krai is located on the western slope of the Ural Mountains, in upper and
                middle reaches of Kama River basin. The climate is cold temperate, with an average
                January temperature of -18.9°С, and varies from +14.8°С in the north to +18.7°С in
                the south during July. The annual precipitation also varies, from 450–600 mm in the
                western plain to 700–1000 mm in eastern mountainous territories of the Northern
                Urals, with snow cover usually 160–170 days/year ( Nazarov 2006 ). </p>
            <p>Samples and collections</p>
            <p> Planktonic samples were collected by the first author using a plankton net with 20
                μm mesh size. Water mineralization and temperature measurements were performed using
                the Hanna device (HI 9828, Hanna Instruments, Inc., Woonsocket, RI, USA ). Strains
                were isolated and cultures perpetually transferred to IPPAS (Culture Collection of
                Microalgae at the K. A . Timiryazev Institute of Plant Physiology of the Russian
                Academy of Sciences). </p>
            <p>Culturing</p>
            <p> Monoclonal strains were established by examination of micropipetted single cells
                under an inverted microscope. Non-axenic unialgal cultures were maintained in WC and
                Waris-H liquid medium ( Andersen 2005 ; McFadden &amp; Melkonian 1986 ) at 10° C in
                a growth chamber with a 12:12 h light:dark photoperiod. </p>
            <p>Light microscopy</p>
            <p> For light microscopy, living cells were immobilized by embedment in ultra-low
                gelling agarose (Sigma- Aldrich, A 4018, USA ) and examined by Nomarski differential
                interference contrast (DIC) with an oil immersion lens (Plan-Apochromat 100x/1.40
                Oil DIC M27; microscope Zeiss AxioScope A 1; Carl Zeiss AG, Oberkochem, Germany ).
                Cell shape, size, shape of the furrow–gullet system and cell plastids, and presence,
                number and position of pyrenoids were examined (88 cells). The morphological
                description follows the nomenclature of Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian (2003) (ventral
                side corresponds to the opening side of the furrow–gullet system). Calibration of
                magnification was done with a grated micrometer. Light micrographs were taken with
                an AxioCam ERc 5s Rev.2. </p>
            <p>DNA extraction and amplification</p>
            <p> Total DNA was extracted from monoclonal cultures using InstaGeneTM Matrix according
                to manufacturer’s protocol. Fragments of SSU (length 1533 bp) and LSU rDNA (length
                946 bp) and ITS 2 rDNA (402 bp) were amplified using primers from Choi et al. (2013)
                : 18S_CrN1F, 18S_826F, 18S_956R, 18S_BRK for nuclear SSU rDNA, crLSU_29F and
                crLSU_942R for partial nuclear LSU rDNA, and crITS_03F and crITS_05R for nuclear ITS
                2 rDNA. Amplification of all studied fragments was carried out using the premade mix
                ScreenMix (Evrogen, Russia ) for the polymerase chain reaction (PCR). The conditions
                of amplification for SSU rDNA, LSU rDNA and ITS 2 rDNA fragments were: an initial
                denaturation of 5 min at 95° C , followed by 35 cycles at 94° C for denaturation (30
                s), 52° C for annealing (30 s) and 72° C for extension (50–80 s), and a final
                extension step of 10 min at 72° C . The resulting amplicons were visualized by
                horizontal agarose gel electrophoresis (1.5%), colored with SYBR Safe (Life
                Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA ). Purification of DNA fragments was performed with
                the ExoSAP-IT kit (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA, USA ) according to manufacturer’s
                protocol. SSU rDNA, LSU rDNA and ITS 2 rDNA fragments were decoded from two sides
                using forward and reverse PCR primers and the Big Dye system (Applied Biosystems,
                Foster City, CA, USA ), followed by electrophoresis using a Genetic Analyzer 3500
                sequencer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA ). </p>
            <p>Phylogenetic analysis</p>
            <p> Electropherograms were verified by eye and sequences were assembled using BioEdit
                ver. 7.1.3 and MegaX ( Kumar et al. 2018 ). Newly determined sequences and GenBank
                sequences of 45 other cryptomonads from different morphological groups were included
                in the alignments. The species <tp:taxon-name>Rhodomonas</tp:taxon-name> sp. strain
                M1480 and <tp:taxon-name>Chroomonas</tp:taxon-name> sp. strain SAG 980-1 were chosen
                as outgroup taxa. Sequences were aligned using MAFFT ver. 7 with model EINS-i (
                Katoh &amp; Toh 2010 ), refined by eye and difficult to align regions were excluded
                from the analysis. jModelTest ver. 2.1.1 indicated that the GTR model of nucleotide
                substitution, with Gamma (G) distributed rates across sites and a proportion of
                invariable sites (I), was the most appropriate evolutionary model for the SSU rDNA
                and LSU rDNA alignments separately and combined ( Posada 2006 ). Finally, we
                constructed the concatenated SSU + LSU rDNA alignment of 47 taxa. The SSU and LSU
                sequences were combined from the same strain. Phylogenies were constructed based on
                this model for the concatenated alignment using a single partition Bayesian
                Inference (BI) and Maximum Likelihood (ML) analyses. BI analysis was conducted with
                MrBayes ver. 3.2.5 ( Ronquist &amp; Huelsenbeck 2003 ). Three “hot” and one “cold”
                Markov chains were run for 1 × 106 cycles in two repetitions with the selection of
                each 200 th generated tree. Phylogenetic tree and posterior probabilities were
                obtained after discarding the first 25% to produce estimate parameter models of
                nucleotide substitutions and likelihood. ML-analysis was performed using MegaX (
                Kumar et al. 2018 ). Branch support was estimated using bootstrap analysis with 1000
                replicas. Viewing and editing of trees were performed in FigTree ver. 1.4.2 (FigTree
                2014) and Adobe Photoshop CC (ver. 19.0). </p>
            <p>RNA secondary structure prediction</p>
            <p> Nuclear ITS 2 sequences were folded using the mfold server
                (http://mfold.rna.albany.edu/?q=mfold/RNA-Folding-Form) ( Zuker 2003 ) with default
                values. Hoef- Emden (2007) provided a complete RNA secondary structure graph of the
                nuclear ITS 2 rDNA of <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas</tp:taxon-name> sp. M1634, which
                was used as a template and assisted in inference of common stems, loops, and bulges. </p>
            <p>Results</p>
            <p>Molecular phylogeny</p>
            <p> The new species, <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> , represents a
                separate clade with high statistical support, sister to <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas
                    tetrapyrenoidosa Skuja emend. Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian </tp:taxon-name> ( ).
                    <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> differs from the
                type strain of <tp:taxon-name>C. tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> by the SSU rDNA,
                LSU rDNA and ITS 2 rDNA sequences as well as in the secondary structure of ITS 2 (
                ). For ITS 2 sequence of <tp:taxon-name>C. uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> four-helix
                structures could be inferred with long third helices ( ). An unpaired U-U was found
                in Helix II. The length of the helices was different between two taxa ( ). For the
                new species, length of ITS 2 was 402 nt, while for <tp:taxon-name>C.
                    tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> was 370 nt. Three Compensatory Base Changes
                (CBCs) between <tp:taxon-name>C. uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> and
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> were observed in Helix III (
                ). </p>
            <p> Phylum Cryptophyta Cavalier-Smith Class <tp:taxon-name>Cryptophyceae
                    F.E.Fritsch</tp:taxon-name> Order <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonadales
                    Pascher</tp:taxon-name> Genus <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas Ehrenb.
                </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
        </sec>
        <tp:taxon-treatment>
            <tp:treatment-meta>
                <kwd-group>
                    <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                        <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis Martynenko, Gusev, Kulizin &amp; Guseva
                        </tp:taxon-name>
                    </kwd>
                    <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                        <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                    </kwd>
                    <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                        <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                    </kwd>
                    <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                        <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                    </kwd>
                </kwd-group>
                <mixed-citation>
                    <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new species of Cryptomonas
                        (Cryptophyceae) from the Western Urals (Russia)</named-content>
                    <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.649</uri>
                    <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FB2013129664FF8E6C30FFF5FFE2FFF5</uri>
                    <article-title/>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.649</pub-id>
                    <issn>2118-9773</issn>
                    <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
                </mixed-citation>
            </tp:treatment-meta>
            <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
                <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis Martynenko, Gusev, Kulizin &amp; Guseva </tp:taxon-name>
                <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
            </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
                <p>Description</p>
                <p/>
            </tp:treatment-sec>
            <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
                <p>Diagnosis</p>
                <p>Diagnosis</p>
                <p> Cells (absolute minimal and maximal values of strain UR168) 15–26 µm long, 8–17
                    µm wide, 8–12 µm thick. Cells more or less flattened in dorso-ventral plane, in
                    ventral view elliptical to ovoid. In lateral view with oblique or rounded apex
                    and rounded antapex. One plastid with two to four pyrenoids. Species differs
                    from other species of the genus by the order of nucleotides in nuclear ITS2, LSU
                    and SSU rDNA gene sequences. </p>
            </tp:treatment-sec>
            <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
                <p>Etymology</p>
                <p>The species name derived from “Ural”, the region from which this taxon was
                    described.</p>
            </tp:treatment-sec>
            <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
                <p>Type material</p>
                <p>Holotype</p>
                <p>
                    <tp:material-citation>RUSSIA • Solikamsk town , water-body in the Usolka River
                        flood plain ; 59°38′59″ N , 56°44′57″ E ; 2014; collected by N.A. Martynenko
                        ; strain UR168; GenBank MN509781, MN509779 ; MHA [
                            <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis</tp:taxon-name> Russia Martynenko
                        20-2 MHA, strain UR168]. </tp:material-citation>
                </p>
                <p> The holotype is a large drop of unfixed dried cells of the strain UR168 (= IPPAS
                    H-2046) on water colour paper ( hic designatus ), deposited at MHA (Herbarium,
                    Main Botanical Garden, Botanicheskaya Str. 4, Moscow , 127276, Russia ) under
                    the designation <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis</tp:taxon-name>Russia
                    Martynenko 20-2 MHA , strain UR168. Representative living strain and DNA sample
                    are kept at IPPAS . </p>
                <p>Representative DNA sequences</p>
                <p> GenBank accession numbers MN 509781 (nuclear ITS 2 and partial nuclear LSU
                    rDNA), and MN 509779 (nuclear SSU rDNA). </p>
                <p>Authentic strain</p>
                <p> UR168 (= IPPAS H-2046). </p>
                <p>Type locality A water-body in the Usolka River flood plain, Solikamsk town,
                    Russia . Latitude/Longitude 59°38′59″ N , </p>
                <p>56°44′57″ E , collected by N.A. Martynenko in 2014. </p>
                <p>Other representative culture</p>
                <p> UR167, GenBank accession numbers MN 509780 (nuclear ITS 2 and partial nuclear
                    LSU rDNA), and MN 509778 (nuclear SSU rDNA). </p>
                <p>Geographical distribution</p>
                <p> To date, <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                    <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> has only been
                    observed at the type locality. At the time of collection, the pH was 6.5,
                    temperature 18°C. </p>
            </tp:treatment-sec>
        </tp:taxon-treatment>
        <sec sec-type="discussion">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>
                <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> represents a
                distinct clade with high statistical support, sister to <tp:taxon-name>C.
                    tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> , but no obvious morphological characters
                distinguishing the two taxa were found. Initially <tp:taxon-name>C.
                    tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> was described based on LM studies of
                populations from Sweden and Latvia ( Skuja 1948 ). Later, the strain M1092 from
                Germany (Remscheid) was chosen as the epitype and sequenced ( Hoef-Emden &amp;
                Melkonian 2003 ). To date, <tp:taxon-name>C. tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> has
                not been recorded in the Urals, thus areals of this species and <tp:taxon-name>C.
                    uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> do not overlap.
                Mention should be made that there were no previous intensive molecular studies of
                cryptophytes in the Urals. Recent studies of cryptomonads of South Korea , region
                remote from Europe, revealed several strains from the <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas
                    tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> clade that showed SSU rDNA, LSU rDNA and ITS 2
                rDNA nucleotide differences from the type specimen and formed two subclades ( Choi
                et al. 2013 ). However, no formal taxonomic descriptions have been made. In our
                opinion, these are very likely a new species. Thus, the <tp:taxon-name>C.
                    tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> clade requires further study. </p>
            <p> Previous studies have suggested that the nuclear internal transcribed spacer 2 ( ITS
                2) is a good marker to identify biological species using degree of conservation.
                Coleman (2000) and Müller et al. (2007) have proposed that CBCs in the ITS 2
                correlate with speciation and thus can be used to distinguish species. The CBC
                species concept states that two organisms/strains whose ITS 2 sequences differ by
                even a single CBC in the conserved regions of Helix II and Helix III represent two
                different biological species ( Coleman 2000 ). According to Müller et al. (2007) and
                Wolf et al. (2013) the presence of any CBC in the whole ITS 2 molecule is sufficient
                for distinguishing species. Later, Caisová et al. (2013) identified consensus
                structure model of the ITS 2 molecule that can be applied to two classes of green
                algae. Also was reported that CBCs in the ITS 2 of four orders of the green algal
                class <tp:taxon-name>Chlorophyceae Wille in Warming</tp:taxon-name> were mostly
                associated with higher order taxonomic levels like genera, families and orders, and
                CBC concept for species delimitation have some constraints in chlorophycean algae (
                Caisová et al. 2013 ). Dimorphic strains and a few reports of sexual reproduction
                indicate the presence of biological species also in cryptophyte taxa (Hoef-Emden
                2007). The nuclear ITS 2 was successfully used to predict putative biological
                species in the last revision of <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas (Hoef-Emden 2007)
                </tp:taxon-name> . Here, comparison of the secondary structures of ITS 2 confirms
                separation between <tp:taxon-name>C. uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> and
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> . </p>
            <p>
                <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas pyrenoidifera Geitler emend. Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian
                </tp:taxon-name> was found to be sister to the clade containing <tp:taxon-name>C.
                    uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> and
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> . <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas
                    pyrenoidifera</tp:taxon-name> is known from Germany , United Kingdom , Czech
                Republic and Australia based on molecular data. The morphology and cell sizes of
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> are very similar
                to cryptomorphs of <tp:taxon-name>C. pyrenoidifera</tp:taxon-name> , as well as
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. tetrapyrenoidosa</tp:taxon-name> . <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas
                    curvata Ehrenberg emend. Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian </tp:taxon-name> is one more
                species which has cryptomorph cells with the same morphological features (shape,
                size, number of pyrenoids), but placed distantly on phylogenetic tree from
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> Incongruences
                between classical morphospecies and molecular phylogenetic trees have previously
                been reported for many species in the genus <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas (Hoef-Emden
                    2007) </tp:taxon-name> . Morphological species descriptions of this genus are
                often ambiguous because of microscopic cells and only few visible characters. The
                most recent revisions of the genus show that correct identification of most
                    <tp:taxon-name>Cryptomonas</tp:taxon-name> species may be possible only with
                molecular data ( Hoef-Emden &amp; Melkonian 2003 , Hoef-Emden 2007). In the case of
                    <tp:taxon-name>C. uralensis</tp:taxon-name>
                <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content> , no sufficiently
                distinct morphological characters could be identified. The species can only be
                distinguished by molecular characters. </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <p> Authors are grateful to D. Kapustin for help in preparation of two images ( ) and I.
                Pozdeev for collection assistance. Authors are grateful for reviewers for
                constructive comments which help to improve the manuscript. This study was supported
                by RFBR grant N ° 18-04-01280_а and a framework of the state assignment (theme
                АААА-А19-119041190086-6). </p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <title>References</title>
            <p>Andersen R.A. (ed.) 2005 . Algal Culturing Techniques . Elsevier Academic Press,
                Oxford . </p>
            <p>Belyaeva P.G.2013 . Species composition and phytoplankton structure of the Kama
                reservoir . Bulletin of Perm University. Series: Biology3 : 4–12 . </p>
            <p>Belyaeva P.G.2015 . Spatio-temporal changes in the phytoplankton of the Kama
                reservoir Bulletin of the Samara Scientific Center of the Russian Academy of
                Sciences17 : 733–738 . </p>
            <p>Caisová L. , Marin B. , Melkonian M.2013 . A consensus secondary structure of ITS 2
                in the Chlorophyta identified by phylogenetic reconstruction . Protist164 : 482–496
                . https://doi.org/10.1016/j.protis.2013.04.005</p>
            <p>Choi B. , Son M. , Jong Im Kim J.I. &amp; Shin W.2013 . Taxonomy and phylogeny of the
                genus Cryptomonas (Cryptophyceae, Cryptophyta) from Korea . Algae28 : 307–330 .
                https://doi.org/10.4490/algae.2013.28.4.307</p>
            <p>Coleman A.W.2000 . The significance of a coincidence between evolutionary landmarks
                found in mating affinity and a DNA sequence . Protist151 : 1–9 .
                https://doi.org/10.1078/1434-4610-00002</p>
            <p>Ehrenberg C.G.1831 . Symbolae physicae seu icones et descriptiones animalium
                evertebratorum sepositis insectis quae ex itinere per Africanum Borealem et Asiam
                Occidentalem Friderici Guilelmi Hemprich et Christiani Godofredi Ehrenberg medicinae
                et chirurgiae doctorum studio novae aut illustratae redierunt . Berlin, Mittler . </p>
            <p>FigTree2014 . FigTree version 1.3 .2. Available from
                http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/ [accessed 20 Apr. 2020 ]. </p>
            <p>Hill D.R.A.1991 . A revised circumscription of Cryptomonas (Cryptophyceae) based on
                examinations of Australian strains . Phycologia 30 (2): 170–188.
                https://doi.org/10.2216/i0031-8884-30-2-170.1 Hoef-Emden K. 2007. Revision of the
                genus Cryptomonas (Cryptophyceae) II: Incongruences between classical morphospecies
                concept and molecular phylogeny in smaller pyrenoid-less cells. Phycologia46 ( 4 ):
                402–428 . </p>
            <p>Hoef-Emden K. &amp; Archibald J.M.2016 . Cryptophyta (Cryptomonads) . In : Archibald
                J.M. , Simpson A.G.B. , Slamovits C.H. , Margulis L. , Melkonian M. , Chapman D.J.
                &amp; Corliss J.O. (eds) Handbook of the Protists . Springer International
                Publishing, Cham, Switzerland . </p>
            <p>https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-28149-0_35</p>
            <p>Hoef-Emden K. &amp; Melkonian M.2003 . Revision of the genus Cryptomonas
                (Cryptophyceae): A combination of molecular phylogeny and morphology provides
                insights into a long-hidden dimorphism . Protist154 : 371–409 .
                https://doi.org/10.1078/143446103322454130</p>
            <p>Katoh K. &amp; Toh H.2010 . Parallelization of the MAFFT multiple sequence alignment
                program . Bioinformatics26 : 1899–1900 .
                https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btq224</p>
            <p>Kumar S. , Stecher G. , Li M. , Knyaz C. &amp; Tamura K.2018 . MEGA X: Molecular
                Evolutionary Genetics Analysis across computing platforms . Molecular Biology and
                Evolution35 : 1547–1549 . https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msy096</p>
            <p>Lane C.E. &amp; Archibald J.M.2008 . New marine members of the genus Hemiselmis
                (Cryptomonadales, Cryptophyceae) . Journal of Phycology44 ( 2 ): 439–450 .
                https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1529-8817.2008.00486.x</p>
            <p>McFadden G.I. &amp; Melkonian M.1986 . Use of Hepes buffer for microalgal culture
                media and fixation for electron microscopy . Phycologia25 : 551–557 .
                https://doi.org/10.2216/i0031-8884-25-4-551.1</p>
            <p>Müller T. , Philippi N. , Dandekar T. , Schultz J. &amp; Wolf M.2007 . Distinguishing
                species . RNA13 : 1469– 1472 . https://doi.org/10.1261/rna.617107</p>
            <p>Nazarov N.N.2006 . Geography of the Perm region. Part I. Natural (physical) geography
                . Publishing House of Perm State University, Perm . </p>
            <p>Posada D.2006 . Modeltest Server: a web-based tool for the statistical selection of
                models of nucleotide substitution online . Nucleic Acids Research34 : 700–703 .
                https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkl042</p>
            <p>Ronquist F. &amp; Huelsenbeck J.P.2003 . MrBayes 3: Bayesian phylogenetic inference
                under mixed models . Bioinformatics19 : 1572–1574 .
                https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btg180</p>
            <p>Shalchian-Tabrizi K. , Brate J. , Logares R. , Klaveness D. , Berney C. &amp;
                Jakobsen K.S.2008 . Diversification of unicellular eukaryotes: Cryptomonad
                colonizations of marine and fresh waters inferred from revised 18S rRNA phylogeny .
                Environmental Microbiology10 ( 10 ): 2635–2644 .
                https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1462-2920.2008.01685.x</p>
            <p>Skuja H.1948 . Taxonomie des Phytoplanktons einiger Seen in Uppland, Schweden .
                Symbolae Botanicae Upsaliensis9 ( 1 ): 1–399 . </p>
            <p>Tretyakova S.A.1989 . Phytoplankton of the Kama reservoirs . In : Yarushina M.I.
                (ed.) Hydrobiological characteristics of the Urals . Ural Branch of USSR Academy of
                Sciences, Sverdlovsk . </p>
            <p>Tretyakova S.A. , Golovacheva S.I. &amp; Batova E.M.1988 . Phytoplankton . In :
                Aleksevnina M.S. (ed.) Biology of the Votkinsk reservoir . Publishing of Irkutsk
                University, Irkutsk . </p>
            <p>Wolf M. , Chen S. , Song J. , Ankenbrand M. &amp; Müller T.2013 . Compensatory Base
                Changes in ITS2 Secondary Structures Correlate with the Biological Species Concept
                Despite Intragenomic Variability in ITS2 Sequences – A Proof of Concept . PLoS ONE8
                : e 66726 . </p>
            <p>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0066726</p>
            <p>Zuker M.2003 . Mfold web server for nucleic acid folding and hybridization prediction
                . Nucleic Acids Research31 : 3406–3415 . https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkg595</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="multiple">
            <title>DUMMY HEADING</title>
            <p> Manuscript received: 26 September 2019</p>
            <p> Manuscript accepted: 26 February 2020</p>
            <p> Published on: 20 May 2020</p>
            <p>Topic editor:Frederik Leliaert</p>
            <p>Desk editor: Natacha Beau</p>
            <p> Printed versions of all papers are also deposited in the libraries of the institutes
                that are members of the EJT consortium: Muséum national d’histoire naturelle, Paris,
                France ; Meise Botanic Garden, Belgium ; Royal Museum for Central Africa, Tervuren,
                Belgium ; Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences, Brussels , Belgium ; Natural
                History Museum of Denmark , Copenhagen, Denmark ; Naturalis Biodiversity Center,
                Leiden, the Netherlands ; Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales-CSIC, Madrid , Spain
                ; Real Jardín Botánico de Madrid CSIC, Spain ; Zoological Research Museum Alexander
                Koenig, Bonn, Germany ; National Museum, Prague , Czech Republic . </p>
        </sec>
    </body>
</article>
