<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112464</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Isolation of CFTR and TMEM16A inhibitors from Neorautanenia mitis (A. Rich) Verdcourt: Potential lead compounds for treatment of secretory diarrhea</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia mitis
(A.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia mitis
(A. Rich) Verdc. (Fabacae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia pseudopacyrrhiza
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. amboensis
(
Breytenbach and Rall, 1980
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. edulis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pachyrrhiza erosus
(
Krishnamurti et al., 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Vibrio cholerae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Vibrio cholera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>N. mitis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
(A. Rich) Verdc. (Fabacae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Isolation of CFTR and TMEM16A inhibitors from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia mitis
(A.
</tp:taxon-name>
Rich) Verdcourt: Potential lead compounds for treatment of secretory diarrhea

</p>
         <p>
Christiana J. Dawurung
a,b
, Rattikarn Noitem
c
, Roonglawan Rattanajak
d
, Ratchanu Bunyong
d
,
Christopher Richardson 
a

, Anthony 
C
. Willis

e
, Sumalee Kamchonwongpaisan
d
,
Chantapol Yimnual 
c
, Chatchai Muanprasat
c
, Stephen G. Pyne

a, 
*
</p>
         <p>
a

School of Chemistry and Molecular Bioscience, University of Wollongong, Wollongong, NSW, 2522, 
Australia
</p>
         <p>
b

Department of Veterinary Physiology, Biochemistry and Pharmacology, University of Jos, Jos 
Plateau State
, 
Nigeria
</p>
         <p>
c
Division of Preclinical Sciences, Chakri Naruebodindra Medical Institute, Faculty of Medicine Ramathibodi Hospital, Mahidol University, Samutprakarn, 10540,
</p>
         <p>
Thailand
</p>
         <p>
d

National Center for Genetic Engineering and 
Biotechnology
, National Science and 
Technology Development Agency
, 
Pathum Thani
, 12120, 
Thailand
e
Research School of Chemistry
, 
The Australian National University
, 
Canberra
, ACT, 2601, 
Australia
</p>
         <p>
ARTICLE
INFO
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
ABSTRACT
</p>
         <p>
A phytochemical study on the root extracts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
, a Nigerian medicinal plant used in the management of diarrhea, led to the isolation of one new and 19 known natural products. These compounds and crude extracts were evaluated for Cystic Fibrosis Transmembrane Conductance Regulator (CFTR) Cl channel and calcium-activated Cl channel (TMEM16A) inhibitory activities in T84 and Calu-3 cells, respectively. Four compounds namely dolineon, neodulin, pachyrrhizine, and neotenone inhibited cAMP-induced Cl secretion across T84 cell monolayers with IC 
50
values of ~0.81 μM, ~2.42 μM, ~2.87 μM, and ~4.66 μM, respectively. Dolineon having the highest inhibitory activity also inhibited a Ca + activated Cl channel (TMEM16A) with an IC 
50
value of ~4.38 μM. The 
in vitro
antidiarrheal activity of dolineon was evaluated on cholera toxin (CT) induced chloride secretion in T84 cells, where it inhibited CT-induced chloride secretion by
&gt;
70% at 100 μM. Dolineon also inhibited CT-induced fluid secretion by ~70% in an in vivo mouse closed loop model at a dose of 16.9 μg/loop. The cytotoxicity of the extracts and compounds was evaluated on KB, Vero and BHK21 cells, dolineon showed low cytotoxicity of
&gt;
29.6 μM and 57.30 + 6.77 μM against Vero and BHK21 cells, respectively. Our study revealed that several compounds isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
showed antidiarrheal activity. The most active compound dolineon can potentially serve as a lead compound towards the development of CFTR and TMEM16A inhibitors as future therapeutics for secretory diarrhea.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Fabacae</p>
         <p>Nigerian traditional medicine</p>
         <p>Phytochemical</p>
         <p>CFTR</p>
         <p>TMEM16A</p>
         <p>Antidiarrheal</p>
         <p>Cytotoxicity</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Herbal preparations made by water maceration of the rhizome (root) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia mitis
(A. Rich) Verdc. (Fabacae)
</tp:taxon-name>
are used by Traditional Medicine (TM) practitioners and livestock owners in 
Nigeria
, as an effective means of treating the symptoms of diarrhea in both humans and livestock (

, 

; 

). This plant is native to West, Central and South African countries, and in 
Nigeria
it is found in the middle belt region (

</p>
         <p>
2019; 

). Some species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia
</tp:taxon-name>
have been studied for their medicinal properties including 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
, formally named 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neorautanenia pseudopacyrrhiza
</tp:taxon-name>
(

, 

), 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. amboensis
(
Breytenbach and Rall, 1980
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. edulis
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

; 

) and the closely related 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pachyrrhiza erosus
(
Krishnamurti et al., 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
is used in TM practice in many African countries to treat conditions such as; syphilis, dysmenorrhea, scabies, rashes, female frigidity, and diarrhea. (

; 

; 

). Phytochemical and biological studies on this plant have been reported by many groups. Individual phytochemicals and crude extracts have been shown to have cytotoxicity (

), acaricidal, insecticidal (

), larvicidal, mosquitocidal (

), antinocicetive, anti-inflammatory (

, 

), antimicrobial (

) and antidiarrheal activities (

). In our current study, we continue to explore Nigerian medicinal plants that are useful in alleviating the symptoms of diarrhrea and sought to identify the compound(s) responsible for this activity.
</p>
         <p>
Diarrhea is a global problem and a common symptom in many diseases, when it persists; it can lead to loss of electrolytes, dehydration and in severe cases it can be fatal (

; 

). Causes can range from bacterial, viral, fungal and parasitic infections, the side effects from drugs and other physiological disorders. In developing countries, periodic outbreaks of severe secretory diarrhea caused by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Vibrio cholerae
</tp:taxon-name>
results in high morbidity and mortality, especially in children under the age of 5 years. Despite improvements in diarrhea case management, it still accounts for 1.5 million deaths annually and 1% of deaths in children under the age of 5 years (

). Most of these deaths are recorded in developing countries, with 78% child deaths from diarrhea occurring in the African and South-East Asian regions (World gastroenterology global guidelines, 2012). While in 
Nigeria
, the mortality rate in children was about 331.3 per 
100,000 in
2016 (

, Diarrhoeal Disease Collaborators, 2018). Diarrhea, however, remains a common reason for hospital consultation in developed countries leading to discomfort and loss of productivity (

). The search for new drugs and approaches in the management of diarrhea are eminent and medicinal plants have been reported as effective means of treating the symptoms of diarrhea among farmers, rural dwellers and TM practitioners (

). The World Health Organisation (WHO) also suggested the use of herbal formulations in treating these conditions (

).
</p>
         <p>
One approach in the treatment of secretory diarrhea involves the use of CFTR and TMEM16A inhibitors. CFTR is a cAMP-activated chloride channel expressed in epithelia of the intestine and other organs and tissues, where it facilitates transepithelial fluid transport. In the intestine, cholera toxin (CT) released by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Vibrio cholera
</tp:taxon-name>
leads to a rise in intracellular cAMP which triggers CFTR chloride secretion and is followed by massive fluid secretion into the GIT resulting in diarrhea. CFTR and TMEM16A inhibitors are specific and effective in the management of secretory diarrheas (

; 

). Herein we report the CFTR and TMEM16A inhibitory activities and cytotoxicity of the compounds isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
. (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
The phytochemical components of the dichloromethane (DCM) extract of the dried roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
were separated by thin layer chromatography (TLC), column chromatography (CC) over silica gel or Sephadex LH-20, and preparative thin layer chromatography (PTLC), to give the following compounds; neoduleen (
1
) (

), neodulin (
2
) (

), ferulic acid (
3
) (

), ambonane (
4
) (

), stigmasterole (
5
) (

; 

), pachyrrhizine (
6
) (

), neotenone (
7
) (

), 7-methoxy-3-(6-methoxybenzo[d][1,3]dioxol-5-yl) chroman-4-one (
8
) (

), 12a-hydroxydolineon (
9
) (

), dolineon (
10
) (

), ()-2-isopentenyl-3-hydroxy-8-9-methylenedioxypterocarpan (
11
) (

), nepseudin (
12
) (

), neorautenol (
13
) (

; 

), isoneorautenol (
14
) (

), ()-2-hydroxypterocarpin (
15
) (

), rotenone (
16
) (

; Phrutivorapongkul et al., 2002), 12a-hydroxyrotenone (
17
) (

; 

), dehydroneotenone (
18
) (

), rautandiol A (
19
) (

) and rautandiol B (
20
) (

) 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
8
was a new natural product, while single crystal X-ray diffraction allowed the configurations of compounds 
11
and 
20
to be established for the first time as (6a- 
R
,11a- 
R
) and (6a- 
R
,11a- 
R
, 2 
′
- 
S
), respectively (
Fig. 2
). This study has also allowed us to provide complete NMR assignments and supporting spectroscopic data for compounds 
1
, 
3
, 
4
, 
11
, 
12
, 
13
and 
15
which were lacking in the literature. Compound 
3
was isolated as a single entity for the first time, therefore its full physical and spectroscopic data is also provided. Nine compounds, 
1
, 
3
, 
4
, 
5
, 
8
, 
11
, 
13
, 
14
and 
15
, were isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
for the first time.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Because the TM practitioners administer the aqueous extract of the roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
orally to treat the symptoms of diarrhea, we also prepared the crude aqueous extract using the traditional method (water maceration) (

). This extract was concentrated in vacuo and further extracted with chloroform and the components separated by CC to give compounds 
2
, 
6
, 
7
and 
18
with the percentage yields of 0.20%, 0.58%, 1.1% and 0.78%, respectively based on the dry weight of the root material.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
8
was isolated as a white solid after purification by Prep. TLC, mp 133–135 
◦
C
, and [α] 
22
-11.2 (
c
0.2 CHCl 
3
). Its HRESITOFMS data afforded an [M + H] + ion peak at 
m/z
329.1025, implying a molecular formula of 
C
18
H 
16
O 
6
(calcd for 
C
18
H 
17
O 
6
, 
m/z
329.1025). The 
13
C
NMR and DEPT spectra indicated the presence of a total of 18 carbons, eight of which were quaternary, five aromatic methines, two methylenes, one sp 
3
methine and two methoxy carbons (
Table 1
). The resonance for the oxygenated aromatic carbons were at 
δC
165.8 (C-7), 163.8 (C-8a), 152.8 (C-2 
′
), 147.7 (C-5 
′
), 141.3 (C-4 
′
), while C-4 resonated at 
δC
191.5. The 
1
H NMR spectrum showed aromatic proton resonances at 
δH
7.92 (d, 
J
= 8.8 Hz, 1H), 6.61 (dd, 
J
= 8.8, 2.1 Hz, 1H), 6.59 (s, 1H), 6.56 (s, 1H), and 6.44 (d, 
J
= 2.0 Hz, 1H). The HMBC correlations (
Table 1
) allowed the assignment of the aromatic ring protons to the A and B rings which were consistent with an isoflavonoid skeleton. The methylenedioxy group, 
δH
5.91 (s, 2H), was substituted at C-4 
′
and C-5 
′
on the B ring from its HMBC correlations, while the 
1
H NMR resonances at 
δH
3.85 (s, 3H) and 3.74 (s, 3H) represented the methoxy groups that were substituted at C-7 and C-2 
′
on the A and B rings, respectively. The methylene protons at 
δH
4.57–4.45 (m, 2H) and the methine proton at 
δH
4.25 (dd, 
J
=11.3, 5.5 Hz, 1H) were part of the heterocyclic 
C
ring. Their chemical shifts and splitting patterns were comparable to those of the corresponding protons of compound 
7
(

), which was also isolated in this study. Compound 
8
, or its isomer was prepared by synthesis; however the authors were not able to distinguish between the two possible structures. The NMR spectroscopic data of the synthetic compound was not provided to allow for a comparison (

).
</p>
         <p>
a
Assignments were made on the basis of COSY,HSQC and HMBC correlations, chemical shift values are in δ (ppm), and coupling constants (
J
) are in Hz.

</p>
         <p>
Compounds 
2
, 
6
, 
7
, 
10
, 
11
, 
15
, 
16
, and 
18–20
, which we had in sufficient quantities, and the crude DCM and aqueous extract were tested in a primary screen at 5 μM (compound) or 5 μg/mL (extracts) for their CFTR inhibitory activities. The results are shown in 
Table 2
.
</p>
         <p>
The IC 
50
values of the most active compounds and of the two extracts in the inhibition of cAMP-induced chloride secretion were determined as shown in 
Fig. 3
and 
Fig. 4
. Compounds 
2
, 
6
, 
7
, and 
10
and the aqueous extract (ABAQ) inhibited cAMP-induced chloride secretion in a concentration-dependent manner with significant IC 
50
values of 2.23 ± 0.26 μM, 6.21 ±0.78 μM, 2.86 ± 0.43 μM, 0.81 ± 0.19 μM and 2.49 ± 0.43 μg/mL, respectively, when compared to the reference compound CFTRinh-172 which showed a consistent IC 
50
of ~5 μM in intact T84 cells. These results indicated that compound 
10
had the highest inhibitory activity. No further investigations were carried out on compounds 
11
and 
16
or the DCM extract (ABDCM), because they did not give dosedependent responses.
</p>
         <p>
TMEM16A is a Ca 
2+
-activated Cl channel that transports Cl across biological membranes. It plays an important role in various physiological processes, and also an active role in fluid secretion in epithelial cells. The TMEM16A inhibitory effects of the isolated compounds and the two extracts were assessed by apical Cl current (
ICl
) analysis in human airway epithelial (Calu-3) cells since these cells endogenously expressed high levels of TMEM16A (

).
</p>
         <p>
As shown in 
Fig. 5
, pre-treatment of Calu-3 cells with MONNA, a specific TMEM16A inhibitor (

), almost completely diminished Cl current induced by 
Eact
, a specific TMEM16A activator (

), ensuring functional existence of TMEM16A in Calu-3 cells. The TMEM16A inhibitory effects of the isolated compounds and extracts were determined at 10 μM or 10 μg/mL, respectively. This primary screening revealed that the ABDCM and ABAQ extracts produced the highest TMEM16A inhibition (
Table 3
). The inhibitory activity of the DCM extract was determined as shown in 
Fig. 6
. ABDCM inhibited TMEM16A in a concentration-dependent manner with an IC 
50
value of 8.05 ± 0.96 μg/mL, with complete inhibition observed at 20 μg/mL.
</p>
         <p>
To help understand the possible mechanism of action of compound 
10
on CFTR chloride channel activity, apical 
I
Clˉ
current was measured in basolateral permeabilized T84 cells. These experiments were designed to determine whether compound 
10
inhibited the CFTR chloride channel through cAMP alteration. As shown in 
Fig. 7
, compound 
10
showed concentration-dependent inhibition of CFTR-mediated apical 
I
Clˉ
stimulated by various cAMP agonist, including forskolin (adenylate cyclase activator), forskolin plus IBMX (phosphodiesterase inhibitor) and CPT-cAMP (a cell-permeable cAMP) with IC 
50
values of 2.12 ±0.39 μM, 1.9 ± 0.18 μM and 1.49 ± 0.23 μM, respectively. These findings indicated that CFTR inhibition by compound 
10
does not involve cAMP alteration.
</p>
         <p>
CFTR Cl current can be suppressed by negative regulators including protein phosphatase (PP) and multidrug-resistance protein 4 (MRP4). As shown in 
Fig. 8
, compound 
10
concentration-dependently inhibited CFTR-mediated apical 
I
Clˉ
after treatment with the protein phosphatase inhibitor (Na 
3
VO
4
) or MRP4 inhibitor (MK571) with IC 
50
values of 1.93 ± 0.04 μM and 2.4 ± 0.08 μM, respectively. Thus CFTR inhibition by compound 
10
was not significantly affected by pre-treatment with protein phosphatase inhibitor or MRP4 inhibitor. These findings indicate that the inhibitory effect of compound 
10
on CFTR chloride channel activity does not involve activation of protein phosphatase and/or MRP4.
</p>
         <p>
Apart from CFTR, intestinal Ca 
2+
-activated Cl channel (CaCC) also plays a pivotal role in the pathogenesis of secretory diarrheas. 
43
Therefore, we investigated whether compound 
10
could inhibit intestinal CaCC. Apical Cl current measurement was performed in T84 cell monolayers. The results showed that compound 
10
inhibited intestinal CaCC current in a concentration-dependent manner with an IC 
50
value of 4.38 ±0.38 μM. Maximal inhibition was observed at 100 μM as shown in 
Fig. 9
.
</p>
         <p>
Next, we evaluated the anti-diarrheal activity of compound 

10
in

in vitro
models of chloride secretion in T84 cell monolayers and an in vivo closed loop model of fluid secretion induced by cholera toxin (CT) challenge (

). It was found that compound 
10
inhibited CT-induced chloride secretion in T84 cells with an IC 
50
value of 1.16 μM and
&gt;
70% of inhibition of fluid secretion at 100 μM (
Fig. 10A
). In a mouse closed loop model, the weight/length ratios of loops were determined to assess intestinal fluid secretion. In this experiment, intestinal loops were instilled with CT (1 μg/loop) with or without compound 
10
at a dose of 16.9 μg/loop. Interestingly, compound 
10
at this dose inhibited CT-induced fluid secretion by ~70% (
Fig. 10B
). These results indicate that compound 
10
could serve as a lead compound for the development of future CFTR inhibitors that may have therapeutic potential for the treatment of diarrhea.
</p>
         <p>
Most of the isolated compounds were assayed for cytotoxicity against KB (mouth epidermal carcinoma cells), Vero (kidney epithelial cells of an African green monkey) and BHK21 (baby hamster kidney fibroblast) cell lines. 
Table 4
shows the results of these assays. The aqueous (ABAQ) and DCM (ABDCM) extracts showed significant activities against KB cells with IC 
50
values of 1.0 ±0.2 and 0.35 ±0.04 μg/mL, respectively, they were also cytotoxic against Vero cells with IC 
50
values of 5.8 ±1.1 and 2.7 ±0.6 μg/mL, respectively. Compound 
16
and 
17
were identified as responsible for the cytotoxicity observed in the crude DCM extract, as they also showed high cytotoxic activities against KB cells with IC 
50
values of 0.006 ± 0.003, and 0.09 ± 0.003 μM, respectively. This is similar to the activity reported for these compounds against MCF-7 breast cancer cells and A-549 lung cancer cells (

). However, these compounds were found to be highly toxic against Vero cells with IC 
50
values of 0.17 ±0.02, and 0.02 ±0.02 μM, respectively. Compound 
17
was the most toxic, consistent with its insecticidal properties (

). Compounds 
2
, 
6
, 
7
, 
10
and 
20
showed no cytotoxicity. Importantly, compound 
10
being identified as a lead CFTR inhibitor showed low toxicity on non-cancerous cell lines giving IC 
50
values of
&gt;
29.6 and 57.30 μM against Vero and BHK21 cells, respectively. Therefore consistent with earlier reports (

).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
3. Conclusions
</p>
         <p>
This study has led to the isolation and characterization of one new compound (
8
) and 19 known compounds from the root extracts of 

<tp:taxon-name>N. mitis</tp:taxon-name>
.

With the aid of crystallography, the absolute configurations of two compounds (
11
and 
20
) were determined. The presence of multiple compounds (
2
, 
6
, 
7
, and 
10
) with CFTR inhibitory activity in the extracts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
may account for its anti-secretory activity and there by its antidiarrheal activity as acclaimed by TM practitioners. The most potent CFTR inhibitor, compound 
10 (
IC 
50
=0.81 ±0.19 μM), was judged to be relatively safe based on the IC 
50
values of
&gt;
29.6 μM against Vero cells and 57.30 ±6.77 μM against BHK21 cells. Therefore, this compound can be considered as a potential lead candidate for drug development towards the treatment of secretory diarrhea.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental section
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
The structures of all isolated compounds were elucidated using the following spectroscopic methods; IR, MS, NMR (1D and 2D), MP, and optical rotation. The IR was measured on FTIR Shimadzu IRAffinity-1 with MIRacle, MS was measured on LCMS-2020 Shimadzu for ESI and HRSIMS on Thermo Scientific Electron Transfer Dissociated (ETD) Orbitrap Fusion FSN 10314-1. The NMR data was recorded on Bruker Avance with Cryoprobe (500 MHz) and Bruker Ascend (400 MHz) using deuterated chloroform (CDCl 
3
) and d 
4
-methanol as solvents with TMS as an internal solvent. Melting points were measured on a Buchi M.560 apparatus and optical rotation was measured on Jasco P-2000 polarimeter. The short-circuit current and chloride current (
Isc
, 
ICl
) were measured on using a DVC-1000 voltage-clamp (World Precision Instruments, Sarasota, FL, 
U.S.A.
) with Ag/AgCl electrodes and 1 M KCl agar bridges.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>
The roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
(A. Rich) Verdc. (Fabacae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected from Kabwir in Kanke Local Government Area of 
Plateau state
, 
Nigeria
(Latitude 

9 
o
29ʹ 18.2ʹʹ N

and Longitude 

9 
o
29ʹ 30.0ʹʹ E

) in 
July 2016
. The plant was identified by botanist Mr Otuwose Agyeno of the Department of Plant Science and Technology, University of Jos, 
Nigeria
. The plant sample was deposited in the University of Jos herbarium where the voucher number was allocated as UJ16000246.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
were washed with water and shredded into small pieces and dried in an oven at 45 
◦
C
for 2 d. The dried root was pulverized using a mortar and pestle. About 
1000 g
of the powder was successively extracted for 72 h with dichloromethane (DCM, 4 L) and then ethanol (4 L). The extracts were filtered through a sieve (150 μm), a cotton plug and then filter paper. The filtrates were dried under a constant stream of air provided by a laboratory electric fan overnight, to obtain dark brown solids for both extracts. The yields for the DCM and ethanol extracts were 
15 g
(1.5%) and 
10 g
(1%), respectively. Both extracts show similar TLC profiles.
</p>
         <p>
A portion of the DCM extract (
14 g
) was separated by column chromatography (CC) over silica gel using a gradient system from ethyl acetate (EtOAc)/hexanes (1:9) to 100% EtOAc to yield 40 fractions; these were combined based on their similarities by TLC and NMR analysis to afford 12 fractions (F1–F12). Fraction F2 (
150 mg
) was separated by CC over silica gel using a gradient system from EtOAc/ hexanes (1:9) to 100% EtOAc to give seven sub-fractions (F2f1-F2f7). Sub-fraction F2f5 was triturated with hexane, the hexane was decanted to leave a white solid identified as compound 
1
(
9.2 mg
). Fraction F3 (
490 mg
) was purified by CC over silica gel using a gradient system from EtOAc/hexanes (1:9) to 100% EtOAc to give compound 
2
(
343 mg
) as a white solid. Separation of fraction F4 (
150 mg
) by CC over silica gel and elution with a gradient system of hexanes/DCM (95:5) gave ten sub-fractions (F4f1-F4f10). Evaporation of sub-fraction F4f5 gave compound 
3
(
22 mg
) as a white solid. Fraction F5 (
90 mg
) yielded five sub-fractions (F5f1-F5f5), when chromatographed on silica gel by elution with hexanes/DCM (5:95). Evaporation of sub-fraction F5f3 gave compound 
4
(
1.9 mg
) as a white solid. Fraction F6 (
250 mg
) was separated by CC over silica gel by elution with hexanes/DCM (5:95) to give ten sub-fractions (F6f1-F6f10), F6f3 was crystallized from DCM/hexanes (1:3) to give large white crystals identified as compound 
5
(
82 mg
). Fraction F7 (
560 mg
) was separated by CC over silica gel using a gradient system of EtOAc/DCM (2:98) to give seven sub-fractions (F7f1- F7f7). Evaporation of sub-fraction F7f4 gave compound 
6
(
150 mg
) as a yellow solid, while, evaporation of sub-fraction F7f5 gave compound 
7
(
227 mg
) as white needles. Fraction F8 (380.0 mg) was separated by CC over silica gel elution with EtOAc/DCM (5:95) to give 15 sub-fractions (F8f1-F8f15). The purification of sub-fraction F8f2 (
19 mg
) by prep. TLC with elution with EtOAc/DCM (5:95) yielded compounds 
8
(
4.9 mg
) as a white solid, and 
9
(
3.9 mg
) as a yellow solid. Sub-fractions F8f3, F8f5, and F8f8 respectively provided compounds 
10
, (
84.1 mg
) as brown solid and compounds 
11
(
15.4 mg
) and 
12
(15.0 mg) as white sticky solids. Compound 
11
was identified by X-ray crystallography; single white crystals were grown from DCM/hexanes (1:3). Sub-fractions F8f9 and F8f10 were combined based on their TLC and NMR spectrum similarities and named F8f910 (
15 mg
) which was purified by prep. TLC with elution with EtOAc/DCM (95:5) to yield compounds 
13
(
4.5 mg
) and 
14
(
2.7 mg
), both as white sticky solids. Fraction 9 (
160 mg
) was separated by CC over silica gel with a gradient system of EtOAc/ 
CH
2
Cl 
2
(5:95) to afford ten sub-fractions (F9f1-F9f10), on the bases of their TLC similarities, sub-fractions F9f5, F9f6 and F9f7 were combined, evaporated and the solid residue was triturated with hexane to obtain a white powder identified as compound 
15
(
9.1 mg
). Fraction F10 (
1.18 g
) was purified by CC over silica gel elution with DCM/ 
CH
2
Cl 
2
(5:95) to afford 26 sub-fractions (F10f1-F10f26). Sub-fractions F10f16 to F10f21 were combined based on their TLC and NMR similarities. The combined fraction (
215 mg
) was triturated with methanol and the soluble portion (
113 mg
) was separated by CC over Sephadex (LH20) by elution with 100% methanol to yield four fractions (A-D). Fraction B was purified once more by CC over Sephadex (LH20) by elution with 100% methanol to yield compound 
16
(
19.2 mg
), as yellow needles and compound 
17
(
9.4 mg
) as a brown solid. Fraction F11 (
90 mg
) was separated by CC over silica gel using a gradient system of EtOAc/DCM (10:90) to yield ten fractions (F11f1-F11f10). Sub-fraction F10f6 was identified as compound 
18
(
21.3 mg
) with a white fluffy appearance. Fraction F12 (
2.28 g
) was evaporated, washed with methanol to obtain the methanol soluble portion (
1.18 g
), which was separated by CC over Sephadex (LH20) by elution with 100% methanol to obtain ten sub-fractions (F12f1-F12f10). Sub-fractions F12f7, F12f8 and F12f9 were combined based on their TLC and NMR similarities. The combined portion was again purified over Sephadex (LH20) by elution with 100% methanol to yield two fractions (A and B). Fraction A (
2.9 mg
) a white solid was identified as compound 
19
(
2.9 mg
), while fraction B was further washed with DCM to obtain a white solid (
15 mg
) which was crystallized from methanol, DCM, hexanes (1:1:2) and the white crystal were identified as compound 
20
(
15 mg
).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.1. Preparation of aqueous extract and isolation of chloroform soluble compounds
</p>
         <p>
The aqueous root extract (ABAQ) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
was prepared as described (

), and about 
1 g
of ABAQ was dissolved in chloroform, filtered and evaporated in rotary evaporator to obtain a yield of 
291.1 mg
, which is tagged ABAQ-Chlo. The whole amount of ABAQ-Chlo was chromatographed on CC over silica gel using a gradient system from EtOAc/hexanes (2:8) to 100% EtOAc to give eight fractions (F1–F7). Fraction F1 (
11.7 mg
) was identified as compound 
2
, while fraction F4 was confirmed as compound 
7
(
11.1 mg
). Compound 
6
(
5.8 mg
) was purified from fraction F5, and fraction F6 resulted in compound 
18
(
7.1 mg
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

4.4. Short-circuit current (ISC) and apical Cl current (
ICl
) measurement

</p>
         <p>
T84 and Calu-3 cells were obtained from American 
Type
Culture Collection (Manassas, VA, 
USA
). They were maintained in DMEM and Ham’ s F-12 medium (1:1) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 μg/mL streptomycin, at 37 
◦
C
under a humidified 95% O 
2
/5% CO 
2
atmosphere. T84 and Calu-3 cells at the density of 5 × 10 
5
cells/insert were seeded in snapwell™ insert, and cultured in a humidified incubator with replacement of the cultured medium on alternate day. After transepithelial electrical resistance of the cells monolayer reached 1000 Ω cm 
2
as measured by an EVOM2 voltohm meter (World Precision Instruments, Sarasota, 
Florida
, 
USA
), the cells were mounted in an Ussing chamber. For ISC analysis, both hemichambers were filled with Kreb’ s solution (pH 7.4) containing 20 mM NaCl, 25 mM NaHCO 
3
, 3.3 mM KH 
2
PO 
4
, 0.8 mM K 
2
HPO 
4
, 1.2 mM MgCl 
2
, 1.2 mM CaCl 
2
and 10 mM glucose. For apical 
ICl
analysis, basolateral-to-apical Cl gradient buffers were applied. The basolateral high Cl buffer (pH 7.4) was composed of 130 mM NaCl, 2.7 mM KCl, 1.5 mM KH 
2
PO 
4
, 1 mM CaCl 
2,
0.5 mM MgCl 
2
, 10 mM Na-HEPES (pH 7.4) and 10 mM glucose. In apical low Cl buffer (pH 7.4), 65 mM NaCl was substituted with 65 mM sodium gluconate, and the CaCl 
2
concentration was increased to 2 mM. In addition, amphotericin B (250 μg/mL) was added into the basolateral solution 20 min before 
ICl
measurement to capacitate basolateral membrane permeabilization. The solutions were maintained at 37 
◦
C
with bubbling of 95% O 
2
/5% CO 
2
for the ISC measurements, or 100% O 
2
for the 
ICl
measurements (Phrutivorapongkul et al., 2002; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Mouse model of cholera toxin-induced intestinal fluid secretion
</title>
         <p>
ICR male mice (
30–35g
) were obtained from 
Nomura
Siam 
International
, 
Pathumwan
, 
Bangkok
, 
Thailand
. 
Mice
were maintained under a controlled environment (temperature 25 ± 1 
◦
C; humidity 30–70%; 12:12 h dark-light). 
Mice
were fasting for 24 h prior to the experiment. 
After
that, mice were anesthetized by intraperitoneal administration of thiopental (
50 mg
/kg). 
During
the surgery, the body temperatures of the mice were maintained at 37 
◦
C using heating pads. 
Abdominal
incision was made and the ileal segment of the small intestine was ligated twopoint in 
2–3 cm
length with sterile silk thread. 
Ileal
loops were instilled with 100 μL of phosphate-buffered saline (
PBS
) or 
PBS
containing cholera toxin (1 μg/loop) with or without intraluminal administration of compound 10 (16.9 μg/loop). The abdomen was closed and mice were allowed to recover from anaesthesia. After 6 h, both mice were euthanized for collection of lileal loops. The weight/length ratios of ileal loops were measured and were used as an indicator of intestinal fluid secretion. This study has been approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of the 
Faculty of Science
, Mahidol University (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Cytotoxicity
</title>
         <p>
Three mammalian cells: KB cells, (mouth epidermal carcinoma cells), Vero cells (kidney African green monkey epithelial cells) and BHK cells (baby hamster kidney fibroblasts) were cultured at 37 
◦
C
in a 5% CO 
2
incubator. KB and BHK cells were maintained in DMEM Dulbecco’ s Modified Eagle media supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 
3.7 g
/L sodium bicarbonate and 1% MEM non-essential amino acids. For BHK21 cell, the media was also supplemented with 1% glutamax. Vero cell was maintained in Minimal Essential Medium with Earle’ s salts (MEM/EBSS) supplemented with 10% FBS, 
2.2 g
/L sodium bicarbonate and 1 mM sodium pyruvate.
</p>
         <p>
For 
in vitro
cytotoxicity assays, the crude extract/pure compound stocks were dissolved DMSO and then diluted with cell culture medium. 25 μL of working crude extracts/pure compounds were added to each well of a 96 wells-plate containing 125 μL growth media. Then, the cells were plated at a density of 19, 000 cells/well. Following 72 h incubation, 100 μL of 10% trichloroacetic acid was added to each well and the plates incubated at 4 
◦
C
for 45 min. Fixed cells were washed with distilled water, air-dried and stained with 0.057% (w/v) sulforhodamine B in 1% acetic acid. The plate was incubated in the dark for 30 min. The wells were washed four times with 1% acetic acids and air dried. Then, 200 μL of 10× Tris-buffer was added to each well and shaken for 30 min at 400 rpm. The absorbance for each well was measured at 
510 nm
wavelength in a microplate reader. The 50% inhibitory concentration (IC 
50
) values of the crude extracts/pure compounds were determined following literature procedures (

; 

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Statistical analysis
</title>
         <p>
Results were presented as means ± S.E.M. Student’ s 
t
-test or Oneway ANOVA with Tukey’ s post test was performed to evaluate statistical difference between control and treatment groups, where appropriate. 
p
value 
&lt;
0.05 was considered as statistical significance.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Crystal structure data
</title>
         <p>
The crystal data of 
11
and 
20
have been deposited with the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre and assigned a supplementary publication numbers, CCDC 1973442 for 
11
and CCDC 1972703 for 
20
. These data can be access from Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre via www.ccdc.cam.ac.uk/data_request/cif.
</p>
         <p>
Research data
</p>
         <p>Research data to this article will be provided on request.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>We wish to confirm that there are no known conflicts of interest associated with this publication and there has been no significant financial support for this work that could have influenced its outcome.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
The University of Wollongong, NSW, 
Australia
and the University of Jos, 
Plateau State
, 
Nigeria
are highly appreciated for providing the financial support for this project. The TM practioners, especially Mr Yilnya Gosomji, are acknowledged for sharing their traditional knowledge. SK was supported by a Research Chair Grant (project no. P-18- 50116) from the National Science and Technology Development Agency (NSTDA), 
Thailand
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112464.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Breytenbach, J.C.
, 
Rall, G.J.H.
, 
1980
. 

Structure and synthesis of isoflavonoid analogues from 
Neorautanenia amboensis
Schinz

. 
J. Chem. Soc, Perkin Trans
. 
1804–1809
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/P19800001804
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Brink, A.J.
, 
Rall, G.J.H.
, 
Engelbrecht, J.
, 
1974
. 

Structures of some minor pterocarpans of 
Neorautanenia edulis

. 
Phytochemistry
8
, 
1581–1585
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031- 9422 (74)80332-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chaturvedula, V.S.P.
, 
Prakash, I.
, 
2012
. 

Isolation of stigmasterol and β- sitosterol from the dichloromethane extract of 
Rubus suavissimus

. 
ICPJ
9
, 
239–242
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.3329/icpj.v1i9.11613
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Crombie, L.
, 
Whiting, D.A.
, 
1962
. 
The constitution of neotenone and dolichone biogenetic connexions in the sub-family Papilionatae
. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
18
, 
801–804
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040-4039(00)70522-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Crombie, L.
, 
Whiting, D.A.
, 
1963
. 

The extractives of 
Neorautanenia pseudopachyrrhiza
the isolation and structure of a new rotenoid and two isoflavanones

. 
J. Chem. Soc.
1963
, 
1569–1579
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/JR9630001569
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cullen, D.R.
, 
Pengon, J.
, 
Rattanajak, R.
, 
Chaplin, J.
, 
Kamchonwongpaisan, S.
, 
Mocerino, M.
, 
2016
. 

Scoping Studies into the structure-activity relationship (SAR) of phenylephrine- derived analogues as inhibitors of 
Trypanosoma brucei rhodesiense

. 
Chem. Select.
15
, 
4533–4538
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/slct.201601059
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dawurung, C.J.
, 
Jurbe, G.G.
, 
Usman, J.G.
, 
Elisha, I.L.
, 
Lombin, L.H.
, 
Pyne, S.G.
, 
2019
. 
Antidiarrheal activity of some selected Nigerian plants used in traditional medicine
. 
Phcog. Res.
11
, 
371–777
. 
https://doi.org/10.4103/pr.pr_43_19
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Estrella-Parra, E.A.
, 
Gomez-Verjan, J.C.
, 
Gonzalez-Sanchez, I.
, 
Vazquez-Martinez, E.R.
, 
Vergara-Castaneda, E.
, 
Cerbon, M.A.
, 
Alavez-Solano, D.
, 
Reyes-Chilpa, R.
, 
2014
. 

Rotenone ioslated from 
Pachyrhizus erosus
displays cytotoxicity and geneotoxicity in K562 cells

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
20
https://doi.org/10.1080/14786419.2014.939081
, 1780-1758.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fine, K.D.
, 
Schiller, L.R.
, 
1999
. 
AGA technical review on the evaluation and management of chronic diarrhea gasteroenterology
6
, 
1464–1486
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ S0016- 5085(99)70513-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fraga, B.M.
, 
Gonzalez-Coloma, A.
, 
Alegre-Gomez, S.
, 
Lopez-Rodriguez, M.
, 
Amador, L.J.
, 
Daiz, C.E.
, 
2017
. 

Bioactive constituents from transformed root cultures of 
Nepeta teydea

. 
Phytochemistry
133
, 
59–69
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2016.10.008
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
GBD
2016
Diarrhoeal Disease Collaborators, 2018. Estimates of the global, regional, and national morbidity, mortality, and aetiologies of diarrhoea in 195 countries: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2016
. 
Lancet Inf. Dis.
18
, 
1211–1228
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-3099(18)30362-1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jia, L.
, 
Liu, W.
, 
Guan, L.
, 
Lu, M.
, 
Wang, K.
, 
2015
. 
Inhibition of calcium-activated chloride channel ANO1/TMEM16A suppresses tumor growth and invasion in human lung cancer
. 
PloS One
10
, 
0136584
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0136584
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Joseph, C.C.
, 
Ndoile, M.M.
, 
Malima, R.C.
, 
Nkunya, M.H.H.
, 
2004
. 

Larvicidal and mosquitocidal extracts, a coumarin, isoflavonoids and pterocarpans from 
Neorautanenia mitis

. 
Trop. Med. Hygiene
98
, 
451–455
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. trstmh.2003.10.008
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Krishnamurti, M.
, 
Sambhy, Y.
, 
Seshadri, T.R.
, 
1970
. 

Chemical studies of Indian yam beans (
Pachyrrhizus erosis
): Isolation of two rotenoids: 12a-hydroxydolineon and 12a- hydroxypachyrrhizone

. 
Tetrahedron
1

2

, 
3023–3027
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ S0040-4020 (01)92883-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lasisi, A.A.
, 
Adesomoju, A.
, 
2015
. 

Neoraudiol, a new isoflavonoid and other antimicrobial constituents from the tuberous root of 
Neorautanenia mitis
(A. Rich) Verdcourt. J

. 
Saudi Chem. Soc.
19
, 
404–409
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. jscs.2012.04.011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Levine, G.A.
, 
Walson, J.L.
, 
Atlas, H.E.
, 
Lamberti, L.M.
, 
Patricia, P.B.
, 
2017
. 
Defining pediatric diarrhea in low-resource settings
. 
J. Pedia. Infec. Dis. Soc.
3
, 
289–293
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/jpids/pix024
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mandal, A.
, 
Sahi, P.K.
, 
2017
. 
Probiotics for diarrhea in children
. 
JMRI
2
, 
5–12
. 
https:// doi.org/10.15419/jmri.66
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mitscher, L.A.
, 
Okwute, S.K.
, 
Gollapudi, S.R.
, 
Drake, S.
, 
Avona, E.
, 
1988
. 

Antimicrobial pterocarpans of Nigerian 
Erythrina mildbraedii

. 
Phytochemistry
11
, 
3449–3452
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(88)80746-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Muangnil, P.
, 
Satitsri, S.
, 
Tadpetch, K.
, 
Saparpakorn, P.
, 
Chatsudthipong, V.
, 
Hannongbua, S.
, 
Rukachaisirikul, V.
, 
Muanprasat, C.
, 
2018
. 
A fungal metabolite zearalenone as a CFTR inhibitor and potential and therapy of secretory diarrheas
. 
Biochem. Pharmacol.
150
, 
293–304
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcp.2018.02.024
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Muanprasat, C.
, 
Chatsudthipong, V.
, 
2013
. 
Cholera: pathophysiology and emerging therapeutic targets. Future Med
. 
Chem.
7
, 
781–798
. 
https://doi.org/10.4155/ fmc.13.42
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Namkung, W.
, 
Yao, Z.
, 
Finkbeiner, W.E.
, 
Verkman, A.S.
, 
2011
. 
Small-molecule activators of TMEM16A, a calcium-activated chloride channel, stimulate epithelial chloride secretion and intestinal contraction
. 
Am. Soc. Expt. Bio.
11
, 
4048–4062
. 
https://doi. org/10.1096/fj.11-191627
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nkengfack, A.E.
, 
Vardamides, J.C.
, 
Tanee Fomum, Z.T.
, 
Meyer, M.
, 
1995
. 

Prenylated isoflavanone from 
Erythrina eriotricha

. 
Phytochemistry
6
, 
1803–1808
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/0031-9422(95)00037-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oberholzer, M.E.
, 
Rall, G.J.H.
, 
Roux, D.G.
, 
1974
. 
The concurrence of 12a-hydroxy- and 12a-O- methylrotenoids. Isolation of the first natural 12a-O-methylrotenoids
. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
25
, 
2211–2214
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040-4039(01)93179- X
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Offiah, N.V.
, 
Dawurung, C.J.
, 
Oladipo, O.O.
, 
Makoshi, M.S.
, 
Makama, S.
, 
Elisha, I.L.
, 
Gotep, J.G.
, 
Samuel, A.L.
, 
Shamaki, D.
, 
2012
. 
Survey of herbal remedies used by Fulani herdsmen in the management of animal diarrhea in plateau state, Nigeria
. 
J. Med. Plants Res.
312
, 
4625–4632
. 
http://hdl.handle.net/123456789/2851
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Offiah, N.V.
, 
Makama, S.
, 
Elisha, I.L.
, 
Makoshi, M.S.
, 
Gotep, J.G.
, 
Dawurung, C.J.
, 
Oladipo, O.O.
, 
Samuel, A.L.
, 
Shamaki, D.
, 
2011
. 
Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants used in the treatment of animal diarrhoea in Plateau state, Nigeria
. 
BMC Vet. Res.
7
, 
36–45
. 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1746-6148/7/36
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oh, S.J.
, 
Hwang, S.J.
, 
Jung, J.
, 
Yu, K.
, 
Kim, J.
, 
Choi, J.Y.
, 
2013
. 
MONNA, a potent and selective blocker for transmembrane protein with unknown function 16/anoctamin- 1
. 
Mol. Pharmacol.
5
https://doi.org/10.1124/mol.113.087502
, 726-375.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Phrutivorapongkul, A.
, 
Lipipun, V.
, 
Ruangrungsi, N.
, 
Watanabe, T.
, 
Ishikawa, T.
, 
2002
. 

Studies of the constituents of seeds of 
Pachyrrhizus erosus
and their anti-herpes simplex virus (HSV) activities

. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
50
, 
534–537
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1248/cpb.50.534
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Puyvelde, L.V.
, 
Norbert, D.
, 
Kimpe, N.D.
, Jean-Pierre, 
Mudaheranwa, J.P.
, 
Gasiga, A.
, 
Schamp, N.
, Jean-Paul, 
Declercq, J.P.
, 
Meerssche, M.V.
, 
1987
. 

Isolation and structure elucidation of potentially insecticidal and acaricidal isoflovone- type compounds from 
Neorautanenia mitis

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
50
, 
349–356
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/np50051a002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rall, G.J.H.
, 
Engelbreght, J.P.
, 
Brink, A.J.
, 
1970
. 

The isolation, structure and absolute configuration of (-)-2-hydroxypterocarpin from 
Neorautenenia edulis

. 
Tetrahedron
26
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040-4020(01)93152-7
, 507-5012.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rall, G.J.H.
, 
Engelbreght, J.P.
, 
Brink, A.J.
, 
1971
. 

The chemistry of 
Neorautanenia edulis
G. A, Sm. The constitution of (-)-2-isopentenyl-3-hydoxy-8-9 methylenedioxypterocarpan, a new pterocarpan from the root bark. J. South Afri

. 
Chem. Inst.
26
, 
56–60
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sakurai, Y.
, 
Sakurai, N.
, 
Masahiko, T.
, 
Nakanishi, Y.
, 
Bastow, K.F.
, 
Wang, X.
, 
Cragg, G.M.
, 
Lee, K.H.
, 
2006
. 

Rautandiols A and B, pterocarpans and cytotoxic constituents from 
Neorautanenia mitis

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
69
, 
397–399
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np058070c
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Satitsri, S.
, 
Pongkorpsakol, P.
, 
Srimanote, P.
, 
Chatsudthipong, V.
, 
Muanprasat, C.
, 
2016
. 

Pathophysiological mechanisms of diarrhea caused by the 
Vibrio cholerae
O1 El Tor variant: an in vivo study in mice

. 
Virulence
7
, 
789–805
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 21505594.2016.1192743
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Suguinome, H.
, 
1959
. 

Oxygen heteocycles. A new isoflavanone from 
Sohora japonica

. 
J. Org. Chem.
24
, 
1655–1662
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jo01093a008
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tradtrantip, L.
, 
Namkung, W.
, 
Verkman, A.S.
, 
2010
. 

Crofelemer, an antisecretory antidiarrheal proanthocyanidin oligomer extracted from 
Croton lechleri
, targets two distinct intestinal chloride channels

. 
Mol. Pharmacol.
77
, 
69–78
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1124/mol.109.061051
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Van Duuren, B.L.
, 
1961
. 

Chemistry of edulin, neorautone, and related compounds from 
Neorautanenia edulis
C

. 
A. Sm. J. Org. Chem.
26
, 
5013–5020
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/jo01070a057
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vichai, V.
, 
Kirtikara, K.
, 
2006
. 
Sulforhodamine B colorimetric assay for cytotoxicity screening
. 
Nat. Protoc.
1
, 
1112–1116
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2006.179
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vongtau, H.O.
, 
Abbah, J.
, 
Mosugu, O.
, 
Chindo, B.A.
, 
Ngazal, I.E.
, 
Salawu, A.O.
, 
Kwanashie, H.O.
, 
Gamaniel, K.S.
, 
2004
. 

Antinociceptive profile of the methanolic extract of 
Neorautanenia mitis
root in rats and mice

. 
J. Ethnopharmcol.
92
, 
317–324
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2004.03.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vongtau, H.O.
, 
Amos, S.
, 
Binda, L.
, 
Kapu, S.D.
, 
Gamaniel, K.S.
, 
Kunle, O.F.
, 
Wambebe, C.
, 
2000
. 

Pharmacological effects of the aqueous extract of 
Neorautanenia mitis
in rodents

. 
J. Ethnopharmacol.
72
, 
207–214
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/s0378-8741(00) 00247-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wangchuk, P.
, 
Keller, P.A.
, 
Pyne, S.G.
, 
Taweechotipatr, M.
, 
Tonsomboon, A.
, 
Rattanajak, R.
, 
Kamchonwongpaisa, S.
, 
2011
. 
Screening of ethnopharmacologically selected Bhutanese medicinal plants for their phytochemical profiles and biological activities. J
. 
Ethnopharmacol.
1
, 
730–742
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. jep.2011.06.032
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

WHO Research Guidelines
for 
Evaluating the Safety
and

Efficacy of Herbal Medicines
, 
1993
. 
WHO, Manila
, p. 
94
. 
https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/20 7008/9290611103_en.pdf
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
World
gastroenterology global guidelines, February
2012
. 
Acute Diarrhea in Adults and Children: a Global Perspective
. 
http://www.worldgastroenterology.org/UserFile s/file/guidelines/acute-diarrhea-english-2012.pdf
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
