<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112430</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>CYP71BL9, the missing link in costunolide synthesis of sunflower</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Enzyme</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Enzyme</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Apiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Orobanche cumana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lactuca sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tanacetum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Nicotiana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lactuca sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Nicotiana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
N. benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae STL</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Nicotiana benthamiana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
CYP71BL9, the missing link in costunolide synthesis of sunflower
</p>
         <p>
Maximilian Frey
a, 
∗
, Iris Klaiber
b
, Jürgen Conrad
c
, Otmar Spring
a a 

Institute of Biology, Biochemistry of Plant Secondary Metabolism (190b), University of Hohenheim, Garbenstrasse 30, 70593, Stuttgart, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
b

Mass Spectrometry Unit, Core Facility Hohenheim, University of Hohenheim, Emil-Wolff-Str. 12, 70599, Stuttgart, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>
c

Institute of Chemistry, University of Hohenheim, Garbenstrasse 30, 70593, Stuttgart, 
Germany
</p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
L.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Sunflower</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Enzyme</tp:taxon-name>
characterization
</p>
         <p>Sesquiterpene lactone</p>
         <p>Costunolide synthase</p>
         <p>p450 enzyme</p>
         <p>CYP71BL9</p>
         <p>Hydroxylation</p>
         <p>CYP71BL subfamily</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Enzyme</tp:taxon-name>
phylogeny
</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Despite intensive research in recent years, the biosynthetic route to costunolide in sunflower so far remained obscured. Additional P450 sequences from public sunflower transcriptomic database were screened to search for candidate enzymes which are able to introduce the 6α-hydroxy-group required for the esterification with the carboxy group of germacarane A acid, the final step in costunolide formation. CYP71BL9, a new P450 enzyme from sunflower was shown to catalyze this hydroxylation, hence being identified as HaCOS. Phylogentically, HaCOS is closer related to HaG8H than to any other known costunolide synthase in 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
.The enzyme was successfully employed to reconstruct the sunflower biosynthesis of costunolide in transformed tobacco. Contrary, in yeast, only minor amounts of sesquiterpene lactone was produced, while 5-hydroxyfarnesylic acid was formed instead. HaCOS in combination with HaG8H produced 8β-hydroxycostunolide (eupatolide) in transformed plants, thus indicating that sunflower possesses two independent modes of eupatolide synthesis via HaCOS and via HaES. The lack of HaCOS expression and of costunolide in trichomes suggests that the enzyme triggers the costunolied synthesis of the inner tissues of sunflower and might be linked to growth regulation processes.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Sesquiterpene lactones (STL) are one of the largest groups of secondary metabolites in higher plants. They are defined by a 15 carbon backbone and a heterocyclic lactone ring which derives from an internal esterfication (

; 

). Compounds with an α-methylene-γ-lactone mojety usually show a wide range of bioactivities due to the electron affinity of the oxygen atoms in the lactone ring, which enables Michael 
type
addition to bionucleophils (

). Mostly, STL are attributed to secretory tissues of 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Apiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
where they serve as protectants against herbivory (

). In sunflower, derivatives of eupatolide (8β-hydroxycostunolide) occur highly concentrated in socalled capitate glandular trichomes (

; 

; 

). These biseriate multicellular trichomes are typical for many 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
, and in sunflower they develop very early on leave primordia (

, 

; 

) and on anthers, where they form a bitter and toxic barrier against predators (

). However, there is evidence, that STL can also be produced in inner tissues of sunflower, where they are found in 1000- fold lower concentrations and apparently have a physiological function in plant growth processes. So 8-epixanthatin, a xanthanolide-type STL was found in sunflower hypocotyls (Yokotani-Tomita et al., 1997) and seems to be involved in the phototropism of young seedlings (

). More recently, the guaianolide-type dehydrocostuslactone (

), the germacranolide-type costunolide and an additional xanthanolide named tomentosin (

) were found in sunflower roots and root exsudates where these STL trigger the germination and host recognition of broomrape, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Orobanche cumana
</tp:taxon-name>
. This shows the high signalling capacity of STL when acting in very low concentrations. Costunolide and its derivatives, such as dehydrocostuslactone, have been reported to inibit polar auxin transport in seedlings (

; 

; 

), thus confirming the possibility of a natural function of STL in plant growth regulation as suggested earlier (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The biosynthetic route to costunolide is well established for most Astereaceae lineages. All 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
possess the genes to produce the precursor, germacrene A acid, from farnesyl-diphospahte (FPP) (

, 

): Germacrene A synthase (GAS) converts FPP to germacrene A and germacrene A oxidase (GAO) catalyzes the subsequent three-step oxidation to germacrene A acid (GAA) (

; 

, 

). 

expressed the first costunolide synthase (LsCOS) from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lactuca sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
in combination with sunflower HaGAS and HaGAO in yeast cells. It was shown that the enzyme introduces a 6α-hydroxy-group which spontaneusly cyclizes germacrene A acid to costunoilde. EST sequence comparison showed that most 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
lineages possess LsCOS homologs and some of these have subsequently been characterized (

; 

; 

). However, in sunflower and related species of the Heliantheae tribe, LsCOS homologs were absent, whereas ESTs homolgous to HaG8H could be found (

). Most recently, it was shown that the STL present in sunflower capitate glandular trichomes are formed via 6α-hydroxylation of 8sshydroxy-germacrene A acid by means of the socalled eupatolide synthase HaES (

). The formation of costunolide (without 8β-hydroxy group) and dehydrocostuslactone in inner tissues of sunflower remained elusive, although, a costunolide 14-hydroxylase was recently found in sunflower (

). Therefore, we screened additional P450 sequences from public sunflower transcriptomic database to search for candidate enzymes for the final step in costunolide synthesis. CYP71BL9, a homolog to HaG8H was identified and showed the capacity to hydroxylate germacrene A acid in 6α position, the prerequisite for the subsequent lactonization to costunolide. This 
<tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
costunolide synthase (HaCOS, CYP71BL9) is characterized here. We also show, how two alternative pathways can lead to the same end product eupatolide and that the reconstruction in a yeast system can lead to unusual previously undescribed products.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Gene identification and phylogenetic analysis
</title>
         <p>
Previously, from the cDNA of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
cv. HA300 several candidate genes were described that had a similar expression pattern in a public transcriptome database (Heliagene). This led to the characterization of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
eupatolide synthase (

). We found in this database one accession that had a similar expression pattern to HaGAO. This gene was predominantly expressed in leaves and bracts and had a high sequence similarity to both HaG8H (the only so far characterized CYP71BL enzyme from sunflower) and to the costunolide synthases from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tanacetum
</tp:taxon-name>
and other 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
species. Using 5′and 3′RACE PCR we identified the whole open reading frame and the UTR regions of this gene, that was officially assigned CYP71BL9 (http://drnelson.uthsc.edu/cytochromeP450.html). The CYP71BL subfamily comprises only genes that use germacrene A acid as a substrate. In this group, CYP71BL9 clustered together with the 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
germacrene A acid 8β-hydroxylase HaG8H (CYP71BL1), but clearly separated from yet characterized costunolide synthases (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.2. Reconstruction of the costunolide biosynthesis in 
<tp:taxon-name>Nicotiana</tp:taxon-name>
benthamiana
</title>
         <p>
The biosynthetic pathway of germacrene A acid was recently resonstructed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
using the native sunflower enzymes HaGAS1 and HaGAO (

, 

). Ten enzyme candidates from 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
were now tested downstream of germacrene A acid and the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lactuca sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
costunolide synthase LsCOS (CYP71BL2) was used as a positive control. The expression of the candidate gene CYP71BL9 [p19/DXS + HaGAS1 + HaGAO + CYP71BL9] led to two major peaks (peak 
a
, 9.00 min) and (peak 
b
, 9.15 min), that were absent in the negative control [p19/DXS + HaGAS1 + HaGAO] (
Fig. 2A
). The masses and UV spectra of peak 
a
and 
b
indicated that these peaks could be the SH adducts costunolide-cysteine and costunolide-glutathione 
Fig..2B–D
). Indeed, comparison of retention time, exact mass and mass spectrum with synthetic adducts identified these peaks as costunolide-cysteine and costunolide-glutathione (peak a and b in 
Fig. S1
and 
Fig. S2
). Free costunolide (
c
**,14.18 min in 
Fig. 2A
) was only detected in trace amounts. In general, the production of costunolide (and its SH adducts) by CYP71BL9 was higher than in the control experiment with LsCOS. While both LsCOS and CYP71BL9 converted GAA to costunolide 
in planta
, the composition of the costunolide derivatives was different, with LsCOS producing relatively less contunolide-glutathione (
Fig. S3
). The costunolide-glutathione peak produced by LsCOS could only be deduced from the extracted ion chromatogram (peak 
b
*). The generation of glutathione and cysteine conjugates with α-methylene-γ-lactones as well as other unspecific reactions in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
has been widely reported and the underlying mechanisms are well understood (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.3. Two alternative routes to eupatolide biosynthesis in 
<tp:taxon-name>Nicotiana</tp:taxon-name>
benthamiana
</title>
         <p>
After CYP71BL9 was shown to convert germacrene A acid into costunolide we investigated if the co-expression of CYP71BL9 with the germacrene A acid 8β-hydroxylase (CYP71BL1) would lead to new enzyme products. Indeed, the introduction of CYP71BL9 [p19/ DXS + HaGAS1 + HaGAO + HaG8H + CYP71BL9] led to the formation of eupatolide which was found as cystein- and glutathion-adduct in 
HPLC
diagrams (peak 
d
and 
h
in 
Fig. 3A–E
). The negative control [p19/DXS + HaGAS1 + HaGAO + HaG8H] did not show these products. The identity of eupatolide-adducts was confirmed by comparison to synthetic adducts (
Fig. S4
and Fig. S5). As a main intermediate product, costunolide-cysteine was detected (
Fig. 3A
, peak 
a
). This was in contrast to the previously described co-expression of HaG8H with 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
eupatolide synthase HaES (

) which also led to the production of eupatolide, but without forming costunolide adducts. Instead, the inunolide SH adducts inunolide-cystein and inunolide-GSH (
Fig. 3A
, peak 
l
and 
m
) were found and four peak tandems that were tentatively assigned to eudesmanolide rearrangement products of eupatolide-SH adducts (

). Apparently, the combination of HaG8H and HaES, as well as HaG8H and CYP71BL9 downstream of GAA lead to the production of eupatolide, but on different biosynthetic routes. When HaG8H and HaES were expressed together, GAA was converted to 8β-OH-GAA. 8β-OHGAA then partly cyclized to inunolide and partly was converted by HaES to eupatolide. No costunolide or its SH adducts were detected in plants expressing this set of enzymes indicating that the metabolic route did not pass via costunolide (Table 1). When HaES was replaced with CYP71BL9, there was mainly costunolide, only very little inunolide, and 8β-hydroxy-cyclocostunolide derivatives. This indicates, that with CYP71BL9, in the first step, costunolide was produced which subsequently was converted to eupatolide by the 8β-hydroxylation of HaG8H. In yeast and plant expression systems, it has already been reported that acid-induced rearrangement can be observed for GAA, 8βhydroxy-GAA and inunolide, but not for the 6,7-cis lactone costunolide (

; 

; 

; 

). So far, for the biosynthesis of STL in 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
only linear pathways have been elucidated (

; 

; 

), while the different pattern of rearrangement products here, clearly indicated two possible independent pathways leading to the same core STL skeleton.
</p>
         <p>

2.4. Expression of CYP71BL 
9 in
yeast

</p>
         <p>
When CYP71BL9 was expressed together with the substrate vector for GAA [Leu2d:GAS/GAO/CR| Ura:CYP71BL9], a new product (peak a, 10.19 min, 
λ
max
= 
204 nm
) appeared in 
HPLC
analysis in comparison to the negative control [Leu2d:GAS/GAO/CR| Ura:empty] (data not shown). When CYP71BL9 was expressed downstream of 8β-OH-GAA [Leu2d:GAS/GAO/CR/HaG8H|Ura:CYP71BL9], peak 
a
was still detected together with a second peak (peak 
b
, 15.5 min, 
λ
max
= 
207 nm
) (
Fig. 4A
). A small amount of peak 
b
could be collected from the 
HPLC
runs. It showed the same retention time and absorption spectrum as the costunolide standard (
Fig. 4B
). The identity of the purified peak b with costunolide was confirmed by MS-MS spectra (
Fig 4
,D-E) and 1H NMR analysis. Peak 
a
was purified by preparative 
HPLC
. NMR analysis and comparison of NMR data to a structurally similar farnesyl lactone (

) identified the compound as 5-hydroxyfarnesylic acid. The formation of this side product may be caused by a reaction of farnesol with CYP71BL9. The underlying reaction mechanism remains unclear, however.
</p>
         <p>
2.5. Structural comparison of CYP71BL9 and CYP71BL1
</p>
         <p>
Regarding the amino acid sequence, CYP71BL9/HaCOS is more similar to HaG8H than to the so far published costunolide synthases from other 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
. The substrate recognition site 5 (SRS5) is one of the most important regions for substrate specificity, especially position five after the KETLR/ExxR motiv which is closest to the catalytic center (

) (Fig. S6). All costunolide synthases that have so far been described share a Prolin and Valin amino acid on positions 4 and 5 while HaG8H and HaCOS have a Valin and a free position there. The loss of a conserved Prolin rest at Pos 4 together with an amino acid substitution at position 5 after the ExxR motiv is reported to change the substrate speficity and enzyme function in the closely relatey subfamily CYP71AJ (

). As HaCOS differs in this crucial region, there might be a different mechanism of substrate binding in the catalytic center. Generally, docking the substrates of multiple sesquiterpene oxidizing cytochrome p450s to the catalytic center of their respective enzymes as it has recently been performed for monoterpenes (

) could shed light on this aspect of cytochrome p450 function in future studies.
</p>
         <p>
2.6. Biological considerations
</p>
         <p>
The expression pattern in the public transcriptome database revealed that CYP71BL9 is mainly expressed in bracts and leaves. The surface of bracts, though densly covered by linear an nonglandular trichomes, is lacking CGT and on leaves and florets it was shown, that the biosynthesis of STL in CGT is restricted to a very early and short period of organ development (

; 

). Moreover, CYP71BL9 was not reported from ESTs of capitate galdular trichomes (CGT) in the previous study of HaG8H (CYP71BL1) (

). This was confirmed by our own studies on trichome-based transcription of P450 genes in sunflower (

) and corroborates with the fact, that so far no costunolide was found in trichomes of the plant (

; 

). This implies that CYP71BL9 is part of an independent route of STL production in the inner tissues of sunflower, where small amounts of costunolide and dehydrostcostuslactone were found along with two xanthanolides (

). We found a very similar variant of CYP71BL9, “HaCos_var” (Fig. S6), expressed in sunflower seedlings, where it may be involved in the production of the inner STL. The function of these inner STL appears to be linked to plant growth processes in sunflower(

, 1997) and underlines that STL can be more than protective plant compounds with high toxicity (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
In our study we have characterized the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
costunolide synthase HaCOS (CYP71BL9) that converted germacrene A acid to costunolide, the commonly presumed precursor of a wide range of STL. Our results will fuel the elucidation of biosynthetic routes downstream of costunolide in sunflower and related species of the Heliantheae tribe and the understanding of the physiological role of costunolide and DCL in sunflower.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental section
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. Identification of candidate genes, cloning and phylogeny
</title>
         <p>
Candidate gene fragments were retrieved from a public sunflower transcriptomic database (www.heliagene.org) and filtered by similarity to known P450 enzymes involved in 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae STL</tp:taxon-name>
metabolism regarding amino acid identity and gene expression pattern as previously described (

). The whole open reading frame and UTS regions of CYP71BL9 was identified by 3′and 5′RACE (Clontech Laboratories, Inc., Mountain View, CA, 
USA
).
</p>
         <p>
The cds of CYP71BL9 was amplified from bract cDNA using a proofreading polymerase, and cloned into the MCS1 site of the pESC-Ura plasmid using the primers 

GTC 
AAT
GAA TTC 
ATG
GAG CCT TTC ACA ATT TTC TTC

and 

GTC AAT
ACT AGT 
CTA
ATT TGG TTC TGA TAC GGA GAT AGG

. Amino acid sequences for phylogeny were aligned with BioEdit and a phylogeny was constructed with MEGA6 (1000 Bootstraps). CYP71BL9 and genes upstream in the biosynthetic pathway were inserted into the vector pLIFE33 by USER cloning as previously described (

; 

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

4.2. Pathway reconstruction in yeast and 
<tp:taxon-name>Nicotiana benthamiana</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Pathway reconstruction in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
and yeast was performed as described recently (

; 

). Extraction from yeast cultures was performed as previously described (

; 

; 

) and enzyme products were purified from 0.5 mL cultures by preparative HPLC.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.3. Characterization of enzyme products by 
HPLC
NMR spectroscopy and

mass spectrometry
</title>
         <p>
Extracts from yeast cultures were analyzed by HPLC-DAD (Prominence system Shimadzu 
Germany
GmbH, Duisburg) with a Kromasil C18 column (100 18C, 
25 cm
× 
4 mm
x 5 μm particle size; MZ Analysentechnik, Mainz, 
Germany
). After the injection of 80 μl (corresponding to 2 mL culture volume), extracts were separated using the following program: min 40–100 B, 1 min 100 B, 4 min 40 B; A:ddH 
2
O/ 0.01% TFA B: ACN, 1 ml/min). 5-hydroxyfarnesylic acid and costunolide were purified from yeast cultures by 
HPLC
and anylzed by NMR spectroscopy and mass spectrometry. NMR spectrometry was conducted with a 500 MHz Varian Unity Inova (Varian, Inc./Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, 
USA
) spectrometer with a 
3 mm
ID PFG probe in 
3 mm
NMR vials. Spectra were referenced to the solvent signal of chloroform (δH/C 7.27/77 ppm). For a full structural analysis, 1H NMR, 1D TOCSY and several 2D spectra were recorded (gCOSY, gHSQAD, gHMBCAD, ROESY, NOESY, TOCSY). For mass spectrometry the purified compound was re-run on a LC-MS system with Agilent (Waldbronn, 
Germany
) 1290 UHPLC on a HSS T3 column (1.8 μm particle size, 
50 mm
× 
2.1 mm
, Waters, 
Dublin
, 
Ireland
) in combination with a quadrupole mass spectrometer (QTRAP 5500, LC-MS/MS system (AB Sciex Instruments, Darmstadt, 
Germany
) Q3-MS, ESI-pos. Screening of extracts from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana benthamiana
</tp:taxon-name>
with putative enzyme products, and comparison of enzyme products to synthetic adducts was conducted using LC-MS as previously described (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112430.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Amrehn, E.
, 
Aschenbrenner, A.K.
, 
Heller, A.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
2016
. 
Localization of sesquiterpene lactone biosynthesis in cells of capitate glandular trichomes of Helianthus annuus (Asteraceae)
. 
Protoplasma
253
(
2
), 
447–455
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ s00709-015-0823-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Amrehn, E.
, 
Heller, A.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
2014
. 
Capitate glandular trichomes of Helianthus annuus (Asteraceae): ultrastructure and cytological development
. 
Protoplasma
251
, 
161–167
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00709-013-0534-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Arai, T.
, 
Toda, Y.
, 
Kato, K.
, 
Miyamoto, K.
, 
Hasegawa, T.
, 
Yamada, K.
, 
Ueda, J.
, 
Hasegawa, K.
, 
Inoue, T.
, 
Shigemori, H.
, 
2013
. 
Artabolide, a novel polar auxin transport inhibitor isolated from Artemisia absinthium
. 
Tetrahedron
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tet. 2013.06.052
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aschenbrenner, A.K.
, 
Amrehn, E.
, 
Bechtel, L.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
2015
. 
Trichome differentiation on leaf primordia of Helianthus annuus (Asteraceae): morphology, gene expression and metabolite profile
. 
Planta
241
, 
837–846
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00425-014- 2223-y
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bitinaite, J.
, 
Rubino, M.
, 
Varma, K.H.
, 
Schildkraut, I.
, 
Vaisvila, R.
, 
Vaiskunaite, R.
, 
2007
. 
USER friendly DNA engineering and cloning method by uracil excision
. 
Nucleic Acids Res.
35
, 
1992–2002
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkm041
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dueholm, B.
, 
Krieger, C.
, 
Drew, D.
, 
Olry, A.
, 
Kamo, T.
, 
Taboureau, O.
, 
Weitzel, C.
, 
Bourgaud, F.
, 
Hehn, A.
, 
Simonsen, H.T.
, 
2015
. 
Evolution of substrate recognition sites (SRSs) in cytochromes P450 from Apiaceae exemplified by the CYP71AJ subfamily
. 
BMC Evol. Biol.
15
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/s12862-015-0396-z
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eljounaidi, K.
, 
Cankar, K.
, 
Comino, C.
, 
Moglia, A.
, 
Hehn, A.
, 
Bourgaud, F.
, 
Bouwmeester, H.
, 
Menin, B.
, 
Lanteri, S.
, 
Beekwilder, J.
, 
2014
. 
Cytochrome P450s from Cynara cardunculus L. CYP71AV9 and CYP71BL5, catalyze distinct hydroxylations in the sesquiterpene lactone biosynthetic pathway
. 
Plant Sci.
223
, 
59–68
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.plantsci.2014.03.007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fischer, N.H.
, 
Olivier, E.J.
, 
Fischer, H.D.
, 
1979
. 
The biogenesis and chemistry of sesquiterpene lactones
. In: 
Herz, W.
, 
Grisebach, H.
, 
Kirby, G.W.
(Eds.), 
Fortschritte Der Chemie Organischer Naturstoffe/Progress in the Chemistry of Organic Natural Products
. 
Springer, Vienna
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frey, M.
, 
Schmauder, K.
, 
Pateraki, I.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
2018
. 
Biosynthesis of eupatolide—a metabolic route for sesquiterpene lactone formation involving the P450 enzyme CYP71DD6
. 
ACS Chem. Biol.
13
, 
1536–1543
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acschembio. 8b00126
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frey, M.
, 
Klaiber, I.
, 
Conrad, J.
, 
Bersch, A.
, 
Pateraki, I.
, 
Ro, D.-K.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
2019
. 

Characterization of CYP71AX36 from sunflower (
Helianthus annuus
L., asteraceae)

. 
Sci. Rep.
9
, 
14295
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-50520-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frey, M.
, 
2020
. 
Traps and pitfalls—unspecific reactions in metabolic engineering of sesquiterpenoid pathways
. 
Molecules
25
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules25081935
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Göpfert, J.C.
, 
Heil, N.
, 
Conrad, J.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
2005
. 
Cytological development and sesquiterpene lactone secretion in capitate glandular trichomes of sunflower
. 
Plant Biol
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2005-837575
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Göpfert, J.C.
, 
Macnevin, G.
, 
Ro, D.-K.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
2009
. 
Identification, functional characterization and developmental regulation of sesquiterpene synthases from sunflower capitate glandular trichomes
. 
BMC Plant Biol.
9
, 
86
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/1471- 2229-9-86
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Herz, W.
, 
1977
. 
Biogenetic aspects of sesquiterpene lactone chemistry
. 
Isr. J. Chem.
16
, 
32–44
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ijch.197700010
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hubert, J.G.
, 
Furkert, D.P.
, 
Brimble, M.A.
, 
2015
. 
Synthesis of the spirocyclic framework of sesterterpenoid natural products
. 
J. Org. Chem.
80
, 
2715–2723
. 
https://doi.org/10. 1021/jo502897u
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ikezawa, N.
, 
Göpfert, J.C.
, 
Nguyen, D.T.
, 
Kim, S.U.
, 
O'Maille, P.E.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
Ro, D.K.
, 
2011
. 
Lettuce costunolide synthase
(
CYP
71
BL2) and its homolog (CYP 
71
BL1) from sunflower catalyze distinct regio- and stereoselective hydroxylations in sesquiterpene lactone metabolism. J. Biol. Chem. 
https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M110.216804
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Joel, D.M.
, 
Chaudhuri, S.K.
, 
Plakhine, D.
, 
Ziadna, H.
, 
Steffens, J.C.
, 
2011
. 
Dehydrocostus lactone is exuded from sunflower roots and stimulates germination of the root parasite Orobanche cumana
. 
Phytochemistry
72
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2011.01.037
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lange, B.M.
, 
Srividya, N.
, 
2019
. 
Enzymology of monoterpene functionalization in glandular trichomes
. 
J. Exp. Bot.
70
(
4
), 
1095–1108
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/jxb/ ery436
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Q.
, 
Majdi, M.
, 
Cankar, K.
, 
Goedbloed, M.
, 
Charnikhova, T.
, 
Verstappen, F.W.A.
, 
de Vos, R.C.H.
, 
Beekwilder, J.
, 
van der Krol, S.
, 
Bouwmeester, H.J.
, 
2011
. 
Reconstitution of the costunolide biosynthetic pathway in yeast and Nicotiana benthamiana
. 
PloS One
6
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0023255
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Q.
, 
Manzano, D.
, 
Tanić, N.
, 
Pesic, M.
, 
Bankovic, J.
, 
Pateraki, I.
, 
Ricard, L.
, 
Ferrer, A.
, 
de Vos, R.
, 
de Krol, S.
van, 
Bouwmeester, H.
, 
2014
. 
Elucidation and in planta reconstitution of the parthenolide biosynthetic pathway
. 
Metab. Eng.
23
, 
145–153
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/J.YMBEN.2014.03.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nguyen, D.T.
, 
Gopfert, J.C.
, 
Ikezawa, N.
, 
Macnevin, G.
, 
Kathiresan, M.
, 
Conrad, J.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
Ro, D.-K.
, 
2010
. 
Biochemical conservation and evolution of germacrene A oxidase in asteraceae
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
285
, 
16588–16598
. 
https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M110. 111757
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nguyen, T.-D.
, 
Faraldos, J.A.
, 
Vardakou, M.
, 
Salmon, M.
, 
O'Maille, P.E.
, 
Ro, D.-K.
, 
2016
. 
Discovery of germacrene A synthases in Barnadesia spinosa: the first committed step in sesquiterpene lactone biosynthesis in the basal member of the Asteraceae
. 
Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.
479
, 
622–627
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbrc. 2016.09.165
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nour-Eldin, H.H.
, 
Hansen, B.G.
, 
Nørholm, M.H.H.
, 
Jensen, J.K.
, 
Halkier, B.A.
, 
2006
. 
Advancing uracil-excision based cloning towards an ideal technique for cloning PCR fragments
. 
Nucleic Acids Res.
34
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkl635
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Padilla-Gonzalez, G.F.
, 
dos Santos, F.A.
, 
Da Costa, F.B.
, 
2016
. 
Sesquiterpene lactones: more than protective plant compounds with high toxicity
. 
CRC Crit. Rev. Plant Sci.
35
, 
18–37
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/07352689.2016.1145956
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Picman, A.K.
, 
1986
. 
Biological activities of sesquiterpene lactones
. 
Biochem. Systemat. Ecol.
14
, 
255–281
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0305-1978(86)90101-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Prasifka, J.R.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
Conrad, J.
, 
Cook, L.W.
, 
Palmquist, D.E.
, 
Foley, M.E.
, 
2015
. 
Sesquiterpene lactone composition of wild and cultivated sunflowers and biological activity against an insect pest
. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
63
, 
4042–4049
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.jafc.5b00362
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ramirez, A.M.
, 
Saillard, N.
, 
Yang, T.
, 
Franssen, M.C.R.
, 
Bouwmeester, H.J.
, 
Jongsma, M.A.
, 
2013
. 
Biosynthesis of sesquiterpene lactones in pyrethrum (Tanacetum cinerariifolium)
. 
PloS One
8
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0065030
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Raupp, F.M.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
2013
. 
New sesquiterpene lactones from sunflower root exudate as germination stimulants for Orobanche cumana
. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
61
, 
10481–10487
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jf402392e
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ro, D.-K.
, 
Paradise, E.M.
, 
Ouellet, M.
, 
Fisher, K.J.
, 
Newman, K.L.
, 
Ndungu, J.M.
, 
Ho, K.A.
, 
Eachus, R.A.
, 
Ham, T.S.
, 
Kirby, J.
, 
Chang, M.C.Y.
, 
Withers, S.T.
, 
Shiba, Y.
, 
Sarpong, R.
, 
Keasling, J.D.
, 
2006
. 
Production of the antimalarial drug precursor artemisinic acid in engineered yeast
. 
Nature
440
, 
940
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodriguez, E.
, 
Towers, G.H.N.
, 
Mitchell, J.C.
, 
1976
. 
Biological activities of sesquiterpene lactones
. 
Phytochemistry
15
, 
1573–1580
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(00) 97430-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Seifert, A.
, 
Pleiss, J.
, 
2009
. 
Identification of selectivity-determining residues in cytochrome P450 monooxygenases: a systematic analysis of the substrate recognition site 5. Proteins Struct. Funct
. 
Bioinforma.
74
, 
1028–1035
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/prot. 22242
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Silva, D.B.
, 
Aschenbrenner, A.-K.
, 
Lopes, N.P.
, 
Spring, O.
, 
2017
. 
Direct analyses of secondary metabolites by mass spectrometry imaging (MSI) from sunflower (Helianthus annuus L.) trichomes
. 
Molecules
22
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules22050774
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Spring, O.
, 
Benz, T.
, 
Ilg, M.
, 
1989
. 
Sesquiterpene lactones of the capitate glandular trichomes of Helianthus annuus
. 
Phytochemistry
28
, 
745–749
. 
https://doi.org/10. 1016/0031-9422(89)80107-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Spring, O.
, 
Bienert, U.
, 
1987
. 
Capitate glandular hairs from sunflower leaves: development, distribution and sesquiterpene lactone content. J
. 
Plant Physiol.
130
, 
441–448
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0176-1617(87)80209-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Spring, O.
, 
Hager, A.
, 
1982
. 
Inhibition of elongation growth by two sesquiterpene lactones isolated from Helianthus annuus L. - possible molecular mechanism
. 
Planta
156
, 
433–440
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00393314
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Spring, O.
, 
Priester, T.
, 
Stransky, H.
, 
Hager, A.
, 
1985
. 
Sesquiterpene lactones in sunflower seedlings: distribution in the plant and occurrence in genetic varieties as determined by an isocratic HPLC technique. J
. 
Plant Physiol.
120
, 
321–329
. 
https://doi.org/10. 1016/S0176-1617(85)80131-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Toda, Y.
, 
Shigemori, H.
, 
Ueda, J.
, 
Miyamoto, K.
, 
2017
. 
Isolation and identification of polar auxin transport inhibitors from Saussurea costus and Atractylodes japonica
. 
Acta Agrobot.
70
. 
https://doi.org/10.5586/aa.1700
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ueda, J.
, 
Toda, Y.
, 
Kato, K.
, 
Kuroda, Y.
, 
Arai, T.
, 
Hasegawa, T.
, 
Shigemori, H.
, 
Hasegawa, K.
, 
Kitagawa, J.
, 
Miyamoto, K.
, 
Uheda, E.
, 
2013
. 
Identification of dehydrocostus lactone and 4-hydroxy-β-thujone as auxin polar transport inhibitors
. 
Acta Physiol. Plant.
35
, 
2251–2258
. 

https://doi.org/10.1007/s11738-013-1261-6. 
Yokotani-Tomita

, K., 
Kato, J.
, 
Kosemura, S.
, 
Yamamura, S.
, 
Kushima, M.
, 
Kakuta, H.
, 
Hasegawa, K.
, 
1997
. 
Light-induced auxin-inhibiting substance from sunflower seedlings
. 
Phytochemistry
46
, 
503–506
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1016/S0031-9422(97) 00307-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yokotani-Tomita, K.
, 
Kato, J.
, 
Yamada, K.
, 
Kosemura, S.
, 
Yamamura, S.
, 
Bruinsma, J.
, 
Hasegawa, K.
, 
1999
. 8- 
epixanthatin, a light-induced growth inhibitor, mediates the phototropic curvature in sunflower (Helianthus annuus) hypocotyls
. 
Physiol. Plantarum
106
, 
326–330
. 
https://doi.org/10.1034/j.1399-3054.1999.106310.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
