<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112795</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>trans-Tiliroside: A potent α-glucosidase inhibitor from the leaves of Elaeagnus angustifolia L</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
L
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
L
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Elaeagnaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Elaeagnaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Elaeagnaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
(
Farzaei et al., 2015
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Minimum Maximum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. angustifolia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. angustifolia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potentilla chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Allium cepa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Minimum Maximum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. angustifolia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Saccharomyces cerevisiae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
L
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Elaeagnaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
trans
-Tiliroside: A potent 
α
-glucosidase inhibitor from the leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
L
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Hafize Yuca

a, b, 
*

, Hilal 
¨Ozbek a, b
, Lütfiye ¨Omür Demirezer 
c
, Handan G¨okben Kasil 
a
, 
Zühal Güvenalp
a, b
</p>
         <p>
a
Department of Pharmacognosy
, 
Faculty of Pharmacy
, 
Ataturk University
, 25240, 
Erzurum
, 
Turkey
</p>
         <p>
b

Medicinal and Aromatic Plant and 
Drug Research Center
, 
Ataturk University
, 25240, 
Erzurum
, 
Turkey
</p>
         <p>
c
Department of Pharmacognosy
, 
Faculty of Pharmacy
, 
Hacettepe University
, 06100, 
Ankara
, 
Turkey
</p>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
ABSTRACT
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
L
</tp:taxon-name>
. (
<tp:taxon-name>Elaeagnaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) is an important medicinal plant associated with numerous pharmacological activities. Its leaves are used as a therapeutic agent in traditional medicinal systems to treat diabetes. However, the active compounds responsible for the beneficial effects of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
remain unclear. In this study, we determined the bioactive profile of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
leaves using open column chromatography and semi-preparative HPLC. Further, we sought to determine its 
α
-glucosidase and 
α
-amylase inhibitory activities, and its DPPH and ABTS radical-scavenging activities. Four undescribed flavonol glycosides, igdoside A–D, and four known glucosides were isolated from the ethyl acetate and 
n
-butanol extracts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
leaves. Thereafter, the compound structures were identified using spectroscopic methods, including NMR and mass spectrometry. Of the compounds extracted, kaempferol-3- 
O
-(6 
′′
- 
trans -p
-coumaroyl)- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside (
trans
-tiliroside), exhibited the highest 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory activity with an IC 
50
value of 2128 ± 63 μM compared to the positive control, acarbose (IC 
50
= 6561 ± 207 μM). 
trans
-Tiliroside was also found to exhibit potent scavenging activity against the ABTS radical, with an IC 
50
value of 5 ± 0 μM, compared to the positive controls, trolox (31 ± 1 μM) and 
α
-tocopherol (50 ± 1 μM). In addition, isorhamnetin-3- 
O -β
-D-galactopyranoside (IC 
50
= 6 ± 0 μM) and astragalin (IC 
50
= 6 ± 0 μM) showed similar ABTS radical-scavenging activity as 
transtiliroside
. Based on HPLC, the content of 
trans
-tiliroside was 9.69% in the ethyl acetate extract, 1.04% in decoction, 0.34% in 70% methanol extract, and 0.23% in infusion. None of the extracts and compounds showed 
α
-amylase inhibition or DPPH-scavenging activity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Elaeagnaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
α
-Glucosidase inhibition
</p>
         <p>Radical scavenging</p>
         <p>Natural products</p>
         <p>Flavonoids</p>
         <p>
trans
-Tiliroside
</p>
         <p>Igdoside A-D</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The 
<tp:taxon-name>Elaeagnaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family is represented by two floral species in 
Turkey
. One of them, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
, is a thorny shrub that can reach a height of 

7 m
.

<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
is deciduous; grows naturally in Europe, 
Turkey
, Caucasus, 
Syria
, 
Iran
, 
Afghanistan
, and 
Pakistan
; and is widely cultivated throughout 
Turkey
(

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
has been identified as having numerous ethnobotanical uses by the local people of 
Turkey
and is a potential herbal medicine for the treatment of diabetes mellitus (DM). The decoction of its leaves is consumed as a blood glucose-lowering agent (

) while the infusions from its flowers and leaves are consumed as diuretics and antipyretics (

). Previous studies have shown that 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
exerts antiarthritic, anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial, antimutagenic, antinociceptive, antioxidant, antitumor, cardioprotective, gastroprotective, hypolipidemic, insecticidal, tyrosinase inhibitory, and wound-healing effects (

; 

). The 
in vitro α
-glucosidase and 
α
-amylase inhibitory effects of the 70% methanol extract prepared from the leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
have been evaluated using different methods. However, to the best of our knowledge, further studies have not been conducted to determine the effective compounds in the extract (

). By investigating the hypoglycemic effect of polysaccharides obtained from the fruit of this plant, a previous study found that these polysaccharides could potently prevent increased levels of glucose in streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice compared to control mice (

). Angustifolinoid B, which is obtained from the flowers, was also found to exhibit strong 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory activity (

). Specialized metabolites, such as 
β
-carboline alkaloids, esters, flavone glycosides, ketones, phenolic acids, phenols, phenyl ethers, polysaccharides, steroids, and terpenes, have also been identified previously in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
(
Farzaei et al., 2015
)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
DM is an endocrine disease characterized by hyperglycemia. This condition is also associated with deficient or excess insulin secretion induced by irregularities in carbohydrate, fat, and protein metabolism. Approximately 85–95% of people with DM have 
type
II DM, which is a chronic metabolic disease caused by the inability of the body to secrete sufficient insulin or the development of insulin resistance (

; 

). Defects in 
α
-amylase, 
α
-glucosidase, aldose reductase, angiotensin-converting enzyme, and dipeptidyl peptidase-4 play a role in the pathogenesis of 
type
II DM (

). Drugs used in a clinical setting to control DM include insulin, sulfonylureas, biguanides, thiazolidinediones, carbamoylmethyl benzoic acid, insulin-like growth factor, aldose reductase-, 
α
-glucosidase-, and 
α
-amylase inhibitors (

; 

; 

). In addition to using these drugs for the treatment of 
type
II DM, other therapeutic approaches, such as inhibiting the degradation of oligosaccharides and disaccharides, can be used to reduce hyperglycemia. 

α
-

Glucosidase and 

α
-

amylase can hydrolyze carbohydrates; thus, inhibitors of these enzymes are considered useful drug candidates for 
type
II DM therapy (

; 

; 

). Inhibitors of 

α
-

glucosidase and 

α
-

amylase delay carbohydrate digestion, thereby prolonging carbohydrate digestion time and decreasing glucose absorption rate, which lead to an decrease in postprandial plasma glucose (

). Long-term use of synthetic enzyme inhibitors, such as acarbose, may cause various side effects, such as flatulence and abdominal problems (

). Natural 

α
-

glucosidase inhibitors have thus been presented as a better alternative to control postprandial hyperglycemia as they exhibit minor or no side effects (

).
</p>
         <p>
In this study, we investigated the antioxidant and 
α
-glucosidase and 
α
-amylase inhibitory activities of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
leaves, used to treat DM as folk medicine, and determined the compound(s) responsible for the effects. Based on our findings, among the leaf extracts, the ethyl acetate and 
n
-butanol extracts were found to exhibit the highest 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory effect. According to the isolation studies performed with these extracts, four undescribed flavonol glycosides, igdoside A-D (
2–5
), and four known glucosides (
1, 6–8
) were identified. The 
α
-glucosidase and 
α
-amylase inhibitory activities of these compounds were subsequently evaluated. The extracts and isolated compounds were also assayed for their ABTS and DPPH radical-scavenging effects. Lastly, the active compound, 
trans
-tiliroside, in the extracts was quantified using HPLC.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>nd: Not determined.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Positive control for 
α
-glucosidase and 
α
-amylase inhibitory activities.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Positive controls for DPPH and ABTS radical scavenging activities.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>

2.1. Enzyme inhibitory activity of the leaf extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. angustifolia</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
The 70% methanolic extract and its subfractions (
n
-hexane, dichloromethane, ethyl acetate, 
n
-butanol, and water extracts) were evaluated to determine their 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory activity, using acarbose as the positive control. Accordingly, the 70% methanol (IC 
50
= 124.80 ± 32.20 μg/mL), ethyl acetate (IC 
50
= 82.05 ± 2.76 μg/ mL), and 
n
-butanol (IC 
50
= 216.49 ± 23.83 μg/mL) extracts were found to exhibit a higher activity than acarbose (IC 
50
= 4212.62 ± 130.00 μg/ mL) (
Table 1
, 
Figures S1
and S 
2
). Thus, the ethyl acetate and 
n
-butanol extracts were further fractionated and analyzed to determine the activity of the isolated compound(s).
</p>
         <p>
2.2. Isolation and structure determination of the undescribed compounds

in the leaf extracts of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. angustifolia</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Four undescribed flavonol glycosides, igdoside A-D (
2–5
), and four known glucosides (
1, 6–8
) (
Fig. 1
) were isolated from the ethyl acetate and 
n
-butanol extracts.
</p>
         <p>
Igdoside A (
2
) appeared as a yellow amorphous powder. Its molecular formula, C 
37
H 
46
O 
18
, was determined based on the negative HRESIMS ion (
Figure S3
) observed at 
m/z
777.2233 [M – H] (calcd. 778.2684). The UV spectrum (DMSO) of 
2
displayed two absorption maxima (log 
ε
) at 283 (4.25) and 362 (4.18) nm, indicating its flavonol skeleton. The 
1
H and 
13
C-NMR spectra (
Table 2
, 
Figures S4
and 
S
5
) showed the typical pattern of a flavonol acyl glycoside. Owing to the presence of two meta-coupled protons for ring A (δ 6.49 and 6.76, d, 
J
= 2.0 Hz), an ABX system signal for ring B (δ 6.91 d, 
J
= 8.4 Hz, 7.61 dd, 
J
= 8.3, 2.2 Hz, and 8.04 d, 
J
= 2.2 Hz), and one singlet signal at δ 3.97 for a methoxy group, the compound 
2
aglycon was identified as isorhamnetin (

; 

). Two anomeric protons from the sugar moieties appeared at δ 5.40 (
J
= 7.7 Hz) and 5.61 (
J
= 1.4 Hz); these protons were found to respectively correlate with signals at δ 102.7 and 
98.3 in
the HMQC spectrum. COSY and HMQC (
Figures S6
and 
S
7) experiments led to the identification of one 
β
-galactopyranosyl and one 
α
-rhamnopyranosyl sugar unit. Furthermore, the 
1
H-NMR spectrum (
Table 2
, 
Figure S4
) revealed the presence of a quaternary methyl (δ 1.30, s), an olefinic methyl (δ 1.90, d, 
J
= 3.4 Hz), a terminal olefin (δ 5.08, dd, 
J
= 10.8, 1.5 Hz, δ 5.25, dd, 
J
= 17.4, 1.5 Hz, δ 5.95, ddd, 
J
= 17.4, 10.8, 1.5 Hz), an olefinic proton (δ 6.96, m), and two methylene protons (δ 1.67 and 2.30, m). These protons correlated with signals at δ 11.1 and 26.4 for methyl carbons; δ 23.2, 40.3, and 111.0 for methylene carbons; and δ 143.2 and 144.5 for methyn carbons. In addition, two quaternary carbons (δ 127.2 and 72.2) and one ester carbon (δ 168.1) are seen in the 
13
C-NMR spectrum (
Table 2
, 
Figure S5
), and δ 6.96 (m) and 1.90 (d, 
J
= 3.4) were found to correlate with δ 168.1. These findings suggest that this compound is an ester of the monoterpenoid, 
α,β
-unsaturated carboxylic acid. The correlations between H-1 (δ 5.40) of galactose and C-3 of aglycone (δ 134.2), H-1 of rhamnose (δ 5.61) and C-7 of aglycone (δ 161.9), and H-4 of rhamnose (δ 5.18) and C-1 of acyl (δ 168.0) were detected in the HMBC spectrum (
Fig. 2
and 
S
8) of 
2
. As a result of these interactions, 
β
-D-Gal-(1 → 3)-Agl, 
α
-L-Rham-(1 → 7)-Agl, and Acyl-(1 → 4)- 
α
-L-Rham linkages were detected. Compound 
2
was thus identified as isorhamnetin-3- 
O -β
-D-galactopyranosyl-7- 
O
-[2,6-dimethyl-6-hydroxy-2, 7-octadienoyl-(1 → 4)]- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranoside (igdoside A).
</p>
         <p>
Igdoside B (
3
) appeared as a yellow amorphous powder. Its molecular formula, C 
44
H 
56
O 
22
, was determined based on the positive HRESIMS ion (Figure 
S
9) observed at 
m/z
935.31984 [M – H] 
+
(calcd. 936.3263). The UV spectrum (DMSO) of 
3
showed two absorption maxima (log 
ε
) at 278 (4.01) and 359 (4.30) nm, indicating its flavonol skeleton. By comparing the MS and NMR data of 
3
(
Table 2
, Figures 
S
9- 
S
14) to those of 
2
, an additional rhamnose unit and a different linkage of acyl monoterpene to rhamnose in 
3
were identified. In addition, H-3 of rhamnose was correlated with the ester carbon (δ 167.1) and H-1 of the second rhamnose was linked to C-6 (65.7) of galactose (
Fig. 2
). Compound 
3
was thus identified as isorhamnetin-3- 
O-α
-L-rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 6)- 
β
-D-galactopyranosyl-7- 
O
-[2,6-dimethyl-6-hydroxy-2,7-octadienoyl-(1 → 3)]- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranoside (igdoside B).
</p>
         <p>
Igdoside C (
4
) was obtained as a yellow amorphous powder. Based on the positive HRESIMS ion (Figure 
S
15) observed at 
m/z
1129.37324 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. 1128.369), its molecular formula was determined to be C 
54
H 
64
O 
26
. The UV spectrum (DMSO) of 
4
showed two absorption maxima (log 
ε
) at 298 (3.81) and 338 (4.09) nm, indicating its flavonol skeleton. By comparing the MS and NMR data of 
4
(
Table 2
, Figures 
S
15- 
S
20) to those of 
3
, glucose and feruloyl groups were identified. Three anomeric protons from the sugar moieties appeared at δ 4.60 (d, 
J
= 7.6 Hz), 5.72 (d, 
J
= 7.5 Hz), and 5.55 (bs); these protons were found to respectively correlate with signals at δ 104.5, 99.0, and 
98.5 in
the HMQC spectrum (Figure 
S
19). COSY and HMQC (Figures 
S
18 and 
S
19) experiments using compound 
4
led to the identification of one 
β
-glucopyranosyl, one 
β
-galactopyranosyl, and one 
α
-rhamnopyranosyl sugar unit. In addition to other proton signals of the compound, the 
1
H-NMR spectrum (Figure 
S
16) indicated a methoxy group at δ 3.73 (s); aromatic protons as an ABX system at δ 6.70 (d, 
J
= 8.1 Hz), 6.85 (dd, 
J
= 8.2 and 1.5 Hz), and 7.08 (d, 
J
= 1.8 Hz); and two protons at δ 6.14 and 7.31 (d, 
J
= 15.8 Hz) of a 
trans
-double bond, ultimately confirming the feruloyl moiety. In the HMBC spectrum (
Fig. 2
and 
S
20) of 
4
, which had the same correlations found in compound 
3
, the following correlations were observed: H-1 
glu
(δ 4.60) with C-3 (δ 133.7), H-2 
glu
(δ 3.80) with C-1 
gal
(δ 99.0), and H-6 
gal
(δ 4.18 and 4.23) with C-9 
fer
(166.8). Based on these findings, compound 
4
was identified as isorhamnetin-3- 
O
-(6 
′′′
- 
O -trans
- feruloyl)- 
β
-D-galactopyranosyl-(1 → 2) 
-β
-D-glucopyranosyl-7- 
O
-[2,6- dimethyl-6-hydroxy-2,7-octadienoyl-(1 → 3)]- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranoside (igdoside C).
</p>
         <p>
Igdoside D (
5
) was obtained as a yellow amorphous powder. Based on the positive HRESIMS ion (Figure 
S
21) observed at 
m/z
922.29953 [M-(Glucose+ Galactose+ Methoxy)] 
+
(calcd. 1276.427), its molecular formula was identified as C 
56
H 
76
O 
33
. The UV spectrum (DMSO) of 
5
showed two absorption maxima (log 
ε
) at 278 (4.02) and 360 (4.21) nm, indicating its flavonol skeleton. Compound 
5
was identified to be composed of isorhamnetin aglycone, five sugar units, and an acyl group, as previously described. In the 
1
H-NMR spectrum (
Table 2
, Figure 
S
22), five anomeric protons [δ 5.66 (d, 
J
= 7.6 Hz), 5.61 (d, 
J
= 8.0 Hz), 5.69 (bs), 4.59 (d, 
J
= 7.4 Hz), 4.57 (d, 
J
= 5.7 Hz)] were observed. Based on the 1D and 2D-NMR data (Figures 
S
22- 
S
26), the sugar units were determined to be two 
β
-galactopyranose, two 
β
-glucopyranose, and one 
α
-rhamnopyranose unit. In the HMBC spectrum (
Fig. 2
and 
S
26), the correlations from H-1 of rhamnose (δ 5.69) to C-7 of aglycone (δ 161.7), H-1 of galactose-2 (δ 5.61) to C-3 of rhamnose (δ 73.7), H-2 of rhamnose (δ 4.06) to C-1 of acyl (δ 167.5), H-1 of glucose-1 (δ 4.59) to C-3 of aglycone (δ 133.7), H-2 of glucose-1 (δ 3.85) to C-1 of glucose-2 (δ 104.6), and H-2 of glucose-2 (δ 3.76) to C-1 of galactose-1 (δ 98.8) suggested the linkages 
β
-D-Glu 
1
-(1 → 3)-Agl, 
β
-D-Glu 
2
-(1 → 2)- 
β
-D-Glu 
1
, 
β
-D-Gal 
1
-(1 → 2)- 
β
-D-Glu 
2
, 
α
-L-Rham-(1 → 7)-Agl, Acyl-(1 → 2)- 
α
-L-Rham, and 
β
-D-Gal 
2
-(1 → 3)- 
α
-L-Rham, respectively. Therefore, compound 
5
was identified as isorhamnetin-3- 
O -β
-D-galactopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl-7- 
O
-[2,6- dimethyl-6-hydroxy-2,7-octadienoyl-(1 → 2)]-[
β
-D-galactopyranosyl-(1 → 3)]- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranoside (igdoside D).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>(</p>
         <p>continued</p>
         <p>on</p>
         <p>next</p>
         <p>page</p>
         <p>)</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>sig. = signal.</p>
         <p>
a
Gal = 
β
-D-galactopyranose.
</p>
         <p>
b
Rham = 
α
-D-rhamnopyranose.
</p>
         <p>
c
Glu = 
β
-D-glucopyranose.
</p>
         <p>
d
Acyl = acyl monoterpene.
</p>
         <p>
e
Fer = ferulic acid.
</p>
         <p>
In addition, four known flavonol glycosides (
Fig. 1
), namely 
transtiliroside
(
1
) (

), isorhamnetin-3- 
O -β
-D-galactopyranoside (
6
) (

), astragalin (
7
) (

), and isorhamnetin-3- 
O -β
-D-galactopyranosyl-7- 
O -α
-L-rhamnopyranoside (
8
) (

, 

; 

) were identified by comparing their NMR and/or LC-MS data to previously reported values. Notably, this is the first instance of isolation of compound 
8
from this species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Enzyme inhibitory activities of the isolated compounds
</title>
         <p>
The isolated compounds were assessed to determine their 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory activities; acarbose was used as the positive control (IC 
50
= 6561 ± 207 μM). Compound 
1
(
trans
-tiliroside) was the only compound to exhibit 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory activity (IC 
50
= 2128 ± 63 μM) (
Table 3
, 
Fig. 3
and 
S
1
). All extracts and compounds were also evaluated to determine their 
α
-amylase inhibitory activity compared to that of acarbose (IC 
50
= 1930 ± 46 μM), but none of them were effective enzyme inhibitors (
Tables 1
and 
3
, 
Fig. 4
, 
S
27 and 
S
28). As stated in a previous report, compounds glycosylated at the C-3 and/or C-7 position (
Fig. 1
) do not exhibit 
α
-amylase inhibitory activity (

).
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
1
(
trans
-tiliroside) showed high 
α
-glucosidase inhibition, whereas compound 
7
(astragalin) had no effect (
Table 3
, 
Fig. 3
). Although both compounds have a kaempferol unit, the effect exhibited by compound 
1
could be attributed to the linkage of 
trans
-coumaroyl with the C-6 of glucose (

). Such findings are supported by those of 

. The anti-glycation effect of 
trans
--tiliroside, the major compound of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
flowers, was previously evaluated. Aminoguanidine (the comparative standard) displayed an anti-glycation effect of 55.3%, while 37.5 μg/mL of 
trans
-tiliroside displayed an effect of 78.9% (

). 
trans
-Tiliroside has also been isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potentilla chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Allium cepa
</tp:taxon-name>
and its hypoglycemic effect has been determined. Accordingly, a significant anti-hyperglycemic effect was identified based on the reduction in blood glucose in diabetic rats (

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>nd: Not determined.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Positive control for 
α
-glucosidase and 
α
-amylase inhibitory activities.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Positive controls for DPPH and ABTS radical scavenging activities.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.4. Antioxidant capacity of the extracts and isolated compounds
</title>
         <p>
All extracts and compounds were evaluated for their antioxidant capacity using ABTS and DPPH radical-scavenging assays. Trolox and 
α
-tocopherol were used as positive controls in both assays. The extracts and compounds were found to be less effective than trolox (IC 
50
= 67 ± 2 μM) and 
α
-tocopherol (IC 
50
= 95 ± 3 μM) in the DPPH radical-scavenging assay (
Tables 1
and 
3
, 
Fig. 5
, 
S
29 and 
S
30). However, when the extracts were compared to trolox (IC 
50
= 7.65 ± 0.16 μg/mL) and 
α
-tocopherol (IC 
50
= 21.34 ± 0.48 μg/mL) in the ABTS radical-scavenging assay, the ethyl acetate extract (IC 
50
= 13.79 ± 0.14 μg/ mL) had a higher effect than 
α
-tocopherol, whereas the 
n
-butanol extract (IC 
50
= 23.98 ± 0.34 μg/mL) displayed an effect similar to that of the standard compounds (
Table 1
, Figures 
S
31 and 
S
32). When the isolated compounds were compared to trolox (IC 
50
= 31 ± 1 μM) and 
α
-tocopherol (IC 
50
= 50 ± 1 μM), all were found to exhibit higher ABTS radical-scavenging effects than the standards (
Table 3
, 
Fig. 6
and 
S
31).
</p>
         <p>
Consistent with the results of the 
α
-glucosidase enzyme-inhibition assay, compound 
1
(
trans
-tiliroside) was found to be most effective in scavenging ABTS radicals (
Table 3
, 
Fig. 6
), likely owing to the presence of kaempferol and 
trans
-coumaric acid in its structure (
Fig. 1
). Methoxylation of the B ring was found to decrease this effect, whereas the presence of phenolic acid in the structure increased the effect (

). 
trans
-Tiliroside (
1
) was previously shown to possess exhibit ABTS radical-scavenging activity, but was found to be ineffective in scavenging DPPH radicals, as observed in our study (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.5. Quantification of the active compound trans-tiliroside by HPLC
</title>
         <p>
The concentration of 
trans-tiliroside
in the 70% methanol extract, ethyl acetate extract (active subfraction), decoction, and infusion was determined using HPLC (g/ 
100 g
dry extract for extracts and g/ 
100 g
dry leaves for decoction and infusion). The retention time of 
trans
-tiliroside was 38.405 min. Its concentration in the 70% methanol extract, ethyl acetate extract, decoction, and infusion was 0.34%, 9.69%, 1.04%, and 0.23%, respectively. The HPLC chromatograms of pure 
trans
-tiliroside and the 70% methanol and ethyl acetate extracts, decoction, and infusion of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
are presented in Figure 
S
33. The 70% methanol extract is a suitable solvent for extracting all metabolites, whereas ethyl acetate is a semi-polar solvent that can extract both polar and non-polar components. Owing to the fractionation process, the quantity of compounds extracted by ethyl acetate was higher than that obtained using 70% methanol. Therefore, the concentration of 
trans
-tiliroside was higher in the ethyl acetate extract than in the 70% methanol extract. Further, the concentration of 
trans
-tiliroside was higher in the decoction than in the infusion due to the reflux process. The traditional antidiabetic activity of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
leaves can be ascribed to the presence of 
trans
-tiliroside in decoctions and infusions.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study wherein a potent 
α
-glucosidase inhibitor was isolated from the leaves of 

<tp:taxon-name>E. angustifolia</tp:taxon-name>
.

Notably, the leaf extracts of ethyl acetate and 
n
-butanol exhibited the highest 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory effects. Upon purification of these extracts, four undescribed flavonol glycosides, igdoside A-D (
2-5
), and four known glucosides, namely 
trans
-tiliroside (
1
), isorhamnetin-3- 
O - β
-D-galactopyranoside (
6
), astragalin (
7
), and isorhamnetin-3- 
O -β
-Dgalactopyranosyl-7- 
O -α
-L-rhamnopyranoside (
8
), were identified. The undescribed compounds were isorhamnetin-3- 
O -β
-D-galactopyranosyl-7- 
O
-[2,6-dimethyl-6-hydroxy-2,7-octadienoyl-(1 → 4)]- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranoside (igdoside A, 
2
), isorhamnetin-3- 
O-α
-L-rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 6)- 
β
-D-galactopyranosyl-7- 
O
-[2,6-dimethyl-6-hydroxy-2,7-octadienoyl-(1 → 3)]- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranoside (igdoside B, 
3
), isorhamnetin-3- 
O
-(6 
′′′
- 
O -trans
-feruloyl)- 
β
-D-galactopyranosyl-(1 → 2) 
-β
-D-glucopyranosyl-7- 
O
-[2,6-dimethyl-6-hydroxy-2,7-octadienoyl-(1 → 3)]- 
α
-Lrhamnopyranoside (igdoside C, 
4
), and isorhamnetin-3- 
O -β
-D-galactopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl-7- 
O
-[2,6-dimethyl-6-hydroxy-2,7-octadienoyl-(1 → 2)]-[
β
-D-galactopyranosyl-(1 → 3)]- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranoside (igdoside D, 
5
). After the isolated compounds were assessed to determine their 
α
-glucosidase and 
α
-amylase inhibitory activities, their antioxidant activities against ABTS and DPPH radicals were also assessed. Based on the findings, 
transtiliroside
is responsible for the 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory and antioxidant effects of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
as well as its strong 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory and ABTS radical-scavenging activities. In addition, isorhamnetin-3- 
O -β
-Dgalactopyranoside and astragalin showed similar ABTS radical-scavenging activity as 
trans
-tiliroside. Because infusions and decoctions prepared from the leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
have been used traditionally, 
trans
-tiliroside levels in both extracts and the active extracts were determined. Based on HPLC, the highest concentration of 
trans
-tiliroside (9.69%) was present in the ethyl acetate extract followed by the decoction (1.04%), 70% methanol extract (0.34%), and infusion (0.23%). Collectively, these findings suggest the potential of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
trans
-tiliroside (
1
) as novel therapeutic candidates and herbal medicines for the treatment of 
type
II DM.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedure
</title>
         <p>
1D (
1
H-NMR, 
13
C-NMR, and DEPT) and 2D (COSY, HMQC, and HMBC) NMR spectra were derived using Varian Mercury Plus (400 MHz for 
1
H-NMR and 100 MHz for 
13
C-NMR) spectrometers, with TMS as an internal standard. These instruments were accessed in the Faculty of Science at Ataturk University. HRESIMS data were recorded using an Agilent 6530 Accurate-Mass apparatus and AB Sciex TripleTOF 4600 (Agilent Technologies Inc., 
California
, 
USA
) at the Ataturk University East 
Anatolia
High Technology Application and Research Center (DAYTAM). The UV spectra were obtained using a Thermo Scientific Multiscan Go UV–Vis spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, 
California
, 
USA
). The specific optical rotations of compounds 
2–5
were measured using a Bellingham &amp; Stanley ADP 220 
589 nm
polarimeter (Bellingham &amp; Stanley Ltd., Tunbridge Wells, 
United Kingdom
) equipped with an LED light at the Faculty of Science, Ataturk University. Open column chromatography (CC) was carried out using silica gel 60 (
0.063–0.2 mm
) (Merck, 
Germany
), Sephadex LH-20, polyamide 6 (Fluka, 
Switzerland
), and RP-18 reverse-phase silica gel (LiChroprep RP-18, 25–40 μm (Merck, 
Germany
) columns. Semi-preparative HPLC was performed using an Agilent 1260 liquid chromatograph (Agilent Technologies Inc.) equipped with Supelco-Ascentis RP Amide (250 × 
10 mm
, 5 μm) and ACE 5 C18 (250 × 
7.75 mm
) columns. The purities and retention times (Rt) of the isolated compounds were determined using HPLC at 
350 nm
[acetonitrile (ACN):0.2% formic acid (FA) (0:100 → 40:60, v/v), flow rate of 0.3 mL/min, Supelco Ascentis Express RP-Amide (100 × 
2.1 mm
, 2.7 μm)]. Solvents were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (
USA
). TLC was performed using precoated silica gel 60 F 
254
plates (Merck), and the spots were visualized by spraying with 1% vanillin solution in concentrated sulfuric acid, followed by heating at 110 
◦
C. Dinitrosalicylic acid, 
α
-glucosidase from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Saccharomyces cerevisiae
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Type
1, lyophilized powder), 
α
-amylase (from porcine pancreas), acarbose, 
p
-nitrophenol- 
α
-D-glucopyranoside, ABTS, DPPH, trolox, and 
α
-tocopherol from Sigma-Aldrich (
USA
) were used for bioactivity assays.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>
In the early summer of 
June 2016
, the leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elaeagnus angustifolia
L
</tp:taxon-name>
. (
<tp:taxon-name>Elaeagnaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) were collected in Ormanagzı Village, Olur, 
Erzurum
City, 
Turkey
(

40 
◦
46 
′
07.00 
′′
N

, 

42 
◦
05 
′
09.96 
′′
E

). The plant material was authenticated by the Forest Engineer, Mehmet ONAL ¨, MSc. A voucher specimen (No. AUEF 1349) was deposited at the Biodiversity Application and Research Center, Ataturk University, 
Erzurum
, 
Turkey
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
leaves (
800 g
) were dried in the open air in a shaded location, powdered, and allowed to macerate overnight in 2 L of 70% methanol. The medicinal plants were generally used following preparation with water and three rounds of extraction for 3 h at 40 
◦
C using a mantle heater and reflux cooler. The filtered extracts were concentrated to dryness in a rotary evaporator at 40 
◦
C and 120 rpm. The 70% methanol extract (
181.5 g
) in water was fractionated using 
n
-hexane (2 × 500 mL), dichloromethane (4 × 500 mL), ethyl acetate (3 × 500 mL), and 
n
-butanol (6 × 500 mL). Thereafter, the extracts and remaining aqueous phases were concentrated. After concentrating to dryness, 0.2, 87.4, 12.0, 34.1, and 
40.9 g
of extracts were obtained from the 
n
-hexane, dichloromethane, ethyl acetate, 
n
-butanol, and water fractions, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
The ethyl acetate extract (
3 g
of total extract) was fractionated using silica gel CC (70–230 mesh, 
337 g
) with toluene:CHCl 
3
:MeOH (5:75:20, v/v/v) to yield two fractions, Fr. A and Fr. B. Fr. A (
0.48 g
) was further fractionated using semi-preparative HPLC (RP-Amide column, 250 × 
10 mm
, 5 μm) using a suitable method [ACN:0.2% FA (20:80 → 48:52, v/v), flow rate = 5 mL/min] to obtain subfractions Frs. A.1–5. Fr. A.5 (
138.23 mg
) was purified using a Sephadex LH-20 CC (
50 g
, MeOH), followed by RP-18 CC (
40 g
) with a H 
2
O:MeOH (100:0 → 0:100, v/v) gradient system to yield compound 
1
(
12.8 mg
). Based on HPLC, the purity of compound 
1
was determined to be 96.51% and its Rt was 38.405 min. Fr. B (
0.26 g
) was further fractionated using semi-preparative HPLC [ACN:0.2% FA (30:70 → 38:62 v/v), flow rate = 5 mL/min] to obtain four subfractions, Frs. B.1–4. Fr. B.4 (
39.85 mg
) was purified using Sephadex LH-20 CC (
50 g
, MeOH) followed by RP-18 CC (
40 g
) with a H 
2
O:MeOH (100:0 → 0:100, v/v) gradient system to yield compound 
2
(
11 mg
). The purity of compound 
2
was determined to be 97.94% using HPLC, with a Rt of 31.297 min.
</p>
         <p>
The ethyl acetate extract (
9 g
of total extract) was fractionated using polyamide CC (
40 g
) with H 
2
O:MeOH (100:0 → 30:70, v/v) to yield three fractions, Frs. A–C. Fr. B (
3.34 g
) was further fractionated via silica gel CC (
40 g
) with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
:MeOH (100:0 → 20:80, v/v) to obtain three subfractions, Frs. B.1–3. Fr. B.1 (
583.60 mg
) was further fractionated using silica gel CC (
17 g
) with a 
CH
2
Cl 
2
:MeOH:H 
2
O (90:10:1, v/v/v) solvent system to yield two subfractions, Fr. B.1.1 (
96.30 mg
) and Fr. B.1.2 (
319.30 mg
). Fr. B.1.2 (
319.30 mg
) was purified using semi-preparative HPLC [ACN:0.2% FA (10:90 → 46:54 v/v), flow rate = 5 mL/min] to obtain compound 
6
(
5.70 mg
) and compound 
7
(
12.80 mg
). Using HPLC (
350 nm
), the purities of compounds 
6
and 
7
were determined to be 96.41% (Rt = 37.779 min) and 95.28% (Rt = 36.673 min), respectively. Fr. B.3 (
833.10 mg
) was fractionated using silica gel CC (
17 g
) and 
CH
2
Cl 
2
:MeOH:H 
2
O (90:10:1, v/v/v) as a solvent system to yield four subfractions, Frs. B.3.1 (28.00 mg), Fr. B.3.2 (295.00 mg), Fr. B.3.3 (
143.10 mg
), and Fr. B.3.4 (
104.50 mg
). Fr. B.3.2 (295.00 mg) was purified using semi-preparative HPLC [ACN:0.2% FA (10:90 → 46:54 v/v), flow rate = 5 mL/min] to yield compound 
3
(
49.90 mg
) and compound 
4
(
40.10 mg
). Fr. B.3.4 (
104.50 mg
) was also purified using semi-preparative HPLC [ACN:0.2% FA (10:90 → 46:54 v/ v), flow rate = 5 mL/min] to yield compound 
5
(
19.50 mg
). Using HPLC (
350 nm
), the purities of compounds 
3–5
were determined to be 96.44% (Rt = 45.656 min), 97.30% (Rt = 46.991 min), and 96.63% (Rt = 39.445 min), respectively.
</p>
         <p>
The 
n
-butanol extract (20.00 g) was fractionated using silica gel CC (70–230 mesh, 
100 g
) and 
CH
2
Cl 
2
:MeOH (100:0 → 0:100 v/v) to yield Frs. A and B. Fr. A (
4.20 g
) was further fractionated using RP-18 CC (
40 g
) and a H 
2
O:MeOH (100:0 → 0:100, v/v) gradient system to yield two subfractions, Frs. A.1 and A.2. Fr. A.1 (
1.30 g
) was purified using Sephadex LH-20 CC (
50 g
, MeOH) to yield three subfractions, Fr. A.1.1 (
711.80 mg
), Fr. A.1.2 (
58.50 mg
), and Fr. A.1.3 (
18.60 mg
). Fr. A.1.2 (
58.50 mg
) was further purified using semi-preparative HPLC [C18 column, 250 × 
7.75 mm
, 5 μm, MeOH:0.2% FA (30:70 → 80:20, v/v), flow rate = 5 mL/min] to obtain compound 
8
(
8.8 mg
). Using HPLC, the purity of compound 
8
was determined to be 96.93% and was found to have a Rt of 30.956 min.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Igdoside A (2)
</title>
         <p>
Yellow amorphous powder; [α] 
D
24
84.5 (c 1.03, MeOH); UV (DMSO) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 283 (4.25), 362 (4.18) nm; for 
1
H-NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
, 400 MHz) and 
13
C-NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
, 100 MHz) spectroscopic data, 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
: 777.2233 [M – H] (calcd. for C 
37
H 
46
O 
18
, 778.2684).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Igdoside B (3)
</title>
         <p>
Yellow amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
24
72.6 (
c
1.06, MeOH); UV (DMSO) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 278 (4.01), 359 (4.30) nm; for 
1
H-NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
, 400 MHz) and 
13
C-NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
, 100 MHz) spectroscopic data, 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
: 935.31984 [M – H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
44
H 
56
O 
22
, 936.3263).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. Igdoside C (4)
</title>
         <p>
Yellow amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
24
58.3 (
c
1.03, MeOH); UV (DMSO) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 298 (3.81), 338 (4.09) nm; for 
1
H-NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
, 400 MHz) and 
13
C-NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
, 100 MHz) spectroscopic data, 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
: 1129.37324 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
54
H 
64
O 
26
, 1128.369).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.4. Igdoside D (5)
</title>
         <p>
Yellow amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
24
73.6 (
c
0.91, MeOH); UV (DMSO) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 278 (4.02), 360 (4.21) nm; for 
1
H-NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
, 400 MHz) and 
13
C-NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
, 100 MHz) spectroscopic data, 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
: 922.29953 [M-(Glucose+ Galactose+ Methoxy)] 
+
(calcd. for C 
56
H 
76
O 
33
, 1276.427).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. α- Glucosidase inhibition assay
</title>
         <p>
The inhibitory effect on 
α
-glucosidase was determined according to the method of 

, with slight modifications (

). All samples (20 μL), enzyme solution (10 μL, 1 U/mL), and potassium phosphate buffer (50 μL, 50 mM, pH 6.9) were mixed in a 96-well plate and incubated at 37 
◦
C for 5 min. To initiate the reaction, the substrate, 
p
-nitrophenyl- 
α
-D-glucopyranoside (20 μL, 3 mM), was added to each well. The mixtures were subsequently incubated at 37 
◦
C for 30 min. Thereafter, to quench the reaction, 0.1 M sodium carbonate (50 μL) was added to each well. Acarbose was used as a positive control. The amount of 
p
-nitrophenol was measured using a 96-well microplate reader at 
405 nm
. Each assay was performed in triplicate for all samples. The percentage inhibition of all samples was calculated using the following equation:
</p>
         <p>
Inhibition(%) = (1 ΔA 
405
sample 
/
ΔA 
405
control) × 100
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.1. α- Amylase inhibition assay
</title>
         <p>
The inhibitory effect on 
α
-amylase was determined according to the method of 

, with slight modifications (

). All samples (100 μL) and 1% starch solution (100 μL) in 20 mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH 6.9 containing 6 mM sodium chloride) were incubated at 25 
◦
C for 10 min in a 24-well microplate. After incubation, 100 μL 
α
-amylase solution (
0.5 mg
/mL) was added to each well and the reaction mixtures were incubated at 25 
◦
C for 10 min. The reaction was subsequently terminated by the addition of dinitrosalicylic acid color reagent (200 μL). After the microplate was heated in a boiling water bath for 5 min and cooled to 25 
◦
C, 50 μL was removed from each well and transferred to a 96-well microplate. The reaction mixture was diluted by the addition of 200 μL distilled water, and the absorbance at 
540 nm
was measured. Acarbose was used as the positive control. Each assay was performed in triplicate for all samples. The percentage inhibition of all samples was calculated using the following equation:
</p>
         <p>
Inhibition (%) = (1 ΔA 
540
sample 
/
ΔA 
540
control) × 100
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.2. DPPH radical-scavenging assay
</title>
         <p>
The DPPH radical-scavenging activity was evaluated according to the method of 

. All samples (210 μL) and DPPH solution (70 μL, 1 mM) were transferred to the respective microplate wells. The mixture was shaken for approximately 1 min and incubated for 30 min at room temperature in the dark. The absorbance of all samples was recorded at 
517 nm
against ethanol. 
α
-Tocopherol and trolox were used as positive controls. Each assay was performed in triplicate for all samples. The percentage radical scavenging capacity of all samples was calculated using the following equation:
</p>
         <p>
Radical scavenging capacity(%) = (1 ΔA 
517
sample 
/
ΔA 
517
control) × 100
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.3. ABTS radical-scavenging assay
</title>
         <p>
The ABTS radical-scavenging activity was determined according to the method of 

. Briefly, 2 mM of ABTS solution was prepared. Thereafter, ABTS free radicals were generated via the addition of an equal volume of 2.45 mM potassium persulfate. All samples (140 μL) and ABTS solution (100 μL) were transferred to the wells and shaken for 1 min. At the end of the 30-min incubation period, the absorbances at 
734 nm
were recorded. The absorbance value of the control sample at 
734 nm
was 0.700 ± 0.025. 
α
-Tocopherol and trolox were used as positive controls. Each assay was performed in triplicate for all samples. The percentage radical scavenging capacity of all samples was calculated using the following equation:
</p>
         <p>
Radical scavenging capacity (%) = (1 ΔA 
734
sample 
/
ΔA 
734
control) × 100
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.4. Quantitative determination using HPLC
</title>
         <p>
To evaluate the role of the active compounds, the leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. angustifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
, used traditionally in the management of DM, were used to prepare an infusion (
0.5 g
leaves in 50 mL water, 15 min) and a decoction (
0.5 g
leaves in 50 mL water, 30 min) (

). HPLC was used to determine the concentrations of 
trans
-tiliroside in the 70% methanol extract, ethyl acetate extract, decoction, and infusion using a Supelco Ascentis Express RP-Amide column (100 × 
2.1 mm
, 2.7 μm) as the stationary phase. The column temperature was maintained at 40 
◦
C. The mobile phase consisted of a gradient system of ACN:0.2% FA (0:100 → 40:60, v/v) at a flow rate of 0.3 mL/min and a run time of 50 min. The injection volume was 20 μL. The absorbance of the eluent was monitored at 
254 nm
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.5. Method validation
</title>
         <p>
Standard solutions of 
trans
-tiliroside (six dilutions ranging from 10 to 125 μg/mL) were prepared. Each standard solution was injected three times. A calibration curve was plotted using the peak areas and concentrations. The linear regression equation was y = 3761.5x + 11048, with a correlation coefficient (R) of 0.9973. The limit of detection (LOD: 0.5 μg/mL) and limit of quantification (LOQ: 1.5 μg/mL) were determined based on the signal-to-noise (
S
/N) ratio. Specifically, a series of diluted standard solutions were analyzed, and ratios of 3 and 10 (
S
/N) were obtained and expressed in concentrations equivalent to the ratios.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Statistical analysis
</title>
         <p>
All experiments were performed in triplicate. Kruskal-Wallis test was used to determine statistical significance. Results were analyzed using SPSS (IBM SPSS Statistics 20, IBM Corporation, Armonk, NY, 
USA
) at the significance level of P = 0.05. The percent inhibition and IC 
50
value data for extracts and compounds are presented as means ± standard deviation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
This work was financially supported by The Scientific and Technological Research Council of 
Turkey
(TÜBITAK ˙) 3001 – Starting R&amp;D Projects Funding Program (No. 217 
S
206). The authors would like to thank the Forest Engineer, Mehmet ONAL ¨, MSc (Eastern 
Anatolia
Forestry Research Institute) for identifying the plant assessed herein. The authors would also like to thank Prof. Dr. Cavit Kazaz (Ataturk University) for obtaining the NMR spectra of the compounds and Prof. Dr. Hamdullah Kılıç (Ataturk University) for obtaining the specific optical rotations of the compounds.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112795.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
References
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Al-Azzawie, H.F.
, 
Alhamdani, M.S.
, 
2006
. 
Hypoglycemic and antioxidant effect of oleuropein in alloxan-diabetic rabbits
. 
Life Sci.
78
, 
1371–1377
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.lfs.2005.07.029
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Arıtuluk, Z.C.
, 
Ezer, N.
, 
2012
. 
Plants used against diabetes among the people (Turkey)-II
. 
Hacettepe Univ. Eczacı. Fak. Derg.
32
, 
179–208
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Bachhawat, J.A.
, 
Shihabudeen, M.S.
, 
Thirumurugan, K.
, 
2011
. 

Screening of fifteen Indian ayurvedic plants for 
alpha
-glucosidase inhibitory activity and enzyme kinetics

. 
Int. J. Pharm. Pharmaceut. Sci.
3
, 
267–274
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Baytop, T.
, 
1999
. 
Therapy with Medicinal Plants in Turkey (Past and Present), second ed
. 
Nobel, Istanbul
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Bechlem, H.
, 
Mencherini, T.
, 
Bouheroum, M.
, 
Benayache, S.
, 
Cotugno, R.
, 
Braca, A.
, 
De Tommasi, N.
, 
2017
. 

New constituents from 
Gymnocarpos decander

. 
Planta Med.
83
, 
1200–1206
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-0043-111599
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Blois, M.S.
, 
1958
. 
Antioxidant determinations by the use of a stable free radical
. 
Nature
181
, 
1199–1200
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/1811199a0
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Broadhurst, C.L.
, 
Polansky, M.M.
, 
Anderson, R.A.
, 
2000
. 

Insulin-like biological activity of culinary and medicinal plant aqueous extracts 
in vitro

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
48
, 
849–852
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jf9904517
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cao, H.
, 
Chen, X.
, 
2012
. 
Structures required of flavonoids for inhibiting digestive enzymes. Anticancer Agents Med
. 
Chem.
12
, 
929–939
. 
https://doi.org/10.2174/ 187152012802650110
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Carradori, S.
, 
Cairone, F.
, 
Garzoli, S.
, 
Fabrizi, G.
, 
Iazzetti, A.
, 
Giusti, A.M.
, 
Menghini, L.
, 
Uysal, S.
, 
Ak, G.
, 
Zengin, G.
, 
Cesa, S.
, 
2020
. 

Phytocomplex characterization and biological evaluation of powdered fruits and leaves from 
Elaeagnus angustifolia

. 
Molecules
25
, 
2021
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules25092021
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Chakrabarti, R.
, 
Rajagopalan, R.
, 
2002
. 
Diabetes and insulin resistance associated disorders: disease and the therapy
. 
Curr. Sci.
83
, 
1533–1538
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cheng, A.Y.Y.
, 
Fantus, I.G.
, 
2005
. 
Oral antihyperglycemic therapy for type 2 diabetes mellitus
. 
Can. Med. Assoc. J.
172
, 
213–226
. 
https://doi.org/10.1503/cmaj.1031414
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cowie, C.C.
, 
Eberhardt, M.S.
, 
1996
. 
Diabetes 1996: Vital Statistics, second ed
. 
American Diabetes Association, Virginia
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Dey, B.
, 
Mitra, A.
, 
Katakam, P.
, 
Singla, R.K.
, 
2014
. 

Exploration of natural enzyme inhibitors with hypoglycemic potentials amongst 
Eucalyptus
spp. by 
in vitro
assays

. 
World J. Diabetes
5
, 
209
. 
https://doi.org/10.4239/wjd.v5.i2.209
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
European Medicines Agency
, 
2010
. 
Glossary on Herbal Teas
. In: 
https://www.ema.eur opa.eu/en/documents/regulatory-procedural-guideline/glossary-herbal-teas_en.pdf
. (Accessed 
13 February 2021
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Farzaei, M.H.
, 
Bahramsoltani, R.
, 
Abbasabadi, Z.
, 
Rahimi, R.
, 
2015
. 

A comprehensive review on phytochemical and pharmacological aspects of 
Elaeagnus angustifolia
L

. 
J. Pharm. Pharmacol.
67
, 
1467–1480
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jphp.12442
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fred-Jaiyesimi, A.
, 
Kio, A.
, 
Richard, W.
, 
2009
. 

α
-Amylase inhibitory effect of 3 
β
-olean-12-en-3-yl(9Z)-hexadec-9-enoate isolated from 
Spondias mombin
leaf

. 
Food Chem.
116
, 
285–288
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2009.02.047
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Funke, I.
, 
Melzing, M.F.
, 
2006
. 

Traditionally used plants in diabetes therapyphytotherapeutics as inhibitors of 
α
-amylase activity

. 
Rev. Bras. Farmacogn.
16
, 
1–5
. 
https://doi.org/10.1590/S0102-695X2006000100002
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ghavam-Haghi, F.
, 
Dinani, M.S.
, 
2017
. 

Isolation and identification of astragalin and 2- methoxy tyrosol from the bulbs of 
Allium paradoxum

. 
J. Herbmed. Pharmacol.
6
, 
114–118
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Güner, A.
, 
Aslan, S.
, 
Ekim, T.
, 
Vural, M.
, 
Babaç, M.T.
, 
2012
. 
Turkey Plant List (Vascular Plants), first ed
. 
Nezahat G¨okyi˘git Botanical Garden and Flora Research Association, Istanbul
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Güvenalp, Z.
, Ozbek ¨, H., Dursuno˘glu, B., 
Yuca, H.
, G¨ozcü, S., 
Çil, Y.M.
, 
Kazaz, C.
, 
Kara, K.
, 
Demirezer, O
¨.L., 
2017
. 

α
-Amylase and 
α
-glucosidase inhibitory activities of the herbs of 
Artemisia dracunculus
L. and its active constituents

. 
Med. Chem. Res.
26
, 
3209–3215
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00044-017-2014-7
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ikechukwu, O.J.
, 
Ifeanyi, O.S.
, 
2016
. 

The antidiabetic effects of the bioactive flavonoid (kaempferol-3- 
O-beta
-D-6

{
p
-coumaroyl}glucopyranoside) isolated from 
Allium cepa
. 
Recent Pat. Anti-Infect. Drug Discov.
11
, 
44–52
. 
https://doi.org/10.2174/ 1574891X11666151105130233
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Inzucchi, S.E.
, 
2002
. 
Oral antihyperglycemic therapy for type 2 diabetes
. 
J. Am. Med. Assoc.
287
, 
360–372
. 
https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.287.3.360
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Jia, L.
, 
Zhang, L.
, 
Ye, Y.H.
, 
Li, J.L.
, 
Cong, M.
, 
Yuan, T.
, 
2019
. 

Effect and mechanism of 
Elaeagnus angustifolia
flower and its major flavonoid tiliroside on inhibiting nonenzymatic glycosylation

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
67
, 
13960–13968
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.jafc.9b06712
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Kumarasamy, Y.
, 
Cox, P.J.
, 
Jaspars, M.
, 
Rashid, M.A.
, 
Sarker, S.D.
, 
2003
. 

Bioactive flavonoid glycosides from the seeds of 
Rosa canina

. 
Pharm. Biol.
41
, 
237–242
. 
https://doi.org/10.1076/phbi.41.4.237.15663
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Liu, C.
, 
Chen, J.
, 
Wang, J.
, 
2009
. 

A novel kaempferol triglycoside from flower buds of 
Panax quinquefolium

. 
Chem. Nat. Compd.
45
, 
808–810
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ s10600-010-9500-1
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Liu, Y.
, 
Fan, G.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Li, J.J.
, 
Xiong, C.
, 
Zhang, Q.
, 
Li, X.D.
, 
Lai, X.R.
, 
2017
. 

Metabolic discrimination of sea buckthorn from different 
Hippophae
species by H-1 NMR based metabolomics

. 
Sci. Rep-Uk.
7
, 
1–11
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/ s41598-017-01722-3
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Maritim, A.C.
, 
Sanders, R.A.
, 
Watkins, J.B.
, 
2003
. 
Diabetes, oxidative stress, and antioxidants: a review
. 
J. Biochem. Mol. Toxicol.
17
, 
24–38
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1002/jbt.10058
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Marshall, J.J.
, 
Lauda, C.M.
, 
1975
. 

Purification and properties of phaseolamin, an inhibitor of 
α
-amylase, from the kidney bean, 
Phaseolus vulgaris

. 
J. Biol. Chem.
250
, 
8030–8037
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0021-9258(19)40811-9
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Matsui, T.
, 
Ueda, T.
, 
Oki, T.
, 
Sugita, K.
, 
Terahara, N.
, 
Matsumoto, K.
, 
2001
. 

alpha
- Glucosidase inhibitory action of natural acylated anthocyanins. 1. Survey of natural pigments with potent inhibitory activity

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
49
, 
1948–1951
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jf001251u
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
McKean, D.R.
, 
1965
. 
Elaeagnaceae L
. In: 
Davis, P.H.
(Ed.), 
Flora of Turkey and the East Aegean Islands
, vol. 7. 
Edinburgh University Press, Edinburgh
, p. 
532
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Mekhelfi, T.
, 
Adouni, K.
, 
Zaiter, L.
, 
Guella, G.
, 
Benayache, S.
, 
Benayache, F.
, 
Venskutonis, P.R.
, 
2016
. 

Antioxidant activity of extracts, 
cis
and 
trans
tilirosides, and other compounds from 
Thymelaea microphylla
Coss. et Dur

. 
Der Pharm. Lett.
8
, 
233–239
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Nampoothiri, S.V.
, 
Prathapan, A.
, 
Cherian, O.L.
, 
Raghu, K.G.
, 
Venugopalan, V.V.
, 
Sundaresan, A.
, 
2011
. 

In vitro
antioxidant and inhibitorypotential of 
Terminalia bellerica
and 
Emblica officinalis
fruits against LDL oxidation and key enzymes linked to type 2 diabetes

. 
Food Chem. Toxicol.
49
, 
125–131
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. fct.2010.10.006
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ozbek, H.
, 
Guvenalp, Z.
, 
Kuruuzum-Uz, A.E.
, 
Kazaz, C.
, 
Demirezer, L.O.
, 
2016
. 

beta
- Hydroxydihydrochalcone and flavonoid glycosides along with triterpene saponin and sesquiterpene from the herbs of 
Pimpinella rhodantha
Boiss

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
30
, 
750–754
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/14786419.2015.1062006
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Qiao, W.
, 
Zhao, C.
, 
Qin, N.
, 
Zhai, H.Y.
, 
Duan, H.Q.
, 
2011
. 

Identification of 
trans
-tiliroside as active principle with anti-hyperglycemic, anti-hyperlipidemic and antioxidant effects from 
Potentilla chinesis

. 
J. Ethnopharmacol.
135
, 
515–521
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.jep.2011.03.062
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Qin, N.
, 
Li, C.B.
, 
Jin, M.N.
, 
Shi, L.H.
, 
Duan, H.Q.
, 
Niu, W.Y.
, 
2011
. 
Synthesis and biological activity of novel tiliroside derivants
. 
Eur. J. Med. Chem.
46
, 
5189–5195
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2011.07.059
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Re, R.
, 
Pellegrini, N.
, 
Proteggente, A.
, 
Pannala, A.
, 
Yang, M.
, 
Rice-Evans, C.
, 
1999
. 
Antioxidant activity applying an improved ABTS radical cation decolorization assay
. 
Free Radical Biol. Med.
26
, 
1231–1237
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0891-5849(98) 00315-3
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Roesch, D.
, 
Krumbein, A.
, 
Muegge, C.
, 
Kroh, L.W.
, 
2004
. 

Structural investigations of flavonol glycosides from sea buckthorn (
Hippophae rhamnoides
) pomace by NMR spectroscopy and HPLC-ESI-MS

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
52
, 
4039–4046
. 
https://doi. org/10.1021/jf0306791
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Saltan, F.Z.
, 
Okutucu, B.
, 
Canbay, H.S.
, 
Ozel, D.
, 
2017
. 

In vitro α
-glucosidase and 
α
-amylase enzyme inhibitory effects in 
Elaeagnus angustifolia
leaves extracts

. 
Eurasian J. Anal. Chem.
12
, 
117–126
. 
https://doi.org/10.12973/ejac.2017.00158a
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Wang, Y.
, 
Guo, T.
, 
Li, J.Y.
, 
Zhou, S.Z.
, 
Zhao, P.
, 
Fan, M.T.
, 
2013
. 

Four flavonoid glycosides from the pulps of 
Elaeagnus angustifolia
and their antioxidant activities

. 
Adv. Mater. Res.
756
– 
759
, 
16–20
. 
https://doi.org/10.4028/www.scientific.net/ AMR.756-759.16
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Wang, Y.
, 
Zou, H.
, 
Sun, C.
, 
Guo, T.
, 
Feng, Z.
, 
2018
. 

Hypoglycemic potential of 
Elaeagnus angustifolia
fruit polysaccharide on streptozotocin-induced type 2 diabetic mice

. 
Bangladesh J. Pharmacol.
13
, 
297–301
. 
https://doi.org/10.3329/bjp.v13i4.37069
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Xie, H.
, 
Chen, X.
, 
Li, M.
, 
Aisa, H.A.
, 
Yuan, T.
, 
2020
. 

Angustifolinoid B, a flavonoid glycoside dimer with cyclobutane from 
Elaeagnus angustifolia
flowers

. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
61
, 
1–3
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tetlet.2020.151946
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Yordi, E.G.
, P´erez, E.M., 
Matos, M.J.
, 
Villares, E.U.
, 
2012
. 
Antioxidant and pro-oxidant effects of polyphenolic compounds and structure-activity relationship evidence
. 
Nutrition, well-being and health
10
, 
29471
. 
https://doi.org/10.5772/29471
.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
