<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2023.113585</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Undescribed phloroglucinol derivatives with antiviral activities from Dryopteris atrata (Wall. Ex Kunze) Ching</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris atrata
(Wall. Ex Kunze) Ching
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Dryopteris atrata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Dryopteridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris atrata
(Wall. Ex Kunze) Ching (Dryopteridaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris atrata
(Wall. Ex Kunze) Ching
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Dryopteridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris wallichiana
(Spreng.) Hyl. Showing
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
D. atrata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
D. atrata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris atrata
(Wall. Ex Kunze) Ching (Dryopteridaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
D. atrata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Undescribed phloroglucinol derivatives with antiviral activities from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris atrata
(Wall. Ex Kunze) Ching
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ji-hui Zhang
a, 1
, Jin-lin Chen
a, 1
, Wei-bin Xu
a
, Yi-ping Xia
a, e
, Hao-yue Zhu
a
, Jing-hao Wang
b, c
,
Yao-lan Li a

, Guo-cai Wang

a, c, 

***
, Yu-bo Zhang

c,d, **
, Neng-hua Chen
b, c, *
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Institute of Traditional Chinese Medicine

&amp; 

Natural Products
, 
Guangdong Province
Key Laboratory of Pharmacodynamic Constituents
of TCM and New Drugs Research


, College of Pharmacy, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b

Department of Pharmacy, The First Affiliated Hospital, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510630, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c

The Guangzhou Key Laboratory of Basic and Translational Research on Chronic Diseases, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510630, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
d
Guangdong
Clinical Translational Center for Targeted Drug, Department of Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Jinan University, Guangzhou, 510632, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
e

Department of Dermatology, Shunde Hospital, Southern Medical University (The First People’ s Hospital of Shunde Foshan), Foshan, 528308, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Dryopteris atrata</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Dryopteridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Phloroglucinol derivatives</p>
         <p>Structural elucidation</p>
         <p>Antiviral activities</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Nine undescribed phloroglucinol derivatives (dryatraols A-I) with five different backbones and three known dimeric acylphloroglucinols were isolated from the rhizome of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris atrata
(Wall. Ex Kunze) Ching (Dryopteridaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Dryatraol A contains an unprecedented carbon skeleton—a butyrylphloroglucinol and a rulepidanol-type sesquiterpene are linked via a furan ring to form a 6/5/6/6 ring system. Dryatraols B and C are the first examples of monomeric phloroglucinols coupled with the aristolane-type sesquiterpene through the C–C bond. Dryatraol D features a rare spiro [benzofuran-2 
′
,5 
′′
-furan] backbone. Dryatraols E-I are five undescribed adducts with a butyrylphloroglucinol or filicinic acid incorporated into the germacrene-type sesquiterpene via a pyran ring. These undescribed structures were determined by comprehensively analysing the spectroscopic data, X-ray diffraction results, and electronic circular dichroism calculations. The result of 
in vitro
antiviral activity evaluation indicated that dryatraol C displayed the strongest antiviral effect against both respiratory syncytial virus and influenza A virus (H1N1), with IC 
50
values of 11.9 μM and 5.5 μM, respectively. Dryatraols F–H exhibited considerable inhibitory activity against herpes simplex virus 
type
1 (HSV-1), with IC 
50
values ranging from 2.6 to 6.3 μM. Analysis of the inhibitory mechanism using a time-of-addition assay revealed that dryatraol G may inhibit the replication of HSV-1 by interfering with the late stage of the viral life cycle.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris atrata
(Wall. Ex Kunze) Ching
</tp:taxon-name>
, which belongs to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Dryopteridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family, is widely distributed in the southern provinces adjacent to the Yangtze River in 
China
(Editorial 

). Its rhizome can be used for treating ascariasis, paediatric worms, and functional uterine bleeding (

). Phloroglucinol derivatives are the characteristic constituents (

) as well as the principal active substances of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
that display anthelmintic (

), antitumour (

), antimicrobial (

), antiviral (

), and antioxidant (

) activities. Furthermore, with more structurally interesting phloroglucinol derivatives identified from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
(

, 

; 

; 

)—in particular, some adducts from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris wallichiana
(Spreng.) Hyl. Showing
</tp:taxon-name>
unambiguous inhibitory activity against SARS-CoV-2 (

)—the phloroglucinol derivatives of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
have drawn the attention of the research community.
</p>
         <p>
* Corresponding author. The First Affiliated Hospital, Jinan University, 613 Huangpu Avenue West, Guangzhou, 510630, 
China
.
</p>
         <p>
** Corresponding author. 
Guangdong
Clinical Translational Center for Targeted Drug, Department of Pharmacology, School of Medicine, Jinan University, 601 Huangpu Avenue West, Guangzhou, 510630, 
China
.
</p>
         <p>
*** Corresponding author. Institute of Traditional Chinese Medicine &amp; Natural Products, 
Guangdong Province
Key Laboratory of Pharmacodynamic Constituents of TCM and New Drugs Research, College of Pharmacy, Jinan University, 601 Huangpu Avenue West, Guangzhou, 510630, 
China
.
</p>
         <p>
E-mail addresses:
twangguocai@jnu.edu.cn (G.-c. Wang), ybzhang99@126.com (Y.-b. Zhang), chennengflo@163.com (N.-h. Chen).
</p>
         <p>
1
The authors contributed equally to this work.
</p>
         <p>
The phytochemical composition of the rhizome of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. atrata
</tp:taxon-name>
was studied as a part of our ongoing research on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
plants. Nine undescribed phloroglucinol derivatives (
1–9
) and three known dimeric acylphloroglucinols (
10–12
) were isolated. The structures of the compounds were determined by interpretation of spectroscopic data, X-ray diffraction, and electronic circular dichroism calculations. Most isolates were evaluated for antiviral activity against respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), influenza A virus (H1N1), and herpes simplex virus 
type
1 (HSV-1). Herein, we report a detailed isolation, structural elucidation, and evaluation of antiviral activity of these compounds.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Structural elucidation
</title>
         <p>
Dryatraol A (
1
) had a molecular formula of C 
26
H 
34
O 
5
as deduced by high-resolution electrospray ionisation mass spectrometry (HRESIMS) (
m/z
427.2476 [M + H] 
+
, calculated for C 
26
H 
35
O 
5
, 427.2479), suggestive of ten degrees of unsaturation. The 
1
H NMR spectrum (
Table 1
) revealed six methyl groups [
δ
H
2.05, 1.28, 1.22, 1.10 (each 3H, s), 0.99 (3H, d, 
J
= 6.4 Hz), and 0.94 (3H, t, 
J
= 7.4 Hz)], three olefinic protons [
δ
H
6.13 (1H, d, 
J
= 5.2 Hz), 6.06 (1H, dd, 
J
= 9.7, 5.2 Hz), and 5.88 (1H, dd, 
J
= 9.7, 6.6 Hz)], and a hydrogen-bonded hydroxyl proton [
δ
H
13.60 (1H, s)]. The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 1
) with the aid of HSQC and DEPT experiments displayed twenty-six carbon signals for six methyl, three methylene, seven methine, and ten non-protonated carbons. The above data implied that 
1
might be a phloroglucinol-sesquiterpene adduct (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The assignment of the phloroglucinol (
1.1
) and sesquiterpene (
1.2
) moieties was further confirmed by interpretation of the 1D and 2D NMR spectra. The 
13
C NMR data of fragment 
1.1
were similar to those of the phloroglucinol unit in jejuguajavone I (

), which were further determined by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY and HMBC correlations shown in 
Fig. 2
. The 1D NMR signals for fragment 
1.2
showed many similarities to those of rulepidanol (

), and the main difference was that the two methylene carbons at 
δ
C
32.4 (C-1) and 
δ
C
24.7 (C-2) in rulepidanol were replaced by two methine carbons at 
δ
C
87.7 (C-1 
′
), 38.2 (C-2 
′
) in 
1
. This conclusion was verified by the spin system from H-1’ (
δ
H
5.00) to H-4’ (
δ
H
2.59) in the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY spectrum, as well as the HMBC correlations from H-1 
′
to C-3’ (
δ
C
33.5)/C-5’ (
δ
C
40.0)/C-9’ (
δ
C
128.5)/C-10’ (
δ
C
140.3). Additionally, the linkage between fragments 
1.1
and 
1.2
via the C-2 
′
–C-6 bond was deduced from the HMBC correlations from H-2’ (
δ
H
3.18) to C-1 (
δ
C
160.0)/C-6 (
δ
C
110.8). Finally, an oxygen bridge between C-1 
′
and C-5 to form a furan ring was deduced from the downfield chemical shifts of C-5 (
δ
C
156.1) and C-1’ (
δ
C
87.7), as well as the remaining one degree of unsaturation.
</p>
         <p>
The relative configuration was determined by coupling constants and interpretation of the NOESY data. The correlations of H-6’ (
δ
H
2.31) and H 
3
-14’ (
δ
H
1.10)/H 
3
-15’ (
δ
H
0.99)indicated that these protons were located on the same side and arbitrarily designated as 
α
-orientation. The correlations of H-2’ (
δ
H
3.18) and H-4’ (
δ
H
2.59), H-1’ (
δ
H
5.00)/H-4’ (
δ
H
2.59) and H 
3
-13’ (
δ
H
1.22) suggested that H-1 
′
, H-2 
′
, and H-4 
′
were cofacial and 
β
-oriented. The 
Z
-geometry of the C-7/C-8 olefin is consistent with the observed coupling constant (
J
7 8
= 9.7 Hz). To determine the absolute configuration of 
1
, the quantum chemical calculations on (1 
′
S
, 2 
′
R
, 4 
′
R
, 5 
′
R
, 6 
′
R
)- 
1
and (1 
′
R
, 2 
′
S
, 4 
′
S
, 5 
′
S
, 6 
′
S
)- 
1
were calculated, as well as a comparison between the calculated and the experimental ECD spectra was performed. The calculated ECD spectrum for (1 
′
R
, 2 
′
S
, 4 
′
S
, 5 
′
S
, 6 
′
S
)- 
1
was in agreement with the experimental one. Accordingly, the structure of dryatraol A was established.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>Overlapped signals are reported without designating multiplicity.</p>
         <p>
a
Measured in CDCl.
</p>
         <p>
3
b
Measured in MeOD.
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol B (
2
) had a molecular formula of C 
23
H 
30
O 
4
as established by its 
13
C NMR and HRESIMS data (
m/z
371.2214 [M + H] 
+
, calculated for C 
23
H 
31
O 
4
, 371.2217). The 1D NMR data of 
2
(Figures S22 and S23, Supplementary data) presented two sets of signals in a ratio of approximately 5:2 (
2a
: 
2b
). The 
1
H NMR spectrum of the major isomer 
2a
showed signals assigned to five methyl groups [
δ
H
2.68, 1.21, 1.19, 1.08 (each 3H, s), and 0.99 (3H, d, 
J
= 6.9 Hz)], an olefinic methine [
δ
H
5.29 (1H, d, 
J
= 4.1 Hz)], an aromatic proton [
δ
H
5.79 (1H, s)], and two phenolic hydroxyl groups [
δ
H
14.10 and 7.04 (each 1H, s)]. The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 1
) with the aid of the HSQC experiment disclosed twenty-three carbon signals attributable to five methyl, three methylene, six methine, and nine non-protonated carbons. A comprehensive analysis of the 1D NMR data of 
2a
suggested that it was also a phloroglucinol–sesquiterpene adduct.
</p>
         <p>
The planar structure of 
2a
was established by further analysis of its 2D NMR data. The presence of an acetyl–phloroglucinol moiety (
2.1
) was deduced from the characteristic signal of a hydrogen-bonded hydroxyl proton [
δ
H
14.10 (1H, s)] and the HMBC correlations from H-4 (
δ
H
5.79) to C-3 (
δ
C
158.8)/C-5 (
δ
C
162.4), H 
3
-8 (
δ
H
2.68) to C-2 (
δ
C
104.9)/C-7 (
δ
C
203.6), and 5-OH (
δ
H
7.04) to C-4 (
δ
C
95.2)/C-5 (
δ
C
162.4)/C-6 (
δ
C
110.4). Moreover, the remaining fifteen carbons implied the presence of an aristolene unit (
2.2
) (

), which was further verified by 
1
H– 
1
H COSY and HMBC correlations as shown in 
Fig. 2
. The connection between 
2.1
and 
2.2
via the C-8 
′
–C-6 bond was accomplished by the key HMBC correlations from H-9’ (
δ
H
5.29) to C-6 and from H-8’ (
δ
H
3.96) to C-5/C-6. Thus, the planar structure was delineated.
</p>
         <p>
The relative configuration of 
2a
was determined by interpretation of the NOESY spectrum (
Fig. 4
), in which the correlations between H-6’ (
δ
H
0.72) and H 
3
-14’ (
δ
H
1.21)/H 
3
-15’ (
δ
H
0.99), and between H 
3
-12’ (
δ
H
1.19) and H-6’/H-7’ (
δ
H
0.70) indicated that H-6’/H-7’/H 
3
-14’/H 
3
-15 
′
were occupied on the same side and designated as 
α
-orientation. Thus, the correlation between H-8’ (
δ
H
3.96) and H 
3
-13’ (
δ
H
1.08) indicated that H-8 
′
and H 
3
-13 
′
were cofacial and 
β
-oriented. The relative configuration of 
2a
was determined accordingly. Finally, the tendency of the calculated ECD spectrum of (4 
′
S
, 5 
′
S
, 6 
′
R
, 7 
′
S
, 8 
′
R
)– 
2a
agreed with the experimental one, allowing the assignment of the absolute configuration to be 4 
′
S
, 5 
′
S
, 6 
′
R
, 7 
′
S
, 8 
′
R
.
</p>
         <p>
The NMR data of the minor isomer 
2b
greatly resembled that of 
2a
, and a comprehensive interpretation showed that 
2b
had nearly the same structure as 
2a
. The main difference between 
2a
and 
2b
involved the signals assigned to fragment 
2.1
(
δ
C
163.8, 104.9, 158.8, 95.2, 162.4, 110.4 for C-1 C- 
6 in
2a
; 
δ
C
160.2, 106.1, 164.4, 95.9, 160.0, 108.9 for C-1 C- 
6 in
2b
) (Figure S23, Supplementary data). These indicated that 
2a
and 
2b
were a pair of isomers formed by the rotation of the intramolecular hydrogen bond (

; 

). Moreover, the key HMBC correlations between the hydrogen-bonded hydroxyl proton 3-OH (
δ
H
13.65) and C-2 (
δ
C
106.1)/C-3 (
δ
C
164.4)/C-4 (
δ
C
95.9) suggested that the intramolecular hydrogen bond in 
2b
was located between the 3-OH and C-7 ketone carbonyl, and that in 
2a
was formed between the 1-OH and C-7 ketone carbonyl, accordingly.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of dryatraol C (
3
) was assigned as C 
24
H 
32
O 
4
by HRESIMS at 
m/z
385.2370 [M + H] 
+
(calculated for C 
24
H 
33
O 
4
, 385.2373), containing a 
CH
2
unit more than that of compound 
2
. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of 
3
also displayed two similar sets of signals in a 5:2 ratio (in CDCl 
3
), suggesting the presence of two isomers (
3a
and 
3b
) similar to those of 
2
. The only difference was that the acetyl group (
δ
C
203.6, 32.9) in 
2a
was replaced by a propionyl group (
δ
C
206.7, 37.4, 8.9) in 
3a
, which was confirmed by 
1
H– 
1
H COSY cross-peaks of H 
2
-8 (
δ
H
3.10) and H 
3
-9 (
δ
H
1.18), and the HMBC correlation from H 
2
-8 to C-7 (
δ
C
206.7). Owing to the structural similarities and identical experimental ECD spectra between 
3
and 
2
, the absolute configuration of (4 
′
S
, 5 
′
S
, 6 
′
R
, 7 
′
S
, 8 
′
R
)- 
3
was assigned.
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol D (
4
) possessed a molecular formula of C 
21
H 
26
O 
6
with nine degrees of unsaturation, as established by the HRESIMS ion peak at 
m/z
375.1801 [M + H] 
+
(calculated for C 
21
H 
27
O 
6
, 375.1802). Careful analysis of the 1D NMR data of 
4
indicated the presence of an identical phloroglucinol unit (
4.1
) as 
1
, and the remaining ten signals were attributed to a similar unit (
4.2
) of 5-[(
E
)-hexylidene]-5 
H-
furan-2-one (

). The main difference was that a pair of double bond carbons in 5-[(
E
)-hexylidene]-5 
H
-furan-2-one was replaced by an oxygenated non-pronated carbon (
δ
C
117.7) and a methine carbon (
δ
C
48.0). A comprehensive interpretation of the 2D NMR data further established the construction of 
4
. Two spin systems from H-3’’ (
δ
H
6.40) to H-4’’ (
δ
H
7.45) and from H-3’ (
δ
H
3.57) to H-8’ (
δ
H
0.87), together with the HMBC correlations from H-3’’/H-4 
′′
to C-2’’ (
δ
C
169.0)/C-2’ (
δ
C
117.7), from H-3 
′
to C-2’/C-4’’ (
δ
C
149.3) supported the construction of fraction 
4.2
. The key HMBC correlations between H-3 
′
and C-3 (
δ
C
157.4)/C-4 (
δ
C
106.2) indicated that fragment 
4.1
and fragment 
4.2
were connected via C-4 and C-3’. Similarly, an oxygen bridge between C-2 
′
and C-5 to form a furan ring was identified by the downfield chemical shifts of C-5 (
δ
C
156.2) and C-2’ (
δ
C
117.7), as well as the molecular formular information.
</p>
         <p>
The relative configuration of 
4
was determined using the NOESY spectrum and coupling constants data. The correlation between H-4’’ (
δ
H
7.45) and H 
2
-4’ (
δ
H
1.70) indicated that H 
2
-4 
′
and H-4 
′′
were located on the same side. The coupling constant (
J
′′ 
3,4’’
= 5.6 Hz) indicated the 
Z
-geometry of the C-3’’/C-4 
′′
olefin. Finally, the absolute configuration was established as 2 
′
S
, 3 
′
R
by comparing the calculated and experimental ECD spectra.
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol E (
5
) was obtained as colorless crystals (MeOH). The HRESIMS data revealed a 
pseudo
-molecular ion peak [M + H] 
+
at 
m/
z 431.2791, which was consistent with the molecular formula of C 
26
H 
38
O 
5
(calculated for C 
26
H 
39
O 
5
, 431.2792). Detailed analysis of the 1D NMR data of 
5
indicated a similar phloroglucinol moiety (
5.1
) as that (
2.1
) of 
2
and the same sesquiterpenoid moiety (
5.2
) as that of hyperjaponol G (

). The difference between 
5.1
and 
2.1
was that the acetyl (
δ
C
203.6, 32.9) in 
2.1
was replaced by a butyryl (
δ
C
207.5, 46.8, 19.6, 14.4). This deduction was further confirmed by the spin system from H 
2
-9 (
δ
H
3.02) to H 
3
-11 (
δ
H
0.97) displayed in the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY spectrum, together with the HMBC correlation from H 
2
-9 to C-8 (
δ
C
207.5). Then, 
5.1
was incorporated into 
5.2
to form a pyran ring, which was supported by the HMBC correlations from H 
2
-7 to C-1 (
δ
C
164.3)/C-5 (
δ
C
162.0)/C-6 (
δ
C
101.9)/C-1 
′
(
δ
C
83.4) and the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY cross-peaks of H 
2
-7 and H-2 
′
. Thus, the planar structure of 
5
with a 6/6/10 ring system was established.
</p>
         <p>
However, the relative configuration of 
5
could not be completely determined by NMR spectroscopy. Fortunately, a single crystal of 
5
was successfully obtained, and X-ray crystallography analysis with Cu Kα radiation resulted in a Flack parameter of 0.00 (16) allowing an explicit assignment of the absolute conformation as 1 
′
R
, 2 
′
S
, 5 
′
S
, 8 
′
R
(
Fig. 3
; CCDC: 1,903,935). Consequently, the structure of 
5
was established, and named as dryatraol E.
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol F (
6
) was obtained as a light yellow gum. The molecular formula was deduced as C 
27
H 
40
O 
5
from the protonated molecular ion peak at 
m/z
445.2939 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
27
H 
41
O 
5
, 445.2949). Its 
1
H NMR spectrum (Figure S62, Supplementary data) showed two signals at 
δ
H
18.98 and 
δ
H
18.32 in
a very low field with a ratio of approximately 5:1, suggesting the presence of two isomers (
6a
and 
6b
). Further analysis of the 1D NMR data suggested the acetylfilicinic acid moiety (
6.1
) identical to that of dryocrassoid B (

), which led to keto-enol tautomerism, as previously reported. In the HMBC spectrum, the major signal for the hydrogen-bonded hydroxyl proton (
δ
H
18.98) was observed to be correlated with C-1 (
δ
C
188.0)/C-2 (
δ
C
105.4)/C-6 (
δ
C
101.6)/C-8 (
δ
C
204.5) of 
6a
. While, the minor signal 
δ
H
18.32 showed correlations with C-2 (
δ
C
108.6)/C-3 (
δ
C
197.4)/C-8 (
δ
C
208.5) of 
6b
. These differences supported that 
6a
and 
6b
were a pair of keto-enol tautomers as depicted in 
Fig. 1
. Additionally, a detailed comparison of the 1D NMR data between 
6
and 
5
revealed the presence of the same germacrene-type sesquiterpene moiety (
6.2
). With the aid of the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HSQC, and HMBC spectra (
Fig. 2
), the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data were assigned, as shown in 
Table 2
. The linkage between 
6.1
and 
6.2
via a pyran ring similar to that of 
5
was supported by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY cross-peaks of H 
2
-7 (
δ
H
2.79, 1.73) and H-2 
′
(
δ
H
1.52), HMBC correlations from H 
2
-7 to C-5 (
δ
C
173.2)/C-6 (
δ
C
101.6)/C-1 
′
(
δ
C
84.9), and the molecular formula information. Finally, the configuration of 
6
was determined by comparing the experimental and calculated ECD spectra (
Fig. 5
). Thus, the structure of 
6
was constructed as depicted.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formulas of dryatraol G (
7
) and dryatraol H (
8
) were assigned as C 
26
H 
38
O 
5
and C 
28
H 
42
O 
5
by the ion peaks at 
m/z
431.2784 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
26
H 
39
O 
5
, 431.2792) and 
m/z
459.3096 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
28
H 
43
O 
5
, 459.3105) in their HRESIMS spectra, respectively. They respectively showed fourteen (
CH
2
) mass units less and more than that of 
6
. Detailed and careful analysis of the NMR data showed high similarity to those of 
6
indicated that compounds 
7
and 
8
were also mixtures of two isomers with the same ratio as that of 
6
. The only difference was that the propionyl group (
δ
C
204.5, 33.5, 9.1) in 
6
was replaced by an acetyl group (
δ
C
200.4, 28.1) in 
7
and a butyryl group (
δ
C
203.3, 41.6, 18.6, 14.0) in 
8
, respectively. These conclusions were respectively confirmed by the HMBC correlations from H 
3
-9 (
δ
H
2.58, s) to C-8 (
δ
C
200.4) in 
7
, and from H 
2
-9 (
δ
H
2.97) to C-8 (
δ
C
203.3) in 
8
, and the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY spin system of H 
2
-9 H 

3
-11 in

8
(
Fig. 2
). Thus, the 2D structures of 
7
and 
8
were elucidated, and the configurations were determined to be the same as that of 
6
, which was further confirmed by comparison with the experimental ECD spectra (
Fig. 5
).
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol I (
9
) possessed the same molecular formula of C 
28
H 
42
O 
5
as 
8
based on the HRESIMS ion peak 
m/z
459.3100 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
28
H 
43
O 
5
, 459.3105) and 
13
C NMR data. Detailed analysis of the 1D NMR of 
9
indicated that it was an analogue of hyperjaponol G except that the 
iso
-butyryl group (
δ
C
201.6, 35.9, 20.5, 19.7) in hyperjaponol G was replaced by a butyryl group (
δ
C
197.0, 42.1, 20.4, 14.6) in 
9
. This was verified by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations of H 
2
-9 (
δ
H
3.06) to H 
3
-11 (
δ
H
1.02) and the HMBC correlations between H 
2
-9 (
δ
H
3.06)/H 
2
-10 (
δ
H
1.75) and C-8 (
δ
C
197.0). Therefore, the planar structure of 
9
was identified. Then, the relative and absolute configurations were determined by comparison of the 1D NMR data, NOESY correlations, and experimental ECD spectrum with those of 
6–8
and hyperjaponol G, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
In addition to these undescribed compounds, three known acylphloroglucinols were identified as norflavaspidic acid AA, norflavaspidic acid AP, and norflavaspidic acid AB by comparing the spectroscopic and physical data with the respective literature values (

).
</p>
         <p>
A careful review of the literature (

, 

; 

; 

; 

) indicates that the coupling patterns between phloroglucinols and terpenes from the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
genus are via a pyran ring or a C–C single bond, no pattern of forming a furan ring has been discovered so far. Thus, in this study, a putative biosynthetic pathway of compound 
1,
which represented the first example of phloroglucinol-terpene adduct featuring an acylphloroglucinol motif fused with a rulepidanol-type sesquiterpene via a furan ring to form a 6/5/6/6 ring system, was proposed (Scheme S1, Supplementary data). First, the acylphloroglucinol motif 4-methylbutyrylphloroglucinol was derived from a Claisen reaction between butyryl-CoA and three molecules of malonyl-CoA, followed by methylation (

). Successive hydroxylation and dehydration of rulepidanol could lead to the formation of sesquiterpene intermediate 
v
. Finally, a radical coupling reaction between the acylphloroglucinol intermediate 
iii
and sesquiterpene intermediate 
v
generated compound 
1
(

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Pharmacological activity
</title>
         <p>
The isolates were evaluated for their antiviral activities 
in vitro
against RSV, HSV-1, and H1N1 using a cytopathic effect (CPE) reduction assay. As shown in 
Table 3
, most of the tested compounds displayed different degrees of antiviral activity against HSV-1, with IC 
50
values ranging from 2.6 to 47.5 μM, while fewer compounds showed activity against RSV and H1N1 (A/PR/8/34). Compounds 
2
and 
3
displayed comparable antiviral effects against H1N1 (A/PR/8/34) to the positive control. Compounds 
6–8
showed substantial inhibitory effects against HSV-1, with IC 
50
values ranging from 2.6 to 6.3 μM. Furthermore, a time-of-addition assay indicated that the most remarkable compound 
7
exerted its anti-HSV-1 activity by inhibiting the late [L]-phase among the virus replication phases (
Fig. 6
). However, the detailed mechanism still requires further investigation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
In the present study, nine undescribed phloroglucinol derivatives and three known dimeric acylphloroglucinols were obtained from the rhizome of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. atrata
</tp:taxon-name>
. Their structures were determined using comprehensive spectroscopic data, X-ray diffraction, and quantum chemical ECD calculations. The antiviral activity assays revealed that some of the isolates displayed considerable antiviral effects against RSV, HSV-1, and H1N1. In summary, these findings enrich the record of chemical diversity of the phloroglucinol derivatives from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris
</tp:taxon-name>
. In addition, some these active compounds may be useful for developing medicinal antiviral agents.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
Optical rotations were recorded on a JASCO P–1020 polarimeter. HRESIMS data were determined on an Agilent 6210 LC/MSD TOF mass spectrometer. A JASCO V–550 UV/vis spectrophotometer was used for scanning UV spectra. 1D and 2D NMR spectra were recorded on Bruker AV–400 (
1
H: 400 MHz, 
13
C: 100 MHz), Bruker AV–500 (
1
H: 500 MHz, 
13
C: 125 MHz), and Bruker AV–600 (
1
H: 600 MHz, 
13
C: 150 MHz) spectrometers with TMS as an internal standard. Analytical HPLC (high–performance liquid chromatography) was performed through a Shimadzu LC system equipped with an LC–20AD pump and an SPDM-20 A PDA detector, as well as a Cosmosil C 
18
analytical column (5 μm, 4.6 × 
250 mm
). Preparative HPLC was carried out on a Varian Prostar system equipped with a preparative Cosmosil C 
18
column (5 μm, 20 × 
250 mm
). Open column chromatography (CC) was performed using silica gel (200–300, mesh), ODS (50 μm, 120 Å; YMC) and Sephadex LH–20 (25–100 μm). All reagents used in CC and HPLC were analytical grade and chromatographic grade, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
4.2. Plant materials
</p>
         <p>

The rhizomes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dryopteris atrata
(Wall. Ex Kunze) Ching (Dryopteridaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected in 
Yunnan Province
of 
China
(

21.10 
◦
N

, 

100.80 
◦
E

) in 

September of 2019

. The plant was authenticated by Prof. 
Guangxiong Zhou
(College of Pharmacy, Jinan University). A voucher specimen (No. 
2019092601
) was deposited in the 
Institute of Traditional Chinese Medicine &amp; Natural Products
, Jinan University, Guangzhou, China

.
</p>
         <p>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</p>
         <p>
The dried and powered rhizomes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. atrata
</tp:taxon-name>
(8.0 kg) were extracted four times with 95% ethanol at room temperature (4 × 60.0 L). After filtration, the solvent was removed under reduced pressure using a rotary evaporator to give a crude extract (
1.1 kg
), which was suspended in water (1.0 L) and then partitioned with petroleum ether (PE) (3 × 3.0 L). After removal of solvent, the entire PE extract (
250.7 g
) was subjected to a silica gel CC eluted with PE/ethyl acetate (EA) in a gradient (100:0 to 0:100, v/v) to give seven fractions (Fr. A to Fr. G). Fr. C (
53.2 g
) was further purified by Sephadex LH-20 (chloroform (CHCl 
3
)/methanol (MeOH), 1:1, v/v) to obtain five subfractions (Fr. C1 to Fr. C5). Fr. C3 (
20.7 g
) was loaded on an ODS CC with a step gradient solvent of MeOH/ water (H 
2
O) (30:70 to 100:0, v/v) to afford ten subfractions (Fr. C3a to Fr. C3j). Compounds 
1
(
4.2 mg
, 
t
R
34.0 min) and 
4
(6.0 mg, 
t
R
25.0 min) were isolated from Fr. C3d (
0.7 g
) by preparative HPLC [MeOH/H 
2
O (0.1% formic acid (HCOOH)), 85:15, v/v]. Compounds 
2
(
10.6 mg
, 
t
R
33.0 min), 
3
(
6.4 mg
, 
t
R
36.0 min), and 
9
(3.0 mg, 
t
R
32.0 min) were obtained from Fr. C3e (
1.2 g
) using preparative HPLC [MeOH/H 
2
O (0.1% HCOOH), 85:15, v/v]. Fr. C3f (
0.7 g
) was isolated by semipreparative HPLC [MeOH/H 
2
O (0.1% HCOOH), 85:15, v/v] to obtain 
5
(
4.2 mg
, 
t
R
27.0 min) and 
7
(
3.6 mg
, 
t
R
33.0 min). Compounds 
6
(5.0 mg, 
t
R
23.0 min) and 
8
(
6.3 mg
, 
t
R
27.0 min) were acquired from Fr. C3i (
0.8 g
) by preparative HPLC [MeOH/H 
2
O (0.1% HCOOH), 90:10, v/v]. Fr. A (27.0 g) was subjected to a silica gel CC eluted with a gradient mixture of PE/EA (100:0 to 0:100, v/v), and then divided into three parts (Fr. A1 to Fr. A3). Fr. A2 (9.0 g) was chromatographed on an ODS CC using MeOH/ H 
2
O (40:60 to 100:0, v/v) as eluent to afford seven parts (Fr. A2a to Fr. A 
2g
). Compounds 
10
(
10.2 mg
, 
t
R
24.0 min), 
11
(
12.6 mg
, 
t
R
30.0 min), and 
12
(
15.5 mg
, 
t
R
36.0 min) were obtained from Fr. A2d (1.0 g) by preparative HPLC [MeOH/H 
2
O (0.1% trifluoroacetic acid (TFA)), 90:10, v/v].
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Overlapped signals are reported without designating multiplicity.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Measured in CDCl.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
3
b
Measured in C D N.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
5 5
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Spectroscopic data of compounds
</title>
         <p>
Dryatraol A (1)
: yellow oil; [
α
]25 D +43 (
c
0.1, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δε) 219 (+9.0), 291 (+34.5); UV–vis (MeOH) 
λ
max
226, 291 nm
; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3412, 2924, 2860, 1687, 1617, 1451, 1370, 1196, 1127, 
1031, 861, 805 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
427.2476 [M + H] 
+
(calculated for C 
26
H 
35
O 
5
, 427.2479).
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol B (2)
: yellow oil; [
α
]25 D 51 (
c
0.1, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δε) 212 (43.8); UV–vis (MeOH) 
λ
max
226, 291 nm
; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3477, 3366, 2929, 2865, 1616, 1441, 1367, 1261, 1169, 
1070, 879, 823 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
371.2214 [M + H] 
+
(calculated for C 
23
H 
31
O 
4
, 371.2217).
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol C (3)
: yellow oil; [
α
]25 D 47 (
c
0.1, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δε) 212 (53.2); UV–vis (MeOH) 
λ
max
229, 290 nm
; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3474, 3356, 2930, 2858, 1623, 1442, 1365, 1278, 1169, 
1074, 971, 881, 823 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
385.2370 [M + H] 
+
(calculated for C 
24
H 
33
O 
4
, 385.2373).
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol D (4)
: orange oil; [
α
]25 D +23 (
c
0.6, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δε) 207 (+28.3), 241 (13.3), 365 (+3.5); UV–vis (MeOH) 
λ
max
226, 291 nm
; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3426, 2948, 2877, 1677, 1580, 1429, 1252, 1166, 1094, 
1052, 957, 893 cm
1
. 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
375.1801 [M + H] 
+
(calculated for C 
21
H 
27
O 
6
, 375.1802).
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol E (5)
: colorless needles; [
α
]25 D +15 (
c
0.5, 
CH
3
CN); UV–vis (
CH
3
CN) 
λ
max
195, 291 nm
; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
: 3395, 2962, 2940, 1623, 1592, 1432, 1380, 1173, 1141, 
1065, 920, 879, 818 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
431.2791 [M + H] 
+
(calculate for C 
26
H 
39
O 
5
, 431.2792).
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol F
(
6
): violet gum; [
α
]25 D +37 (
c
0.2, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δε) 228 (+25.3); UV–vis (MeOH) 
λ
max
225, 242, 274, 327 nm
; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3513, 3460, 2971, 2933, 2877, 1659, 1617, 1527, 1458, 1379, 1194, 
1062, 943, 881 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
445.2939 [M + H] 
+
(calculate for C 
27
H 
41
O 
5
, 445.2949).
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol G (7)
: yellow gum; [
α
]25 D +28 (
c
1.0, 
CH
3
CN); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δε) 228 (+21.3); UV–vis (
CH
3
CN) 
λ
max
: 
194, 223, 245, 273, 330 nm
; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
: 3389, 2962, 2939, 1620, 1592, 1429, 1383, 1170, 1147, 
1065, 990, 929, 813 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
431.2784 [M + H] 
+
(calculate for C 
26
H 
39
O 
5
, 431.2792).
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol H (8)
: violet gum; [
α
]25 D +25 (
c
0.2, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δε) 228 (+19.3); UV–vis (MeOH) 
λ
max
225, 241, 273, 326 nm
; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3460, 2967, 2933, 2879, 1659, 1619, 1532, 1464, 1378, 1267, 1193, 1145, 
1059, 993, 838 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
459.3096 [M + H] 
+
(calculate for C 
28
H 
43
O 
5
, 459.3105).
</p>
         <p>
Dryatraol I (9)
: white amorphous powder; [
α
]25 D[
α
]25 D +18 (
c
0.2, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δε) 236 (+3.3), 270 (+2.3), 335 (+2.2); UV–vis (MeOH) 
λ
max
220, 242, 311 nm
; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3516, 3439, 2969, 2933, 2879, 1657, 1617, 1522, 1459, 1378, 1191, 1147, 
1062, 988, 942, 876 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
459.3100 [M + H] 
+
(calculate for C 
28
H 
43
O 
5
, 459.3105).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
IC is the concentration of compound that reduced 50% CPE as compared with control cells infected with virus and data were expressed as mean (n = 3).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
50
b
CC is the concentration of compound with half maximal inhibition on the growth and survival of host cells.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
50
c
Selectivity index (SI) = CC /IC.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
50 50
d
The positive controls.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
e
Not active at the tested concentration.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. X-ray crystallographic analysis
</title>
         <p>
Crystallographic data of dryatraol E. Colorless needles, C 
26
H 
38
O 
5
(
M
= 
430.56 g
/mol), orthorhombic, space group P212121 (no. 19), 
a
= 9.1424 (1) Å, 
b
= 14.1834 (2) Å, 
c
= 18.0517 (2) Å, 
V
= 2340.77 (5) Å 
3
, 
Z
= 4, μ (Cu Kα) = 
0.663 mm
1
, 
D
calc
= 
1.2217 g
/cm 
3
, 19,672 reflections measured (7.92 
◦
≤ 2θ ≤ 148.36 
◦
), 4608 unique (
R
int
= 0.0498, 
R
sigma
= 0.0381) which were used in all calculations. The final 

R 
1

was 0.0455 (4320) and wR 
2
was 0.1193 (4608), Flack parameter: 0.00 (16). Crystallographic data for the structure has been deposited with the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Center as CCDC 1903935.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. ECD calculations
</title>
         <p>
Conformational analysis of compounds 
1
, 
2a
, 
4
and 
6a
were carried out via random searching in SYBYL 8.1 program by using the MMFF94S force field with an energy cutoff of 10.0 kcal mol 
1
. Subsequently, the conformers were further optimized using DFT at the B3LYP/6-31 + G(d) level by using Gaussian09 software (Frisch et al., 2009). The ECD spectra were computed by DFT calculations at the same level of theory with UV correction, and produced by SpecDis 1.6 software (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. In vitro anti-viral assay
</title>
         <p>
The isolated compounds were evaluated for their antiviral activities 
in vitro
against RSV, HSV-1 and H1N1 by using the CPE reduction assay. The details, including the time-of-addition assay of dryatraol G against HSV-1, were described in Supplementary data.
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Data availability
</p>
         <p>Data will be made available on request.</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgement
</p>
         <p>
This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(Nos. 82173695, 82003609, 82003743, 82104015), the 
Guangdong
Basic and Applied Basic Research Foundation (Nos. 2020A1515110453, 2020A1515110415), 
China
Postdoctoral Science Foundations (Nos. 2019M663403, 2021M691261), Foshan Science and Technology Burea (No. FS0AA-KJ218-1301-0013), and the high performance public computing service platform of Jinan University.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2023.113585.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Boland, D.J.
, 
Brophy, J.J.
, 
Fookes, C.J.
, 
1992
. 

Jensenone, a ketone from 
Eucalyptus jen

. 
Phytochemistry
31
, 
2178–2179
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(92)80396-V
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Boti, J.B.
, 
Koukoua, G.
, N’ 
Guessan, T.Y.
, 
Muselli, A.
, 
Bernardini, A.F.
, 
Casanova, J.
, 
2005
. 

Composition of the leaf, stem bark and root bark oils of 
Isolona cooperi
investigated by GC (retention index), GC-MS and 13 C-NMR spectroscopy
.Phytochem

. Anal. 
16
, 
357–363
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/pca.857
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bruhn, T.
, Schaumloffel ¨, A., 
Hemberger, Y.
, 
Bringmann, G.
, 
2012
. 
SpecDis Version 1.60
. 
University of Wuerzburg, Germany
, 2012.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cao, J.Q.
, 
Tian, H.Y.
, 
Li, M.M.
, 
Zhang, W.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
Wang, L.
, 
Ye, W.C.
, 
2018
. 

Rearranged phloroglucinol-monoterpenoid adducts from 
Callistemon rigidus

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
81
, 
57–62
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.7b00606
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, N.H.
, 
Wu, Z.N.
, 
Li, W.
, 
Li, Y.Y.
, 
Luo, D.
, 
Chen, L.F.
, 
Zhang, X.L.
, 
Zhang, Y.B.
, 
Wang, G.C.
, 
Li, Y.L.
, 
2020
. 

Acylphloroglucinols-based meroterpenoid enantiomers with antiviral activities from 
Dryopteris crassirhizoma

. 
Ind. Crop. Prod.
150
, 
112415
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2020.112415
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, N.H.
, 
Zhang, Y.B.
, 
Huang, X.J.
, 
Jiang, L.
, 
Jiang, S.Q.
, 
Li, G.Q.
, 
Li, Y.L.
, 
Wang, G.C.
, 
2016
. 

Drychampones A-C: three meroterpenoids from 
Dryopteris championii

. 
J. Org. Chem.
81
, 
9443–9448
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.joc.6b01720
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dewick, P.M.
, 
2009
. 
Medicinal Natural Products: A Biosynthetic Approach, 3rd et
. 
John Wiley &amp; Sons, td., New York
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Editorial Committee of Flora of China
, 
2000
. 
Flora of China
. 
Science Press, Beijing, China
, p. 
123
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Editorial Committee of Zhonghua Bencao
, 
1999
. 
Zhonghua Bencao
. 
Shanghai Science and Technology Press, Shanghai, China
, p. 
198
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frisch, M.J
., 
Trucks, G.W
., 
Schlegel, H.B
., 
Scuseria, G.E
., 
Robb, M.A
., 
Cheeseman, J.R
., 
Scalmani, G
., 
Barone, V
., 
Mennucci, B
., 
Petersson, G.A
., 
Nakatsuji, H
., 
Caricato, M
., 
Li, X
., 
Hratchian, H.P
., 
Izmaylov, A.F
., 
Bloino, J
., 
Zheng, G
., 
Sonnenberg, J.L
., 
Hada, M
., 
Ehara, M
., 
Toyota, K
., 
Fukuda, R
., 
Hasegawa, J
., 
Ishida, M
., 
Nakajima, T
., 
Honda, Y
., 
Kitao, O
., 
Nakai, H
., 
Vreven, T
., 
Montgomery, J.A
., 
Peralta, J.E
., 
Ogliaro, F
., 
Bearpark, M
., 
Heyd, J.J
., 
Brothers, E
., 
Kudin, K.N
., 

Staroverov, 

V.N


., 
Kobayashi, R
., 
Normand, J
., 
Raghavachari, K
., 
Rendel, A
., 
Burant, J.C
., 
Iyengar, S.S
., 
Tomasi, J
., 
Cossi, M
., 
Rega, N
., 
Millam, J.M
., 
Klene, M
., 
Knox, J.E
., 
Cross, J.B
., 
Bakken, V
., 
Adamo, C
., 
Jaramillo, J
., 
Gomperts, R
., 
Stratmann, R.E
., 
Yazyev, O
., 
Austin, A.J
., 
Cammi, R
., 
Pomelli, C
., 
Ochterski, J.W
., 
Martin, R.L
., 
Morokuma, K
., 
Zakrzewski, V.G
., 
Voth, G.A
., 

Salvador
, P

., 
Dannenberg, J.J
., 
Dapprich, S.
, 
Daniels, A.D.
, 
Farkas, O.
, 
Foresman, J.B.
, 
Ortiz, J.V.
, 
Cioslowski, J.
, 
Fox, D.J.
, 
2009
. 
Gaussian 09, Revision B.01
. 
Gaussian, Inc
.
, Wallingford, CT
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hai, P.
, 
Rao, K.P.
, 
Jiang, N.
, 
Liu, D.
, 
Wang, R.R.
, 
Gao, Y.
, 
Liu, X.C.
, 
Deng, S.H.
, 
Zhou, Y.
, 
Chen, X.Q.
, 
Li, X.N.
, 
Li, R.T.
, 
2021
. 

Structure elucidation, biogenesis, and bioactivities of acylphloroglucinol-derived meroterpenoid enantiomers from 
Dryopteris crassirhizoma

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
119
, 
105567
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. bioorg.2021.105567
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Han, X.
, 
Li, Z.
, 
Li, C.Y.
, 
Jia, W.N.
, 
Wang, H.T.
, 
Wang, C.H.
, 
2015
. 

Phytochemical constituents and biological activities of plants from the genus 
Dryopteris

. 
Chem. Biodivers.
12
, 
1131–1162
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/cbdv.201400157
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hirota, H.
, 
Tomono, Y.
, 
Fusetani, N.
, 
1996
. 

Terpenoids with antifouling activity against barnacle larvae from the marine sponge 
Acanthella cavernosa

. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
52
, 
2359–2368
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0040-4020(95)01079-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hou, B.
, 
Zhang, Y.M.
, 
Liao, H.Y.
, 
Fu, L.F.
, 
Li, D.D.
, 
Zhao, X.
, 
Qi, J.X.
, 
Yang, W.
, 
Xiao, G.F.
, 
Yang, L.
, 
Zuo, Z.Y.
, 
Wang, L.
, 
Zhang, X.L.
, 
Bai, F.
, 
Yang, L.
, 
Gao, G.F.
, 
Song, H.
, 
Hu, J. M.
, 
Shang, W.J.
, 
Zhou, J.
, 
2022
. 
Target-based virtual screening and LC/MS-guided isolation procedure for identifying phloroglucinol-terpenoid Inhibitors of SARS-CoV-2
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
85
, 
327–336
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.1c00805
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hu, L.Z.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Zhu, H.C.
, 
Liu, J.J.
, 
Li, H.
, 
Li, X.N.
, 
Sun, W.G.
, 
Zeng, J.F.
, 
Xue, Y.B.
, 
Zhang, Y.H.
, 
2016
. 

Filicinic acid based meroterpenoids with anti-epstein-barr virus activities from 
Hypericum japonicum

. 
Org. Lett.
18
, 
2272–2275
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.orglett.6b00906
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lee, H.B.
, 
Kim, J.C.
, 
Lee, S.M.
, 
2009
. 

Antibacterial activity of two phloroglucinols, flavaspidic acids AB and PB, from 
Dryopteris crassirhizoma

. 
Arch Pharm. Res. (Seoul)
32
, 
655–659
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s12272-009-1502-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lee, S.M.
, 
Na, M.K.
, 
An, R.
Bo
, 
Min, B.S.
, 
Lee, H.K.
, 
2003
. 

Antioxidant activity of two phloroglucinol derivatives from 
Dryopteris crassirhizoma

. 
Biol. Pharm. Bull.
26
, 
1354–1356
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/bpb.26.1354
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Magalhaes, L.G.
, 
Kapadia, G.J.
, 
Da Silva Tonuci, L.R.
, 
Caixeta, S.C.
, 
Parreira, N.A.
, 
Rodrigues, V.
, 
Da Silva Filho, A.A.
, 
2010
. 

In 
vitro
schistosomicidal effects of some phloroglucinol derivatives from 
Dryopteris
species against 
Schistosoma mansoni
adult worms

. 
Parasitol. Res.
106
, 
395–401
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00436-009-1674-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mustafa, K.A.
, 
Kjaergaard, H.G.
, 
Perry, N.B.
, 
Weavers, R.T.
, 
2003
. 

Hydrogen-bonded rotamers of 2 
′
,4 
′
,6 
′
-trihydroxy-3 
′
-formyldihydrochalcone, an intermediate in the synthesis of a dihydrochalcone from 
Leptospermum recurvum

. 
Tetrahedron
59
, 
6113–6120
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Phong, N.V.
, 
Oanh, V.T.
, 
Yang, S.Y.
, 
Choi, J.S.
, 
Min, B.S.
, 
Kim, J.A.
, 
2021
. 

PTP1B inhibition studies of biological active phloroglucinols from the rhizomes of 
Dryopteris crassirhizoma
: kinetic properties and molecular docking simulation

. 
Int. J. Biol. Macromol.
188
, 
719–728
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Qin, X.J.
, 
Jin, L.Y.
, 
Yu, Q.
, 
Liu, H.
, 
Khan, A.
, 
Yan, H.
, 
Hao, X.J.
, 
An, L.K.
, 
Liu, H.Y.
, 
2018
. 

Eucalypglobulusals A-J, formyl-phloroglucinol-terpene meroterpenoids from 
Eucalyptus globulus
fruits

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
81
, 
2638–2646
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. jnatprod.8b00430
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ryu, B.
, 
Cho, H.M.
, 
Zhang, M.
, 
Lee, B.W.
, 
Doan, T.P.
, 
Park, E.J.
, 
Lee, H.J.
, 
Oh, W.K.
, 
2021
. 

Meroterpenoids from the leaves of 
Psidium guajava
(guava) cultivated in Korea using MS/MS-based molecular networking

. 
Phytochemistry
186
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Socolsky, C.
, 
Dominguez, L.
, 
Asakawa, Y.
, 
Bardon, A.
, 
2012
. 

Unusual terpenylated acylphloroglucinols from 
Dryopteris wallichiana

. 
Phytochemistry
80
, 
115–122
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sun, Y.
, 
Gao, C.
, 
Luo, M.
, 
Wang, W.
, 
Gu, C.B.
, 
Zu, Y.G.
, 
Li, J.
, 
Efferth, T.
, 
Fu, Y.J.
, 
2013
. 
Aspidin PB, a phloroglucinol derivative, induces apoptosis in human hepatocarcinoma HepG2 cells by modulating PI3K/Akt/GSK3β pathway
. 
Chem. Biol. Interact.
201
, 
1–8
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cbi.2012.11.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vidari, G.
, 
Che, Z.L.
, 
Garlaschelli, L.
, 
1998
. 

New nardosinane and aristolane sesquiterpenes from the fruiting bodies of 
Russula lepida

. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
39
, 
6073–6076
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040-4039(98)01251-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yang, Q.
, 
Gao, L.
, 
Si, J.Y.
, 
Sun, Y.P.
, 
Liu, J.H.
, 
Cao, L.
, 
Feng, W.H.
, 
2013
. 
Inhibition of porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus replication by flavaspidic acid AB
. 
Antivir. Res.
97
, 
66–73
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2012.11.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
