<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113013</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Agrocinopine C, a Ti-plasmid-coded enzyme-product, is a 2-O, 6-O linked phosphodiester of D-Glucose and sucrose</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium radiobacter
(Beijerinck and van Delden) Conn
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rhizobiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. tumefaciens
(Smith and Townsend) Conn
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form that</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhizobium rhizogenes
(Riker et al.) Young et al.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rhizobiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhizobium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. tumefaciens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Agrocinopine C, a Ti-plasmid-coded enzyme-product, is a 2-O, 6-O linked phosphodiester of D-Glucose and sucrose
☆
</p>
         <p>
Robert E. Asenstorfer, Maarten H. Ryder
*
, Graham P. Jones
</p>
         <p>
School of Agriculture
, Food and 
Wine, University of Adelaide, Waite Research Institute
, PMB 1, 
Glen Osmond
, 
South Australia
, 5064, 
Australia
</p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>Ti plasmid</p>
         <p>Plant biochemistry</p>
         <p>Sugar transport</p>
         <p>Crown gall</p>
         <p>Agrocinopine</p>
         <p>Sucrose phospho-diester</p>
         <p>Permease induction</p>
         <p>Acyclic aldehyde-anomers</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Agrocinopine C is a small molecule found in crown gall tumours induced by pathogenic 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
carrying the tumour-inducing plasmid pTi Bo542. This phosphodiester opine was isolated (at 
0.02 g
/ 
100 g
fresh wt.) from sunflower (
<tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
L.) galls. It is structurally related to agrocinopine A and is a glucose-2- phosphodiester linked to the C6-hydroxy-methyl group of the glucose moiety of sucrose. Sugar-2-phosphates are uncommon in plant tissues, whether transformed by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
or not. 
1
H and 
31
P NMR signal multiplicity indicates five-fold anomeric complexity of agrocinopine C in solution, implying that the permeases taking up these sucrose-phosphodiesters could recognise any one of the five anomers. Data suggests that the open chain aldehyde forms of the 2-phosphorylated opines agrocinopine C and agrocinopine A and the corresponding phosphorylated glucose-2-phosphoramidate component of the antibiotic agrocin 84 play a central role in agrocin’ s selective toxicity to certain strains of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
after uptake via Ti plasmid-encoded permeases.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Formulation of the “opine” concept (

) made the fundamental connection between a particular agrobacterial Ti plasmid and the genes encoded on the T-DNA portion that is inserted into the plant genome. Most of the known opines such as octopine, nopaline, leucinopine, mannopine etc. are secondary amines, formed by the reductive conjugation of either the carbonyl of an α- keto acid (or a reducing sugar aldehyde) condensation product with the α- amino group of an L-amino acid. They were isolated individually from tumours incited by various pathogenic strains of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium radiobacter
(Beijerinck and van Delden) Conn
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Rhizobiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
(formerly 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tumefaciens
(Smith and Townsend) Conn
</tp:taxon-name>
). Thus the “opine” concept led to the realisation that by “engineering” the plant’ s metabolic activities, the bacterium forces the plant to provide nitrogen in a 
<tp:taxon-name>form that</tp:taxon-name>
only the bacterium can catabolise. Considerations by 

predicted and confirmed that other opines must exist in plant tumours and two different carbohydrate phospho-diesters, agrocinopine A and agrocinopine C, were discovered, each one providing both a phosphorus source and an energy source (carbohydrate) for the tumour-inciting bacteria. The complete structure of agrocinopine A was published by 

and an Honours degree project on agrocinopine C was submitted by the late Anna E. Savage (A.E.S.; 

). The discovery of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
-derived T-DNA genes in the genomes of all 291 cultivated sweet potato accessions tested, including a gene showing significant similarity to a Ti-plasmid encoded agrocinopine synthase gene (
acs
; 

) prompted us to re-examine A.E.S’ s original 1983 agrocinopine C sample using current mass spectrometry and NMR techniques and facilities.
</p>
         <p>
Recent work has provided insight into the close link between the active uptake of agrocinopines into tumour inducing strains of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
, via specific transporters, and the “Trojan horse” uptake of the structurally-related, naturally occurring fraudulent adenine-dinucleotide bacteriocin, agrocin 84 (

; 

; 

). Agrocin 84 is produced by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhizobium rhizogenes
(Riker et al.) Young et al.
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Rhizobiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
(formerly 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
biovar 2) strain K84 and its derivative strain K1026 (

) and belongs to an emerging class of antibiotics termed amino acyl tRNA inhibitors (

; 

; Travin et al., 2021). The production of agrocin 84 by 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
strain K1026 also plays a vital role in the commercial biological control of the economically important crown gall disease of plants including stone fruits and roses (

).
</p>
         <p>
We now report the structure of agrocinopine C which is related to, but nevertheless somewhat different from the sucrose phosphodiester structure of agrocinopine A (

). Agrocinopine A is a phospho-diester of sucrose linked from the C4-hydroxyl of the fructo-furanosyl moiety to the C2-hydroxyl of L-arabinose. Agrocinopine B is also a phosphodiester and was obtained from agrocinopine A by acid cleavage of the glucose moiety from the sucrose moiety. The original agrocinopine A structure (

) was initially disputed by 

but later confirmed by Messens et al. (1986), albeit with two mis-attribution errors in key references. In the same context, it should be noted that although agrocinopines each contain three sugar moieties, only the two in sucrose are linked by a glycosidic bond and consequently the agrocinopines A and C should not be referred to as tri-saccharides. Ultimately, the original structure (

) for the L-arabinosyl-phosphodiester of sucrose was unequivocally confirmed by synthesis and shown to be identical in all respects with the natural product agrocinopine A by 

and 

, including its biological activity.
</p>
         <p>
☆
This paper is dedicated to the memory of Anna E. Savage (dec’ d 1997) and Max E. Tate (dec’ d 2016) and is based on their and Maarten Ryder’ s initial studies. * Corresponding author.
</p>
         <p>
E-mail address:
maarten.ryder@adelaide.edu.au (M.H. Ryder).
</p>
         <p>
The critical molecular feature determining the specific, active uptake of agrocin 84 and agrocinopines via agrocinopine transporters appears to be a sugar 2-phosphate (

; 

; 

). An additional reason for publishing the structure of agrocinopine C at this time is that recent papers (

; 

; 

) have cited and presented incorrect structures for this molecule based on the previous synthesis of an incorrect version (

). It was apparent that Tate for some time considered that the compound D-glucos-2-yl sucros-2-yl phosphate, synthesised by 

, was the correct structure for agrocinopine C as per Tate’ s correspondence with Lindberg and Norberg in 1990 and later with 

. However, it is now clear that the original structure determined by Savage and Tate (

) was correct and modern NMR spectroscopic methods have confirmed this.
</p>
         <p>
The purpose of the current paper is to provide evidence for the structure of agrocinopine C present in plant tumours incited by pathogenic 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
which carry the Ti-plasmid pTiBo542, and to emphasise the hitherto unrecognised complexity of the anomeric equilibria for solutions of agrocinopines A and C in addition to the corresponding anomeric complexity in solutions of the structurally-related, naturally occurring fraudulent adenine-dinucleotide bacteriocin, agrocin 84.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. High resolution mass spectrometry
</title>
         <p>
The agrocinopine C negative ion (M-H) gave an observed mass 
583.1275 m
/z (
Fig. 1
), the calculated mass for the M-H formula: C 
18
H 
32
O 
19
P is 583.1281. The ionisation pattern, 
m/z
(relative intensity; ion), gave 583.1275 (b.p.; M-H 
+
) 
-
, 421.0740 (0.37; M-H 
+
-glucose) 
-
, 353.2107 (0.09; M-H 
+
-229.9168) 
-
, 283.2625 (0.13; M-H 
+
-229.8650) 
-
, 255.2318 (0.25; M-H 
+
-327.8957) 
-
, 112.9852 (0.54; H 
2
PO 
5
) 
-
, 96.9602 (0.13; H 
2
PO 
4
) 
-
. The ion at m/z 421.0740 indicated a loss of glucose, peaks at 353.21, 283.26 and 
255.23 m
/z suggested fragmentation of the remaining sucrose-phosphate moiety, while the peak 
96.6 m
/z was consistent with dihydrogen phosphate.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Infrared spectrum
</title>
         <p>
IR (diffuse reflectance; 
Fig. 2
): 
ν
= 3402 (OH, stretch), 2929 (
CH
2
asymmetric vibration), 2863 (
CH
2
symmetric vibration), 1623 (OH deformation, 1412 (
CH
bending), 1353 (P––O), 1101 (OH–P––O), 1035 (C–O, C–C vibration), 847 (
CH
deformation), 812 (
CH
deformation), 683, 618 (
CH
2
), 
592 cm
1
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. pH mobility profile
</title>
         <p>
Fig. 3 shows the characteristically linear pH mobility profiles for the phosphodiesters agrocinopines C and D and a two-step dissociation profile for the ribose 5-phosphate monoester control. The biological activity of agrocinopine C following electrophoretic separation and further purification steps was detected in the plate bioassay (Fig. 4) developed by 

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.4. Agrocinopine C component moiety ratios
</title>
         <p>
Total phosphorus estimated by the method of 

gave 0.64 μMoles/mg. Total hexose estimated by the phenol-sulphuric acid method (

) yielded 1.96 μMoles/mg, and the total D-glucose determined by the glucose oxidase assay gave 1.2 μMoles/mg. These data provided mole ratios of 1:3.06:1.87, i.e. integer values approximating to 1:3:2.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.5. Alkaline degradation
</title>
         <p>
Ammonolysis products (1.5 M NH 
4
OH/110 
◦
C/40min, sealed tube) separated by electrophoresis at pH 1.7 (formic/acetic buffer) yielded neutral sugars (
RmOG
0.0), unresolved D-glucose mono-phosphates (
RmOG
0.61) and inorganic phosphate (
RmOG
0.53).
</p>
         <p>
Ammonium borate (0.2 M) electrophoresis (pH 9.2) of the ammonolysis neutral sugar (pH 1.7) fraction showed the presence of glucose (
RmOG
0.91) and sucrose (
RmOG
0.09). Electrophoretic separation of the glucose phosphates ex ammonolysis indicated the presence of unresolved cyclic glucose 1,2- and 2,3-phosphates (
RmOG
0.81), glucose 1- phosphate (
RmOG
0.97), glucose 2-phosphate (
RmOG
1.11) and glucose 3-phosphate (
RmOG
1.27). Alkaline phosphatase (E.C. 3.1.3.1) treatment (32 
◦
C/2 h) converted all glucose phosphates to D-glucose (
RmOG
0.83) and inorganic phosphate. Treatment of the glucose (32 
◦
C/1 h) with glucose oxidase (E.C. 1.1.3.4) smoothly converted it quantitatively to Dgluconate (
RmOG
1.07).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.6. Borohydride reduction of agrocinopine C
</title>
         <p>
Addition of a slight excess of sodium borohydride (NaBH 
4
, 0.6 mol per mole of aqueous agrocinopine C) produced a compound (
RmOG
0.55, pH 1.7) that was no longer positive to the 
p
-anisidine reagent for reducing sugars (

). Ammonolysis (1.5 M NH 
4
OH) followed by alkaline phosphatase (EC 3.1.3.1) treatment yielded a non-reducing polyol (
RmOG
0.94; 0.2 M ammonium borate buffer pH 9.2), which was indistinguishable from D-glucitol (
RmOG
0.94). Electrophoresis of this polyol in a lanthanum trinitrate buffer (0.2 M in 0.75 M formic acid/1 M acetic acid) produced a cationic (lanthanum-complex) polyol spot (
RmOG
0.71) indistinguishable from a reference sample of D-glucitol (
RmOG
0.71).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.7. Acid degradation
</title>
         <p>
Brief acid hydrolysis (1 M acetic acid/15min/110 
◦
C) produced 4 distinct components (A, B, C and D), when examined by paper electrophoresis at pH 1.7 (

). Component A (
RmOG
0.57) had the same relative mobility and biological activity as agrocinopine D and also no longer reacted positively to the ketose sugar reagent of urea/phosphoric acid (

). The remaining components, B, C, D, were not formally identified.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.8. NMR data for agrocinopine C
</title>
         <p>
At the time of the original isolation (by A.E.S, 1983) the complexity of the isomeric proton NMR data due to the available instrumentation was not interpreted, nevertheless the greater resolution of the proton decoupled 
13
C NMR data provided good support for the proposed structure for agrocinopine C based around the observed degradation data (

). Recent 
13
C NMR data obtained using the HSQC protocol agreed well with the data collected in 1983 and has permitted detailed and improved assignments (
Table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Proton NMR (estimated purity 76.2%) exhibited ten methylene signals (
4.070
–3.324
ppm), four methine (
3.519
–3.704
ppm) and major signals for two anomeric protons 5.269 ppm and 5.271 ppm, glucose-2- phosphate and the glucose unit of sucrose respectively (
Table 1
, 
Figs. S1–S
3
). The glucose-2-phosphate anomeric proton had four signals indicating the presence of the α- pyranosyl, β- pyranosyl, α- furanosyl and β- furanosyl anomers (
Table 2
). Two signals observed in the HSQC (
Fig. S4
) for glucose-2-phosphate g5 proton, 3.706 ppm and 3.714 ppm, confirm the presence of the pyranosyl and furanosyl anomers. Similarly, two pairs of signals observed for the g2 and g3 protons were associated with the pyranosyl and furanosyl anomers.
</p>
         <p>
Coupling constants of the methylene glucose protons g2 (pyrano, 4.066 ppm/furano, 4.070 ppm) and g3 (3.928 ppm) were 8.9 Hz, 8.5 Hz, respectively. Both shifts and coupling constants were clearly influenced by the presence of phosphate when compared with the 
1
H NMR of glucose (MestReNova, 2014). The non-phosphorylated glucose g2 proton had a shift of 3.233 ppm (double-doublet) while the g3 had shift of 3.728 which was not resolved from the g6 protons. The glucose unit of sucrose methylene proton sg5 (3.441 ppm) had three coupling constants (j =0.9, 3.9, 10.0 Hz) consistent with coupling with the sg6 protons as well as long range coupling with the phosphate. Coupling constants of the methine protons sg6 (3.995 ppm) (dd; j =3.3; 5.5 Hz) also indicated coupling with the phosphate. Expected doublets for the anomeric protons g1 and sg1 (5.269 ppm and 5.271 ppm) were not resolved.
</p>
         <p>
The initial carbon spectrum, obtained by Tate and 

indicated carbons sg6c (63.5 ppm, 
2
Jpoc
3.06) g3, (77.55 ppm 
3
Jpocc
6.1), g2c (82.0, 
2
Jpoc
1.88) and g1 (98.1, 
3
Jpocc
0.87) were coupled with the phosphate. Subsequent two-dimensional NMR agrees with the initial carbon assignments except that sf1 and sf6 are reversed (
Figs. S4
and S 
5
). There was satisfactory agreement of 
13
C NMR with literature data for sucrose (

), glucose 2-phosphate (

) and the Mnova Prediction Software (MestReNova, 2014).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Protons at 4.070 ppm (j =8.9 Hz) and 3.995 ppm (j = 3.3, 5.0 Hz) were coupled with phosphate. The 
31
P NMR (estimated purity 85.4%) indicates the presence of both pyranosyl (3.241 ppm) and furanosyl anomers (2.80 ppm) with no splitting of the individual anomers (
Fig. 5
). The aldehyde/gemdiol, which cannot be differentiated, can be observed at 4.029 ppm. 
1
H – 
31
P gHMBC confirmed that only these three phosphate signals were associated with agrocinopine C (
Fig. S6
). These three signals collapsed into a single peak when the glucose-2- phosphate was reduced by sodium borohydride to give glucitol-2- phosphate (1.55 ppm) which only has a single anomer (
Fig. 5
).
</p>
         <p>
3. Discussion
</p>
         <p>
The high-resolution mass spectrum for the agrocinopine C sample provided an elemental M-H anion composition (C 
18
H 
32
O 
19
P) which corresponds to that for a phospho-diester linking sucrose to a hexose instead of the pentose (L-arabinose) observed for agrocinopine A (

). An erroneous preliminary structure for agrocinopine C based on an 
in vitro
synthesis was reported by 

and subsequently in a review by 

, and this must be corrected. In agrocinopine C, D-glucose-2-phosphate is linked to the 6-hydroxymethyl carbon of the glucopyranosyl moiety of sucrose (
Fig. 6
) and consequently it is the fructosyl moiety which is lost by brief acid hydrolysis of the labile sucrose C1α- linkage of glucose to C2α- fructose to yield agrocinopine D. In contrast, agrocinopine A has L-arabinose-2-phosphate linked to the C4-hydroxyl of the fructo-furanosyl moiety of sucrose and it is glucose that is lost by brief acid hydrolysis (yielding agrocinopine B).
</p>
         <p>
Lindberg and co-workers made two attempts at synthesising agrocinopine C: D-glucos-2-yl sucros-6-yl phosphate and D-glucos-2-yl sucros-2-yl phosphate (

; 

). Their attempted synthesis of D-glucos-2-yl sucros-6-yl phosphate (

) should have yielded a product identical to agrocinopine C, but a phosphate coupling (
2
Jpoc
4.6 Hz) to a carbon at 95.8 ppm indicates that coupling was to carbon 1 rather than carbon 2. Furthermore, acid degradation of this synthetic product yielded glucose-1-phosphate which is consistent with synthesis of D-glucos-1-yl sucros-6-yl phosphate. The synthetic compound (

) was biologically active, but this does not unequivocally prove identity with the structure of the natural product agrocinopine C, rather that a particular feature of the molecule required for uptake recognition has sufficient similarity to the natural product. A subsequent paper describing a revised synthesis of agrocinopine C, in this case referred to as “agrocinopin C” (

), has a sucros-2-yl phosphate linkage which is in error. Although Tate clearly considered for some time that the structure of the 

synthetic product was correct, it is important that the structure of the natural compound is now corrected, as several recent publications that either refer to or are based on 

have the incorrect linkage of the sucrosyl moiety for the structure of agrocinopines C and D (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
a
22.5 MHz (JEOL FX90Q).
</p>
         <p>
b
HSQC.
</p>
         <p>
c
HMBC (600 MHz Varian).
</p>
         <p>
d
NOESY coupling between Hsg2 and Hsf1.
</p>
         <p>
e
HMBC 
31
P, phosphate at 2.80 ppm is coupled to protons at 4.070 ppm and 3.996 ppm.
</p>
         <p>
f
see
</p>
         <p>Table 2 for anomers.</p>
         <p>It is remarkable that two quite different Ti plasmids (the Bo542 agropine and the T37 nopaline plasmid) contain biosynthetic genes on their T-DNAs for two related phospho-diesters of sucrose. The close structural relationship of the glucose-2-phosphoramidate motif of agrocin 84 (Fig. S7) to the glucose-2-phosphodiester of agrocinopine C is evident.</p>
         <p>

provided clear 
32
P evidence for enhanced uptake of agrocin 84 by the nopaline strain 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
K57A, after pre-incubation for 4 h with agrocinopine A. In the absence of pre-incubation, agrocinopine A also completely blocked the normal uptake of agrocin 84 by the pathogen K57A, thereby demonstrating that they both entered the cell by the same uptake mechanism. By contrast with the nopaline strain K57A, there was no uptake of agrocin 84 whatsoever in the absence of agrocinopine C by the agropine strain A281. However, pre-incubation of strain A281 for 6 h with a similar concentration of agrocinopine C allowed subsequent uptake of agrocin 84, leading to the toxic effect seen in 
Fig. 4
. It is apparent that the transport system for uptake of agrocinopine C is normally repressed but is induced when this opine is present. The tumour-inducing plasmid pTiBo542 contains an operon which is homologous to the 
acc
operon of the agrocinopine A-encoding plasmid pTiC58 (

; 

). The 
acc
operon of pTiC58 codes for an ABC-type uptake system (genes 
accA
to 
accE
) and for catabolism of agrocinopine A via genes 
accF
and 
accG
(

). It is evident that the 
acc
operon of pTiBo542 encodes similar functions that enable the uptake and catabolism of agrocinopine C as well as the uptake of agrocin 84. The repressors coded for by the 
accR
genes on pTiC58 and pTiBo542 function differently in that the 
acc
operon on pTi58 (agrocinopine A) is normally partially expressed, whereas it is not expressed on pTiBo542 until agrocinopine C is present. This accounts for the difference between 
Fig. 4
and 

in agrocin 84/agrocinopine bioassay result, an effect first reported by 

.
</p>
         <p>
From a structural perspective, it is of interest to consider which part of the agrocinopine molecules might be recognized by the related periplasmic binding proteins (

) that mediate their uptake, and also for the uptake of agrocin 84, as distinct from the quite different (P–O and P–N) phosphoryl-cleavage sites required to release the sucrose as an essential nutrient in the case of the agrocinopines C and A. The latter process also releases the biologically active mono-nucleotide (

), later referred to as the “Toxic Moiety, TM84” (

) from agrocin 84, which is required for the antibiosis against 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
pathogens carrying a suitable Ti plasmid. Recent studies (

; 

) have shown that sugar phosphate analogues with the appropriate 2-phosphate substitution can also be taken up via the transport mechanism encoded by the 
acc
operon. Thus it appears that it is the sugar-2-phosphate motif, where the sugar is either D-glucose (agrocinopine C) or L-arabinose (agrocinopine A), that is recognized by the uptake mechanisms coded by the 
accA
genes on the respective Ti-plasmids. The hexose-2-P motif is also mimicked by agrocin 84, allowing this “Trojan horse” molecule to be actively taken up, followed by intracellular hydrolysis to 
<tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
toxic “TM 84” (

) which acts as an inhibitor of leucyl-tRNA synthetase (

).
</p>
         <p>
In solutions of D-glucose (the hexose associated with agrocinopine C), essentially only pyranose anomers are observed, with a small amount of β- furanose (

; 

) and a very small amount (0.002%) of the aldehyde (

). However, phosphorylation at the adjacent 2-hydroxyl position markedly changes these ratios in agrocinopine C such that the glucose-2-phosphate moiety shows a considerable amount of the two furanosyl anomers (α- 6%, β- 8%) in addition to a large increase in the intermediate acyclic aldehyde and/or aldehyde hydrate isomer (10%) (
Table 2
, 
Table S1
). Similarly, in aqueous solution of L-arabinose, the sugar associated with agrocinopine A, a mixture of anomers with only a small amount of the open ring form (0.03%) was observed (

), however phosphorylation in the 2-hydroxy position greatly increased the concentration of acyclic aldehyde and/or aldehyde hydrate isomer (8%) (
Table 2
, 
Table S1
).
</p>
         <p>

emphasise a point originally made by 

that “cyclic configurations are equilibrated via the open chain configurations, aldehydes and ketones respectively”. The possibility that acyclic forms such as the aldehyde or its hydrate might be present in significant amounts in some equilibria has not been addressed in previous studies (

; Messens et al., 1986; 

). Nevertheless, the presence of aldehydic proton signals in the 
1
H NMR leave little doubt that aldehydic species contribute significantly to anomeric mixtures of sugars phosphorylated at the 2- or 6- position for the reducing sugars examined in this study.
</p>
         <p>

detected 
&lt;
0.4% of the aldehyde of D-glucose-6-phosphate in aqueous solution. Allowing for the difference in methodologies, in this study we observed a similar value for the aldehyde (0.6%) in the 
31
P NMR data for glucose-6-phosphate (
Table S1
). Because of its enhanced resolving power, 
31
P NMR signal multiplicity data appears to be a useful method to detect the presence of anomeric acyclic aldehyde and or aldehyde hydrate forms in reducing sugar phosphate solutions. However, in order to prevent 
31
P interpretation problems due to complexity associated with anomeric solution equilibria (

; 

) we suggest three approaches:
</p>
         <p>
Firstly, examine whether the 
31
P signal multiplicity is increased by slowing down the rate of anomerisation, by lowering the temperature as, for example, in the case of L-arabinose-2-phosphate (Fig. S8).
</p>
         <p>
Secondly, observe whether borohydride reduction of the acyclic carbonyl collapses the phosphorylated reducing sugar 
31
P multiplet to a polyol-phosphate singlet (
Fig. 5
, Fig. S8).
</p>
         <p>
Thirdly, two-dimensional NMR, 
1
H– 
31
P HMBC provides information regarding the correlation between closely linked protons and phosphate atoms (
Fig. S6
).
</p>
         <p>
Sodium borohydride reduction of glucose-2-phosphate to a glucitol–phosphoryl moiety in agrocinopine C removed its effect in the agrocin 84/ 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
strain K478 bioassay. Similarly, sodium borohydride reduction of agrocinopine A converted the arabinose 2- phosphoryl moiety to the corresponding L-arabinitol 2-phosphoryl moiety and this molecule no longer enhanced the diameter of the inhibition zone in an agrocin 84 bioassay overlaid with the nopaline/agrocinopine A 
type
pathogenic 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
strain A208 (

). The simplest explanation for this loss of biological activity of the agrocinopines after reduction of the aldehyde to the polyol, is that the carbonyl of the acyclic aldehyde group plays a pivotal role in binding the reducing sugar moieties to the respective periplasmic binding proteins responsible for their uptake by the pathogen. Transient condensation of the carbonyl group of the acyclic aldehyde anomers of reducing sugar species, with an α- amino group of a binding protein or the free amino group of a membrane lipid as for example phosphatidyl ethanolamine or phosphatidyl serine to form a lipophilic-complex with a weak (-C-OH. NH-) bond, enables transport into the cell. Imine formation, such as this, is favoured at pH 5 which is close to physiological pH. The toxic agrocin 84 enters the cell using the same mechanism (Fig. S7). Once inside the cell, with subsequent hydration in a different pH environment, the transiently bound phosphorylated reducing sugar is released, thereby achieving transport across a very hydrophobic lipid bilayer.
</p>
         <p>
Two non-pathogenic 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
strains, K84 and its derivative K1026, have provided world-wide protection against the plant cancer known as crown gall caused by pathogenic strains of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
on stone fruits and roses for more than four decades. Agrocin 84 production by these strains, and the uptake of this “pro-toxin” by crown gall-inciting 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhizobium
</tp:taxon-name>
is critically important to the success of biological control. On the basis of X-ray crystal structures of the periplasmic binding protein AccA, coded for by the nopaline Ti C58 plasmid, and affinity studies, 

concluded that the importation of agrocin 84 and agrocinopine A both require a pyranose-2-phosphate moiety. We also are in agreement with the necessity for a reducing sugar 2-phosphate for Ti plasmid-coded entry of the agrocinopines and agrocin 84 into the target bacterium. However, because of the loss of biological activity after reduction (

) we are not convinced that the data provided by these authors has proven beyond doubt that the most important motif is the pyranoside species and not an alternative component of the rapidly equilibrating anomeric mixture, especially the acyclic linear aldehyde and/or hydrate.
</p>
         <p>
The essential basis for the control of crown gall pathogens by 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
strains K84 and K1026 (

) is due to the entry of agrocin 84 via the same transport mechanism as agrocinopines A and C which act as nutrients for pathogen growth.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. Microorganisms
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
(formerly 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tumefaciens
</tp:taxon-name>
) strain K478, a strain which produces agrocinopine C in its tumours, is also the agrocin 84 overlay strain for detection of agrocinopine C. Strain K478 contains the pTi Bo542 plasmid from the agropine tumour-inducing strain Bo542 and is synonymous with strain A281 (Sciaky et al., 1978), which does not catabolise either octopine or nopaline. Strain K84 the producer strain for agrocin 84 is deposited with NCPPB in the 
UK
. The agrocinopine C producer strain 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
A281 (Syn K478) was generously provided by Dr Mary-Dell Chilton (University of 
Washington
, Seattle, 
Washington
, 
USA
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Isolation of agrocinopine C
</title>
         <p>
Electrophoretically homogeneous agrocinopine C was isolated from tumours induced by the pathogenic 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agrobacterium radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
strain K478 as follows. Crude agrocinopine C was obtained from crown gall tissue (
312 g
), harvested from wounded sunflower-stems that had been previously inoculated with 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. radiobacter
</tp:taxon-name>
strain K478. The macerated gall tissue was homogenised in 70% v/v ethanol and centrifuged (Sorvall RC-5B at 2310× 
g
for 15 min). The supernatant was collected and combined with three 70% ethanol washes of the pellet. The ethanol was removed by rotary evaporation 
in vacuo
, and residual water insoluble material was removed by filtration through Whatman 541 filter paper. The crude aqueous extract was loaded onto a 500 mL bed of Dowex 1X-2 Anion exchange resin (
100 g
, 
25 mm
× 
300 mm
) in the acetate form, washed with water 2.5 L, and eluted with a volatile acetate buffer (pyridine 0.2 M/acetic acid 0.1 M), ~pH 5, and 10 mL fractions were collected. Biologically active fractions (10 μL subsamples) were detected using Whatman No 1 filter paper squares placed around a centrally located 36 h-old patch culture of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. rhizogenes
</tp:taxon-name>
strain K84 on Petri plates of Stonier’ s medium (

) as producer of agrocin 84 to provide a source of this adenine nucleotide antibiotic (
Fig. 4
). The squares with aliquots of the agrocinopine C ion-exchange eluate fractions were placed on the agar which was then overlaid with the normally insensitive strain K478 and plates were incubated at 27 
◦
C for 2–3 d. Active eluate fractions (100–240) induced agrocin 84 inhibition zones as shown (
Fig. 4
). Buffer was removed from the bulk sample by evaporation 
in vacuo
at 30 
◦
C to yield a semisolid residue (
590 mg
), yield 0.19% of the fresh tumour weight. This active residue was dissolved in distilled water (300 mL), loaded onto a 500 mL bed of Dowex 1X- 
2 in
the bicarbonate form, washed with water (2 L) and eluted into fractions (10 mL) with a linear gradient (0–0.2 M) of NH 
4
HCO 
3
at pH 9.2. Biologically active material eluted in fractions 130–180 (0.05–0.1 M NH 
4
HCO 
3
), 
in vacuo
concentration at 30 
◦
C yielded a dry residue (
340 mg
, 0.11%) of the ammonium salt. This crude agrocinopine C was then eluted with water through a 50 mL Dowex 50 column in the lanthanum form. The un-retained, biologically active, agrocinopine C component eluted in fractions 2, 3 and 4 and was found to be AgNO 
3
/NaOEt reagent (

) glycol-positive, molybdate reagent phosphate-positive (

), urea/phosphoric acid reagent (

) ketose-positive, 
p
-anisidine reagent (

) hexose-positive. Its electrophoretic mobility (
RmOG
) at pH 1.7 was 0.43, and yield was 
158 mg
(0.05%). Repetitive preparative electrophoresis in the volatile formic acetic buffer (pH 1.7) with subsequent elution, neutralisation with ammonia and drying, yielded 
57.3 mg
(0.02%) of electrophoretically homogeneous agrocinopine C.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Electrophoresis
</title>
         <p>
High voltage paper electrophoresis (HVPE) was carried out according to the method of 

using Orange G, fructose, 2-deoxyadenosine and inorganic phosphate as markers. Relative mobilityvalues were estimated using the mobility of either Orange G (
RmOG
), or 2, 4-dinitrobenzene sulfonate (
RmDNBS
) with fructose as the non-migrating marker (
RmOG
0.0) except in the borate buffer where 2-deoxyadenosine was used as the non-migrating marker. In the pH range used, Orange G has formal charge 2 and 2,4-dinitrobenzene sulfonate has formal charge 1. The buffers used were 0.75 M formic acid/1.0 M acetic acid (pH 1.7) and 0.2 M ammonium borate buffer (pH 9.2). The voltage used for paper strips (15 × 
55 cm
) was 
2000 V
for 0.5 h for both buffers.
</p>
         <p>
UV absorbing species were detected on electrophoretograms using a UV lamp (
254 nm
, 
366 nm
). Non-UV absorbing products were detected by developing chromatograms in silver nitrate reagent for vicinal hydroxyl groups (

). Phosphomolybdate reagent was used for detection of phosphate (

), 
p
-anisidine for hexoses and pentoses (

), and urea phosphoric acid reagent for ketoses (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Infrared spectrum
</title>
         <p>
The mid-infrared spectrum was obtained using Spectrum One Fourier Transform Infra-Red (FTIR) spectrometer (PerkinElmer, Waltham, 
Massachusetts
, 
USA
) using a diffuse reflectance attachment (Pike Technologies, Madison, 
Wisconsin
, 
USA
. Approximately 
10 mg
of agrocinopine C was mixed with about 
90 mg
potassium chloride and loaded into the measurement cell.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Mass spectrometry
</title>
         <p>
Mass spectra were obtained using a high resolution electrospray mass spectrometer (MicroTOF-Q, Bruker Daltonics Corporation, 
USA
) operated in negative ion mode for analysis. Capillary voltage was set at 3500 V with an end plate offset potential of 500 V. Data were collected from 
50 to 1500 m
/z with an acquisition rate of 1 s. Dry gas was set to 6 L min 
1
at 200 
◦
C with a nebulization gas pressure of 2.0 bar. Samples were introduced by direct infusion.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. NMR spectroscopy
</title>
         <p>
Original 
13
C NMR spectra were recorded (
17.5 mg
in 0.5 mL D 
2
O) on a JEOL FX-90Q spectrometer. Subsequent 
1
H, 
31
P and two-dimensional (
2 mg
in 0.6 mL 20% D 
2
O) NMR data were obtained using a Varian Inova-600 spectrometer. For comparison, data was obtained for glucose-6-phosphate (Sigma Aldrich), glucose-1-phosphate (Sigma Aldrich) and arabinose-2-phosphate (synthesised by Ryder, 1984 according to the method of 

) all at a similar concentration of 
2 mg
in 0.6 mL 20% D 
2
O. The 
31
P NMR was measured relative to H 
3
PO 
4
.
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
The authors thank Prof Allen Kerr for helpful discussions. A.E.S was the recipient of the R.K. Morton and J.R. Barker scholarships. M.E.T. has funded the completion of this work via the University of Adelaide Alumni Society. NMR data was obtained originally for A.E.S. on a Jeol FX90Q instrument by G.P.J. More recent data was obtained by Phil Clements on a Varian 600 MHz instrument at the University of Adelaide, North Terrace Campus. High resolution MS data was obtained by Jeremy Hack on a Bruker-Daltronics micrOTOF-Q instrument at Metabolomics 
Australia
located within the Australian Wine Research Institute, Urrbrae, 
South Australia
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113013.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Angyal, S.J.
, 
1991
. 
The composition of reducing sugars in solution
. 
Adv. Carbohydr. Chem. Biochem.
49
, 
19–35
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Angyal, S.J.
, 
Pickles, V.A.
, 
1972
. 
Equilibria between pyranoses and furanoses. II
. 
Aldoses. Aust. J. Chem.
25
, 
1695–1710
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Avela, E.
, 
Aspelund, S.
, 
Holmbom, B.
, 
Melander, B.
, 
Jalonen, H.
, 
Peltonen, C.
, 
1977
. 
Selective substitution of sucrose hydroxyl groups via chelates
. In: 
Sucrochemistry, L. Hickson
(Ed.), Washington D.C., vol. 41. 
A.C.S. Symposium
Series, USA
, pp. 
62–79
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bartlett, G.R.
, 
1959
. 
Phosphorus assay in column chromatography
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
234
, 
466–468
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ChemBioDraw, 
2014
. 
Version Ultra 14.0.0.117. PerkinElmer Inc
., 
Waltham MA
, 
USA
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chopra, S.
, 
Palencia, A.
, 
Virus, C.
, 
Tripathy, A.
, 
Temple, B.R.
, 
Velazquez-Campoy, A.
, 
Cusack, S.
, 
Reader, J.S.
, 
2013
. 
Plant tumour biocontrol agent employs a tRNAdependent mechanism to inhibit leucyl-tRNA synthetase
. 
Nat. Commun.
4
, 
1417
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms2421
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Clare, B.G.
, 
1995
. 
Agrocins
. In: 
Vining, Leo C., Stuttard, Colin
(Eds.), 
Genetics and Biochemistry of Antibiotic Production. Butterworth-Heinemann Publishers
, 
Oxford, UK
, pp. 
619–632
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DePaoli-Roach, A.A.
, 
Contreras, C.J.
, 
Segvich, D.M.
, 
Heiss, C.
, 
Ishihara, M.
, 
Azadi, P.
, 
Roach, P.J.
, 
2015
. 
Glycogen phosphomonoester distribution in mouse models of the progressive myoclonic epilepsy, Lafora disease
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
290
, 
841–850
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dessaux, Y.
, 
Petit, A.
, 
Farrand, S.K.
, 
Murphy, P.J.
, 
1998
. 
Opines and opine-like molecules involved in plant-Rhizobiaceae interactions
. In: 
Spaink, H.P.
, 
Kondorosi, A.
, 
Hooykaas, P.J.J.
(Eds.), 
The Rhizobiaceae
. 
Kluwer Academic Publishers, Dordrecht
, pp. 
173–197
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dubois, M.
, 
Gilles, K.
, 
Hamilton, J.K.
, 
Rebers, P.A.
, 
Smith, F.
, 
1951
. 
A colorimetric method for determination of sugars
. 
Nature
168
, 
167
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
El Sahili, A.
, 
Li, S.-Z.
, 
Lang, J.
, 
Virus, C.
, 
Planamente, S.
, 
Ahmar, M.
, 
Guimaraes, B.G.
, 
Aumont-Nicaise, M.
, 
Vigouroux, A.
, 
Soulere, L.
, 
Reader, J.
, 
Queneau, Y.
, 
Faure, D.
, 
Morera, S.
, 
2015
. 

A pyranose 2-phosphate motif is responsible for both antibiotic import and quorum sensing regulation in 
Agrobacterium tumefaciens

. 
PLoS Pathog
.1–24
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1005071
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ellis, J.G.
, 
Murphy, P.J.
, 
1981
. 
Four new opines from crown gall tumours – their detection and properties
. 
Mol. Gen. Genet.
181
, 
36–43
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Franzkowiak, M.
, 
Thiem, J.
, 
1987
. 
Synthesen von Agrocinopin A und B
. 
Liebigs Ann. Chem.
1987
, 
1065–1071
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guyon, P.
, 
Chilton, M.D.
, 
Petit, A.
, Temp´e, J., 
1980
. 
Agropine in null-type crown gall tumors: evidence for the generality of the opine concept
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
77
, 
2693–2697
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harrap, F.E.G.
, 
1960
. 
The detection of phosphate esters on paper chromatograms
. 
Analyst
85
, 
452
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hayward, L.D.
, 
Angyal, S.J.
, 
1977
. 
Symmetry rule for the circular dichroism of reducing sugars, and the proportion of carbonyl forms in aqueous solutions thereof
. 
Carbohydr. Res.
53
, 
13–20
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hough, L.
, 
Jones, J.K.N.
, 
Wadman, W.H.
, 
1950
. 
Quantitative analysis of mixtures of sugars by the method of partition chromatography; Part V Improved methods for the separation and detection of the sugars and their methylated derivatives on the paper chromatogram
. 
J. Chem. Soc.
1950
, 
1702–1703
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kaufmann, M.
, 
Mügge, C.
, 
Kroh, L.W.
, 
2018
. 
NMR analyses of complex d-glucose anomerization
. 
Food Chem.
265
, 
222–226
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kerr, A.
, 
2016
. 
Biological control of crown gall. Australas
. 
Plant Pathol.
45
, 
15–18
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kim, H.
, 
Farrand, S.K.
, 
1997
. 

Characterization of the 
acc
operon from the nopaline-type Ti plasmid pTiC58, which encodes utilization of agrocinopines A and B and susceptibility to agrocin 84. J

. 
Bacteriol.
179
, 
7559–7572
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kyndt, T.
, 
Quispe, D.
, 
Zhai, H.
, 
Jarret, R.
, 
Ghislain, M.
, 
Liu, Q.
, 
Gheysen, G.
, 
Kreuze, J.F.
, 
2015
. 

The genome of cultivated sweet potato contains 
Agrobacterium
T-DNAs with expressed genes: an example of a naturally transgenic food crop

. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A
112
, 
5844–5849
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, S.-Z.
, 
Vigouroux, A.
, 
Ahmar, M.
, 
El Sahili, A.
, Soul`ere, L., 
Sago, L.
, 
Cornu, D.
, Mor´era, S., 
Queneau, Y.
, 
2019
. 

Synthesis of a non-natural glucose-2-phosphate ester able to dupe the acc system of 
Agrobacterium fabrum

. 
Org. Biomol. Chem.
17
, 
1090–1096
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
31 
Lim, S.
, 
Seib, P.A.
, 
1993
. 
Location of phosphate esters in wheat starch phosphate by Pnuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy
. 
Cereal Chem.
70
, 
145–215
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lindberg, M.
, 
Norberg, T.
, 
1988
. 
Synthesis of sucrose 4’-(L-arabinose-2-yl phosphate) (Agrocinopine A) using an arabinose 2-H-phosphonate intermediate
. 
J. Carbohydr. Chem.
7
, 
749–755
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lindberg, M.
, 
Norberg, T.
, 
Oscarson, S.
, 
1992
. 
Synthesis of sucros-6-yl D-glucos-2-yl phosphate via the hydrogenphosphonate approach
. 
J. Carbohydr. Chem.
11
, 
243–253
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lindberg, M.
, 
Oscarson, S.
, 
1993
. 
Synthesis of D-glucos-2-yl sucros-2-yl phosphate (agrocinopin C) and bis (D-glucos-2-yl) phosphate (agrocinopin D)
. 
J. Carbohydr. Chem.
12
, 
1139–1147
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Los, J.M.
, 
Simpson, L.B.
, 
Wiesner, K.
, 
1956
. 
The kinetics of mutarotation of D-glucose with consideration of an intermediate free-aldehyde form
. 
J. Am. Chem. Soc.
78
, 
1564–1568
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Matveeva, T.
, 
Otten, L.
, 
2021
. 
Opine biosynthesis in naturally transgenic plants: genes and products
. 
Phytochemistry (Oxf.)
189
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2021.112813
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Messens, E.
, 
Lenaerts, A.
, 
Hedges, R.W.
, 
Van Montagu, M.
, 
1985
. 
Agrocinopine A, a phosphorylated opine is secreted from crown gall cells
. 

EMBO J.
4
, 
571–577
.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Messens, E.
, 
Lenaerts, A.
, 
Van Montagu, M.
, 
De Bruyn, A.
, 
Jans, A.W.H.
, 
Van Binst, G.
, 
1986
. 
1 H and 31 P NMR spectroscopy of agrocinopine.
J. Carbohydr. Chem.
5
, 
683–699
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
MestReNova, 
2014
. 
MnovaNMRPrediction Software (Version 10.0.0-14381)
. 
Mestrelab Research S.
L, Santiago de Compostela, Spain
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Murphy, P.J.
, 
Tate, M.E.
, 
Kerr, A.
, 
1981
. 
Substituents at N6 and C-5’ control selective uptake and toxicity of the adenine-nucleotide bacteriocin, agrocin 84
, in 
agrobacteria
. 
Eur. J. Biochem.
115
, 
539–543
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oger, P.
, 
Reich, C.
, 
Olsen, G.J.
, 
Farrand, S.K.
, 
2001
. 
Complete nucleotide sequence and analysis of pTiBo542: what genomics tells us about structure and evolution of plasmids in the family Rhizobiaceae
. 
Plasmid
45
, 
169–170
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
O’ Connor, J.V.
, 
Nunez, H.A.
, 
Barker, R.
, 
1979
. 
α- and β- Glucopyranosyl phosphates and 1,2-phosphates. Assignments of conformation in solution by 13 C and 1 H NMR.
Biochemistry
18, 
500–507
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pang, L.
, 
Weeks, S.D.
, 
Van Aerschot, A.
, 
2021
. 
Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases as valuable targets for antimicrobial drug discovery
. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
22
, 
1750
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.3390/ijms22041750
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ryder, M.H.
, 
1984
. 
Opines in Crown Gall and Hairy Root Diseases
. PhD Thesis, 
University of Adelaide
. 
http://hdl.handle.net/2440/19557
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ryder, M.H.
, 
Tate, M.E.
, 
Jones, G.P.
, 
1984
. 
Agrocinopine A, a tumor-inducing plasmid-coded enzyme product, is a phosphodiester of sucrose and L-arabinose
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
259
, 
9704–9710
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sarfati, R.S.
, 
Mondange, M.
, Szab´o, L., 
1977
. 
Phosphorylated sugars. Part 21. Synthesis of 3-deoxy-D-manno-and 3-deoxy-D-gluco-oct-2-ulosonic acid 5-(dihydrogen phosphates)
. 
J. Chem. Soc. Perkin Trans.
I
, 
2074–2077
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Savage, A.E.
, 
1983
. 
The Isolation and Structural Elucidation of Agrocinopine C
. 
B. Ag. Sci. Honours Thesis. The University of Adelaide.
http://hdl.handle.net/2440/98296. Sciaky
, D., Montoya, A.L., Chilton, M.D., 1978. Fingerprints of 
Agrobacterium
Ti plasmids. Plasmid 
1
, 
238–253
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stonier, T.
, 
1960
. 

Agrobacterium tumefaciens
Conn. II. Production of an antibiotic substance. J

. 
Bacteriol.
79
, 
889–898
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Swenson, C.A.
, 
Barker, R.
, 
1971
. 
Proportion of keto and aldehydo forms in solutions of sugars and sugar phosphates
. 
Biochemistry
10
, 
3151–3154
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tate, M.E.
, 
1981
. 
Determination of ionization constants by paper electrophoresis
. 
Biochem. J.
195
, 
419–426
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tate, M.E.
, 
Murphy, P.J.
, 
Roberts, W.P.
, 
Kerr, A.
, 
1979
. 
Adenine N 6 -substituent of agrocin 84 determines its bacteriocin-like specificity
. 
Nature
280
, 
697–699
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Travin, D.Y.
, 
Severinov, K.
, 
Dubiley, S.
, 
2021
. 
Natural Trojan horse inhibitors of aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases
. 
RSC Chem. Biol.
https://doi.org/10.1039/ d0cb00208a
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Trevelyan, W.E.
, 
Procter, D.P.
, 
Harrison, J.S.
, 
1950
. 
Detection of sugars on paper chromatograms
. 
Nature
166
, 
444–445
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wetzel, M.E.
, 
Olsen, G.J.
, 
Chakravartty, V.
, 
Farrand, S.K.
, 
2015
. 
The repABC plasmids with quorum-regulated transfer systems in members of the Rhizobiales divide into two structurally and separately evolving groups
. 
Genome Biol. Evol.
7
, 
3337–3357
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evv227
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Williams, C.
, 
Allerhand, A.
, 
1977
. 
Detection of β- D-glucofuranose in aqueous solutions of D-glucose. Application of carbon-13 Fourier-transform n.m.r. spectroscopy
. 
Carbohydr. Res.
56
, 
173–179
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wishart, D.S.
, 
Knox, C.
, 
Guo, A.C.
, 
Eisner, R.
, 
Young, N.
, 
Gautam, B.
, 
Hau, D.D.
, 
Psychogios, N.
, 
Dong, E.
, 
Bouatra, S.
, 
Mandal, R.
, 
Sinelnikov, I.
, 
Xia, J.
, 
Jia, L.
, 
Cruz, J.A.
, 
Lim, E.
, 
Sobsey, C.A.
, 
Shrivastava, S.
, 
Huang, P.
, 
Liu, P.
, 
Fang, L.
, 
Peng, J.
, 
Fradette, R.
, 
Cheng, D.
, 
Tzur, D.
, 
Clements, M.
, 
Lewis, A.
, 
De Souza, A.
, 
Zuniga, A.
, 
Dawe, M.
, 
Xiong, Y.
, 
Clive, D.
, 
Greiner, R.
, 
Nazyrova, A.
, 
Shaykhutdinov, R.
, 
Li, L.
, 
Vogel, H.J.
, 
Forsythe, I.
, 
2009
. 
HMDB: a knowledgebase for the human metabolome
. 
Nucleic Acids Res.
37
(Database issue), D603–D610. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/ gkn810. Epub 2008 Oct 25. PMID: 18953024
; PMCID: PMC2686599.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wurster, B.
, 
Hess, B.
, 
1974
. 
Anomeric specificity of enzymes of D-glucose metabolism
. 
FEBS Lett.
40
, s112–s 
118
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, Q.
, 
Li, S.-Z.
, 
Ahmar, M.
, Soul`ere, L., 
Queneau, Y.
, 
2020
. 
Esters of glucose-2- phosphate: occurrence and chemistry
. 
Molecules
25
, 
2829
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ molecules25122829
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
