<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112396</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A metallothionein type 2 from Avicennia marina binds to iron and mediates hydrogen peroxide balance by activation of enzyme catalase</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Avicennia marina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Avicennia marina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Acanthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Avicennia marina (Forssk.) Vierh.</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Escherichia coli
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Avicennia marina (Forssk.) Vierh. (Acanthaceae)</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Avicennia
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. marina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form stable</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>A. marina</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. coli</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E.</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. marina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Avicennia germinans
(
Gonzalez-Mendoza et al., 2007
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. marina
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
(
Grobe et al., 2006
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Saccharomyces cerevisae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E
. 
coli
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. coli cells</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
A
metallothionein 
type
2 from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Avicennia marina
</tp:taxon-name>
binds to iron and mediates hydrogen peroxide balance by activation of enzyme catalase

</p>
         <p>
Zahra Babaei-Bondarti, Azar Shahpiri
∗
</p>
         <p>

Department of Biotechnology, College of Agriculture, 
Isfahan
University of Technology, 
Isfahan
, 84156-83111, 
Iran
</p>
         <p>
A
R T I 
C
L E I N F 
O
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Avicennia marina
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Acanthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Metallothionein</p>
         <p>Metal accumulation</p>
         <p>Recombinant protein</p>
         <p>Iron</p>
         <p>Hydrogen peroxide tolerance</p>
         <p>
A
B S T R 
A
C
T
</p>
         <p>
Metallothioneins (MTs) are low molecular weight, cysteine-rich, metal-binding proteins that are important for essential metal homeostasis, protection against oxidative stress, and buffering against toxic heavy metals. In this work the gene encoding an MT 
type
2 from 
<tp:taxon-name>Avicennia marina (Forssk.) Vierh.</tp:taxon-name>
(AmMT2) was cloned into pET41a and transformed into the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Escherichia coli
</tp:taxon-name>
strain Rosetta (DE3). Following the induction with isopropyl 
β-D-
1- thiogalactopyranoside, AmMT2 was expressed as glutathione-S-transferase (GST)-tagged fusion protein. The accumulation of Zn 
2+
, Cu 
2+
, Fe 
2+
, Ni 
2+
and Cd 
2+
for strain R-AmMT2 was 4, 8, 5.4, 2 and 1.6 fold of control strain suggesting the role of AmMT 
2 in
accumulation of metals. Particularly the strain R-AmMT2 was able to accumulate 
30.7 mg
per g dry weight. The cells expressing AmMT2 was more tolerant to hydrogen peroxide and had higher catalase (CAT) activity. To understand the mechanistic action of AmMT2 hydrogen peroxide tolerance, the activity of CAT in the 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
protein extract was assayed after addition of pure Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT complex and Apo/GST-AmMT 

2 
in

vitro. Whereas, the activity of CAT did not change by the addition of Apo/GSTAmMT2, the activity of CAT significantly increased after addition of Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT2. These results show that AmMT2 activates CAT through Fe 
2+
transfer which subsequently causes the oxidative stress tolerance.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Avicennia marina (Forssk.) Vierh. (Acanthaceae)</tp:taxon-name>
, which known as gray mangrove is a widely distributed mangrove species that thrives in high-salinity habitats (

; 

; 

). It is a main species of the mangrove forest ecosystem, which plays an essential role in supporting biodiversity, maintaining coastal stability, and protecting water quality (

). Iranian mangrove forests occur between the northern orbits 25°19′- 27°84’ (

). This area covers the north part of the Persian Gulf and 
Oman
Sea, and three coastal provinces in the south of 
Iran
(from southwest to southeast: 
Bushehr
, 
Hormuzgan
and Sistan &amp; Balouchestan (

). It plays a significant role in supporting coastal ecosystem and holds unique potential for studying molecular mechanisms underlying ecological adaptation (

).
</p>
         <p>
Mangrove trees are tolerant to high levels of heavy metals (

). Specially 
<tp:taxon-name>
Avicennia
species
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibit greater tolerance and have accumulative properties to numerous metals than other mangrove species (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
A. marina
</tp:taxon-name>
like all other plants possess different cellular mechanisms to maintain the correct concentrations of essential metal ions in different cellular compartments and to minimize the damage from exposure to toxic concentration of essential and non-essential metals (

; 

). 
A
regulated network of metal transport, chelation, trafficking and sequestration activities maintain the metal homeostasis in the cell environment (

). Protein chelators including phytochelatins (PCs) and metallothioneins (MTs) are important chelating molecules that 
<tp:taxon-name>form stable</tp:taxon-name>
metal-complexes which are subsequently sequestered into vacuoles (

; 

; 

). MTs are low molecular weight, cysteine-rich, metal-binding proteins found in a wide variety of organisms including bacteria, fungi and all eukaryotic plant and animal species (

; 

). The ability of MTs for binding to metals through the thiol groups is their main function (

; 

; 

; 

). However they are also considered as scavenger of reactive oxygen species (ROS) (

; 

). Plant MTs are categorized in 
four types
based on the Cys distribution in amino acid sequences (

; 

). Whereas the MT 
types
1, 2 and 3 have two Cys-rich domain at N- and C- terminal that are separated by a linker of variable sizes. The MT 
type
4 is characterized with three Cys-rich domain (

; 

). With few exceptions, a typical 
type
1 MT contains six Cys residues in CXC motifs (where X denotes any amino acid other than Cys) at the N-terminal part. 
Type
2 MTs have eight Cys residues at their N-terminal arranged in CC, CXC, and CXXC motifs (

). 
Type
3 MTs are small proteins with four Cys residues in their N-terminal Cys-rich region (

). The distribution of Cys residues within the C-terminal part follows the consensus sequence CXCXXXCXCXXCXC that is highly conserved in all 
three types
. Until now the sequence of two members of MT families have been identified in 

<tp:taxon-name>A. marina</tp:taxon-name>
.

The protein AmMT2 with eight Cys residues at the N-terminal region has been classified into the 
type
2 MTs and AmMT3 with four Cys residues seems to be classified into typ 3 (

). In the present work the gene encoding AmMT2 has been cloned and heterologously expressed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
as fusion protein with glutathione-S-transferase (GST). The tolerance of transgenic cells in response to different metals and hydrogen peroxide was compared with the control strain. Because of high ability of strain for accumulation of Fe 
2+
, the ability of GST-AmMT2 for formation of complex with Fe 
+2
was investigated 
in vitro
and the effect of complex Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT2 was studied on the catalase (CAT) activity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

2.1. GST-AmMT2 was expressed in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. coli</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The full-length coding sequence of AmMT2 with 240 bp encodes a 79 amino acid protein with a theoretical molecular weight of 7.7/4.55 (kDa)/pI. The presence of two Cys-rich regions with eight Cys residues (CCXXXCXCXXXCXCXXXCXXC) at the N-terminal and six Cys residues (CXCXXXCXCXXCXC) at the C-terminal parts, respectively, confirms that AmMT2 is classified in 
type
2 MTs (
Fig. 1A
). The coding sequence of AmMT2 was subcloned into the expression vector pET41a containing coding sequences for an N-terminal fusion partner of glutathione-S-transferase (GST-tag), a 6His-tag, and an S-tag (the complete tag was named GST) (
Fig. 1B
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Following induction with IPTG, the recombinant proteins GST and GST-AmMT2 were expressed in the soluble fraction of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
carrying the pET41a and pET41-AmMT2, respectively. The theoretical molecular weight/pI of GST and GST-AmMT2 were 35.5/6.3 and 40.2/ 5.7 kDa, respectively. The proteins GST and GST-AmMT2 at the correct molecular weight appeared on the SDS-PAGE as sharp bands (
Fig. 2A
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The large scale production of protein was performed as described in part 2.3. The recombinant GST-AmMT2 was purified from the soluble fraction using nickel affinity chromatography and dialysis and the extent of purification was assessed by SDS-PAGE analysis (
Fig. 2B
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. The strain R-AmMT2 is able to uptake considerable amounts of iron
from culture medium
</title>
         <p>
The strain R-AmMT2 as well as control was grown in the medium containing Zn 
2+
, Cu 
2+
, Fe 
2+
, Ni 
2+
and Cd 
2+
. As shown in 
Fig. 3
the final cell densities (cell density after 12 h) of strain R-AmMT2 were similar to that from control (
A
600 = 1.8) when the strains were grown in the medium with no stress. However, in the presence of Zn 
2+
, Cu 
2+
, Fe 
2+
and Ni 
2+
the strain R-AmMT2 with the final OD600 of 1.38, 1.86, 1.97 and 1.53, respectively had higher OD than that of control strain. These data show that the heterologous expression of GST–AmMT2 enhances the tolerance of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
to Zn 
2+
, Cu 
2+
, Fe 
2+
and Ni 
2+
. Nevertheless the heterologous expression of AmMT2 did not affect on the growth rate of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
in the presence of Cd 
2+
.
</p>
         <p>
To determine whether the enhanced of tolerance of R-AmMT2 to metals is accompanied by increasing accumulation of metal ions in these cells, the recombinant strains as well as control were grown in liquid medium supplemented with Zn 
2+
, Cu 
2+
, Fe 
2+
, Ni 
2+
and Cd 
2+
(
Fig. 4
). The concentrations of heavy metal ions in the culture medium were determined by atomic absorption at time of addition of metal (T0) and 6 h (T1) after the addition of 
IPTG
and metals to the cultures. The concentration variations of Zn 
2+
, Cu 
2+
, Fe 
2+
, Ni 
2+
and Cd 
2+
in the medium of control strain were 3 ± 0.1, 0.8 ± 0.04, 3.2 ± 0.15, 5.3 ± 0.1 and 2 ± 0.1 ppm. In comparison the changes in concentration of corresponding metal ions in the medium of R-AmMT2 were 12 ± 0.2, 8.3 ± 1, 17.5 ± 0.015, 11.1 ± 0.1 and 3.34 ± 0.01. These data show that the amount of metal ion variations in the medium of strain R-AmMT2 is significantly (P &lt;0.01 for Zn 
2+
, Cu 
2+
, Fe 
2+
, Ni 
2+
and P &lt;0.05 for Cd 
2+)
higher than that for control strain, suggesting the role of AmMT 
2 in
accumulation of metals.
</p>
         <p>
In particular the elimination of 17.5 ppm Fe 
2+
(
30.7 mg
Fe 
2+
/g d.W.) by R-AmMT2 is an outstanding property of this strain.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.3. The recombinant GST-AmMT2 is able to bind Fe 
2+
in vitro

</title>
         <p>
The characteristic ligand-to-metal charge transfer bands observed in the UV spectra (
210–360 nm
) recorded after incubating the recombinant apo-proteins of GST-AmMT2 with Fe 
2+
verified the presence of Fe 
2+
-thiolate clusters (
Fig. 5A
). Compared to the apo-forms of GST-AmMT2, the proteins Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT2 showed increased absorbance at 
314 nm
typical of Fe 
2+
containing proteins which confirms the binding of Fe 
2+
to GST-AmMT 

2 
in

vitro. Moreover the ability of GST-AmMT2 to bind Fe 
2+
was also studied by using the DTNB assay (
Fig. 5B
). The initial velocity of GST-AmMT2 incubated with saturated concentration of Fe 
2+
(Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT2) was lower than that from apo-forms of GST-AmMT2. This could be due to binding of Fe 
2+
to GSTAmMT2 which causes in decrease of available titratable thiol content. Therefore the lower initial velocity of Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT 
2 in
reaction with DTNB confirmed the ability of GST-AmMT2 to bind Fe 
2+
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.4. The tolerance of R-AmMT2 was enhanced in response to 
H
2
O
2
stress

</title>
         <p>
The final cell densities (cell density after 12 h) of strains AmMT2 were similar to that from control when the strains were grown in the medium with no stress (
Fig. 6A
). However, in the presence of 2 mM 
H
2
O
2
whereas the density for control strain after 12 h reached 1.02, the density for strains R-AmMT2 was 1.37, respectively (
Fig. 6A
). These data show that the heterologous expression of GST-AmMT2 enhances the tolerance of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
H
2
O
2
.
</p>
         <p>
Since one of the important antioxidant enzymes that is activated in response to 
H
2
O
2
is CAT, the activity of CAT in control and R-AmMT2 strains was determined in the medium containing 
H
2
O
2
in

the presence or absence of 
IPTG
. As shown in 
Fig. 6B
the enzyme CAT was active in both control and R-AmMT 
2 in
the response to 
H
2
O
2
. The CAT activity in the control strain in the presence and absence of 
IPTG
was almost similar which suggests that the expression of GST has not affected on the CAT activity. However in the strain R-AmMT2 the CAT activity is significantly (P &lt;0.01) higher than that from control strain when 
IPTG
was added and the protein GST-AmMT2 was expressed. Based on these results, it seems that one of the important reasons for enhancement of tolerance R-AmMT 
2 in
response to 
H
2
O
2
is the higher activity of CAT compared to control strain.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.5. Addition of pure Fe 
2+/
AmMT2 enhanced the activity of CAT in the 
<tp:taxon-name>E.</tp:taxon-name>
coli extract

</title>
         <p>
The CAT activity was determined in the protein extract from control strain before and after addition of pure recombinant forms of Apo/GSTAmMT2 as well as Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT2. The CAT activity in the extract was 50 Umg 
−1
. This value did not change by the addition of Apo/GSTAmMT2 (
Fig. 7
). However, the CAT activity was increased to 75.4 Umg 
−1
after additions of Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT2. These data may demonstrate that Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT2 behave as an activator for CAT by supplying Fe 
2+
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Discussion
</title>
         <p>
Metallothioneins (MTs) are defined as a family of proteins with the characteristics of low molecular weight, high cysteine (Cys) residue content, and metal-binding ability (

; 

; 

). Plants have multiple members of MTs which are classified in 
four types
(

). Different MT 
types
seem to be differentially expressed in different plant organs. In Arabidopsis the genes encoding 
type
1 are predominantly expressed in root, 
type
2 in
aerial organs, 
type
3 in
ripening fruits as well as leaves and 
type
4 isoforms seem to be seed specific (

; 

; 

). The expression of genes encoding MTs are up-regulated in response to several abiotic stresses factors, including toxic concentration of heavy metals, salinity, drought, low temperature, abscisic acid and ethylene, suggesting different roles for MT protein family in plants. Recently several studies demonstrate the role of MTs as ROS scavengers, which may explain the enhanced expression of MT genes in response to above abiotic stress (

; 

; 

; 

). The protein AmMT2 from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. marina
</tp:taxon-name>
is classified as 
type
2 plant MTs due to the presence of Cys-Cys and Cys-X-X-Cys motifs in the N-terminal domain (

).
</p>
         <p>
The gene expression analysis of genes encoding 
type
2 MTs has been previously reported in some mangrove species. The significant increase in the transcript level of genes encoding AvMT2, BgMT2, KcMT2, and LlMT2 (

) 
in
<tp:taxon-name>
Avicennia germinans
(
Gonzalez-Mendoza et al., 2007
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, Bruguiera gymnorrhiza (

) Kandelia candel (

), and Lupinus Luteus, respectively in the contaminated sites with Cu 
2+
, Zn 
2+
, Pb 
2+
, Cd 
2+
, Ni 
2+
and Ag 
1+
suggests that MT 
type
2 has a critical role in detoxification of heavy metals in the mangroves. Moreover the expression of genes encoding MTs has been also reported in response to oxidative stress. For instance the expression of BrMT (

), CgMT (

), GhMT (

) OsMT (

) or DpMT (

) decreased ROS production in transgenic plants or bacteria. The Arabidopsis T-DNA insertion mutant, mt2a, had higher 
H
2
O
2
levels than wild-type plants during cold stress (

). Here we describe a MT 
type
2 from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. marina
</tp:taxon-name>
with high ability for binding to Fe 
2+
. The 
Ecoli
cells expressing GST-AmMT2 were able to accumulate 
30.7 mg
Fe 
2+
per g (dry weight cells) which is significantly higher than previous reports regarding to iron uptake by engineered 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
(
Grobe et al., 2006
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. The production and purification of AmMT 
2 in
considerable amount enabled us to test the ability of binding of Fe 
2+
to AmMT2. Both DTNB assay and UV absorption spectra demonstrate the formation of Fe 
2+
/AmMT2 complex 
in vitro
and confirm the binding ability of AmMT2 to Fe 
2+
(

).
</p>
         <p>
The transgenic 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
showed also tolerance to hydrogen peroxide supporting the previous studies that found the heterologous expression of rice MT isoforms enhances the hydrogen peroxide tolerance in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Saccharomyces cerevisae
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

). Hydrogen peroxide is a strong oxidising agent that dissociates to hydrogen (
H
+
) and hydroxyl (OH 
−
) radicals. These oxidative agents readily attack proteins, lipids and nucleic acids. Several explanations for enhancement of tolerance of cells expressing MTs in response to 
H
2
O
2
are possible. First, MTs may act in zinc donation to apo-proteins, including zinc finger proteins (

). The presence of several zinc coordination sites in the zinc-finger proteins provides the opportunity for the transfer of zinc from MTs to these sites (

; 

; 

) Subsequently zinc finger transcription factors which are activated by zinc, regulate the expression of antioxidant genes resulted in enhancement of concentration of antioxidant enzymes in the cells (

). Secondly, the antioxidant enzymes such as CAT and superoxide dismutase (SOD) are metalloenzymes which require metal ions for activation (

; 

; 

; 

). Therefore it is possible that MTs directly act as donator of ion metals to the metal binding site of these enzymes. In the present work we found that the activity of CAT in the transgenic strain expressing AmMT2 was significantly higher compared to control strain in response to 
H
2
O
2
. This may explain the higher tolerance of transgenic strain (R-AmMT2) in response to 
H
2
O
2
because the CAT is the key antioxidant enzyme in bacteria involved in elimination of 
H
2
O
2
. The enzyme CAT is an ubiquitous tetramer hemecontaining enzyme that catalyzes the dismutation of two molecules of 
H
2
O
2
into water and oxygen. Therefore the presence of Fe 
2+
is required for the CAT activity. Here it has been shown that the Fe 
2+
/AmMT2 complex enhances the activity of CAT in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
</tp:taxon-name>
cell extract 
in vitro
while the treatment with Apo/GST-AmMT2 did not affect on CAT activity. These results show that AmMT acts as activator for CAT by supplementation of Fe 
2+
and by this way enhances the tolerance of cells
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
Taken together the protein AmMT2 is a member of MT 
type
2 with the ability for binding to essential and non-essential metals. However the 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
expressing GST-AmMT2 were significantly able to accumulate Fe 
2+
more than other metals. The heterologous expression of AmMT2 confers tolerance to 
H
2
O
2
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
by increasing the activity of CAT. It seems that AmMT2 might release Fe 
2+
during oxidative stress and activate the enzymes such as CAT that requires Fe 
2+
and thus trigger a Fe 
2+
mediated antioxidant response.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Materials and methods
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.1. Cloning of gene encoding AmMT2
</title>
         <p>
The gene encoding AmMT2 (NCBI accession number: AF333385.1) was synthesized and cloned in pUC57 between two restriction sites 
Eco
RI and 
Hin
dIII. For subcloning of gene in pET41a, the plasmid pUC57-AmMT2 was digested with 
Eco
RI and 
Hin
dIII and the digestion product was run on agarose gel. The fragment containing AmMT2 gene was isolated from the gel. The fragment was then ligated into pET-41a (Novagen) after linearization with 
Eco
RI and 
Hin
dIII using T4 ligase (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The new constructs were named pET41aAmMT2.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.2. Heterologous expression of GST-AmMT2
</title>
         <p>
The resulting construct pET41-AmMT2 was verified by sequencing and then introduced in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E
. 
coli
</tp:taxon-name>
protease-deficient strain Rosetta (DE3) for protein expression. The resulted strain was termed R-AmMT2. The control strain was also made by transferring plasmid pET41a without gene. The 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. coli
cells
</tp:taxon-name>
containing either pET41a (Control) or pET41aAmMT2 (R-AmMT2) were grown at 37 ° 
C
in Luria-Bertani (LB) medium in the volume of 50 ml supplemented with 50 μg/ml kanamycin and 5 μg/ml chloramphenicol to an OD 
600
of about 0.6. At this OD cultures were induced by 100 μM Isopropyl β-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside (
IPTG
). In addition the culture medium was supplemented with 0.6 mM ZnSO 
4.
7 
H
2
O
20 min after addition of 
IPTG
. To confirm heterologous expression of the protein, 1 ml samples of culture medium were harvested by centrifugation 1, 2, 3 and 4 h after addition of 
IPTG
and frozen at −80 ° 
C
until use. The frozen pellets were resuspended in 250 μl pre-cold 10 mM Tris–HCl, pH 8.0, disrupted by mild sonication at 4 ° 
C
and centrifugated at 
12,000 g
, for 20 min. The soluble proteins recovered in supernatant phase were analyzed by 12% SDS-PAGE and stained by Coomassie Brilliant Blue R-250 (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.3. Large scale production of GST-AmMT2 and purification
</title>
         <p>
For large scale production of proteins the cells were grown in 500 ml of medium. Induction with Isopropyl β-d-1-thiogalactopyranoside (
IPTG
), and supplementation with 0.6 mM ZnSO 
4.
7 
H
2
O
were performed as explained above. The cells from whole volume were harvested 4 h after addition of 
IPTG
. The soluble proteins were extracted as explained above. For purification the extracted soluble proteins were applied on to His-Trap HP column (GE, Healthcare) preequilibrated with loading buffer (10 mM imidazole, 500 mM NaCl, 30 mM Tris–HCl, pH 8.0) and the bound proteins were eluted by 68.5–283 mM imidazole gradient. Aliquots of the protein fractions were analyzed by 12% SDS-PAGE and stained by Coomasie Brilliant Blue R-250. The pure fractions were pooled and transferred into 12 kDa molecular weight cutoff cellulose tubes (Sigma) and dialyzed against 10 mM Tris–HCl, pH 8.0, at 4 ° 
C
overnight to remove imidazole and other salts. Protein concentrations were determined by Beer-Lambert law with the molar extinction coefficient of 44,537.5 and 49,382.5 for GST and GST-AmMT2 respectively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4. Metal ion tolerance of transformed cells
</title>
         <p>
Tolerance of strains control and R-AmMT2 to metals in the growth medium was examined in concentrations of 0.9 mM CdCl 
2
· 
H
2
O
, 1 mM ZnSO 
4
·7 
H
2
O
, 2 mM CuSO 
4
·5 
H
2
O
, 2.5 mM NiCl 
2.6
H
2
O
, and (1–3 mM) FeSO 
4.
7 
H
2
O
. For the analysis 5 ml of the overnight cultures of cells were inoculated in 80 ml of LB medium supplemented with desired antibiotics. The cultures were induced at OD 
600
= 0.6 by addition of 0.1 mM of 
IPTG
. After 20 min, the metals were added to the cultures. Bacterial growth was monitored up to 12 h by OD 
600
measurements. The data represent the mean obtained from two independent experiments with two replicates. The means were compared with 
t
-test: *p &lt;0.05; **p &lt;0.01.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.5. Analysis of metal ion accumulation in transformed cells
</title>
         <p>
The growth of cells, induction with 
IPTG
, and supplementation with metals were performed as explained in part 2.3. For the analysis of metals, cells from 10 ml of culture at 0 (T0) and 6 h after metal addition (T1) were precipitated by centrifugation at 

6000 
g

for 20 min. The supernatant was analyzed for metals Zn 
2+
, Cu 
2+
, Ni 
2+
, Cd 
2+
and Fe 
2+
using inductively coupled plasma atomic absorption spectroscopy (PerkinElmer Analyst 700). The metal concentration changes in the medium of strains control and R-AmMT2 between T1 and T0 (CT 
0
-CT 
1
) was calculated. The data represent the mean ± 
SD
obtained from two independent experiments with two replicates. The means were compared with 
t
-test: *p &lt;0.05; **p &lt;0.01.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

5.6. Tolerance of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. coli cells</tp:taxon-name>
to H 
2
O 
2
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Overnight cultures of different strains were inoculated into 80 mL of LB medium with desired antibiotics and grown at 37 °C under agitation. Protein expression was induced at an A 
600
of 0.6 by addition of 0.1 mM IPTG. After 20 min, culture flasks were supplemented with either 2 mM H 
2
O 
2
or 4% ethanol and bacterial growth was monitored by A 
600
measurements at 1 h intervals up to 12 h. The data represent the mean ± SD obtained from two independent experiments with two replicates. The means were compared with 
t
-test: *p &lt;0.05; **p &lt;0.01.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.7. Determination of CAT activity in transgenic bacteria
</title>
         <p>
Overnight cultures of different strains were inoculated into 50 mL of LB medium with desired antibiotics and grown at 37 ° 
C
under agitation. Protein expression was induced at an 
A
600
of 0.6 by addition of 0.1 mM 
IPTG
. After 20 min, culture flasks were supplemented with 2 mM 
H
2
O
2.
The cells from whole volume were harvested 4 h after addition of 
IPTG
. For extraction of soluble proteins first the cells were resuspended in 40 ml buffer 
A
(50 mM Tris-HCl, 50 mM Glucose, pH 7.8). Then the cells were harvested by centrifugation at 4 ° 
C
for 20 min. The harvested cells were again resuspended in 3 ml buffer 
A
containing 
1 mg
/ml lysozyme. The cell suspensions were kept at room temperature for 15 min. Then 3 ml of buffer B (50 mM Tris-HCl, 50 mM KCl, 1% Triton X-100) was added and the cell suspensions were shaken for 2 h at 37 ° 
C
. Then the cell suspension was centrifuged (25 min, 4 ° 
C
, 
10000g
) to remove cell debris. The supernatant containing soluble protein was transferred to clean tubes and kept in – 20 ° 
C
until use. The concentration of proteins was determined by the Bradford assay with bovine serum albumin as standard (

). The CAT activity was determined spectrophotometrically following 
H
2
O
2
consumption at 240 nM (

). 
A
500 μl reaction mixture containing 100 μg/ml extracted protein, 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4 was started with the addition of 20 μM 
H
2
O
2
. The reaction was monitored at 
240 nm
for 1 min and the rate of 
H
2
O
2
consumption was calculated (using the extinction coeffiecient of 36 M 
−1
Cm 
−1
). One unit of CAT activity is defined as the degradation of 1 μmol 
H
2
O
2
/min. The CAT activity was compared between control and R-AmMT2 strains in the medium containing 
H
2
O
2
in

the presence or absence of 
IPTG
. The data represent the mean ± 
SD
obtained from two independent experiments with two replicates. The means were compared with least significant difference test (LSD, P 0.01) test.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

5.8. Preparation of Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT2

</title>
         <p>
The production and purification of recombinant GST-AmMT were performed as described above. The concentration of proteins was determined by Beer-Lambert law. Apo-proteins were prepared by the methods previously described (

). For preparation of apo-proteins, aliquots of 25 μM purified GST-MTs were acidified with HCl to pH 2.0 and the samples were then dialyzed against 
0.1 N
HCl, pH 2.0, to remove bound metal ions. Reconstitution with Fe 
2+
was achieved by the addition of 10 mol equivalents of Fe 
2+
followed by neutralization of the samples to pH 8.0 with 200 mM Tris. The unbound metals were removed by dialyzing against 10 mM Tris–HCl, pH 8.0, at 4 ° 
C
overnight.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.9. UV absorption spectra
</title>
         <p>The absorption spectra of metal-incubated and apo-forms of GSTAmMT proteins were determined between 220 and 360 nmusing spectrophotometer (DU 530).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.10. Reaction with DTNB
</title>
         <p>
For this reaction 1.5 nmol of each protein which were obtained by reconstitution of apo-form of GST-AmMT with Fe 
2+
was diluted in 300 μl of 10 mM Tris–HCl, pH 8.0 and placed into aquartz cuvette. The reaction was started by addition of 75 nmol of 5, 5′-dithio-bis-[2-nitrobenzoic acid] (DTNB). The absorbance at 
412 nm
was recorded on the spectrophotometer for 60 min at 25 ° 
C
, reflecting the formation of 2-nitro-5-thiobenzoic acid (TNB). 
A
300 μl of 10 mM Tris–HCl solution containing 75 nmol of DTNB was used as blank. The initial velocity was obtained from each curve of absorbance versus the reaction time (t, min).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

5.11. The effect of pure Fe 
2+
/GST-AmMT2 on the activity of CAT

</title>
         <p>
The soluble protein fraction was extracted from control strain that was grown in the presence of 2 mM 
H
2
O
2
. The activities of CAT in this extract were determined before and after addition of 2 μM Apo/GSTAmMT2 or Fe/GST-AmMT2 by the methods described above. The data represents the mean ± 
SD
obtained from two independent experiments with two replicates. The means were compared with least significant difference test (LSD, P 0.01) test.
</p>
         <p>
Compliance with ethical standards
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgement
</p>
         <p>
Iran
National Science Foundation is thanked for financial support (grant No. 97000792).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aebi, H.
, 
1974
. 
Catalase. Methods of Enzymatic Analysis
. 
Elsevier
, pp. 
673–684
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Akashi, K.
, 
Nishimura, N.
, 
Ishida, Y.
, 
Yokota, A.
, 
2004
. 
Potent hydroxyl radical-scavenging activity of drought-induced type-2 metallothionein in wild watermelon
. 
Biochem. Bioph. Res. Co
323
(
1
), 
72–78
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ansarypour, Z.
, 
Shahpiri, A.
, 
2017
. 

Heterologous expression of a rice metallothionein isoform (OsMTI-1b) in 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae
enhances cadmium, hydrogen peroxide and ethanol tolerance brazilian. J

. 
Microbiol.
48
(
3
), 
537–543
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bradford, M.M.
, 
1976
. 
A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding
. 
Anal. Biochem.
72
(
1
), 
248–254
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cabral, A.C.S.
, 
Jakovleska, J.
, 
Deb, A.
, 
Penner-Hahn, J.E.
, 
Pecoraro, V.L.
, 
Freisinger, E.
, 
2018
. 
Further insights into the metal ion binding abilities and the metalat ion pathway of a plant metallothionein from Musa acuminata
. 
J. Biol. Inorg. Chem.
23
(
1
), 
91–107
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chelikani, P.
, 
Fita, I.
, 
Loewen, P.C.
, 
2004
. 
Diversity of structures and properties among catalases
. 
Cellular and Molecular Life Sciences CMLS
61
(
2
), 
192–208
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cobbett, C.
, 
Goldsbrough, P.
, 
2002
. 
Phytochelatins and metallothioneins: roles in heavy metal detoxification and homeostasis
. 
Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.
53
(
1
), 
159–182
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cobbett, C.S.
, 
2000
. 
Phytochelatin biosynthesis and function in heavy-metal detoxification
. 
Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.
3
(
3
), 
211–216
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Connor, D.
, 
1969
. 
Growth of grey mangrove (Avicennia marina) in nutrient culture
. 
Biotropica
1
(
2
), 
36–40
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Domenech, J.
, 
Mir, G.
, 
Huguet, G.
, 
Capdevila, M.
, 
Molinas, M.
, 
Atrian, S.
, 
2006
. 
Plant metallothionein domains: functional insight into physiological metal binding and protein folding
. 
Biochimie
88
(
6
), 
583–593
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dong, C.J.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
Yu, S.S.
, 
Liu, J.Y.
, 
2010
. 
Characterization of a novel rice metallothionein gene promoter: its tissue specificity and heavy metal responsiveness
. 
J. Integr. Plant Biol.
52
(
10
), 
914–924
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Downton, W.
, 
1982
. 
Growth and osmotic relations of the mangrove Avicennia marina, as influenced by salinity. Funct
. 
Plant Biol.
9
(
5
), 
519–528
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Freisinger, E.
, 
2007
. 
Spectroscopic characterization of a fruit-specific metallothionein: M. acuminata MT3
. 
Inorg. Chim. Acta.
360
(
1
), 
369–380
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gonzalez-Mendoza, D.
, 
Moreno, A.Q.
, 
Zapata-Perez, O.
, 
2007
. 
Coordinated responses of phytochelatin synthase and metallothionein genes in black mangrove, Avicennia germinans, exposed to cadmium and copper
. 
Aquat. Toxicol.
83
(
4
), 
306–314
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Good, M.
, 
Vasak, M.
, 
1986
. 
Iron (II)-substituted metallothionein: evidence for the existence of iron-thiolate clusters
. 
Biochemistry
25
, 
8353–8356
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grobe, C.
, 
Scherer, J.
, 
Koch, D.
, 
Otto, M.
, 
Taudte, N.
, 
Grass, G.
, 
2006
. 
A new ferrous ironuptake transporter, EfeU (YcdN), from Escherichia coli
. 
Mol. Microbiol.
62
(
1
), 
120–131
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guo, W.J.
, 
Bundithya, W.
, 
Goldsbrough, P.B.
, 
2003
. 
Characterization of the Arabidopsis metallothionein gene family: tissue specific expression and induction during senescence and in response to copper
. 
New Phytol.
159
(
2
), 
369–381
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hall, J.
, 
2002
. 
Cellular mechanisms for heavy metal detoxification and tolerance
. 
J. Exp. Bot.
53
(
366
), 
1–11
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hamer, D.H.
, 
1986
. 
Metallothionein
. 
Annu. Rev. Biochem
55
(
1
), 
913–951
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hassinen, V.
, 
Tervahauta, A.
, 
Schat, H.
, 
Kärenlampi, S.
, 
2011
. 
Plant metallothioneins–metal chelators with ROS scavenging activity?
Plant Biol.
13
(
2
), 
225–232
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hassinen, V.
, 
Tuomainen, M.
, 
Peräniemi, S.
, 
Schat, H.
, 
Kärenlampi, S.
, 
Tervahauta, A.
, 
2008
. 
Metallothioneins 2 and 3 contribute to the metal-adapted phenotype but are not directly linked to Zn accumulation in the metal hyperaccumulator, Thlaspi caerulescens
. 
J. Exp. Bot.
60
(
1
), 
187–196
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hathout, Y.
, 
Fabris, D.
, 
Fenselau, C.
, 
2001
. 
Stoichiometry in zinc ion transfer from metallothionein to zinc finger peptides
. 
Int. J. Mass Spectrom.
204
, 
1–3
1-6.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, G.-Y.
, 
Wang, Y.-S.
, 
2009
. 
Expression analysis of type 2 metallothionein gene in mangrove species (Bruguiera gymnorrhiza) under heavy metal stress
. 
Chemosphere
77
(
7
), 
1026–1029
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, G.-Y.
, 
Wang, Y.-S.
, 
2010
. 
Expression and characterization analysis of type 2 metallothionein from grey mangrove species (Avicennia marina) in response to metal stress
. 
Aquat. Toxicol.
99
(
1
), 
86–92
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, G.-Y.
, 
Wang, Y.-S.
, 
Ying, G.-G.
, 
Dang, A.-C.
, 
2012
. 
Analysis of type 2 metallothionein gene from mangrove species (Kandelia candel)
. 
Trees (Berl.)
26
(
5
), 
1537–1544
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hussain, S.
, 
Slikker Jr., W.
, 
Ali, S.F.
, 
1996
. 
Role of metallothionein and other antioxidants in scavenging superoxide radicals and their possible role in neuroprotection. Neurochem
. 
Int.
29
(
2
), 
145–152
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Imlay, K.
, 
Imlay, J.A.
, 
1996
. 
Cloning and analysis of sodC, encoding the copper-zinc superoxide dismutase of Escherichia coli. J
. 
Bacteriol.
178
(
9
), 
2564–2571
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jacob, C.
, 
Maret, W.
, 
Vallee, B.L.
, 
1998
. 
Control of zinc transfer between thionein, metallothionein, and zinc proteins
. 
P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
95
(
7
), 
3489–3494
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jaskulak, M.
, 
Rorat, A.
, 
Grobelak, A.
, 
Chaabene, Z.
, 
Kacprzak, M.
, 
Vandenbulcke, F.
, 
2019
. 
Bioaccumulation, antioxidative response, and metallothionein expression in Lupinus luteus L. exposed to heavy metals and silver nanoparticles
. 
Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res. Int.
26
(
16
), 
16040–16052
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kathiresan, K.
, 
Bingham, B.L.
, 
2001
. 
Biology of mangroves and mangrove ecosystems
. 
Mar. Biol.
40
, 
81–251
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kim, S.-H.
, 
Song, W.-Y.
, 
Ahn, Y.-O.
, 
Lee, H.-S.
, 
Kwak, S.-S.
, 
Choi, K.-S.
, 
2009
. 

Enhancement of cadmium resistance by overexpression of BrMT 
3 in
Arabidopsis. J

. 
Plant Biotechnol.
36
, 
68–74
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Krezel, A.
, 
Maret, W.
, 
2008
. 
Thionein/metallothionein control Zn (II) availability and the activity of enzymes
. 
J. Biol. Inorg. Chem.
13
(
3
), 
401–409
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lane, B.
, 
Kajioka, R.
, 
Kennedy, T.
, 
1987
. 
The wheat-germ Ec protein is a zinc-containing metallothionein
. 
Biochem. Cell. Biol.
65
(
11
), 
1001–1005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Leszczyszyn, O.I.
, 
Imam, H.T.
, 
Blindauer, C.A.
, 
2013
. 
Diversity and distribution of plant metallothioneins: a review of structure, properties and functions
. 
Metall
5
(
9
), 
1146–1169
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
MacFarlane, G.
, 
Burchett, M.
, 
2002
. 
Toxicity, growth and accumulation relationships of copper, lead and zinc in the grey mangrove Avicennia marina (Forsk.) Vierh
. 
Environ. Res.
54
(
1
), 
65–84
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
MacFarlane, G.R.
, 
Koller, C.E.
, 
Blomberg, S.P.
, 
2007
. 
Accumulation and partitioning of heavy metals in mangroves: a synthesis of field-based studies
. 
Chemosphere
69
(
9
), 
1454–1464
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mierek-Adamska, A.
, 
Dąbrowska, G.B.
, 
Blindauer, C.A.
, 
2018
. 
The type 4 metallothionein from Brassica napus seeds folds in a metal-dependent fashion and favours zinc over other metals
. 
Metall
10
, 
1430–1443
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mir, G.
, 
Domènech, J.
, 
Huguet, G.
, 
Guo, W.-J.
, 
Goldsbrough, P.
, 
Atrian, S.
, 
Molinas, M.
, 
2004
. 
A plant type 2 metallothionein (MT) from cork tissue responds to oxidative stress
. 
J. Exp. Bot.
55
(
408
), 
2483–2493
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nath, B.
, 
Chaudhuri, P.
, 
Birch, G.
, 
2014
. 
Assessment of biotic response to heavy metal contamination in Avicennia marina mangrove ecosystems in Sydney Estuary, Australia. Ecotoxicol
. 
Environ. Saf.
107
, 
284–290
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Obertello, M.
, 
Wall, L.
, 
Laplaze, L.
, 
Nicole, M.
, 
Auguy, F.
, 
Gherbi, H.
, 
Bogusz, D.
, 
Franche, C.
, 
2007
. 
Functional analysis of the metallothionein gene cgMT1 isolated from the actinorhizal tree Casuarina glauca
. 
Mol. Plant Microbe Interact.
20
(
10
), 
1231–1240
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Patankar, H.V.
, 
Al-Harrasi, I.
, 
Al Kharusi, L.
, 
Jana, G.A.
, 
Al-Yahyai, R.
, 
Sunkar, R.
, 
Yaish, M.W.
, 
2019
. 
Overexpression of a Metallothionein 2A gene from date palm confers abiotic stress tolerance to yeast and Arabidopsis thaliana
. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
20
(
12
), 
1–21
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rauser, W.E.
, 
1999
. 
Structure and function of metal chelators produced by plants
. 
Cell Biochem. Biophys.
31
(
1
), 
19–48
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Robertson, A.I.
, 
1991
. 
Plant animal interactions and the structure and function of mangrove forest ecosystems
. 
Aust. J. Ecol.
16
(
4
), 
433–443
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sambrook, H.
, 
1989
. 
Molecular Cloning. a laboratory manual, Cold Spring Harbor
, 
NY
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shahpiri, A.
, 
Deljoonia, R.
, 
2018
. 
Enhancement of catalase and superoxide dismutase activities in transgenic Escherichia coli expressing rice metallothionein isoforms
. 
J. Biosci. Biot
7
(
1
), 
5–10
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Soepadmo, E.
, 
Rao, A.N.
, 
MacIntosh, D.J.
, 
Malaya, U.
, 
Unesco
, 
1984
. 
Proceedings of the Asian Symposium on Mangrove Environment
. 
Research and Management, Kuala Lumpur
, pp. 
25–29
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Toriumi, S.
, 
Saito, T.
, 
Hosokawa, T.
, 
Takahashi, Y.
, 
Numata, T.
, 
Kurasaki, M.
, 
2005
. 
Metal binding ability of metallothionein-3 expressed in Escherichia coli
. 
Basic Clin. Pharma
96
(
4
), 
295–301
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Usha, B.
, 
Prashanth, S.
, 
Parida, A.
, 
2007
. 
Differential expression of two metallothionein encoding genes during heavy metal stress in the mangrove species, Avicennia marina (Forsk.) Vierh
. 
Curr. Sci. India
93
(
9
), 
1215–1219
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xue, T.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Zhu, W.
, 
Wu, C.
, 
Yang, G.
, 
Zheng, C.
, 
2008
. 
Cotton metallothionein GhMT3a, a reactive oxygen species scavenger, increased tolerance against abiotic stress in transgenic tobacco and yeast
. 
J. Exp. Bot.
60
(
1
), 
339–349
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zahed, M.A.
, 
Rouhani, F.
, 
Mohajeri, S.
, 
Bateni, F.
, 
Mohajeri, L.
, 
2010
. 
An overview of Iranian mangrove ecosystems, northern part of the Persian Gulf and Oman Sea
. 
Acta Ecol. Sin.
30
(
4
), 
240–244
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zamocky, M.
, 
Koller, F.
, 
1999
. 
Understanding the structure and function of catalases: clues from molecular evolution and in vitro mutagenesis
. 
Prog. Biophys. Mol. Biol.
72
(
1
), 
19–66
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhou, G.
, 
Xu, Y.
, 
Liu, J.
, 
2005
. 
Tissue expression patterns and induction in response to abiotic factors
. 
Plant Physiol.
162
, 
686–696
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhu, W.
, 
Zhao, D.-X.
, 
Miao, Q.
, 
Xue, T.-T.
, 
Li, X.-Z.
, 
Zheng, C.-C.
, 
2009
. 
Arabidopsis thaliana metallothionein, AtMT2a, mediates ROS balance during oxidative stress. J
. 
Plant Biol.
52
(
6
), 
585
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
