<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.112187</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>An electrophysiological characterization of naturally occurring tobacco alkaloids and their action on human α4β2 and α7 nicotinic acetylcholine receptors</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>29</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana tabacum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana tabacum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>oocytes: Nicotine</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
An electrophysiological characterization of naturally occurring tobacco alkaloids and their action on human α4β2 and α7 nicotinic acetylcholine receptors
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Omar Alijevic
a
, Damian McHugh

a, 

∗
, Lucien Rufener
b
, Anatoly Mazurov
a
, Julia Hoeng
a
,

Manuel Peitsch 
a
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a

PMI R&amp;D, Philip Morris Products S.A., Quai Jeanrenaud 5, CH-2000, 
Neuchâtel
, 
Switzerland
b

INVENesis Sárl, CH-2000, 
Neuchatel
, 
Switzerland
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana tabacum
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Tobacco alkaloids</p>
         <p>nAChR</p>
         <p>α4β2</p>
         <p>α7</p>
         <p>Nicotine</p>
         <p>Nornicotine</p>
         <p>Anabasine</p>
         <p>Anatabine</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
Nicotinic acetylcholine receptor (nAChR) subtype-selective pharmacological profiles of tobacco alkaloids are essential for understanding the physiological effects of tobacco products. In this study, automated electrophysiology was used to functionally characterize the effects of distinct groups of tobacco alkaloids on human α4β2 and α7 nAChRs. We found that, in tobacco alkaloids, pyridine as a hydrogen bond acceptor and a basic nitrogen atom at a distance of 4–7 Å are pharmacophoric elements necessary for molecular recognition by α4β2 and α7 nAChRs with various degrees of selectivity, potency, and efficacy. While four alkaloids—nicotine, nornicotine, anabasine and 
R
-anatabine—potently activated α4β2, they were also weak agonists of α7 nAChRs. Nicotine was the most potent agonist of α4β2, while anabasine elicited the highest activation of α7. None of the tobacco alkaloids enhanced nAChR activity elicited by the endogenous ligand acetylcholine; therefore, none was considered to be a positive allosteric modulator (PAM) of either α4β2 or α7 nAChRs. In contrast, we identified tobacco alkaloids, such as the tryptophan metabolite 6-hydroxykynurenic acid, that decreased the activity of both α4β2 and α7 nAChRs. Our study identified a class of alkaloids with positive and negative effects against human α4β2 and α7 nAChRs. It also revealed human α4β2 to be the principal receptor for sensing the most abundant alkaloids in tobacco leaves.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Alkaloids are nitrogen-containing natural organic compounds widely distributed throughout the plant kingdom. The major pyridine alkaloids of tobacco (
<tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana tabacum
</tp:taxon-name>
L.) have been the subject of particularly intensive exploration. A typical commercial tobacco plant produces alkaloids at levels between 2% and 4% of its total dry weight. Approximately 90% of the total alkaloid content is nicotine (

), with the structurally related alkaloids nornicotine, anabasine, and anatabine accounting for almost all of the remaining 10%. Pyridine alkaloids containing pyrrolidine or piperidine rings with a positively charged nitrogen atom serve as a defense against herbivores (

). Historically, research on nicotine and other tobacco alkaloids has focused mainly on the insecticidal and pharmacological properties of these compounds (

; 

). Although nicotine analogs and other pyridine alkaloids have shown a certain degree of toxicity in clinical studies (Kleinsasser et al., 2003; 

; 

; 

), they have demonstrated potential for treating cognitive disorders, depression, anxiety, cancer, and nociceptive and chronic inflammatory pain (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Similar to the endogenous neurotransmitter acetylcholine (ACh), nicotine activates ionotropic cholinergic receptors to depolarize neuronal membranes with diverse kinetic, electrophysiological, and pharmacological properties. Human nAChRs are encoded by sixteen genes, including nine that are expressed primarily in the brain (α2–α7 and β2–β4). The other seven, including those that 
<tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
muscle-nAChR subtype (α1, β1, γ, δ, and 
ε
) and α9 and α10, show primarily peripheral expression. The encoded protein subunits assemble in a pentameric structure around a central ion pore (

).
</p>
         <p>
Heteromeric α4β2 and homomeric α7 subtypes are the most abundant nicotinic receptors in the human brain. The role of these nAChR subtypes in cognitive processes, mood, pain, and neuroprotection has motivated the discovery of nAChR-selective compounds, some of which have been developed for Alzheimer's disease, attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), pain, schizophrenia, and major depression (

; 

; 

). nAChRs containing α3β4 protein units play a role in the well-known deleterious effects of nicotine on respiratory, cardiovascular, and gastrointestinal functions and in its addiction liability (

; 

). Except for metanicotine, tobacco alkaloids with pharmacophoric elements required for interaction with nAChRs are nonselective (

).
</p>
         <p>In the present study, we wanted to examine the therapeutic potential of tobacco by performing an electrophysiological characterization of naturally occurring tobacco alkaloids. We screened 71 tobacco alkaloids in “agonist mode” to explore their standalone properties and in the presence of the endogenous ligand acetylcholine to explore their capacity to act as positive modulators “PAM mode”.</p>
         <p>
The electrophysiological screening was performed against human α4β2 and α7 nAChRs with the goal of identifying compounds with activity for these receptor subtypes and against the human α3β4 nAChR deployed as a counter screen. The nAChRs were either stably expressed in Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cell lines or transiently injected into 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
for compound validation. Both expression systems have previously been deployed for characterizing nAChR pharmacology since no endogenous ionotropic nicotinic receptors are found (

; 

; 

; Papke and Smith-Maxwell, 2009). In the present study, the majority of tobacco alkaloids showed inhibitory effects against both α4β2 and α7 nAChRs. Importantly, four tobacco alkaloids—namely nicotine, nornicotine, anabasine, and R-anatabine—showed selective agonistic effects against human α4β2 nAChRs, providing insights for designing ligands that selectively interact with a distinct nAChR subtype.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
ACh exposure resulted in concentration-dependent activation of human α4β2 and α7 receptors in CHO cells (
Fig. 1
). The kinetics of ACh-induced transient currents in human α7 receptors were faster than those in human α4β2 receptors, with half-maximal effective concentration (EC 
50
) values of 142 ± 16 and 1.02 ± 1.0 μM, respectively (
Fig. 1
). The EC 
50
values of ACh against human α4β2, α7, and α3β4 nAChRs in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
were 6.16 ± 1.34, 98.71 ± 0.98, and 29.50 ± 5.74 μM, respectively (Supplementary 
Fig. 1
). Both expression systems (mammalian cells and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
) clearly demonstrated nAChR activity, in agreement with previous studies (

, 

; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The alkaloids were categorized into four groups according to the established pharmacophoric elements required for interaction with the α7 (

) and α4β2 (

) subtypes of nAChRs (
Table 1
):
</p>
         <p>A. Compounds containing pyridine as a hydrogen bond acceptor and a basic nitrogen atom, both of which are pharmacophoric elements necessary for molecular recognition by nAChRs;</p>
         <p>B. Compounds containing pyridine and an amide moiety replacing a basic nitrogen atom;</p>
         <p>C. Heteroaromatic compounds;</p>
         <p>D. Miscellaneous compounds.</p>
         <p>
The mechanisms of action of the tobacco alkaloids were tested in “agonist mode” and/or in “PAM mode” (
Fig. 2
). The compounds were tested in CHO cell lines stably expressing human α4β2 or α7 nAChRs by using an automated patch-clamp electrophysiology-based assay (see sections 4.3). In parallel, the most active alkaloids—that is, those in group A—were validated by a two-electrode voltage-clamp electrophysiological assay in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
expressing human α4β2 and α7 nAChRs and then counterscreened against α3β4 nAChRs (see section 4.5).
</p>
         <p>
To evaluate the agonistic effect, cells were exposed at 2-min intervals to a single alkaloid concentration (3.7 and/or 33.3 μM) for approximately 40–80 ms by using the integrated perfusion feature of the automated patch-clamp system (Patchliner, Nanion Technologies). At the end of the protocol, maximal activation of nAChR current was elicited by exposing the CHO cells to the 
ECmax
ACh corresponding to 33.3 and 900 μM for human α4β2 and α7 nAChRs, respectively. If the agonistic effect of an alkaloid exceeded ~10% of the maximum response induced by the ACh signal, additional concentration–response experiments were performed for potency assessment. A similar strategy was used to assess the agonistic effect of the alkaloids from group A in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
experiments (Supplementary 
Fig. 2
and section 4.5). The electrophysiological patch-clamp and two-electrode voltage-clamp endpoint data of the agonistic effects of the tobacco alkaloids are presented in 
Tables 1
and 
2
, respectively. The electrophysiological data are summarized as a heatmap in 
Table 4
.
</p>
         <p>
Nicotine (
1
) was found to be the most potent α4β2 agonist among the tested alkaloids, with 70 times greater potency than that against α7 (EC 
50
: 0.79 ± 0.16 and 57 ± 13.7 μM, respectively) (

; 

). However, it showed similar efficacy for both receptors (
Imax
values relative to the response of 
ECmax
ACh for α4β2 and α7 were 159% ± 17% and 150% ± 90%, respectively).
</p>
         <p>
The same trend was observed in the results obtained with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>oocytes: Nicotine</tp:taxon-name>
(
1
) was the most potent α4β2 agonist among the tested alkaloids, with 60 and 80 times greater potency than for α7 and α3β4 (EC 
50
: 0.45 ± 3.9, 27.08 ± 3.2, and 36.60 ± 3.2 μM, respectively). In contrast to the patch-clamp results, the results of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
</tp:taxon-name>
oocyte experiments suggest that nicotine has a lower efficacy against α4β2 and α7, while still behaving as a full agonist when applied to α3β4 (
Imax
: 17% ± 4%, 57% ± 13%, and 256% ± 89%, respectively).
</p>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
         <p>
Table 1
(
continued
)
</p>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
         <p>
Table 1
(
continued
)
</p>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
         <p>
Table 1
(
continued
)
</p>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
         <p>
Table 1
(
continued
)
</p>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
         <p>
Table 1
(
continued
)
</p>
         <p>
Alkaloids 
7–11
, which are structurally closely related to nicotine, exhibit structure–activity relationships similar to those of nicotine's synthetic analogue's, according to their affinity binding data for the rat brain agonist site (

) as well as the ability of these alkaloids to stimulate dopamine release from striatal synaptosomes (

). The increase in nitrogen basicity in the pyrrolidine ring (compound 
7
) and incorporation of bulky substituents (compounds 
8
and 
9
) were both found to negatively impact the ability of the molecules to activate nAChRs. Nornicotine (
7
) showed similar agonistic efficacies for α4β2 and α7, but it was at least 20 times more potent for α4β2 than for α7 (
Imax
α4β2: 70% ± 11%; 
Imax
α7: 59.15% ± 15%, and EC 
50
α4β2: 4.92 ± 0.7 μM; EC 
50
α7&gt; 100 μM). Similar to the experiments in CHO cell lines, those in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
proved nornicotine (
7
) to be a partial agonist of α4β2 and a weak agonist of α7 but with a high efficacy (EC 
50
α4β2: 3.12 ± 2.9 μM; 
Imax
α4β2: 19% ± 2%). The EC 
50
for α7 could not be fitted, as the current response did not reach a plateau at 300 μM (
Imax
α7: 70% ± 10%). Nornicotine (
7
) also produced pronounced effects on α3β4 nAChR (EC 
50
: 42.7 ± 2.8 μM; 
Imax
: 122% ± 18%).
</p>
         <p>
Myosmine (
10
) and isomyosmine (
11
) have been found to exist in two forms, cyclic and linear. The latter is protonated at physiological pH, unlike the cyclic imine. While basicity of the pyrroline ring is insufficient to ensure interaction with nAChRs, the linear form of isomyosmine contains a fragment of 3-(aminomethyl)pyridine (

), which might contribute to the modest interaction of isomyosmine (
11
) with the α4β2 nAChR (EC 
50
: 30.5 ± 9.9 μM). When tested in oocytes at 33.3 μM, myosmine (
10
) and isomyosmine (
11
) failed to exert any agonistic effect on α4β2, α7, or α3β4 (
Table 2
and 
Table 4
).
</p>
         <p>
Anabasine (
12
), a cyclic homolog of nornicotine (
7
), was the only alkaloid demonstrating greater agonist efficacy for α7 (
Imax
: 136% ± 53%) versus α4β2 and α3β4. Although it was more potent (but less effective) at opening α4β2 than α7, anabasine (
12
) displayed weak α4β2 agonistic effects (
Imax
α4β2: 12% ± 7%; EC 
50
α4β2: 0.9 ± 0.0 μM; EC 
50
α7: 42.6 ± 14.6 μM).
</p>
         <p>
The results of the two-electrode voltage-clamp experiments in oocytes for anabasine (
12
) were comparable with those from the patch-clamp experiments in CHO cells. While anabasine (
12
) was the alkaloid with the greatest agonist efficacy for α7 and can be classified as a superagonist of this receptor, it was almost inefficacious against α4β2 and relatively active against α3β4 (
Imax
: 122% ± 10%, 3% ± 2.1%, and 82% ± 20%, respectively; EC 
50
: 15.45 ± 3.1, 4.41 ± 11, and 26.20 ± 3 μM, respectively).
</p>
         <p>
However, anabasine derivatives with small (compound 
13
) or aromatic (compounds 
14
, 
15
, 
20–23
) substituents were practically inactive against all nicotinic channels. Anatabine (
16
, 
17
) is a dehydrogenated analogue of anabasine. The incorporation of a double bond almost eliminated the weak agonism of anatabine for α7 nAChR without significantly influencing its interaction with α4β2 nAChR, although α4β2 nAChR exhibited stereochemical preference for the (
R
)-enantiomer (for α4β2, S-anatabine [
16]
EC 
50
and 
Imax
: 7.7 ± 2.2 μM and 8% ± 1%, respectively; R-anatabine [
17
] EC 
50
and 
Imax
: 3.41 ± 0.8 μM and 23% ± 6%). The potency and efficacy of N-methylanatabine (
18
) were comparable with those of (R)-anatabine (
17
) for α4β2 (EC 
50
: 6.2 ± 2.0 μM; 
Imax
: 25.6% ± 1%).
</p>
         <p>
In oocytes, S-anatabine (
16
) was more effective than R-anatabine (
17
), with greater potency against α7. In contrast, both enantiomers showed similar potency and efficacy for the α4β2 nAChR (
Table 2
). Both compounds were also found to be partial agonists of the α3β4 nAChR, with moderate efficacies (S-anatabine, 
Imax
: 16% ± 7% and EC 
50
: 52.30 ± 3.8 μM; R-anatabine, 
Imax
: 43% ± 27% and EC 
50
: 37.70 ± 4.4 μM).
</p>
         <p>
Similarly, in the patch-clamp experiments, the potency and efficacy of N-methylanatabine (
18
) for α4β2 were comparable with those of (
R
)- anatabine (
17
) (EC 
50
: 10.8 ± 3.5 μM; 
Imax
: 6 ± 2%). In addition, Nmethylanatabine (
18
) was also found to be a weak partial agonist of the α3β4 nAChR (
Table 2
).
</p>
         <p>
Metanicotine (
5
) was the most selective α4β2 agonist among all tobacco alkaloids tested with demonstrable nAChR activity, with a maximal response of 261.5% in CHO cell lines (151% in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
), but without appreciable activation of α7 nAChR (
Tables 1
and 
2
). Structurally related to metanicotine, pseudooxynicotines (
24–26
) appeared to be inactive in our experiments (
Tables 1
and 
2
).
</p>
         <p>
Among the compounds from groups B, C, and D, only cotinine (
30
) displayed weak agonist activity for α4β2 (EC 
50
: 85.3 ± 13.4 μM). Alkaloids from groups B, C, and D had negligible effects on α4β2 and α7 nAChRs, as they likely do not fit the common nicotinic pharmacophore model, which consists of two essential elements: a cationic center, typically a protonated amino group, and a hydrogen bond acceptor, often contained in a π-electron moiety such as the pyridine ring. The distance between these two elements varies from 4 Å to 7 Å (

). This pattern of essential pharmacophoric elements among the tobacco alkaloids in group A is consistent with our functional electrophysiological data on α4β2 and α7 nAChRs. However, additional work is required to establish a comprehensive pharmacophore model for other subtypes of the human nAChR family.
</p>
         <p>
A subset of the tobacco alkaloid library was screened at concentrations of 3.7 μM and/or 33.3 μM in the PAM mode (
Fig. 2
). To investigate the PAM potential of a given alkaloid, ionic currents were first elicited by applying the EC 
20
dose of ACh, after which the CHO cells were exposed to a given alkaloid for 2 min before a final cotreatment with the ACh EC 
20
dose (
Fig. 2
; see section 4.4). It is pertinent to mention that the EC 
20
concentration of ACh was selected in order to minimize the α4β2 and α7 current run-down over time (
Fig. 3
). The EC 
20
ACh corresponded to 0.412 μM for α4β2 nAChRs and 100 μM for α7 nAChRs. A similar approach was used to investigate the PAM effects of the alkaloids in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
(see Supplementary 
Fig. 2
and section 4.5). The electrophysiological patch-clamp and two-electrode voltage-clamp endpoint data of the PAM effects for the tobacco alkaloids are presented in 
Table 3
(see also 
Table 4
).
</p>
         <p>
Table 2
(
continued
)
</p>
         <p>
We defined a relevant PAM as a compound that potentiated the ACh EC 
20
-induced peak current by at least two-fold without displaying any agonistic effects. While no compound with PAM properties was identified, several alkaloids inhibited the ACh-induced response of both nAChRs. On the basis of our data, we could not distinguish competitive/ non-competitive antagonists from negative allosteric modulators (NAMs). Thirteen alkaloids were identified as inhibitors of the ACh-induced α4β2 nAChR current (by ≥ 80%) without showing any agonistic activity (at least up to 33.3 μM). In order of degree of inhibition, these were compounds 
37
, 
8
, 
13
, 
14
, 
36
, 
54
, 
40
, 
45
, 
10
, 
68
, 
33
, 
34
, and 
65
. Nine alkaloids were found to be α7 nAChR inhibitors with no agonistic effects (
54
, 
5
, 
37
, 
36
, 
16
, 
17
, 
23
, 
13
, and 
14
). Despite the fact that metanicotine (
5
) and S- and R-anatabine (
16
and 
17
) activated α4β2, we only detected their strong inhibitory effects against human α7 nAChR. Additionally, we identified 6-hydroxykynurenic acid (
54
) (

), a tryptophan metabolite, as a dual α4β2 and α7 nAChR-inhibitory alkaloid. Interestingly, 6-hydroxykynurenic acid (
54
) has already been shown to differentially inhibit other neuronal ion channels, such as AMPA and NMDA receptors, in hippocampal neurons, suggesting a wider role as an endogenous inhibitor (

).
</p>
         <p>
The two approaches most commonly used for heterologous expression of cloned ion channels and transporters involve transfection of the genes into cells grown in tissue culture or injection of the genetic material into larger cells (

; Papke and Smith-Maxwell, 2009). We used both approaches—mammalian cell lines and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
—for compound validation because some channels express more readily in oocytes than in mammalian cells and vice versa. We observed a shift in the concentration–response curves of many compounds when comparing EC50 values between 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
and mammalian CHO cells. The possible reasons for this inequality in compound potency have not been clearly investigated, but the discrepancy can be attributed to several differences in post-translational processing of proteins, the diverse composition of the cell membrane, and dissimilarities in extracellular ion concentrations during electrophysiological analysis of oocytes and mammalian cell lines (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
When consuming tobacco products, the free plasma concentration of nicotine, nornicotine, anabasine, and anatabine has been reported to range from 0.06 to 0.6 μM (

, 

). While the absolute concentration of tobacco alkaloids present at synapses is unknown, the levels of nicotine in the cerebrospinal fluid of smokers have been found to be high (up to 1.3 μM), double that reported in plasma (

). We found four alkaloids (nicotine, nornicotine, anabasine, and R-anatabine) with potencies below 5 μM for α4β2; these compounds represent the most abundant alkaloids present in commercial tobacco plants (

). Interestingly, none of the alkaloids displayed such potency (&lt;5 μM) against the α7 and α3β4 subtypes. Although their EC 
50
for α4β2 receptors (0.79–4.92 μM; 
Table 1
) is outside their expected plasma concentration in tobacco users (0.06–0.6 μM), channel opening can nevertheless be anticipated at these concentrations (
Fig. 4
). Furthermore, certain pathological conditions (e.g., kidney failure or exposure to medications inhibiting nicotine clearance by CYPA6) might cause an increase in the levels of tobacco alkaloids (

). Therefore, the physiological and pathological concentrations of the main tobacco alkaloids in tobacco users most likely reach sufficient levels to uniquely impact the function of α4β2 nAChRs.
</p>
         <p>
Gaining a better understanding of nicotine's interaction with diverse receptor subtypes with therapeutic potential has helped to develop clinical drug candidates for neuropathological conditions such as Alzheimer's disease, ADHD, pain, schizophrenia, and major depression (

; 

). The electrophysiological characterization of the tobacco alkaloids presented in our manuscript would help to better understand the interactions of the tobacco alkaloids with the diverse nAChR subtypes and, optimistically, facilitate the development of appropriate scaffolds for further drug development.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>In summary, 71 tobacco alkaloids were categorized into four groups on the basis of nAChR pharmacophoric elements and characterized by automated electrophysiological assays. We demonstrated that tobacco alkaloids containing pyridine as a hydrogen bond acceptor and a basic nitrogen atom—pharmacophoric elements necessary for molecular recognition by nAChRs—stimulated both α4β2 and α7 nAChRs with varying degrees of selectivity, potency, and efficacy. Four alkaloids—nicotine, nornicotine, anabasine and R-anatabine—potently activated α4β2 and weakly activated α7 nAChRs. While nicotine was the most potent α4β2 agonist, cotinine was the weakest among the active alkaloids. Anabasine produced the highest α7 activation. Metanicotine was the most selective α4β2 agonist and exerted maximum efficacy. The tobacco alkaloids did not enhance the nAChR activity elicited by the endogenous ligand ACh (i.e., they were not PAMs of α4β2 or α7 nAChRs) but rather acted as inhibitory compounds of both receptors by reducing the channel function evoked by ACh. In conclusion, we have demonstrated the pharmacological characteristics of an entire panel of tobacco alkaloids by using human α4β2 and α7 nAChRs to provide evidence that the human α4β2 nAChR is a pharmacologically relevant target for sensing the physiological concentrations of the most abundant alkaloids present in tobacco plants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Table 3
(
continued
)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Table 3
(
continued
)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Table 3
(
continued
)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Table 3
(
continued
)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. Alkaloids
</title>
         <p>
Alkaloids (of ACS reagent-grade purity or higher) were purchased from commercial sources or provided by WuXi AppTec Co., Ltd. (
Shanghai
, 
China
) and Selvita S.A. (Krakow, 
Poland
). Stock solutions of the alkaloids were prepared as 100 mM solutions in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and stored at −20 °C. All chemicals were prepared daily in external recording solutions and diluted to appropriate concentrations for electrophysiological recordings. Compound solutions contained 0.3% DMSO and were prepared in 96-well compound plates.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Cell culture
</title>
         <p>
CHO cell lines stably expressing human α7/Ric3 nAChR (hα7/Ric3 nAChR-CHO) and human α4β2 nAChR (hα4β2 nAChR-CHO) were obtained from Charles River Laboratories (Wilmington, MA, 
USA
). The cells were maintained in DMEM/F12 medium (Gibco, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, 
USA
) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (Gibco) and penicillin–streptomycin (100 U/mL and 
0.1 mg
/mL, respectively) solution (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, 
USA
) at 37 °C in 5% CO 
2
and 70% humidity. Hα7/Ric3 nAChR-CHO cells were continuously cultured in the presence of G418 (
0.25 mg
/mL, Sigma-Aldrich) and zeocin (
0.4 mg
/mL, InvivoGen, San Diego, CA, 
USA
). Hα4β2 nAChR CHO cells were continuously cultured in the presence of puromycin (8 μg/mL, InvivoGen) and hygromycin (
0.4 mg
/mL, Gibco) per manufacturer protocols.
</p>
         <p>
For patch-clamp experiments, the cells were seeded in 
60 mm
cell culture dishes. Six hours later, the cells were transferred to a 30 °C incubator (5% CO 
2
, 70% humidity) and cultured for 1–4 days to enhance nAChR expression (

). On the day of the electrophysiological recordings, the cells were washed with phosphate-buffered saline (Sigma-Aldrich), detached by using 10% StemPro Accutase (4 min at 30 °C; Gibco), re-suspended in extracellular solution, and maintained at 4 °C for 15 min. Cells used for automated patch-clamp measurements were kept in suspension for approximately 2 h.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Automated patch-clamp electrophysiology in CHO cells
</title>
         <p>
Electrophysiological measurements were performed by using the whole-cell configuration of the patch-clamp technique with an automated patch-clamp system (Patchliner Octo 
®
, Nanion Technologies, Munich, 
Germany
) in accordance with the manufacturer's standard procedures. The Patchliner Octo 
®
is equipped with two EPC-10 Quadro patch-clamp amplifiers (HEKA Elektronik, Lambrecht, 
Germany
) permitting electrophysiological recordings of up to eight cells simultaneously. The external solution contained 140 mM NaCl, 4 mM KCl, 1 mM MgCl 
2
, 2 mM CaCl 
2
, 5 mM glucose, and 10 mM HEPES, adjusted to pH 7.4 with NaOH (298 mOsmol). The internal solution contained 50 mM KCl, 60 mM kF, 10 mM NaCl, 20 mM EGTA, and 10 mM HEPES, adjusted to pH 7.2 with KOH (285 mOsmol). A seal-enhancer solution containing 80 mM NaCl, 3 mM KCl, 10 mM MgCl 
2
, 35 mM CaCl 
2
, and 10 mM HEPES (pH 7.4 adjusted with HCl, 298 mOsmol) was used and replaced with the external solution once the whole-cell configuration was established. The solutions were filtered through a 0.22-μM membrane (Merck Millipore, Burlington, MA, 
USA
) and maintained for up to 6 months at room temperature (24 °C).
</p>
         <p>Data acquisition was performed with the PatchControlHT software (Nanion Technologies, ver. 2.01.31) in combination with the Patchmaster software (HEKA Elektronik, ver. 2 × 90.4 beta). For ligand-gated channel activation, 5 μL of a given ligand was applied at a speed of 114 μL/s, directly followed by 120 μL of external solution for washout. Data were recorded at a holding potential of −70 mV and a sampling rate of 20 kHz and filtered at 3 kHz.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Data analysis and acceptance criteria
</title>
         <p>
Data were analyzed by using Patchmaster and corrected for leak current. The data acceptance criteria were as follows: seal resistance,&gt; 100 M 
Ώ
; seal resistance loss variation, &lt;50%; access resistance, &lt;20 M 
Ώ
; and minimum current amplitude elicited by 
ECmaxACh
,&gt; 100 pA. Offline data analysis was performed in Apache OpenOffice™ (Microsoft, Redmond, WA, 
USA
; ver. 4.1.2). Data are presented as mean ± SD. All experiments were performed at room temperature (24 °C).
</p>
         <p>Agonistic effects (percent activation) were calculated as:</p>
         <p>(I ago/I max ACh)100,</p>
         <p>
where 
Iago
is the agonist-induced current of the tobacco alkaloids at 3.7 or 33.3 μM.
</p>
         <p>PAM effects of the alkaloids (in percent) on the channels were calculated as:</p>
         <p>(I ago+EC20ACh/I EC20ACh)100,</p>
         <p>
where 
Iago+EC20ACh
was the ACh EC 
20
-elicited current in the presence of 3.7 or 33.3 μM of the tobacco alkaloids.
</p>
         <p>
Igor Pro (ver. 6.2.2.2, Lake Oswego, OR, 
USA
) was used for assessing the concentration-response curves by fitting with the following Hill equation: I max/([1 + (Ago EC50/Ago)nH]),
</p>
         <p>
where 
Imax
is the maximal current, Ago EC 
50
is the agonist concentration producing half-maximal activation, Ago is the agonist concentration, and nH is the Hill coefficient.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Automated two-electrode voltage-clamp electrophysiological assay in
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
All experiments were conducted with human nAChRs expressed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
. Currents evoked by ACh and other compounds of interest were recorded by using an automated two-electrode voltage-clamp system (HiClamp, Multichannel Systems, Reutlingen, 
Germany
). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenopus
oocytes
</tp:taxon-name>
were prepared and injected using standard procedures. Defoliculated oocytes (Ecocyte Bioscience, Castrop-Rauxel, 
Germany
) were injected with 
0.1–1 ng
of cRNA per oocyte by using an automated injector (Roboinject, Multi Channel Systems). For all experiments conducted with subunits, the oocytes were injected at a 1:1 cRNA ratio such that both forms would be expressed at equal levels (Supplementary 
Fig. 3
). All recordings were performed at 18 ± 4 °C, and the cells were perfused with OR2 medium containing 88.5 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM KCl, 1.5 mM HEPES, and 2.5 mM CaCl 
2
(pH 7.4). The cells were held at −80 mV, and data were captured at 100 Hz, filtered at 20 Hz, and analyzed by using the HiClamp data acquisition and analysis software running under MATLAB (MathWorks Inc., Natick, MA, 
USA
). Statistical analysis was performed by using Prism (GraphPad, La Jolla, CA, 
USA
; ver. 5) and Excel (Microsoft, ver. 14.7.3). Selected tobacco alkaloids were tested on oocytes expressing human α7, α4β2, and α3β4 nAChRs. Cells expressing significant current evoked by a brief ACh pulse (10 μM) were tested for their response to tobacco alkaloids (concentrations, 3.7 and 33.3 μM) by using the screening protocol in order to determine the agonistic effects of the compounds. The percentage of agonism was assessed by comparing the response to the reference ACh peak current.
</p>
         <p>
Funding
</p>
         <p>Philip Morris International is the sole source of funding and sponsor of this research.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>We would like to thank Marco Van der Toorn and Yueh-Wen Lin for compound preparation and Dean Meyer for manuscript review.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.112187.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baldwin, I.T.
, 
Halitschke, R.
, 
Kessler, A.
, 
Schittko, U.
, 
2001
. 
Merging molecular and ecological approaches in plant–insect interactions
. 
Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.
4
, 
351–358
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S1369-5266(00)00184-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Blum
, 
Angela P.
, 
Lester
, 
Henry A.
, 
Dougherty
, 
Dennis A.
, 
2010
. 
Nicotinic pharmacophore: the pyridine N of nicotine and carbonyl of acetylcholine hydrogen bond across a subunit interface to a backbone NH
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci
. 
13206–13211
. 
https://doi. org/10.1073/pnas.1007140107
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Briggs, C.A.
, 
Mckenna, D.G.
, Piattina-kaplan, M., 
1995
. 
Human α 7 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor responses to novel ligands
. 
Neuropharmacology
583–590
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/0028-3908(95)00028-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Buisson, B.
, 
Gopalakrishnan, M.
, 
Arneric, S.P.
, 
Sullivan, J.P.
, 
Bertrand, D.
, 
1996
. 
Human α4β2 neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptor in HEK 293 cells: a patch-clamp study. J
. 
Neurosci.
16
, 
24
. 
https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.16-24-07880.1996
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Burton, R.F.
, 
1983
. 
The composition of animal cells: solutes contributing to osmotic pressure and charge balance
. 
Comp. Biochem. Physiol. B
76
(
4
), 
663–671
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/0305-0491(83)90375-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cosford, N.D.
, 
Bleicher, L.
, 
Vernier, J.M.
, 
Chavez-Noriega, L.
, 
Rao, T.S.
, 
Siegel, R.S.
, 
Suto, C.
, 
Washburn, M.
, 
Lloyd, G.K.
, 
McDonald, I.A.
, 
2000
. 
Recombinant human receptors and functional assays in the discovery of altinicline (SIB-1508Y), a novel acetylcholine-gated ion channel (nAChR) agonist
. 
Pharm. Acta Helv.
74
(2– 
3
), 
125–130
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0165-7208(00)80008-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Echeverria, V.
, 
2012
. 
Cotinine: beyond that expected, more than a biomarker of tobacco consumption
. 
Front. Pharmacol.
3
, 
1–9
. 
https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2012.00173
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Echeverria, V.
, 
Grizzell, J.A.
, GE, Barreto, 
2016
. 
Neuroinflammation: a therapeutic target of cotinine for the treatment of psychiatric disorders? Curr. Pharmaceut
. 
Des.
22
, 
1324–1333
. 

https://doi.org/10.2174/ 
138161282210160304112511

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Glennon, R.A.
, 
Dukat, M.
, 
2004
. 
α4β2 nACh receptor pharmacophore models
. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett
14
, 
1841–1844
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmcl.2003.07.035
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Glennon, R.A.
, 
Maarouf, A.
, 
Fahmy, S.
, 
Martin, B.
, 
Fan, F.
, 
Yousif, M.
, 
Shafik, R.M.
, 
Dukat, M.
, 
1993
. 
Structure-activity relationships of simple nicotine analogs
. 
Med. Chem. Res.
2
, 
546–551
. 
https://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/10011030393
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Graham, A.
, 
Court, J.A.
, 
CM
Martin-Ruiz, E
Jaros
, 
Perry, R.
, 
Volsen, S.G.
, 
Bose, S.
, et al., 
2002
. 
Immunohistochemical localisation of nicotinic acetylcholine receptor subunits in human cerebellum
. 
Neuroscience
113
(
3
), 
493–507
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ S0306-4522(02)00223-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grando
, 
Sergei A.
, 
2014
. 
Connections of nicotine to cancer
. 
Nat. Rev. Cancer
419–429
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/nrc3725
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hamouda
, 
Ayman K.
, 
Deba, Farah
, 
Wang, Ze-Jun
, 
Cohen
, 
Jonathan B.
, 
2016
. 
Photolabeling a nicotinic acetylcholine receptor (nAChR) with an (α4)3(β2)2 nAChR-selective positive allosteric modulator
. 
Mol. Pharmacol.
89
(
5
), 
575–584
. 
https://doi. org/10.1124/mol.116.103341
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Holtman, J.R.
, 
Crooks, P.A.
, 
Dwoskin, L.
, 
Wala, E.P.
, 
2010
. 
Nornicotine for the Treatment of Pain
. 
USA Patent
20100216847
, August 
26
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hone
, 
Arik J.
, 
Michael McIntosh, J.
, Rueda-Ruzafa, Lola, Passas, Juan, de Castro-Guerín, Cristina, Blázq, Jesús, González-Enguita, Carmen, Albillos, Almudena, 
2017
. 
Therapeutic concentrations of varenicline in the presence of nicotine increase action potential firing in human adrenal chromaffin cells. J
. 
Neurochem.
140
(
1
), 
37–52
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jnc.13883
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hukkanen, J.
, 
Jacob III, P.
, 
Benowitz, N.L.
, 
2005
. 
Metabolism and disposition kinetics of nicotine
. 
Pharmacol. Rev.
79
, 
115
. 
https://doi.org/10.1124/pr.57.1.3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jacob III, P L Yu
, 
Shulgin, A.T.
, 
Benowitz, N.L.
, 
1999
. 
Minor tobacco alkaloids as biomarkers for tobacco use: comparison ofUsers of Cigarettes, smokeless tobacco, cigars, and pipes
. 
Am. J. Public Health
731–736 PMID: 
10224986
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ji
, 
Lin
, Melkonian, Goar, Riveles, Karen, Tal, Prue, 
2002
. 
Identification of pyridine compounds in cigarette smoke solution that inhibit growth of the chick chorioallantoic membrane
. 
Toxicol. Sci.
69
(
1
), 
217–225
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/ toxsci/69.1.217
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Josefsberg, Ben-Yehoshua
, 
Nava
, Dekel, 
2002
. 
Translational and post-translational modifications in meiosis of the mammalian oocyte
. 
Mol. Cell. Endocrinol.
187
, 
161–171
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0303-7207(01)00688-8. Issues 1–2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Khan, H.
, 
Patel, S.
, 
Kamal, M.S.
, 
2017
. 
Pharmacological and toxicological profile of harmane-β-carboline alkaloid: friend or foe
. 
Curr. Drug Metabol.
18
(
9
), 
853–857
. 

https://doi.org/10.2174/ 
1389200218666170607100947

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kirsch
, 
Glenn E.
, 
Fedorov
, 
Nikolai B.
, 
Kuryshev
, 
Yuri A.
, 
Liu, Zhiqi
, 
Armstrong
, 
Lucas C.
, 
Orr
, 
Michael S.
, 
2016
. 
Electrophysiology-based assays to detect subtype-selective modulation of human nicotinic acetylcholine receptors. Assay Drug Dev
. 
Technol.
14
(
6
), 
333–344
. 
https://doi.org/10.1089/adt.2015.688
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kleinsasser, N.H.
, 
Wallner, B.C.
, 
Harréus, U.A.
, 
Zwickenpflug, W.
, 
Richter, E.
, 
2003
. 
Genotoxic effects of myosmine in human lymphocytes and upper aerodigestive tract epithelial cells
. 
Toxicology
192
, 
171–177
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0300-483X(03) 00296-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lin, N.H.
, 
Carrera, C.M.
, 
Anderson, D.J.
, 
1994
. 
Synthesis and evaluation of nicotine analogs as neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptor ligands
. 
J. Med. Chem.
37
, 
3542–3553
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jm00047a012
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lin, C.Y.
, 
Huang, Z.
, 
Wen, W.
, 
Wu, A.
, 
Wang, C.
, 
Niu, L.
, 
2015
. 
Enhancing protein expression in HEK-293 cells by lowering culture temperature
. 
PLoS One
10
(
4
), e 
0123562
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0123562
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lippiello, P.M.
, 
Caldwell, W.S.
, 
1993
. 
Method for Treatment of Neurodegenerative Diseases
. 
USA Patent
, pp. 5242934.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lippiello, P.M.
, 
Bencherif, M.
, 
Caldwell, W.S.
, 
Arrington, S.R.
, 
Fowler, K.W.
, 
Lovette, M.E.
, 
Reeves, L.K.
, 
1996
. 
Metanicotine: a nicotinic agonist with central nervous system selectivity-in vitro and in vivo characterization. Drug Dev
. 
Res.
38
, 
169–176
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1098-2299(199607/08)38:3/4&lt;169::AID-DDR5&gt;3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Macnicol, P.K.
, 
1968
. 
Isolation for 6-hydroxykynurenic acid from the tobacco leaf
. 
Biochem. J.
473–479 PMID: 
5665251
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Malkawia, A.H.
, 
Al-Ghananeema, A.M.
, 
Leon, Jd
, 
Crooks, P.A.
, 
2008
. 
Nicotine exposure can be detected in cerebrospinal fluid of active
. 
J. Pharm. Biomed. Anal.
129
, 
132
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpba.2008.10.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mazurov, A.A.
, 
Speake, J.D.
, 
Yohannes, D.
, 
2011
. 
Discovery and development of α7 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor modulators
. 
J. Med. Chem.
54
, 
7943–7961
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1021/jm2007672
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mazurov, A.A.
, 
Miao, L.
, 
Bhatti, B.S.
, 
Strachan, J.P.
, 
Akireddy, S.
, 
Murthy, S.
, 
Kombo, D.
, et al., 
2012
. 
Discovery of 3-(5-chloro-2-furoyl)-3,7-diazabicyclo[3.3.0]octane (TC-6683, AZD1446), a novel highly selective α4β2 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor agonist for the treatment of cognitive disorders
. 
J. Med. Chem.
55
, 
9181–9194
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jm3006542
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Miller, E.I.
, 
Norris, HR
, 
Rollins, DE
, 
Tiffany, S.T.
, 
Wilkins, D.G.
, 
2009
. 
A novel validated procedure for the determination of nicotine, eight nicotine metabolites and two minor tobacco alkaloids in human plasma or urine by solid-phase extraction coupled with liquid chromatography-electrospray ionization-tandem mass spectrometr. J Chromatogr
. 
B Anal. Technol. Biomed. Life Sci
. 
725–737
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. jchromb.2009.12.018
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mishra, Aseem, Chaturvedi, Pankaj, Datta, Sourav, Sinukumar, Snita, Joshi, Poonam, Garg, Apurva
, 
2015
. 
Harmful effects of nicotine
. 
Indian J. Med. Paediatr. Oncol
. 
24–31
. 
https://doi.org/10.4103/0971-5851.151771
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Owen, R.T.
, 
Serradell, N.
, 
Rosa, E.
, 
2008
. 
Ispronicline: nicotinic acetylcholine α4β2 agonist treatment of cognition disorders
. 
Drugs Future
33
(
3
), 
197–202
. 
https://doi. org/10.1358/dof.2008.033.03.1184544
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Papke, R.L.
, 
Porter Papke, J.K.
, 
2002
. 
Comparative pharmacology of rat and human α7 nAChR conducted with net charge analysis
. 
Br. J. Pharmacol.
49
, 
61
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1038/sj.bjp.0704833
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Papke
, 
Roger L.
, Smith-Maxwell, Cathy, 
2009
. 
High-throughput electrophysiology with Xenopus oocytes
. 
Comb. Chem. High Throughput Screen.
12
(
1
), 
38–50
. 
https://doi. org/10.2174/138620709787047975
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Potter, A.
, 
Corwin, J.
, 
Lang, J.
, 
Piasecki, M.
, 
Lenox, R.
, 
Newhouse, P.A.
, 
1999
. 

Acute effects of the selective cholinergic channel activator (nicotinic agonist) ABT- 
418 in
Alzheimer's disease

. 
Psychopharmacology
142
(
4
), 
334–342
. 
https://doi.org/10. 1007/s002130050897
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Roncarati, Renza
, 
Seredenina, Tamara
, 
Jow, Brian
, 
Jow, Flora
, 
Papini, Silvia
, 
Kramer, Angela
, 
Bothmann, Hendrick
, 
Dunlop, John

, 
Georg, C.
, Terstappen, 
2008
. 
Functional properties of α
7
nicotinic acetylcholine receptors Co-expressed with RIC- 

3
in

a stable recombinant CHO-K1 cell line. Assay Drug Dev. Technol. 6 (2). 
https://doi.org/10. 1089/adt.2007.120
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rueter, L.E.
, 
Anderson, D.J.
, 
Birggs, C.A.
, 
Donnelly-Roberts, D.L.
, 
Gintant, G.A.
, 
Gopalakrishnan, M.
, 
Lin, N.H.
, et al., 
2004
. 
ABT-089: pharmacological properties of a neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptor agonist for the potential treatment of cognitive disorders
. 
CNS Drug Rev.
10
(
2
), 
167–182
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j. 1527-3458.2004.tb00011.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Saitoh, F.
, 
Nona, M.
, 
Kawashima, N.
, 
1985
. 
The alkaloid contents of sixty Nicotiana species
. 
Phytochemistry
24
, 
477–480
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(00) 80751-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sapronov, N.S.
, 
Khnychenko, L.K.
, 
1982
. 
Pharmacology of the Anabasis aphylla alkaloids anabasine and anabasamine
. 
Farmakologiia i toksikologiia
45
(
6
), 
25–27
PMID: 7151996.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Scheffel, Corinna
, 
Niessen, K.V.
, 
Rappenglück, S.
, 
Wanner, K.T.
, 
Thiermann, H.
, 
Worek, F.
, 
Seeger, T.
, 
2018
. 
Counteracting desensitization of human α7-nicotinic acetylcholine receptors with bispyridinium compounds as an approach against organophosphorus poisoning
. 
Toxicol. Lett.
293
, 
149–156
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxlet. 2017.12.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Steppuhn, A K
Gase
, 
Krock, B.
, 
Halitschke, R.
, 
Baldwin, I.T.
, 
2004
. 
Nicotine's defensive function in nature
. 
PLoS Biol.
2
, 
1074–1080
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio. 0020217
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tang, Jing-shu
, 
Xie, Bing-xue
, 
Bian, Xi-ling
, 
Xue, Yu
, 
Wei, Ning-ning
, 
Zhou, Jing-heng
, 
Yu-chen
, 
Hao, Li
, Gang, Zhang, Liang-ren, Wang, Ke-wei, 
2015
. 
Identification and in vitro pharmacological characterization of a novel and selective α7 nicotinic acetylcholine receptor agonist, Br-IQ17B
. 
Acta Pharmacol. Sin.
36
, 
800–812
. 
https://doi. org/10.1038/aps.2015.9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tsuzaki, Y.
, 
Ito, A.
, 
Kiuchi, K.
, 
1994
. 
Lumichrome Derivatives as Inhibitors for Cancer Metastasis
., 06279445 Japan Patent.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Weber, M.
, 
Dietrich, D.
, 
Gräsel, I.
, 
Reuter, G.
, 
Seifert, G.
, 
Steinhäuser, C.
, 
2001
. 6- 
Hydroxykynurenic acid and kynurenic acid differently antagonise AMPA and NMDA receptors in hippocampal neurones. J
. 
Neurochem
. 
1108–1115
. 
https://doi.org/10. 1046/j.1471-4159.2001.00340.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wu, Jie
, 
Liu
, 
Qiang, Yu
, 
Kewei, Hu
, 
Jun, Kuo
, 
Yen-Ping, Segerberg
, 
Marsha, Paul A
St John, J
Lukas, Ronald, 
2006
. 
Roles of nicotinic acetylcholine receptor βsubunits in function of human α4-containing nicotinic receptors
. 
J. Physiol
. 
103–118
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1113/jphysiol.2006.114645
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yang, Taoyi
, 
Xiao, Ting
, 
Sun, Qi
, Wanga, Kewei, 
2017
. 
The current agonists and positive allosteric modulators of α7 nAChR for CNS indications in clinical trials
. 
Acta Pharm. Sin. B
611–622
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apsb.2017.09.001
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
