<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112920</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Eudesmane-type and agarospirane-type sesquiterpenes from agarwood of Aquilaria agallocha</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
Roxb.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
Roxb.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
Roxb. (Thymelaeaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Actinobole uliginosum
(A. Grey) H. Eichler
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. sinensis
(
Li et al., 2015
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A.agallocha
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. agallocha
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. agallocha
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
Roxb. (Thymelaeaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Eudesmane-type and agarospirane-type sesquiterpenes from agarwood of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Yanqiao Xie
a
, Leixin Song
a
, Chunge Li
c
, Yingbo Yang
a
, Siyu Zhang
a
, Hong Xu
a, b
,

Zhengtao Wang a, b

, Zhuzhen Han

a, 

**
, Li Yang

a, b, 
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
The MOE Key Laboratory of Standardization of Chinese Medicines and the SATCM Key Laboratory of New Resources and Quality Evaluation of Chinese Medicines,
Institute of Chinese Materia Medica, 
Shanghai
University of Traditional Chinese Medicine
, 
Shanghai
, 201203, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Shanghai
R

&amp; 

D Center for 
Standardization of Chinese Medicines
, 
Shanghai
, 201203, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c
School of Life Science
, 
Zhengzhou Normal University
, 
Henan Province
, 
Zhengzhou
, 450044, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
Roxb.
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Eudesmane-type sesquiterpenes</p>
         <p>Agarospirane-type sesquiterpenes</p>
         <p>Anti-inflammatory activity</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
Eleven previously unreported sesquiterpenes, including nine eudesmane-type (agalleudesmanol A-I) and two agarospirane-type sesquiterpenes (agarospiranic aldehyde A-B), together with eight known sesquiterpenes, were isolated from the agarwood of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
Roxb.
</tp:taxon-name>
The structures were established based on extensive spectroscopic analyses, including infrared (IR), high-resolution electrospray ionisation mass spectrometry (HRESIMS), nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), X-ray diffraction, quantum chemical calculations based on empirical electronic circular dichroism (ECD) data, and DP4+ probability analysis. The bioactivity of these undescribed compounds against lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced NO production in RAW 264.7 cells was evaluated. Compounds 
1
and 
2
exhibited significant anti-inflammatory activities, with 

IC 
50

values of 5.46–14.07 
μ
M (aminoguanidine as positive control, 

IC 
50

20.33 ± 1.08 
μ
M).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Agarwood is a resinous, odoriferous, and highly valuable heartwood derived from the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria
species
</tp:taxon-name>
of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family (

). Agarwood is also known as chen-xiang in 
China
, gaharu in 
Indonesia
and 
Malaysia
, jin-koh in 
Japan
, chim-hyuang in 
Korea
, and oud in the Middle East (

). The resin of agarwood is not generated under natural growth conditions, but rather, is formed as a response to injury of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria
</tp:taxon-name>
plants caused by natural factors involving animal grazing, lightning strikes, microbial invasions, insect attacks, or artificial manipulations such as physical wounding, chemical wounding, and fungal inoculation (

). The resinous wood is highly prized, which commands an exceptionally high value due to its unique fragrance. Agarwood was first documented in old Indian Sanskrit texts in 1500 B.C.E, and it has aroused a wide spectrum of applications from then on. The medical history of agarwood can be traced back to 65 B.C.E (L´opez-Sampson and 

), it was well-known as a traditional medicine with sedative, analgesic, and carminative effects, and was able to relieve gastric problems, cough, rheumatism, and high fever in modern medicine. Agarwood is widely considered to be a precious raw material of essential oils for aromatherapy and perfumery. It is also utilized as an incense for the holy religious rites and for decorations, as well as in other fields globally (

; 

). Previous phytochemical studies have isolated numerous chemical constituents from agarwood, including sesquiterpenes, 2-(2-phenylethyl)chromone derivatives, aromatics, and triterpenes. Sesquiterpenes and 2-(2-phenylethyl)chromones are the predominant bioactive constituents, accounting for 52% and 41% of the chemical constituents from agarwood, respectively (

). Sesquiterpenes are considered to be important components of the volatile oil, and contribute to the unique aroma of agarwood, where the total content of these compounds may reflect the quality of agarwood to a certain extent. These sesquiterpenes are further classified into eudesmanes, eremophilanes, agarospiranes, agarofurans, guaianes, cadinanes, prezizanes, acoranes, and other skeleton 
types
according to their basic structure (

). Studies have documented numerous bioactivities of the sesquiterpenes isolated from agarwood, including neural activity, gastrointestinal regulation, antibacterial, anti-inflammatory, and cytotoxic effects (

), highlighting the significance to find more active compounds from agarwood.
</p>
         <p>
Herein, to further investigate the chemical components and bioactivities of agarwood, systematic phytochemical research on agarwood originating from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
Roxb. (Thymelaeaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
is carried out, leading to the isolation of a series of sesquiterpenes. The structures are elucidated by extensive mass spectroscopy (MS) and NMR methods, as well as single crystal X-ray diffraction, optical rotation, and electronic circular dichroism (ECD) analyses. The inhibitory effects of all compounds on NO production in RAW 264.7 cells are evaluated. The isolation and structural elucidation of eleven previously undescribed sesquiterpenes, including nine eudesmane-type (1–9) and two agarospirane-type (10–11), as well as their anti-inflammatory activities, are presented.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Structural elucidation
</title>
         <p>
Compound 1, a pale yellow oil, possesses the molecular formula C 
15
H 
22
O 
3
based on the HRESIMS ion peak at 
m/z
268.1901 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. for C 
15
H 
22
O 
3
NH 
4
, 268.1907) with five degrees of unsaturation. The IR spectrum indicated the presence of hydroxy (
3393 cm
1
) and 
α
, 
β
-unsaturated carbonyl (
1679 cm
1
) groups. The 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) of 1 exhibited characteristic resonances of a singlet methyl [
δ
H
0.90 (3H, s)], an oxygenated methylene [
δ
H
4.07 (2H, s)], a terminal double bond [
δ
H
4.87 (1H, overlap), 5.04 (1H, m)], an olefinic methine [
δ
H
6.63 (1H, m)], and an aldehyde group [
δ
H
9.47 (1H, s)]. The 
13
C NMR spectrum (
Table 3
) revealed 15 carbon resonances, attributable to one methyl, six methylenes, five methines, and three quaternary carbons according to the DEPT spectrum. The 1D NMR spectroscopic data (
Tables 1
and 
2
) for 1 were similar to those of ()-selina-3,11-dien-14-al reported isolated from agarwood 

(


et al., 
1993)
. The main difference was the replacement of the 
CH
3
on the isopropenyl group by 
CH
2
OH, and the present of oxymethine signals [
δ
H
4.55 (H-2)/ 
δ
C
66.8 (C-2)]. By detailed 2D NMR analysis, the presence of 
CH
2
OH-12 and CHOH-2 was unambiguously confirmed based on the HMBC correlations of H-12 (
δ
H
4.07) to C-11 (
δ
C
155.3)/C-13 (
δ
C
108.4) and the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations between H-1 (
δ
H
1.30, 1.88) and H-2 (
δ
H
4.55), H-2 and H-3 (
δ
H
6.63) (
Fig. 2
). The relative configuration of 1 was established based on the NOESY data. The NOE correlations of H-1 
β
/H 
3
-15/H-2, H-1 
β
/H-9 
β
, H-9 
β
/H 
3
-15, and H-6 
β
/H 
3
-15 indicated that these hydrogens were cofacial and 
β-
oriented. In addition, the H-1 
α
/H-5, H-7/H-6 
α
/H-5, H-7/H-9 
α
/H-5 correlations suggested that these hydrogens were 
α-
oriented (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
The absolute configuration of 1 was determined by comparing the experimental and calculated ECD spectra, where the latter were simulated in methanol using the time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) methodology at the CAM-B3LYP/def2-TZVP level. The experimental ECD spectrum of 1 fits well with the calculated ECD spectrum of (2 
R
, 5 
R
, 7 
R
, 10 
S
)-1 (

Fig. 
S1.10

). Accordingly, the structure of 1 was determined to be (3 
R
,4a 
S
,7 
R
,8a 
R
)-3-hydroxy-7-(3-hydroxyprop-1-en-2- yl)-4a-methyl-3,4,4a,5,6,7,8,8a-octahydronaphthalene-1-carbaldehyde and named agalleudesmanol A.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Measured in CD OD and 400 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
a
Measured in CD OD and 400 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
b
Measured in CDCl and 400 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
b
Measured in CDCl and 400 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
c
Overlap.
</p>
         <p>
3
c
Overlap.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Measured in CD OD and 100 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
b
Measured in CDCl and 100 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
</p>
         <p>
Compound 2 was obtained as a colourless oil, and its molecular formula was determined to be C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
based on the HRESIMS peak at 
m/z
270.2061 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. for C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
NH 
4
, 270.2064) and NMR data. The 1D NMR spectroscopic data (
Tables 1
and 
3
) of 2 were similar to those of the sesquiterpene aldehyde from the aerial parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Actinobole uliginosum
(A. Grey) H. Eichler
</tp:taxon-name>
(

), except for the hydroxy group at C-12 (
δ
C
68.6). The proposed structure of 2 was confirmed by the HMBC correlations of H 
3
-13 (
δ
H
1.11) to C-11 (
δ
C
75.3)/C-12 (
δ
C
68.6)/C-7 (
δ
C
45.1) (
Fig. 2
). The relative configuration of 2 was partly resolved using the NOESY spectrum, which showed correlations between H-6 
β
/ 
CH
3
-15, H-1 
β
/ 
CH
3
-15, H-1 
α
/H-5, H-6 
α
/H-5, H-6 
α
/H-7, and H-5/H-7, indicating that H-5 and H-7 were 
α-
oriented, while H 
3
-15 was 
β-
oriented (
Fig. 3
). However, because of the free rotation of the single bond, the configuration at C- 
11 in
the side chain could not be determined easily by NMR experiments, and calculations of the NMR chemical shifts with support from DP4+ probability analysis were used to clarify the relative configuration. The calculations were performed using the gauge-including atomic orbital (GIAO) method at the mPW1PW91/6-311G** level in polarizable continuum model (PCM) MeOH. The results of the linear correlation analysis of the experimental and the calculated 
13
C NMR spectra are shown in 

Fig. 
S2.10

, the deviation between the calculated and empirical data was smaller for the 11 
R
configuration (

R 
2

= 0.9987) than for the 11 
S
congener (

R 
2

= 0.9976), ultimately, with a DP4+ probability of 100%, the relative configuration of C-11 was established tentatively as 
R
. Its structure was elucidated as (4a 
R
,7 
R
,8a 
R
)-7-(( 
R
)-1,2-dihydroxypropan-2-yl)-4a-methyl-3,4,4a,5,6, 7,8,8a-octahydronaphthalene-1-carbaldehyde and named agalleudesmanol B.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 3 was obtained as a colourless needle-like crystal. The molecular formula was determined to be C 
15
H 
24
O 
2
based on the HRESIMS peak at 
m/z
259.1679 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. for C 
15
H 
24
O 
2
Na, 259.1669), indicating four degrees of unsaturation. Analysis of the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data (
Tables 1
and 
3
) of compound 3 showed a structure related to the known compound 15-hydroxy-l2-oxo- 
α
-selinen (16) (

). The main difference between these two compounds is that an additional hydroxy group was located at C-2 (
δ
C
67.1) in 3, which was further confirmed by the COSY correlations between H-1 (
δ
H
1.30, 1.81)/H-2 (
δ
H
4.31), H-2/H-3 (
δ
H
5.62) (
Fig. 2
). In the NOESY spectrum, the correlation between H 
3
-15/H-1 
β
/H-2 and H 
3
-15/H-6 
β
suggested 
β
-orientations, while the correlation between H-5/H-6 
α
/H-7 and H-5/H-1 
α
suggested 
α
-orientations (
Fig. 3
). Single-crystal X-ray crystallographic analysis of 3 (
Fig. 4
) using the anomalous scattering of Cu-Kα radiation [Flack parameter = 0.1(4)] was performed. However, the Flack parameter was somewhat large, precluding assignment of the absolute configuration of 3 by this approach. Thus, ECD calculation was utilized to identify the absolute configuration. As shown in 

Fig. 
S3.10

, ultimately, the absolute configuration of 3 was assigned as (2 
R
, 5 
R
, 7 
R
, 10 
S
)-3 by comparison of the experimental and calculated ECD spectra. The structure of compound 3 was established to be (2 
R
,4a 
R
,6 
R
,8a 
S
)-4-(hydroxymethyl)-8a-methyl-6-(prop-1-en-2-yl)-1,2,4a,5,6,7,8,8a-octahydronaphthalen-2-ol and named agalleudesmanol C.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of compound 4, isolated as a pale yellow oil, was C 
15
H 
22
O 
3
based on HRESIMS analysis [
m/z
251.1622 [M + H] 
+
, (calcd. for C 
15
H 
23
O 
3
, 251.1628)], indicating five indices of hydrogen deficiency. According to the NMR spectroscopic data (
Tables 1
and 
3
), the structure closely resembled that of (7 
S
, 9 
S
, 10 
S
)-(+)-9-hydroxyselina-4,11-dien-14-al, which was previously isolated from Chinese agarwood originating from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. sinensis
(
Li et al., 2015
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and detailed comparison of the data for these two compounds indicated that 
CH
3
-13 in

(7 
S
, 9 
S
, 10 
S
)-(+)-9-hydroxy-selina-4,11-dien-14-al was replaced by an oxygenated methylene group. The HMBC correlations from H-12 (
δ
H
4.16) to C-7 (
δ
C
39.0)/C-11 (
δ
C
151.3)/C-13 (
δ
C
110.2) for compound 4 demonstrated the presence of oxygen-bearing 
CH
2
-12 (
Fig. 2
). The relative configuration of compound 4 was deduced by the NOE correlation of H 
3
-15/H-6 
β
and H 
3
-15/H-8 
β
, indicating that the protons were 
β
-oriented. In turn, the NOEs of H-7/H-6 
α
, H-7/H-9, and H-9/H-8 
α
revealed that these hydrogens were 
α
-oriented (
Fig. 3
). The absolute configuration of 4 was further confirmed by ECD calculations, which showed that the experimental ECD of 4 matched well with (7 
S
, 9 
S
, 10 
S
)-4 (

Fig. 
S4.10

). Therefore, the structure of 4 was established as (4a 
S
, 5 
S
, 7 
S
)-5-hydroxy-7-(3-hydroxyprop-1-en-2-yl)-4a-methyl-2,3,4,4a,5,6, 7,8-octahydronaphthalene-1-carbaldehyde and named agalleudesmanol D.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 5 was obtained as a colourless oil. The molecular formula was determined to be C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
based on HRESIMS [
m/z
270.2059 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
, (calcd. for C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
NH 
4
, 270.2069)], indicating four indices of hydrogen deficiency. Comparative analysis of the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra (
Tables 1
and 
3
) of 4 and 5 revealed that the differences lie in two singlet methyls [
δ
H
1.22 (H-12) and 
δ
H
1.24 (H-13)] in 5 instead of an Δ 
11,12
double bond and an oxymethylene in 4. This assumption was verified by the HMBC correlations from H 
3
-12 (
δ
H
1.22) to C-7 (
δ
C
48.4)/ C-11 (
δ
C
72.9)/C-13 (
δ
C
28.0) (
Fig. 2
). The NOE correlations revealed the relative configuration of C-7, C-9, and C-10 (
Fig. 3
). Likewise, the absolute configuration of 5 was established by comparing the calculated ECD data with the experimental data. The experimental ECD curves were consistent with the calculated ECD spectra of (7 
S
, 9 
S
, 10 
S
)-5 (

Fig. 
S5.10

). The structure of 5 was established as (4a 
S
, 5 
S
, 7 
S
)-5- hydroxy-7-(2-hydroxypropan-2-yl)-4a-methyl-2,3,4,4a,5,6,7,8-octahy dronaphthalene-1-carbaldehyde and named agalleudesmanol E.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 6 was a colourless oil with the molecular formula of C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
on the basis of its HRESIMS data ([M + NH 
4
] 
+
m/z 256.2273, calcd for C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
NH 
4
, 256.2271), and compound 7 possessed the same molecular formula as compound 6 by the analysis of its HRESIMS ([M + NH 
4
] 
+
m/z 256.2272, calcd for C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
NH 
4
, 256.2271). The 1D and 2D NMR (
Tables 2
and 
3
) analyses of 6 and 7 suggested that they share the same planar structure (
Fig. 1
and 
Fig. 2
) and the same orientations at H-5, H-7, and 
CH
3
-15 (
Fig. 3
). The minor differences in the chemical shifts preliminarily suggested that compound 7 was an epimer of 6 at C-11. Because of the present of a flexible exocyclic segment, it was challenging to determine the configuration of all the chiral centers from the NMR data; thus, the relative configuration of 6 and 7 was further confirmed by employing calculations of NMR chemical shifts with support from DP4+ analysis. The probability results from DP4+ analysis also confirmed that compounds 6 and 7 differed in terms of the configuration at C-11, with the probability being 90.65% and 9.35%, respectively (

Fig. 
S7.10

). In addition, ECD calculation was used to determine the absolute configuration of 6, the experimental ECD curve was in agreement with the calculated ECD spectra of (5 
R
, 7 
R
, 10 
R,
11 
S
)- 6 (

Fig. 
S6.10

). Finally, the structure of 6 was assigned as (
S
)-2-((2 
R
, 4a 
R
, 8a 
R
)-8-(hydroxymethyl)-4a-methyl-1,2,3,4,4a,5,6,8a-octahydronaphthalen-2-yl)propan-1-ol and named agalleudesmanol F; in turn, the structure of 7 was deduced as (
R
)-2-((2 
R
, 4a 
R
, 8a 
R
)-8-(hydroxymethyl)- 4a-methyl-1,2,3,4,4a,5,6,8a.
</p>
         <p>-octahydronaphthalen-2-yl)propan-1-ol and named agalleudesmanol G.</p>
         <p>
Compound 8 was obtained as a colourless oil. The molecular formula was found to be C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
based on HREIMS (
m/z
261.1829 [M + Na] 
+
, calcd. for C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
Na, 261.1825), revealing three degrees of unsaturation. Detailed analysis of the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data (
Tables 2
and 
3
) of 8 and comparison to the data with those of 6 and 7 demonstrated that the differences came from the replacement of 
CH
2
OH-14 by 
CH
3
and of 
CH
2
-9 by CHOH in 8, as evidenced by the HMBC correlations from H-14 (
δ
H
1.62) to C-3 (
δ
C
122.2)/C-4 (
δ
C
135.5)/C-5 (
δ
C
46.6) and H-9 (
δ
H
3.27) to C-7 (
δ
C
38.8) and C-15 (
δ
C
10.6) and 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlation between H-9 (
δ
H
3.27) and H-8 
β
(
δ
H
1.48). Thus, the gross structure of 8 was solved based on the correlations observed from the HSQC, HMBC, and COSY experiments (
Fig. 2
). Additionally, from the NOESY correlation of H-9/H-5, 
β
-orientation was assigned to OH-9 (
Fig. 3
); however, the configuration at C- 
11 in
the side chain requires further NMR calculations. As shown in Fig. 
S8.10
, the deviation between the calculated and observed spectra was smaller for the 11 
S
configuration (

R 
2

= 0.9989) than for the 11 
R
congener (

R 
2

= 0.9983), and the DP4+ probability was 99.30% for isomer 2 (Fig. 
S8.10
), indicating that the structure of 8 corresponded to (1 
S
, 3 
S
, 4a 
S
, 8a 
S
)-3-(( 
R
)-1-hydroxypropan-2-yl)-5,8a-dimethyl-1,2,3, 4, 4a, 7, 8, 8a-octahydronaph
</p>
         <p>thalen-1-ol and named agalleudesmanol H.</p>
         <p>
Compound 9 was isolated as a colourless needles. The molecular formula was found to be C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
based on the HREIMS peak at 
m/z
261.1835 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. for C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
Na, 261.1825), revealing three degrees of unsaturation. Comprehensive analysis of the NMR data (
Tables 2
and 
3
) of 9 revealed a planar structure closely consistent with rhombidiol (

). However, the large axial-axial coupling constant (

J 
9,8β

= 11.4 Hz) in conjunction with the NOEs of H-9/H-5 and H-9/H-7 confirmed that 9-OH was 
β
-oriented. Furthermore, a high-quality crystal of 9 was obtained from a methanol solution, allowing successful Cu-Kα X-ray crystallographic analysis. Ultimately, the absolute configuration of 9 was determined to be 5 
S
, 7 
S
, 9 
S
, 10 
S
with a Flack parameter of 0.05 (13) (
Fig. 5
); thus, compound 9 was identified as (1 
S
, 3 
S
, 4a 
S
, 8a 
S
)-3-(2-hydroxypropan-2-yl)-
</p>
         <p>8a-methyl-5-methylenedecahydronaphthalen-1-ol and named agalleudesmanol I.</p>
         <p>
Compound 10 was isolated as a colourless needles. The molecular formula was found to be C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
based on the HREIMS peak at 
m/z
270.2060 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. for C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
NH 
4
, 270.2064), indicating four degrees of unsaturation. The IR spectrum of 10 showed absorption bands at 
3443 cm
1
and 
1674 cm
1
, suggesting the presence of hydroxy and carbonyl functional groups. The 
1
H NMR spectrum (
Table 2
) showed the presence of three methyl [
δ
H
1.16 (3H, s), 1.19 (3H, s), and 
δ
H
1.00 (3H, d, 
J
= 6.6 Hz)], one oxygenated [
δ
H
4.45 (1H, m)], one olefinic [
δ
H
6.60 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.8 Hz)], and one carbonyl methine [
δ
H
9.40 (1H, s)]. The 
13
C (
Table 3
) and DEPT NMR data exhibited 15 carbon resonances, including those of three methyls, four methylenes, five methines, and three quaternary carbons. Detailed analysis of the 1D and 2D NMR spectra of 10 indicated an agarospirane-type sesquiterpenoid (
Fig. 2
), which was similar to 2-hydroxyhinesols (

) except for the presence of an additional aldehyde in 10. HMBC correlations from H-14 (
δ
H
9.40) to C-5 (
δ
C
47.4), C-9 (
δ
C
153.2), and C-10 (
δ
C
150.0) indicated that the above aldehyde group was attached to C-10. The relative configuration was revealed based on interpretation of the NOESY data. The NOEs of H 
3
-15/H-8, H 
3
-15/H-4, and H-4/H-3 indicated that these protons were cofacial, and these protons were thus assigned as 
β
-oriented, while the hydroxy group at C-8 was 
α
-oriented. Fortunately, needle-like crystals were obtained from methanol solution. Single-crystal X-ray diffraction with Cu-Kα radiation [Flack parameter of 0.15 (15)] (
Fig. 6
) was used to determine the absolute configuration of 10 as 3 
R
, 5 
R
, 6 
R
, 8 
R
. Consequently, the structure of 10 was proposed to be (2 
R
, 5 
R
, 8 
R
, 10 
R
)-8-hydroxy-2-(2-hydroxypropan-2-yl)-10-methylspiro[4.5]dec-6-ene-6-carbaldehyde and named agarospiranic aldehyde A.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 11 was isolated as a fragrant colourless oil with the same molecular formula C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
[
m/z
270.2065 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
, (calcd. for C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
NH 
4
, 270.2064)] as 10. The IR spectrum and 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (
Tables 2
and 
3
) of 11 were quite close to those of 10, suggesting that 10 and 11 are a pair of epimers. The HSQC, HMBC, and 
1
H– 
1
H COSY data further support this inference (
Fig. 2
). In the NOESY spectrum of 11, the H 
3
-15/H-4 and H-3/H-4 correlations indicated that these protons were cofacial and 
β
-oriented. The additional NOE of H-6/H-8 indicated 
α-
orientation of these protons. Thus, the hydroxy group at C-8 was 
β
-oriented. Furthermore, the absolute configuration was confirmed from the ECD spectrum of 11 (Fig. 
S11.10
), and the structure of 11 was proposed to be (2 
R
, 5 
R
, 8 
R
, 10 
S
)-8-hydroxy-2-(2-hydroxypropan-2-yl)- 10-methylspiro[4.5]dec-6-ene-6-carbaldehyde and named agarospiranic aldehyde B.
</p>
         <p>
Other known sesquiterpenes were identified as petafolia A (12) (

), 
β
-elemene-12,14-diol (13) (

), (2 
R
,5 
S
, 10 
S
)-α 
2
,α 
2,
10-Trimethylspiro[4.5]dec-6-ene-2,6-dimethanol (14) (

), 
ent
-4(15)-eudesmen-1 
α
,11-diol (15) (

), 15-hydroxy-l2-oxo- 
α
-selinen (16) (

), pterodondiol (17) (

), and eudesma-4-en-11,15-diol (18) (

).
</p>
         <p>
2.2. Pharmacological evaluation of isolated compounds
</p>
         <p>
Nitric oxide (NO) is a vital signaling molecule, which participates in the regulation of various physiological functions. In normal circumstances, NO is lowly expressed in cells or tissues, while the expression of NO will significantly augment upon experiencing inflammation caused by external stimuli. Therefore, the release of NO is commonly recognized as a biomarker for screening active compounds with anti-inflammatory bioactivities in vitro (

).
</p>
         <p>
To investigate the anti-inflammatory activity of the isolated compounds, the cytotoxicity of the compounds on RAW 264.7 cells was first determined using a Cell Counting Kit-8 (CCK-8) to eliminate false positive results, where the results clearly indicated that none of the tested compounds was cytotoxic. The inhibitory effects of compounds 1–11 against LPS-induced NO production in RAW 264.7 cells were evaluated on the basis of cell viability results. As shown in 
Fig. 7
, compounds 1, 2, 4, 10, and 11 exhibited inhibitory activity against NO production with 

IC 
50

values of 5.46 ± 4.11, 14.07 ± 2.08, 45.59 ± 4.35, 52.25 ± 2.37, and 62.57 ± 2.31 
μ
M, respectively. At each test concentration, the inhibition rates of compounds 1 and 2 were consistently greater than that of the positive control, aminoguanidine hydrochloride (

IC 
50

= 20.33 ± 1.08 
μ
M). Other compounds showed no distinct effects in reducing NO release from LPS-induced RAW 264.7 cells at 100 
μ
M.
</p>
         <p>The results of the structure-activity relationships indicated that compounds with an aldehyde group at the C-14 position obtained in this study (compounds 1, 2, 4, 10, and 11) enhanced their anti-inflammatory activities. However, further studies are required to prove this preliminary conclusion by analysing more analogues with this substituent group.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
In summary, eleven previously unreported sesquiterpenes, including nine eudesmane-type (1–9) and two agarospirane-type sesquiterpenes (10–11), together with eight known sesquiterpenes (12–18), were isolated from the agarwood of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. agallocha
</tp:taxon-name>
. The discovery of more isolated chemical compounds is beneficial for increasing the possibility of unearthing more active components, especially in the case of the agarospirane-type sesquiterpenes that have been isolated and identified in small amounts. The structures of these compounds were elucidated by detailed spectroscopic data analyses, ECD calculations, DP4+ probability analysis, and single-crystal X-ray diffraction analysis. On the basis of published literatures and the eudesmane-type sesquiterpenes obtained in our experiment, we found that this 
type
of sesquiterpenes share same orientation of hydrogen protons at C-5, C-7 and methyl at C-15 position, indicating that they have commonality in chiral centers. The bioactivity of the isolated sesquiterpenes (1–11) against LPS-induced NO production in RAW 264.7 cells was evaluated, where compounds 1, 2, 4, 10, and 11 exhibited inhibitory effects. Compounds 1 and 2 showed obvious anti-inflammatory activity, with 

IC 
50

values of 5. 46 ± 4.11 
μ
M and 14.07 ± 2.08 
μ
M, respectively. These findings enrich the knowledge of the structural diversity of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. agallocha
</tp:taxon-name>
and lay the foundation for elucidating the pharmacodynamics of agarwood.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
The optical rotations were measured using a Rudolph Research Analytical Autopol IV automatic polarimeter (Rudolph, 
New Jersey
, 
USA
). The IR spectra were recorded using a PerkinElmer Spectrum 100 FTIR spectrometer equipped with a universal attenuated total reflectance accessory (UATR) in the range of 4000 
600 cm
1
(Waltham, 
Massachusetts
, 
USA
). The NMR spectra were recorded on a Bruker AV III spectrometer operating at 400 or 600 MHz (Bruker, Karlsruhe, 
Germany
), using TMS as an internal standard. HRESIMS data were obtained using a Q-TOF mass spectrometer (Waters, 
Massachusetts
, 
USA
). Single crystal X-ray diffraction data were collected with a Bruker d8 Venture system (Bruker, Karlsruhe, 
Germany
) using Cu-Kα radiation (λ = 1.54178 Å). Reverse-phase medium-pressure liquid chromatography (RP-MPLC) was performed on a Buchi RP-MPLC instrument (Buchi Labortechnik AG, Flawil, 
Switzerland
) with a YMC gel ODS column (50 
μ
m, YMC Co., Ltd., 
Kyoto
, 
Japan
). Preparative high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) was carried out by a LC3000 preparative HPLC system with P3000 HPLC pump and UV3000 UV-VIS detector (
Beijing
Tong Heng Innovation Technology Co., Ltd., 
Beijing
, 
China
), preparative RP-HPLC columns (CAPCELL PAK C18 MG II, 250 × 
20 mm
, 5 μm and YMC-Pack ODS-A, 250 × 
10 mm
, 5 μm) were used for the isolation. Column chromatography (CC) was performed using silica gel (200–300 mesh, Qingdao Marine Chemical Co. Ltd., Qingdao, 
China
) and Sephadex LH-20 (GE Healthcare Bio-Sciences AB, 
Uppsala
, 
Sweden
). Thinlayer chromatography (TLC) and preparative TLC (PTLC) analyses were performed on HSGF 
254
plates (Yantai Jiangyou Silica Gel Development Co., Ltd., Yantai, 
China
), and spots were visualised under a UV lamp at 
254 nm
and detected by spraying with a solution of vanillin in sulfuric acid, followed by heating.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>
Dried agarwood of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilaria agallocha
Roxb. (Thymelaeaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
was purchased from Hue, 
Vietnam
in 
August 2017
by the Agarwood Professional Committee of Shanghai Commercial Federation. The sample was authenticated by Professor Lihong Wu (Institute of Chinese Materia Medicica, Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine), and a voucher specimen (No. CX170824) was deposited in the herbarium of the Institute of Chinese Materia Medica, Shanghai University of Traditional Chinese Medicine.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
Agarwood chips (
1.74 kg
) were crushed and refluxed with 95% ethanol (3 × 20 L, 2 h each time). The EtOH extract (510.0 g) was suspended in H 
2
O (2.5 L) and partitioned with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
(2.5 L × 3) to afford 
CH
2
Cl 
2
(
158.4 g
) and H 
2
O (
176.3 g
) soluble extracts, respectively. The 
CH
2
Cl 
2
extract (
158.4 g
) was chromatographed on a silica gel column and eluted with a gradient solvent system (PE-EtOAc, 1:0, 50:1, 10:1, 5:1, 3:1, 1:1, 0:1) to yield nine major fractions (Fr.1 9) based on the TLC analyses.
</p>
         <p>
Fr.1 (
2.8 g
) was further subjected to RP-MPLC (MeOH/H 
2
O, 30–100%) to give 11 fractions (Fr.1a 1k), Fr. 
1g
(
511.1 mg
) was further fractionated by Sephadex LH-20 column chromatography with MeOH and PE-CH 
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (5:5:1) to obtain four subfractions (Fr.1g-1 to Fr.1g-4), compounds 13 (
11.3 mg
) and 14 (
45.3 mg
) were obtained from Fr.1g-3 (
17.6 mg
) and Fr.1g-4 (
257.5 mg
) by preparative TLC, respectively. Fr.1h (
181.4 mg
) was subjected to Sephadex LH-20 column chromatography with MeOH and purified by preparative TLC to yield compound 12 (
22.7 mg
).
</p>
         <p>
Fr.2 (
1.8 g
) was also subjected to RP-MPLC (MeOH/H 
2
O, 30–100%) to give six fractions (Fr.2a 2f), Fr.2b was separated by Sephadex LH-20 column chromatography with MeOH, followed by preparative TLC to yield compound 15 (
39.4 mg
).
</p>
         <p>
Fr.3 (2.0 g) was subjected to RP-MPLC (MeOH/H 
2
O, 30–100%) to give eight fractions (Fr.3a 3h), Fr.3a (
78.9 mg
), Fr.3b (
46.9 mg
), and Fr.3d (
222.9 mg
) were subjected to Sephadex LH-20 column chromatography and eluted with PE-CH 
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (5:5:1) and then purified by preparative TLC to afford compounds 10 (
37.8 mg
), 2 (9.0 mg), and 9 (22.0 mg), respectively. Fr. 
3g
(114.0 mg) was subjected to Sephadex LH-20 column chromatography and eluted with MeOH and PE-CH 
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (5:5:1) successively to obtain four subfractions (Fr.3g-1 to Fr.3g-4); compound 16 (11.0 mg) was acquired from Fr.3g-3 by preparative TLC.
</p>
         <p>
Fr.4 (
3.6 g
) was chromatographed over RP-MPLC (MeOH/H 
2
O, 30–100%) to obtain 12 subfractions (Fr.4a Fr.4l). Compound 1 (
12.4 mg
) was isolated from Fr.4a (
59.7 mg
) using a Sephadex LH-20 column (PE-CH 
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH, 5:5:1) and preparative TLC. Fr.4c (
366.5 mg
) was subjected to Sephadex LH-20 column chromatography with MeOH and PE/ 
CH
2
Cl/MeOH (5:5:1) successively to obtain five subfractions (Fr.4c-1 to Fr.4c-5); compound 8 (
11.1 mg
, 

tR

= 40.4 min) was separated from Fr. 4c-4 (
32.2 mg
) by semi-preparative HPLC using 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O (38:62, 8.0 mL/min). Similarly, Fr.4d (
313.2 mg
) and Fr.4e (125.0 mg) were divided into six subfractions (Fr.4d-1 to Fr.4d-6) and three subfractions (Fr.4e-1 to Fr.4e-3) using the same method as applied to Fr.4c, respectively. Fr.4d-1 (
27.3 mg
) and Fr.4d-2 (
15.9 mg
) were purified by semi-preparative HPLC with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O (49:51, 8 mL/min) and MeOH–H 
2
O (75:25, 8 mL/min) to produce compounds 17 (
11.1 mg
, 

tR

= 19.5 min) and 18 (
6.1 mg
, 

tR

= 24.5 min), respectively. Fr.4e-3 (
37.7 mg
) was purified by preparative TLC and semi-preparative HPLC (MeOH–H 
2
O (50:50, 8.0 mL/min) to obtain compounds 6 (
12.2 mg
, 

tR

= 23.5 min) and 7 (
11.2 mg
, 

tR

= 24.5 min).
</p>
         <p>
Fr.5 (
2.9 g
) was isolated by RP-MPLC (MeOH/H 
2
O, 30–100%) to obtain eleven fractions (Fr.5a Fr.5k). Fr.5a (
180.4 mg
) was further fractionated on a Sephadex LH-20 column and eluted with MeOH and PE/ 
CH
2
Cl/MeOH (5:5:1) successively to give five subfractions (Fr.5a-1 to Fr.5a-5). Compound 4 (
9.3 mg
, 

tR

= 16.0 min) was acquired from Fr.5a-2 by employing 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O (28:72, 5.0 mL/min); compound 5 (
15.2 mg
, 

tR

= 12.8 min) was acquired from Fr.5a- 
3 in
the same manner (
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O (25:75), 5.0 mL/min). Likewise, Fr. 
5g
(
213.1 mg
) was subjected to Sephadex LH-20 column chromatography by eluting with MeOH and PE/ 
CH
2
Cl/MeOH (5:5:1) successively, and further purified by semi-preparative HPLC using 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O (42:58, 4.0 mL/min) as the mobile phase to produce 3 (
4.2 mg
, 

tR

= 14.0 min).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Agalleudesmanol A (1)
</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil, [
α
] +18 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3393, 2923, 1679, 1383, 1255, 
1034, 903, 771 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 1
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
268.1901 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
22
O 
3
NH 
4
, 268.1907).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Agalleudesmanol B (2)
</title>
         <p>
Colourless oil, [
α
] +9 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3396, 2919, 1679, 1620, 1454, 1379, 1139, 
1047, 945, 728 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 1
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
270.2061 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
NH 
4
, 270.2064).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. Agalleudesmanol C (3)
</title>
         <p>
Colourless needles, [
α
] +31 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3368, 2925, 1679, 1454, 1377, 1204, 1140, 
1030, 885, 803, 724 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 1
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
259.1679 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
24
O 
2
Na, 259.1669).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.4. Agalleudesmanol D (4)
</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil, [
α
] +34 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3366, 2936, 2868, 1650, 1611, 1450, 1406, 1270, 1196, 
1054, 988, 903, 783, 689 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 1
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
251.1622 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
23
O 
3
, 251.1628)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.5. Agalleudesmanol E (5)
</title>
         <p>
Colourless oil, [
α
] +82 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3356, 2940, 2870, 1650, 1610, 1448, 1364, 1193, 1053, 
1031, 949, 773, 680 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 1
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
270.2059 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
NH 
4
, 270.2069)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.6. Agalleudesmanol F (6)
</title>
         <p>
Colourless oil, [
α
] +8 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3317, 2916, 1453, 1378, 
1033, 995, 868, 806, 736 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 2
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
256.2273 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
NH 
4
, 256.2271)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.7. Agalleudesmanol G (7)
</title>
         <p>
Colourless oil, [
α
] 10 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3304, 2916, 1727, 1450, 1370, 1217, 1084, 
1034, 986, 868, 794, 737 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 2
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
256.2272 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
NH 
4
256.2271)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.8. Agalleudesmanol H (8)
</title>
         <p>
Colourless oil, [
α
] +29 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3340, 2931, 2874, 1679, 1441, 1379, 1143, 
1023, 916, 884, 791, 722 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 2
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
261.1829 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
Na, 261.1825)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.9. Agalleudesmanol I (9)
</title>
         <p>
Colourless needles, [
α
] +33 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3282, 2938, 1647, 1378, 1281, 1179, 1136, 
1046, 990, 895, 782 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 2
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
261.1835 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
Na, 261.1825)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.10. Agarospiranic aldehyde A (10)
</title>
         <p>
Colourless needles, [
α
] +50 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3443, 2964, 1674, 1459, 1382, 1214, 1169, 1063, 
1021, 941, 744 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 2
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
270.2060 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
NH 
4
, 270.2064)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.11. Agarospiranic aldehyde B (11)
</title>
         <p>
Colourless oil, [
α
] +7 (
c
0.1, 
CH
3
OH); IR vmax 3406, 2966, 1680, 1377, 1138, 
1033, 934 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data see 
Tables 2
and 
3
; positive ion HRESIMS 
m/z
270.2065 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd. For C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
NH 
4
, 270.2064)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. ECD calculation
</title>
         <p>
The conformers of compounds 1, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 11 after conformational analyses were optimised using DFT at the PBE0-D3(BJ)/def2-SVP level in MeOH using the polarizable conductor calculation model (SMD) by applying the ORCA4.2.1 program (

, 

). The energies, oscillator strengths, and rotational strengths (velocity) of the first 60 electronic excitations were calculated using the TDDFT methodology at the CAM-B3LYP/def2-TZVP level in MeOH. The ECD spectra were simulated by applying the overlapping Gaussian function (half the bandwidth at 1/e peak height, sigma = 0.30, for all) (

). To get the final spectra, the simulated spectra of the conformers were averaged according to Boltzmann distribution theory based on the relative Gibbs free energy (
ΔG
) of the conformers.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. NMR calculation
</title>
         <p>
The NMR shielding constants were computed after geometry optimisation using the gauge-including atomic orbital (GIAO) method at the mPW1PW91/6-311G** level in PCM MeOH using the Gaussian 09 program (

). The Boltzmann weights were computed using the relative free energies at the wB97M-V/def2-TZVP level in SMD MeOH using ORCA. The shielding constants were applied in the DP4+ probability analysis (

). The linear correlation coefficient (

R 
2

) and DP4+ probability were used to evaluate the deviation between the experimental and calculated results.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Single crystal X-ray diffraction analysis
</title>
         <p>
The single-crystal X-ray intensity data for compounds 3, 9, and 10 were measured using a Bruker d8 venture system with Cu-Kα radiation (λ = 1.54178 Å). The structure was solved by the SHELXS method and refined based on full-matrix least-squares on F 
2
using the SHELXL-2018/ 3 program (

; Uson´and 

). The crystallographic data for 3, 9, and 10 were deposited at the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Center (for 3, CCDC Number: 2074215; for 9, CCDC Number: 2069006; and for 10, CCDC Number: 2064299). The data can be obtained free of charge from the www via http://www.ccdc.cam.ac. uk/data_request/cif.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.1. Crystallographic data of 3
</title>
         <p>
The crystals of compound 3 were obtained from methanoldichloromethane (1:1) solution at room temperature for one week. Clear light colourless plate-like, crystal size 0.120 x 0.130 × 
0.150 mm
, C 
15
H 
24
O 
2
, Mr = 
236.34 g
/mol, T = 303 (2) K, monoclinic, P 1 21 1, a = 7.8212 (6) Å, b = 6.5436 (6) Å, c = 14.0807 (14) Å, α = 90 
◦
, β = 98.531 (6) 
◦
, γ = 90 
◦
, V = 712.66 (11) Å 
3
, Z = 2, 
Dcalcd
= 
1.101 g
/cm 
3
, absorption coefficient = 
0.553 mm
1
, multi-scan, trans min = 0.922, trans max = 0.937, F(000) = 260. The total number of reflections was 6815 (9 
&lt;
= h 
&lt;
= 9, 7 
&lt;
= k 
&lt;
= 7, 16 
&lt;
= l 
&lt;
= 16) measured in the range 3.17 
◦
–65.28 
◦
, independent reflections 2302 [R(int) = 0.0818]. Final indices: R 
1
= 0.0874, wR 
2
= 0.2200 [I ≥ 2σ (I)]; R 
1
= 0.1106, wR 
2
= 0.2655 [all data], absolute structure parameter (Flack parameter) = 0.1 (4).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.2. Crystallographic data of 9
</title>
         <p>
The crystals of compound 9 were obtained from methanol solution at room temperature for one week. Clear light colourless block, crystal size 0.100 x 0.200 × 0.300 mm, C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
, Mr = 
238.37 g
/mol, T = 303 (2) K, trigonal, R 3, a = 23.716 (8) Å, b = 23.617 (8) Å, c = 6.553 (2) Å, α = 90 
◦
, β = 90 
◦
, γ = 120 
◦
, V = 3165 (2) Å 
3
, Z = 3, 
Dcalcd
= 
1.125 g
/cm 
3
, absorption coefficient = 
0.561 mm
1
, multi-scan, trans min = 0.850, trans max = 0.946, F(000) = 1188. The total number of reflections was 12768 (29 
&lt;
= h 
&lt;
= 29, 28 
&lt;
= k 
&lt;
= 29, 7 
&lt;
= l 
&lt;
= 7) measured in the range 7.50 
◦
–72.03 
◦
, independent reflections 2654 [R(int) = 0.0919]. Final indices: R 
1
= 0.0426, wR 
2
= 0.1246 [I ≥ 2σ (I)]; R 
1
= 0.0531, wR 
2
= 0.1374 [all data], absolute structure parameter (Flack parameter) = 0.05 (13).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.3. Crystallographic data of 10
</title>
         <p>
The crystals of compound 10 were obtained from methanol solution at room temperature for one week. Clear light colourless plate, crystal size 0.020 x 0.110 × 
0.120 mm
, C 
15
H 
24
O 
3
, Mr = 
252.35 g
/mol, T = 292 (2) K, orthorhombic, space group P 
21 21
21
, a = 8.4873 (10) Å, b = 12.9534 (16) Å, c = 25.376 (3) Å, α = 90 
◦
, β = 90 
◦
, γ = 90 
◦
, V = 2789.8 (6) Å 
3
, Z = 4, 
Dcalcd
= 
1.202 g
/cm 
3
, absorption coefficient = 
0.653 mm
1
, multi-scan, trans min = 0.926, trans max = 0.987, F(000) = 1104. The total number of reflections was 19808 (10 
&lt;
= h 
&lt;
= 10, 15 
&lt;
= k 
&lt;
= 15, 29 
&lt;
= l 
&lt;
= 30) measured in the range 3.48 
◦
–68.46 
◦
, independent reflections 5085 [R(int) = 0.0826]. Final indices: R 
1
= 0.0579, wR 
2
= 0.1466 [I ≥ 2σ (I)]; R 
1
= 0.0642, wR 
2
= 0.1517 [all data], absolute structure parameter (Flack parameter) = 0.15 (15).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Reagents and preparation of test solution
</title>
         <p>
Dulbecco’ s modified Eagle’ s medium (DMEM), fetal bovine serum (FBS), penicillin and streptomycin were purchased from Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc. (Waltham, 
USA
). Cell Counting Kit-8 was purchased from Dojindo Molecular Technologies, Inc. (
Kumamoto
, 
Japan
). Griess reagent was obtained from Beyotime (
Shanghai
, 
China
). Aminoguanidine hydrochloride and DMSO were from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, MO, 
USA
).
</p>
         <p>
Dissolve a quantity of test compounds, weigh accurately, in DMSO to produce the stock solutions with a concentration of 100 mM, store at 4 
◦
C. Aminoguanidine hydrochloride was used as positive control.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Cell culture
</title>
         <p>
RAW 264.7 cells were maintained in high-glucose Dulbecco’ s modified Eagle’ s medium (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., Waltham, 
USA
) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 100 U/mL penicillin and 100 
μ
g/mL streptomycin at 37 
◦
C in 5% CO 
2
. The medium was routinely changed every 48 h, and RAW 264.7 cells in the exponential growth phase were used for assays.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.9. Cell viability assay
</title>
         <p>
RAW 264.7 cells (5 x 10 
4
cells/well) treated with compounds or equal volume of DMSO, and subsequently incubated at 37 
◦
C with 5% CO 
2
. After 24 h, cells were subjected to Cell Counting Kit-8 according to the manufacturer’ s instructions (incubated at 37 
◦
C for 30 min). Absorbance at 
450 nm
was assessed using a microplate reader when the measured value of blank group was 0.8–1.0.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.10. Griess test assay
</title>
         <p>
RAW 264.7 cells (5 x 10 
4
cells/well) were stimulated with LPS (
100 ng
/mL) for 24 h at 37 
◦
C with 5% CO 
2
. Compound or an equal volume of DMSO was added for 30 min before the LPS stimulation. 24 h later, cells supernatant interact with Griess reagents for 5 min. Absorbance was measured by a microplate reader at 
540 nm
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgement
</p>
         <p>
This work was financially supported by the Science and Technology Commission of 
Shanghai
Municipality of 
China
(19DZ2201500). We would like to thank Agarwood Professional Committee of 
Shanghai
Commercial Federation for providing research samples in this study.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112920.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bohlmann, F.
, 
Zdero, C.
, 
Cuatrecasas, J.
, 
King, R.M.
, 
Robinson, H.
, 
1980
. 

Neue sesquiterpene und norditerpene aus vertretern der gattung 
Libanothamnus

. 
Phytochemistry
19
, 
1145–1148
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(80)83072-X
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, H.Q.
, 
Wei, J.H.
, 
Yang, J.S.
, 
Zhang, Z.
, 
Yang, Y.
, 
Gao, Z.H.
, 
Sui, C.
, 
Gong, B.
, 
2012
. 

Chemical constituents of agarwood originating from the endemic genus 
Aquilaria
plants

. 
Chem. Biodivers.
9
, 
236–250
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/cbdv.201100077
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chhipa, H.
, 
Chowdhary, K.
, 
Kaushik, N.
, 
2017
. 

Artificial production of agarwood oil in 
Aquilaria
sp. by fungi: a review

. 
Phytochem. Rev.
16
, 
835–860
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s11101-017-9492-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frisch, M.J.
, 
Trucks, G.W.
, 
Schlegel, H.B.
, 
Scuseria, G.E.
, 
Robb, M.A.
, 
Cheeseman, J.R.
, 
Scalmani, G.
, 
Barone, V.
, 
Petersson, G.A.
, 
Nakatsuji, H.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Caricato, M.
, 
Marenich, A.
, 
Bloino, J.
, 
Janesko, B.G.
, 
Gomperts, R.
, 
Mennucci, B.
, 
Hratchian, H.P.
, 
Ortiz, J.V.
, 
Izmaylov, A.F.
, 
Sonnenberg, J.L.
, 
Williams-Young, D.
, 
Ding, F.
, 
Lipparini, F.
, 
Egidi, F.
, 
Goings, J.
, 
Peng, B.
, 
Petrone, A.
, 
Henderson, T.
, 
Ranasinghe, D.
, 
Zakrzewski, V.G.
, 
Gao, J.
, 
Rega, N.
, 
Zheng, G.
, 
Liang, W.
, 
Hada, M.
, 
Ehara, M.
, 
Toyota, K.
, 
Fukuda, R.
, 
Hasegawa, J.
, 
Ishida, M.
, 
Nakajima, T.
, 
Honda, Y.
, 
Kitao, O.
, 
Nakai, H.
, 
Vreven, T.
, 
Throssell, K.
, 
Montgomery, J.A.
, 
Peralta, J.E.
, 
Ogliaro, F.
, 
Bearpark, M.
, 
Heyd, J.J.
, 
Brothers, E.
, 
Kudin, K.N.
, 
Staroverov, V.N.
, 
Keith, T.
, 
Kobayashi, R.
, 
Normand, J.
, 
Raghavachari, K.
, 
Rendell, A.
, 
Burant, J.C.
, 
Iyengar, S.S.
, 
Tomasi, J.
, 
Cossi, M.
, 
Millam, J.M.
, 
Klene, M.
, 
Adamo, C.
, 
Cammi, R.
, 
Ochterski, J.W.
, 
Martin, R.L.
, 
Morokuma, K.
, 
Farkas, O.
, 
Foresman, J.B.
, 
Fox, D.J.
, 
2016
. 
Gaussian 09, Revision A
.02. 
Gaussian, Inc, Wallingford, CT
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grimblat, N.
, 
Zanardi, M.M.
, 
Sarotti, A.M.
, 
2015
. 
Beyond DP4: an improved probability for the stereochemical assignment of isomeric compounds using quantum chemical calculations of NMR shifts
. 
J. Org. Chem.
80
, 
12526–12534
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.joc.5b02396
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hashim, Y.Z.H.-Y.
, 
Kerr, P.G.
, 
Abbas, P.
, 
Salleh, H.M.
, 
2016
. 

Aquilaria
spp. (agarwood) as source of health beneficial compounds: a review of traditional use, phytochemistry and pharmacology. J

. 
Ethnopharmacol.
189
, 
331–360
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. jep.2016.06.055
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hashimoto, T.
, 
Noma, Y.
, 
Kato, S.
, 
Tanaka, M.
, 
Takaoka, S.
, 
Asakawa, Y.
, 
1999
. 

Biotransformation of hinesol isolated from the crude drug 
Atractylodes lancea
by 
Aspergillus Niger
and 
Aspergillus cellulosae

. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
47
, 
716–717
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1248/cpb.47.716
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Isaka, M.
, 
Palasarn, S.
, 
Lapanun, S.
, 
Chanthaket, R.
, 
Boonyuen, N.
, 
Lumyong, S.
, 
2009
. 

γ
-lactones and 
ent
-eudesmane sesquiterpenes from the endophytic fungus 
Eutypella
sp. BCC 13199

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
72
, 
1720–1722
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np900316x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ishihara, M.
, 
Tsuneya, T.
, 
Uneyama, K.
, 
1993
. 
Fragrant sesquiterpenes from agarwood
. 
Phytochemistry
33
, 
1147–1155
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(93)85039-T
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jakupovic, J.
, 
Lehmann, L.
, 
Bohlmann, F.
, 
King, R.M.
, 
Robinson, H.
, 
1988
. 

Sesquiterpene lactones and other constituents from 
Cassinia, Actinobole
and 
Anaxeton
species

. 
Phytochemistry
27
, 
3831–3839
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(88)83027-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jia, W.M.
, 
Yang, L.M.
, 
Li, C.H.
, 
Hu, J.H.
, 
1991
. 

Synthesis of the antitumor 
β
-elemene derivatives

. 
Chin. J. Org. Chem.
11
, 
608–610
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kalra, R.
, 
Kaushik, N.
, 
2017
. 

A review of chemistry, quality and analysis of infected agarwood tree (
Aquilaria
sp.)

. 
Phytochem. Rev.
16
, 
1045–1079
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s11101-017-9518-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, W.
, 
Cai, C.H.
, 
Guo, Z.K.
, 
Wang, H.
, 
Zuo, W.J.
, 
Dong, W.H.
, 
Mei, W.L.
, 
Dai, H.F.
, 
2015
. 
Five new eudesmane-type sesquiterpenoids from Chinese agarwood induced by artificial holing
. 
Fitoterapia
100
, 
44–49
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. fitote.2014.11.010
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, W.
, 
Chen, H.Q.
, 
Wang, H.
, 
Mei, W.L.
, 
Dai, H.F.
, 
2020
. 

Natural products in agarwood and 
Aquilaria
plants: chemistry, biological activities and biosynthesis

. 
Nat. Prod. Rep.
38
, 
528–565
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/D0NP00042F
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Y.Y.
, 
Wei, J.H.
, 
Gao, Z.H.
, 
Zhang, Z.
, 
Lyu, J.C.
, 
2017
. 
A review of quality assessment and grading for agarwood
. 
Chin Herb Med
9
, 
22–30
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ S1674-6384(17)60072-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
L´opez-Sampson, A., 
Page, T.
, 
2018
. 
History of use and trade of agarwood
. 
Econ. Bot.
72
, 
107–129
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s12231-018-9408-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maatooq, G.T.
, 
2002
. 

Microbial transformation of a 
β
- and 
γ
-eudesmols mixture

. 
Z. Naturforsch.
57
c, 
654–659
. 
https://doi.org/10.1515/znc-2002-7-818
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Naef, R.
, 
2011
. 

The volatile and semi-volatile constituents of agarwood, the infected heartwood of 
Aquilaria
species: a review

. 
Flavour Fragrance J.
26
, 
73–89
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1002/ffj.2034
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Neese, F.
, 
2012
. 
The ORCA program system
. 
Wiley Interdiscip. Rev.-Comput. Mol. Sci.
2
, 
73–78
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/wcms.81
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Neese, F.
, 
2018
. 
Software update: the ORCA program system, version 4.0. Interdiscip
. 
Rev.-Comput. Mol. Sci.
8
, e 
1327
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/wcms.1327
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rukachaisirikul, V.
, 
Kaewbumrung, C.
, 
Phongpaichit, S.
, 
Hajiwangoh, Z.
, 
2005
. 

Eudesmane sesquiterpenes from the aquatic fungus 
Beltrania rhombica

. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
53
, 
238–240
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/cpb.53.238
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sheldrick, G.M.
, 
2015
. 

Crystal structure refinement with 
SHELXL

. 
Acta Crystallogr. C
71
, 
3–8
. 
https://doi.org/10.1107/S2053229614024218
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stephens, P.J.
, 
Harada, N.
, 
2010
. 
ECD cotton effect approximated by the Gaussian curve and other methods
. 
Chirality
22
, 
229–233
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/chir.20733
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Uson´, I., 
Sheldrick, G.M.
, 
2018
. 

An introduction to experimental phasing of macromolecules illustrated by 
SHELX
; new autotracing features

. 
Acta Crystallogr.
74
, 
106
. 
https://doi.org/10.1107/S2059798317015121
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, S.
, 
Yu, Z.X.
, 
Wang, C.H.
, 
Wu, C.M.
, 
Guo, P.
, 
Wei, J.H.
, 
2018
. 

Chemical constituents and pharmacological activity of agarwood and 
Aquilaria
plants

. 
Molecules
23
, 
342
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules23020342
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, J.
, 
Zeng, G.Z.
, 
Liu, Y.M.
, 
Chen, K.L.
, 
Sun, Z.H.
, 
Zhang, Y.M.
, 
Tan, N.H.
, 
2014
. 

Sesquiterpenoids and diterpenes from 
Chamaecyparis obtusa
var. 
breviramea
f. crippsii

. 
Z. Naturforsch.
69
b, 
362–368
. 
https://doi.org/10.5560/ZNB.2014-3243
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zaki, M.H.
, 
Akuta, T.
, 
Akaike, T.
, 
2005
. 
Nitric oxide-induced nitrative stress involved in microbial pathogenesis
. 
J. Pharmacol. Sci.
98
, 
117–129
. 
https://doi.org/10.1254/ jphs.CRJ05004X
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhao, L.Z.
, 
Jin, Y.
, 
Han, X.M.
, 
Chu, Q.L.
, 
Yang, J.S.
, 
2016
. 

Two new sesquiterpenes from the aerial parts of 
Schizonepeta tenuifolia
. J

. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
19
, 
152–156
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/10286020.2016.1190341
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
