<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113473</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Alkaloids with cholinesterase inhibitory activities from the bulbs of Crinum × amabile Donn ex Ker Gawl</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
× 
amabile
Donn ex Ker Gawl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
× 
amabile
Donn ex Ker Gawl. Their
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
× 
amabile
Donn ex Ker Gawl. (Amaryllidaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Galanthus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Narcissus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhodophiala
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Zephyranthes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
× 
amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form two</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
× 
amabile
Donn ex Ker Gawl. (Amaryllidaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C.
× 
amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Electrophorus electricus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
× 
amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Alkaloids with cholinesterase inhibitory activities from the bulbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
</tp:taxon-name>
× 
amabile
Donn ex Ker Gawl

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Waraluck Chaichompoo
a, b
, Pornchai Rojsitthisak

a, b, 
*
, Wachirachai Pabuprapap
c
,
Yuttana Siriwattanasathien 
c
, Pathumwadee Yotmanee
c
, Apichart Suksamrarn
c
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Department of Food
and 
Pharmaceutical Chemistry
, 
Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences
, 
Chulalongkorn University
, 
Bangkok
, 10330, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b

Center of 
Excellence

in Natural Products for Aging and 
Chronic Diseases
, 
Chulalongkorn University
, 
Bangkok
, 10330, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c
Department of Chemistry
and 
Center of Excellence
for Innovation in 
Chemistry
, 
Faculty of Science
, 
Ramkhamhaeng University
, 
Bangkok
, 10240, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
C 
rinum
<tp:taxon-name>
× 
amabile
Donn ex Ker Gawl.
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Alkaloids</p>
         <p>Acetylcholinesterase</p>
         <p>Butyrylcholinesterase</p>
         <p>Molecular docking</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
Seven previously undescribed alkaloids, crinamabilines A–G, two non-alkaloidal compounds, crinamabidiene and 6-phenylpiperonyl alcohol, two first naturally occurring alkaloids, 3-epibuphanisine and (+)-1 
β
,2 
β
-epoxy-epicrinine, together with nineteen known alkaloids, were isolated from the bulbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
× 
amabile
Donn ex Ker Gawl. Their
</tp:taxon-name>
structures and absolute configurations were elucidated by NMR, MS and ECD spectroscopic techniques. Ungeremine displayed the most potent inhibitory activity against acetylcholinesterase (IC 
50
0.21 μM), which was about 6-fold more active than the reference drug, galanthamine (IC 
50
1.23 μM). Ungeremine also exhibited the strongest inhibitory activity against butyrylcholinesterase (IC 
50
3.57 μM), which was comparable to galanthamine (IC 
50
3.11 μM). The molecular docking studies were performed and were well in agreement with the experimental results.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
plants are generally bulbous plants, which are widely distributed in the tropical and subtropical regions of the world (

). The family comprises more than 1600 species belonging to about 75 genera (

). The traditional uses of plants of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family are attributed to the exclusive alkaloid chemistry (

). More than 500 alkaloids have been reported from various 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
plants with a wide range of pharmacological activities (

). Members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
plants are well known for their biologically active alkaloids, including galanthamine, which is currently available in the market for the treatment of Alzheimer’ s disease (AD) (

).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
× 
amabile
Donn ex Ker Gawl. (Amaryllidaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
is locally known in Thai as ‘phlap phlueng dok daeng’ or ‘giant lily’ (

). In 
Thailand
, the bulbs of this plant have been traditionally used as diuretics (

). In addition, this plant species has been widely used in Vietnamese folk medicine as an emetic and a remedy for rheumatism and earache (

). Recent phytochemical investigations of this plant showed the presence of haemanthamine-, crinine-, lycorine- and galanthamine-type alkaloids (

; 

, 

; 

). Previous pharmacological evaluations of the extracts and phytochemicals from this plant revealed their cytotoxic, anti-malarial, anti-cholinesterase and anti-inflammatory potentials (

; 

; 

, 

; 

). However, the studies on phytochemicals and biological activities of this plant species have not much been reported.
</p>
         <p>
AD is a neurodegenerative disorder that represents the most common cause of human dementia (

). Cholinergic neurotransmission represents the main approach to impaired cognitive function in AD and dementia patients. In the brain tissue, two cholinesterase enzymes including acetylcholinesterase (AChE) and butyrylcholinesterase (BuChE) play a crucial role in the neurotransmitters imbalance, particularly acetylcholine (ACh). These enzymes contribute to the hydrolytic degradation of ACh in the cerebral cortex and hippocampus. Accordingly, the inhibition of AChE and BuChE is considered a promising strategy for the treatment of AD (

). As part of our ongoing studies on a potential source of ChE inhibitors from Thai medicinal plants, a number of plant species have been screened for AChE and BuChE inhibitory activities. The results showed that the crude extracts of the bulbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibited anti-AChE and anti-BuChE potentials. Thus, we report herein the isolation and structure elucidation of seven previously undescribed alkaloids, crinamabilines A–G (
1–7
), two non-alkaloidal compounds, crinamabidiene (
8
) and 6-phenylpiperonyl alcohol (
9
), two first naturally occurring alkaloids, 3-epibuphanisine (
10
) and (+)-1 
β
,2 
β
-epoxy-epicrinine (
11
), along with nineteen known alkaloids 
12–30
(
Fig. 1
). The 
in vitro
AChE and BuChE inhibitory activities of most of the isolated compounds were assessed. The molecular docking studies were successfully performed to illustrate the bindings between the top-scoring alkaloids and the active sites of AChE and BuChE.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
Based on our preliminary screening of Thai medicinal plants with cholinesterase inhibition, we found that the active EtOAc and BuOH crude extracts of the bulbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
showed inhibitory activities against AChE and BuChE with IC 
50
ranging from 0.2 to 1.1 μg/mL and 1.2–2.3 μg/mL, respectively. These extracts were therefore subjected to column chromatography and led to the isolation of thirty compounds. The chemical structures of the isolated compounds were elucidated and characterized by spectroscopic (
1
H and 
13
C NMR, HR-TOFMS, optical rotation and ECD spectra) data.
</p>
         <p>
The known alkaloids were identified as epibuphanisine (
12
) (

), (+)-bulbispermine (
13
), yemenine A (
14
) (Abdel-- Halim et al., 2004), ()-11-epihaemanthamine (
15
) (

), haemanthidine (
16
) (

), hamayne (
17
) (

), crinamine (
18
) (

), 6-hydroxycrinamine (
19
) (

), buphanisine (
20
), flexinine (
21
), augustine (
22
) (

), epijosephinine (
23
) (

), augustamine (
24
) (

), ()-lycorine (
25
) (

), 1- 
O
-acetyllycorine (
26
) (

), 1- 
O
-acetylisopseudolycorine (
27
) (

), 1- 
O
-acetylnorpluviine (
28
) (

), ungeremine (
29
) (

) and trisphaeridine (
30
) (

) by spectroscopic (
1
H and 
13
C NMR, and HR-TOFMS spectra) data and by comparison of their experimental and reported values. Previous reports on the alkaloid constituents of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
included compounds 
18
, 
20
, 
22
and 
24–27
, and two alkaloid 
N
-oxide analogs of compounds 
20
and 
22
(

; 

, 

). The two major 
types
of alkaloids isolated in the present work include the crinane- and lycorine-type alkaloids (

), with the first 
type
predominating.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
1
was obtained as a white amorphous solid. The HR-TOFMS (positive ion electrospray ionization, ESI 
+
) at 
m/z
288.1243 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
16
H 
18
NO 
4
, 288.1230) was compatible with the molecular formula C 
16
H 
17
NO 
4
. The IR spectrum indicated the presence of hydroxy (
3253 cm
1
), olefinic (
1654 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
931 cm
1
) groups. The 
1
H NMR spectrum (
Table 1
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, 
Fig. S1 S
4
) showed the presence of two 
para
- oriented aromatic protons as singlets at 
δ
H
6.91 and 6.53 assignable to H-10 and H-7, respectively. The singlet signal at 
δ
H
5.86 could be assigned to the methylenedioxy proton. Two benzylic protons appeared as two doublet resonances at 
δ
H
4.28 and 3.74 (
J
= 16.7 Hz) corresponding to H-6. The olefinic proton signals at 
δ
H
6.40 (brd, 
J
= 10.1 Hz) and 6.17 (ddd, 
J
= 10.1, 5.1 and 0.7 Hz) were ascribable to H-1 and H-2, respectively. The small coupling constant (0.7 Hz) was due to the long-range W coupling between the H-2 and the H-4eq (

; 

). The presence of one lowfield methine signal at 
δ
H
4.25–4.28 was indicative of a hydroxy group located on C-3. H-4ax and H-4eq appeared at 
δ
H
2.23 (ddd, 
J
= 13.4, 13.4 and 4.4 Hz) and 
δ
H
1.80, dddd, 
J
= 13.4, 4.7, 1.3 and 0.7 Hz), respectively. The small coupling constants between H-3 (W 
½
= 11.1 Hz) and both H-4ax (4.4 Hz) and H-4eq (1.3 Hz) were in agreement with the 
α
-ethano bridge and an axial-oriented hydroxy substituent at C-3 (

). The 
13
C NMR and DEPT-135 data (
Table 5
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, 
Fig. S5 S
6) showed the presence of sixteen carbon resonances attributed to five quaternary, seven methine and four methylene carbons. In addition, in the HMBC experiments (
Fig. 2
and 
Table S1
), H-1 showed correlations with C-2 (
δ
C
133.3), C-3 (
δ
C
65.2), C-4a (
δ
C
64.1), C-10a (
δ
C
137.6) and C-10 b (
δ
C
51.8), whereas H-2 correlated with C-4 (
δ
C
33.5) and C-10 b. The H-4a (
δ
H
3.39, brdd, 
J
= 13.4 and 4.7 Hz) was connected to C-6 (
δ
C
62.2), C-10a, C-11 (
δ
C
81.5) and C-12 (
δ
C
64.3) through three-bonds HMBC interaction. The benzylic protons at position 6 were also correlated with C-4a, C-7 (
δ
C
108.3), C-10a and C- 
12 in
the HMBC spectrum. Moreover, the HMBC correlations between H-7 with C-6, C-9 (
δ
C
148.6) and C-10a, and H-10 with C-6a (
δ
C
127.4), C-8 (
δ
C
148.1), and C-10 b, along with the correlation between methylenedioxy proton and C-8 and C-9, were also observed. The structural assignment for compound 
1
was supported by the analysis of its NOESY spectrum (
Fig. 3
). The H-3eq signal displayed a key interaction with H-4ax, whereas H-4eq correlated with H-4a, suggesting the equatorial-orientation of H-3. Moreover, H-4a displayed key interactions with H-6 
β
and H-4eq, whereas H-4ax showed a correlation with H-12 
exo
(
δ
H
3.11, dd, 
J
= 13.8 and 3.4 Hz). Moreover, H-6 
α
correlated with H-12 
endo
(
δ
H
3.41, brdd, 
J
= 13.8 and 7.0 Hz), and H-10 showed a correlation with H-1. The relative configuration of C-11 was also determined by the NOESY relationship with H-12 
exo,
which indicated an 
exo
disposition of H-11 (
δ
H
3.94, ddd, 
J
= 7.0, 3.4 and 0.9 Hz). It should be noted that the presence of very small coupling constants or the broad signals of the H-4a, H-6, H-11 and H-12 resulted from the long-range couplings in this 
type
of core structure (

). As illustrated in 
Fig. 3
, the findings suggest that C-11 has the 
R
configuration (

). The ECD spectral patterns of the 
α
-ethano and 
β
-ethano bridges have been reported (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). A comparison was made between the ECD spectra of vittatine, the 
α
-ethano oriented alkaloid, which showed a negative Cotton effect around 
240 nm
and a positive Cotton effect around 
290 nm
, and the 
β
-ethano oriented alkaloid, crinine, which showed Cotton effects at the two wavelengths with opposite signs (

; 

). The experimental ECD spectrum of compound 
1
(
Fig. 4
) showed a negative Cotton effect at 
244 nm
(Δ 
ε
34.5) and a positive Cotton effect at 
294 nm
(Δ 
ε
+ 31.3), which was in agreement with the haemanthamine-type alkaloid, haemanthamine (

). These observations suggest that the absolute configuration of compound 
1
was 3 
S
,4a 
S
,5 
R
,10bR,11 
R
as presented in 
Fig. 1
. On the basis of these data, the structure of compound 
1
was established as shown and was named crinamabiline A.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
2
was isolated as a white amorphous solid and was assigned a molecular formula of C 
19
H 
21
NO 
6
as deduced by HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) at 
m/z
360.1445 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
19
H 
22
NO 
6
, 360.1441). The IR spectrum showed absorption bands of hydroxy (3400
</p>
         <p>
cm 
1
), acetoxy (
1735 cm
1
), olefinic (
1644 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
933 cm
1
) groups. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of compound 
2
(
Tables 1
and 
5
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S17 S21) were similar to those of compound 
1
. The main differences were the presence of an additional singlet methoxy group (
δ
H
3.38) in the pseudoaxial orientation at the 3-position that induced a shielding effect on H-3eq, which was confirmed by the HMBC correlation of the methoxy group with C-3 (
δ
C
78.3) (see 
Fig. 2
and 
Table S1
). The small coupling constant between H-3eq (
δ
H
4.04–4.07, m, W 
½
= 11.8 Hz) and both H-4ax (
δ
H
2.06–2.12) and H-4eq (
δ
H
1.96, dddd, 
J
= 13.0, 5.4, 4.0 and 1.3 Hz) confirmed the orientation of the 
α
-ethano bridge and an axial-oriented methoxy substituent at C-3 (

). In addition, the NOE difference experiments were also confirmed to be similar to those of the NOESY experiments. Thus, irradiation at the H-3 frequency of compound 
2
resulted in key NOE enhancement of the H-4ax signal (Fig. S165). In addition, the presence of one highly deshielded benzylic proton as a singlet signal at 
δ
H
6.14 was indicative of an acetoxy group located on C-6. The presence of this acetoxy group was supported by the carbonyl resonance at 
δ
C
172.3 in
the 
13
C NMR spectra and the HMBC correlations of H-6 with carbonyl and methyl (
δ
C
20.9) carbon resonances. The 
β
-orientation of the C-6 acetoxy group was established from the NOESY correlation (
Fig. 3
) between H-6 and H-12 
endo
(
δ
H
3.50, brdd, 
J
= 13.9 and 7.0 Hz) confirmed the 
α
-orientation of H-6. The absolute configuration of this alkaloid was determined from the ECD experiments in analogy to compound 
1
(
Fig. 4
) that exhibited a similar negative Cotton effect at 
245 nm
(Δ 
ε
35.0) and a positive Cotton effect at 
290 nm
(Δ 
ε
+ 35.6). The stereochemistry of the substituents at C-3 and C-6, which does not affect the signs of the ECD spectrum, is consistent with the previous report (

). The absolute configuration of 
2
was thus determined as 3 
S
, 4a 
S
,5 
R
,6 
S
,10bR,11 
R
. Based on these data, the structure of compound 
2
was established and was named crinamabiline B.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Assignments were based on 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HMQC, HMBC, and NOESY experiments.
</p>
         <p>
b
Partially overlapping signal.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
3
was obtained as a white amorphous solid, which was deduced to have a molecular formula of C 
19
H 
21
NO 
6
by the HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) at 
m/z
360.1439 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
19
H 
22
NO 
6
, 360.1441). The IR spectrum displayed absorption bands of hydroxy (
3399 cm
1
), acetoxy (
1738 cm
1
), olefinic (
1642 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
928 cm
1
) functionalities. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of compound 
3
(
Tables 1
and 
5
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S32 S36) showed closely similar spectral features to those of compound 
2
. The significant difference was the acetoxy signal (
δ
H
2.20 and 
δ
C
171.9) in the 
α
-orientation, which is evident from the NOESY correlation of the benzylic proton H-6 (
δ
H
6.63) and H-4a (
δ
H
3.49, brdd, 
J
= 13.0 and 3.7 Hz) (see 
Fig. 3
). It should be mentioned that the relatively more down-field signal of H-6 
β
(
δ
H
6.63) of compound 
3
than that of the H-6 
α
(
δ
H
6.14) of compound 
2
was consistent with that reported previously (

). Furthermore, the 
α
-oriented OAc group in compound 
3
caused considerable downfield shift (0.47 ppm) of the H-12 
endo
and upfield shift (0.21 ppm) of the H-12 
exo
resonances compared with compound 
1
. The absolute configuration of this compound was also determined from the ECD experiments that exhibited a similar negative Cotton effect at 
250 nm
(Δ 
ε
52.3) and a positive Cotton effect at 
280 nm
(Δ 
ε
+ 37.0) to those of compound 
2
. The absolute configuration of 
3
was confirmed as 3 
S
,4a 
S
,5 
R
,6 
R
,10bR,11 
R
. Therefore, the structure of compound 
3
was established as shown and this compound was named crinamabiline C.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
4
was obtained as a white amorphous solid. The HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) at 
m/z
332.1494 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
18
H 
22
NO 
5
, 332.1492) was compatible with the molecular formula C 
18
H 
21
NO 
5
. The IR spectrum exhibited absorption bands of hydroxy (
3424 cm
1
), olefinic (
1664 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
931 cm
1
) groups. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of compound 
4
(
Tables 2
and 
5
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S48 S53) were similar to those of compound 
2
. The first significant difference was the presence of a pseudoequatorial methoxy proton (
δ
H
3.38, s). The HMBC correlation between this methoxy proton with a carbon resonance at 
δ
C
78.4 confirmed that the location of the methoxy group was C-3 (see 
Fig. 2
and 
Table S2
). The magnitude of coupling constants between H-3ax (
δ
H
4.00–4.05, m, W 
½
= 20.8 Hz) and both H-4ax (
δ
H
2.09, ddd, 
J
= 13.7, 10.6 and 9.7 Hz) and H-4eq (
δ
H
1.91, dddd, 
J
= 13.7, 5.6, 3.0 and 0.7 Hz) were in agreement with the 
α
-ethano bridge and an equatorial-oriented methoxy substituent at C-3. The difference of the large coupling constant (10.6 Hz) between H-3ax and H-4ax in compound 
4
and between H-3eq and H-4ax (W 
½
of H-3 was 11.8 Hz) in compound 
2
was noted. The equatorial-orientation of the C-3 methoxy group was also established from the NOESY interaction of H-3 with H-4a (
δ
H
3.36, brdd, 
J
= 9.7 and 3.0 Hz) and correlations of H-4a with H-3 and H-4eq confirmed the axial-orientation of H-3 (
Fig. 3
). In addition, the NOE difference experiments also confirmed the orientation of H-3. Thus, irradiation at the H-3 frequency of compound 
4
resulted in key NOE enhancements of the H-4a and H-4eq signals (Fig. S167). The second main difference was the presence of a singlet proton at 
δ
H
3.57 assignable to the pseudoaxial methoxy proton at C-6. This assignment was confirmed by the HMBC correlation of the 6-methoxy proton with C-6 (
δ
C
97.8). Moreover, the NOESY relationship between H-6 (
δ
H
4.47) and H-12 
endo
(
δ
H
3.31, brdd, 
J
= 14.1 and 7.0 Hz) indicated the 
α
-orientation for H-6. The absolute configuration of 
4
was also confirmed by the ECD experiments that exhibited a similar negative Cotton effect at 
245 nm
(Δ 
ε
16.7) and a positive Cotton effect at 
292 nm
(Δ 
ε
+ 18.6) to those of compound 
2
. The absolute configuration of 
4
was therefore elucidated as 3 
R
,4a 
S
,5 
R
,6 
S
,10bR,11 
R
and this compound was named crinamabiline D.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
5
was obtained as a white amorphous solid. The molecular formula of compound 
5
was determined to be C 
18
H 
21
NO 
5
based on the HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) at 
m/z
332.1496 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
18
H 
22
NO 
5
, 332.1492). The IR spectrum indicated the presence of hydroxy (
3419 cm
1
), olefinic (
1652 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
936 cm
1
) groups. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of 
5
(
Tables 2
and 
5
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S65 S70) closely resembled those of 
4
. The significant difference was the C-6 methoxy group was in the 
α
-orientation, which was established by the NOESY experiment. The NOESY correlation between H-6 (
δ
H
5.06) and H-4a (
δ
H
3.29–3.32) confirmed the 
β
-orientation of H-6 (see 
Fig. 3
). It is noteworthy that the methoxy substituent exerted a similar effect to that of the acetoxy substituent in compound 
3
. The 
α
-oriented 6-OMe group in compound 
5
caused a downfield shift (0.52 ppm) of the H-12 
endo
and an upfield shift (0.37 ppm) of the H-12 
exo
resonances compared with the 
β
-oriented 6-OMe of compound 
4
. The absolute configuration of this alkaloid was confirmed from the ECD experiments analogous to compound 
4
with a similar negative Cotton effect at 
245 nm
(Δ 
ε
41.7) and a positive Cotton effect at 
292 nm
(Δ 
ε
+ 46.5). The absolute configuration of 
5
was established as 3 
R
,4a 
S
,5 
R
,6 
R
,10bR,11 
R
. On the basis of these data, the structure of compound 
5
was elucidated as shown and was named crinamabiline E.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
6
was isolated as a white amorphous solid. The HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) at 
m/z
402.1547 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
21
H 
24
NO 
7
, 402.1547) was compatible with the molecular formula C 
21
H 
23
NO 
7
. The IR spectrum showed absorption bands of acetoxy (
1738 cm
1
), olefinic (
1622 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
931 cm
1
) groups. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of compound 
6
(
Tables 2
and 
5
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S81 S85) were similar to those of compound 
4
. The significant difference was the presence of a highly deshielded benzylic proton as a singlet at 
δ
H
6.15 and a carbon resonance at 
δ
C
88.2, together with an acetoxy group (
δ
H
2.10, and 
δ
C
172.4 and 
δ
C
21.7). The HMBC correlations between the benzylic proton and the acetoxy methyl proton and the carbonyl carbon resonance confirmed that the acetoxy group was located at C-6 (
Fig. 2
and 
Table S2
). Another main difference was the presence of an additional acetoxy group (
δ
H
2.00, and 
δ
C
172.5 and 21.6) and this group should be placed at C-11 as evidenced by the highly deshielded methine signal at 
δ
H
4.84–4.87. This was further supported by the HMBC interaction between the acetoxy methyl proton and H-11. Compound 
6
exhibited a similar ECD spectrum as those of compound 
4
with a similar negative Cotton effect at 
252 nm
(Δ 
ε
8.5) and a positive Cotton effect at 
280 nm
(Δ 
ε
+ 30.6), suggesting the same 
R
-configuration at C-11. The absolute configuration of 
6
was therefore concluded as 3 
R
,4a 
S
,5 
R
,6 
S
,10bR,11 
R
. Consequently, compound 
6
was elucidated as shown and was named crinamabiline F.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
7
was obtained as a white amorphous solid. The molecular formula C 
17
H 
21
NO 
5
was determined by the HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) at 
m/ z
320.1491 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
17
H 
22
NO 
5
, 320.1492). The IR spectrum exhibited the absorption bands of hydroxy (
3356 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
933 cm
1
) groups. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of compound 
7
(
Tables 3
and 
5
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S96 S101) showed most spectral patterns similar to those of compound 
4
and other compounds, but some differences in spectral patterns were present. The notable difference was the absence of the olefinic proton signals at C-1 and C-2. Additionally, the presence of two coupled methylene protons at 
δ
H
2.58 (ddd, 
J
= 13.5, 4.8 and 2.1 Hz, H-1eq), 1.92 (ddd, 
J
= 13.5, 12.9 and 5.2 Hz, H-1ax), 1.83 (dddd, 
J
= 13.3, 12.9, 11.2 and 4.8 Hz, H-2ax) and 1.97 (brdddd, 
J
= 13.3, 5.2, 4.4 and 2.1 Hz, H-2eq) indicated that compound 
7
had an additional hydrogenated residue relative to those of 6-hydroxycrinamine (
18
) (

), which has also been isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
in the present work. The 
13
C NMR data are consistent with these observations (
Table 5
). The 
1
H– 
1
H COSY and HMBC experiments (
Fig. 2
) confirmed the foregoing assignments. The presence of the benzylic proton signal at 
δ
H
4.97 suggested that a hydroxy substituent was located at position 6, which was confirmed by HMBC correlations of H-6 with C-4a (
δ
C
60.4), C-7 (
δ
C
108.6), C-10a (
δ
C
139.7) and C-12 (
δ
C
58.1) (
Fig. 2
). The 
α
-orientation of H-6 was confirmed by the NOESY correlation of this proton with H-12 
endo
. The configuration of C-11 was established by the NOESY correlations of H-11 (
δ
H
4.02, brdd, 
J
= 6.7 and 3.9 Hz) with H-1eq and H-10 (
δ
H
6.64), which indicated an 
endo
disposition of H-11. The results, illustrated in 
Fig. 3
, therefore, suggest that C-11 has the 
S
configuration. The absolute configuration of this alkaloid was determined from the ECD experiment, which showed a negative Cotton effect at 
246 nm
(Δ 
ε
33.2) and a positive Cotton effect at 
280 nm
(Δ 
ε
+ 20.8), which is in agreement with compound 
19
. As the 
endo
disposition of H-11 does not exert a considerable effect on the ECD spectrum (

; 

; 

), the similar ECD curve of compound 
7
(
Fig. 4
) compared with those of compounds 
1–6
has led to a conclusion that the absolute configuration of compound 
7
is an 
α
-ethano oriented alkaloid (

; 

; 

). The absolute configuration of 
7
was elucidated as 3 
R
,4a 
S
,5 
R
,6 
S
,10bR,11 
S
. On the basis of these findings, compound 
7
was concluded as crinamabiline G.
</p>
         <p>
a
Assignments were based on 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HMQC, HMBC, and NOESY experiments.
</p>
         <p>
b
Partially overlapping signal.
</p>
         <p>
c
Overlapping signal.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Assignments were based on, 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HMQC, HMBC, and NOESY
</p>
         <p>
experiments. 
b
Recorded in CDCl. 
3
c
Recorded in CD OD. 
3
d
Partially overlapping signal. 
e
Partially overlapping signal. The signal was resolved into 
δ
4.02–4.07 (m,
</p>
         <p>
H
W 
½
= 20.5 Hz, H-3) and 
δ
H
3.85 (d, 
J
= 17.0 Hz, H-6 
β
) in CD 
3
OD.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
8
was isolated as a white amorphous solid with a sodiated molecular ion of the HR-TOFMS at 
m/z
283.0947 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. for C 
15
H 
16
NaO 
4
, 283.0940) and the NMR data have led to the assignment of the molecular formula C 
15
H 
16
O 
4
. The IR spectrum revealed the absorption bands of hydroxy (
3274 cm
1
), olefinic (
1635 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
931 cm
1
) groups. The 
13
C NMR and DEPT-135 data (
Table 4
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S115 S116) showed the presence of fifteen carbons belonging to one methyl, six methine, three methylene and five quaternary carbons, suggesting the phenylcyclohexadiene analog (

). The 
1
H NMR spectrum (
Table 4
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S112 S114) showed the presence of a 1,2,4,5-tetrasubstituted aromatic ring at 
δ
H
6.93 and 6.59, which are assigned to H-2 and H-5, respectively. The singlet signal at 
δ
H
5.91 is assignable to the methylenedioxy proton. The occurrences of two-coupled olefinic protons at 
δ
H
6.14 (brd, 
J
= 9.5 Hz) and 6.01 (brdd, 
J
= 9.5 and 3.9 Hz), together with an olefinic proton at 
δ
H
5.78 (dddd, 
J
= 4.6, 4.2, 1.1 and 1.0 Hz) were ascribable to H-6 
′
, H-5 
′
and H-2 
′
, respectively. The presences of one highly deshielded methine signal at 
δ
H
4.10 (dddd, 
J
= 6.6, 6.6, 3.9 and 1.1 Hz) and one methyl proton at 
δ
H
3.34 (s) were indicative of a methoxy group and the correlations of 4 
′
-OCH 
3
with C-4 
′
(
δ
C
73.0) and H-4 
′
with H-2 
′
and H-5 
′
confirmed the location of a methoxy group at C-4 
′
. The small coupling constants of H-4 
′
with H-3 
′
(
δ
H
2.59, ddd, 
J
= 6.6, 4.6 and 4.2 Hz) and H-5 
′
were in agreement with the axial-oriented methoxy substituent at C-4 
′
. The axial-orientation of the C-4 
′
methoxy group was also established from the NOESY correlation of H-4 
′
with H-5 
′
and correlations of H-5 
′
with H-6 
′
confirmed the equatorial-orientation of H-4 
′
(
Fig. 3
). One oxygenated methylene proton appeared as a singlet at 
δ
H
4.45, indicating the benzylic methylene group. In the HMBC experiments (
Fig. 2
and 
Table S4
), the 
α
-H (
δ
H
4.45, s) showed the correlations with C-1 (
δ
C
136.6), C-6 (
δ
C
136.0) and C-1 
′
(
δ
C
134.0), whereas H-2 correlated with C-3 (
δ
C
148.6), C-4 (
δ
C
148.8), C-6 and 
α
-C (
δ
C
63.0). Moreover, the HMBC interactions between H-5 with C-1, C-3, C-4, C-6 and C-1 
′
were also observed. According to the above evidence, the structure of 
8
was determined as 6-(4 
′
-methoxy-1 
′
,5 
′
-cyclohexadienyl)piperonyl alcohol and was named crinamabidiene. The skeleton of compound 

8
in

relation to those of the alkaloids isolated in this work has led to a postulate that this compound could possibly derive from the degradation of a constituent alkaloid present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
similar to the previous report for the degradation of other 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
alkaloids (

). More information is needed on whether the transformation has occurred by enzymatic or non-enzymatic means.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
9
was isolated along with compound 
8
. The molecular formula C 
14
H 
12
O 
3
was deduced from the HR-TOFMS at 
m/z
251.0682 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. for C 
14
H 
12
NaO 
3
, 251.0678). The IR spectrum revealed the absorption bands of hydroxy (
3393 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
932 cm
1
) groups. The 
1
H NMR spectra (
Table 4
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S128 S130) revealed the presence of the same piperonyl alcohol moiety as that of compound 
8
. The presence of the aromatic proton signals at 
δ
H
7.31 (m, 3H, H-3 
′
, H-4 
′
and H-5 
′
) and 
δ
H
7.38 (m, 2H, H-2 
′
and H-6 
′
) has led to the conclusion that compound 
9
is 6-phenylpiperonyl alcohol. In fact, this compound has been reported previously as an intermediate of chemical degradation of an alkaloid (

). Compound 
9
should therefore be obtained from compound 
8
by the elimination of methanol.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
10
was obtained as a white amorphous solid. The HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) at 
m/z
286.1432 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
17
H 
20
NO 
3
, 286.1437) was compatible with the molecular formula C 
17
H 
19
NO 
3
. The IR spectrum indicated the presence of olefinic (
1644 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
932 cm
1
) groups. The 
1
H NMR spectra (
Table 3
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S132 S135) showed the presence of a 1,2,4,5-tetrasubstituted aromatic ring and the methylenedioxy group, which are characteristic of the aromatic ring of the alkaloids found in this plant species. Two doublets at 
δ
H
4.47 and 3.85 (each 
J
= 17.0 Hz) are indicative of the unsubstituted C-6 benzylic carbon. The olefinic proton signals at 
δ
H
6.61 (brd, 
J
= 10.0 Hz) and 6.00 (dd, 
J
= 10.0 and 5.2 Hz) were ascribable to H-1 and H-2, respectively. The presence of one deshielded methine signal at 
δ
H
3.83–3.87 (m, W 
½
= 20.5 Hz) and a methoxy signal at 
δ
H
3.88 (s) was noted. The ECD experiment of 
10
has thus been determined and it was found that its ECD curve exhibited opposite Cotton effects to those of compounds 
1–7
with a positive Cotton effect at 
244 nm
(Δ 
ε
+ 24.0) and a negative Cotton effect at 
294 nm
(Δ 
ε
22.8) (
Fig. 4
), which was in agreement with the crinine-type alkaloid (

). The large coupling constants between H-3ax and both H-4 (
δ
H
2.22 and 1.64) were in agreement with an 
β
-ethano bridge and an equatorial-oriented methoxy substituent at C-3. The HMBC spectrum (
Fig. 2
) confirmed the methoxy group was placed at C-3. The structural assignment for compound 
10
was supported by the analysis of its NOESY spectrum (
Fig. 3
). The NOESY experiments thus confirmed the relative configuration of compound 
10
. A comparison was made between the ECD spectra of the 
β
-ethano oriented crinine, which showed a positive Cotton effect around 
240 nm
and a negative Cotton effect around 
290 nm
, and the 
α
-ethano oriented vittatine, which showed Cotton effects at the two wavelengths with opposite signs (

). These observations suggest that the absolute configuration of 
10
is as shown in 
Fig. 1
. Compound 
10
, epibuphanisine, has been mentioned as one of the products in the synthesis of crinine analogs (

), but no information about this compound was provided. It should be noted that the name of the synthetic compound given by the previous work may lead to confusion since this name has already been used for compound 
12
previously isolated (

) and this compound has also been isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
in this study. We therefore suggest that the alkaloid 
10
should be named 3-epibuphanisine. This compound has therefore been isolated from a natural source for the first time.
</p>
         <p>
a
Assignments were based on 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HMQC, HMBC, and NOESY experiments.

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Assignments were based on, 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HMQC, HMBC, and NOESY experiments.
</p>
         <p>
b
Recorded in CD OD.
</p>
         <p>
3
c
Recorded in CDCl.
</p>
         <p>
3
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
11
was isolated as a white amorphous solid and was assigned the molecular formula C 
16
H 
17
NO 
4
as determined from the HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) at 
m/z
288.1255 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
16
H 
18
NO 
4
, 288.1230). The IR spectrum indicated the presence of hydroxy (
3356 cm
1
), epoxide (
1284 cm
1
) and methylenedioxy (
934 cm
1
) moieties. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of compound 
11
(
Tables 3
and 
5
, the NMR spectra are in Supplementary data, Fig. S148 S153) displayed similar spectral features to those of compound 
10
, except two olefinic proton signals in compound 
10
were replaced by two oxygenated methine signals at 
δ
H
3.89 (d, 
J
= 3.5 Hz) and 
δ
H
3.26 (brdd, 
J
= 3.5 and 2.7 Hz) assignable to H-1 and H-2, respectively. These NMR spectral data, together with the evidence from the HR-TOFMS, indicate that the double bond at C-1 and C-2 is epoxidized. The conformation of the epoxide ring was assigned from the small coupling constants of H-1 with H-2 (
J
= 3.5 Hz) and H-2 with H-3 (
J
= 2.7 Hz). In addition, a deshielded methine proton at 
δ
H
4.37–4.43 (m, W 
½
= 21.0 Hz) was observed. The HMBC correlations from H-2 and H-4a to C-3 (
δ
C
65.9) unambiguously placed the hydroxy group at C-3 (
Fig. 2
and 
Table S3
). The NOESY correlation (see 
Fig. 3
) between H-3 and H-4a (
δ
H
3.40, brdd, 
J
= 10.5 and 6.1 Hz) was in agreement with an equatorial-oriented hydroxy substituent at C-3. Comparison of the 
1
H NMR spectral features with those of flexinine (
21
) (

), which has been isolated from this plant species in the present work, reveals that they closely resemble; the notable difference being the small W 
½
value (9.1 Hz) of compound 
21
that indicates the equatorial-orientation of H-3. The absolute configuration of this alkaloid was determined from the ECD experiments (
Fig. 4
). As expected, the ECD curve of compound 
11
exhibited a similar positive Cotton effect at 
249 nm
(Δ 
ε
+ 31.5) and a negative Cotton effect at 
279 nm
(Δ 
ε
9.1) to those of compound 
10
. Compound 
11
has previously been reported as a synthetic compound, (+)-1 
β
,2 
β
-epoxy-epicrinine (

; 

) and it has therefore been first reported from a natural source in this study.
</p>
         <p>
In the previous reports, a variety of genera in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family including 
<tp:taxon-name>
Galanthus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Narcissus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhodophiala
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zephyranthes
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
</tp:taxon-name>
revealed the different structural 
types
of alkaloids. The members of galanthamine-, lycorine- and haemanthamine-type alkaloids are the most abundant 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
plants, which have superior AChE inhibitory activities, especially, an AChEI galanthamine was approved by the FDA for treatment of AD revealing possibilities for structural modification or semi-synthesis of potent AChEIs. Alkaloid extracts and fractions of about 100 species of 20 genera resulted in more than 200 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
alkaloids that have been studied for their 
in vitro
AChE inhibitory activity. Some of these alkaloids have been studied 
in silico
to study the interactions between 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
alkaloids and the AChE enzyme (

; 

; 

). For example, compounds 
17–20
, 
22
, 
24
, 
25
, 
27–30
have been reported for their AChE inhibitory activity evaluation (

; 

; Cahlíkova´et al., 2013; 

). Thus, the 
<tp:taxon-name>Amaryllidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
alkaloids prompt the interest of researchers as promising compounds that deserve further 
in vitro
and 
in vivo
study to reveal new AD drugs.
</p>
         <p>
In this study, most of the isolated compounds were evaluated for their AChE and BuChE inhibitory activities by the method described previously by our group (Chaichompoo et al., 2021) and the results are shown in 
Table 6
. Galanthamine, the well-known AChE and BuChE inhibitor, was used as the reference drug. The alkaloid ungeremine (2 
9
) exhibited the strongest inhibitory activity against AChE, with the IC 
50
values of 0.21 μM, which was about 6-fold more active than galanthamine (IC 
50
1.23 μM), followed by compound 
19
, which showed similar inhibitory activity (IC 
50
1.86 μM) to that of galanthamine. Compounds 
16
and 
28
showed high inhibitory activities with the IC 
50
values of 6.41 and 7.08 μM, followed by compounds 
7
, 
10
, 
12
, 
15
, 
18
, 
20
and 
21
and 
23–27
, which exhibited moderate to weak AChE inhibitory activity with the IC 
50
values ranging from 16.76 to 99.51 μM. In addition, alkaloid 
29
also displayed the highest BuChE inhibitory activity among the tested alkaloids, with the IC 
50
value of 3.57 μM, which was slightly less active than galanthamine (IC 
50
3.11 μM). Furthermore, compounds 
10
, 
12
, 
15
, 
16
, 
18–21
, 
23, 24
and 
26
showed good to low degrees of BuChE inhibitory activity with IC 
50
values of 9.31–247.57 μM, whereas compounds 
7
, 
25
, 
27
and 
28
were inactive to the anti-BuChE assay. The tested compounds included 
two types
of alkaloids, the crinane- and lycorine-type alkaloids (

). As the number of each member of the compounds and the structural diversity of each 
type
of the alkaloids are somewhat limited, a detailed structure–anti-ChE activity relationship (SAR) study could not be concluded. However, a preliminary SAR study revealed that, for the crinane-type alkaloids, the presence of the 6-hydroxy group seemed to enhance both AChE and BuChE inhibitory activities. Comparing the structures of 6-hydroxycrinamine (
19
) with that of galanthamine, the two compounds have comparable sizes. However, the presence of the 6-hydroxy group might contribute to its high AChE inhibitory activity since crinamine (
18
) was only approximately 18-folds less active than 
19
. Moreover, the 
α
-hydroxyamino function in 
19
might also exist in the form of the open-ring amino aldehyde function under the test condition (

; 

) and might contribute to the high activity of 
19
. However, further study is required to verify this postulate. For the lycorine-type alkaloids, the high potency of compound 
29
was attributed to the presence of the ring C aromatic connected to the quaternary ammonium functionality, which is important for ChE inhibitory activities. For comparison with galanthamine, the presence of a nitrogen atom connected to the ring C aromatic seemed to be similar to active pharmacophores to those of 

29
in

ChE inhibitory activities (

; 

). The observation was confirmed by molecular docking results.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Data represent as IC values in μM ± S.D. of three independent experiments. 
50
b
Inactive at 0.1 mg/mL.
</p>
         <p>
c
Galanthamine was used as the reference drug.
</p>
         <p>
The binding interaction of the alkaloid 

29
in

the active site of AChE and BuChE has been studied. A molecular docking study was performed using Autodock 4.2 software to investigate the binding affinity of alkaloid 
29
against AChE and BuChE by docking to its binding pocket. The relevance of the docking parameters was verified by re-docking galanthamine and tacrine to their binding sites in AChE and BuChE, respectively. The docking models of the original drugs were well aligned with their crystal structures, indicating that the setting parameters were appropriate for this study (
Fig. 5A and D
). The binding interaction, binding energy (BE, kcal/mol) and % conformation (%C) of alkaloid 
29
and galantamine to the target proteins are summarized in 
Table S5
. The docking results suggested that alkaloid 
29
has a better binding affinity to AChE than galanthamine and is equally proportional at BuChE. The strong binding interaction with key residues in the receptor binding domain was also considered as criteria in determining the potential inhibitor. Alkaloid 
29
showed good binding affinity values of 8.26 kcal/ mol with a high %C of 88.5. 
Fig. 5C
shows that compound 
29
was well occupied in the active gorge of AChE at a different subsite from that of galanthamine. It was able to 
<tp:taxon-name>form two</tp:taxon-name>
hydrogen bonds at the acyl pocket with R296 (distance of 1.75 Å) and S293 (distance of 2.11 Å) and two pi-pi interactions with Y124 and W286 at the peripheral anionic site (distances of 5.81, 5.67 Å for Y124 and 5.22 and 5.38 Å for W286), while two hydrogen bonds with the oxygen anion cavity G120 (distance of 2.84 Å) and the anionic site E202 (distance of 1.73 Å) and a pi-alkyl interaction of the oxygen anion cavity G121 (distance of 3.92 Å) were found for the galanthamine (
Fig. 5B
). It can be seen that the alkaloid 
29
is not only more hydrophobic to AChE, but also has shorter hydrogen bonding distances. Therefore, it could bind to AChE better than galanthamine, which is consistent with the experimental IC 
50
value. Furthermore, when compound 
29
was considered in the BuChE binding pocket, it was found to bind at the same subsite as galanthamine. This alkaloid was stabilized by two pi-pi interactions with W82 (5.34 and 4.99 Å) and two hydrogen bonds with Y128 and D70 (distances of 1.80 and 2.05 Å, respectively) (
Fig. 5F
). It has a proportional binding affinity to the BuChE binding pocket as galanthamine, which forms two hydrogen bonds with the catalytic triad residue Y440 (1.86 and 1.91 Å) and two pi-pi interactions with the catalytic anionic site W82 (3.68 and 4.36 Å) (
Fig. 5E
). This is likewise the IC 
50
values found in the experiment.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
In conclusion, seven undescribed alkaloids (
1–7
), two undescribed analogs (
8
and 
9
) and two first naturally occurring alkaloids (
10
and 
11
), together with nineteen known alkaloids (
12–30
), have been isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
bulbs. Compound 
29
exhibited the most potent acetylcholinesterase (AChE) inhibitory activity, which was about 6-fold more active than galanthamine, the reference drug. Molecular docking studies are well in agreement with the experimental results. The alkaloid 
29
may serve as a lead compound for anti-AChE drug development.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
Optical rotations were measured on a JASCO-1020 polarimeter. Electronic Circular Dichroism (ECD) was recorded on a JASCO J-810 spectropolarimeter. IR spectra were recorded in the ATR mode using a PerkinElmer FT-IR Spectrum 400 spectrophotometer. 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra were recorded at 25 
◦
C on a Bruker ASCEND 400 FT-NMR spectrometer, operating at 400 MHz and 100 MHz for 
1
H and 
13
C NMR, respectively. Chemical shift values are depicted as 
δ
values in parts per million (ppm) and were indirectly referenced to tetramethylsilane (TMS) via the solvent residual signals 
δ
H
7.24 and 
δ
C
77.00 for CDCl 
3
; 
δ
H
3.30 and 
δ
C
49.50 for CD 
3
OD. The coupling constants are expressed as 
J
in Hz. HR-TOFMS spectra were measured with a Bruker micrOTOF-QII mass spectrometer, using electrospray ionization (ESI, positive ion mode) as the ionization technique. Unless otherwise indicated, column chromatography was carried out using Merck silica gel 60 (particle sizes less than 
0.063 mm
) and Merck silica gel 60 RP-18 (particle sizes 

0.040
–0.063
mm

). The slurry method of column packing has been employed. For thin-layer chromatography (TLC), Merck pre-coated silica gel 60 F 
254
plates were used. Spots on TLC were detected under UV light and by spraying with anisaldehyde-H 
2
SO 
4
reagent and Dragendorff’ s reagent followed by heating.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>
The
bulbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
× 
amabile
Donn ex Ker Gawl. (Amaryllidaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected from 
Bang Kruai District
, 
Nonthaburi Province
, 
Thailand
(13 
◦
80 
′
35.7 
′′
N, 100 
◦
41 
′
77.4 
′′
E) in 

January 2020

and the plant species was identified by 
Assoc. Prof. Nopporn Dumrongsiri
, 
Ramkhamhaeng University. A
voucher specimen is deposited at the 
Faculty of Science
, 
Ramkhamhaeng University
, Thailand (
Apichart Suksamrarn, No.
103)

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The fresh bulbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C.
× 
amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
(
1.5 kg
) were minced and macerated with MeOH (5 × 20 L) at room temperature for 72 h in each extraction. The filtered solution was evaporated 
in vacuo
to yield the crude MeOH extract (
50.5 g
). The MeOH extract was suspended in 1 L distilled water and sequentially partitioned with 
n
-hexane, EtOAc, and 
n
-BuOH (3 × 1 L for each solvent) to give the hexane (
0.8 g
), EtOAc (3.0 g) and butanol (36.0 g) extracts, respectively. The EtOAc and butanol extracts gave a positive test to Dragendorff’ s reagent.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Isolation of the compounds from the EtOAc extract
</title>
         <p>
The crude EtOAc extract (
2.9 g
) was fractionated by column chromatography using a gradient solvent system of 
CH
2
Cl 
2
, 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH, and MeOH with increasing amounts of the more polar solvent. The eluates were examined by TLC and five combined fractions (A1–A5) were obtained. Fraction A1 (
232.8 mg
) was subjected to column chromatography eluting with an isocratic condition of 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:2, v/v) to give compound 
6
(
2.4 mg
). Fraction A2 (
1.4 g
) was column chromatographed using 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:3, v/v) as eluent to provide three subfractions (A2.1–A2.3). Subfraction A2.1 (
86.7 mg
) was chromatographed on a silica gel column eluting with hexane–EtOAc (5:95, v/v) to yield compound 
22
(
1.6 mg
). Subfraction A2.2 (
198.1 mg
) was further subjected to column chromatography using hexane– 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (20:80:4, v/v) as eluent to yield compounds 
10
(1.0 mg) and 
12
(
2.2 mg
). Subfraction A2.3 (1.0 g) was chromatographed on silica gel column eluting with hexane– 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (20:80:5, v/v) to provide compound 
20
(
16.4 mg
). Fraction A3 (
165.5 mg
) was subjected to column chromatography (column diameter 
1 cm
, with a 
20 cm
height of the packing material) eluting with a gradient solvent system of 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:2–100:5, v/v) to yield compounds 
2
(
1.1 mg
) and 
3
(
1.4 mg
). Fraction A4 (1.0 g) was further chromatographed by silica gel column eluting with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:4, v/v, with 
ca
0.5 mL volume for each fraction) to give compounds 
18
(
11.4 mg
) and 
24
(
4.5 mg
). Compound 
28
(4.0 mg) was obtained after purification of fraction A5 (
66.2 mg
) by silica column chromatography using 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:8, v/v) as eluent.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Isolation of the compounds from the BuOH extract
</title>
         <p>
The crude BuOH extract (29.0 g) was fractionated by column chromatography using a gradient solvent system of 
CH
2
Cl 
2
, 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH, and MeOH with increasing amounts of the more polar solvent. The eluates were examined by TLC and seven combined fractions (B1–B7) were obtained. Fraction B1 (
12.7 mg
) was subjected to column chromatography eluting with a gradient solvent system of 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:2–100:4, v/v) to yield compounds 
8
(1.0 mg), 
9
(
0.2 mg
) and 
15
(5.0 mg). Fraction B2 (
16.6 mg
) was repeatedly chromatographed on a silica gel column in a similar manner to that employed for the isolation of compound 
2
from compound 
3
, with hexane– 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (20:80:6, v/v) as eluent, to afford compounds 
4
(
0.8 mg
), 
5
(
0.5 mg
) and 
23
(
1.3 mg
). Fraction B3 (
186.9 mg
) was further separated by silica column chromatography, using a gradient solvent system of 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:6–100:8, v/v) to provide compounds 
11
(
1.9 mg
), 
16
(
12.5 mg
), 
19
(
4.3 mg
) and 
26
(
10.5 mg
). Fraction B4 (
8.4 g
) was chromatographed on silica column eluting with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:10, v/v) to give compounds 
21
(
1.4 mg
), 
25
(130.0 mg), 
27
(
20.3 mg
) and 
30
(
0.8 mg
). Fraction B5 (144.0 mg) was similarly chromatographed eluting with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:12, v/v) to give compound 
7
(
22.5 mg
). Reversed-phase column chromatography of fraction B6 (
78.7 mg
) using RP-18 column, with MeOH–H 
2
O (6:4, v/v) as eluting solvent, furnished compounds 
1
(
1.5 mg
), 
13
(
0.8 mg
), 
14
(
0.8 mg
) and 
17
(
3.2 mg
). Column chromatography of fraction B7 (
167.8 mg
) eluting with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (100:30, v/v) afforded compound 
29
(5.0 mg).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Compound characterization
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.1. Crinamabiline A (1)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
25
16.1 (c 0.95, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 244 (34.5), 294 (+ 31.3) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3253, 2893, 1654, 1483, 1300, 1237, 
1032, 931 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CD 
3
OD), see 
Tables 1
and 
5
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
288.1243 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
16
H 
18
NO 
4
, 288.1230).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.2. Crinamabiline B (2)
</title>
         <p>
25
</p>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
20.3 (
c
0.20, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 245 (35.0), 290 (+ 35.6) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3400, 2982, 1735, 1644, 1483, 1359, 1251, 1071, 
1036, 933 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CD 
3
OD), see 
Tables 1
and 
5
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
360.1445 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
19
H 
22
NO 
6
, 360.1441).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.3. Crinamabiline C (3)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
24
38.0 (
c
0.03, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 250 (52.3), 280 (+ 37.0) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3399, 2986, 1738, 1642, 1483, 1258, 1069, 
1037, 928 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CD 
3
OD), see 
Tables 1
and 
5
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
360.1439 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
19
H 
22
NO 
6
, 360.1441).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.4. Crinamabiline D (4)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
25
+ 73.0 (
c
0.04, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 245 (16.7), 292 (+ 18.6) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3424, 2933, 1664, 1481, 1327, 1256, 1088, 
1037, 931 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CD 
3
OD), see 
Tables 2
and 
5
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
332.1494 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
18
H 
22
NO 
5
, 332.1492).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.5. Crinamabiline E (5)
</title>
         <p>
25
</p>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
+ 94.9 (
c
0.13, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 245 (41.7), 292 (+ 46.5) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3419, 2972, 1652, 1482, 1319, 1243, 1096, 
1037, 936 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CD 
3
OD), see 
Tables 2
and 
5
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
332.1496 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
18
H 
22
NO 
5
, 332.1492).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.6. Crinamabiline F (6)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
25
+ 33.8 (
c
0.19, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 252 (8.5), 280 (+ 30.6) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
2987, 1738, 1622, 1483, 1370, 1237, 1096, 
1034, 931 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CD 
3
OD), see 
Tables 2
and 
5
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
402.1547 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
21
H 
24
NO 
7
, 402.1547).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.7. Crinamabiline G (7)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
25
+ 144.0 (
c
0.25, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 246 (33.2), 280 (+ 20.8) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3356, 2938, 1482, 1378, 1240, 1093, 
1037, 933 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CDCl 
3
), see 
Tables 3
and 
5
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
320.1491 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
17
H 
22
NO 
5
, 320.1492).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.8. Crinamabidiene (8)
</title>
         <p>
25
</p>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
59.5 (
c
0.08, MeOH); IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3274, 2896, 1635, 1483, 1301, 1233, 
1035, 931 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CD 
3
OD), see 
Table 4
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
283.0947 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. for C 
15
H 
16
NaO 
4
, 283.0940).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.9. 6-Phenylpiperonyl alcohol (9)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3393, 2928, 1601, 1551, 1480, 1227, 
1039, 932 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR data (CD 
3
OD), see 
Table 4
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
251.0682 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. for C 
14
H 
12
NaO 
3
, 251.0678).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.10. 3-Epibuphanisine (10)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
25
+ 35.1 (
c
0.38, EtOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 244 (+ 24.0), 294 (22.8) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
2932, 1644, 1481, 1319, 1232, 1087, 
1036, 932 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CDCl 
3
), see 
Tables 3
and 
5
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
286.1432 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
17
H 
20
NO 
3
, 286.1437).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.11. (
+
)-1β,2β- epoxy-epicrinine (11)
</title>
         <p>
25
</p>
         <p>
White amorphous solid; [
α
] 
D
+ 89.1 (
c
0.07, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 249 (+ 31.5), 279 (9.1) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3356, 2895, 1483, 1284, 1238, 
1037, 934 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (CD 
3
OD), see 
Tables 3
and 
5
; HR-TOFMS (ESI 
+
) 
m/z
288.1255 [M + H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
16
H 
18
NO 
4
, 288.1230).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Anti-cholinesterase activities assay
</title>
         <p>
The inhibitory activities of the crude extracts and isolated compounds on AChE and BuChE were conducted using Ellman’ s method (

) with minor modifications mentioned in the previous report (Chaichompoo et al., 2021). The enzymes and chemicals including AChE (from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Electrophorus electricus
</tp:taxon-name>
), BuChE (from equine serum), galanthamine (as hydrobromide salt), 5,5 
′
-dithiobis (2-nitrobenzoic acid) (DTNB), bovine serum albumin (BSA), acetylthiocholine iodide (ATCI) and 
S
-butyrylthiocholine iodide (BTCI) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, 
Missouri
, 
USA
). Briefly, the enzyme solutions were prepared at 0.2 U/mL in 10 mM phosphate buffer solution (PBS, pH 8.0). The assay medium consisted of 140 μL of 10 mM PBS, 20 μL of the enzyme and 20 μL of the test compounds were mixed in a 96-well plate and shaken for 10 min. The reaction was initiated by the addition of 20 μL of a mixture of 5 mM DTNB, 0.1% BSA, and substrate (ATCI or BTCI) and was then incubated at room temperature for 5 min. The absorbance was measured using a microplate reader (Sunrise, 
Switzerland
) at a wavelength of 
405 nm
. The percentage of AChE inhibition was calculated by comparing the rate of enzymatic hydrolysis of ASCI for the sample to that of the blank (80% MeOH in buffer). The percentage of BuChE inhibition was similarly performed as described for AChE. Galanthamine was used as a positive control. All experiments were conducted in triplicate and IC 
50
values were calculated by linear regression.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Molecular docking calculations
</title>
         <p>
The molecular docking technique was applied to study the binding orientation and affinity of the alkaloid 
29
from the bulbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Crinum
× 
amabile
</tp:taxon-name>
toward the binding gorge of AChE and BuChE enzymes using Autodock 4.2 (

). The compound was created with the program ACD Lab and then optimized by Hartree-Fock level calculations with the 6-31G* basis set using the GAUSSIAN09 package (

). The 3D protein structures of the human AChE and human BuChE enzymes were obtained from the Protein Data Bank with PDB IDs: 4EY6 and 4BDS, respectively. Galanthamine, used as a control molecule, was re-docked into the AChE binding site to determine the appropriate binding parameters for docking. Proteins were processed using AutoDock Tools (

) to remove all water molecules and generate all hydrogen atoms of the molecule. Nonpolar hydrogen atoms and lone pairs were then merged and Gasteiger partial charges were assigned to each atom. A grid box of 80 × 80 × 80 points with a spacing of 0.375 Å was positioned at the center of the active site gorge. The protein molecule was kept rigid while the ligand was flexible. The autogrid4 parameter was used to attain grid maps. Furthermore, autodock4 was performed using Lamarckian genetic algorithms to obtain the best docking conformation. For each docking experiment, 250 independent docking runs were performed. The conformations were selected based on the lowest binding energy in the cluster with the most %conformations (see 
Table S5
). They were then compared to their experimental IC 
50
values to confirm relative accuracy. Analysis and visualization of the docking results were done using the BIOVIA Discovery studio visualizer (BIOVIA, Dassault Syst`emes, 2019).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Data availability
</p>
         <p>No data was used for the research described in the article.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>The authors express gratitude to the Ratchadaphiseksomphot Endowment Fund for Postdoctoral Fellowship, Chulalongkorn University (W.C.) and for the Center of Excellence in Natural Products for Ageing and Chronic Diseases, Chulalongkorn University (GCE 6503433003-1, P.R.). Support from the Center of Excellence for Innovation in Chemistry, Ministry of Higher Education, Science, Research and Innovation is gratefully acknowledged (A.S.).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113473.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Abdel-Halim, O.B.
, 
Morikawa, T.
, 
Ando, S.
, 
Matsuda, H.
, 
Yoshikawa, M.
, 
2004
. 

New crinine-type alkaloids with inhibitory effect on induction of inducible nitric oxide synthase from 
Crinum yemense

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
67
, 
1119–1124
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/np030529k
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ail, A.A.
, 
Sayed, H.M.E.
, 
Abdallah, O.M.
, 
Steglich, W.
, 
1986
. 

Oxocrinine and other alkaloids from 
Crinum americanum

. 
Phytochemistry
25
, 
2399–2401
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/S0031-9422(00)81704-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ali, A.A.
, 
Hambloch, H.
, 
Frahm, W.
, 
1983
. 
Relative configuration of the alkaloid augustamine
. 
Phytochemistry
22
, 
283–287
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422 (00)80106-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bastida, J.
, 
Lavilla, R.
, 
Viladomat, F.
, 
2006
. 

Chemical and biological aspects of 
Narcissus
alkaloids

. 
Alkaloids - Chem. Biol.
63
, 
87–179
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S1099-4831 (06)63003-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Berkov, S.
, 
Atanasova, M.
, 
Georgiev, B.
, 
Bastida, J.
, 
Doytchinova, I.
, 
2021
. 
The Amaryllidaceae alkaloids: an untapped source of acetylcholinesterase inhibitors
. 
Phytochemistry Rev
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11101-021-09790-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bru, C.
, 
Guillou, C.
, 
2006
. 
Total syntheses of crinine and related alkaloids
. 
Tetrahedron
62
, 
9043–9048
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tet.2006.07.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bunyapraphatsara, N.
, 
Chokchaicharoenporn, O.
, 
1999
. 
Indigenous Medicinal Herbs
. 
Prachachon, Bangkok
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cahlíkov´a, L., Locˇ´arek, M., Beneˇsov´a, N., Kuˇcera, R., 
Chlebek, J.
, Nov´ak, Z., 
Opletal, L.
, 
2013
. 

Isolation and cholinesterase inhibitory activity of 
Narcissus
extracts and Amaryllidaceae alkaloid

. 
Nat. Prod. Commun.
8
, 
781–785
. 
https://doi.org/10.1177/ 1934578x1300800625
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Campbell, W.E.
, 
Nair, J.J.
, 
Gammon, D.W.
, 
Codina, C.
, 
Bastida, J.
, 
Viladomat, F.
, 
Smith, P.J.
, 
Albrecht, C.F.
, 
2000
. 

Bioactive alkaloids from 
Brunsvigia radulosa

. 
Phytochemistry
53
, 
587–591
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(99)00575-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chaichompoo, W.
, 
Chokchaisiri, R.
, 
Sangkaew, A.
, 
Pabuprapap, W.
, 
Yompakdee, C.
, 
Suksamrarn, A.
, 
2020
. 

Alkaloids with anti-human carbonic anhydrase isozyme II activity from the bulbs of 
Crinum asiaticum
L. var. 
asiaticum

. 
Phytochem. Lett.
37
, 
101–105
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytol.2020.03.006
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chaichompoo, W., Rojsitthisak, P., Pabuprapap, W., Siriwattanasathien, Y., 
Yotmanee, P.
, 
Haritakun, W.
, 
Suksamrarn, A.
, 
2021
. 
Stephapierrines A–H, new tetrahydroprotoberberine and aporphine alkaloids from the tubers of Stephania pierrei Diels and their anti-cholinesterase activities
. 
RSC Adv.
11
, 
21153–21169
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/D1RA03276C
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, C.K.
, 
Lin, F.H.
, 
Tseng, L.H.
, 
Jiang, C.L.
, 
Lee, S.S.
, 
2011
. 

Comprehensive study of alkaloids from 
Crinum asiaticum
var. 
sinicum
assisted by HPLC-DAD-SPE-NMR

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
74
, 
411–419
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np100819n
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Christenhusz, M.J.M.
, 
Byng, J.W.
, 
2016
. 
The number of known plants species in the world and its annual increase
. 
Phytotaxa
261
, 
201–217
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/ phytotaxa.261.3.1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cortes, N.
, 
Sierra, K.
, 
Alzate, F.
, 
Osorio, E.H.
, 
Osorio, E.
, 
2017
. 
Alkaloids of Amaryllidaceae as inhibitors of cholinesterases (AChEs and BChEs): an integrated bioguided study
. 
Phytochem. Anal.
29
, 
217–227
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ pca.2736
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DeAngelis, G.G.
, 
Wildman, W.C.
, 
1969
. 
Identification of amaryllidaceae alkaloids utilizing ORD and CD spectroscopy
. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
10
, 
729–732
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/S0040-4039(01)87794-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Diego, V.
, 
Santiago, P.
, 
Gisela, P.
, 
Marlene, G.
, 
Karen, A.
, 
Susana, A.
, 
2018
. 
In vitro anti-inflammatory and cytotoxicity of Crinum × amabile grown in Ecuador
. 
Asian J. Pharmaceut. Clin. Res.
11
, 
99–103
. 
https://doi.org/10.22159/ajpcr.2018. v11i10.26962
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elgorashi, E.E.
, 
2019
. 
Phytochemistry and pharmacology of the family Amaryllidaceae: an overview of research at RCPGD
. 
Nat. Prod. Commun.
14
, 
1–11
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1177/2F1934578X19872929
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elgorashi, E.E.
, 
Stafford, G.I.
, 
van Staden, J.
, 
2004
. 
Acetylcholinesterase enzyme inhibitory effects of Amaryllidaceae alkaloids
. 
Planta Med.
70
, 
260–262
. 
https://doi. org/10.1055/s-2004-818919
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ellman, G.L.
, 
Courtney, K.D.
, 
Andres Jr., V.
, 
Featherstone, R.M.
, 
1961
. 
A new and rapid colorimetric determination of acetylcholinesterase activity
. 
Biochem. Pharmacol.
7
, 
88–90
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0006-2952(61)90145-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Emir, A.
, 
Emir, C.
, 
Bozkurt, B.
, 
Onur, M.
, 
Bastida, J.
, 
Somer, N.U.
, 
2016
. 
Alkaloids from Galanthus fosteri
. 
Phytochem. Lett.
17
, 
167–172
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytol.2016.07.016
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Evidente, A.
, 
Iasiello, I.
, 
Randazzo, G.
, 
1984
. 

Isolation of sternbergine, a new alkaloid from bulbs of 
Sternbergia lutea

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
47
, 
1003–1008
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/np50036a017
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frahm, A.W.
, 
Ali, A.A.
, 
Kating, H.
, 
1981
. 
Relative configuration of the alkaloid augustine
. 
Phytochemistry
20
, 
1735–1738
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422 (00)98566-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frisch, M.J.
, 
Trucks, G.W.
, 
Schlegel, H.B.
, 
Scuseria, G.E.
, 
Robb, M.A.
, 
Cheeseman, J.R.
, 
Scalmani, G.
, 
Barone, V.
, 
Mennucci, B.
, 
Petersson, G.A.
, 
Nakatsuji, H.
, 
Caricato, M.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Hratchian, H.P.
, 
Izmaylov, A.F.
, 
Bloino, J.
, 
Zheng, G.
, 
Sonnenberg, J.L.
, 
Hada, M.
, 
Ehara, M.
, 
Toyota, K.
, 
Fukuda, R.
, 
Hasegawa, J.
, 
Ishida, M.
, 
Nakajima, T.
, 
Honda, Y.
, 
Kitao, O.
, 
Nakai, H.
, 
Vreven, T.
, 
Montgomery, J.A.J.
, 
Peralta, J.E.
, 
Ogliaro, F.
, 
Bearpark, M.
, 
Heyd, J.J.
, 
Brothers, E.
, 
Kudin, K.N.
, 
Staroverov, V.N.
, 
Keith, T.
, 
Kobayashi, R.
, 
Normand, J.
, 
Raghavachari, K.
, 
Rendell, A.
, 
Burant, J.C.
, 
Iyengar, S.S.
, 
Tomasi, J.
, 
Cossi, M.
, 
Rega, N.
, 
Millam, M.
, 
Klene, M.
, 
Knox, J.E.
, 
Cross, J.B.
, 
Bakken, V.
, 
Adamo, C.
, 
Jarammillo, J.
, 
Gomperts, R.
, 
Stratmann, R.E.
, 
Yazyev, O.
, 
Austin, A.J.
, 
Cammi, R.
, 
Pomelli, C.
, 
Ochterski, J.W.
, 
Martin, R.L.
, 
Morokuma, K.
, 
Zakrzewski, V.G.
, 
Voth, G.A.
, 
Salvador, P.
, 
Dennenberg, J.J.
, 
Dapprich, S.
, 
Daniels, A.D.
, 
Farkas, O.
, 
Foresman, J.B.
, 
Ortiz, J.V.
, 
Cioslowski, J.
, 
2010
. 
Gaussian 09
. 
Wallingford CT
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Highet, R.J.
, 
Ma, J.C.N.
, 
Highet, P.E.
, 
1968
. 
Dihydrotazettine methine, an unusual noncoplanar phenylcyclohexene
. 
J. Org. Chem.
33
, 
3096–3105
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/jo01272a017
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hohmann, J.
, 
Forgo, P.
, 
Molnar, J.
, 
Wolfard, K.
, 
Molnar, A.
, 
Thalhammer, T.
, 
Mathe, I.
, 
Sharples, D.
, 
2002
. 
Antiproliferative amaryllidaceae alkaloids isolated from the bulbs of Sprekelia formosissima and Hymenocallis × festalis
. 
Planta Med.
68
, 
454–457
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2002-32068
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ikeda, T.
, 
Taylor, W.I.
, 
Tsuda, Y.
, 
Uyeo, S.
, 
Yajima, H.
, 
1956
. 
The structure and stereochemistry of tazettine
. 
J. Chem. Soc.
4749–4761
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/ JR9560004749
, 1956.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jin, Z.
, 
Xu, X.-H.
, 
2013
. 
Amaryllidaceae alkaloids
. In: 
Ramawat, K.
, 
M´erillon, J.M
. (Eds.), 
Natural Products. Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg
, pp. 
479–522
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/978-3-642-22144-6_18
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Katoch, D.
, 
Kumar, D.
, 
Sharma, U.
, 
Kumar, N.
, 
Padwad, Y.S.
, 
Lal, B.
, 
Singh, B.
, 
2013
. 

Zephgrabetaine: a new betaine-type Amaryllidaceae alkaloid from 
Zephyranthes grandiflora

. 
Nat. Prod. Commun.
8
, 
161–164
. 
https://doi.org/10.1177/ 1934578x1300800206
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
King, R.W.
, 
Murphy, C.F.
, 
Wildman, W.C.
, 
1965
. 6- 
Hydroxycrinamine and haemanthidine
. 
J. Am. Chem. Soc.
87
, 
4912–4917
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ ja00949a039
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lamoral-Theys, D.
, 
Andolfi, A.
, 
Goietsenoven, G.V.
, 
Cimmino, A.
, 
Calve, B.L.
, 
Wauthoz, N.
, 
Megalizzi, V.
, 
Gras, T.
, 
Bruyere, C.
, 
Dubois, J.
, 
Mathieu, V.
, 
Kornienko, A.
, 
Kiss, R.
, 
Evidente, A.
, 
2009
. 
Lycorine, the main phenanthridine amaryllidaceae alkaloid, exhibits significant antitumor activity in cancer cells that display resistance to proapoptotic stimuli: an investigation of structure-activity relationship and mechanistic insight
. 
J. Med. Chem.
52
, 
6244–6256
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/jm901031h
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Larson, E.B.
, 
Kukull, W.A.
, 
Katzman, R.L.
, 
1992
. 
Cognitive impairment, dementia and Alzheimer’ s disease
. 
Annu. Rev. Publ. Health
13
, 
431–439
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1146/annurev.pu.13.050192.002243
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Likhitwitayawuid, K.
, 
Angerhofer, C.K.
, 
Chai, H.
, 
Pezzuto, J.M.P.
, 
Cordell, G.A.
, 
1993
. 

Cytotoxic and antimalarial alkaloids from the bulbs of 
Crinum amabile

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
56
, 
1331–1338
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np50098a017
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Loy, C.
, 
Schneider, L.
, 
2006
. 
Galantamine for Alzheimer’ s disease and mild cognitive impairment
. 
Cochrane Database Syst. Rev.
1
, 
1–48
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ 14651858.cd001747.pub3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Marucci, G.
, 
Buccioni, M.
, 
Ben, D.D.
, 
Lambertucci, C.
, 
Volpini, R.
, 
Amenta, F.
, 
2020
. 
Efficacy of acetylcholinesterase inhibitors in Alzheimer’ s disease
. 
Neuropharmacology
190
, 
108352
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. neuropharm.2020.108352
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morris, G.M.
, 
Goodsell, D.S.
, 
Halliday, R.S.
, 
Huey, R.
, 
Hart, W.E.
, 
Belew, R.K.
, 
Olson, A. J.
, 
1998
. 
Automated docking using a Lamarckian genetic algorithm and empirical binding free energy function
. 
J. Comput. Chem.
19
, 
1639–1662
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1002/(SICI)1096-987X(19981115)19:14%3C1639::AID-JCC10%3E3.0.CO;2-B
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morris, G.M.
, 
Huey, R.
, 
Lindstrom, W.
, 
Sanner, M.F.
, 
Belew, R.K.
, 
Goodsell, D.S.
, 
Olson, A.J.
, 
2009
. 
AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: automated docking with selective receptor flexibility
. 
J. Comput. Chem.
30
, 
2785–2791
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1002/jcc.21256
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nair, J.J.
, 
van Staden, J.
, 
2013
. 
Pharmacological and toxicological insights to the South African Amaryllidaceae
. 
Food Chem. Toxicol.
62
, 
262–275
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.fct.2013.08.042
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nair, J.J.
, 
Aremu, A.O.
, 
van Staden, J.
, 
2011
. 

Isolation of narciprimine from 
Cyrtanthus contractus
(Amaryllidaceae) and evaluation of its acetylcholinesterase inhibitory activity

. 
J. Ethnopharmacol.
137
, 
1102–1106
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. jep.2011.07.028
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pabuççuoglu, V.
, 
Richomme, P.
, G¨ozler, T., 
Kivçak, B.
, 
Freyer, A.J.
, 
Shamma, M.
, 
1989
. 

Four new crinine-type alkaloids from 
Sternbergia
species

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
52
, 
785–791
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np50064a020
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Panthong, K.
, 
Ingkaninan, K.
, 
2021
. 
Amabiloid A from Crinum × amabile Donn ex ker Gawl
. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
35
, 
3220–3225
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 14786419.2019.1693561
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pham, L.H.
, D¨opke, W., 
Wagner, J.
, 
Mügge, C.
, 
1998
. 

Alkaloids from 
Crinum amabile

. 
Phytochemistry
48
, 
371–376
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(97)01081-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pinho, B.R.
, 
Ferreres, F.
, 
Valent˜ao, P.
, 
Andrade, P.B.
, 
2013
. 
Nature as a source of metabolites with cholinesterase-inhibitory activity: an approach to Alzheimer’ s disease treatment
. 
J. Pharm. Pharmacol.
65
, 
1681–1700
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/ jphp.12081
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rønsted, N.
, 
Symonds, M.R.E.
, 
Birkholm, T.
, 
Christensen, S.B.
, 
Meerow, A.W.
, 
Molander, M.
, 
Mølgaard, P.
, 
Petersen, G.
, 
Rasmusse, N.
, 
2012
. 
Can phylogeny predict chemical diversity and potential medicinal activity of plants? A case study of amaryllidaceae
. 
BMC Evol. Biol.
12
, 
182
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-12- 182
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sanz, R.
, Fern´andez, Y., 
Castroviejo, M.P.
, P´erez, A., Fanan ˜´as, F.J., 
2007
. 
Functionalized phenanthridine and dibenzopyranone derivatives through benzyne cyclization–application to the total syntheses of trisphaeridine and Nmethylcrinasiadine
. 
Eur. J. Org. Chem
. 
62–69
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ ejoc.200600621
, 2007.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smitinand, T.
, 
2014
. 
Thai Plant Names
. 
Office of the Forest Herbarium, Department of National Parks, Wildlife and Plant Conservation, Bangkok
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

BIOVIA Dassault
Syst`emes

. In: 

BIOVIA Discovery Studio Visualizer Version
2019

, 
2019
. 
San, Diego
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tallini, L.R.
, 
Carrasco, A.
, Acosta Le´on, K., 
Vinueza, D.
, 
Bastida, J.
, 
Oleas, N.H.
, 
2021
. 
Alkaloid profiling and cholinesterase inhibitory potential of Crinum × amabile Donn. (Amaryllidaceae) collected in Ecuador
. 
Plants
10
, 
2686
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.3390/plants10122686
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tang, W.
, 
2017
. 
Method for efficiently synthesizing crinine and analogue thereof through intramolecular dearomatization
. 
Chinese Patent. CN
106565730
. April 19, 2017.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Torras-Claveria, L.
, 
Berkov, S.
, 
Codina, C.
, 
Viladomat, F.
, 
Bastida, J.
, 
2013
. 
Daffodils as potential crops of galanthamine: assessment of more than 100 ornamental varieties for their alkaloid content and acetylcholinesterase inhibitory activity
. 
Ind. Crop
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tram, N.T.N.
, 
Titorenkova, TzV
., 
Bankovab, V.St
, 
Handjievab, N.V.
, 
Popov, S.S.
, 
2002
. 

Crinum
L. (Amaryllidaceae)

. 
Fitoterapia
73
, 
183–208
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ S0367-326X(02)00068-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Viladomat, F.
, 
Bastida, L.
, 
Codina, C.
, 
Campbell, W.E.
, 
Mathee, S.
, 
1994
. 

Alkaloids from 
Brunsvigia josephinae

. 
Phytochemistry
35
, 
809–812
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031- 9422(00)90611-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Viladomat, F.
, 
Bastida, J.
, 
Codina, C.
, 
Compbell, W.E.
, 
Mathee, S.
, 
1995
. 

Alkaloids from 
Brunsvigia flava

. 
Phytochemistry
40
, 
307–311
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422 (95)00191-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Viladomat, F.
, 
Almanza, G.R.
, 
Codina, C.
, 
Bastida, J.
, 
Campbell, W.E.
, 
Mathee, S.
, 
1996
. 

Alkaloids from 
Brunsvigia orientalis

. 
Phytochemistry
43
, 
1379–1384
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/S0031-9422(96)00506-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wagner, J.
, 
Pham, H.L.
, 
Dopke, W.
, 
1996
. 
Alkaloids from Hippeastrum equestre Herb. –5. Circular dichroism studies
. 
Tetrahedron
52
, 
6591–6600
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ 0040-4020(96)00297-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhan, G.
, 
Liu, J.
, 
Zhou, J.
, 
Sun, B.
, 
Aisa, H.A.
, 
Yao, G.
, 
2017
. 

Amaryllidaceae alkaloids with new framework types from 
Zephyranthes candida
as potent acetylcholinesterase inhibitors

. 
Eur. J. Med. Chem.
127
, 
771–780
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j
. ejmech.2016.10.057.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zuo, X.-D.
, 
Guo, S.-M.
, 
Yang, R.
, 
Xie, J.-H.
, 
Zhou, Q.-L.
, 
2017
. 
Bioinspired enantioselective synthesis of crinine-type alkaloids via iridium-catalyzed asymmetric hydrogenation of enones
. 
Chem. Sci.
8
, 
6202–6206
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/ C7SC02112G
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
