<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113504</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Arundinosides I-IX and graminifolosides A-B: 2R-benzylmalate and 2R-isobutylmalates derivatives from Arundina graminifolia (D.Don) Hochr. with antioxidant, cytocompatibility and cytoprotective properties</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Arundina graminifolia (D.Don) Hochr.</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Arundina graminifolia D.Don Hochr</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Orchidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arundina graminifolia
D.Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Orchidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arundina graminifolia
D.Don Hochr. (Orchidaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. graminifolia
D.Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. graminifolia
D.Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. graminifolia
D.Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A
. 
graminifolia
D. Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arundina graminifolia
D.Don Hochr.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. graminifolia
D.Don Hochr. It
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arundina graminifolia
D.Don Hochr (Orchidaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Arundina graminifolia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Arundinosides I-IX and graminifolosides A-B: 2R-benzylmalate and 2R-isobutylmalates derivatives from 
<tp:taxon-name>Arundina graminifolia (D.Don) Hochr.</tp:taxon-name>
with antioxidant, cytocompatibility and cytoprotective properties

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Florence Auberon
a, *
, 
Opeyemi Joshua Olatunji
b, c
, 
Pierre Waffo-Teguo
d
, 
Oladipupo Odunayo Olatunde
e
, 
Sudarshan Singh
f
, Fr´ed´eric 
Bont´e g
, Jean-Michel M´erillon 
d
, 
Annelise Lobstein
a, 1
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a

Strasbourg University, Faculty of Pharmacy, UMR 7200, 67400, Illkirch-Graffenstaden, 
France
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b

African Genome Center, Mohammed VI Polytechnic University, Ben Guerir, 43150, 
Morocco
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c

Traditional Thai Medical Research and Innovation Center, Faculty of Traditional Thai Medicine, Prince of Songkla University, Hat Yai, 90110, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
d
Bordeaux University, Faculty of Pharmacy, ISVV, EA 4577, USC 1366 INRA, 33400, Villenave d
’ 

Ornon Cedex, 
France
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
e
Department of Food
and Human Nutritional Sciences, 
Faculty of Agricultural
and Food Sciences, University of 
Manitoba
, 
Winnipeg, MB
, R3T 2N2, 
Canada
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
f
Faculty of Pharmacy
, 
Chiang Mai
University, 
Chiang Mai
, 50200, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
g

LVMH Recherche, 45800, Saint Jean de Braye, 
France
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Arundina graminifolia D.Don Hochr</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Orchidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Glucosyloxybenzyl 2 
R
-benzylmalate derivatives
</p>
         <p>
Glucosyloxybenzyl 2 
R
-isobutylmalate derivatives
</p>
         <p>Arundinosides I-IX</p>
         <p>Graminifolosides A-B</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
Phytochemical investigation of the underground parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arundina graminifolia
D.Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
was conducted leading to the isolation of nine new glucosyloxybenzyl 2 
R
-benzylmalate and two new glucosyloxybenzyl 2 
R
- isobutylmalate derivatives. The compounds were purified using chromatographic techniques and their structures were deduced based on spectroscopic techniques including nuclear magnetic resonance and high-resolution mass spectrometry as well as comparing with previous literature. The antioxidant activities of the isolated compounds were also evaluated. The compounds showed potent antioxidant activities in the ABTS radical scavenging, DPPH radical scavenging and FRAP activities. Furthermore, the isolated compounds were observed to exert minimal cytotoxic effects against RAW 264.7 cell, suggesting biocompatibility as well as cytoprotective effects against hydrogen peroxide induced cell toxicity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Glucosyloxybenzyl 2 
R
-benzylmalate and glucosyloxybenzyl 2 
R
-isobutylmalate derivatives are structurally unique group of plant metabolites that occurs primarily in the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Orchidaceae</tp:taxon-name>
. There are very limited studies reporting this class of compounds due to their rare occurrence in nature. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arundina graminifolia
D.Don Hochr. (Orchidaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
popularly known as bamboo orchid is widely distributed in subtropical Asia, particularly in 
South East Asian
countries. It is a terrestrially growing orchid accepted as the only species in the genus (

; 

). In 
China
, the plant is found in 
Fujian
, 
Yunnan
, 
Zhejiang
, 
Jiangxi
, 
Guangdong
and 
Sichuan
provinces and it is popularly used as alone or in combination with other medicinal plants by the Bulang, Dai and Wa ethic groups. Traditionally, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. graminifolia
D.Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
is popular as an antidote for food and drug poisoning by the Dai ethnic group and it is one of the important ingredients found in several medicinal preparations because of the characteristic detoxification theory of the Dai ethnic group of “relieving before cure”. In addition, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. graminifolia
D.Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
is considered in Traditional Chinese Medicine as a drug that is effective for heat clearance, pain alleviation, eliminating wind and dampness (

). Furthermore, the roots/rhizomes and leaves of the plant are used for treating blood stasis and liver detoxification, pulmonary infection, beriberi edema, rheumatism, snakebites, traumatic injuries and as a skin moisturizer (

; 

; 

, 

). This plant is known to be a rich source of bibenzyls (

; 

; 

), phenanthrenes (

,b; 

,b), phenolic (

; 

; 

; Shu
</p>
         <p>
et al., 2013) and glucosyloxybenzyl 2 
R
-benzylmalate derivatives (

, 

, 

; 

,b) with several pharmacological activities including antibacterial, antiviral, cytotoxic and anti-liver fibrotic effects. As a furtherance to the studies on the bioactive constituents from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. graminifolia
D.Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
, nine new glucosyloxybenzyl 2R-benzylmalate, arundinosides I-IX (1–9) and two new glucosyloxybenzyl 2 
R
-isobutylmalates, graminifolosides A-B (10–11) were isolated and identified from the underground part of the plant.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Table 1
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>1H (500 MHz, methanol-d4) and 13C (125 MHz, methanol-d4) NMR data of arundinosides I-III</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
Arundinoside I (1) was obtained as a white amorphous powder with the molecular formula of C 
38
H 
46
O 
20
, which was determined from the HRESIMS at 
m/z
840.2915 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
. The 
13
C NMR data showed resonances corresponding to 34 carbons; including four methyls, five methylenes, nine sp 
2
methines, ten sp 
3
methines and six carbonyl carbons. Comparison of the NMR spectroscopic data (
Table 1
) of 1 with those of arundinoside T, a previously isolated compound from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A
. 
graminifolia
D. Don Hochr
</tp:taxon-name>
indicated that compound 1 shared similar structural features with it (benzylmalic acid and glucosyloxybenzyl moieties) (

). Compound 1 differs from arundioside T based on the acetyl substituent attached to C-6 
′′′
’. The benzylmalic-glucosyloxybenzyl skeleton is composed of a benzylmalic unit [
δH
/ 
δC
3.11, 2.96 (d, 
J
= 17.8 Hz, H-3)/44.3; 3.01, 2.94 (d, 
J
= 13.5 Hz, H-5)/47.3; 7.02 (m, H-7/11)/132.0; 7.15 (m, H-8/10)/129.1; 
δC
172.7 (C-1), 82.5 (C-2), 174.0 (C-4) and 136.5 (C-6)] and a glucosyloxybenzyl unit [
δH
/ 
δC
7.28 (d, 
J
= 8.7 Hz, H-2’/6 
′
)/131.7; 7.07 (d, 
J
= 8.7 Hz, H-3’/5 
′
)/117.9; 5.11, 4.95 (d, 
J
= 12.0 Hz, H-7 
′
)/67.9; 4.93 (d, 
J
= 7.4 Hz, 4 
′
- 
O
-glc-1 
′′′
’)/102.3; 3.47 (m, 4 
′
- 
O
-glc-2 
′′′
’)/75.0; 3.47 (dd, 
J
= 9.3, 9.3 Hz, 4 
′
- 
O
-glc-3 
′′′
’)/77.9; 3.39 (dd, 
J
= 9.3, 9.3 Hz, 4 
′
- 
O
-glc-4 
′′′
’)/71.6; 3.66 (ddd, 
J
= 9.3, 6.1, 2.2 Hz, 4 
′
- 
O
-glc-5 
′′′
’)/75.4; 4.24 (dd, 
J
= 11.9, 6.1 Hz, 4 
′
- 
O
-glc-6a’’’’) and 4.41 (dd, 
J
= 11.9, 2.2 Hz, 4 
′
- 
O
-glc-6b’’’’)/64.8; 2.07 (s, 6 
′′′
’-Ac-2)/20.9; 
δC
131.0 (C-1 
′
), 159.2 (C-4 
′
) and 172.9 (C-6 
′′′
’-Ac-1)]. The resonance of an additional acetyl group at C-6 
′′′
[
δH
/ 
δC
2.05 (s, 6 
′′′
-Ac-2/20.9; 
δC
172.8 (C-6 
′′′
-Ac-1)] on the glucose unit connected to C-2 of the benzylmalic unit which replaces the hydroxyl group in arundioside T was confirmed by HMBC correlations of H-6 
′′′
with C-6 
′′′
-Ac-1 and H-6 
′′′
-Ac-2 with C-6 
′′′
-Ac-1. The absolute configuration of 1 was determined by alkaline hydrolysis that yielded a 2R-benzymalic acid, which was identified by
</p>
         <p>
25
comparison of its NMR spectroscopic data and optical rotation value [
α
] 

D

75 (
c
0.2, 
CH
3
OH) and it was deduced as 2 
R
according to the configuration of previously reported arundinoside derivatives (

, 

; 

,b; 

; 

). As such, the structure of arundinoside I was established as 1-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl-6-acetyl)-2-(ss- D-glucopyranosyl-2,3,6-triacetyl)- 2 
R
-benzylmalic acid.
</p>
         <p>
Arundinoside II (2) was also obtained as a white amorphous solid with a molecular formula of C 
41
H 
46
O 
18
according to its HR-ESI-MS data [M-H] 
-
ion at 
m/z
825.2546. Analysis of the NMR data (
Table 1
) suggested that compound 2 was similar to compound 1, suggesting that both compounds have structural similarities (benzylmalic and glucosyloxybenzyl moieties), except for the absence of the acetyl groups at C- 3 
′′′
, C-6?and C-6 
′′′
’. In addition, the presence of a 
trans
-cinnamoyl moiety at 
δH
/ 
δC
7.64 (dd, 
J
= 7.7, 2.1 Hz, H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-2/6)/129.4; 7.42 (m, H- 3 
′′′
’-Cin-3/5)/130.2; 7.42 (m, H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-4)/131.6; 7.77 (d, 
J
= 16.0 Hz, H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-7)/146.5; 6.64 (d, 
J
= 16.0 Hz, H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-8)/119.3; 
δC
136.0 (C– H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-1) and 168.5 (C– H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-9) in 2 replaced the hydroxyl group at C-3 
′′′
’ in 1. The position of the 
trans
-cinnamoyl moiety was confirmed by HMBC correlations of H-3 
′′′
’ and H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-7 with C-3 
′′′
’- Cin-9, H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-8 with C– H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-1 and H-3 
′′′
’-Cin-7 with C-3 
′′′
’- Cin-2/6. The absolute configuration of 2 was determined using the same method as that of 1. Thus, arundinoside II was elucidated as 1-(ss- Dglucopyranosyloxybenzyl-3-trans-cinnamoyl)-2-(ss- D-glucopyranosyl-2- acetyl)-2R-benzylmalic acid.
</p>
         <p>
Arundinoside III (3) yielded a molecular formula of C 
62
H 
72
O 
30
, as confirmed by the HR-ESI-MS at 
m/z
1314.4461 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
. A comparison of the NMR data of 3 (
Table 1
) with arundinoside C (

) revealed a striking structural resemblance, except the addition of an acetyl group [(
δH
/ 
δC
2.04 (s, H-6 
′′′
’-Ac-2)/21.0; 
δC
172.8 (C-6 
′ ′ ′ ′
-Ac-1) esterified on C-6 
′′′
’. The absolute configuration of 3 was determined using the same method as that of 1. The absolute configuration was deduced based on the exhibited negative optical rotation ([
α
] 

D
25
</p>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
         <p>
Table 1
(
continued
)
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
56 (
c
0.4, 
CH
3
OH)), which is consistent with a 
R
absolute configuration and based on the biogenetic relationship as previously reported in the literature (

, 

; 

). Therefore, arundinoside III was structurally deduced as shown and named as 1-(
ss
-D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl-6-acetyl)-2-(
ss
-D-glucopyranosyl-2,3,4 -triacetyl-6-
&gt;
1–2 
R
-benzylmalyl)-4-(
ss
-D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl)-2 
R
- benzylmalic acid.
</p>
         <p>
Arundinoside IV (4) was purified as a white amorphous powder with a molecular formula of C 
56
H 
64
O 
25
as established by the HR-ESI-MS [M- H] 
-
ion peak at 
m/z
1135.3583 (calcd. for C 
56
H 
63
O 
25
for 1135.3663). Analysis of the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectral data (
Table 2
) of 4 suggested that the planar structure compound 4 was similar to arundinoside Z (

); one benzylmalic acid, two hydroxybenzoyl, three sugars, one acetyl group on C-2 
′′′
, one cinnamoyl group on c-3 
′′′
’, except for the presence of an acetyl group at C-6 
′′′
’ in 4 [
δH
/ 
δC
1.69 (s, H-2 
′′′
-Ac-2)/21.4; 
δC
172.7 (C-2 
′′′
-Ac-1). This was confirmed by the HMBC correlations between H-6 
′′′
’ and C-2 
′′′
-Ac-1 and H-2 
′′′
-Ac-2 to C-2 
′′′
-Ac-1. The absolute configuration of 4 was determined using the same method as that of 1. Thus, 4 was deduced as 1-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl-3- 
trans
-cinnamoyl-6-acetyl)-2-(ss- D-glucopyranosyl-2- acetyl)-4-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl)-2 
R
-benzylmalic acid (see 
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
         <p>
Table 2
(
continued
)
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Arundinoside V (5) was isolated as a white amorphous powder. The [M –H] 
-
ion peak appeared at 
m/z
1135.358 (calcd. for C 
56
H 
63
O 
25
for 1135.3663) in the HRESIMS spectrum indicated the same molecular formula of C 
56
H 
64
O 
25
as compound 4. Apart from the absence of the acetyl group at C-6 
′′′
’, the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data (
Table 2
) of 5 was quite similar with those of 4. The acetyl group was however positioned at C-6 
′′′
. The HMBC correlations of H-6 
′′′
with C-6 
′′′
-Ac-1 and H-6 
′′′
-Ac-2 with C-6 
′′′
-Ac-1 proved the position of acetyl group at C-6 
′′′
’ (see 
Fig. 2
). The absolute configuration of the benzylmalic acid (2R) was determined by using the same method employed for the previous compounds described above. Compound 5 was thus elucidated as 1-(ss- Dglucopyranosyloxybenzyl-3- 
trans
-cinnamoyl)-2-(ss- D-glucopyranosyl-2, 6-diacetyl)-4-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl)-2 
R
-benzylmalic acid.
</p>
         <p>
Arundinoside VI (6) was isolated as a white amorphous solid with the same molecular formula (C 
56
H 
64
O 
25
) as compounds 4 and 5. The NMR spectroscopic data (
Table 2
) of 6 showed strong resemblance to those of 5, suggesting that 6 is also a 2 
R
-benzylmalate derivative. The only difference between these two compounds was the absence of the acetyl group attached to C-6 
′′′
in 6 which was now positioned at C-3 
′′′
. This was confirmed by HMBC correlations of H-4 
′′′
and H-3 
′′′
-Ac-2 with C-3 
′′′
-Ac- 1. The 2 
R
configuration was assigned to 6 based on the negative optical rotation as previously described for other 2R-benzylmalate derivative. Arundinoside VI was proposed structurally as shown and elucidated as 1-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl-3- 
trans
-cinnamoyl)-2-(ss- D-glucopyranosyl-2,3-diacetyl)-4-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl)-2 
R
-benzylmalic acid (see 
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
Arundinoside VII (7) had a molecular formula of C 
56
H 
63
O 
25
deduced from its HR-ESI-MS data at 
m/z
1135.3542 [M-H] 
-
(calcd. for C 
56
H 
63
O 
25
for 1135.3663). The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectral (
Table 3
) of 7 revealed an overall structural resemblance to 4, except for the difference in the position of the 
trans
-cinnamoyl moiety at C-4 
′′′
’ in 7 due to the HMBC correlations of H-4 
′′′
’ with C-4 
′′′
’- 
Cin
-9. Accordingly, the structure of 7 was assigned as shown and elucidated as 1-(
ss
-D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl-4- 
trans
-cinnamoyl-6-acetyl)-2-(
ss
-D-glucopyranosyl-2-acetyl)-4- (
ss
-D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl)-2 
R
-benzylmalic acid (see 
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
Arundinoside VIII (8) showed similar 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra data (
Table 3
) with those of 7, except for the presence of an additional acetyl group. The HRESIMS data of 8 (
m/z
1177.3715 [M-H] 
-
; calcd. for C 
58
H 
65
O 
26
for 1177.3710) was consistent with the molecular formula of C 
58
H 
66
O 
26
and the difference in the 
m/z
values of 43 amu compared to 7. The additional acetyl group signal [
δH
/ 
δC
1.97 (s, H-6 
′′′
-Ac-2)/20.9; 
δC
172.9 (C-6 
′′′
-Ac-1)] in the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR resonances as well as HMBC cross peaks of H-6 
′′′
with C-6 
′′′
-Ac-2 confirmed that an acetyl group is substituted at C-6 
′′′
(see 
Fig. 3
).. Compound 8 was therefore elucidated as 1-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl-3- 
trans
-cinnamoyl-6-acetyl)-2-(ss- Dglucopyranosyl-2,6-diacetyl)-4-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl)-2 
R
-benzylmalic acid.
</p>
         <p>
Arundinoside IX (9) was assigned a molecular formula of C 
63
H 
68
O 
25
according to the HR-ESI-MS peak at 
m/z
1242.4394 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
(calcd.for C 
63
H 
72
NO 
25
for 1242.4387). The NMR data of 9 showed characteristic features of one benzylmalic acid, two glucosyloxybenzyl, three ss- Dglucose, one acetyl and two 
trans
-cinnamoyl acid moieties. Analysis of the NMR data of 9 (
Table 3
) showed an overall structural resemblance to arundinoside A (

),except for the presence of a hydroxyl which replaced the acetyl group at C-2?in arundinoside A. On the basis of these findings, the structure of compound 9 was identified as 1-(
ss
- 
D-
glucopyranosyloxybenzyl-3,4-di- 
trans
-cinnamoyl-6-acetyl)-2-(
ss
-D-glucopyranosyl)-4-(
ss
-D-glucopyranosyl-oxybenzyl)-2 
R
-benzylmalate (see 
Fig. 4
)..
</p>
         <p>
Graminifoloside A (10) was purified as a white amorphous powder, with a molecular formula of C 
53
H 
66
O 
25
based on the HR-ESI-MS: 
m/z
1101.3755 [M-H] 
-
(calcd. for C 
53
H 
65
O 
25
for 1101.3820). Comparison of the NMR data of 10 (
Table 4
) with 7 showed similar signals, suggesting a close similarity in their structures. However, the major difference resides on the acid moiety which is an isobutylmalic acid in 10. In the 
1
H NMR spectra, one methine and two methyl protons were observed at 
δH
1.77 (m, H-6), 0.76 (d, 
J
= 6.6 Hz, H-7) and 0.83 (d, 
J
= 6.6 Hz, H-8) which corresponds to the isobutylmalic acid group. This was further verified by HMBC correlations of H-7 and H-8 with C-5 and C-6 (see 
Fig. 4
).. In addition, the absence of the benzylmalic signals in the 1H NMR spectra also validated this analogy. Moreover, the isobutylmalic acid moiety was established as a 2 
R
configuration based on the negative optical rotation which has been reported for previous derivatives (

; 

,b; 

; 

; 

). Thus, the structure of graminifoloside A was elucidated as 1-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl-4- 
trans
-cinnamoyl-6-acetyl)-2-(ss- D-glucopyranosyl-2-ac etyl)-4-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl)-2 
R
-isobutylmalic acid and structurally determined as shown.
</p>
         <p>
Based on the HR-ESI-MS data 
m/z
1208. 1208.4513 [M + NH 
4
] 
+
, the molecular formula of graminifoloside B (11) was deduced as C 
60
H 
70
O 
25
. The spectroscopic data of compound 11 were very similar to those of 10. A detailed analysis of the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data revealed the presence of two glucosyloxybenzyl, three sugars and one isobutylmalic acid moieties analogous to those in compound 10. The most noticeable difference in these data were the presence of additional signals assigned to a 
trans
- cinnamoyl moiety at C-3 
′′′
’ in 11 (
Table 4
). These difference were confirmed by 
1
H NMR signals at 
δH
7.54 (m, 3 
′ ′ ′ ′
-cin-2/6), 7.38 (m, 3 
′ ′ ′ ′
- cin-3/5), 7.68 (d, 
J
= 15.9 Hz, 3 
′ ′ ′ ′
-cin-4) and 6.52 (d, 
J
= 15.9 Hz, 3 
′ ′ ′ ′
- cin-8) and in the 
13
C NMR 
δC
135.6 (3 
′ ′ ′ ′
-cin-1), 129.5 (3 
′ ′ ′ ′
-cin-2/6), 130.2 (3 
′ ′ ′ ′
-cin-3/5), 131.8 (3 
′ ′ ′ ′
-cin-4), 147.3 (3 
′ ′ ′ ′
-cin-7), 118.3 (3 
′ ′ ′ ′
- cin-8) and 168.0 (3 
′ ′ ′ ′
-cin-9). These analogies were confirmed by HMBC correlations from the H-3 
′′′
’ with 3 
′ ′ ′ ′
-cin-9. Thus, graminifoloside B was defined as 1-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl-3,4-di- 
trans
-cinnamoyl-6- acetyl)-2-(ss- D-glucopyranosyl-2-acetyl)-4-(ss- D-glucopyranosyloxybenzyl)-2 
R
-isobutylmalic acid.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Antioxidant activity
</title>
         <p>
The isolated compounds were tested for their antioxidant activity against ABTS radical, DPPH radical scavenging and FRAP (
Table 5
). Antioxidant activity ranging from 543.71 to 1311.09 mmol Trolox equivalent/g sample for ABST radical, 370.67–545.03 mmol Trolox equivalent/g sample for DPPH and 103.14–1098.77 mmol Trolox equivalent/g sample for FRAP were observed for the isolated compounds (compounds 3–8).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Cytocompatibility activity
</title>
         <p>
The isolated compounds were also investigated for their cytotoxicity against macrophage (RAW 264.7) cells at a range of 3.9–500 μg/mL. The results of cytotoxicity indicated that the compounds demonstrated a dose dependent toxicity against RAW 264.7 cell. Moreover, the isolated constituents at tested concentration of ~125 μg/mL showed
&gt;
70% of cell viability. The results suggested that phyto-constituents are more biocompatible.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Cytoprotective effects
</title>
         <p>
Oxidative stress caused by the excessive production of reactive oxygen species, results in cellular damage that leads to several diseases including aging, diabetes, and cardiovascular diseases. Cellular viability was investigated after exposure to varying concentration of H 
2
O 
2
(1–8 mM). The results revealed a concentration dependent cell viability (
Fig. 5
). Hydrogen peroxide has been reported to mediate cell necrosis and death in both bacterial and cell-lines through the induction of intracellular free radical generation. Exposure of RAW 264.7 cells to 3 mM of H 
2
O 
2
resulted in a ~60% reduction of cell viability. However, pretreatment of RAW 264.7 cells with the isolated compounds (compounds 3, 5, 6 and 8) at concentrations of 
7.81–125 mg
/mL resulted in cytoprotective effect against H 
2
O 
2
induced cell mortality. The compounds treated cells demonstrated 39–77% increase in cell viability in presence of 3.0 mM of H 
2
O 
2
(
Fig. 6
). This results collaborate with antioxidant efficacy of the compounds with effective attenuations of H 
2
O 
2
induced oxidative stress medicated cell death.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
3. Conclusions
</p>
         <p>
In conclusion, eleven new compounds, including nine 2 
R
-benzylmalate derivatives designated as arundinosides I-IX (1–9) and two new 2 
R
-isobutylmalates derivatives designated as graminifolosides A-B (10–11) were purified from the undergrounds parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arundina graminifolia
D.Don Hochr.
</tp:taxon-name>
This is the first report on the isobutylmalic acid derivatives in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. graminifolia
D.Don Hochr. It
</tp:taxon-name>
is quite interesting to note that some orchids are able to produce this 
type
of glucosides based on different acids (benzylmalyl and isobutyl and tartaric acid) as the pivot (

; 

; 

; 

,b; 

; 

). The isolated compounds were tested for their antioxidant activity using DDPH, ABTS and FRAP assays. Compounds 3–8 showed antioxidant activity against DPPH (370.6–545 mmol Trolox equivalent/g sample), ABTS (543.7–1311.0 mmol Trolox equivalent/g sample) and FRAP (103.1–1098.7 mmol Trolox equivalent/g sample). Additionally, the compounds (3, 5, 6 and 8) showed cytocompatibility and cytoprotective effects in RAW macrophage cells.
</p>
         <p>
4. Experimental
</p>
         <p>
4.1. General methods
</p>
         <p>All information regarding the general experimental procedures including the instruments and procedures were included in the supplementary information.</p>
         <p>
4.2. Plant material
</p>
         <p>

The dried roots and rhizomes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arundina graminifolia
D.Don Hochr (Orchidaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected in 

September 2010

at 
Joe Orchid Farm
(
Chiang Mai
, 
Thailand
, GPS 18.919048339241826, 98.93458399321969) and the voucher samples (n 
◦
05–563) of the plant were authenticated and deposited at the herbarium of the 
Faculty of Science
, Chiang Mai 
University
, Thailand. 
The
importation of the plant materials to France followed the guidelines of the 

Convention on 
International Trade

in Endangered Species

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The comprehensive details on the extraction protocol were reported in previous report (

, 

, 

). Centrifugal partition chromatography (CPC) of the EtOAc soluble fraction (
10.93 g
) afforded 14 fractions. The fractions 9–13 (
3.57 g
) were further separated using Sephadex LH-20 column eluted with MeOH. Sub-fractions 9b (
72.4 mg
) and 9d (
63.5 mg
) were purified on a semi-preparative RP-HPLC using a gradient elution (H 
2
O (A) and MeCN (B) both containing 0.05% formic acid; 45% B for 5 min, 45–50% B for 35 min, 50–100% B for 5 min, 100% B for 5 min at a flow rate of 14 mL/min) to yield 7 (
5.8 mg
) and 10 (
3.8 mg
).
</p>
         <p>
Similarly sub-fraction 10b (
206 mg
) was further purified using semi-preparative RP HPLC (using a gradient elution of 45% B for 5 min, 45–55% B for 40 min, 55–100% B for 5 min and 100% B for 5 min at a flow rate 14 mL/min) to give 1 (2.0 mg) and 3 (
4.7 mg
). 2 (
2.1 mg
), 4 (
9.2 mg
) and 5 (
3.1 mg
) were acquired from sub-fractions 11c-11d by semi-preparative RP-HPLC using the same gradient elution described above.
</p>
         <p>
Sub-fractions 12c (
504.3 mg
) and 12d (
602.8 mg
) were also purified on semi-preparative HPLC to afford 6 (
16.6 mg
), 8 (
20.2 mg
), 9 (
3.7 mg
) and 11 (
2.2 mg
), whereas, sub-fraction 13c (
90.4 mg
) was further purified by semi-preparative HPLC using a gradient elution of 50% B for 5 min, 50–60% B for 30 min, 60–100% B for 5 min and 100% B for 5 min at a flow rate of 14 mL/min to give 12 (
6.1 mg
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Arundinoside I (1)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder (2.0 mg); [
α
] 

D
25
75 (c 0.2, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 218 (3.05), 270 (1.84); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 1
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 840.2915 [M + NH4]+ (calcd. for C38H50NO20 for 840.2920).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Arundinoside II (2)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder (
2.1 mg
); [
α
] 

D
25
67 (c 0.2, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 218 (3.12), 280 (3.01); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 1
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 825.2546 [M-H]- (calcd. for C41H45O18 for 825.2611).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. Arundinoside III (3)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder (
4.7 mg
); [
α
] 

D
25
39 (c 0.2, 
CH
3OH); UV
</p>
         <p>
(
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 219 (3.11), 277 (1.91); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 1
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 1314.4461 [M + NH4]+ (calcd. for C62H76NO30 for 1314. 4446).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.4. Arundinoside IV (4)
</p>
         <p>
25
White amorphous powder (
9.2 mg
); [
α
] 

D

48 (c 0.2, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 218 (3.15), 269 (2.14), 280 (2.00); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 2
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 1135.3583 [M-H]- (calcd. for C56H63O25 for 1135.3663).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.5. Arundinoside V (5)
</p>
         <p>
White amorphous powder (
3.1 mg
); [
α
] 

D
25
19 (c 0.1, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 218 (3.06), 269 (2.12), 278 (1.92); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 2
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 1135.3589 [M-H]- (calcd. for C56H63O25 for 1135.3663).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.6. Arundinoside VI (6)
</p>
         <p>
25
White amorphous powder (
16.6 mg
); [
α
] 

D

18 (c 0.1, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 219 (3.03), 370 (2.15), 279 (1.81); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 2
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 1135.3586 [M-H]- (calcd. for C56H63O25 for 1135.3663).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.7. Arundinoside VII (7)
</p>
         <p>
White amorphous powder (
20.2 mg
); [
α
] 

D
25
55 (c 0.2, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 217 (3.01), 269 (2.12), 278 (1.85); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 3
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 1135.3542 [M-H]- (calcd. for C56H63O25 for 1135.3663).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.8. Arundinoside VII (8)
</p>
         <p>
White amorphous powder (
5.8 mg
); [
α
] 

D
25
80 (c 0.1, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 222 (3.05), 270 (2.10), 277 (1.94); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 3
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 1177.3715 [M-H]- (calcd. for C58H65O26 for 1177.3710).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.9. Arundinoside IX (9)
</p>
         <p>
25
White amorphous powder (
3.7 mg
); [
α
] 

D

63 (c 0.4, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 221 (3.11), 271 (2.12), 279 (1.96); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 3
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 1242.4394 [M + NH4]+ (calcd. for C63H72NO25 for 1242.4387).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.10. Graminifoloside A (10)
</p>
         <p>
White amorphous powder (
3.8 mg
); [
α
] 

D
25
34 (c 0.2, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 219 (3.07), 270 (2.12), 278 (1.96); 1H NMR and
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>Values represent mean ± standard deviation (n = 3). Different superscripts in</p>
         <p>
the same column indicate significant differences (p 
˂
0.05).
</p>
         <p>
13C NMR see 
Table 4
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 1101.3755 [M-H]- (calcd. for C53H65O25 for 1101.3820).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.11. Graminifolosides B (11)
</p>
         <p>
25
White amorphous powder (
2.2 mg
); [
α
] 

D

67 (c 0.4, 
CH
3OH); UV (
CH
3OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 218 (3.08), 270 (2.13), 278 (1.93); 1H NMR and 13C NMR see 
Table 4
; HR-ESI-MS: m/z 1208.4513 [M + NH4]+ (calcd. for C60H74NO25 for 1208.4544).
</p>
         <p>
4.4. Determination of the absolute configuration of the sugar moiety
</p>
         <p>

was used for the determination of the absolute configuration of the sugar moiety. Briefly, 
1 mg
of the compound was solubilized 0.5 mL of 2 M HCl and subjected to reflux for 3 h. Thereafter, the solution was allowed to cool down and partitioned with n-butanol. The aqueous phase obtained after partitioning was concentrated under reduced pressure and derivatized with pyridine and 1-(trimethylsilyl) imidazole (4:1 v/v) for 60 min a temperature of 60 
◦
C. The derivatized sample was identified using a GC-MS Trace GC Ultra instrument with the following conditions: column; TR-5MS SQC (0.25 μm, 
15 m
× 
0.25 mm
); Detection was achieved on a DSQII Thermo Scientific mass spectrometer (mass range of m/z 0 to 500). D-glucose was identified by comparing the retention time of the derivatized sample with the standard glucose.
</p>
         <p>
4.5. Antioxidant activity
</p>
         <p>
The antioxidant activities including ABTS and DPPH scavenging activities as well as ferric reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) of the isolated compounds were determined as we previously reported (

; 

). The results were expressed as mmol Trolox equivalent (TE)/g sample.
</p>
         <p>
4.6. Biocompatibility studies on macrophage RAW264.7 cells
</p>
         <p>
The biocompatibility of the isolated compounds were assessed on macrophage RAW 264.7 cells. Briefly, cells procured from the Institute of Research and Innovation, Walailak University, 
Nakhon Si Thammarat
, were cultured in high glucose RPMI-1640 supplemented with 10% of fetal bovine serum and 100 μg/mL of streptomycin and 100 U/ml penicillin solution. Approximately 4 × 105 cells were seeded in 96-well plate and incubated at 37 
◦
C with 5% CO2. After 24 h of incubation, the culture medium was replaced with fresh RPMI-1640 as negative control in triplicate, whereas DMSO was tested for solvent effect. Moreover, cells were treated with 200 μL of varying concentrations of the isolated compounds (3.9–500 μg/mL) and incubated for 24 h. The viability of cells after treatment was analyzed using MTT assay and the optical density measured at 
570 nm
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Cytoprotective effects against H2O2 medicated cytotoxicity
</title>
         <p>
The confluent monolayer of RAW 264.7 cells (4 × 105) were incubated with different concentrations of the isolated compounds (
7.81–125 mg
/mL) for 1 h. Further, the cells were treated with H2O2 (3.0 mM) and maintained at 37 
◦
C with 5% CO2 for 12 h. Cells were then washed and inhibitory effects of the compounds on H2O2 induced cytotoxicity was
</p>
         <p>
evaluated by measuring cell mortality using MTT assay at 
570 nm
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Data availability
</p>
         <p>Data will be made available on request.</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgement
</p>
         <p>
The authors are grateful to the French Ministry of Research and Education for the PhD scholarship offered to F. Auberon. The authors are also grateful to Guerlain and LVMH Recherche for the financial support and the botanic material supply. We also would like to thank Mr. 
Maurice
Coppe´for his assistance in the NMR facility.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix B. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113504.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Auberon, F.
, 
Olatunji, O.J.
, 
Krisa, S.
, 
Herbette, G.
, 
Antheaume, C.
, 
Bonte, F.
, 
Merillon, J. M.
, 
Lobstein, A.
, 
2018
. 
Arundinosides A-G, new glucosyloxybenzyl 2R-benzylmalate derivatives from the aerial parts of Arundina graminifolia
. 
Fitoterapia
125
, 
199–207
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2017.11.019
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Auberon, F.
, 
Olatunji, O.J.
, 
Waffo-Teguo, P.
, 
Adekoya, A.E.
, Bont´e, F., M´erillon, J.M., 
Lobstein, A.
, 
2019
. 
New glucosyloxybenzyl 2R-benzylmalate derivatives from the undergrounds parts of Arundina graminifolia (Orchidaceae)
. 
Fitoterapia
135
, 
33–43
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2019.03.030
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Auberon, F.
, 
Olatunji, O.J.
, 
Waffo-Teguo, P.
, 
Makinde, E.A.
, 
Nwabor, O.F.
, Bont´e, F., M´erillon, J.M., 
Lobstein, A.
, 
2020
. 
Further 2R-Benzylmalate derivatives from the undergrounds parts of Arundina graminifolia (Orchidaceae)
. 
Phytochem. Lett.
35
, 
156–163
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2019.03.030
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Benjakul, S.
, 
Kittiphattanabawon, P.
, 
Sumpavapol, P.
, 
Maqsood, S.
, 
2014
. 
Antioxidant activities of lead (Leucaena leucocephala) seed as affected by extraction solvent, prior dechlorophyllisation and drying methods. J
. 
Food Sci. Technol.
51
, 
3026–3037
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s13197-012-0846-1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cota, B.B.
, 
Magalh˜aes, A.
, 
Pimenta, A.
, 
Siqueira, E.P.
, 
Alves, T.
, 
Zani, C.L.
, 
2008
. 
Chemical constituents of Habenaria petalodes lindl.(orchidaceae)
. 
J. Braz. Chem. Soc.
19
, 
1098–1104
. 
https://doi.org/10.1590/S0103-50532008000600007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Du, G.
, 
Shen, Y.
, 
Yang, L.
, 
Shu, L.
, 
Wen, M.L.
, 
Hu, Q.F.
, 
2014
. 
Bibenzyl derivatives of Arundina graminifolia and their cytotoxicity
. 
Chem. Nat. Compd.
49
, 
1019–1022
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10600-014-0813-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
El Bialy, S.A.A.
, 
Braun, H.
, 
Tietze, L.F.
, 
2005
. 
Enantioselective synthesis of α- alkylmalates as the pharmacophoric group of several natural alkaloids and glycosides
. 
Eur. J. Org. Chem.
14
, 
2965–2972
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gao, X.
, 
Yang, L.
, 
Shen, Y.
, 
Shu, L.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Hu, Q.F.
, 
2012
. 
Phenolic compounds from Arundina graminifolia and their anti-tobacco mosaic virus activity
. 
Bull. Kor. Chem. Soc.
33
, 
2447–2449
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ejoc.200500065
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hong, D.Y.
, 
Lian, Y.S.
, 
Shen, L.D.
, 
1983
. 
Flora of China
. 
Chinese Science Press, Beijing, China
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hossain, M.M.
, 
2009
. 
Traditional therapeutic uses of some indigenous orchids of Bangladesh. Med. Aromat. Plant Sci
. 
Biotechnol.
42
, 
101–106
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hossain, M.M.
, 
2011
. 
Therapeutic orchids: traditional uses and recent advances–an overview
. 
Fitoterapia
82
, 
102–140
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2010.09.007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hu, Q.F.
, 
Zhou, B.
, 
Huang, J.M.
, 
Gao, X.M.
, 
Shu, L.D.
, 
Yang, G.Y.
, 
Che, C.T.
, 
2013
. 
Antiviral phenolic compounds from Arundina gramnifolia
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
76
, 
292–296
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np300727f
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, S.
, 
Shi, J.
, 
Yang, Y.
, 
Hu, S.
, 
2002
. 
Studies on the chemical constituents of Coeloglossum viride Hartm. var. bracteatum (Willd.) Richter
. 
Yaoxue Xuebao
37
, 
199–203
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, S.Y.
, 
Li, G.Q.
, 
Shi, J.G.
, 
Mo, S.Y.
, 
Wang, S.J.
, 
Yang, Y.C.
, 
2004
. 
Chemical constituents of the rhizomes of Coeloglossum viride var. bracteatum. J
. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
6
, 
49–61
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/1028602031000119826
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Karnjanapratum, S.
, 
Benjakul, S.
, 
2015
. 
Characteristics and antioxidative activity of gelatin hydrolysates from unicorn leatherjacket skin as affected by autolysis. assisted process. J
. 
Food Process Preserv
39
, 
915–926
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jfpp.12304
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kizu, H.
, 
Kaneko, E.I.
, 
Tomimori, T.
, 
1999
. 
Studies on nepalese crude drugs. XXVI. Chemical constituents of panch aunle, the roots of Dactylorhiza hatagirea D. don
. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
47
, 
1618–1625
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/cpb.47.1618
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, M.
, 
Guo, S.
, 
Wang, C.
, 
Xiao, P.
, 
2007
. 
Studies on chemical constituents of tubers of Gymnadenia conopsea
. 
Zhongguo Yaoxue Zazhi
42
, 
1696–1698
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, Y.
, 
Yang, L.
, 
Shu, L.
, 
Shen, Y.
, 
Hu, Q.
, 
Xia, Z.
, 
2013
. 
Flavonoid compounds from Arundina graminifolia
. 
Asian J. Chem.
25
, 
4922–4924
. 
https://doi.org/10.14233/ ajchem.2013.14143
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, M.F.
, 
Han, Y.
, 
Xing, D.M.
, 
Shi, Y.
, 
Xu, L.Z.
, 
Du, L.J.
, 
Ding, Y.
, 
2004
. 
A new stilbenoid from Arundina graminifolia. J
. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
6
, 
229–232
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1080/10286020310001653219
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, M.F.
, 
Ding, Y.
, 
Zhang, D.M.
, 
2005
a. 
Phenanthrene constituents from rhizome of Arundina graminifolia
. 
Zhongguo Zhongyao Zazhi
30
, 
353–356
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, M.F.
, 
Han, Y.
, 
Xing, D.M.
, 
Wang, W.
, 
Xu, L.Z.
, 
Du, L.J.
, 
Ding, Y.
, 
2005
b. 
One new benzyldihydrophenanthrene from Arundina graminifolia. J
. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
7
, 
767–770
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/102860204100016890181
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Q.
, 
Sun, F.
, 
Deng, Y.
, 
Dai, R.
, Lv, F., 
2019
a. 
HPLC-ESI-MSn identification and NMR characterization of glucosyloxybenzyl 2R-benzylmalate derivatives from Arundina graminifolia and their anti-liver fibrotic effects in vitro
. 
Molecules
24
, 
525
. 
https:// doi.org/10.3390/molecules24030525
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Q.
, 
Sun, F.
, 
Deng, Y.
, 
Dai, R.
, Lv, F., 
2019
b. 
HPLC-ESI-MSn identification and NMR characterization of glucosyloxybenzyl 2R-benzylmalate derivatives from Arundina Graminifolia and their anti-liver fibrotic effects in vtro
. 
Molecules
24
, 
525
. 
https:// doi.org/10.3390/molecules24030525
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Majumder, P.L.
, 
Ghosal, S.
, 
1994
. 
Two stilbenoids from the orchid Arundina bambusifolia
. 
Phytochemistry
35
, 
205–208
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422 (00)95011-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morikawa, T.
, 
Xie, H.
, 
Matsuda, H.
, 
Yoshikawa, M.
, 
2006
a. 
Glucosyloxybenzyl 2-isobutylmalates from the tubers of gymnadenia conopsea
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
69
, 
881–886
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np0581115
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morikawa, T.
, 
Xie, H.
, 
Matsuda, H.
, 
Wang, T.
, 
Yoshikawa, M.
, 
2006
b. 
Bioactive constituents from Chinese natural medicines. XVII. Constituents with radical scavenging effect and new glucosyloxybenzyl 2-isobutylmalates from Gymnadenia conopsea
. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
54
, 
506–513
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/cpb.54.506
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sahakitpichan, P.
, 
Mahidol, C.
, 
Disadee, W.
, 
Chimnoi, N.
, 
Ruchirawat, S.
, 
Kanchanapoom, T.
, 
2013
. 
Glucopyranosyloxybenzyl derivatives of (R)-2- benzylmalic acid and (R)-eucomic acid, and an aromatic glucoside from the pseudobulbs of Grammatophyllum speciosum
. 
Tetrahedron
69
, 
1031–1037
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.tet.2012.11.082
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shu, L.
, 
Shen, Y.
, 
Yang, L.
, 
Gao, X.
, 
Hu, Q.F.
, 
2013
. 
Flavonoids derivatives from Arundina graminifolia and their cytotoxicity. Asian J
. 
Chem.
25
, 
8358–8360
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.14233/ajchem.2013.14743A
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Simmler, C.
, 
Antheaume, C.
, 
Andre, P.
, 
Bonte, F.
, 
Lobstein, A.
, 
2011
. 
Glucosyloxybenzyl eucomate derivatives from Vanda teres stimulate HaCaT cytochrome c oxidase
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
74
, 
949–955
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np1006636
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tanaka, T.
, 
Suda, H.
, 
Naganawa, H.
, 
Hamada, M.
, 
Takeuchi, T.
, 
Aoyagi, T.
, 
Umezawa, H.
, 
1984
. 
Production of (S)-α- benzylmalic acid, inhibitor of carboxypeptidase A by actinomycetes. J
. 
Antibiot.
37
, 
682–684
. 
https://doi.org/10.7164/ antibiotics.37.682
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, Y.
, 
Guan, S.H.
, 
Meng, Y.H.
, 
Zhang, Y.B.
, 
Cheng, C.R.
, 
Shi, Y.Y.
, 
Feng, R.H.
, 
Zeng, F.
, 
Wu, Z.Y.
, 
Zhang, J.X.
, 
Yang, M.
, 
Liu, X.
, 
Li, Q.
, 
Chen, X.H.
, 
Bi, K.S.
, 
Guo, D. A.
, 
2013
. 
Phenanthrenes, 9,10-dihydrophenanthrenes, bibenzyls with their derivatives, and malate or tartrate benzyl ester glucosides from tubers of Cremastra appendiculata
. 
Phytochemistry
94
, 
268–276
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2013.06.001
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, X.
, 
Chen, W.
, 
Du, Y.
, 
Su, P.
, 
Qiu, Y.
, 
Ning, J.
, 
Liu, M.
, 
2021
. 
Phytochemistry and pharmacological activities of Arundina graminifolia (D.Don) Hochr. And other common Orchidaceae medicinal plants. J
. 
Ethnopharmacol.
276
, 
114143
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2021.114143
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zi, J.
, 
Li, S.
, 
Liu, M.
, 
Gan, M.
, 
Lin, S.
, 
Song, W.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Fan, X.
, 
Yang, Y.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Shi, J.
, 
Di, D.
, 
2008
. 
Glycosidic constituents of the tubers of Gymnadenia conopsea
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
71
, 
799–805
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np070670j
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
