<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113522</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Phytotoxic meroterpenoids with herbicidal activities from the phytopathogenic fungus Pseudopestalotiopsis theae</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopestalotiopsis theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopestalotiopsis theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sporocadaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pseudopestalotiopsis theae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Illigera celebica</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P
. 
theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Setaria viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pestalotiopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopestalotiopsis theae
(Sawada) Maharachch. K.D. Hyde &amp; Crous (Sporocadaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Illigera celebica
Miq. (Hernandiaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
I. celebica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Setaria viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pestalotiopsis theae
(Sawada) Maharachch. K.D. Hyde &amp; Crous (Sporocadaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Illigera celebica
Miq. (Hernandiaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Phytotoxic meroterpenoids with herbicidal activities from the phytopathogenic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopestalotiopsis theae
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Dong Gan
a

, 
Jia-Qi Liu
a

, 
Yu-Jun Yang
a

, 
Cheng-Yao Wang
a

, 
Li Zhu
a

, 
Chen-Zhe Li
a

, 
Le Cai

a, 
*

, 
Zhong-Tao Ding
a, b, 
**
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Key Laboratory of Medicinal Chemistry
for Natural Resource, 
Ministry of Education
, 
Yunnan
Characteristic Plant Extraction Laboratory, Functional Molecules Analysis and 
Biotransformation Key Laboratory of Universities
in 
Yunnan Province
, 
School of Chemical Science
and Technology, 
Yunnan
University, Kunming, 650091, PR 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b

Dali University, Dali, 671003, PR 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopestalotiopsis theae
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Sporocadaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Phytotoxic meroterpenoids</p>
         <p>Herbicidal activity</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
The fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudopestalotiopsis theae</tp:taxon-name>
isolated from the fresh leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>Illigera celebica</tp:taxon-name>
, has been reported to be a pathogenic fungus that can cause gray blight on tea leaves, a disease characterized by the appearance of necrotic lesions on tea leaves. The pathogenic substances in this fungus have not been clearly identified. Considering the possible involvement of specialized metabolites in symptom appearance, a chemical investigation of specialized metabolites on 
<tp:taxon-name>
P
. 
theae
</tp:taxon-name>
was conducted, resulting in the isolation of eight meroterpenoids, including six undescribed biscognienynes G-L and two known ones (biscognienynes B and D). The structures of these new compounds were characterized by extensive NMR spectroscopic and HR-ESI-MS data, and their absolute configurations were elucidated by ECD calculations. Except for biscogniyne L, all the isolated biscognienynes showed different degrees of phytotoxicity to tea 
in vivo
, thereby revealing for the first time the substances in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
that cause tea gray blight. Inspired by the fact that phytotoxins produced by pathogenic fungus are an effective resource for designing natural and safe bioherbicides, when assayed the herbicidal activity through Petri dish bioassays, biscognienynes G-J showed phytotoxic effects against seed germination and seedling growth of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setaria viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
, strongly inhibiting seed germination percentage and radicle and germ lengths of seedlings. The results of this study demonstrated the great potential of biscognienynes G-J to be proposed and developed as ecofriendly herbicides.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Pestalotiopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
-like species are pathogens which can cause numerous diseases in different hosts and are widely distributed in tropical and temperate ecosystems (

; 

; 

). Tea gray blight is one of the most serious leaf diseases of tea trees, caused by the phytopathogenic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopestalotiopsis theae
(Sawada) Maharachch. K.D. Hyde &amp; Crous (Sporocadaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
, affecting the production and quality of tea worldwide (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). However, the pathogenic substances in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
that cause tea gray blight have not been identified. Knowledge of these pathogenic substances can facilitate the development of disease control strategies, such as gene modification to improve host resistance and the identification of toxin biosynthesis inhibitors or toxin deactivators (

; 

). Therefore, the study of pathogenic substances is indispensable for fully understanding the pathogenic mechanism.
</p>
         <p>
Weeds have long been considered one of the most dangerous biotic stresses for crop production (

). Although synthetic herbicides have always been used as an effective strategy for weed control and indeed play a huge role in the development of agriculture, excessive and inappropriate use has resulted in the evolution of resistant weeds, environmental pollution, food contamination, and more is a serious threat to human and animal health (

). Consequently, the development of new herbicides with high-efficiency and low-toxicity based on the usage of fungal phytotoxins as natural bioherbicides are of great significance for crop protection. At present, fungal phytotoxins are generally regarded as one of the important resources for the development of eco-friendly and safe bioherbicides (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>
** Corresponding author. 
Key Laboratory of Medicinal Chemistry
for Natural Resource, 
Ministry of Education
, 
Yunnan
Characteristic Plant Extraction Laboratory, Functional Molecules Analysis and 
Biotransformation Key Laboratory of Universities
in 
Yunnan Province
, 
School of Chemical Science
and Technology, 
Yunnan
University, Kunming, 650091, PR 
China
.
</p>
         <p>
E-mail addresses:
1162635732@qq.com (D. Gan), caile@ynu.edu.cn (L. Cai), ztding@ynu.edu.cn (Z.-T. Ding).
</p>
         <p>
Our group has been working on the discovery of structurally interesting and biologically significant natural products from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Illigera celebica
Miq. (Hernandiaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
and its endophyte (

, 

). In the present study, the pathogenic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
was isolated from the leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
I. celebica
</tp:taxon-name>
, which is associated with tea leaf blight. Although the specialized metabolites of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
have been reported in the literature (

; 

), their phytotoxicity has not been described. Therefore, we have a strong motivation to identify the substances in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
causing tea gray blight and to search for natural products with potent herbicidal activity. Fermentation of the fungus on potato solid medium yielded eight compounds, including six undescribed meroterpenoids biscognienynes (1–5 and 8) and two known ones (6 and 7) (
Fig. 1
). Compounds 1–7 exhibited varying degrees of phytotoxicity to tea leaves 
in vivo
. In addition, the herbicidal activities of compounds 1–4 were evaluated through Petri dish bioassays, and the results showed that they showed phytotoxic effects against seed germination and seedling growth of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setaria viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
, strongly inhibiting seed germination percentage and radicle and germ lengths of seedlings.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Structural elucidation
</title>
         <p>
Compound 1 was obtained as a yellowish oil. The molecular formula of 1 was determined to be C 
16
H 
22
O 
4
by HR-ESI-MS analysis, which requires six degrees of unsaturation. The 
1
H, 
13
C, DEPT, and HSQC NMR spectra revealed that 1 contains 16 carbons, including three methyls [
δ
H
1.90 (H 
3
-11), 1.68 (H 
3
-15) and 1.75 (H 
3
-16); 
δ
C
23.6 (C-11), 18.2 (C-15) and 26.3(C-16)], two methylenes [
δ
H
5.25 (H-10, olefinic) and 2.50 (H-12); 
δ
C
121.9 (C-10, olefinic) and 34.2 (C-12)], five methines [
δ
H
4.01(H-1, oxygenated), 4.42 (H-3, oxygenated), 3.84 (H-4, oxygenated), 5.89 (H-5, olefinic) and 5.34 (H-13, olefinic); 
δ
C
71.2 (C-1, oxygenated), 72.9 (C-3, oxygenated), 67.9 (C-4, oxygenated), 136.9 (C-5, olefinic) and 119.9 (C-13, olefinic)], and six quaternary carbons [
δ
C
77.1 (C-2, oxygenated), 125.4 (C-6, olefinic), 88.6 (C-7, alkyne carbon), 91.2 (C-8, alkyne carbon), 128.5 (C-9, olefinic) and 135.5 (C-14, olefinic)]. These data of 1 (
Table 1
) were similar to those of biscognienyne B (7) (

; 

), except that the oxygenated carbons at 
δ
C
77.1 (C-2) and 
δ
C
72.9 (C-3) were significantly shifted to the downfield region in the spectrum of 1 compared to those of 7. This result implied there were two hydroxyl groups at C-2 (
δ
C
77.1) and C-3 (
δ
C
72.9) in 1 instead of the epoxy unit in 7, which was supported by HR-ESI-MS analysis. The planar structure of 1 was further confirmed by 
1
H– 
1
H COSY and HMBC correlation analyses (
Fig. 2
). The stereochemistry of 1 was suggested to be the same as that of 7, for which the absolute configuration was determined by comparison of the coupling constants, NOE correlations (
Fig. 3
), specific optical rotation value, and biogenesis. The absolute configuration of 1 was further supported by a combination of electronic circular dichroism (ECD) calculations based on time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) method at the B3LYP/6-31G (d, p) level with the ECD spectra experimentally collected in methanol (
Fig. 4
). 1 was named biscognienyne G.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 2 was obtained as a yellowish oil and with the molecular formula C 
16
H 
24
O 
4
based on its HR-ESI-MS data, which was in accordance with 
1
H, 
13
C and DEPT NMR data ((Fig. S9) and showed five degrees of unsaturation. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of 2 were similar to those of 1 except for the presence of a methylene at 
δ
H
1.82 (H-5) and a methine at 
δ
H
2.79 (H-6) instead of the double bond in 1. This assignment was supported by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations (
Fig. 2
) of H-4 (
δ
H
3.91)/H 
2
-5 (
δ
H
1.82)/H-6 (
δ
H
2.79)/H-1 (
δ
H
3.49). The remaining substructure of 2 was further confirmed by 
1
H– 
1
H COSY and HMBC correlation analyses (
Fig. 2
). The relative configuration of 2 was ascertained by examination of its NOESY spectrum (
Fig. 3
). The NOE correlations of H-1/H-12 and H-3/H-12 indicated that H-1, H-3 and H-12 are 
β
-oriented. In addition, the NOE correlation of H-4 with H-6 indicated that H-4 and H-6 are on the same face. Furthermore, the value of 
J
H-1/H-6
(10.5 Hz) suggested a trans-orientation of these protons, which also indicated that H-4 and H-6 are 
α
-oriented. The aforementioned data supported the existence of two possible enantiomers, (1 
R
,2 
R
,3 
S
,4 
R
,6 
R
)- 2 and (1 
S
,2 
S
,3 
R
,4 
S
,6 
S
)-2. Finally, the absolute configuration of 2 was established as 1 
R
, 2 
R
, 3 
S
, 4 
R
, 6 
R
based on the good fit between the calculated and experimental ECD spectra of (1 
R
,2 
R
,3 
S
,4 
R
,6 
R
)-2. 2was named biscognienyne H.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 3 was isolated as a yellowish oil with the molecular formula C 
16
H 
24
O 
6
based on its HRESIMS data. The NMR data (
Table 1
) of 3 closely resemble those of biscognienyne G (1), indicating that they share the same skeleton. A prominent difference between the spectra of the two compounds was the appearance of peaks corresponding to two additional hydroxy groups at C-9 (
δ
C
69.9) and C-10 (
δ
C
71.2) in the spectrum of 3. The planar structure of 3 was elucidated by extensive analysis of the 2D NMR spectra (
Fig. 2
). It was concluded that the core structure of 3 should retain the same stereochemistry as that of the cooccurring 1 based on comparing the corresponding NOE correlations (
Fig. 3
) and coupling constants and considering the results in conjunction with the biogenesis. However, the configuration of C-9 could not be assigned from the NOESY data. In summary, the possible configurations of 3 were determined to be (1 
R
,2 
R
,3 
S
,4 
R
,9 
S
)-3 and (1 
R
,2 
R
,3 
S
,4 
R
,9 
R
)-3. Finally, the absolute configuration of 3 was determined to be 1 
R
, 2 
R
, 3 
S
, 4 
R
, 9 
S
according to the agreement between the experimental spectrum and the calculated spectrum (
Fig. 4
). Thus, the structure of 3 was revealed and named biscognienyne I.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Compound 4 was isolated as a yellowish oil. The molecular formula of 4 was determined to be C 
16
H 
24
O 
6
by analysis of the positive HR-ESI-MS data. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (
Table 2
) of 4 were very similar to those of biscognienyne I (3), indicating that they share the same backbone. The chemical shifts of C-2 (
δ
C
63.2) and C-3 (
δ
C
61.1) in the spectrum of 4 were significantly upfield of those for the corresponding carbons in the spectrum of 3, indicating the formation of an epoxy unit between the C-2 and C-3 of 4. This conclusion was confirmed by HR-ESI-MS analysis. The planer structure of 4 was further confirmed by analysis of other 2D NMR spectra, including 
1
H– 
1
H COSY and HMBC spectra (
Fig. 2
). It was concluded that the chiral carbons of 4 should retain the same properties as those of the cooccurring 3 by comparing the respective chemical shifts, coupling constants and NOE correlations (
Fig. 3
) in conjunction with the biogenetic characteristics. In addition, this was further confirmed by comparing the experimental and calculated ECD spectra (
Fig. 4
). Thus, the structure of 4 was revealed and named biscognienyne J.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 5 was also isolated as a yellowish oil. The molecular formula of 5 was determined to be C 
16
H 
24
O 
6
by its HR-ESI-MS data. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (
Table 2
) of 5 were very similar to those of 4, except that the oxymethine at 
δ
H
3.30 (m, H-3) and 
δ
H
4.41 (dd, 
J
= 2.5, 3.9 Hz, H-4), as well as the olefinic proton at 
δ
H
5.76 (m, H-5) were significantly shifted to the downfield region in 5 compared to 4, while the chemical shifts of 5 and biscognienyne D (6) [
δ
H
3.30 (t, 
J
= 2.5, H-3), 
δ
H
4.43 (dd, 
J
= 2.5, 5.0 Hz, H-4), 
δ
H
5.76 (q, 
J
= 2.4 Hz H-5)] (

) were almost the same at these corresponding positions. This result suggested that the configurations of C-3 and C-4 of 5 and 6 were the same, and 5 was a C-4-epimer of 4. This assignment was further supported by NOE experiment. The NOE correlations (
Fig. 3
) from H-1 to H-4 and H-12 and from H-3 to H-12 indicated that these protons were on the same face. From a biogenetic point of view, the configuration of C-9 should be the same as that of the 4. Thus, the absolute configuration of 5 was established as 1 
R
, 2 
R
, 3 
S
, 4 
S
, 9 
S
. 5 was named biscognienyne K.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 8 was isolated as a colorless gum and had the molecular formula C 
16
H 
22
O 
5
on the basis of the HR-ESI-MS data. The 
1
H NMR spectroscopic data (
Table 2
) displayed signals for four methyl groups [
δ
H
1.72, 1.68 (each s, 3H),1.52 and 1.41 (each s, 3H)], two sets of nonequivalent methylene protons [
δ
H
2.81 (dd, 
J
= 15.1 and 8.1 Hz, 1H) and 
δ
H
2.36 (dd, 
J
= 15.1 and 6.3 Hz, 1H); 
δ
H
2.65 (d, 
J
= 16.5 Hz, 1H) and 
δ
H
2.50 (d, 
J
= 16.5 Hz, 1H)], three methine protons [
δ
H
4.61 (t, 
J
= 2.3 Hz, 1H), 
δ
H
4.23 (t, 
J
= 2.5 Hz, 1H) and 
δ
H
3.85 (t, 
J
= 2.5 Hz, 1H)] and one olefinic proton [
δ
H
5.14 (m, 1H)]. The 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data (
Table 2
) showed signals for four methyl carbons (
δ
C
27.2, 26.0, 25.1 and 18.3), two methylene carbons (
δ
C
29.4 and 47.7), three oxymethine carbons (
δ
C
64.0, 66.0 and 68.2), three olefinic quaternary carbons (
δ
C
170.3, 136.0 and 111.1), one conjugated ketone carbonyl carbon (
δ
C
193.6) and one olefinic methine carbon (
δ
C
118.8). A prenyl unit was constructed based on the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations of H-10/H-9, and the HMBC correlations of H-9 with C-9 and C-11 and those of H 
3
-12 and H 
3
-13 with C-10 and C-11 (
Fig. 2
). The 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations of H-6/H-5 and H-7, and the HMBC correlations from H-5 to C-4a and C-8a, from H-6 to C-8 and C-4a, from H-7 to C-8a and C-9, as well as the chemical shifts of C-7, C-8, C-4a and C-8a established a cyclohexene unit with the attachment of the prenyl group at C-8, an epoxy group at C-7 and C-8, and a double bond at C-4a and C-8a. According to the HMBC correlations of H 
3
-14 and H 
3
-15 to C-2 and C-3, from H-3 to C-2, C-4 and C-4a, and from H-5 to C-4 together with the chemical shifts of C-2 and C-8a, a fused cyclohexene-dihydropyran-4-one was established. In addition, the substituents at C-5 and C-6 were hydroxy groups based on their chemical shifts. The relative configuration was assigned by the NOE data (
Fig. 3
). The NOE correlations from H-7 to H-5 and H-9 implied that these protons were on the same face. This suggested that there were four possible configurations of 8: 8-(5 
S
,6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
), 8-(5 
R
,6 
S
,7 
R
,8 
R
), 8- (5 
S
,6 
S
,7 
S
,8 
S
), 8-(5 
R
,6 
R
,7 
R
,8 
R
). Because the experimental ECD data of 8 was similar to the calculated ECD data of 8-(5 
S
,6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
) isomer (
Fig. 4
), the absolute configuration of 8 was assigned as 5 
S
, 6 
R
, 7 
S
, 8 
S
. 8 was named biscognienyne L.
</p>
         <p>
The remaining two known compounds from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
were identified based on their spectroscopic data and the literature. These natural products were identified as biscognienyne D (6) (

), biscognienyne B (7) (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Determination of phytotoxicity and herbicidal activity
</title>
         <p>
The fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
is a very successful pathogen that can cause tea leaf gray blight and has inflicted enormous losses on tea production (

; 

). However, the pathogenic substances in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
have not been clearly identified. Compounds 1–8 were isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
and assayed on detached tea leaves at concentrations of 
1 mg
/mL, and the results are presented in 
Table 3
. In phytotoxicity bioassay experiments, compounds 1–7 caused severe leaf shrinkage and deformation with necrotic spots, while compound 8 showed no obvious symptoms. However, no phytotoxic symptoms were observed on the leaves that received the negative control treatment. These results indicated that compounds 1–7 exhibited different degrees of phytotoxicity to tea leaves and revealed the substances in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
causing tea gray blight.
</p>
         <p>
Inspired by the fact that phytotoxins produced by pathogenic fungus are an effective resource for designing natural and safe bioherbicides (

; 

; 

), sufficient amounts of compounds 1–4 and 8 were selected and assayed the herbicidal activity through Petri dish bioassays (

). Due to insufficient amounts of compounds 5–7, their herbicidal activities were not evaluated. Compounds 1–4 showed phytotoxic effects inhibiting seed germination and seedling growth of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Figs. 5–8
). The germination percentage values of seeds treated with compounds 1–4 ranged from 5% to 16%, while that of seeds in the control reached 62% (
Figs. 5–8
). Compound 8 (germination percentage value 55%) did not significantly inhibit the seed germination of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
, with respect to the control (
Figs. 5–8
). Furthermore, radicle and germ length were strongly inhibited by compounds 1–4, while little phytotoxic effects toward seedling growth of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
were observed in the case of compound 8 (
Figs. 5–8
). The alkyne group could be the key factor for the phytotoxicity of this 
type
of meroterpenoids.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
In summary, compounds 1–7 isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
showed varying degrees of phytotoxicity to tea leaves 
in vivo
, and the causative agent of tea gray blight was proposed for the first time. This result not only expanded the knowledge of phytotoxic metabolites produced by 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
, but could facilitate the development of strategies for the disease control, such as genetic modification to improve host resistance and the identification of toxin biosynthesis inhibitors or toxin deactivators (

; 

). Moreover, compounds 1–4 showed potential herbicidal activities toward 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
and could be proposed and developed as natural bioherbicides in order to increase the control of this problematic weed in the future.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Measured at 600 MHz. 
b
Measured at 400 MHz.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
NMR spectra were recorded on a Bruker DRX-400. Chemical shifts are expressed in ppm and as CD 
3
OD (
δ
H
3.31/ 
δ
C
49.0) signals. Optical rotations were determined using a Jasco P-1020 digital polarimeter. Electronic circular dichroism (ECD) spectra were obtained using an Applied Photophysics spectropolarimeter. UV spectra were measured on a Shimadzu UV-2401PC spectrometer. HR-ESI-MS data were acquired on an Agilent 1290 UPLC/6545Q-TOF-MS spectrometer. Column chromatography (CC) was performed using RP-18 (50 μm, Merck, 
Germany
), Si gel (200–300 mesh, Qingdao Marine Chemical Co. Ltd), and Sephadex LH-20 (GE Chemical Corporation). An Agilent 1260 instrument equipped with a Zorbax SB-C 18 column (5 μm, 9.4 × 
250 mm
) was employed for semipreparative HPLC. Thin-layer chromatography (TLC) (GF 
254
, Qingdao Ocean Chemical Co. Ltd.) was used to monitor fractions.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Fungal material and fermentation
</title>
         <p>

The fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pestalotiopsis theae
(Sawada) Maharachch. K.D. Hyde &amp; Crous (Sporocadaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
was isolated from the fresh leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Illigera celebica
Miq. (Hernandiaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
collected from 
Shiping County
, 
Honghe Prefecture
, 
Yunnan Province
, 
China
(

102.716 
◦
E

, 

24.101 
◦
N

) in 

July 2018

. The species was identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. theae
</tp:taxon-name>
based on its morphological and genetic (ITS) characteristics (GenBank accession No. 
MW309862
). The strain was preserved in the 
School of Chemical Science and Technology
, Yunnan University, China

. 
The
strain was maintained on modified PDA medium (1 L of water, 
15 g
of agar, 
20 g
of glucose, 
200 g
of potato, and natural pH) and cultured in a 28 
◦
C constant-temperature incubator for 3 d. 
Aliquots
(
5 kg
) of potatoes were placed in 50 glass inoculum flasks as a medium, which was then sterilized the medium at 121 
◦
C for 30 min. 
Finally
, the fungi were added to the medium and incubated at room temperature for 30 d.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The fermented potato medium was ultrasonically extracted 3 times for 30 min each time. The extract was concentrated using a rotary evaporator to obtain a final mass of 
10 g
. The extract was first fractionated by column chromatography using silica gel with a gradient of CHCl 
3
–MeOH (100:0 → 30: 1 → 3:1 
v
/ 
v
) to obtain three fractions (Fr.1- Fr.3). Fr. 1 was passed through a silica gel column with petroleum ether (PE)-EtOAc (30:1 → 3:1 
v
/ 
v
) to yield 6 (
3.5 mg
), 7 (
3.5 mg
) and 8 (6.0 mg). Fr. 2 was separated via a silica gel column (
250 mm
× 
25 mm
) washed with CHCl 
3
–MeOH (100:1 → 3:1 
v
/ 
v
) to provide three fractions (Fr. 2–1 to Fr. 2–3). Further separation of Fr. 2-1 by CC over silica gel (
250 mm
× 
10 mm
) with PE- EtOAc (20:1 → 3:1 v/v) as the eluent afforded 1 (10.0 mg) and 2 (8.0 mg). Fr. 2-2 was further purified by RP-HPLC with MeCN–H 
2
O (1:10 → 1:0 
v
/ 
v
) to obtain 4 (
7.5 mg
) and 5 (
3.5 mg
). Fr. 2–3 was fractionated on a Sephadex LH-20 column eluted with MeOH to yield 3 (
10.5 mg
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Biscognienyne G (1)
</title>
         <p>
20
</p>
         <p>
Yellowish oil; [
a
] 
D
: 25.9 (
c
= 0.22, MeOH); positive HR-ESI-MS 
m/ z
301.1409 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
16
H 
22
O 
4
Na 
+
,301.1410); 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.5. Biscognienyne K (5)
</title>
         <p>
Yellowish oil; [
a
] 
D
20
: 20.4 (
c
= 0.25, MeOH); positive HR-ESI-MS 
m/ z
317.1359 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
16
H 
22
O 
5
Na 
+
, 317.1359); 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.6. Biscognienyne L (8)
</title>
         <p>
20
</p>
         <p>
Colorless gum; [
a
] 
D
: 52.3 (
c
= 0.25, MeOH); positive HR-ESI-MS 
m/z
317.1354 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
16
H 
22
O 
5
Na 
+
, 317.1359); 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Phytotoxicity assay
</title>
         <p>
Phytotoxicity was assessed using the method reported in the literature (

). All the isolated compounds were dissolved in 40 μL of MeOH, to which sterile distilled water (SDW) was added to obtain a volume of 1 mL. The bioassays were conducted at a final concentration of 
1 mg
/mL for each test sample, after which 0.1 mL of each sample was added to tea leaves. SDW with 4% MeOH was used as a negative control. All experiments were repeated three times.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Herbicidal activity
</title>
         <p>
The herbicidal activities of compounds 1–4 and 8 were evaluated using a slightly modified the method reported by 

. Seeds of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
were presterilized with 2% NaOCl for 1 min and washed with distilled water before the experiments. Fifty seeds of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. viridis
</tp:taxon-name>
were evenly placed on filter paper and individually placed in sterilized 
90 mm
Petri dishes. Compounds 1–4 and 8 were diluted in 0.1 mL of MeOH to which 2.4 mL of distilled water was added in order to obtain concentrations of 2 × 10 

3
M.

These concentrations were added at 2.5 mL per Petri dish. MeOH at the concentration of 4% in distilled water was also added at 2.5 mL per Petri dish as control. In the experiments, all treatments were replicated three times in a completely randomized design, and all petri dishes were placed in growth chambers (25 
◦
C, dark). Germinated seeds were counted after 5 days, and 5 representative seedlings were selected from each dish to determine radicle and germ length. Seeds were considered germinated when the radicle protruded
&gt;
1 mm
. All data were presented as the mean ± SD using the Student’ s 
t
-test and one-way ANOVA test for group differences. 

P
&lt;

0.05 was considered as statistically significant.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Biscognienyne H (2)
</title>
         <p>
Yellowish oil; [
a
] 
D
20
: 46.0 (
c
= 0.15, MeOH); positive HR-ESI-MS 
m/ z
303.1565 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
16
H 
24
O 
4
Na 
+
, 303.1567); 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. Biscognienyne I (3)
</title>
         <p>
20
</p>
         <p>
Yellowish oil; [
a
] 
D
: 40.7 (
c
= 0.15, MeOH); positive HR-ESI-MS 
m/ z
335.1460 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
16
H 
24
O 
6
Na 
+
, 335.1465); 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.4. Biscognienyne J (4)
</title>
         <p>
Yellowish oil; [
a
] 
D
20
: 26.1 (
c
= 0.10, MeOH); positive HR-ESI-MS 
m/ z
317.1358 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C H O Na 
+
, 317.1359); 
1
H and 
13
C 
16
22 5
NMR data see Table 2.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. ECD calculation
</title>
         <p>
Conformational searches of the relative energy within 5.0 kcal/mol were performed using molecular mechanics force-field (MMFF94s) calculations with CONFLEX software (

). ECD calculations were performed on the conformers using time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) at the B3LYP/6-31G (d,p) level in methanol with the polarizable continuum model (PCM) (

). The simulated spectra of the conformers were averaged based on the Boltzmann distribution theory and the relative Gibbs free energy of the conformers to obtain the final spectra (

).
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Data availability
</p>
         <p>Data will be made available on request.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
This work was supported by the Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(No. 81860623); the Natural Science Foundation of the 
Yunnan Province
(202001BB050042); the Program for Innovative Research Team of 
Yunnan Province
(202105AE160006); the project of 
Yunnan
University “Double First-Class” Construction Joint Project (202201BF070001-014); the Project of 
Yunnan
Characteristic Plant Screening and 
R&amp;D Service
CXO Platform (2022YKZY001); and Scientific Research Fund of 
Yunnan
Provincial Department of Education
(2022Y029). Authors thank Advanced Analysis and ent Center of 
Yunnan
University for the sample testing service.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113522.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Akone, S.H.
, 
Wang, H.
, 
Mouelle, E.N.M.
, 
Mandi, A.
, 
Kurtan, T.
, 
Koliye, P.R.
, 
Hartmann, R.
, 
Bhatia, S.
, 
Yang, J.
, 
Muller, W.E.G.
, 
Lai, D.W.
, 
Liu, Z.
, 
Kalscheuer, R.
, 
Proksch, P.
, 
2022
. 

Prenylated cyclohexene-type meroterpenoids and sulfurcontaining xanthones produced by 
Pseudopestalotiopsis theae

. 
Phytochemistry
197
, 
8
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113124
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Berestetskiy, A.O.
, 
2008
. 
A review of fungal phytotoxins: from basic studies to practical use
. 
Appl. Biochem. Microbiol.
44
, 
453–465
. 
https://doi.org/10.1134/ s0003683808050013
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bruhn, T.
, 
Schaumloffel, A.
, 
Hemberger, Y.
, 
Bringmann, G.
, 
2013
. 
SpecDis: quantifying the comparison of calculated and experimental electronic circular dichroism spectra
. 
Chirality
25
, 
243–249
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/chir.22138
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Catarino, A.D.
, 
Hanada, R.E.
, 
de Queiroz, C.A.
, 
Sousa, T.F.
, 
Lima, I.N.
, 
Gasparotto, L.
, 
da Silva, G.F.
, 
2020
. 

First report of 
Pseudopestalotiopsis dawaina
causing spots in caryota mitis in Brazil

. 
Plant Dis.
104
, 
989
. 
https://doi.org/10.1094/pdis-08-19-1771-pdn
, 989.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cimmino, A.
, 
Masi, M.
, 
Evidente, M.
, 
Superchi, S.
, 
Evidente, A.
, 
2015
. 
Fungal phytotoxins with potential herbicidal activity: chemical and biological characterization
. 
Nat. Prod. Rep.
32
, 
1629–1653
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/ c5np00081e
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Darapanit, A.
, 
Boonyuen, N.
, 
Leesutthiphonchai, W.
, 
Nuankaew, S.
, 
Piasai, O.
, 
2021
. 

Identification, pathogenicity and effects of plant extracts on 
Neopestalotiopsis
and 
Pseudopestalotiopsis
causing fruit diseases

. 
Sci. Rep.
11
, 
11
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/ s41598-021-02113-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gan, D.
, 
Wang, C.Y.
, 
Li, C.Z.
, 
Zhu, L.
, 
Zhang, X.R.
, 
Ding, H.
, 
Cai, L.
, 
Ding, Z.T.
, 
2022
a. 

Secondary metabolites from 
annulohypoxylon
sp. and structural revision of emericellins A and B

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
85
, 
828–837
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. jnatprod.1c00922
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gan, D.
, 
Zhu, L.
, 
Zhang, X.R.
, 
Li, C.Z.
, 
Wang, C.Y.
, 
Cai, L.
, 
Ding, Z.T.
, 
2022
b. 

Penaloidines A and B: two unprecedented pyridine alkaloids from 
Penicillium
sp. KYJ-6

. 
Org. Chem. Front.
9
, 
2405–2411
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/d1qo01879e
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, F.L.
, 
Ye, Z.
, 
Huang, Z.Y.
, 
Chen, X.
, 
Sun, W.G.
, 
Gao, W.X.
, 
Zhang, S.T.
, 
Cao, F.
, 
Wang, J. P.
, 
Hu, Z.X.
, 
Zhang, Y.H.
, 
2021
a. 

New alpha-pyrone derivatives with herbicidal activity from the endophytic fungus 
Alternaria brassicicola

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
117
, 
10
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bioorg.2021.105452
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, Y.Z.
, 
Gai, Z.
, 
Wang, C.X.
, 
Li, P.L.
, 
Li, B.H.
, 
2021
b. 

Identification of mellein as a pathogenic substance of 
Botryosphaeria dothidea
by UPLC-MS/MS analysis and phytotoxic bioassay

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
69
, 
8471–8481
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ acs.jafc.1c03249
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liao, H.L.
, 
Chung, K.R.
, 
2008
. 

Genetic dissection defines the roles of elsinochrome phytotoxin for fungal pathogenesis and conidiation of the citrus pathogen 
Elsinoe fawcettii

. 
Mol. Plant-Microbe Interact.
21
, 
469–479
. 
https://doi.org/10.1094/mpmi-21-4-0469
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maharachchikumbura, S.S.N.
, 
Guo, L.D.
, 
Liu, Z.Y.
, 
Hyde, K.D.
, 
2016
. 

Pseudopestalotiopsis ignota
and 
Ps. camelliae
spp. nov associated with grey blight disease of tea in China

. 
Mycol. Prog.
15
, 
7
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11557-016-1162-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Masi, M.
, 
Pannacci, E.
, 
Santoro, E.
, 
Nadjia, Z.
, 
Superchi, S.
, 
Evidente, A.
, 
2020
. 

Stoechanones A and B, phytotoxic copaane sesquiterpenoids isolated from 
Lavandula stoechas
with potential herbicidal activity against 
Amaranthus retroflexus

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
83
, 
1658–1665
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.0c00182
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Reveglia, P.
, 
Savocchia, S.
, 
Billones-Baaijens, R.
, 
Masi, M.
, 
Cimmino, A.
, 
Evidente, A.
, 
2018
. 

Diploquinones A and B, two new phytotoxic tetrasubstituted 1,4-naphthoquinones from 
Diplodia mutila
, a causal agent of grapevine trunk disease

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
66
, 
11968–11973
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.8b05004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shahriar, S.A.
, 
Nur-Shakirah, A.O.
, 
Mohd, M.H.
, 
2022
. 

Neopestalotiopsis clavispora and 
Pseudopestalotiopsis camelliae-sinensis
causing grey blight disease of tea (
Camellia sinensis
) in Malaysia

. 
Eur. J. Plant Pathol.
162
, 
709–724
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ s00425-020-03353-x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tsai, I.
, 
Maharachchikumbura, S.S.N.
, 
Hyde, K.D.
, 
Ariyawansa, H.A.
, 
2018
. 

Molecular phylogeny, morphology and pathogenicity of 
Pseudopestalotiopsis
species on Ixora in Taiwan

. 
Mycol. Prog.
17
, 
941–952
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11557-018-1404-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, S.S.
, 
Liu, S.R.
, 
Liu, L.
, 
Li, R.
, 
Guo, R.
, 
Xia, X.B.
, 
Wei, C.L.
, 
2020
. 

miR477 targets the phenylalanine ammonia-lyase gene and enhances the susceptibility of the tea plant (
Camellia sinensis
) to disease during 
Pseudopestalotiopsis
species infection

. 
Planta
251
, 
12
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00425-020-03353-x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, Z.F.
, 
Sun, Z.C.
, 
Xiao, L.
, 
Zhou, Y.M.
, 
Du, F.Y.
, 
2019
. 

Herbicidal polyketides and diketopiperazine derivatives from 
Penicillium viridicatum

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
67
, 
14102–14109
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.9b06116
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, J.
, 
Ji, F.F.
, 
Kang, J.
, 
Wang, H.
, 
Li, S.
, 
Jin, D.Q.
, 
Zhang, Q.
, 
Sun, H.W.
, 
Guo, Y.Q.
, 
2015
. 

Absolute configurations and NO inhibitory activities of terpenoids from 
Curcuma longa

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
63
, 
5805–5812
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. jafc.5b01584
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yang, R.
, 
Jiang, S.L.
, 
Wen, X.D.
, 
Song, X.C.
, 
Wang, X.
, 
Li, D.X.
, 
Yin, Q.X.
, 
Wu, X.
, 
Wang, D.L.
, 
Chen, Z.
, 
2021
. 

Antifungal activity and possible mode of action of ningnanmycin against tea gray blight disease pathogen 
Pseudopestalotiopsis camelliae-sinensis

. 
Phytopathology
111
, 
1735–1742
. 
https://doi.org/10.1094/phyto-09-20- 0382-r
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yu, X.Q.
, 
Muller, W.E.G.
, 
Meier, D.
, 
Kalscheuer, R.
, 
Guo, Z.Y.
, 
Zou, K.
, 
Umeokoli, B.O.
, 
Liu, Z.
, 
Proksch, P.
, 
2020
. 

Polyketide derivatives from mangrove derived endophytic fungus 
Pseudopestalotiopsis theae
. Mar

. 
Drugs
18
, 
15
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ md18020129
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhao, D.L.
, 
Han, X.B.
, 
Wang, M.
, 
Zeng, Y.T.
, 
Li, Y.Q.
, 
Ma, G.Y.
, 
Liu, J.
, 
Zheng, C.J.
, 
Wen, M.X.
, 
Zhang, Z.F.
, 
Zhang, P.
, 
Zhang, C.S.
, 
2020
. 

Herbicidal and antifungal xanthone derivatives from the alga-derived fungus 
Aspergillus versicolor
D5

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
68
, 
11207–11214
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.0c04265
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhao, H.
, 
Chen, G.D.
, 
Zou, J.
, 
He, R.R.
, 
Qin, S.Y.
, 
Hu, D.
, 
Li, G.Q.
, 
Guo, L.D.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
Gao, H.
, 
2017
. 

Dimericbiscognienyne A: a meroterpenoid dimer from 
biscogniauxia
sp with new skeleton and its activity

. 
Org. Lett.
19
, 
38–41
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ acs.orglett.6b03264
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zheng, S.Q.
, 
Chen, R.Q.
, 
Wang, Z.
, 
Liu, J.
, 
Cai, Y.
, 
Peng, M.H.
, 
Zhang, T.
, 
Li, Y.X.
, 
Wang, B.H.
, 
Bao, J.D.
, 
Zhang, D.M.
, 
Wang, Z.H.
, 
Hu, H.L.
, 
2021
. 

High-quality genome assembly of 
Pseudopestalotiopsis theae
, the pathogenic fungus causing tea gray blight

. 
Plant Dis.
105
, 
3723–3726
. 
https://doi.org/10.1094/pdis-02-21-0318-a
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
