<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112727</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Anthocyanin 5,3 -aromatic acyltransferase from Gentiana triflora, a structural insight into biosynthesis of a blue anthocyanin</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>06</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana triflora
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana triflora
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gentianaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana triflora
Pall. (Gentianaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana triflora
Pall.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gentianaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eustoma grandiflorum
(Raf.)Shinn.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gentianaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gentianaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>acyltransferase</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana tabacum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form was</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Salvia splendens
Sellow ex Nees (Lamiaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form hydrogen</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rauvolfia serpentine
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Apocynaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eustoma</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eustoma
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Escherichia coli
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Mini Macro-Prep High Q Cartridge</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Anthocyanin 5,3 
′
-aromatic acyltransferase from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana triflora
</tp:taxon-name>
, a structural insight into biosynthesis of a blue anthocyanin

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Kazutaka Murayama
a, b
, Miyuki Kato-Murayama
b
, Tomohiro Sato
c
, Toshiaki Hosaka
b
,
Kanako Ishiguro 
d
, Takayuki Mizuno
e
, Kazunori Kitao
d
, Teruki Honma
c
, Shigeyuki Yokoyama
f
,
Yoshikazu Tanaka 
d
, Mikako Shirouzu

b, 
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a

Division of Biomedical Measurements and Diagnostics, Graduate School of Biomedical Engineering, Tohoku University, Sendai, 980-8575, 
Japan
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b

Laboratory for Protein Functional and Structural Biology, RIKEN Center for Biosystems Dynamics Research, Yokohama, 230-0045, 
Japan
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c

Laboratory for Structure-Based Molecular Design, RIKEN Center for Biosystems Dynamics Research, Yokohama, 230-0045, 
Japan
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
d
Research Institute
, 
Suntory Global Innovation Center Ltd
, 
Kyoto
, 619-0284, 
Japan
e
Department of Botany
, National Museum of Nature and 
Science
, 
Tsukuba
, 305-0005, 
Japan
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
f

RIKEN Cluster for Science, Technology and Innovation Hub, Yokohama, 230-0045, 
Japan
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
ARTICLE
INFO
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana triflora
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Gentianaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Structure analysis</p>
         <p>Anthocyanin</p>
         <p>Delphinidin</p>
         <p>Caffeoyl-CoA</p>
         <p>Acyltransferase</p>
         <p>
ABSTRACT
</p>
         <p>
The acylation of anthocyanins contributes to their structural diversity. Aromatic acylation is responsible for the blue color of anthocyanins and certain flowers. Aromatic acyltransferase from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana triflora
Pall. (Gentianaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Gt5,3 
′
AT
) catalyzes the acylation of glucosyl moieties at the 5 and 3 
′
positions of anthocyanins. Anthocyanin acyltransferase transfers an acyl group to a single position, such that Gt5,3 
′
AT
possesses a unique enzymatic activity. Structural investigation of this aromatic acyl group transfer is fundamental to understand the molecular mechanism of the acylation of double positions. In this study, structural analyses of Gt5,3 
′
AT
were conducted to identify the underlying mechanism. The crystal structure indicated that Gt5,3 
′
AT
shares structural similarities with other 
BAHD
family enzymes, consisting of N and C terminal lobes. Structural comparison revealed that acyl group preference (aromatic or aliphatic) for the enzymes was determined by four amino acid positions, which are well conserved in aromatic and aliphatic CoA-binding acyltransferases. Although a complex structure with anthocyanins was not obtained, the binding of delphinidin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucoside to Gt5,3 
′
AT
was investigated by evaluating the molecular dynamics. The simulation indicated that acyl transfer by Gt5,3 
′
AT
preferentially occurs at the 5-position rather than at the 3 
′
-position, with interacting amino acids that are mainly located in the C-terminal lobe. Subsequent assays of chimeric enzymes (exchange of the N-terminal lobe and the C-terminal lobe between Gt5,3 
′
AT
and lisianthus anthocyanin 5 
AT
) demonstrated that acyl transfer selectivity may be caused by the C-terminal lobe.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Acyl-CoA dependent anthocyanin acyltransferases (ATs) belong to the 
BAHD AT
family (

) and catalyze the specific transfer of an acyl group to the glucose moiety of anthocyanins, contributing to the structural diversity of anthocyanins. Anthocyanins are a class of flavonoids and major floral pigments that confer red and blue colors (

). The aromatic acylation of anthocyanins shifts their color to blue, and thus aromatic 
AT
can be a useful molecular tool to modify flower color. The blue color of gentian (
<tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana triflora
Pall.
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Gentianaceae</tp:taxon-name>
)) is derived from gentiodelphin (delphinidin 3- 
O
-β- 
D-
glucoside 5- 
O
-(6
</p>
         <p>
- 
O
-caffeoyl-β- 
D-
glucoside) 3 
′
- 
O
-(6- 
O
-caffeoyl-β- 
D-
glucoside), where the 3 
′
-caffeoyl residue contributes to the production of a bluer color than the 5-caffeoyl residue (

). The gene encoding gentian hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:anthocyanidin 3,5-diglucoside 5- 
O
-glucoside-6 
′
- 
O
-hydroxycinnamoyltransferase (Gt5 
AT
) was isolated for the first time as an anthocyanin 
AT
gene (

). Gt5 
AT
was later shown to catalyze acylation of 3 
′
-glucoside of anthocyanidin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucoside following the acylation of 5-glucoside, and was accordingly renamed Gt5,3 
′
AT
(

) (
Fig. 1
). Gt5,3 
′
AT
has been shown to utilize caffeoyl-CoA and coumaroyl-CoA, but not aliphatic CoAs, such as malonyl-CoA, as an acyl donor (

, resolution of 2.2–1.8 
Å
(

). Malonyl-CoA (acyl donor) and anthocyanin (acyl acceptor) binding sites were identified in Dm3MAT3, where the latter was found to be different from that of vinorine synthase, another 
BAHD AT
(

). These structures indicated that the acyl-CoA binding sites share structural similarities in their acceptance of common acyl-CoA (malonyl-CoA), whereas the structure of the acyl acceptor moieties can be adapted for individual ligands. In general, 
BAHD
ATs share sequence similarities and conserved motifs, including HxxxD and 
DFGWG
motifs, which play an important role in catalytic reactions (

). The ligand specificity of 
BAHD
ATs can be investigated in two ways: (1) acyl-CoA recognition as a common binding mechanism and (2) anthocyanin recognition as diverse acyl acceptors. Structural analysis would provide critical information for understanding the molecular mechanisms underlying ligand recognition specificities.
</p>
         <p>
In this study, we determined the crystal structures of Gt5,3 
′
AT
alone and in a complex with caffeoyl-CoA using molecular replacement at 3.1 and 2.5 
Å
resolutions, respectively, to identify the molecular basis of substrate specificity. The crystal structures of Gt5,3 
′
AT
revealed differences in substrate recognition for an aromatic acyl-CoA donor compared to other flavonoid 
BAHD AT
family enzymes. Additionally, the substrate specificity of Gt5,3 
′
AT
is discussed based on the docking model calculations. The specificity of Eg5 
AT
was successfully modified to harbor 5,3 
′
AT
activity based on the crystal structure and docking model.
</p>
         <p>
1998bib_Fujiwara_et_al_1997bib_Fujiwara_et_al_1998). Lisianthus (
<tp:taxon-name>
Eustoma grandiflorum
(Raf.)Shinn.
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Gentianaceae</tp:taxon-name>
)),which belongs to the same family as gentian (
<tp:taxon-name>Gentianaceae</tp:taxon-name>
), produces purple flowers, which mainly accumulate delphinidin 3-rhamnosylgalactoside 5- 
p
-coumaroylglucoside (

). The acylation of 5-glucoside is catalyzed by lisianthus 5 
AT
(Eg5 
AT
), and its cDNA and Eg5 
AT
cDNA has been isolated (GenBank accession no.AB078964.1).Anthocyanin ATs are regiospecific, that is, they usually catalyze the acylation of one glucose moiety at specific positions of anthocyanins, and their genes diversified after speciation of plant families, unlike the other flavonoid biosynthetic genes (

). Gt5,3 
′
AT
and Eg5 
AT
are homologous and share 69% amino acid sequence identity. Although the substrate specificity of Eg5 
AT
has not been published, differences in the anthocyanins accumulated in gentian and lisianthus indicate that Gt5,3 
′
AT
and Eg5 
AT
have distinctive enzymatic specificities. Therefore, structural insights are needed to understand how Gt5,3 
′
AT
transfers acyl groups to the two anthocyanin positions. Furthermore, Gt5,3 
′
AT
is the only so-far characterized 
BAHD
type
AT
that catalyzes the acylation of the 3 
′
-glucoside of anthocyanins.
</p>
         <p>
Malonyl-CoA-dependent anthocyanin ATs and their genes have been studied and isolated from salvia (

), dahlia (

), and chrysanthemum (

). In a previous study, chrysanthemum malonyl anthocyanin ATs were subjected to amino acid replacement/domain swapping studies, and the crystal structure of one of the homologues (Dm3MAT3) was solved with a
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

2.1. Structure of gentian 
<tp:taxon-name>acyltransferase</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The crystal structures of Gt5,3 
′
AT
were determined for the apo and complex forms of the His174Ala mutant with caffeoyl-CoA (
Fig. 2
). In the apo form, the electron density of the region 302–308 was poor and the structural model was not built. The structure is composed of 14 α- helices and 16 β- strands, including several short helices, such as the 
310
helix. Although the mutant/truncated Gt5,3 
′
AT
was soaked with caffeoyl-CoA and delphinidin 3,5-diglucoside, in the crystal structure, the electron density of delphinidin 3,5-diglucoside could not be found, and caffeoyl-CoA binding was demonstrated by the electron density around the binding pocket (
Fig. 2
). The adenosine moiety exhibited poor electron density. This is similar to the structural analysis conducted on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana tabacum
</tp:taxon-name>
L
. (
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) malonyltransferase (NtMAT1) (

). The two structures (apo and complex forms) were very similar, with an 
RMSD
of 0.47 
Å
, suggesting that caffeoyl-CoA fit simply to the binding pocket and did not induce significant conformational changes.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
According to a 
BLAST
search against the Protein Data Bank database using the Gt5,3 
′
AT
sequence as a query, Gt5,3 
′
AT
showed high sequence similarity with Dm3MAT3 (sequence identity 35.5%, PDB: 2 
E
1 
U
) (

) and NtMAT1 (sequence identity 40.3%, 2 
XR
7) (

), and these enzymes belong to the same family (flavonoid 
BAHD
ATs) of Gt5,3 
′
AT
.The structural similarities between two flavonoid 
BAHD
ATs and Gt5,3 
′
AT
are 
RMSD
of 1.48 
Å
for Dm3MAT3 and 
RMSD
of 1.38 
Å
for NtMAT1, comparing with common Cα atoms. Based on these two enzymes, PvHCT1a(5 
FAL
) (

), SbHCT(4 
KE
4) (

), SmHCT(6 
DD
2) (

), CcHQT(4 
G
22) (

), AtHCT(5 
KJT
) (

), and RsVS (2 
BGH
) (

) were also found to have structures similar to those of Gt5,3 
′
AT
. These enzymes belong to hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA: shikimate/quinate hydroxycinnamoyltransferases (
HCT
/ 
HQT
) and vinorine synthase (
VS
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
As a member of the 
BAHD
ATs, Gt5,3 
′
AT
possesses two conserved motifs (

): HxxxD and 
DFGWG
. The HxxxD motif is conserved as 
174
His-Ser-Ile-Ala-Asp 

178
in

Gt5,3 
′
AT
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Caffeoyl-CoA binding site
</title>
         <p>
Among the three flavonoid 
BAHD AT
enzymes with known structures (Gt5,3 
′
AT
, Dm3MAT3, and NtMAT1), Dm3MAT3 and NtMAT1 catalyze the transfer of a malonyl group to flavonoid ligands, while Gt5,3 
′
AT
catalyzes the transfer of a caffeoyl/coumaroyl group to the ligand. Acylgroup recognition can occur at the narrow end of the acyl-CoA binding pocket. In the Gt5,3 
′
AT
structure, the caffeoyl group is sandwiched between Met43 and Phe182, stabilized by three hydrogen bonds, one between the carbonyl oxygen of the caffeoyl group and Gly401(N) and Thr400(Oγ1), and one between the hydroxyl group at position 3 and Ser45(Oγ) (
Fig. 3A
). The third hydrogen bond is only possible for the caffeoyl group and can contribute to acyl-CoA binding. In our previous study, Gt5,3 
′
AT
showed a higher affinity for the caffeoyl group than the coumaroyl group as an acyl-CoA donor (

). As mentioned above, the Gt5,3 
′
AT
structure did not show significant conformational changes upon caffeoyl-CoA binding. However, caffeoyl group binding induced a local change in the amino acid structural environment. The Met43 residue in the apo 
<tp:taxon-name>form was</tp:taxon-name>
directed toward the empty pocket space. In the complex form, the rotamer of methionine changed and created space for caffeoyl group binding (
Fig. 3B
). In addition, the main chain of the loop between α1 and β3 was shifted to extend the pocket: a shift of 0.57 
Å
at the Cα position of Met43.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
On the contrary, to accept a malonyl group, arginine residues contribute to the stabilization of the malonyl group via hydrogen bonds in Dm3MAT3 and NtMAT1, although these enzymes applied Arg at different positions: Arg 
178 in
Dm3MAT3 and Arg 
39 in
NtMAT1. These Arg positions correspond to Phe182 and Ser45, respectively, in Gt5,3 
′
AT
(
Table 1
). It has been reported that the three residue mutants of malonyl transferase from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Salvia splendens
Sellow ex Nees (Lamiaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Ss5MaT1) exhibited a change in ligand specificity to aromatic acyl-CoA (

). The mutation was engineered at Val39-Arg40-Arg41 of Ss5MaT1 to Met-Leu-Gln. Considering these results, the two positions (positions 45 and 182) in Gt5,3 
′
AT
are likely to be critical for acyl-CoA recognition specificity. Supplementary 
Figure S1
shows the sequence alignment among the characterized flavonoid 
BAHD
ATs (

). For malonyl-CoA ATs, it is important to include Arg either at position 45 or position 182, except for two malonyl-CoA ATs, Ss5MaT2 and MaT5. However, Ss5MaT2 includes Val at position 179 and Asp at position 401, and MaT5 includes Trp at position 401. These positions in other flavonoid 
BAHD
ATs are occupied with Ala/Gly and Gly/Ser at positions 179 and 401, respectively (Supplementary 
Figure S1
). These two positions correspond to the side wall of the acyl-CoA binding site (
Fig. 3A
). Bulky amino acids in these positions make the binding site narrower, thus inhibiting aromatic acyl-CoA binding.
</p>
         <p>
a
These amino acids 
<tp:taxon-name>form hydrogen</tp:taxon-name>
bonds with the malonyl/caffeoyl group.

</p>
         <p>
Aromatic acyl-CoA ATs possess Ser/Gln and Phe/Ile/Gly at positions 45 and 182, respectively (Supplementary 
Figure S1
). These aromatic acyl-CoA ATs avoid bulky amino acids at critical positions, especially at positions 179 and 401, and maintain sufficient space to adapt to an aromatic acyl-CoA donor. The comparison among the other 
BAHD
ATs with known structures (mentioned above) also supports these observations. Vinorine synthase from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rauvolfia serpentine
</tp:taxon-name>
(
L
.) Benth. Ex Kurz (
<tp:taxon-name>Apocynaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) is another 
BAHD
superfamily enzyme that is involved in the biosynthesis of the ajmalan-type alkaloid vinorine from the alkaloid 16-epi-vellosimine (

). Structural comparison revealed that this enzyme possesses a valine (Val165) at position 
179 in
Gt5,3 
′
AT
that accepts non-aromatic acyl-CoA (
Fig. 4
). The important amino acid locations for acyl-CoA specificity are summarized in 
Fig. 5.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Internal environment of anthocyanin binding pocket and acylation
preference
</title>
         <p>
The structure of Gt5,3 
′
AT
is composed of two lobes, the N-lobe and the C-lobe (
Fig. 6A
). These are connected by a loop between α7 and β10. The putative anthocyanin-binding pocket is constructed between these two lobes, the bottom of which is linked to the acyl-CoA binding site. The estimated anthocyanin binding pocket volume was 268 
Å
3
, calculated using the POCASA program (

). The surface model of the anthocyanin-binding pocket is shown in 
Fig. 6A
. Since the crystal structure of the anthocyanin• 
AT
complex has yet to be elucidated, we conducted a docking model study to investigate the positional selectivity of anthocyanin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucoside for Gt5,3 
′
AT
(
Fig. 6B
). The results revealed that eight of the ten docking poses, including those showing the highest docking score, indicated acyl group transfer at position 5, including the top score. This suggests that Gt5,3 
′
AT
preferred acyl group transfer at position 5 to that at position 3’. In the model structures, anthocyanin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucoside binding could be stabilized by van der Waals contacts with hydrophobic amino acids: Trp37, Leu40, Met43, Val232, Phe236, Ile391, Phe396, Ile399, Ala428, and Leu430. These amino acids consist of the side wall of the putative anthocyanin-binding pocket. In addition, each binding mode (at positions 5 and 3 
′
) had some hydrogen bonds with the hydroxyl groups of glucose. Ser316, Ser393, Ile391, Asn389, and Gly398 were related to hydrogen bonds in the model of transfer at position 5, and Ser316, Ser388, Ile399, Tyr427, and Glu 
429 in
the model of transfer at position 3’. The results are summarized in Supplementary 
Figure S2
.
</p>
         <p>
Eg5 
AT
and Gt5,3 
′
AT
are functionally similar and their amino acid sequences are closely related. Eg5 
AT
transfers the aromatic acyl group to anthocyanin at position 5, whereas Gt5,3 
′
AT
transfers it at positions 5 and 3’. The homology model indicated the corresponding amino acids between Gt5,3 
′
AT
and Eg5 
AT
. Although these enzymes shared amino acids within the anthocyanin binding pocket, differences were observed at several positions: (Gt5,3 
′
AT
/Eg5 
AT
, “prime” indicates the residue in These results are consistent with our previous observations (

), as well as the structures of anthocyanins that gentian and lisianthus accumulate. These results led us to analyze the chimeric enzymes of Gt5,3 
′
AT
and Eg5 
AT
in subsequent experiments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.4. Analysis of chimeric acyltransferases made of Gt5,3
′
AT
and Eg5 
AT
</title>
         <p>
When delphinidin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucoside and caffeoyl-CoA were utilized as substrates, Gt5,3 
′
AT-catalyzed the synthesis of gentiodelphin (delphinidin 3-glucoside 5-caffeoyl-glucoside 3 
′
-caffeoyl-glucoside) and delphinidin 3-glucoside 5-caffeoyl-glucoside 3 
′
-glucoside (
Fig. 7A
). Eg5 
AT
catalyzed the synthesis of delphinidin 3,3 
′
-diglucoside 5-caffeoyl-glucoside (
Fig. 7D
) and a very small amount of gentiodelphin. Interestingly, Eg5 
AT
was able to catalyze the acylation of 3 
′
-glucoside. This is an unexpected result since lisianthus does not accumulate gentiodelphin but is in agreement with the structural analysis mentioned above. Under the same conditions, a chimeric 
AT
with Gt5,3 
′
AT
at the Nterminal side and Eg5 
AT
at the C-terminal side (GEAT) and a chimeric 
AT
with Eg5 
AT
at the N-terminal side and Gt5,3 
′
AT
at the C-terminal side (EGAT) resulted in gentiodelphin, in addition to delphinidin 3, 3 
′
- diglucoside 5-caffeoyl-glucoside (
Fig. 7B and C
, 
Fig. 8
). The order of the ability of these enzymes to synthesize gentiodelphin was as follows: Gt5,3 
′
AT
&gt;
EGAT
&gt;
GEAT ≓ Eg5 
AT
, although the activities of GEAT and Eg5 
AT
were very low. These results indicate that EGAT has 5,3 
′
AT
activity and that the C-terminal side may be crucial for determining the positions of the glucosides of delphinidin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucoside. Most amino acid differences were found in the C-lobe area in the putative anthocyanin binding pocket, as described in the previous section. Gt5,3 
′
AT
may have evolved from the preceding 5 
AT
by acquiring 3 
′
- 
AT
activity with changing amino acid residues. Additionally, ancestral 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana
</tp:taxon-name>
plants acquired the gene encoding 3 
′
-glucosyltransferase to generate blue gentiodelphin. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gentiana
</tp:taxon-name>
plants are mostly alpine in contrast to the related genera (

), and a blue flower color may be beneficial for attracting pollinators, such as bees, to maintain high genetic diversity in alpine regions (

).
</p>
         <p>
Eg5 
AT
) Asn41/Tyr41 
′
, Met235/Leu234 
′
, Lys242/Gly241 
′
, Arg245/ Gln244 
′
, Asn389/Lys389 
′
, Pro392/Leu392 
′
, Phe396/Leu396 
′
, Thr400/ Ser400 
′
, and Glu429/Gly429’. The hydrophobic amino acids present in the putative anthocyanin-binding pocket (mentioned above) are conserved between Gt5,3 
′
AT
/Eg5 
AT
, and these amino acids are considered to be important for maintaining the backbone structure of the pocket. However, two differences were observed in the hydrogenbonding amino acids. Asn 
389 in
Gt5,3 
′
AT
is Lys389 
′
in Eg5 
AT
. These amino acid residues have an amide or amino group, and may be involved in the formation of alternative hydrogen bonds in each structure. Another difference was Glu429/Gly429’. In the Gt5,3 
′
AT
docking model, the Glu429 residue forms a hydrogen bond and contributes to anthocyanin binding stability, whereas Gly429 
′
showed no contribution to Eg5 
AT
. The docking model studies were performed to elucidate the roles of these residues, and the studies supported this observation. The two positions (Asn389 and Glu429) are involved in interaction with the glucose moiety. Subsequently, the anthocyanin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucoside selectivity for these enzymes is 5
&gt;
3 
′
for Gt5,3 
′
AT
and 5»3 
′
for Eg5 
AT
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Materials and methods
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1. Protein expression and purification for crystallization
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Gt5,3 
′
AT
was cloned into the expression vector pDEST10.1 (Invitrogen/Thermo Fisher Scientific, Beverly, 
USA
) as a fusion with an Nterminal His tag and a TEV protease cleavage site. Gt5,3 
′
AT
was expressed in Sf9 cells using the Bac-to-Bac Baculovirus Expression System (Invitrogen). The C-terminal truncated mutant Gt5,3 
′
AT
(residues 1–465, His174Ala) with an N-terminal SUMO tag was expressed in a cell-free expression system (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Gt5,3 
′
AT
and truncated Gt5,3 
′
AT
were purified by chromatography using a HisTrap column (GE Healthcare 
Japan
, 
Tokyo
), and then subjected to TEV protease and SUMO protease digestion, respectively. The proteins were subsequently purified using anion exchange chromatography (HiTrap Q and MonoQ) and Superdex75 (GE Healthcare 
Japan
) gel filtration chromatography steps. Gt5,3 
′
AT
and truncated Gt5,3 
′
AT
were concentrated in 20 mM Tris-HCl buffer (pH 8.0) containing 150 mM NaCl and 1 mM TCEP, to a final concentration of 3 and 1. 
5 mg
/mL, respectively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.2. Crystallization and data collection
</title>
         <p>
Crystallization was performed using the sitting-drop vapor-diffusion method at 293 K. The drops were composed of 1.0 μL of protein solution and 0.3–0.7 μL of reservoir solution. The crystals of Gt5,3 
′
AT
and truncated Gt5,3 
′
AT
were grown in 0.1 M HEPES buffer (pH 7.5) with 1.1–1.4 M sodium citrate. The crystals of the truncated Gt5,3 
′
AT
were soaked in 1 mM caffeoyl-CoA and 1 mM delphinidin 3,5-diglucoside overnight at 293 K. Data collection was carried out at 100 K with 5% glycerol as a cryoprotectant. The crystal data of Gt5,3 
′
AT
and truncated Gt5,3 
′
AT
were collected at BL17 
A
at the Photon Factory (Tsukuba, 
Japan
) and using beamline X10SA (Swiss Light Source, Villigen, 
Switzerland
), respectively. The diffraction data of Gt5,3 
′
AT
were processed and scaled using the HKL2000 program package (

). The diffraction data of the truncated Gt5,3 
′
AT
were processed using the XDS program package (

) and scaled with the CCP4 program suite (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.3. Structure determination and refinement
</title>
         <p>
All structures were solved by the molecular replacement method with Molrep (MR) in the CCP4 program suite (

). As a search model, the coordinates of the Dm3MAT3 (PDB: 2 
E
1 
U
) (

) were used at the MR for Gt5, 3 
′
AT
. For the truncated Gt5,3 
′
AT
, the structure of Gt5,3 
′
AT
was used as the search model. The model was corrected and further refined by the programs O (

), Coot (

), CNS (

), and Phenix (Adams et al., 2010). The final model was assessed using PROCHECK in the CCP4 program suite (

). Data collection and refinement statistics are summarized in Supplementary 
Table S1
. The ribbon and molecular surface models in the figures were depicted using PyMol (

) and MolFeat (FiatLux). The atomic coordinates and structural factors have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank under the accession numbers 7DEV and 7DEX.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.4. Ligand docking simulations
</title>
         <p>
To investigate the positional selectivity of anthocyanin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucoside for Gt5,3 
′
AT
, docking simulation using the Glide program (

; 

) was performed to predict its binding mode. For the docking preparation, anthocyanin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucoside was ionized at pH 7.0 ± 2.0 by Epik implemented in Ligprep. The crystal structure of Gt5,3 
′
AT
was ionized at pH 7.0, and the hydrogen atoms were optimized by the OPLS3e force field using Protein Preparation Wizard. The receptor grid was then generated with a scaling factor of 1.0. Using the Glide SP mode with expanded sampling option, 202 docking poses were obtained. Considering the accessibility of the 5 or 3 
′
glucose moiety to the catalytic site, 10 docking poses of which either the hydroxyl oxygen in the 5 or 3 
′
glucose moiety came closest to the linker carbon atom of caffeoyl-CoA among all the ligand atoms and positioned within 6 
Å
were selected to assess the positional selectivity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

3.5. Sequence comparisons and homology modeling of 
<tp:taxon-name>Eustoma</tp:taxon-name>
acyltransferase
</title>
         <p>
A
sequence similarity search was conducted using protein-protein 
BLAST
(https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi) against the Protein Data Bank database with the Gt5,3 
′
AT
sequence as a query. Sequence alignments were performed using ClustalW (https://www.genome.jp /tools-bin/clustalw). The homology model was built for the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eustoma
</tp:taxon-name>
hydroxycinnamoyltransferase (hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:anthocyanin 5- glucoside-6’’’-O-hydroxycinnamoyltransferase; GenBANK ID: BAF49288.1; Eg5 
AT
) using Modellar (

) and the standard protocol. The Gt5,3 
′
AT
•caffeoyl-CoA complex structure (this study) was used as the template model. Homology modeling was performed for the Eg5 
AT
sequence from 6 to 465.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.6. Characterization of chimeric acyltransferases derived from Gt5, 3
′
AT

and Eg5 
AT
</title>
         <p>
Two chimeric cDNAs with the Gt5,3 
′
AT
sequence on the 5 side and Eg5 
AT
sequence on the 3 
′
side and vice versa were constructed using the 
Xba
I site located in the middle of both sequences (TCTAGA: Ser237- Arg238). These sequences were cloned into the expression vector pET32c (Novagen, Darmstadt, 
Germany
) and expressed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Escherichia coli
</tp:taxon-name>
. The resultant proteins were designated GEAT and EGAT, respectively. In addition, the Gt5,3 
′
AT
and Eg5 
AT
sequences were expressed for comparison. The crude soluble extracts were obtained by sonication of the cells in 10 mM Tris buffer (pH 8.0) containing 1 mM DTT. The extracts were subjected to Bio-Scale 
<tp:taxon-name>Mini Macro-Prep High Q Cartridge</tp:taxon-name>
(Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, 
USA
), and the fractions containing anthocyanin 
AT
activities were recovered with 10 mM Tris buffer (pH 8.0) containing 500 mM NaCl and 1 mM DTT. They were subjected to an anthocyanin 
AT
assay since further purification was not possible because of the low quantities of the recombinant enzymes in the soluble fractions. The assay mixture consisted of 127 μМ delphinidin 3,5,3 
′
- triglucoside, 400 μМ caffeoyl CoA, and 50 mM Tris buffer (pH 8.0). The crude extract was kept at 30 
◦
C for 30 min and the reaction was terminated by the addition of the same volume of 90% acetonitrile and 0.1% TFA. The supernatants resulting from centrifugation were subjected to reversed-phase HPLC analysis as described previously (

) to measure areas of delphinidin 3,5,3 
′
-triglucosides, delphinidin 3-glucoside 5-caffeoyl-glucoside 3 
′
-glucoside and gentiodelphin. The relative ratio of delphinidin 3-glucoside 5-caffeoyl-glucoside 3 
′
-glucoside to gentiodelphin was adopted to assess the ability of the enzyme to catalyze acylation of 3 
′
-glucoside.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors of this publication received partial financial support from Suntory Global Innovation Center Ltd., according to a collaborative research contract.</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgment
</p>
         <p>We would like to thank Mio Inoue for the plasmid preparation. We acknowledge the technical support of the Biomedical Research Core of Tohoku University Graduate School of Medicine. We also thank the beamline staff at Photon Factory (BL17) and Swiss Light Source (X10SA)</p>
         <p>for their assistance during data collection. We would like to thank Editage (www.editage.com) for English language editing.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Appendix 
A
. Supplementary data

</title>
         <p>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112727.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zwart, P.H.
, 
2010
. 
PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution
. 
Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.
66
, 
213–221
. 
https://doi.org/10.1107/S0907444909052925
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bontpart, T.
, 
Cheynier, V.
, 
Ageorges, A.
, 
Terrier, N.
, 
2015
. 
BAHD or SCPL acyltransferase? What a dilemma for acylation in the world of plant phenolic compounds
. 
New Phytol.
208
, 
695–707
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.13498
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Brunger, A.T.
, 
Adams, P.D.
, 
Clore, G.M.
, 
DeLano, W.L.
, 
Gros, P.
, 
Grosse-Kunstleve, R.W.
, 
Jiang, J.S.
, 
Kuszewski, J.
, 
Nilges, M.
, 
Pannu, N.S.
, 
Read, R.J.
, 
Rice, L.M.
, 
Simonson, T.
, 
Warren, G.L.
, 
1998
. 
Crystallography &amp; NMR system: a new software suite for macromolecular structure determination
. 
Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.
54
, 
905–921
. 
https://doi.org/10.1107/s0907444998003254
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chiang, Y.C.
, 
Levsh, O.
, 
Lam, C.K.
, 
Weng, J.K.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
2018
. 
Structural and dynamic basis of substrate permissiveness in hydroxycinnamoyltransferase (HCT)
. 
PLoS Comput. Biol.
14
, e 
1006511
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006511
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Collaborative Computational Project, N.
, 
1994
. 
The CCP4 suite: programs for protein crystallography
. 
Acta Crystallogr. Sect. D Biol. Crystallogr.
50
, 
760–763
. 
https://doi. org/10.1107/S0907444994003112
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
D’ Auria, J.C.
, 
2006
. 
Acyltransferases in plants: a good time to be BAHD
. 
Curr. Opin. Plant Biol.
9
, 
331–340
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pbi.2006.03.016
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DeLano, W.L.
, 
2002
. 
The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System
. 
http://www.pymol.org
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Emsley, P.
, 
Lohkamp, B.
, 
Scott, W.G.
, 
Cowtan, K.
, 
2010
. 
Features and development of Coot. Acta Crystallogr. Sect
. 
D Biol. Crystallogr.
66
, 
486–501
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1107/S0907444910007493
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eudes, A.
, 
Pereira, J.H.
, 
Yogiswara, S.
, 
Wang, G.
, 
Teixeira Benites, V.
, 
Baidoo, E.E.
, 
Lee, T.S.
, 
Adams, P.D.
, 
Keasling, J.D.
, 
Loque, D.
, 
2016
. 
Exploiting the substrate promiscuity of hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:shikimate hydroxycinnamoyl transferase to reduce lignin
. 
Plant Cell Physiol.
57
, 
568–579
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/pcp/ pcw016
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Favre, A.
, 
Yuan, Y.M.
, 
Kupfer, P.
, 
Alvarez, N.
, 
2010
. 
Phylogeny of subtribe Gentianinae (Gentianaceae): biogeographic inferences despite limitations in temporal calibration points
. 
Taxon
59
, 
1701–1711
. 
https://doi.org/10.2307/41059867
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Friesner, R.A.
, 
Banks, J.L.
, 
Murphy, R.B.
, 
Halgren, T.A.
, 
Klicic, J.J.
, 
Mainz, D.T.
, 
Repasky, M.P.
, 
Knoll, E.H.
, 
Shelley, M.
, 
Perry, J.K.
, 
Shaw, D.E.
, 
Francis, P.
, 
Shenkin, P.S.
, 
2004
. 
Glide: a new approach for rapid, accurate docking and scoring. 1. Method and assessment of docking accuracy
. 
J. Med. Chem.
47
, 
1739–1749
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jm0306430
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fujiwara, H.
, 
Tanaka, Y.
, 
Fukui, Y.
, 
Nakao, M.
, 
Ashikari, T.
, 
Kusumi, T.
, 
1997
. 

Anthocyanin 5-aromatic acyltransferase from 
Gentiana triflora
. Purification, characterization and its role in anthocyanin biosynthesis

. 
Eur. J. Biochem.
249
, 
45–51
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1432-1033.1997.t01-1-00045.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fujiwara, H.
, 
Tanaka, Y.
, 
Yonekura-Sakakibara, K.
, 
Fukuchi-Mizutani, M.
, 
Nakao, M.
, 
Fukui, Y.
, 
Yamaguchi, M.
, 
Ashikari, T.
, 
Kusumi, T.
, 
1998
. 

cDNA cloning, gene expression and subcellular localization of anthocyanin 5-aromatic acyltransferase from 
Gentiana triflora

. 
Plant J.
16
, 
421–431
. 
https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365- 313x.1998.00312.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fukuchi-Mizutani, M.
, 
Okuhara, H.
, 
Fukui, Y.
, 
Nakao, M.
, 
Katsumoto, Y.
, 
Yonekura-Sakakibara, K.
, 
Kusumi, T.
, 
Hase, T.
, 
Tanaka, Y.
, 
2003
. 
Biochemical and molecular characterization of a novel UDP-glucose:anthocyanin 3’-O-glucosyltransferase, a key enzyme for blue anthocyanin biosynthesis, from gentian
. 
Plant Physiol.
132
, 
1652–1663
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Halgren, T.A.
, 
Murphy, R.B.
, 
Friesner, R.A.
, 
Beard, H.S.
, 
Frye, L.L.
, 
Pollard, W.T.
, 
Banks, J.L.
, 
2004
. 
Glide: a new approach for rapid, accurate docking and scoring. 2. Enrichment factors in database screening
. 
J. Med. Chem.
47
, 
1750–1759
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1021/jm030644s
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jones, T.A.
, 
Zou, J.Y.
, 
Cowan, S.W.
, 
Kjeldgaard, M.
, 
1991
. 
Improved methods for building protein models in electron density maps and the location of errors in these models
. 
Acta Crystallogr. A
47
, 
110–119
. 
https://doi.org/10.1107/ s0108767390010224
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kabsch, W.
, 
2010
. 
Xds. Acta Crystallogr. Sect
. 
D Biol. Crystallogr.
66
, 
125–132
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1107/S0907444909047337
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kigawa, T.
, 
Yabuki, T.
, 
Matsuda, N.
, 
Matsuda, T.
, 
Nakajima, R.
, 
Tanaka, A.
, 
Yokoyama, S.
, 
2004
. 

Preparation of 
Escherichia coli
cell extract for highly productive cell-free protein expression

. 
J. Struct. Funct. Genom.
5
, 
63–68
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1023/B:JSFG.0000029204.57846.7d
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lallemand, L.A.
, 
Zubieta, C.
, 
Lee, S.G.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
Acajjaoui, S.
, 
Timmins, J.
, 
McSweeney, S.
, 
Jez, J.M.
, 
McCarthy, J.G.
, 
McCarthy, A.A.
, 
2012
. 
A structural basis for the biosynthesis of the major chlorogenic acids found in coffee
. 
Plant Physiol.
160
, 
249–260
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Levsh, O.
, 
Chiang, Y.C.
, 
Tung, C.F.
, 
Noel, J.P.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
Weng, J.K.
, 
2016
. 
Dynamic conformational states dictate selectivity toward the native substrate in a substratepermissive acyltransferase
. 
Biochemistry
55
, 
6314–6326
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ acs.biochem.6b00887
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ma, X.
, 
Koepke, J.
, 
Panjikar, S.
, 
Fritzsch, G.
, 
Stockigt, J.
, 
2005
. 
Crystal structure of vinorine synthase, the first representative of the BAHD superfamily
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
280
, 
13576–13583
. 
https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M414508200
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Manjasetty, B.A.
, 
Yu, X.H.
, 
Panjikar, S.
, 
Taguchi, G.
, 
Chance, M.R.
, 
Liu, C.J.
, 
2012
. 
Structural basis for modification of flavonol and naphthol glucoconjugates by Nicotiana tabacum malonyltransferase (NtMaT1)
. 
Planta
236
, 
781–793
. 
https://doi. org/10.1007/s00425-012-1660-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Markham, K.R.
, 
Ofman, D.J.
, 
1993
. 
Lisianthus flavonoid pigments and factors influencing their expression in flower colour
. 
Phytochemistry (Oxf.)
34
, 
679–685
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(93)85339-s
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Marti-Renom, M.A.
, 
Stuart, A.C.
, 
Fiser, A.
, 
Sanchez, R.
, 
Melo, F.
, 
Sali, A.
, 
2000
. 
Comparative protein structure modeling of genes and genomes
. 
Annu. Rev. Biophys. Biomol. Struct.
29
, 
291–325
. 
https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.biophys.29.1.291
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mizutani, M.
, 
Katsumoto, Y.
, 
Fukui, Y.
, 
Togami, J.
, 
Nakamura, N.
, 
Okuhara, H.
, 
Tanaka, Y.
, 
2006
. 
An acyl-transferase involved in biosynthesis of polyacylated anthocyanin
. 
Plant Cell Physiol.
47
, S 
198
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mu, J.P.
, 
Li, G.Y.
, 
Niklas, K.J.
, 
Sun, S.C.
, 
2011
. 
Difference in floral traits, pollination, and reproductive success between white and blue flowers of Gentiana leucomelaena (Gentianaceae) in an alpine meadow. Arctic Antarct
. 
Alpine Res.
43
, 
410–416
. 
https://doi.org/10.1657/1938-4246-43.3.410
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Otwinowski, Z.
, 
Minor, W.
, 
1997
. 
Processing of X-ray diffraction data collected in oscillation mode
. 
Methods Enzymol.
276
, 
307–326
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0076- 6879(97)76066-X
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Suzuki, H.
, 
Nakayama, T.
, 
Yamaguchi, M.A.
, 
Nishino, T.
, 
2004
. 
cDNA cloning and characterization of two Dendranthema x morifolium anthocyanin malonyltransferases with different functional activities
. 
Plant Sci.
166
, 
89–96
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/J.PLANTSCI.2003.08.010
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Suzuki, H.
, 
Nakayama, T.
, 
Yonekura-Sakakibara, K.
, 
Fukui, Y.
, 
Nakamura, N.
, 
Nakao, M.
, 
Tanaka, Y.
, 
Yamaguchi, M.A.
, 
Kusumi, T.
, 
Nishino, T.
, 
2001
. 
Malonyl-CoA: anthocyanin 5-O-glucoside-6"’-O-malonyltransferase from scarlet sage (Salvia splendens) flowers. Enzyme purification, gene cloning, expression, and characterization
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
276
, 
49013–49019
. 
https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc. M108444200
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Suzuki, H.
, 
Nakayama, T.
, 
Yonekura-Sakakibara, K.
, 
Fukui, Y.
, 
Nakamura, N.
, 
Yamaguchi, M.A.
, 
Tanaka, Y.
, 
Kusumi, T.
, 
Nishino, T.
, 
2002
. 
cDNA cloning, heterologous expressions, and functional characterization of malonyl-coenzyme a: anthocyanidin 3-o-glucoside-6"-o-malonyltransferase from dahlia flowers
. 
Plant Physiol.
130
, 
2142–2151
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Suzuki, H.
, 
Nishino, T.
, 
Nakayama, T.
, 
2007
. 
Anthocyanin acyltransferase engineered for the synthesis of a novel polyacylated anthocyanin
. 
Plant Biotechnol.
24
, 
495–501
. 
https://doi.org/10.5511/plantbiotechnology.24.495
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tanaka, Y.
, 
Sasaki, N.
, 
Ohmiya, A.
, 
2008
. 
Biosynthesis of plant pigments: anthocyanins, betalains and carotenoids
. 
Plant J.
54
, 
733–749
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365- 313X.2008.03447.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Unno, H.
, 
Ichimaida, F.
, 
Suzuki, H.
, 
Takahashi, S.
, 
Tanaka, Y.
, 
Saito, A.
, 
Nishino, T.
, 
Kusunoki, M.
, 
Nakayama, T.
, 
2007
. 
Structural and mutational studies of anthocyanin malonyltransferases establish the features of BAHD enzyme catalysis
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
282
, 
15812–15822
. 
https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M700638200
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Walker, A.M.
, 
Hayes, R.P.
, 
Youn, B.
, 
Vermerris, W.
, 
Sattler, S.E.
, 
Kang, C.
, 
2013
. 
Elucidation of the structure and reaction mechanism of sorghum hydroxycinnamoyltransferase and its structural relationship to other coenzyme adependent transferases and synthases
. 
Plant Physiol.
162
, 
640–651
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yoshida, K.
, 
Toyama, Y.
, 
Kameda, K.
, 
Kondo, T.
, 
2000
. 
Contribution of each caffeoyl residue of the pigment molecule of gentiodelphin to blue color development
. 
Phytochemistry (Oxf.)
54
, 
85–92
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(00)00049- 2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yu, J.
, 
Zhou, Y.
, 
Tanaka, I.
, 
Yao, M.
, 
2010
. 
Roll: a new algorithm for the detection of protein pockets and cavities with a rolling probe sphere
. 
Bioinformatics
26
, 
46–52
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btp599
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
