<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.112176</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Phytochemical Society of Europe</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>International Symposium</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>International</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>International</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>International</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>International</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
The Phytochemical Society of Europe
</p>
         <p>
The Phytochemical Society of Europe (PSE)
was founded in 1957. Its aim is to promote natural products research by supporting the organization of several international meetings a year. The Society’s main interests are related to the chemistry, functions, biosynthesis, and effects of natural compounds on the physiology and pathology of living organisms and the application of such knowledge in agriculture and industry.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. PSE meetings
</title>
         <p>
During 
19 -22 June 2019
, the PSE Young Scientists Meeting 
Trends in Natural Product Research: On Biochemistry, Molecular Aspects and Pharmacology of Bioactive Natural Products
took place in Budapest, chaired by Prof. Judit Hohmann. The Symposium was organised jointly by the PSE, the University of Szeged, Faculty of Pharmacy and Institute of Pharmacognosy, the Committee on Pharmaceutical Sciences, and the Hungarian Academy of Sciences. The programme of the conference covered different aspects of natural product research, including phytochemistry, molecular biology, phytochemical analysis, bioactivity of natural products, phytotherapy. The aim of the conference was to serve as a forum for discussions on trends, most current topics and latest results of natural product research, and to bring together senior scientists, young researchers, and PhD students from all over the world. The scientific programme included 15 plenary lectures by leading scientists, keynote talks, 33 oral presentations and 37 poster presentations. In this YSM, several young scientists were awarded prizes. The Jeffrey Harborne Prize for the best oral presentation was given to Nóra Gampe, while the 
Phytochemical Analysis
/Wiley prizes went to Johanna Gasser, Agata Rogowska, and Aimond Axelle. In addition, the PSE supported five young scientists with travel bursaries: Gokay Albayrak, Odeta Celaj, Afaf Al Groshi, Shaymaa Al-Majmaie and Marie Pokorná. The PSE/Pierre Fabre Innovation Award 2019 went to Prof. Marc Diederich (
Seoul
, 
South Korea
), who, as always, delivered an inspiring lecture. Further information can be found at: https://ysm2019.weebly.com/.
</p>
         <p>
During 

28 –31 July 2019

the 

Natural Products in Drug Discovery
and 
Health
–NatProDDH

conference was organised in 
Lisbon
, 
Portugal
by 

Prof. 

Maria 
José Umbelino Ferreira.

The Faculty of Pharmacy of the 
University of Lisbon
amassed an exciting group of 
Natural Products
researchers, bringing together 270 senior scientists, young researchers, and PhD students from 37 countries to share their latest advances. 
The
attractive program of 
NatProdDDH
covered the state-of-the-art in natural products research, up to their application as value-added products for human health. 
Through
plenary sessions, lectures, poster presentations and coffee breaks, the participants took advantage of this propitious environment for the generation of innovative ideas, networking, and making new contacts. 
Profs
: 
Francisco A Macias
, 
University of Cadiz
(
Spain
), 
Satyajit Sarker
, 
University
of 
Liverpool
John Moores
(
UK
), 
Simon Gibbons
, University College London (
UK
), 
Virginia Lanzotti
, 
University of Naples Federico
II (
Italy
), 
Robert Verpoorte
, 
University of Leiden
(
The Netherlands
), 
Artur Silva
, 
University
of 
Aveiro
(
Portugal
), 
Franz Bucar
, 
University of Graz
(
Austria
), 
Hermann Stuppner
, 
University of Innsbruck
(
Austria
), 
Giovanni Appendino
, 
University of Eastern
Piedmont
(
Italy
), 
Deniz Tasdemir
, GEOMAR Helmholtz Centre for 
Ocean Research Kiel
(
Germany
), 
Randolph Arroo
, 
University of De Montfort
Leicester
(
UK
). 
Strnad Miroslav
, 
University
of 
Olomouc
(
Czech Republic
), 
Isabel
CFR 
Ferreira
, Polytechnic Institute of 
Bragança
(
Portugal
), 
Jianbo Xiao
, 
University
of 
Macao
(
China
), 
Vassilios Roussis
, 
University of Athens
(
Greece
), 
Emerson F. Queiroz
, University of 
Geneva
(
Switzerland
), 
Wim Dehaen
, 
University of Leuven
(
Belgium
) and 
Thomas Efferth
, 
Johannes Gutenberg University
(
Germany
) were invited speakers. 
Additionally
53 oral communications were delivered and 165 posters were presented. 
Five
PSE travel grants were awarded to: 
Taofiq Oludemi
(
Portugal
), 
Daniela Correia da Silva
(
Portugal
), 
Vera de Macedo Ribeiro
(
Portugal
), 
Amruta Deshpande
(
Ireland
) and Diana Patricia Rey Padilla (
Colombia
). 
The Wiley
prizes were given to 
Elisa Bonandi
(
Italy
) and 
Joao Dutra-Gomes
(
Brazil
). Further information can be obtained at: (https://www.ff.ul.pt/pselisbonmeeting2019/).
</p>
         <p>An attractive programme of conferences is planned for 2020 and further information can be found at the PSE website: www. phytochemicalsociety.org</p>
         <p>
Natural products for Healthy Living

will be held during 


16 -18 January 
2020

in 
Khulna
, 
Bangladesh
. Prof. Jamil Shilpi will organize the symposium. 
The
organizing committee is very active trying to attract numbers of high level specialists as lecturers to talk to this interesting topic. 
Additionally
a trip to the 
Sundarbans forest
is planned. 
This
is the largest stretch of mangrove forest in the world with a diverse 
type
of flora and fauna, including rare tigers. More information can be found at https://psenpss2020.wixsite.com/khulana

.
</p>
         <p>

The 
T

20 PSE Conference is an innovative concept; with 20 oral presentations of 20 minutes each and 20 three-minute short oral presentations. This will be held at the University of 
Liverpool
John Moores, 
UK
on 

6 March 2020

and is being organized by Prof. Satyajit Sarker

.
</p>
         <p>The conference will be limited to 60-70 participants (on a first come first serve basis) with free registration, free tea-coffee and lunch. All details will be available at https://ysm2018.wixsite.com/t20liverpool.</p>
         <p>
The
next in the series 

<tp:taxon-name>International Symposium</tp:taxon-name>
on 
Phytochemicals in Medicine
and 
Food
(ISPMF)

will be organized jointly by the 
<tp:taxon-name>International</tp:taxon-name>
Association of Dietetic Nutrition
and 
Safety
(IADNS), the 
Phytochemical Society of Europe
(PSE), and the 
Phytochemical Society of Asia
(PSA) under the chairmanship of Prof. Jianbo Xiao (
University
of 
Macao
, 
China
). 
This
time the 4-ISPMF will take place in the beautiful city of 
Xi’an
, during 

25 – 30 June 2020

Xi’an is the capital of 
Shaanxi Province
, 
China
and it is one of the oldest cities in 
China
. It has held the position under several of the most important dynasties in Chinese history and is the location of the famous terracotta army. All abstracts will be published in a conference proceeding of 
eFood
. Ten awards will be given for best oral and poster presentations by young scientists (under 35 years old) (5 awards for poster and 5 awards for oral presentation). Each winner will be awarded US$ 
250 in
cash and a certification provided by 
<tp:taxon-name>International</tp:taxon-name>
Association of Food Nutrition
and Safety. Journal special issues are planned to be published in 
Food Chemistry
(Elsevier), 
Marine Drugs
(MDPI), and 
Pharmacological Research
(Elsevier). For more information please see https://381313990.wixsite.com/4-ispmf
</p>
         <p>
The next PSE Young Scientists Meeting 
Trends in Natural Product Research
will be held in Kolymbari, 
Crete
during 
12 – 15 July 2020
, and is organized by Dr. Efstathia Ioannou and Prof. Vassilios Roussis. The meeting will take the regular format of a combination of thought-provoking lectures from senior scientist and providing a forum for junior scientists to present their ongoing research. For further information please see http://phytochemicalsociety.org/?tribe_events=trends-innatural-product-research-pse-young-scientists-meeting-2
</p>
         <p>
The twelfth 

<tp:taxon-name>International</tp:taxon-name>
Congress on Natural Products Research 2020

is a Joint Meeting organized between the GA, ASP, AFERP, JSP, PSE and SIF every 5 years. In 2020, this will take place during 

25 - 30 July 
2020

in San Francisco, 
USA
. All details can be found at http:// icnpr2020.org/
</p>
         <p>

A conference on 

Isoprenoids

is planned to be held in 
Karaganda
, 
Republic of Kazakhstan
during the 

9 – 11 September 2020

. Further details will be made available on the PSE website in in the updated PSE page in due course

.
</p>
         <p>
Phytochemicals in Nutrition and Health: Advances and Challenges,
the second congress on this topic, will take place in Bari, 
Italy
during 
22 – 25 September 2020
. Further details will be made available on the PSE website in in the updated PSE page in due course. Researchers interested in attending can obtain further information at http://phytochemicalsociety. org/?tribe_events=phytochemicals-in-nutrition-and-health
</p>
         <p>Ideas on topics of future meetings can be e-mailed to the President of the PSE, Prof. Satyajit Sarker (profsarker@gmail.com)</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. PSE – Pierre Fabre Award
</title>
         <p>
Pierre Fabre is the 2 
nd
largest private French pharmaceutical group and the 2 
nd
largest dermo-cosmetics laboratory in the world. From its very beginning, Pierre Fabre Laboratories have always explored and used plants as they are truly convinced of their great potential for health and beauty. For more information you are invited to visit their website at http://www.pierre-fabre.com
</p>
         <p>
Candidatures are invited for the 
Phytochemical Society of Europe-Pierre Fabre Research Institute Joint Prize
to be given in 2020. The prize of 3000€ will be awarded to the candidature considered to have made an exceptionally significant contribution to innovative research in phytochemistry.
</p>
         <p>
Applicants for the 2020 PSE-PF Prize are invited to submit their application before 
31 December 2019
directly to the PSE President (profsarker@gmail.com). The application should include:
</p>
         <p>– a short CV</p>
         <p>– a summary (2-4 pages) highlighting the candidate’s cutting edge research in phytochemistry</p>
         <p>– letters of support from two or three independent referees</p>
         <p>
For further information on the application, visit the PSE website http://phytochemicalsociety.org/?page_id=11976 The call is opened to any scientist from PhD to skilled researcher. The awardee will be invited to deliver an oral presentation during The 12th 
<tp:taxon-name>International</tp:taxon-name>
Congress on Natural Products Research (ICNPR), to be held 
July 25 - July 30, 2020
at the Hyatt Regency – San Francisco.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. The Phytochemical Society of Europe
</title>
         <p>In order to advance phytochemical research, the PSE undertakes a number of activities:</p>
         <p>
• Organization of several scientific meetings each year and publication of the proceedings in the peer-reviewed journal 
Phytochemistry Reviews
’.
</p>
         <p>• The PSE–Bruker Prize, awarded annually to an outstanding phytochemist.</p>
         <p>• The Jeffrey Harborne Prize, given to a young scientist in recognition of an outstanding oral and/or poster presentation at a PSE Young Scientists’ Meeting.</p>
         <p>• The Pierre Fabre Innovation Award in recognition of an exceptionally significant contribution to innovative research in phytochemistry.</p>
         <p>• The provision of Travel Bursaries for young scientists to enable them to present their research at PSE meetings.</p>
         <p>
Benefits of PSE membership
</p>
         <p>Membership of the PSE is worldwide and open to anyone with an interest in plant natural products and related fields. Members benefit from:</p>
         <p>• Reduced registration fees for PSE meetings.</p>
         <p>• Regular mailing and/or e-mailing of information.</p>
         <p>• Up-to-date information on the PSE website.</p>
         <p>
• Reduced subscription rates for the journals 
Phytochemistry
, 
Phytochemistry Letters
and 
Phytochemistry Reviews
. Reduced prices are available to members for some books from Publishers associated with these journals.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Contact with the PSE
</title>
         <p>For details of membership, consult the PSE homepage at http:// www.phytochemicalsociety.org or send an email to the Membership Secretary Professor Pinarosa Avato at pinarosa.avato@uniba.it</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. PLEASE!
</title>
         <p>All PSE members wishing to receive regular information on PSE events need to send their valid e-mail address to Professor Pinarosa Avato at the membership email address of pinarosa.avato@uniba.it Postal mailings from the PSE have ceased.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
6. Officers of the PSE (2019-2020)
</title>
         <p>President: Professor Satyajit Sarker</p>
         <p>
Vice-President (outgoing): Professor 
Virginia
Lanzotti Vice-President (incoming): Professor Franz Bucar
</p>
         <p>Treasurer: Dr. Kenneth Ritchie</p>
         <p>General Secretary: Professor Krystyna Skalicka-Woźniak Membership Secretary: Professor Pinarosa Avato</p>
         <p>Meetings Secretary: Dr. Efstathia Ioannou</p>
         <p>Web Editor: Professor Randolph Arroo</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
7. Trustees of the PSE
</title>
         <p>
Dr. Angela Stafford (
Sheffield
, 
UK
)
</p>
         <p>
Dr. Richard Robins (Nantes, 
France
)
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
