<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113516</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Gagones A-F: Six prenylated chalcones from the heartwood of Mansonia gagei</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
J.R.Drumm.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Malvaceae Prenylated</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
J.R.Drumm. (Malvaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
J.R.Drumm. (Malvaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M. gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Gagones A–F: Six prenylated chalcones from the heartwood of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Huong Thi Thu Le

a, 
*
, Lam H. Nguyen
b
, Tuan H. Nguyen
c
, Van-Kieu Nguyen
d, e
, Ade Danova
f
,
Thanh N. Truong 
g
, Warinthorn Chavasiri
h, **
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Department of Chemistry
, 
Ho Chi Minh City
University of Education
, 280 An Duong Vuong Street, District 5, 
Ho Chi Minh City
, 700000, 
Viet Nam
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b

Institute for Computational Science and 
Technology
, 
Ho Chi Minh City
, 700000, 
Viet Nam
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c
Faculty of Chemical Engineering
, 
Ho Chi Minh City
University of Technology
, 268 Ly Thuong Kiet Street, District 10, 
Ho Chi Minh City
, 700000, 
Viet Nam
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
d
Institute of Fundamental
and 
Applied Sciences
, 
Duy Tan University
, 
Ho Chi Minh City
, 700000, 
Viet Nam
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
e
Faculty of Natural Sciences
, 
Duy Tan University
, 
Da Nang
, 550000, 
Viet Nam
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
f
Organic Chemistry Division
, 
Faculty of Mathematics
and 
Natural Sciences, Bandung Institute of Technology
, JI. 
Ganesha
10, 
Bandung
, 
West Java
, 40132, 
Indonesia
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
g
Department of Chemistry
, 
University
of 
Utah
, 
Salt Lake City
, UT, 84112, 
USA
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
h
Center of Excellence
in 
Natural Products Chemistry
, 
Department of Chemistry
, 
Faculty of Science
, 
Chulalongkorn University
, 
Pathumwan
, 
Bangkok
, 10330, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
J.R.Drumm.
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Malvaceae Prenylated</tp:taxon-name>
chalcones
</p>
         <p>Calculated NMR and ECD</p>
         <p>Antioxidant</p>
         <p>α- Glucosidase inhibitory activity</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Six undescribed prenylated chalcones gagones A–F were isolated from the acetone fraction of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
heartwood. Their structures were unambiguously established based on spectroscopic analysis (HRESIMS, 1D and 2D NMR), as well as comparison to literature data. Their absolute configurations were elucidated using DP4 and electronic circular dichroism calculations. Isolated compounds were evaluated for their inhibitory activity against α- glucosidase and DPPH assay. All of the tested compounds exhibited better activity than that of acarbose (IC 
50
93.6 ± 0.5 μM). Among them, gagone D exhibited the highest α- glucosidase inhibitory with the IC 
50
value of 3.6 ± 0.4 μM. For antioxidant activity, gagones A–C, and E showed more active than that of ascorbic acid (IC 
50
30.2 ± 0.5 μM) with the IC 
50
values of 13.2 ± 0.7, 20.1 ± 0.4, 19.3 ± 0.5 and 12.8 ± 0.2 μM, respectively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Type
2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) is a chronic disease defined by insulin resistance and high levels of sugar in the blood (

). T2DM consists of around 90% of diabetes cases (

). The World Health Organization (WHO) Global report on diabetes reveals that the number of adults suffering from diabetes had nearly fourfold since 1980 to 422 million adults, and it is predicted to reach 693 million by 2045 (

). To treat T2DM, a variety of different 
types
of diabetes drugs has been used such as acarbose, miglitol and voglibose. However, these drugs cause some side effects namely diarrhoea, gas and upset stomach (

; 

). Thus, the search for new potent α- glucosidase inhibitors from plants is necessary.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
J.R.Drumm. (Malvaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
is a medium-sized tree belonging to the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia
</tp:taxon-name>
genus that comprises 5 species found in tropical countries, such as 
Myanmar
and 
Thailand
(

). In the past two decades, a variety of mansonones and mansorins have been isolated and characterised from chloroform fractions of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
that present various bioactivities such as anticancer (

), antibacterial (

) and anti-melanogenesis (

).
</p>
         <p>
Our current study showed that the acetone fraction exhibited excellent activity against α- glucosidase inhibitory activity, with 93.1% inhibition at 7.81 μg/mL, in comparison with acarbose (5.7%). After bioactivity screening, separation was carried out, and six unprecedented prenylated chalcones (
1–6
) were isolated from the acetone fraction of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
heartwood (
Fig. 1
). All prenylated chalcones were separated for the first time from nature. The isolation, structural elucidation and evaluation of α- glucosidase inhibitory and antioxidant activities are described here.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Structural elucidation
</title>
         <p>
Gagone A (1) was isolated as a yellow amorphous powder. The (+)-HRESIMS spectrum depicted a protonated ion [M + H] 
+
at m/z 441.1910 (calcd for C 
25
H 
29
O 
7
, 441.1913), which was assigned to a molecular formula of C 
25
H 
28
O 
7
with 12 double-bond equivalents. The 
1
H NMR spectrum (
Table 1
) shows the presence of one olefinic proton at 
δ
H
7.64 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.5, H-7), three aromatic protons at 6.63 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.0 Hz, H-2), 6.61 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.0 Hz, H-6), and 6.56 (1H, s, H-3 
′
), a methoxy at 
δ
H
3.83 (3H, s), three methine protons, one methylene and four methyl groups. The 
13
C NMR, in accordance with the HSQC spectrum of 1, suggested the presence of 25 carbons consisting of two carbonyls (
δ
C
191.3 and 180.2), one methoxy (
δ
C
56.7), four methyls (
δ
C
22.6, 21.2, 20.3 and 17.2), seven methines (
δ
C
138.8, 119.4, 112.0, 107.1, 46.6, 37.7 and 29.5), ten quaternary carbons (
δ
C
161.4, 149.4, 146.4, 145.7, 141.7, 136.7, 133.1, 130.8, 128.1 and 125.9) and one methylene carbon (
δ
C
32.5).
</p>
         <p>
The planar structure of 1 was determined by a detailed analysis of its 2D NMR spectra, including correlation spectroscopy (
1
H– 
1
H COSY) and HMBC data (
Fig. 2
). The appearance of a 1,3,4,5-substituted aromatic ring (A-ring) was identified by HMBC correlations from H-2 (
δ
H
6.63) and H-6 (
δ
H
6.61) to C-1 (
δ
C
128.1), C-4 (
δ
C
136.7) and C-7 (
δ
C
138.8). In addition, the HMBC correlations of H-7 (
δ
H
7.64) to C-2 (
δ
C
112.0) and C- 6 (
δ
C
107.1) accommodated 1,3,4,5-substituted on ring A in the following order: a methine, hydroxy, hydroxy and methoxy, respectively, further supported by the HMBC correlation between methoxy protons at 
δ
H
3.83 to C-5 (
δ
C
149.4).
</p>
         <p>
Moreover, an isopropyl moiety located at C-5 
′
determined based on the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY spectrum that allowed spin system identified of H 
3
-9 
′
/ H-8 
′
/H 
3
-10 
′
, further suggested by the HMBC correlation of methine proton H-8 
′
(
δ
H
3.39), along with two methyl H 
3
-9 
′
(
δ
H
1.41) and H 
3
-10 
′
(
δ
H
1.31) to C-5 
′
(
δ
C
130.8). Furthermore, the HMBC correlations of methyl proton H 
3
-7 
′
(
δ
H
2.42) to C-1 
′
(
δ
C
125.9), C-2 
′
(
δ
C
141.7) and C-3 
′
(
δ
C
119.4); of methine proton H-8 
′
(
δ
H
3.39) to C-4 
′
(
δ
C
161.4), C-5 
′
(
δ
C
130.8) and C-6 
′
(
δ
C
145.7) determined the occurrence of a pentasubstituted aromatic ring moiety (B-ring). Additionally, the HMBC correlations of H 
2
-1" (
δ
H
3.33, 2.75) to C-7 (
δ
C
138.8), C-8 (
δ
C
133.1), C-9 (
δ
C
191.3), C-6 
′
(
δ
C
145.7) and C-2" (
δ
C
37.7); H-2" (
δ
H
3.66) to C-8, C-1 
′
(
δ
C
125.9), C-6 
′
and C-1" (
δ
C
32.5); H 
3
-5"(
δ
H
0.92) to C-2", C-3"(
δ
C
46.6) and C-4" (
δ
C
180.2) indicated the presence of a cyclohexanone ring with a 1- carboxyethyl moiety at C-2", further backed up by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY spectrum allowing the spin system as H 
2
-1"/H-2"/H-3"/H 
3
-5". Finally, the geometric double bond at Δ 

7
in

1 was determined to be 
E
by the key NOESY correlation between H-6 and H-1" (
Fig. 3
). Thus, the planar structure of 1 was fully established.
</p>
         <p>
For the relative configuration, the NOESY spectrum exhibited the presence of the correlations between H-2"/H-3" instead of H-2"/H 
3
-5" suggesting the 
cis
orientation of these protons similar to those of pestaphthalides A and B (

) and allowing the determination of two candidate enantiomers of 1, being (2" 
S
,3" 
S
)-1a or (2" 
R
,3" 
R
)-1 b, which were recognised through the calculated ECD spectrum. The absolute configuration of 1 was inferred by comparison between both predicted spectra with the experimental one, which showed an excellent fit for a (2" 
S
,3" 
S
)-1a (
Fig. 4
). Therefore, 1 was assumed to be (7 E,2" 
S
, 3" 
S
)-gagone A bearing an unprecedented 2-benzylidene-1-tetralone moiety similar to some synthetic compounds (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Gagones B and C (2–3) showed the common molecular formula of C 
25
H 
28
O 
7
, determined by HRESIMS, with 12 degrees of unsaturation similar to those of 1. The high similarity of their UV–vis spectra and the doubled resonances in the 1D NMR spectra (
Tables 1
and 
2
), especially in the 
13
C NMR spectra of 2–3, implied that they share the same skeletons.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 2 was obtained as a yellow amorphous powder. Despite their closely related molecular formulas, the examination of the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra revealed some important structural differences with compound 1, including the occurrences of an oxymethine proton at 
δ
H
5.57 (1H, s, H-7) and one carbonyl carbon (
δ
C
215.4) instead of an olefinic proton (
δ
H
7.64, in 1) and carboxyl carbon (
δ
C
180.2, in 1), respectively, which recommended the formation of C-8-C-4" linkage of bicyclo [3.2.1]octane moiety, further suggested by the HMBC correlations of oxymethine proton H-7 (
δ
H
5.57) to C-8 (
δ
C
77.1), C-9 (
δ
C
193.0) and C-4" (
δ
C
215.4). Thus, the planar structure of 2 was elucidated as an unprecedented compound that contained bicyclo [3.2.1]octane unit occurring in both natural and synthetic compounds (

; 

; 

; 

). The key 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HMBC, correlations of 1 and 2 are summarised in 
Fig. 2
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Data were extracted from HMBC spectrum.

</p>
         <p>
Gagone C (3) was obtained as a pale yellow amorphous powder. Similarly to 2, it was also constructed from a bicyclo [3.2.1]octane unit. However, methyl protons were shifted upfield to 
δ
H
0.71 (H 
3
-5") in comparison to those of 2, suggesting that 3 was a diastereomer of 2 with the opposite configuration at C-3".
</p>
         <p>
The positive-ion HRESIMS, with the ions [M + Na] 
+
at m/z 477.1921 (calcd for C 
26
H 
30
O 
7
Na, 477.1889, compound 4), at m/z 477.1918 (calcd for C 
26
H 
30
O 
7
Na, 477.1889, compound 5) and m/z 491.2049 (calcd for C 
27
H 
30
O 
7
Na, 491.2046, compound 6) showed that these isolates can be considered as a pair of isomers for 4 and 5 (C 
26
H 
30
O 
7
) and as a homologous series for 4 and 6 (C 
26
H 
30
O 
7
, C 
27
H 
30
O 
7
, respectively). The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of 4 and 6 were also close to those of 2, with the significant differences being the appearance of a methoxy signal at 
δ
H
3.18 (3H, s, 7-OCH 
3
, 
δ
C
57.8) in 4 and an ethoxy signal at [
δ
H
1.08 (3H, t, 
J
= 7.0 Hz), and 
δ
H
3.38 (2H, m), 
δ
C
15.6 and 65.5, respectively] in 6, which could be located at C-7 based on the HMBC correlations of methoxy proton (
δ
H
3.18, 4) and oxygenated methylene proton (
δ
H
3.38, 6) to C-7 (
δ
C
81.1 and 79.1, respectively). Likewise, the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data of 5 were highly similar (
Tables 1
and 
2
) to those of 3 with the addition of a methoxy moiety [
δ
H
3.26 and 
δ
C
57.6 (7-OCH 
3
)] located at C-7, further confirmed by the HMBC correlations of methoxy proton at (
δ
H
3.26) to C-7 (
δ
C
81.8) (Fig. S31, Fig. S40 and Fig. S48 Supporting Information). Altogether, 4 and 6 were elucidated as methoxylated and ethoxylated from 2, whereas 5 was methoxylated from 3.
</p>
         <p>
Compounds 2–6 have no Cotton effects in the ECD spectrum, suggesting that these compounds were obtained as racemic compounds. The NOESY correlations between H 
2
-1"/H 
3
-5" in 2 indicated 
syn
-orientation of these protons. In contrast, 
anti
-orientation was identified in 3 further backed up by the lack of the NOESY correlations between H 
2
-1" and H 
3
- 5". In addition, DP4 calculations were applied to establish the relative stereochemistry of 2 and 3. As a result, DP4 calculation indicated the structural equivalence of stereoisomer 2"* 
S
,3"* 
R
,7* 
S
,8* 
S
of 2 with 97.6% probability and 2"* 
S
,3"* 
S
,7* 
S
,8* 
S
of 3 with 100% probability (Tables S7 and S8).
</p>
         <p>
The unusual structures of compounds 1–6 motivated us to study their plausible biosynthesis pathway (
Fig. 5
). First, thymol (I) was obtained from geranyl diphosphate (

), and this precursor is transformed into Ia through ethylation and oxidation processes. Intermediate II could be formed by the Claisen–Schmidt condensation reaction between ketone Ia and gallic aldehyde. Then, dimethylallyl pyrophosphate could become an electrophile to attack the double bond of II, followed by loss of proton and then cyclisation to create intermediate IIIa. After that, 1 could be constructed from aromatisation, hydration, oxidation and methylation. Finally, the nucleophilic intramolecular addition of 1 afforded 2 and 3, which underwent methylation or ethylation to produce 4–6.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Biological evaluation
</title>
         <p>
Selected compounds (1–5) were evaluated for α- glucosidase inhibitory activity in vitro. Interestingly, all of the tested compounds revealed not only excellent activity with an IC 
50
value of 3.6–33.4 μM, but also better activity than the positive control, acarbose (IC 
50
93.6 ± 0.5). Among them, 4 and 5 showed the highest inhibitory effect on α- glucosidase with IC 
50
values of 3.6 ± 0.4 and 4.3 ± 0.04 μM, respectively, (
Table 3
). For antioxidant activities of compounds 1–3 and 5–6 evaluating using the DPPH radical scavenging assay with ascorbic acid as the positive control (IC 
50
30.2 ± 0.5), 1, 2, 3 and 5 illustrated stronger antioxidant activity than the positive control with the IC 
50
values of 13.2 ± 0.7, 20.1 ± 0.4, 19.3 ± 0.5 and 12.8 ± 0.2 μM (
Table 3
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
In conclusion, six undescribed prenylated chalcones with two unprecedented 2-benzylidene-1-tetralone and bicyclo [3.2.1]octane scaffolds were isolated from the heartwood of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
. Interestingly, 2–6 were found as five pairs of enantiomers. In addition, all tested compounds showed potent inhibitory activity against the α- glucosidase from the yeast and antioxidant activity. Among them, 5 not only possessed strong activity against the α- glucosidase with an IC 
50
of 4.3 ± 0.04 μM but also potential antioxidant activity with an IC 
50
of 12.8 ± 0.2 μM.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General methods
</title>
         <p>
The chromatographic materials and instruments were the same as those previously published (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>

The heartwood of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mansonia gagei
J.R.Drumm. (Malvaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
was collected in 

January 2019

from 
Muak Lek district
, 
Saraburi province
, 
Thailand
(

14 
◦
26 
′
27.8"N

, 

101 
◦
22 
′
22.4"E

). 
The
identity of this plant was compared with voucher specimen No. 43281 at the herbarium of the 
Royal Forestry Department
of Thailand. A voucher for the actual plant was assigned with the code (CUCHEM, 2022–01) and is deposited at the 
Department of Chemistry
, 
Faculty of Science
, 
Chulalongkorn University

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The dried milled heartwood of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. gagei
</tp:taxon-name>
(15.0 kg) was extracted three times with ethyl acetate (3 × 40 L) at room temperature. The crude EtOAc extract (750.0 g) was fractionated by a silica gel quick column (No. 7729, Merck) using n-hexane-EtOAc (from 85:15 to 0:100, v/v), and acetone as the eluent resulted in five fractions HE1–HE3, EA, Ac. Fraction Ac (
150.2 g
) was fractionated using silica gel CC with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH of increasing polarity to give four fractions Ac1–Ac4. Fraction Ac2 (
9.1 g
) was chromatographed on a Sephadex LH-20 column with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (1:1) to obtain three subfractions Ac2.1–Ac2.3. Subfraction Ac2.2 was further purified by RP-18 CC and eluted with MeOH–H 
2
O (2:1) to get 4 (
41 mg
), 5 (
10 mg
) and 6 (
6 mg
). Fraction Ac3 (
22.5 g
), Ac4 (25.0 g) were separated on silica gel CC with n-hexane/ 
CH
2
Cl 
2
/acetone (5:3:2) to get six subfractions Ac3.1–Ac3.3, Ac4.1–Ac4.3, respectively. Subfraction Ac3.3 was subjected to a Sephadex LH-20 with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (1:1), and then an RP-18 CC, eluted with MeOH–H 
2
O (2:1) to give 2 (
30 mg
), and 3 (
25 mg
). Subfraction Ac4.2 was subjected to silica gel CC eluted with a solvent system nhexane-CH 
2
Cl 
2
-EtOAc-MeOH (1:2:1:0.2) yield 1 (
8 mg
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
-1
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Gagone A (1)
</title>
         <p>
Yellow amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
20
+ 98 (
c
0.4, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 209 (4.36), 298 (2.56) nm; ECD (MeOH) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 273 (7.79), 344 (2.42) nm; IR 
vmax
3268, 2926, 1684, 1587, 1514, 1449, 
1089 cm
-1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 441.1910, [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
25
H 
29
O 
7
, 441.1913).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Gagone B (2)
</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
20
+ 2 (
c
1.0, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 207 (4.36), 241 (3.89), 302 (3.82) nm; IR 
vmax
3331, 2960,
</p>
         <p>
2922, 1733, 1648, 1588, 1520, 1449, 1358, 
1178 cm
-1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 463.1740, [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
25
H 
28
O 
7
Na, 463.1733).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. Gagone C (3)
</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
20
+ 3 (
c
0.7, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 207 (4.25), 241 (3.86), 302 (3.80) nm; IR 
vmax
3378, 2927, 1732, 1588, 1517, 
1450 cm
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 463.1735, [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
25
H 
28
O 
7
Na, 463.1733).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.4. Gagone D (4)
</title>
         <p>
Yellowish amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
20
+ 3 (
c
0.2, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 207 (4.19), 239 (3.12) nm; IR 
vmax
3358, 2932, 1735, 1588, 1518, 1449, 
1090 cm
-1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 477.1921, [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
26
H 
30
O 
7
Na, 477.1889).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.5. Gagone E (5)
</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
20
+ 3 (
c
1.0, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 207 (4.18), 240 (3.02) nm; IR 
vmax
3389, 2967, 1737, 1588, 1450, 
1361 cm
-1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 477.1918, [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
26
H 
30
O 
7
Na, 477.1889).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.6. Gagone F (6)
</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
20
+ 3 (
c
0.7, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 207 (4.20), 240 (3.36) nm; IR 
vmax
3357, 2969, 2935, 1739, 1660, 1588, 1449, 1359, 
1088 cm
-1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 491.2049, [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
27
H 
32
O 
7
Na, 491.2046).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Computational details
</title>
         <p>
The structures were fully optimised in methanol by using the PCM model at the DFT/B3LYP/6–31++ G (d,p) level in the Gaussian 16 package (

). The DP4 calculation to compare the NMR results between experimental and computational values of 2 and 3 is from 

with an open source available at https://www-jmg.ch.cam.ac.uk/tools/nmr/DP4/. The methanol solvent is also used to perform ECD spectroscopy for compound 1 at the CAM-B3LYP/TZVP level of theory (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Biological assays
</title>
         <p>
The α- glucosidase inhibition assay was performed according to previous protocols (

), and the DPPH assay followed the method described in the literature (Rankovic´et al., 2012). Experiments were performed in triplicate. The results were described as the mean ± SD of three independent experiments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Data availability
</p>
         <p>The data that has been used is confidential.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
This work was financially supported by a scholarship from the Graduate School, Chulalongkorn University to commemorate the 100th anniversary of Chulalongkorn University. In addition, we are also indebted for support from the 
Thailand
Research Fund via Directed Basic Research Grant (Grant no. DBG6180029). Authors thank the University of Utah Center and Institute for Computational Science and Technology for High Performance Computing for computing resources.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113516.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
References
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Artasensi, A.
, 
Pedretti, A.
, 
Vistoli, G.
, 
Fumagalli, L.
, 
2020
. 
Type 2 diabetes mellitus: a review of multi-target drugs
. 
Molecules
25
, 
1987
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ molecules25081987
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Baghdadi, M.A.
, 
Al-Abbasi, F.A.
, 
El-Halawany, A.M.
, 
Aseeri, A.H.
, 
Al-Abd, A.M.
, 
2018
. 

Anticancer profiling for coumarins and related 
O
-naphthoquinones from 
Mansonia gagei
against solid tumor cells in vitro

. 
Molecules
23
, 
1020
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.3390/molecules23051020
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ding, G.
, 
Liu, S.
, 
Guo, L.
, 
Zhou, Y.
, 
Che, Y.
, 
2008
. 
Antifungal metabolites from the plant endophytic fungus Pestalotiopsis foedan
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
71
, 
615–618
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/np070590f
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Frisch, M.J.
, 
Trucks, G.W.
, 
Schlegel, H.B.
, 
Scuseria, G.E.
, 
Robb, M.A.
, 
Cheeseman, J.R.
, 
Scalmani, G.
, 
Barone, V.
, 
Petersson, G.A.
, 
Nakatsuji, H.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Caricato, M.
, 
Marenich, A.V.
, 
Bloino, J.
, 
Janesko, B.G.
, 
Gomperts, R.
, 
Mennucci, B.
, 
Hratchian, H. P.
, 
Ortiz, J.V.
, 
Izmaylov, A.F.
, 
Sonnenberg, J.L.
, 
Williams Ding, F.
, 
Lipparini, F.
, 
Egidi, F.
, 
Goings, J.
, 
Peng, B.
, 
Petrone, A.
, 
Henderson, T.
, 
Ranasinghe, D.
, 
Zakrzewski, V.G.
, 
Gao, J.
, 
Rega, N.
, 
Zheng, G.
, 
Liang, W.
, 
Hada, M.
, 
Ehara, M.
, 
Toyota, K.
, 
Fukuda, R.
, 
Hasegawa, J.
, 
Ishida, M.
, 
Nakajima, T.
, 
Honda, Y.
, 
Kitao, O.
, 
Nakai, H.
, 
Vreven, T.
, 
Throssell, K.
, 
Montgomery Jr., J.A.
, 
Peralta, J.E.
, 
Ogliaro, F.
, 
Bearpark, M.J.
, 
Heyd, J.J.
, 
Brothers, E.N.
, 
Kudin, K.N.
, 
Staroverov, V.N.
, 
Keith, T.A.
, 
Kobayashi, R.
, 
Normand, J.
, 
Raghavachari, K.
, 
Rendell, A.P.
, 
Burant, J.C.
, 
Iyengar, S. S.
, 
Tomasi, J.
, 
Cossi, M.
, 
Millam, J.M.
, 
Klene, M.
, 
Adamo, C.
, 
Cammi, R.
, 
Ochterski, J. W.
, 
Martin, R.L.
, 
Morokuma, K.
, 
Farkas, O.
, 
Foresman, J.B.
, 
Fox, D.J.
, 
2016
. 
Gaussian 16
. Rev. C.01, 
Wallingford, CT
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Howarth, A.
, 
Ermanis, K.
, 
Goodman, J.M.
, 
2020
. 
DP4-AI automated NMR data analysis: straight from spectrometer to structure
. 
Chem. Sci.
11
, 
4351–4359
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1039/D0SC00442A
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ismail, T.S.E.S.
, 
Deshmukh, S.A.
, 
2012
. 
Comparative study of effect of alpha glucosidase inhibitors–miglitol, acarbose and voglibose on postprandial hyperglycemia and glycosylated hemoglobin in type-2 diabetes mellitus
. 
Diabetes
7
, 8.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Kaysser, L.
, 
Bernhardt, P.
, 
Nam, S.-J.
, 
Loesgen, S.
, 
Ruby, J.G.
, 
Skewes-Cox, P.
, 
Jensen, P. R.
, 
Fenical, W.
, 
Moore, B.S.
, 
2012
. 
Merochlorins A–D, cyclic meroterpenoid antibiotics biosynthesized in divergent pathways with vanadium-dependent chloroperoxidases
. 
J. Am. Chem. Soc.
134
, 
11988–11991
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ ja305665f
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Krause, S.T.
, 
Liao, P.
, 
Crocoll, C.
, 
Boachon, B.
, Forster ¨, C., 
Leidecker, F.
, 
Wiese, N.
, 
Zhao, D.
, 
Wood, J.C.
, 
Buell, C.R.
, 
2021
. 
The biosynthesis of thymol, carvacrol, and thymohydroquinone in Lamiaceae proceeds via cytochrome P450s and a short-chain dehydrogenase
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA
118
, e 
2110092118
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1073/pnas.2110092118
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Le, H.T.T.
, 
Yusuke, H.
, 
Wonganan, P.
, 
Le, T.-K.-D.
, 
Nguyen, V.-K.
, 
Kita, M.
, 
Chavasiri, W.
, 
2022
. 

A new neolignan and a new phenolic acid from the heartwood of 
Mansonia gagei

. 
J.R. Drumm. Nat. Prod. Res
. 
1–8
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 14786419.2022.2116022
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Liu, J.
, 
Zheng, C.-H.
, 
Ren, X.-H.
, 
Zhou, F.
, 
Li, W.
, 
Zhu, J.
, 
Lv, J.-G
., 

Zhou, Y.-J
.

, 
2012
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Synthesis and biological evaluation of 1-benzylidene-3, 4-dihydronaphthalen-2-one as a new class of microtubule-targeting agents. J. Med. Chem. 55, 5720–5733.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1021/jm300596s.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Maguire, C.J.
, 
Carlson, G.J.
, 
Ford, J.W.
, 
Strecker, T.E.
, 
Hamel, E.
, 
Trawick, M.L.
, 
Pinney, K.G.
, 
2019
. 
Synthesis and biological evaluation of structurally diverse α- conformationally restricted chalcones and related analogues
. 
Med. Chem. Comm.
10
, 
1445–1456
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/C9MD00127A
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Moneva, M.
, 
Dagogo-Jack, S.
, 
2002
. 
Multiple drug targets in the management of type 2 diabetes
. 
Curr. Drug Targets
3
, 
203–221
. 
https://doi.org/10.2174/ 1389450023347803
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Mongkol, R.
, 
Chavasiri, W.
, 
2016
. 

Antimicrobial, herbicidal and antifeedant activities of mansonone E from the heartwoods of 
Mansonia gagei
Drumm

. 
J. Integr. Agric.
15
, 
2795–2802
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S2095-3119(16)61444-2
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Nishina, A.
, 
Miura, A.
, 
Goto, M.
, 
Terakado, K.
, 
Sato, D.
, 
Kimura, H.
, 
Hirai, Y.
, 
Sato, H.
, 
Phay, N.
, 
2018
. 

Mansonone E from 
Mansonia gagei
inhibited α- MSH-induced melanogenesis in B16 cells by inhibiting CREB expression and phosphorylation in the PI3K/Akt pathway

. 
Biol. Pharm. Bull.
41
, 
770–776
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/ bpb.b17-01045
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Oboh, G.
, 
Ogunsuyi, O.B.
, 
Ogunbadejo, M.D.
, 
Adefegha, S.A.
, 
2016
. 
Influence of gallic acid on α- amylase and α- glucosidase inhibitory properties of acarbose. J
. 
Food Drug Anal.
24
, 
627–634
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jfda.2016.03.003
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Olokoba, A.B.
, 
Obateru, O.A.
, 
Olokoba, L.B.
, 
2012
. 
Type 2 diabetes mellitus: a review of current trends
. 
Oman Med. J.
27
, 
269
. 
https://doi.org/10.5001/omj.2012.68
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ramachary, D.B.
, 
Anif Pasha, M.
, 
Thirupathi, G.
, 
2017
. 
Organocatalytic asymmetric formal [3+ 2] cycloaddition as a versatile platform to access methanobenzo [7] annulenes
. 
Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.
56
, 
12930–12934
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ anie.201706557
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ramadhan, R.
, 
Phuwapraisirisan, P.
, 
2015
. 

New arylalkanones from 
Horsfieldia macrobotrys
, effective antidiabetic agents concomitantly inhibiting α- glucosidase and free radicals

. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett.
25
, 
4529–4533
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. bmcl.2015.08.069
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Rankovi´c, B.
, 
Kosani´c, M.
, 
Stanojkovi´c, T.
, 
Vasiljevi´c, P.
, 
Manojlovi´c, N.
, 
2012
. 

Biological activities of 
Toninia candida
and 
Usnea barbata
together with their norstictic acid and usnic acid constituents

. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
13
, 
14707–14722
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ ijms131114707
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Sakoulas, G.
, 
Nam, S.-J.
, 
Loesgen, S.
, 
Fenical, W.
, 
Jensen, P.R.
, 
Nizet, V.
, 
Hensler, M.
, 
2012
. 

Novel bacterial metabolite merochlorin A demonstrates in vitro activity against multi-drug resistant methicillin-resistant 
Staphylococcus aureus

. 
PLoS One
7
, e 
29439
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0029439
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Shih, H.
, 
Deng, L.
, 
Carrera, C.J.
, 
Adachi, S.
, 
Cottam, H.B.
, 
Carson, D.A.
, 
2000
. 
Rational design, synthesis and structure–activity relationships of antitumor (E)-2- benzylidene-1-tetralones and (E)-2-benzylidene-1-indanones
. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Lett. 10, 487–490. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0960-894x(00)00032-9.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Tiew, P.
, 
Puntumchai, A.
, 
Kokpol, U.
, 
Chavasiri, W.
, 
2002
. 

Coumarins from the heartwoods of 
Mansonia gagei
drumm

. 
Phytochemistry
60
, 
773–776
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/s0031-9422(02)00194-2
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Wang, Z.
, 
Zhao, L.
, 
Chen, Y.
, 
Xu, W.
, 
Sun, T.
, 
2014
. 
Determination of absolute configurations of bedaquiline analogs by quantum chemical electronic circular dichroism calculations and an X. ray diffraction study
. 
Eur. J. Org. Chem
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
3814–3821
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ejoc.201400135
, 
2014
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Winkelmann, K.
, 
Heilmann, J.
, 
Zerbe, O.
, 
Rali, T.
, 
Sticher, O.
, 
2001
. 

Further prenylated bi-and tricyclic phloroglucinol derivatives from 
Hypericum papuanum

. 
Helv. Chim
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Acta
84
, 
3380–3392
. 

https://doi.org/10.1002/1522-2675(20011114)84:11 
&lt;
3380:: AID-HLCA3380
&gt;
3.0.CO;2-O

.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
