<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112933</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Flavonoid biosynthesis in Dianthus caryophyllus L. is early regulated during interaction with Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. dianthi</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Caryophyllaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
Flavonoid
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Caryophyllaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Zea mays
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Petunia
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>resistance</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
(
Pouralibaba et al., 2017
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gloriana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tirana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
resistance (
Desmedt et al., 2021
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Caryophyllaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>race were</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Flavonoid biosynthesis in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
L. is early regulated during interaction with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
f. sp. 
dianthi
</p>
         <p>
Ana Romero-Rinc´on
a, b
, Sixta Tulia Martínez
a
, Blanca Ligia Higuera
a
, Ericsson Coy-Barrera
b
,
</p>
         <p>
Harold Duban Ardila 

a, 
*
</p>
         <p>
a

Laboratory Research in Vegetal Metabolic Activities, Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, Universidad Nacional de 
Colombia
, Ciudad Universitaria, Cra 30 No.

</p>
         <p>
45-03, Bogot´a
, 111321, 
Colombia
</p>
         <p>
b

Bioorganic Chemistry Laboratory, Department of Chemistry, Universidad Militar 
Nueva Granada
, Cajic´a

, 250247, 
Colombia
</p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Caryophyllaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Resistance</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
Flavonoid
</tp:taxon-name>
biosynthesis Carnation
</p>
         <p>Targeted metabolite profiling mRNA levels</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Rooted cuttings from two carnation (
<tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
L.) cultivars showing contrasting responses to the vascular wilt caused by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
f. sp. 
dianthi
(
Fod
) were inoculated with this phytopathogen, and some of the biochemical responses associated with flavonoid biosynthesis were investigated in the roots. The resistant cultivar (‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’) showed a significant increase in the levels of phenolic and flavonoid compounds at 48–96 h post-inoculation (hpi) (
α
= 
0.05
). LC-MS-based analysis indicated that the flavonoids mainly included flavanol-type glycosides, especially quercetin and kaempferol aglycones. Quantification of the mRNA levels of genes encoding CHS (
Chalcone Synthase
), CHI (
Chalcone Isomerase
), FLS (
Flavonol Synthase
), and the transcription factor MYB11 by using reverse transcription quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) indicated that the resistant cultivar exhibited higher expression levels of these genes and, therefore, showed more flavonoid accumulation at 96 hpi. The differences in the temporal regulation of the assessed variables during infection support the idea that the early expression of enzymes of the flavonoid biosynthesis pathway in carnation roots is linked to a resistance response to the hemibiotrophic pathogen 
Fod
race 2. The present experimental approach is the first report describing the molecular mechanisms underlying flavonoid biosynthesis in carnation roots during their interaction with 
Fod
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
f. sp. 
dianthi
(
Fod
) is the causal agent of vascular wilting of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Caryophyllaceae</tp:taxon-name>
), commonly called as carnation. This phytopathogen constitutes the most devastating disease of the carnation crop worldwide. The frequent presence of this pathogen in soils used for carnation cultivation causes major economic losses when susceptible cultivars are grown in greenhouses (

; 

). Despite the application of sanitary and cultural practices (e.g., substrate suppressiveness, clean growing surfaces, plant material and water, appropriate handling of rotation patterns, fertilization, and removal of diseased plants) to prevent the introduction and further dispersal of this pathogen in carnation crops, the occurrence of this disease has promoted interest in the development of new efficient control methods (

; 

). Endogenous antifungal-based resistance modulation represents an ecofriendly alternative for the control of this disease (Shah
</p>
         <p>
* Corresponding author. 
E-mail address:
hdardilab@unal.edu.co (H.D. Ardila).
</p>
         <p>
et al., 2020). In this regard, although the relationship between the presence and content of some endogenous specialized metabolites and the resistance level against 
Fod
has been previously determined in several studies, recent studies on this topic are limited. The information available until now indicates that 
Fod
-resistant carnation cultivars produce several antifungal compounds, such as anthranilate derivatives (e. g., dianthalexins) and phenolics (e.g., benzoic acids and flavonoids), against the pathogenic infection (

, 

; 

). However, accumulation of antifungal metabolites in carnation tissues depends on the plant part involved, since nitrogenous compounds usually accumulate in stems (

), whereas phenolics appear to be preferably accumulated in roots (

).
</p>
         <p>
The role of flavonoids in plant defense has been reviewed (

; 

; 

), and these compounds have been proposed to be associated with antimicrobial and even antioxidant activity (

, 

; 

). These compounds can be used by plants to regulate the levels of highly reactive oxygen species (ROS) during infection of necrotrophic pathogens (

; 

). For biotrophic pathogens, flavonoids have been suggested to be mainly associated with antifungal activity and modulation of hormonal responses to generate a more effective response to the pathogen (

). In general, the role of these naturally occurring compounds in resistance depends on several variables such as the plant genotype, the environmental conditions, and the pathogen lifestyle (Gorniak´et al., 2019; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The presence of antifungal flavonoids against 
Fod
in carnation has attracted the attention of researchers because these compounds have been isolated from healthy and inoculated plant parts and tissues of resistant carnation cultivars. A previous study reported that inoculated plants of the 
Fod
-resistant 
‘Novada
’ carnation cultivar exhibited increased accumulation of kaempferide 3- 
O
-[2 
G
-β- D- glucopyranosyl]- β- rutinoside in both stems and roots for 10 days after inoculation (

, 

). The anti- 
Fod
fungitoxic effect of this constitutive flavonol glycoside in this cultivar has also been reported (

). Other 
Fod
-resistant carnation cultivars (i.e., ‘ 
Roland
’) yielded fungitoxic flavonoids such as quercetin 3- 
O
-α- L- arabinopyranosyl-(1 → 6)-β- D- glucopyranoside (peltatoside) and 3,5,7,2 
′
-tetrahydroxyflavone (datiscetin) from healthy and inoculated 
in vitro
-generated calli and parent plants (

). Other flavonoids such as apigenin 6, 8-di- 
C
-β- D- glucopyranoside, kaempferol 3- 
O
-β- D- glucopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
O
-[α- L- rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 6)]-β- D- glucopyranoside, and kaempferol 3- 
O
-[α- L- rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 6)]-β- D- glucopyranoside have also been described and quantified in several carnation cultivars (

). Additionally, roots of resistant cultivars were found to contain higher levels of flavonoids than those of susceptible cultivars (

).
</p>
         <p>
The phenylpropanoid pathway is an important source of phenolic compounds, including flavonoids, in plants (

). In this pathway, a wide variety of enzymes play essential roles in regulating the levels of phenolic compounds. Accordingly, chalcone synthase (CHS) and chalcone isomerase (CHI) have been considered to be the control points for flavonoid biosynthesis (

; 

). While CHS (EC 2.3.1.74) catalyzes the condensation of three iterative malonyl-CoA units on 
p
-coumaroyl CoA, the final product of the phenylpropanoid pathway, to generate 4,2 
′
,4 
′
,6 
′
-tetrahydroxy-chalcone, CHI (EC 5.5.1.6) catalyzes the enantioselective intramolecular cyclization product of CHS to generate (
2S
)-naringenin, the basic structural core of flavonoids. These enzymes have been mainly studied in carnation in relation to flavonoid biosynthesis in carnation petals (

; 

). Flavonol synthase (FLS, EC 1.14.20.6) is also an important contributor to the flavonoid biosynthetic pathway. It catalyzes the regioselective desaturation of dihydroflavonols to produce flavonols through the formation of a double bond between C2 and C3 at the C-ring (

). Flavonols are an important group of flavonoids and perform various biological functions such as protection against UV, transport of auxins, and protection against pathogens (Gorniak´et al., 2019; 

). In fact, flavonol-type compounds are mostly described in carnation and are commonly associated with resistance against phytopathogens (

). Another important checkpoint involved in the regulation of flavonoid biosynthesis is related to the V-myb myeloblastosis viral oncogene homolog (MYB) transcription factor (TF) family, such as MYB11, 12, and 111 (also recognized as PFG2, 1, and 3, respectively) (

). These TFs are highly dependent on tissue 
type
and respond to external signals, e.g., elicitors or UV radiation (

; 

). MYB TFs have also been characterized in model plants, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zea mays
</tp:taxon-name>
(corn), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Petunia
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

), but there is no information regarding these TFs for carnation.
</p>
         <p>
Activation of the biosynthetic pathway for a specific metabolite at the early phase of pathogen infection is a key point influencing the role of these pathways in resistance (

; 

). In carnation, the current evidence for flavonoid biosynthesis associated with 
Fod
resistance includes the differential expression of genes encoding proteins involved in the biosynthetic pathway. Thus, the differential constitutive expression of these two flavonoid biosynthesis enzymes (i.e., CHS and CHI) in the roots of cuttings from susceptible and resistant cultivars (

), as well as the isolation of specific fungitoxic flavonoids from the roots of resistant cultivars (

, 

, 

), have been previously explored. However, holistic evaluations of the differential accumulation of these compounds and molecular evidence for the dynamics of flavonoid biosynthesis in carnation roots in response to 
Fod
inoculation are limited. Therefore, as a part of our research on carnation– 
Fod
interaction, we investigated the differential flavonoid accumulation responses and the expression of biosynthetic genes during the interaction with this pathogen in carnation roots, and then evaluated the differences between resistant/susceptible and constitutive/inoculated pairs. The results confirmed the importance of flavonoid-related production and accumulation within those roles in the resistance of carnation against 
Fod.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
The effects of 
Fod
infection on flavonoid biosynthesis in carnation were investigated under a three-phase study, whose workflow is outlined in 
Fig. 1
. The study phases consisted of several experimental and analytical steps. Phase 1 involved an assessment of the phenotypic responses of two carnation cultivars to 
Fod
infection on the basis of their differential responses against this pathogen in the field in order to classify them into resistant and susceptible cultivars. Once these cultivar-dependent responses were verified, phase II was oriented to design an 
in vivo Fod
-inoculation assay to evaluate the early responses of these carnation cultivars by sampling roots at different post-inoculation times. In phase III, the collected roots (per time, cultivar and 
Fod
-inoculated or non-inoculated condition) were extracted and the chemical and transcriptional changes caused by 
Fod
presence were finally examined.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

2.1. Differential Fod 
<tp:taxon-name>resistance</tp:taxon-name>
levels of the carnation cultivars used in the in vivo assay

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The differential pathogen responses of the two carnation cultivars (‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’ and ‘ 
Mizuki
’) were examined in a 7-week post-inoculation 
in vivo
assay. Plants of these cultivars were rigorously scrutinized each week during the experiment and, if symptoms of vascular wilting were detected, these plants were registered at those time points and the severity index (SI) was calculated (see Experimental section). Disease evolution (expressed as SI over time) exhibited differences among cultivars and between inoculated and control plants (
Fig. 2
). ‘ 
Mizuki
’ began to show symptoms of the disease at the fourth week (SI = 0.1), while ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’ showed symptoms from the sixth week, indicating differences in the disease progression in these cultivars. Finally, ‘ 
Mizuki
’ reached an SI value of 0.7 at the seventh week, which was significantly higher (

P
&lt;
0.05

) than that of ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’ (SI = 0.3). The symptoms of the carnation cultivar ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’ are consistent with the previously reported quantitative 
Fod
resistance trait, wherein some symptoms of wilting may appear under a high inoculum pressure (

; 

; 

). Visual analysis of cross-sections of the stems of the inoculated carnation plants shows degradation of the vascular tissue in ‘ 
Mizuki
’, and an evident browning process in the vascular xylematic tissues of ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’, as reported previously in resistant genotypes (

). The contrasting phenotypic responses of these two carnation cultivars against 
Fod
was confirmed from this 
in vivo
experiment and comparable to the field observations. Therefore, under these experimental conditions, these cultivars were classified as ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’ resistant cultivar (GRC) and ‘ 
Mizuki
’ susceptible cultivar (MSC). These cultivars were then used in the subsequent 
in vivo
assays to evaluate the early-stage chemical and transcriptional changes.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Chemical variations in carnation roots during the Fod-inoculation in
vivo assay
</title>
         <p>
Both carnation cultivars with contrasting responses to 
Fod
infection (i.e., 
GRC
and 
MSC
) were employed in a subsequent 96-h 
Fod
-inoculation 
in vivo
assay to explore the variations of the phenolic and flavonoid contents as well as the liquid chromatography–mass spectrometry (LC-MS)-derived flavonoid profiles of carnation roots at the early phase in response to 
Fod
presence, according to our workflow (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2.1. Total phenolic and flavonoid contents in carnation roots during Fod
infection
</title>
         <p>
The changes in total phenolic content (TPC) and total flavonoid content (TFC) constitute a first-line approach to determine the early changes occurring in flavonoid biosynthesis (

). During the 96-h 
in vivo
assay, carnation plants effectively exhibited variations in TPC and TFC at different levels. For the TPC of the two cultivars with and without 
Fod
inoculation, values were found to be in the range of 50–210 μg of gallic acid equivalents (GAE) per g fresh weight (fw) of plant material (
Fig. 3a
). However, the constitutive TPC values showed significant differences between cultivars; therefore, 
GRC
yielded an average value of 100 μg GAE/g fw, whereas 
MSC
afforded 50 μg GAE/g fw. These results coincided with the values reported for nine carnation cultivars grown and commercialized in 
Colombia
with contrasting levels of resistance to 
Fod
(

).
</p>
         <p>
These results additionally agreed with the findings of a previous study, in which pathogen inoculation caused variations in certain phenolic compounds evaluated by high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) (

). However, this study reported a phenolics-based increase only at 96 h post-inoculation (hpi), since plants collected at earlier times showed no variations. In the present study, pathogen inoculation in 
GRC
caused a significant increase in the TPC at the same time (96 hpi), while 
MSC
exhibited no effects of 
Fod
inoculation on both TPC and TFC at all test times. The phenolic compounds that were potentially accumulated included some glycosylated flavonoids and other cinnamic acid derivatives, which may be a part of the first-line chemical defense since they accumulate at the early phase after pathogen inoculation (

; 

; 

). Phenolic compounds are involved in complex phenomena associated with the strengthening of cell walls during pathogen response (Bell´es et al., 2008; 

; 

; 

). Thus, such compounds could be esterified with the polymeric carbohydrate components of the cell wall, decreasing its degradation by the cell wall-degrading enzymes (CWDEs) secreted by necrotrophic and hemibiotrophic pathogens (

). Thus, the increase in the levels of phenolic compounds at 96 hpi may be associated with the histological events reported in the roots of resistant carnation cultivars during pathogen inoculation (

). Phenolics may play a very important role in resistance to vascular wilt-causing pathogens, since they have direct antimicrobial activity, are constituents of polymeric vascular coatings (

), and have been associated with the extravascular defense by roots against 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
(
Pouralibaba et al., 2017
)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
On the other hand, the TFC also showed some changes in the carnation plants evaluated in this study (
Fig. 3b
). TFC values were found to be in the range of 40–120 μg of catechin equivalents (CE) per g of fresh plant material (
Fig. 3
). Constitutive TFC expression showed similar behavior as that of TPC. 
GRC
showed higher average TFC values (i.e., 
70 mg
CE/gtw), which were significantly different from those of 
MSC
(i.e., 40 CE/gtw). These results also coincide with the findings of previous studies in other carnation cultivars (

), in which enhanced flavonoid contents were related to resistance against 
Fod
(

, 

, 

; 

). In fact, variations in the flavonoid contents of resistant cultivars and different tissues have been also reported for pathosystems involving 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium
</tp:taxon-name>
pathogens (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). In addition, inoculation with 
Fod
race 2 causes a significant increase (

P

&lt;
0.05

) in both TPC and TFC values at 96 hpi in 
GRC
roots, since such elevations were not observed in the respective controls, nor in the inoculated 
MSC
, at the same time (i.e., 96 hpi) (
Fig. 3a
). However, the TFC of inoculated 
GRC
roots exhibited a significant difference at 48 hpi in comparison to the non-inoculated plants. The increase in TFC after inoculation may be associated with the role of these metabolites in the regulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) (

; Dumanovi´c et al., 2020), whose mechanism has been reported to be important for preventing activation of the necrotrophic pathogen phase (

).
</p>
         <p>
Another widely reported function of flavonoids is related to their phytoalexin-based action (

; 

; 

). The role of flavonoids in carnation may be associated with antifungal activity (

, 

), but it is also related to their antioxidant activity (

; 

; 

; S´a et al., 2009). Accordingly, fluctuations in the oxidative balance caused by the pathogen infection promote a response related to the enhanced levels of these compounds (

; Dumanovic´et al., 2020; 

; 

). Since the antioxidant action is limited to plant tissue-related locations (

), the possibility that flavonoid-type compounds completely regulate the oxidative burst within the plant defense response cannot be ruled out. However, the inactivation of highly reactive oxygen species (ROS) is a response associated with resistance to necrotrophic pathogens. After recognition, these highly oxidizing species are not required in the same proportion and should be eliminated to avoid cell death. Such an event might favor the colonization by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium
</tp:taxon-name>
pathogens showing necrotrophic phases (

; Sa´et al., 2009). For this reason, accumulation of phenolic compounds and flavonoids is proposed to be a part of the basal plant response that could be associated with the horizontal or polygenic resistance presented by carnation against 
Fod
(

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2.2. Chemical variability through targeted metabolic profiling of
carnation roots during Fod-inoculation in vivo assay
</title>
         <p>
Variations in the chemical composition of the 54 raw extracts from carnation roots were also investigated by means of targeted metabolic profiling in order to expand the flavonoid characterization and distribution beyond TFC during 
Fod
inoculation, and select the statistically top-ranked constitutively expressed and induced flavonoids in the carnation resistance response. LC-MS profiles were processed and the MS-derived features were then recovered from the raw profiles and labelled with the respective retention time–mass/charge ratio (rt/ 
m/z
) pairs. In total, 1235 negative ion mode-derived features were identified and subsequently filtered to compile specifically flavonoid-like metabolites according to the typical flavonoid bands I and II (i.e., 270–295 and 
310–350 nm
, respectively) in the UV spectra. After this filtering process, 96 filtered features (i.e., flavonoids) from 54 observations (i.e., samples) were gathered into a dataset to create a feature intensity table (FIT) and used to explore and analyze the metabolite changes under supervised statistics. The most important features ranked and selected by the statistical analysis were annotated at MSI level 2 (

) by using accurate mass and diagnostic MS fragment evidence. The rest of the features were annotated at MSI levels 3–4 or remained unannotated. The most statistically important annotated features exhibited quasimolecular ions above 
m/z
500 and triggered fragment ions at 
m/z
285, 301, and 315, indicating the presence of kaempferol, quercetin, and methylquercetin flavonols as aglycones, which was confirmed by the UV maximum absorptions at 
ca.
340 and 
280 nm
(i.e., bands I and II, respectively) for flavonols. Additionally, the presence of fragment ions at 
m/z
162, 146, 132 loses, which are the typical sugar fragments of glycosides for hexose (glucose), pentose (arabinose), and deoxyhexose (rhamnose) residues, respectively, and the deduced presence of ester substitutions (such as acetyl, galloyl, synapyl, feruroyl, and malyl) led to the compound annotation presented in 
Table 1
. In this regard, some authors suggested that the flavonoid glycosylation mediated by uridine diphosphate glucosyltransferase (UGT) enzymes played a significant role in responses to biotic stresses (

; 

; 

). However, while the addition of a particular glycosyl group does not directly influence the biological activity, it can indirectly improve other physicochemical properties to facilitate the action, such as transport and targeting (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Annotation at level 3 of MSI confidence (

) by diagnostic evidence from UV, accurate mass and MS fragments data; Sugar residues: glc =
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
glucose, ara = arabinose, rha = rhamnose, glu = glucuronide. 
b
Molecular formula of the annotated compound [M], deduced from the adduct [M-H] 
-
. 
c
Diagnostic fragments observed in the respective HRMS spectra. 
d
Annotated compound at level 4 of MSI confidence by HRMS, whose flavonoid type was deduced from UV spectrum data. PCA = principal component analysis;
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>MEBA = multivariate empirical bayes approach; PLS-DA = partial-least squares-discriminant analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2.2.1. Metabolic profiling-based analysis of constitutive flavonoids from
the roots of carnation cultivars.

An exploratory overview of these constitutive root flavonoids that are potentially relevant in discriminating the non-inoculated carnation cultivars studied herein was initially performed through univariate analysis. A paired fold change (FC) analysis was then conducted to compare the absolute change values between both cultivars for all the evaluated time-points, by using these two global categories as group means (i.e., 
GRC
and 
MSC
, gathering the different sampling times per cultivar) to classify the whole dataset. It was then pre-processed through log transformation and mean-centering (i.e., column-wise normalization) to calculate the ratio between group means. Thus, the number of 
GRC
/ 
MSC
pairs with consistent change above or below |2| (as selected threshold) was counted, and the resulting pairs were expressed as log2 scale (FC). The significant features identified by FC analysis are presented in 
Fig. 4a
. The number of significant features per cultivar was found to be 37 for 
GRC
(red dots) and 9 for 
MSC
(blue dots), indicating a global difference in the flavonoid composition between these cultivars. The existence of a higher number of significant flavonoid-related features in 
GRC
can be firstly rationalized due to the genetic differences among 
GRC
and 
MSC
. However, other resistant cultivars were recognized to accumulate higher amounts of some metabolites and even more metabolites than susceptible cultivars, which were related to 
Fod
resistance (

, 

, 

). In addition, as mentioned above, this accumulation may exhibit a time-dependent occurrence (

; 

). Therefore, a principal component analysis (PCA) was performed to evaluate the flavonoid-based chemical differences along sampling times (0–96 h). The resulting three-dimensional (principal component 1 [PC1] vs. PC2 vs. PC3) score plot is presented in 
Fig. 4b
. This score plot showed a particular clustering pattern, representing 81% of the explained variance. The earlier times (0 and 12 h) of both cultivars were grouped to form a single cluster, but the later times (24, 48, and 96 h) were separated among cultivars. 
MSC
exhibited a greater difference than 
GRC
between 24 and 48 h. The highest difference between cultivars was observed at the latest time point (i.e., 96 h), which agreed with the findings for TPC and TFC. The PCA-derived loadings plot revealed four features that influenced the discrimination of these 
GRC
samples collected at later times (see 
Fig. 4c
). In order to evaluate the performance of these features over time, the dataset was analyzed through a multivariate empirical Bayes approach (MEBA) (

). This approach led us to rank the features by the differences in temporal profiles among cultivars according to the Hotelling-T2 values. The most-discriminating features selected by PCA for 
GRC
(i.e., 42.4/579.1371, 61.8/582.1423, 43.1/801.2053, and 63.1/797.2114) were ranked by the highest Hotelling-T2 values (
&gt;
105
), which indicate that the time-course profiles of these features are more different between 
GRC
and 
MSC
cultivars (
Fig. 4d
). The behavior of these features was found to be different, showing a modest abundance at earlier times but increasing over time to reach the maximum values at 48 or 96 h, and showing a differential constitutive accumulation of these compounds between cultivars. This differential response showed a higher capacity to biosynthesize flavonoids at a constitutive level in the carnation resistant cultivar ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’ during the early times in the 
in vivo
assay, so this fact will provide important insights into carnation plant selection based on discriminatory flavonoids (

; 

).
</title>
         <p>
Other features were also selected as important variables on the basis of the PCA- and MEBA-derived Hotelling-T2 values (
Fig. 4e
). From these important features, six flavonoids influenced the 
GRC
discrimination maximally, whereas 
MSC
was differentiated by the abundance of four flavonoids. These features showing the highest influence on discrimination of 
GRC
and 
MSC
, annotated at level 3 of MSI confidence as mentioned above, are listed in 
Table 1
. The annotated, statistically important glycosylated flavonoids 
1–9
were found to be particularly related to the flavonol 
type
, except flavone 
10
. In particular, flavonol glycosides exhibited a structural trend based on a flavonoid aglycone (quercetin or kaempferol) attached to 1–3 sugar residues with an esterified group, except compounds 
2, 3,
and 
7
. The presence of constitutive flavonols in these cultivars is a part of the metabolic characteristics of this plant species (

, 

), since the distribution of some specific flavonoids at higher amounts in the resistant cultivar would support the hypothesis of their role in resistance (

; 

, 

). The most important flavonoids statistically ranked and selected in this study have not been previously described in carnation, except quercetin 3- 
O
-α- L- arabinopyranosyl (1 → 6)-β- D- galactoside, which has the same aglycone and substitution pattern of the top-ranked compound 
7
, a quercetin pentosyl-hexoside. The reported flavonol glycoside was previously detected in inter-node explants of ‘ 
Roland
’ resistant and ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gloriana
</tp:taxon-name>
’ susceptible carnation cultivars, and it proved to be slightly inhibitory toward the pathogen (

). This fact is in agreement with our findings, since the abundance of the glycosylated flavonoid 
7
was greater in 
GRC
than in 
MSC
(although it occurred in both cultivars). Therefore, such GRC-abundant flavonoids (i.e., 
2
, 
5–9
) are of interest since they may be involved in some role in the resistance against 
Fod
. The antifungal activity of glycosylated flavonoids isolated from carnation has been previously reported. For instance, kaempferol 3- 
O
-β- D- glucopyranosyl (1 → 2)- 
O
-[α- L- rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 6)]-β- D- glucopyranoside isolated from the ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tirana
</tp:taxon-name>
’ cultivar exhibited fungitoxic activity against 
Fod
race 2 (

) and the kaempferide 3- 
O
-[2 
G-
β- D- glucopyranosyl]-β- rutinoside, a constituent of the carnation cultivar ‘ 
Novada
’, was postulated to be a phytoanticipin (

) with a phytoalexin-like role, considering its levels during pathogen infection (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2.2.2. Metabolic profiling-based analysis of induced flavonoids associated
with carnation defense against Fod.

Once resistant and susceptible cultivars were discriminated over time on the basis of constitutive flavonoids, the analysis was oriented to compare the flavonoid composition of 
Fod
-inoculated and non-inoculated plants of both carnation cultivars at different post-inoculation times. Such a comparison was initially accomplished by two-factor clustering using Ward algorithm, whose intuitive visualization as a heat map is presented in 
Fig. 5a
. The factors considered for this clustering were post-inoculation ‘time’ (12, 24, 48, and 96 hpi) and the plant ‘condition’ as primary ordering. In this case, the factor ‘condition’ refers to the combination of each cultivar (
GRC
and 
MSC
) with and without 
Fod
inoculation. Similar to the findings for the analysis of constitutive flavonoids (
Fig. 4a
), during this assay, 
GRC
exhibited more flavonoid-related features with higher intensity than 
MSC
, and 96 hpi also turned out to be the time that yielded the maximal number of higher-intensity features. The findings at 48 hpi also revealed other important features in 
GRC
that were different from those of 
MSC
. Additionally, 
Fod
-inoculated 
GRC
showed meaningful abundance differences from its control (non-inoculated plants), and these features also differed from those of 
MSC
, indicating the induction of distinctive flavonoids between cultivars as a consequence of the 
Fod
infection. Indeed, Ward clustering divided the dataset into two main groups according to the comparative metabolic distribution of each cultivar. However, the number of induced flavonoids in 
GRC
was higher than those induced in 
MSC
(See 
Fig. 5a
). Therefore, in order to explore the major patterns associated with each factor, an ANOVA-simultaneous component analysis (ASCA) (

) was employed on a flavonoid-filtered FIT dataset. This algorithm first splits the overall data variance into individual variances induced by each factor (i.e., “time” and “condition”), as well as by one interaction (i.e., “time × condition”), and the major variations in each partition are summarized by a PCA applied to individual factors and interaction. The resulting models (see 
Fig. 5b
) illustrated the score variations associated with the factors “condition” and “time” on the first component, which explained 87.7% and 68.2% of the variation, respectively. The model of the factor “condition” (
Figs. 5b
– 
1
) indicated that the highest variations were presented in 
Fod
-inoculated 
GRC
, being oppositely different to that of 
MSC
, as noticed in the previous two-factor clustering. Furthermore, flavonoid induction was more evident in the inoculated 
GRC
in comparison to the control, so the 
Fod
-related response of 
GRC
can be considered to be higher. On the other hand, the “time” factor-related model (
Figs. 5b
– 
2
) revealed a time-dependent behavior of the variations. This finding suggested that variations between cultivars and inoculation regarding control is enhanced over time, reaching a statistically important maximum variation at 96 hpi. The “time × condition” interaction-derived submodels on the first component (which explained 41.5% of the variation) confirmed the behavior observed for individual factors, since the highest variations were caused by inoculated 
GRC
(
Figs. 5c
– 
3
) and 96 hpi (
Figs. 5c
– 
1
) in comparison to the other conditions and times. 
MSC
exhibited decreasing variation, implying a lower flavonoid-related response against Fod, possibly as part of the susceptibility phenotype related to the higher disease progression (
Fig. 2
). The same interaction scores for the second component (28.2% of variation explained) exhibited a second behavior involving the highest variations at 48 hpi by inoculated 
GRC
, which is in agreement with the enhanced accumulation over time. Under this context, the resistant cultivar exhibited the highest time-course response for flavonoid accumulation caused by 
Fod
inoculation, and 96 hpi appeared to be the time point with the highest response at root level.
</title>
         <p>
To elucidate these findings, a dual comparison between 
Fod
-inoculated and non-inoculated plants of carnation 
GRC
at 96 hpi was carried out to identify the features that influence the discrimination of such a condition. Thus, the ten top-ranked features by an unpaired parametric 
t
-test exhibited four compounds previously related to constitutive levels (
4
, 
5
, 
6
, 
7
) and six other flavonoids that were not ranked in the previous analysis related to constitutive metabolites (
11–16
) (
Fig. 6a
). Two flavonoids (
5
, 
16
) were selected to be related to 
GRC
control and the remaining eight top-ranked flavonoids were important for inoculated 
GRC
(
4
, 
7
, 
11–15
); therefore, these last flavonoids were considered to show a possible association with pathogen resistance. Among these compounds, a flavonoid (
12
) was annotated at MSI level 4 of confidence since the diagnostic evidence was not useful to clarify a higher annotation level and the 
type
of flavonoid was deduced by the UV bands (
Table 1
), whereas compounds 
11
, 
13,
and 
15
exhibited the same structural pattern as the top-ranked constitutive flavonoids (i.e., an aglycone attached to pentose or hexose residues with an ester substitution), even flavone 
14
. On the other hand, three glycosides (
6
, 
7
, 
11
) showed the lowest P-values (-log 
10
(raw P-value)
&gt;
6), so their fold changes in comparison with the control could be interpreted as indicating that these were the most induced flavonoids by 
Fod
inoculation in the resistant cultivar. Compounds 
6–7
(previously found to be as constitutively abundant flavonoids in 
GRC
) are significantly induced by 
Fod
inoculation, and compound 
11
, which was constitutively expressed in lower amounts, is also largely induced. These observations, as well as the classification model performance, were demonstrated and validated by classical receiver operating characteristic (
ROC
) curves under the same dual inoculation comparison (
Fig. 6b
). For these three 
t
-testderived top-ranked flavonoids, the area under the curve (AUC) was found to be 1 with high FC values (
&gt;
2). The mean distribution and optimal cutoffs between 
Fod
-inoculated and non-inoculated group samples were additionally very dissimilar according to the respective box-plots (
Fig. 6b
). The MEBA-derived time-course profiles also confirmed our findings, exhibiting significant abundance increments at 96 hpi for 
Fod
-inoculated 
GRC
roots (
Fig. 6c
). On the findings for constitutive and induced expression, flavonoids 
6
(even 
4
) and 
11
can be proposed as phytoanticipin and/or phytoalexin-like candidates, respectively, since kaempferol derivatives have exhibited biological activity against 
Fod
(

) and other phytopathogens (Gorniak´et al., 2019). However, this hypothesis requires additional studies to demonstrate such a role against this pathogen (e.g., fungitoxic activity). In addition, flavonols can act as antioxidants and can function as direct scavengers of reactive oxygen species (ROS), in addition to their functions in activation of antioxidant enzymes and/or inhibition of oxidases (

; 

), and they are related to resistance against nechotrophic and hemibiotrhophic pathogens (

; 

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Variations in the transcript levels of genes encoding flavonoid
biosynthesis enzymes in carnation roots during the Fod-inoculation in vivo assay

</title>
         <p>
The transcript levels of genes encoding flavonoid biosynthesis enzymes were evaluated by RT-qPCR during the 96-h 
in vivo Fod
-inoculation assay. In this study, inoculation with the pathogen generated a significant increase in mRNA levels of the putative genes encoding CHS, CHI, and FLS enzymes and the TF cMYB (
Fig. 7
). At the constitutive level (0 hpi), no significant differences were observed in the transcription of the 
chs
and 
chi
genes for two carnation cultivars (
GRC
and 
MSC
) and, in general, 
chi
showed a similar profile to that observed for 
chs
(
Fig. 7a and b
). These results do not completely coincide with the findings reported by 

, who showed that resistant carnation cultivars have higher transcriptional levels than susceptible cultivars. However, the two sets of results cannot be directly compared because the strategy for gene expression quantification differed across the studies, with the previous study using the absolute quantification expressed as transcript copies of each gene by the total RNA extracted. Transcript levels of 
chs
in roots during the pathogen infection did not exhibit differences between the treatments at 12 and 24 hpi, but a significant mRNA level increase at 48 hpi was observed in both cultivars, with the increase being higher in the resistant cultivar (
Fig. 7a
). Additionally, significant differences were only observed in the inoculated roots of 
GRC
at 96 hpi. For the transcript levels of the 
chi
gene, a significant increase in the resistant genotype 
GRC
at 24 and 48 hpi was caused by pathogen inoculation (
Fig. 7b
). The results for the transcriptional levels of these genes (
chs
and 
chi
) at 24 and 48 hpi can be related to the accumulation of flavonoids at 96 hpi for this resistant cultivar (
Figs. 5–6
). Therefore, the transcriptional increase of the 
chs
and 
chi
genes may be a response possibly associated with pathogen resistance.
</p>
         <p>
The transcriptional constitutive levels of putative 
fls
(
Dca12008.1
gene) in 
GRC
were found to be significantly higher than those in the susceptible cultivar (
Fig. 7c
). These levels in the 
Fod
-inoculated 
GRC
particularly increased at 24 and 96 hpi in comparison to the control, whereas 
MSC
roots only exhibited a difference between control and inoculated samples at 24 hpi. The higher mRNA levels of 
fls
in the resistant cultivar may be associated with the aforementioned abundance of flavonols (

; 

; 

). However, increased transcription of the 
fls
gene was found to occur earlier than those of the 
chs
and 
chi
genes (i.e., from 24 hpi in 
GRC
), which can be also associated with the accumulation of certain flavonoids at 48 hpi (
Figs. 4–6
) and an early response through production of flavonols that, due to their antioxidant capacity, would present a quick counteracting effect against the elevated ROS levels caused by the pathogen recognition (

).
</p>
         <p>
Regarding transcriptional levels of the putative 
cmyb11
gene (
Dca2677.1
) coding for the TF cMYB, both cultivars showed significant differences between the constitutive levels and those derived at 12 hpi and 48 hpi after 
Fod
inoculation. In contrast, no significant differences were observed between the controls and inoculated plants at 24 hpi. Although 48 hpi represents a reasonably prompt response against 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium
</tp:taxon-name>
pathogens (

; 

), 
GRC
exhibited an earlier response based on the significant increase in 
cmyb11
levels at 12 hpi. These results suggest that this Dca26277.1-encoded TF may be involved in the gene regulatory processes for flavonoid biosynthesis. Thus, the joint activation of this gene with other genes coding for TFs of 
chs
, 
chi
, 
f3h
, and 
fls
(

) could be considered as a part of the molecular mechanism related to the polygenic mechanisms against 
Fod
, particularly emphasizing the essential regulatory role of the phenylpropanoid pathway in plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
resistance (
Desmedt et al., 2021
)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
A Pearson correlation analysis was eventually employed to compare the test flavonoid biosynthesis-related parameters (
Table 2
). A positive correlation was found between TFC and the transcriptional levels of 
chs
(0.56, 
α
= 
0.05
), as well as the transcriptional levels of 
chi
and 
chs
(0.95, 
α
= 
0.05
) and the mRNA encoding the TF MYB11. Flavonoid biosynthesis in carnation roots can be considered to be a transcriptionally regulated complex process. However, the total content and semiquantitative levels of flavonoids in carnation roots were related to the transcriptional increase in the genes encoding CHI, CHS, and FLS enzymes, which are particularly important for flavonoid accumulation in plants (

; 

). We suggest that the transcriptional activation of the 
chs
, 
chi
, and 
fls
genes is a part of the complex response related to the innate resistance mechanisms for recognizing MAMPs (microbe-associated molecular patterns) conserved in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium
</tp:taxon-name>
genus. The changes in the ROS levels caused by pathogen recognition may generate the activation of MYB TFs, which have been reported to be associated with transcriptional activation of flavonoid biosynthesis enzymes (

; 

). It is likely that the increase in H 
2
O 
2
content during 
Fod
inoculation activates these carnation MYB TFs to increase the transcriptional levels of the genes encoding flavonoid biosynthesis enzymes. Thus, our findings indicate the influence of the protein cMYB11 on flavonoid biosynthesis in carnation roots, consistent with the regulatory role of 
myb11
over 
chs
and 
chi
genes (

; 

). This fact coincides with the polygenic nature of carnation resistance against race 2 of this pathogen (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Our findings yielded some insights involving flavonoid biosynthesis in the resistance response against 
Fod
in carnation roots. Pathogen recognition occurred in the early phase, as previously reported for this pathosystem (

). This recognition triggered signaling toward the cellular nucleus and induced increased 
cmyb
gene transcription at 12 hpi (
Fig. 7d
). Elevated protein levels of the cMYB TF enhanced the promoter activity of 
chi
and 
chs
genes and favored the increase in the mRNA levels of these genes at 24 hpi (
Fig. 7a and b
). Higher transcriptional levels of 
chs
and 
chi
led to increased CHI and CHS enzyme activity in the endoplasmic reticulum, where flavonoid biosynthesis occurs (

; 

). Subsequently, the mRNA level of the 
fls
gene increased at 48 hpi, which, in turn, enhanced the levels of this protein. Glucosyltransferase (GTF) enzymes are estimated to be important during flavonoid synthesis, as previously described, mainly in relation to the accumulation and transport of these compounds (

). Finally, certain acylglycosylated kaempferol-like flavonoids (such as 
4
, 
6
, 
11
) will accumulate at 96 hpi, mostly in vacuoles (

). The final localization of the accumulated flavonoids during infection should be in the apoplast, and their action would be related to its antioxidant and/or antifungal activity against 
Fod
(

, 

; 

). In summary, the early phase of flavonoid biosynthesis in both carnation cultivars was perturbed differentially by the presence of 
Fod
, and involved the accumulation of certain flavonols and the temporal transcriptional upregulation of MYB11 TF, CHI, CHS, and FLS enzymes from 12 to 96 hpi. The temporal variations of these components during 
Fod
infection support the events related to the early flavonoid biosynthesis-based response as a resistance trait of carnation against the hemibiotrophic pathogen 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
f. sp. 
dianthi
(
Fod
) race 2.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>TFC: total flavonoid content, CHS: chalcone synthase, CHI: chalcone isomerase, FLS: flavonol synthase, MYB: transcription factor.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Concluding remarks
</title>
         <p>
Since phenylpropanoid-derived specialized metabolites are valuable components in plant defense responses, flavonoid-based discrimination of resistant and susceptible carnation cultivars is a favorable strategy to identify these resistance-related biochemical and molecular traits. Thus, to expand the current understanding of the mechanisms underlying the inherent resistance and induced response against vascular wilting, the present study determined the early variations in the metabolite and transcriptional levels in carnation roots in response to 
Fod
. The disease evolved faster in the susceptible variety (‘ 
Mizuki
’, 
MSC
) than in the resistant variety (‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’, 
GRC
), while the accumulation of certain flavonol acylglycosides (e.g., kaempferol 3- 
O
-(acetyl-rhamnosyl)- diglucoside (
6
) and kaempferol 3- 
O
-(sinapoyl-glucosyl)-glucoside (
11
)) in 
GRC
was faster (48 hpi) to those in 
MSC
(at 96 hpi), suggesting that these compounds play a defensive role (e.g., phytoanticipins, phytoalexins and/or antioxidants) against 
Fod
. In addition, both cultivars exhibited a pathogen presence-dependent early response (12–96 hpi) based on an increase in transcriptional levels of flavonoid biosynthesis pathway-related enzymes, but 
GRC
showed the highest expression levels of such genes faster (i.e., 
cmyb11
at 12 hpi, 
chi
and 
chs
genes at 24 hpi, and 
fls
at 48 hpi) to promote a temporally controlled polygenic response against 
Fod
that was oriented to favor a particular accumulation of acylglycosylated kaempferol-like flavonols at 96 hpi. However, antifungal and antioxidant evaluation and functional assays using carnation mutants will be useful to demonstrate the role of each component in this molecular and biochemical model. Our findings using the present combined metabolomics- and transcriptional-based approach confirmed that flavonoid biosynthesis is a part of the complex response related to carnation resistance to the vascular wilting caused by 
Fod
. This constitutes valuable background information for the selection of plants for carnation breeding based on differences in flavonoids and genes conferring disease resistance.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. Biological samples
</title>
         <p>
Rooted cuttings (3-week rooting) from two commercial cultivars (‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Golem
</tp:taxon-name>
’ resistant (
GRC
) and ‘ 
Mizuki
’ susceptible (MCS)) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dianthus caryophyllus
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Caryophyllaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) were used. These carnation plants were grown in 
Colombia
and were supplied by the company Florval SAS campus QFC (Bogota´Plateu, 
Colombia
). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium oxysporum
</tp:taxon-name>
f. sp 
dianthi
(
Fod
) race 2 was isolated from susceptible plants with typical symptoms of vascular wilt. This fungal isolate was maintained in a solid potato dextrose agar (PDA) medium. The typical morphology of conidia was observed through microscopy, and the species and 
<tp:taxon-name>race were</tp:taxon-name>
verified through molecular tools described below (Abd-elsalam et al., 2003; 

). Inoculum was prepared in previously sterilized Czapek-Dox broth by stirring for 7 days at 25 
◦
C. Medium was diluted with sterile water to obtain a suspension with a final concentration of 1.0 × 10 
6
conidia/mL.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Inoculation and sampling process
</title>
         <p>
Inoculation with a pathogenic isolate of 
Fod
was carried out according to the previous study (

). A total of 300 rooted cuttings of each cultivar (
GRC
and 
MSC
) were inoculated by immersion of the roots into the pathogen suspension for 20 s. Simultaneously, 300 cuttings of each cultivar were subjected to the same process using sterile water instead of conidial suspension. Under a randomized 2 × 2 × 4 × 3 experimental design (i.e., cultivars × 
Fod
- and non-inoculated × sampling times × triplicate), cuttings were planted independently for each treatment, in a 50/50 mixture of sterilized soil and rice hulls. The inoculated and control cuttings were harvested at 12, 24, 48, and 96 h after inoculation, according to previous results describing early responses associated to resistance in this pathosystem (

). For each time, three biological replicates consisted of 25 cuttings per treatment were used. The samples were washed with water to remove soil excess, and stems and roots were separated and kept at
</p>
         <p>
80 
◦
C for further analysis. Resistance levels of test cultivars were confirmed by means of an 
in vivo
assay. Hence, 25 plants of each treatment were maintained until 7 weeks post-inoculation and disease incidence were evaluated as the severity index (
SI
) based on the 0–4 scale previously proposed (

) as follows: 0 = no symptomatic plant, 1 = plant with 1/3 of symptoms, 2 = plant with 2/3 of symptoms, 3 = whole plant with symptoms, 4 = plant death. 
SI
(%) = ([Σ(Class frequency × score of rating class)]/(Total number of observations) × (maximal score of rating class)) × 100, where ‘score of rating class’ is related to the disease level based on the proposed scale, ‘class frequency’ is the number of plants showing that score, ‘total number of observations’ is the total number of plants within the experiment, and the ‘maximal score of rating class’ is 4.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Phenolic total extraction
</title>
         <p>
Polar metabolites from controls and inoculated carnation roots were extracted from 
200 mg
of roots using 1 mL of 80% (v/v) methanol. The samples were crushed, sonicated for 15 min (42 Hz and 100 W) and centrifuged (12,000× 
g
, 15 min). The supernatants were transferred to eppendorf tubes and stored in the dark at 20 
◦
C for subsequent analysis (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Total phenolic content
</title>
         <p>
Total phenolic content (TPC) were measured using the Folin–Ciocalteu method (

) with slight modifications. Each reaction mixture contained 20 μL of the methanolic extracts and 40 μL of the Folin–Ciocalteu. After 5 min, 150 μL of 7.35% Na 
2
CO 
3
aqueous solution and 10 μL of deionized water was added. Reaction mixture was incubated at room temperature for 1 h, and the absorbance (
765 nm
) was measured (Varioskan™ LUX). Results were compared to a calibration curve prepared using samples containing 0, 5, 10, 20, 40, 60 ppm of gallic acid (Sigma). TPC values were expressed as microgram of gallic acid equivalents per gram of fresh tissue, according to previous research (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Determination of flavonoid content
</title>
         <p>
Flavonoid content was determined using the aluminum chloride method (

). Each reaction mixture contained carnation roots extract (100 μL), 5% NaNO 
2
(30 μL) and deionized water (100 μL). After 5 min, 10% AlCl 
3
(60 μL) was added, and after additional 6 min at room temperature, 2 M NaOH (100 μL) was also added. Absorbance was measured at 
510 nm
in a Varioskan™ LUX plate reader. Absorbance units were compared to a calibration curve previously prepared using samples containing 0, 5, 10, 20, 40, 60 ppm of catechin (Sigma). TFC values were expressed as microgram of catechin equivalents per gram of fresh tissue.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Reverse phase ultra-high performance liquid chromatography
coupled to diode array detector and mass spectrometry (RP-UHPLC-PDA-MS) analyses

</title>
         <p>
RP-UHPLC-PDA-MS analyses were performed on an Ultra-Fast Liquid Chromatographic (UFLC) Prominence system (Shimadzu, Columbia, MD, 
USA
) equipped with a photodiode array detector (SPD-M20A) and coupled to a LCMS2020 mass spectrometer with quadrupole analyzer and electrospray ionization (ESI). Chromatographic separation was carried out on a C18 Kinetex® 250 × 4.60 × 2.2 μm column. Elution was conducted with a mobile phase consisting of 0.1% HCOOH in H 
20
(solvent A) and 0.1% HCOOH in acetonitrile (Solvent B), which was pumped at a 0.7 mL/min flow rate and the oven temperature was set at 35 
◦
C. Gradient program was set as follows: 0% B (0–3 min), 0%–15% B (4–29 min), 15%–30% B (29–48 min), 30%–100% (48–65 min). Analysis was monitored at 
330 nm
. ESI was operated simultaneously in positive and negative ion modes (scan 
100–2000 m
/z), desolvation line temperature at 250 
◦
C, nitrogen as nebulizer gas at 1.5 L/min, drying gas at 15 L/min, and detector voltage at 1.4 kV. Additionally, RP-UHPLCESI-HRMS data were also performed on a UFLC Prominence system coupled to a Bruker MicrOToF-Q II consisting of a Quadrupole-Time of Flight (QToF) analyzer and ESI. Identical chromatographic parameters above mentioned were used. ESI was operated in negative ion mode (scan 
100–1500 m
/z), capillary voltage at 4.5 kV, desolvation line temperature at 400 
◦
C, nitrogen as nebulizer gas at 4 Bar, drying gas at 8 L/min, quadrupole and collision energy at 7 and 20 eV, respectively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.4.1. Flavonoid-related feature filtering and annotation of the 
mostimportant

features

</title>
         <p>
After LC-HRMS analyses, HRMS-derived features were recovered from raw profiles using MZmine 2 and following a previous procedure for feature filtering (

). Detected features were listed and labelled with the respective retention time/(- mass/charge) ratio (rt/ 
m/z
) pairs. After a detailed scrutiny of the combined LC-DAD, LC-MS and LC-HRMS data, HRMS-features were filtered to gather specifically the flavonoid-like metabolites according to the typical flavonoid bands I and II (i.e., 270–295 and 
310–350 nm
, respectively) in the UV spectra (see 
Table 1
). Once features were filtered, peak annotation procedure led to characterize metabolites into the categories such as unequivocal molecular formula (level 4) or tentative candidates (level 3), following the confidence levels of the metabolomics standard initiative (MSI) (

). The MSI level 1 (confirmed structure) and 2 (probable structure) were not possible to be reached in this study due to a lack of authentic standards and/or enough information using only HRMS to propose a unique structure (e.g., exact isomer of sugar residues) of the conjugated specialized metabolites detected, filtered and processed. Molecular formulas were predominantly deduced from the accurate mass of the quasi-molecular ion obtained in negative ion mode ([M+ H] 
-
). Feature annotation was therefore achieved by the combined diagnostic of the accurate mass errors (in ppm) and the typical MS fragments, supported by phylogenetic filtering, chromatographic behavior (if possible) and data comparison with different databases (e.g., dictionary of natural products, Metlin, KNApSAcK, PubChem).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Quantification by real-time RT-PCR
</title>
         <p>
Transcriptional levels of putative genes encoding CHS, CHI, FLS, and MYB TF were evaluated according to the previous study using a relative quantification to histone (

). To obtain the RNA extracts, carnation roots were macerated using liquid nitrogen in a mortar previously washed with a DEPC (diethylpyrocarbonate) solution. Extraction was performed with 
0.4 g
of the macerated material using Trizol (Invitrogen) according to the supplier’ s instructions. The RNA in the samples was quantified by absorbance readings at 
260 nm
. The A260/A280 ratio ranged from 1.9 to 2.0. To avoid contamination with DNA, 2 μg of the total RNA sample was treated with DNase (Invitrogen) under the conditions recommended by the supplier. The synthesis of cDNA from RNA was subsequently performed using oligo dT and M-MLV reverse transcriptase (Moloney murine leukemia virus, Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer’ s protocol. The transcriptional levels quantification was performed using the system SYBR® Green MasterMix IQTM, Bio-Rad. To ensure that the same amount of cDNA was used in each reaction (
10 ng
), the cDNA amount was quantified by fluorescence (Qbit®, Invitrogen). The primers used for amplification of the 
chs
, 
chi
, 
fls
, and 
myb11
genes are listed in 
Table 3
. Primers of CHS and CHI were designed according to the sequences reported previously (

). For histone was used the primers described by 

, and for 
fls
and 
myb11,
primers were designed using the Genome of Carnation database (ID 
fls
: Dca12008.1 and gen ID 
cmyb11
: Dca26277.1). Amplification of 
chs
y 
chi
genes was performed using an initial denaturation at 95 
◦
C for 10 min followed by 35 cycles at 95 
◦
C (15 s), 60 
◦
C (20 s), and 72 
◦
C (20 s) and finally 72 
◦
C (1 min). For the 
fls
, 
myb11
and histone genes, a modification was made, using an initial denaturation at 95 
◦
C for 10 min followed by 35 cycles at 95 
◦
C (15 s), 59 
◦
C (20 s) and 72 
◦
C (20 s) and finally 72 
◦
C (1 min). The specificity of the products was validated by analyzing the melting curves. The analysis was performed using a C1000 Thermal cycler coupled to a Bio-Rad CFX96 real-time system. The quantification was performed by comparing the values of Ct (threshold cycle) obtained for the different treatments and those obtained by the reference gene using the following formula: (
E
1) 

Δ 
CPtarget
(
control sample
)

) 
/
(
E
2) 

Δ 
CPref
(
control sample
)

, where E2 = target gen and E1 = reference gen (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
According to the previous study by 

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Statistical analysis
</title>
         <p>
Statistical analysis was performed for each variable for the different treatments (n = 3). Data were expressed as means ± standard deviations (SD) or SEM. The analysis of variance and differences between means were analyzed using the Statgraphics® software version 5.1 with oneway ANOVA and Tukey test (

P

˂ 
0.05

). Pearson’ s correlation (
α
= 
0.05
) was done using the software IBM SPSS Statistics v22.0. Furthermore, major patterns and important features from flavonoid-related metabolic profiles were obtained and described by univariate and multivariate statistics, using unpaired parametric 
t
-test, PCA, ASCA, MEBA and 
ROC
approaches. These analyses were performed after recovery of the peak intensity of each 
m/z
feature present in each of the negative mode ionization-derived total ion current (TIC) chromatograms. These HRMS features were compiled under processing of the whole set of the raw TICs with MZmine 2 (

), through the typical steps of normalization, signal detection, deconvolution, deisotopization, filtering, alignment, and gap-filling. As mentioned above, under comparison of LC-PDA data, the flavonoid-related compounds were filtered. The resulting matrix (FIT) corresponding to the combination of Observations (i.e., samples) versus Variables (i.e., features labelled as rt/ 
m/z
pairs) was exported to.csv format and statistically analyzed through the different modules of MetaboAnalyst 4.0 (McGill University, 
Quebec
, 
Canada
).
</p>
         <p>
Funding
</p>
         <p>This study was supported by the Ministerio de Ciencia, Tecnología e Innovacion´, MinCiencias through the project ‘Study of the biotic elicitor application for controlling vascular wilting in carnation: an alternative to the use of synthetic fungicides’ (grant number RC No. 002-2017 Cod.10174558226).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
The authors thank Universidad Militar 
Nueva Granada
and Universidad Nacional de 
Colombia
for their financial support. Gratitude is extended to the Florval S.A.S. company for the rooted cutting donation as well as Laboratorio´de Química de Produtos Naturais at the Institute of Chemistry, University of Sao ˜Paulo, for the analytical support. A. Romero-Rincon´thanks the artist Camila Rodríguez for her support in the scientific illustration of carnation cutting and flower of the graphical abstract.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Abd-elsalam, K.A., 
Aly, I.N.
, Abdel-satar, M.A., 
Khalil, M.S.
, 
Verreet, J.A.
, 
2003
. 

PCR identification of 
Fusarium
genus based on nuclear ribosomal-DNA sequence data

. 
Afr. J. Biothecnol.
2
, 
82–85
. 
https://doi.org/10.5897/AJB2003.000-1016
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Agati, G.
, 
Azzarello, E.
, 
Pollastri, S.
, 
Tattini, M.
, 
2012
. 
Flavonoids as antioxidants in plants: location and functional significance
. 
Plant Sci.
196
, 
67–76
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.plantsci.2012.07.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Agati, G.
, 
Brunetti, C.
, 
Fini, A.
, 
Gori, A.
, 
Guidi, L.
, 
Landi, M.
, 
Sebastiani, F.
, 
Tattini, M.
, 
2020
. 
Are flavonoids effective antioxidants in plants? Twenty years of our investigation
. 
Antioxidants
9
, 
1098
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/antiox9111098
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ahuja, I.
, 
Kissen, R.
, 
Bones, A.M.
, 
2012
. 
Phytoalexins in defense against pathogens
. 
Trends Plant Sci.
17
, 
73–90
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2011.11.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ambawat, S.
, 
Sharma, P.
, 
Yadav, N.R.
, 
Yadav, R.C.
, 
2013
. 
MYB transcription factor genes as regulators for plant responses: an overview
. 
Physiol. Mol. Biol. plants an Int. J. Funct. plant Biol.
19
, 
307–321
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s12298-013-0179-1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ardila, H.D.
, 
Martínez, S.T.
, 
Higuera, B.L.
, 
2013
. 

Levels of constitutive flavonoid biosynthetic enzymes in carnation (
Dianthus caryophyllus
L.) cultivars with differential response to Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. dianthi

. 
Acta Physiol. Plant.
35
, 
1233–1245
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11738-012-1162-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ardila, H.D.
, 
Torres, A.M.
, 
Martínez, S.T.
, 
Higuera, B.L.
, 
2014
. 

Biochemical and molecular evidence for the role of class III peroxidases in the resistance of carnation (
Dianthus caryophyllus
L) to 
Fusar
ium oxysporum f. sp. dianthi

. 
Physiol. Mol. Plant Pathol.
85
, 
42–52
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pmpp.2014.01.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Arfaoui, A.
, 
El Hadrami, A.
, 
Mabrouk, Y.
, 
Sifi, B.
, 
Boudabous, A.
, 
El Hadrami, I.
, 
Daayf, F.
, Ch´erif, M., 
2007
. 

Treatment of chickpea with 
Rhizobium
isolates enhances the expression of phenylpropanoid defense-related genes in response to infection by 
Fusarium oxysporum
f. sp. 
ciceris

. 
Plant Physiol. Biochem.
45
, 
470–479
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2007.04.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baayen, R.P.
, 
Commelin, W.
, 
Phytopathological, S.
, 
1986
. 

Regeneration of vascular tissues in relation to 
Fusarium
wilt resistance of carnation

. 
Neth. J. Plant Pathol.
92
, 
273–285
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01977590
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baayen, R.P.
, 
Elgersma, D.M.
, 
Demmink, J.F.
, 
Sparnaaij, L.D.
, 
1988
. 

Differences in pathogenesis observed among susceptible interactions of carnation with four races of 
Fusarium oxysporum
f.sp. 
dianthi

. 
Neth. J. Plant Pathol
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ BF01998398
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baayen, R.P.
, 
Niemann, G.J.
, 
1989
. 

Correlations between accumulation of dianthramides, dianthalexin and unknown compounds, and partial resistance to 
Fusarium oxysporum
f. sp. 
dianthi
in eleven carnation cultivars

. 
J. Phytopathol.
126
, 
281–292
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1439-0434.1989.tb04491.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baayen, R.P.
, 
Sparnaaij, L.D.
, 
Jansen, J.
, 
Niemann, G.J.
, 
1991
. 

Inheritance of resistance in carnation against 
Fusarium oxysporum
f.sp. 
dianthi
races 1 and 2

, in 
relation to resistance components
. 
Neth. J. Plant Pathol.
97
, 
73–86
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ BF01974271
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baba, S.A.
, 
Malik, S.A.
, 
2015
. 

Determination of total phenolic and flavonoid content, antimicrobial and antioxidant activity of a root extract of 
Arisaema jacquemontii
Blume. J

. 
Taibah Univ. Sci.
9
, 
449–454
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. jtusci.2014.11.001
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Basallote-Ureba, M.J.
, 
Vela-Delgado, M.D.
, 
Capote, N.
, 
Melero-Vara, J.M.
, 
L´opezHerrera, C.J.
, 
Prados-Ligero, A.M.
, 
Talavera-Rubia, M.F.
, 
2016
. 

Control of 
Fusarium
wilt of carnation using organic amendments combined with soil solarization, and report of associated 
Fusarium
species in southern Spain

. 
Crop Protect.
89
, 
184–192
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cropro.2016.07.013
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Baskar, V.
, 
Venkatesh, R.
, 
Ramalingam, S.
, 
2018
. In: 
Gupta, D.K.
, 
Palma, J.M.
, 
Corpas, F. J.
(Eds.), 
Flavonoids (Antioxidants Systems) in Higher Plants and Their Response to Stresses BT - Antioxidants and Antioxidant Enzymes in Higher Plants
. 
Springer International Publishing, Cham
, pp. 
253–268
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319- 75088-0_12
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Beckman, C.H.
, 
2000
. 
Phenolic-storing cells: keys to programmed cell death and periderm formation in wilt disease resistance and in general defence responses in plants?
Physiol. Mol. Plant Pathol.
57
, 
101–110
. 
https://doi.org/10.1006/ pmpp.2000.0287
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bell´es, J.M., L´opez-Gresa, M.P., 
Fayos, J.
, Pall´as, V., 
Rodrigo, I.
, 
Conejero, V.
, 
2008
. 
Induction of cinnamate 4-hydroxylase and phenylpropanoids in virus-infected cucumber and melon plants
. 
Plant Sci.
174
, 
524–533
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. plantsci.2008.02.008
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ben-Yephet, Y.
, 
Shtienberg, D.I.
, 
1997
. 

Effects of the host, the pathogen, the environment and their interactions, on 
Fusarium
Wilt in Carnation

. 
Phytoparasitica
25
, 
207–216
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Boba, A.
, 
Kulma, A.
, 
Kostyn, K.
, 
Starzycki, M.
, 
Starzycka, E.
, 
Szopa, J.
, 
2011
. 

The influence of carotenoid biosynthesis modification on the 
Fusarium culmorum
and 
Fusarium oxysporum
resistance in flax

. 
Physiol. Mol. Plant Pathol.
76
, 
39–47
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.pmpp.2011.06.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Campos, L.
, Lopez-Gresa´, M.P., 
Fuertes, D.
, Bell´es, J.M., 
Rodrigo, I.
, Lison´, P., 
2019
. 
Tomato glycosyltransferase Twi1 plays a role in flavonoid glycosylation and defence against virus
. 
BMC Plant Biol.
19
, 
450
https://doi.org/10.1186/s12870-019-2063-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chiocchetti, A.
, 
Bernardo, I.
, 
Daboussi, M.J.
, 
Garibaldi, A.
, 
Gullino, L.
, 
Langin, T.
, 
Migheli, Q.
, 
2009
. 

Detection of 
Fusarium oxysporum
f. sp. 
dianthi
in carnation tissue by PCR amplification of transposon insertions

. 
Phytopathology
89
, 
1169–1175
. 
https://doi.org/10.1094/PHYTO.1999.89.12.1169
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Curir, P.
, 
Dolci, M.
, 
Dolci, P.
, 
Lanzotti, V.
, 
De Cooman, L.
, 
2003
. 

Fungitoxic phenols from carnation (
Dianthus caryophyllus
) effective against Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. dianthi

. 
Phytochem. Anal.
14
, 
8–12
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/pca.672
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Curir, P.
, 
Dolci, M.
, 
Galeotti, F.
, 
2005
. 

A Phytoalexin-Like Flavonol involved in the carnation (
Dianthus caryophyllus
) - 
Fusarium oxysporum
f. sp. 
dianthi
pathosystem

. 
J. Phytopathol.
153
, 
65–67
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1439-0434.2004.00916.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Curir, P.
, 
Dolci, M.
, 
Lanzotti, V.
, Taglialatela-scafati, O., 
2001
. 

Kaempferide triglycoside: a possible factor of resistance of carnation (
Dianthus caryophyllus
) to Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. dianthi

. 
Phytochemistry
56
, 
717–721
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ S0031-9422(00)00488-X
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Curir, P.
, 
Marchesini, A.
, 
Danieli, B.
, 
Mariani, F.
, 
1996
. 3- 
Hydroxyacetophenone in carnations is a phytoanticipin active against Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. dianthi
. 
Phytochemistry
41
, 
447–450
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(95)00603-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Deng, Y.
, 
Lu, S.
, 
2017
. 
Biosynthesis and regulation of phenylpropanoids in plants
. 
CRC Crit. Rev. Plant Sci.
36
, 
257–290
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 07352689.2017.1402852
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Desmedt, W.
, 
Jonckheere, W.
, 
Nguyen, V.H.
, 
Ameye, M.
, 
De Zutter, N.
, 
De Kock, K.
, 
Debode, J.
, 
Van Leeuwen, T.
, 
Audenaert, K.
, 
Vanholme, B.
, 
Kyndt, T.
, 
2021
. 
The phenylpropanoid pathway inhibitor piperonylic acid induces broad-spectrum pest and disease resistance in plants
. 
Plant. Cell Environ
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/ pce.14119 n/a
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Desta, K.T.
, 
Shin, S.C.
, 
Shim, J.
, 
Kim, G.
, 
Shin, S.C.
, 
El-Aty, A.M.
, 
2016
. 
Flavonoid variations in pathogen-infected plants
. 
Front. Nat. Prod. Chem.
2
, 
3–49
. 
https://doi. org/10.2174/9781681083599116020009
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dihazi, A.
, 
Serghini, M.A.
, 
Jaiti, F.
, 
Daayf, F.
, 
Driouich, A.
, 
Dihazi, H.
, 
El Hadrami, I.
, 
2011
. 

Structural and biochemical changes in salicylic-acid-treated date palm roots challenged with 
Fusarium oxysporum
f. sp. 
albedinis

. 
J. Pathog.
2011
, 
280481
. 
https://doi.org/10.4061/2011/280481
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dodds, P.N.
, 
Rathjen, J.P.
, 
2010
. 
Plant immunity: towards an integrated view of plant–pathogen interactions
. 
Nat. Rev. Genet.
11
, 
539–548
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1038/nrg2812
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dubos, C.
, 
Stracke, R.
, 
Grotewold, E.
, 
Weisshaar, B.
, 
Martin, C.
, 
Lepiniec, L.
, 
2010
. 

MYB transcription factors in 
Arabidopsis

. 
Trends Plant Sci.
15
, 
573–581
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.tplants.2010.06.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dumanovi´c, J., 
Nepovimova, E.
, Natic´, M., Kuˇca, K., Ja´cevic´, V., 
2020
. 
The significance of reactive oxygen species and antioxidant defense system in plants: a concise overview. Front
. 
Plant Sci.
11
, 
552969
https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2020.552969
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fukui, Y.
, 
Tanaka, Y.
, 
Kusumi, T.
, 
Iwashita, T.
, 
Nomoto, K.
, 
2003
. 

A rationale for the shift in colour towards blue in transgenic carnation flowers expressing the flavonoid 3 
′
,5 
′
- hydroxylase gene

. 
Phytochemistry
63
, 
15–23
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422 (02)00684-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Galeotti, F.
, 
Barile, E.
, 
Curir, P.
, 
Dolci, M.
, 
Lanzotti, V.
, 
2008
a. 

Flavonoids from carnation (
Dianthus caryophyllus
) and their antifungal activity

. 
Phytochem. Lett.
1
, 
44–48
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytol.2007.10.001
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Galeotti, F.
, 
Barile, E.
, 
Lanzotti, V.
, 
Dolci, M.
, 
Curir, P.
, 
2008
b. 

Quantification of major flavonoids in carnation tissues (
Dianthus caryophyllus
) as a tool for cultivar discrimination

. 
Z. Naturforsch.
63
, 
161–168
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
G´orniak, I., 
Bartoszewski, R.
, Kr´oliczewski, J., 
2019
. 
Comprehensive review of antimicrobial activities of plant flavonoids
. 
Phytochemistry Rev.
18
, 
241–272
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11101-018-9591-z
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hassan, S.
, 
Mathesius, U.
, 
2012
. 
The role of flavonoids in root-rhizosphere signalling: opportunities and challenges for improving plant-microbe interactions
. 
J. Exp. Bot.
63
, 
3429–3444
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/jxb/err430
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hegde, K.T.
, 
Narayanaswamy, H.
, 
Veeraghanti, K.S.
, Tg, M., 
2017
. 

Efficacy of bio-agents, botanicals and fungicides against 
Fusarium oxysporum
f. sp. 
dianthi
causing wilt of carnation

. 
Int. J. Chem. Stud.
5
, 
139–142
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Higuera, B.L.
, 
Ebrahim-Nesbat, F.
, 
1999
. 

Study of vascular root responses as defense mechanisms in carnation resistance or susceptible to 
Fusarium oxysporum
f. sp. 
dianthi
by transmission electron microscopy

. 
Acta Hortic.
482
, 
101–108
. 
https://doi. org/10.17660/ActaHortic.1999.482.14
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Higuera, B.L.
, 
Montes, V.M.
, 
1996
. 

Contribution of HPLC to the Study of the defense mechanisms acting in carnation (
Dianthus caryophyllus
L.) roots on infection with Fusarium oxysporum f. sp. dianthi

. 
J. High Resolut. Chromatogr.
19
, 
706–708
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/jhrc.1240191213
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hoang, V.L.T.
, 
Innes, D.J.
, 
Shaw, P.N.
, 
Monteith, G.R.
, 
Gidley, M.J.
, 
Dietzgen, R.G.
, 
2015
. 
Sequence diversity and differential expression of major phenylpropanoidflavonoid biosynthetic genes among three mango varieties
. 
BMC Genom.
16
, 
1–12
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/s12864-015-1784-x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Horbach, R.
, 
Navarro-Quesada, A.R.
, 
Knogge, W.
, 
Deising, H.B.
, 
2011
. 
When and how to kill a plant cell: infection strategies of plant pathogenic fungi. J
. 
Plant Physiol.
168
, 
51–62
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jplph.2010.06.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hou, M.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Mu, G.
, 
Cui, S.
, 
Yang, X.
, 
Liu, L.
, 
2020
. 

Molecular cloning and expression characterization of flavonol synthase genes in peanut (
Arachis hypogaea
)

. 
Sci. Rep.
10
, 
17717
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-74763-w
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jones, A.M.
, 
Chattopadhyay, A.
, 
Shukla, M.
, Zon´, J., 
Saxena, P.K.
, 
2012
. 

Inhibition of phenylpropanoid biosynthesis increases cell wall digestibility, protoplast isolation, and facilitates sustained cell division in American elm (
Ulmus americana
)

. 
BMC Plant Biol.
12
, 
75
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-12-75
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kashyap, A.
, Planas-Marqu`es, M., 
Capellades, M.
, 
Valls, M.
, 
Coll, N.S.
, 
2021
. 
Blocking intruders: inducible physico-chemical barriers against plant vascular wilt pathogens
. 
J. Exp. Bot.
72
, 
184–198
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/jxb/eraa444
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kumudini, B.S.
, 
Jayamohan, N.S.
, 
Patil, S.V.
, 
Govardhana, M.
, 
2018
. 
Primary plant metabolism during plant-pathogen interactions and its role in defense
. In: 
Plant Metabolites and Regulation under Environmental Stress
. 
Elsevier Inc
., pp. 
215–229
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-812689-9.00011-X
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lanubile, A.
, 
Bernardi, J.
, 
Battilani, P.
, 
Logrieco, A.
, 
Marocco, A.
, 
2012
. 

Resistant and susceptible maize genotypes activate different transcriptional responses against 
Fusarium verticillioides

. 
Physiol. Mol. Plant Pathol.
77
, 
52–59
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.pmpp.2011.12.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lattanzio, V.
, 
Lattanzio, V.M.T.
, 
Cardinali, A.
, 
Amendola, V.
, 
2006
. 
Role of phenolics in the resistance mechanisms of plants against fungal pathogens and insects
. In: 
Imperato, F.
(Ed.), 
Phytochemistry: Advances in Research
. 
Research Signpost, Kerala
, pp. 
23–67
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Le Roy, J.
, 
Huss, B.
, 
Creach, A.
, 
Hawkins, S.
, 
Neutelings, G.
, 
2016
. 
Glycosylation is a major regulator of phenylpropanoid availability and biological activity in plants. Front
. 
Plant Sci.
7
, 
735
https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2016.00735
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lecomte, C.
, 
Alabouvette, C.
, 
Edel-Hermann, V.
, 
Robert, F.
, 
Steinberg, C.
, 
2016
. 

Biological control of ornamental plant diseases caused by 
Fusarium oxysporum
: a review

. 
Biol. Contr.
101
, 
17–30
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocontrol.2016.06.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, S.
, 
2014
. 
Transcriptional control of flavonoid biosynthesis: fine-tuning of the MYBbHLH-WD40 (MBW) complex. Plant Signal
. 
Behav.
9
https://doi.org/10.4161/ psb.27522 e27522–e27522
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, J.
, 
Osbourn, A.
, 
Ma, P.
, 
2015
. 
MYB Transcription factors as regulators of phenylpropanoid metabolism in plants
. 
Mol. Plant
8
, 
689–708
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.molp.2015.03.012
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Z.
, 
Luan, Y.
, 
Li, J.
, 
Yin, Y.
, 
2016
. 

Expression of a tomato MYB gene in transgenic tobacco increases resistance to 
Fusarium oxysporum
and 
Botrytis cinerea

. 
Eur. J. Plant Pathol.
144
, 
607–617
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10658-015-0799-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Long, L.
, 
Liu, J.
, 
Gao, Y.
, 
Xu, F.-C.
, 
Zhao, J.-R.
, 
Li, B.
, 
Gao, W.
, 
2019
. 
Flavonoid accumulation in spontaneous cotton mutant results in red coloration and enhanced disease resistance
. 
Plant Physiol. Biochem.
143
, 
40–49
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. plaphy.2019.08.021
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lorenc-Kukuła, K.
, Wr´obel-Kwiatkowska, M., 
Starzycki, M.
, 
Szopa, J.
, 
2007
. 

Engineering flax with increased flavonoid content and thus 
Fusarium resistance

. 
Physiol. Mol. Plant Pathol.
70
, 
38–48
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pmpp.2007.05.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lu, Y.
, 
Chen, Q.
, 
Bu, Y.
, 
Luo, R.
, 
Hao, S.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Tian, J.
, 
Yao, Y.
, 
2017
. 
Flavonoid accumulation plays an important role in the rust resistance of malus plant leaves. Front
. 
Plant Sci.
8
, 
1286
https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2017.01286
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ma, D.
, 
Constabel, C.P.
, 
2019
. 
MYB repressors as regulators of phenylpropanoid metabolism in plants
. 
Trends Plant Sci.
24
, 
275–289
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. tplants.2018.12.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ma, D.
, 
Sun, D.
, 
Wang, C.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
Guo, T.
, 
2014
. 
Expression of flavonoid biosynthesis genes and accumulation of flavonoid in wheat leaves in response to drought stress
. 
Plant Physiol. Biochem.
80
, 
60–66
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2014.03.024
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maia, M.
, 
Ferreira, A.E.N.
, 
Nascimento, R.
, 
Monteiro, F.
, 
Traquete, F.
, 
Marques, A.P.
, 
Cunha, J.
, 
Dias, J.E.E.
, 
Cordeiro, C.
, 
Figueiredo, A.
, 
Silva, M.S.
, 
2020
. 
Integrating metabolomics and targeted gene expression to uncover potential biomarkers of fungal/oomycetes-associated disease susceptibility in grapevine
. 
Sci. Rep
. 
1–15
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-72781-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mandal, S.
, 
Mitra, A.
, 
2007
. 

Reinforcement of cell wall in roots of 
Lycopersicon esculentum
through induction of phenolic compounds and lignin by elicitors

. 
Physiol. Mol. Plant Pathol.
71
, 
201–209
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pmpp.2008.02.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mato, M.
, 
Onozaki, T.
, 
Ozeki, Y.
, 
Higeta, D.
, 
Itoh, Y.
, 
Yoshimoto, Y.
, 
Ikeda, H.
, 
Yoshida, H.
, 
Shibata, M.
, 
2000
. 

Flavonoid biosynthesis in white-flowered Sim carnations (
Dianthus caryophyllus
)

. 
Sci. Hortic.
84
, 
333–347
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/S0304-4238(99)00140-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
McLay, E.R.
, 
Pontaroli, A.C.
, 
Wargent, J.J.
, 
2020
. 
UV-B induced flavonoids contribute to reduced biotrophic disease susceptibility in lettuce seedlings. Front
. 
Plant Sci.
11
, 
1691
https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2020.594681
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mierziak, J.
, 
Kostyn, K.
, 
Kulma, A.
, 
2014
. 
Flavonoids as important molecules of plant interactions with the environment
. 
Molecules
19
, 
16240–16265
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.3390/molecules191016240
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Monroy-Mena, S.
, Chac´on-Parra, A.L., Farfan-Angarita´, J.P., 
Martínez-Peralta, S.T.
, 
Ardila-Barrantes, H.D.
, 
2019
. 

Selection of reference genes for transcriptional analysis in the pathosystem carnation (
Dianthus caryophyllus
L.)- 
Fusarium oxysporu
m f. sp. dianthi

. 
Rev. Colomb. Quim.
48
, 
5–14
. 

https://doi.org/10.15446/rev.colomb.quim. v48 
n2.72771

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morkunas, I.
, 
Bednarski, W.
, 
2008
. 

Fusarium oxysporum
-induced oxidative stress and antioxidative defenses of yellow lupine embryo axes with different sugar levels. J

. 
Plant Physiol.
165
, 
262–277
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jplph.2007.01.020
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morkunas, I.
, 
Narona, D.
, 
Nowak, W.
, 
Samardakiewicz, S.
, 
Remlein-Starosta, D.
, 
2011
. 

Cross-talk interactions of sucrose and 
Fusarium oxysporum
in the phenylpropanoid pathway and the accumulation and localization of flavonoids in embryo axes of yellow lupine. J

. 
Plant Physiol.
168
, 
424–433
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. jplph.2010.08.017
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niemann, G.J.
, 
Liem, J.
, van der Kerk-van 
Hoof, A.
, 
Niessen, W.M.A.
, 
1992
. 

Phytoalexins, benzoxazinones, 
N
-aroylanthranilates and 
N
-aroylanilines, from 
Fusarium
-infected carnation stems

. 
Phytochemistry
31
, 
3761–3767
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031- 9422(00)97523-X
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pandey, A.
, 
Misra, P.
, 
Kumar, P.
, 
2015
. 
Constitutive expression of Arabidopsis MYB transcription factor, AtMYB11
, in 
tobacco modulates flavonoid biosynthesis in favor of flavonol accumulation
. 
Plant Cell Rep.
34
, 
1515–1528
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ s00299-015-1803-z
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Patra, B.
, 
Schluttenhofer, C.
, 
Wu, Y.
, 
Pattanaik, S.
, 
Yuan, L.
, 
2013
. 
Transcriptional regulation of secondary metabolite biosynthesis in plants
. 
Biochim. Biophys. Acta - Gene Regul. Mech.
1829
, 
1236–1247
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. bbagrm.2013.09.006
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Petrussa, E.
, 
Braidot, E.
, 
Zancani, M.
, 
Peresson, C.
, 
Bertolini, A.
, 
Patui, S.
, 
Vianello, A.
, 
2013
. 
Plant flavonoids-biosynthesis, transport and involvement in stress responses
. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
14
, 
14950–14973
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms140714950
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pfaffl, M.W.
, 
2001
. 
A new mathematical model for relative quantification in real-time RT-PCR
. 
Nucleic Acids Res.
29
, e 
45
https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/29.9.e45
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pluskal, T.
, 
Castillo, S.
, 
Villar-Briones, A.
, Oreˇsiˇc, M., 
2010
. 
MZmine 2: modular framework for processing, visualizing, and analyzing mass spectrometry-based molecular profile data
. 
BMC Bioinf.
11
, 
395
https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-11- 395
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pouralibaba, H.R.
, P´erez-de-Luque, A., 
Rubiales, D.
, 
2017
. 

Histopathology of the infection on resistant and susceptible lentil accessions by two contrasting pathotypes of 
Fusarium oxysporum
f.sp. lentis

. 
Eur. J. Plant Pathol.
148
, 
53–63
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s10658-016-1068-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ramirez-Prado, J.S.
, 
Abulfaraj, A.A.
, 
Rayapuram, N.
, 
Benhamed, M.
, 
Hirt, H.
, 
2018
. 
Plant immunity: from signaling to epigenetic control of defense
. 
Trends Plant Sci
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2018.06.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ravaglia, D.
, 
Espley, R.V.
, 
Henry-Kirk, R.A.
, 
Andreotti, C.
, 
Ziosi, V.
, 
Hellens, R.P.
, 
Costa, G.
, 
Allan, A.C.
, 
2013
. 

Transcriptional regulation of flavonoid biosynthesis in nectarine (
Prunus persica
) by a set of R2R3 MYB transcription factors

. 
BMC Plant Biol.
13
, 
68
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-13-68
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
S´a, 
R.A
., 
Argolo, A.C.C.
, 
Napole˜ao, T.H.
, 
Gomes, F.S.
, 
Santos, N.D.L.
, 
Melo, C.M.L.
, 
Albuquerque, A.C.
, 
Xavier, H.S.
, 
Coelho, L.C.B.B.
, 
Bieber, L.W.
, 
Paiva, P.M.G.
, 
2009
. 

Antioxidant, 
Fusarium
growth inhibition and 
Nasutitermes corniger
repellent activities of secondary metabolites from 
Myracrodruon urundeuva
heartwood

. 
Int. Biodeterior. Biodegrad.
63
, 
470–477
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ibiod.2009.01.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sahebi, M.
, 
Hanafi, M.M.
, 
van Wijnen, A.J.
, 
Akmar, A.S.N.
, 
Azizi, P.
, 
Idris, A.S.
, 
Taheri, S.
, 
Foroughi, M.
, 
2017
. 

Profiling secondary metabolites of plant defence mechanisms and oil palm in response to 
Ganoderma boninense
attack

. 
Int. Biodeterior. Biodegrad.
122
, 
151–164
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. ibiod.2017.04.016
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Santiago, R.
, 
Armas, R. De
, 
2009
. 

Changes in soluble and cell wall-bound hydroxycinnamic and hydroxybenzoic acids in sugarcane cultivars inoculated with 
Sporisorium scitamineum
sporidia

. 
Eur. J. Plant Pathol.
124
, 
439–450
. 
https://doi. org/10.1007/s10658-009-9431-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Santos-Rodriguez, J.
, 
Coy-Barrera, E.
, 
Ardila, H.D.
, 
2021
. 

Mycelium dispersion from 
Fusarium oxysporum
f. sp. 
dianthi
elicits a reduction of wilt severity and influences phenolic profiles of carnation (
Dianthus caryophyllus
L.) roots

. 
Plants
10
, 
1–20
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schymanski, E.L.
, 
Jeon, J.
, 
Gulde, R.
, 
Fenner, K.
, 
Ruff, M.
, 
Singer, H.P.
, 
Hollender, J.
, 
2014
. 
Identifying small molecules via high resolution mass spectrometry: communicating confidence
. 
Environ. Sci. Technol.
48
, 
2097–2098
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/es5002105
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sekhon, R.S.
, 
Kuldau, G.
, 
Mansfield, M.
, 
Chopra, S.
, 
2006
. 

Characterization of 
Fusarium
- induced expression of flavonoids and PR genes in maize

. 
Physiol. Mol. Plant Pathol.
69
, 
109–117
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pmpp.2007.02.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shah, I.
, 
Shah, M.A.
, 
Nawaz, M.A.
, 
Pervez, S.
, 
Noreen, N.
, 
Vargas-de
la Cruz, C.
, 
Khan, F.
, 
Blundell, R.
, 
Briffa, J.
, 
Azzopardi, J.
, 
Niaz, K.
, 
2020
. 
Analysis of other phenolics (capsaicin, gingerol, and alkylresorcinols)
. In: 
Silva, A.S.
, 
Nabavi, S.F.
, 
Saeedi, M.
, 
Nabavi, S.M.
(Eds.), 
Recent Advances in Natural Products Analysis
, vol. 6. 
Elsevier Inc
., pp. 
255–271
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/b978-0-12-816455-6.00006-8
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smilde, A.K.
, 
Jansen, J.J.
, 
Hoefsloot, H.C.J.
, 
Lamers, R.-J.A.N.
, 
van der Greef, J.
, 
Timmerman, M.E.
, 
2005
. 
ANOVA-simultaneous component analysis (ASCA): a new tool for analyzing designed metabolomics data
. 
Bioinformatics
21
, 
3043–3048
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bti476
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Soto-Sedano, J.C.
, 
Clavijo-Ortiz, M.J.
, 
Filgueira-Duarte, J.J.
, 
2012
. 

Phenotypic evaluation of the resistance in F1 carnation populations to vascular wilt caused by 
Fusarium oxyspor
um f.sp. dianthi

. 
Agron. Colomb.
30
, 
172–178
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stracke, R.
, 
Jahns, O.
, 
Keck, M.
, 
Tohge, T.
, 
Niehaus, K.
, 
Fernie, A.R.
, 
Weisshaar, B.
, 
2010
. 

Analysis of production of flavonol glycosides-dependent flavonol glycoside accumulation in 
Arabidopsis thaliana
plants reveals MYB11-, MYB12- and MYB111- independent flavonol glycoside accumulation

. 
New Phytol.
188
, 
985–1000
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03421.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Treutter, D.
, 
2006
. 
Significance of flavonoids in plant resistance: a review
. 
Environ. Chem. Lett.
4
, 
147–157
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10311-006-0068-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Treutter, D.
, 
2005
. 
Significance of flavonoids in plant resistance and enhancement of their biosynthesis
. 
Plant Biol.
7
, 
581–591
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2005-873009
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vogt, T.
, 
2010
. 
Phenylpropanoid biosynthesis
. 
Mol. Plant
3
, 
2–20
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1093/mp/ssp106
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, X.
, 
Niu, Y.
, 
Zheng, Y.
, 
2021
. 
Multiple Functions of MYB transcription factors in abiotic stress responses
. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
22 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms22116125
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wiesel, L.
, 
Newton, A.C.
, 
Elliott, I.
, 
Booty, D.
, 
Gilroy, E.M.
, 
Birch, P.R.J.
, 
Hein, I.
, 
2014
. 
Molecular effects of resistance elicitors from biological origin and their potential for crop protection. Front
. 
Plant Sci.
5
, 
655
https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2014.00655
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wolcan, S.M.
, Malbr´an, I., 
Mourelos, C.A.
, 
Sisterna, M.N.
, Gonz´alez, M., del, P., 
Alippi, A. M.
, 
Nico, A.
, 
Lori, G.A.
, 
2018
. In: 
McGovern, R.J.
, 
Elmer, W.H.
(Eds.), 
Diseases of Carnation BT - Handbook of Florists’ Crops Diseases
. 
Springer International Publishing, Cham
, pp. 
317–378
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-39670-5_14
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xia, J.
, 
Sinelnikov, I.V.
, 
Wishart, D.S.
, 
2011
. 
MetATT: a web-based metabolomics tool for analyzing time-series and two-factor datasets
. 
Bioinformatics
27
, 
2455–2456
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btr392
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xing, L.-P.
, 
He, L.-Q.
, 
Xiao, J.
, 
Chen, Q.-G.
, 
Li, M.-H.
, 
Shang, Y.
, 
Zhu, Y.-F.
, 
Chen, P.-D.
, 
Cao, A.-Z.
, 
Wang, X.-E.
, 
2017
. 

An UDP-glucosyltransferase gene from barley confers disease resistance to 
Fusarium
head blight

. 
Plant Mol. Biol. Rep.
35
, 
224–236
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11105-016-1014-y
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, F.
, 
Li, L.
, 
Zhang, W.
, 
Cheng, H.
, 
Sun, N.
, 
Cheng, S.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
2012
. 

Isolation, characterization, and function analysis of a flavonol synthase gene from 
Ginkgo biloba

. 
Mol. Biol. Rep.
39
, 
2285–2296
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11033-011-0978-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yadav, V.
, 
Wang, Z.
, 
Wei, C.
, 
Amo, A.
, 
Ahmed, B.
, 
Yang, X.
, 
Zhang, X.
, 
2020
. 
Phenylpropanoid pathway engineering: an emerging approach towards plant defense
. 
Pathogens
9
, 
1–25
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens9040312
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zaynab, M.
, 
Fatima, M.
, 
Abbas, S.
, 
Sharif, Y.
, 
Umair, M.
, 
Zafar, M.H.
, 
Bahadar, K.
, 
2018
. 
Role of secondary metabolites in plant defense against pathogens
. 
Microb. Pathog.
124
, 
198–202
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.micpath.2018.08.034
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, J.
, 
Zhang, S.
, 
Li, H.
, 
Du, H.
, 
Huang, H.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
Hu, Y.
, 
Liu, H.
, 
Liu, Y.
, 
Yu, G.
, 
Huang, Y.
, 
2016
. 
Identification of transcription factors ZmMYB111 and ZmMYB148 involved in phenylpropanoid metabolism. Front
. 
Plant Sci.
7
, 
148
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.3389/fpls.2016.00148
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhao, J.
, 
2015
. 
Flavonoid transport mechanisms: how to go, and with whom
. 
Trends Plant Sci.
20
, 
576–585
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2015.06.007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhao, J.
, 
Dixon, R.A.
, 
2010
. 
The “ins” and “outs” of flavonoid transport
. 
Trends Plant Sci.
15
, 
72–80
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tplants.2009.11.006
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
