<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113022</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Structure and activity of a novel robust peroxidase from Alkanna frigida cell culture</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Boraginaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Boraginaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arachis hypogaea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
Boiss. (Boraginaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Boraginaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ocimum basilicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
O. basilicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arnebia euchroma
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lithospermum officinale
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Onosma dasytrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nonea caspica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Daucus carota
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ipomoea batatas
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Solanum aviculare
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eruca vesicaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana tubacum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Allium sativum
L
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Jatropha curcas
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Brassica oleracea
(
Thongsook and Barrett, 2005
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eruca vesicaria
(
Nadaroglu et al., 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. thaliana
POX
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Salvia splendens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. hypogaea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Panicum virgatum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
Boiss. (Boraginaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>A. frigida</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Structure and activity of a novel robust peroxidase from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
cell culture

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Saeed Soleimani Asl
a
, Ali Asghar Karkhane
a
, Javad Zamani Amirzakaria
a
,

Kambiz Akbari Noghabi 
a
, Jaleh Ghashghaie
b
, Kamahldin haghbeen

a, 
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a

National Institute for Genetic Engineering and 
Biotechnology
, 
Tehran
, 
Iran
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Laboratoire d’ Ecologie, Syst´ematique
et Evolution (ESE), Universite

´de Paris-Sud, CNRS, AgroParisTech, Universite´de Paris-Saclay, 91400 Orsay, 
France
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boraginaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Active site pocket</p>
         <p>Callus</p>
         <p>Functional stability</p>
         <p>Peanut peroxidase</p>
         <p>Suicide substrate</p>
         <p>
A B S T 
R
A C T
</p>
         <p>
Demands for peroxidases (POX)s with diverse physicochemical properties have steadily grown as more applications of POXs are demonstrated. Plants are among the best sources of versatile POXs, and plant biotechnology, as an agricultural hassle-free technology, promises to circumvent the limitations of natural resource exploitation and to address the demands. Following this trend, it was shown that POX production steadily increased during the 31-day subculture of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
(from 
<tp:taxon-name>Boraginaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) callus on Murashige-Skoog medium containing 2,4- dichlorophenoxyacetic acid (10 
6
M) and kinetin (10 
5
M). The purified cationic enzyme (
POXalf
) maintained its optimal activity over pH 4–7 for 2 years. It was resistant to H 
2
O 
2
high concentrations (IC50 = 543.7 mM) and showed high specific activity in the reaction with phenol (4320.5 AU mg 
1
&gt;
20-fold of HRP AU). Furthermore, the specificity constant ratio of guaiacol to phenol indicated a 100 times faster reaction of 
POXalf
with guaiacol. However, in contrast to HRP, it had little effect on diazo derivatives of aniline and meta-diaminobenzene. Based on the resulting primary structure from the tandem mass analysis, the 
POXalf
3D structure was constructed via homology modelling. Despite the high topological similarity between the HRP and 
POXalf
structures, there were important differences between the active site pockets that could explain the observed differences in the corresponding substrate spectra and the specific activities. Considering the dynamics of 
POXalf
production, its inactivity towards IAA and its high affinity for guaiacol, 
POXalf
may have associated roles with 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
cell wall construction and monolignol metabolism.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Despite advances in the production of various enzymes by employing genetic engineering techniques, the preparation of some enzymes still relies on extraction from natural resources such as papain, ficain, bromelain, and peroxidase (POX), which are all of plant origin 

. POX (EC.1.11.1.x) is a ubiquitous oxidoreductase with the ability to reduce one molecule of hydrogen peroxide to two molecules of water at the expense of oxidizing two reducing molecules (

). This ability, in addition to its affinity for a broad spectrum of reducing species, has endowed POXs with the possibility of participating in vital physiological processes in various organisms and to find versatile applications in different industries (

). An important subgroup of the POX superfamily belongs to Class III plant POXs (EC 1.11.1.7), which are extracellular enzymes 

). Due to its accessibility, stability, and important applications, horseradish peroxidase (HRP) has already reached the market (

).
</p>
         <p>
The large-scale preparation of HRP relies on horseradish cultivation, which is currently ongoing in several countries (

). The global HRP market was valued at approximately 38 million USD in 2018, and it is anticipated to reach 73 million USD by the end of 2025, growing by approximately 8.5% annually during 2019–2025 (

). However, the seasonal availability of horseradish combined with low yields makes this method of HRP production problematic. In addition to the cultivation hassle, the current large-scale production of HRP offers mainly 
one type
of this enzyme (mainly HRP-C) (

).
</p>
         <p>
As the research proceeds, the POX applications have also expanded, ranging from the pulp, paper, textile, and polymer industries to immunoassays, analytical, bioanalytical and diagnostic kits as well as biosensor fabrication, wastewater treatment, etc. (

). Concomitantly, the anticipated possible POX applications have increased the demand for miscellaneous POXs with diverse operational stabilities, substrate spectra, and pH tolerances. This trend has worked as the driving force behind the ongoing research on different POXs (

).
</p>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>
E-mail addresses:
Kamahl@nigeb.ac.ir, Kamahlh@gmail.com (K. haghbeen).
</p>
         <p>
In contrast to the classical method of HRP production, some biotechnology-based methods, such as plant cell and hairy root culture, are bioreactor-dependent technologies (

). These approaches allow us to bypass the biological growth period of the plant as well as its agricultural difficulties. Therefore, the desired product is built up under controlled 
in vitro
conditions and harvested at the end of each subculture. Plant cell and tissue culture not only boosted the search for novel POXs but also improve the current knowledge about these important enzymes from both an applied and physiological point of view (

; 

). In fact, studies on peanut (
<tp:taxon-name>
Arachis hypogaea
</tp:taxon-name>
) cell culture resulted in the first POX crystallography report (

). There are still serious challenges ahead for plant cell culture to be used in cost-effective large-scale production plans (

), however, advances in this field are promising (

).
</p>
         <p>
Considering the booming applicability of POXs and the growing demands for versatile 
types
of these enzymes, the production of a novel POX from the cell culture of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
Boiss. (Boraginaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
POXalf
) was studied. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
is a 
<tp:taxon-name>Boraginaceae</tp:taxon-name>
plant with the ability to produce both phenolic acids and naphthoquinone derivatives in its root (

). Callus induction occurs easily in its root explants, and the production of 
POXalf
steadily increases as the subculture of the cells ages. The essential physicochemical properties of this enzyme are presented and discussed in the context of its 3D structure.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.1. Callus proliferation and 
POXalf
production

</title>
         <p>
Callus induction gradually occurred after Day 7 of implantation of the root explants of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
on solid MS medium. The resulting cells proliferated on the same medium in darkness at 25 
◦
C (
Fig. 1A
), with an average growth of 280% (
Fig. 1B
). The results were quantified (
Fig. 1C
) by using a standard curve (activity unit versus mg of the enzyme, 
Fig. S1A
) for commercial HRP. 
Fig. 1C
reveals the remarkable POX content of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
callus compared with the other 4 calluses. This could be a result of either higher activity, higher production of 
POXalf
or a combination of both factors.
</p>
         <p>
The dynamics of 
POXalf
production were studied in the context of catalase (CAT) activity in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
calli at different time intervals after the subculture, as they both deal with H 
2
O 
2
. 
Fig. 1D
shows that CAT gradually left its role to 
POXalf
. As a result, 
POXalf
production increased throughout the subculture. A similar phenomenon was also observed during the proliferation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ocimum basilicum
</tp:taxon-name>
calli (

). In contrast to the disproportionation action of CAT on hydrogen peroxide, as shown in Equation (1), POX is able to host different organic molecules as electron donors. Therefore, in addition to water, a pair of organic radicals are also produced during a catalytic cycle of POX, see Equation (2). This capability allows 
POXalf
to support both the developmental phenomena and the active biosynthetic processes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
cells during growth and ageing on solid culture (

).
</p>
         <p>Catalase</p>
         <p>
2H 
2
O 
2
→ 2H 
2
O + O 
2
(1)
</p>
         <p>Peroxidase</p>
         <p>
2RH + H2O2 → 2 
R
⋅ + 2H2O (2)
</p>
         <p>

2.2. Purification of 

POXalf
</p>
         <p>
POXalf
was purified to homogeneity, as verified by 
SDS
– 
PAGE
(
Fig. 2A
), through a 4-step procedure. The quantified results of this method are summarized in 
Table 1
. The salt precipitation step removed approximately 31% of the undesirable proteins from the raw extract, with a less than 10% loss of POX activity (
Table 1
). Although size exclusion chromatography (
Fig. 2B
) gave rise to a 3-fold purification, it was the cation-exchange chromatography on S-Sepharose (
Fig. 2C
) that resulted in 117-fold purification of 
POXalf
. The UV–visible spectrum of the purified enzyme (
Fig. 2D
) showed the characteristic absorption band of the haem group of plant class III-POXs (

) with a Reinheitszah ratio (RZ = A402/A280) value of 0.57, close to the RZ value of soybean POXs (0.5) (

), 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. basilicum
</tp:taxon-name>
(0.67) (

), and tomato POX (0.7) (

).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Ammonium sulfate precipitation.
</p>
         <p>
b
SP: Specific activity was calculated by using 
ε
= 6500 cm 
1
M 
1
for the 
516
quinone-imine product (

).
</p>
         <p>
The yields of POX production by the hairy roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Daucus carota
</tp:taxon-name>
(2.1 U mg 
1
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipomoea batatas
</tp:taxon-name>
(15.6 U mg 
1
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Solanum aviculare
</tp:taxon-name>
(7.6 U mg 
1
) were reported on the basis of the total proteins of the corresponding raw extracts (5.8, 6.5, and 
4.9 mg
g 
1
of the fresh root, respectively) using guaiacol in the assay measurements (

). Regardless of the different substrates used in the activity assays, these data can be compared with the data in the first row of 
Table 1
, indicating an approximately 2-fold higher protein content of the roots with POX activities, at least one-third of that of 
POXalf
. As comparable data, the production of peanut POX (
POXpnt
) is also noteworthy. An enzyme yield of 3.8 μg g 
1
of cells was reported for cationic 
POXpnt
after proliferation of the peanut cells in a suspension culture for 14 days. This gives a pure 
POXpnt
yield of 
7.6 mg
kg 
1
peanut cells with a specific activity of 1477 U mg 
1
(in the presence of guaiacol) over one month (

) versus 
2 mg
of pure 
POXalf
per kg of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
callus with a specific activity of 4320.5 U mg 
1
(in the presence of phenol) after a 31-day subculture (
Table 1
). These data show the remarkable specific activity of 
POXalf,
which is rooted in the kinetics specifications demonstrated below.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.3. Essential physicochemical properties of 

POXalf
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3.1. MW, optimal pH and thermal stability
</title>
         <p>
In parallel with the structural analysis results (presented in the next section), an average molecular weight of 33.5 ± 1 kD was determined for 
POXalf
from its 
SDS
– 
PAGE
analysis (
Fig. 2A
). This is close to the MW of the cationic POXs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eruca vesicaria
</tp:taxon-name>
leaves (34 kD) (

) and the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nicotiana tubacum
</tp:taxon-name>
cell culture (34 kD) (

). Two-dimensional gel isoelectric focusing (2-D gel IEF, 
Fig. 3A
), revealed that 
POXalf
was a mixture of several cationic POXs with close MWs and PI ranging from 9 to 10. A similar range of PI was reported for some other cationic POXs, such as garlic (
<tp:taxon-name>
Allium sativum
L
</tp:taxon-name>
) POXs (

) and POX isozymes obtained from the cell culture of tobacco (

).
</p>
         <p>
The optimal pH of POX activity may vary from one substrate to another because the changes in pH influence the redox potentials of both the substrate and the intermediate I [oxyferryl haem (Fe 
IV
––O) cation radical], which is formed after a reaction of H 
2
O 
2
with a POX (

). 
Fig. 3B
indicates that 
POXalf
showed its optimal activity at pH 5.5 and maintained 75% of its optimal activity between pH 4.5 and 
7 in
the presence of phenol. Changing the substrate from phenol to guaiacol shifted the range of the optimal pH to 3.5 to 6, while there were no significant changes in the optimal activity. Although a few plant POXs, such as POX of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jatropha curcas
</tp:taxon-name>
leaves (

), could maintain their optimal activities over a wider range of pH values, many plant POXs show sharp activity drops within a ≤1 unit change around the optimal pH, such as cationic POXs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brassica oleracea
(
Thongsook and Barrett, 2005
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and sorghum grain (

). It is also understood from 
Fig. 3C
that 
POXalf
tolerates high temperatures during the assay period, but it is not stable above 50 
◦
C (
Fig. 3D
), regardless of the substrate identity. Similar feedback to the temperature changes has been reported for many POXs, including those of sorghum grain (

) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eruca vesicaria
(
Nadaroglu et al., 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Examination of the shelf life of the 
POXalf
solution at 4 
◦
C revealed its high stability at the examined temperature, as there was only a 15% decrease in the functional stability of the enzyme after 2 years (
Fig. 3E and F
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3.2. Substrate spectrum
</title>
         <p>
To examine the ability of 
POXalf
to oxidize different 
types
of substrates, synthetic phenolic, catecholic, guaiacolic, and aniline derivatives of the diazo dyes, illustrated in 
Fig. 4
, were reacted with 
POXalf
in the presence of H 
2
O 
2
. Using this diazo skeleton allowed us to control both the structural and electronic changes in the derivatives. In addition, the course of the enzymatic reactions could be followed spectrophotometrically (

). These examinations revealed that 
POXalf
was able to oxidize phenolic, guaiacolic, and catecholic azo derivatives (
Fig. S2
, Supplementary document). It has been demonstrated that HRP can oxidize all of the structures illustrated in 
Fig. 4
, including IV and 
V
(

). However, the reactions of 
POXalf
with monoamines (structure IV) were slow (
Fig. S2D
, supplementary document), and reactions with structure 
V
did not proceed. Unlike HRP but similar to cationic 
POXpnt
, 
POXalf
had little effect on indole-3-acetic acid (IAA) (
Fig. S2E
, supplementary document). This suggests that 
POXalf
might have no direct impact on the regulation of IAA homeostasis (

). However, similar to other plant POXs, 
POXalf
could easily oxidize ascorbate (
Fig. S2F
, Supplementary document).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.3.3. Kinetics parameters of 

POXalf
</title>
         <p>
The kinetic parameters of 
POXalf
for phenol, guaiacol, H 
2
O 
2
and KCN are shown in 
Table 2
. This data promotes the practical importance of 
POXalf
. A specific activity of 4320.5 AU mg 
1
(in the presence of phenol) was reported for 
POXalf
, which was approximately 20 times higher than the corresponding specific activity reported for commercial HRP (206 AU mg 
1
) (

). This high specific activity could be behind the significant difference between the POX activities illustrated in 
Fig. 1C
. However, 
Table 2
shows the higher affinity of 
POXalf
towards guaiacol with a fast rate of reaction. This gives guaiacol a specificity constant more than 100 times higher than that of phenol in its reaction with 
POXalf
. These data reveal significantly different specific activities of 
POXalf
compared with those of HRP and 
POXpnt
(

).
</p>
         <p>
Similar to other plant type-III POXs, 
POXalf
was inhibited at higher concentrations of H 
2
O 
2
as well as by KCN. However, the high IC50 value of H 
2
O 
2
revealed the remarkable functional stability of 
POXalf
in the presence of this suicide substrate. The 
Km
values of 
POXalf
for guaiacol and H 
2
O 
2
are comparable to the 
Km
values reported for cationic POXs of garlic (9.5 and 2 mM) (

) and broccoli (8.8 and 9.73 mM) (

), respectively. Possible roles of cationic POXs in the metabolism of monolignols have been documented (

). Considering the dynamics of 
POXalf
production (
Fig. 1D
), its inactivity towards IAA and its high affinity for guaiacol support the assumption that this cationic enzyme might have associated roles with 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
cell wall construction and the regulation of cell wall plasticity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.4. 
POXalf
structure

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.4.1. Primary structure of 

POXalf
</title>
         <p>
Mass analysis of 
POXalf
, taken from the SDS-PADE spot (
Fig. 2A
), led to the identification of the peptide fragments that all belonged to plant POXs (
Table S1A
, Supplementary document). Analysis of this data by X! Tandem (xtpcpp-mingwv0.4.27) revealed a 38.85% overlap between the abundant fragments and the cationic POX of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Salvia splendens
</tp:taxon-name>
(
POXsp
), 
Table S1B
. In view of the mass analysis results (both full and partial digestions) and the alignment of the recognized peptides with the primary structure of 
POXsp
(https://www.genome.jp/entry/up: A0A4D8ZTK7_SALSN), an amino acid sequence was identified for 
POXalf
(
Table 3
). The consistency of the resolved primary structure was controlled by amplification of the corresponding cDNA and finding the putative gene of the enzyme by using the designed specific primers for 
POXalf
introduced in the experimental section (data not shown here). Analysis of the data shown in 
Table 3
shows that 
POXalf
has a sequence identity and similarity of 47.1 and 63.4% with HRP, 84.3 and 91.1% with 
POXsp
, 70.6 and 83.6% with 
POXpnt
, and 49.3 and 68.8% with POX of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
. Although a study of 
POXalf
glycosylation was beyond the objectives of this research, 
Table 3
and the electrophoretic mobility of 
POXalf
(
Fig. 2A
) indicate that 
POXalf
is moderately glycosylated compared with HRP-C (approximately 10 kD) (

).
</p>
         <p>

2.4.2. 3D structure of 

POXalf
</p>
         <p>
BLAST of the 
POXalf
sequence against the protein database had 3 hits, including 1SCH (

), 5TWT (

), and 1PA2 (

) with a sequence identity of 70.65, 64.16, and 49.67% belonging to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. hypogaea
</tp:taxon-name>
(peanut), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Panicum virgatum
</tp:taxon-name>
(switchgrass), and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
, respectively. Therefore, 1SCH was selected as the template for the homology modelling. Accordingly, 6 models were built with the genetic Algorithm 341 (GA341) score of 1.0. Although all of the predicted models had close discrete optimized protein energy (DOPE) scores close to 30000, the model with the least Modeller objective function (molpdf) score of 1571.79 was selected for 
POXalf
(
Fig. 5A
). The structure was validated by ProSA tools. The Z score of the model (8.26) was in the range of the structures identified by X-ray diffraction (
Fig. S4A
, Supplementary document). The Ramachandran plot of the 
POXalf
model revealed that 96.22 and 2.40% of the amino acid residues were in favoured and acceptable conformations, respectively, while only 1.38% of the residues were experiencing steric strain (
Fig. S4B
, Supplementary document). The quality of the model structure was further assessed by a Verify3D program that investigated the folding compatibility of the atomic Model (3D) with its own amino acid sequence (1D). The resulting profile of the residues (
Fig. S4C
, Supplementary document) had scores between 0.1 and 0.71, while 97.95% of the residues had an average 3D–1D score
&gt;
0.2. The compatibility score
&gt;
0 in a VERIFY3D graph corresponds to an acceptable side-chain environment (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.4.3. Structural features of 

POXalf
</title>
         <p>
The refinement of the selected model was carried out through 120 ns MD. The RMSD plot (
Fig. 6A
) revealed that the structure reached full stability in less than 90 ns. The refinement of the structural attributes of 
POXalf
before and after MD is summarized in 
Table S2
(Supplementary document) and discussed below.
</p>
         <p>

2.4.3.1. Overall fold of 
POXalf
.

The core fold of plant POXs is similar due to the special topological arrangement of the 10 α- helices, designated by letters from A to J, but they are usually accompanied by some variable helices. For instance, there are two more short helices after helix B (
Fig. 5B
, in salmon colour) in both the 
POXalf
and HRP structures, while 
POXpnt
contains only helix B (

). These differences make the total number of helices in plant POXs dissimilar, with 
13 in
POXpnt
, 
15 in
POXalf
and 
16 in
HRP (
Fig. 5B
). Key residues for the catalytic activity of a plant POX reside on helices B and F, which are located on two sides (distal and proximal, respectively) of the haem group (
Fig. 5A
, in green colour). Although the β- strands do not play a significant role in the overall folding of plant POXs, a short antiparallel β- sheet is observed near the haem group, i.e., residues 174–176 and 
209–211 in
POXalf
(
Fig. 5A
, in purple colour) and 173–175 and 
210–212 in
POXpnt
(

).
</p>
         <p>
2.4.3.2. Disulfide bonds, salt bridge, and calcium ions.
The functional stability of the 
POXalf
solution at 4 
◦
C over 2 years is illustrated in 
Fig. 3E and F
. Plant POX folding owes its stability to some structural elements that support the scaffold of the enzyme against the hydrodynamic pressure of the solution. Four conserved disulfide bonds and one salt bridge (
Table S2
, Supplementary document) remarkably decreased the degrees of freedom of the structural components of the enzyme. The disulfide bonds of C10–C90, C43–C48, C96–C289, and C175–C 
200 in
POXalf
(
Fig. 5A
in yellow colour) match the C11–C91, C44–C49, C97–C290, C176–C201 and C11–C91, C44–C49, C97–C301, C177–C209 bonds in 
POXpnt
and HRP-C1, respectively (

; 

). D98 and 
R
122 in
POXalf
also build the salt bridge (2.89 Å, 
Table S2
) between the helix D and the adjacent loop. This is achieved by D99- 
R
123 in
both 
POXpnt
(2.82 Å) and HRP-C1 (2.90 Å).
</p>
         <p>
Two Ca 
2+
ions occupy 2 cavities, close to helices B and F, on both sides of the haem group (
Fig. 5A and C
). Both the distal and proximal calcium ions are surrounded by residues that provide them with favourable electrostatic interactions that work as local constraints and enhance the structural stability of the enzyme. 
Fig. 5C
illustrates the surrounding residues of Ca ions in 
POXalf
. Among these residues, D42 directly connects helix B to the distal Ca ion, and a similar role is played by T168 on helix F (
Fig. 5C
). Identical to HRP-C, D43, 
V
46, D50, S 
52 in
POXpnt
are the surrounding residues of distal Ca 
2+
, while T170, D214, T217, and D 
222 in
POXpnt
(
Table S2
, Supplementary document) and T171, D222, T225, and D 
230 in
HRP-C encircle the proximal Ca 
2+
(

). This evidence supports the idea regarding the conserved microenvironment of these ions in plant POXs.
</p>
         <p>

2.4.3.3. Prosthetic group of haem (iron 
III
protoporphyrin IX).

The haem group of a plant POX occupies the central space between helices B and F. It anchors to the protein skeleton by strong H-bonds of its propionate moieties with a few conserved residues. However, small differences are observed in the arrangements of the H-bonds. In 
POXalf
, 
R
30 and 
R
174 produce strong double-interactions with each of the propionate moieties of the haem group (
Table S2
and 
Fig. 5A
in purple). The stabilizing effects of these bonds are seen in the RMSF plot of POXalf (
Fig. 6B
). In fact, the impact of these interactions on the overall stability of 
POXalf
is comparable with those of the salt bridge and Ca ions (
Fig. 6B
). A similar arrangement is observed in 
POXpnt
, where 
R
31, S35, and Q175 participate in H-bonds with haem propionates (2.95, 2.86, and 2.98 Å, respectively), while S73 and 
R
75 stand further at distances of 4.76 and 4.03 Å (

).
</p>
         <p>
The correct position of the haem in the active site of a plant POX is mainly tuned through interactions with the residing residues on helices B and F. Helix B, on the distal side, consists of approximately 13 amino acids, including conserved 
R
38, H42, and F40 (in HRP), which play essential roles in both the function and stability of haem (
Fig. 5A
) (

; 

). Helix F is located almost below the haem in the proximal section and provides the prosthetic group with the conserved H167 (in HRP). The possible roles of 
R
38, H42, and H167 (equal to 
R
37, H41, and H 
168 in
POXalf
, 
Table S2
) have been well discussed in the literature. However, the debates on possible roles of helix F have not been conclusive since the crystallographic data reveal larger variations in the number of total residues of helix F compared with that of helix B (e.g., 13, 15, and 
7 in
HRP, palm POX, and 
POXpnt
, respectively) in addition to the variable helices after helix F (named F 
′
, F 
′′
, F 
′′
2, 
Fig. 5B
in green) (

).
</p>
         <p>
2.4.3.4. Active site pocket in POXalf.
High topological similarity is observed among the structures of the active site pockets of plant POXs. The overlaid structures of HRP-C on 1PA2 and 
POXalf
(
Fig. 7A and B
) indicate that there must be a significant overlap between the substrate spectra of these enzymes. On the other hand, reviewing the constructing amino acids of this region reveals important differences that can influence the affinity of the pocket as well as the final orientation of the substrate in the pocket. The strand comprised of residues 137–142, the loop hosting residue 68, and residues 178–179 on helix F 
′
construct the entrance of the active site pocket (
Fig. 7A
). Reviewing the corresponding amino acids of these residues (underlined in 
Table 3
) and the structural topology of these enzymes reveals important differences. For instance, in addition to dissimilarities in the amino acids of strands 137–142, the spatial position of F67 of HRP is occupied by P 
68 in
1PA2 and 
POXalf
(
Fig. 7B
). The striking difference between HRP and 
POXalf
relates to the spatial position of helix F’, where F179 of HRP has been displaced by a polar residue (threonine) in 
POXalf
(
Fig. 7B
). Although compositional and conformational variations can be considered when explaining the observed different activities of 
POXalf
and HRP towards monoamines and meta-diamines (structures IV and 
V
, 
Fig. 4
), definitive explanations require NMR/X-ray crystallography results.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
The production of POX steadily increases during a 31-day subculture of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
cells. The purified enzyme showed interesting physicochemical properties, including high specific activity, optimal activity over a wide range of pH values, a long shelf life, and resistance to high concentrations of H 
2
O 
2
. Based on the mass analysis results, the 3D structure of 
POXalf
was obtained via homology modelling. Despite high topological similarity among the structures of HRP, 
POXpnt
and 
POXalf
, there were important compositional and conformational differences in the active site pockets that could be considered to explain the observed differences in the corresponding substrate spectra and the specific activities.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
         <p>
4-Aminoantipyrine (4AAP), 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid, kinetin, and phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF) were purchased from SigmaTM Chemical and Biochemical Company (St. Louis, MO, 
USA
). Guaiacol was from Fluka Chemie GmbH. Folin-Ciocalteu reagent, ABTS, and ammonium sulfate were purchased from Merck (Darmstadt, 
Germany
). Azo dyes (
Fig. 4
) were synthesized as described previously (

). Solid Murashige and Skoog medium (MS) was prepared according to the literature using 
8 g
L 
1
agar (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alkanna frigida
Boiss. (Boraginaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
samples were collected from Sheikh Shab˜an (

32 
◦
35 
′
06.3 
′′
N


50 
◦
36 
′
02.7 
′′
E

) in Charmahal Bakhtiyari Province of 
Iran
in mid-July, and the plant specimens were identified by the botanist of the scientific board of the 
Iran
Research Institute of Forests and Range Lands, Professor Dr. 
V
. Mozaffarian. The statistical analysis was performed using Microsoft Excel software, and the results are presented as the mean ± standard error.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. Callus induction and proliferation
</title>
         <p>
Sterilized explants (
2–5 mm
) of various tissues of 

<tp:taxon-name>A. frigida</tp:taxon-name>
,

including roots, leaves, and stems, were placed on MS medium (pH 5.8) supplemented with sucrose (
30 g
L 
1
), 2,4-D (1 μM), and kinetin (10 μM) at 25 ± 2 
◦
C in darkness. The resulting callus from the root explant proliferated on MS medium containing the same phytohormones and sucrose (
50 g
L 
1
) in darkness at 25 
◦
C. The subculture period varied from 14 to 31 days according to the goals of the experiments. The biomass was calculated from the weight difference of the callus before and after drying at 37 
◦
C for 48 h.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Profiles of POX and CAT activities
</title>
         <p>
The proliferated 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
callus was sampled at different time intervals during a 31-day subculture. The samples were subjected to concomitant POX and CAT assays. First, at 4 
◦
C, pieces of fresh callus (
1 g
) were crushed and ground in a porcelain mortar containing 3 mL of extraction buffer [Tris base (10 mM, pH 6.0) containing PMSF (0.55 μM)]. The resulting mixture was filtered, and the filtrate (100 μL) was immediately assayed spectrophotometrically (at 
510 nm
) for POX activity in the presence of phenol (8.6 mM), 4AAP (39.4 mM), and H 
2
O 
2
(6.76 mM) in phosphate buffer solution (PBS 10 mM, pH 6.8) at 20 
◦
C. The extinction coefficient of the quinone-imine product (
6500 cm
1
M 
1
) was used in the relevant calculations (

). A spectrophotometric assay of CAT activity (at 
240 nm
) was carried out with 100 μL of the filtrate in PBS (10 mM, pH 6.8) containing H 
2
O 
2
(10 mM) (

). The standard curves [
Fig. S1
, Supplementary Document] obtained for commercial HRP-C [Merck (Darmstadt, 
Germany
)] and CAT [Serva electrophoresis GmbH (D-69115 Heidelberg)] were used to calculate the results in terms of mg of POX and CAT per gram of wet callus. All spectrophotometric measurements were carried out using a UV/Visible Specord 50+ spectrophotometer (Analytik Jena, 
Germany
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.3. Extraction and purification of 

POXalf
</title>
         <p>
Fresh 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
calli (
120 g
) were homogenized in 150 mL of Tris buffer (10 mM, pH 6.0) containing PMSF (0.55 μM). The tissue debris was removed by centrifugation (

8500 
g

, 20 min at 4 
◦
C) using a Beckman Centrifuge, J-21 model. The pellet was washed twice using 90 mL of the same buffer. The resulting homogenate was saturated (80%) by ammonium sulfate and was maintained overnight at 4 
◦
C. The precipitated proteins were collected by centrifugation (

13000 
g

, 4 min at 4 
◦
C) and then dissolved in 3 mL of PBS (10 mM, pH 6.0) for further experiments.
</p>
         <p>
The protein solution of the previous step (2 mL) was chromatographed on a Sephadex G-50 column (5 × 
15 cm
, Pharmacia) using Tris (10 mM, pH 6.0) as the mobile phase. The output of the column was monitored spectrophotometrically at 
λ
= 
280 nm
. The fractions were examined for POX activity. The selected fractions were pooled and passed through an S-Sepharose column (1 × 
20 cm
) that had already been equilibrated with Tris buffer (10 mM, pH 6.0). The proteins were eluted with a stepwise gradient of NaCl (100–1000 mM) in the same buffer. The fractions (1 mL) were monitored at 
280 nm
and examined for POX activity. According to the resulting chromatogram, the selected active fractions were pooled and used in subsequent experiments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="">
         <title>
4.4. Electrophoreses, isoelectric focusing, and 2D electrophoresis
</title>
         <p>
The protein content of the desired solutions was measured by the 
Bradford
method. PAGE and SDS–PAGE of the samples were performed according to the conventional Laemmli method using a resolving (12.5%) and stacking (4%) polyacrylamide gel at a constant electrophoretic field of 200 V. The protein bands were visualized by both Coomassie brilliant blue R250 and AgNO 
3
staining methods. To perform high-resolution 2D gel electrophoresis, isoelectric focusing (IEF) was conducted as described earlier (

). The second dimension electrophoretic separation was carried out on a 12.5% gel according to the Laemmli method (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.5. Physicochemical properties of 

POXalf
</title>
         <p>
Important physicochemical properties of the purified 
POXalf
, including optimal pH, optimal temperature, thermal stability, operational stability, substrate spectrum (reactivity), inhibition, and relevant kinetics parameters, were measured spectrophotometrically in a conventional UV–visible quartz cell in a total volume of 3 mL using PBS (10 mM, at the desired pH) as the reaction medium using the desired organic substrate. In addition to phenol (mentioned above), guaiacol was also used as the organic substrate in some kinetics studies on 
POXalf
. Subsequently, the formation of the chromophoric product (
ε
= 
26,600 cm
1
M 
1
) was followed at 
470 nm
(

). Additional information about the experiments is mentioned in the captions of the corresponding data. The kinetics parameters of the substrates were extracted from Lineweaver-Burk analysis of the corresponding velocity curves under steady-state conditions, and the inhibition constants were obtained from the fitted equations of the inhibition graphs as well as by using the Cheng–Prusoff equation (

): IC50 = 
Ki
[1 + [S]/ 
Km
]. The results of the kinetic studies are the average of at least triplicate measurements. A unit of activity is equal to the formation of the chromophoric product (1 μM min 
1
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Structural studies
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.1. Protein digestion and tandem mass analysis
</title>
         <p>
For structural elucidation, the eluted 
POXalf
from 
SDS
– 
PAGE
was reduced and digested by trypsin as previously described (

). Fifteen microlitres of the sample was injected into a Dionex Ultimate 3000 LC–MS/MS system coupled to a Q-Exactive mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, 
Bremen
, 
Germany
). For peptide LC separation, an Aeris peptide XB-C18 reversed-phase column (150 × 
2.1 mm
; 1.7 μm; 100 Å; Phenomex, Le Pecq, 
France
) was used. The mobile phase consisted of phase A [water (LC–MS grade water) containing formic acid (0.1%)] and phase B [acetonitrile containing formic acid (0.1%)] that was delivered at a flow rate of 0.5 mL min 
1
. The results were analysed using the X! TandemPipeline (version0.2.40).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.2. RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis
</title>
         <p>
Total RNA was extracted from frozen 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. frigida
</tp:taxon-name>
callus powder by a TRIzol-like reagent (

). An Invitrogen™ cDNA synthesis kit (Thermo Fisher Science, 
United States
) was used to synthesize cDNA. Then, the cDNA (5 μL) was amplified by PCR with the selected primers, designed based on the beginning and end peptides of the 
POXalf
protein identified by mass spectrometry and the conserved domains of plant POXs obtained by BLASTn. The primers were:
</p>
         <p>Forward primer: 5-GCTGTTAACTCTGCGGTGTCG-3.</p>
         <p>Reverse primer: 5-TTAGTTAGTTCTCCTGCAGTTCC-3.</p>
         <p>
The thermocycling conditions were 94 
◦
C (5 min) followed by 34 cycles at 94 
◦
C (30 s), 58 
◦
C (30 s), 72 
◦
C (1 min), and 72 
◦
C (10 min).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.3. Homology modelling, validation, and refinement
</title>
         <p>
The 3D structure of 
POXalf
was predicted via homology modelling by Modeller 9v19, while the 3D structure of 
POXpnt
(PDB ID: 1SCHA) was used as the template (

). To evaluate the predicted 3D model structure, a Ramachandran plot was constructed using the PROCHECK server (http://services.mbi.ucla.edu/PROCHECK) through the SAVE server (http://services.mbi.ucla.edu/SAVES). The ProSA web server (https://prosa.services.came.sbg.ac.at/prosa.pHp) was used to calculate the Z score. The model structure was further evaluated with the VERIFY3D server by assessing the compatibility of each amino acid residue with the local 3D structure by averaging the 3D–1D score (

). Molecular dynamics (MD) simulation was used to refine the structures obtained from homology modelling. Structural refinement was performed using GROMACS 4.6.3. To run the simulation, previously reported conditions and settings for analysis were applied (

). See the Supplementary document for the experimental details. Visualization and analysis of molecular structures were performed by UCSF Chimera 1.10.2 and web-based iCn3D (https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/icn3d/full.html).
</p>
         <p>
Authors’ agreement
</p>
         <p>This manuscript is based on original research data that have not been published elsewhere. The authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest. All authors read and approved the final manuscript and agree to submission for publication.</p>
         <p>
Funding
</p>
         <p>Funding was provided by the National Institute for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology (Project 730) in collaboration with Laboratoire d’ Ecologie, Syst´ematique et Evolution (ESE), Paris-Saclay University.</p>
         <p>
Credit author statement
</p>
         <p>S. Soleimani Asl: Investigation, Data curation. A.A. Karkhane: Methodology, Data curation, Validation. J.Z. Amirzakaria: Software, Visualization. K. Akbari: Data curation, Validation. J. Ghashghaie: Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition. K. Haghbeen: Conceptualization, Methodology, Resources, Supervision, Funding acquisition. All authors participated in the preparation and revision of the manuscript.</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgements
</p>
         <p>
We gratefully acknowledge the excellent technical assistance by Marl`eene Davanture (Plateforme d’ Analyse Proteomique de Paris-Sud Ouest–PAPPSO, Moulon, 
France
) for MS analysis.
</p>
         <p>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</p>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113022.</p>
         <p>
References
</p>
         <p>
Araujo, B.
, de-Oliveira, 
J.O
., 
Machado, S.
, et al., 
2004
. 
Comparative studies of the peroxidases from hairy roots of Daucus carota, Ipomoea batatas and Solanum aviculare
. 
Plant Sci.
167
, 
1151–1157
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. plantsci.2004.06.015
.

</p>
         <p>
Berglund, G.I.
, 
Carlsson, G.H.
, 
Smith, A.T.
, et al., 
2002
. 
The catalytic pathway of horseradish peroxidase at high resolution
. 
Nature
417
, 
463–480
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1038/417463a
.

</p>
         <p>
Cai, F.
, 
OuYang, C.
, 
Duan, P.
, 
Gao, S.
, 
Xu, Y.
, 
Chen, F.
, 
2012
. 

Purification and characterization of a novel thermal stable peroxidase from 
Jatropha curcas
leaves

.J. Mol. Catal. B Enzym.
77
, 
59–66
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molcatb.2011.12.002
.

</p>
         <p>
Cheng, H.
, 
2001
. 
The power issue: determination of KB or Ki from IC50: a closer look at the Cheng–Prusoff equation, the Schild plot and related power equations
.J. Pharmacol. Toxicol. Methods
46
, 
61–71
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/s1056-8719 (02)00166-1
.

</p>
         <p>
Dicko, M.H.
, 
Gruppen, H.
, 
Hilhorst, R.
, 
Voragen, A.G.J.
, 
Berkel, W.J. H.
v., 
2006
. 
Biochemical characterization of the major sorghum grain peroxidase
. 
FEBS J.
273
, 
2293–2307
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1742-4658.2006.05243.x
.

</p>
         <p>
Eisenberg, D.
, 
Lüthy, R.
, U 
Bowie, J.
, 
1997
. 
VERIFY3D: assessment of protein models with three-dimensional profiles
. 
Methods Enzymol.
277
, 
396–404
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/s0076-6879(97)77022-8
.

</p>
         <p>
Enachi, E.
, 
Grigore-Gurgu, L.
, 
Aprodu, I.
, et al., 
2018
. 

Extraction, purification and processing stability of peroxidase from plums (
Prunus domestica
)

. 
Int. J. Food Prop.
21
, 
2744–2757
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/10942912.2018.1560311
.

</p>
         <p>
Farhadi, S.
, 
Haghbeen, K.
, et al., 
2011
. 

Anionic peroxidase production by 
Arnebia euchroma
callus

. 
Biotechnol. Appl. Biochem.
58
, 
456–463
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ bab.42
.

</p>
         <p>
Ghofrani, N.S.
, 
Sheikhi, M.
, 
Amirzakaria, J.Z.
, 
Hassani, S.
, 
Aminzadeh, S.
, 
Haghbeen, K.
, 
2021
. 
New insight into the interactions of arbutin with mushroom tyrosinase
. 
Protein J.
40
(
5
), 
689–698
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10930-021-10004-x
.

</p>
         <p>
Hayashi, Y.
, 
Yamazaki, I.
, 
1979
. 
The oxidation-reduction potentials of compound I/ compound II and compound II/ferric couples of horseradish peroxidases A2 and C
.J. Biol. Chem.
54
, 
9101–9106
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0021-9258(19)86816-3
.

</p>
         <p>
Humer, D.
, 
Ebner, J.
, 
Spadiut, O.
, 
2020
. 
Scalable high-performance production of recombinant horseradish peroxidase from e. coli inclusion bodies
. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
21
, 
4625
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21134625
.

</p>
         <p>
Jovanovi´c, S.V.
, 
Kukavica, B.
, 
Vidovi´c, M.
, 
Morina, F.
, 
Menckhoff, L.
, 
2018
. 
Class III peroxidases: functions, localization and redox regulation of isoenzymes
. In: 
Gupta, D.
, 
Palma, J.
, 
Corpas, F.
(Eds.), 
Antioxidants and Antioxidant Enzymes in Higher Plants.
Springer, Cham
, pp. 
269–300
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319- 75088-0_13.
</p>
         <p>
Krainer, F.W.
, 
Glieder, A.
, 
2015
. 
An updated view on horseradish peroxidases: recombinant production and biotechnological applications
. 
Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.
99
, 
1611–1625
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253-014-6346-7
.

</p>
         <p>
Kreis, W.
, 
2019
. 
Exploiting plant cell culture for natural product formation
. 
J. Appl. Bot. Food Qual.
92
, 
216–225
. 
https://doi.org/10.5073/JABFQ.2019.092.030
.

</p>
         <p>
Laemmli, U.K.
, 
1979
. 
Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4
. 
Nature
227
, 
680–685
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/227680a0
.

</p>
         <p>
Marangoni, A.G.
, 
Brown, E.D.
, 
Stanley, D.W.
, 
Yada, R.Y.
, 
1989
. 
Tomato peroxidase: rapid isolation and partial characterization. J
. 
Food Sci.
54
, 
1269–1271
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1111/J.1365-2621.1989.TB05971.X
.

</p>
         <p>
Marzouki, S.M.
, 
Limam, F.
, 
Smaali, M.I.
, 
Ulber, R.
, 
Marzouki, M.N.
, 
2005
. 

A new thermostable peroxidase from garlic 
Allium sativum
: purification, biochemical properties, immobilization, and use in H2O2 detection in milk

. 
Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol.
127
, 
201–214
. 
https://doi.org/10.1385/abab:127:3:201
.

</p>
         <p>
Mirazizi, F.
, 
Bahrami, A.
, 
Haghbeen, K.
, 
Zahiri, H.S.
, 
Bakavoli, M.
, 
Legge, R.L.
, 
2016
. 
Rapid and direct spectrophotometric method for kinetics studies and routine assay of peroxidase based on aniline diazo substrates
. 
J. Enzym. Inhib. Med. Chem.
31
, 
1162–1169
. 
https://doi.org/10.3109/14756366.2015.1103234
.

</p>
         <p>
Mirazizi, F.
, 
Bahrami, A.
, 
Soleimani-Asl, S.
, 
Haghbeen, K.
, 
Aminzadeh, S.
, 
2018
. 
Evaluation of oxidative enzymes for efficient oxidation of aniline and phenolic pollutants
. 
Inter. J. Environ. Sci. Technol.
15
, 
1679–1686
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ s13762-017-1493-x
.

</p>
         <p>
Mohammadnejad, P.
, 
Soleimani-Asl, S.
, 
Aminzadeh, S.
, 
Haghbeen, K.
, 
2020
. 
A new sensitive spectrophotometric method for determination of saliva and blood glucose. Spectrochim
. 
Acta Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.
15
, 
229–274
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. saa.2019.117897
.

</p>
         <p>
Mohammadnejad, P.
, 
Soleimani-Asl, S.
, 
Rasoulian, Z.
, 
Aminzadeh, S.
, 
Ghashghaie, J.
, 
Haghbeen, K.
, 
2021
. 

A potent peroxidase from solid cell culture of 
Ocimum basilicum
with high sensitivity for blood glucose determination

. 
Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult.
146
, 
375–386
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11240-021-02076-5
.

</p>
         <p>
Monsef-Esfahani, H.
, 
Navvab-Esfahani, Z.
, 
Dehaghi, N.K.
, et al., 
2012
. 

Anti-inflammatory and anti-nociceptive effects of the ethanolic extracts of 
Alkanna frigida
and 
Alkanna orientalis

. 
J. Nat. Med.
66
, 
447–452
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11418-011-0603-1
.

</p>
         <p>
More, A.
, 
2021
. 
Global and japan Horseradish Peroxidase (Hrp) Market Insights
, 
Forecast to
2027
. Marketwatch. SKU ID. QYR- 
18837609
.

</p>
         <p>
Moural, T.W.
, 
Lewis, K.M.
, et al., 
2017
. 
Characterization of class III peroxidases from switchgrass
. 
Plant Physiol.
173
, 
417–433
. 
https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.16.01426
.

</p>
         <p>
Nadaroglu, H.
, 
Celebi, N.
, 
Demir, N.
, 
Demir, Y.
, 
2013
. 

Purification and characterisation of a plant peroxidase from rocket (
Eruca vesicaria
sbsp. Sativa) (Mill.) (syn. E. sativa) and effects of some chemicals on peroxidase activity in vitro

. 
Afr. J. Agric. Res.
8
, 
2520–2528
. 
https://doi.org/10.5897/AJAR2013.6764
.

</p>
         <p>
Narita, H.
, 
Asaka, Y.
, 
Ikura, K.
, 
Matsumoto, S.
, 
Sasaki, R.
, 
1995
. 
Isolation, characterization and expression of cationic peroxidase isozymes released into the medium of cultured tobacco cells
. 
Eur. J. Biochem.
228
, 
855–862
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1111/j.1432-1033.1995.0855m.x
.

</p>
         <p>
Nnamchi, C.I.
, 
Parkin, G.
, 
Efimov, I.
, et al., 
2016
. 
Structural and spectroscopic characterisation of a heme peroxidase from sorghum
. 
J. Biol. Inorg. Chem.
21
, 
63–70
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00775-015-1313-z
.

</p>
         <p>
Pandey, V.P.
, 
Awasthi, M.
, 
Singh, S.
, 
Tiwari, S.
, 
2017
. 
A comprehensive review on function and application of plant peroxidases
. 
Anal. Biochem.
6
, 
1–16
. 
https://doi. org/10.4172/2161-1009.1000308
.

</p>
         <p>
Parsiavash, L.
, 
Saboora, A.
, 
Nejad, S.Z.M.
, 
2021
. 
Investigating on the stability of peroxidase extracted from soybean (glycine max var. williams) and effects of Na + and K + ions on its activity. J
. 
Cell Mol. Res.
21
, 
58–71
. 
https://doi.org/10.22067/ JCMR.V7I2.43716
.

</p>
         <p>
Puad, N.I.M.
, 
Wai, T.C.
, 
2016
. 
A simple and easy method for preparing solid and liquid media for plant culture
. In: 
Experimental Methods in Modern Biotechnology
. 
IIUM Press
, 
Malaysia, ISBN
9789674183844
, pp. 
9–15
.

</p>
         <p>
Qstergaard, L.
, 
Teilum, K.
, et al., 
2000
. 
Arabidopsis ATP A2 peroxidase. espression and high-resolution structure of a plant peroxidase with implications for lignification
. 
Plant Mol. Biol.
44
, 
231–243
. 
https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1006442618860.
</p>
         <p>
Rio, D.C., Jr
, 
M.A
., 
Hannon, G.J.
, 
Nilsen, T.W.
, 
2010
. 
Polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis of RNA
. 
Cold Spring Harb. Protoc.
6
, prot 
5444
. 
https://doi.org/10.1101/pdb.prot5444
.

</p>
         <p>
Savitsky, P.A.
, 
Gazaryan, I.G.
, 
Tishkov, V.I.
, 
Lagrimini, L.M.
, 
Ruzgas, T.
, 
Gorton, L.
, 
1999
. 
Oxidation of indole-3-acetic acid by dioxygen catalysed by plant peroxidases: specificity for the enzyme structure
. 
Biochem. J.
15
(
340
), 
579–583
. 
https://doi.org/10.1042/bj3400579
.

</p>
         <p>
Schuller, D.J.
, 
Ban, N.
, 
Huystee, R.B.
, et al., 
1996
. 
The crystal structure of peanut peroxidase
. 
Structure
4
, 
311–321
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/s0969-2126(96)00035- 4
.

</p>
         <p>

Sebasti´an, D., 
Guevara, M.G.
, 
Rocío, T.F.
, 
Virginia, T.C.
, 
2018
. 
An overview of plant proteolytic enzymes
. In: 
Guevara, M.
, 
Daleo, G.
(Eds.), 
Biotechnological Applications of Plant Proteolytic Enzymes
. 
Springer, Cham
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319- 97132-2_1
.

</p>
         <p>
Sesto, P.A.
, 
Huystee, R.B.
v., 
1989
. 
Purification and yield of a cationic peroxidase from a peanut suspension cell culture
. 
Plant Sci.
61
, 
163–168
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ 0168-9452(89)90220-3
.

</p>
         <p>
Shevchenko, A.
, 
Tomas, H.
, 
Havlis, J.
, 
Olsen, J.V.
, 
Mann, M.
, 
2006
. 
In-gel digestion for mass spectrometric characterization of proteins and proteomes
. 
Nat. Protoc.
1
, 
2856–2860
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2006.468
.

</p>
         <p>
Shigeto, J.
, 
Tsutsumi, Y.
, 
2016
. 
Diverse functions and reactions of class III peroxidases
. 
New Phytol.
209
, 
1395–1402
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.13738
.

</p>
         <p>
Spadiut, O.
, 
Herwig, C.
, 
2013
. 
Production and purification of the multifunctional enzyme horseradish peroxidase
. 
Pharm. Bioprocess.
1
, 
283–295
. 
https://doi.org/10.4155/ pbp.13.23
.

</p>
         <p>
Takeda, H.
, 
Kotake, T.
, 
Nakagawa, N.
, 
Nevins, D.J.
, 
2003
. 
Expression and function of cell wall-bound cationic peroxidase in asparagus somatic embryogenesis
. 
Plant Physiol.
131
, 
1765–1774
. 
https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.102.014654
.

</p>
         <p>
Thongsook, T.
, 
Barrett, D.M.
, 
2005
. 

Purification and partial characterization of broccoli (
Brassica oleracea
var. italica) peroxidases

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
53
, 
3206–3214
.
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/10.1021/jf048162s
.
</p>
         <p>
Veitch, N.C.
, 
2004
. 
Structural determinants of plant peroxidase function
. 
Phytochemistry Rev.
3
, 
3–18
. 
https://doi.org/10.1023/B:PHYT.0000047799.17604.94
.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
