<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112839</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Squamins C-F, four cyclopeptides from the seeds of Annona globiflora</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cristina Cuadrado
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
Schltdl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Annonaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
Schltdl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona muricata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Annonaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
Schltdl. (Annonaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona squamosa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Annonaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. squamosa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
Schltdl. (Annonaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mycoplasma
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Mycoplasma</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Mycoplasma PCR</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Squamins C–F, four cyclopeptides from the seeds of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Javier Sosa-Rueda
a
, Vanihamin Domínguez-Mel´endez 
b
, 
Araceli Ortiz-Celiseo
a, c
, 

Fernando C. 
L´opez-Fentanes

a, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cristina Cuadrado
</tp:taxon-name>
d
, Jos´e J. Fern´andez 
e, **
, Antonio Hern´andez Daranas 
d, ***
, 
Francisco Cen-Pacheco
a, e, *
</p>
         <p>
a
Facultad de Bioan´alisis
, 
Veracruz
University, Iturbide s/n, 91700, 
Veracruz
, Ver., 
Mexico
</p>
         <p>
b
Centro de Estudios
y 
Servicios en Salud
, 
Veracruz
University, Iturbide s/n, 91700, 
Veracruz
, Ver., 
Mexico
</p>
         <p>
c
Instituto Tecnol´ogico
de Orizaba, 
Tecnol´ogico Nacional de M´exico
Oriente 9, Emiliano Zapata, 94320, Orizaba, Ver., 
Mexico
</p>
         <p>
d

Instituto de Productos Naturales y Agrobiología del CSIC (IPNA-CSIC), La Laguna, 38206, Tenerife, 
Spain
</p>
         <p>
e
Instituto Universitario de Bio-Org´anica
Antonio Gonzalez
´(IUBO-AG), Departamento de Química Organica
´, 

University of La Laguna, Av. Astrofísico Francisco 
S´anchez
</p>
         <p>

2, 38206, Tenerife, 
Spain
</p>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
Schltdl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Annonaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Cyclopeptides</p>
         <p>Cytotoxic activity</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
Four cyclic octapeptides, squamins C–F, were isolated from the seeds of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
Schltdl.
</tp:taxon-name>
These compounds share part of their amino acid sequence, -Pro-Met(O)-Tyr-Gly-Thr-, with previously reported squamins A and B. Their structures were determined using NMR spectroscopic techniques together with quantum mechanical calculations (QM-NMR), ESI-HRMS data and a modified version of Marfey’ s chromatographic method. All compounds showed cytotoxic activity against DU-145 (human prostate cancer) and HeLa (human cervical carcinoma) cell lines. Clearly, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
is an important source of bioactive molecules, which could promote the sustainable exploitation of this undervalued specie.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
In 
Mexico
, there are about 20 species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona
</tp:taxon-name>
genus, mainly located in southeastern tropical regions. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona muricata
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Annonaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) is one the most cultivated species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona
</tp:taxon-name>
genus, because it produces exotic edible fruits (

). However, the economic importance of this genus is diverse and not restricted to their fruits, as it also includes species with aromatic, medicinal and insecticidal properties (Hern´andez 

). Despite this, most of them are known as wild 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona
species
</tp:taxon-name>
(

) and remain underutilized. Within this group of wild native 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona
species
</tp:taxon-name>
, we focused the current study on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
Schltdl. (Annonaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
. This Mexican endemic species is named “chirimoyito” by local people, and grows in the central area of the state of 
Veracruz
(Escobedo-L´opez et al., 2018). To our knowledge, previous studies of its phytochemistry or biological activity have not been reported.
</p>
         <p>
The 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona
</tp:taxon-name>
genus is well known for producing interesting compounds, including alkaloids, isoquinolines, peptides, acetogenins, lectins, volatile oils, etc. (

). Cyclic peptides isolated from the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona
</tp:taxon-name>
constitute an important class of natural molecules with a great diversity of ring sizes (

). Some of them show useful pharmacologic properties such as potent cytotoxic, vasorelaxant or anti-inflammatory activities (

). Consequently, they have been described as interesting leads in the drug discovery process (

; 

). Therefore, knowledge of the functional potential of wild native 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona
species
</tp:taxon-name>
, and evidence on the possible health benefits derived from them, may promote the expansion of their cultivation and commercial importance.
</p>
         <p>
Here, we report a phytochemical study of the seeds of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
collected in spring 
2018 in
Veracruz state
(M´exico), in which four previously unreported cyclopeptides named squamins C–F (
1–4
) were isolated. Their structures were determined using NMR spectroscopic techniques together with quantum mechanical calculations (QM-NMR) (

), ESI-HRMS data and a modified version of Marfey’ s method using LC-UV (

; 

). Squamins C/D and E/F were found to be pairs of epimeric methionine sulfoxides, which may be oxidation products of undetected
</p>
         <p>
cyclopeptides containing 
L
-Met. Importantly, unlike other compounds containing a methionine sulfoxide group, squamins can be separated by chromatographic techniques (

). The cytotoxicity bioassays undertaken indicated that these compounds possess moderate activity against the DU-145 (human prostate cancer) and HeLa (human cervical carcinoma) cell lines.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
Seeds of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
(
500 g
) were dried under shade and triturated using a steel blender. Next, the resulting powder was extracted using MeOH (4 × (3 L × 3 h)) at room temperature and the solvent evaporated 
in vacuo
to yield a brownish viscous extract (
12.5 g
). This extract was first fractionated by liquid-liquid extraction, using the modified Kupchan method (

; 

,b). The AcOEt fraction (
416 mg
) was chromatographed using medium pressure liquid chromatography Lobar LiChroprep-RP18 with MeOH/H 
2
O 7:3, then finally purified in a μ- Bondapack C-18 HPLC column using MeOH:H2O as mobile phase. This procedure yielded 
2.9 mg
of squamin C (
1
), 
2.5 mg
of squamin D (
2
), 
1.9 mg
of squamin E (
3
) and 
1.5 mg
of squamin F (
4
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Structural elucidation
</title>
         <p>
Squamin C (
1
) was isolated as an optically active amorphous white solid [α] 
D
25
-52 (
c
= 0.29, MeOH). ESI-HRMS mass spectra showed a molecular ion peak [M+ Na] 
+
at 
m
/ 
z
843.3691, providing the molecular formula C 
37
H 
56
N 
8
O 
11
S. The NMR spectroscopic data were obtained using CD 
3
OD and CD 
3
OH as solvents. The observed 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data for 
1
allowed us to establish the presence of six 
CH
3
, eight 
CH
2
, thirteen 
CH
and ten non-protonated carbons. Importantly, eight signals characteristic of carbonyl groups were observed in the 
13
C NMR spectrum, suggesting that 
1
should be an octapeptide (
Table 1
). Indeed, 
1
H– 
1
H COSY and TOCSY spectra of 
1
revealed the presence of nine 
1
H– 
1
H spin systems, belonging to eight amino acid units. Thus, two alanine residues showed the typical AX 
3
system between H 
3
-β (
δH
1.42, d, 
J
= 7.3 Hz) and H-α (
δH
3.99, q, 
J
= 7.3 Hz) and between H 
3
-β (
δH
1.44, d, 
J
= 7.4 Hz) and H-α (
δH
4.22, q, 
J
= 7.4 Hz). The 
sec
-butyl group of the isoleucine residue was identified, beginning with proton H-α (
δH
4.37, d, 
J
= 10.4 Hz). This was correlated with the methine proton H-β (
δH
2.09), then in turn with the methyl group H 
3
-ε (
δH
0.77, d, 
J
= 6.5 Hz) and the diastereotopic methylene H 
2
-γ (
δH
1.07/1.49). The latter was further correlated with H 
3
-δ (
δH
0.94, t, 
J
= 7.4 Hz). The proline residue started with H-α (
δH
4.74, dd, 
J
= 7.9, 9.7 Hz). This was linked to H 
2
-β (
δH
1.91/2.34), this in turn to H 
2
-γ (
δH
2.08) and the latter to H 
2
-δ (
δH
3.57/3.75). The 
1
H NMR signal assignment of the nonessential amino acid, methionine oxide, commenced with H-α (
δH
4.20, t, 
J
= 7.1 Hz), which was connected to H 
2
-β (
δH
2.06/2.21) and these sequentially to H 
2
-γ (
δH
2.60/2.67). For the tyrosine residue, twospin systems were determined: the first linked H-α (
δH
5.02, dd, 
J
= 3.0, 12.4 Hz) with H 
2
-β (
δH
2.85/3.62, dd/dd, 
J
= 12.4, 15.8 Hz/ 
J
= 3.0, 15.7 Hz), while the second joined protons H-δ/H-θ (
δH
7.04, d, 
J
= 8.5 Hz) with H-ε/H-η (
δH
6.71, d, 
J
= 8.5 Hz). Observation of a 
1
H– 
1
H spin coupling between two geminal protons H 
2
-α (
δH
3.74/4.27, d, 
J
= 17.1 Hz) indicated the presence of a glycine residue. Finally, the threonine residue began at H 
3
-γ (
δH
1.23, d, 
J
= 6.1 Hz), which was joined with methine H-β (
δH
4.52, dq, 
J
= 3.1, 6.1 Hz), and this sequentially connected with H-α (
δH
4.89, d, 
J
= 3.1 Hz). The peptide sequence was unambiguously established by long-range 
1
H– 
13
C connectivity, extrapolated from the HMBC experiment. This further secured the presence of eight amino acid residues in 
1
. Thus, key HMBC correlations between the carbonyl group of residue i and the amide and/or α protons of residue i+ 1 (Ala 
1
H-α and Thr(CO), Ala 
2
H-α and Ala 
1
(CO), IleH-α and Ala 
2
(CO), ProH-α and Ile(CO), Met(O)H-α and Pro(CO), TyrNH and Met(O)(CO), GlyH 
2
-α and Tyr(CO), ThrNH and Gly(CO)) allowed us to determine the planar structure of 
1
, as shown in 
Fig. 1
. Squamin D (
2
) showed the same molecular formula as 
1
, C 
37
H 
56
N 
8
O 
11
S, according to ESI-HRMS results that displayed a peak at 
m/z
843.3668 [M+ Na] 
+
. Detailed analysis of its 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, assisted by 2D NMR spectroscopy, established the planar structure of 
2
as identical to 
1
. However, slight variations between the NMR chemical shifts of the two compounds were found, particularly involving the methylsulfinyl group (
Table 1
). Sulfoxide groups can be considered as asymmetric centers, due to their high activation energies for inversion (162–197 kJ mol 
1
) that prevent enantiomers interconverting (

). Therefore, we concluded that 
1
and 
2
were a pair of diasteroisomers with different configurations at the sulfoxide stereogenic center.
</p>
         <p>
Two closely related metabolites, squamins E (
3
) and F (
4
), were also isolated in this study. Analysis of their ESI-HRMS data showed peaks at 
m/z
831.3330 [M+ Na] 
+
for 
3
and 
m/z
831.3325 [M+ Na] 
+
for 
4
, both corresponding to a molecular formula of C 
35
H 
52
N 
8
O 
12
S. A detailed structural analysis of these compounds suggested a partial amino acid sequence -Pro-Met(O)-Tyr-Gly-Thr 
2
-Ala 
1
-Ala 
2
-, identical to those observed in squamins C (
1
) and D (
2
). However, the experimental data indicated the presence of a new threonine residue, replacing the previously described isoleucine residue in 
1
and 
2
. The 
1
H NMR spectra for the new Thr 
1
were assigned commencing from H 
3
-γ (
δH
1.14, d, 
J
= 6.5 Hz), which was coupled with methine H-β (
δH
4.25, dq, 
J
= 2.4, 6.5 Hz). This was sequentially connected with the proton of methine H-α (
δH
4.64, d, 
J
= 2.4 Hz). The new threonine residue was linked using the HMBC experiment, where the proton Thr 
1
H-α was correlated with Ala 
2
(CO, 
δC
176.3). The signal corresponding to ProH-α (4.74, t, 
J
= 8.2 Hz) was also connected with Thr 
1
(CO) (
δC
173.4) (
Table 2
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
A literature search revealed that two similar molecules, squamins A and B (
5–6
), had been isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona squamosa
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Annonaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) (

; 

). Squamins C and D (
1–2
) show an alanine residue in place of the valine residue present in 
5
and 
6
. Squamins E and F (
3–4
), in addition to the previous substitution, incorporate a new threonine residue instead of the characteristic isoleucine in 
5
and 
6
.
</p>
         <p>
Absolute configurations of the amino acid residues were established by a modified version of Marfey’ s method (

). Thus, each compound (
1–4
) was first hydrolyzed using HCl and subsequently each hydrolysate was derivatized using Nα-(2,4-dinitro-5-fluorophenyl)- 
L
-alaninamide (
L
-FDLA). The chromatographic retention times of these FDAA amino-acid derivatives were established by HPLC, monitored by UV absorption at 
340 nm
. All FDAA derivatives were identified by comparison of their HPLC retention times with those measured for amino-acid standards. The absolute configurations of the amino-acid residues of 
1–4
were all identified as 
L
. However, regarding the configuration of the methionine oxide residues, it has to be noted that sulfoxides are quickly racemized in HCl solution (

), such as that used for peptide hydrolysis in Marfey’ s analyses. Consequently, the rapid interconversion between the 
L
-Met (R*/S*)-oxides in acid conditions made it impossible to assign a configuration to the sulfoxide groups in compounds 
1–4
. Although a number of methods to determine the configuration of chiral sulfoxides have been described, it is still far from a routine matter to establish them reliably. The comparison between experimental and calculated values have been successfully used to address complex stereochemical problems involving natural products (

; 

; 

), without the need of a total synthesis (

). In fact, this approach has been successfully used on chiral sulfoxides (

). Methods based on Bayes’ theorem such as DP4, DP4+ or 
J
-DP4 stand out (

; 

; 

). Moreover, specific methodologies have been proposed to assign the configuration of groups of stereoisomers when experimental NMR data is available for all of them, as for squamins 
1–6
(

). Specifically, the recently proposed statistical parameter 

MAEΔΔ 
δ

(MAE = Mean Average Error) calculates differences between the experimental and calculated NMR data for groups of stereoisomers, reducing systematic errors and providing a more robust assignment than DP4-based methods in these cases (

). Nevertheless, the great similarity observed in the NMR data experimentally measured for all pairs of squamin stereoisomers studied here makes this approach very challenging. In effect, the resemblance between the experimental NMR data of 
1
and 
2
suggests that both compounds adopt a similar conformation. They mainly diverge only in the configuration of the sulfoxide group, as observed in their crystalline structures. Thus, the crystallographic structures of squamins A (
5
) (CCDC 196170) and B (
6
) (CCDC 196169) were used to test if the previously mentioned approach could be useful for these molecules (

).
</p>
         <p>

ΔΔ 
δ
</p>
         <p>
First, both structures were geometrically optimized using the B3LYP/ 6-31G(d) functional/basis set. Next, 
1
H and 
13
C NMR chemical shifts for the two structures were calculated at the MPW1PW91/6-31 + G(d,p) level of theory. Finally, the 

MAEΔΔ 
δ

parameter was calculated for the two possible experimental/calculated comparisons. As a result, an 
S
configuration turned out to be the most likely answer for compound 
5,
while an 
R
configuration should be proposed for compound 
6
(
Table 3
). Importantly, our result agrees with a previous proposal made for 
5
, where the configuration of the sulfoxide group was also determined as 
S
based on a chemical shift comparison with a standard sample of 
S
-oxo-methionine (

). The structures of squamins C (
1
) and D (
2
) were built using the crystallographic coordinates of compounds 
5
and 
6
, but modifying the valine to an alanine residue. Next, quantum mechanical NMR calculations and the previously described analysis were undertaken. As a result, an 
S
configuration was found for compound 
1
and an 
R
for compound 
2
. Finally, the same procedure was applied to squamins E (
3
) and F (
4
). Despite the 3D structures for 
3
and 
4
adopting a preferential conformation similar to other squamins, the configuration at the sulfoxide could not be assured (
Fig. 2
). The reason was that the MAEparameter calculated using 
1
H data pointed to an 
S
configuration for compound 
3
and an 
R
for compound 
4
, but the opposite was found using the 
13
C NMR data (
Table 3
and S17-S19). In order to solve this discrepancy, experimental data were compared. This showed that the 
1
H NMR chemical shift measured for the methyl group of the oxo-methionine residue was 2.35 ppm in squamin A (
5
), 2.34 ppm in squamin C (
1
) and 2.36 ppm in squamin E (
3
), indicating that all of them share the same 
S
configuration. On the other hand, squamins B (
6
), D (
2
) and F (
4
) showed signals above 2.5 ppm, indicating that all three share the 
R
configuration.
</p>
         <p>
2.3. Biological activity
</p>
         <p>
Cyclopeptides show a variety of biological properties; among these their cytotoxicity is important (

). Therefore, the 
in vitro
cytotoxic activity of squamins C–F (
1–4
) was assessed using XTT assays and two cancer cell lines: DU-145 (human prostate cancer) and HeLa (human cervical carcinoma) (

). As shown in 
Table 4
, all these compounds were able to inhibit cell proliferation at μM concentration.
</p>
         <p>
3. Conclusions
</p>
         <p>
In conclusion, the structures of four previously undescribed cyclopeptides, named squamins C–F (
1–4
), were determined by the combined use of computational and spectroscopic techniques (QM-NMR) as well as a modified version of Marfey’ s chromatographic method. Compounds 
1–4
turned out to be two pairs of conformational isomers that differed in the configuration of an asymmetric sulfoxide group, characteristic of methionine oxide residues. Squamins C–F (
1–4
) are structurally related to the squamins A and B (
5–6
), epimers previously isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. squamosa
</tp:taxon-name>
. All compounds were active against the cell lines DU-145 (prostate cancer) and HeLa (human cervical carcinoma) in the range 8–25 μM. These results suggested that this 
type
of compounds could be candidates in the search for lead therapeutic compounds. Clearly, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
is an important source of bioactive molecules, which could promote the sustainable exploitation of this undervalued species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
Optical rotation was determined on a Perkin–Elmer 241 polarimeter (Waltham, MA, 
USA
), using a sodium lamp operating at 
589 nm
. NMR spectroscopy was performed on Bruker AVANCE 600 MHz instruments using CD 
3
OD and CD 
3
OH at 298 K, and coupling constants are given in Hz. The NMR, COSY, HSQC-TOCSY, HSQC and HMBC data were acquired using standard pulse sequences. 
3
J
H,H
values were measured from 1D 
1
H NMR. NMR data were processed using MestReNova software (v 11.01, Santiago de Compostela, 
Spain
). Mass spectra were recorded on a VG AutoSpec FISON spectrometer (Danvers, MA, 
USA
). HPLC separations were carried out with an LKB 2248 system (LKB-Producter AB, Bromma, 
Sweden
) equipped with a photodiode array detector. All of the solvents used were HPLC-grade. HPLC was monitored by TLC, performed on AL Si gel Merck 60 F254 (Kenilworth, NJ, 
USA
). TLC plates were visualized by UV light (
365 nm
) and phosphomolybdic acid solution 10 wt % in ethanol.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant materials
</title>
         <p>
The
seeds of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
Schltdl. (Annonaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected from the municipality 

Medellín 
de Bravo

, 
Veracruz
Ignacio de la Llave
(M´exico) in 

May 2018

(wet season) (

19 
◦
01 
′
44.5 
′′
N


96 
◦
08 
′
20.4 
′′
W

) and identified by taxonomists of the Institute for Biological Research at 
Veracruz
University. After collection, the biological material was dried at room temperature for one week, and then triturated using a steel blender (particle size 
0.1–0.5 cm
)

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and chromatographic separation
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Annona globiflora
</tp:taxon-name>
seeds (
500 g
) were extracted with MeOH (4 × (3L × 3 h) at room temperature and the solvent removed 
in vacuo
to give a brownish viscous oil (AGS-1 
12.5 g
). The methanolic extract was first fractioned for liquid-liquid extraction using a modified Kupchan method (

; 

,b). The ethyl acetate fraction (AGS-1C; 
416 mg
) was chromatographed at medium pressure in a Lobar LiChroprep-RP18, eluted with MeOH/H 
2
O (6:4) at 2.5 mL/min flow. Fractions collected between 19 and 24 min, and 25–28 min were pooled together (AGS-1C6 and AGS-1C7 19.7 and 
21.5 mg
, respectively). Both fractions (AGS-1C6 and 1C7) were finally purified in a μ- BondapakTM C-18 (
1.9 Ø
x 
15 cm
) HPLC column, using H 
2
O/MeOH (7:3 or 8:2) as mobile phase at 1 mL/min, to afford pure squamin C (
1
) (
2.9 mg
), squamin D (
2
) (
2.5 mg
), squamin E (
3
) (
1.9 mg
) and squamin F (
4
) (
1.5 mg
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Squamin C (1)
</title>
         <p>
Amorphous white solid; [α] 
D
25
-52 (
c
= 0.29, MeOH); ESI-MS 
m/z
856.4, 843.4, 821.3, 579.3, 433.2, 413.3; ESI-HRMS 
m/z
843.3691 [M+ Na] 
+
(calc for C 
37
H 
56
N 
8
O 
11
NaS 
m/z
843.3687); 
1
H (600 MHz, CD 
3
OD) and 
13
C NMR (125 MHz, CD 
3
OD) data in CD 
3
OD are given in
</p>
         <p>
Table 1.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Squamin D (2)
</title>
         <p>
Amorphous white solid; [α] 
D
25
-48 (
c
= 0.25, MeOH); ESI-MS 
m/z
845.4, 844.4, 843.4, 450.2, 413.3; ESI-HRMS 
m/z
843.3668 [M+ Na] 
+
(calc for C 
37
H 
56
N 
8
O 
11
NaS 
m/z
843.3687); 
1
H (600 MHz, CD 
3
OD) and 
13
C NMR (125 MHz, CD 
3
OD) data in CD 
3
OD are given in 
Table 1.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. Squamin E (3)
</title>
         <p>
Amorphous white solid; [α] 
D
25
-42 (
c
= 0.19, MeOH); ESI-MS 
m/z
833.3, 832.3, 831.3, 676.3, 675.3, 427.2; ESI-HRMS 
m/z
831.3330 [M+ Na] 
+
(calc for C 
35
H 
52
N 
8
O 
12
NaS 
m/z
831.3323); 
1
H (600 MHz, CD 
3
OD) and 
13
C NMR (125 MHz, CD 
3
OD) data in CD 
3
OD are given in 
Table S3.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.4. Squamin F (4)
</title>
         <p>
Amorphous white solid; [α] 
D
25
-41 (
c
= 0.15, MeOH); ESI-MS 
m/z
833.3, 832.4, 831.3, 675.3, 463.3, 427.2; ESI-HRMS 
m/z
831.3325 [M+ Na] 
+
(calc for C 
35
H 
52
N 
8
O 
12
NaS 
m/z
831.3323); 
1
H (600 MHz, CD 
3
OD) and 
13
C NMR (125 MHz, CD 
3
OD) data in CD 
3
OD are given in 
Table S4.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Marfey
’ 
s analysis
</title>
         <p>
Samples of squamins C–F (
1–4
) (400 μg) were hydrolyzed in 200 μL 6 N HCl at 50 
◦
C for 24 h. After the residual HCl was removed 
in vacuo
, to the residues was added 100 μL of an acetone solution containing 0.1 M of NaHCO 
3
and 25 μg of 1-fluoro-2,4-dinitrophenyl-5-d-alaninamide (
L
- FDAA). The solution was heated at 75 
◦
C for 4 h. Next, the reaction mixtures were cooled, neutralized with 2 N HCl (50 μL) and dissolved in MeOH (200 μL). Ten μL of each solution of FDLA derivatives was analyzed by HPLC. Additionally, standards of Gly, 
L
-Ala
,
L
-Thr, 
L
-Ile, 
L
- Pro, 
L
-Met(O), 
L
-Tyr (Sigma-Aldrich) were treated with 
L
-FDAA as described above. The 
L
-FDAA derivative of the 
L
-amino acid standard was analyzed by HPLC-UV, and the retention times 
L
-FDAA (8.16 min), Gly (5.80 min), 
L
-Ala (6.60 min)
,
L
-Thr (4.84 min), 
L
-Ile (12.49 min), 
L
- Pro (7.35 min), 
L
-Met(O) (4.17 min), 
L
-Tyr (15.97 min) were compared with the Marfey’ s derivative of 
1–4
. HPLC conditions: a 5 μM X-Bridge® C-18 column (100 × 
4.6 mm
) maintained at 40 
◦
C was operated at 0.8 mL/min with a gradient elution profile of 
CH
3
CN/H 
2
O (2:8; acidified with 0.05% HCOOH) to 
CH
3
CN/H 
2
O (6:4; acidified with 0.05% HCOOH) over 45 min, monitoring at 340 ηm.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Cell culture
</title>
         <p>
DU-145 (prostate cancer) and HeLa (human cervical carcinoma) cells were maintained in DMEM culture medium containing 10% (v/v) heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS), 2 mM L-glutamine, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 μg/mL streptomycin at 37 
◦
C in air containing 95% humidity and 5% CO 
2
. Cells were periodically tested for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mycoplasma
</tp:taxon-name>
infection using the MycoAlert© 
<tp:taxon-name>Mycoplasma</tp:taxon-name>
detection kit (Lonza, Basel, 
Switzerland
) as well as the Venor©GeM Advance 
<tp:taxon-name>Mycoplasma PCR</tp:taxon-name>
detection Kit (Minerva Biolabs, 
Berlin
, 
Germany
), and found to be negative.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Preparation of samples for assay
</title>
         <p>
Squamins C–F (
1–4
) were dissolved initially in DMSO at 40 mM, i.e., 400 times the maximum test concentration. For each test compound, the cells were exposed to serial decimal dilutions in the range of 10 
4
to 10 
9
M for a period of 48 h. Doxorubicin used as a positive control rendered IC 
50
values in the order of 10 
6
– 10 
7
M and 0.25% DMSO as negative control.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Cell growth inhibition assay
</title>
         <p>
The effect of each compound on the proliferation of human tumor cell lines was determined using the XTT (sodium 3’-[1-(phenylaminocarbonyl)-3,4-tetrazolium]-bis (4-methoxy-6-nitro) benzene sulfonic acid hydrate) cell proliferation kit (Roche Molecular Biochemicals, Mannheim, 
Germany
), as previously described (

). Cells (1.5–5.0 × 10 

3
in

100 μL) were incubated in DMEM culture medium containing 10% heat-inactivated FBS, in the absence and presence of the indicated compounds at a concentration range of 10 
4
to 10 
9
M, in 96-well flat-bottomed microtiter plates. Following 72 h of incubation at 37 
◦
C in a humidified atmosphere of air/CO 
2
(19/1), the XTT assay was performed. Measurements were made in triplicate, and each experiment was also repeated three times. The IC 
50
(50% inhibitory concentration) value, defined as the drug concentration required to cause 50% inhibition of cell proliferation with respect to the untreated controls, was determined for each compound. Data are shown as means ± standard deviation (SD) of three independent experiments, each performed in triplicate.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Computational details
</title>
         <p>
QM-NMR calculations followed the approach previously described by Lauro et al. This relies on establishing the statistical 
MAEΔΔδ
parameter, defined as
</p>
         <p>∑</p>
         <p>
(
ΔΔδ
) 
MAEΔΔδ
=
</p>
         <p>
nΔΔδ
</p>
         <p>
obtained from the summation (Σ) of the n computed absolute 
δ
error values (Δ 
δ
), normalized to the number of Δ 
δ
errors considered (n).
</p>
         <p>
The crystallographic structures for squamins A (CCDC 196170) and B (CCDC 196169) were optimized at the B3LYP/6-31G (d) level of theory. These optimized structures were then used to obtain the calculated magnetic shielding constants (σ) at the mPW1PW91/6-31 + G(d,p) level of theory. Subsequently, unscaled chemical shifts (
δ
u
) were calculated using TMS as reference standard according to the expression 
δ
u
= σ 
0
- 
σx
, where 
σx
is the shielding tensor and σ 
0
is the shielding tensor of TMS computed at the same level of theory used to calculate 
σx
. The structures of squamins C–F (
1–4
) were built using the crystallographic coordinates of compounds 
5
and 
6
as templates, making the necessary modifications in selected amino acids. Afterward, the resulting structures were geometrically optimized at the B3LYP/6-31G (d) level of theory. Due to the large size of the molecules, availability of crystallographic structures for 
1–2
and the resemblance of their NMR data with those of 
3–6
(which suggests that all of them adopt very similar conformations) computational studies were undertaken using only single conformations for each compound.
</p>
         <p>
As all comparisons are between two sets of calculated data (
A
, 
B
) and two sets of experimental data (
1
, 
2
), the number of possible comparisons for each pair of data is two (
AB
/ 
12
and 
AB
/ 
21
). For each comparison, Δ 
δ
calc
and Δ 
δ
exp
parameters are calculated using the equation Δ 
δ

calc 
A -
B

= 
δ

calc 
A

- 
δ
, where 
δ

calc 
A

and 
δ
are chemical shifts calculated for 
A
and 
B
data sets. This procedure is also followed to calculate Δ 
δ
exp
. Finally, the specific Δ 
δ
calc
and Δ 
δ
exp
values are compared atom by atom, using the ΔΔ 
δ
parameter defined as ΔΔ 
δ
= | Δ 
δ
calc
- Δ 
δ
exp
|. The ΔΔ 
δ
parameter detects similarities between calculated and experimental data sets and is used for calculating the 
MAEΔΔδ
parameter (
Table 3
and S17- S19).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

calc 
B
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

calc 
B
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
This work was supported by the Government of the State of 
Veracruz de Ignacio de la Llave
, 
Veracruz
Council for Scientific Research and Technological Development [COVEICyDET, grant number 14 1953/ 2021], and by the Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation (PID2019- 109476RB-C21). This study made use of the CESGA and SGAI-CSIC supercomputing facilities. We thank G. Jones for English text edition, funded by Cabildo de Tenerife, TFinnova Program supported by MEDI and FDCAN.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112839.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
References
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Anaya-Esparza, L.M.
, García-Magana ˜, M.L., Domínguez-Avila´, 
J.A
., 
Yahia, E.M.
, Salazar- L´opez, N.J., Gonz´alez-Aguilar, 
G.A
., Montalvo-Gonz´alez, E., 
2020
. 
Annonas: underutilized species as a potential source of bioactive compounds
. 
Food Res. Int.
138
, 
109775
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109775
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Bhushan, R.
, 
Brückner, H.
, 
2004
. 
Marfey’ s reagent for chiral amino acid analysis: a review
. 
Amino Acids
27
(3– 
4
), 
231–247
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00726-004- 0118-0
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Capon, R.J.
, 
2020
. 
Extracting value: mechanistic insights into the formation of natural product artifacts - case studies in marine natural products
. 
Nat. Prod. Rep.
37
, 
55–79
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/C9NP00013E
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cen-Pacheco, F.
, 
Mollinedo, F.
, 
Villa-Pulgarín, J.A.
, 
Norte, M.
, Fern´andez, J.J., Hern´andez 
Daranas, A.
, 
2012
. 
Saiyacenols A and B: the key to solve the controversy about the configuration of aplysiols
. 
Tetrahedron
68
(
39
), 
7275–7279
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.tet.2012.07.005
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cen-Pacheco, F.
, 
Ortiz-Celiseo, A.
, Peniche-Cardena ˜, A., 
Bravo-Ruiz, O.
, L´opez-Fentanes, F.C., 
Valerio-Alfaro, G.
, Fern´andez, J.J., 
2019
a. 

Studies on the bioactive flavonoids isolated from 
Azadirachta indica

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
34
(
24
), 
3483–3491
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/14786419.2019.1579808
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cen-Pacheco, F.
, 
Valerio-Alfaro, G.
, 
Santos-Luna, D.
, Fernandez´, J.J., 
2019
b. 

Sclerin, a new cytotoxic cyclononapeptide from 
Annona scleroderma

. 
Molecules
24
, 
554
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules24030554
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Dahiya, R.
, 
Dahiya, S.
, 
2021
. 

Natural bioeffective cyclooligopeptides from plant seeds of 
Annona
genus

. 
Eur. J. Med. Chem.
214
, 
113221
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. ejmech.2021.113221
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Daranas, A.H.
, 
Sarotti, A.M.
, 
2021
. 
Are computational methods useful for structure elucidation of large and flexible molecules? Belizentrin as a case study
. 
Org. Lett.
23
(
2
), 
503–507
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.orglett.0c04016
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Domínguez, H.J.
, 
Napolitano, J.G.
, Fern´andez-S´anchez, M.T., 
Cabrera-García, D.
, 
Novelli, A.
, 
Norte, M.
, Fern´andez, J.J., 
Daranas, A.H.
, 
2014
. 
Belizentrin, a highly bioactive macrocycle from the dinoflagellate prorocentrum belizeanum
. 
Org. Lett.
16
(
17
), 
4546–4549
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ol502102f
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Escobedo-L´opez, D., 
Campos-Rojas, E.
, 
Rodríguez-Nú˜nez, J.R.
, 
Alia-Tejacal, I.
, Nú˜nez- 
Colin, C.A.
, 
2018
. 

Priority areas to collect germplasm of 
Annona
(annonaceae) in Mexico based on diversity and species richness indices

. 
Genet. Resour. Crop. Evol. Published online
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10722-018-0718-2
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Grimblat, N.
, 
Gavín, J.A.
, 
Daranas, A.H.
, 
Sarotti, A.M.
, 
2019
. 
Combining the power of J coupling and DP4 analysis on stereochemical assignments: The J-DP4 methods
. 
Org. Lett.
21
(
11
), 
4003–4007
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.orglett.9b01193
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Grimblat, N.
, 
Zanardi, M.M.
, 
Sarotti, A.M.
, 
2015
. 
Beyond DP4: an improved probability for the stereochemical assignment of isomeric compounds using quantum chemical calculations of NMR shifts
. 
J. Org. Chem.
80
(
24
), 
12526–12534
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.joc.5b02396
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Hern´andez 
Vidal, L.
, L´opez 
Moctezuma, H.
, 
Vidal Martínez, N.A.
, 
Ruiz Bello, R.
, 
Castillo Rocha, D.G.
, 
Chiquito Contreras, R.G.
, 
2014
. 
La situacion´de las Annonaceae en M´exico: principales Plagas, Enfermedades y su Control
. 
Rev. Bras. Frutic.
36
, 
44–54
. 
https://doi.org/10.1590/S0100-29452014000500005
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Kutateladze, A.G.
, 
Holt, T.
, 
2019
. 
Structure validation of complex natural products: time to change the paradigm
. 
What did synthesis of alstofolinine A prove? J. Org. Chem.
84
(
12
), 
8297–8299
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.joc.9b00969
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Kupchan, S.M.
, 
Tsou, G.
, 
Sigel, C.W.
, 
1973
. 

Datiscacin, a novel cytotoxic cucurbitacin 20- acetate from 
Datisca glomerata

. 
J. Org. Chem.
38
(
7
), 
1420–1421
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/jo00947a041
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Lauro, G.
, 
Das, P.
, 
Riccio, R.
, 
Reddy, D.S.
, 
Bifulco, G.
, 
2020
. 
DFT/NMR approach for the configuration assignment of groups of stereoisomers by the combination and comparison of experimental and predicted sets of data
. 
J. Org. Chem.
85
(
5
), 
3297–3306
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.joc.9b03129
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Leite, D.O.D.
, 
Nonato, C.de
F.A
., 
Camilo, C.J.
, 
de Carvalho, N.K.G.
, 
da Nobrega, M.G.L. A.
, 
Pereira, R.C.
, 
da Costa, J.G.M.
, 
2020
. 

Annona
genus: traditional uses, phytochemistry and biological activities

. 
Curr. Pharmaceut. Des.
26
(
33
), 
4056–4091
. 

https://doi.org/10.2174/ 
1381612826666200325094422

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Li, S.W.
, 
Cuadrado, C.
, 
Yao, L.G.
, 
Daranas, A.H.
, 
Guo, Y.W.
, 
2020
. 
Quantum mechanical- NMR-aided configuration and conformation of two unreported macrocycles isolated from the soft coral lobophytum sp.: energy calculations versus coupling constants
. 
Org. Lett.
22
(
11
), 
4093–4096
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.orglett.0c01155
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Li, W.
, 
Hwang, D.J.
, 
Cremer, D.
, 
Joo, H.
, 
Kraka, E.
, 
Kim, J.
, 
Ross II, C.R.
, 
Nguyen, V.Q.
, 
Dalton, J.T.
, 
Miller, D.D.
, 
2008
. 
Structure determination of chiral sulfoxide in diastereomeric bicalutamide derivatives
. 
Chirality
21
(
6
), 
578–583
. https:// 
10.1002/chir.20642
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Marom, H.
, 
Biedermann, P.U.
, 
Agranat, I.
, 
2007
. 
Pyramidal inversion mechanism of simple chiral and achiral sulfoxides: a theoretical study
. 
Chirality
19
(
7
), 
559–569
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/chir.20417
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Mislow, K.
, 
Simmons, T.
, 
Melillo, J.T.
, 
Ternay, A.L.
, 
1694
. 
The hydrogen chloridecatalyzed racemization of sulfoxides
. 
J. Am. Chem. Soc.
86
(
7
), 
1452–1453
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1021/ja010661a048
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ren-Wang, J.
, 
Yang, L.
, 
Zhi-Da, M.
, 
Qi-Tai, Z.
, 
2003
. 

Molecular structure and pseudopolymorphism of squamtin A from 
Annona squamosa

. 
J. molec. Struct.
655
(
1
), 
157–162
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0022-2860(03)00227-8
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Shi, J.X.
, 
Wu, H.M.
, 
He, F.H.
, 
Inoue, K.
, 
Min, Z.D.
, 
1999
. 

Squamin-A, novel cyclopeptide from 
Annona squamosa

. 
Chin. Chem. Lett.
10
, 
299–302
. 
http://caod.oriprobe.com /articles/46023390/Squamin_A__Novel_Cyclopeptide_from_Annona_squamosa.htm
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Smith, S.G.
, 
Goodman, J.M.
, 
2009
. 
Assigning the stereochemistry of pairs of diastereoisomers using GIAO NMR shift calculation
. 
J. Org. Chem.
74
(
12
), 
4597–4607
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jo900408d
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Smith, S.G.
, 
Goodman, J.M.
, 
2010
. 
Assigning stereochemistry to single diastereoisomers by GIAO NMR calculation: the DP4 probability
. 
J. Am. Chem. Soc.
132
(
37
), 
12946–12959
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ja105035r
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Unno, K.
, 
Kaweewan, I.
, 
Nakagawa, H.
, 
Kodani, S.
, 
2020
. 
Heterologous expression of a cryptic gene cluster from Grimontia marina affords a novel tricyclic peptide grimoviridin
. 
Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.
104
(
12
), 
5293–5302
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s00253-020-10605-z
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Zhi-Da, M.
, 
Jian-Xia, S.
, 
Na, L.
, 
Qi-Tai, Z.
, 
Hou-Ming, W.
, 
2000
. 

Two conformational isomers of cyclopeptide from 
Annona squamosa

. 
J. China Pharm. Univ.
31
, 
332–338
. 
http://www.zgykdxxb.cn/jcpu/article/abstract/200005159
.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
