<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112520</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>An extensive study on the chemical diversity of lipophilic extractives from Eucalyptus globulus wood</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. urograndis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. grandis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. maidenii</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. 
globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
Labill. Trees
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. grandis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. urophylla
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. camaldulensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. urograndis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. urograndis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. globulus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. globulus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. nitens</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. maidenii</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. grandis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. dunnii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. grandis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. urograndis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. grandis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. urograndis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E. pellita</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

An extensive study on the chemical diversity of lipophilic extractives from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Jorge Gominho

a, 
*
, Ana Lourenço
a
, Ant´onio V´elez Marques
a, b
, Helena Pereira
a
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Centro de Estudos Florestais
, 
Instituto Superior de Agronomia
, 
Universidade de Lisboa
, Tapada da 
Ajuda

, 1349-017, 
Lisboa
, 
Portugal
b
Instituto Superior de Engenharia
de 
Lisboa
, Instituto Polit´ecnico

de 
Lisboa
, Rua Conselheiro Emídio Navarro 1, 1959-007, 
Lisboa
, 
Portugal
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Heartwood</p>
         <p>Sapwood</p>
         <p>Fatty acids</p>
         <p>Phytosterols</p>
         <p>Triterpenes</p>
         <p>Biorefinery</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Three mature 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
trees with 40 years of age were studied at three height levels (0%, 35%, and 60% of total tree height) and at three radial regions (sapwood, inner and outer heartwood). The composition of lipophilic extracts was evaluated and an extensive list of 202 compounds was reported for the first time. The fatty acids were the major chemical family, representing 40.8% of the total compounds, followed by phytosterols (19.0%), aromatics (10.5%) and triterpenes (10.4%). Saturated fatty acids accounted for 74.2% of total compounds (C 
16:0
, C 
24:0
and C 
26:0
were predominant), β- Sitosterol and stigmastanol were the main sterols (80 and 7% respectively), while aromatics were mainly represented by syringic acid, 4-hydroxy-3,5-dimethoxybenzaldehyde, vanillic acid, and vanillin. The main triterpenes were asiatic and arjunolic acids.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Most of the chemical diversity of wood (colour, fragrance and durability) is embedded in the extractives 
i.e.
the non-structural components that are solubilized by solvents with different polarities, and that include a diverse array of chemical families. In the case of the lipophilic soluble fraction extracted by non-polar solvents such as dichloromethane, hexane or petroleum ether, the chemical families include mainly fatty acids and alcohols, phytosterols, hydrocarbons and triterpenes (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Some of these compounds have received attention due to their potential interest as bioactive and functional molecules and to the possibility of integrating extractives recovery as a process step in biorefineries (

). Moreover, some wood lipophilic extractives may be a nuisance in pulp processing, because of equipment fouling and product staining (

; Sjostr ¨¨om and 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
is a major pulpwood feedstock, similarly to other eucalypt species 
i.e
. 

<tp:taxon-name>E. urograndis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. grandis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. maidenii</tp:taxon-name>

and therefore extractives of their wood and forest residues have been researched both aiming at decreasing their effect in pulping as well as valorising them as value added chemicals (

; 

). Most studies restricted the quantification and identification of the lipophilic extractives in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
to only those present in higher amounts and without addressing the question of their variability (

; Guti´errez et al., 1999; 

; 

). In fact, the extractives are produced and accumulated along the tree’ s lifetime, and it is expected to find an intrinsic variability of extractives composition within or between trees. It is therefore foreseeable that the presence and proportion of specific compounds or chemical families will differ in different parts of the tree 
e.g.
in sapwood and heartwood and at the different levels of stem height (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
In this work, we address the chemical diversity of the lipophilic extractives in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. 
globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood aiming at a near-complete detection of the compounds. For that, we did an extensive sampling in three mature 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
trees at different positions radially (sapwood, outer and inner heartwood) and in height (0%, 30% and 60% of total height) in order to cover different tree and cambial ages, and tested duplicates that were independently taken at each sampling point. The objective was to compile the maximum number of chemical compounds and families that were present as non-polar soluble compounds, regardless of proportion and location in the tree. The experimental methodology was based on a GC-MS analysis of dichloromethane extracts that was optimized regarding column and operative conditions, and on an accurate replication for all the tested samples. Special care was given on the accuracy of compound identification and on their quantification by making use of calibration with reference compounds for each family. Our goal was to bring a more complete insight on the chemical diversity of the lipophilic extractives from 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
E-mail address:
jgominho@isa.ulisboa.pt (J. Gominho).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Material and methods
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Material
</title>
         <p>
Three mature 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus globulus
Labill. Trees
</tp:taxon-name>
with 40 years of age were harvested and sampled at three height levels (0%, 35%, and 60% of total tree height) by taking a cross-sectional stem disk. The trees were on average 
31.6 m
high, with 
42.7 cm
over-bark diameter (at 
1.30 m
) and 
20.1 m
crown height. The sapwood and heartwood were manually separated from each stem disk and the heartwood was divided in outer and inner regions by separation at half the heartwood radius. The samples were milled and screened, and the 40–60 mesh fraction was used for analysis. These trees had been previously characterized, including the quantification of the heartwood proportion in the crosssection and the determination of extractives (
Fig. 1
), as reported in 

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Sample extraction
</title>
         <p>
For each tree, two samples from each level (0%, 35% and 60%) and from each radial position (sapwood, outer and inner heartwood), totalizing 18 samples were collected for analysis. From each sample, 
5 g
were exhaustively extracted with dichloromethane (DCM), previously purified by distillation to avoid contamination with solvent impurities, during 16 h in a Soxhlet apparatus. The extracted material was further extracted with ethanol (16 h) and water (16 h) to enable the quantification of total extractives, following adaptations to standard TAPPI T204 cm-07. The DCM extracts were concentrated in a vacuum rotary evaporator, the residual DCM was evaporated by a stream of N 
2
and the extract residue vacuum oven-dried overnight at 0.15 bar and 35 
◦
C, and weighed.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. GC-MS analysis
</title>
         <p>
For the GC-MS analysis, one aliquot from the DCM extracts (
1 mg
) was derivatized to trimethylsilyl ethers/esters (TMS) with 120 μL of pyridine (Sigma–Aldrich) and 80 μL of BSTFA (
N,O
-bis(trimethylsilyl) trifluoroacetamide with 1% trimethylchlorosilane, Sigma–Aldrich) at 60 
◦
C for 30 min. After cooling at room temperature, the extracts were injected in splitless mode in a GC–MS (Agilent 7890 A-5975C MSD) with an autoinjector and a high-temperature capillary column (Zebron 5 H T, 
30 m
× 
0.25 mm
x 0.1 μm) using He as carrier gas at a constant flow of 1 mL/min. The injector temperature was 280 
◦
C and the oven programmed with an initial temperature of 100 
◦
C (hold for 1 min), 10 
◦
C/ min to 150 
◦
C, 5 
◦
C/min to 200 
◦
C, 4 
◦
C/min to 300 
◦
C and 10 
◦
C/min to 380 
◦
C (hold for 5 min).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Overlapped compounds.

</p>
         <p>
The MS source conditions were: MSD transfer-line temperature maintained at 330 
◦
C, the MS source at 230 
◦
C, the quadrupole at 150 
◦
C and the electron ionization energy at 70eV. The electronic impact mass spectra (EIMS) were taken over a range of m/z 40–950.
</p>
         <p>
For semi-quantification purposes, the GC-MS was externally calibrated with authentic standards (hexadecanoic acid, β- sitosterol, and asiatic acid) that are representative of the major families of the lipophilic extracts (saturated fatty acids, sterols and triterpenes, respectively). The respective multiplication factors needed to acquire a correct quantification of the peak areas were calculated as an average of three GC-MS runs. The compounds were expressed as mg.g 
1
of dichloromethane extract. Each aliquot was injected in duplicated.
</p>
         <p>The identification of the compounds (as TMS derivatives) were based on comparisons with authentic standards, literature mass spectra, Wiley 6 and NIST libraries data, and interpretation of mass spectrometric fragmentation patterns.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Results
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1. Composition and abundance
</title>
         <p>
The DCM extractives content of the mature 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
trees ranged from 0.2% to 0.5% (o.d. Wood mass), which represents 4.0–12.5% of the total extractives content (

, 
Fig. 1
). Total extractives were mainly accumulated at the base of the tree (0% of height) principally in the inner heartwood representing 12.5%, from which 0.5% were lipophilic extractives (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Fig. 2
exemplifies one GC–MS chromatogram and the range of the different chemical families identified in the silylated DCM extracts. It was possible to identify about 85.4% of the total ion chromatogram area, corresponding to 202 compounds (189 totally identified and 13 only partially identified). The identified peaks were grouped by families and listed in 
Tables 1–6
.
</p>
         <p>
Fatty acids were the major family, representing 40.8% of the total compounds (as % of total area), followed by phytosterols (19.0%), aromatics (10.5%) and triterpenes (10.4%) (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
The total fatty acid families accounted on average to 
433.3 mg
/g of extract (
Table 1
). This family was mainly composed by monoacids (
394.5 mg
/g of extract), where the saturated fatty acids (SFA) accounts for 74.2% of the total, presenting a carbon chain from C 
10
to C 
30
, where the C 
16:0
(peak 
39
), C 
24:0
(
90
) and C 
26:0
(
97
) where the predominant compounds with respectively 90.4, 44.3 and 
52.8 mg
/g of extract. The unsaturated fatty acids (UFA) had a slightly lower range of carbon chain (C 
15
to C 
24
), mostly including C 
18:1
(
Z
and 
E
forms, peaks 
53
and 
54,
41.9 mg
/g of extract) and by C 
18:2
(peak 
52
, 
33.7 mg
/g of extract).
</p>
         <p>
Other groups of fatty compounds were identified, such as monoacylglycerols (MAGs, 
58.2 mg
/g of extract), α and ω- hydroxy fatty acids (HFAs, 
16.3 mg
/g of extract) and saturated α,ω- diacids (SDAs, 
9.3 mg
/g of extract). The main 
α
-hydroxyacid was the 2-hydroxytetracosanoic (C 
24:0
, peak 
95
), accounting for 
6.4 mg
/g of extract and the main monoacylglycerols were the 1-tetracosanoylglycerol (G-C 
24:0
, peak 
126
) and 1-hexacosanoylglycerol (G-C 
26:0
, peak 
146
) with respectively 14.0 and 18.0 mg/g of extract.
</p>
         <p>
Phytosterols content was 
186.1 mg
/g of extract (
Table 2
), where β- sitosterol (peak 
118
) and stigmastanol (peak 
119
) represented 80% and 7% of the total sterols, and with the presence of minor amounts of fucosterol (peak 
121
), and stigmast-4-en-3-one (peak 
128
).
</p>
         <p>
The aromatic compounds accounted for 
87.3 mg
/g of extract (
Table 3
), where syringic acid (peak 
25
), vanillic acid (peak 
14
), syringaldehyde (peak 
12
), and vanillin (peak 
5
) were the most abundant compounds with respectively 14.6, 12.2, 12.0 and 
8.2 mg
/g of extract.
</p>
         <p>
Triterpenes were also present (
75.6 mg
/g of extract, 
Table 4
), mainly represented by asiatic acid (peak 
162
) and arjunolic acid (peak 
161
) with respectively 14.5 and 
11.7 mg
/g of extract.
</p>
         <p>
Small amounts of hydrocarbons were identified with an average content of 
33.9 mg
/g of extract (
Table 5
). A homologous series of 
n
-alkanes from C 
16
to C 
40
was identified as well as one series of fatty alcohols from C 
16
to C 
29
. Docosane (peak 
51
) was the main alkane with 
4.4 mg
/g of extract, while octacosan-1-ol (peak 
104
) was the main fatty alcohol with 
1.3 mg
/g of extract.
</p>
         <p>
Finally, other compounds identified among DCM extracts with some relevance were one saponine (sitosteryl 3-β- D-glucopyranoside, peak 
168
) with a value of 
7.4 mg
/g of extract, a lignan (pinoresinol, peak 
120
and isomer, peak 
110
) with 
9.2 mg
/g of extract and 
a
-tocoferol (peak 
102
) with 4.0 mg/g of extract (
Table 6
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.2. Radial and axial compounds profile
</title>
         <p>
Fig. 4 presents the radial profile of the major chemical families identified in the 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
trees at the three heights levels (0%, 35% and 60% of total height).
</p>
         <p>Fig. 4 illustrates the distribution of the different chemical families in radial and axial positions. Heartwood regions were rich in fatty acids (≈55% of compounds), phytosterols (15–30%) and monoacylglycerols (≈10%). Sapwood presented a considerable content of triterpenes (10–35%), fatty acids (30–40%) and phytosterols (15–30%), but presented low amounts of monoacylglycerols (less than 10%).</p>
         <p>A clear distinction exists between the three height levels of the tree: at the base fatty acids predominate, at the middle prevail fatty acids, phytosterols and aromatics, and at the top fatty acids, phytosterols and triterpenes are more relevant. The triterpenes content were more expressive in sapwood and the maximum value was found in the top of the tree (34%).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Two sterols were not completely identified.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Reported for the first time in eucalypt wood; **eleven triterpenes were not
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>completely identified.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Discussion
</title>
         <p>
In spite the fact that the lipophilic content (by DCM extraction) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood was low in all the samples studied, since it ranged from only 0.2–0.5% of the oven dry wood mass (
Fig. 1
), the composition and the variability along the tree of the extractives are more important than only their content. This was the driver for this study, where a detailed and comprehensive composition of the DCM extracts from sapwood, outer heartwood and inner heartwood at different height levels (0%, 30% and 65%) were obtained. In fact, it was possible to identify 202 compounds in the DCM extracts, an extremely high number of compounds when compared to other works with eucalyptus that only reported up to 88 compounds (

, 

; Guti´errez et al., 1999; 

). In addition to the targeted design of this study that aimed at considering all compounds regardless of their content, the age of the trees (40 years) is above that of the previously studied trees (8–12 years) and this may contribute to increase the number of extractives since it is known that age favours the accumulation of some secondary metabolites (

).
</p>
         <p>
The DCM extracts were quite rich in fatty acids (40.8% of the total compounds), followed by phytosterols but with only half the percentage of FA (19.0%), aromatics (AR) and triterpenes with similar percentages, respectively 10.5% and 10.4% (
Fig. 3
). According to literature, the main lipophilic compounds found in DCM extracts from 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood were steroids, followed by fatty acids (

; Guti´errez et al., 1999). A similar pattern of distribution was reported in acetone extracts from 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. grandis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. urophylla
</tp:taxon-name>
8-year-old wood (and 12-year-old 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. camaldulensis
</tp:taxon-name>
wood (Silv´erio et al., 2007b).
</p>
         <p>
In the present study, the major lipophilic extracts were fatty acids and, as far as our knowledge goes, this is the first time that a large homologue series of fatty acids (18 SFA and 15 UFA) is reported for 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood. Hexadecanoic acid, hexacosanoic acid and tetracosanoic acid were the most abundant compounds (
Table 1
). The occurrence of fatty acids was more expressive in the wood at the base level, especially in outer and inner heartwood regions (
Fig. 4
). This distribution of fatty acids is not in complete agreement with the results found by other authors for 12-year-old 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
where the C 
16:0
was the predominant fatty acid accompanied by the C24:0 and C26:0 (

; Guti´errez et al., 1999), while in the present mature trees two other fatty acids are present, C 
18:2
(peak 
52
) and C 
18:1
(peak 
54
).
</p>
         <p>
Besides the already mentioned SFA and UFA compounds, the fatty acids included also 16 monoacylglycerols (MAGs), eight α- and ω- hydroxy fatty acids (HFAs) and seven saturated α,ω- diacids compounds (SDAs). The presence of ω- hydroxy acids such as 24-hydroxytetracosanoic (C 
24:0
) and 26-hydroxyhexacosanoic acids (C 
26:0
) were also reported in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood (

), and in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. urograndis
</tp:taxon-name>
(Silv´erio et al., 2007a). The 25-hydroxypentacosanoic (C 
25:0
) was reported in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. urograndis
</tp:taxon-name>
, but was not detected in the present mature 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
trees.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

reported the presence of six α- hydroxy fatty acids in 

<tp:taxon-name>E. globulus</tp:taxon-name>
,

some of which were also identified in this study (
Table 1
): 2-hydroxyhexadecanoic, 2-hydroxydocosanoic, 2-hydroxytricosanoic, 2-hydroxytetracosanoic, 2-hydroxypentacosanoic and 2-hydroxyhexacosanoic acids. A similar pattern was described by 

in five eucalyptus (

<tp:taxon-name>E. globulus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. nitens</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. maidenii</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. grandis</tp:taxon-name>

and 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. dunnii
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
         <p>
The presence of monoacylglycerols (MAGs) is very common in the lipophilic extracts from barks but scarce in wood (Guti´errez et al., 1999). However, in these mature trees, MAGs reached an average of 
58.2 mg
/g of extract, wherein 1-tetracosanoylglycerol and 1-hexacosanoylglycerol were the major compounds (
Table 1
). 

also mention the predominance of MAGs with carbon chains of C 
24
, C 
26
and C 

28
in

<tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus
</tp:taxon-name>
hybrids. 

showed that the 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
presented the highest amount of MAGs (
117.4 mg
/kg of wood) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. grandis
</tp:taxon-name>
the lowest (
58.7 mg
/kg of wood). In our study, the outer heartwood is the wood region with the higher accumulation of MAGs (9.5, 9.6 and 11.6% respectively at 0%, 35% and 60% of height levels, 
Fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
Sapwood at stem base accumulates more saturated diacids (SDAs) than the outer or the inner heartwood, 
e.g.
41.6, 27.8 and 
19.5 mg
/kg of dry wood at 0% of height, and 28.1, 28.1 and 
29.1 mg
/kg of dry wood at 60% of height, respectively. The information about the presence of SDAs in wood extracts is scarce. 

identified in different hardwoods (
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. urograndis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. grandis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
B. verrucosa
and 
A. mangium)
the presence of several SDAs: in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood, the total values ranged from 
10.2 to 29.9 mg
/kg of dry wood (before and after alkaline hydrolysis of the extract), but the maximum values were obtained in 
B. verrucosa
with 
400.4–468.1 mg
/kg of dry wood, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
Phytosterols are the second group of compounds present in DCM extracts accounting an average of 
186.1 mg
/g of extract (
Table 2
). Their occurrence is noticed in the heartwood regions principally in the outer region and at higher levels of the trees (
Fig. 4
). The main sterol is by far β- sitosterol (
149.7 mg
/g of extract) followed by stigmastanol (
13.2 mg
/g of extract, 
Table 2
), which are quite common in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eucalyptus
species
</tp:taxon-name>
as reported in different studies (

; Guti´errez et al., 1999; Silv´erio et al., 2007b, 2007a).
</p>
         <p>
The aromatic compounds (AR) represent nearly 10% of DCM extracts (
Fig. 3
), with an average of 
87 mg
/g of extract (
Table 3
), where the main compounds were syringic acid, vanillic acid and vanillin. Aromatics predominate at the basal level where they preferentially accumulated in the sapwood while at the other axial levels they were similarly distributed in all the wood regions.
</p>
         <p>
As expected, in these mature trees the content of aromatic compounds is higher compared with the values reported by other authors. For example, in 8-year old 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. urograndis
</tp:taxon-name>
clones the reported values ranged from 81.7 to 
29.5 mg
/kg dry wood, including mainly vanillin, 4- hydroxy-3,5-dimethoxybenzaldehyde, vanillic acid and syringic acid (Silv´erio et al., 2007a).
</p>
         <p>
Terpenes (totalling 14 compounds) were also identified in considerable amount (
75.6 mg
/g of extract), where the foremost compounds were asiatic acid, arjunolic acid and betulinic acid (
Table 4
). The preferential site for terpenic accumulation was sapwood, mainly at the top of the tree (34.4%, 
Fig. 4
) and thus under tree canopy influence. As far as we know, this is the first time that the following triterpenes are reported in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood: hederagenin (peak 
152
), maslinic acid (peak 
155
), asiatic acid (peak 
162
), caulophyllogenin (peak 
163
) and madecassic acid (
164
). In barks, leaves and fruits of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
the presence of triterpenic acids such as betulonic, betulinic, ursolic, oleanolic, 3-acetylursolic and 3-acetyloleanolic acids has been reported (

, 

, 2011b, 2010). These compounds are interesting since have biological activities and can be used for example for medical applications (

).
</p>
         <p>
Alkanes and fatty alcohols amounted to an average of 
33.9 mg
/g of extract, and included a series of long chain alcohols and 
n
-alkanes (these represented 75% of total) (
Table 5
). To the best of our knowledge, this is the first time that in eucalypt wood a complete homologous series of 
n
- alkanes were identified with a chain length ranging from 16 to 40 carbon atoms, and of LCAs with a chain length from 16 to 29 carbons.
</p>
         <p>
The presence of other 
type
of compounds (
Table 6
) represents less than 5% of the total DCM extract (
Fig. 3
), and includes α- tocopherol, ferulates, sitosteryl 3-β- D-glucopyranoside and lignans (pinoresinol, syringaresinol). The content of α- tocopherol (4.0 mg/g of extract corresponding to 
114.5 mg
/kg of wood) was higher than the values of 
0.9–5.4 mg
/kg of wood reported by 

. Regarding the lignans identified, as far as we know, this is the first time that these compounds are identified in eucalypt. Potential new therapeutic agents of lignans are reported for the production of lignan-rich to prevention of chronic illness, such as certain 
types
of cancers and cardiovascular disease (

).
</p>
         <p>
The huge variation found in CV reflected the axial and radial of the natural compounds present wood tissues. 

describe for these trees the higher content in extractives in heartwood principally in the inner heartwood than the sapwood and in the lower part of the stem. Same variation of lipophilic constituents within the tree in axial and radial directions were found by 

in 

<tp:taxon-name>E. pellita</tp:taxon-name>
.

</p>
         <p>
In practical terms, the high content in fatty acids found in this mature 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
trees point out to the need to take some precautions when such an aged wood is used as feedstock for pulping processes since it is known that these compounds affect negatively the pulp and paper production 
e.g.
by increasing the alkali consumption, decreasing the yield and promoting pitch and stickies formation (Guti´errez et al., 2001). A controlled small addition of aged wood to the regular wood feedstock to the pulping might be a solution. Another option could be the removal of such extractives before pulping by a pre-treatment that could lead to a potential side stream valorisation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
Important results were obtained for the complete knowledge of the apolar extractives composition of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood that included fatty acids (40.8% of the extract), phytosterols (19.0%), aromatics (10.5%) and triterpenes (10.4%). This is the first time that an exhaustive list of 202 compounds is reported, a number very much above those given by other researches focused in eucalypt. This was also the first time that a large homologue series of fatty acids was reported, including 18 saturated and 15 unsaturated fatty acids with chain lengths ranging from 10 to 30 carbons. Triterpenes included 14 compounds, from which five were reported for the first time in eucalypt wood (hederagenin, maslinic acid, asiatic acid, caulophyllogenin and madecassic acid). Homologous series of 
n
-alkanes (C 
16
to C 
40
) and alcohols (C 
16
to C 
29
) were identified.
</p>
         <p>The results showed within tree variation of lipophilic extractives composition with an accumulation of fatty acids at stem base of the trees and especially in the heartwood, while sapwood is enriched in triterpenes especially at the top level.</p>
         <p>
This work reveal that there are chemical components of high value in the lipophilic extractives of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. globulus
</tp:taxon-name>
wood, namely triterpenes, 
e.g.
asiatic and arjunolic acids, that can be valorised prior the pulp production under a biorefinery context.
</p>
         <p>
Author contribution statement
</p>
         <p>Jorge Gominho: Conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments; analysed and interpreted the data; wrote the paper.</p>
         <p>Ana Lourenco: performed the experiments, analysed the data and wrote the paper.</p>
         <p>Ant´onio Velez Marques: contributed for the identification of compounds and revised the paper.</p>
         <p>Helena Pereira: revised the paper.</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
This work was supported by FCT (Fundaç˜ao para a Ciˆencia e Tecnologia, 
Portugal
) by financing the Forest Research Centre (UIDB/ 00239/2020) and PTDC/AGR-CFL/110419/2009. Ana Lourenço was supported by FCT through a research contract (DL 57/2016/CP1382/ CT0007).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Arisandi, R.
, 
Ashitani, T.
, 
Takahashi, K.
, 
Marsoem, S.N.
, 
Lukmandaru, G.
, 
2020
. 
Lipophilic extractives of the wood and bark from Eucalyptus pellita F. Muell grown in Merauke, Indonesia. J
. 
Wood Chem. Technol.
40
, 
146–154
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Christopher, L.P.
(Ed.), 
2012
. 
Integrated Forest Biorefineries, RSC Green Chemistry
. 
Royal Society of Chemistry, Cambridge
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Domingues, R.
, 
Guerra, A.
, 
Duarte, M.
, 
Freire, C.
, 
Neto, C.
, 
Silva, C.
, 
Silvestre, A.
, 
2014
. 
Bioactive triterpenic acids: from agroforestry biomass residues to promising therapeutic tools. Mini-Reviews Org
. 
Chem.
11
, 
382–399
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Domingues, R.M.A.
, 
de Melo, M.M.R.
, 
Oliveira, E.L.G.
, 
Neto, C.P.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Silva, C.M.
, 
2013
. 
Optimization of the supercritical fluid extraction of triterpenic acids from Eucalyptus globulus bark using experimental design
. 
J. Supercrit. Fluids
74
, 
105–114
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Domingues, R.M.A.
, 
Oliveira, E.L.G.
, 
Freire, C.S.R.
, 
Couto, R.M.
, 
Sim˜oes, P.C.
, 
Neto, C.P.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Silva, C.M.
, 
2012
. 
Supercritical fluid extraction of Eucalyptus globulus bark-A promising approach for triterpenoid production
. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
13
, 
7648–7662
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Domingues, R.M.A.
, 
Patinha, D.S.J.
, 
Sousa, G.D.A.
, 
Villaverde, J.J.
, 
Silva, C.M.
, 
Freire, C. S.R.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Neto, C.P.
, 
2011
a. 
Eucalyptus biomass residues from agroforest and pulping industries as sources of high-value triterpenic compounds
. 
Cellul. Chem. Technol.
45
, 
475–481
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Domingues, R.M.A.
, 
Sousa, G.D.A.
, 
Freire, C.S.R.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Neto, C.P.
, 
2010
. 

Eucalyptus globulus
biomass residues from pulping industry as a source of high value triterpenic compounds

. 
Ind. Crop. Prod.
31
, 
65–70
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Domingues, R.M.A.
, 
Sousa, G.D.A.
, 
Silva, C.M.M.
, 
Freire, C.S.R.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Neto, C.P.
, 
2011
b. 
High value triterpenic compounds from the outer barks of several Eucalyptus species cultivated in Brazil and in Portugal
. 
Ind. Crop. Prod.
33
, 
158–164
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fengel, D.
, 
Wegener, G.
, 
1984
. 
Wood: chemistry, ultrastructure, reactions
., 
Wood: chemistry, ultrastructure, reactions
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Freire, C.S.R.
, 
Pinto, P.C.R.
, 
Santiago, A.S.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Evtuguin, D.V.
, 
Neto, C.P.
, 
2006
. 
Comparative study of lipophilic extractives of hardwoods and corresponding ECF bleached kraft pulps
. 
BioResources
1
, 
3–17
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Freire, C.S.R.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Neto, C.P.
, 
2002
. 

Identification of new hydroxy fatty acids and ferulic acid esters in the wood of 
Eucalyptus globulus

. 
Holzforschung
56
, 
143–149
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Freire, C.S.R.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Pascoal Neto, C.
, 
2005
. 

Lipophilic extractives in 
Eucalyptus globulus
Kraft pulps. Behavior during ECF bleaching. J

. 
Wood Chem. Technol.
25
, 
67–80
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gominho, J.
, 
Lourenço, A.
, 
Miranda, I.
, 
Pereira, H.
, 
2015
. 

Radial and axial variation of heartwood and extractives in mature trees of 
Eucalyptus globulus

. 
BioResources
10
, 
721–731
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guti´errez, A.
, 
del Río, J.C.
, 
Martínez, M.J.
, 
Martínez, A.T.
, 
2001
. 
The biotechnological control of pitch in paper pulp manufacturing
. 
Trends Biotechnol.
19
, 
340–348
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guti´errez, A.
, 
Del Río, J.C.C.
, 
Gonzalez-Vila´, F.J.J.
, 
Martín, F.
, 
1999
. 

Chemical composition of lipophilic extractives from 
Eucalyptus globulus
Labill. wood

. 
Holzforschung
53
, 
481–486
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hillis, W.E.
, 
1962
. 
Wood Extractives and Their Significance to the Pulp and Paper Industries
. 
Academic Press, New York
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hillis, W.E.
, 
1971
. 
Distribution, properties and formation of some wood extractives
. 
Wood Sci. Technol.
5
, 
272–289
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hillis, W.E.
, 
Brown, A.G.
, 
1984
. 
Eucalyptus for Wood Production
. 
CSIRO/Academic press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hon, D.N.-S.
, 
Shiraishi, N.
, 
2001
. 
Wood and Cellulosic Chemistry, second ed
. 
CRC Press Book, New York
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Prinsen, P.
, Guti´errez, A., 
Rencoret, J.
, 
Nieto, L.
, Jim´enez-Barbero, J., 
Burnet, A.
, 
Petit-Conil, M.
, 
Colodette, J.L.
, 
Martínez, A
´.T., del 
Río, J.C.
, 
2012
. 
Morphological characteristics and composition of lipophilic extractives and lignin in Brazilian woods from different eucalypt hybrids
. 
Ind. Crop. Prod.
36
, 
572–583
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rencoret, J.
, Guti´errez, A., del 
Río, J.C.
, 
2007
. 
Lipid and lignin composition of woods from different eucalypt species
. 
Holzforschung
61
, 
165–174
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Rodríguez-García, C.
, Sanchez-Quesada´, C

., 
Toledo, E.
, 
Delgado-Rodríguez, M.
, 
Gaforio, J.J.
, 
2019
. 
Naturally lignan-rich foods: a dietary tool for health promotion? Molecules
24
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Silv´erio, F.O
., 
Barbosa, L.C.A.
, 
Maltha, C.R.A´.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Veloso, D.P.
, 
Gomide, J. L.
, 
2007
a. 

Characterization of lipophilic wood extractives from clones of 
&lt;
i
&gt;
Eucalyptus urograndis 
&lt;
i/
&gt;
cultivate in Brazil

. 
BioResources
2
, 
157–168
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Silv´erio, F.O
., 
Barbosa, L.C.A.
, 
Silvestre, A.J.D.
, 
Pil´o-Veloso, D.
, 
Gomide, J.L.
, 
2007
b. 
Comparative study on the chemical composition of lipophilic fractions from three wood tissues of Eucalyptus species by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry analysis. J
. 
Wood Sci.
53
, 
533–540
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sjostr ¨¨om, E.
, 
Marchessault, R.H.
, 
1993
. 
Wood Chemistry, Fundamentals and Applications, Wood Chemistry
. 
Gulf Professional Publishing
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Valto, P.
, 
Knuutinen, J.
, Al´en, R., 
2012
. 
Overview of analytical procedures for fatty and resin acids in the papermaking process
. 
BioResources
7
, 
6041–6076
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
