<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112514</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Seladelicatulasine A-G, C steroidal glycosides with cholinesterase inhibitory activities from Selaginella delicatula</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Selaginellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Selaginella delicatula</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Selaginellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Selaginellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Selaginella species</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella delicatula
(Desv.) Alston
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Selaginellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
, Seladelicatulasine
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Drosophila
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Seladelicatulasine A–G, C 
27
steroidal glycosides with cholinesterase inhibitory activities from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cai-Ping Yao
a,c, 1
, Jing Li
a, 1
, Jian-Feng Liu
c
, Zhen-Xing Zou
b
, Feng-Hua Kang
b
, Xiao-Min Li
a
,

Dai Li 
a
, Kang-Ping Xu
b
, Ping-Sheng Xu

a, 
**
, Gui-Shan Tan

a, b, 
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a

Phase 1 Clinical Trial Center, Xiangya Hospital, Central South University, Changsha, 410008, PR 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b

Xiangya School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Central South University, Changsha, 410013, PR 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c

The First Affiliated Hospital of 
Hunan
University of Medicine, Huaihua, 418000, PR 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Selaginellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Steroidal glycosides Cholinesterase</p>
         <p>Monoamine oxidase</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
Seven undescribed C 
27
steroidal glycosides, Seladelicatulasine A–G, including six cholestanol glycosides and one spirostanol glycoside, were isolated from 

<tp:taxon-name>Selaginella delicatula</tp:taxon-name>
.

Their structures were elucidated by 1D/2D NMR spectra and HRESIMS analyses. The absolute configurations of the sugars were determined by enzymatic hydrolysis and GC/MS analyses. These cholestanol glycosides were isolated from the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Selaginellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
for the first time. Seladelicatulasine F is characterized as a rare B-5,6-secosteroid. In addition, all the compounds were evaluated for their inhibitory activities against cholinesterase (AChE/BChE) and monoamine oxidase (MAO-A/ MAO-B). These steroidal glycosides displayed selective inhibition activities on cholinesterase. Seladelicatulasine A, B and E inhibited the AChE activity with IC 
50
values of 0.31, 0.09, and 0.04 
μ
M, respectively. Seladelicatulasine A and F showed the strongest inhibition activity on BChE with IC 
50
values of 0.37 and 0.65 
μ
M, respectively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
is the sole genus in the spike moss family (
<tp:taxon-name>Selaginellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
), containing approximately 700 species that are spread over temperate, tropical, arctic, and desert regions (

). In the Flora of 
China
, 66 
<tp:taxon-name>Selaginella species</tp:taxon-name>
were recorded, most of them were used as traditional medicine (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella delicatula
(Desv.) Alston
</tp:taxon-name>
is an herb that belonging to the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
, which mainly distributed in the south of the Yangtze River. In 
China
, the whole plants are used as a folk medicine for promoting blood circulation, regulating menstruation, and heat-clearing and detoxifying (

). Previous phytochemical studies of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
have led to the isolation of bioflavonoids, sterols, anthraquinones, alkaloid, neolignans and adenine analogues (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). Some of them exhibited various biological activities, such as cytotoxicity, anticancer and neuroprotection (

; 

; Chandran et al., 2013). The unusual genetic characteristics of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
and its evolution process suggested that plants of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
have the potential to synthesize unique and biologically active secondary metabolites (

; 

). As part of our continuing efforts to search for structurally unique and biologically interesting secondary metabolites from plants of the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Selaginellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

; 

,b; 

; 

; 

), seven undescribed C 
27
steroidal glycosides were isolated from the 
n
-BuOH portion of the extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
, Seladelicatulasine
</tp:taxon-name>
A-G (1–7), including six cholestanol glycosides (1–6) and one spirostanol glycoside (7). The structures of 1–7 were determined by analysis of extensive spectroscopic data and enzymatic hydrolysis. Compound 6 represent the first example of 5,6-secosteroid isolated from the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Selaginella
</tp:taxon-name>
. Herein, we describe the isolation, structure elucidation, and the inhibitory activities against cholinesterase and monoamine oxidase of the steroidal glycosides.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
Seladelicatulasine A (1) was obtained as an amorphous powder, whose molecular formula was determined to be C 
49
H 
78
O 
21
based on the sodium adduct ion at 
m/z
1025.4891 [M + Na] 
+
in the HRESIMS (calcd for 1025.4928). The 1D NMR spectra of 1 showed the characteristic signals for the aglycone of C 
27
steroidal glycosides ascribable to two angular methyl singlets at 
δ
H
0.98 (
CH
3
-19) and 0.75 (
CH
3
-18), two secondary methyl groups at 
δ
H
0.96 (
CH
3
-21) and 0.83 (
CH
3
-27), seven methines including one oxygenated one [
δ
C
78.5 (C-3), 
δ
C
30.8 (C-8), 
δ
C
49.7 (C-9), 
δ
C
50.7 (C-14), 
δ
C
65.8 (C-17), 
δ
C
43.2 (C-20), 
δ
C
35.4 (C-25)], 10 methylenes including one oxygenated carbon [
δ
C
37.0 (C-1), 
δ
C
29.5 (C-2), 
δ
C
38.2 (C-4), 
δ
C
31.6 (C-7), 
δ
C
20.6 (C-11), 
δ
C
38.4 (C-12), 
δ
C
37.3 (C-15), 
δ
C
39.4 (C-23), 
δ
C
27.1 (C-24), 
δ
C
66.5 (C-26)], a trisubstituted olefin bond carbons at 
δ
C
121.5 (C-6) and 140.9 (C-5), two ketone carbons at 
δ
C
218.0 (C-16) and 213.2 (C-22), and two quaternary carbons. Analysis of the 1D/2D NMR data suggested that the aglycone moiety was (25 
R
)-cholest-5(6)-en-3 
β
,26-diol-16,22-dione (kryptogenin) (

), which was further confirmed by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY and HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
). The configuration of C-25 was deduced to be 
R
by the typical chemical shifts of the geminal protons at H 
2
-26 (
δ
a
– 
δ
b
= 0.05 ppm 
&lt;
0.48 ppm) (

). In addition to the aforementioned signals of the aglyconee moiety, the 
1
H-NMR spectrum exhibited four anomeric protons signals at 
δ
H
5.20 (1H, brs), 4.46 (1H, d, 
J
= 7.8), 4.29 (1H, d, 
J
= 7.6), 4.24 (1H, d, 
J
= 7.7) indicated the presence of four sugar units. Enzymatic hydrolysis of 1 with cellulase afforded D-glucose, L-rhamnose and L-arabinose, whose absolute configurations were determined by GC-MS analysis (see the Supporting Information). The linkages of the sugar moiety were determined by HMBC spectrum. The HMBC correlations between 
δ
H
4.46 (H 
1
-Glu) and 
δ
C
75.8 (C-3) suggested that the glucose was located at C-3 of the aglycone moiety, and the linkages of 
α
-L-ara-(1 → 2)-[
α
-L-rha-(1 → 3)]- 
α
-L-ara-(1 → 4)- 
β
-D-glc were deduced from the HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
) between H 
1
-Rha (
δ
H
5.20) and C 
3
-Glc (
δ
C
76.7), between H 
1
-Ara-II (
δ
H
4.29) and C 
2
-Rha (
δ
C
81.1), and between H 
1
-Ara -I (
δ
H
4.24) and C 
4
-Glc (
δ
C
79.9). Thus, the structure of 1 was determined to be (25 
R
)-3 
β
,26-diol-cholest-5(6)-en-16,22-dione-3- 
O -α
-L-arabinopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 3)-[
α
-L-arabinopyranosyl-(1 → 4)]- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside, and named as Seladelicatulasine A (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Seladelicatulasine B (2) was isolated as an amorphous powder. Its molecular formula was determined to be C 
50
H 
80
O 
22
by its HRESIMS (
m/ z
1055.5007 [M + Na] 
+
, calcd for 1055.5033) data. Interpretation of the NMR data (
Tables 1
and 
2
) of 2 and 1 disclosed that the aglycone of 2 was identical to that of 1. The only difference was the sugar moiety at C-3. The sugar moiety of 2 were comprised of D-glucose, L-rhamnose and L-arabinose, which determined by combining the 1D NMR data and the GC-MS analysis. The sequence of the tetrasaccharide chain was established by the HMBC correlations from H 
1
-Glc-I (
δ
H
4.46) to C-3 (
δ
C
75.9), from H 
1
-Rha (
δ
H
5.19) to C 
3
-Glc-I (
δ
C
77.2), from H 
1
-Glc-II (
δ
H
4.23) to C 
2
-Rha (
δ
C
80.1), and from H 
1
-Ara (
δ
H
4.30) to C 
3
-Glc-II (
δ
C
81.1). Compound 2 was therefore fully identified as (25 
R
)-3 
β
,26-diol-cholest-5 (6)-en-16,22-dione-3- 
O -α
-L-arabinopyranosyl-(1 → 3)- 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 3)- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside, and named as Seladelicatulasine B (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Seladelicatulasine C (3) was purified as white amorphous powder with molecular formula determined to be C 
44
H 
70
O 
17
by HRESIMS at 
m/z
893.4477 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for 893.4505), suggesting that it has one less glucosyl unit in comparison to compound 2. Analysis of the NMR data of 3 suggested that it was a cholestanol glucoside bearing structural similarities to 1 and 2, except for the sugar moiety. Further analysis of the 1D/2D NMR spectra and GC-MS chromatogram of 3 afford D-glucose, Lrhamnose and L-arabinose. As shown in 
Fig. 2
, the linkage of L-Ara-(1 → 2)-L-Rha-(1 → 3)-D-Glc were deduced by the HMBC cross peaks between H 
1
-Rha with C 
3
-Glc and H 
1
-Ara with C 
2
-Rha. The HMBC correlation from H 
1
-Glc to C-3 suggested that the D-Glc was attached to C-3 of the aglycone. Therefore, the structure of 3 was determined as (25 
R
)-3 
β
,26- diol-cholest-5(6)-en-16,22-dione-3- 
O -α
-L-arabinopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 3)- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside and named as Seladelicatulasine C (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Seladelicatulasine D (4) was obtained as white amorphous powder.Its molecular formula was determined as C 
56
H 
90
O 
27
by HRESIMS at 
m/z
1217.5515 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for 1217.5562), which suggested one more glucosyl unit than 2. Comparing the NMR data of 4 and 2 suggested that they are similar compounds, and the downfield chemical shift of C-26 (
δ
c 66.5 ppm → 74.3 ppm) indicated that the hydroxy group at C-26 of the aglycone was replaced by the sugar moiety. The extensive analysis of the 2D NMR spectra, as well as GC-MS analysis allowed the characterization of three 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl units (Glc-I, Glc-II, Glc-III), one 
α
-L-arabinopyranosyl unit, and one 
α
-L-rhamnopyranosyl unit. The long-range correlation from the anomeric proton signal at 
δ
H
4.10 (H 
1
-Ara) to C-26 (
δ
C
74.3), and from proton signal at 
δ
H
4.30 (H 
1
-Glc-III) to C 
2
-Ara(
δ
C
73.9) in the HMBC spectrum (
Fig. 2
) suggested that one 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl (Glc-III) was attached to C-2 of 
α
-L-arabinopyranosyl and the 
α
-L-arabinopyranosyl was linked to C-26. The linkages of Glc-II, Rha and Glc-I was deduced by HMBC correlations from H 
1
-Glc-I to C-3, from H 
1
-Rha to C 
3
- Glc-I, and from H 
1
-Glc-II to C 
2
-Rha. The configuration of C-25 was deduced to be 
S
based on the difference of chemical shifts of the geminal protons at H 
2
-26 (
δ
a
– 
δ
b
= 0.61 ppm
&gt;
0.48 ppm) (

). On the basis of above evidence, the structure of 4 was defined as (25 
S
)-26- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
α
-L-arabinopy-ranosyl-cholest -5(6)-en-3 
β
,26-diol-16,22-dione-3- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
α
-Lrhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 3)- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside, and given a trivial name of Seladelicatulasine D (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of seladelicatulasine E (5) was determined as C 
55
H 
88
O 
26
by the HRESIMS (
m/z
1187.5420 [M + Na] 
+
, calcd for 1187.5456) data. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic features of 5 were similar to 4, which suggested the two compounds possess the same aglycone. Further analysis of the 1D NMR data together with the GC-MS analysis indicated the presence of two 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl, one 
α
-Lrhamnopyranosyl, and two 
α
-L-arabinopyranosyl moieties. And the linkages of the sugar moieties were confirmed by the HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
). Therefore, compound 5 was assigned the structure of (25 
R
)-26- 
O -α
-L-arabinopyranosyl-cholest-5(6)-en-3 
β
,26-diol-16,22-dione-3- 
O - α
-L-arabinopyranosyl-(1 → 2)- 
α
-L-rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 3)-[
β
-D-glucopyranosyl-(1 → 4)]- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside, and named as Seladelicatulasine E (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
(
continued on next page
)
</p>
         <p>
Table 1
(
continued
)
</p>
         <p>
‑
6
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Seladelicatulasine F (6) was isolated as a pale brown amorphous powder with molecular formula of C 
33
H 
56
O 
8
according to the sodium adduct ion peak at 
m/z
603.3871 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for 603.3867) in the positive HRESIMS, indicating six indices of hydrogen deficiency. The 1D NMR data of 6 showed signals ascribable to five methyls, 12 methylenes including two oxygenated one, 12 methines, four quaternary carbons, including an olefin bond, a ketones carbonyl, and a 
β
-glucopyranosyl unit, accounting for three of six degrees of unsaturation, which indicated the presence of three rings in 6. The NMR data analysis indicated that 6 was a 5,6-secosteroid glucoside. Moreover, the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data of 6 were similar to those of 5-oxo-5,6-seco-3-cholesten-6-oic acid (

; 

), except for the carboxyl group at C-7 was replaced by a hydroxymethyl group, and the hydrogen atom at C-25 was replaced by a 
β
-glucopyranosyl. This was further confirmed by the HMBC correlations of H 
1
-Glc (
δ
H
4.24) with C-25 (
δ
c 76.9) and the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY (
Fig. 3
) correlations of H-6/H-7 and H-7/H-8. The relative configuration of 6 was determined to be 8 
S
, 9 
S
, 10 
R
, 13 
R
, 14 
S
, 17 
R
, 20 
R
by the NOESY (
Fig. 3
) cross peaks between H-9/H-14/H-17/Me-21 and Me-18/H-8/Me-19. Enzymatic hydrolysis and GC-MS analysis of 6 allowed the characterization of a 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl unit. Therefore, the structure of 6 was elucidated as (17 
α
, 20 
β
) 5-oxo-5,6-seco-3-cholesten-6-ol-25-O- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside and named as Seladelicatulasine F (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Seladelicatulasine G (7) was obtained as a white amorphous powder with the molecular formula C 
45
H 
72
O 
18
, deduced from its HRESIMS (
m/z
923.4581 [M + Na] 
+
, calcd for 923.4611) data. The 
1
H NMR spectrum of 7 displayed three anomeric protons at 
δ
H
5.13 (brs), 4.44 (d, 
J
= 7.9), and 4.28 (d, 
J
= 7.8), two angular methyl signals at 
δ
H
0.79 (3H, s, 
CH
3
- 18), 0.97 (3H, s, 
CH
3
-19) and two secondary methyl signals at 
δ
H
0.75 (3H, d, 
J
= 6.3, 
CH
3
-27), 0.86 (3H, d, 
J
= 6.9, 
CH
3
-21), which are the characteristic signals of a typical steroidal triglucoside (

). The 
13
C NMR data of 7 revealed 45 resonances. In addition to the carbon signals of three sugar moieties, the remaining 27 signals were attributed to one ketal, one oxygenated methylenes, three oxygenated methines, a trisubstituted olefin bond, eight methylenes, six methines, four methyls, and two quaternary carbons. Detailed analysis of the NMR data, suggesting the aglycone of 7 to be a 3,23-dihydroxyspirost-5-ene derivative (

). The 
R
configuration of C-25 was confirmed by the difference of chemical shifts of the geminal protons at H 
2
-26 (
δ
a
– 
δ
b
= 0.20 ppm 
&lt;
0.48 ppm). Moreover, the key NOESY correlations (
Fig. 3
) of H-23/H-20, H-23/H-25, H-26 
eq
/H-25, H-26 
ax
/H-27, and H-26 
ax
/H-16 revealed the absolute configurations of C-20, C-22, and C-23 were 
S
, 
R
, 
S
, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
The sugar residue of Glc-I, Glc-II and Rha in 7 were determined by enzymatic hydrolysis and GC-MS analysis. The linkage of the sugar moieties was confirmed by the HMBC correlations from H 
1
-Glc-I (
δ
H
4.44) to C-3 (
δ
C
76.4), from H 
1
-Rha (
δ
H
5.13) to C 
2
-Glc-I (
δ
C
75.7), and from H 
1
-Glc-II (
δ
H
4.28) to C4-Glc-I (
δ
C
88.9). Based on the above evidence, the structure of 7 was determined to be (20 
S
, 22 
R
, 23 
S
, 25 
R
)-23- hydroxyspirost-5-en-3 
β
-yl 
O -α
-L-rhamnopyranosyl-(1 → 2)-[
β
-D-glucopyra-nosyl-(1 → 4)]- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside and assigned the name Seladelicatulasine G (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
It has been reported previously that the extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
showed protective effects against the damage caused by experimental oxidative stress and nerve toxicity in the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Drosophila
</tp:taxon-name>
model (

; Chandran et al., 2013). In order to identify novel potent cholinesterase and monoamine oxidase inhibitors from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
, which can be applied to the treatment of Alzheimer’ s disease (AD) and related dementias, compounds 1–7 were tested in vitro for their inhibitory activities on AChE, BChE, MAO-A and MAO-B. As shown in 
Table 3
, most of these steroidal glycosides displayed selective inhibition activities on cholinesterase. Compounds 1, 2 and 5 showed sub-micromolar inhibition potency on AChE with IC 
50
values of 0.31, 0.09 and 0.04 
μ
M, respectively. In particular, compound 5 was found to be two times more potent than the standard compound huperzine A (IC 
50
= 0.08 
μ
M). Compounds 3 and 4 showed weak AChE-inhibitory activity. Among all tested compounds, compound 5 showed the highest anti-AChE activity, therefore, kinetics of 5 was further measured to determine the nature of AChE inhibition, based on graphical analysis of steady-state inhibition data. As depicted in 
Fig. 4
, the Lineweavere–Burk plots exhibited both increasing slopes and increasing intercepts on the y-axis at higher inhibitor concentration, which suggested a mixed-type inhibition of 5 toward AChE.
</p>
         <p>Additionally, in the BChE assay, compounds 1, 2, 5 and 6 showed the significant inhibition activity, especially compounds 1 and 6 showed better inhibition effects than the positive control (Donepezil), whereas 3 and 4 showed less potent inhibition activity. On the contrary, all of these compounds in this study showed inactivity on MAO-A and MAO-B.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
The phytochemical study of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
led to the identification of seven C 
27
steroidal glycosides, named Seladelicatulasine A-G (1–7). All the isolates were elucidated using comprehensive spectroscopic techniques and enzymatic hydrolysis. The inhibitory activities of compounds 1–7 against cholinesterase and monoamine oxidase were assayed. The results showed that some of these steroidal glycosides demonstrating potent and selective AChE and BChE inhibitory activity under in vitro conditions. As far as we know, AChE inhibitors and BChE inhibitors have been adopted for clinical use to treat several clinical conditions including bladder distention, glaucoma, vascular dementia, and symptoms of AD. Our discovery of new steroidal glycosides, some with potent and specific dual inhibitory activity both on AChE and BChE, could provide leads for the development of better clinical cholinesterase inhibitors.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experiment procedures
</title>
         <p>
Optical rotations were measured on an INESA SGW-3 polarimeter (SGW, 
Shanghai
, 
China
). 1D and 2D NMR spectra were recorded on a Bruker AV-400 spectrometer and a Bruker AV-500 spectrometer (Bruker, Karlsruhe, 
Germany
). HRESIMS were recorded on a Finnigan LTQ-FT (Thermo Finnigan, MA, 
USA
) and a Q-TOF mass spectrometer (Agilent 6540, CA, 
USA
). Semi-preparative or analytical HPLC was performed on an Agilent 1200 unit equipped with a DAD detector, and a siligreen C18 column (10 μm, 250 × 
10 mm
, siligreen, 
Beijing
, 
China
). GC-MS analysis of the derivative sugars were performed on a Shimadzu GCMS-QP2010 Ultra (Shimadzu, 
Japan
) using a Gas Chromatograph (GC-2010 Plus, Shimadzu, 
Japan
) equipped with a Single Quadrupole Mass Spectrometer as detector. All solvents were analytical grade. Macroporous resin HPD-100 (
Hebei
, 
China
) and Toyopearl HW-40C (TOYOPEARL, TOSOH, 
Japan
) were used for column chromatography (CC). Standard sugars (D-glucose, L-arabinose, and L-rhamnose) for GC-MS analysis were purchased from Shanghai Yuanye Biological Co. and L-Cysteine Methyl Ester Hydrochloride and N-(Trimethylsilyl) imidazole were purchased from Aladdin Industrial Co.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>

Whole herbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected from 
Hainan province
(coordinates 109 
◦
19 
′
- 

109 
◦
44 
′
E

, 18 
◦
38 
′
- 

19 
◦
02 
′
N

), 
People’
s Republic of China, and authenticated by Prof. Zhen-Ji 
Li
(
Xiamen University
, 
Xiamen
, 
China
). A voucher specimen (NO. 20140817) has been deposited in the 
Xiangya School of Pharmaceutical Sciences
, 
Central South University

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The air-dried whole herbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. delicatula
</tp:taxon-name>
(10.0 kg) were extracted with 75% aqueous EtOH (× 2) under reflux, then concentrated under reduced pressure to yield a residue. The residue was suspended in H 
2
O and partitioned with petroleum ether, EtOAc, and 
n
-BuOH, successively, to yield a 
n
-BuOH fraction (85.0 g).
</p>
         <p>
The 
n
-BuOH fraction was loaded on a macroporous adsorbent resin (HPD-100) column, and eluted with H 
2
O, 30, 70, and 95% EtOH–H 
2
O successively to obtain four fractions (Fr. A-D). Fr. C (
18.2 g
) was subjected to HW-40C (MeOH–H 
2
O in gradient) to yield 10 fractions (Fr. C1–C10). Fr. C2 was subjected to HW-40C to obtained five fractions (Fr. C2.1-C2.5). Fr. C2.1 was purified by prep-HPLC (MeCN–H 
2
O, 23:77 to 30:70) to yield 4 (
3.7 mg
, 
t
R
= 15.8 min) and 5 (3.0 mg, 
t
R
= 19.0 min). Fr. C2.3 was subjected to HW-40C to yield four fractions (Fr. C2.3.1 - C2.3.4). Compound 1 (3.0 mg, 
t
R
= 11.1 min), 2 (
4.5 mg
, 
t
R
= 12.3 min), and 3 (
3.3 mg
, 
t
R
= 13.5 min) were obtained from Fr. C2.3.1 by prep-HPLC (MeCN–H 
2
O, 35:65). Fr. C2.3.2 was purified by prep-HPLC (MeCN–H 
2
O, 45:55) to yield 7 (5.0 mg, 
t
R
= 10.9 min), and compound 6 (
3.1 mg
, 
t
R
= 18.9 min) was obtained from Fr. C2.3.3 by prep-HPLC (MeCN–H 
2
O, 38:62 to 48:52).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Seladelicatulasine A (1)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
]25 D +1.80 (
c
0.05, MeOH); UV (MeCN–H 
2
O) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 205 (3.57) nm; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
) data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS 
m/z
1025.4891 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
49
H 
78
O 
21
Na, 1025.4928).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Seladelicatulasine B (2)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
]25 D +4.43 (
c
0.06, MeOH); UV (MeCN–H 
2
O) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 205 (3.18) nm; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
) data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS 
m/z
1055.5007 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
50
H 
80
O 
22
Na, 1055.5033).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. Seladelicatulasine C (3)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
]25 D +0.69 (
c
0.05, MeOH); UV (MeCN–H 
2
O) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 205 (3.05) nm; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
) data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS 
m/z
893.4477 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
44
H 
70
O 
17
Na, 893.4505).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.4. Seladelicatulasine D (4)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
]25 D +7.43 (
c
0.05, MeOH); UV (MeCN–H 
2
O) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 205 (3.38) nm; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
) data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS 
m/z
1217.5515 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
56
H 
90
O 
27
Na, 1217.5562).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.5. Seladelicatulasine E (5)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
]25 D +5.69 (
c
0.06, MeOH); UV (MeCN–H 
2
O) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 205 (3.42) nm; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
) data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS 
m/z
1187.5420 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
55
H 
88
O 
26
Na, 1187.5456).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.6. Seladelicatulasine F (6)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
]25 D +1.73 (
c
0.04, MeOH); UV (MeCN–H 
2
O) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 235 (3.71) nm; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
) data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS 
m/z
603.3871 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
33
H 
56
O 
8
Na, 603.3867).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.7. Seladelicatulasine G (7)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
]25 D+34.5 (
c
0.04, MeOH); UV (MeCN–H 
2
O) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 205 (3.22) nm; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (DMSO 
‑d
6
) data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; (+)-HRESIMS 
m/z
923.4581 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
45
H 
72
O 
18
Na, 923.4611).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Enzymatic hydrolysis and GC-MS analysis
</title>
         <p>
Compounds 1–7 (about 
0.5 mg
each) dissolved in HOAc-NaOAc (pH 6.0, 3 mL) were separately treated with cellulase (400u/mg, 1:30) and kept at 37 
◦
C for 96 h. After incubation, each reaction mixture was added water to 5 mL, then extracted with CHCl 
3
(5 mL × 3). Each aqueous layer was evaporated to dryness. Each dried residue and standard sugars were mixed with L-cysteine methyl ester hydrochloride (1.0 mg) and dissolved in pyridine (0.6 mL), with the solutions kept at 60 
◦
C for 1 h, following which N-trimethylsilimidazole (0.6 mL) was added, with the whole then kept for 30 min. The supernatants were analyzed by GC-MS, respectively, under the following conditions: Rtx-5MS capillary column (

30 m

× 0.5 μm × 
0.32 mm
, SHIMADZU, 
Japan
); carrier gas was N 
2
(1 mL/min); injector port: 300 
◦
C; ion source: 280 
◦
C; injection volume: 1 
μ
L; and the split ratio: 1/50. 
The
mass ranges from m/z 50–1000 amu was acquisition in the full scan mode with a dwell time of 0.6 min. 
Initially
the oven temperature was held at 150 
◦
C for 2 min, and then the temperature was increased to the final temperature 300 
◦
C within 10 min and held for 8 min. 
Under
these conditions, the retention times of 
Dglucose
were 
9.790
, 
10.608
min, and L-rhamnose were 
6.862
, 
7.666
min, L-arabinose were 6.678, 6.735, 7.094 and 7.412 min, respectively. The absolute configurations of the sugar moieties in 1–7 were thus identified by comparing their retention times with standard sugars.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. AChE and BChE assays
</title>
         <p>
AChE and BChE activities were determined based on modified Ellman’ s method (

; 

). (S)-acetylthiocholine iodide (ATCI), (S)-butyrylthiocholine iodide (BTCI), 5, 5 
′
-dithiobis-2-nitrobenzoic acid (DTNB), electric eel AChE and horse serum BChE were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. The assay was carried out in the 96-well microplates. Each well was filled with 158 
μ
L of Ellman’ s reagent (0.15 mM of 5,5 
′
-dithiobis-2-nitrobenzoic acid) in 0.1 M phosphate buffer pH 7.4), 20 
μ
L of a solution of the substrate [ATCI for AChE (
K
m
= 0.33 mM) and BTCI for BChE (
K
m
= 0.30 mM)], and 2 
μ
L of different concentrations tested compounds in DMSO. For the blank control, the corresponding volume of DMSO was used. Huperzine A and Donepezil were used as the positive control. Reactions were started by the addition of 20 
μ
L of electric eel AChE or horse serum BChE solution (1 IU/mL in 0.1 M phosphate buffer pH 7.4), containing human serum albumin (
1 mg
/mL). Then, the reaction incubated at 37 
◦
C for 6 min, the optical densities were measured at 
412 nm
by Enzymatic Calibration instrument. Data analysis was performed on GraphPad Prism 6.0 software and expressed as mean ± standard deviation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Kinetic study of AChE inhibition
</title>
         <p>
The kinetic study of AChE inhibition was operated by using Ellman’ s method (described above). Compound 5 was added into the assay solution and pre-incubated with the AChE at 37 
◦
C for 15 min, followed by the addition of ATCI. The incubation system (158 μL) containing 2 
μ
L of different concentrations compound 5 (0.06, 0.04, 0.02 μM), DTNB (0.15 mM), 10 μL AChE and 20 
μ
L of ATCI (0.05, 0.075, 0.1, 0.15, 0.2, 0.5 mM) was dissolved in 0.1 M phosphate buffer pH 7.4. Kinetic characterization of the hydrolysis of acetylthiocholine catalyzed by AChE was recorded spectrometrically at 
412 nm
. The parallel control experiment was carried out without compound 
5 in
the mixture, allowed adjusting activities to be measured at various times.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. MAO-A and MAO-B assays
</title>
         <p>
MAO inhibition assay was determined using a fluorescence-based method (

). The microplates containing 158 
μ
L of 0.1 M phosphate buffer pH 7.4, 20 
μ
L of 0.5 mM kynuramine solution, and 2 
μ
L of the tested compound solutions were preincubated (20 min; 37 
◦
C). DMSO was used as the negative control, while Clorgyline was used as the positive control. 20 
μ
L of a human recombinant MAO-A (
0.009 mg
/mL) or MAO-B (
0.015 mg
/mL) solution was added to this reaction mixture. The reaction incubated at 37 
◦
C for 30 min, and stopped by adding 75 
μ
L of 2 M NaOH. Enzyme activity were performed on a microplate reader (SpectraMax; excitation at 
315 nm
and emission at 
380 nm
). Data analysis was performed on GraphPad Prism 6.0 software and expressed as mean ± standard deviation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
The work was financially supported by National Natural Sciences Foundation of 
China
(No. 31700303), Natural Sciences Foundation of 
Hunan Province
(No. 2018JJ3839), 
Key Projects of Science
and 
Technology Plan of Changsha
(No. kq 1801072), Science and Technology Innovation Platform and Talent Special Project of 
Hunan Province
(No. 2017TP 2013). The authors gratefully acknowledge the NMR measurements from the Modern Analysis and Testing Centre of CSU.
</p>
         <p>
The 1D (
1
H, 
13
C and DEPT135 NMR), 2D NMR (
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HSQC, HMBC, NOESY) and HRESIMS spectra of compounds 1–7 are available in the supplementary data.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix B. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112514.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Agrawal, P.K.
, 
2004
. 
Dependence of 1 H NMR chemical shifts of geminal protons of glycosyloxy methylene (H2-26) on the orientation of the 27-methyl group of furostane-type steroidal saponins
. 
Magn. Reson. Chem.
42
, 
990–993
. 
https://doi. org/10.1002/mrc.1474
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Banks, J.A.
, 
Nishiyama, T.
, 
Hasebe, M.
, 
2011
. 
The Selaginella genome identifies genetic changes associated with the evolution of vascular plants
. 
Science
332
, 
960–963
. 
https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1203810
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, J.J.
, 
Duh, C.Y.
, 
Chen, J.F.
, 
2005
. 

New cytotoxic biflavonoids from 
Selaginella delicatula

. 
Planta Med.
71
, 
659–665
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2005-871273
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chandran, G.
, 
Muralidhara
, 
2013
a. 

Neuroprotective Effect of aqueous extract of 
Selaginella delicatula
as evidenced by abrogation of rotenone-induced motor deficits, oxidative dysfunctions, and neurotoxicity in mice

. 
Cell. Mol. Neurobiol.
33
, 
929–942
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10571-013-9959-y
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, X.
, 
Xu, P.S.
, 
Zou, Z.X.
, 
Liu, Y.
, 
Zhou, W.H.
, 
Ren, Q.
, 
Li, D.
, 
Li, X.M.
, 
Xu, K.P.
, 
Tan, G.S.
, 
2019
. 

Sinensiols B-G, six novel neolignans from 
Selaginella sinensis

. 
Fitoterapia
134
, 
256–263
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2019.02.034
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cheng, F.
, 
Xu, K.P.
, 
Liu, L.F.
, 
Yao, C.P.
, 
Xu, P.S.
, 
Zhou, G.
, 
Li, D.
, 
Li, X.M.
, 
Chen, K.
, 
Zou, Z.X.
, 
Tan, G.S.
, 
2018
. 

New neolignans from 
Selaginella picta
and their protective effect on HT-22 cells

. 
Fitoterapia
127
, 
69–73
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. fitote.2018.02.008
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chandran, G.
, 
Muralidhara
, 
2012
. 

Propensity of 
Selaginella delicatula
aqueous extract to offset rotenone-induced oxidative dysfunctions and neurotoxicity in 
Drosophila melanogaster
: implications for Parkinson’ s disease

. 
Neurotoxicology
33
, 
444–456
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuro.2012.04.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chandran, G.
, 
Muralidhara
, 
2013
b. 

Enhanced susceptibility of GSH-depleted drosophila larvae to rotenone-induced oxidative dysfunctions: attenuation by 
Selaginella delicatula
(A pteridophyte) flavonoids

. 
J. Neurol. Sci.
333
, 
109–151
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.jns.2013.07.483
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Deng, Y.H.
, 
Wang, N.N.
, 
Zou, Z.X.
, 
Zhang, L.
, 
Xu, K.P.
, 
Chen, A.F.
, 
Cao, D.S.
, 
Tan, G.S.
, 
2017
. 

Multi-target screening and experimental validation of natural products from 
Selaginella
plants against Alzheimer’ s Disease

. 
Front. Pharmacol.
8
, 
539
. 
https://doi. org/10.3389/fphar.2017.0039
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ellman, G.L.
, 
Courtney, D.
, 
Andres, V.J.
, 
Featherstone, R.M.
, 
1961
. 
A new and rapid colorimetric determination of acetylcholinesterase activity
. 
Biochem. Pharmacol.
7
, 
88–95
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0006-2952(61)90145-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gu, W.
, 
Song, J.
, 
Cao, Y.
, 
Sun, Q.
, 
Yao, H.
, 
Wu, Q.
, 
Chao, J.
, 
Zhou, J.
, 
Xue, W.
, 
Duan, J.
, 
2013
. 
Application of the ITS2 region for barcoding medicinal plants of Selaginellaceae in pteridophyta
. 
PloS One
8
, e 
67818
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/ journal.pone.0067818
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gao, L.L.
, 
Yin, S.L.
, 
Li, Z.L.
, 
Sha, Y.
, 
Pei, Y.H.
, 
Shi, G.
, 
Jing, Y.K.
, 
Hua, H.M.
, 
2007
. 

Three novel sterols isolated from 
Selaginella tamariscina
with antiproliferative activity in leukemia cells

. 
Planta Med.
73
, 
1112–1115
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2007- 981562
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Giovanni, S.D.
, 
Borloz, A.
, 
Urbain, A.
, 
Marston, A.
, 
Hostettmann, K.
, 
Carrupt, P.A.
, 
Reist, M.
, 
2008
. 
In vitro screening assays to identify natural or synthetic acetylcholinesterase inhibitors: thin layer chromatography versus microplate methods
. 
Eur. J. Pharmaceut. Sci.
339
, 
109–119
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. ejps.2007.10.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Honbu, T.
, 
Ikeda, T.
, 
Zhu, X.H.
, 
Yoshihara, O.
, 
Okawa, M.
, 
Nafady, A.M.
, 
Nohara, T.
, 
2002
. 

New steroidal glycosides from the fruits of 
Solanum anguivi

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
65
, 
1918–1920
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np020254t
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lin, L.C.
, 
Kuo, Y.C.
, 
Chou, C.J.
, 
2000
. 

Cytotoxic biflavonoids from 
Selaginella delicatula

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
63
, 
627–630
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2005-871273
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Long, H.P.
, 
Zou, H.
, 
Li, F.S.
, 
Li, J.
, 
Luo, P.
, 
Zou, Z.X.
, 
Hu, C.P.
, 
Xu, K.P.
, 
Tan, G.S.
, 
2015
. 

Involvenflavones A-F, six new flavonoids with 3 
′
-aryl substituent from 
Selaginella involven

. 
Fitoterapia
105
, 
254–259
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2015.07.013
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mimaki, Y.
, 
Satou, T.
, 
Kuroda, M.
, 
Sashida, Y.
, 
Hatakeyam, Y.
, 
1999
. 

Steroidal saponins from the bulbs of 
Lilium candidum

. 
Phytochemistry
51
, 
567–573
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/S0031-9422(99)00022-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Passos, C.S.
, 
Simões-Pires, C.A.
, 
Nurisso, A.
, 
Soldi, T.C.
, 
Kato, L.
, 
De Oliveira, C.M.A.
, 
De Faria, E.O.
, 
Marcourt, L.
, 
Gottfried, C.
, 
Carrupt, P.A.
, 
Henriques, A.T.
, 
2013
. 

Indole alkaloids of 
Psychotria
as multifunctional cholinesterases and monoamine oxidases inhibitors

. 
Phytochemistry
86
, 
8–20
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2012.11.015
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Song, L.R.
, 
1999
. 
Chinese Materia Medica
. 
Shanghai Scientific &amp; Technical Publishers
, p. 
44
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tan, Y.P.
, 
Savchenko, A.I.
, 
Broit, N.
, 
Boyle, G.M.
, 
2017
. 

The first plant 5,6-secosteroid from the Australian arid zone species 
Frankenia foliosa

. 
Eur. J. Org Chem.
11
, 
1498–1501
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ejoc.201700035
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, Z.
, 
Xin, T.
, 
Bartels, D.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
Gu, W.
, 
Yao, H.
, 
Liu, S.
, 
Yu, H.
, 
Pu, X.
, 
Zhou, J.
, 
Xu, J.
, 
Xi, C.
, 
Lei, H.
, 
Song, J.
, 
Chen, S.
, 
2018
. 

Genome analysis of the ancient tracheophyte 
Selaginella tamariscina
reveals evolutionary features relevant to the acquisition of desiccation tolerance

. 
Mol. Plant
11
, 
983–994
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. molp.2018.05.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yang, F.
, 
Xu, K.P.
, 
Shen, J.
, 
Li, F.S.
, 
Zhou, M.C.
, 
Tan, G.S.
, 
2011
. 

Anthraquinones and biflavonoids from 
Selaginella delicatula

. 
Chem. Nat. Compd.
47
, 
627–629
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1007/s10600-011-0013-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yao, C.P.
, 
Zou, Z.X.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Li, J.
, 
Cheng, F.
, 
Xu, P.S.
, 
Zhou, G.
, 
Li, X.M.
, 
Xu, K.P.
, 
Tan, G.S.
, 
2019
. 

New adenine analogues and a pyrrole alkaloid from 
Selaginella delicatula

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
33
, 
1985–1991
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 14786419.2018.1482892
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yang, S.F.
, 
Chu, S.C.
, 
Liu, S.J.
, 
Chen, Y.C.
, 
Chang, Y.Z.
, 
Hsieh, Y.S.
, 
2007
. 

Antimetastatic activities of 
Selaginella tamariscina
(Beauv.) on lung cancer cells in vitro and in vivo

. 
J. Ethnopharmacol.
110
, 
483–489
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2006.10.010
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zheng, X.
, 
Du, J.
, 
Xu, Y.
, 
Zhu, B.
, 
Liao, D.
, 
2007
. 

A new steroid from 
Selaginella pulvinata

. 
Fitoterapia
78
, 
598–599
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2007.04.008
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zou, Z.X.
, 
Tan, G.S.
, 
Zhang, G.G.
, 
Yu, X.
, 
Xu, P.S.
, 
Xu, K.P.
, 
2017
a. 

New cytotoxic apigenin derivatives from 
Selaginella doederleinii

. 
Chin. Chem. Lett.
28
, 
931–934
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cclet.2017.01.011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zou, Z.X.
, 
Xu, P.S.
, 
Zhang, G.G.
, 
Cheng, F.
, 
Chen, K.
, 
Li, J.
, 
Zhu, W.X.
, 
Cao, D.S.
, 
Xu, K.P.
, 
Tan, G.S.
, 
2017
b. 

Selagintriflavonoids with BACE1 inhibitory activity from the fern 
Selaginella doederleinii

. 
Phytochemistry
134
, 
114–121
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2016.11.011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zou, H.
, 
Xu, P.S.
, 
Liu, R.
, 
Zou, Z.X.
, 
Li, J.
, 
Zhong, A.G.
, 
Hu, J.Z.
, 
Xu, K.P.
, 
Tan, G.S.
, 
2016
. 

Selacyclicbiflavone A, an unusual macrocyclic biflavone from 
Selaginella uncinata
(Desv.) Spring

. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
57
, 
892–894
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. tetlet.2016.01.038
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
