<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112969</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Phaeosphspirone (1/1 ), a pair of unique polyketide enantiomers with an unusual 6/5/5/6 tetracyclic ring from the desert plant endophytic fungus Phaeosphaeriaceae sp.</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bassia dasyphylla
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form another</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium fujikuroi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form intermediate</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phaeosphaeriaceae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Stagonospora pseudovitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Database (CDD)</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Phaeosphspirone (1/1 
′
), a pair of unique polyketide enantiomers with an unusual 6/5/5/6 tetracyclic ring from the desert plant endophytic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
sp.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Zhen-Lu Xu
a, b, c
, Dao-Jiang Yan
d
, Xiang-Mei Tan
a
, Shu-Bin Niu
e
, Meng Yu
a
, Bing-Da Sun
f
,
Cai-Feng Ding 
g
, Yong-Gang Zhang

b, c, 
**
, Gang Ding

a, 
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a

Key Laboratory of Bioactive Substances and Resources Utilization of Chinese Herbal Medicines, Ministry of Education, Institute of Medicinal Plant Development, Peking Union Medical College and Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Beijing, 100193, People’ s 
Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b

Biology Institute, Qilu University of Technology (Shandong Academy of Sciences), Shandong, Jinan, 250103, People’ s 
Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c

College of Life Sciences, Shandong Normal University, Shandong, Jinan, 250014, People’ s 
Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
d

State Key Laboratory of Bioactive Substance and Function of Natural Medicines, Institute of Materia Medica, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, 100050, People’ s 
Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
e

School of Biological Medicine, Beijing City University, Beijing, 450046, People’ s 
Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
f

Institute of Microbiology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, 100101, People’ s 
Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
g

State Key Laboratory of Phytochemistry and Plant Resources in West 
China
, Kunming Institute of Botany, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, 650201, People’ s 
Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>Phaeosphspirone</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Absolute configurations</p>
         <p>Biosynthetic pathway</p>
         <p>Cytotoxicity</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
Phaeosphspirone, an undescribed polyketide with a unique 6/5/5/6-fused tetracyclic system, and two known analogues, herbarin and 
O
-methylherbarin, were purified from the endophytic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
sp. isolated from the desert plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bassia dasyphylla
</tp:taxon-name>
. The connectivity and relative configuration of phaeosphspirone was elucidated by comprehensive HR-ESI-MS and NMR analysis together with a computer-assisted structure elucidation (CASE) method. A pair of enantiomers existing in phaeosphspirone were separated by HPLC chromatography after reacting with chiral reagents, from which the absolute configuration of phaeosphspirone was simultaneously determined based on Mosher’ s rule. This tandem strategy provides a useful approach for the separation and stereochemical determination of enantiomers possessing secondary hydroxyl groups. The structural feature of phaeosphspirone, herbarin and 
O
-methylherbarin together with gene cluster analysis suggested their polyketide biosynthetic origin. Herbarin and 
O
-methylherbarin exhibited moderate cytotoxicity against three cancer cell lines.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Secondary metabolites are usually biosynthesized as single stereoisomers in nature, but some natural products exist as enantiomers (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

, 

). As stereocentres in structures often determine biological and pharmaceutical properties together with chemical and physical characteristics, it is very important to chirally separate enantiomers and establish their absolute configurations. Enantiomers can usually be separated by chiral columns, but suitable or new approaches can be used or developed to separate enantiomers with limited amounts. Recently, our group initiated the chemical investigation of desert plant endophytic fungi from Northwest 
China
considering their special bioenvironments and few chemical investigations. A series of new secondary metabolites with diverse biological activities were isolated from this group of fungi (

, 

; 

; 

, 

; 

). Per our ongoing research to mine secondary metabolites with unique structures and potential bioactivities from this special group of fungi, the EtOAc extracts of the endophytic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
sp. were investigated, which led to the isolation of a novel polyketide-originated secondary metabolite, phaeosphspirone (
1
), and two known pyranonaphthoquinones, herbarin (
2
) and 
O
-methylherbarin (
3
) (
Fig. 1
) (

). A pair of enantiomers (
1
/ 
1
′
) existing in phaeosphspirone were separated by HPLC chromatography after derivatization with Mosher’ s reagents, and the absolute configurations of 
1
/ 
1
′
were simultaneously determined according to Mosher’ s rule. This tandem strategy provides a useful approach for the separation and stereochemical determination of enantiomers with secondary hydroxyl groups. In this report, the structural elucidation, separation, possible biogenetic pathway, and biological activities of these compounds are presented.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
The molecular formula of phaeosphspirone was determined to be C H O via HRESIMS (m/z 373.0898, [M+Na] 
+
, calcd. 373.0899, Δ 
17
18
8
0.1 mmu), with nine degrees of unsaturation. The 
1
H, 
13
C and HSQC NMR data of phaeosphspirone (
Table 1
and 
Figs. S1-S
4
, S7-S9) revealed the presence of 17 carbons, including four methyls (three methyl ethers), one oxymethylene, one oxymethine, three tetra-substituted carbons, one 1, 2, 4, 6-substituted phenyl ring, and two carbonyl carbons (
δ
=199.2, 192.7), which accounted for all the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR 
C
resonances except for a hydroxyl group (d, 
δ
H
= 6.88, 
J
= 4.8 Hz in DMSO‑ 
d
6
). This demonstrated that 
1
possessed three additional rings aside from the phenyl ring. The 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations revealed that the hydroxyl group was connected to H-3 (
Fig. 2
and 
Fig. S5
), and the remaining phaeosphspirone connectivity was completely elucidated from the HMBC spectrum (
Fig. 2
and Fig. S6, 
S10
). The HMBC correlations from H-7 to C-5, C-6, C-8, C-9 and C-11 and H-9 to C-7, C-8, C-10 and C-11 together with those of the two methoxyls (
δ
H
=3.86, 3.87) to C-8 and C-10 established a 1, 2, 4, 6-substituted phenyl ring with a ketogroup (C-5, 
δ
C
=192.5) connected to C-6, and two methoxyls connected with C-8 and C-10, respectively. The HMBC correlations from 1-Me to C-2 and C-3; 3-OH to C-2, C-3 and C-4; H-3 to C-4 and C-13; and 14- 
CH
2
- to C-2, C-4 and C-13 confirmed the existence of a dihydro- 
2H
-pyran-3(
4H
)- one ring with a methyl and a hydroxyl group connected with C-2 and C-3, respectively. The correlation of H-3 with C- 
5 in
the HMBC spectrum demonstrated that C-5 was connected to C-4. The quaternary carbon C-12 possessed methyl ethers based on the correlation from –OMe (
δ
H
= 3.25) to C-12. The key long-range HMBC correlation of H-9 to C-12 confirmed that C-11 was connected to C-12. According to the molecular formula, only an oxygen atom remained. Analysis of the chemical shift values of C-2 (
δ
C
=108.4) and C-12 (
δ
C
=109.6) demonstrated that C-2 was connected to C-12 by an ether bond to 
<tp:taxon-name>form another</tp:taxon-name>
furan ring. Although there were no HMBC correlations from H-3 to C-12 (this might be because the dihedral degree between H-3 with C-12 is close to 90 
◦
C, leading to no HMBC correlations observed), considering the degrees of unsaturation, C-4 was suggested to be connected with C-12, which created a hexahydro-2,5a-methanocyclopenta[
d
][1,3]dioxepine skeleton (6/5/6/5 tetracyclic system).
</p>
         <p>
1
H-NMR was recorded at 600 MHz; 
13
C-NMR was recorded at 150 MHz.

</p>
         <p>
To support this conclusion, computer-assisted structure elucidation (CASE) was used to analyse the NMR data of phaeosphspirone. CASE, as a technological development, was developed in recent years to overcome obstacles in NMR data interpretation (

, 

; 

; 

; 

). ACD/Structure Elucidator was used to resolve the uncertain connection of C-4 with C-12, which gave 519 candidates filtered from 126,650 isomers in 2 min 2 s from the MCD (molecular connectivity diagram). The top ten candidates were generated by ACD/Structure Elucidator. Structure ranking is based on the overall differences between experimental and predicted 
13
C chemical shifts (
Fig. 3
). The lower the value (
dN
(
13
C)-neural network and 
dA
(
13
C)-HOSE), the better the ranking. Atom colour coding is based on the individual atom difference between experimental and predicted 
13
C chemical shifts. The green colour represents a difference between 0 and 3 ppm, and the yellow colour is
&gt;
3–15 ppm. Structures ranking 1–4 display “the same flat structures” as that of phaeosphspirone but with different atom/NMR shift assignments. Thus, according to the calculated CASE results together with NMR data analysis, the planar structure of phaeosphspirone was established.
</p>
         <p>
The relative configuration of phaeosphspirone was determined by NOE spectra analysis (
Fig. 2
). Upon irradiation with H-3, enhancements of 12-OMe and 1-Me were observed, while irradiation with 12-OMe or 1- Me led to the enhancement of 1-Me and H-3 or H-3 and 12-OMe, respectively. These results confirmed that 1-Me, H-3 and 12-OMe had the same orientation on the furan ring, which established the relative configuration of phaeosphspirone (Fig. S11-S13).
</p>
         <p>
The optical rotation of phaeosphspirone was near zero, implying that a pair of enantiomers (
1
/ 
1
′
) might exist for this compound. It was difficult to obtain enough enantiomers by chiral column separation due to the limited amounts of enantiomers (
1
/ 
1
′
). Considering a secondary hydroxyl group in the structure of phaeosphspirone, if chiral reagents (such as Mosher’ s reagents) are mixed with phaeosphspirone (
1
/ 
1
′
), theoretically, two diastereomers would be generated, which could then be separated using an HPLC column (C 
18
). This approach could also determine the stereochemistry of C-3 based on Mosher’ s rule. Reactions of phaeosphspirone (
1
/ 
1
′
) with (
R
)-MTPA-Cl will 
<tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
corresponding 
S
-MTPA ester (
1a
and 
1
′
a
), and reactions of phaeosphspirone (
1
/ 
1
′
) with (
S
)-MTPA-Cl will 
<tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
corresponding 
R
-MTPA ester (
1b
and 
1
′
b
) (

). As expected, two peaks were observed in the corresponding HPLC profiles (Supporting 
Information
). This demonstrated that a pair of enantiomers existed in phaeosphspirone. According to Mosher’ s rule, the difference in chemical shifts (Δ 

δSR

= 

δS
- 
δR

) for 
1a
and 
1b
assigned the C- 
3 in
1
/ 
1
′
to be 
S
/ 
R
(
Fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
Considering the coisolation of herbarin (
2
) and 
O
-methylherbarin (
3
) from the same fungus and the similar structural features, phaeosphspirone (
1
/ 
1
′
) is likely to be derived from 
2
with a pyranonaphthoquinone core skeleton. Isotopic enrichment experiments revealed that pyranonaphthoquinone scorpinone coisolated with 
2
from the same fungus originating from polyketide biosynthesis (

), and Tudzynski et al. investigated the biosynthetic polyketide (PKS) gene cluster of fusarubin, a pyranonaphthoquinone analogue similar to scorpinone (

). This evidence supported that phaeosphspirone, as a heptaketide, was biosynthesized from a PKS pathway similar to the metabolites mentioned above. Polyketides (PKSs) can be further divided into the following three subtypes: nonreduced (NR), partially reduced (PR), and highly reduced (HR), which are biosynthesized from the corresponding mega-synthase NR-PKS synthases (NR-PKSs), PR-PKSs and HR-PKSs, respectively (Fig. S18) (

).
</p>
         <p>
The structural features of herbarin (
2
), 
O
-methylherbarin (
3
) and phaeosphspirone imply that compounds 
1–3
originate from nonreducing polyketide synthases (NR-PKSs) (

). The genome of this fungus was then sequenced and shown to possess eight reducing polyketide synthase (HR-PKSs and PR-PKSs) and four nonreducing polyketide synthase (NR-PKS) gene clusters. Bioinformatics and phylogenetic analysis revealed that an NR-PKS gene cluster in scaffold3 (
sgp
cluster) of 
<tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
sp. is hypothesized to be the polyketide product (phaeosphspirone) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fusarium fujikuroi
</tp:taxon-name>
fsr1 (gene cluster of fusarubin) (
Fig. 5
and Fig. S18-S20). The multimodular polyketide synthases fsr1 and sgpC have the same domains, including SAT, KS, AT, PT, ACP and R. Further analysis of the conserved active sites of fsr1 and sgpC shows that these domains are all active (Fig. S21). The predicted proteins in the 
sgp
cluster include SgpC (NR-PKSs), SgpB and SgpF (
O
-methyltransferases); SgpE (cytochrome P450 monooxygenase); and two Baeyer Villiger monooxygenase (DUF4243) family oxidases (SgpA and SgpG), which are the key enzymes that catalyse the skeleton formation of phaeosphspirone (Fig. S22 and S23). Thus, the biosynthetic pathway of phaeosphspirone is proposed as depicted in Scheme 1. First, SgpC (PKSs), SgpB/F and SgpA/G biosynthesize herbarin (
2
) similar to the 
fsr
gene cluster forming fusarubin (

). Then, Baeyer-Villiger oxidation (SgpA or SgpG) leads herbarin (
2
) to produce compound (
4
), after which addition and dehydration (which might be spontaneous) 
<tp:taxon-name>form intermediate</tp:taxon-name>
(
5
). Further oxidation (SgpE) of (
5
) at C-3 generates compound (
6
), and phaeosphspirone is finally formed by methylation (SgpB/F) of compound (
6
). The biosynthesis of phaeosphspirone is currently under investigation.
</p>
         <p>
Herbarin (
2
) was reported to display biological activity against PC-3 M cell lines (

), whereas no report about bioactivities of 
O
-methylherbarin (
3
) was found. The cytotoxic effects of compounds 
1–3
were evaluated in three cancer cell lines, HepG2, HCT116, and B16 (

). Compounds 
2
and 
3
exhibited cytotoxic activity with IC 
50
= 4.62 ± 0.55/3.64 ± 1.21, 2.56 ± 0.67/1.22 ± 0.18, and 2.25 ± 0.06/1.97 ± 0.32 
μ
M, respectively, compared with the positive control 
cis
-platin (IC 
50
=21.73 ±1.10, 9.71 ± 0.11, and 16.79 ± 2.85 
μ
M). Unfortunately, phaeosphspirone (
1
/ 
1
′
) did not display cytotoxic effects.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
Phaeosphspirone (
1
/ 
1
′) features a unique 6/5/5/6-fused polyketide core skeleton that is not encountered in nature. Four stereocentres, including two ketal carbons (C-2 and C-12) connected by an ether linkage and eight oxygen atoms from different functionalities, including carbonyl, ether bond, –OH, -OMe and ketal groups, are present in its structure, which enhances the structural complexity of 
1
/ 
1
’ (
Fig. 1
). Structurally, 
1
/ 
1
′ is most likely derived from pyranonaphthoquinone herbarin (
2
) via further oxidation, condensation and methylation. Hence, 
1
/ 
1
′ represents a new 
type
of pyranonaphthoquinone-derived polyketide. The unique structure of 
1
/ 
1
′ further supports that endophytic fungi inhabiting desert plants are an important resource for the discovery of novel secondary metabolites. Enantiomers are mainly separated by chiral columns, and then their absolute configurations are determined. In this report, the separation and absolute determination of the enantiomer phaeosphspirone (
1
/ 
1
′) were solved through a tandem strategy, which provides a useful method for enantiomer separation and stereochemical determination. Our results further support that endophytic fungi with few chemical investigation from desert plants are a potent biological resources of new/novel secondary metabolites with a wide range of bioactivities.
</p>
         <p>
4. Experimental
</p>
         <p>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</p>
         <p>
Optical rotations were taken on a PerkinElmer 241 polarimeter, and UV data were recorded on a Thermo Genesys-10S UV–Vis spectrometer. The IR spectra were measured using a Nicolet IS5FT-IR spectrophotometer. 1D and 2D NMR spectra were measured on a Bruker 600 spectrometer (
1
H: 600 MHz, 
13
C: 150 MHz). HRESIMS was obtained using a TOF-ESI-MS (Waters Synapt G2, 
USA
). Semipreparative HPLC separation was performed on a Shimadzu LC-6AD instrument packed with a YMC-Pack ODS-A column (5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
). Sephadex LH-20 was purchased from Pharmacia Biotech, 
Sweden
. TLC was performed on silica gel GF254 (10–40 
μ
m; Qingdao Marine Chemical, Inc.). Silica gel (60–100 or 200–300 mesh) for column chromatography was produced by Qingdao Marine Chemical Factory, Qingdao, 
China
.
</p>
         <p>
4.2. Strain and fermentation
</p>
         <p>
The
endophytic fungus 
Phaeosphaeriaceae
sp

. (TR-4-12) was provided and identified by 

Dr Bing-da Sun

from the plant 

Bassia
dasyphylla

(Fisch. et Mey.) 
O. Kuntze
(Chenopodiaceae) growing in the 
Tengger Desert
, 
Ningxia Province
, 
China
(Latitude: 37 
◦
75 
′
46 
′′
N, Longitude: 

104 
◦
57 
′
43 
′′
E

and Elevation above sea level: 

1050
m


), which was deposited at the 
Institute of Microbiology
, 
Chinese Academy of Science
Scheme 1.
Potential gene cluster and biogenetic pathway of phaeosphspirone.
</p>
         <p>
(VOUCHER NUMBER: CGMCC3.17,737) and the 
Institute of Medicinal Plant Development
, 
Peking
Union Medical College
and 
Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences
(Number: TR-4-12). 
This
fungus was identified based on the sequences of the ITS/ 
5.8S
regions of its ribosomal DNA, which was also referred to different references (Phookamsak et al., 2014; 

; 

; 

). The sequence data derived from the fungal strain have been submitted and deposited at GenBank with accession number 
KT347320
. BLAST search results showed that the sequence was similar (94%) to the sequence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stagonospora pseudovitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(CBS135094) in GenBank with the accession number 
KF251261
. The fungus was grown on PDA plates at 25 
◦
C for 7 days. Then, the fresh mycelium was inoculated into autoclaving sterilized solid medium containing rice (60.0 g) and distilled water (80 mL) in Fernbach flasks (500 mL) for further fermentation at 25 
◦
C for 40 days with 45 bottles of Fernbach flasks (500 mL).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The fermented rice substrate was extracted with EtOAc (2.5 L 4 times), and the organic solvent was evaporated to dryness under vacuum to afford 
37.1 g
of extract. The crude extract (
37.1 g
) was subjected to isolation by silica gel column chromatography (CC) (10 × 
11.5 cm
, 200–300 mesh, 
400 g
) using a petroleum ether-acetone gradient elution (50:1–0:1, each 1 L) to afford nine corresponding fractions (A–I). Fr. D (
1.3 g
) was subjected to Sephadex LH-20 and eluted with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (1:1, v/v) to give five fractions (D1-D5). Fraction D3 (
0.8 g
) was fractionated by silica gel CC (32 × 
2.4 cm
, 200–300 mesh, 
45 g
) using a petroleum ether-acetone gradient elution (100:1–0:1, each 60 mL) to give seven fractions (D3a–D 
3 g
). Fr. D3e (
20.6 mg
) was applied to HPLC (MeOH: H 
2
O =53%: 46%, 2 mL/min, 
210 nm
) to afford 
1
(
t
R
19.5 min, 
2.2 mg
).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.1. Phaeosphspirone (1)
</p>
         <p>
Colourless powder (MeOH); [α] 26D +4 (
c
= 0.14, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 220 (3.99), 270 (3.32), 328 (2.93) nm; IR (Neat) 
ν
max
: 2923, 1750, 1606, 
1315, 955 cm
1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
: 373.0898 [M+Na] 
+
(calcd. 373.0899 for C 
17
H 
18
O 
8
). 
1
HNMR (600 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) and 
13
C NMR (150 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) see 

Table S1. 
1

HNMR (600 MHz, MeOD- 
d
4
) and 
13
C NMR (150 MHz, MeOD- 
d
4
) see Table S2.
</p>
         <p>
4.4. Preparation of (R)- and (S)-MTPA esters of compound 1
</p>
         <p>
(
R
)-MTPACl (8 μL) was added to a solution of compound 
1
(
0.5 mg
) in pyridin- 
d
5
(200 μL) and placed at room temperature for 24 h. The crude product was purified by HPLC (acetonitrile: H 
2
O = 69%: 31%, 2 mL/min, 
210 nm
) to afford (
S
)-MTPA ester (
1a
) (≈ 
0.4 mg
, 
t
R
= 28.42 min) and (
S
)-MTPA ester (
1
′ 
a
) (≈ 
0.4 mg
, 
t
R
= 31.30 min). (
S
)-MTPACl (8 μL) was added to a solution of compound 
1
(
0.5 mg
) in pyridin- 
d
5
(200 μL) and placed at room temperature for 24 h. The crude product was purified by HPLC (acetonitrile: H 
2
O = 69%: 31%, 2 mL/min, 
210 nm
) to afford (
R
)-MTPA ester (
1
′ 
b
) (≈ 
0.4 mg
, 
t
R
= 28.51 min) and (
R
)- MTPA ester (
1b
) (
0.4 mg
, 
t
R
= 31.41 min). 
1
H NMR data from phaeosphspirone (
1
) and the (
S
)- and (
R
)-MTPA ester derivatives of phaeosphspirone (
1/1
′) are shown in Table S3.
</p>
         <p>
4.5. Genome sequencing and bioinformatic analysis
</p>
         <p>
Genomic DNA of the endophytic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>Phaeosphaeriaceae</tp:taxon-name>
sp. was prepared according to the CTAB method. Shotgun genome sequencing was performed at Hangzhou 1 Gene Company using the Illumina HiSeq 4000 sequencing platform. The contigs were assembled by Discover and then formatted to the BLAST protein database for local BLAST search. The PKS gene clusters were predicted by antiSMASH and NCBI local BLAST 2.11.0. The coding region of the gene cluster protein was predicted by 2nd Find (http://biosyn.nih.go.jp/2ndfind) and manually checked with the online NCBI BLAST (http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/). The PKS domains were analysed by the Protein Conserved Domain 
<tp:taxon-name>Database (CDD)</tp:taxon-name>
at the NCBI server and the PKS/NRPS Analysis website. NR-PKSs and their responsible polyketides were collected from the literature. The amino acid sequences of NR-PKSs were obtained from NCBI GenBank and aligned by ClustalW for phylogenetic analysis. A phylogenetic tree was constructed by the neighbour-joining method using MEGA 6.0 and is illustrated in Figure S16.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.6. Bioassay procedures (

)

</title>
         <p>
The cytotoxic activities of the isolated compounds were evaluated against the HepG2, HCT116, and B16 cell lines by the MTT colorimetric method with 
cis
-platin as a positive control.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
We acknowledge financial support from key project at central government level: The ability establishment of sustainable use for valuable Chinese medicine resources (2060302-2101-18), and the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(31570340 and 31670011).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112969.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, M.H.
, 
Lin, S.
, 
Li, L.
, 
Zhu, C.G.
, 
Wang, X.L.
, 
Wang, Y.N.
, 
Jiang, B.Y.
, 
Wang, S.J.
, 
Li, Y.H.
, 
Jiang, J.D.
, 
Shi, J.G.
, 
2012
. 

Enantiomers of an indole alkaloid containing unusual dihydrothiopyran and 1,2,4-thiadiazole rings from the root of 
Isatis indigotica

. 
Org. Lett.
14
, 
5668–5671
. 

https://doi.org/10.1021/ol 
302660t

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cox, R.J.
, 
2017
. 
Polyketides, proteins and genes in fungi: programmed nano-machines begin to reveal their secrets
. 
Org. Biomol. Chem.
5
, 
2010–2026
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1039/b704420h
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, L.
, 
Niu, S.B.
, 
Li, L.
, 
Ding, G.
, 
Yu, M.
, 
Zhang, G.S.
, 
Wang, M.H.
, 
Li, L.Y.
, 
Zhang, T.
, 
Jia, H.M.
, 
Zhang, H.W.
, 
Shang, H.
, 
Liu, X.Z.
, 
Zong, Z.M.
, 
2017
. 

Trichoderpyrone, a unique polyketide hybrid with a cyclopentenone-pyrone skeleton from the plant endophytic fungus 
Trichoderma gamsii

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
80
, 
1944–1947
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.jnatprod.7b00190
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ding, C.F.
, 
Yu, H.F.
, 
Shi, X.L.
, 
Ge, S.H.
, 
Njateng, G.S.S.
, 
Qin, X.J.
, 
Dai, Z.
, 
Zhang, R.P.
, 
Zhang, H.B.
, 
Luo, X.D.
, 
2021
. 

Rapid and unambiguous assignment of protondeficient 
N
-acyl amidine indole alkaloid by a combination of calculation methods

. 
Tetrahedron. Letters. Online
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tetlet.2021.152949
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elyashberg, M.
, 
Williams, A.J.
, 
Blinov, K.
, 
2010
. 
Structural revisions of natural products by computer assisted structure elucidation (CASE) systems
. 
Nat. Prod. Rep.
27
, 
1296–1328
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/c002332a
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elyashberg, M.
, 
Blinov, K.
, 
Molodtsov, S.
, 
Williams, A.J.
, 
2013
. 
Structure revision of asperjinone using computer-assisted structure elucidation methods
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
76
, 
113–116
. 

https://doi.org/10.1021/np 
300218g

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Finefield, J.M.
, 
Sherman, D.H.
, 
Kreitman, M.
, 
Williams, R.M.
, 
2012
. 
Enantiomeric natural products: occurrence and biogenesis
. 
Angew. Chem.
51
, 
4802–4837
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1002/anie.201107204
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Helaly, S.E.
, 
Ashrafi, S.
, 
Teponno, R.B.
, 
Bernecker, S.
, 
Dababat, A.A.
, 
Maier, W.
, 
Stadler, M.
, 
2018
. 

Nematicidal cyclic lipodepsipeptides and a Xanthocillin derivative from a phaeosphariaceous fungus parasitizing eggs of the plant parasitic nematode 
Heterodera filipjevi

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
81
, 
2228–2234
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. jnatprod.8b00486
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kittakoop, K.
, 
2019
. 
Part 1: occurrence of racemic natural products and their biological activities. J
. 
Chulabhorn Roya Acad.
1
, 
53–66
. 
https://he02.tci-thaijo.org/index.ph p/jcra/article/view/225218
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kittakoop, K.
, 
2020
. 
Part 2: occurrence of racemic natural products and their biological activities. J
. 
Chulabhorn Royal Acad
. 2, 27-3. 
https://he02.tci-thaijo.org/index.php/ jcra/article/view/240787
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, L.Y.
, 
Sun, B.D.
, 
Zhang, G.S.
, 
Deng, H.
, 
Wang, M.H.
, 
Tan, X.M.
, 
Zhang, X.Y.
, 
Jia, H.M.
, 
Zhang, T.
, 
Zou, Z.M.
, 
Ding, G.
, 
2018
. 

Polyketides with different post-modifications from desert endophytic fungus 
Paraphoma
sp

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
32
, 
939–943
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1080/14786419.2017.1371166
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moser, A.
, 
Elyashberg, M.E.
, 
Williams, A.J.
, 
Blinov, K.A.
, 
DiMartino, J.C.
, 
2012
. 
Blind trials of computer-assisted structure elucidation software
. 
J. Cheminf.
4
, 
5
. htt p://www.jcheminf.com/content/4/1/5.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Naman, C.B.
, 
Li, J.
, 
Moser, A.
, 
Hendrycks, J.M.
, 
Benatrehina, P.A.
, 
Chai, H.
, 
Yuan, C.H.
, 
Keller, W.J.
, 
Kinghorn, D.A.
, 
2015
. 

Computer-assisted structure elucidation of black chokeberry (
Aronia melanocarpa
) fruit juice isolates with a new fused pentacyclic flavonoid skeleton

. 
Org. Lett.
17
, 
2988–2991
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1021/acsorglett.5b01284
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ohtani, I.
, 
Kusumi, T.
, 
Kashman, Y.
, 
Kakisawa, H.
, 
1991
. 
High-field FT NMR application of Mosher’ s method
. 
The absolute configurations of marine terpenoids. J. Am. Chem. Soc.
56
, 
4092–4096
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ja00011a006
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Paranagama, P.A.
, 
Wijeratne, E.M.K.
, 
Burns, A.M.
, 
Marron, M.T.
, 
Gunatilaka, M.K.
, 
Arnold, A.E.
, 
Gunatilaka, A.A.L.
, 
2007
. 

Heptaketides from corynespora sp. inhabiting the cavern beard lichen, 
Usnea cavernosa
: first report of metabolites of an (1) endolichenic fungus

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
70
, 
1700–1705
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ np070466w
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Phookamasak, R.
, 
Liu, J.
, 
Mckenzie, E.H.C.
, 
Manamgoda, D.S.
, 
Ariyawansa, H.
, 
Thambugala, K.M.
, 
Dai, D.
, 
Camporesi, E.
, 
Chukeatirote, E.
, 
Wijayawardene, N.N.
, 
Bahakali, A.H.
, 
Mortimer, P.E.
, 
Xu, J.
, 
Hyde, K.D.
, 
2014
. 
Revision of Phaeosphaeriaceae
. 
Fungal Divers.
68
, 
159–238
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s13225- 014-0308-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sai, C.M.
, 
Li, D.H.
, 
Xue, C.M.
, 
Wang, K.B.
, 
Hu, P.
, 
Pei, Y.H.
, 
Bai, J.
, 
Jing, Y.K.
, 
Li, Z.L.
, 
Hua, H.M.
, 
2015
. 

Two pairs of enantiomeric alkaloid dimers from 
Macleaya cordata

. 
Org. Lett.
17
, 
4102–4105
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.orglett.5b02044
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Song, B.
, 
Li, L.Y.
, 
Shang, H.
, 
Liu, Y.
, 
Yu, M.
, 
Ding, G.
, 
Zou, Z.M.
, 
2019
. 

Trematosphones A and B, two unique dimeric structures from the desert plant endophytic fungus 
Trematosphaeria terricola

. 
Org. Lett.
21
, 
2139–2142
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1021/acsorglett.9b00454
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Studt, L.
, 
Wiemann, P.
, 
Kleigrewe, K.
, 
Humpf, H.U.
, 
Tudzynski, B.
, 
2012
. 

Biosynthesis of fusarubins accounts for pigmentation of 
Fusarium fujikuroi
perithecia

. 
Appl. Environ. Microbiol.
78
, 
4468–4480
. 
https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.00823-12
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tian, D.S.
, 
Yi, P.
, 
Xia, L.
, 
Xiao, X.
, 
Fan, Y.M.
, 
Gu, W.
, 
Huang, L.J.
, 
Ben-David, Y.
, 
Di, Y.T.
, 
Yuan, C.M.
, 
Hao, X.J.
, 
2016
. 

Garmultins A-G, biogenetically related polycyclic acylphloroglucinols from 
Garcinia multiflora

. 
Org. Lett.
18
, 
5904–5907
. 
https://doi. org/10.1021/acs.orglett.6b03004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tan, X.M.
, 
Zhang, X.Y.
, 
Yu, M.
, 
Yu, Y.T.
, 
Guo, Z.
, 
Gong, T.
, 
Niu, S.B.
, 
Qin, J.C.
, 
Zou, Z.M.
, 
Ding, G.
, 
2019
. 
Sesquiterpenoids and mycotoxin swainsonine from the locoweed endophytic fungus Alternaria oxytropis
. 
Phytochemistry
164
, 
154–161
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.05.012
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tan, X.M.
, 
Li, L.Y.
, 
Sun, L.Y.
, 
Sun, B.D.
, 
Niu, S.B.
, 
Wang, M.H.
, 
Zhang, X.Y.
, 
Sun, W.S.
, 
Zhang, G.S.
, 
Deng, H.
, 
Xing, X.K.
, 
Zou, Z.M.
, 
Ding, G.
, 
2018
. 

Spiciferone analogs from an endophytic fungus 
Phoma betae
collected from desert plants in West 
China

. 
J. Antibiot.
71
, 
613–617
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41429-018-0037-z
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Van Wagoner, R.M.
, 
Mantle, P.G.
, 
Wright, J.L.C.
, 
2008
. 
Biosynthesis of scorpinone, a 2- azaanthraquinone from amorosia littoralis, a fungus from marine Sediment ⊥
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
71
, 
426–430
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np070614i
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, X.Y.
, 
Liu, Z.L.
, 
Sun, B.D.
, 
Niu, S.N.
, 
Wang, M.H.
, 
Tan, X.M.
, 
Zou, Z.M.
, 
Ding, G.
, 
2018
. 
Bioactive resorcylic acid lactones with different ring systems from desert plant endophytic fungus Chaetosphaeronema hispidulur
. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
66
, 
8976–8982
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.8b02648
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
