<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2015.01.008</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Cell wall integrity, genotoxic injury and PCD dynamics in alfalfa saponin-treated white poplar cells highlight a complex link between molecule structure and activity</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>03</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Medicago</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>sativa</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Populus alba
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Medicago</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>sativa</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Populus alba
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Medicago</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>sativa</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Medicago</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoderma viride
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Populus alba
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Nauclea
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ginseng
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>M. sativa saponins</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>M. sativa saponins</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
alba
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
alba
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
alba
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
saponins
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>alba</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
saponins
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sapindus mukorossi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Musa sapientum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
saponins
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>alba</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>M. sativa saponins</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form after</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>M. sativa saponins</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
alba
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Cell wall integrity, genotoxic injury and PCD dynamics in alfalfa saponin-treated white poplar cells highlight a complex link between molecule structure and activity
</p>
         <p>
Stefania Paparella
a
, Aldo Tava
b
, Pinarosa Avato
c
, Elisa Biazzi
b
, Anca Macovei
a,1
, Marco Biggiogera
a
, Daniela Carbonera
a
, Alma Balestrazzi

a, 
*
</p>
         <p>
a

Dipartimento di Biologia e Biotecnologie ‘ 
L
. Spallanzani’, via Ferrata 1, 27100 Pavia, 
Italy
</p>
         <p>
b

Consiglio per la Ricerca e la Sperimentazione in Agricoltura – Centro di Ricerca per le Produzioni Foraggere e Lattiero-Casearie, viale Piacenza 29, 29600 Lodi, 
Italy
</p>
         <p>
c

Dipartimento di Farmacia-Scienze del Farmaco, Università degli Studi di Bari Aldo Moro, via Orabona 4, 70125 Bari, 
Italy
</p>
         <p>
ARTICLE
INFO

</p>
         <p>
Article history:
</p>
         <p>
Received 
27 October 2014
</p>
         <p>
Received in revised form 
10 January 2015
Available online 

3 February 2015
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>Saponins</p>
         <p>Cell wall</p>
         <p>DNA damage response</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Medicago</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>sativa</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Populus alba
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Programmed cell death</p>
         <p>
ABSTRACT
</p>
         <p>
In the present work, eleven saponins and three sapogenins purified from 

<tp:taxon-name>Medicago</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>sativa</tp:taxon-name>

were tested for their cytotoxicity against highly proliferating white poplar (
<tp:taxon-name>
Populus alba
</tp:taxon-name>
L
.) cell suspension cultures. After preliminary screening, four saponins with different structural features in terms of aglycone moieties and sugar chains (saponin 
3
, a bidesmoside of hederagenin; saponins 
4
and 
5
, monodesmoside and bidesmoside of medicagenic acid respectively, and saponin 
10
, a bidesmoside of zanhic acid) and different cytotoxicity were selected and used for further investigation on their structure–activity relationship. Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM) analyses provided for the first time evidence of the effects exerted by saponins on plant cell wall integrity. Exposure to saponin 
3
and saponin 
10
resulted into disorganization of the outer wall layer and the effect was even more pronounced in white poplar cells treated with the two medicagenic acid derivatives, saponins 
4
and 
5
. Oxidative burst and nitric oxide accumulation were common hallmarks of the response of white poplar cells to saponins. When DNA damage accumulation and DNA repair profiles were evaluated by Single Cell Gel Electrophoresis, induction of single and double strand breaks followed by effective repair was observed within 24 h. The reported data are discussed in view of the current issues dealing with saponin structure–activity relationship.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Saponins are biologically active plant-derived glycosides consisting of a sugar moiety linked to a hydrophobic aglycone (sapogenin) with a triterpenoid or a steroid structure (

). In the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
</tp:taxon-name>
, saponins are a complex mixture of triterpenic pentacyclic glycosides with medicagenic acid, hederagenin, bayogenin, zanhic acid and soyasapogenols 
A
and B as the dominant aglycones. Sugars or sugar chains are then attached at the triterpenic core of the molecule in selected positions to give monodesmosidic or bidesmosidic saponins: in monodesmosides,
</p>
         <p>
sugars are linked at the 3- 
O
position, while glycosylation at 3- 
O
and 28- 
O
positions gives bidesmosidic saponins. An additional glycosylation at the 23- 
O
position of the triterpenic core gives tridesmosidic saponins, detected until now only in 

<tp:taxon-name>Medicago</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>sativa</tp:taxon-name>

(alfalfa) and 

<tp:taxon-name>Medicago</tp:taxon-name>
truncatula

(

). Detailed stage as well as organ or tissue in which they are synthesized (

; Tava and investigations on saponin content and chemical identification have been carried out in several 
<tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
species
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

, 2011a,b). Saponin content and composition can change depending on environmental conditions, plant genotype, growth 

; 

). 

showed evidenced that medicagenic acid glycosides are found in roots and aerial parts, while hederagenin glycosides are more dominant in roots while leaves are abundant in zanhic acid glycosides.
</p>
         <p>
It has been shown that saponins from the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
</tp:taxon-name>
display fungicidal, molluscicidal, nematicidal, antibacterial, antiviral and antitumoral properties (

; 

). The biological activity of saponins extracted from 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
root and aerial system has been extensively investigated to acquire information on their structure–activity relationship (

; 

; 

; 

). The chemical structure certainly plays a key role in the bioactivity of saponins, and the current investigations aim to unravel the specific role of aglycone, as well as the nature and position of the sugar(s) in the molecule. However, these studies have provided contrasting results so far. In some cases there is evidence that sugar moieties play a relevant role, while according to other authors sapogenins are more active (

). The observed antimicrobial activity of alfalfa root saponins against 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichoderma viride
</tp:taxon-name>
indicated that the monodesmoside derivatives of medicagenic acid were more effective than related bidesmosides, even though a direct correlation between number of sugar residues and saponin bioactivity could not be established. In contrast, bioassays with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
</tp:taxon-name>
saponins against human pathogenic fungi and bacteria have highlighted that the presence of sugar residues in the molecule is not determinant for the antibiotic activity (

). It is worth noting that the majority of the reports currently available on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Medicago
</tp:taxon-name>
saponins bioactivity is focused on the chemical structure and composition of these compounds, while only few studies have been published on the biological effects. Thus, a specific correlation must be established between saponins and their cellular or subcellular target. For instance, 

, have recently deduced some structural features essential for cytotoxic activity, by carrying out 
in vitro
and preclinical studies carried out with novel synthetic saponins.
</p>
         <p>
In animal cells, saponins target the plasma membrane, binding cholesterol and forming micelle-like aggregates that disrupt membrane functionality and cause lysis. Other cellular targets of saponins in animals are microtubules, endoplasmic reticulum and voltage-dependent anion channels (

). By affecting these cellular components, saponins alter cell cycle progression, with the consequent inhibition of cell proliferation and induction of apoptosis. 

,b, in press) have evidenced that animal and plant cells share common elements in their response to saponins, suggesting for the possible use of plant systems for preliminary large-scale cytotoxicity tests performed on wide collections of natural extracts and/or purified compounds.
</p>
         <p>
The biological activity of alfalfa root saponin extracts on white poplar (
<tp:taxon-name>
Populus alba
</tp:taxon-name>
L
.) cell suspension cultures has been investigated by 

, who described dose-dependent cell death, as well as reactive oxygen species (ROS) and nitric oxide (NO) production. Furthermore, the up-regulation of the 
VFMT2
gene, encoding a 
type
2 metallothionein, was evidenced in white poplar cells exposed to root saponins and this finding demonstrated that, similarly to animal cells, also plant metallothioneins play a role in the response to saponins (

). In recent years, several investigations have been conducted in order to unravel saponin biosynthesis in model plants and optimize their production for industrial applications (

; 

,b; 

). The large-scale preliminary screening of compounds relevant for pharmaco-industrial applications, includes the assessment of potential genotoxic effects. There are reports dealing with the effects of saponins on genome integrity in animal cells, while no information is currently available on saponin toxicity in plant cells. 

demonstrated that saponins extracted from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nauclea
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
were able to induce DSBs (double strand breaks) in CHO (Chinese Hamster Ovary) cells, as evidenced by micronucleus and SCGE (Single Cell Gel Electrophoresis) assays. 
A
direct link between DNA repair and saponins activity was evidenced by 

who found that the treatment of human keratinocytes with steroidal saponin Rb1 from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ginseng
</tp:taxon-name>
enhanced NER (Nucleotide Excision Repair) pathway response.
</p>
         <p>
In the present work, four saponins having different structural features (aglycone moieties and sugar chains) were selected out of a preliminary screening of fourteen molecules purified from 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
leaves and root extracts. The purified saponins were tested for their cytotoxicity against highly proliferating white poplar cell suspension cultures to assess the effects they have on plant cells. Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM) imaging provided for the first time evidence of the effects exerted by saponins on plant cell wall integrity. Based on the reported data, a working hypothesis is presented, which includes the overall physiological changes triggered by saponin treatment and highlights some key molecular aspects of the plant cell response that still remain an open question.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results
</title>
         <p>

2.1. Purification and structural elucidation of 
<tp:taxon-name>M. sativa saponins</tp:taxon-name>
/ sapogenins and preliminary screening for cytotoxic activity against white poplar cells

</p>
         <p>
The chemical structure of the purified compounds from alfalfa (
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
L
.) used in this investigation is reported in 
Fig. 1
. The detailed structural elucidation of the purified saponins (
1–11
) and sapogenins (
12–14
) was obtained by combining Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (
NMR
), Electrospray Ionization Mass Spectrometry/Mass Spectrometry 
(
ESI-MS
/ 
MS
), and Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry (
GC
/ 
MS
) analyses (

; 

, 2009, 2011a). The saponins/sapogenins listed in 
Fig. 1
were previously described as the most abundant and representative compounds in alfalfa plant material (

). 
A
preliminary screening of the cytotoxic effects caused by the purified alfalfa saponins (
1–11
) and sapogenins (
12–14
) on white poplar cell suspension cultures was carried out using Evans Blue staining assay. Loss of plasma membrane integrity was used as hallmark of saponin cytotoxicity in the cell suspension cultures stained with Evans Blue dye. For each saponin/sapogenin, different concentrations (in the range 0–100 nmol mL 

―
1

) were added to exponentially growing four-day-old white poplar cultures. For each 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
saponin/sapogenin, the concentration able to induce 50% of plasma membrane damage of the total cell population at 24 h following treatment was established (
Fig. 1
). Based on results of these preliminary experiments, the alfalfa purified saponins were grouped in different classes according to their different cytotoxic activity. As shown in 
Fig. 2
, high amounts of saponins 
1
and 
3
(106.1 nmol mL 

―
1

, and 94.3 nmol mL 

―
1

, respectively) were required to cause damage at the plasma membrane level in 50% of the white poplar cell population. Both these compounds are bidesmosidic saponin of hederagenin (
Fig. 1
) and had low cytotoxic activity towards white poplar cells. Almost half of the dose (54.6 and 51.0 nmol mL 

―
1

, respectively) was able to cause the expected cellular damage in the case of saponins 
2
and 
7
, which consequently revealed higher cytotoxic activity, compared to saponins 
1
and 
3
(
Fig. 2
). Compound 
2
is an hederagenin monodesmoside, while saponin 
7
is a medicagenic acid bidesmoside with a glucuronic acid unit (
Fig. 1
). The group including saponins 
4– 6
and 
9–11
was characterized by enhanced cytotoxicity. Indeed the doses required to induce damage at the plasma membrane in 50% of the white poplar cell population progressively decreased: saponin 
10
, 12.9 nmol mL 

―
1

; saponin 
11
, 9.7 nmol mL 

―
1

; saponin 
5
, 12.1 nmol mL 

―
1

; saponin 
4
, 7.5 nmol mL 

―
1

; saponin 
6
, 6.3 nmol mL 

―
1

; saponin 
9
, 5.8 nmol mL 

―
1

and saponin 
8
, 3.6 nmol mL 

―
1

(
Fig. 2
). This was observed for saponins showing different structures, such as zanhic acid bidesmosides (compounds 
9
and 
10)
, soyasaponin I (
11
), and for mono- and bidesmoside derivatives of medicagenic acid, namely saponins 
4
, 
5
, 
6
and 
8
, respectively (
Fig.1
). 
A
range of cytotoxicity was also observed for the tested sapogenins: the lowest cytotoxic effect was registered for zanhic acid (compound 
14
) for which the 34.6 nmol mL 

―
1

concentration was requested, while medicagenic acid (compound 
13
) showed the highest cytotoxic effect when used at 4.1 nmol mL 

―
1

concentration. Hederagenin (compound 
12
) exhibited an intermediate effect at 14.8 nmol mL 

―
1

concentration. The reported data highlights significant differences in the ability to induce cell death of purified alfalfa saponins and sapogenins, characterized by distinct structural features.
</p>
         <p>
(*) Biological activity expressed as saponin/sapogenin concentration (mmol mL -1) able to induce 50% of plasma membrane damage in white poplar cell suspension cultures.
</p>
         <p>
Based on the different cytotoxic activities, four saponins representative of the different chemical structures, were selected for further studies: compound 
3
, hederagenin bidesmoside; compound 
10
, zanhic acid bidesmoside; and compounds 
4
and 
5
, which are mono- and bidesmosidic derivatives of medicagenic acid, respectively. For each saponin, the following dose was used: 94.3 nmol mL 

―
1

(saponin 
3
), 12.9 nmol mL 

―
1

(saponin 
10
), 12.1 nmol mL 

―
1

(saponin 
5
) and 7.5 nmol mL 

―
1

(saponin 
4
). 

2.2. Exposure to 
<tp:taxon-name>M. sativa saponins</tp:taxon-name>
results in cell wall perturbation 
and plasma membrane disruption
</p>
         <p>
To visualize the effect of purified alfalfa saponins on the cell wall structure of white poplar suspension cultures, TEM analysis was carried out on cells collected at 4 h following treatment with each saponin. The morphology of an intact cell wall as it appears in the untreated white poplar suspension cultures, is shown in 
Fig. 3
(CTRL). An electron-dense region is visible in the outer part of the cell wall with few and short fibrillar structures protruding towards the external environment (
Fig. 3
, CTRL, arrow). When treatments with alfalfa saponins were performed, the saponin-induced cell wall degradation was evident. The effects caused by saponin 
3
and 
10
are shown in 
Fig. 3
. Perturbations resulting from exposure to saponin 
3
were particularly evident along cell wall (
Fig. 3
, SAP3, arrow on the left image). Exposure to saponin 
10
resulted into strong disorganization of the outer wall layer with the appearance of long filamentous structures, possibly cellulose microfibrils. This perturbation was even more pronounced in response to saponin 
5
and 
4
. Distinct aggregates of the filamentous structures detached from the outer wall layer appeared to be randomly distributed in the extracellular environment. The filamentous structures released by saponin 
4
are shown in 
Fig. 3
(arrow).
</p>
         <p>
Moreover, TEM analysis allowed to evidence the effects of alfalfa saponins on the integrity of the plasma membrane of white poplar cells. In animals, saponins bind cholesterol molecules associated with plasma membrane causing functional alterations and lysis. The untreated white poplar cells revealed an intact plasma membrane (
Fig. 4
, CTRL, arrow) while exposure to alfalfa saponin resulted into dramatic disruption of the plasma membrane structure. As evidenced in 
Fig. 4
(saponin 
4
, arrow), in the saponin-treated white poplar cells the intact plasma membrane is replaced by an irregular area that appears less electron-dense compared to the surrounding cell wall and to cytosol. Thus, it is reasonable to hypothesize that the purified saponin molecules hereby investigated are able to act also on the plasma membrane of plant cells causing evident destabilization of the whole cell structure, as previously demonstrated in animal cells.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. PCD events in saponin-treated white poplar cells
</title>
         <p>
Oxidative burst, along with controlled nitric oxide (NO) accumulation, is one of the early events triggered in the cell by exogenous stresses. Hydrogen peroxide (H 
2
O 
2
) and NO act as signals to activate molecular defence responses that can lead eventually to the induction of the PCD pathway. Hence, to investigate the early response of white poplar cells to saponins, H 
2
O 
2
and NO production was assessed by staining with DAF 
2
-DA and DCFH-DA (see Supplementary information). Different time points (0, 15, 30, 45, 60 and 120 min) were tested following saponin addition. Results of these experiments are shown in 
Fig. S1
. Data revealed that NO accumulation in white poplar cells is apparently independent on saponin structure and toxicity. As for ROS production, saponin-dependent profiles have been evidenced, with a peak in H 
2
O 
2
accumulation at 60 min observed for both zanhic acid bidesmoside (saponin 
10
) and medicagenic acid monodesmoside (saponin 
4
).
</p>
         <p>
The DNA diffusion test was subsequently used to discriminate between programmed cell death (PCD) and necrosis events in saponin-treated white poplar cells. In case of PCD, nuclei show an undefined outline, due to nucleosomal sized DNA diffusing into the agarose, while necrotic nuclei appear bigger and non homogeneous and viable nuclei were small and compact (

). The percentage of viable, necrotic and PCD nuclei was calculated at 0, 6 and 24 h following saponin addition. As shown in 
Fig. 5
, the percentage of viable cells in the untreated sample (CTRL) showed only slight non significant (

P

&gt; 0.05) fluctuations with estimated values of 78.5 ± 1.5% (0 h), 86.0 ± 5.0% (6 h), 82.5 ± 8.0% (24 h). PCD events corresponded to 20–25% of the total cell population. Nuclei with necrotic morphology were barely detected in CTRL suspension cultures (
Fig. 5
, CTRL).
</p>
         <p>
In case of saponin 
3
(hederagenin bidesmoside), a significant (

P

&lt;0.05) reduction in the percentage of viable nuclei was observed at 6 h (60.5 ± 5.5%) compared to the beginning of the experiment (0 h, 82.0 ± 4.0%). At 24 h, the fraction of viable cells significantly (

P

&lt;0.05) increased up to 81.0 ± 11.0%. PCD was always the predominant cell death event induced by saponin 
3
, reaching a frequency of 36.0 ± 4% at 6 h, while no significant (

P

&gt; 0.05) differences were observed at 24 h compared to CTRL (
Fig. 5
, saponin 
3
). The frequency of necrosis did not show significant (

P

&gt; 0.05) changes throughout the tested time period. As previously recorded for saponin 
3
, treatments with saponin 
10
(zanhic acid bidesmoside) caused a significant (

P

&lt;0.05) reduction in the percentage of viable nuclei at 6 h (55.0 ± 6%) while a peak in viability (78.0 ± 1.0%) occurred at 24 h. No significant (

P

&gt; 0.05) differences in PCD and necrosis frequency, respectively were observed at 24 h compared to CTRL.
</p>
         <p>
Exposure to saponin 
4
and 
5
(medicagenic acid mono and bidesmosides) resulted into different viability/cell death profiles, compared to those observed for saponin 
3
and 
10
(
Fig. 5
). 
A
reduction in the percentage of viable nuclei was evident immediately after exposure (0 h) with estimated values of 64.5 ± 4.5% (saponin 
5
) and 73.5 ± 4.5% (saponin 
4
). Viability further decreased at 6 h (43.5 ± 5.5%, saponin 
5
; 51.5 ± 1.5%, saponin 
4
), dropping to the lowest values at 24 h (27.5 ± 1.5%, saponin 
5
; 31.0 ± 2.0%, saponin 
4
). As for PCD, the highest frequencies were observed at 6 and 24 h for both saponins. The recorded values were 55.0 ± 5.0% (saponin 
5
) and 44.0 ± 3.0% (saponin 
4
) at 6 h, 55.5 ± 12% (saponin 
5
) and 47.0 ± 3.0% (saponin 
4
) at 24 h. The highest frequency of necrosis was recorded at 24 h (17.0 ± 11.0%, saponin 
5
and 22.0 ± 1.0%, saponin 
4
). According to the reported data, the observed differences in the temporal profiles of cell death might be influenced by the saponin structure.
</p>
         <p>
Saponin 
3
Saponin 
10
</p>
         <p>
100 100) % (morphology 50 0 0 6 24 (h) 50 0 0 6 24 (h) Nuclear 100 Saponin 
4
100 Saponin 
5
</p>
         <p>50 50</p>
         <p>0 0</p>
         <p>0 6 24 (h) 0 6 24 (h)</p>
         <p>Time after treatment</p>
         <p>

2.4. DNA damage and repair profiles in saponin-treated white poplar 
cells
</p>
         <p>
The genotoxic effects of the four purified 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
saponins
</tp:taxon-name>
were assessed using SCGE assay. The alkaline version of the assay (Alkaline-SCGE) allows to detect DNA damage accumulation in terms of DNA strand breaks (single and double strand breaks, SSBs and DSBs, respectively) at different time points (6, 12 and 24 h) following saponin addition. 
A
parallel investigation was carried out using the untreated (CTRL) cells. As shown in 
Fig. 6
(AlkalineSCGE), slight but significant (

P

&lt;0.05) fluctuations in the level of DNA damage, possibly associated with the physiological cycling of the cell population, were observed in the untreated white poplar cells between 6 h (122.40 ± 3.90 a.u.) and 24 h (164.75 ± 1.32 a.u.). When saponin 
3
was provided, a significant (

P

&lt;0.05) increase (216.00 ± 1.97 a.u.) in the amount of DNA lesions was observed immediately after treatment (0 h) as compared to CTRL. Subsequently, a slight but significant (

P

&lt;0.05) decrease was detected at 6 h (180.60 ± 8.15 a.u.) with no further changes at 24 h (182.85 ± 1.42 a.u.). 
A
different profile was highlighted for saponin 
10
since a significant (

P

&lt;0.05) peak in DNA damage occurred at 6 h (315 ± 8.88 a.u., approximately 2.3-fold compared to the values recorded at 0 h in both CTRL and saponin 
10
-treated samples). The genotoxic injury caused by exposure to saponin 
10
was however promptly repaired by the white poplar cells as demonstrated by the finding that the amount of DNA strand breaks at 24 h (157.55 ± 1.32 a.u.) was similar to that recorded at the beginning of the experiment (152.30 ± 4.20 a.u., 0 h) (
Fig. 6
, Alkaline-SCGE). 
A
similar profile was obtained with saponin 
5
which caused a significant (

P

&lt;0.05) enhancement (251.35 ± 7.76 a.u.) of DNA strand breaks at 6 h, compared to 0 h (111.60 ± 5.05 a.u.). Also in this case, the white poplar cells were able to repair the saponin-induced DNA damage within 24 h. At this time point, the recorded value was significantly (

P

&lt;0.05) lower (150.70 ± 9.65 a.u.) compared to 6 h but still higher than the value detected at the beginning of the treatment. Finally, exposure to saponin 
4
resulted in slight although significant (

P

&lt;0.05) fluctuations in the level of DNA strand breaks at 6 h (165.55 ± 6.62 a.u.) and 24 h (137.55 ± 3.77 a.u.) compared to 0 h (152.60 ± 0.60 a.u.) (
Fig. 6
, Alkaline-SCGE).
</p>
         <p>
The Neutral-SCGE was then used to monitor the level of DSBs in the untreated and saponin-treated cells. As shown in 
Fig. 6
(Neutral-SCGE), at the beginning of the treatment (0 h) only slight but significant (

P

&lt;0.05) changes in the level of DSBs were observed when comparing the untreated samples with the saponin-treated cells. The following values were recorded: 46.85 ± 3.22 a.u. (CTRL), 40.60 ± 0.10 a.u. (saponin 
3
), 42.35 ± 4.32 a.u. (saponin 
10
), 50.90 ± 0.65 a.u. (saponin 
5
), and 39.30 ± 3.65 a.u. (saponin 
4
). All the tested saponins were able to induce DSBs accumulation at 6 h. In the case of saponin 
3
, the estimated enhancement was 108.15 ± 4.07 a.u. (2.66-fold compared to 0 h). Saponin 
10
and saponin 
5
resulted into similar values (99.00 ± 0.50 a.u. and 99.00 ± 9.80 a.u., respectively, 2.33-fold and 1.94-fold compared to 0 h) while for saponin 
4
the estimated value was 83.20 ± 13.09 a.u. (2.11-fold compared to 0 h) (
Fig. 6
, NeutralSCGE). According to the reported data, the white poplar cells were able to repair the DSBs triggered by the different saponins since a significant (

P

&lt;0.05) reduction in the level of these lesions was always detected at 24 h. As for saponin 
3
, the level of DSBs at 24 h dropped to 69.50 ± 0.60 a.u., a value still significantly (

P

&lt;0.05) higher compared to 0 h. In the case of saponin 
10
, the recorded amount (50.25 ± 4.37 a.u.) was only slightly higher compared to 0 h. 
A
similar trend was observed for saponin 
4
which resulted into an estimated DSBs level of 53.00 ± 6.50 a.u. while for saponin 
5
the amount of DSBs measured at 24 h (51.00 ± 0.50 a.u.) was similar to that observed at 0 h (
Fig. 6
, Neutral-SCGE). Thus, induction of DSBs appears as a common feature of all four tested saponins, independent on their chemical structure while similar repair dynamics were displayed by the white poplar suspension cultures in response to different saponins.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Discussion
</title>
         <p>
In the present work, the availability of purified 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
saponins
</tp:taxon-name>
with different aglycone moieties and sugar chain composition has provided a unique opportunity for dissecting the interaction between these molecules and plant cells, looking at any possible link that might correlate saponin structure and observed cytotoxic effects. The reported data add novel elements to the discussion about the use of plant cells as a reliable and low-cost alternative to animal models for pharmacological research, at least in preliminary large-scale cytotoxicity tests (Balestrazzi et al., in press). The observed interaction between saponins and cell wall represents a relevant finding, since no information is currently available on the chemical processes that mediate the saponin action at this cellular site. The filamentous structures detached from cell wall might correspond to cellulose microfibrilles whose organization has been dramatically altered by the purified saponins. The cell wall perturbation observed in saponin-treated white poplar cells resembles the images provided by 

who described the digestion of crystalline cellulose by the 
Chlostridium thermocellum
cellulosome. In both cases, the filamentous structures resulting from degradation seem to be spliced into shorter components (sub-fibrillation) until aggregates of smaller fragments are produced. To date, only 

have described the effects of saponin extracts obtained from seeds of the soapnut tree (
<tp:taxon-name>
Sapindus mukorossi
</tp:taxon-name>
) on the structure and morphology of crystalline cellulose fibrilles produced from the pseudostem of banana (
<tp:taxon-name>
Musa sapientum
</tp:taxon-name>
) plants. Inverse Gas Chromatography (IGC) revealed that the reactive side groups of the soapnut saponins, made of saccharide residues, could interact through hydrogen bonds with the hydroxyl groups of cellulose on the surface of the treated banana fibers. Additional interactions, involving the polar residues of adjacent saponin molecules, also contributed to strengthen the resulting coating effect. After saponin treatment, the hydrophobic and acid-base nature of crystalline cellulose fibers was changed, improving their properties for industrial applications (

). It is possible that the same chemical events described by 

might have occurred at the wall of white poplar cells exposed to the purified saponins. Although the purified 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
saponins
</tp:taxon-name>
do not carry the same functional groups of soapnut saponins, they own hydroxyl and carboxyl groups on their aglycone and sugar components, which might play a key role in establishing hydrogen bonds with the cell wall polysaccharides, disrupting the ultrastructural organization. The biological effects recorded in relation to the peculiar structure of alfalfa saponins however do not explain the connection between the presence of a specific functional side group in the saponin molecule and the specific effect on cell wall. Hence, further investigations will be necessary to fully understand the chemical interactions underlying the observed effects on the plant cell wall.
</p>
         <p>
Correlation between structure and cytotoxicity of plant saponins have until now led to contrasting results regarding the specific structural requirements for the bioactivity (

; 

). In the present study, the highest activity was observed for saponin containing medicagenic acid, in agreement with the observation that this aglycone was the most toxic to the plant cells, compared to zanhic acid and hederagenin. In addition, our findings suggest that saponin sugar components are important for the activity and that saponins toxicity towards white poplar cells is higher when specific sugars (arabinose, rhamnose and xylose) are present in the molecule. This is well evidenced in the case of zanhic acid (compound 
14
) whose cytotoxicity is enhanced by the addition of the sugar chain AraRhaXyl in saponin 
9
.
</p>
         <p>
Considering the complexity of the molecular events possibly involved in the response of plant cells to the saponin-mediated toxicity, the results hereby presented have been summarized and integrated within a working hypothesis (
Fig. 7
). It is known that the cell wall plays a critical role in sensing biotic/abiotic stresses and in the activation of defence response (

). Pathogen-mediated hydrolysis of the plant cell wall releases oligogalacturonides (OG), as products of pectin partial degradation, that are perceived by the wall-associated Kinase 1 (WAK1) specific receptor (

). WAK1 initiates a signaling pathway consisting of free cytosolic calcium fluctuations, ROS and NO production (

), finally leading to the modulation of defence genes expression (

). Based on the reported data, it is possible that the deleterious effects of alfalfa saponins observed at the cell wall might trigger the above described defence-related signaling pathway. The involvement of ROS and NO in the response of white poplar suspension cultures to saponin extracts from 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
had been already highlighted (

), even if the possible target(s) of this signaling pathway in the nuclear compartment are still unknown.
</p>
         <p>
In this work, white poplar cells have been treated with four different saponins, characterized by increasing cytotoxic activity. According to the working hypothesis (
Fig. 7
), if the saponin exerts a moderate perturbation of the cell wall homeostasis, as recorded with saponin 
3
and saponin 
10
, the cell is more likely to promote stress recovery responses, e.g., DNA repair pathways and antioxidant mechanisms. Otherwise, in case of a severe perturbation of cell wall homeostasis, as reported for saponin 
4
and saponin 
5
, the signal transduction components will trigger PCD. Accordingly, the DNA diffusion analysis revealed peculiar cell death profiles depending on saponin structure. Saponin 
3
and 
10
showed a similar profile, inducing a peak in PCD events at 6 h after treatment that subsides at 24 h, indicating that the stress response has been effective and the homeostasis has been restored in the majority of the cell population. Both saponin 
4
and 
5
having the strongest toxic activity at the cell wall were able to induce a significant peak of PCD events at 6 h, but differently from saponin 
3
and 
10,
PCD frequency was still high at 24 h in association with a significant enhancement of necrosis.
</p>
         <p>Saponin-dependent profiles of the cell recovery response within the nucleus were registered with the SCGE analysis, which allowed to investigate the ability of the population to withstand to the genotoxic damage inflicted by saponins. For all the tested saponins, Neutral SCGE resulted in similar DSBs patterns, indicating that DSBs accumulation is a general response to saponin-induced genotoxic stress, not related to the specific structure of these molecules. Differently, the evaluation of total DNA strand breaks (both SSBs and DSBs) performed with Alkaline SCGE, provided distinct profiles, depending on the tested saponin. This finding suggests that saponins with different chemical structures exhibited different</p>
         <p>
genotoxic activity towards the DNA of white poplar cells, triggering mainly those mechanisms that lead to SSBs accumulation. However, the specific correlation between saponin structure and its genotoxic activity remains unknown. The possible involvement of any cell cycle checkpoints in the response of plant cells to saponins is another key point underlined in 
Fig. 7
. Due to the specific action of alfalfa saponins on the white poplar cell wall, it could be hypothesized that the associated signal cascade might lead to the activation of the so-called ‘Cell Wall Integrity’ checkpoint so far characterized only in yeast (

) and algae (

). In animals, evidence has been provided that different saponin molecules trigger cell cycle arrest at G 
2
/M checkpoint acting on different signaling pathways. 

recently reported the triterpenoid saponin Platycodin can induce cell cycle block at G 
2
/M in Human Glioma cells by decreasing the PI3K/Akt pathway while the triterpene saponin Buddlejasaponin IV (BS-IV) triggers the same response by activating mitochondrial-dependent pathways in human osteosarcoma cells (

). These findings seem to support the idea that different saponin molecules can trigger different signaling pathways, all of them converging at G 
2
/M checkpoint. The cell wall integrity checkpoint is known to regulate cell cycle progression in response to cell wall perturbation resulting from environmental stresses. The involvement of other cell cycle checkpoints cannot be ruled out, as it is known that saponins can target key elements in cell cycle regulation in animal systems (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Based on these results, we can only speculate on the possible effects of saponin-mediated damage in relation to the complex cell cycle machinery. The study by 

describes the cell cycle phase distribution throughout the culture period of non-synchronized poplar (

P

. 

<tp:taxon-name>alba</tp:taxon-name>
x 
P

. 
tremula
) cells. According to this report, during the exponential growth phase the fraction of cells in G 
2
and M phases was significantly increased and this condition should be reasonably expected also for the white poplar suspension cultures exposed to saponin during the exponential growth phase. Interestingly, the cell wall integrity checkpoint that, accordingly to the present working hypothesis (
Fig. 7
), would be involved in sensing the saponin-induced perturbations of cell wall homeostasis is located at the G 
2
/M boundary (

). Additional investigations on synchronized cells will be required to validate this hypothesis, allowing a better understanding on how the structural features of saponins might influence the signaling events and the final decision of cell fate.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>The present work opens novel perspectives in the research field dedicated to the complex issue of saponin structure–activity. The saponin action on cell wall represents an original starting point for future biotechnological applications dealing with biomass production, a valuable aspect, considering the lack of information and the urgent need for innovative industrial strategies in this context. As for the link between saponins toxicity and genome integrity, the reported data add a consistent piece of information in the search for common hallmarks in animal and plant systems, further stimulating the discussion about the proper use of plant cells as tools in pharmaco-industrial screenings.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

5.1. Extraction, purification and characterization of 
<tp:taxon-name>M. sativa saponins</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Saponins were extracted and purified as previously described (

; 

, 2009, 2011a). Pure saponins were obtained by a combination of chromatographic separation steps (silica gel open column chromatography and semi-preparative Reversed Phase-High Performance Liquid Chromatography, RP-HPLC) from the crude saponin mixture from leaves and roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
L. as described by 

, 2009, 2011a,b). Acid hydrolysis of saponin mixture afforded the related sapogenins that were obtained in a pure 
<tp:taxon-name>form after</tp:taxon-name>
silica gel open column chromatography (

; 

). Detailed structural elucidation of pure saponins was obtained by Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) and Electrospray Ionization/Mass Spectrometry (ESI-MS/MS). Sapogenins were also evaluated by Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry (GC/MS) analysis as their methyl-trimethylsilyl derivatives (

; 

, 2009, 2011a; 

). Saponins were dissolved in 30–70% ethanol solution according to their solubility, while sapogenins were dissolved in ethanol and added at the indicated concentration to white poplar cell cultures.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

5.2. Cell cultures and treatments with 
<tp:taxon-name>M. sativa saponins</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cell suspension cultures of the white poplar (
P
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
alba
</tp:taxon-name>
L.) cultivar ‘Villafranca’ were obtained and maintained 
in vitro
as previously described (

). Exponentially growing (four days-old) cell suspension cultures were exposed to increasing concentrations (0–100 nmol mL 

―
1

) of 14 different 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
purified saponins and sapogenins. A preliminary screening of cytotoxic activity was carried out using the Evans Blue assay as described by 

. This allowed to assess the saponin/sapogenin dose able to induce damage at the plasma membrane in 50% of the white poplar cell population. Untreated cells and cells exposed to the same volume of the ethanol solutions used to dissolve the pure compounds were tested as control. Dead cells resulting from heat shock treatment (55 °C, 10 min) were also analyzed as positive control. For each saponin/sapogenin treatment, three independent experiments were performed and three replicated samples were used for each treatment.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.3. Transmission Electron Microscopy
</title>
         <p>
Aliquots (2–3 mL) of four days-old white poplar cell suspension cultures treated with each saponin/sapogenin, at the indicated doses, and untreated cells were collected and fixed with 1.5% glutaraldehyde (Sigma–Aldrich, Milan, 
Italy
) for 3 h at room temperature. Cells were then rinsed in phosphate buffered saline solution (PBS, pH 7.2) overnight, post-fixed in 1% aqueous OsO 
4
(Sigma– Aldrich) and embedded in epoxy resin. These sections were stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate and observed with a Zeiss EM900 electron microscope equipped with a 
30 mm
objective aperture and operating at 80 kV.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4. DNA diffusion test
</title>
         <p>
The DNA diffusion assay (

) was performed in order to evaluate cell death. Nuclei were extracted as described by 

. Agarose precoated slides were prepared by spreading 1 mL of 1% agarose on each slide. Aliquots (300 µL) of nuclei suspension were mixed with 200 µL of 1% Low Melting Point Agarose (Sigma–Aldrich) in PBS at 37 ° 
C
and gently transferred onto slides. Slides were incubated in lysis buffer (2.5 M NaCl, 100 mM EDTA, 10 mM Tris HCl pH 7.5) for 20 min, washed twice in neutral buffer TBE (89 mM Tris Base, 89 mM Boric Acid, 2 mM EDTA, pH 8.3) for 5 min and rinsed in 70% ethanol (v/v) for 10 min. Slides were air-dried and stored at room temperature, stained with 20 µL DAPI (4 

0

,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole, 1 µg mL 

―
1

) (Sigma–Aldrich) and covered with a cover slip. One hundred nuclei were analyzed per slide. Cells undergoing PCD or necrosis were distinguished from viable cells as indicated by 

. For each treatment, two replicated samples were analyzed in two independent experiments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.5. Single Cell Gel Electrophoresis (Comet assay)
</title>
         <p>
Nuclei were extracted as described by 

. The suspension containing the purified nuclei and a solution of 1% Low Melting Point Agarose (Sigma–Aldrich) in PBS at 37 ° 
C
were mixed in equal volume. Two drops of the resulting suspension were then pipetted onto agarose precoated slides and solidified on ice. Slides were incubated 20 min in high salt lysis buffer (2.5 M NaCl, 100 mM Tris–HCl pH 7.5, 100 mM EDTA) to disrupt the nuclear membrane. For the neutral SCGE slides were electrophoresed 8 min at 1 V cm 

―
1

in TBE while for alkaline SCGE, nuclei were denatured in alkaline buffer (1 mM Na 
2
EDTA, 300 mM NaOH, pH&gt; 13) 20 min at 4 ° 
C
and then electrophoresed in the same buffer for 20 min at 0.72 V cm 

―
1

in a cold chamber. After electrophoresis, slides were washed in 0.4 M Tris–HCl pH 7.5 three times for 5 min, rinsed in 70% ethanol (v/v) three times for 5 min at 4 ° 
C
and dried overnight at room temperature. Subsequently, slides were stained with 20 µL DAPI (1 µg mL 

―
1

, Sigma–Aldrich). For each slide, one hundred nucleoids were scored, using a fluorescence microscope with an excitation filter of 
340–380 nm
and a barrier filter of 
400 nm
. Nucleoids were classified and results were expressed in arbitrary units (a.u.) according to 

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.6. Statistical analysis
</title>
         <p>
Experiments were repeated three times and carried out in triplicate. Data are expressed as means (standard deviation (SD) values. Differences observed in cell viability, H 
2
O 
2
and NO production, DNA damage level and gene expression profiles in saponin-treated cells compared with the control were statistically evaluated. Statistical significance of differences was determined using Student’s 
t
-test.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
This research was supported by grants from University of Pavia – 
Italy
and Consiglio per la Ricerca e la Sperimentazione in Agricoltura (
C
.R. 
A
.) – 
Italy
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

Appendix 
A
. Supplementary data

</title>
         <p>Supplementary data associated with this article can be found, in the online version, at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2015. 01.008.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Argentieri, M.P.
, 
D’Addabbo, T.
, 
Tava, A.
, 
Agostinelli, A.
, 
Jurzysta, M.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
2008
. 

Evaluation of nematicidal properties of saponins from 
Medicago
spp

. 
Eur. J. Plant Pathol.
120
, 
189–197
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Avato, P.
, 
Bucci, R.
, 
Tava, A.
, 
Vitali, C.
, 
Rosato, A.
, 
Bialy, Z.
, 
Jurzysta, M.
, 
2006
. 

Antimicrobial activity of saponins from 
Medicago
sp.: structure–activity relationship

. 
Phytother. Res.
20
, 
454–457
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Balestrazzi, A.
, 
Agoni, V.
, 
Tava, A.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
Biazzi, E.
, 
Raimondi, E.
, 
Macovei, A.
, 
Carbonera, D.
, 
2011
a. 

Cell death induction and nitric oxide biosynthesis in white poplar (
Populus alba
) suspension cultures exposed to alfalfa saponins

. 
Physiol. Plant.
1
, 
227–238
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Balestrazzi, A.
, 
Carbonera, D.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
Tava, A.
, in press. 
White poplar (Populus alba) suspension cultures as a model system to study apoptosis induced by alfalfa saponins
. 
Anticancer Agents Med. Chem.
14
, 
1324–1331
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Balestrazzi, A.
, 
Macovei, A.
, 
Tava, A.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
Raimondi, E.
, 
Carbonera, D.
, 
2011
b. 
Unraveling the response of plant cells to cytotoxic saponins: role of metallothionein and nitric oxide. Plant Signal
. 
Behav.
6
, 
1–4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Balestrazzi, A.
, 
Macovei, A.
, 
Testoni, C.
, 
Raimondi, E.
, 
Donà, M.
, 
Carbonera, D.
, 
2009
. 

Nitric oxide biosynthesis in white poplar (
Populus alba
L.) suspension cultures challenged with heavy metals

. 
Plant Stress
3
, 
1–6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Berenjian, S.
, 
Hu, K.
, 
Abedi-Valugerdi, M.
, 
Hassan, M.
, 
Bashir Hassan, S.
, 
Morein, B.
, 
2013
. 

The nanoparticulate 
Quillaja
saponin KGI exerts anti-proliferative effects by down-regulation of cell cycle molecules in U937 and HL-60 human leukemia cells

. 
Lymphoma, Leuk
. 
http://dx.doi.org/10.3109/10428194.2013. 853301
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bialy, Z.
, 
Jurzysta, M.
, 
Oleszek, W.
, 
Piacente, S.
, 
Pizza, C.
, 
1999
. 

Saponins in alfalfa (
Medicago sativa
L.) root and their structural elucidation

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
47
, 
3185–3192
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Boisset, C.
, 
Chanzy, H.
, 
Henrissat, B.
, 
Lamed, R.
, 
Shoham, Y.
, 
Bayer, E.A.
, 
1999
. 

Digestion of crystalline cellulose substrates by the 
Clostridium thermocellum
cellulosome: structural and morphological aspects

. 
Biochem. J.
340
, 
829–835
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Brutus, A.
, 
Sicilia, F.
, 
Macone, A.
, 
Cervone, F.
, 
De Lorenzo, G.
, 
2010
. 
A domain swap approach reveals a role of the plant wall associated kinase 1 (WAK1) as a receptor of oligogalacturonides
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
107
, 
9452–9457
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cai, B.X.
, 
Jin, S.L.
, 
Jin, S.L.
, 
Luo, D.
, 
Lin, X.F.
, 
Gao, J.
, 
2009
. 
Ginsenoside Rb1 suppresses ultraviolet radiation-induced apoptosis by inducing DNA repair
. 
Biol. Pharm. Bull.
32
, 
837–841
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Carelli, M.
, 
Biazzi, E.
, 
Panara, F.
, 
Tava, A.
, 
Scaramelli, L.
, 
Porceddu, A.
, 
Graham, N.
, 
Odoardi, M.
, 
Piano, E.
, 
Arcioni, S.
, 
May, S.
, 
Scotti, C.
, 
Calderini, O.
, 
2011
. 

Medicago truncatula
CYP716A12 is a multifunctional oxidase involved in the biosynthesis of hemolytic saponins

. 
Plant Cell
23
, 
3070–3081
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Carimi, F.
, 
Zottini, M.
, 
Formentin, E.
, 
Terzi, M.
, 
LoSchiavo, F.
, 
2003
. 
Cytokinins: new apoptotic inducers in plants
. 
Planta
216
, 
413–421
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Collins, A.R.
, 
2004
. 
The comet assay for DNA damage and repair
. 
Mol. Biotechnol.
26
, 
249–261
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Confalonieri, M.
, 
Cammareri, M.
, 
Biazzi, E.
, 
Pecchia, P.
, 
Fevereiro, M.P.S.
, 
Balestrazzi, A.
, 
Tava, A.
, 
Conicella, C.
, 
2009
. 

Enhanced triterpene sapogenin biosynthesis and root nodulation in transgenic barrel medic (
Medicago truncatula
Gaertn.) expressing a novel β- amyrin synthase (AsOXA1) gene

. 
Plant Biotechnol. J.
7
, 
172–182
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cordeiro, M.
, 
Faria, M.
, 
Abraham, E.
, 
Pothan, L.A.
, 
2013
. 
Assessment of the changes in the cellulosic surface of micro and nano banana fibres due to saponin treatment
. 
Carbohydr. Polym.
98
, 
1065–1071
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
D’Addabbo, T.
, 
Carbonara, T.
, 
Leonetti, P.
, 
Radicci, V.
, 
Tava, A.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
2011
. 

Control of plant parasitic nemtodes with active saponins and biomass from 
Medicago sativa

. 
Phytochem. Rev.
10
, 
503–519
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Donà, M.
, 
Ventura, L.
, 
Macovei, A.
, 
Gonfalonieri, M.
, 
Savio, M.
, 
Giovannini, A.
, 
Carbonera, D.
, 
Balestrazzi, A.
, 
2013
. 

Gamma irradiation with different dose rates induces different DNA damage responses in 
Petunia x hybrida
cells. J

. 
Plant Physiol
. 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jplph.2013.01.010
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ferrari, S.
, 
Savatin, D.V.
, 
Sicilia, F.
, 
Gramegna, G.
, 
Cervone, F.
, 
De Lorenzo, G.
, 
2013
. 
Oligogalacturonides: plant damage-associated molecular patterns and regulators of growth and development. Front
. 
Plant Sci.
4
, 
1–8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hostettmann, K.
, 
Marston, A.
, 
1995
. 
Chemistry and pharmacology of natural products
. In: 
Phillipson, J.D.
, 
Baxter, H.
(Eds.), 
Saponins
. 
Cambridge University Press, UK
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jurzysta, M.
, 
1982
. 
Polsky Urzad Patentowy
. 
Patent No
. 114171.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kwok, A.C.M.
, 
Wong, T.T.J.
, 
2010
. 

The activity of a wall-bound cellulase is required for and is coupled to cell cycle progression in the dinoflagellate 
Crypthecodinium cohnii

. 
Plant Cell
22
, 
1281–1298
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lee, H.
, 
Bae, E.K.
, 
Park, S.Y.
, 
Sjodin, A.
, 
Lee, J.S.
, 
Noh, E.W.
, 
Jansson, S.
, 
2007
. 

Growthphase-dependent gene expression profiling of poplar (
Populus alba x Populus tremula
var. 
glandulosa
) suspension cells

. 
Physiol. Plant.
131
, 
599–613
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Levin, D.E.
, 
2005
. 

Cell wall integrity signaling in 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae

. 
Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.
69
, 
262–291
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, W.
, 
Di Giorgio, C.
, 
Lamidi, M.
, 
Elias, R.
, 
Olliver, E.
, 
De Meo, M.P.
, 
2011
. 

Genotoxic and clastogenic activity of saponins extracted from 
Nauclea
bark as assessed by the micronucleus and comet assays

in Chinese 
Hamster Ovary cells. J. Ethopharmacol
. 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2011.05.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pecetti, L.
, 
Tava, A.
, 
Romani, M.
, 
De Benedetto, M.G.
, 
Corsi, P.
, 
2006
. 

Variety and environment effects on the dynamics of saponins in lucerne (
Medicago sativa
L.)

. 
Eur. J. Agron.
25
, 
187–192
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Podolak, I.
, 
Galanty, A.
, 
Sobolewska, D.
, 
2010
. 
Saponins as cytotoxic agents: a review
. 
Phytochem. Rev.
9
, 
425–474
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Qin, H.
, 
Du, X.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Wang, R.
, 
2013
. 

Platycodin D, a triterpenoid saponin from 
Platycodon grandiflorum
, induces G 
2
/M arrest and apoptosis in human hepatoma HepG2 cells by modulating the PI3K/Akt pathway

. 
Tumor Biol.
http:// dx.doi.org/10.1007/s13277-013-1169-1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rasul, S.
, 
Dubreuil-Maurizi, C.
, 
Lamotte, O.
, 
Koen, E.
, 
Poinssot, B.
, 
Alcaraz, G.
, 
Wendehenne, D.
, 
Jeandroz, S.
, 
2012
. 

Nitric oxide production mediates oligogalacturonide-triggered immunity and resistance to 
Botrytis cinerea
in 
Arabidopsis thaliana

. 
Plant Cell Environ.
35
, 
1483–1499
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shangguan, W.J.
, 
Li, H.
, 
Zhang, Y.H.
, 
2014
. 
Induction of G2/M phase cell cycle arrest and apoptosis by ginsenoside Rf in human osteosarcoma MG-63 cells through the mitochondrial pathway
. 
Oncol. Rep.
31
, 
305–313
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singh, N.P.
, 
2003
. 
Apoptosis by DNA diffusion assay
. In: 
Blumenthal, R.
(Ed.), 
Methods in Molecular Medicine – Chemiosensitivity
. 
Humana Press, New York
, pp. 
78–94
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tava, A.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
2006
. 

Chemical and biological activity of triterpene saponins from 
Medicago
species

. 
Nat. Prod. Commun.
1
, 
1159–1180
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tava, A.
, 
Pecetti, L.
, 
2012
. 

Chemical investigation of saponins from twelve annual 
Medicago
species and their bioassay with the brine shrimp 
Artemia salina

. 
Nat. Prod. Commun.
7
, 
837–840
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tava, A.
, 
Mella, M.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
Argentieri, M.P.
, 
Bialy, Z.
, 
Yurzysta, M.
, 
2005
. 

Triterpene saponins from leaves of 
Medicago arborea
L

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
53
, 
9954–9965
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tava, A.
, 
Mella, M.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
Biazzi, E.
, 
Pecetti, L.
, 
Bialy, Z.
, 
Jurzysta, M.
, 
2009
. 

New triterpenic saponins from the aerial parts of 
Medicago arabica
(L.) huds

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
57
, 
2826–2835
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tava, A.
, 
Odoardi, M.
, 
Oleszek, W.
, 
1999
. 

Seasonal changes of saponin content in five alfalfa (
Medicago sativa
) cultivars

. 
Agric. Mediterr.
129
, 
111–116
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tava, A.
, 
Pecetti, L.
, 
Romani, M.
, 
Mella, M.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
2011
a. 

Triterpenoid glycosides from the leaves of two cultivars of 
Medicago polymorpha
L

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
59
, 
6142–6149
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tava, A.
, 
Scotti, C.
, 
Avato, P.
, 
2011
b. 

Biosynthesis of saponins in the genus 
Medicago

. 
Phytochem. Rev.
10
, 
459–469
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Thakur, M.
, 
Melzig, M.F.
, 
Fuchs, H.
, 
Weng, A.
, 
2011
. 
Chemistry and pharmacology of saponins: special focus on cytotoxic properties
. 
Botanics Targets Ther.
1
, 
19–29
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ventura, L.
, 
Macovei, A.
, 
Donà, M.
, 
Paparella, S.
, 
Buttafava, A.
, 
Giovannini, A.
, 
Carbonera, D.
, 
Balestrazzi, A.
, 
2013
. 

Genotoxic effects due to in vitro culture and H 
2
O 
2
treatments in 
Petunia x hybrida
cells monitored through DNA diffusion assay, FPG-SCGE and gene expression profile analyses

. 
Acta Physiol. Plant
. 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11738-013-1415-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, C.
, 
Sun, G.
, 
Yuan, G.
, 
Wang, R.
, 
Sun, X.
, 
2014
. 
Effects of Platycodin D on proliferation, apoptosis and PI3K/Akt signal pathway of human glioma U251 cells
. 
Molecules
19
, 
21411–21423
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
