<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2023.113588</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Diversity of sesquiterpenoids from Stellera chamaejasme with neuroprotective effects</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Diversity of sesquiterpenoids from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
with neuroprotective effects

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fang-Yu Yuan
1
, Zhuo-Ya Tang
1
, Xue-Long Yan, Dong Huang, Han-Zhuang Weng,

Jia-Luo Huang
, Run-Zhu Fan, Ye Chen, Sheng Yin, Gui-Hua Tang
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, 510006, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Sesquiterpenoids</p>
         <p>
Seco
-guaiane
</p>
         <p>Neuroprotective activity</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
Chromatographic fractionation of the 95% EtOH extract of the roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
yielded 20 sesquiterpenoids of four different 
types
, guaiane-, carotane-, sesquicarane-, and alpiniane-types. Among them, sesquistrachanoids A F were previously undescribed ones, whose structures including absolute configurations were elucidated by spectroscopic methods, the Mo 
2
(OAc) 
4
-induced ECD experiment, and analysis of experimental and calculated 1D NMR and ECD data. Sesquistrachanoid A is a 2,3- 
seco
-guaiane-type sesquiterpenoid with a 
α
-pyrone core and sesquistrachanoid B is the first example of 8,9- 
seco
-guaiane-type sesquiterpenoid featured with an 1,8- 
δ
-lactone core. Sesquistrachanoid C is a guaiane sesquiterpenoid characterized by a peroxide bridge between C-8 and C-10. All sesquiterpenoids were evaluated for their neuroprotective effects on cell damage induced by sodium nitroprusside in PC-12 cells. The bioassay results showed that six compounds at 10 μM could restore the cell viability, being comparable to that of the positive control edaravone. The mechanistic study on the most pronounced activity compound, stelleraguaianone B, demonstrated that it played a neuroprotective role by promoting the mRNA expression of antioxidant enzymes to reduce oxidative stress.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
L. is a perennial herb belonging to the plant family, 
<tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
, and is mainly distributed in 
Northwest
(
Gansu
, 
Ningxia
, 
Qinghai
, 
Shaanxi
, and 
Xinjiang
), 
Southwest
(
Sichuan
, 
Xizang
, and 
Yunnan
), 
Northeast
(
Heilongjiang
, 
Jilin
, and 
Liaoning
), 
North
(
Hebei
, 
Nei Mongol
, and 
Shanxi
), and 
Central
China
(
Henan
) (

). 
Besides
, this plant species is also found in 
Bhutan, Mongolia
, 
Nepal
, and 
Russia
(

). 
In
China
, the roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
are traditionally used as a medicine called “Langdu”, widely acclaimed for multiple pharmacological actions such as the relief of cough, elimination of bloating, treatment of long-term accumulation of food and sputum, and for curing of scabies and diarrhea (

). 
Such
beneficial medicinal attributes compelled the natural medicinal chemists to systematically study the chemical composition of “Langdu” and found that it was rich in flavonoids, diterpenoids, lignans, and coumarins (

; 

; 

). 
Recently
, a number of guaiane sesquiterpenoids and their derivatives (including 2,3- 
seco
-, 3,4- 
seco
-, 8,9- 
seco
-, 1,10- 
seco
-, 10,11-cyclo-, and 1, 12-cyclo-guaianes) have been found in the roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
(

, 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

), their structures have been enlisted in 

Figs. 
S1.1
S1.2

and 

Table 
S1.1

(Supplementary data). Furthermore, 
in vivo
and 
in vitro
bioactivity evaluation demonstrated that the crude extracts and chemical components of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
possessed potential anti-viral, anti-bacterial, anti-convulsive, anti-epileptic, anti-inflammation, anti-tumor, neuroprotective, and insecticide properties (

, 

; 

; 

; 

, 2021).
</p>
         <p>
In the course of our continuing work of discovering structurally intriguing and neuroprotective agents from natural sources (

; 

; 

; 

), chemical investigation of the roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
led to the isolation of 20 sesquiterpenoids with various structures including 14 guaianes, four carotanes, a sesquicarane, and one alpiniane. Among these, compounds 
1–6
were undescribed ones, whose structures were determined by analysis of their spectroscopic and the Mo 
2
(OAc) 
4
-induced ECD data together with the utilization of 1D NMR and ECD calculation methods. In the sodium nitroprusside (SNP)-induced PC-12 cell (pheochromocytoma cell line) model, compounds 
1–20
were screened for their neuroprotective effects on cell damage and the possible mechanisms of neuroprotection of the most active compound were further explored. Herein, details of the isolation, structural elucidation, and neuroprotective effects of these sesquiterpenoids are reported.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
Extracting the air-dried powdered roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
with 95% EtOH yielded the crude extract. After suspending the crude extract in appropriate amount of H 
2
O, it was successively extracted with petroleum ether and EtOAc. The EtOAc partition was subjected to purification by macroporous resin column, silica gel column, Rp-C 
18
column, Sephadex LH-20 column, and semipreparative HPLC, which had afforded 20 sesquiterpenoids (
1–20
) including six undescribed ones (sesquistrachanoids A F) (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Sesquistrachanoid A (
1
) was obtained as a pale-yellow oil and had a molecular formula of C 
15
H 
20
O 
3
with six degrees of unsaturation based on the HRESIMS ion at 
m/z
271.1292 [M +Na] 
+
(calcd 271.1305) and its 1D NMR data. The IR characteristic absorption bands at 
u
max
3432, 1671, and 
1454 cm
1
suggested the presence of hydroxyl and conjugated carbonyl groups. The 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR data (
Table 1
) displayed signals of one OH proton [
δ
H
5.72 (1H, s)], one isopropenyl group [
δ
C
148.1 (C), 110.8 (
CH
2
), and 21.4 (
CH
3
); 
δ
H
4.76, 4.73 (each 1H, s) and 1.75 (3H, s)], a trisubstituted 
α
-pyrone system [
δ
C
164.3 (C), 152.8 (C), 144.4 (
CH
), 130.5 (C), and 117.1 (C); 
δ
H
7.21 (1H, s)], two tertiary methyls [
δ
C
27.6 (
CH
3
) and 15.2 (
CH
3
); 
δ
H
1.91 and 1.59 (each 3H, s)], three methylenes, one methine, and an oxygenated quaternary carbon [
δ
C
75.2 (C)]. The aforementioned data and the remaining degree of unsaturation (five of the six degrees of unsaturation were accounted for by 
α
-pyrone system and one isopropenyl group) indicated that 
1
was a bicyclic sesquiterpenoid.
</p>
         <p>
The 2D structure of 
1
was constructed by detailed 2D NMR analysis (HSQC, 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, and HMBC). As shown in 
Fig. 2
, the presence of the 
CH
2
(6) 
CH
(7) 
CH
2
(8) 
CH
2
(9) unit was first determined by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations of H 
2
-6/H-7, H-7/H 
2
-8, and H 
2
-8/H 
2
-9. The HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
) further supported that the isopropenyl group located at C-7 of the C-6 C9 fragment together with a 5- 
methylα
-pyrone moiety were present in 
1
, and the tertiary methyl [
δ
C
27.6 (
CH
3
); 
δ
H
1.59 (1H, s)] and the OH were linked to the quaternary carbon (C-10). The aforementioned fragments were connected to form a 6/7 bicyclic system characteristic with an 
α
-pyrone core by the HMBC correlations from H-3 to C-2 and C-5, H 
2
-6 to C-1 and C-4, H 
2
-9 to C-1, and H 
3
-14 to C-1 and C-9. The NOE correlation of H-7/H 
3
-14 indicated that H-7 and 
CH
3
-14 were cofacial and arbitrarily assigned 
α
-orientations (
Fig. 3
). The absolute configuration of 
1
was further studied by comparison of its experimental and simulated ECD spectra using the quantum chemical time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) method (see S 
2 in
Supplementary data). As shown in 
Fig. 4
, the experimental ECD curve of 
1
matched well with the calculated ECD curve for (7 
R
,10 
S
)- 
1a
, which indicated that 
1
possessed the same corresponding absolute configuration (7 
R
,10 
S
). Thus, the structure of 
1
was assigned as depicted, which was a rare 2,3- 
seco
-guaiane-type sesquiterpenoid with an 
α
-pyrone core.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Sesquistrachanoid B (
2
) possessed a molecular formula of C 
15
H 
22
O 
3
with five degrees of unsaturation as determined by the HRESIMS ion at 
m
/ 
z
271.1292 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd 271.1305) and 1D NMR data. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data exhibited signals for an isopropenyl and a 3-hydroxyprop-1-en-2-yl, which were further confirmed by the HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
). In addition, signals for one ester carbonyl, one secondary methyl group, three methylenes, three methines, and an oxygenated quaternary carbon were observed in its 1D NMR spectra. The secondary methyl group, three methylenes, and three methines were linked to form a long fragment 
CH
2
(2) 
CH
2
(3) 
CH
(4)[
CH
3
(15)] 
CH
(5) 
CH
2
(6) 
CH
(7) by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations as shown in 
Fig. 2
. The HMBC correlations from H 
2
-6 and H-7 to C-8 as well as H 
2
-12 and H 
2
-13 to C-7 suggested that the ester carbonyl (C-8) and the 3-hydroxyprop-1-en-2-yl group were linked at the C-7 methine. The HMBC correlations from H 
2
-2 and H 
2
-3 to the oxygenated quaternary carbon (C-1) confirmed that there was a carbon bond between C-1 and C-2. The location of the isopropenyl group was assigned at C-1 on the basis of the HMBC correlations from H 
2
-9 and H 
3
-14 to C-1 and H 
2
-2 to C-10. As three of the five degrees of unsaturation were represented by a carbonyl group and two double bonds, the remaining two degrees of unsaturation indicated that compound 
2
was bicyclic system. Subsequently, a 5/6 dicyclic skeleton featured with an 1,8- 
δ
-lactone was constructed on the basis of the chemical shifts of the oxygenated sp 
3
tertiary carbon C-1 (
δ
C
95.7) and the ester carbonyl C-8 (
δ
C
176.0) and the HMBC correlation from H 
2
-2 to C-5 and H 
2
-6 to C-1. In the NOESY spectrum, these key NOE correlations of H-5/H-7 and H-5/H-9a indicated that H-5, H-7, and the isopropenyl group were cofacial and randomly assigned as 
α
-oriented (
Fig. 3
). While the NOE correlations of H 
3
-15/H-6a and H-6b, H 
3
-15/H-3a and 3b, and H-4/H-5 suggested that 
CH
3
-15 was 
β
-equatorial orientation and H-4 was 
α
-oriented. The absolute configuration of 
2
was determined by the TDDFT-ECD method. According to the ECD calculation results (
Fig. 4
), the assignment of the (1 
R
,4 
S
,5 
S
,7 
R
) absolute configuration to compound 
2
was undoubtedly confirmed. Therefore, the structure of sesquistrachanoid B (
2
) was determined as a rare 8,9- 
seco
-guaiane-type sesquiterpenoid featured with an 1,8- 
δ
-lactone core.
</p>
         <p>
Sesquistrachanoid C (
3
) was obtained pale-yellow in color, having a molecular formula of C 
15
H 
20
O 
5
with six degrees of unsaturation as determined by the HRESIMS ion at 
m
/ 
z
303.1218 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd 303.1203) and 1D NMR data. The 
1
H NMR data in CDCl 
3
(
Table 2
) showed the presence of an olefinic proton [
δ
H
5.95 (1H, br. s)], a tertiary methyl [
δ
H
1.58 (3H, s)], two secondary methyls [
δ
H
1.20 (3H, d, 
J
=7.2 Hz) and 0.97 (3H, d, 
J
= 6.8 Hz)], an isolated methylene [
δ
H
3.26 and 2.69 (each 1H, d, 
J
= 12.7 Hz)], and a series of aliphatic multiplets. In combination with the DEPT experiments, the 
13
C NMR data of 
3
(
Table 2
, recorded in CDCl 
3
) revealed 15 carbons including an ester carbonyl (
δ
C
176.3), a trisubstituented double bond [
δ
C
147.9 (C) and 130.6 (
CH
)], three methyls (
δ
C
21.3, 16.3, and 6.9), three methylenes, three methines, and three oxygenated quaternary carbons (including a ketal or hemiketal one at 
δ
C
116.0). This collective information together with the comparison of its 1D NMR data (
Table 2
) with those of the known compound stelleraterpenoid D (

) suggested that 
3
was a guaiane skeleton with an 8,12-γ- lactone. The 
1
H– 
1
H COSY and HMBC correlations as shown in 
Fig. 2
determined that the Δ 
1,10
double bond, the C-7 and C-10 oxygenated quaternary carbons, and the C-8 ketal or hemiketal were present in 
3
. A hydroxyl group was unquestionably located at C-7 by the HMBC correlations from the OH proton [
δ
H
5.82 (1H, s), observed in DMSO‑ 
d
6
] to C-6, C-7, and C-8 as drawn in pink arrows in 
Fig. 2
. By analysis of its degrees of unsaturation data as well as the carbon chemical shifts of C-8 and C-10, it could be confirmed that 
3
had a peroxide bridge between C-8 and C-10, which also satisfied its MS data. The relative configuration of 
3
was assigned by its NOESY spectrum and analysis of its coupling constants. As shown in 
J
6a,6b
= 13.3 Hz) together with the NOE signal of H-6 
β
/H-11 also supported the 
β
-orientations of these two protons. In addition, the NOE correlation of H 
3
-15/H-6 
β
also confirmed the 
α
-orientation of H-4. The experimental ECD curve of 
3
matched well with the calculated ECD curve for 
3a
(4 
S
,5 
S
,7 
S
,8 
R
,10 
S
,11 
R
) (
Fig. 4
), suggesting that they shared the same (4 
S
,5 
S
,7 
S
,8 
R
,10 
S
,11 
R
) absolute configuration. Therefore, the structure of 
3
was deduced as guaiane sesquiterpenoid with a unique peroxide bridge structure.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Recorded in 400 Hz for 
1
H NMR and 100 Hz for 
13
C NMR.
</p>
         <p>
b
Recorded in 500 Hz for 
1
H NMR and 125 Hz for 
13
C NMR.
</p>
         <p>
Sesquistrachanoid D (
4
) exhibited an ion at 
m
/ 
z
301.1410 [M +Na] 
+
(calcd 301.1410), suggesting the molecular formula C 
16
H 
22
O 
4
. By comparison of its 1D NMR data with those of auranticanol F (

), 
4
exhibited a ketocarbonyl (
δ
C
206.8) instead of a methylene in the known compound and had an additional methoxyl group [
δ
C
48.4; 
δ
H
3.27 (3H, s)]. The HMBC correlations from H 
2
-3 and H-4 to the ketocarbonyl and from the protons of the methoxyl group to C-8 indicated that the ketocarbonyl and the methoxyl group were located at C-2 and C-8, respectively. The relative configuration of 
4
was confirmed by NOE correlations (
Fig. 3
) and analysis of its coupling constants. The strong NOE correlation of H-5/H-9 
α
indicated they were cofacial and randomly assigned as 
α
-oriented. The large coupling constants of H-6b at 1.41 ppm (
J
5,6b
= 
J
6a,6b
=13.6 Hz) suggested the relationship of H-5 and H-6b was 
trans
-configuration, so H-6b was assigned as 
β
-oriented. The observed NOE correlation of H 
3
-15/H-6 
β
supported that 
CH
3
-15 was 
β
-oriented while H-4 was 
α
-oriented. The NOE signals of H-3 
β
/H-6 
β
and H-6 
β
/H-13 
β
suggested that 7-OH and 8-OMe groups should be 
α
-oriented. The (4 
S
,5 
S
,7 
S
,8 
R
) absolute configuration of 
4
was determined by comparison of its experimental ECD spectrum with that of the calculated ECD curve for 
4a
(4 
S
,5 
S
,7 
S
,8 
R
) (
Fig. 4
). Thus, the structure of 
4
was defined as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Sesquistrachanoid E (
5
) had a molecular formula C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
as determined by the HRESIMS ion at 
m
/ 
z
261.1821 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd 261.1825) and 1D NMR data. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (
Table 3
) of 
5
showed a high similarity to those of auranticanol L (
18
) (

) with notable differences in the carbon chemical shifts of C-3, C-12, and C-13 being attributable to the orientation of OH-11. The relative configurations of the chiral carbons C-3, C-4, and C-10 of 
5
were confirmed to be the same as 
18
by the NOE correlations (
Fig. 3
). The gauge-independent atomic orbital (GIAO) calculations of the 1D NMR chemical shifts of 3 
S*
,4 
S*
,10 
R*
,11 

S*
-5

and 3 
S*
,4 
S*
,10 
R*
,11 

R*
-5

using density functional theory at the rmpw1pw91/ 
6-31g
(d,p) level in PCM were adopted to validate the relative configuration of C-11 (

S 
2.1

in Supplementary data). The improved probability DP4+ analysis of the experimental and calculated data showed that 3 
S*
,4 
S*
,10 
R*
,11 

S*
-5

(100.00%) had an absolute advantage to that of 3 
S*
,4 
S*
,10 
R*
,11 

R*
-5

(0.00%), which secured the 11 
S
*-configuration of 
5
(

Fig. 

S 
1.3

in Supplementary data). While the 11 
R
*-configuration was assigned to compound 
18
, which was also supported by the DP4+analysis (

Fig. 

S 
1.4

in Supplementary data). The experimental ECD curve of 
5
matched well with the calculated ECD curve for 
5b
(3 
R
,4 
R
,10 
S
,11 
R
) (

Fig. 
S1.5
A

in Supplementary data), suggesting that the absolute configuration of 
5
was determined as 3 
R
,4 
R
,10 
S
,11 
R
. In addition, the (3 
R
,4 
R
,10 
S
,11 
S
) absolute configuration of 
18
was also defined by comparison of its experimental ECD spectrum with that of the calculated ECD curve for 
18b
(3 
R
,4 
R
,10 
S
,11 
S
) (

Fig. 
S1.5
B

in Supplementary data). Thus, the structures of the C-11 epimers 
5
and 
18
were determined as shown.
</p>
         <p>
The
molecular formula of compound 
6
was determined to be C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
by the HRESIMS ion at 
m
/ 
z
261.1828 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd 261.1825) and its 1D NMR data. 
The
1
H NMR data (
Table 3
) displayed signals for four tertiary methyls [
δ
H
1.58, 1.20, 1.15, and 0.72 (each 3H, s)], an olefinic proton [
δ
H
5.22 (1H, br. s)], an oxygenated methine [
δ
H
3.29 (1H, d, 
J
=10.1 Hz)], and two high-field methine protons [
δ
H
0.76 and 0.62 (each 1H, m)]. 
The
observed 15 carbon signals in the 
13
C NMR spectrum were classified into four methyls, a trisubstituented double bond, four methylenes, three methines (including an oxygenated one), and two quaternary carbons (including an oxygenated one) according to the DEPT experiments. 
As
shown in 
Fig. 2
, two fragments 
CH
(3) 
CH
2
(2) 
CH
(1) 
CH
(6) 
CH
2
(5) and 
CH
2
(8) 
CH
2
(9) 
CH
(10) were confirmed by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations. 
According
to the HMBC correlations from H 
3
-15 to C-3, C-4, and C-5, H 
3
-14 to C-1, C-6, C-7, and C-8, and H 
3
-12(13) to C-10 and C-11 (
Fig. 2
), the aforementioned two fragments, four methyls (
CH
3
-12/13/14/15), and three quaternary carbons (C-4/7/11) were constructed to form a sesquicarane-type sesquiterpenoid. 
The
key NOE correlations of H-1/H-8a and H-6/H-8a suggested that H-1, H-6, and the C-8 chain were cofacial and randomly assigned as 
β
-oriented, indicating the 
CH
3
-14 to be 
α
-oriented (
Fig. 3
). 
In
addition, the 10 
S
configuration of 
6
was determined by the 
Mo
2
(OAc) 
4
- induced ECD experiment (

; 

), which displayed the positive 
Cotton
effect at 
316 nm
(Δ 
ε
+2.32) (

Fig. 

S 
1.6

in 
Supplementary
data). Thus, the structure of 
6
was determined as shown and given a trivial name sesquistrachanoid F.
</p>
         <p>
A known alpiniane-type sesquiterpenoid, stellerasespene B (
7
) (

), ten known guaiane-type sesquiterpenoids, 1 
α
,7 
α
, 10 
αH
-guaia-4,11-dien-3-one (
8
) (

), wikstronone A (
9
) (

), stelleraguaianone A (
10
) (

), stelleraguaianone B (
11
) (

), chamaejasmin D (
12
) (

), stelleraterpenoid C (
13
) (

), holosericin B (
14
) (

), chamaejasmone D (
15
) (

), auranticanol A (
16
) (

), and stelleraterpenoid B (
17
) (

), as well as three known carotane-type sesquiterpenoids, auranticanol L (
18
) (

), isodaucene enone (
19
) (

), and auranticanol J (
20
) (

), were also isolated from the roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
. Their structures were identified by analysis of their NMR, ECD, and X-Ray data (

Tables 
S1.2
S1.8

and 

Fig. 
1.7–1.8

in Supplementary data and 
Fig. 5
) together with the 1D NMR and ECD calculation methods (see 
S2.1
and 

S 
2.2

in Supplementary data). It is noteworthy that the (3 
R
,4 
R
,10 
S
) absolute configuration of the known carotanes 
19
and 
20
was determined in current study (

Fig. 

S 
1.9

in Supplementary data).
</p>
         <p>
The neuroprotective effects of compounds 
1–20
were evaluated in the SNP-induced PC-12 cell model. Edaravone (Eda) is a brain protective agent, which is used as a positive control (

; 

</p>
         <p>
2021). As shown in 
Fig. 6A
, the cell viability of the model group (treated with 600 μM SNP) was reduced to about 65%, while the pretreatments of 
5
, 
10
, 
11
, 
15
, 
16
, and 
18
at 10 μM significantly restored the cell viability, being comparable with that of Eda. Moreover, the protective effects of most of these active compounds showed a good dose-dependent manner (
Fig. 6B
). Given the preliminary screening and dose dependency assessment, stelleraguaianone B (
11
), the compound with most pronounced activity, was selected for further mechanistic study.
</p>
         <p>
In SNP-induced PC-12 cell model, nerve cells damage was caused by reactive oxygen species (ROS)-mediated oxidative stress (

; 

), thus we explored the effect of 
11
on this biological process. As shown in 
Fig. 6C
and 
Table 4
, when the PC-12 cells were exposed to SNP, some indicators related to oxidative stress have changed significantly. For example, the levels of ROS and malonic dialdehyde (MDA) showed a remarkable increase, while the levels of glutathione (GSH) and superoxide dismutase (SOD) were substantially reduced. Meanwhile, the intervention of SNP could also lead to the loss of mitochondrial membrane potential (MMP) (
Fig. 6D
). Such abnormal changes in the aforementioned indicators caused by SNP could be significantly reversed by the pretreatment of 
11
(
Fig. 6C and D
and 
Table 4
), which therefore suggests that 
11
could play a protective role by reducing oxidative stress.
</p>
         <p>
Heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1) is an important therapeutic target in neuronal oxidative damage (

). Therefore, we further investigated whether 
11
could affect the level of HO-1. As shown in 
Fig. 6E
, 
11
could dose-dependently up-regulate the mRNA levels of 
Ho-1
, suggesting that 
11
may protect PC-12 cells from oxidative stress damage by promoting the mRNA expression of antioxidant enzymes.
</p>
         <p>
3. Conclusions
</p>
         <p>
In summary, 20 sesquiterpenoids including six undescribed ones named sesquistrachanoids A F were isolated and identified from the roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
. These sesquiterpenoids belong to four different skeleton 
types
, including guaianes (
1–4
and 
8–17
), carotanes (
5
and 
18–20
), sesquicarane (
6
), and alpiniane (
7
). Sesquistrachanoids A (
1
) and (
2
) are rare 2,3- 
seco
- and 8,9- 
seco
-guaiane-type sesquiterpenoids, respectively. Sesquistrachanoid C (
3
) is a unique guaiane sesquiterpenoid characterized by a peroxide bridge between C-8 and C-10. Among them, compounds (
1–6
) and three known ones (
18–20
) were reported for the first time from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
. So far, the number of sesquiterpenoids isolated from the plant has increased to 62, which claims the diversity of sesquiterpenoids in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
to be the most abundant, followed by flavonoids, diterpenoids, lignans, and coumarins (

; 

, 2021). Meanwhile, the neuroprotective effects of sesquiterpenoids 
1–20
against SNP-induced cell damage were evaluated in PC-12 cells and the results showed that six compounds possessed potential activities comparable to that of the positive control. Stelleraguaianone B (
11
) with the most pronounced activity was selected as the representative for the preliminary mechanism study, which showed that its protective effects on SNP-induced PC-12 cells were achieved by promoting the mRNA expression of antioxidant enzymes to reduce oxidative stress. These isolated sesquiterpenoids covering guaiane-type, 2,3- 
seco
- and 8,9- 
seco
-guaiane-type, carotane-type, sesquicarane-type, and alpiniane-type from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
do not only expand the structural diversity of sesquiterpenoids but also provide material basis for the development of neuroprotective lead compounds.
</p>
         <p>
4. Experimental
</p>
         <p>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</p>
         <p>X-ray single crystal diffraction was performed on an Agilent Xcalibur</p>
         <p>
Nova X-ray diffractometer (Santa Clara, CA, 
USA
). Optical rotations were obtained on an Anton Paar MCP200 polarimeter (Graz, 
Austria
). UV spectra were measured on a Shimadzu UV-2450 spectrophotometer (
Kyoto
, 
Japan
), and ECD spectra were determined on an Applied Photophysics Chirascan spectrometer (Leatherhead, 
Surrey
, 
UK
). IR (KBr disks) spectra were recorded on a Bruker Tensor 37 infrared spectrophotometer (Madison, WI, 
USA
). 1D and 2D NMR spectra were measured on Bruker Avance III 400 (
Zurich
, 
Switzerland
) and Bruker Ascend TM 500 (Rheinstetten, 
Germany
) spectrometers at 25 
◦
C with TMS as the internal standard. HRESIMS were determined on a Waters Micromass Q-TOF spectrometer (Milford, MA, 
USA
). HPLC using a NanoChrom ChromCoreTM 5–120 C18 column (10 × 
250 mm
, 5 μm), or a YMC-pack ODS-A column (10 × 
250 mm
, S-5 μm), or a Phenomenex Lux cellulose-2 chiral column (10 × 
250 mm
, 5 μm) was performed on a Shimadzu LC-20 AT with an SPD-M20A PDA detector (
Kyoto
, 
Japan
). D101 macroporous resin (Donghong Chemical Co., Ltd.), silica gel (100–200 and 300–400 mesh, Qingdao Haiyang Chemical Co., Ltd.), Sephadex LH-20 gel (Amersham Biosciences), and reversed-phase C 
18
(Rp-C 
18
) silica gel (
12 nm
, S-50 μm, YMC Co., Ltd.) were used for column chromatography (CC). Acetonitrile (MeCN) was of HPLC grade (Grace Chemical Technology Co., Ltd.) and other chemical solvents were of analytical grade (Guangzhou Chemical Reagents Company, Ltd.).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
*p 
&lt;
0.05, **p 
&lt;
0.01, and ***p 
&lt;
0.001 compared with SNP alone group.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
The concentration of SNP was 600 μM. Data represent the M ±SD of at least three independent experiments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>

The roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stellera chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Thymelaeaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) were obtained in 

November 2020

(dry season) from Kunming City, 
Yunnan Province
, P. R. 
China
. It was identified by one of the authors (
G.-H. Tang
) and the voucher specimen (accession number: YSCT202011) was deposited at the 
School of Pharmaceutical Sciences
, Sun Yat-sen University

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The dried roots of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chamaejasme
</tp:taxon-name>
(
40 kg
) were extracted with 95% EtOH (100 L × 3) at room temperature. After removing the EtOH solvent under vacuum, the residue (
8.5 kg
) was suspended in an appropriate amount H 
2
O and successively extracted with petroleum ether (PE, 20 L × 3) and EtOAc (20 L × 3). The EtOAc part (
3.2 kg
) was chromatographed over silica gel CC eluted with PE/EtOAc (50:1 → 0:1) to give four fractions (I IV). Fr. II (
400 g
) was chromatographed over D101 column (MeOH/H 
2
O, 50%→100%) to yield three sub-fractions (Frs. IIA IIC). Frs. A and B were applied to repeated silica gel columns, Sephadex LH-20 column, RP-C 
18
column, and semipreparative HPLC to obtain compounds 
12
(
210 mg
), 
11
(
1.9 g
), 
13
(
176 mg
), 
2
(
2.1 mg
), 
8
(
9.2 mg
), 
9
(
2.3 mg
), and 
14
(
8.2 mg
). Fr. III was subjected to CC over D101 column eluted with MeOH/H 
2
O (50%→100%) to give four sub-fractions (Frs. IIIA IIID). Frs. IIIA IIIC were chromatographed over silica gel column, RP-C 
18
column, Sephadex LH-20, and semipreparative HPLC to obtain compounds 
5
(
120 mg
), 
3
(9.0 mg), 
6
(
31 mg
), 
18
(
150 mg
), 
7
(
1.2 mg
), 
1
(
1.3 mg
), 
4
(1.0 mg), 
10
(
2.8 mg
), 
20
(
138 mg
), 
15
(
206 mg
), 
16
(
89 mg
), 
17
(
200 mg
), and 
19
(
30 mg
). More details on isolation of compounds 
1–20
are provided in 

Fig. 
S1.10

(Supplementary data).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Sesquistrachanoid a (1)
</title>
         <p>
Pale-yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
+24.7 (
c
0.3, 
CH
3
CN); UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 300 (4.25), 197 (3.67) nm; ECD (
c
1.7 × 10 
3
M, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 197 (3.01), 217 (+2.07), 251 (+1.16), 291 (+0.74) nm; IR (KBr) 
u
max
3432, 2931, 2860, 1671, 1454, 1376, 
1081 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m
/ 
z
271.1292 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
15
H 
20
O 
3
Na 
+
, 271.1305).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. Sesquistrachanoid B (2)
</title>
         <p>
Pale-yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
+17.0 (
c
0.3, 
CH
3
CN); UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 210 (4.28), 190 (4.20) nm; ECD (
c
2.0 × 10 
3
M, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 199 (1.18), 227 (+3.18) nm; IR (KBr) 
u
max
3439, 2935, 1738, 
1036, 900 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m
/ 
z
273.1466 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
15
H 
22
O 
3
Na 
+
, 273.1461).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. Sesquistrachanoid C (3)
</title>
         <p>
Pale-yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
+34.7 (
c
0.3, 
CH
3
CN); UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 194 (4.20) nm; ECD (
c
1.7 × 10 
3
M, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 190 (5.29), 205 (+3.19), 226 (1.02), 259 (+0.26) nm; IR (KBr) 
u
max
3424, 2926, 1789, 
1716, 968 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m
/ 
z
303.1218 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
15
H 
20
O 
5
Na 
+
, 303.1203).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.4. Sesquistrachanoid D (4)
</title>
         <p>
Pale-yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
9.0 (
c
0.3, 
CH
3
CN); UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 333 (3.36), 251 (4.03), 194 (4.50) nm; ECD (
c
2.0 × 10 
3
M, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 190 (1.07), 202 (+0.52), 231 (0.76), 360 (0.18) nm; IR (KBr) 
u
max
3417, 2926, 1706, 1631, 
1031, 736 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m
/ 
z
301.1410 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
16
H 
22
O 
4
Na 
+
, 301.1410).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.5. Sesquistrachanoid E (5)
</title>
         <p>
Pale-yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
1.0 (
c
0.3, 
CH
3
CN); UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 194 (4.28) nm; ECD (
c
1.5 × 10 
3
M, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 197 (1.40), 294
</p>
         <p>
(+0.07) nm; IR (KBr) 
u
max
3392, 2931, 1704, 1452, 1381, 
1046, 739 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 3
; HRESIMS 
m
/ 
z
261.1821 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
Na 
+
, 261.1825).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.6. Sesquistrachanoid F (6)
</title>
         <p>
Pale-yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
12.7 (
c
0.3, 
CH
3
CN); UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 195 (4.66) nm; ECD (
c
1.9 × 10 
3
M, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 197 (2.58), 217 (+1.77), 291 (+0.63) nm; IR (KBr) 
u
max
3392, 2971, 2931, 1714, 1670, 1379, 
1076 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 3
; HRESIMS 
m
/ 
z
261.1828 [M +Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
Na 
+
, 261.1825).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.7. Stellerasespene B (7)
</title>
         <p>
Pale-yellow oil; UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 243 (3.20) nm; ECD (
c
1.9 × 10 
3
M, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δ 
ε
) 193 (+9.39), 220 (8.60), 248 (5.78), 290 (+3.57) nm; IR (KBr) 
u
max
2928, 2858, 1706, 1651, 
1437, 892 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 

Table 
S2.1

; HRESIMS 
m
/ 
z
255.1350 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
15
H 
20
O 
2
Na 
+
, 255.1356).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Determination of the absolute configuration of 10,11-diol moiety in 6
</title>
         <p>
using the Snatzke’ s method
</p>
         <p>
According to the reported procedure (

), a diol/dimolybdenum tetraacetate mixture (1:1) was prepared using 
0.5 mg
/mL of the chiral substrate (
6
) in DMSO. After mixing, the ECD spectrum was measured from 
250 to 400 nm
at room temperature and its evolution monitored until stationary (30–40 min).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. X-ray crystallographic analysis
</title>
         <p>

At room temperature, compounds 
12
and 
13
were crystallized from EtOH/H 
2
O (3:7). Crystallographic data (see 

Tables 
S1.7
and 

S 
1.8

in 
Supplementary
data for X-ray 
Crystallographic
data details) for chamaejasmin D (
12
) and stelleraterpenoid C (
13
) have CCDC numbers 2211876 and 2211874 at the 
Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre
, respectively

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. NMR and ECD calculations
</title>
         <p>
For details of NMR calculation for compounds 
5
and 
7
and ECD calculation for compounds 

1 
–
5

, 
7
, 
18
, and 
19
, see S 
2 in
Supplementary data.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Biological assay materials
</title>
         <p>
SNP and Eda was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, 
USA
). Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) was acquired from MP Biomedicals (Irvine, 
USA
). Dulbecco’ s Modified Eagle’ s Medium (DMEM), fetal bovine serum (FBS), horse serum (HS), penicillin-streptomycin, and Trypsin-EDTA were purchased from Gibco (
Maryland
, 
USA
). The superoxide dismutase (SOD, S0101S), malondialdehyde (MDA, S0131S), and glutathione (GSH, (S0053) assay kits, thiazolyl blue tetrazolium bromide (MTT), as well as phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) were obtained from Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology (Nanjing, 
Jiangsu
, 
China
). JC-1 assay kit was purchased from KeyGen Biotech (Nanjing, 
Jiangsu
, 
China
), and RNeasy Plus Mini kit, cDNA synthesis kit, qPCR kit, and PrimeScript RT-PCR kit were from Yeasen (
Shanghai
, 
China
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Cell culture
</title>
         <p>
The PC-12 cell line was purchased from the Laboratory Animal Center of Sun Yat-sen University (Guangzhou, 
Guangdong
, 
China
). Cells were maintained in DMEM containing HS and FBS (each 5%), and incubated in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO 
2
at 37 
◦
C.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.9. Cell viability assay
</title>
         <p>
The cell viability of PC-12 was determined using the MTT assay. Briefly, PC-12 cells (5 × 10 
3
cells/well) were cultured in 96-well plates for 24 h. The cells were then pretreated with different concentrations of samples including the positive drug (Eda) for 2 h followed by adding 600 μM SNP to co-incubate for additional 24 h. Afterwards, MTT (
5 mg
/ mL) was added to each well and incubated for 3.5 h. The supernatant was discarded and 100 μL of DMSO per well was added to each well to thoroughly dissolve the dark blue crystals. The absorbance was measured at 
570 nm
using a multifunctional microplate reader (BioTek).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.10. Detecting of ROS levels
</title>
         <p>
PC-12 cells were seeded into glass-bottomed cell culture dishes for culturing 24 h. Then, the cells were pretreated without or with 
11
(10 μM) for 2 h followed by incubation in the present of 600 μM SNP for 24 h. After changing to serum-free medium, the cells were co-incubated with 20 μM 2 
′
,7 
′
-dichlorodi-hydrofluorescein diacetate (DCFH-DA) in the dark for 30 min. Subsequently, the medium was removed and the cells were washed twice with PBS. The relative fluorescence intensities of ROS were detected using a fluorescence microscope (Olympus, FV3000, 
Japan
) with excitation wavelength at 
488 nm
and emission wavelength at 
525 nm
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.11. Detecting the levels of GSH, MDA, and SOD
</title>
         <p>
PC-12 cells were seeded in 6-well plates for 24 h. After the pretreatment of the cells with or without 
11
(10 μM) for 2 h, 600 μM SNP was added to each well for another 24 h incubation. Finally, the SOD, MDA and GSH levels were measured using the SOD, MDA, and GSH assay kits, respectively, according to the manufacturer’ s instructions.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.12. Mitochondrial membrane potential detection
</title>
         <p>
The effect of 
11
on MMP was determined using a JC-1 assay kit. PC-12 cells at a density of 1 × 10 
4
cells were cultured in 
20 mm
Laser confocal dishes for 24 h. Then, the cells were pretreated without or with 
11
(10 μM) for 2 h, followed by incubation in the present of 600 μM SNP for 24 h. Subsequently, according to the protocol of the JC-1 assay kit, a detailed procedure was implemented. The fluorescence density images were captured using an OLYMPUS FV3000 laser scanning confocal microscope.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.13. Quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) assay
</title>
         <p>
The extraction of total RNA was performed via a RNeasy Plus Mini kit. Reverse transcription was then performed via the cDNA synthesis kit. Next, the target gene 
Ho-1
was quantitatively analyzed by qPCR and PrimeScript RT-PCR kits. Relative fold changes were calculated by the 2 
ΔΔCt
method. 
Gapdh
was used as the reference for normalization. The primer sequences of each gene are provided in 

Table 
S2.9

(see Supplementary data).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Data availability
</p>
         <p>Data will be made available on request.</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgements
</p>
         <p>
The authors thank the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(81973203, 81973195, and 82273804), the 
Guangdong
Basic and Applied Basic Research Foundation, 
China
(2020A1515010841), the Key-Area Research and Development Program of 
Guangdong Province
, 
China
(2020B1111110003), and the Open Program of Shenzhen Bay Laboratory (SZBL2021080601007) for providing financial support for this work. We also thank Dr. Abrar Ahmed from 
Punjab
University College of Pharmacy, University of the 
Punjab
, 
Pakistan
, for polishing the article.
</p>
         <p>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</p>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2023.113588.</p>
         <p>
References
</p>
         <p>
Aladedunye, F.A.
, 
Benn, M.H.
, 
Okorie, D.A.
, 
2008
. 

Sesquiterpenes from 
Culcasia scandens
P

. 
Beauv. Nat. Prod. Res.
22
, 
879–883
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 14786410701642490
.

</p>
         <p>
Bari, L.D.
, 
Pescitelli, G.
, 
Pratelli, C.
, 
Pini, D.
, 
Salvadori, P.
, 
2001
. 
Determination of absolute configuration of acyclic 1,2-diols with Mo2(OAc)4. 1. Snatzke’ s method revisited
. 
J. Org. Chem.
66
, 
4819–4825
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jo010136v
.

</p>
         <p>
Cheng, Z.Y.
, 
Hou, Z.L.
, 
Ren, J.X.
, 
Zhang, D.D.
, 
Lin, B.
, 
Huang, X.X.
, 
Song, S.J.
, 
2021
. 

Guaiane-type sesquiterpenoids from the roots of 
Stellera chamaejasme
L. and their neuroprotective activities

. 
Phytochemistry
183
, 
112628
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2020.112628
.

</p>
         <p>
Cheng, Z.Y.
, 
Zhang, D.D.
, 
Ren, J.X.
, 
Li, Y.L.
, 
Yao, G.D.
, 
Song, S.J.
, 
Huang, X.X.
, 
2022
. 

Stellerasespenes A‒E: sesquiterpenoids from 
Stellera chamaejasme
and their antineuroinflammatory effects

. 
Phytochemistry
201
, 
113275
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ j.phytochem.2022.113275
.

</p>
         <p>
Cho, N.
, 
Yang, H.
, 
Lee, M.
, 
Huh, J.
, 
Kim, H.W.
, 
Kim, H.P.
, 
Sung, S.H.
, 
2013
. 

Neuroprotective benzyl benzoate glycosides from 
Disporum viridescens
roots in HT22 hippocampal neuronal cells

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
76
, 
2291–2297
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ np400676b
.

</p>
         <p>
El-Desoky, A.H.H.
, 
Eguchi, K.
, 
Kato, H.
, 
Kishimoto, N.
, 
Misumi, S.
, 
Watanabe, T.
, 
Tsukamoto, S.
, 
2020
. 

Chamaejasmins, cytotoxic guaiane sesquiterpenes from the root of 
Stellera chamaejasme
L

. 
Fitoterapia
146
, 
104714
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. fitote.2020.104714
.

</p>
         <p>
He, J.
, 
Xu, J.K.
, 
Liu, S.N.
, 
Yang, Y.F.
, 
Zhang, W.K.
, 
2018
. 

A new guaiane sesquiterpene from rhizome of 
Stellera chamaejasme

. 
Chin. Tradit. Herb. Drugs
49
, 
5235–5237
. 
https://doi.org/10.7501/j.issn.0253-2670.2018.22.002
.

</p>
         <p>
Hu, F.F.
, 
Qi, D.D.
, 
Xu, S.
, 
Mao, W.
, 
2021
. 

A new 11,10-guaiane-type sesquiterpenoid from the roots of 
Stellera chamaejasme
Linn

. 
J. Chem. Res.
45
, 
225–227
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1177/1747519820961047
.

</p>
         <p>
Huang, S.Z.
, 
Zhang, X.
, 
Ma, Q.Y.
, 
Zheng, Y.T.
, 
Dai, H.F.
, 
Wang, Q.
, 
Zhou, J.
, 
Zhao, Y.X.
, 
2015
. 

Anti-HIV terpenoids from 
Daphne aurantiaca
Diels. stems

. 
RSC Adv.
5
, 
80254–80263
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/C5RA17099K
.

</p>
         <p>
Jing, C.X.
, 
Guo, J.J.
, 
Yang, B.J.
, 
Fan, S.R.
, 
Wang, Y.T.
, 
Chen, D.Z.
, 
Hao, X.J.
, 
2019
. 

Stelleraguaianone B and C, two new sesquiterpenoids from 
Stellera chamaejasme
L

. 
Fitoterapia
134
, 
443–446
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2019.03.024
.

</p>
         <p>
Li, X.Q.
, 
Rahman, K.
, 
Zhu, J.Y.
, 
Zhang, H.
, 
2018
. 

Chemical constituents and pharmacological activities of 
Stellera chamaejasme

. 
Curr. Pharmaceut. Des.
24
, 
2825–2838
. 

https://doi.org/10.2174/ 
1381612824666180903110802

.

</p>
         <p>
Liao, L.P.
, 
Jiang, C.B.
, 
Chen, J.W.
, 
Shi, J.G.
, 
Li, X.H.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
Wen, J.
, 
Zhou, S.J.
, 
Liang, J.
, 
Lao, Y.Q.
, 
Zhang, J.X.
, 
2020
. 
Synthesis and biological evaluation of 1,2,4- triazole derivatives as potential neuroprotectant against ischemic brain injury
. 
Eur. J. Med. Chem.
190
, 
112114
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2020.112114
.

</p>
         <p>
Lin, R.W.
, 
Tsai, I.L.
, 
Duh, C.Y.
, 
Lee, K.H.
, 
Chen, I.S.
, 
2004
. 

New lignans and cytotoxic constituents from 
Wikstroemia lanceolata

. 
Planta Med.
70
, 
234–238
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1055/s-2004-815540
.

</p>
         <p>
Liu, L.P.
, 
Han, K.
, 
Chen, W.
, 
Zhang, Y.Y.
, 
Tong, L.J.
, 
Peng, T.
, 
Xie, H.
, 
Ding, J.
, 
Wang, H. B.
, 
2014
. 

Topoisomerase II inhibitors from the roots of 
Stellera chamaejasme
L

. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem.
22
, 
4198–4203
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2014.05.042
.

</p>
         <p>
Liu, Z.H.
, 
Dong, M.Y.
, 
Chang, H.
, 
Han, N.
, 
Yin, J.
, 
2020
. 

Guaiane type of sesquiterpene with NO inhibitory activity from the root of 
Wikstroemia indica

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
99
, 
103785
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bioorg.2020.103785
.

</p>
         <p>
Luo, S.Y.
, 
Pu, R.
, 
Tang, Y.Q.
, 
Fan, R.Z.
, 
Yin, S.
, 
Tang, G.H.
, 
2020
. 

Euphane- and 19 (10→9) 
abeo
-euphane-type triterpenoids from 
Jatropha gossypiifolia

. 
Fitoterapia
143
, 
104582
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2020.104582
.

</p>
         <p>
Pan, J.
, 
Su, J.C.
, 
Liu, Y.H.
, 
Deng, B.
, 
Hu, Z.F.
, 
Wu, J.L.
, 
Xia, R.F.
, 
Chen, C.
, 
He, Q.
, 
Chen, J.C.
, 
Wan, L.S.
, 
2021
. 

Stelleranoids A‒M, guaiane-type sesquiterpenoids based on [5,7] bicyclic system from 
Stellera chamaejasme
and their cytotoxic activity

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
115
, 
105251
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bioorg.2021.105251
.

</p>
         <p>
Qiao, L.
, 
Yang, L.
, 
Zhang, D.
, 
Zuo, J.
, 
Dai, J.
, 
2011
. 

Studies on chemical constitutes from cell cultures of 
Stellera chamaejasme
. China J

. 
Chin. Mater. Med.
36
, 
3457–3462
. 
https://doi.org/10.4268/cjcmm20112415
.

</p>
         <p>
Shi, J.G.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
Chen, J.W.
, 
Lao, Y.Q.
, 
Huang, P.
, 
Liao, L.P.
, 
Jiang, C.B.
, 
Li, X.H.
, 
Wen, J.
, 
Zhou, S.J.
, 
Zhang, J.X.
, 
2021
. 
Synthesis and biological evaluation of 1,2,4- oxadiazole core derivatives as potential neuroprotectants against acute ischemic stroke
. 
Neurochem. Int.
148
, 
105103
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. neuint.2021.105103
.

</p>
         <p>
Tang, G.H.
, 
Chen, Z.W.
, 
Lin, T.T.
, 
Tan, M.
, 
Gao, X.Y.
, 
Bao, J.M.
, 
Cheng, Z.B.
, 
Sun, Z.H.
, 
Huang, G.
, 
Yin, S.
, 
2015
. 

Neolignans from 
Aristolochia fordiana
prevent oxidative stress-induced neuronal death through maintaining the Nrf2/HO-1 pathway in HT22 cells

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
78
, 
1894
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.5b00220
, 903.

</p>
         <p>
Wang, Y.
, 
Michael, G.G.
, 
Brian, M.
, 
Christopher, D.B.
, 
Lorin, I.N.
, 
2007
. 
Thymelaeaceae
. 
Flora of China
13
, pp. 
213–250
. 
http://www.iplant.cn/foc/pdf/Thymelaeaceae.pdf
.

</p>
         <p>
Weng, H.Z.
, 
Zhu, J.Y.
, 
Yuan, F.Y.
, 
Tang, Z.Y.
, 
Tian, X.Q.
, 
Chen, Y.
, 
Fan, C.Q.
, 
Tang, G.H.
, 
Yin, S.
, 
2022
. 

Homo/hetero-dimers of aromatic bisabolane sesquiterpenoids with neuroprotective activity from the fungus 
Aspergillus versicolor
A18 from south China sea. Mar

. 
Drugs
20
, 
322
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/md20050322
.

</p>
         <p>
Wu, M.
, 
Shao, J.
, 
Zhu, J.
, 
Zi, J.
, 
2022
. 

Chamaejasnoids A‒E, a 2,3- 
seco
-guaiane sesquiterpenoid with a 5/6/7 bridged ring system and related metabolites from 
Stellera chamaejasme
L

. 
Fitoterapia
158
, 
105171
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. fitote.2022.105171
.

</p>
         <p>
Xia, C.L.
, 
Tang, G.H.
, 
Guo, Y.Q.
, 
Xu, Y.K.
, 
Huang, Z.S.
, 
Yin, S.
, 
2019
. 

Mulberry Diels- Alder-type adducts from 
Morus alba
as multi-targeted agents for Alzheimer’ s disease

. 
Phytochemistry
157
, 
82–91
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.10.028
.

</p>
         <p>
Yuan, F.Y.
, 
Tang, Z.Y.
, 
Huang, D.
, 
Li, W.
, 
Wu, S.Q.
, 
Huang, J.L.
, 
Yan, X.L.
, 
Fan, R.Z.
, 
Tang, G.H.
, 
Yin, S.
, 
2022
. 

Tigliane and rhamnofolane glycosides from 
Euphorbia wallichii
prevent oxidative stress-induced neuronal death in PC-12 cells

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
128
, 
106103
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bioorg.2022.106103
.

</p>
         <p>Zhang, N., He, J., Xia, C.Y., Lian, W.W., Yan, Y., Ding, K., Zhang, Y.Y., Xu, J.K.,</p>
         <p>
Zhang, W.K.
, 
2021
. 

Ethnopharmacology, phytochemistry, pharmacology, clinical applications and toxicology of the genus 
Stellera
Linn.: a review

. 
J. Ethnopharmacol.
264
, 
112915
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2020.112915
.

</p>
         <p>
Zhang, Q.
, 
Du, Y.
, 
Cheng, Z.
, 
Huang, X.
, 
Song, S.
, 
2018
. 

Studies on the chemical components and biological activities of 
Stellera chamaejasme
L

. 
Asian J. Tradit. Medicines
13
, 
49–59
. 
http://asianjtm.syphu.edu.cn/EN/Y2018/V13/I1/49
.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
