<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112977</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Long-chain fatty acid acylated derivatives of isoflavone glycosides from the rhizomes of Iris domestica</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Belamcanda chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>I. domestica</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Belamcanda chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Long-chain fatty acid acylated derivatives of isoflavone glycosides from the rhizomes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Jiayuan Li, Gang Ni, Yanfei Liu, Renzhong Wang, Dequan Yu
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

State Key Laboratory of Bioactive Substance and Function of Natural Medicines, Institute of Materia Medica, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Peking Union Medical College, Beijing, 100050, People’ s 
Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Long-chain fatty acid derivatives Cytotoxicity</p>
         <p>Antioxidation</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
Six undescribed long-chain fatty acid esters of isoflavone glycosides were obtained from the rhizomes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
(L.). Their structures were elucidated by comprehensive spectroscopic data, alkaline hydrolysis, and acid hydrolysis. This is the first report of the long-chain (C 
14
–C 
18
) fatty acid derivatives of isoflavone glycosides from natural products. Belamcandnoate B and D exhibited moderate cytotoxic activities against HCT-116, HepG2, and BGC823 cell lines with IC 
50
values of 1.69–6.86 
μ
M. Belamcandnoate B and E exhibited 72.27 and 58.98% inhibitory activities, respectively, against Fe 
2+
/cysteine-induced liver microsomal lipid peroxidation at a concentration of 10 
μ
M.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) Goldblatt &amp; Mabb [the name 
<tp:taxon-name>
Belamcanda chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) DC (
<tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) was recorded in Chinese Pharmacopoeia for 2020] belongs to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
and is widely distributed in eastern Asia. Its rhizomes have been historically used as a traditional Chinese folk medicine to treat sore throat, cough, tonsillitis and pharyngitis (

). Pharmacological research has shown that 
<tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
is often used with other herbs as antipyretic agents, antidotes, expectorants, antiphlogistics, and analgesics (

). Prior phytochemical investigation of this plant demonstrates that flavonoids, especially isoflavones, are the primary active ingredient of 
<tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
(Wo´zniak and Matkowski, 2015). Isoflavones and their glycosides, such as tectorigenin, irigenin, tectoridin, iridin, and irisflorentin, possess a wide range of biological activities, such as anti-inflammatory (

), antioxidative (

), antiviral (

), antibacterial (

), and antitumor (

) activities. However, the applications of diverse and bioactive flavones are often limited by their poor solubility in both hydrophobic and hydrophilic media. Therefore, modification of flavonoid glycosides via acylation has become a promising approach. Previous studies have shown that fatty acid acylated flavonoid glycosides improve the lipophilicity, and biological activities of the parent flavones (

; 

; 

; 

,b; 

).
</p>
         <p>
To date, chemical, enzymatic and chemoenzymatic acylation of flavonoids and dihydrochalcone with various acyl donors (C2–C18 chain length) has been reported (

, 2016; 

; Ziaullah et al., 2013). However, there are no reports about long-chain (C 
14
–C 
18
) fatty acid esters of isoflavone glycosides isolated from natural products. The rich isoflavones in 
<tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
enable us to obtain the chain length of fatty acid derivatives of isoflavone glycosides from this plant. In the course of our ongoing search for structurally unique and biologically diverse metabolites, six undescribed long-chain fatty acid acylated derivatives of isoflavone glycosides (
Fig. 1
) were isolated from the rhizomes of 

<tp:taxon-name>I. domestica</tp:taxon-name>
.

Acylation occurs at C-6 of glucoside, and the chain length of fatty acids as acyl donors is from C14 to C18. In addition, in an 
in vitro
bioassay, the cytotoxic, antioxidative, and anti-inflammatory activities of the isolated compounds are evaluated. Here, we describe the isolation, structural elucidation, and bioactive evaluation of compounds 
1–6
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
Belamcandnoate A (
1
) was obtained as a pale yellow oil (MeOH). Its molecular formula, C 
37
H 
50
O 
13
, was determined by the HRESIMS ion at [M + H] 
+
m/z
703.33234 (calcd 703.33242), which indicated 13 indices of hydrogen deficiency. 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) also exhibited five hydroxyl groups at 
δ
H
12.92 (1H, s, OH-5), 9.09 (1H, s, OH-3 
′
), 5.57 (1H, d, 
J
= 5.8 Hz, OH-2 
′′
), 5.38 (1H, d, 
J
= 6.4 Hz, OH-4 
′′
), 5.31 (1H, m, OH-3 
′′
), including two hydroxyl groups at the aromatic ring. A characteristic singlet at 
δ
H
8.45 (1H, s, H-2) implies that 
1
is an isoflavone. The aromatic signals at 
δ
H
7.04 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.3 Hz, H-2 
′
) and 6.96 (2H, m, H-6 
′
, 5 
′
) show the presence of an ABX aromatic system. An aromatic proton singlet at 
δ
H
6.85 (1H, s, H-8) is observed, which suggest the presence of a trisubstituted aromatic ring A. Two methoxyl groups at 
δ
H
3.79 (3H, s, OMe-4 
′
) and 3.75 (3H, s, OMe-6) are assigned. The anomeric proton signal at 5.16 (1H, d, 
J
= 8.8 Hz, H-1 
′′
), an isolated methylene at 
δ
H
4.29 (1H, dd, 
J
= 14.5, 1.9 Hz, H-6 
′′
a), 4.09 (1H, dd, 
J
= 14.5, 9.5 Hz, H-6 
′′
b), and four methines at 
δ
H
3.75 (1H, m, H-5 
′′
), 3.36 (1H, m, H-2 
′′
), 3.31 (1H, m, H-3 
′′
), 3.18 (1H, m, H-4 
′′
) demonstrate the presence of a 
β
-glucopyranosyl unit. These signals at 
δ
H
0.84 (3H, t, 
J
= 8.5 Hz, H-16 
′′′
), 2.26 (2H, m, H-2 
′′′
), and partially overlapping aliphatic protons at 
δ
H
1.24–1.07 are characteristic of fatty acids. Based on the HSQC spectrum, the 
13
C NMR data identified 37 resonances, which were categorized as a ketone carbonyl at 
δ
C
180.7 (C-3); an ester carbonyl at 
δ
C
172.8 (C-1 
′′′
); seven oxygenated aromatic carbons at 
δ
C
156.4 (C-7), 154.9 (C- 2), 153.0 (C-5), 152.4 (C-9), 146.2 (C-3 
′
), 147.8 (C-4 
′
), 132.5 (C-6); seven aromatic carbons at 
δ
C
122.0 (C-3), 123.1 (C-1 
′
), 119.7 (C-6 
′
), 116.3 (C-2 
′
), 111.9 (C-5 
′
), 106.6 (C-10), 94.0 (C-8); a glucosyl group at 
δ
C
99.7 (C-1 
′′
), 76.4 (C-3 
′′
), 73.8 (C-5 
′′
), 73.0 (C-2 
′′
), 70.1 (C-4 
′′
), 63.4 (C- 6 
′′
); as well as some partially overlapping aliphatic carbons at 
δ
C
22.1–33.5. A detailed comparison of the spectroscopic data of 
1
with those of the known isoflavone iristectorin A (

) indicates that compound 
1
is a long-chain fatty acid acylated derivative of iristectorin A. The HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
) from OMe (
δ
H
3.79) to C-4 
′
and from OMe (
δ
H
3.75) to C-6, along with the NOESY correlations from OMe (
δ
H
3.79) to H-5 
′
and from OMe (
δ
H
3.75) to H-1 
′′
indicate that two methoxyl groups are located at C-4 
′
and C-6, respectively, which further confirms the presence of iristectorin A. The HMBC correlation from H-6 
′′
to C-1 
′′′
indicates that the acylated site is located on OH-6’’. Analysis of the unsaturation of 
1
reveals that the long-chain fatty acid is saturated.
</p>
         <p>
To determine the length of the fatty acid, alkaline hydrolysis by NaOH was used. Analysis of the alkaline hydrolysis products by LC–MS, reveals the molecular formulas of C 
23
H 
24
O 
12
(MW: 492) and C 
14
H 
28
O 
2
(MW: 228), which indicates the presence of myristic acid. Subsequently, the products of alkaline hydrolysis for 
1
were isolated to yield the pure compound iristectorin A with a molecular weight of 492. For compound 
1
, the characteristic signal of an anomeric proton with the coupling constant 
J
′′ 
H-1 -2’’
= 8.8 Hz demonstrates that the relative configuration of pyranohexose is 
β
(

; 

). The absolute configuration of glucopyranosyl is defined by the GC analysis of products from the acid hydrolysis and derivatization reactions by L-cysteine methyl ester hydrochloride and trimethylsilylimidazole of iristectorin A. The acid hydrolysis result indicates that glucopyranosyl is D-glc. Therefore, 
1
originated from iristectorin A esterified by myristic acid. Compound 
1
was named Belamcandnoate A.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
2
was obtained as a pale yellow oil (MeOH). Its molecular formula, C 
38
H 
52
O 
14
, was deduced from the HRESIMS ion at [M + H] 
+
m/z
733.34265 (calcd 733.34298), which indicated 13 indices of hydrogen deficiency. Compared with the corresponding NMR signals of 
1
, there are spectroscopic differences due to AB aromatic system signals at 
δ
H
6.72 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.3 Hz, H-6 
′
), 6.66 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.3 Hz, H-2 
′
), 
δ
C
104.4 (C-2 
′
), 110.4 (C-6 
′
) and a methoxyl group at 
δ
H
3.78 (3H, s), 
δ
C
55.9 (-OCH 
3
). The methoxyl group is ascribed to C-5 
′
based on the HMBC correlations from 
δ
H
3.78 to C-5 
′
and C-2’. The above mentioned data demonstrate that the isoflavone glycoside is iridin (

). The sugar of 
2
is defined as glucopranosyl by comparing the NMR data with those of glycosides in the literature (

; 

). 
1
H NMR data of 
2
display an anomeric proton signal at 
δ
H
5.16 (1H, d, 
J
= 8.6 Hz, H-1 
′′
), which reveals the 
β
-configuration of glucose (
J
′′ 
1 -2’’
&gt;
7 Hz) (

). Using the GC analysis of acid hydrolysis products of iridin, the absolute configuration of the sugar unit is determined to be the D-configuration. Analysis of the alkaline hydrolysis products for 
2
by LC–MS, reveals the same molecular weights of mw = 522 (C 
24
H 
26
O 
13
) and mw = 228 (C 
14
H 
28
O 
2
) as 
1
, which indicates that iridin is esterified by myristic acid. Thus, compound 
2
was named Belamcandnoate B.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
3
was isolated as a pale oil. HRESIMS indicates a proton adduct ion [M + H] 
+
at 
m/z
723.33417 (calcd 723.33510), which corresponds to a molecular formula of C 
38
H 
52
O 
12
with 13 indices of hydrogen deficiency. Examination of the NMR data of compounds 
3
and 
1
indicates that the differences between the two compounds can be attributed to an A’ A’ B’ B’ aromatic system with signals at 
δ
H
7.38 (2H, d, 
J
= 10.3 Hz, H-2 
′
, 6 
′
), 6.82 (2H, m, H-3 
′
, 5 
′
); 
δ
C
130.1 (C-2 
′
, 6 
′
), 115.1 (C- 3 
′
, 5 
′
) for 
3
. Subsequently, an alkaline hydrolysis reaction was conducted, and the results of LC MS analysis show molecular weights of mw = 462 (C 
22
H 
22
O 
11
) and mw = 256 (C 
16
H 
32
O 
2
), which support that compound 
3
is the palmitic acid acylated derivative of tectoridin (

). Comparison of the NMR data with those of glycosides in the literature (

; 

), and the coupling constant values 
J
′′ 
1 -2’’
= 8.9 Hz (
&gt;
7 Hz) demonstrate that the sugar of 
3
was glucopranosyl, and the relative configuration was assigned as 
β
. An acid hydrolysis experiment shows that glucopyranosyl was D-glc. Therefore, compound 
3
was named Belamcandnoate C.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
4
was obtained as a pale yellow oil (MeOH). Its molecular formula, C 
42
H 
56
O 
14
, was determined by the HRESIMS ion at [M + H] 
+
m/z
785.37329 (calcd for 785.37428), which indicates 15 indices of hydrogen deficiency, two degrees of unsaturation higher than 
1
. The NMR data (
Table 2
) closely resembled those of 
1
. The differences mainly involved two double bonds at 
δ
H
5.28 (4H, m, H-6 
′′′
, 7 
′′′
, 9 
′′′
, 10 
′′′
); 
δ
C
129.7 (C-6 
′′′
), 129.6 (C-10 
′′′
), 127.7 (C-7 
′′′
), 129.6 (C-9 
′′′
), which corresponded to the degrees of unsaturation. Analysis of the alkaline hydrolysis products of 
4
by LC—MS reveals molecular weights of mw = 522 (C 
24
H 
26
O 
13
) and mw = 280 (C 
18
H 
32
O 
2
), which indicates that compound 
4
was an octadecadienoic acid acylated derivative of tectoridin. The 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations show two fragments: C(2 
′′′
)H 
2
–C(3 
′′′
)H 
2
–C(4 
′′′
) H 
2
–C(5 
′′′
)H 
2
–C(6 
′′′
)H and C(7 
′′′
)H–C(8 
′′′
)H 
2
–C(9 
′′′
)H–C(10 
′′′
)H. HMBC correlations from H-6 
′′′
to C-4 
′′′
, C-7 
′′′
, C-8 
′′′
, from H-10 
′′′
to C-8 
′′′
, C-9 
′′′
, C-12 
′′′
, demonstrate that the long-chain fatty acid was 6 
′′′
, 9 
′′′
-octadecadienoic acid. Moreover, the obvious upfield shift of the bisallylic methylene signal at 
δ
C
25.2 (C-8 
′′′
), along with the typical carbon resonances of two allylic methylenes at 
δ
C
26.6 (C-5 
′′′
) and 
δ
C
26.6 (C-11 
′′′
) indicate that the methylene interrupted double bonds were 
Z
-configuration (

; 

). Therefore, the long-chain fatty acid side chain was defined as 6? 
Z
, 9? 
Z
-octadecadienoic acid. Besides, the NMR data were highly similar to those of glycosides in literature (

; 

), combined with the coupling constant value 
J
= 8.8 Hz of anomeric proton, they enabled the identification of the sugar unit as 
β
-glucose. The acid hydrolysis indicates that glucopyranosyl was D-glc. Compound 
4
was defined as Belamcandnoate D.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
5
was obtained as a pale oil, and the HRESIMS data displayed an [M – H] 
–
ion at 
m/z
753.34924 (calcd 753.34916), which established a molecular formula of C 
41
H 
54
O 
13
with 15 degrees of unsaturation. Considering the HRESIMS data, the molecular weight of 
5
was 30 mass units less than that of 
4
, which indicates the absence of a methoxy group in 
5
. The comparison of the NMR data of compounds 
5
and 
4
reveals a difference due to different substituent groups of ring B. In the 
1
H NMR spectrum, the resonances at 
δ
H
7.05 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.3 Hz, H- 2 
′
), 6.95 (2H, m, H-6 
′
, 5 
′
) are attributed to an ABX aromatic system for ring B. Comparison of the NMR data with 
1
indicates that 
5
and 
1
share identical isoflavone glycosides. An LC MS analysis of the alkaline hydrolysis products of 
5
reveals molecular weights of 492 (C 
23
H 
24
O 
12
) and 280 (C 
18
H 
32
O 
2
), which indicates that compound 
5
was an octadecadienoic acid acylated derivative of iristectorin A. Similar double bonds NMR data as 

4
in

side chain are displayed at 
δ
H
5.28 (4H, m, H-6 
′′′
, 7 
′′′
, 9 
′′′
, 10 
′′′
), 
δ
C
129.7 (C-6 
′′′
), 129.6 (C-10 
′′′
), 127.8 (C-7 
′′′
), 127.8 (C-9 
′′′
), which supports the conclusion that 
5
and 
4
share the same fatty acid side chain—6 
′′′
, 9 
′′′
-octadecadienoic acid. Besides, the characteristic 
13
C NMR data of two bisallylic methylenes at 
δ
C
26.6 (C-5 
′′′
) and 
δ
C
26.6 (C-11 
′′′
), and the upfield shift value of an interrupted methylene signal at 
δ
C
25.2 (C-8 
′′′
) are observed, which demonstrate that the geometry of double bonds Δ 
6′′′, 7′′′
and Δ 
9′′′, 10′′′
is 
Z
-configuration (

; 

). The relative configuration of the sugar unit is determined as the 
β
-configuration according to the coupling constant value 
J
′′ 
1 -2’’
= 8.6 Hz (
J
′′ 
1 -2’’
&gt;
7 Hz) (

; 

). The absolute configuration of D-glc is further confirmed by acid hydrolysis using GC analysis. Compound 
5
was elucidated as Belamcandnoate E.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
6
was obtained as a pale oil, and its molecular formula C 
40
H 
52
O 
12
was determined by HRESIMS with [M + Na] 
+
ion at 
m/z
747.33429 (calcd 747.33510), which indicated that it was 15 indices of hydrogen deficiency. Analysis of the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data of compounds 
6
and 
4
(except the fatty acid side chains), ascribed the differences to an A’ A’ B’ B’ aromatic system at 
δ
H
7.38 (2H, d, 
J
= 10.3 Hz, H-2 
′
, 6 
′
), 6.84 (2H, d, 
J
= 10.3 Hz, H-3 
′
, 5 
′
); 
δ
C
130.1 (C-2 
′
, 6 
′
), 115.1 (C-3 
′
, 5 
′
) for 
6
. To determine the length of the fatty acid chain, alkaline hydrolysis by NaOH was performed. The LC MS analysis results displayed molecular weights of 462 (C 
22
H 
22
O 
11
) and 280 (C 
18
H 
32
O 
2
), indicating that it was the octadecadienoic acid acylated derivative of tectoridin. The NMR data of 
6
reveal two double bonds at 
δ
H
5.29 (4H, m, H-6 
′′′
, 7 
′′′
, 9 
′′′
, 10 
′′′
), and 
δ
C
129.7 (C-6 
′′′
), 129.6 (C-10 
′′′
), 127.8 (C-7 
′′′
), 127.8 (C-9 
′′′
), which verify that 
6
and 
4
share the same fatty acid side chain. The geometry configuration of the double bonds in the side chain was deduced as 6? 
Z
, 9? 
Z
, based on the typical 
13
C NMR data of an upfield shift allylic methylene at 
δ
C
25.2 (C-8 
′′′
), and two bisallylic methylenes at 
δ
C
26.6 (C- 5 
′′′
) and 
δ
C
26.6 (C-11 
′′′
) (

; 

). Moreover, the sugar unit NMR data in the literature (

; 

), and the coupling constant value 
J
′′ 
1 -2’’
= 8.8 Hz enabled us to determine the relative configuration of the sugar moiety as 
β
-glucose. The D-configuration at the anomeric center of glucose was established by acid hydrolysis and GC analysis. Compound 
6
was elucidated as Belamcandnoate F.
</p>
         <p>
In an i 
n vitro
bioassay, the cytotoxicities (against HCT-116, HepG2, BGC-823, A549, and MCF-7 five human cancer cell lines with paclitaxel as a positive control), antiinflammation (inhibitory effects against lipopolysaccharide-induced nitric oxide (NO) production on BV2 microglial cells), and antioxidation (Fe2+ /cysteine-induced liver microsomal lipid peroxidation) of the isolated compounds were evaluated. The cytotoxic activities showed that compound 
2
exhibited moderate cytotoxic activities against the HCT-116, HepG2, and BGC823 cell lines with IC 
50
values of 6.80, 5.74, and 5.95 
μ
M (
Table 3
). Compound 
4
displayed moderated cytotoxic activities against the HCT-116, HepG2, and BGC823 cell lines with IC 
50
values of 5.73, 6.86, and 1.69 
μ
M. Compounds 
2
and 
5
exhibited 72.27 and 58.98% inhibitory activities, respectively, against the Fe 
2+
/cysteine-induced liver microsomal lipid peroxidation at a concentration of 10 
μ
M (curcumin as the positive control drug, 87.08%). The anti-inflammatory results displayed that they were inactive with IC 
50
values
&gt;
10 
μ
M.
</p>
         <p>
In addition, the brief structure and activity were discussed. Compounds 
2
and 
4
with the 5 
′
-OCH 
3
group displayed significant cytotoxic activities, which suggested that the presence of 5 
′
-OCH 
3
might be crucial for the cytotoxic activities. Moreover, OCH 
3
at C-5 
′
in the saturated long-chain fatty acid acylated derivatives of isoflavones might play an important role in antioxidant activities. However, there were too little data to conclude whether the length and the degree of unsaturation of the fatty acid side chain are equally important. More evidence should be supported in the future.
</p>
         <p>
3. Conclusion
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
, a 
type
of traditional Chinese medicine rich in isoflavones, is mainly used to treat sore throat. The diverse structures and inspired bioactivities of isoflavones from 
<tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
make wider application prospects. In our research, six undescribed long-chain fatty acid acylated derivatives with very long chain unsaturated and saturated fatty acids (C14–C18) were obtained. This is the first report of long-chain fatty acid (C14–C18) ester derivatives of isoflavones from natural products. Our findings enrich the chemical and biological diversity of flavonoid glycosides, and provide a new research idea for compound modification.
</p>
         <p>
4. Experimental
</p>
         <p>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</p>
         <p>
A JASCO P-2000 automatic digital polarimeter was used to record optical rotations. UV spectra were conducted on a JASCO V-650 spectrophotometer. A Nicolet 5700 spectrometer using an FT-IR microscope transmission method was used to obtain IR spectra. Bruker-600 spectrometer was employed to measure NMR spectra. HRESIMS data were measured on Dionex UltiMate 3000 UHPLC and Thermo Scientific Q Exactive Focus Mass Spectrometer. Analytical HPLC was performed on an Agilent 1260 infinity system equipped with a DAD-UV detector. Preparative HPLC was conducted on a CXTH system (Beijing Chuangxintongheng instrument Co. Ltd., People’ s 
Republic of China
), equipped with a UV3000 detector using a YMC-Pack ODS-A column (250 × 
20 mm
, 5 μm, 
Kyoto
, 
Japan
). ODS (50 
μ
m, YMC, 
Japan
), and silica gel (200–300 mesh, Qingdao Marine Chemical Factory, Qingdao, People’ s 
Republic of China
) were used for column chromatography. Silica gel GF 
254
plates purchased from Qingdao Marine Chemical Factory (Qingdao, People’ s 
Republic of China
) were used for TLC analysis.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

Rhizomes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Iris domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) [the name 
<tp:taxon-name>
Belamcanda chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) DC (
<tp:taxon-name>Iridaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) was recorded in Chinense Pharmacopoeia for 2020] were purchased from Anguo (
Hebei Province
, 
P.R.
China
) in September (autumn) 2017, and identified by Prof. Lin Ma (
Institute of Materia Medica
). A voucher specimen (S-2895) was deposited at 
Institute of Materia Medica
, 
Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences
and 
Peking
Union Medical College

.
</p>
         <p>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</p>
         <p>
The air-dried and powdered rhizomes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
I. domestica
</tp:taxon-name>
(
50 kg
) were extracted with 95% ethanol (3 × 2 h × 120 L) to give 
7.8 kg
residues after evaporation under reduced pressure. The residue was successively partitioned with dichloromethane (
CH
2
Cl 
2
), ethyl acetate (EtOAc), and 
n
-butanol (
n
-BuOH). Iridal-type triterpenoids were mainly distributed in dichloromethane extract based on the TLC analysis. Subsequently, the 
CH
2
Cl 
2
extract was chromatographed on a silica gel column and eluted with petroleum/acetone (10:1, 5:1, 3:1, 2:1, 1:1, v/v) to obtain five fractions A-E. Fraction C was subjected to an ODS column and eluted with a gradient of MeOH–H 
2
O of 65–100% to obtain eight fractions C-a to C-h. Fraction C-g was run on a silica gel column eluting with petroleum ether-ethyl acetate (20:1, 10:1, 5:1, 3:1, 2:1, 1:1, 1:2) to obtain seven subfractions C-g-1 to C-g-7. C-g-3 was separated by preparative HPLC (MeCN–H 
2
O 75:25, 4 mL/min) to afford six subfractions: C-g-3-1 to C-g-3-6. C-g-3-3 was also fractioned by preparative HPLC (MeOH–H 
2
O 85:15, 4 mL/min) to obtain compounds 
1
(
4.2 mg
), 
2
(
6.8 mg
), and 
6
(3.0 mg). Fraction C-g-3-4 was purified by preparative HPLC (MeOH–H 
2
O 84:16, 4 mL/min) to afford compounds 
3
(
1.9 mg
), 
4
(
11.8 mg
), and 
5
(10.0 mg).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.1. Belamcandnoate A (1)
</p>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
–82 (
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 267 (3.26), 342 (0.82) nm; IR 
u
max
3224, 2925, 2861, 1736, 1635, 1452, 
1075 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
703.33234 [M + H] 
+
(calcd C 
37
H 
51
O 
13
, 703.33242).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.2. Belamcandnoate B (2)
</p>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
–71 (
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 268 (2.75), 335 (0.33) nm; IR 
u
max
3422, 2924, 2853, 1735, 1657, 1620, 1587, 1512, 1459, 1431, 1358, 1305, 1207, 
1079 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
733.34265 [M + H] 
+
(calcd C 
38
H 
53
O 
14
, 733.34298).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.3. Belamcandnoate C (3)
</p>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
–34 (
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 267 (3.56), 338 (0.40) nm; IR 
u
max
3387, 2924, 2853, 1719, 1655, 1613, 1587, 1516, 1459, 1366, 1316, 1217, 
1079 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
723.33417 [M + H] 
+
(calcd C 
38
H 
53
O 
12
, 723.33510).
</p>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
–49 (
c
0.2, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 267 (2.34), 338 (0.25) nm; IR 
u
max
3411, 2928, 2855, 1734, 1657, 1620, 1587, 1512, 1459, 1431, 1358, 1306, 1207, 
1081 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
785.37329 [M + H] 
+
(calcd C 
42
H 
57
O 
14
, 785.37428).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
4.3.5. Belamcandnoate E (5)
</p>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
–58 (
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 267 (2.34), 338 (0.28) nm; IR 
u
max
3400, 2928, 2855, 1734, 1656, 1620, 1586, 1513, 1460, 1435, 1372, 1286, 1207, 
1080 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR data see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
753.34924 [M–H] 
–
(calcd C 
41
H 
53
O 
13
, 753.34916).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.6. Belamcandnoate F (6)
</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil, [
α
] 
D
20
–56 (
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 267 (3.92), 343 (0.77) nm; IR 
u
max
3397, 2928, 2857, 1731, 1655, 1614, 1589, 1516, 1460, 1365, 1317, 1272, 
1078 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
747.33429 [M+ Na] 
+
(calcd C 
40
H 
52
O 
12
Na, 747.33510).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Alkaline hydrolysis of 1–6
</title>
         <p>
Compound 
4
(
2.4 mg
) was dissolved in 
CH
3
OH (3 mL), and excess NaOH aqueous solution (1 mol/L, 5 mL) was added. The mixture was stirred at room temperature for 24 h. The solution was acidified to a pH of 4 using 1 mol/L HCl and extracted with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
. The 
CH
2
Cl 
2
extract was analyzed by MS and two molecular formulas were probed: C 
24
H 
26
O 
13
(M = 522) and C 
18
H 
32
O 
2
(M = 280), which indicated that the chain length of fatty acid of 
4
was C-18. Utilizing the same methods, alkaline hydrolysis products of compounds 
1–3
, and 
5–6
were detected by MS to determine that the carbon chain length of fatty acids were 14, 14, 16, 18 and 18, respectively. The structural elucidation of the glucoside moiety of 
4
demonstrated that it shared the same structure with the known compound iridin. Iridin was obtained from the reaction mixture via preparative HPLC (MeCN–H 
2
O 30:70, 4 mL/min) (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Acidic hydrolysis of iridin, iristectorin A, tectoridin
</title>
         <p>
Iridin (
1 mg
), iristectorin A (
1.5 mg
), and tectoridin (
1.2 mg
) were hydrolyzed with HCl (2 mol/L, 3 mL) and reacted at 90 
◦
C for 2 h, respectively. The reaction mixture was partitioned with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
three times (5 mL × 3). After evaporating under reduced pressure, the 
CH
2
Cl 
2
extract was analyzed by MS to find the aglycone (C 
18
H 
16
O 
8
, M = 360). The aqueous phase extract was placed in a desiccator overnight. Then, Lcysteine methyl ester hydrochloride (
5 mg
) and anhydrous pyridine (1 mL) were added to the aqueous layer. The mixture was vigorously stirred at 60 
◦
C for 2 h. Then, 200 
μ
L trimethylsilylimidazole was added to the mixture and kept at 60 
◦
C for 2 h. The solution was poured into water (3 mL), followed by extraction with hexane (3 × 5 mL). The authentic sugar (D- and L-glucoses) derivatives were obtained using the same methods. The hexane mixture (5 
μ
L) was analyzed by GC chromatography and subjected to an Agilent 7890A gas chromatograph with an HP-5 column (
60 m
× 
0.25 mm
, with a 0.25 
μ
m film, Dikma) and an FID detector under the following conditions: column temperature: 200–280 
◦
C; programmed increase: 10 
◦
C/min; carrier gas: N 
2
(1 mL/ min); injector and detector temperature: 280 
◦
C; injection volume: 5 
μ
L; split ratio: 1/50. The configuration of the sugar moiety was determined by comparing the retention time with the derivatives of authentic samples. The retention times of D and L-glucose were 29.405 and 30.219 min, respectively, which helped identify the configuration of the sugar moiety of compounds 
1–6
as D-glucose (

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. In vitro bioassays
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.1. Cytotoxic assay
</title>
         <p>
Cytotoxic activities of compounds 
1–6
against HCT-116, HepG2, BGC-823, A549 and MCF-7 cells were measured by using the MTT method. Briefly, test cells in culture medium 100 
μ
L were seeded in each well of 96-well plates (Falcon, CA). Cells were treated in triplicate with 10 
μ
L of grade concentrations 0.1, 1, 10 
μ
M of the compounds at 37 
◦
C. After 72 h, a 20 
μ
L aliquot of MTT solution (
5 mg
/mL) was added to the wells. The cultures were incubated for another 4 h, and then 100 
μ
L of “triplex solution” (10% SDS/5% isobutanol/10 mM HCl) was added. The plates were incubated at 37 
◦
C in 5% CO 
2
overnight. The OD values were measured at 
570 nm
by a plate reader (VERSA Max, Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA). Average values determined from triplicate readings
</p>
         <p>
were used for the inhibitory rate calculation by the formula: (
ODcontrol well
– 
ODtreated well
)/ 
ODcontrol well
– 
ODblank well
× 100%. The IC 
50
was calculated using Logistic regression from three independent tests. Paclitaxel was used as the positive control with IC 
50
values of 0.2, 10.69, 2.08, 2.68, 19 
n
M, respectively (

,b).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.2. NO production bioassay
</title>
         <p>
Compounds 
1–6
were tested for their inhibitory effect on LPSinduced NO production in the BV2 cell line. The BV2 cells were plated in a 96-well plate and pretreated with the compounds for 24 h followed by an additional 24 h of LPS (0.3 μg/mL) exposure. The Griess reaction was used to determine the nitrite content in the culture supernatant. NaNO 
2
served as a standard to assess the NO 
2
concentration. The OD values were recorded at 
550 nm
. Curcumin was used as the positive control. Cell viability was measured by an MTT assay (

,b).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.3. Antioxidant bioassays
</title>
         <p>
The antioxidant activities of compounds 
1–6
were determined by an MDA colorimetric assay in Fe 
2+
/cysteine-induced liver microsomal lipid peroxidation. Hepatic microsomes were maintained in 0.1 M PBS (pH 7.4), and the system contained 
1.5 mg
/mL liver microsomal protein, 0.1 
μ
M compounds and 200 
μ
M cysteine and was cultured in a 37 
◦
C water bath for 15 min FeSO 
4
(50 
μ
M) was added into the reactions, and the plates were cultured in a 37 
◦
C water bath for an additional 15 min. The reactions were terminated by the addition of 20% TCA. The reaction mixtures were centrifuged at 2000 r/min for 10 min, and then 1 mL of each supernatant was combined with 1 mL of 0.67% TBA and cultured in a boiling water bath for 10 min. The optical density (OD) of each reaction solution was measured with a microplate reader at 
532 nm
. The content of MDA was used as a measure of oxidizing strength: lower MDA contents indicated stronger oxidation resistance. The concentration of MDA was obtained using the following formula: C (
n
M) = [(OD– 0.006)/ 0.07] × 10, and the antioxidant activities of the compounds were calculated using the following formula: Inhibition (%) = 1–[C(sample)– C(blank))/(C(model)–C(blank))] × 100 (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Associated content
</p>
         <p>
Supporting Information
</p>
         <p>
Additional material (1D and 2D NMR, UV, IR, HRESIMS spectra of compounds 
1–6
) is provided in the Supporting Information.
</p>
         <p>
Notes
</p>
         <p>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
This
work was supported by the 
National Natural Science Foundation
of 
China
(No. 21472245) and CAMS 
Innovation Fund
for 
Medical Sciences
(CIFMS, 

2016-I2

M-1–010)

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112977.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bhullar, K.S.
, 
Ziaullah, Z.
, 
Rupasinghe, V.H.P.
, 
2014
. 

In vitro
regulation of enzymes of the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system by isoquercitrin, phloridzin and their long chain fatty acid derivatives

. 
Funct. Foods Health
D 
4
, 
208–221
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.31989/ffhd.v4i5.11
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bock, K.
, 
Pedersen, C.
, 
1983
. 
Carbon-13 nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy of monosaccharides
. 
Adv. Carbohydr. Chem. Biochem.
41
, 
27–66
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/S0065-2318(08)60055-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bugoni, S.
, 
Merlini, V.
, 
Porta, A.
, 
Gailard, S.
, 
Zanoni, G.
, 
Nolan, S.P.
, 
Vidari, G.
, 
2015
. 
Competitive gold-promoted Meyer-Schuster and oxy-Cope rearrangements of 3- acyloxy-1,5-enynes: selective catalysis for the synthesis of (+)-(S)-γ- Ionone and (-)-(2S,6R)-cis-γ- irone
. 
Chem. Eur J.
21
, 
14068–14074
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ chem.201502382
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, X.Y.
, 
Wang, H.Q.
, 
Zhang, T.
, 
Liu, C.
, 
Kang, J.
, 
Chen, R.Y.
, 
Yu, D.Q.
, 
2013
. 

Aromatic glucosides from the seeds of 
Prunus davidiana

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
76
, 
1528–1534
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1021/np4000922
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Farag, S.F.
, 
Kimura, Y.
, 
Ito, H.
, 
Takayasu, J.
, 
Tokuda, H.
, 
Hatano, T.
, 
2009
. 

New isoflavone glycosides from 
Iris spuria
L. (Calizona) cultivated in Egypt

. 
J. Nat. Med.
63
, 
91–95
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11418-008-0291-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gunstone, F.D.
, 
Polard, M.R.
, 
Scrimgeour, C.M.
, 
Vedanayagam, H.S.
, 
1977
. 
Fatty acids
. 13
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Han, S.W.
, 
Wang, C.
, 
Cui, B.S.
, 
Sun, H.
, 
Zhang, J.J.
, 
Li, S.
, 
2019
. 
Hepatoprotective activity of glucosyloxybenzyl succinate derivatives from the pseudobulbs of pleione bulbocodioides
. 
Phytochemistry
157
, 
71–81
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2018.10.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, J.Y.
, 
Ni, G.
, 
Liu, Y.F.
, 
Li, L.
, 
Mai, Z.P.
, 
Wang, R.Z.
, 
Yu, D.Q.
, 
2019
a. 
New iridal-type triterpenoid derivatives with cytotoxic activities from Belamcanda chinensis
. 
Bioorg. Chem.
83
, 
20–28
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bioorg.2018.08.039
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, J.Y.
, 
Ni, G.
, 
Liu, Y.F.
, 
Mao, Z.P.
, 
Wang, R.Z.
, 
Yu, D.Q.
, 
2019
b. 

Iridal-type triterpenoids with a cyclopentane unit from the rhizomes of 
Belamcanda chinensis

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
82
, 
1759–1767
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.8b00993
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lim, H.S.
, 
Kim, Y.J.
, 
Kim, B.Y.
, 
Park, G.
, 
Jeong, S.J.
, 
2018
. 

The anti-neuroinflammatory activity of tectorigenin pretreatment via downregulated NF- 
κ
B and ERK/JNK pathways in BV-2 microglial and microglia inactivation in mice with lipopolysaccharide

. 
Front. Pharmacol.
9
, 
462–475
. 
https://doi.org/10.3389/ fphar.2018.00462
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Q.
, 
Wang, Y.F.
, 
Chen, R.J.
, 
Zhang, M.Y.
, 
Wang, Y.F.
, 
Yang, C.R.
, 
Zhang, Y.J.
, 
2009
. 

Anti-coxsackie virus B3 norsesquiterpenoids from the roots of 
phyllanthus emblica

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
72
, 
969–972
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np800792d
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Y.Y.
, 
Yang, Y.N.
, 
Feng, Z.M.
, 
Jiang, J.S.
, 
Zhang, P.C.
, 
2019
. 

Eight new triterpenoid saponins with antioxidant activity from the roots of 
Glycyrrhiza uralensis
Fisch

. 
Fitoterapia
133
, 
186–192
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2019.01.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Monthakantirat, O.
, 
Wanchai, De-Eknamkul
, 
Umehara, K.
, 
Yoshinaga, Y.
, 
Miyase, T.
, 
Warashina, T.
, 
Noguchi, H.
, 
2005
. 
Phenolic constituents of the rhizomes of the Thai medicinal plant Belamcanda chinensis with proliferative activity for two breast cancer cell lines
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
68
, 
361–364
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np040175c
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Noh, D.
, 
Choi, J.G.
, 
Huh, E.
, 
Oh, M.S.
, 
2018
. 
Tectorigenin, a flavonoid-based compound of Leopard Lily Rhizome, attenuates UV-B-induced apoptosis and collagen degradation by inhibiting oxidative stress in human keratinocytes
. 
Nutrients
10
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/nu10121998
, 1998–2008.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oh, K.B.
, 
Kang, He
, 
Matsuoka, H.
, 
2001
. 

Detection of antifungal activity in 
Belamcanda chinensis
by a single-cell bioassay method and isolation of its active compound, tectorigenin. Biosci

. 
Biotechnol. Biochem.
65
, 
939–942
. 
https://doi.org/10.1271/ bbb.65.939
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sekhon-Loodu, S.
, 
Ziaullah, Z.
, 
Rupasinghe, H.P.V.
, 
2015
. 
Novel quercetin-3-O-glucoside eicosapentaenoic acid ester ameliorates inflammation and hyperlipidemia
. 
Inflammopharmacology
23
, 
173–185
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10787-015-0237-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Song, J.G.
, 
Tang, W.
, 
Wang, X.J.
, 
Su, J.C.
, 
Huang, X.J.
, 
Shi, L.
, 
Ye, W.C.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
2021
. 
Phloroglucinol-derived lipids from the leaves of Syzygium cumini and their neuroprotective activities
. 
Fitoterapia
153
, 
104968
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. fitote.2021.104968
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sudan, S.
, 
Rupasinghe, H.V.
, 
2015
. 
Antiproliferative activity of long chain acylated esters of quercetin-3-O-glucoside in hepatocellular carcinoma HepG2 cells
. 
Exp. Biol. Med.
240
, 
1452–1464
. 
https://doi.org/10.1177/1535370215570828
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Thelen, P.
, 
Scharf, J.G.
, 
Burfeind, P.
, 
Hemmerlein, B.
, 
Wuttke, W.
, 
Spengler, B.
, 
Christoffel, V.
, 
Ringert, R.H.
, Seidlov´a-Wuttke, D., 
2005
. 

Tectorigenin and other phytochemicals extracted from leopard lily 
Belamcanda chinensis
affect new and established targets for therapies in prostate cancer

. 
Carcinogenesis
26
, 
1360–1367
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/carcin/bgi092
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Usui, A.
, 
Matsuo, Y.
, 
Tanaka, T.
, 
Ohshima, K.
, 
Fukuda, S.
, 
Mine, T.
, 
Yakashiro, I.
, 
Ishimaru, K.
, 
2017
. 

Ferulic acid esters of glucosylglucose from 
Allium macrostemon
Bunge. J

. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
19
, 
215–221
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 10286020.2016.1213722
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Warnakulasuriya, S.N.
, 
Ziaullah
, 
Rupasinghe, H.P.V.
, 
2016
a. 
Long chain fatty acid esters of Quercetin-3-O-glucoside attenuate H2O2-induced acute cytotoxicity in human lung fibroblasts and primary hepatocytes
. 
Molecules
21
, 
452
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.3390/molecules21040452
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Warnakulasuriya, S.N.
, 
Ziaullah
, 
Rupasinghe, H.P.V.
, 
2016
b. 
Novel long chain fatty acid derivatives of quercetin-3-O-glucoside reduce cytotoxicity induced by cigarette smoke toxicants in human fetal lung fibroblasts
. 
Eur. J. Pharmacol.
781
, 
128–138
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejphar.2016.04.011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wozniak, D.
, 
Matkowski, A.
, 
2015
. 
Belamcandae chinensis rhizoma a review of phytochemistry and bioactivity
. 
Fitoterapia
107
, 
1–14
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. fitote.2015.08.015
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xin, R.H.
, 
Zheng, J.F.
, 
Cheng, L.
, 
Peng, W.J.
, 
Luo, Y.J.
, 
2015
. 
Belamcanda chinensis (L.) DC: ethnopharmacology, phytochemistryand pharmacology of an important traditional Chinese medicine. Afr. J. Tradit., Complementary Altern
. 
Med.
12
, 
39–70
. 
https://doi.org/10.4314/ajtcam.v12i6.6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xin, X.
, 
Zhang, M.
, 
Li, X.F.
, 
Zhao, G.L.
, 
2019
. 
Biocatalytic synthesis of lipophilic Baicalin derivatives as antimicrobial agents
. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
67
, 
11684–11693
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.9b04667
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, L.
, 
Wei, K.H.
, 
Xu, J.P.
, 
Yang, D.W.
, 
Zhang, C.H.
, 
Wang, Z.P.
, 
Li, M.H.
, 
2016
. 

Belamcanda chinensis
(L.) DC-An ethnopharmacological, phytochemical and pharmacological review

. 
J. Ethnopharmacol.
186
, 
1–13
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. jep.2016.03.046
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ziaullah
, 
Rupasinghe, H.P.V.
, 
2013
. 
An efficient microwave-assisted enzyme-catalyzed regioselective synthesis of long chain acylated derivatives of flavonoid glycosides
. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
54
, 
1933–1937
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tetlet.2013.01.103
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ziaullah
, 
Bhullar, K.S.
, 
Warnakulasuriya, S.N.
, 
Rupasinghe, H.P.V.
, 
2013
. 
Biocatalytic synthesis, structural elucidation, antioxidant capacity and tyrosinase inhibition activity of long chain fatty acid acylated derivatives of phloridzin and isoquercitrin
. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem.
21
, 
684–692
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2012.11.034
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ziaullah
, 
Rupasinghe, H.P.V.
, 
2016
. 
Sonochemical enzyme-catalyzed regioselective acylation of flavonoid glycosides
. 
Bioorg. Chem.
65
, 
17–25
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.bioorg.2016.01.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
