<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112792</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Brevianthrones, bianthrones from a Chinese isolate of the endophytic fungus Colletotrichum brevisporum</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Glomerellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Piper sarmentosum
Roxb.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum tofieldiae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
PSSF
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Glomerellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Colletotrichum brevisporum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
PSSF
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Piper sarmentosum
Roxb. (Piperaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Vismia orientalis
(
Mbwambo et al., 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus wentii
(
Form et al., 2019
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus alliaceus
(
Mandelare et al., 2018
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Colletotrichum brevisporum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus alliaceus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Plasmodium falciparum
(
Ndjakou Lenta et al., 2008
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
(Glomerellaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Piper sarmentosum
Roxb. (Piperaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Brevianthrones, bianthrones from a Chinese isolate of the endophytic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Min Lin
a
, Donovon A. Adpressa
b
, Meiyu Feng
a
, Ya Lu
a
, Benjamin R. Clark

a, 
*
</p>
         <p>
a

School of Pharmaceutical Science and Technology, 
Tianjin
University, 92 Weijin Road, 
Tianjin
, 300092, People’ s 
Republic of China
</p>
         <p>
b
Department of Analytical Research and Development, Merck
&amp; 

Co., Inc. Boston, MA, 02115, 
United States
</p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Glomerellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Structure elucidation</p>
         <p>Bianthrones</p>
         <p>Anthraquinones</p>
         <p>Plant-derived fungus</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Seven undescribed bianthrones, the brevianthrones, together with two known anthraquinones, were isolated from the plant-derived fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
, obtained from the plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Piper sarmentosum
Roxb.
</tp:taxon-name>
, collected in 
Guangxi
, 
China
. This is the first report of the isolation of bianthrones from the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
genus. The structures of the compounds were elucidated by a combination of NMR and MS spectroscopic analysis, while the absolute configurations were determined by X-ray crystallography and by simulation of ECD spectra.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Plant-derived fungi are of great interest to both chemical and agricultural researchers, due to both their role as a source of potential drug leads, and their ecological importance (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
is a widely-distributed genus of important plant-associated fungi: although members of the genus are best-known as plant pathogens, many 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
species
</tp:taxon-name>
are harmless and, in some cases, they can be beneficial to plants (Barth´elemy et al., 2020; 

). 

found that the presence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum tofieldiae
</tp:taxon-name>
in the roots of the plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
enhanced the fitness of the host. Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
are known to produce diverse metabolites, such as polyketides, peptides, alkaloids, and terpenoids (

; 

; 

; 

; 

), with biological activities including antimicrobial, cytotoxic, phytotoxic, antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
is a recently-discovered member of the genus, first reported in 
2012 in
Thailand
, from plant leaves that were infected by anthracnose (

). Later, this species was found to cause anthracnose in a range of agriculturally important plant species, including papaya fruit, chaoyote, pumpkins (

; 

; 

), etc. Overall, the majority of scientific studies on this species have focused on its role in plant disease, rather than its potential as a source of chemical diversity.
</p>
         <p>
During the investigation of a Chinese isolate of the endophytic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
PSSF
</tp:taxon-name>
01 (
<tp:taxon-name>Glomerellaceae</tp:taxon-name>
), we have isolated seven undescribed bianthrones, together with two known anthraquinones. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first paper focusing on the chemical investigation of 

<tp:taxon-name>Colletotrichum brevisporum</tp:taxon-name>
,

and the first report of bianthrones isolated from the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
genus.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
The fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
PSSF
</tp:taxon-name>
01 was obtained from the plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Piper sarmentosum
Roxb. (Piperaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
, collected in 
Guangxi
, 
China
. The fungus was cultured in Potato Dextrose Broth for 10 days, and both biomass and supernatant extracted with organic solvents to yield an organic extract. The extract was fractionated by a combination of solvent-solvent partition, silica gel column chromatography, and semipreparative reverse phase 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
, to yield seven undescribed bianthrones, the brevianthrones (
1–7
), along with two structurally related anthraquinones. The anthraquinones were identified as nalgiovensin (
8
) and 1-methoxy-nalgiovensin (
9
) by comparing their HRMS data, UV spectra, and 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data with literature values (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). Comparison of optical rotation data with literature values confirmed that both anthraquinones possessed 
S
-configuration at the C-12 position (see 
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of brevianthrone A1 (
1
) was determined to be C 
36
H 
34
O 
10
, based on the HRESIMS analysis, which showed a strong sodiated adduct ion peak at 
m/z
649.2049. The UV–vis spectrum showed maxima at 359 and 
277 nm
, consistent with the UV spectra of bianthrones (

; 

). In the 
13
C NMR spectrum, only 18 signals were observed in the spectrum, indicating that the molecule was likely a symmetrical dimer. The carbon signals showed similarities to the spectroscopic data found for bianthrone A 
1
, isolated from the plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Vismia orientalis
(
Mbwambo et al., 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, exhibiting typical chemical shifts for the bianthrone skeleton (
Table 1
), including oxygenated 

sp 
2

carbons (

δC

164.6, 165.4, 161.8). In addition to signals consistent with a bianthrone core, a methoxy group (

δC

55.7), and signals belonging to a 2-hydroxypropyl side chain (

δC

45.8, 68.1, 23.2) were also observed. The 
1
H NMR spectrum showed four characteristic aromatic signals (

δH

6.39, 6.04, 6.19, 6.72), two hydroxy protons (

δH

12.08, 11.82) and the signals arising from 2-hydroxypropyl side chain, which suggested that the compound was composed of two nalgiovensin-like subunits. The position of substituents was confirmed by HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
). 1-OH was assigned based on its correlation to C-1, C-2 and C-9a, while 8-OH showed correlations to C-7 and C-8. The position of the methoxy group at C-3 was confirmed by its correlation to C-3 and correlation from H-2 to the methoxy carbon. The position of the 2-hydroxypropyl side chain was confirmed based on correlations from H-11 to the aromatic carbons C-5,6,7 (
Fig. 2
). In contrast to the deshielded quinone carbon of nalgiovensin (

δC

181.9), C-10 of compound 
1
was at much lower chemical shift (

δC

56.5), consistent with the presence of a C10–C10 
′
linked bianthrone, instead of an anthraquinone. HMBC correlations from H-10 to C-4, 4a, 5, 8a, 9a confirmed the connectivity of the two subunits as shown. After being dissolved in chloroform, brevianthrone A1 (
1
) formed X-ray diffraction suitable crystals. X-ray analysis confirmed the structure (
Fig. 3
), while the Flack parameter of 0.08(9) allowed assignment of the absolute configuration of 
1
as 10 
R
, 10 
′
R
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
. Comparison of experimental and calculated ECD spectra of 
1
show excellent agreement (
Fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
Brevianthrones A2 (
2
) and A3 (
3
) were isolated as an inseparable mixture, in a 1:2 ratio. The molecular formulae of the two compounds were both C 
36
H 
34
O 
10
, based on the HRESIMS analysis, and also possessed a UV spectrum consistent with the presence of a bianthrone core. In the 
1
H NMR spectrum, the same key resonances were observed as for compound 
1
, while the HMBC spectrum established the same connectivity. Thus, compounds 
2
and 
3
were determined to be stereoisomers of 
1
, differing in configuration at C-10 and C-10 
′
. In the 
13
C NMR analysis, three sets of signals were observed in an approximately 1:1:1 ratio. This was attributed to one set of signals from the chiral brevianthrone A2 (
2
), and two sets of signals from the mesomer brevianthrone A3 (
3
), present in a 1:2 ratio. Diasteromeric bianthrones have been obtained as mixtures before: Form et al. isolated inseparable wentibianthrones from the lake-derived fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus wentii
(
Form et al., 2019
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. In contrast, similar isomeric compounds, the allianthrones, have been reported from co-culture of two developmental stages of a marine-derived fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus alliaceus
(
Mandelare et al., 2018
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and all three isomers could be separated using achiral reversed-phase chromatography.
</p>
         <p>
Brevianthrone B1 (
4
) was isolated as a pure compound, and displayed a similar UV absorbance to compounds 
1–3
, suggesting that it was also a bianthrone. Its molecular formula was determined to be C 
37
H 
36
O 
10
, based on HRESIMS analysis, which showed a strong ion at 
m/z
663.2189 [M+Na] 
+
. In the 
13
C NMR two sets of paired signals were observed, indicating that compound 
4
was asymmetrical dimer consisting of two structurally related monomers. Further inspection of the 
1
H-NMR and 
13
C-NMR spectra (
Table 2
) allowed the assignment of two anthrone moieties that are structurally related to the known anthraquinones 
8
and 
9
. The 
1
H-NMR and 
13
C-NMR spectra were similar to those of brevianthrone A1 (
1
), except one of the hydroxy groups in compound 
1
was replaced by a methoxy group in compound 
4
. The molecular weight difference of 14 amu between compound 
1
and compound 
4
was consistent with the presence of an additional methoxy group, the position of which was confirmed by an HMBC correlation to C-1. Comparison of computed ECD spectra of 
4
showed an excellent qualitative agreement with calculated spectra, allowing for assignment of absolute stereochemistry of the stereocenters as 10 
R
, 10 
′
R
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
.
</p>
         <p>
Brevianthrones B2 (
5
) and B3 (
6
) were isolated as a 1:1-mixture of diastereomers. They displayed the characteristic UV absorbances of bianthrones, and were also isomers of 
4
, based on the HRESIMS analysis (
m/z
663.2176 [M+Na] 
+
). After analyzing the NMR data, the planar structures were determined to be the same as for compound 
4
.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Spectra were recorded at 400 MHz for 
1
H NMR and 100 MHz for 
13
C NMR in CDCl 
3
.

</p>
         <p>
Brevianthrone B4 (
7
) was isolated as another diastereomer of brevianthrone B1 (
4
). The molecular formula was determined to be C 
37
H 
36
O 
10
, based on the HRESIMS analysis (
m/z
663.2182 [M+Na] 
+
). The HRMS data, UV spectrum, 1D and 2D NMR data was almost identical to those of compound 
4
, and indicated that the compound, brevianthrone B4 (
7
), was a stereoisomer of brevianthrone B1 (
4
). Comparison of experimental ECD spectra with spectra calculated for 10 
R
, 10 
′
S
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
allowed for confident assignment of the absolute configuration (
Fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
To further confirm our hypothesis that 
2/3
and 
5/6
were both twocompound mixtures, these two samples were subjected to analysis using chiral 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
. Following analysis on a Chiralcel OD-H column, compounds 
2
and 
3
could be separated as two peaks (
2
: 
tR
= 32.2; 
3
: 
tR
= 27.4), with a peak area ratio close to 1:2 (
Fig. S1
). For compounds 
5
and 
6
(
tR
= 24.4, 
tR
= 31.5), two peaks were also visible, with a peak area ratio of approximately 1:1 (
Fig. S2
).
</p>
         <p>
The number of possible isomers for bianthrones depends on a number of factors. In homobianthrones, where each anthrone half is substituted by the same achiral groups, three possible isomers exist: two enantiomers and the 
meso
-isomer. This is the case for the homodimeric brevianthrones A1-A3 (
1-3
): the pseudo 
-meso
isomer, brevianthrone A3 (
3
), would be expected to be found in twice the amount as the two pseudoenantiomers (
1
, 
2
), as there are two ways to 
<tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
pseudo 
- meso
isomer in a non-stereospecific dimerization process: the 10 
S
, 10 
′
R
and 10 
R
, 10 
′
S
fusions produce the same compound. This is in line with the results from chiral 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. S2
), and with the ratios observed for the related allianthrones (

). In the heterobianthrones, where the two anthrone subunits have different structures, there will be four stereoisomeric possibilities, all present in equal amounts, as was observed for brevianthrones B1–B4 (
4–7
). If there are chiral substituents, the situation becomes more complex (

). Each of the brevianthrones possesses four chiral centers and has chiral centers in the side-chains, leading to a large number of possible isomers; however, based on the known absolute configurations of the anthraquinones 
8
and 
9
, and for brevianthrone A1 (
1
), the 
S
-configuration was assigned to the 12 and 12 
′
positions of the remaining bianthrones (
2–7
), simplifying the analysis.
</p>
         <p>
Determining the absolute configurations at the 10 and 10 
′
positions was more challenging. Determining absolute configuration of bianthrones can be conducted through a variety of methods. 

developed a method to determine relative configuration based on 
1
H-NMR. In a 2009 report, using NMR shift calculation and use of the CP3 parameter, which compares differences in calculated shift with differences in experimental shift, experimental spectra could be assigned to two diastereomers (

); this method was subsequently applied by 

. However, the most commonly used methods are X-ray crystallography and electronic circular dichroism (ECD), which were used in a 2018 study in determining the absolute configurations of the allianthrones (

).
</p>
         <p>
Thus, in the current study, we have used simulation of ECD spectra to determine the absolute configurations of 
4
and 
7
, as well as corroborate the absolute configuration of 
1
. 
Fig. 4
shows experimental spectra for 
1
, 
4
, and 

7
in

comparison to sTDDFT calculated spectra at the CAMB3LYP//GNF2-xTB level with ALPB solvation in acetonitrile. The calculated and experimental spectra for each show excellent qualitative agreement and allow for corroboration of the absolute configuration of 
1
as 10 
R
, 10 
′
R
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
. The isomeric brevianthrones A2 (
2
) and A3 (
3
), isolated as an inseparable mixture were thus assigned as the 10 
S
, 10 
′
S
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
, and 10 
S
, 10 
′
R
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
, isomers, respectively. ECD was also used to confirm the configurations of brevianthrones B1 (
4
) and B4 (
7
) as 10 
R
, 10 
′
R
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
and 10 
R
, 10 
′
S
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
respectively. By elimination, that suggests that brevianthrones B2 (
5
) and B3 (
6
), obtained as an inseparable mixture, must be the 10 
S
, 10 
′
S
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
and 10 
S
, 10 
′
R
, 12 
S
, 12 
′
S
stereoisomers.
</p>
         <p>
The allianthrones, isolated from a marine-derived 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus alliaceus
</tp:taxon-name>
strain by 

were similar to compounds 
1–3
, except for the presence of a chlorine atom in position 2. To determine whether 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
could produce analogous metabolites incorporating halogen atoms, experiments were conducted in media enriched in halide salts. Similar enrichment studies have been successful in producing additional analogues in other fungi (

; 

). The fungus was grown in the presence of NaCl, NaBr and KI (2%), however, according to the 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
analysis, no new peaks were detected compared to the controls, suggesting that this fungus lacked a suitable halogenase capable of producing halogenated bianthrones. Halogenase enzymes are common in microorganisms isolated from marine environments (

), where higher levels of halide salts are present. Thus, the difference in biosynthetic capability of the two fungi might be attributed to the different environments from which they were isolated.
</p>
         <p>
Anthraquinones are abundant in plants, lichens and fungi, with more than 700 examples in the literature (

). Anthraquinones have been shown to possess biological activities like cytotoxic, antimicrobial, and anti-diabetic activities, and are also applied in the dyeing industry (

; 

; 

). Anthraquinones have been reported from the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
genus before; several anthraquinones from the endophytic fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
JS-0367 possessed significant neuroprotective activity (

). Bianthrones are a class of compound formed by fusion of two anthrone precursors. Much rarer than the anthraquinones, these compounds have been reported in plants, animals and fungi (

). The naturally-occurring bianthrones tend to be substituted by methyl, hydroxy, methoxy groups, and occasionally more complex substituents. Studies have shown that bianthrones can exhibit potent biological activity, for example cytotoxicity against a range of cancer cell lines (

; 

), antifungal properties (

), and antiplasmodial activity against 
<tp:taxon-name>
Plasmodium falciparum
(
Ndjakou Lenta et al., 2008
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. While the biosynthesis of anthraquinones have been well-studied in several fungi (

), the biosynthesis of bianthrones has been far less well studied in microbes. The ratios of stereoisomers produced in the current study is consistent with a non-stereospecific dimerization mechanism, though whether this is enzyme catalyzed or spontaneous is unknown.
</p>
         <p>
The crude extracts and all pure compounds were tested for antimicrobial activity against eight bacteria and two fungi (Table S3), unfortunately, no activity was observed against any of the test strains. Compounds 
1
, 
8
and 
9
were tested for cytotoxicity against human breast cancer (MDA-MB-231) and human liver cancer (HepG-2) cell lines, however none of the compounds showed obvious cytotoxicity at the concentrations tested (0–100 μM).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
In summary, seven undescribed bianthrones along with two known anthraquinones were isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
. The structures of the undescribed bianthrones were elucidated by analysis of 1D and 2D NMR spectra and HRMS data. Based on the fact that the nalgiovensin (
8
) and 1-methoxy-nalgiovensin (
9
) are biogenetic building blocks of the brevianthrones (
1–7
), it is assumed that the orientation at C-12/12 
′
is 
S
. The absolute configuration of brevianthrones (
1–7
) at C-10 was determined by ECD simulation, with the support of the X-ray crystallography of brevianthone A1 (
1
). The mixture of isomers observed is consistent with an achiral dimerization mechanism. Our findings enrich the chemical diversity of bianthrones to date, and continue to highlight the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum
</tp:taxon-name>
genus as a potential source of new chemistry, not just as plant pathogens. Compounds were tested for antimicrobial and cytotoxic properties, but none showed any bioactivity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

(
continued on next page
)

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Spectra were recorded at 400 MHz for 
1
H NMR and 100 MHz for 
13
C NMR in CDCl 
3
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General
</title>
         <p>
Aseptic operations were carried out in a ZHJH-C115C Laminar hood (Zhicheng, Shanghai). Microbes were grown in a ZXSD-A1090 incubator (Zhicheng, Shanghai), and were fermented in a ZWYR-240 shakerincubator (Zhicheng, Shanghai). Optical rotations were recorded using an Anton Par Polarimeter (λ 589) using a 300 μL cell with a path length of 0.5 dm. UV data was measured on a U-3900 spectrophotometer (Hitachi, 
Japan
). Electronic circular dichroism (ECD) spectra were measured on a Bio-Logic MOS-500 spectrometer using a 
1 cm
path length quartz cuvette. 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
analysis was performed on an Agilent 1260 series 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
system using a ZORBAX SB-C18 (3.5 μm, 4.6 × 
150 mm
; Agilent Technologies), Pursuit XRs5, C-18 (3.5 μm, 4.6 × 
150 mm
, Agilent Technologies) and Chiralcel® OD-H (5 μm, 4.6 × 
250 mm
, Daicel Chiral Technologies) columns. Semipreparative 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
separation was carried out on a Shimadzu LC-20AR series 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
instrument, using a reversed-phase C18 column (ZORBAX SB-C18, 5 μm, 9.4 × 
250 mm
). NMR spectra were recorded on a Bruker Avance III 400 spectrometer. HRESIMS spectra were obtained from an Agilent 1290 UPLC system with a Bruker microTOF-Q II mass spectrometer.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Fungal material
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Colletotrichum brevisporum
(Glomerellaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
strain PSSF01 was isolated from a plant stem collected in Baise City (
Guangxi province
, 
China
) at GPS coordinates 
23.5445 N
, 
106.3840 E
in 
November 2018
. The plant was identified by Dr. Tianxiang Li, 
Tianjin
College of Traditional Chinese Medicine, as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Piper sarmentosum
Roxb. (Piperaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
. First, the plant was washed by water to get rid of soil, then surface sterilization was conducted using 70% ethanol for 1 min, sodium hypochlorite (with 5–10% available chlorite) for 2 min, followed by a rinse of sterile water. The plant was divided into leaf, stem and root, and each section was cut into small pieces (
2–5 mm
) and placed onto the surface of solid media (

; 

). After two weeks, individual colonies were isolated and grown separately on agar plates. The isolated strains are retained in the internal fungal collection at the School of Pharmaceutical Science and Technology.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Identification of plant-derived fungus
</title>
         <p>
To identify the strain under investigation, the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) region and 28S region were amplified and sequenced using the following primers: ITS1/ITS4, LR6/LROR. The results were analyzed and compared to database sequences at National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The data revealed 100% identity to the ITS region of a fungal isolate (accession number JN943072.1), and 99.8% identity to 28S region of a fungal isolate (accession number NG_067524.1). Both accession numbers were derived from the known species 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. brevisporum
</tp:taxon-name>
. The ITS sequence was submitted to Genbank under accession number 
MW445186
. Phylogenetic trees were constructed and analyzed by neighbor-joining statistical method (
Fig. S3
and S 
4
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Fermentation
</title>
         <p>
The fungal strain was grown on Potato Dextrose Broth (PDB) media (Solarbio, 
Beijing
), which contained potato powder (6.0 g/L) and glucose (20.0 g/L) in distilled water (1 L) in a 2 L Erlenmeyer flask. Media was autoclaved for 20 min at 120 
◦
C. Fermentation was performed in twenty flasks for ten days (total 20 L) at 30 
◦
C in the shaker with rotating speed of 120 rpm/min.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
After fermentation, the fungal culture in each flask was first filtered through cheesecloth, the broth was extracted with EtOAc (400 mL) three times, while the mycelium was extracted with MeOH (200 mL) under ultrasonication. Then the EtOAc extracts and MeOH extracts were combined together and reduced under vacuum to yield a crude extract (
8.73 g
). To remove polar media components, aqueous-organic solvent partitions was conducted on the crude extract using EtOAc and BuOH in turn; the organic fractions were then combined and concentrated under vacuum (Savant SC 210A, Ameritech) to yield an organic-soluble extract (
2.85 g
).
</p>
         <p>
The extract was subjected to fractionation using a silica gel column (
25.8 g
) with eluents of increasing polarity using dichloromethane: methanol (400:1, 300:1, 200:1, 100:1, 80:1, 40:1, 20:1, 1:1, 0:1) to obtain a total of 9 fractions (Fr 1–9). Final purification was performed by reverse phase 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
with acetonitrile/H 
2
O as a mobile phase, at 8 mL/ min. Fr.2 was purified by semipreparative 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
, using isocratic conditions at 60% ACN to yield compound 
9
(3.0 mg). Fr.4 was purified by semipreparative 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
, using a gradient from 36 to 42% ACN to yield compound 
8
(10.0 mg). Fr.5 was separated by semipreparative 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
under isocratic condition at 48% ACN to yield pure compound 
1
(
6.4 mg
) and 
2/3
(
12.2 mg
). Fr. 6 was separated by semipreparative 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
under isocratic condition at 38% ACN to yield compounds 
4
(
2.4 mg
), and 
5/6
(4.0 mg), and 
7
(2.0 mg).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.5.1. Brevianthrone A1 (1) (
tR

= 
14.8)
</title>
         <p>
Light yellow solid; [α] 
20
D
+2 (c 0.05, MeCN); UV–vis (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 359 (1.96), 277 (1.95) nm; ECD (c 0.05, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δε): 365 (+0.90), 304 (5.79), 277 (+2.86), 254 (0.99), 232 (+2.85), 216 (8.46), 200 (+4.66) nm; 
1
H NMR (CDCl 
3
, 400 MHz) and 
13
C NMR (CDCl 
3
, 100 MHz) spectra, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
649.2049 [M+Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
36
H 
34
NaO 
10
, 649.2044).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.5.2. Brevianthrone A2/3 (2/3) (
tR

= 
15.1)
</title>
         <p>
Light yellow solid; [α] 
20
D
+8 (c 0.1, MeCN); UV–vis (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 360 (2.40), 278 (2.35) nm; ECD (c 0.1, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δε): 367 (2.14), 305 (+4.60), 279 (5.19), 233 (5.00), 216 (+9.75), 200 (5.47) nm; 
1
H NMR (CDCl 
3
, 400 MHz) and 
13
C NMR (CDCl 
3
, 100 MHz) spectra, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
649.2072 [M+Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
36
H 
34
NaO 
10
, 649.2044).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.5.3. Brevianthrone B1 (4) (
tR

= 
13.4)
</title>
         <p>
Dark yellow solid; [α] 
20
D
27 (c 0.1, MeCN); UV–vis (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 351 (2.27), 277 (2.22) nm; ECD (c 0.1, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δε): 384 (5.02), 348 (+5.11), 307 (10.7), 263 (+6.74), 232 (+9.02), 216 (7.60), 200 (+16.6) nm; 
1
H NMR (CDCl 
3
, 400 MHz) and 
13
C NMR (CDCl 
3
, 100 MHz) spectra, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
663.2189 [M+Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
37
H 
36
NaO 
10
, 663.2201).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.5.4. Brevianthrone B2/B3 (5/6) (
tR

= 
13.5)
</title>
         <p>
Dark yellow solid; [α] 
20
D
+26 (c 0.1, MeCN); UV–vis (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 350 (2.56), 276 (2.58) nm; 
1
H NMR (CDCl 
3
, 400 MHz) and 
13
C NMR (CDCl 
3
, 100 MHz) spectra, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
663.2176 [M+Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
37
H 
36
NaO 
10
, 663.2201).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.5.5. Brevianthrone B4 (7) (
tR

= 
14.2)
</title>
         <p>
Dark yellow solid; [α] 
20
D
+62 (c 0.1, MeCN); UV–vis (MeCN) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 351 (2.36), 271 (2.64) nm; ECD (c 0.1, MeCN) 
λ
max
(Δε): 386 (+11.24), 344 (11.60), 303 (+0.20), 262 (5.83), 243 (+2.28), 232 (4.46), 219 (+6.27), 200 (2.29) nm; 
1
H NMR (CDCl 
3
, 400 MHz) and 
13
C NMR (CDCl 
3
, 100 MHz) spectra, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
663.2182 [M+Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
37
H 
36
NaO 
10
, 663.2201).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.5.6. Nalgiovensin (8) (
tR

= 
14.7)
</title>
         <p>
Orange-yellow needle crystals; [α] 
20
D
+12 (c 0.1, CHCl 
3
); UV–vis (CHCl 
3
) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 438 (2.18), 287 (2.36), 265 (2.40), 249 (2.41) nm; HRESIMS 
m/z
351.0853 [M+Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
18
H 
16
NaO 
6
, 351.0839).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.5.7. Methoxy-nalgiovensin (9) (
tR

= 
12.6)
</title>
         <p>
Yellow needle crystals; [α] 
20
D
+10 (c 0.1, CHCl 
3
); UV–vis (CHCl 
3
) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
): 424 (2.13), 271 (2.53), 245 (2.40) nm; HRESIMS 
m/z
343.1179 [M+H] 
+
(calcd for C 
19
H 
19
O 
6
, 343.1176).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Computational details
</title>
         <p>
10 
R
, 10 
′
R
and 10 
S
, 10 
′
S
1

, and 10 
R
, 10 
′
R
; 10 
S
, 10 
′
R
; 10 
R
, 10 
′
S
; and 10 
S
, 10 
′
S
4

and 
7
were subjected to thorough mixed torsional/low-mode conformational sampling in Maestro (Schrodinger ¨Release 2020-2: Maestro, Schr¨odinger, LLC, 
New York
, NY, 2020) for a maximum number of 100,000 steps with a window for saving conformations of 10 kcal/mol and a 0.5 Å RMSD cutoff. Each conformer ensemble produced was subjected to geometry optimization, frequency calculations (maximally tight SCC convergence, extreme energy convergence for geometry optimization, ALPB solvation in acetonitrile, with 10,000 maximum steps), and sTDDFT at the CAM-B3LYP level utilizing GNF2- xTB and sTDA respectively (

; 

). Calculated UV and ECD spectra were Boltzmann averaged and compared to experimental spectra utilizing SpecDis (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

4.7. Chiral 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
analysis

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Samples were analyzed using Agilent 1260 normal-phase 
<tp:taxon-name>HPLC</tp:taxon-name>
equipped with an analytical CHIRALCEL® OD-H column, with hexane/ isopropanol as the mobile phase. Samples were run at isocratic conditions (20% isopropanol) for 60 min at 1 mL/min.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. X-ray crystallography
</title>
         <p>
Diffraction intensity was collected at 159.99 (10) K on a Rigaku XtaLAB FRX Diffractometer equipped with a Hypix6000HE detector, using Cu Kα radiation (λ = 1.54184 Å). Data reduction was accomplished using program crysAlispro (version 1.171. 
35.45 g
). The structure was solved by intrinsic phasing method using SHELXT and was refined by full-matrix least-squares technique using SHELXL-2015 embedded into OLEX2 1.3. All non-H atoms were refined with anisotropic displacement parameters. H atoms were placed in calculated positions and were refined using a riding model with an isotropic displacement parameter.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8.1. Crystallographic data for compound 1
</title>
         <p>
C 
36
H 
24
O 
10
, 2C 
36
H 
34
O 
10
, M = 1253.26, 0.2 × 0.03 × 
0.03 mm
, 
T
= 159.99 (10) K, monoclinic, space group P21, 
a
= 11.5419(2)Å, 
b
= 19.8213(4)Å, 
c
= 14.2445(3)Å, 
α
= 90 
◦
, 
β
= 113.029(2) 
◦
, γ = 90 
◦
, 
V
= 999.09(11)Å 
3
, 
Z
= 2, ρc = 
1.388 g
/cm 
3
, 
μ
(Cu) = 
0.840 mm
1
, 
F
(000) = 1320.0, 2 
θ
max
= 146.022 
◦
, 33,639 reflections, 11,450 independent reflections [
Rint
= 0.0548, 
Rsigma
= 0.0565], R1 = 0.0459, wR2 = 0.1092, and GOF = 1.010 for 11,450 reflections (849 parameters) with I ≥ 2σ (I), R1 = 0.0587, wR2 = 0.1173 and GOF = 1.010 for all reflections, the Flack = 0.08(9), max/min residual electron density 0.41/- 
0.18 e
Å 
3
. Crystallography data have been deposited in the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Center (CCDC). Deposition number: CCDC 2068588.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.9. Biological testing
</title>
         <p>Procedures for well diffusion assays and cytotoxic activity testing are provided in the supporting information.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
This work was funded in part by an award from the Research Fund for International Young Scientists (81850410550) from the National Science Foundation of 
China
, and by startup funds from 
Tianjin
University. The authors would like to thank S. Loesgen for her valuable comments during preparation of the manuscript, and Y. Zhao for providing the cell lines for cytotoxicity screening. The authors also acknowledge J. Xu and Y. Gao at the analytical center of the School of Pharmaceutical Science and Technology for their assistance in the acquisition of X-ray crystal structures and MS data, respectively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112792.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aly, A.H.
, 
Edrada-Ebel, R.A.
, 
Indriani, I.D.
, 
Wray, V.
, 
Müller, W.E.G.
, 
Totzke, F.
, 
Zirrgiebel, U.
, Sch¨achtele, C., 
Kubbutat, M.H.G.
, 
Lin, W.H.
, 
Proksch, P.
, 
Ebel, R.
, 
2008
. 

Cytotoxic metabolites from the fungal endophyte 
Alternaria
sp. and their subsequent detection in its host plant 
Polygonum senegalense

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
71
, 
972–980
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np070447m
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aoyagi, A.
, 
Ito-Kobayashi, M.
, 
Ono, Y.
, 
Furukawa, Y.
, 
Takahashi, M.
, 
Muramatsu, Y.
, 
Umetani, M.
, 
Takatsu, T.
, 
2008
. 

Colletoic acid, a novel 11β- hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase type 1 inhibitor from 
Colletotrichum gloeosporioides
SANK 21404

. 
J. Antibiot. (Tokyo)
61
, 
136–141
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/ja.2008.122
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ayo, R.G.
, 
Amupitan, J.O.
, 
Zhao, Y.
, 
2007
. 

Trihydroxy-3-methyl-anthraquinone (emodin) isolated from the leaves of 
Cassia nigricans
Vahl

. 
Afr. J. Biotechnol.
6
, 
1276–1279
. 
https://doi.org/10.4314/ajb.v6i11.57453
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bannwarth, C.
, 
Ehlert, S.
, 
Grimme, S.
, 
2019
. 
GFN2-xTB-An accurate and broadly parametrized self-consistent tight-binding quantum chemical method with multipole electrostatics and density-dependent dispersion contributions
. 
J. Chem. Theor. Comput.
15
, 
1652–1671
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jctc.8b01176
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Barth´elemy, M., Gu´erineau, V., 
Genta-Jouve, G.
, 
Roy, M.
, 
Chave, J.
, 
Guillot, R.
, 
Pellissier, L.
, 
Wolfender, J.L.
, 
Stien, D.
, 
Eparvier, V.
, 
Touboul, D.
, 
2020
. 

Identification and dereplication of endophytic 
Colletotrichum
strains by MALDI TOF mass spectrometry and molecular networking

. 
Sci. Rep.
10
, 
1–17
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1038/s41598-020-74852-w
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bezerra, J.P.
, 
Ferreira, P.V.
, 
Barbosa, L.
, da, F., 
Ramos-Sobrinho, R.
, 
Pinho, D.B.
, 
Reis, A.
, 
Assunç˜ao, I.P.
, 
Lima, G.S.A.
, 
2015
. 

First report of anthracnose on Chayote fruits (
Sechium edule
) caused by 
Colletotrichum brevisporum

. 
Plant Dis.
100
, 
217
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1094/PDIS-07-15-0793-PDN
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Borghi, S.M.
, 
Carvalho, T.T.
, 
Staurengo-Ferrari, L.
, 
Hohmann, M.S.N.
, 
Pinge-Filho, P.
, 
Casagrande, R.
, 
Verri, W.A.
, 
2013
. 
Vitexin inhibits inflammatory pain in mice by targeting TRPV1, oxidative stress, and cytokines
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
76
, 
1141–1146
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np400222v
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bruhn, T.
, Schaumloffel ¨, A., 
Hemberger, Y.
, 
Bringmann, G.
, 
2013
. 
SpecDis: quantifying the comparison of calculated and experimental electronic circular dichroism spectra
. 
Chirality
25
, 
243–249
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/chir.22138
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chiang, Y.M.
, 
Szewczyk, E.
, 
Davidson, A.D.
, 
Entwistle, R.
, 
Keller, N.P.
, 
Wang, C.C.C.
, 
Oakley, B.R.
, 
2010
. 

Characterization of the 
Aspergillus nidulans
monodictyphenone gene cluster

. 
Appl. Environ. Microbiol.
76
, 
2067–2074
. 
https://doi.org/10.1128/ AEM.02187-09
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Clark, B.R.
, 
Lacey, E.
, 
Gill, J.H.
, 
Capon, R.J.
, 
2007
. 

The effect of halide salts on the production of 
Gymnoascus reessii
polyenylpyrroles

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
70
, 
665–667
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np0605283
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
De Silva, D.D.
, 
Crous, P.W.
, 
Ades, P.K.
, 
Hyde, K.D.
, 
Taylor, P.W.J.
, 
2017
. 

Life styles of 
Colletotrichum
species and implications for plant biosecurity

. 
Fungal Biol. Rev.
31
, 
155–168
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbr.2017.05.001
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Duval, J.
, 
Pecher, V.
, 
Poujol, M.
, 
Lesellier, E.
, 
2016
. 
Research advances for the extraction, analysis and uses of anthraquinones: a review
. 
Ind. Crop. Prod.
94
, 
812–833
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2016.09.056
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elbanna, A.H.
, 
Khalil, Z.G.
, 
Bernhardt, P.V.
, 
Capon, R.J.
, 
2021
. 

Neobulgarones revisited: anti and syn bianthrones from an Australian mud dauber wasp nest-associated fungus, 
Penicillium
sp. CMB-MD22

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
84
, 
762–770
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.jnatprod.0c01035
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Figueroa, M.
, 
Jarmusch, A.K.
, 
Raja, H.A.
, 
El-Elimat, T.
, 
Kavanaugh, J.S.
, 
Horswill, A.R.
, 
Cooks, R.G.
, 
Cech, N.B.
, 
Oberlies, N.H.
, 
2014
. 

Polyhydroxy anthraquinones as quorum sensing inhibitors from the guttates of 
Penicillium restrictum
and their analysis by desorption electrospray ionization mass spectrometry

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
77
, 
1351–1358
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np5000704
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Form, I.C.
, 
Bonus, M.
, 
Gohlke, H.
, 
Lin, W.
, 
Daletos, G.
, 
Proksch, P.
, 
2019
. 

Xanthone, benzophenone and bianthrone derivatives from the hypersaline lake-derived fungus 
Aspergillus wentii

. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem.
27
, 
115005
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. bmc.2019.07.021
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fouillaud, M.
, 
Venkatachalam, M.
, 
Girard-Valenciennes, E.
, 
Caro, Y.
, Dufoss´e, L., 
2016
. 
Anthraquinones and derivatives from marine-derived fungi: structural diversity and selected biological activities. Mar
. 
Drugs
14
, 
64
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ md14040064
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fredimoses, M.
, 
Zhou, X.
, 
Ai, W.
, 
Tian, X.
, 
Yang, B.
, 
Lin, X.
, 
Liu, J.
, 
Liu, Y.
, 
2019
. 

Emerixanthone E, a new xanthone derivative from deep sea fungus 
Emericella
sp SCSIO 05240

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
33
, 
2088–2094
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 14786419.2018.1487966
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grimme, S.
, 
Bannwarth, C.
, 
2016
. 
Ultra-fast computation of electronic spectra for large systems by tight-binding based simplified Tamm-Dancoff approximation (sTDAxTB)
. 
J. Chem. Phys.
145

https://doi.org/ 
10.1063
/ 
1.4959605

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hiruma, K.
, 
Gerlach, N.
, Sacrist´an, S., 
Nakano, R.T.
, 
Hacquard, S.
, 
Kracher, B.
, 
Neumann, U.
, 
Ramírez, D.
, 
Bucher, M.
, O’ 
Connell, R.J.
, 
Schulze-Lefert, P.
, 
2016
. 

Root endophyte 
Colletotrichum tofieldiae
confers plant fitness benefits that are phosphate status dependent

. 
Cell
165
, 
464–474
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. cell.2016.02.028
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ji, N.Y.
, 
Liang, X.R.
, 
Sun, R.R.
, 
Miao, F.P.
, 
2014
. 
A rule to distinguish diastereomeric bianthrones by 1H NMR
. 
RSC Adv.
4
, 
7710–7715
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/ c3ra47055e
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kim, J.W.
, 
Shim, S.H.
, 
2019
. 

The fungus 
Colletotrichum
as a source for bioactive secondary metabolites

. 
Arch Pharm. Res. (Seoul)
42
, 
735–753
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s12272-019-01142-z
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kusari, S.
, 
Pandey, S.P.
, 
Spiteller, M.
, 
2013
. 
Untapped mutualistic paradigms linking host plant and endophytic fungal production of similar bioactive secondary metabolites
. 
Phytochemistry
91
, 
81–87
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2012.07.021
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lee, M.S.
, 
Sohn, C.B.
, 
2008
. 
Anti-diabetic properties of chrysophanol and its glucoside from rhubarb rhizome
. 
Biol. Pharm. Bull.
31
, 
2154–2157
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/ bpb.31.2154
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lin, X.
, 
Yu, M.
, 
Lin, T.
, 
Zhang, L.
, 
2016
. 

Secondary metabolites of 
Xylaria
sp., an endophytic fungus from 
Taxus mairei

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
30
, 
2442–2447
. 
https://doi. org/10.1080/14786419.2016.1198350
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, L.P.
, 
Zhang, L.
, 
Qiu, P.L.
, 
Xu, Z.
, 
Zhao, Z.M.
, 
Ren, S.C.
, 
Bai, Q.R.
, 
Chen, C.Q.
, 
Lu, B. H.
, 
Yang, L.N.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
Gao, J.
, 
Hsiang, T.
, 
2017
. 

First report of 
Colletotrichum brevisporum
causing anthracnose on pumpkin in China

. 
Plant Dis.
102
, 
1038
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1094/PDIS-08-17-1271-PDN
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ludewig, H.
, 
Molyneux, S.
, 
Ferrinho, S.
, 
Guo, K.
, 
Lynch, R.
, 
Gkotsi, D.S.
, 
Goss, R.J.M.
, 
2020
. 
Halogenases: structures and functions
. 
Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.
65
, 
51–60
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sbi.2020.05.012
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mandelare, P.E.
, 
Adpressa, D.A.
, 
Kaweesa, E.N.
, 
Zakharov, L.N.
, 
Loesgen, S.
, 
2018
. 

Coculture of two developmental stages of a marine-derived 
Aspergillus alliaceus
results in the production of the cytotoxic bianthrone allianthrone A

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
81
, 
1014–1022
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.8b00024
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maor, R.
, 
Haskin, S.
, 
Levi-Kedmi, H.
, 
Sharon, A.
, 
2004
. 

In planta production of indole-3- acetic acid by 
Colletotrichum gloeosporioides
f. sp. 
aeschynomene

. 
Appl. Environ. Microbiol.
70
, 
1852–1854
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1128/AEM.70.3.1852-1854.2004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mbwambo, Z.H.
, 
Apers, S.
, 
Moshi, M.J.
, 
Kapingu, M.C.
, 
Van Miert, S.
, 
Claeys, M.
, 
Brun, R.
, 
Cos, P.
, 
Pieters, L.
, 
Vlietinck, A.
, 
2004
. 

Anthranoid compounds with antiprotozoal activity from 
Vismia orientalis

. 
Planta Med.
70
, 
706–710
. 
https://doi. org/10.1055/s-2004-827199
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moraga, J.
, 
Gomes, W.
, 
Pinedo, C.
, 
Cantoral, J.M.
, 
Hanson, J.R.
, 
Carbú, M.
, 
Garrido, C.
, Dur´an-Patron´, R., 
Collado, I.G.
, 
2019
. 

The current status on secondary metabolites produced by plant pathogenic 
Colletotrichum
species

. 
Phytochemistry Rev.
18
, 
215–239
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11101-018-9590-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ndjakou Lenta, B.
, 
Devkota, K.P.
, 
Ngouela, S.
, 
Fekam Boyom, F.
, 
Naz, Q.
, 
Choudhary, M. I.
, 
Tsamo, E.
, 
Rosenthal, P.J.
, 
Sewald, N.
, 
2008
. 

Anti-plasmodial and cholinesterase inhibiting activities of some constituents of 
Psorospermum glaberrimum

. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
56
, 
222–226
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/cpb.56.222
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Noireung, P.
, 
Phoulivong, S.
, 
Liu, F.
, 
Cai, L.
, 
Mckenzie, E.H.C.
, 
Chukeatirote, E.
, 
Jones, E. B.G.
, 
Bahkali, A.H.
, 
Hyde, K.D.
, 
2012
. 

Novel species of 
Colletotrichum
revealed by morphology and molecular analysis

. 
Cryptogam. Mycol.
33
, 
1–16
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.7872/crym.v33.iss3.2012.347
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ohra, J.
, 
Morita, K.
, 
Tsujino, Y.
, 
Tazaki, H.
, 
Fujimori, T.
, 
Goering, M.
, 
Evans, S.
, 
Zorner, P.
, 
1995
. 

Production of the phytotoxic metabolite, ferricrocin, by the fungus 
Colletotrichum gloeosporioides
. Biosci. Biotechnol

. 
Biochem.
59
, 
113–114
. 
https://doi. org/10.1271/bbb.59.113
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Powell, V.H.
, 
Sutherland, M.D.
, 
1967
. 

Pigments of marine animals. VI. Anthraquinoid pigments of the crinoids 
Ptilometra australis
Wilton and 
Tropiometra afra
Hartlaub

. 
Aust. J. Chem.
20
, 
541–553
. 
https://doi.org/10.1071/CH9670541
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smith, S.G.
, 
Goodman, J.M.
, 
2009
. 
Assigning the stereochemistry of pairs of diastereoisomers using GIAO NMR shift calculation
. 
J. Org. Chem.
74
, 
4597–4607
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jo900408d
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Song, J.H.
, 
Lee, C.
, 
Lee, D.
, 
Kim, S.
, 
Bang, S.
, 
Shin, M.S.
, 
Lee, J.
, 
Kang, K.S.
, 
Shim, S.H.
, 
2018
. 

Neuroprotective compound from an endophytic fungus, 
Colletotrichum
sp. JS-0367

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
81
, 
1411–1416
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.8b00033
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sureram, S.
, 
Kesornpun, C.
, 
Mahidol, C.
, 
Ruchirawat, S.
, 
Kittakoop, P.
, 
2013
. 

Directed biosynthesis through biohalogenation of secondary metabolites of the marine-derived fungus 
Aspergillus unguis

. 
RSC Adv.
3
, 
1781–1788
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/ c2ra23021f
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tianpanich, K.
, 
Prachya, S.
, 
Wiyakrutta, S.
, 
Mahidol, C.
, 
Ruchirawat, S.
, 
Kittakoop, P.
, 
2011
. 

Radical scavenging and antioxidant activities of isocoumarins and a phthalide from the endophytic fungus 
Colletotrichum
sp

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
74
, 
79–81
. 
https://doi. org/10.1021/np1003752
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vieira, W.A.S.
, 
Nascimento, R.J.
, 
Michereff, S.J.
, 
Hyde, K.D.
, Cˆamara, M.P.S., 
2013
. 

First report of papaya fruit anthracnose caused by 
Colletotrichum brevisporum
in Brazil

. 
Plant Dis.
97
, 
1659
. 
https://doi.org/10.1094/PDIS-05-13-0520-PDN
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, F.
, 
Zhu, H.
, 
Ma, H.
, 
Jiang, J.
, 
Sun, W.
, 
Cheng, L.
, 
Zhang, G.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
2016
. 

Citrinal B, a new secondary metabolite from endophytic fungus 
Colletotrichum capsici
and structure revision of citrinal A

. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
57
, 
4250–4253
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.tetlet.2016.08.029
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
You, X.
, 
Feng, S.
, 
Luo, S.
, 
Cong, D.
, 
Yu, Z.
, 
Yang, Z.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
2013
. 

Studies on a rheinproducing endophytic fungus isolated from 
Rheum palmatum
L

. 
Fitoterapia
85
, 
161–168
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2012.12.010
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zou, W.X.
, 
Meng, J.C.
, 
Lu, H.
, 
Chen, G.X.
, 
Shi, G.X.
, 
Zhang, T.Y.
, 
Tan, R.X.
, 
2000
. 

Metabolites of 
Colletotrichum gloeosporioides
, an endophytic fungus in 
Artemisia mongolica

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
63
, 
1529–1530
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np000204t
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
