<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2023.113589</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Phenolic compounds from the flowers of Rosa hugonis Hemsl. and their neuroprotective effects</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rosa hugonis
Hemsl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rosa hugonis
Hemsl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rosa hugonis
Hemsl. Contain
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rosa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rosa hugonis
Hemsl. Is
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ginkgo biloba
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rosa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
(Rosaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Phenolic compounds from the flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rosa hugonis
Hemsl.
</tp:taxon-name>
and their neuroprotective effects

</p>
         <p>
Xia Zhang
a, d
, Bin Chen
a
, Yuan Xie
c
, Yeye Hu
c
, Zhiqiang Niu
c
, Ziliang He
c
, Lun Wang
a
,
</p>
         <p>
Guolin Zhang 
a
, Mingkui Wang
a
, Weicheng Hu
b, *
, Fu Li

a, 
**
</p>
         <p>
a

Natural Products Research Center, Chengdu Institute of Biology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Chengdu, 610041, 
China
</p>
         <p>
b

Medical College, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, 225001, 
China
</p>
         <p>
c
Jiangsu
Collaborative Innovation Center of Regional Modern Agriculture

&amp; 

Environmental Protection
/ 
Jiangsu
Key Laboratory for Eco-Agricultural Biotechnology


Around Hongze Lake, Huaiyin Normal University, Huaian, 223300, 
China
</p>
         <p>
d

University of 
Chinese Academy of Sciences
, 
Beijing
, 100049, 
China
</p>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Rosa hugonis
Hemsl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Phenolics</p>
         <p>Neuroprotective activity</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
The fragrant flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rosa hugonis
Hemsl. Contain
</tp:taxon-name>
abundant valuable rose oil and carotenoids. However, phytochemical investigation of this resource rich in phenolics with neuroprotective activity 
in vitro
has been rarely reported. Purification of the 70% ethanol extracts from the flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
by various chromatographic methods resulted in the isolation and characterization of five undescribed acylated flavonoid glycosides (Hugonisflavonoid A-E) together with forty known phenolics. The chemical structures of the undescribed compounds were elucidated by extensive analysis of their spectroscopic data and chemical methods. All the isolates were found from 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
for the first time and evaluated for their neuroprotective effects on 6-OHDA induced injury in PC12 cells. Seventeen compounds displayed remarkable protective effects at concentrations of 10 μM. Hugonisflavonoid E can reduce excessive reactive oxygen species and up-regulate mRNA expression levels of superoxide dismutase 1 and catalase. Additionally, hugonisflavonoid E activated the phosphorylated proteins such as PDK1, Akt and GSk-3β. These findings suggested that 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
could be a potential source for neuroprotective agents.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rosa
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) is composed of more than 100 wild species and tens of thousands of modern rose cultivars (

). In addition to be famous ornamental plants, rose flowers are rich in essential oil and other bioactive constituents such as ellagitannins, flavonoids and phenolic acids (

). Therefore, they are widely used in food, cosmetics and pharmaceutical fields. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rosa hugonis
Hemsl. Is
</tp:taxon-name>
a perennial shrub widely distributed in many provinces in western and northern 
China
(

). The fresh flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
contain valuable volatile oil which smells sweet and fragrant, while the fruits of this plant rich in nutrients can be eaten and brewed (

; 

). Also, several carotenoids were reported from the yellow petals of this resource (M¨arki-Fischer and 

).
</p>
         <p>
With the increase of human life expectancy, more and more people, especially the elderly, are suffering from neurodegenerative diseases such as Parkinson’ s, Alzheimer’ s and senile dementia (

; 

). At present, several chemosynthetic drugs with various side effects are mainly used for the treatment of cognitive deficits and memory loss related to these diseases (

). Also, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ginkgo biloba
</tp:taxon-name>
L., folium extract as a natural medicine was confirmed to be effective and safe in treating mild cognitive impairment and Alzheimer’ s disease and had been approved by European Medicines Agency (

). Thus, searching for alternatives from natural resources with better neuroprotective activities and less adverse effects is a promising direction. As a continuous study of our research team and collaborators to screen undescribed neuroprotective candidates from natural plants (

; 

), we found the 70% ethanol extracts of the flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibited moderate neuroprotective activity (
Table S1
). However, to the best of our knowledge, detailed phytochemical investigations on this species have not been
</p>
         <p>
reported. A high performance liquid chromatography/photo-diode array (HPLC-PDA) experiment on the flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
showed that they were abundant of flavonoids and other phenolic substances (
Fig. S1
and 
Table S2
), which might be responsible for the neuroactive activity. Thus, the present study focused on the isolation and structural characterization of phenolics from the flowers of the title plant. As a result, five undescribed acylated flavonoid glycosides together with forty known phenolics were obtained from this resource (
Fig. 1
). Furthermore, the neuroprotective effects of the isolates and the underlying mechanism were deeply explored.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Structural elucidation
</title>
         <p>
Compound 
1
, a yellow amorphous powder, had the molecular formula of C 
28
H 
24
O 
13
based on its HRESIMS at 
m/z
591.1109 [M +Na] 
+
in positive ion mode. The IR spectrumn of 
1
showed characteristic absorption bands for hydroxyl (
3421 cm
1
), double bonds (
1608 cm
1
) and an O-glycosidic group (
1079 cm
1
). The UV spectrum of 
1
demonstrated absorption bands at 
λ
max
251 and 
368 nm
, suggesting that compound 
1
was a flavonoid. The 
1
H NMR data of 
1
(
Table 1
) presented the proton signals at 
δ
H
8.10 (2H, d, 
J
=8.7 Hz), 
δ
H
7.20 (2H, d, 
J
=8.7 Hz), 
δ
H
6.47 (1H, brs), 
δ
H
6.20 (1H, brs) and 
δ
H
5.07 (1H, d, 
J
=7.1 Hz), which were in good accordance with those of kaempferol-4 
′
-O-β- Dglucopyranoside (

). The 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR spectra of 
1
(
Tables 1
and 
2
) also showed two doublet signals at 
δ
H
7.84 (2H, d, 
J
= 8.6 Hz) and 
δ
H
6.88 (2H, d, 
J
=8.6 Hz) and 
δ
C
165.4, 
δ
C
162.2, 
δ
C
131.5, 
δ
C
120.3 and 
δ
C
115.4, respectively, indicating the presence of a 
p
-hydroxybenzoyl group in 
1
(

). Acid hydrolysis of 
1
afforded kaempferol, 
p
-hydroxybenzoic acid and glucose, which were compared by co-TLC and HPLC with the authentic samples. Moreover, the glucose moiety was determined to be in 
β
-D-glucose form by measuring its optical rotation and inferring from the large coupling constant (7.2 Hz) of the anomeric proton. The linkages between kaempferol, glucose and 
p
-hydroxybenzoic acid were determined by the key long-range correlations from 
δ
H
5.07 (H-1 of Glc) to 
δ
C
158.2 (C-4 
′
of kaempferol unit), and from 
δ
H
4.59, 4.18 (H-6 of Glc) to 
δ
C
165.4 (C-7 of 
p
-hydroxybenzoyl unit) (
Fig. 2
). By extensive analysis of the 
1
H-NMR, 
13
C-NMR, DEPT, 
1
H– 
1
H COSY) HSQC, and HMBC data, the structure of compound 
1
was ulteriorly defined as kaempferol 4 
′
- 
O
-(6 
′′
- 
O -p
-hydroxybenzoyl)- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside (
Fig. 1
), named hugonisflavonoid A.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Recorded at 150 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
b
Recorded at 100 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
a
Recorded at 600 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
c
Recorded in DMSO‑ 
d
.
</p>
         <p>
6
d
Recorded in CD OD.
</p>
         <p>
b
Recorded at 400 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
</p>
         <p>
c
Recorded in DMSO‑ 
d
.
</p>
         <p>
6
d
Recorded in CD OD. m: multiple signal, o:overlapped.
</p>
         <p>
3
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
2
was isolated as a yellow amorphous powder and showed an HRESIMS peak at 
m/z
607.1059 [M + Na] 
+
, indicating a molecular formula of C 
28
H 
24
O 
14
. The 
13
C and 
1
H NMR data of 
2
(
Tables 1
and 
2
) were similar to those of known compound 
6
, except that the galloyl group in 
6
was replaced by a 
p
-hydroxybenzoyl in 
2
. Acid hydrolysis of 
2
gave quercetin, 
p
-hydroxybenzoic acid and glucose, further confirming the difference between compounds 
2
and 
6
. Detailed analysis of the DEPT, 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HSQC, and HMBC spectra definitely supported the structure of compound 
2
as quercetin 4 
′
- 
O
-(6 
′′
- 
O -p
- hydroxybenzoyl)- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside and named as hugonisflavonoid B.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of compound 
3
was determined as C 
30
H 
26
O 
13
according to the peak at 
m/z
617.1264 [M +Na] 
+
in HRESIMS. The 
13
C and 
1
H NMR data of 
3
(
Tables 1
and 
2
) was almost identical to those of 
1
for the kaempferol and sugar residue. The 
1
H NMR signals appearing at 
δ
H
7.51 (1H, d, 
J
=15.8 Hz), 
δ
H
7.48 (2H, d, 
J
=8.5 Hz), 
δ
H
6.70 (2H, d, 
J
=8.5 Hz), and 
δ
H
6.37 (1H, d, 
J
=15.8 Hz) suggested the existence of a 
trans -p
-coumaroyl fragment in 
3
rather than a 
p
-hydroxybenzoyl group in 
1
(

). By extensive 1D and 2D NMR data analysis, along with acid hydrolysis, compound 
3
was unambiguously defined as kaempferol 4 
′
- 
O
-(6 
′′
- 
O - (E)-p
-coumaroyl)- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside, named hugonisflavonoid C.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
4
was isolated as a yellow amorphous powder, and the peak at 
m/z
633.1210 [M + Na] 
+
in HRESIMS suggested its molecular formula as C 
30
H 
26
O 
14
. Comparison of the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (
Tables 1
and 
2
) of 
4
to those of 
3
could easily conclude that the discrepancies between these two compounds were in accordance with those between compounds 
1
and 
2
, revealing compound 
4
bore a quercetin backbone. In combination with the DEPT, 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HSQC, and HMBC data, the structure of 
4
was characterized as quercetin 4 
′
- 
O
-(6 
′′
- 
O - (E)-p
-coumaroyl)- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside, named hugonisflavonoid D.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of compound 
5
, C 
28
H 
24
O 
15
, was deduced from the peak at 
m/z
623.1002 [M +Na] 
+
in its HRESIMS. Compounds 
5
and 
1
shared the same kaempferol 4 
′
- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranoside fragment by comparison of their NMR data (
Tables 1
and 
2
). The 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR spectra of 
5
also showed one singlet at 
δ
H
7.14 (2H, s) and 
δ
C
168.2, 
δ
C
146.5, 
δ
C
139.9, 
δ
C
121.3 and 
δ
C
110.3, respectively, indicating the presence of a galloyl group [

,b]. With the aid of 1D and 2D NMR spectra, compound 
5
was finally elucidated as kaempferol 4 
′
- 
O
-(6 
′′
- 
O
- galloyl)- 
β
-D-glucopyranoside, named hugonisflavonoid E.
</p>
         <p>
Forty known compounds were also isolated and identified as quercetin 4 
′
- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranoside-6 
′′
-gallate (
6
) (

,b), kaempferol 3- 
O -β
-D-glucuronide (
7
) (

), kaempferol 3- 
O -β
-D-glucuronide 6 
′′
-methyl ester (
8
) (

), quercetin 3- 
O -β
-D-glucuronide 6 
′′
-methyl ester (
9
) (

), apigenin (
10
) (

), kaempferol (
11
) (

), kaempferol 3- 
O -β
-D-galactopyranoside (
12
) (

), kaempferol 4 
′
- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranoside (
13
) (

), quercetin (
14
) (

), quercetin 3- 
O -β
-D-galactopyranoside (
15
) (

), spireoside (
16
) (

), kaempferol 3- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranoside (
17
) (

), 8- 
O
-methylherbacetin-3- 
O -β
-D-sophoroside (
18
) (

), 8- 
O
-methylherbacetin -3- 
O -β
-D-(2 
′′
- 
O -α
-L-rhamnopyranosyl)-glucopyranoside (
19
) (

), noreugenin (
20
) (

), undulatoside A (
21
) (

), casuarictin (
22
) (

), eugeniin (
23
) (

), 1, 2, 3, 4, 6-penta- 
O
--galloyl- 
β
-D-glucose (
24
) (

), isocorilagin (
25
) (

), 4 
′
-dihydrophaseic acid (
26
) (

), icariside B 
2
(
27
) (

), icariside B 
1
(
28
) (

), corchoionoside C (
29
) (

), (6 
S
, 9 
R
)-roseoside (
30
) (

), (
E
)- 
p
-hydroxycinnamic acid (
31
) (

), (
E
)-caffeic acid (
32
) (

), citrusin C (
33
) (

), isocitrusin C (
34
) (

), eugenol-4- 
O -β
-D-(6 
′
- 
O
-galloyl) glucoside (
35
) (

), (
E
)-phenylpropene-3-methoxyphenyl-(6 
′
- 
O
-galloyl)-4- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranoside (
36
) (

), 1 
′
- 
O
-methyl-6 
′
- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranosyl caffeic acid ester (
37
) (

), eugenyl β- rutinoside (
38
) (

), (
E
)-8- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranosylcinnamic acid (
39
) (

), brevifolincarboxylic acid (
40
) (

), protocatechuic acid (
41
) (

), gallic acid (
42
) (

), 4- 
O -β
-glucopyranosyl gallic acid (
43
) (

), methyl gallate (
44)
(

), and ethyl gallate (
45
) (

) by comparison of their spectroscopic data with those reported in the literature. All the isolates were obtained from 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
for the first time. Moreover, compounds 
6
, 
8
, 
9
, 
18–21
, 
25–29
, 
34
, 
36–39
and 
43
were firstly isolated from the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rosa
</tp:taxon-name>
L..
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Effects of different compounds on 6-OHDA-induced PC12 cell injury
</title>
         <p>
Parkinson’ s disease (PD) is one of the most common neurodegenerative movement disorder, where oxidative stress appears to be an important element in PD. 6-OHDA could induce intracellular ROS overproduction and was often used in drug screening for Parkinson’ s disease models 
in vitro
(

; 

; 

). As shown in 
Table S1
, compounds 
5
, 
6
, 
13–16
, 
18–19
, 
32
, 
36–38
, 
40–41
, 
43–45
presented significant activities. Nevertheless, many of these compounds showed remarkable ability to promote cell proliferation. In order to eliminate the effects of cell proliferation, compound 
5
, which had a novel chemical structure and exhibited relatively good activity, was selected for further investigation of its inhibitory effect on 6-OHDA-induced toxicity in PC12 cells. As shown in 
Fig. 3A
, the cell viability was increased from 49.83% to 72.91%, 94.78%, 91.76%, 103.08% and 110.67%, respectively. When the concentration of compound 
5
was 20 μM or less, there was almost no effect on cell viability (
Fig. 3B
). Therefore, the concentrations used in subsequent studies were 20 μM or lower. As shown in 
Fig. 3C
, the cell numbers were reduced and attached cells were round and shrunken in 6-OHDA-- treated group. Pretreatment with compound 
5
restored the changes in cell number and morphology.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Effects of compound 5 on 6-OHDA-induced ROS generation
</title>
         <p>
Oxidative stress, defined as the overproduction of ROS, could cause alterations in proteins, lipids, DNA, glycogen and disrupt cellular homeostasis (

; 

). Previous studies suggested that excessive ROS contributed to dopaminergic neuronal cell loss and pathophysiology of disorders in PD patients (

). The antioxidant enzymes, such as SOD and CAT, are the key enzymes in body system to protect against oxidative stress (

). As shown in 
Fig. 4A
, the exposure of PC12 cells to 6-OHDA induced a marked increase of the cell fluorescence intensity in comparison to vehicle group. However, pretreatment with compound 
5
induced a significant decrease of ROS levels. As shown in 
Fig. 4B and C
, treatment of PC12 cells with 6-OHDA for 6 h significantly decreased the activities of SOD and CAT. However, pretreatment with compound 
5
dramatically minimized the 6-OHDA-induced changes in antioxidant enzyme activities. These results suggested that the neuroprotective effect of compound 
5
might be mediated by antioxidant defense mechanism.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.4. Effects of compouond 5 on the 6-OHDA-induced PI3K/Akt/GSK-3β
</title>
         <p>
signaling pathway
</p>
         <p>
PI3K/Akt is an important signaling pathway that controls many cellular processes, including cell division, autophagy, survival, and differentiation (

). Previous investigations have reported that natural products with protective activities against 6-OHDA-induced neurotoxicity may be mediated through the activation of PI3K/Akt/GSK3β signaling pathway, suggesting that the activation of GSK3β should be an important target (

; 

). We therefore examined the phosphorylated levels of PDK1, Akt, and G3K-3β. As shown in 
Fig. 5
, the phosphorylated levels of PDK1, Akt, and G3K-3β were decreased compared with the control group. Compound 
5
pretreatment significantly alleviated the declines of these three phosphorylated proteins.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
In summary, detailed phytochemical investigation suggested that 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
was abundant in flavonoid glycosides with kaempferol, quercetin and 8-methoxykaempferol as the aglycones (
1–19
), which contributted to the main neuroactive activity of this resource. According to the chemcial structures of compounds 
1–6
and their neuroactive activity, it could be conluded that the presence of a hydroxyl group at C-3 
′
was unfavorable for neuroactive activity. Compounds 
5–6
showed better activity than compounds 
1–4
, which might be due to the existence of more hydroxyl groups on the corresponding acylated groups. Compounds 
33
, 
35
and 
38
shared similarities in the chemical structure and exhibited remarkable neuroprotective activity, pointing out the direction for the development of related small molecule synthetic drugs. Although gallic acid analogues (
41
, 
42
, 
44
and 
45
) showed excellent neuroactive activity, they were widespread in nature and lacked selectivity in biological activity. Furthermore, it was demonstrated that compound 
5
protected against 6-OHDA induced oxidative stress through the upregulation of the PI3K/Akt/GSK3β signaling pathway. The results of the present study indicated that the flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
could serve as an alternative source for neuroprotective agents. Spireoside (
16
) showed good neuroactive activity 
in vitro
and had been obtained in gram scale. Thus, a further study is in progress to evaluate the 
in vivo
neuroprotective activity of this compound.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
Infrared (IR) spectra were gained on a PerkinElmer 1725X-FT spectrometer. Ultraviolet (UV) spectra were measured on a PerkinElmer lambda 35 UV/vis spectrophotometer. Optical rotations were obtained on a PerkinElmer 341 polarimeter. 1D (
1
H-NMR, 
13
C-NMR and DEPT135) and 2D (
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HSQC and HMBC) NMR spectra were recorded on a Bruker Avance 600 and a Bruker Avance III 400 spectrometer, respectively. High-resolution electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (HRESIMS) spectra were acquired on an LTQ Orbitrap XL mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, San Jose, CA, 
U.S.A.
). Analytical HPLC analysis was carried out on a Nexera LC-20AD with a model SPD-M40 photo diode array detector (Shimadzu, 
Japan
) and a Neptune C18 column (
250 mm
× 
4.60 mm
, 5 μm). Preparative and semi-preparative HPLC operations were performed on a CXTH apparatus with a UV3000 detector at 
254 nm
(
Beijing
Innovation Technology Co., Ltd., 
Beijing
, 
China
) equipped with GLP Prep-HPLC (250 × 
50 mm
, 10 μm) and GLP Prep-HPLC (250 × 
30 mm
, 10 μm) columns (Nanomicro Technology Co., Ltd., Suzhou, 
China
), respectively. Plates used for TLC were purchased from Qingdao Marine Chemical Group Co., Ltd. (Qingdao, 
China
). Sephadex LH-20 for column chromatography was obtained from GE Healthcare Bio-Sciences AB (
Uppsala
, 
Sweden
). Methanol (HPLC grade), acetonitrile (HPLC grade), 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) and 6-hydroxydopamine hydrobromide (6-OHDA) were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, 
U.S.A.
). The standard sugar of D-glucose, kaempferol, quercetin, 
p
-hydroxybenzoic acid, (
E
)- 
p
-coumaric acid and gallic acid were purchased from Chengdu PhytoElite Bio-technology Company Limited (Chengdu, 
Sichuan
, 
China
). The fetal bovine serum (FBS) was purchased from Corning (Medford, MA, 
U.S.A.
). Penicillin streptomycin solution was obtained from Invitrogen-Gibco (Carlsbad, CA, 
U.S.A.
). Protease and phosphatase inhibitor cocktail tablets were from Roche (Mannheim, 
Germany
). Phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) tables were bought from Amresco (Solon, OH, 
U.S.A.
). Goat antirabbit immunoglobulin G (IgG) H&amp;L horseradish peroxidase (HRP) was purchased from abcam (Cambridge, MA, 
U.S.A.
). Phospho-PDK1, PDK1, phospho-GSK-3β, GSK-3β, phospho-Akt and Akt were maintained from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA, 
U.S.A.
). PC12 cells were obtained from the ATCC (Rockville, MD, 
USA
). All cell culture supplies were bought from Corning (Medford, MA, 
U.S.A.
). A ROS assay kit (CA1410) purchased from Solarbio Life Sciences (
Shanghai
, 
China
). Bradford reagent, eECL Western Blot kit, lysis buffer, nuclear and cytoplasmic extraction kit were obtained from CoWin Biosciences (
Beijing
, 
China
). The deuterated solvents were bought from CIL Co. (YRTC, 
China
). All normal organic solvents (petroleum ether, ethyl acetate, dichloromethane, ethanol and methanol) were of the analytical grade and bought from Chengdu Kelong Chemicals Reagent Co. Ltd. (Chengdu, 
China
). The stock solutions of compounds were prepared in DMSO to 100 mM and the final concentration of DMSO was not in excess of 0.1% at any treatment.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>

The flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
(Rosaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected from 
Mao County
, 
Aba Tibetan
and 
Qiang Autonomous Prefecture
, 
Sichuan Province
, 
China
, in 

April 2019

. 
The
plant materials were identified by 
Professor Weikai Bao
, 
Chengdu Institute of Biology
, 

Chinese Academy of 
Sciences.

A voucher specimen (CIB–H-401) has been deposited in the herbarium of 
Natural Product Research Center
, 
Chengdu Institute of Biology
, 
Chinese Academy of Sciences

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
Air-dried flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. hugonis
</tp:taxon-name>
(
1.9 kg
) were smashed and then extracted with 70% EtOH at room temperature for three times (each time 12 L for 3 days). The combined extract solutions were evaporated under reduced pressure to yield a crude extract (
706 g
), which was suspended in purified water and extracted with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
and 
n
-BuOH, successively. The dried 
n
-BuOH extract (
210 g
) was fractionated over a Sephadex LH-20 column (
460 mm
× 
80 mm
) with a gradient solvent system of MeOH/H 
2
O (10:90, 30:70, 40:60, 50:50, 60:40, 70:30, 80:20, and 90:10) to afford eleven fractions monitored by TLC analysis (Fractions A K). Fraction B was separated over a Toyopearl HW-40 column (
300 mm
× 
40 mm
) with MeOH–H 
2
O (30:70, v/v) as the eluent to yield three subfractions (subfractions B1–B3). Compounds 
27
(
42.2 mg
; 
t
R
, 22.2 min), 
28
(
20.8 mg
; 
t
R
, 13.5 min), 
29
(
34.9 mg
; 
t
R
, 15.3 min), and 
30
(
26.3 mg
; 
t
R
, 18.6 min) were obtained from subfraction B2 by semi-preparative HPLC eluted by the mixed solvent of 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O (20 mL/ min, 32:68, v/v). Fraction C was subject to preparative HPLC using 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O with 1% 
CH
3
COOH (60 mL/min, 25:75, v/v) as the eluent to afford three subfractions (subfractions C1–C3). Subfraction C1 was separated by semi-preparative HPLC eluted with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O with 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 10:90, v/v) to give 
26
(
40.2 mg
; 
t
R
, 30.3 min). Compound 
38
(
31.4 mg
; 
t
R
, 16.8 min) was isolated from subfraction C2 by semi-preparative HPLC eluted by 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O with 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 25:75, v/v). Fraction D was repeatly applied to a Sephadex LH-20 column with MeOH–H 
2
O (30:70, v/v) as the mobile phase to yield four subfractions (subfractions D1-D4). Compound 
21
(
22.7 mg
) and 
39
(
41.8 mg
) were crystallized from subfraction D1 and D2, respectively. Compounds 
33
(
14.2 mg
; 
t
R
, 16.8 min) and 
34
(
19.8 mg
; 
t
R
, 18.0 min) were purified from subfraction D3 by semi-preparative HPLC with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O (20 mL/min, 40:60, v/v) as the eluent. Subfraction D4 was further separated by semi-preparative HPLC eluted with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 6:94, v/v) as the mobile phase to give 
43
(
18.5 mg
; 
t
R
, 16.0 min) and 
44
(
22.2 mg
; 
t
R
, 9.9 min). Fraction E was divided into five subfractions (subfractions E1-E5) by repeated preparative HPLC chromatography eluted by 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (60 mL/min, 19:81, v/v). Compound 
40
(
105.1 mg
; 
t
R
, 15.3 min) was obtained from subfraction E2 by semi-preparative HPLC using 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 11:89, v/v) as the mobile phase. Subfraction E3 was further purified by semi-preparative HPLC with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 15:85, v/v) as the eluent to give 
37
(
22.2 mg
; 
t
R
, 17.8 min). Compounds 
18
(
45.6 mg
; 
t
R
, 12.2 min) and 
19
(
61.8 mg
; 
t
R
, 14.4 min) were obtained from subfraction E4 by semi-preparative HPLC with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 25:75, v/v). Compound 
42
(
1.03 g
) was crystallized from fraction F. The remaining solution was further separated by semi-preparative HPLC eluted with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 10:90, v/v) to afford 
32
(
17.7 mg
; 
t
R
, 16.2 min) and 
41
(
18.1 mg
; 
t
R
, 13.9 min). Fraction G was first applied on an ODS column (
300 mm
× 
40 mm
) eluted with a gradient solvent system of MeOH/H 
2
O (20:80 to 100:0, v/ v) to yield five subfractions (subfractions G1-G5). Compounds 
10
(
60.3 mg
; 
t
R
, 40.3 min), 
11
(
83.3 mg
; 
t
R
, 30.2 min), 
12
(
201.7 mg
; 
t
R
, 21.8 min), and 
15
(
159.9 mg
; 
t
R
, 16.1 min) were purified from subfraction G2 by preparative HPLC eluted with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (60 mL/min, 38:62, v/v). Subfraction G4 was repeatly separated by semi-preparative HPLC with 
CH
3
OH–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 52:48, v/v) to yield compounds 
7
(
40.9 mg
; 
t
R
, 11.2 min), 
8
(
23.8 mg
; 
t
R
, 27.7 min), 
9
(34.0 mg; 
t
R
, 23.0 min), 
17
(
37.3 mg
; 
t
R
, 19.4 min), 
20
(
27.1 mg
; 
t
R
, 22.1 min), 
25
(
543.9 mg
; 
t
R
, 23.4 min), 
31
(
30.6 mg
; 
t
R
, 17.6 min), 
35
(
32.5 mg
; 
t
R
, 39.7 min), 
36
(
29.1 mg
; 
t
R
, 28.4 min), and 
45
(
28.4 mg
; 
t
R
, 18.0 min). Further purification of fraction H by preparative HPLC eluted with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (60 mL/min, 27:73, v/v) gave compounds 
13
(
119.6 mg
; 
t
R
, 27.0 min) and 
16
(
2.04 g
; 
t
R
, 21.9 min). Fraction I was separated by repeat preparative HPLC eluted with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (60 mL/min, 43:57, v/v) to yield seven subfractions (subfractions I1–I7). Compounds 
22
(
400.4 mg
; 
t
R
, 22.0 min), 
23
(
1.10 g
; 
t
R
, 31.6 min), and 
24
(
253.7 mg
; 
t
R
, 18.8 min) were isolated from subfraction I1 through preparative HPLC eluted with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (60 mL/min, 25:75, v/v). Similarly, compounds 
6
(
39.8 mg
; 
t
R
, 14.8 min) and 
5
(20.0 mg; 
t
R
, 16.4 min) were purified by semi-preparative HPLC from subfractions I2 and I3, respectively, with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 33:67, v/v) as the mobile phase. Further separation of subfraction I4 by semi-preparative HPLC using 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 36:64, v/v) as the eluent afforded 
2
(
39.2 mg
; 
t
R
, 38.8 min) and 
4
(28.0 mg; 
t
R
, 30.3 min). Subfraction I5 was further separated by semi-preparative HPLC eluted with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 38:62, v/v) yielded 
14
(60.0 mg; 
t
R
, 29.9 min). Compounds 
1
(
19.4 mg
) and 
3
(
22.7 mg
) were obtained from subfraction I6 by semi-preparative HPLC eluted with 
CH
3
CN–H 
2
O containing 1% 
CH
3
COOH (20 mL/min, 36:64, v/v).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Acid hydrolysis and components analysis of compounds 1–5
</title>
         <p>
Briefly, each undescribed compound (1.0 mg) was dissolved in 2 M HCl (1.0 mL) and heated in a water bath for 5 h at 80 
◦
C. The reactants were firstly neutralized with 2 M NaOH and then extracted exhaustively with EtOAc to get the supernatant, which was dried under reduce pressure. The dried substances were analyzed by co-TLC with anthentic kaempferol, quercetin, 
p
-hydroxybenzoic acid, (
E
)- 
p
-coumaric acid and gallic acid (
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH, 4:1). The remaining water layer was concentrated and then subject to TLC with anthentic glucose sample (
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH–H 
2
O, 2:1, water saturated). The absolute configuration of the glucose residue in compounds 
1–5
was determined to be in D-form by measuring their optical rotations ranging from [α] +45.7 
◦
to [α]+ 53.4 
◦
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Spectroscopic data of compounds 1–5
</title>
         <p>
Hugonisflavonoid A
(
1
). Yellow amorphous powder; [α], 58.1 
◦
(
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
), 
251 nm
(3.63), 
367 nm
(3.16); IR (KBr) 
ν
max
, 3421, 2925, 1608, 
1079 cm
1
; HR-ESI-MS 
m/z
591.1109 [M +Na] 
+
(calcd. For C 
28
H 
24
O 
13
Na 
+
, 591.1109); and 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data are shown in 
Tables 1
and 
2
</p>
         <p>
Hugonisflavonoid B
(
2
). Yellow amorphous powder; [α], 56.2 
◦
(
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 
196 nm
(4.27), 
266 nm
(3.67), 
312 nm
(3.17), 
367 nm
(3.32); IR (KBr) 
ν
max
, 3415, 1609, 1507, 1200, 
1072, 779, 617 cm
1
; HR-ESI-MS 
m/z
607.1059 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. For C 
28
H 
24
O 
14
Na 
+
, 607.1058); and 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data are shown in 
Tables 1
and 
2
</p>
         <p>
Hugonisflavonoid C
(
3
). Yellow amorphous powder; [α], 61.4 
◦
(
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 
254 nm
(3.63), 
367 nm
(3.47); IR (KBr) 
ν
max
, 3421, 2925, 1608, 
1079, 603 cm
1
; HR-ESI-MS 
m/z
617.1264 [M +Na] 
+
(calcd. For C 
30
H 
26
O 
13
Na 
+
, 617.1266); and 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data are shown in 
Tables 1
and 
2
</p>
         <p>
Hugonisflavonoid D
(
4
). Yellow amorphous powder; [α], 63.2 
◦
(
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 
224 nm
(3.54), 
245 nm
(4.27), 
271 nm
(3.37), 
312 nm
(3.29), 
368 nm
(3.27); IR (KBr) 
ν
max
, 3441, 1608, 
1073, 829, 602 cm
1
; HR-ESI-MS 
m/z
633.1210 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. For C 
30
H 
26
O 
14
Na 
+
, 633.1215); and 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data are shown in 
Tables 1
and 
2
</p>
         <p>
Hugonisflavonoid E
(
5
). Yellow amorphous powder; [α], 59.8 
◦
(
c
0.1, MeOH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 
198 nm
(4.36), 
219 nm
(4.37), 
270 nm
(3.25), 
368 nm
(3.17); IR (KBr) 
ν
max
, 3391, 1693, 1653, 1611, 1242, 
1073, 830, 602 cm
1
; HR-ESI-MS 
m/z
623.1002 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. For C 
28
H 
24
O 
15
Na 
+
, 623.1007); and 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data are shown in 
Tables 1
and 
2
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Cell viability
</title>
         <p>
PC12 cells were maintained in DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 5% horse serum, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 
100 mg
/mL streptomycin in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO 
2
. The cytoprotective effect of test samples on 6-OHDA-induced PC12 cells was measured with an MTT-based colorimetric assay (

). Briefly, 3 × 10 
5
cells/well were pre-treated with different compounds for 30 min before exposure to 6-OHDA (250 μM) for 24 h. The supernatant was removed, 100 μL of MTT solution was added and incubated for 4 h at 37 
◦
C. After that 100 μL of MTT solution was added to every well to solubilize formazan. The absorbance at 
550 nm
was determined with a microplate reader.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Bright field microscope photography
</title>
         <p>
PC12 cells were grown overnight at 3 × 
105
cells/well in a 96-well plate. The cells were treated with compound 5 for 10 min before exposure to 6-OHDA for 24 h and photographed under fluorescence microscopy.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Measurement of ROS with DCFH-DA staining
</title>
         <p>
To evaluate intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) production, PC12 cell were treated with different concentration of compound 
5
before exposure to 6-OHDA for 24 h. Cells were then stained with DCFH-DA for 1 h at 37 
◦
C. Cells were subsequently fixed and observed under an Olympus IX71 confocal microscope.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.9. Real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR)
</title>
         <p>Total RNA was extracted from PC12 cell by using TRIzol reagent and reversed transcribed into cDNA using Recert Aid First Strand cDNA synthesis kit (Thermo scientific). Real-time PCR was performed in a 20 μL reaction system containing cDNA, primers, and SYBR (Roche). GAPDH was used an internal control gene. The primers sequences were in this study were listed in Table S3.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.10. Western blot analysis
</title>
         <p>
PC12 cells were pretreated with different concentrations of compound 
5
for 30 min and then exposed to 250 μM 6-OHDA for 24 h. Total cell lysates were prepared using the lysis buffer and total protein concentrations were measured by BCA protein quantitative Kit (Absin, 
Shanghai
, 
China
). The protein bands were visualised using the eECL Western Blot Kit (CWBIO, 
China
) and photographed using the Tanon 5200 Multi imaging system (Tanon, 
Shanghai
, 
China
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.11. Statistical analysis
</title>
         <p>
All tests were carried out independently in triplicate (n =3). Results in the present study were represented as the mean ± SD (standard deviation). The significance was analyzed between the two groups using Student’ s 
t
-test and 
p
-values less than 5% were considered to be statistically different.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Data availability
</p>
         <p>Data will be made available on request.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
This research was financially supported by National Key Research and Development Program of 
China
(2017YFC0505106).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2023.113589.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Anik, M.I.
, 
Mahmud, N.
, 
Masud, A.
Al
, 
Khan, M.I.
, 
Islam, M.N.
, 
Uddin, S.
, 
Hossain, M.K.
, 
2022
. 
Role of reactive oxygen species in aging and age-related diseases: a review
. 
ACS Appl. Bio Mater.
31
, 
36043942
https://doi.org/10.1021/acsabm.2c00411
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bai, W.X.
, 
Wang, C.
, 
Wang, Y.J.
, 
Zheng, W.J.
, 
Wang, W.
, 
Wan, X.C.
, 
Bao, G.H.
, 
2017
. 
Novel acylated flavonol tetraglycoside with inhibitory effect on lipid accumulation in 3T3-L1 cells from Lu’ an GuaPian Tea and quantification of flavonoid glycosides in six major processing types of tea
. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
65
, 
2999–3005
. 
https://doi. org/10.1021/acs.jafc.7b00239
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chang, S.W.
, 
Du, Y.E.
, 
Qi, Y.
, 
Lee, J.S.
, 
Goo, N.
, 
Koo, B.K.
, 
Bae, H.J.
, 
Ryu, J.H.
, 
Jang, D.S.
, 
2019
. 

New depsides and neuroactive phenolic glucosides from the flower buds of Rugosa Rose (
Rosa rugosa
)

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
67
, 
7289–7296
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.jafc.9b01228
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cho, J.Y.
, 
Kim, S.J.
, 
Lee, H.J.
, 
Moon, J.H.
, 
2014
. 

Two novel glycosyl cinnamic and benzoic acids from Korean black raspberry (
Rubus coreanus
) wine

. 
Food Sci. Biotechnol.
23
, 
1081–1085
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10068-014-0148-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chulia, A.J.
, 
Bennini, B.
, 
Kaouadji, M.
, 
Allais, D.P.
, 
Delage, C.
, 
1995
. 

Two flavonol conjugates from 
Erica cinerea

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
58
, 
560–563
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ np50118a012
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ghosal, S.
, 
Singh, S.
, 
Bhagat, M.P.
, 
Kumar, Y.
, 
1982
. 

Three chromones from bulbs of 
Pancratium biflorum

. 
Phytochemistry
21
, 
2943–2946
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ 0031-9422(80)85074-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, D.
, 
Jiang, Y.
, 
Chen, W.
, 
Yao, F.
, 
Xue, D.
, 
Sun, L.
, 
2015
. 

New phenolic glycosides isolated from 
Penthorum chinense
Pursh

. 
Phytochem. Lett.
11
, 
163–167
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytol.2014.12.012
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jafari, M.
, 
Ghadami, E.
, 
Dadkhah, T.
, 
Akhavan-Niaki, H.
, 
2019
. 
PI3k/AKT signaling pathway: erythropoiesis and beyond
. 
J. Cell. Physiol.
234
, 
2373–2385
. 
https://doi. org/10.1002/jcp.27262
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jellinger, K.A.
, 
2010
. 
Basic mechanisms of neurodegeneration: a critical update. J
. 
Cell Mol. Med.
14
, 
457–487
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1582-4934.2010.01010.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ju, M.S.
, 
Kim, H.G.
, 
Choi, J.G.
, 
Ryu, J.H.
, 
Hur, J.
, 
Kim, Y.J.
, 
Oh, M.S.
, 
2010
. 
Cassiae semen, a seed of Cassia obtusifolia, has neuroprotective effects in Parkinson’ s disease models
. 
Food Chem. Toxicol.
48
, 
2037–2044
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. fct.2010.05.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kashiwada, Y.
, 
Nonaka, G.I.
, 
Nishioka, I.
, 
1986
. 
Tannins and related compounds. XLVII. Rhubarb. (6). Isolation and characterization of new
p
-hydroxyphenylbutanones, stilbenes and gallic acid glucosides. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
34
, 
3237–3243
. 
https://doi. org/10.1248/cpb.34.3237
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Khan, A.U.
, 
Akram, M.
, 
Daniyal, M.
, 
Zainab, R.
, 
2019
. 
Awareness and current knowledge of Parkinson’ s disease: a neurodegenerative disorder
. 
Int. J. Neurosci.
129
, 
55–93
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/00207454.2018.1486837
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, W.
, 
Chen, Y.F.
, 
Wang, L.
, 
Lu, P.
, 
Chen, L.J.
, 
Yang, X.X.
, 
2014
. 

Chemical constituents from herb of 
Kummerowia striata

. 
Chin. J. Exp. Tradit. Med. Form.
20
, 
91–94
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, M.
, 
Xia, Z.
ming, 
Li, B.
, 
Tian, Y.
, 
Zhang, G.
jie, 
Xu, C.
, 
Dong, J.
xing, 
2019
. 

Chemical constituents from 
Ginkgo biloba
L. male flowers and their biological activities

. 
Med. Chem. Res.
28
, 
1557–1566
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00044-019-02394-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, X.
, 
Cui, C.
, 
Zhao, M.
, 
Wang, J.
, 
Luo, W.
, 
Yang, B.
, 
Jiang, Y.
, 
2008
. 

Identification of phenolics in the fruit of emblica (
Phyllanthus emblica
L.) and their antioxidant activities

. 
Food Chem.
109
, 
909–915
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. foodchem.2008.01.071
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, C.
, 
Zou, K.
, 
Guo, Z.Y.
, 
Zhao, Y.Y.
, 
Cheng, F.
, 
Zhang, H.Q.
, 
2010
. 

Chemical constituents from leaves of 
Boehmeria nivea
. China J

. 
Chin. Mater. Med.
35
, 
1432–1434
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, J.B.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Cui, B.S.
, 
Li, S.
, 
2013
. 

Chemical constituents from twigs of 
Myricaria bracteata

. 
Chin. Tradit. Herb. Drugs
44
, 
2661–2665
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Long, H.Z.
, 
Cheng, Y.
, 
Zhou, Z.W.
, 
Luo, H.Y.
, 
Wen, D.D.
, 
Gao, L.C.
, 
2021
. 
PI3K/AKT signal pathway: a target of natural products in the prevention and treatment of Alzheimer’ s disease and Parkinson’ s disease
. 
Front. Pharmacol.
15
, 
648636
https:// doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2021.648636
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Luo, Y.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Liu, T.
, 
Cao, Y.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Yaseen, A.
, 
Sun, F.
, 
Zheng, W.
, 
Jiang, Y.
, 
Si, C.L.
, 
Hu, W.
, 
2019
. 

Senkyunolide H protects against MPP+-induced apoptosis 
via
the ROS-mediated mitogen-activated protein kinase pathway in PC12 cells

. 
Environ. Toxicol. Pharmacol.
65
, 
73–81
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.etap.2018.12.007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Luo, Y.
, 
Jiang, Y.
, 
He, Y.
, 
Shen, T.
, 
Ji, L.
, 
Li, F.
, 
Hu, W.
, 
2020
. 

Vina-ginsenoside R4 from 
Panax ginseng
leaves alleviates 6-OHDA-induced neurotoxicity in PC12 cells 
via
the PI3K/Akt/GSK-3 
β
signaling pathway

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
68
, 
15239–15248
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.0c06474
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
M¨arki-Fischer, E., 
Eugster, C.H.
, 
1998
. 

Isolierung von 10 
′
-Apo-β- carotin-10 
′
-ol und (3R)- 10 
′
-Apo-β- carotin-3,10 
′
-diol (galloxanthin) aus rosenblüten

. 
Helv. Chim. Acta
70
, 
1988–1993
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/hlca.19870700803
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ming, D.S.
, 
Jiang, R.W.
, 
But, P.P.H.
, 
Towers, G.H.N.
, 
Yu, D.Q.
, 
2002
. 

A new compound from 
Geum rivale
L. J

. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
4
, 
217–220
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 10286020290024022
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nonaka, G.
, 
Harada, M.
, 
Nishioka, I.E.
, 
1980
. 
A new ellagitannin from cloves
. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
28
, 
685–687
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/cpb.28.685
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Okamura, H.
, 
Mimura, A.
, 
Niwano, M.
, 
Takahara, Y.
, 
Yasuda, H.
, 
Yoshida, H.
, 
1993
a. 

Two acylated flavonol glycosides from 
Eucalyptus rostrata

. 
Phytochemistry
33
, 
512–514
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Okamura, H.
, 
Mimura, A.
, 
Niwano, M.
, 
Takahara, Y.
, 
Yasuda, H.
, 
Yoshida, H.
, 
1993
b. 

Two acylated flavonol glycosides from 
Eucalyptus rostrata

. 
Phytochemistry
33
, 
512–514
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rychlinska, I.
, 
Gudej, J.
, 
2002
. 

Flavonoid compounds from 
Pyrus communis
L. flowers

. 
Acta Pol. Pharm.
59
, 
53–56
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sabaragamuwa, R.
, 
Perera, C.O.
, 
Fedrizzi, B.
, 
2018
. 

Centella asiatica
(
Gotu kola
) as a neuroprotectant and its potential role in healthy ageing

. 
Trends Food Sci. Technol.
79
, 
88–97
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2018.07.024
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shi, X.R.
, 
Hong, Z.Y.
, 
Liu, H.R.
, 
Zhang, Y.C.
, 
Zhu, Y.Z.
, 
2011
. 
Neuroprotective effects of SCM198 on 6-hydroxydopamine-induced behavioral deficit in rats and cytotoxicity in neuronal SH-SY5Y cells. Neurochem
. 
Int.
58
, 
851–860
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. neuint.2010.11.007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Si, Z.
, 
Sun, L.
, 
Wang, X.
, 
2021
. 
Evidence and perspectives of cell senescence in neurodegenerative diseases
. 
Biomed. Pharmacother.
137
, 
111327
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.biopha.2021.111327
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tanaka, T.
, 
Orii, Y.
, 
Nonaka, G.
, 
Nishioka, I.
, 
1993
. 

Tannins and related compounds. CXXIII. Chromone, acetophenone and phenylpropanoid glycosides and their galloyl and/or hexahydroxydiphenoyl esters from the leaves of 
syzygium aromaticum
Merr. et Perry

. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
41
, 
1232–1237
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/cpb.41.1232
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tinelli, E.T.
, 
Sonheimer, E.
, 
Walton, D.C.
, 
Gaskin, P.
, 
MacMillan, J.
, 
1973
. 
Metabolites of 2-14C-abscisic acid
. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
14
, 
139–140
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wan, H.
, 
Yu, C.
, 
Han, Y.
, 
Guo, X.
, 
Ahmad, S.
, 
Tang, A.
, 
Wang, J.
, 
Cheng, T.
, 
Pan, H.
, 
Zhang, Q.
, 
2018
. 

Flavonols and carotenoids in yellow petals of Rose cultivar (
Rosa ‘Sun City
’): a possible rich source of bioactive compounds

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
66
, 
4171–4181
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.8b01509
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, Y.F.
, 
Li, S.W.
, 
He, R.J.
, 
Yang, B.Y.
, 
Huang, Y.L.
, 
2021
. 

Study on the chemical composition and tyrosinase inhibitory activity of 
Castanopsis ceratacantha

. 
Nat. Prod. Res. Dev.
33
, 
1499–1505
. 
https://doi.org/10.16333/j.1001-6880.2021.9.007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Weng, M.
, 
Xie, X.
, 
Liu, C.
, 
Lim, K.L.
, 
Zhang, C.W.
, 
Li, L.
, 
2018
. 
The sources of reactive oxygen species and its possible role in the pathogenesis of Parkinson’ s disease
. 
Parkinsons. Dis.
, 
9163040
https://doi.org/10.1155/2018/9163040
, 2018.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Won, D.J.
, 
Bae, Y.S.
, 
2013
. 
Flavonoids from the stem bark of Acer komarovii
. 
Chem. Nat. Compd.
49
, 
131–132
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10600-013-0531-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wu, Z.W.
, 
Li, W.B.
, 
Zhou, J.
, 
Liu, X.
, 
Wang, L.
, 
Chen, B.
, 
Wang, M.K.
, 
Ji, L.
, 
Hu, W.C.
, 
Li, F.
, 
2020
. 

Oleanane-and ursane-type triterpene saponins from 
Centella asiatica
exhibit neuroprotective effects

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
68
, 
6977–6986
. 
https://doi. org/10.1021/acs.jafc.0c01476
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, L.
, 
Li, Y.R.
, 
Li, C.
, 
Lin, L.M.
, 
Wang, Z.M.
, 
Luo, Y.M.
, 
2013
. 

Chemical constituents from whole plants of 
Aconitum tanguticum
. China J

. 
Chin. Mater. Med.
38
, 
2818–2825
. 
https://doi.org/10.16333/j.1001-6880.2021.9.007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yang, G.Y.
, 
Wang, Y.Y.
, 
Sun, J.
, 
Zhang, K.
, 
Liu, J.P.
, 
2016
. 

Ginkgo biloba
for mild cognitive impairment and Alzheimer’ s disease: a systematic review and metaanalysis of randomized controlled trials

. 
Curr. Top. Med. Chem.
16
, 
520–528
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yaribeygi, H.
, 
Atkin, S.L.
, 
Sahebkar, A.
, 
2019
. 
A review of the molecular mechanisms of hyperglycemia-induced free radical generation leading to oxidative stress
. 
J. Cell. Physiol.
234
, 
1300–1312
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/jcp.27164
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yoshikawa, M.
, 
Shimada, H.
, 
Saka, M.
, 
Yoshizumi, S.
, 
Yamahara, J.
, 
Matsuda, H.
, 
1997
. 

Moroheiya. (1): absolute stereostructures of corchoionosides A, B, and C, histamine release inhibitors from the leaves of 
Vietnamese Corchorus olitorius
L. (Tiliaceae)

. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.
45
, 
464–469
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/cpb.45.464
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, C.
, 
Li, C.
, 
Chen, S.
, 
Li, Z.
, 
Jia, X.
, 
Wang, K.
, 
Bao, J.
, 
Liang, Y.
, 
Wang, X.
, 
Chen, M.
, 
Li, P.
, 
Su, H.
, 
Wan, J.B.
, 
Lee, S.M.Y.
, 
Liu, K.
, 
He, C.
, 
2017
. 
Berberine protects against 6-OHDA-induced neurotoxicity in PC12 cells and zebrafish through hormetic mechanisms involving PI3K/AKT/Bcl-2 and Nrf 2/HO-1 pathways
. 
Redox Biol.
11
, 
1–11
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.redox.2016.10.019
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, Y.
, 
Huang, N.
, 
Chen, M.
, 
Jin, H.
, 
Nie, J.
, 
Shi, J.
, 
Jin, F.
, 
2019
. 

Procyanidin protects against 6-hydroxydopamine-induced dopaminergic neuron damage 
via
the regulation of the PI3K/Akt signalling pathway

. 
Biomed. Pharmacother.
114
, 
108789
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2019.108789
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhao, X.Y.
, 
Zhang, Z.J.
, 
Zhang, H.L.
, 
Wang, Y.M.
, 
1994
. 

Studies on chemical compounds of the essential oil from flowers of 
Rosa hugonis
Hemsl

. 
Acta Bot. Boreali Occident. Sin.
14
, 
154–156
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhao, R.
, 
Guo, A.J.
, 
Li, X.L.
, 
Li, J.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
2018
. 

Study on chemical constituents of 
Geranium wilfordii

. 
Maxim. Mod. Chin. Med.
20
, 
262–264
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhou, Z.Q.
, 
Bao, W.K.
, 
Wu, F.Z.
, 
He, X.
, 
Wu, N.
, 
2008
. 

Differences in growth and reproductive characters of 
Rosa hugonis
in the dry valley of the upper minjiang river, Sichuan

. 
Acta Ecol. Sin.
28
, 
1820–1828
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
