<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.112216</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Hyperelodiones A-C, monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphoroglucinols from Hypericum elodeoides, induce cancer cells apoptosis by targeting RXRα</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>29</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
choisy
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
Choisy. Their
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Guttiferae (Clusiaceae)</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Garcinia
(
Yang et al., 2018
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
Choisy
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. elodeoides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. elodeoides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
Choisy
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
H. elodeoides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Hyperelodiones A-C, monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphoroglucinols from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
</tp:taxon-name>
, induce cancer cells apoptosis by targeting RXRα

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Daren Qiu
1
, Mi Zhou
1
, Junjie Chen, Guanghui Wang, Ting Lin, Yujie Huang, Furong Yu,

Rong Ding
, Cuiling Sun, Wenjing Tian
∗∗
, Haifeng Chen
∗
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fujian
Provincial Key Laboratory of Innovative Drug Target Research, School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Xiamen University, Xiamen 361005, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
choisy
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Hyperelodiones</p>
         <p>MCF-7 cell</p>
         <p>HeLa cell</p>
         <p>RXRα</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Hyperelodiones A-C, three undescribed monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols possessing 6/6/6 fused tricyclic core, were isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
Choisy. Their
</tp:taxon-name>
gross structures were elucidated by HRESIMS and NMR data. The absolute configurations of hyperelodiones A-C were assigned by their calculated and compared electronic circular dichroism (ECD) spectra combined with their common biosynthetic origin. A fluorescence quenching assay suggested that hyperelodiones A-C could bind to RXRα- LBD, whereas hyperelodione C showed the strongest interaction with a KD of 12.81 μΜ. In addition, hyperelodiones A-C dosedependently inhibited RXRα transactivation and the growth of HeLa and MCF-7 cells. Among them, hyperelodione C showed the most potent inhibitory activities and dose-dependent PARP cleavage. Molecular docking results suggested that hyperelodione C showed a different interaction mode compared with hyperelodione A and hyperelodione B. Thus, hyperelodione C can be considered as a promising lead compound for cancer therapy, which can bind to RXRα- LBD and induce HeLa and MCF-7 cell apoptosis.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Polycyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols (PPAPs) are a class of structurally fascinating natural products that possess highly oxygenated acylphloroglucinol-derived cores. Prenylation of this core moiety affords monocyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols (MPAPs), which are further cyclized to various 
types
of PPAP metabolites (

). Monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols, generally decorated with a geranyl or a cyclic monoterpene fragment at C-3 of the phloroglucinol ring are ascribed to the MPAP family (

). Apart from their intriguing chemical structures, PPAPs have been reported to show diverse activities, such as anticancer, anti-inflammatory, anti-HIV, antiplasmodial, and antimicrobial activities (

; 

; 

; 

; 

). However, the mechanism of action of PPAPs still need further investigation. The retinoid X receptor α (RXRα), a ligand-dependent transcriptional factor, has multiple physiological functions including cell proliferation, differentiation, and apoptosis (

). RXRα is an ideal drug target for cancer therapy, and its ligand Targretin has been approved by the FDA for the treatment of cutaneous T-cell lymphoma (

). Our previous research has shown that several PPAPs exhibit RXRα transcriptional inhibitory activities, while some PPAPs have shown a direct interaction with the ligand-binding domain (LBD) of RXRα (

, 

, 

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
The majority of PPAPs have been reported to be isolated from the plants of family 
<tp:taxon-name>Guttiferae (Clusiaceae)</tp:taxon-name>
, especially from the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Garcinia
(
Yang et al., 2018
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. To identify more undescribed PPAPs as small-molecule regulators of RXRα, a phytochemical study of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
Choisy
</tp:taxon-name>
was carried out. As a result, three undescribed monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols (
1–3
) possessing 6/6/6 fused tricyclic core were obtained, of which 
3
could bind to RXRα- LBD and induce HeLa and MCF-7 cell apoptosis. The monoterpenoid fragments in 
1–3
have been predicted to be biosynthesized by an isopentenyl at C-3, forming a dihydropyran ring with the 4-OH of the core structure, with another lateral prenyl group located at C-8 cyclizing into a six-membered ring by a carbon–carbon bond formation between C-5 and C-7, which is quite different from the reported monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols cyclized by a geranyl group (two prenyl groups linked from head to tail) at C-3. In this paper, the isolation, structural elucidation and biological activity evaluation of these three undescribed monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols (
1–3
) will be reported.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
∗

Corresponding author.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
∗∗

Corresponding author.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
E-mail addresses:
tianwj@xmu.edu.cn (W. Tian), haifeng@xmu.edu.cn (H. Chen).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
1
These two authors contributed equally to this research.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Isolation and structural elucidation
</title>
         <p>
The dried whole plants of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. elodeoides
</tp:taxon-name>
(
12.9 kg
) were extracted exhaustively with 95% aqueous EtOH and partitioned consecutively with petroleum ether. The fluorescence quenching assay suggested that the EtOH and petroleum ether extracts could bind to RXRα with a KD values of 56.37 μΜ and 42.09 μΜ, respectively (supporting information). Thus, the petroleum ether extract was further studied to identify the small-molecule regulators of RXRα. As a result, through various column chromatography and reversed-phase HPLC procedures, three undescribed active compounds (
1–3
) were obtained (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Hyperelodione A (
1
) was obtained as a yellowish oil and assigned the molecular formula C 
26
H 
36
O 
4
on the basis of the HRESIMS [M+H] 
+
ion at 
m/z
413.2695 [M+H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
26
H 
37
O 
4
, 413.2686), corresponding to nine indices of hydrogen deficiency. The IR (
1651 cm
−1
and 
3581 cm
-1
) spectrum indicated the presence of carbonyl and hydroxyl groups. The 
13
C NMR and DEPT-135 data of compound 
1
(
Table 1
) showed 26 carbon signals, including an isopropyl group [
δ
C
35.4 (C-2′), 19.0 (C-3′), 19.4 (C-4′)], an isopentenyl group [
δ
C
35.7 (C-17), 120.3 (C-18), 133.6 (C-19), 25.9 (C-20), 18.3 (C-21)], an enol- 
β
- triketone group [
δ
C
106.2 (C-1), 190.1 (C-2), 196.4 (C-6), and 207.2 (C-1′)], an enol group [
δ
C
170.3 (C-4), 107.9 (C-3)], together with two olefinic carbons [
δ
C
134.9 (C-14), 121.6 (C-15)], four methyls [
δ
C
25.83 (Me-10), 25.1 (Me-11), 23.8 (Me-16), 25.78 (Me-22)], two methylenes [
δ
C
19.9 (C-12), 30.1 (C-13)], two methines [
δ
C
30.3 (C-7), 40.0 (C-8)] and one quaternary carbon [
δ
C
80.0 (C-9)], which accounted for six indices of hydrogen deficiency. The remaining three indices of hydrogen deficiency required tricyclic structure in 
1
. The above analyses implied that 
1
was a derivative of acylphloroglucinol. In the HMBC spectrum, the correlations from the active proton of OH-2 (
δ
H
19.34) to C-1 (
δ
c 106.2), C-2 (
δ
c 190.1), C-1′ (
δ
c 207.2), and C-2′ (
δ
c 35.4) confirmed the existence of the enol- 
β
-triketone group and located the position of the OH group at C-2. It also indicated that a pseudo six-membered heterocyclic ring was formed due to strong intramolecular hydrogen bonding between the active hydrogen and O-2′.
</p>
         <p>
The correlations from 
δ
H
1.25 (H 
3
-22) to 
δ
C
170.2 (C-4), 53.1 (C-5), and 196.5 (C-6), together with those from 
δ
H
3.28 (H-7) to 
δ
C
107.9 (C-3) and 170.2 (C-4) indicated the linkage of C3/C4/C5/C6. In addition, the HMBC correlations from 
δ
H
1.11 (Me-3′)/1.17 (Me-4′) to 
δ
C
35.4 (C-2′) and 207.2 (C-1′) suggested that isopropyl group was linked to C-1′ of the enol- 
β
-triketone group. Thus, a methylated acylphloroglucinol core was deduced. Furthermore, the HMBC correlations from 
δ
H
2.71, 2.49 (H 
2
-17) to C-5, C-18, and C-19 suggested the linkage of isoprenyl groups to C-5 of the core structure. In addition, the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations of 
δ
H
6.09 (H-15)/3.28 (H-7), 
δ
H
3.28 (H-7)/1.67 (H-8), 
δ
H
1.67 (H-8)/1.25 (
Ha-
12), and 
δ
H
1.25 (
Ha-
12)/1.98, 1.89 (H 
2
-13) showed a long spin system arising from the C-15 − C-7 − C-8 − C-12 partial structure. Combined with the HMBC correlations from H-7 to C-3/C-6/C-4/C-8/C-12, H-8 to C-3/C-15, H 
3
-10/H 
3
-11 to C-9, H 
2
-13 to C-8/C-14/C-15, and H 
3
-16 to C-13/C-14/C-15 indicated that an isopentenyl at C-3 formed a dihydropyran ring with the 4-OH of the core structure and another lateral prenyl group located at C-8 cyclized to form a six-membered ring by a carbon–carbon bond formed between C-15 and C-7 (
Fig. 2
). Hence, the 2D structure of 
1
was deduced.
</p>
         <p>
In the NOESY spectrum of 
1
, the correlations between 
δ
H
3.28 (H-7) and 1.26 (H 
3
-11) indicated that H-7 and Me-11 were located at the axial position with the same orientation. In addition, the NOESY correlations of 
δ
H
1.67 (H-8)/1.26 (H 
3
-11), and 
δ
H
1.67 (H-8)/1.40 (H 
3
-10) further suggested that the cyclohexene moiety was 
cis
-fused with the dihydropyran ring. Moreover, the NOESY correlations of 
δ
H
1.40 (H 
3
-10)/ 1.59 (H 
3
-21) and 
δ
H
1.40 (H 
3
-10)/1.80 (
Hb-
12) suggested the same orientation of Me-10 and the isoprenyl group at C-5 (
Fig. 2
).
</p>
         <p>
There was the presence of another minor tautomer (
1′
) due to the keto-enol tautomerism of the enol- 
β
-triketone moiety. The NMR data of 
1′
were similar to 
1
, except for the location of the OH group. In the HMBC spectrum of 
1′
, the active proton (
δ
H
18.39) was correlated to C-1 (
δ
c 110.4), C-5 (
δ
c 47.8), and C-6 (
δ
C
197.3), which located the position of the OH group at C-6. Due to the phenomenon of keto-enol tautomerism, the NMR data of 
1
were recorded in different solvents, including CDCl 
3,
CD 
3
OD, acetone- 
d
6
, DMSO‑ 
d
6
, and acetonitrile- 
d
3
. As a result, the ratios of the two tautomers (
1
: 
1′
) were approximately 1:0.23, 1:0.28, 1:0.17, 1:0.20 and 1: 
0.17 in
the CDCl 
3,
CD 
3
OD, 
acetone-d
6
, DMSO‑ 
d
6
, and acetonitrile- 
d
3,
respectively (supporting information). The ratio of the major tautomer (
1
) was larger in acetone- 
d
6
, DMSO‑ 
d
6
and acetonitrile- 
d
3
than in CDCl 
3
and CD 
3
OD. The ECD curve of 
1
was recorded in acetonitrile, the tautomer (
1
) was the main component. The absolute configurations of 
1
were assigned by comparison of the experimental and the calculated electronic circular dichroism (ECD) spectra. Due to the presence of minor tautomer (
1′
), the theoretical ECD calculation was conducted in acetonitrile using time-dependent density functional theory (TD-DFT) at the B3LYP/6–31 + g (d, p) level for the low energy conformers of the two tautomers (5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
)- 
1
and (5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
)- 
1′
. The ECD spectrum of (5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
)- 
1
and fitted ECD curve of two tautomers [(5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
)- 
1
and (5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
)- 
1′
] were generated using the program SpecDis 1.6 (University of Würzburg, Würzburg, 
Germany
) and GraphPad Prism 5 (University of 
California
San Diego, 
USA
) from dipole-length rotational strengths by applying Gaussian band shapes with sigma = 0.3 eV. As a result, the overall experimental ECD curve of 
1
matched well with the calculated ECD spectrum of (5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
)- 
1
as well as the fitted spectrum of two tautomers [(5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
)- 
1
and (5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
)- 
1′
] (
Fig. 3
). Thus, the minor tautomer contributed slightly to the ECD spectrum of 
1
. Consequently, the absolute configurations of 
1
were assigned as 5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
.
</p>
         <p>
Hyperelodione B (
2
) was isolated as a yellowish oil with the molecular formula C 
27
H 
38
O 
4
revealed by its HRESIMS [M+H] 
+
ion signal at m/z 427.2846 [M+H] 
+
(calcd. for C 
27
H 
39
O 
4
, 427.2843), requiring nine indices of hydrogen deficiency. The IR spectrum of 
2
(1656, 
3631 cm
−1
) indicated the presence of carbonyl and hydroxyl groups. The 
13
C NMR data of 
2
were similar to those of 
1
except for the isopropyl group was replaced by a 
sec
-butyl group in 
2
, as assigned by the HMBC correlations from 
δ
H
1.09 (Me-3′) to 
δ
C
206.8 (C-1′)/ 
δ
C
41.7 (C-2′)/ 
δ
C
27.0 (C-4′) and from 
δ
H
0.96 (Me-5′) to C-2′/C-4′ (
Fig. 2
). Thus, the 2D structure of 
2
was elucidated. The NOESY correlations of 
2
were similar to 
1
, which resulted in the same relative configuration (
Fig. 2
). The absolute configuration of the chiral center in the 
α
-methylbutyryl group can be determined on the basis of optical rotation data by the means of Brewster's rule of atomic asymmetry (

). According to this rule, if the absolute configuration of the chiral center in the 
α
-methylbutyryl group is 
S
, the optical value will be dextrorotation (+). The optical rotation value of 
2
([
α
] 
28
D

+26.3) was opposite that of 
1 (
[
α
] 

D
28
–18.6), which assigned the absolute configuration of C-2′ as 
S
. Furthermore, the absolute configuration of the 
α
-methylbutyryl group in the reported analogues hyperjapone C and E from the same genus were unambiguously determined as 
S
by the X-ray analysis (

). Thus, based on the biogenesis relationship, the absolute configuration of C-2′ can be further confirmed as 
S
. Moreover, the experimental ECD data of 
2
had a high degree of similarity to that of the biogenetically related 
1
(
Fig. 3
). Another minor tautomer with an OH group at C-6 also existed for 
2
, which contributed little influence on the CD spectrum of 
2
(
Fig. 4
). Thus, the absolute configurations of the chiral carbons in 
2
were defined as 2′ 
S
,5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
.
</p>
         <p>
Hyperelodione C (
3
), a yellowish oil, was assigned the molecular formula of C 
26
H 
36
O 
4
via 
13
C NMR and HRESIMS data with an [M+H] 
+
ion at m/z 413.2678 (calcd. for C 
26
H 
37
O 
4
, 413.2686), which accounted for nine indices of hydrogen deficiency. The IR absorptions at 3449 and 
1651 cm
−1
also indicated the presence of carbonyl and hydroxyl groups. The 
13
C NMR data of 
3
were identical to those of 
1
except for an 
n
-propyl group substituent at C-1′ instead of an isopropyl group, which was further confirmed by the HMBC and 
1
H– 
1
H COSY data (
Fig. 2
). The relative configuration of 
3
was also determined by the NOESY correlations, which resulted in the same configuration as that of 
1
and 
2
(
Fig. 2
). There was also another minor tautomer with the OH group at C-6 as in 
1
and 
2
, which slightly influenced the CD curve. The experimental ECD data of 
3
well to that of the biogenetically related 
1
(
Fig. 4
), which allowed the assignment of the same absolute configuration of 5 
R
,7 
S
,8 
R
.
</p>
         <p>
The putative biogenetic pathway of 
1–3
was proposed (Scheme 1). The structures of 
1–3
were proposed to derive from the isobutyryl-CoA (
i
), α- methylbutyryl-CoA (
ii
), and butyryl-CoA (
iii
), respectively. Then, further condensation with three malonyl-CoAs formed the acylphloroglucinol core through the represented polyketide-type biosynthesis pathway (

). The acylphloroglucinol core was further prenylated and methylated to afford monocyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols (MPAPs) (

). Finally, compounds 
1–3
were putatively biosynthesized from MPAPs through a series of reactions involving epoxidation, intramolecular cyclization, dehydration and reduction (

; 

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. The interaction between RXR
α 
-LBD and compounds 1–3
</title>
         <p>
RXRα, a crucial member of the nuclear receptor superfamily, is a ligand-dependent transcription factor. RXRα regulates biological processes such as cell differentiation, proliferation and apoptosis through the interaction with small-molecule modulators. RXRα possesses the classical functional domains of nuclear receptors, including a DNAbinding domain (DBD) and a ligand-binding domain (LBD) (

). Many natural products have been demonstrated to bind to the RXRα- LBD to modulate the genomic or nongenomic function of RXRα. In this study, the interactions between the RXRα- LBD and the compounds were investigated by fluorescence quenching technology, a method that measures the fluorescence quenching caused by a ligand binding to the protein. Gradual fluorescence quenching was observed when RXRα- LBD was exposed to increasing concentration of the new compounds 
1–3
(
Fig. 5
). The results showed that the binding constants (KD values) of compounds 
1
and 
2
to the RXRα- LBD were fitted as 47.01 μΜ and 32.50 μΜ, respectively, while compound 
3
could bind to RXRα-LBD with a KD of 12.81 μΜ. These data indicated that compounds 
1–3
have the potential to bind to RXRα, while compound 
3
showed a stronger interaction with the RXRα- LBD than the other two compounds.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. The RXR
α 
transactivation e
ff 
ects of compounds 1–3
</title>
         <p>
As a nuclear receptor, RXRα has genomic functions via transactivation. The effects of compounds 
1–3
on RXRα transactivation were examined by dual-luciferase reporter gene assay. As shown in 
Fig. 5
, all the compounds inhibited 9- 
cis
-RA-induced RXRα transactivation at concentrations of 12.5 μΜ and 25 μΜ, while compound 
3
exhibited better inhibitory activity than the other two compounds at the same concentrations (
Fig. 6
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Scheme 1.
Plausible Biogenetic Pathway of 1–3.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.4. Growth inhibitory activities of compounds 1–3 on MCF-7 and HeLa cells
</title>
         <p>
The growth inhibitory effects of compounds 
1–3
on the human cervical cancer cell line (HeLa) and human breast cancer cell line (MCF-7) were examined. As a result, all the compounds exhibited cytotoxic effects on these two cancer cell lines in a dose-dependent manner (
Fig. 7
). Among them, compound 
3
showed the most potent growth inhibitory effects on the HeLa and MCF-7 cell lines with IC50 values of 24.39 and 26.33 μΜ, respectively, while the IC50 values of compound 
1
on these two cancer cells were 37.80 and 44.37 μΜ, and the IC50 values of compound 
2
were 51.44 and 61.66 μΜ, respectively. The above data suggested that compound 
3
displayed potent anti-proliferative activity against HeLa and MCF-7 cells, while compounds 
1
and 
2
had moderate cytotoxic activities.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.5. Induction of PARP cleavage by compound 3
</title>
         <p>
To investigate whether compound 
3
induces cancer cell apoptosis, HeLa and MCF-7 cells were incubated with increasing concentrations (10–30 μM) of compound 
3
for 48 h. Cleaved poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP), a typical apoptotic marker in the apoptotic response, was measured via Western blot. As a result, 
3
induced HeLa and MCF-7 cell apoptosis with a dose dependent PARP cleavage (
Fig. 8
). Thus, compound 
3
could potentially induce HeLa cells and MCF-7 cell apoptosis.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.6. Molecular docking of 1–3 to RXR
α 
-LBD
</title>
         <p>
Molecular docking is an effective way to preliminarily understand the structure-activity relationship (SAR) by exploring the interaction mode between a compound and the targeted protein. In this study, a molecular docking technique was used to predict the interaction between compounds 
1–3
and the RXRα- LBD protein with Molecular Operating Environment (MOE) (2009.10) software. As a result, the carbonyl group at C-6 of 
1
and the hydroxyl group at C-2 of 
2
could interact with Lys 
440 in
the RXRα- LBD protein, while the carbonyl group at C-1′ of 
3
could bind to the Gln275 of RXRα- LBD with a different interaction mode (
Fig. 9
). The predicted binding sites of 
1–3
to RXRα- LBD were quite different from the traditional ligands which usually bind to Arg316 of the RXRα- LBD, such as for 9- 
cis
-retinoic acid.
</p>
         <p>
A preliminary SAR study was performed by extensive analysis of the structure and bioactivity. Compounds 
1–3
possess the common monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinol skeleton with a 6/6/6 fused tricyclic system, while the only difference lies in the substituents at C-1′. Contrasting the activity results of compounds 
1–3
, it was observed that 
3
, with an 
n
-propyl group at C-1′, showed more potent effects than compounds 
1
and 
2
, with an isopropyl group and a 
sec
-butyl group at C-1′, respectively. Based on the above analysis, the 
n
-propyl group at C-1′ in this 
type
of compound is helpful for the RXRα related activities, which was confirmed by the molecular docking results in which 
3
could bind to the Gln275 of the RXRα- LBD in a different interaction modes compared with 
1
and 
2
. Due to the limited quantities of the isolates, the thorough SAR needs further discussion.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
In summary, three undescribed monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols possessing a 6/6/6 fused tricyclic system, hyperelodiones A-C (
1–3
), were obtained from 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. elodeoides
</tp:taxon-name>
. The monoterpenoid fragments in 
1–3
were predicted to be biosynthesized by an isopentenyl at C-3 that formed a dihydropyran ring with the 4-OH of the core structure and another lateral prenyl group located at C-8 that cyclized into a six-membered ring by the carbon–carbon bond formation between C-5 and C-7. This was quite different from the reported monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols, which were cyclized by a geranyl group (two prenyl groups linked from head to tail) at C-3. The phenomenon of keto-enol tautomerism existed in these monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols. The major tautomer, with OH group at C-2, contributed in a high proportion and might due to the pseudo six-membered heterocyclic ring formed by strong intramolecular hydrogen bonding between the active hydrogen and O-2′. The absolute configuration of 
1
was assigned by the comparison of experimental and calculated ECD data, while the absolute configurations of 
2
and 
3
were assigned to be the same as 
1
by their similar experimental ECD spectra and common biosynthetic origin. In addition, the putative biogenetic pathway of 
1–3
was proposed. A fluorescence quenching assay suggested that 
1–3
could bind to RXRα-LBD, whereas 
3
showed the strongest interaction with a KD of 12.81 μΜ. In addition, compounds 
1–3
inhibited 9- 
cis
-RA-induced RXRα transactivation and the growth of HeLa and MCF-7 cell lines in a dose-dependent manner, while 
3
showed the most potent inhibitory activities. Western-blot assays showed dose-dependent PARP cleavage when HeLa cells and MCF-7 cells were exposed to 
3
. Molecular docking results suggested that 
3
with an 
n
-propyl group could interact with the Gln275 moiety of RXRα- LBD, which was quite different from the interaction mode of 
1
and 
2
. Thus, 
3
can be considered a promising lead compound for cancer therapy, which can bind to the RXRα- LBD and induce HeLa and MCF-7 cell apoptosis.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
Optical rotations were measured by using a Rudolph Autopol IV/IVT polarimeter (NJ, 
USA
). UV data were recorded on an UV-2600 UV/Vis spectrometer (Shimadzu, 
Japan
). CD spectra were measured on a Chirascan spectropolarimeter (Applied Photophysics, 
UK
). NMR spectra were conducted on a Bruker AVANCE III 600 MHz spectrometer (Bruker, 
Germany
). High-resolution electrospray ionization mass spectra (HR-ESI-MS) were acquired by using a Thermo Fisher Q Exactive mass spectrometer (Thermo, 
USA
). HPLC separations were performed with a Shimadzu LC-8A Liquid Chromatography system equipped with a DAD (Shimadzu, 
Japan
). YMC (RP)-18 column (5 μm, 10 × 
250 mm
; YMC, 
Japan
) were performed for reversed phase semipreparative separations. Silica gel (Qingdao Marine Chemical Ltd., 
China
) and Sephadex LH-20 (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech, 
Sweden
) were used for open column chromatography separations. Analytical thin-layer chromatography (TLC) separations were performed on silica gel GF254 plates (Qingdao Marine Chemical Inc., 
China
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>

The whole plants of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hypericum elodeoides
Choisy
</tp:taxon-name>
(wet) were collected from 
Ningde
city, 
Fujian Province
, 
China
, in 

September 2016

. They were authenticated by Prof. 
Zhen-Ji Li
(College of the Environment &amp; Ecology, Xiamen University). A voucher specimen (
HE-201609
) was deposited at the 
School of Pharmaceutical Sciences
, Xiamen University

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The dried and powdered whole plants of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. elodeoides
</tp:taxon-name>
(
12.9 kg
) were soaked overnight in 95% aqueous EtOH (4 × 100 L) at room temperature and then refluxed four times in 95% EtOH for 3 h each time. Concentration of the filtrate 
in vacuo
to yielded the crude extract (
949.7 g
). The extract was suspended in water and partitioned consecutively with petroleum ether. The petroleum ether extract (
150.7 g
) was subjected to silica gel column chromatography (CC) eluted with a gradient of cyclohexane− EtOAc (1:0, 50:1, 25:1, 10:1, 5:1, 2:1, 1:1, 0:1) to afford eight fractions (Fr. a1−Fr. a8). Fr. a3 (
29.5 g
) was further refined by silica gel CC eluted with petroleum ether− EtOAc (1:0, 400:1, 200:1, 100:1, 50:1, 25:1, 0:1) to afford eight fractions (Fr. a3A− Fr. a3H). Fr. a3E (
9.9 g
) was subsequently subjected to silica gel CC eluted with petroleum ether− acetone (200:1, 150:1, 100:1, 15:1, 0:1) to give six fractions (Fr. a3E1−Fr. a3E6). Fr. a3E4 (
5.8 g
) was fractionated by silica gel CC eluted with cyclohexane− EtOAc (1:0, 1000:1, 500:1, 250:1, 100:1, 15:1, 0:1) to give five fractions (Fr. a3E4A− Fr. a3E4E). Finally, compound 
2
(
4.5 mg
) was successfully separated by repeated prep-HPLC with MeOH–H 
2
O (97:3) at a flow rate of 5 mL/min, from Fr. a3E4C. Furthermore, Fr. a3E4D was purified by repeated prep-HPLC with 95% MeOH–H 
2
O at a flow rate of 5 mL/min, to yield compounds 
1
(
4.9 mg
) and 
3
(
8.8 mg
).
</p>
         <p>
Hyperelodione A
(
1
): yellowish oil; [
α
] 

D
28
–18.6 (
c
0.43, 
CH
3
OH); UV (
CH
3
OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 202 (4.06), 228 (3.98), 244 (4.00), 326 (3.82) nm; ECD (ACN) 
λ
max
(Δε) 198 (0.13), 239 (0.01), 313 (0.31) nm; IR (KBr) 
Ν
max
3581, 2979, 2361, 1697, 1652, 1381, 
1116, 974 cm
−1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS m/z 413.2695 [M+H] 
+
(cacld for C 
26
H 
37
O 
4
, 413.2686).
</p>
         <p>
Hyperelodione B
(
2
): yellowish oil; [
α
] 
28
D

+26.3 (
c
0.35, 
CH
3
OH); UV (
CH
3
OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 201 (3.78), 244 (3.74) nm; ECD (ACN) 
λ
max
(Δε) 198 (0.13), 237 (0.04), 313 (0.20) nm; IR (KBr) 
Ν
max
3631, 2977, 2314, 1656, 1526, 1458, 1211, 
1127 cm
−1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS m/z 427.2846 [M+H] 
+
(cacld for C 
27
H 
39
O 
4
, 427.2843).
</p>
         <p>
Hyperelodione C
(
3
): yellowish oil; [
α
] 
28
D

–23.0 (
c
0.66, 
CH
3
OH); UV (
CH
3
OH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 201 (4.12), 227 (4.02), 243 (4.03), 324 (3.87) nm; ECD (ACN) 
λ
max
(Δε) 186 (−0.02), 243 (0.26), 322 (0.28) nm; IR (KBr) 
Ν
max
3449, 2926, 2359, 1651, 1529, 1458, 
1119 cm
−1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS m/z 413.2678 [M+H] 
+
(cacld for C 
26
H 
37
O 
4
, 413.2686).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. RXR
α 
-LBD puri
fi 
ed protein
</title>
         <p>
Human RXRα- LBD (223–462) was cloned as an N-terminal histidine-tagged fusion protein in the pET-15b vector and overexpressed in 
E. coli
BL21 (DE3). After centrifugation, resuspension and sonication, the extract was incubated with the His60 Ni Superflow resin for 4 h. The combined protein was purified by a Ni2+-NTA agarose column at low temperatures.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Fluorescence measurements
</title>
         <p>
Fluorescence measurements were performed on a Cary Eclipse Fluorescence spectrophotometer (Varian) in a 
10 mm
quartz cuvette. The 1 mM concentration of RXRα- LBD was incubated with different concentrations of compounds. The protein was excited at 
280 nm
and the fluorescence spectra between 
290 nm
and 
500 nm
were measured with the a spectrophotometer at RT. The data were analyzed by Origin 2017.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Luciferease report assay
</title>
         <p>First, 293T cells were transfected with plasmids combined with 10 μg/mL pGL5 luciferase reporter vector and 4 μg/mL pBIND- RXRα-LBD vector. After 12 h, cells were treated with different concentrations of compounds for 12 h and then lysed by PLB on an oscillating platform for 20 min. Firefly luciferase (FL) and Renilla luciferase (RL) activities were analyzed with the Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay system (Promega).</p>
         <p>Relative luciferase activity (%) = FL/RL × 100%</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Cytotoxicity assay
</title>
         <p>
HeLa cells and MCF-7 cells were seeded into 96-well plates at a density of 5 × 10 
3
cells per well. After 12 h, cells were treated with different concentrations of compounds. After incubation for 48 h, 15 μL of MTT reagent and 60 μL of MEM (HeLa) or DMEM (MCF-7) was added and the cells were cultured for 4 h. After removing the supernatant, the transformed crystals were dissolved in DMSO (100 μL) and measured at 
490 nm
using a microplate reader (Thermo Multiskan MK3, Thermo Scientific, Helsinki, 
Finland
). The cell proliferation-inhibition rate (%) was calculated as follows:
</p>
         <p>Growth Rate (%)[(ODsample − ODblank)/(ODcontrol − ODblank)] × 100%</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Western blotting
</title>
         <p>Equal amounts of the cell lysates were electrophoresed on a 10% SDS-PAGE gel and transferred to nitrocellulose. The membranes were blocked with 5% nonfat milk in TBST buffer (10 mM Tris–HCl [pH 8.0], 150 mM NaCl, and 0.05% Tween 20) at RT. After 1 h, the membranes were incubated with various primary antibodies at 4 ̊C overnight. After washing three times with TBST, the membranes were detected with either anti-mouse (1:3000) or anti-rabbit (1:3000) antibodies for 1 h and washed four times. The final immunoreactive products were visualized by using an enhanced chemiluminescence system.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.9. Molecular docking studies
</title>
         <p>
Molecular docking studies of compounds bound to RXRα- LBD were performed with MOE (2009.10) software. Compounds were imported into the MOE database in.sdf format which were further optimized via partial charge, energy minimization, and geometry optimization (Rebuild 3D) with a root-mean-square gradient of 0.01 and saved in the.mdb database format. The 3D structure of RXRα- LBD (https://doi. org/10.2210/pdb4zsh) was downloaded from the Research Collaboratory for Structural Bioinformatics Protein Data Bank (RCSB PDB). For the docking process, the “Triangle Matcher” placement method and London dG scoring function were selected, and the results were further refined by the force field method. Molecular docking simulations of compounds 
1–3
with RXRα- LBD were conducted for 30 times, and the London dG scoring system was used to select the best interactions based on the smallest E_score2 provided.
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare no competing financial interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
This study was supported by the grants from National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(NSFC) (No.81602988), Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (No.20720190079) the fund Education and scientific research project of 
Fujian Province
(JAT160005) and Natural Science Foundation of 
Fujian Province
of 
China
(No.2019J007).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.112216.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Abe, I.
, 
Watanabe, T.
, 
Noguchi, H.
, 
2004
. 
Enzymatic formation of long-chain polyketid pyrones by plant type III polyketide synthases
. 
Phytochemistry
65
, 
2447–2453
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2004.08.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Altucci, L.
, 
Leibowitz, M.D.
, 
Ogilvie, K.M.
, 
Lera, A.R.
, 
Gronemeyer, H.
, 
2007
. 
RAR and RXR modulation in cancer and metabolic disease
. 
Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.
6
, 
793–810
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/nrd2397
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ciochina, R.
, 
Grossman, R.B.
, 
2006
. 
Polycyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols
. 
Chem. Rev.
106
, 
3963–3986
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/cr0500582
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Decosterd, L.A.
, 
Stoeckli-Evans, H.
, 
Chapuis, J.C.
, 
Sordat, B.
, 
1989
. 

Hostettmann, K. New cell growth-inhibitory cyclohexadienone derivatives from 
Hypericurn calycinurn
L

. 
Helv. Chim. Acta
72
, 
1833–1845
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/hlca.19890720820
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fobofou, S.A.T.
, 
Franke, K.
, 
Sanna, G.
, 
Prorzel, A.
, 
Bullita, E.
, 
Colla, P.L.
, 
Wessjohann, L.A.
, 
2015
. 

Isolation and anticancer, anthelminthic, and antiviral (HIV) activity of acylphloroglucinols, and regioselective synthesis of empetrifranzinans from 
Hypericum roeperianum

. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett
23
, 
6327–6334
. 
https://doi.org/10. 1016/j.bmc.2015.08.028
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hu, L.H.
, 
Sim, K.Y.
, 
Sampsoniones, A.-M.
, 
2000
. 

A unique family of caged polyprenylated benzoylphloroglucinol derivatives, from 
Hypericum sampsonii

. 
Tetrahedron
56
, 
1379–1386
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/chin.200024231
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lenhard, J.M.
, 
Lancaster, M.E.
, 
Paulik, M.A.
, 
Weiel, J.E.
, 
Binz, J.G.
, 
Sundseth, S.S.
, 
Gaskill, B.A.
, 
Lightfoot, R.M.
, 
Brown, H.R.
, 
1999
. 
The RXR agonist LG100268 causes hepatomegaly, improves glycaemic control and decreases cardiovascular risk and cachexia in diabetic mice suffering from pancreatic beta-cell dysfunction
. 
Diabetologia
42
, 
545–554
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s001250051193
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, Y.R.
, 
Xu, W.J.
, 
Wei, S.S.
, 
Lu, W.J.
, 
Lu, J.
, 
Kong, L.Y.
, 
2019
. 

Hyperbeanols F-Q, Diverse monoterpenoid polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols from the flowers of 
Hypericum beanie

. 
Phytochemistry
159
, 
56–64
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.12. 005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pei, Y.H.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Zu, T.R.
, 
1989
. 
An empirical correlations between optical rotation and absolute configuration of optical active α- methylbutyrylphloroglucinols and its synthesis
. 
Acta Pharm. Sin.
24
, 
413–421
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Robinsonrechavi, M.
, 
Garcia, H.E.
, 
Laudet, V.
, 
2003
. 
The nuclear receptor superfamily. J
. 
Cell Sci.
116
, 
585–586
. 
https://doi.org/10.1242/jcs.00247
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tian, W.J.
, 
Qiu, Y.Q.
, 
Chen, H.F.
, 
Jin, X.J.
, 
Yao, X.J.
, 
Dai, Y.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
2017
a. 

Chiral separation and absolute configurations of two pairs of racemic polyprenylated benzophenones from 
Hypericum sampsonii

. 
Fitoterapia
116
, 
39–44
. 
https://doi.org/10. 1016/j.fitote.2016.10.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tian, W.J.
, 
Qiu, Y.Q.
, 
Chen, J.J.
, 
Yao, X.J.
, 
Wang, G.H.
, 
Dai, Y.
, 
Chen, H.F.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
2017
b. 

Norsampsone E, an unprecedented decarbonyl polycyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinol with a homoadamantyl core from 
Hypericum sampsonii

. 
RSC Adv.
53
, 
33113–33119
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/c7ra05947g
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tian, W.J.
, 
Qiu, Y.Q.
, 
Jin, X.J.
, 
Chen, H.F.
, 
Yao, X.J.
, 
Dai, Y.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
2016
. 

Hypersampsones S–W, new polycyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols from 
Hypericum sampsonii

. 
RSC Adv.
6
, 
50887–50894
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/ c5ra26332h
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tian, W.J.
, 
Qiu, Y.Q.
, 
Jin, X.J.
, 
Chen, H.F.
, 
Yao, X.J.
, 
Dai, Y.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
2014
a. 

Novel polycyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols from 
Hypericum sampsonii

. 
Tetrahedron
70
, 
7912–7916
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-0034-1382626
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tian, W.J.
, 
Qiu, Y.Q.
, 
Yao, X.J.
, 
Chen, H.F.
, 
Dai, Y.
, 
Zhang, X.K.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
2014
b. 

Dioxasampsones A and B, two polycyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols with unusual epoxy-ring-fused skeleton from 
Hypericum sampsonii

. 
Org. Lett.
16
, 
6346–6349
. 

https://doi.org/10.1021/ol 
503122m

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tian, W.J.
, 
Yu, Y.
, 
Yao, X.J.
, 
Chen, H.F.
, 
Dai, Y.
, 
Zhang, X.K.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
2014
c. 

Norsampsones A-D, four new decarbonyl polycylic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols from 
Hypericum sampsonii

. 
Org. Lett.
16
, 
3448–3451
. 
https://doi.org/10. 1039/c7ra05947g
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yang, X.W.
, 
Grossman, R.B.
, 
Xu, G.
, 
2018
. 
Research progress of polycyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinols
. 
Chem. Rev.
118
, 
3508–3558
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. chemrev.7b00551
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yang, X.W.
, 
Li, M.M.
, 
Liu, X.
, 
Ferreira, D.
, 
Ding, Y.
, 
Zhang, J.J.
, 
Liao, Y.
, 
Qin, H.B.
, 
Xu, G.
, 
2015
. 

Polycyclic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinol congeners possessing diverse structures from 
Hypericum henryi

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
78
, 
885–895
. 
https://doi.org/10. 1021/acs.jnatprod.5b00057
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yang, X.W.
, 
Li, Y.P.
, 
Su, J.
, 
Ma, W.G.
, 
Xu, G.
, 
2016
. 

Hyperjapones A− E, terpenoid polymethylated acylphloroglucinols from 
Hypericum japonicum

. 
Org. Lett.
18
, 
1876–1879
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.orglett.6b00650
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, J.J.
, 
Yang, X.W.
, 
Ma, J.Z.
, 
Ye, Y.
, 
Shen, X.L.
, 
Xu, G.
, 
2015
. 

Cytotoxic polyprenylated acylphloroglucinol derivatives from 
Hypericum henryi

. 
Tetrahedron
71
, 
8315–8319
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tet.2015.08.059
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhu, H.
, 
Chen, C.
, 
Liu, J.
, 
Sun, B.
, 
Wei, G.Z.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Yao, G.
, 
Luo, Z.W.
, 
Xue, Y.B.
, 
Zhang, Y.H.
, 
2015
. 

Hyperascyrones A–H, polyprenylated spirocyclic acylphloroglucinol derivatives from 
Hypericum ascyron
Linn

. 
Phytochemistry
115
, 
222–230
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2015.02.009
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
