<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113086</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Autoproteolysis of Procerain and Procerain B mediated by structural changes</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asclepiadaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Autoproteolysis of Procerain and Procerain B mediated by structural changes
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Gaurav Srivastava
a
, Neeraj Gaur
b
, Ravindra D. Makde
b
, Sahayog N. Jamdar

a, 
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a

Food Technology Division, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, 
Mumbai
, 
India
b
Beamline Development
&amp; 

Application Section, Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, 
Mumbai
, 
India
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>Procerain</p>
         <p>Procerain B</p>
         <p>Autolysis</p>
         <p>Proteases</p>
         <p>Structural stability</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>DSF</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Procerain (Pc) and Procerain B (PcB) are two latex proteases from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
having potential applications in food and other industries. However, autolytic degradation of these proteases limits their potential use in industry. Nevertheless, basic mechanism underlying the autoproteolysis has not been detailed. In order to understand the same, we subjected the enzymes to various denaturing and activating conditions. The results showed that structural changes induced by different denaturing conditions trigger their autoproteolysis. We also observed differential response of Pc, PcB and other papain-like proteases towards autocatalysis in presence of reducing agent in-spite of sharing the same structural fold, including the number of disulfide bonds. The possible reason underlying this intriguing observation is also discussed. Further, present work establishes that structural changes in the proteases lead to autoproteolysis and the enzymes are stable unless they experience structural perturbation. These findings could thus be useful for their practical applications in industries.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Procerain (Pc) (

) and Procerain B (PcB) (Singh et al., 2010) are two major proteases of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
(Asclepiadeae tribe of Apocyanaceae family) latex, a widespread tropical plant. Plant parts including the latex has been shown to be useful in treatment of different ailments (

; 

). Both these enzymes have been characterized extensively for their biochemical properties (

; Singh et al., 2010), substrate specificity (

; Singh et al., 2010), stability (

, 

; 

) and industrial applications (

; 

; 

; Abhay Narayan 

). However, the enzymes are reported to be vulnerable to autolytic degradation (

; 

; Singh et al., 2010) and hence the purification of the enzymes was reported at 4 
◦
C in the presence of reversible inhibitor like sodium tetrathionate in order to prevent autodigestion during purification process. The autocatalytic inactivation of Pc and PcB have been reported by (

) and (Singh et al., 2010), respectively, in presence of reducing agent, 50 mM β- ME. For Pc, it occurs at lower concentration of the protein (
&lt;
0.55 mg
/mL) after prolonged incubation of 48 h at pH 8.0 and 37 
◦
C, while for PcB, it was relatively rapid. PcB loses 50% of activity in 5 h at concentration of
&gt;
0.2 mg
/mL in presence of 50 mM β- ME at 37 
◦
C (

; Singh et al., 2010). The same studies, on the other hand, showed high thermal and pH stabilities for these two enzymes. Hence, the mechanism for their autoproteolysis remains elusive and possibly occur in one of the conditions reported earlier for other proteases (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

). For instance, it could be because of activation of the enzyme or its global denaturation or presence of susceptible cleavage site in structurally unperturbed molecule. In view of all these different possible ways for autolytic degradation of these proteases, it was felt necessary to study the kinetic stability of Pc and PcB in detail with respect to their autoproteolytic degradation. Moreover, since 
<tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis
</tp:taxon-name>
cysteine proteases are of great importance due to their potential applications in different industries like food (

; 

; 

), pharmaceutical (

; 

), leather (Lop´ez et al., 2017; 

) or detergents (

), stability towards auto-degradation becomes all the more important aspect for their practical use.
</p>
         <p>
In order to study the stability of these proteases, the purification was carried out in the absence of inhibitor and purified protein was subjected to SDS-PAGE to check the purity of the preparation. Surprisingly, the polypeptide band did not appear on the gel or it was very faint even after loading sufficiently high amount of the purified proteins. This phenomenon was observed for both Pc and PcB. Addition of sodium tetrathionate to the enzyme before subjecting to electrophoresis also yielded similar results. However, addition of E-64, an irreversible inhibitor of cysteine proteases (

) prior to sample preparation for SDS-PAGE was effective to observe the protein bands on the gel. It thus indicated that both the enzymes might be proteolytically active and undergo autolysis during boiling with sample buffer containing 2% SDS and 150 mM β- ME. Hence, the kinetic stability of the enzymes at different temperatures was studied in presence of denaturants/activators like SDS, β- ME and GdnHCl. The main focus of the study is to see the effect of temperature on denaturation 
vis a vis
autodegradation of the enzymes in presence of these agents. Further, it would be interesting to elucidate the mechanism by which the proteases undergo self-degradation in these different environments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
E-mail addresses:
snjam@barc.gov.in, snjam2@gmail.com (S.N. Jamdar).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Purification of Pc and PcB and their SDS-PAGE profile
</title>
         <p>
Pc and PcB were purified according to the method described by (

) and (Singh et al., 2010), respectively, with minor modifications. The purification was carried out at 4 
◦
C in the absence of any inhibitor. The final purification of both enzymes was carried out on Superdex 200 to obtain their single symmetrical peaks. The purified enzymes were subsequently used for all the experiments described here.
</p>
         <p>
The enzymes were incubated for 3 min with individual or mixture of the components of SDS-PAGE sample buffer in boiling condition in presence or absence of E-64. After the incubation, E-64 was added to all the samples devoid of E-64. All these samples were later subjected to SDS-PAGE after treating them with sample buffer. The results of the same are presented in 
Fig. 1A and B
. The results showed that in the absence of E-64, a potent inhibitor of cysteine proteases, complete disappearance of Pc protein band was observed on gel upon boiling in the individual components of SDS-PAGE sample preparation buffer 
viz.
50 mM Tris-Cl pH 6.8, 2% SDS, 150 mM β- ME or their mixture i.e., 2% SDS and 150 mM β- ME. For PcB, partial disappearance of the protein band was observed on the gel when samples were boiled in 50 mM Tris pH 6.8 and 2% SDS and were completely disappeared in 150 mM β- ME and combination of 2% SDS and 150 mM β- ME. On the contrary, addition of E-64 during sample preparation led to appearance of protein bands on the gel for both the enzymes. The possible reason for the observed phenomenon could be autodigestion of the enzymes during sample preparation. Autoproteolysis of papain-like proteases have been reported upon their activation in the presence of reducing agent like β- ME (

; 

). However, the SDS-PAGE profile shows that Pc undergoes autolysis within 3 min in boiling conditions and the autolysis is irrespective of presence of β- ME. On the other hand, PcB exhibits complete autodigestion only in the presence of β- ME. This differential response of the two enzymes to the aforementioned conditions leading to autolysis makes it interesting to understand the basic mechanism behind autodigestion and to find out, if it is linked to kinetic stability of the proteins.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Kinetic stability of Pc and PcB
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2.1. Enzyme activity
</title>
         <p>
Kinetic stability of the enzymes at different temperatures was monitored by measuring their residual activities upon incubation in the conditions where autodigestion was observed (
Fig. 2A and B
). For native enzymes, temperature stability was monitored in absence or presence of reducing agent (1–150 mM β- ME) by incubating at different temperatures for 10 min. The residual activity of Pc and PcB is shown in 
Fig. 2A and B
, respectively. The result shows that Pc is rather stable up to 70 
◦
C and showed gradual decrease in activity thereafter. Similar observations had been made in previous studies (

). The relative stability of PcB is lower than that of Pc, with the former showing steady decrease in activity as the temperature increased from 30 
◦
C to 85 
◦
C. The presence of β- ME did not affect the stability of both the enzymes at lower temperatures at least for 10 min, however, as the temperature increased, higher concentrations of β- ME led to decrease in the activity. On the other hand, lower concentrations (1 and 10 mM) of β- ME actually exhibited activation of PcB in the temperature range of 50–70 
◦
C.
</p>
         <p>
Stability of the enzymes in SDS (2%) alone and in combination with β- ME (150 mM) was assessed at ambient conditions and 50 
◦
C for 3 min (
Fig. 2C and D
). At ambient conditions, Pc retained 25% residual activity in both 2% SDS as well as 2% SDS containing 150 mM β- ME, while at 50 
◦
C, it showed complete loss of activity in both the conditions. PcB on the other hand showed complete inactivation even at ambient conditions. Stability of the enzymes was also studied in presence of GdnHCl in the range of 2–4 M concentration, either alone or in combination with β- ME (150 mM) at ambient conditions, 50 
◦
C and 65 
◦
C for 3 min (
Fig. 2E and F
). At ambient conditions, both the enzymes did not show significant loss in activity even at 4 M concentration of GdnHCl. Previous studies had reported that Pc and PcB are stable in 4 M and 2 M GdnHCl, respectively, at ambient conditions (

; Singh et al., 2010), while our observations show that PcB is also stable even up to 4 M GdnHCl. At 50 
◦
C, PcB, but not Pc, showed steady loss in activity at 3 M and 4 M concentration of GdnHCl. At 65 
◦
C, Pc showed 35% loss in activity at 3 M concentration, while
&gt;
90% loss was observed at 4 M concentration. PcB, at this temperature, showed 70% reduction in activity with 2 M GdnHCl, while
&gt;
90% loss was observed at 3 M and 4 M concentrations. No additional loss of enzyme activity was observed when the combination of β- ME and GdnHCl was used at ambient conditions and 50 
◦
C, however, at 65 
◦
C, it showed significant reduction in activity, which is similar to that observed with β- ME alone (
Fig. 2E and F
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2.2. Protein denaturation kinetics
</title>
         <p>
Thermal denaturation of the enzymes was studied in real-time using differential scanning fluorimetry (DSF). It was carried out for enzymes alone or in combination with GdnHCl and/or β- ME, in presence and absence of E-64 (
Fig. 3A–D
and Supplementary 
Fig. 3A and B
). The denaturation curves of native proteins showed that thermal denaturation of Pc starts at 80 
◦
C, while that of PcB, above 75 
◦
C (
Fig. 3A and B
). The transition temperature of Pc and PcB was not affected due to the presence of E-64. In presence of β- ME, the transition occurred at lower temperatures, with the effect more distinguishable in case of Pc than that in PcB (
Fig. 3A and B
). The increase in fluorescence was higher in case of E-64 inhibited proteins than that of the uninhibited proteins. The relative increase in fluorescence intensity of Pc upon unfolding in presence of β- ME was higher than that observed for native protein, suggesting increased degree of unfolding. Surprisingly, the reverse was observed for PcB, wherein the relative fluorescence intensity decreased in presence of β- ME compared to native protein. Since the thermal denaturation could not be studied in presence of SDS (due to interaction of the dye, SYPRO Orange, with SDS), we used another denaturant GdnHCl to study the same. In case of Pc, for unknown reasons, we could not observe any significant increase in fluorescence irrespective of concentrations of GdnHCl and presence of β- ME and/or E- 
64 in
the mix subjected to DSF studies (Supplementary 
Fig. 3A and B
). Although just a small spur of increase in fluorescence was observed during enzyme alone subjected to denaturation in presence of GdnHCl (Supplementary 
Fig. 1B
), it is not significant to suggest the denaturation temperature in those conditions (Supplementary 
Fig. 1B
). Nevertheless, for PcB, increase in concentration of GdnHCl resulted in decrease in melting temperature and presence of β- ME did not influence thermal denaturation profile of the proteins (
Fig. 3C and D
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Autodigestion of Pc and PcB at different temperatures in presence of
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3.1. SDS sample buffer components
</title>
         <p>
Autodigestion of Pc and PcB in sample buffer and its individual components was monitored at different temperatures. The protein was subjected to individual conditions for 3 min in a similar way as carried out for SDS-PAGE sample preparation. After the incubation time, the reaction tube was quickly transferred to ice bath and 0.1 mM of E-64 was added to stop possible autodigestion during sample preparation and subjected to SDS-PAGE. The results are presented in 
Fig. 4
(A-G). The figures show that Pc and PcB exhibited autodigestion at different temperatures depending on the presence of a particular component of the sample buffer. In native conditions, i.e., 50 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0, both Pc and PcB were observed to be stable to proteolysis by itself up to 80 
◦
C, however, at 85 
◦
C, they undergo autodigestion. Intriguingly, autodigestion of Pc was observed even at 100 
◦
C, while not for PcB. This could be due to rapid loss of activity of PcB at boiling temperature, thereby preventing its complete autodigestion. In 2% SDS, complete autodigestion of Pc and PcB was observed at 50 
◦
C and 37 
◦
C, respectively, after 3 min. However, at temperature ≥70 
◦
C, the autodigestibility of Pc was slightly reduced and protein band started to appear on the gel (
Fig. 4D–G
). This could be due to higher rate of inactivation at these temperatures leading to diminished autodigestion. For PcB, autodigestion in presence of 2% SDS was observed even at higher temperatures (
&gt;
70 
◦
C). Autoproteolysis in presence of 150 mM β- ME, for both the enzymes, was discernible at temperatures ≥70 
◦
C and could be observed even up to 100 
◦
C. Autodegradation profile of the enzymes in presence of 2% SDS and 150 mM β- ME combination is just similar to that observed for individual enzymes in presence of 2% SDS alone except for PcB at temperatures above 70 
◦
C. In the latter conditions, unlike Pc, PcB showed complete autodigestion.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3.2. GdnHCl and GdnHCl in combination with β- ME
</title>
         <p>
The autodigestion of the Pc and PcB was also evaluated in the presence of different concentrations of GdnHCl (2–4 M) (
Fig. 5A–F
). Results showed that Pc is stable towards denaturation by GdnHCl (up to 4 M) till 50 
◦
C, either alone or in combination with β- ME (150 mM). However, autodigestion in presence of GdnHCl was evident at 65 
◦
C in concentration dependent manner and was more pronounced in combination with β- ME. Similar effect was also observed with PcB, although at lower temperature (50 
◦
C) and without much observable influence of the presence of β- ME.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.4. Kinetic stability of different proteases of C1 family in presence of
</title>
         <p>
β- ME
</p>
         <p>
Kinetic stability of four C1 family proteases 
viz
. Pc, PcB, bromelain and papain (
Fig. 6
) was studied in the presence of different concentrations of β- ME at 50 
◦
C up to 2 h. Bromelain was found to be the most susceptible for inactivation in presence of higher concentration of β- ME (100 mM) showing loss of nearly 80% activity at the end of 1 h incubation. In the similar conditions, PcB showed 25 and 41% loss in the activity after 1 and 2 h of incubation, respectively. Pc, on the other hand was quite resistant to get inactivated and showed just 12% and 16% loss of activity at the end of 1 and 2 h of incubation in presence of 200 mM β- ME, respectively. Papain showed the highest resistance towards inactivation by β- ME; it shows less than 5% loss of activity even in the presence of 400 mM of β- ME at the end of 2 h of incubation.
</p>
         <p>
In order to check, if the inactivation also leads to autoproteolysis of the enzymes, SDS-PAGE profile of the proteins was observed at the end of incubation period (
Fig. 6E and F
). The autoproteolysis was mainly observed for bromelain and PcB incubated in the presence of 100 mM β- ME at 50 
◦
C for 1 h and 2 h, respectively. Papain did not exhibit any major changes in the band intensity, while Pc showed marginal change in the band intensity upon incubation in presence of 100 and 200 mM β- ME concentrations.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.5. Evaluating effect of disulphide bonds on the autolysis of PcB by homology modelling and molecular dynamics simulations
</title>
         <p>
Bromelain and PcB were found to be sensitive to autolysis than Pc and papain in presence of reducing agent, β- ME (
Fig. 6A–F
). Reduction of disulphide bonds in PcB or bromelain has possibly made the proteins very sensitive to proteolytic digestion. In order to understand this phenomenon, we examined the solvent accessible surface area (SASA) of each of the three conserved disulphide bonds in the crystal structures of papain and bromelain and the predicted structures of Pc and PcB (Supplementary Table 1). Higher accessibility of β- ME to sulphur atoms of disulphide bonds may facilitate the reduction of the bonds. We expected that SASA would be significantly higher for the disulphide bonds in the structures of the enzymes which are sensitive to autolysis in presence of β- ME. We, however, found no correlation of sensitivity of the proteins to autoproteolysis with their respective solvent accessibility parameters (Supplementary Table 1). This may be due to dynamic nature of the proteins. SASA may show the correlation with autolysis sensitivity in presence of β- ME when we consider the dynamic nature of the proteins.
</p>
         <p>
We further examined the dynamicity using molecular simulations of PcB which is more sensitive to autolysis in presence of reducing agent than Pc. We performed 500 ns molecular dynamics simulations on PcB in presence and absence of disulphide bonds. Molecular dynamics results indicate that both simulations for PcB have converged (Supplementary 
Fig. 4
) and root mean square distance (RMSD) remains fairly stable for the last 100 ns? We found that the PcB lacking disulphide bonds has a higher RMSD value as compared to PcB with disulphide bonds (Supplementary 
Fig. 6
). Radius of gyration for both the proteins shows that none of the two proteins is losing its integrity during the simulations (Supplementary 
Fig.5
). Further, effects of reduced cysteine residues are directly visible by root mean square fluctuation (RMSF) of Cα of the structures during 500 ns simulations in both the forms (Supplementary 
Fig. 6
). The loop regions (residues 147–153, residues 185–195 and residues 216–225) in PcB structure lacking disulphide bonds show significantly higher fluctuation of protein backbone as compared to PcB containing disulphide bonds (Supplementary Fig. 7). This backbone fluctuation is attributed to reduction of cysteine residues of disulphide bond I and II.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Discussion
</title>
         <p>
Autocatalysis has been reported for many proteases (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

) including cysteine proteases. For few enzymes, autocatalysis can be a mechanism for its activation, like catheptic enzymes (

). In other enzymes, it is a process leading to irreversible inactivation of the enzyme which is disadvantageous for industrial applications of many enzymes 
viz.
thermolysin or trypsin (

; 

). Thus, the phenomenon is of great interest to study the vulnerable cleavage sites in such industrially important enzymes and countering it by protein engineering approach. Although there is no generalized mechanism for autodegradation of proteases, partial unfolding of the enzymes has been reported to be the pre-requisite for their autolysis (

; 

). In few cases, however, autodegradation has been reported to occur in conditions optimum for protease activity in which the global protein structure is unperturbed, as in the case of thermolysin (

), TNA1_POP (

) and kallikrein (

), which are known to undergo autolysis at their optimum temperatures. In another example, autoproteolytic inactivation of HtrA protease of 
E. coli
has been suggested to occur by the hyperactivation of the enzyme through allosteric activation by the proteolytic products of its substrates (

). In view of so many different ways the enzymes are reported to undergo autolytic degradation, we studied this phenomenon in two proteases, Pc and PcB, from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
Our initial observations regarding the SDS-PAGE profiles of Pc and PcB were quite surprising as the protein bands corresponding to full-length protein were not visible despite high amounts of loading (up to 20 μg) on the gel. Moreover, proteins purified in the presence of reversible inhibitor, sodium tetrathionate also showed the same behaviour. Appearance of full-length protein bands, however, could only be observed after addition of E-64 (an irreversible cysteine protease inhibitor) during SDS-PAGE sample preparation. These preliminary observations suggested that the proteins were catalytically active in the denaturing conditions during SDS-PAGE sample preparation and thus possibly undergoing autolytic cleavage resulting in the absence of full-length protein bands on the gel. Such autolytic degradation has been reported previously for ‘cholesterol-binding pancreatic proteinase’ in presence of SDS and evidenced by disappearance of the polypeptide band on the gel by 

. The author postulated partial unfolding of the protein to be the cause of this autodigestion. However, this phenomenon of autolytic digestion during SDS-PAGE sample preparation for Pc and PcB or other cysteine proteases has not been reported earlier. Although both Pc and PcB proteins were studied for their stability in different physical and chemical conditions, the proteins used were inhibited with sodium tetrathionate to prevent autodigestion (

; Singh et al., 2010). Stability studies revealed high stability of both the enzymes to wide range of pH and temperature conditions as well as to chemical denaturants like urea, GdnHCl or SDS. In fact, these enzymes are reported to be highly stable even at those temperatures where it possesses optimum activities (50–70 
◦
C). On the contrary, presence of activator like β- ME has been stated to cause autodigestion of these enzymes even at 37 
◦
C where both the enzymes are otherwise shown to be very stable in the absence of β- ME (

; Singh et al., 2010). Thus, it indicates mere activation of the enzymes can lead to their self-cleavage at relatively lower temperature. This paradox has not been discussed in any of the previous reports and it thus felt necessary to establish the cause and conditions of autolytic degradation of these proteases. In order to ascertain whether it is the denaturation or activation of the enzymes, which causes autolysis, we examined the stability of the enzymes at different temperatures in presence of denaturants (SDS and GdnHCl) and activator (β- ME). The kinetic stability of the enzymes was evaluated in terms of enzymatic activities and SDS-PAGE profiles to assess the loss in catalytic activity and autocatalysis, respectively. We also used DSF to study conformational stability of the enzymes in real time.
</p>
         <p>
In order to determine the minimum temperature at which enzymes rapidly lose their activity, individual enzymes were incubated in presence or absence of denaturants and/or activators at different temperatures. The residual activities were measured and are depicted in 
Fig. 2
. Native Pc showed rapid loss of activity at temperature ≥75 
◦
C, while PcB showed steady decline in activity from 50 
◦
C onward with ≥85% loss of activity at 80 
◦
C after 10 min of incubation. However, the presence of higher concentration (≥50 mM) of β- ME resulted in greater loss of activity for both the enzymes at relatively lower temperatures (65 
◦
C) compared to the enzymes incubated in 0, 1 or 10 mM β- ME. In fact, the lower concentrations of β- ME (1, 10 mM) exhibited activation for both the enzymes in the entire range of temperature studied.
</p>
         <p>
The stability studies carried out in the presence of denaturing agent, SDS (2%), showed complete loss of activity at 30 
◦
C and 50 
◦
C for PcB and Pc, respectively (
Fig. 2C and D
). In presence of GdnHCl (4 M), ≥70% inactivation was observed for PcB, but not for Pc even at 50 
◦
C (
Fig. 2E and F
). The latter got inactivated only at 65 
◦
C. In above conditions, presence of β- ME did not have any additional effect on inactivation of the enzymes by either SDS or GdnHCl. The substantial loss of activity observed in presence of 2–4 M GdnHCl in combination with β- ME and at higher temperature (65 
◦
C), especially in case of Pc, is primarily due to presence of β- ME itself.
</p>
         <p>
Overall, the results obtained with enzyme inactivation studies corroborate the findings of DSF experiments carried out to monitor the conformational changes in the protein. For instance, the melting or denaturation started at temperatures ≥75 
◦
C for both the enzymes, which may be the cause of drastic decrease in the activities of the enzymes above this temperature. The presence of β- ME resulted in slight decrease in the denaturation temperature for Pc and PcB, with the effect more pronounced in case of Pc. However, the enzyme assay studies showed inactivation of PcB at much lower temperature in presence of 150 mM β- ME. This could be because the residual activities were estimated after 10 min of incubation at respective temperatures while in DSF studies the enzyme encountered 5 s at each temperature. The DSF studies also provided information on melting of PcB in the presence GdnHCl, however, the same could not be obtained for Pc because we could not observe any increase in fluorescence in the entire range of temperature. Nevertheless, PcB showed lowering of denaturation temperature in the presence of GdnHCl in a concentration dependent manner which is in agreement with the enzyme activity measurement studies.
</p>
         <p>
In view of all the aforementioned results, it is quite clear that activation or denaturation of Pc and PcB is differentially affected by β- ME, SDS or GdnHCl and Pc is relatively more stable than PcB towards the denaturation by these agents. This is in agreement with previous studies by (

; Singh et al., 2010) where it was reported that Pc has higher stability towards temperature and reducing agent than PcB. Thus, it was interesting to check how these two proteins respond to these denaturing or activating conditions in terms of their autodigestion. In order to assess the autocatalysis of the enzymes subjected to these conditions, protein profiles were observed by SDS-PAGE immediately after subjecting to these conditions and inhibiting any residual activity of the enzymes by E-64. The results showed that all those conditions in which denaturation and significant decline in activities were observed, showed autodegradation as well. For instance, the lowest temperature at which Pc and PcB showed complete loss of activity in presence of 2% SDS were 50 
◦
C and 37 
◦
C, respectively. The very conditions also showed near complete degradation of the enzymes on SDS-PAGE as well. Moreover, the proteins showed degradation above 80 
◦
C, where rapid decline in activity and global unfolding were also observed. The collective evidence also confirmed that the loss of activity in presence of 150 mM β- ME, but not that of native protein, at temperatures near 70 
◦
C is due to denaturation and subsequently autodegradation of the enzymes. Higher concentration of β- ME (150 mM) facilitates denaturation of the enzymes at higher temperature which could be attributed to the reduction of disulphide bonds, in turn leading to their autodegradation. It is thus possible that higher concentrations of β- ME might cause denaturation of the enzymes in similar manner at lower temperatures, if incubated for longer time. On the contrary, at lower concentrations (1–10 mM) of β- ME, enhanced activity of the enzymes was observed at all the temperatures. This suggests that activation by β- ME per se would not lead to autodegradation. Thus the autolytic degradation of the enzyme is not due to activation of the enzyme in presence of β- ME as reported byprevious studies (

; Singh et al., 2010), but due to conformational changes brought about by higher concentrations of reducing agent as the activation could only be observedat lower concentration of β- ME, which does not cause autolysis of enzymes. It was confirmed by SDS-PAGE profiles of both the enzymes after incubating for prolonged time (up to 5 h) in lower (
&lt;
10 mM) concentration of β- ME (data not shown). The present studies thus confirm that both the proteins undergo autolysis in those conditions where conformational changes in their structures are observed. Secondly, the rate of autocatalysis was always higher than their denaturation rate even at boiling temperatures in presence of 2% SDS and/or 150 mM β- ME.
</p>
         <p>
It is worth mentioning here that both the proteins are very stable to thermal denaturation in non-reducing conditions. However, presence of β- ME in the concentration range of 50–100 mM could destabilize the enzymes in 2–3 h and bring about autolytic degradation at 50 
◦
C. Pc and PcB both share high sequence identities with other plant cysteine proteases of C1 family, like papain, bromelain, actinidin and ficin. Homology modelling of Pc and PcB shows that they share similar structures to other plant cysteine proteases. It is important to point out that papain does not get inactivated in presence of β- ME (320 mM) unless it is partially unfolded by 8 M urea (

) at 37 
◦
C. In bromelain, however, inactivation is reported at 50 
◦
C in presence of 2 mM DTT leading to loss of 80% activity in 1.5 h (

). In view of this, we also compared the kinetic stability of Pc, PcB, papain and bromelain in the presence of different concentrations of β- ME at 50 
◦
C up to 2 h (
Fig. 6A–F
). We found bromelain was the most susceptible to inactivation in presence of β- ME (100 mM), followed by PcB. This is in agreement with the observations of (

) for bromelain. Pc showed marginal inactivation at 200 mM β- ME after 2 h. Papain was found to be the most resistant towards inactivation even in the presence of 400 mM of β- ME after 2 h. The autoproteolysis was also distinctly observed only for bromelain and PcB as seen from their SDS-PAGE profiles (
Fig. 6A–F
). Crystal structures of papain-like proteases such as papain, bromelain and actinidin (PDB ids: 1PPN, 6YCG, 3P5W, respectively) show the presence of three conserved disulphide bonds and these are primarily responsible for providing structural stability to the proteins from thermal denaturation (Supplementary 
Fig. 2
and Supplementary Table 1). Homology models of Pc and PcB also show presence of three conserved disulphide bonds in them. Higher concentration of β- ME reduce the disulphide bonds in the structure of a protein and make the connecting loops or other adjoining structural elements more flexible, which is enhanced by higher temperature. This could act as a nucleating point for the thermal denaturation of the protein and make the polypeptide regions more accessible to the protease. The first cleavage in the polypeptide could start the cascading events of further denaturation and proteolytic cleavages. Interestingly, in spite of presence of exactly three numbers of disulphide bonds in papain, Pc, PcB and bromelain, the latter two proteins are distinctly susceptible to proteolysis. Therefore, we thought that the solvent accessibility to the disulphide bonds in the structures could be the governing parameters for the access of β- ME to the bonds. Hence, we checked the surface solvent accessibility of the disulphide bonds in the crystal structures of papain and bromelain and homology models of Pc and PcB. We found no correlation of the solvent accessibility and the reducing agent susceptibility of the proteins. Thus, mere solvent accessibility and that too in the static 3-D structures may not be sufficient parameter to provide clue for their differential susceptibility to proteolysis in presence of reducing agent. We later performed 500 ns molecular simulations on PcB protein which is more susceptible to the proteolysis than Pc. We found that RMSF values, a good indicator of backbone flexibility, is more for the loops around the position of disulphide bonds in disulphide-free model than disulphide-containing model (Supplementary 
Fig. 6
and Supplementary Fig. 7). This flexibility could provide the accessibility to the proteolysis and hence PcB in presence of higher concentration of β- ME lacking disulphide bonds are prone to thermal denaturation and proteolysis. Overall, the start of the conformational flexibility either governed by denaturant like SDS and GdnHCl or reducing agent like β- ME may bring about the start point of proteolysis and further cycle of denaturation and proteolysis. However, our findings regarding differential sensitivity towards autoproteolysis of papain-like proteases i.e. C1 family proteases in the presence of β- ME can be helpful for deciding the conditions for their industrial applications.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>Procerain and Procerain B undergo rapid and extensive autocatalysis under highly denaturing conditions like those encountered during sample preparation for SDS-PAGE. The autoproteolysis of the enzymes is initiated once they encounter denaturing conditions. The phenomenon thus suggests that rate of autocatalysis is higher than that of denaturation. Autoproteolysis is also observed in other papain-like cysteine proteases from C1 family, however, the conditions in which the phenomenon is observed varies for individual enzymes. Concentration of reducing agent is one of the major factors that governs autocatalysis near their optimum temperatures and thus has to be taken into consideration while selecting particular enzyme from C1 family for their industrial applications.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Experimental
</title>
         <p>
Azocasein, Sypro-Orange, sodium dodecyl sulphate (SDS), guanidine hydrochloirde (GdnHCl), β- mercaptoethanol (β- ME) were obtained from Sigma (
USA
). CM-Sepharose, Superdex 200 were obtained from Cytiva (
USA
). All other chemicals used were of Analytical Grade.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.1. Purification of Pc and PcB
</title>
         <p>
All the procedure involving purification were carried out at 4 
◦
C unless it is stated.
</p>
         <p>
The latex of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Calotropis procera
</tp:taxon-name>
(family 
<tp:taxon-name>Asclepiadaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) was obtained from the plant stem in 25 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0 in cold. It was mixed thoroughly and centrifuged at 30,000× 
g
for 40 min. The supernatant was then subjected to ion exchange chromatography on CM-Sepharose Fast flow, pre-equilibrated with 25 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0. The adsorbed protein was eluted with gradient (0–0.8 M) of NaCl prepared in equilibrating buffer. The proteins eluted as two major peaks as observed using 
A
280nm
,

pooled separately, concentrated by ultrafiltration and then individually subjected to gel filtration chromatography. The Superdex 200 10/ 
300 mm
(Cytiva, 
US
), connected to a Quaternary pump (Jasco, PU2089 plus, 
Japan
) was pre-equilibrated with 25 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0 containing 150 mM NaCl. It was also calibrated with gel filtration standards (Sigma, 
USA
) 
viz
. β- amylase (200 kDa), alcohol dehydrogenase (150 kDa), bovine serum albumin (66 kDa), carbonic anhydrase (29 kDa), cytochrome C (12.4 kDa) and blue dextran (2000 kDa). The proteins, Pc and PcB, eluted at molecular weight of 29 kDa and 24 kDa, respectively, were then collected and used for all the further studies. The calibration curve of Log molecular weight 
vs V
/ 

Vo

was plotted, where 
V
represents elution volume of the protein and 

Vo

is the void volume of the gel filtration column. The protein concentration was determined with the Bradford assay method (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.2. SDS-PAGE
</title>
         <p>
Homogeneity of the individual protein and molecular weight of the polypeptide was analysed by SDS-PAGE (

) using 15% (w/v) acrylamide resolving gel and standard proteins as molecular weight markers (Merck Genie, 
India
). Protein denaturation was carried out in the presence of 10–100 μM of E 64 wherever necessary either in sample buffer or individual component of sample buffer.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.3. Enzyme assay
</title>
         <p>
The activity of both the enzymes was assessed using azocasein as substrate and in 50 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0 and at 50 
◦
C. The assay mixture consisted of 5 μg of the enzyme, 125 μL of buffer and 125 μL of 3% azocasein prepared in the assay buffer. The mixture was incubated for 10 min at 50 
◦
C and then added 250 μL of 10% ice-cold TCA to terminate the reaction. The TCA soluble products obtained after centrifuging the assay mixture was read at 
366 nm
. One unit of the enzyme was considered as Δ 

A 

366nm

= 0.001.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4. Protein stability studies
</title>
         <p>Stability of the enzymes Pc and PcB was assessed in terms of enzyme activities, autocatalysis and conformational changes in presence of different denaturants (SDS/GdnHCl) or activators (β- ME).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4.1. Native enzymes and in presence of β- ME (1–150 mM)
</title>
         <p>
For stability studies of the native enzymes in the presence and absence of β- ME (1–150 mM), the enzymes (5 μg) were incubated in 125 μL of 50 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0 at different temperatures 
viz
. 4 
◦
C, 30 
◦
C, 50 
◦
C, 60 
◦
C, 65 
◦
C, 70 
◦
C, 75 
◦
C, 80 
◦
C and 85 
◦
C for 10 min. The residual activities of the enzymes were estimated by assaying the enzymes using azocasein as substrate as explained earlier.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4.2. In presence of SDS (2%) and SDS (2%) in combination with β- ME (150 mM) at different temperatures
</title>
         <p>
For the studies, 5 μg of each protein was incubated in the presence of 2% SDS or 2% SDS in combination with β- ME (150 mM) at 30 
◦
C and 50 
◦
C for 3 min and quickly transferring the reaction mixture to ice-bath after the incubation. The residual activities of the enzymes were estimated by assaying enzyme with azocasein as substrate as explained earlier. Enzymes (Pc and PcB) in presence of 50 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0 were kept as control.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4.3. In presence of GdnHCl (2–4 M) or GdnHCl (2–4 M) in combination with β- ME (150 mM) at different temperatures
</title>
         <p>
For the studies, 5 μg of each protein was incubated in the presence of GdnHCl (2, 3 and 4 M) or GdnHCl (2, 3 and 4 M) in combination with β- ME (150 mM) at 30 
◦
C, 50 
◦
C and 65 
◦
C for 3 min and quickly transferring the reaction mixture to ice-bath after the incubation. The residual activities of the enzymes were estimated by assaying enzyme with azocasein as substrate as explained earlier. The autocatalysis in these conditions was monitored by subjecting the proteins to SDS-PAGE in the presence of E-64 (0.1 mM). The reaction mixture was diluted 10- 
fold
before addition of sample buffer in order to avoid precipitation of SDS in presence of high concentration of GdnHCl. Enzymes (Pc and PcB) in presence of 50 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0 were kept as control.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4.4. Autocatalysis in presence of SDS-PAGE sample buffer components
</title>
         <p>For this study, 5 μg of each protein (Pc and PcB) was incubated individually in presence of 50 mM Tris buffer pH 6.8, 2% SDS, 150 mM β- ME and in combination of 2% SDS and 150 mM β- ME for 3 min under boiling conditions. The autocatalysis in these conditions was then monitored by subjecting the proteins to SDS-PAGE in the presence of E-64 (0.1 mM).</p>
         <p>
The same study was also repeated by subjecting the enzymes to all the aforementioned conditions at different temperatures (30 
◦
C, 50 
◦
C, 60 
◦
C, 70 
◦
C, 75 
◦
C, 80 
◦
C and 85 
◦
C) to understand the effect of temperature on autocleavage of the enzymes thereon.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4.5. Kinetic stability of different proteases of C1 family in presence of
</title>
         <p>
β- ME
</p>
         <p>
Papain (40 μg), Bromelain (100 μg), Pc (60 μg) and PcB (70 μg) were incubated at 50 
◦
C in 20 mM phosphate buffer pH 7.0 containing different concentrations of β- ME in the range of 10–400 mM with final volume 50 μL. The residual activities of the enzymes were determined at intervals up to 2 h and expressed as specific activities using 5 μL of the aliquot. The autocatalysis in these conditions at the end of 2 h was also monitored by subjecting the proteins to SDS-PAGE in the presence of E-64 (0.1 mM) using 10 μL of the aliquot.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.5. Differential scanning fluorimetry
</title>
         <p>
The experiment was carried out as described by (

). Pc and PcB were used at a final concentration of 26 μM and 16 μM, respectively, for this assay. SYPRO Orange dye was used at a final concentration of 20X for native protein and 10X for studying thermal denaturation in the presence of denaturant, GdnHCl. Thermal denaturation was carried out in following conditions: 1. Phosphate citrate buffer pH 7.0 (50 mM) in presence and absence of E-64 (0.1 mM). 2. Phosphate citrate buffer pH 7.0 (50 mM) containing activator (150 mM β- ME) and/or denaturant (GdnHCl, at concentration 2 M, 3 M and 4 M) in the presence or absence of E-64 (0.1 mM). All DSF experiments were carried out with Rotogen Q (Qiagen, 
Germany
). Each reaction sample was divided in to three 20 μL replicates. Sample solutions were dispensed into PCR tubes. Fluorescence intensity was measured via the HRM channel (Ex 
460 nm
and Em at 
510 nm
) and temperature in the range pf 35–95 
◦
C was continuously increased at 0.1 
◦
C/s with holding time of 5 s at each temperature. The melting curves obtained were directly exported from the instrument, and then were analysed with Prism 7 (Graph-Pad Software Inc, 
USA
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.6. Homology modelling and Molecular dynamics simulations
</title>
         <p>
Pc and PcB share 88.5% sequence identity between them and both of them share about 47% sequence identity with papain (Supplementary 
Fig.2
). Pc and PcB structural models were prepared by homology modelling using SWISS-MODEL server (

) using default parameters and template as papain structure (PDB id:1PPN) (Supplementary 
Fig. 3
). The molecular dynamics (MD) systems for PcB with and without disulphide bonds were generated using GROMACS 5.1 (

) using CHARMM27 all-atom force field (

). The solvated systems were prepared in cubic boxes with one side of 10 Å which was filled with ~13,000 spc 216 water models (

) for each system. Depending upon the overall charge on the protein, an appropriate number of Na 
+
or Cl ions were added to neutralize the system. Additionally, 0.1 M concentration of NaCl was achieved by replacing water molecules. This was followed by energy minimization using the steepest descent algorithm with 1000 kJ/mol/nm tolerance. The temperature and pressure equilibration runs were performed using Berendsen thermostat (

) and Parrinello-Rahman (

) pressure coupling algorithms, respectively. Both the runs were performed using LINCS holonomic constraints on the protein for 10 ns with step size of 2 fs, while using 
1 nm
cut-off distances for both short range electrostatics and van der Waals cut-off during neighbour searching via the PME electrostatics treatment while temperature and pressure equilibration and MD run were per formed using the leap-frog integrator (

). Final MD run for both PcB with and without disulphide bonds systems was performed for 500 ns (Supplementary 
Fig. 4
and 
5
).
</p>
         <p>
Credit author statement
</p>
         <p>
Gaurav Srivastava
: Methodology, Software, Data curation, Writing – original draft. 
Neeraj Gaur
: Methodology pertaining to Molecular Dynamics Simulations, Software 
Ravindra Makde
: Methodology pertaining to Homology Modelling and Molecular Dynamics Simulations, Software, Writing – original draft, Review and Editing 
Sahayog Jamdar
: Conceptualization, Methodology, Investigation, Resources, Writing – original draft, Writing – review &amp; editing
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113086.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Berendsen, H.
, 
Postma, J.P.M.
, 
van Gunsteren, W.
, 
Hermans, J.
, 
1981
. 
Interaction models for water in relation to protein hydration
. in: 
Intermol Forces
331–342
. 
https://doi. org/10.1007/978-94-015-7658-1_21
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bickerstaff, G.F.
, 
Zhou, H.
, 
1993
. 
Protease activity and autodigestion (autolysis) assays using coomassie blue dye binding
. 
Anal. Biochem.
210
, 
155–158
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1006/abio.1993.1166
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bradford, M.M.
, 
1976
. 
A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding
. 
Anal. Biochem.
72
, 
248–254
. 
https://doi.org/10.1006/abio.1976.9999
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dubey, V.K.
, 
Jagannadham, M.V.
, 
2003
a. 
Procerain, a stable cysteine protease from the latex of Calotropis procera
. 
Phytochemistry
62
, 
1057–1071
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/s0031-9422(02)00676-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dubey, V.K.
, 
Jagannadham, M.V.
, 
2003
b. 
Differences in the unfolding of procerain induced by pH, guanidine hydrochloride, urea, and temperature
. 
Biochemistry
42
, 
12287–12297
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/bi035047m
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huynh, K.
, 
Partch, C.L.
, 
2015
. 
Analysis of protein stability and ligand interactions by thermal shift assay
. 
Curr. protocols protein sci
. 79 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ 0471140864.ps2809s79
, 28.9.1-28.9.14.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jomaa, A.
, 
Iwanczyk, J.
, 
Tran, J.
, 
Ortega, J.
, 
2009
. 

Characterization of the autocleavage process of the 
&lt;
em
&gt;
Escherichia coli 
&lt;
/em
&gt;
HtrA protein: implications for its physiological role. J

. 
Bacteriol.
191
, 
1924–1932
. 
https://doi.org/10.1128/ JB.01187-08
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Laemmli, U.K.
, 
1970
. 
Cleavage of structural proteins during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4
. 
Nature
227
, 
680–685
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/227680a0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lee, H.S.
, 
Kim, Y.J.
, 
Cho, Y.
, 
Kim, S.-J.
, 
Lee, J.-H.
, 
Kang, S.G.
, 
2007
. 
Characterization of prolyl oligopeptidase from hyperthermophilic archaeon Thermococcus sp
. 
NA1.J. Biosci. Bioeng.
103
, 
221–228
. 
https://doi.org/10.1263/jbb.103.221
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lemak, A.S.
, 
Balabaev, N.K.
, 
1994
. 
On the berendsen thermostat
. 
Mol. Simulat.
13
, 
177–187
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/08927029408021981
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lop´ez, 
L.M.I
., 
Viana, C.A.
, 
Errasti, M.E.
, 
Garro, M.L.
, 
Martegani, J.E.
, 
Mazzilli, G.A.
, 
Freitas, C.D.T.
, Araújo,´I.M.S., 
da Silva, R.O.
, 
Ramos, M.V.
, 
2017
. 
Latex peptidases of Calotropis procera for dehairing of leather as an alternative to environmentally toxic sodium sulfide treatment
. 
Bioproc. Biosyst. Eng.
40
, 
1391–1398
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s00449-017-1796-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Maroux, S.
, 
Desnuelle, P.
, 
1969
. 
On some autolyzed derivatives of bovine trypsin
. 
Biochim. Biophys. Acta
181
, 
59–72
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0005-2795(69)90227- x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Matsumiya, Y.
, 
Nishikawa, K.
, 
Aoshima, H.
, 
Inouye, K.
, 
Kubo, M.
, 
2004
. 
Analysis of autodegradation sites of thermolysin and enhancement of its thermostability by modifying Leu 155 at an autodegradation site
. 
J. Biochem.
135
, 
547–553
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1093/jb/mvh067
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Matsumoto, K.
, 
Mizoue, K.
, 
Kitamura, K.
, 
Tse, W.C.
, 
Huber, C.P.
, 
Ishida, T.
, 
1999
. 
Structural basis of inhibition of cysteine proteases by E-64 and its derivatives
. 
Biopolymers
51
, 
99–107
. 

https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1097-0282(1999)51: 1 
&lt;
99::AID-BIP11
&gt;
3.0.CO;2-R

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Memari, N.
, 
Jiang, W.
, 
Diamandis, E.P.
, 
Luo, L.-Y.
, 
2007
. 
Enzymatic properties of human kallikrein-related peptidase 12 (KLK12)
. 
Biol. Chem.
388
, 
427–435
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1515/BC.2007.049
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Parrinello, M.
, 
Rahman, A.
, 
1980
. 
Crystal structure and pair potentials: a moleculardynamics study
. 
Phys. Rev. Lett.
45
, 
1196–1199
. 
https://doi.org/10.1103/ PhysRevLett.45.1196
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rajesh, R.
, 
Raghavendra Gowda, C.D.
, 
Nataraju, A.
, 
Dhananjaya, B.L.
, 
Kemparaju, K.
, 
Vishwanath, B.S.
, 
2005
. 
Procoagulant activity of Calotropis gigantea latex associated with fibrin(ogen)olytic activity
. 
Toxicon. off. j. Intl Soc. Toxinol.
46
, 
84–92
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.toxicon.2005.03.012
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ramos, M.V.
, 
Freitas, A.P.F.
, 
Leit˜ao, R.F.C.
, 
Costa, D.V.S.
, 
Cerqueira, G.S.
, 
Martins, D.S.
, 
Martins, C.S.
, 
Alencar, N.M.N.
, 
Freitas, L.B.N.
, 
Brito, G.A.C.
, 
2020
. 
Antiinflammatory latex proteins of the medicinal plant Calotropis procera: a promising alternative for oral mucositis treatment
. 
Inflamm. Res.
69
, 
951–966
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s00011-020-01365-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shapira, E.
, 
Arnon, R.
, 
1969
. 
Cleavage of one specific disulfide bond in papain
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
244
, 
1026–1032
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sharma, P.
, 
Sharma, J.D.
, 
2001
. 
In vitro hemolysis of human erythrocytes – by plant extracts with antiplasmodial activity.
J. Ethnopharmacol.
74
, 
239–243
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/s0378-8741(00)00370-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Silva, M.Z.R.
, 
Oliveira, J.P.B.
, 
Ramos, M.V.
, 
Farias, D.F.
, de S´a, 
C.A
., 
Ribeiro, J.A.C.
, 
Silva, A.F.B.
, 
de Sousa, J.S.
, 
Zambelli, R.A.
, 
da Silva, A.C.
, 
Furtado, G.P.
, 
Grangeiro, T.B.
, 
Vasconcelos, M.S.
, 
Silveira, S.R.
, 
Freitas, C.D.T.
, 
2020
. 
Biotechnological potential of a cysteine protease (CpCP3) from Calotropis procera latex for cheesemaking
. 
Food Chem.
307
, 
125574
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. foodchem.2019.125574
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Silveira, S.R.
, 
Coelho, R.A.
, 
Sousa, B.F.E.
, 
Oliveira, J.S.
, 
de Lopez, L.M.I.
, 
Lima-Filho, J.V. M.
, 
Rocha Júnior, P.A.V.
, 
Souza, D.P.
, 
de Freitas, C.D.T.
, 
de Ramos, M.V.
, 
2021
. 
Standardized production of a homogeneous latex enzyme source overcoming seasonality and microenvironmental variables
. 
Prep. Biochem. Biotechnol.
51
, 
375–385
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/10826068.2020.1818258
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singh, A.N.
, 
Dubey, V.K.
, 
2011
. 
Exploring applications of procerain b, a novel protease from Calotropis procera, and characterization by N-terminal sequencing as well as peptide mass fingerprinting
. 
Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol.
164
, 
573–580
. 
https://doi. org/10.1007/s12010-011-9158-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singh, A.N.
, 
Shukla, A.K.
, 
Jagannadham, M.
v., 
Dubey, V.K.
, 
2010
a. 
Purification of a novel cysteine protease, procerain B, from Calotropis procera with distinct characteristics compared to procerain
. 
Process Biochem.
45
, 
399–406
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/J.PROCBIO.2009.10.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singh, A.N.
, 
Shukla, A.K.
, 
Jagannadham, M.V.
, 
Dubey, V.K.
, 
2010
b. 
Purification of a novel cysteine protease, procerain B, from Calotropis procera with distinct characteristics compared to procerain
. 
Process Biochem.
45
, 
399–406
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.procbio.2009.10.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singhal, A.
, 
Kumar, V.L.
, 
2009
. 
Effect of aqueous suspension of dried latex of Calotropis procera on hepatorenal functions in rat. J
. 
Ethnopharmacol.
122
, 
172–174
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2008.12.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sziegoleit, A.
, 
1984
. 
A novel proteinase from human pancreas
. 
Biochem. J.
219
, 
735–742
. 
https://doi.org/10.1042/bj2190735
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Urade, R.
, 
Yasunishi, A.
, 
Okudo, H.
, 
Moriyama, T.
, 
Kito, M.
, 
1999
. 
Autodegradation of protein disulfide isomerase
. 
Biosc. Biotech. Biochem.
63
, 
610–613
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1271/bbb.63.610
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Van Der Spoel, D.
, 
Lindahl, E.
, 
Hess, B.
, 
Groenhof, G.
, 
Mark, A.E.
, 
Berendsen, H.J.C.
, 
2005
. 
GROMACS: fast, flexible, and free
. 
J. Comput. Chem.
26
, 
1701–1718
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1002/jcc.20291
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Van Gunsteren, W.F.
, 
Berendsen, H.J.C.
, 
1988
. 
A leap-frog algorithm for stochastic dynamics
. 
Mol. Simulat.
1
, 
173–185
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 08927028808080941
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vanommeslaeghe, K.
, 
Hatcher, E.
, 
Acharya, C.
, 
Kundu, S.
, 
Zhong, S.
, 
Shim, J.
, 
Darian, E.
, 
Guvench, O.
, 
Lopes, P.
, 
Vorobyov, I.
, 
Mackerell, A.D.J.
, 
2010
. 
CHARMM general force field: a force field for drug-like molecules compatible with the CHARMM all-atom additive biological force fields
. 
J. Comput. Chem.
31
, 
671–690
. 
https://doi. org/10.1002/jcc.21367
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Verma, S.
, 
Dixit, R.
, 
Pandey, K.C.
, 
2016
. 
Cysteine proteases: modes of activation and future prospects as pharmacological targets
. 
Front. Pharmacol.
7
(
107
), 
1–12
. 
https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2016.00107
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Waterhouse, A.
, 
Bertoni, M.
, 
Bienert, S.
, 
Studer, G.
, 
Tauriello, G.
, 
Gumienny, R.
, 
Heer, F. T.
, 
de Beer, T.A.P.
, 
Rempfer, C.
, 
Bordoli, L.
, 
Lepore, R.
, 
Schwede, T.
, 
2018
. 
SWISS-MODEL: homology modelling of protein structures and complexes
. 
Nucleic Acids Res.
46
, W296–W 
303
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gky427
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
