<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112486</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Bio-genetic analysis of resistance in tomato to early blight disease, Alternaria alternata</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alternaria alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alternaria alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Solanum lycopersicum
Mill.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Solanum lycopersicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alternaria alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. solani
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Solanum lycopersicum
Mill.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternate
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>tomato</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>A. alternata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>variety and Falat</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A
. 
alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Alternaria alternata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alternaria alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. Alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
lycopersicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alternaria alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A
. 
alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>A. alternata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. lycopersicum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alternaria alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A
. 
alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Giti Alizadeh-Moghaddam
a
, Zahra Rezayatmand

a, 
**
, Mehdi Nasr- Esfahani
b, *
, Mahdi Khozaei
c
</p>
         <p>
a
Department of Biology
, 
Falavarjan Branch
, 
Islamic Azad University
, 
Isfahan
, 84517-31167, 
Iran
</p>
         <p>
b

Plant Protection Research Division, 
Isfahan
Center for Research and Education in Agricultural Science and Natural Resources, (AREEO), 
Isfahan
, 81786-96446, 
Iran
c

Plant Biotechnology, Department of Biology, University of 
Isfahan
, 
Isfahan
, 81746-73441, 
Iran
</p>
         <p>
ARTICLE
INFO

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
ABSTRACT
</p>
         <p>
Early blight disease (EB), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alternaria alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
, is destructive on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Solanum lycopersicum
Mill.
</tp:taxon-name>
The responses of 35 domestic and exotic commercial tomato genotypes to early blight were examined at transplanting and maturing stages using genetic diversity analysis, with 15 Inter Simple Sequence Repeat (ISSR) primers, total phenolic content (TPC), and enzymatic activity of catalase (CAT), phenylalanine ammonia lyase (PAL), peroxidase (POD) and superoxide dismutase (SOD) assays. The disease severity ranged from 18 to 87.5%. Eleven of 15 ISSR primers generated 68 loci of which 63 (90%) were polymorphic. Polymorphism information content value varied from 0.3 to 0.5 with an average of 0.4. Nei’ s measure of the average gene diversity ranged from 0.06 to 0.5. The Tomato genotypes were divided into five clusters in Un-weighted Pair Group Method with Arithmetic Mean (UPGMA) analysis, showing a considerable similarity between resistance level and molecular classification pattern. Antioxidant analysis indicated a significant increase in TPC and CAT, POD, PAL and SOD activities in most inoculated tomato genotypes at both growth stages. The highest increase in activity was seen in PAL (5- fold) and TPC (4-fold) at transplanting stage, whereas the highest TPC (2 to 3-fold) and POD activity (3-fold) were found at maturing stage in all the inoculated resistant genotypes in comparison with controls. 
Esfahan
Local and 
H
. a.s 2274 showed the highest level of activity in POD (2.5- and 3- fold, respectively) and TPC (2.5- and 4- fold, respectively). Our results suggest that using both genetic diversity and enzymatic diversity as markers, it is possible to discriminate resistant from susceptible tomato genotypes to early blight disease.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Solanum lycopersicum
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>ISSR marker</p>
         <p>Catalase</p>
         <p>Phenylalanine ammonia lyase</p>
         <p>Peroxidase</p>
         <p>Superoxide dismutase</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Early blight disease (EB), caused by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alternaria alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. solani
</tp:taxon-name>
, is a pre- and post-harvest disease in tomato (
<tp:taxon-name>
Solanum lycopersicum
Mill.
</tp:taxon-name>
) plants causing economic losses (

; 

; 

). Symptoms of infection are characterized by black, or brown, lesions on leaves leading to defoliation and yield loss (

). Although the disease is managed by application of fungicides (Odilbekov et al., 2019), identification of disease-resistant genotypes may be a sustainable, effective, and bio-rationale alternative (

; 

; 

; 

). Resistance analysis can be an effective part of an integrated EB management strategy but identification of EB-resistance sources in tomato has not been sufficiently explored (

).
</p>
         <p>
Increasingly, molecular methods for assessing genetic diversity are needed to identify and improve disease resistance of tomato germplasms (

; 

; 

). The Inter Simple Sequence Repeat (ISSR) marker is a highly polymorphic and reproducible method, and combines advantages of Simple Sequence Repeat (SSR), Amplified Fragment-Length Polymorphism (AFLP) and Randomly Amplified Polymorphic DNA (RAPD) methods (

; 

). Although, use of DNA marker methods have revealed markers associated with disease resistance gene clusters, they have not been sufficiently extended to EB-resistance genotypes (

).
</p>
         <p>
Several previous studies have highlighted that the expression of a number of defense-related genes was significantly altered by pathogen invasion (

; 

). Plants have developed a range of defense-related enzymes capable of initiating resistance to pathogens (

; 

). Plants alter activities of reactive-oxygen-species scavenging compounds, such as Catalase (CAT; EC1.11.1.6), Peroxidase (PODs; EC1.11.1.7), Phenylalanine-Ammonia-Lyase (PAL; EC4.3.1.5), Superoxide Dismutase (SOD; EC1.15.1.1) and total phenolic contents (TPC) used against causal agents of fungal disease (

; 

; 

; 

). Also, in our previous study on resistant genes, 
S
1WRKYs and 7 PRs, and enzymatic activity of β-1,3 Glucanase and Chitinases, we have reported the effectiveness of these genes and enzymes in increasing resistance to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
in tomatoes, suggesting their roles in defense mechanisms or resistance (

).
</p>
         <p>
This study was undertaken to identify levels and patterns of genetic variability and resistance of tomato genotypes for resistant to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternate
</tp:taxon-name>
, and to apply markers for the identification of resistant lines in tomato breeding programs.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

2.1. Disease severity evaluation of 
<tp:taxon-name>tomato</tp:taxon-name>
genotypes caused by

<tp:taxon-name>A. alternata</tp:taxon-name>
         </title>
         <p>
The EB disease, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
, severity analysis showed that all of the inoculated genotypes were infected under both greenhouse evaluation tests. The control plants (non-infected) were free of EB disease. In every growth stage, the inoculated genotypes exhibited varying severity responses to the disease ranging from 5 to 19% at transplanting stage and from 18 to 88% at maturing stage. These genotypes fell into 5 different categories in terms of the disease severity; highly susceptible (HS), susceptible (S), moderately susceptible (MS), moderately resistant (MR) and resistant (R). There was a significant difference in the percentage of the EB disease severity among tomato genotypes at transplanting and maturing stages (P 
&lt;
0.01) (
Table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
At transplanting stage, EB disease screening of the inoculated tomato genotypes identified eight genotypes as resistant: H. a.s 2274, 
Esfahan
local variety, Roma, Turkish Cherry, 
Valouro RZ
, 
Long Tomato Y
, Shiraz local 
<tp:taxon-name>variety and Falat</tp:taxon-name>
American 111 (5–7%); the others were moderately resistant (8–20%). At maturing stage, the resistant genotypes were; 
Esfahan
local, Turkish Cherry and 
Rio Grande
(18–25%); the remaining genotypes varied in their response to the disease ranging from moderately resistant to highly susceptible (25–88%) (
Table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
The results showed that the greatest severity of the EB disease occurs mostly at the mature stage. The difference of EB disease severity was caused by genotype and growth stage; the interaction between these factors was significant at the 0.01 level. Overall, the results showed that H. a.s2274 and 
Esfahan
local were resistant to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A
. 
alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
infection under both evaluation growth stages tests, while the majority of tomato genotypes varied from moderately to highly susceptible at both stages (
Table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Cluster analysis of EB disease severity at both stages classified tomato genotypes into three main groups (I, II and III), which were consistent with the results of the LSD (
Fig. 1
). The cluster results showed that the resistant tomato genotypes, Rio Grande, Turkish Cherry and 
Esfahan
Local, belonged to the group (II), the highly susceptible tomato genotypes belonged to the group (III), and the moderately susceptible and moderately resistant belonged to group (I).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Values in columns followed by the same letter are not significantly different at 0.01 %.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Properties indicating the ideal growing places of the tomato genotypes that were intended for field and or greenhouse. Nevertheless, the trials were conducted in a greenhouse for all uniformly.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. ISSR analysis
</title>
         <p>
Of the 16 ISSR primers tested on 35 tomato genotypes, only eleven ISSR primers had high-quality amplification products and polymorphic bands. The UBC-815, UBC-820, UBC-867, and UBC-849 primers did not have any amplification products. The ISSR results showed that the total numbers of bands varied between 2 (UBC848) and 14 (INC3) with the average number of 6.18 bands per primer ranging from 100 to 950 bp in size. The UBC855, UBC880 and INC3 primers were found more reproducible and polymorphic. The average value of polymorphism percentages obtained in our study was 86.82%, with the lowest value for primers 430 (25%), UBC848 (50%), and the highest value (100%) for primers A12, UBC855, UBC818, UBC808, UBC840, UBC880 and INC3, suggesting a significant variation among the studied tomato genotypes. The polymorphic information content values ranged from 0.31 (INC3) to 0.50 (UBC840) with the mean value of 0.42. The marker index values varied from 0.33 (UBC848) to 4.45 (UBC855) with the mean value of 2.35 (
Table 2
).
</p>
         <p>
The results obtained from analysis of ISSR primers, such as effective number of alleles (Ne), Nei’ s gene diversity(
H
), and Shannon’ s information index (
I
) are presented in 
Table 2
. The results showed that the highest values of effective number of alleles, Nei’ s gene diversity and Shannon’ s information index were obtained for UBC840 primer (1.89, 0.47 and 0.66, respectively). The lowest value of these indicators was detected in 430 primer (1.06, 0.06 and 0.13, respectively). The mean values of effective alleles, Nei’ s gene diversity and the Shannon index as a genetic diversity index were 1.46, 0.27 and 0.42, for all primers, respectively (
Table 2
).
</p>
         <p>
Evaluations made on the basis of ISSR markers and grouping of genotypes based on the level of EB disease resistance, showed that the highly susceptible group (G1) exhibited the highest value in terms of band frequency, effective number of alleles, expected heterozygosity and unbiased expected heterozygosity (0.36, 1.34, 0.20 and 0.22, respectively) (
Table 3
). The lowest value of polymorphism percentage, band frequency, effective alleles, Shannon’ s information index, expected heterozygosity and unbiased expected heterozygosity were obtained for the resistant group genotypes (G5) (36.76, 0.28, 1.21, 0.19, 0.13 and 0.14%, respectively) (
Table 3
). The Nei’ s genetic distances between pairs of these groups were calculated based on the 63 analyzed bands. The highest value of genetic distance (0.05) was found between G5 and G1 (
Table 4
). Furthermore, AMOVA analysis revealed that the highest total genetic variation was within the grouped genotypes (97%), whereas the variance among these groups was only 3% (Table 5).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

Genomic DNA extraction from young leaf tissue.The PCR-based ISSR reaction mixes were prepared using 15 ISSR primers. The DNA amplifications were programmed in a 10-m initial denaturalization phase at 94 
◦
C followed by 45 cycles of annealing each lasting 45–60 s, at a primer-specific.The process continued with an extension phase at 72 
◦
C for 2 min and with a final extension phase at 72 
◦
C for 10 min when naturalization occurs. The PCR-amplified fragments were electrophoresed on 1.5% (w/v) agarose gels.

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Based on UPGMA analysis, these 35 genotypes were grouped into two major clusters: the first cluster including 111Falat American, and the second cluster including all other genotypes (
Fig. 2
). According to the reference line, all genotypes divided into five clades as shown in 
Fig. 2
. The Cophenetic correlation coefficient based on Jaccard’ s similarity coefficient was 0.67, %, indicating a moderate fitness between the dendrogram and the relative efficiency. The similarity coefficient among these genotypes ranged from 0.36 to 0.93. The lowest similarity coefficient (0.36 and 0.44), which is indicative of the highest genetic diversity, was observed in 111Falat American and Roma, respectively, two moderately resistant genotypes. The fifth clade contained four resistant genotypes, Esfahan Local, Turkish Cherry, Rio Grande and 
H
. a.s 2274 with 60%–88% similarities. The third clade contained four genotypes with the highest susceptibility (
CH
American, Hedieh, Ameera and Izmir) with 80%–90% similarities. Although these results showed a distinct genetic divergence between the resistant and highly susceptible genotype clusters, the other genotypes did not show such a clear distinction and were distributed all over the clades (
Fig. 2
). Principal component analysis (PCA), on 2D basis, showed a significant clustering of tomato genotypes that were plotted into five sub-plots, representing the significant genetic variation and differentiation among genotypes and their low genetic similarity (
Fig. 3
). One group (green oval) was identical to the fifth clade using UPGMA, which were also clear in 3D
</p>
         <p>
a
G1 = highly susceptible group (CH American, Hyb. Retinto, Izmir, Ameera RZ, Hedieh, Super Crystal, Hyb. Sogno); G2 = susceptible group (111 Falat, Santawest Hyb., Supermobile, Shiraz local, Chief, Super Chief American, CH), G3 = moderately susceptible group (Hyb. Prolico, Hyb. Ventero, Chief Falat, Caribo, Hyb. Cherry., Hyb. Belize., Granisum Romani, Long Tomato Y, Hyb. SV 1201., H. a.s 2194); G4 = moderately resistant group (Roma, Falat American 111, Rayosol RZ, Italian Round, Arya Netherlands, Valouro RZ, Sakhia), G5 = resistant group (H.a.s 2274, Turkish Cherry, Rio Grande, Esfahan local).

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
G = highly susceptible group (CH American, Hyb. Retinto, Izmir, Ameera RZ, Hedieh, Super Crystal, Hyb. Sogno); G2 = susceptible group (111 Falat, Santawest
</p>
         <p>Hyb., Supermobile, Shiraz local, Chief, Super Chief American, CH), G3 = moderately susceptible group (Hyb. Prolico, Hyb. Ventero, Chief Falat, Caribo, Hyb. Cherry.,</p>
         <p>Hyb. Belize., Granisum Romani, Long Tomato Y, Hyb.SV 1201., H. a.s 2194); G4 = moderately resistant group (Roma, Falat American 111, Rayosol RZ, Italian Round,</p>
         <p>Arya Netherlands, Valouro RZ, Sakhia), G5 = resistant group (H.a.s 2274, Turkish Cherry, Rio Grande, Esfahan local).</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Among groups = between groups: G1, G2, G3, G4 and G5; within groups = within the groups G1/G2/G3/G4/G5.

</p>
         <p>
basis PCA (
Fig. 4
). Compared to the results of UPGMA analysis, 111Falat American and Roma (purple and yellow ovals, respectively) were scattered on the plot (
Fig. 3
). Based on the results of cluster analysis and PCA, Roma and 111Falat American as moderately resistant genotypes had the largest genetic distances from others, enabling them to be easily distinguished from other groups. In conclusion, using 2D and 3D basis PCA, 35 tomato genotypes were classified into five groups, largely in agreement with the five resistance levels of the genotypes (
Figs. 3–4
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Comparative analysis of biochemical data
</title>
         <p>
The results from the analysis of specific enzymatic activity and the total phenol content at both growth stages showed significant changes in most of the inoculated tomato leaves in comparison with the controls (
Tables 6
and 
7
). At the transplanting stage, there was a significant increase in the CAT activity among all tomato genotypes in comparison with the controls, but the highest increase was observed in 
Esfahan
Local (65.58 U∙mg 
1
), 
H
. a.s 2274 (53.42 U∙mg 
1
), Caribo (53.45 U∙mg 
1
) and Shiraz Local (47.43 U∙mg 
1
) (
Table 6
). At the maturing stage, 
Esfahan
Local and 
H
. a.s 2274 had the highest CAT activity (106.98 and 79.46 U∙mg 
1
respectively) (
Table 7
). The transplanting stage showed an increased level of specific POD activity in response to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. Alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
infection, while the highest level was observed in the resistant genotypes, 
H
. a.s 2274 (116.46 U∙mg 
1
) and Shiraz Local variety (97.76 U∙mg 
1
) as compared with the controls (
Table 6
).
</p>
         <p>
The level of specific POD activity at the maturing stage was higher in the inoculated resistant genotypes, 
H
. a.s 2274, Turkish Cherry, Rio Grande and 
Esfahan
Local variety (340.74, 311.92, 268.06 and 258.66 U∙mg 
1
, respectively) in comparison with the controls (
Table 7
).
</p>
         <p>
Here again, the transplanting stage showed a higher level of specific PAL activity in the inoculated resistant genotypes, Shiraz Local variety (6.96 U∙mg 
1
), 
H
. a.s 2274 (5.45 U∙mg 
1
) and 
Esfahan
Local variety (4.65 U∙mg 
1
) in comparison with the controls and the susceptible genotypes (
Table 6
). Similarly, there was a significant increase in the PAL activity among inoculated resistant genotypes at the maturing stage (
Table 7
). In the transplanting stage, all inoculated resistant genotypes showed a significant increase in the SOD activity, but the highest level of activity was observed in Shiraz Local and 
Esfahan
Local (4.45, and 3.63 U∙mg 
1
, respectively) in comparison with others (
Table 6
). In the maturing stage, increased SOD activity was seen in all the inoculated genotypes, but the highest level was observed in 
H
. a.s 2274, Turkish Cherry and 
Esfahan
Local (9.02, 8.08 and 6.29 U∙mg 
1
, respectively) (
Table 7
).
</p>
         <p>
The transplanting stage showed a large amount of TPC in all inoculated tomato leaves (
16–70 mg
GAE/g f. wt) in comparison with the controls (
Table 6
). The inoculated resistant genotypes, Shiraz Local, 
Esfahan
Local and 
H
. a.s 2274, contained much higher TPC (70.16, 69.25, 53.98 U∙mg 
1
, respectively), than the susceptible genotypes (
Table 6
). The level of TPC was significantly higher at the maturing stage in the infected plants in comparison with the controls (
29–87 mg
GAE/g f. wt). 
Esfahan
Local, Turkish Cherry and 
H
. a.s 2274 contained the highest value of TPC (87.62, 86.53 and 82.89, U∙mg 
1
respectively) in comparison with the controls (
Table 7
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Discussion
</title>
         <p>
This is the first study on the genetic diversity of tomato exploring genetic resistance and biochemical changes in response to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
infection using ISSR as genetic markers. Our findings support the conclusion that different tomato genotypes have different reactions to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
at transplanting and maturing stages (

, 

; 

). Although there was a significant difference in resistance to EB disease among tomato genotypes at both growth stages, disease severity was more pronounced at the maturing stage. Highly infected genotypes at the maturing stage exhibit more resistance arising from the influence of plant age (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
According to our findings, only 
H
. a.s 2274 and 
Esfahan
local Variety were found to be resistant to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
at both growth stages. The screening results of 172 recombinant inbred line population of tomato under field conditions by 

showed a wide range of reactions in response to EB disease, from resistant to susceptible, and no lines were completely resistant. 

reported that out of 401 tested tomato genotypes, only one genotype was resistant. Our results corroborate previous studies, in which no tomato genotype was completely EB disease-resistant.
</p>
         <p>
In the recent literature, resistance variation to EB disease was known to be mainly associated with genetic variation within the studied genotypes. However, there are limited reports on extensive evaluation for genetic EB disease -resistance in tomato genotypes (

; 

; 

). Characterization of genotypes based on ISSR markers has gained attention for genetic variation analysis (

). In the present study, the UBC855, UBC880 and INC3 primers were identified as more reproducible and polymorphic primers with an average of 6.18 bands; 

also found that UBC855 and UBC880 were highly polymorphic primers.
</p>
         <p>
While our study found an average number of 6.18 bands per primer, 

found an average of 7.6 bands per ISSR primer on 12 tomato varieties using 9 primers. Using 9 primers on 96 tomato accessions, 

found an average of 14.4 bands per ISSR primer. 

observed an average of 9.25 bands per ISSR primer using 10 primers on 10 tomato lines. The higher mean of the total bands as reported in these studies could be attributed to either the higher number of tomato genotypes or the higher number of primers. It is noteworthy that our results showed a higher average polymorphism percentage (86.82%), than those reported by 

(36.80%), 

(34.02%), and 

(76.38%), suggesting a significant variation in our tomato genotypes.
</p>
         <p>
The higher polymorphic and genetic diversity level found by our research is consistent with the report by 

, except for 
H
, which in our study yielded the following figures: (Ne = 1.46; 
H
= 0.27; 
I
= 0.42) in 35 genotypes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. 
lycopersicum
</tp:taxon-name>
. 

, studied the genetic diversity among 93 tomato landraces, using 14 primers, and obtained 185 bands with 100% polymorphism, Shannon index (
I
) of 0.37, Ne of 1.33.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Comparative analysis of CAT, POD, PAL, and SOD activities and TPC in genotypes at 20 days post inoculation (dpi) at transplanting stage. U = 1 mmol of hydrogen peroxide∙min 
1
of protein decreased by CAT, 1 mmol of tetraguaiacol or 1 μmol of trans-cinnamic per minute released by POD or PAL activities, respectively, and amount of enzyme required to inhibi 
b
50% of the NBT photoreduction∙min. Each value represents the mean of 3 replicates. Different letters indicate statistically significant differences (P ≤ 0.05).
</p>
         <p>
b
Control, non-inoculated tomato genotypes, 
c
Treatment, inoculated tomato genotypes.
</p>
         <p>
The highest genetic distance obtained in our results revealed significant genetic differences of susceptible and resistant genotypes (

). Clearly, the major genetic variations (97%) obtained within tested genotypes suggest the effectiveness of ISSR markers in identifying higher genetic diversity within genotype groups rather than between the groups (

).
</p>
         <p>
Pathogenesis-related proteins (PRs) have been found to enhance the defensive capacity of plants in necrotic infection (

; 

). We have shown that in tomato, the increased expression of PR proteins, β-1,3-glucanase and chitinase, was related to the resistance response to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
infection (

). In the present study, the enzyme activity analysis showed increased activity of enzymatic antioxidants, CAT, POD, PAL and SOD, in the inoculated tomato genotypes, suggesting possible contribution to plant defense response. Accumulation of CAT and SOD under disease conditions has been reported to promote plant defense responses (

; w. 

). In our study, during infection with 

<tp:taxon-name>A. alternata</tp:taxon-name>
,

the PAL (5-fold at transplanting stage) and POD (3-fold at maturing stage) enzyme activities were markedly increased in the inoculated resistant genotypes compared with the controls and susceptible genotypes. Thus, our findings supported the previous study of 

that 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
infection significantly increased activities of POD and PAL enzymes.
</p>
         <p>
Notably, a significant increase in TPC values was seen in all tomato genotypes during 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
infection. Higher TPC values were seen in inoculated resistant genotypes at both growth stages. These results clearly showed the involvement of TPC in the defense of tomato to EB disease. The highest TPC activity at transplanting stage (4-fold) and maturing stage (2 to 3-fold) were found in all the inoculated resistant genotypes as compared with their respective controls. These findings are consistent with previous studies (

; w. 

), that have reported high level of phenols acting as damaging components in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
infection.
</p>
         <p>
In conclusion, the present study furthers our understanding of the significance of antioxidants and the extent of genetic diversity in 35 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lycopersicum
</tp:taxon-name>
genotypes in response to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. alternata
</tp:taxon-name>
infection. Based on EB disease-resistance levels and ISSR marker data, the 35 tomato genotypes were categorized into five major groups. Among all the inoculated genotypes, 
H
. a.s 2274 and 
Esfahan
local showed a significant resistance level, and increased antioxidant activities at both growth stages. Moreover, enhancement of antioxidants and enzymes production in the EB disease-resistance in tomato genotypes are important observations. Future research is needed to examine the relationship between genetic diversity and EB disease-resistance.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. Plant material and growth conditions
</title>
         <p>
Thirty-five commercial genotypes of exotic and domestic origin, and inbred lines, were used (
Table 1
). Untreated tomato seeds were placed in 

July 
2018

in seedling trays filled with sterilized mix of sand-peat moss in equal parts placed in a forced-air oven at 93 
◦
C for 30 min. They were kept in greenhouse conditions (27 ± 1 
◦
C), with 16 h-light photoperiod and 65% relative humidity. Nutrients to support plant growth were supplied through irrigation with Knop’ s nutrient solution (
10 mg
FeCl 
3
; 
0.25 g
KH 
2
PO 
4
; 
0.25 g
KNO 
3
; 
0.25 g
MgSO 
4
•7 
H
2
O and 
1 g
NaNO 
3
∙L 
1
of tap water) from Columbus Chemical Industries (Columbus, WI 53925) (

).
</p>
         <p>
Two seedlings of each genotype were transferred to 
5 kg
plastic pots filled with a sterilized soil, sand and peat moss (1:1:1) substrate at first fully expanded true leaf stage (

; 

). Screening was conducted at transplanting and maturing stages in the greenhouse, and biochemical and genetic assays carried out in the laboratory of the Agricultural and Natural Resources Research and Education center of 
Esfahan
, 
Iran
. The experiments were arranged in a completely randomized design with 3 replications and 10 plants of each genotype per replication.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Fungal culture inoculum preparation and plant pathogenicity
</title>
         <p>
The pathogen strain (
KY322589
) was isolated from infected tomato leaves. The isolate was cultured in PDA and incubated for 15 days at 24 ± 1 
◦
C, before induction of sporulation as demonstrated by 

under cool-white fluorescent light with a 12-h photoperiod (

). Genotypes were screened for EB resistance. Inocula preparation was carried as described by 

. The conidial suspension (10 
5
spores∙mL 
1
) was sprayed 3 times in a 3-day interval at transplanting and mature stages, on the foliage, under 27 ± 1 
◦
C, 16-h photoperiod, and 65% relative humidity. Screening assays were performed at transplanting (6-week) and maturing (12-week) after transplanting. At 20 days after inoculation at both stages after emergence of symptoms, disease progress was evaluated. Disease severity was assessed based on infection percent (0–100) against the scoring scales of: 0, 5, 10, 25, 50, 75 or 100% (

; 

, 2019). Controls consisted of plants in pots without inoculation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Activity of CAT activity, POD activity, PAL Activity, SOD activity and TPC in six genotypes in 20 days post inoculation (dpi) at transplanting stage. U:1 mmol of hydrogen peroxide per minute of protein decreased by CAT, 1 mmol of tetraguaiacol or 1 μmol of trans-cinnamic per minute liberated by POD or PAL activities, respectively, and the amount of enzyme required to inhibit 50% of th 
b
NBT photo-reduction per minute. Each valu 
c
represents the mean of three replicates. Different letters indicate statistically significant differences (P ≤ 0.05).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Control, non-inoculated tomato genotypes.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c
Treatment, inoculated tomato genotypes.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. DNA extraction and ISSR amplifications
</title>
         <p>
Genomic DNA extraction from about 
1 g
of young leaf tissue (the 5–6 leaf stage) from each tomato genotype was carried out using a modified Cetyl Trimethyl Ammonium Bromide (CTAB) - based method according to 

. The DNA quality and purity were determined using a Nano spectrophotometer. The PCR-based ISSR reaction mixes were prepared according to 

using 15 ISSR primers (Macrogen 
Korea, South Korea
). The amplification reaction mix (25 μL) comprised 1 μL extracted DNA, 1.5 μL of 1 primer, 12.5 μL of 2x Master mix Red and 10 μL distilled water (Ampliqon, Odense, 
Denmark
). The DNA amplifications were performed using an Eppendorf Gradient Mastercycler (Eppendorf, 
Hamburg
, 
Germany
). Amplification reactions were programmed in a 10-m initial denaturalization phase at 94 
◦
C followed by 45 cycles of annealing each lasting 45–60 s, at a primer-specific temperature (
Table 3
). The process continued with an extension phase at 72 
◦
C for 2 min and with a final extension phase at 72 
◦
C for 10 min when naturalization occurs. The PCR-amplified fragments were electrophoresed on 1.5% (w/v) agarose gels, in the 1X TBE Buffer at 80 V for 1.5 h. A gene ruler 100 bp DNA ladder plus (RNA Biotech Co., 
Isfahan
, 
Iran
) was used as a standard to determine size of polymorphic fragments, as visualized by ethidium bromide staining and photographed under UV light.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Antioxidant activities and total phenolic contents analysis
</title>
         <p>
To estimate defense-related enzymes, 14 susceptible and resistant genotypes of tomato were selected based on screening (
Table 1
). After re-inoculation at transplanting and mature stages, third leaves of the tomato genotypes from control, non-inoculated genotypes and inoculated groups were collected separately as samples and stored in aluminum foil at 80 
◦
C for enzyme extraction. All experiments were repeated 3 times (

).
</p>
         <p>
Estimations of defense-related enzyme contents were done on extracts. To obtain CAT, POD, PAL and SOD extracts, pre-weighed infected and non-infected leaves were homogenized in 4 mL buffer [50 mM Tris pH = 8.5, 14.4 mM 2-mercaptoethanol and 1% (w/v) insoluble polyvinylpolypyrrorolidone]. Homogenates were centrifuged at 6000× 
g
for 15 min at 4 
◦
C (

). Total protein in each enzyme extract was determined through the 
Bradford
procedure (1976) using bovine serum albumin as a standard. The method of 

was used to estimate CAT activity. The photometric intensity of the reaction was measured using a spectrophotometer (
240 nm
) in a 10 mM hydrogen peroxide solution. The POD activity was determined by methods as described by 

. The photometric intensity of the reaction was measured using a spectrophotometer (
470 nm
) in a 40 mM hydrogen peroxide solution. The method of 

was used to estimate SOD activity. The photometric intensity of the reaction was measured using a spectrophotometer (
560 nm
) with a 75 μM nitroblue tetrazolium (NBT) and 1.5 μM riboflavin under 40-W fluorescent lamp at 25 
◦
C for 20 min. The PAL activity was assessed as described by 

. The photometric intensity of the reaction was measured using a spectrophotometer (
290 nm
) with 15 mM phenylalanine as the substrate. The TPC of each sample extract was determined with the Folin-Ciocalteu reagent by the method of 

. The photometric intensity of the reaction was measured using a spectrophotometer (
760 nm
) using gallic acid as the substrate.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Statistical analysis
</title>
         <p>
The EB disease severity data were converted using Asin √x + 0.5 for homogeneity, and analysis of variance was performed using SAS (ver. 9.4, SAS Institute, Cary, NC) (SAS, 2004), and the means were compared using least significant difference (LSD). Statistical analysis was done by GenStat software (GenStat for Windows, 6th VSN International, 
UK
). Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed to evaluate the impact of different genotypes on EB disease severity. Pearson correlation analysis was also carried out to analyze the relationship among the tomato genotypes and response variability and cluster analysis of data was performed using SPSS software (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The PCR products were scored as present = 1 or absent = 0. Polymorphism levels and calculated by separating polymorphic bands from total scored bands. The Similarity for Qualitative Data (SIMQUAL) routine was used to determine the Jacquard similarity coefficient. A dendrogram with the Unweighted Pair Group Method with Arithmetic Average (UPGMA) algorithm was constructed using NTSYS software (ver. 2.1, Numerical taxonomy and multivariate analysis system, Applied Biostatistics, 
New York
, 
USA
). The distribution of genetic variation within, and among, groups, was detected using the molecular variance analysis (AMOVA) in GenAlEx software (

). Genetic variation indices, including effective numbers of alleles (Ne), Shannon’ s information index (
I
), Nei’ s gene diversity (
H
), percent of polymorphic loci (PPL), were estimated using POP-GENE software (

). All data were in triplicate.
</p>
         <p>
Biochemical data were analyzed with SPSS (ver. 16.0, Chicago, IL). Two-way ANOVA test was used for data analysis of variance between infected tomato and controls and mean difference analysis of the data was evaluated with LSD test (

).
</p>
         <p>
Author contributions
</p>
         <p>Giti Alizadeh-Moghaddam, Conducting the project, Obtaining resources, Writing the original draft of the manuscript. Zahra Rezayatmand, Supervision, Review, and Data curation. Mehdi Nasr- Esfahani, Supervision, Conceptualization, Methodology, Data curation, Review, and Editing. Mahdi Khozaei, Methodology and Review.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
Thanks go to Professor Roland N. Perry, Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, School of Life and Medical Sciences, University of 
Hertfordshire
, Hatfield, 
Hertfordshire
, AL10 9AB, 
UK
for the final English revision of the manuscript. We also thank the Plant Protection Research Department, 
Isfahan
Center for Agricultural and Natural Resources Research and Education, 
Isfahan
, and the 
Iran
and Plant Protection Research Institute, 
Tehran
, 
Iran
, for providing facilities for the project.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112486.</p>
         <p>
Funding
</p>
         <p>This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Adhikari, P.
, 
Oh, Y.
, 
Panthee, D.R.
, 
2017
. 
Current status of Early Blight resistance in tomato: an update
. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
18
, 
1–22
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ ijms18102019
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aebi, H.
, 
1984
. 
Catalase
. 
Methods Enzymol.
105
, 
121–126
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ s0076-6879(84)05016-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Aguilera, J.G.
, 
Pessoni, L.A.
, 
Rodriguez, G.B.
, 
Elsayed, A.Y.
, 
Silva, D.J.H.
, 
Barros, E.G.
, 
2011
. 

Genetic variability by ISSR markers in tomato (
Solanum lycopersicon
Mill.). Pesqui. Agropecu

. 
Bras.
6
, 
243–252
. 
https://doi.org/10.5039/agraria.v6i2a998
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Akhtar, K.P.
, 
Ullah, N.
, 
Saleem, M.Y.
, 
Iqbal, Q.
, 
Asghar, M.
, 
Khan, A.R.
, 
2019
. 

Evaluation of tomato genotypes for early blight disease resistance caused by 
Alternaria solani
in Pakistan. J

. 
Plant Pathol.
101
, 
1159–1170
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s42161-019.- 00304-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Awan, Z.A.
, 
Shoaib, A.
, 
Khan, K.A.
, 
2019
. 
Crosstalk of Zn in combination with other fertilizers underpins interactive effects and induces resistance in tomato plant against early blight disease
. 
Plant Pathol. J.
35
, 
330–340
. 
https://doi.org/10.5423/ PPJ.OA.01.2019.0002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ayala-Zavala, J.F.
, 
Silva-Espinoza, B.A.
, 
Silva-Espinoza, M.R.
, 
Villegas-Ochoa, M.A.
, 
Esqueda, M.
, Gonzalez-Aguilar´, 
G.A
., Calder´on-Lopez´, Y., 
2012
. 

Antioxidant and antifungal potential of methanol extracts of 
Phellinus
spp. from Sonora, Mexico. Rev. Iberoam

. 
De. Micol.
2
, 
132–138
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.riam.2011.09.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Beauchamp, C.
, 
Fridovich, I.
, 
1971
. 
Superoxide dismutase: improved assays and an assay applicable to acrylamide gels
. 
Anal. Biochem.
44
, 
276–287
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/0003-2697(71)90370-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Beaudoin-Eagan, L.D.
, 
Thorpe, T.A.
, 
1985
. 
Tyrosine and phenylalanine ammonia lyase activities during shoot initiation in tobacco callus cultures
. 
Plant Physiol
78
, 
438–441
. 
https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.78.3.438
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Benabdellah, K.
, 
Azcon-Aguilar, C.
, 
Valderas, A.
, 
Speziga, D.
, 
Fitzpatrick, T.B.
, 
Ferrol, N.
, 
2009
. 

GintPDX1 encodes a protein involved in vitamin B6 biosynthesis that is upregulated by oxidative stress in the arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus 
Glomus intraradices

. 
New Phytol.
184
, 
682–693
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469- 8137.2009.02978.x. New Phytol. 184
, 682–93.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bradford, M.M.
, 
1976
. 
A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding
. 
Anal. Biochem.
72
, 
248–254
. 
https://doi.org/10.1006/abio.1976.9999
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chung, K.R.
, 
2012
. 

Stress response and pathogenicity of the necrotrophic fungal pathogen 
Alternaria alternata

. 
Sci. Tech. Rep.
10
, 
1–17
. 
https://doi.org/10.6064/ 2012/635431
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dazy, M.
, 
Jung, V.
, F´erard, J.F., 
Masfaraud, J.F.
, 
2008
. 
Ecological recovery of 712 vegetation at a former coke-factory industrial wasteland: role of plant 713 antioxidant enzymes and possible implications in site restoration
. 
Chemosphere
74
, 
57–63
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2008.09.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dey, P.
, 
Ramanujam, R.
, 
Venkatesan, G.
, 
Nagarathnam, R.
, 
2019
. 

Sodium alginate potentiates antioxidant defense and PR proteins against early blight disease caused by 
Alternaria solani
in 
Solanum lycopersicum
Linn

. 
PloS One
14
, 
1–26
. 
https://doi. org/10.1371/journal.pone.0223216
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
van Esse, H.P.
, 
Reuber, T.L.
, 
van der Does, D.
, 
2020
. 
Genetic modification to improve disease resistance in crops
. 
New Phytol.
225
, 
70–86
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/ nph.15967
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Figueiredo, A.S.T.
, 
Resende, J.T.V.
, 
Faria, M.V.
, 
Da-Silva, P.R.
, 
Fagundes, B.S.
, 
Morales, R.G.F.
, 
2016
. 
Prediction of industrial tomato hybrids from agronomic traits and ISSR molecular markers
. 
Genet. Mol. Res.
15
, 
1–14
. 
https://doi.org/10.4238/ gmr.15027981
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Foolad, M.R.
, 
Ntahimpera, N.
, 
Christ, B.J.
, 
Lin, G.Y.
, 
2000
. 
Comparison of field, greenhouse, and detached-leaflet evaluations of tomato germplasm for early blight resistance
. 
Plant Dis.
84
, 
967–972
. 
https://doi.org/10.1094/PDIS.2000.84.9.967
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Foolad, M.R.
, 
Ashrafi, H.
, 
2015
. 
Characterization of early blight resistance in a recombinant inbred line population of tomato: I. heritability and trait correlations
. 
Adv. Stud. Biol.
7
, 
131–148
. 
https://doi.org/10.12988/asb.2015.41162
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ghasemi, A.R.
, 
Golparvar, A.R.
, 
Nasr Esfahani, M.
, 
2014
. 
Analysis of genetic diversity of sugar beet genotypes using random amplified polymorphic DNA marker
. 
Genetika
46
, 
975–984
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Govindaraj, M.
, 
Vetriventhan, M.
, 
Srinivasan, M.
, 
2015
. 
Importance of genetic diversity assessment in crop plants and its recent advances: an overview of its analytical perspectives
. 
Genet. Res. Int.
15
, 
1–14
. 
https://doi.org/10.1155/2015/431487
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hasan, K.U.
, 
2017
. 

Study of the effectiveness of some enzymatic antioxidants of tomato plant (
Lycopersicon esculentum
L.) infected by Fusarium wilt disease caused by 
Fusarium oxysporum
with biological control by 
Pseudomonas fluorescens
and 
Bacillus subtilis
bacteria. IOSR J

. 
Agric. Vet. Sci.
10
, 
70–76
. 
https://doi.org/10.9790/2380- 1008027076
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hashemi, L.
, 
Golparvar, A.R.
, 
Nasr Esfahani, M.
, 
Golabadi, M.
, 
2019
. 

Correlation between cucumber genotype and resistance to damping-off disease caused by 
Phytophthora melonis

. 
Biotechnol. Equip.
33
, 
1494–1504
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 13102818.2019.1675535
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hashemi, L.
, 
Golparvar, A.R.
, 
Nasr-Esfahani, M.
, 
Golabadi, M.
, 
2020
. 

Expression analysis of defense-related genes in cucumber (
Cucumis sativus
L.) against 
Phytophthora melonis

. 
Mol Biol
4145–4153
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11033-020-05520-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hayat Moghaddam, M.
, 
Bakhtiar, F.
, 
Bozorgipour, R.
, 
Nikkhah, H.R.
, 
2011
. 
Evaluation of resistance to powdery mildew and some agronomic trails of barley doubled haploid lines
. 
Seed Plant Improv. J.
27
, 
441–443
. 
https://doi.org/10.22092/ SPIJ.2017.111074
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Henareh, M.
, 
Dursun, A.
, 
Abdollahi-Mandoulakani, B.
, 
Kaliloglu, K.
, 
2016
. 
Assessment of genetic diversity in tomato landraces using ISSR markers
. 
Genetika
48
, 
25–35
. 
https://doi.org/10.2298/GENSR1601025H
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jung, W.J.
, 
Maboodb, F.
, 
Souleimanovb, A.
, 
Smith, D.L.
, 
2011
. 

Induction of defense-related enzymes in soybean leaves by class IId bacteriocins (thuricin 17 and bacthuricin F4) purified from 
Bacillus
strains

. 
Microbiol. Res.
167
, 
14–19
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.micres.2011.02.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kiani, G.
, 
Siahchehreh, M.
, 
2018
. 
Genetic diversity in tomato varieties assessed by ISSR markers
. 
Int. J. Veg. Sci.
24
, 
353–360
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 19315260.2017.1419397
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kumar, S.
, 
Singh, R.
, 
Kashyap, P.L.
, 
Srivastava, A.K.
, 
2013
. 

Rapid detection and quantification of 
Alternaria solani
in tomato

. 
Sci. Hortic.
151
, 
184–189
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.scienta. 2012. 12.026
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kumar, T.R.
, 
Praveen Kumar, M.
, 
2019
. 

Survey and screening of Tomato varieties against Early Blight (
Alternaria solani
) under field condition

. 
Int. J. Pure App. Biosci.
7
, 
629–635
. 
https://doi.org/10.18782/2320-7051.7631
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, J.
, 
Mao, L.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Zhang, L.
, 
Jiang, H.
, 
2018
. 

Phytochemical changes in mango fruit in response to 
Alternaria alternata
infection. Czech J

. 
Food Sci.
36
, 
227–232
. 
https://doi.org/10.17221/328/2017-CJFS
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, W.
, 
Yuan, S.
, 
Li, Q.
, 
Sang, W.
, 
Cao, J.
, 
Jiang, W.
, 
2018
. 

Methyl p-coumarate inhibits black spot rot on jujube fruit through membrane damage and oxidative stress against 
Alternaria alternata

. 
Postharvest Biol. Technol.
145
, 
230–238
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.jafc.9b00087
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Meena, M.
, 
Zehra, A.
, 
Dubey, M.K.
, 
Aamir, M.
, 
Gupta, V.K.
, 
Upadhyay, R.S.
, 
2016
. 

Comparative evaluation of biochemical changes in tomato (
Lycopersicon esculentum
Mill.) infected by 
Alternaria alternata
and its toxic metabolites (TeA, AOH, and AME). Front

. 
Plant Sci.
7
, 
1–14
. 
https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2016.01408
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moghaddam, G.A.
, 
Rezayatmand, Z.
, 
Nasr Esfahani, M.
, 
Khozaei, M.
, 
2019
. 

Genetic defense analysis of tomatoes in response to early blight disease, 
Alternaria alternata

. 
Plant Physiol. Biochem. (Paris)
142
, 
500–509
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. plaphy.2019.08.011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Monfared, M.A.
, 
Samsampour, D.
, 
Sharifi-Sirchi, G.R.
, 
Sedighi, F.
, 
2018
. 

Assessment of genetic diversity in 
Salvadora persica
L. based on inter simple sequence repeat (ISSR) genetic marker. J

. 
Genetic Engin. Biotechnol.
6
, 
661–667
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ j.jgeb.2018.04.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nasr Esfahani, M.
, 
Moghaddam, A.G.
, 
Karimkhah, M.A.
, 
2017
a. 
The relation of leaf micro- morphological components with early blight resistant potatoes varieties. Iran. Plant Protect
. 
Sci.
39
, 
51–64
. 
https://doi.org/10.22055/PPR.2017.12549
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nasr Esfahani, M.
, 
Moghaddam, A.G.
, 
Karimkhah, M.A.
, 
2017
b. 
Susceptibility assessment of commercial potato cultivars to early blight disease in the field and glasshouse conditions. Iran. Plant Protect
. 
Sci.
48
, 
169–182
. 
https://doi.org/10.22059/ IJPPS.2017.133390.1006660
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nasr Esfahani, M.
, 
2018
a. 

Analysis of virulence and genetic variability of 
Alternaria alternata
associated with leaf spot disease in potato plants in Iran

. 
Acta Mycol.
53
, 
1–9
. 
https://doi.org/10.5586/am.1105
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nasr Esfahani, M.
, 
2018
b. 

Identification of 
Ulocladium atrum
causing potato leaf blight in Iran

. 
Phytopathol. Mediterr.
57
, 
112–114
. 
https://doi.org/10.14601/Phytopathol_ Mediterr-22282
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nasr Esfahani, M.
, 
2019
. 

An IPM plan for early blight disease of potato 
Alternaria solani
sorauer and 
A. alternata
(Fries.) Keissler

. 
Arch. Phytopathol. Plant Protect
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1080/03235408.2018.1489600
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Odilbekov, F.
, 
Edin, E.
, 

Mostafanezhad, 
H
.

, 

Coolman, 
H
.

, 
Grenville-Briggs, L.
, 
Liljeroth, E.
, 
2019
. 

Within-season changes in 
Alternaria solani
populations in potato in response to fungicide application strategies

. 
Eur. J. Plant Pathol.
155
, 
953–965
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10658-019-01826-8
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Parvin, K.
, 
Hasanuzzaman, M.
, 
Bhuyan, M.H.M.
, 
Nahar, K.
, 
Mohsin, S.M.
, 
Fujita, M.
, 
2019
. 

Comparative physiological and biochemical changes in tomato (
Solanum lycopersicum
L.) under salt stress and recovery: role of antioxidant defense and glyoxalase systems

. 
Antioxidants
8
, 
1–16
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/antiox8090350
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Peakall, R.
, 
Smouse, P.E.
, 
2006
. 
Genalex 6: genetic analysis in Excel
. 
Population genetic software for teaching and research. Mol. Ecol. Notes
6
, 
288–295
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1093/bioinformatics/bts460
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Periyannan, S.
, 
2018
. 
Sustaining global agriculture through rapid detection and deployment of genetic resistance to deadly crop diseases
. 
New Phytol.
219
, 
45–51
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.14928
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Reynolds, M.
, 
Chapman, S.
, 
Crespo-Herrera, L.
, 
Molero, G.
, 
Monda, S.
, 
Pequeno, D.N.L.
, et al., 
2019
. 
Breeder friendly phenotyping
. 
Plant Sci.
110396
, 
1–21
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.plantsci.2019.110396
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shahin, E.A.
, 
Shepard, J.F.
, 
1979
. 

An efficient technique in inducing profuse sporulation of 
Alternaria
species

. 
Phytopathology
69
, 
618–620
. 
https://doi.org/10.1094/Phyto- 69-618
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singleton, V.L.
, 
Orthofer, R.
, 
Lamuela-Raventos, R.M.
, 
1999
. 
Analysis of total phenols and other oxidation substrates and antioxidants by means of Folin-Ciocalteu reagent
. 
Methods Enzymol.
299
, 
152–178
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0076-6879(99)99017- 1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stewart, C.N.J.
, 
Via, L.E.
, 
1993
. 
A rapid CTAB DNA isolation technique useful for RAPD’ s fingerprinting and other PCR applications
. 
Biotechniques
14
, 
748–758
. PubMed ID: 8512694.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Thomma, B.P.H.J.
, 
2003
. 

Alternaria
spp.: from general saprophyte to specific parasite

. 
Mol. Plant Pathol.
4
, 
225–236
. 
https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1364-3703.2003.00173.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tsuda, K.
, 
Somssich, I.E.
, 
2015
. 
Transcriptional networks in plant immunity
. 
New Phytol.
206
, 
932–947
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.13286
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vloutoglou, I.
, 
Kalogerakis, S.N.
, 
2000
. 

Effects of inoculum concentration, wetness duration and plant age on development of early blight (
Alternaria solani
) and on shedding of leaves in tomato plants

. 
Plant Pathol.
49
, 
339–345
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1046/j.1365-3059.2000.00462.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wolters, P.J.
, 
Vos, L.D.
, 
Bijsterbosch, G.
, 
Woudenberg, J.H.C.
, 
Visser, R.G.F.
, 
Linden, G.V. D.
, 
Vleeshouwers, V.G.A.A.
, 
2019
. 

A rapid method to screen wild 
Solanum
for resistance to early blight

. 
Eur. J. Plant Pathol.
154
, 
109–114
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s10658-019-01741-y
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yeh, F.C.
, 
Yang, R.C.
, 
Boyle, T.
, 
1999
. 
POPGENE. Microsoft Window-Based Freeware for Population Genetic Analysis. Release 1.31
. 
Molecular Biology and Biotechnology Centre, University of Alberta, Edmonton
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zietkiewicz, E.
, 
Rafalski, A.
, 
Labuda, D.
, 
1994
. 
Genome fingerprinting by simple sequence repeat (SSR)-anchored polymerase chain reaction amplification
. 
Genomics
20
, 
176–183
. 
https://doi.org/10.1006/geno.1994.1151
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
