<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2017.04.008</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Isolation of antioxidant phenolics from Schinopsis brasiliensis based on a preliminary LC-MS profiling</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2017</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Schinopsis brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Schinopsis brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Schinopsis brasiliensis
Engl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Schinopsis brasiliensis
Engl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Juglans mandshurica
(
Machida et al., 2009
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>S. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Schinopsis brasiliensis
Engl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cristina Farias</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Clisiane Carla de Souza Santos
a, b, c
, Milena Masullo
b
, Antonietta Cerulli
b, d
,
</p>
         <p>
Angela Mari 
b
, Charles Dos Santos Estevam
a
, Cosimo Pizza
b
, Sonia Piacente

b, 

*
</p>
         <p>
a

Departamento de Fisiologia, Universidade Federal de 
Sergipe
, av. Marechal Rondon, Rosa Elze, Sao

~ 
Cristovao
́~, 

SE, 
Brazil
</p>
         <p>
b

Dipartimento di Farmacia, Universitàdegli Studi di Salerno, via Giovanni Paolo II n. 132, 84084, Fisciano, SA, 
Italy
</p>
         <p>
c

PhD 

Program in 
Biotechnology

of Natural Resources — RENORBIO, Universidade Federal de 
Sergipe
, av. Marechal Rondon, Rosa Elze, Sao

~ 
Cristovao
́~, 
SE
,
</p>
         <p>
Brazil
</p>
         <p>
d

PhD 
Program in Drug Discovery
and Development, 
University of Salerno
, 
Via Giovanni Paolo II
132, I-84084, 
Fisciano, SA
, 
Italy
</p>
         <p>
A R T I C L E I N F o
</p>
         <p>
Article history:
</p>
         <p>
Received 
11 February 2017
</p>
         <p>Received in revised form</p>
         <p>
23 March 2017
</p>
         <p>
Accepted 
10 April 2017
</p>
         <p>
Available online 
24 April 2017
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Schinopsis brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) stem bark
</p>
         <p>Phenolics</p>
         <p>LC-MS profile</p>
         <p>Cytotoxicity</p>
         <p>Antioxidant activity</p>
         <p>
A B S T R A C T
</p>
         <p>
The phenolic content of the ethanol extract of the stem bark of the Brazilian plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Schinopsis brasiliensis
Engl.
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) has been evaluated together with the antioxidant activity. The good antioxidant activity exhibited in the Trolox Equivalent Antioxidant Capacity (TEAC) assay (TEAC value 
¼
3.04 mg
/mL) encouraged us to investigate its constituents. An analytical approach based on LC-ESIMS 
n
was applied to rapidly obtain a metabolite profile of the ethanol extract of the stem bark of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
. Sixteen phenolic compounds, among which five galloyl derivatives, never reported before, have been isolated and their structures have been unambiguously elucidated by extensive spectroscopic methods, including 1D (
1
H, 
13
C, TOCSY) and 2D (DQF-COSY, HMBC, and HSQC) NMR experiments. Moreover, the antioxidant activity of all the isolated compounds was evaluated, along with the cytotoxicity against the cancer cell lines A549 (human alveolar basal carcinoma) and Hela (human epitheloid cervix carcinoma). The previously undescribed compounds exhibited a high free-radical-scavenging activity, in the range of 1.10 
—
1.86 mM. None of the tested compounds, in a range of concentrations between 12.5 and 100 
M
M, caused a significant reduction of the cell number.
</p>
         <p>
© 2017 
Elsevier Ltd. All
rights reserved.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Schinopsis brasiliensis
Engl.
</tp:taxon-name>
is a plant belonging to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family, known as “baraúna”, “bŕauna” or “quebracho”, and characterized by arboreal habitat, with dimensions close to 
15 m
high. It can be found in the Brazilian semi-arid regions and it is a native species of the Caatinga and Atlantic forest (

). This plant is considered by the “First National Report for the Convention on Biological Diversity” (CBD) as an endangered species, due to the extensive utilisation of its wood in general construction (

).
</p>
         <p>
Different parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, including leaves, fruits, and mainly bark are used in Brazilian traditional medicine for the treatment of various diseases, such as inflammation, influenza, cough, diarrhea, dysentery, and as vermifuge (

; 

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
has also been used as a natural antiseptic to treat wounds and superficial mycoses (

).
</p>
         <p>
Leaves and bark extracts from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
have been reported to possess antioxidant and antimicrobial activities (

), while a stem bark extract from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and its fractions revealed molluscicidal and larvicidal activities (

).
</p>
         <p>
Previous phytochemical investigations on 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
leaves reported the presence of tannins and polyphenols, such as methyl gallate, gallic acid, ellagic acid derivatives (

), and flavonoids (

). Phytochemical investigation of the MeOH extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
stems showed the presence of a biflavonoid and a chalcone (

), while from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
bark an alkyl phenol along with a steroid derivative were isolated (

).
</p>
         <p>
With the aim to validate some of the biological activities reported for 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, the phenolic content of the ethanol extract of the stem bark has been evaluated by Folin-Ciocalteau method together with the antioxidant activity by Trolox Equivalent Antioxidant Capacity (TEAC) assay (TEAC value 
¼
3.04 mg
/mL). The good antioxidant activity encouraged us to investigate its constituents. An analytical approach, based on LC-ESIMS 
n
, has been applied to rapidly obtain a metabolite profile of the ethanol extract of the stem bark of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
. It guided the isolation of 16 phenolic compounds, among which five previously unreported galloyl derivatives (
8
, 

10 
—
12

and 
14
), which have been unambiguously elucidated by extensive spectroscopic methods, including 1D (
1
H, 
13
C, TOCSY) and 2D NMR experiments (DQF-COSY, HMBC, and HSQC). The antioxidant activity of all isolated metabolites was also assayed.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>Moreover, the cytotoxic activity of isolated compounds against the cancer cell lines A549 (human alveolar basal carcinoma) and Hela (human epitheloid cervix carcinoma) has been evaluated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
The ethanol extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
stem bark collected in summer showed a high total phenol content determined by the Folin-Ciocalteau method and expressed as gallic acid equivalent (
403.26 mg
GAE/g of extract).
</p>
         <p>Aberrant production of reactive oxygen (ROS) or nitrogen (RNS) species has been demonstrated to contribute to the development of some prevalent diseases, including cancer and cardiovascular diseases. Polyphenols are able to react directly with ROS and RNS, preventing their concentrations from reaching harmful intracellular levels.</p>
         <p>
Thus the antioxidant activity of the ethanol extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
stem bark extract has been evaluated by TEAC assay, revealing a significant concentration-dependent free-radical scavenging activity (
3.04 mg
/mL).
</p>
         <p>
Preliminary, LC-ESIMS 
n
analysis in negative ionization mode of the ethanol extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
stem bark has been carried out (
Fig. 1
). Analysis of the LC-MS profile of the extract showed sixteen main peaks. The careful investigation of the multistage mass spectra of these compounds suggested their phenolic nature (
Table 1
). In particular, the careful study of the ESIMS 
n
fragmentation pattern of each compound pointed out to assign common features to compounds 

1 
—
2

, 

4 
—
8

, 

10 
—
12

and 
14
, showing the presence of a main ion fragment [M-H] 
-
at 
m/z
169, corresponding to a galloyl moiety. Moreover, for compounds 
2
, 
5
, 
6
, 
8
, 
10
, 
12
and 
14
additional main ion fragments [M-H] 
-
at 
m/z
331 or at 
m/z
313 were evident, corresponding to the loss of a galloylhexose unit with or without a water molecule (
Table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
In order to unambiguously elucidate their structures by NMR experiments, the ethanol extract was purified by size exclusion chromatography, followed by further purification steps by reversed-phase HPLC-RI, to obtain sixteen compounds. Their structures were established by 1D and 2D-NMR experiments along with ESIMS and HRESIMS analysis (
Fig. 2
).
</p>
         <p>
A detailed analysis of NMR data of compounds 
8
, 

10 
—
12

, and 
14
showed the presence of a common moiety. For compound 
8
, the 
1
H NMR spectrum showed an aromatic signal at 
d
7.10 (2H, s), ascribable to a galloyl moiety as confirmed by the HMBC correlation between the proton signal at 
d
7.10 with the carbon resonances at 
d
121.1 (C-1 

00

), 146.4 (C-3 

00

and C-5 

00

), 139.5 (C-4 

00

) and 167.9 (C-7 

00

) (
Table 2
). Moreover, for the sugar unit an anomeric signal at 
d
4.89 (d, 
J
¼
7.8 Hz) was evident. On the basis of HSQC, HMBC, COSY and 1D-TOCSY experiments a 
b
-glucopyranosyl unit was identified. The absolute configuration of the sugar unit was determined by acid hydrolysis of compound 
8
and was assigned as D-glucose on the basis of its optical rotation value (

). The downfield shifts of protons at 
d
4.60 and 4.43 (H 
2
-6 

0

) of the primary alcoholic function of glucose and their HMBC correlation with the carbon resonance at 
d
167.9 (C-7 

00

) revealed the site of esterification. The 
b
- D-glucopyranosyl-(6- 
O
-galloyl)-unit was also identified in the NMR spectra of compounds 

10 
—
12

and 
14
.
</p>
         <p>
The HRESIMS of compound 
8
(
m/z
467.1190 [M-H] 
-
, calcd for C 
21
H 
23
O 
12
, 467.1173) and the 
13
C NMR data supported a molecular formula of C 
21
H 
24
O 
12
. The 
1
H NMR spectrum showed additional aromatic signals at 
d
7.07 (d, 
J
¼
8.0 Hz), 7.03 (d, 
J
¼
1.8 Hz) and 6.76 (dd, 
J
¼
1.8, 8.0 Hz) typical of a 1,3,4-trisubstituted aromatic ring, at 
d
4.53 (2H, s) ascribable to a primary alcoholic group and at 
d
3.88 (3H, s), corresponding to a methoxy group (
Table 2
). The HMBC correlations between the proton signal at 
d
7.03 (H-2) with the carbon signals at 
d
137.4 (C-1), 150.4 (C-3), 146.6 (C-4) and 64.9 (C- 7) and the cross-peak between the methoxy function at 
d
3.88 with the carbon resonance at 
d
150.4 (C-3) allowed us to identify the aglycone as vanillyl alcohol. A further HMBC correlation between the anomeric signal at 
d
4.89 with the carbon resonance at 
d
146.6 (C-4) established the structure of 
8
as the previously unreported vanillyl alcohol-4- 
O
- 
b
-D-(6 

0

- 
O
-galloyl)-glucopyranoside.
</p>
         <p>
The HRESIMS of 
10
(
m/z
453.1033 [M-H] 
-
, calcd for C 
20
H 
21
O 
12
, 453.2500) and the 
13
C NMR data supported a molecular formula of C 
20
H 
22
O 
12
. The 
1
H NMR spectrum showed along with the signals ascribable to a 
b
-D-glucopyranosyl-(6- 
O
-galloyl)-unit, signals at 
d
6.98 (d, 
J
¼
8.3 Hz), 6.46 (d, 
J
¼
1.8 Hz) and 6.20 (dd, 
J
¼
1.8, 8.3 Hz) typical of a 1,3,4-trisubstituted aromatic ring, and a signal at 
d
3.82 (3H, s), corresponding to a methoxy group, assigned by the HMBC correlation to C-4 (
Table 2
). Thus, the aglycone of 
10
was identified as 2-hydroxy-4-methoxyphenol. A further HMBC correlation between the anomeric signal at 
d
4.70 with the carbon resonance at 
d
141.3 (C-1) allowed to establish the structure of 
10
as the previously unreported 2-hydroxy-4-methoxyphenol-1- 
O
- 
b
-D-(6 

0

- 
O
- galloyl)-glucopyranoside. A similar compound, the 2-hydroxy-4- methoxyphenol 1- 
O
- 
b
-D-(6 

0

- 
O
-syringoyl)-glucopyranoside, differing for the presence of methoxy group on the galloyl unit, was reported in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Juglans mandshurica
(
Machida et al., 2009
)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of 
11
was established as C 
24
H 
30
O 
13
by HRESIMS (
m/z
525.1608 [M-H] 
-
, calcd for C 
24
H 
29
O 
13
, 525.1587) and 
13
C NMR data. The 
1
H NMR spectrum showed along with the signals ascribable to a 
b
-D-glucopyranosyl-(6- 
O
-galloyl)-unit, an aromatic signal at 
d
6.48 (2H, s) and a signal at 
d
3.78 (6H, s) typical of two methoxy groups, assigned on the basis of 2D-NMR data to a 1,3,4,5- tetrasubstituted aromatic ring. Further signals in the proton spectrum at 
d
3.52 (2H, t, 
J
¼
7.2 Hz), 2.61 (t, 
J
¼
8.0 Hz) and 1.81 (2H, q, 
J
¼
8.0 Hz), suggested the presence of a propanol unit, as confirmed by the linear connectivity observed in the COSY spectrum (
Table 2
). The HMBC correlation between the proton signals at 
d
2.61 and 1.81 with the carbon resonances at 
d
140.0 (C-1) and 107.0 (C-2, C-6) prompted us to identify the aglycone of 
11
as the dihydrosinapyl alcohol. Finally, the HMBC correlation between the anomeric proton at 
d
4.80 with the carbon resonance at 
d
133.7 (C-4) established compound 
11
as the previously unreported dihydrosinapyl alcohol- 4- 
O
-(6 

0

- 
O
-galloyl)- 
b
-D-glucopyranoside.
</p>
         <p>
3
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
The HRESIMS mass spectrum of 
12
(
m/z
479.1190 [M-H] 
-
, calcd for C 
22
H 
23
O 
12
, 479.1173) supported a molecular formula of C 
22
H 
24
O 
12
. In addition to the signals corresponding to the 
b
-Dglucopyranosyl-(6- 
O
-galloyl) moiety, further signals in the aromatic region at 
d
7.94 (2H, d, 
J
¼
8.0) and 6.87 (2H, d, 
J
¼
8.0) typical of a 1,4-disubstituted aromatic ring, at 
d
4.27 (dd, 
J
¼
12.0, 7.0) and 4.07 (dd, 
J
¼
12.0, 7.0) ascribable to a primary alcoholic function and at 
d
3.18 (overlapped) were evident in the 
1
H NMR spectrum of compound 
12
(
Table 2
). Analysis of NMR data allowed the structure of the aglycone of 
12
to be established as 4,9- dihydroxypropiophenone. The HMBC correlation between the anomeric signal at 
d
4.39 (H-1' 
glc
) with the carbon resonance at 
d
66.4 (C-9) allowed to assign unambiguously the site of linkage of the sugar moiety. Consequently, the structure of 
12
was determined as the previously unreported 4,9-dihydroxypropiophenone-9- 
O
- (6 

0

- 
O
-galloyl)- 
b
-D-glucopyranoside.
</p>
         <p>
The HRESIMS mass spectrum of 
14
(
m/z
511.1452 [M-H] 
-
, calcd for C 
23
H 
27
O 
13
, 511.1434) showed a molecular formula of C 
23
H 
28
O 
13
, also supported by the 
13
C NMR data. The 
1
H NMR spectrum showed along with the signals ascribable to a 
b
-D-glucopyranosyl-(6- 
O
- galloyl)-unit, signals at 
d
6.70 (2H, s), 3.80 (6H, s), and 3.75 (3H, s) assigned on the basis of 2D-NMR data to a 3,4,5-trimethoxyphenyl ring, and at 
d
4.80 and 4.64 (each, d, 
J
¼
12.0 Hz), ascribable to a primary alcoholic group (
Table 2
). The HMBC correlation between the proton signals at 
d
4.80 and 4.64 with the carbon resonances at 
d
134.5 (C-1) and 105.9 (C-2, C-6) prompted us to identify the aglycone of 
14
as 3,4,5-trimethoxybenzyl alcohol. Finally, the HMBC correlation between the anomeric proton at 
d
4.36 with the carbon resonance at 
d
71.2 (C-7) established compound 
14
as the previously unreported 3,4,5- trimethoxybenzyl alcohol-7- 
O
-(6- 
O
-galloyl)- 
b
-D-glucopyranoside.
</p>
         <p>
Comparison with NMR data reported in literature allowed us to identify the known compounds as gallic acid 4- 
O
- 
b
-D-glucopyranoside (
1
) (

), gallic acid 4- 
O -
b
-D-(6 

0

- 
O
- galloyl)-glucopyranoside (
2
) (

), nikoenoside (
3
) (

), ethyl- 
O -
b
-D-(6 

0

- 
O
-galloyl)-glucopyranoside (
4
) (

), 4-hydroxy-3-methoxyphenol-1- 
O
-(6 

0

- 
O
-galloyl)- 
b
-D-glucopyranoside (
5
) (

), 4-hydroxy-2- methoxyphenol-1- 
O -
b
-D-(6 

0

- 
O
-galloyl) glucopyranoside (
6
) (

), 3,4-di- 
O
-galloyl-quinic acid (
7
) (

), catechin (
9
) (

), 4,9-dihydroxypropiophenone- 9- 
O
- 
b
-D-glucopyranoside (
13
) (

), 4-hydroxy-2- methoxyphenol-1- 
O -
b
-D-glucopyranoside (
15
) (

) and schizandriside (
16
) (

).
</p>
         <p>
Thus, in addition to previously unreported compounds (
8
, 

10 
—
12

, 
14
), also compounds 
2
, 

4 
—
6

possess a 
b
-D-glucopyranosyl- (6- 
O
-galloyl)-moiety. The above cited compounds along with compounds 
1
, 
3
and 
15
, possessing a phenolic ring, and catechin (
9
) and lignan (
16
) justify the high phenolic content and the high antioxidant activity exhibited by the extract of 

<tp:taxon-name>S. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
.

</p>
         <p>
With the aim to investigate if the qualitative profile of the extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
was affected by season changes, the LC-ESIMS 
n
analysis, in negative ionization mode, of the ethanol extract of the stem bark collected in winter has been performed. No changes in the qualitative profile have been observed in the winter extract, evidencing that seasonality is not a factor that influences the occurrence of chemical constituents of the plant (See Supporting Information).
</p>
         <p>
The antioxidant activity of compounds 

1 
—
16

was tested by TEAC assay and expressed as TEAC value, defined as the concentration of Trolox solution with antioxidant capacity equivalent to a 1 mM concentration of the test sample (

) (
Table 3
), and compared to that of quercetin 3- 
O
-glucopyranoside. The results showed that most of isolated compounds (
2
, 

5 
—
7

, 
10
and 
12
) exhibited higher free-radical-scavenging activity than quercetin 3- 
O
-glucopyranoside. Compounds 
8
, 

10 
—
12

and 
14
never reported before exhibited a good free-radical-scavenging activity, in the range of 1.10 
—
1.86 mM.
</p>
         <p>
The ability of several antioxidant plant phenolics to reduce the risk and slow the progression of some cancer diseases by prevention of cell oxidation has been widely reported (

). Thus, the cytotoxic activity of compounds 

1 
—
16

was tested against two cancer cell lines, A549 and Hela, by the MTT assay. None of the tested compounds, in a range of concentrations between 12.5 and 100 
M
M, caused a significant reduction of the cell number (data not shown).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Experimental section
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.1. General instrumentation
</title>
         <p>
IR measurements were obtained on a Bruker IFS-48 spectrometer and UV measurements were recorded on a UV 
—
visible spectrophotometer (Evolution 201, Thermo Fisher Scientific). NMR experiments were performed on a Bruker DRX-600 spectrometer (Bruker BioSpin GmBH, Rheinstetten, 
Germany
) equipped with a Bruker 
5 mm
TCI
CryoProbe at 300 K. All 2D-NMR spectra were acquired in methanol- 

d 
4

(99.95%, Sigma-Aldrich) and standard pulse sequences and phase cycling were used for DQF-COSY, HSQC, and HMBC spectra. The NMR data were processed using TOPSPIN 3.2 software. HPLC separations were carried out on a Waters 590 system equipped with a Waters R401 refractive index detector, a Waters XTerra Prep MSC18 column (300 
×
7.8 mm
i.d.), and a Rheodyne injector. HRESIMS spectra were carried out by an LTQ Orbitrap XL mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, San Jose, CA, 
USA
) operating in negative ion mode. The Orbitrap mass analyzer was calibrated according to the manufacturer's directions using a mixture of caffeine, methionine-arginine-phenylalaninealanine-acetate (MRFA), sodium dodecyl sulfate, sodium taurocholate and Ultramark 1621. Data were collected and analyzed using the software provided by the manufacturer.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>

The stem bark of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Schinopsis brasiliensis
Engl.
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) was collected between 


February and August 
2014

in summer and winter period, respectively in the city of 
Piranhas
in 
Alagoas
, 
Brazil

, 

whose geographical coordinates were identified by a Garmin Forerunner GPS function (9 

ǫ

35 

0

54.37

00

S and 37 

ǫ

46 

0

08.31

00

W). 
The
species was identified by the biologist 
Marta Maria
<tp:taxon-name>Cristina Farias</tp:taxon-name>
and a voucher specimen (24442 ASE) was deposited at the herbarium of the 
Department of Biology
of the 
Federal University
of 
Sergipe

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.3. Extraction procedure
</title>
         <p>
The stem bark of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(4 Kg) was dried at room temperature, reduced to powder and extracted at room temperature using ethanol-water (9:1) for five days. After filtration and evaporation of the solvent to dryness in vacuo, 
420 g
of hydralcoholic extract were obtained.
</p>
         <p>

3.4. Determination of total phenol content (Folin 
‒
Ciocalteu

</p>
         <p>
method)
</p>
         <p>
The ethanol extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
stem bark, collected in summer, was analyzed according to the Folin-Ciocalteu (FC) colorimetric method (

). The ethanol extract was dissolved in MeOH to obtain a concentration of 
0.5 mg
/mL. Folin-Ciocalteu phenol reagent (0.5 mL) was added to centrifuge tubes containing 0.5 mL of the extracts. The contents were mixed, and 1 mL of a saturated sodium carbonate solution was added to each tube, to arrive to the volume of 10 mL with distilled water. The contents in the tubes were mixed by vortex, kept at room temperature for 45 min (until the characteristic blue color developed) and then centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 5 min. Absorbance of the clear supernatant was measured at 
517 nm
on a UV 
—
visible spectrophotometer (Evolution 201, Thermo Fisher Scientific). A control without FC reagent and a blank with methanol instead of sample were included in the assay. The total polyphenol content was expressed as gallic acid equivalents (mg GAE/g extract, means ± SD of three determinations) calculated by calibration curves (y 
¼
0.0027x 
þ
0.0982 R 
2
¼
0.9929).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.5. Antioxidant activity (TEAC assay)
</title>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
The antioxidant activity of the ethanol extract of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
stem bark, collected in summer, was determined by the Trolox Equivalent Antioxidant Capacity (TEAC) assay as previously reported (

). The TEAC value is based on the ability of the antioxidant to scavenge the radical cation 2,2 

0

-azinobis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonate) ABTS 

•þ

by spectrophotometric analysis. The ABTS 

•þ

cation radical was produced by the reaction between 7 mM ABTS in H 
2
O and 2.45 mM potassium persulfate, stored in the dark at room temperature for 12 h. ABTS is a blue-green chromogen with a characteristic absorption at 
734 nm
. The ABTS 

•þ

solution was then diluted with PBS (phosphate saline buffer, pH 
¼
7.4) to obtain an absorbance of 0.70 at 
734 nm
and equilibrated at 30 

ǫ

C.
</p>
         <p>
•þ
</p>
         <p>
The extract was diluted with methanol to produce solutions of 250, 500, 750, 1000 
M
g/mL. Samples 

1 
—
16

were diluted with methanol to produce solutions of 0.3, 0.5, 1 and 1.5 mM. The reaction was initiated by the addition of 1.5 mL of diluted ABTS to 15 
M
L of each sample solution. Determinations were repeated three times for each sample solution. The inhibition percentage of absorbance at 
734 nm
was calculated for each concentration relative to a blank absorbance (methanol) and was plotted as a function of concentration of compound or standard, 6-hydroxy-2,5,7,8- tetramethylchroman-2-carboxylic acid (Trolox, Aldrich Chemical Co., Gillingham, 
Dorset
, 
UK
). The antioxidant activities are expressed as TEAC values in comparison with TEAC activity of quercetin 3- 
O
-glucopyranoside, used as reference compound. The TEAC value is defined as the concentration of a standard Trolox solution with the same antioxidant capacity as a 
1 mg
/mL of the tested extract.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
The TEAC value is the concentration of a standard Trolox solution with the same antioxidant capacity as a 1 mg/mL of the tested sample.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.6. LC-ESI(Orbitrap)MS analysis
</title>
         <p>
Qualitative LC-MS was performed using a Thermo Scientific Accela HPLC system (Thermo Scientific, 
Germany
) equipped with a C 
18
reversed-phase (RP) column (2.1 
×
250 mm
; X-Terra MS C18 5 lm; Waters, Milford, MA) at a flow rate of 0.2 
M
l/min and coupled to a LTQ-Orbitrap XL mass spectrometer. The gradient elution was carried out by using 0.1% formic acid as eluent A and acetonitrile as B. The HPLC gradient started at 5% (B) hold for 5 min and after 50 min, %B was at 100% holding it for 5 min before returning back to the starting percentage. The instrument was calibrated using the manufacturer's calibration standards. The scan was collected in the Orbitrap at a resolution of 30 000 in a 
m/z
range of 230 
—
1500 amu. The 
m/z
of each identified compound was calculated to 4 decimal places and measured with a mass accuracy &lt;3.5 ppm. The source voltage was 4.0 kV and capillary voltage 
‒
35 kV, the tube lens offset 
‒
126 V and the capillary temperature was set at 280 

ǫ

C, the auxiliary gas was set at 10 (arbitrary units) and the sheath gas at 20 (arbitrary units). In full LC-ESIMS experiments Total Ion Current (TIC) profile was produced by monitoring the intensity of all the ions produced and acquired in every scan during the chromatographic run. In order to get structural information, Data Dependent experiments were performed by acquiring MS 
2
spectra of the most intense ions produced during the acquisition.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3.7. Isolation procedure
</title>
         <p>
The hydroalcoholic extract was dried under vacuum and 
3 g
were fractionated on a Sephadex LH-20 (Pharmacia) column (100 
×
5 cm
), using MeOH as mobile phase, affording 91 fractions (8 mL), monitored by TLC.
</p>
         <p>
Fraction 14 
—
18 (111.0 mg) were chromatographed by semipreparative HPLC using MeOH-H 
2
O (3:7) as mobile phase (flow rate 2.5 mL/min) to yield compounds 
3
(
6.3 mg
, 
tR
¼
4.8 min), 
11
(
5.8 mg
, 
tR
¼
10.0 min) and 
16
(
8.2 mg
, 
tR
¼
48.0 min). Fractions 19 
—
25 (
134.3 mg
) were chromatographed by semipreparative HPLC using MeOH-H 
2
O (3:7) as mobile phase (flow rate 2.5 mL/min) to yield compounds 
8
(
8.6 mg
, 
tR
¼
10.5 min) and 
14
(
10.2 mg
, 
tR
¼
46.0 min). Fractions 26 
—
31 (
130.9 mg
) were chromatographed by semipreparative HPLC using MeOH-H 
2
O (1:3) as mobile phase (flow rate 2.5 mL/min) to yield compounds 
4
(
6.6 mg
, 
tR
¼
10.0 min), 
5
(
5.1 mg
, 
tR
¼
16.2 min) and 
6
(
5.7 mg
, 
tR
¼
15.8 min). Fractions 31 
—
32 (
103.5 mg
) were chromatographed by semipreparative HPLC using MeOH-H 
2
O (3:7) as mobile phase (flow rate 2.5 mL/min) to yield compound 
10
(
4.8 mg
, 
tR
¼
11.5 min). Fractions 37 
—
39 (
31.8 mg
) were chromatographed by semipreparative HPLC using MeOH-H 
2
O (3:7) as mobile phase (flow rate 2.5 mL/min) to yield compound 
9
(5.0 mg, 
tR
¼
10.4 min). Fraction 48 (
32.4 mg
) were chromatographed by semipreparative HPLC using MeOH-H 
2
O (3:7) as mobile phase (flow rate 2.5 mL/ min) to yield compounds 
2
(
5.5 mg
, 
tR
¼
9.0 min) and 
7
(
9.4 mg
, 
tR
¼
43.0 min).
</p>
         <p>
Fractions 64 
—
74 (
105.9 mg
) were chromatographed by semipreparative HPLC using MeOH-H 
2
O (3:7) as mobile phase (flow rate 2.5 mL/min) to yield compounds 
12
(
5.2 mg
, 
tR
¼
26.0 min) 
13
(
5.9 mg
, 
tR
¼
30.0 min) and 
15
(
5.7 mg
, 
tR
¼
36.2 min), Fractions 90 
—
91 (
65.9 mg
) were chromatographed by semipreparative HPLC using MeOH-H 
2
O (3:7) as mobile phase (flow rate 2.5 mL/min) to yield compound 
1
(
10.1 mg
, 
tR
¼
10.0 min).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

3.8. Vanillyl alcohol 4-O- 
b
-D-(6

0

-O-galloyl) glucopyranoside (
8
)

</title>
         <p>
Amorphous white solid; C 
21
H 
24
O 
12
; IR 
n
KBr
max
cm 

‒
1

: 3450, 2930, 1785, 1660; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (methanol- 

d 
4

, 600 MHz) data, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
467.1190 [M-H] 
-
(calcd for C 
21
H 
23
O 
12
, 467.1173).
</p>
         <p>

3.9. 2-Hydroxy-4-methoxyphenol 1-O- 
b
-D-(6

0

-O-galloyl) glucopyranoside (
10
)

</p>
         <p>
Amorphous white solid; C 
20
H 
22
O 
12
; IR 
n
KBr
max
cm 

‒
1

: 3430, 2945, 1765, 1675; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (methanol- 

d 
4

, 600 MHz) data, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
453.1033 [M-H] 
-
(calcd for C 
20
H 
21
O 
12
, 453.2500).
</p>
         <p>
3.10. Dihydrosinapyl alcohol 4-O-(6
0

-O-galloyl)- 
b
-Dglucopyranoside (
11
)

</p>
         <p>
Amorphous white solid; C 
24
H 
30
O 
13
; IR 
n
KBr
max
cm 

‒
1

: 3420, 2950, 1750,1685, 1130; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (methanol- 

d 
4

, 600 MHz) data, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
525.1608 [M-H] 
-
(calcd for C 
24
H 
29
O 
13
, 525.1587).
</p>
         <p>
3.11. 4,9-Dihydroxypropiophenone-9-O-(6
0

-O-galloyl)- 
b
-Dglucopyranoside (
12
)

</p>
         <p>
Amorphous white solid; C 
22
H 
24
O 
12
; IR 
n
KBr
max
cm 

‒
1

: 3410, 2930, 1770, 1715, 1680, 1200; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (methanol- 

d 
4

, 600 MHz) data, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
479.1190 [M-H] 
-
(calcd for C 
22
H 
23
O 
12
, 479.1173).
</p>
         <p>
3.12. 3,4,5- trimethoxybenzyl alcohol 7-O-(6
0

-O-galloyl)- 
b
-Dglucopyranoside (
14
)

</p>
         <p>
Amorphous white solid; C 
23
H 
28
O 
13
; IR 
n
KBr
max
cm 

‒
1

: 3400, 2925, 1775, 1720, 1685, 1135; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (methanol- 

d 
4

, 600 MHz) data, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
511.1452 [M-H] 
-
(calcd for C 
23
H 
27
O 
13
, 511.1434).
</p>
         <p>
3.13. Acid hydrolysis
</p>
         <p>
A mixture of compounds 
8
(
5 mg
), 
10
(
3 mg
), 
11
(
3 mg
), 
12
(
3 mg
) and 
14
(
5 mg
) was heated at 60 

ǫ

C with 1:1 0.5 N HCl-dioxane (3 mL) for 2 h, and then evaporated in vacuo. The solution was partitioned with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
-H 
2
O, and the H 
2
O layer was neutralized with Amberlite MB-3. The H 
2
O layer was then concentrated and passed through a silica gel column, using CHCl 
3
-MeOH-H 
2
O (7:1:1.2, lower layer) as eluting solvent to afford glucose. The D configuration of glucose was established by comparison of its optical rotation value with those reported in the literature (

). The optical rotation was determined after dissolving the sugars in H 
2
O and allowing them to stand for 24 h; D-glucose [
a
] 
22
D
þ
47.9 (
c
0.1).
</p>
         <p>
3.14. Cancer cell lines
</p>
         <p>Human alveolar basal carcinoma (A549), obtained from the</p>
         <p>
European Collection of Cell Cultures (ECACC), and HeLa cells (human epitheloid cervix carcinoma), obtained from Cell Bank in GMP-IST (Genova, 
Italy
) were cultured in DMEM medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Invitrogen), 1% penicillin/ streptomycin and 2 mM L-glutamine (37 

ǫ

C, 5% CO 
2
).
</p>
         <p>
3.15. Analysis of cell viability
</p>
         <p>
A549 (5 
×
10 
3
), and Hela (5 
×
10 
3
) were plated in 96-well microtiter plates and incubated for 48 h in the absence and in the presence of compounds 

1 
—
16

(at concentrations of 12.5, 25, 50, 100 
M
M). The viability of cells was determined by MTT assay to detect functional mitochondria in living cells (

), as previously reported (

). 25 
M
l of MTT (
5 mg
/ mL) were added to each well and the cells were incubated for an additional 3 h. Thereafter, cells were lysed with 100 
M
l of a solution containing 50% (v/v) N,N-dimethylformamide and 20% (w/v) SDS (pH 4.5) to allow solubilization of dark blue crystals. The optical density (OD) of each well was measured with a microplate spectrophotometer (Mutiscan Go, Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc. Waltham, MA, 
USA
) equipped with a 
620 nm
filter. IC 
50
values were calculated from cell viability dose-response curves and defined as the concentration resulting in 50% inhibition of cell survival at 48 h, compared to untreated cells.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
Authors thank the Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnoĺogico (CNPq/ 
Brazil
) for fellowship to Clisiane C. S. Santos.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at http:// dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2017.04.008.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
References
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Altunkeyik, H.
, 
Gulcemal, D.
, 
Masullo, M.
, 
Alankus-Caliskan, O.
, 
Piacente, S.
, 
Karayildirim, T.
, 
2012
. 

Triterpene saponins from 
Cyclamen hederifolium

. 
Phytochemistry
73
, 

127 
—
133

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Benavides, A.
, 
Montoro, P.
, 
Bassarello, C.
, 
Piacente, S.
, 
Pizza, C.
, 
2006
. 

Catechin derivatives in 
Jatropha macrantha
stems: characterisation and LC/ESI/MS/MS quali-quantitative analysis

. 
J. Pharm. Biomed. Anal.
40
, 

639 
—
647

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cardoso, M.P.
, 
David, J.M.
, 
David, J.P.
, 
2005
. 

A new alkyl phenol from 
Schinopsis brasiliensis

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
19
, 

431 
—
433

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cardoso, M.P.
, 
Lima, L.S.
, 
David, J.P.
, 
Moreira, B.O.
, 
Santos, E.O.
, 
David, J.M.
, 
Alves, C.Q.
, 
2015
. 

A new biflavonoid from 
Schinopsis brasiliensis
(Anacardiaceae)

. 
J. Braz. Chem. Soc.
26
, 

1527 
—
1531

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
de Albuquerque, U.P.
, Muniz, d.M.P., de, A.A.L.S., 
Monteiro, J.M.
, Machado, d.F.L.N. E., Gomes, d.M.J., dos, S.J.P., 
2007
. 
Medicinal plants of the caatinga (semi-arid) vegetation of NE Brazil: a quantitative approach. J
. 
Ethnopharmacol.
114
, 

325 
—
354

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fernandes, F.H.A.
, 
Batista, R. S.
d. A., 
de Medeiros, F.D.
, 
Santos, F.S.
, 
Medeiros, A.C.D.
, 
2015
. 

Development of a rapid and simple HPLC-UV method for determination of gallic acid in 
Schinopsis brasiliensis

. 
Rev. Bras. Farmacogn.
25
, 

208 
—
211

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fotiric Aksic, M.M.
, 
Dabic, D.C.
, 
Gasic, U.M.
, 
Zec, G.N.
, 
Vulic, T.B.
, 
Tesic, Z.L.
, 
Natic, M.M.
, 
2015
. 
Polyphenolic profile of pear leaves with different resistance to pear psylla (cacopsylla pyri)
. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
63
, 

7476 
—
7486

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Horo, I.
, 
Masullo, M.
, 
Falco, A.
, 
Senol, S.G.
, 
Piacente, S.
, 
Alankus-Caliskan, O.
, 
2015
. 

New triterpene saponins from 
Phryna ortegioides

. 
Phytochem. Lett.
14
, 

39 
—
44

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Junior, W.S.F.
, 
Ladio, A.H.
, 
Albuquerque, U. P.
d., 
2011
. 
Resilience and adaptation in the use of medicinal plants with suspected anti-inflammatory activity in the Brazilian Northeast. J
. 
Ethnopharmacol.
138
, 

238 
—
252

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Kang, Q.
-j., 
Yang, X.
-w., 
Wu, S.
-h., 
Ma, Y.
-l., 
Li, L.
, 
Shen, Y.
-m., 
2008
. 

Chemical constituents from the stem bark of 

Trewia nudi 
fl
ora

L. and their antioxidant activities

. 
Planta Med.
74
, 

445 
—
448

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Kim, K.H.
, 
Moon, E.
, 
Kim, S.Y.
, 
Choi, S.U.
, 
Lee, K.R.
, 
2012
. 

Lignan constituents of 
Tilia amurensis
and their biological evaluation on antitumor and anti-inflammatory activities

. 
Food Chem. Toxicol.
50
, 

3680 
—
3686

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Kirmizibekmez, H.
, 
Ariburnu, E.
, 
Masullo, M.
, 
Festa, M.
, 
Capasso, A.
, 
Yesilada, E.
, 
Piacente, S.
, 
2012
. 

Iridoid, phenylethanoid and flavonoid glycosides from 
Sideritis trojana

. 
Fitoterapia
83
, 

130 
—
136

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Lee, J.
, 
Jang, D.S.
, 
Kim, N.H.
, 
Lee, Y.M.
, 
Kim, J.
, 
Kim, J.S.
, 
2011
. 

Galloyl glucoses from the seeds of 

Cornus of 
fi
cinalis

with inhibitory activity against protein glycation, aldose reductase, and cataractogenesis ex vivo

. 
Biol. Pharm. Bull.
34
, 

443 
—
446

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Machida, K.
, 
Yogiashi, Y.
, 
Matsuda, S.
, 
Suzuki, A.
, 
Kikuchi, M.
, 
2009
. 

A new phenolic glycoside syringate from the bark of 
Juglans mandshurica
MAXIM. var. 
sieboldiana
MAKINO

. 
J. Nat. Med.
63
, 

220 
—
222

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Meng, D.
, 
Wu, J.
, 
Zhao, W.
, 
2010
. 

Glycosides from 
Breynia fruticosa
and 
Breynia rostrata

. 
Phytochemistry
71
, 

325 
—
331

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Mosmann, T.
, 
1983
. 
Rapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: application to proliferation and cytotoxicity assays
. 
J. Immunol. Methods
65
, 

55 
—
63

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Pereira do Amaral, F.
, 
Napolitano, A.
, 
Masullo, M.
, 
Campaner dos Santos, L.
, 
Festa, M.
, 
Vilegas, W.
, 
Pizza, C.
, 
Piacente, S.
, 
2012
. 

HPLC-ESIMSn profiling, isolation, structural elucidation, and evaluation of the antioxidant potential of phenolics from 
Paepalanthus geniculatus

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
75
, 

547 
—
556

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Saijo, R.
, 
Nonaka, G.
, 
Nishioka, I.
, 
1989
. 

Tannins and related compounds. Part 82. Phenol glucoside gallates from 
Mallotus japonicus

. 
Phytochemistry
28
, 

2443 
—
2446

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Santos, C.C.S.
, 
Araujo, S.S.
, 
Santos, A.L.L.M.
, 
Almeida, E.C.V.
, 
Dias, A.S.
, 
Damascena, N.P.
, 
Santos, D.M.
, 
Santos, M.I.S.
, 
Junior, K.A.L.R.
, 
Pereira, C.K.B.
, 
Lima, A.C.B.
, 
Shan, A.Y.K.V.
, 
Sant'ana, A.E.G.
, 
Estevam, C.S.
, 
Araujo, B.S.
, 
2014
. 

Evaluation of the toxicity and molluscicidal and larvicidal activities of 
Schinopsis brasiliensis
stem bark extract and its fractions

. 
Rev. Bras. Farmacogn.
24
, 

298 
—
303

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Saraiva, A.M.
, 
Castro, R.H.A.
, 
Cordeiro, R.P.
, 
Peixoto Sobrinho, T.J.S.
, 
Castro, V.T.N.A.
, 
Amorim, E.L.C.
, 
Xavier, H.S.
, 
Pisciottano, M.N.C.
, 
2011
. In 
vitro evaluation of antioxidant
, 

antimicrobial and toxicity properties of extracts of 
Schinopsis brasiliensis
Engl. (Anacardiaceae). Afr. J. Pharm. Pharmacol.

5
, 

1724 
—
1731

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Shahidi, F.
, 
Alasalvar, C.
, 
Liyana-Pathirana, C.M.
, 
2007
. 

Antioxidant phytochemicals in hazelnut kernel (
Corylus avellana
L.) and hazelnut byproducts

. 
J. Agr. Food Chem.
55
, 

1212 
—
1220

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Shi, C.
, 
Xu, M.-J.
, 
Bayer, M.
, 
Deng, Z.-W.
, 
Kubbutat, M.H.G.
, 
Waejen, W.
, 
Proksch, P.
, 
Lin, W.-H.
, 
2010
. 

Phenolic compounds and their anti-oxidative properties and protein kinase inhibition from the Chinese mangrove plant 
Laguncularia racemosa

. 
Phytochem. (Elsevier)
71
, 

435 
—
442

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Zhu, L.-F.
, 
Xu, M.
, 
Zhu, H.-T.
, 
Wang, D.
, 
Yang, S.-X.
, 
Yang, C.-R.
, 
Zhang, Y.-J.
, 
2012
. 

New flavan-3-ol dimer from green tea produced from 
Camellia taliensis
in the Ai-Lao mountains of Southwest China

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
60
, 

12170 
—
12176

.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
