<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112842</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Unusual matrine-adenine hybrids isolated from Sophora davidii and their inhibitory effects on human cytomegalovirus</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
(Franch.) 
Pavol.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sophora viciifolia
Hance
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form intermediates</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
(Franch.) Pavol. (Fabaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Unusual matrine–adenine hybrids isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
and their inhibitory effects on human cytomegalovirus

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Zhi-Jun Zhang
1
, Shu-Wei Dong
1
, Dan-Dan Gao, Xin-Ye Du, Yan-Qing Xie, Xue-Shan Xia,

Rong-Tao Li 
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Faculty of Life Science and Technology, Kunming University of Science and Technology, Kunming, 650500, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Edible flowers</p>
         <p>Alkaloids</p>
         <p>Matrine–adenine hybrids</p>
         <p>Anti- human cytomegalovirus</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
A phytochemical investigation on the flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
resulted in the isolation of three unusual matrine–adenine hybrids, sophovicines A–C, together with biogenetically related analogue sophocarpine. Their structures and absolute configurations were determined by NMR analysis, single-crystal X-ray diffraction, and electronic circular dichroism (ECD) data. Since sophovicines represent the first example of matrine-adenine hybrids, a putative biosynthetic pathway toward sophovicines A–C was proposed. In addition, computational molecular modeling suggested that compounds sophovicines B and C may have potent activities against human cytomegalovirus (HCMV). So, the inhibit effects of isolates on HCMV were evaluated. The results show that sophovicines B and C can inhibit HCMV replication effectively with IC 
50
values of 7.12 and 7.32 
μ
M, respectively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
(Franch.) 
Pavol.
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name>
; synonym 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sophora viciifolia
Hance
</tp:taxon-name>
) is a deciduous shrub, growing on hillside, wayside and sandy places in valleys in the 
Yunnan
, 
Sichuan
, 
Ningxia
, and 
Guizhou
provinces (

; 

). The roots, leaves, flowers, and fruits of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
have been used by local people as folk medicines. The roots have been used to treat cough, sore throat, dysentery, and hematochezia, etc (

). Many minorities in the 
Yunnan province
of 
China
, such as Yi, Bai, Miao, etc., have the tradition of using flowers as food. Conventionally, after being quickly dipped in boil water, then cleaned and soaked in water for 1–2 days, the flower of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
is cooked with egg, chicken, or meat for the remedy of heat stroke, night sweat, oedema, etc (

).
</p>
         <p>
As reported previously, the phytochemical research of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
have focused on the seeds and branches, and some flavonoids, alkaloids, and stilbene oligomers showed diversified bioactivities, including antiinflammatory, antitumor, and antiallergic activities (

; 

; 

). However, few studies on the chemical constituents of its flowers have been reported. We previously reported four new quinolizidine alkaloids from its flowers collected from Urumqi, 
Xinjiang Province
, 
China
(

). Since different ecological environments of plants may lead to the difference of specialised metabolites (

). We continued to explore structurally novel quinolizidine alkaloids of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
collected from Honghe county, 
Yunnan Province
, 
China
. As a result, three unusual matrine–adenine hybrids, named sophovicines A–C (1–3), as well as biogenetically related compound sophocarpine (4), were isolated and identified (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) is an opportunistic pathogen leading to life-threatening disease in immune-compromised patients and to significant congenital disease following primary infection of pregnant women (

). Currently, three licensed antiviral drugs are used for the prevention and/or treatment of HCMV infection: ganciclovir (VAL) (

), foscavir (FOS) (

), and cidofovir (CDV) (

). However, the prevalence of drug-resistant and cross-resistant strains of HCMV has severely reduced the effectiveness of these drugs (

; Lurain and Chou 2015; 

). Moreover, these drugs also effectuate obvious adverse reactions, such as bone marrow suppression, nephrotoxicity, neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, and electrolyte disturbance (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Nucleoside and nucleotide analogs are the focus of current interest as antiviral and antitumor agents. A great number of HCMV inhibitors are concentrated in this group of compounds (
Fig. 2
). The HCMV protease is essential for proper assembly of viral capsids and replication (

). So, a great deal of attention is being paid to it as therapeutic targets for the development of anti-HCMV drugs (

; 

). Based on the existence of adenine group in compounds 1–3, we speculate that 1–3 may have anti-HCMV activity. So, molecular docking studies were carried out between compounds 1–4 with HCMV protease. The results revealed that compounds 2 and 3 could be buried into the hydrophobic pocket of HCMV protease. Therefore, the inhibit effects of compounds 1–4 on HCMV were evaluated. The results show that compounds 2 and 3 can inhibit HCMV replication effectively with IC 
50
values of 7.12 and 7.32 
μ
M, respectively. Herein, the isolation, structural elucidation and biological evaluation of the isolated alkaloids are discussed.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
E-mail address:
rongtaolikm@163.com (R.-T. Li).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
1
These authors contributed equally to this work.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Recorded in CD OD.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
3
b
Recorded in CDCl.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
3
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Isolation and structure elucidation
</title>
         <p>
The dried flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
were extracted with EtOH/H 
2
O (95:5) at room temperature three times. The extract was partitioned between 1.0‰ HCl/H 
2
O and EtOAc. Then, the water-soluble materials were adjusted to pH 10 with saturated Na 
2
CO 
3
aq, were extracted with CHCl 
3
to obtained crude alkaloid. Fractionation and purification of the crude alkaloid by column chromatography (CC) over MCI, silica gel, reversedphase silica gel, and Sephadex LH-20 afforded three unusual matrine-–adenine hybrids, named sophovicines A–C (1–3), as well as biogenetically related compound sophocarpine (4) (

).
</p>
         <p>
Sophovicine A (1), obtained as colorless needles crystals (toluene–methanol, 9:1). The molecular formula of 1 was determined to be C 
20
H 
27
N 
7
O with eleven degrees of unsaturation based on the HRESIMS data at 
m/z
404.2168 [M+ Na] 
+
(calcd for 404.2169). IR absorptions implied the presence of lactam carbonyl group (
1641 cm
1
). The 
1
H NMR spectrum (
Table 1
) exhibited signals of two olefinic protons (
δ
H
8.06 and 8.11) and four deshielded aliphatic proton signals (
δ
H
5.17, 4.15, 4.11, and 3.22). The 
13
C NMR (
Table 1
) and the HSQC spectra revealed the existence of 20 carbons due to one lactam carbonyl group (
δ
C
167.0), two sp 
2
methines (
δ
C
142.8 and 153.5), three sp 
2
quaternary carbons (
δ
C
120.1, 150.9, and 157.1), and 14 sp 
3
carbons including nine methylenes and five methines (
δ
C
37.6, 40.9, 55.3, 56.9, and 65.8).
</p>
         <p>
Detailed analyses of the NMR data and molecular formula implied that 1 may be a dimer composing of matrine (1a) (

), and adenine (1 b) (

) moieties. The most remarkable difference was the methylene (
δ
C
33.0) at C- 
14 in
matrine was replaced by a methine (
δ
C
56.9) in 1, suggesting the matrine and adenine units may be connected by the bond between C-14 and N-9’. The C-14 (
δ
C
56.9), C-4’ (
δ
C
150.9), and C-8’ (
δ
C
142.8) were connected by a nitrogen atom, which was demonstrated by the HMBC (
Fig. 3
) correlations between H-14 and C-4 
′
and C-8 
′
, and between H-8 
′
and C-14. The matrine unit was further confirmed by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlation peaks of H 
2
-2/H 
2
-3/H 
2
-4/H-5/H-6/H-7/H 
2
-8/H 
2
-9/H 
2
-10, H-5/H 
2
-17, and H-7/H-11/H 
2
-12/H 
2
-13/H-14, together with HMBC correlations between H-2 and C-6 and C-10, H 
2
-10 and C-6, H-11, and C-15, H-14 and C-15, and H 
2
-17 and C-11 and C-15 (
Fig. 3
). Apart from 1a structure, the remaining five carbon signals (
δ
C
120.1, 142.8, 150.9, 153.5, and 157.1) assigned to 1 b (

). With these data, finally, the planar structure of 1 was determined.
</p>
         <p>
The relative configuration of 1 was assigned by a ROESY spectrum, in which the correlations H-5/H-12 b, H-6/H-12 b, H-7/H-12 b, H-8a/H-17 b, H-17 b/H-11, and H-11/H-14 suggested that H-5, H-6, and H-7 (
Fig. 3
) were in the same orientations, whereas H-11 and H-14 were on the same face. The absolute configuration of 1 was confirmed by the single X-ray diffraction experiment. Qualified crystals of 1 were acquired by recrystallization in toluene/methanol (9:1), which obtained a successful performance of X-ray crystallography by using graphitemono-chromated Cu K 
α
radiation (
λ
= 1.54178 A). It not only exhibited the unique structure of matrine–adenine hybrids in 1 as revealed by spectroscopic data analysis, but also determined its absolute configurations of C-5, C-6, C-7, C-11, and C-14 as (5 
S
, 6 
S
, 7 
R
, 11 
R
, 14 
R
) (
Fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
Sophovicine B (2), obtained as white amorphous powder, exhibited an [M+ Na] 
+
ion peak at 
m/z
404.2168 in
its positive HRESIMS, which was consistent with the molecular formula C 
20
H 
27
N 
7
O with 11 degrees of unsaturation. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectroscopic data of 2 (
Table 1
) together with the HSQC spectrum revealed the presence of 20 carbon signals. Comparison of 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data of 2 with those of 1 revealed that the structure of 2 was similar to that of 1. The main difference between them was reflected in the chemical shifts of C-11 (
δ
C
55.3 (d) in 1; 50.4 (d) in 2), C-12 (
δ
C
22.5 (t) in 1; 30.6 (t) in 2), C-13 (
δ
C
27.6 (t) in 1; 47.0 (d) in 2), and C-14 (
δ
C
56.9 (d) in 1; 37.3 (t) in 2). These differences suggested that the matrine and adenine units were connected by the bond between C-13 and N-9’. This hypothesis was further supported by the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlation peaks of H 
2
-12/H-13/ H 
2
-14 and HMBC correlations between H-13 and C-11, C-12, C-14, C-4 
′
, and C-8’. By comparing the 
1
H NMR spectral data and ROESY correlations, the relative configuration of matrine unit of 2 was similar as 1, this means H-5, H-6, H-7 were 
α
-oriented and H-11 was 
β
-oriented. The H-13 was 
β
-oriented, which was determined by ROESY correlation of H-11/H-13.
</p>
         <p>
The absolute configuration of compound 2 was confirmed by comparison of calculated and experimental ECD spectra (
Fig. 5
). The experimental spectrum of 2 exhibited positive Cotton effect (CE) at 
215 nm
, and negative CE at 
260 nm
, which agreed with the calculated spectrum of the (5 
S
, 6 
S
, 7 
R
, 11 
R
, 13 
R
) enantiomer. Therefore, the structure of 2 was final elucidated, and named as sophovicine B.
</p>
         <p>
Sophovicine C (3), obtained as white amorphous powder. The molecular formula of C 
20
H 
27
N 
7
O 
2
as determined by the HRESIMS (
m/z
396.2156 [M-H] 
-
, calcd for C 
20
H 
26
N 
7
O 

2
m

/z 396.2153), 16 mass units higher than that of 2. The UV and IR spectra of 3 revealed characteristic absorptions similar to those of 2. Interpretation of the 2D NMR data of 3 demonstrated that it was the 
N
-1 oxide of 2, which was confirmed by the characteristic downfield NMR shifts of C-3 (
δ
C
69.8), C-6 (
δ
C
67.9), and C-10 (
δ
C
69.6). In addition, the experimental ECD spectrum of 3 showed the same CE as 2, manifesting that the absolute configuration of 3 was identical to that of 2.
</p>
         <p>
2.2. Proposed biosynthesis pathways
</p>
         <p>
Based on the co-isolated major alkaloid sophocarpine (4) from the same plant material. At first, we thought that the isolated compounds 2 and 3 with 
β
-substituted adenine may be derived from 4 and adenine through a Michael addition. Unfortunately, none of the desired compound was detected albeit some efforts using basic or acidic conditions had been made. Given compound 1 had an 
α
-substituted adenine, another hypothetical biogenetic pathway of 1–3 involved epoxidation of 4 was proposed as shown in 
Fig. 6
. Namely, starting from the epoxide intermediate i, the 13,14-epoxy ring was subsequently opened by adenine through path a and b to 
<tp:taxon-name>form intermediates</tp:taxon-name>
ii and iii, respectively. Then, intermediates ii and iii could be further reduced to give 1 and 2, respectively. Certainly, compound 2 was further oxidation to yield 3.
</p>
         <p>
2.3. Molecular docking investigation
</p>
         <p>
Considering three new compounds contain adenine units, molecular docking studies between all isolates with HCMV protease (PDB: 2WPO) were carried out (

; 

). As illustrated in 
Fig. 7
, both compounds 2 and 3 could bind to the active pocket with stretched poses. In detail, 2 and 3 share a very similar binding mode, besides strong hydrogen bond (HB) interactions (2.46 and 2.10 Å) with the same residue GLY164 were detected in both modes, weak HB interaction with CYS161 (3.58 Å) and strong HB interaction with SER135 (2.09 Å) were found in 2 and 3, respectively (
Fig. 6B and C
). In addition, π- cation and π- π interactions between the adenine moieties of 2 and 3 with HIS63 were observed; meanwhile, one more π- cation interaction with ARG165 was formed in binding mode of 2. Whereas, less interactions were found in binding modes of compounds 1 and 4 (
Fig. 6A and D
) suggesting that 2 and 3 may be active in inhibition of HCMV and more potent than compounds 1 and 4.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.4. Inhibitory effects on HCMV
</title>
         <p>
Based on the results of molecular docking, compounds 1–4 were evaluated for their inhibition on HCMV, and ganciclovir was used as positive control (IC 
50
= 5.28 
μ
M). Among them, compounds 2 and 3 can inhibit HCMV replication effectively with IC 
50
values of 7.12 and 7.32 
μ
M, respectively (
Table 2
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.5. SAR analysis
</title>
         <p>
On the basis of the structural features of the isolates and their anti-HCMV activity, brief structure-activity relationships were analyzed. According to biological results, matrine–adenine hybrids between C-13 and N-9’ (2 and 3) are active. But matrine–adenine hybrids between C-14 and N-9’ (1) or matrine-type alkaloid (4) are inactive. In addition, no obvious differences will be caused by whether the 
N
-1 atom of matrine unit is oxidized or not.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Ganciclovir was used as positive control.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
IC: 50% inhibitory concentration. (Mean ± SD of 3 tests).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
50
c
TC: 50% toxic concentration. (Mean ± SD of 3 tests).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
50
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
In summary, three matrine–adenine hybrids, named sophovicines A–C (1–3), together with biogenetically related compound sophocarpine (4), were isolated from the flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
. The structures and absolute configurations of new compounds were elucidated by extensive spectroscopic techniques, X-ray diffraction analysis, along with the experimental and calculated electronic circular dichroism (ECD). Since new compounds represent the first example of matrine-adenine hybrids, a possible biosynthetic pathway for 1–3 was proposed. In addition, all the isolates were evaluated for their inhibition on HCMV. Among them, compounds 2 and 3 can inhibit HCMV replication effectively with IC 
50
values of 7.12 and 7.32 
μ
M, respectively. Moreover, brief structure-activity relationships were analyzed. This discovery not only extends the chemical diversity of natural alkaloids, but also could be extremely meaningful to the discovery of new anti-HCMV drugs. Meanwhile, these novel structures might give some insight into new leading heterocyclic compounds for the development of related drugs, while further investigations such as synthetic effort and in-depth biological testing are really needed.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
UV, Shimadzu UV-2401 A spectrophotometer; Optical rotations, Jasco DIP-370 digital polarimeter; IR, Tenor 27 spectrophotometer; 1D and 2D-NMR, Bruker AVANCE III-600 spectrometer; HRESIMS, Agilent 6530Q of spectrometer; medium-pressure liquid chromatography (MPLC), Büchi Labortechnik AG CH-9230 Flawil; Silica gel, Qingdao Marine Chemical Factory; sephadex LH-20; mersham Biosciences AB; column, Soochow high tech chromatography CO., Ltd.; ODS-C 
18
, YMC Co., Ltd.; precoated silica gel plates, Qingdao Marine Chemical Factory.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>
The
flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sophora davidii
(Franch.) Pavol. (Fabaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected 
Honghe county
, 
Yunnan Province
, 
China
(

N23 
◦
59 
′

, 

E103 
◦
41 
′

), in 

August 2019

, and identified by 
Dr. Xuan-Qin Chen. A
voucher specimen (number: KUMST20190818) has been deposited at the 
Key Laboratory of Phytochemistry
(
Kunming University of Science
and 
Technology
)

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
Dried flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. davidii
</tp:taxon-name>
(
5 kg
) were powered and extracted with EtOH/H 
2
O (95:5, 24 h × 3) at room temperature, the extract was partitioned between 1.0‰ HCl/H 
2
O and EtOAc. Then, the water-soluble materials were adjusted to pH 10 with saturated Na 
2
CO 
3
aq, were extracted with CHCl 
3
to obtained crude alkaloid (
18 g
). The crude alkaloid was subjected to basic alumina CC eluting with a gradient of petroleum ether EtOAc system (20:1 → 1:1) adjusted by diethylamine (5‰) to afford five fractions A-E. Fraction A (
5.8 g
) was further separated by silica gel CC (petroleum ether acetone diethylamine, 85:15:0.5) to yield three subfractions A01-03. Fraction A02 (
2.3 g
) was further subjected to silica gel CC (EtOAc MeOH, 40:1) to yield 4 (
458.6 mg
). Fraction B (
3.6 g
) was further separated by silica gel CC (petroleum ether acetone diethylamine, 70:30:0.5) to obtained six subfractions B01-06. Fraction B03 (
815 mg
) was further purified by a silica gel CC (CHCl 
3
–MeOH, 30:1) to afford compound 3 (
6.2 mg
). Fraction B06 (
460 mg
) was separated by silica gel CC (EtOAc MeOH, 40:1) to yield 2 (
4.6 mg
). Fraction C (
3.2 g
) was further purified by a silica gel CC (CHCl 
3
–MeOH, 10:1) and Sephadex LH-20 (CHCl 
3
–MeOH, 1:1) to afford four subfractions C01-04. Fraction C01 (
260 mg
) was chromatographed over repeated silica gel CC (CHCl 
3
–MeOH–H 
2
O, 40:10:0.1) to yield 1 (
8.2 mg
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Characterization data
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.1. Sophovicine A (1)
</title>
         <p>
Colorless crystals (toluene–methanol, 9:1); mp 189.5–190.5 
◦
C; 
24
</p>
         <p>
[
α
] 
D
+ 82 (
c
0.11, 
CH
3
OH); UV (
CH
3
OH) 
λ

ma 
x

(log 
ε
): 196 (4.66), 260 (4.30) nm; ECD (
c
2.36 × 10 
4
M, MeOH), 
λ

ma 
x

(Δ 
ε
) 209 (+ 23.80), 232 (1.41), 256 (+ 3.45) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
: 2929, 1641, 1598, 1576, 1473, 1328, 1250, 
1104 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR (CD 
3
OD, 600 MHz) and 
13
C NMR (CD 
3
OD, 150 MHz) data, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
404.2168 ([M+ Na] 
+
, calcd for C 
20
H 
27
N 
7
ONa 
+
, 404.2169).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.2. Sophovicine B (2)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
24
+ 61 (
c
0.10, 
CH
3
OH); UV (
CH
3
OH) 
λ

ma 
x

(log 
ε
): 196 (4.58), 261 (4.20) nm; ECD (
c
3.15 × 10 
4
M, MeOH), 
λ

ma 
x

(Δ 
ε
) 215 (+ 18.41), 260 (2.48) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
: 2928, 1638, 1573, 1473, 1444, 1415, 1296, 
1257 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR (CD 
3
Cl, 600 MHz) and 
13
C NMR (CD 
3
Cl, 150 MHz) data, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
404.2168 ([M+ Na] 
+
, calcd for C 
20
H 
27
N 
7
ONa 
+
, 404.2169).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.3. Sophovicine C (3)
</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
24
+ 27 (
c
0.12, 
CH
3
OH); UV (
CH
3
OH) 
λ

ma 
x

(log 
ε
): 196 (4.61), 261 (4.23) nm; ECD (
c
5.74 × 10 
4
M, MeOH), 
λ

ma 
x

(Δ 
ε
) 216 (+ 9.03), 266 (1.16) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
: 2919, 1631, 1573, 1472, 1440, 1414, 1293, 
1259 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR (CD 
3
OD, 600 MHz) and 
13
C NMR (CD 
3
OD, 150 MHz) data, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
396.2156 [M-H] 
-
, calcd for C 
20
H 
25
N 
7
O, 396.2153).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.4. Crystallographic data for compound 1
</title>
         <p>
C 
20
H 
27
N 
7
O, 
M
= 381.48, 
a
= 7.7400(2) Å, 
b
= 8.0194(2) Å, 
c
= 30.4457(8) Å, 
α
= 90 
◦
, 
β
= 90 
◦
, 
γ
= 90 
◦
, 
V
= 1889.77(8) Å 
3
, 
T
= 100.(2) K, space group 
P
212121
, 
Z
= 4, 
μ
(Cu Kα) = 
0.705 mm
1
, 18,368 reflections measured, 3717 independent reflections (

Rint

= 0.0552). The final 

R 
1

values were 0.0551 (

I
&gt;

2 
σ
(
I
)). The final 
wR
(
F
2
) values were 0.1462 (

I
&gt;

2 
σ
(
I
)). The final 

R 
1

values were 0.0553 (all data). The final 
wR
(
F
2
) values were 0.1463 (all data). The goodness of fit on 
F
2
was 1.119. Flack parameter = 0.20(8). The crystallographic data for 1 has been deposited in the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre (no. 2022229).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. ECD calculation
</title>
         <p>
The methods for ECD calculation were performed according to previous work (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Molecular modeling
</title>
         <p>
Discovery Studio was used to carry out molecular docking studies using recently published methods (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Biological assay
</title>
         <p>
Cells and viruses: The human colorectal carcinoma (HRT-18) cells (ATCC CCL-244) were cultured in Roswell Park Memorial Institute 1640 medium (RPMI 1640, Hyclone, 
USA
). The primary human foreskin fibroblasts (HFF) were cultured in minimal essential medium (MEM) medium (Hyclone, 
USA
). All cells were supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), penicillin and streptomycin (100 U/mL and 100 μg/ mL, respectively, Gibco, 
USA
), and HRT-18 cells were cultured with additional 10 mM HEPES (Gibco, 
USA
). The VR-1558 strain of HCoV-OC43 was propagated in HRT-18 cells, and the titer of viral stock was determined by 50% tissue culture infective dose (TCID 
50
) according to the cytopathic effect by use of Reed-Muench method (Xia et al., 2019). A BAC clone of HCMV Towne strain expressing a 
gfp
gene in the viral genome was propagated in HFF, and viral titers were titrated by plaque assay on monolayer of HFF as described previously (

).
</p>
         <p>
Cytotoxicity assay: The cytotoxic effects of candidate reagents on HRT-18 and HFF cells were evaluated by methylthiazolyldiphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assay. Briefly, monolayer of cells grown in 96-well plates was incubated with indicated concentrations of reagents. After 48 h, the cells were stained with MTT solution at 
0.5 mg
/mL for 4 h. The supernatants were removed and the cells were added with the formed formazan crystals dissolved in 200 
μ
L DMSO. The absorbance at 
490 nm
was determined by using Multiskan GO Microplate Spectrophotometer. (Thermo Fisher, 
USA
). The 50% cytotoxic concentration (CC 
50
) was calculated by the GraphPad Prism 8.0 software.
</p>
         <p>
Cytopathic effect (CPE) inhibition assay: Cell monolayers were grown in 96-well plates. The HRT-18 cell monolayers were inoculated with 100 TCID 
50
of the VR-1558 strain of HCoV-OC43 at 34 
◦
C for 2 h, and the HFF cell monolayers were inoculated with HCMV with a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 1 at 37 
◦
C for 2 h. The inoculum was then removed and the cells were treated with indicated concentrations of reagents. When 75% or more of the infected cells showed CPE under the microscope, the inhibition effect was evaluated by MTT assay as mentioned above. The 50% inhibition concentration (IC 
50
) was then calculated by the GraphPad Prism 8.0 software.
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
This work was supported financially by the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(No. 31960092, 22067012, and 82073737) and the Innovative Team of 
Yunnan Province
(No. 2019HC018).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112842.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Agut, H.
, 
2012
. 
Emergence of cytomegalovirus resistance to foscarnet in a patient receiving foscarnet salvage therapy for multidrug-resistant HIV infection
. 
J. Clin. Virol.
54
, 
194–196
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcv.2012.02.008
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alam, M.M.
, 
Bayoumy, M.
, 
Ali, A.
, 
Alali, M.
, 
Al-Enezi, B.
, 
Abosoudah, I.
, 
2016
. 
Cytomegalovirus infection in children after bone marrow transplantation: risk factors, clinical aspects and outcomes
. 
Pediatr. Infect. Dis.
8
, 
1–7
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.pid.2016.03.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ariza-Heredia, E.J.
, 
Lior, N.
, 
Chemaly, R.F.
, 
2014
. 
Cytomegalovirus diseases after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation: a mini-review
. 
Canc. Lett.
342
, 
1–8
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.canlet.2013.09.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bai, G.Y.
, 
Wang, D.Q.
, 
Ye, C.H.
, 
Liu, M.L.
, 
2002
. 
1 H and 13C chemical shift assignments and stereochemistry of matrine and oxymatrine
. 
Appl. Magn. Reson.
23
, 
113–121
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF03166189
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Borthwick, A.D.
, 
2005
. 
Design of translactam HCMV protease inhibitors as potent antivirals
. 
Med. Res. Rev.
25
, 
427–452
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/med.20030
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chrisp, P.
, 
Clissold, S.P.
, 
1991
. 
Foscarnet
. 
Drugs
41
, 
104–129
. 
https://doi.org/10.2165/ 00003495-199141010-00009
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ding, W.Y.
, 
Yan, Y.M.
, 
Meng, X.H.
, 
Nafie, L.A.
, 
Xu, T.
, 
Dukor, R.K.
, 
Qin, H.B.
, 
Cheng, Y. X.
, 
2020
. 

Isolation, total Synthesis, and absolute configuration determination of renoprotective dimeric 
N
-acetyldopamine–adenine hybrids from the Insect 
Aspongopus chinensis

. 
Org. Lett.
22
, 
5726–5730
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. orglett.0c01593
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dong, L.H.
, 
Tai, Z.G.
, 
Yang, Y.B.
, 
Liu, C.S.
, 
Cai, L.
, 
Ding, Z.T.
, 
2010
. 

Chemical constituents of the flowers of 
Sophora viciifolia
hance. West chin

. 
J. Pharm. Sci.
25
, 
636–640
. 
https://doi.org/10.13375/j.cnki.wcjps.2010.06.017
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dong, S.W.
, 
Jiao, L.S.
, 
Yang, M.
, 
Duan, Y.L.
, 
Chen, Y.B.
, 
Zhao, F.
, 
Zhang, A.M.
, 
Liu, L.
, 
Luo, M.H.
, 
Xia, X.S.
, 
2019
. 
The susceptibility of primary dermis fibroblasts from the Chinese tree shrew to human cytomegalovirus infection
. 
Virol. Sin.
34
, 
270–277
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s12250-019-00106-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Flynn, D.L.
, 
Abood, N.A.
, 
Holwerda, B.C.
, 
1997
. 
Recent advances in antiviral research: identification of inhibitors of the herpesvirus proteases
. 
Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol.
1
, 
190–196
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S1367-5931(97)80009-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gao, D.D.
, 
Zhang, Z.J.
, 
Li, H.M.
, 
Chen, X.Q.
, 
Liu, D.
, 
Li, R.T.
, 
2020
. 

Four new quinolizidine alkaloids from the flowers of 
Sophora viciifolia

. 
Phytochem. Lett.
36
, 
91–94
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytol.2020.01.007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guo, L.P.
, 
Wang, S.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Yang, G.
, 
Zhao, M.X.
, 
Ma, W.F.
, 
Zhang, X.B.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Han, B. X.
, 
Chen, N.F.
, 
Huang, L.Q.
, 
2013
. 

Effects of ecological factors on secondary metabolites and inorganic elements of 
Scutellaria baicalensis
and analysis of geoherblism

. 
Sci. China Life Sci.
56
, 
1047–1056
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11427- 013-4562-5
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Holwerda, B.C.
, 
1997
. 
Herpesvirus proteases: targets for novel antiviral drugs
. 
Antivir. Res.
35
, 
1–21
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0166-3542(97)00012-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Huang, Y.
, 
Hao, J.
, 
Tian, D.
, 
Wen, Y.
, 
Zhao, P.
, 
Chen, H.
, Lv, Y., 
Yang, X.
, 
2018
. 

Antidiabetic activity of a flavonoid-rich extract from 
Sophora davidii
(Franch.) skeels in KK-Ay mice 
via
activation of AMP-activated protein kinase

. 
Front. Pharmacol.
9
, 
760
. 
https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2018.00760
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kimberlin, D.W.
, 
Jester, P.M.
, S´anchez, P.J., 
Ahmed, A.
, 
Arav-Boger, R.
, 
Michaels, M.G.
, 
Ashouri, N.
, 
Englund, J.A.
, 
Estrada, B.
, 
Jacobs, R.F.
, 
Romero, J.R.
, 
Sood, S.K.
, 
Whitworth, M.S.
, 
Abzug, M.J.
, 
Caserta, M.T.
, 
Fowler, S.
, 
Lujan-Zilbermann, J.
, 
Storch, G.A.
, 
DeBiasi, R.L.
, 
Han, J.Y.
, 
Palmer, A.
, 
Weiner, L.B.
, 
Bocchini, J.A.
, 
Dennehy, P.H.
, 
Finn, A.
, 
Griffiths, P.D.
, 
Luck, S.
, 
Gutierrez, K.
, 
Halasa, N.
, 
Homans, J.
, 
Shane, A.L.
, 
Sharland, M.
, 
Simonsen, K.
, 
Vanchiere, J.A.
, 
Woods, C.R.
, 
Sabo, D.L.
, 
Aban, I.
, 
Kuo, H.
, 
James, S.H.
, 
Prichard, M.N.
, 
Griffin, J.
, 
Giles, D.
, 
Acosta, E.P.
, 
Whitley, R.J.
, 
2015
. 
Valganciclovir for symptomatic congenital cytomegalovirus disease
. 
N. Engl. J. Med.
372
, 
933–943
. 
https://doi.org/10.1056/ NEJMoa1404599
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, J.C.
, 
Dai, W.F.
, 
Liu, D.
, 
Jiang, M.Y.
, 
Zhang, Z.J.
, 
Chen, X.Q.
, 
Chen, C.H.
, 
Li, R.T.
, 
Li, H. M.
, 
2020
. 

Bioactive ent-isopimarane diterpenoids from 
Euphorbia neriifolia

. 
Phytochemistry
175
, 
112373
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112373
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lin, B.B.
, 
Liu, X.
, 
Wu, S.Q.
, 
Zheng, H.X.
, 
Huo, K.K.
, 
Qi, S.S.
, 
Chen, C.
, 
2019
. 

Phytochemicals content, antioxidant and antibacterial activities of 
Sophora viciifolia

. 
Chem. Biodivers.
16
, e 
1900080
https://doi.org/10.1002/cbdv.201900080
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ljungman, P.
, 
Deliliers, G.L.
, 
Platzbecker, U.
, 
Matthes-Martin, S.
, 
Bacigalupo, A.
, 
Einsele, H.
, 
Ullmann, J.
, 
Musso, M.
, 
Trenschel, R.
, 
Ribaud, P.
, Bornh¨auser, M., 
Cesaro, S.
, 
Crooks, B.
, 
Dekker, A.
, 
Gratecos, N.
, 
Klingebiel, T.
, 
Tagliaferri, E.
, 
Ullmann, A.J.
, 
Wacker, P.
, 
Cordonnier, C.
, 
2001
. 
Cidofovir for cytomegalovirus infection and disease in allogeneic stem cell transplant recipients
. 
The infectious diseases working party of the European group for blood and marrow transplantation. Blood
97
, 
388–392
. 
https://doi.org/10.1182/blood.v97.2.388
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lurain, N.S.
, 
Chou, S.
, 
2010
. 
Antiviral drug resistance of human cytomegalovirus
. 
Clin. Microbiol. Rev.
23
, 
689–712
. 
https://doi.org/10.1128/CMR.00009-10
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mohamed, T.A.
, 
Shabaan, I.A.
, 
Zoghaib, W.M.
, 
Husband, J.
, 
Farag, R.S.
, 
Alajhaz, A.E.N. M.A.
, 
2009
. 
Tautomerism, normal coordinate analysis, vibrational assignments, calculated IR, Raman and NMR spectra of adenine
. 
J. Mol. Struct.
938
, 
263–276
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molstruc.2009.09.040
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morillo-Gutierrez, B.
, 
Waugh, S.
, 
Pickering, A.
, 
Flood, T.
, 
Emonts, M.
, 
2017
. 
Emerging (val)ganciclovir resistance during treatment of congenital CMV infection: a case report and review of the literature
. 
BMC Pediatr.
17
, 
181
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/ s12887-017-0933-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morris, G.M.
, 
Goodsell, D.S.
, 
Halliday, R.S.
, 
Huey, R.
, 
Hart, W.E.
, 
Belew, R.K.
, 
Olson, A. J.
, 
1998
. 
Automated docking using a Lamarckian genetic algorithm and an empirical binding free energy function
. 
J. Comput. Chem.
19
, 
1639–1662
. 

https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1096-987X, 19981115)19:14 
&lt;
1639::AIDJCC10
&gt;
3.0.CO;2-B

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ohyama, M.
, 
Ichise, M.
, 
Tanaka, T.
, 
Iinuma, M.
, 
Burandt, C.L.
, 
1996
. 

Davidiol D, first naturally occurring resveratrol pentamer isolated from 
Sophora davidii

. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
37
, 
5155–5158
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0040-4039(96)01078-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shao, L.D.
, 
Su, J.
, 
Ye, B.
, 
Liu, J.X.
, 
Zuo, Z.L.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
Wang, Y.Y.
, 
Xia, C.
, 
Zhao, Q.S.
, 
2017
. 
Design, synthesis, and biological activities of vibsanin B derivatives: a new class of HSP90 C-terminal inhibitors
. 
J. Med. Chem.
60
, 
9053–9066
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.jmedchem.7b01395
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tai, Z.
, 
Cai, L.
, 
Dai, L.
, 
Dong, L.
, 
Wang, M.
, 
Yang, Y.
, 
Cao, Q.
, 
Ding, Z.
, 
2011
. 

Antioxidant activity and chemical constituents of edible flower of 
Sophora viciifolia

. 
Food Chem.
126
, 
1648–1654
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2010.12.048
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tanaka, T.
, 
Ito, T.
, 
Iinuma, M.
, 
Ohyama, M.
, 
Ichise, M.
, 
Tateishi, Y.
, 
2000
. 

Stilbene oligomers in roots of 
Sophora davidii

. 
Phytochemistry
53
, 
1009–1014
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/S0031-9422(00)00016-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tong, L.
, 
Qian, C.
, 
Massariol, M.J.
, D´eziel, R., 
Yoakim, C.
, Lagac´e, L., 
1998
. 
Conserved mode of peptidomimetic inhibition and substrate recognition of human cytomegalovirus protease
. 
Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol.
5
, 
819–826
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1038/1860
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xia, S.
, 
Liu, M.
, 
Wang, C.
, 
Xu, W.
, 
Lan, Q.
, 
Feng, S.
, 
Qi, F.
, 
Bao, L.
, 
Du, L.
, 
Liu, S.
, 
Qin, C.
, 
Sun, F.
, 
Shi, Z.
, 
Zhu, Y.
, 
Jiang, S.
, 
Lu, L.
, 
2020
. 
Inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 (previously 2019-nCoV) infection by a highly potent pan-coronavirus fusion inhibitor targeting its spike protein that harbors a high capacity to mediate membrane fusion
. 
Cell Res.
30
, 
343–355
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41422-020-0305-x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xiong, X.
, 
Smith, J.L.
, 
Chen, M.S.
, 
1997
. 
Effect of incorporation of cidofovir into DNA by human cytomegalovirus DNA polymerase on DNA elongation. Antimicrob
. 
Agents Chemother.
41
, 
594–599
. 
https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.41.3.594
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
