<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112627</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Impairment of botrydial production in Botrytis cinerea allows the isolation of undescribed polyketides and reveals new insights into the botcinins biosynthetic pathway</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cristina Pinedo</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Río</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sclerotiniaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
Persoon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sclerotiniaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis
species.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>B. cinerea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Botryotinia fuckeliana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis
(
Marumo et al., 1982
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>B. cinerea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
Pers
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sclerotiniaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Impairment of botrydial production in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
allows the isolation of undescribed polyketides and reveals new insights into the botcinins biosynthetic pathway

</p>
         <p>
Javier Moraga
a, 1
, Inmaculada Izquierdo-Bueno Reina
a, 1

, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cristina Pinedo</tp:taxon-name>
a
,
</p>
         <p>
Rosario 
Hern´andez-Gal´an
a
, Muriel Viaud
b
, Isidro G. Collado

a, 
*
</p>
         <p>
a
Departamento de Química Org´anica
, Facultad de Ciencias, Campus Universitario 
<tp:taxon-name>Río</tp:taxon-name>
San Pedro s/n, Torre sur, 4a planta, Universidad de 
C´adiz, 11510, Puerto Real,
</p>
         <p>
C´adiz
, 
Spain
</p>
         <p>
b
Universite´Paris-Saclay, INRAE, AgroParisTech, UMR BIOGER, Avenue Lucien Br´etigni`eres
, 78850, Thiverval-Grignon, 
France
</p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Sclerotiniaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Genome</p>
         <p>Polyketides</p>
         <p>Botcinins</p>
         <p>Botrylactones</p>
         <p>Cinbotolides</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
is a necrotrophic fungal pathogen that affects a total of 586 genera representing approximately 1400 plant species. This pathogen produces two families of phytotoxins involved in its infection process i.e. botrydial and its relatives, and botcinic and botcineric acids and their relatives, botcinins. The botrydial biosynthetic cluster consists of seven genes, where the gene 
BcBOT4
encodes a cytochrome P450 monooxygenase that was shown to catalyse regio- and stereospecific hydroxylation at position C-4 of the presilphiperfolan-8-β- ol skeleton. The null mutant 

bcbot4
Δ

halted the production of botrydial and its derivatives, and instead accumulated tricyclic presilphiperfolane alcohol and overproduced a significant number of polyketides. A detailed study of the 

bcbot4
Δ

mutant led us to the isolation and characterization of five undescribed polyketides, three derived from botcinic and botcineric acids (botcinins H, I, J), one derived from the initial pentaketide (botcinin K), and one cinbotolide derivative (cinbotolide D). Botcinins are tetra-methylated tetraketides biosynthesized by the sequential assembly of a pentaketide (C10) based on an acetate primer unit which is lost through a retro-Claisen 
type
C–C bond cleavage. The structural characterization of botcinin K showed a basic chemical structure corresponding to a botcinin (C14) derivative obtained directly from the original per-methylated pentaketide leading to the biosynthesis of botrylactone and other botcinins, confirming the previously proposed biosynthetic route.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The 
<tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis
</tp:taxon-name>
genus comprises a wide range of fungal species found world-wide (

; 

). The species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
Persoon
</tp:taxon-name>
: Fries (
<tp:taxon-name>Sclerotiniaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) was first characterized by Micheli in 1729 and later confirmed by Persoon in 1801. Many other species have been described since then thanks to advances in molecular genetic techniques and today there are approximately 30 different 
<tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis
species.
</tp:taxon-name>
Seven new species, a hybrid, and a species complex have been isolated and identified over the last ten years (

). 

<tp:taxon-name>B. cinerea</tp:taxon-name>
(teleomorph: 
<tp:taxon-name>Botryotinia fuckeliana</tp:taxon-name>
)

is the causal agent of grey mold disease that affects a total of 586 genera of vascular plants, representing over 1400 ornamental and agriculturally important plant species (

; 

). This fungus is a typical necrotroph whose infective cycle includes the killing of plant cells, maceration of plant tissue and then reproduction by forming asexual spores on the decomposing plant material. Throughout the infection, 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
uses a battery of phytotoxins, enzymes, and reactive oxygen species (

). Two groups of phytotoxins have been identified (
Fig. 1
), i.e. the sesquiterpene botrydial (
1
) and related compounds (

) and the polyketides: botcinic and botcineric acid (
2
, 
3
) and their botcinin derivatives (
4
, 
5
) (

, 

), as well as botrylactone, (
6
) (

) an intermediate in the biosynthetic route to 
4
and 
5
. Furthermore, a structurally different group of compounds with the same polyketide chain as that of botcinins (
4, 5
), whose main representative is cinbotolide A (
7
) (

) and the sesquiterpenoid abscisic acid (
8
), have been isolated from several strains of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis
(
Marumo et al., 1982
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. * Corresponding author.
</p>
         <p>
E-mail address:
isidro.gonzalez@uca.es (I.G. Collado).
</p>
         <p>
1
These authors contributed equally to this work.
</p>
         <p>
Additionally, a family of sporogenic eremophilenols potentially used by 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
as effectors to circumvent plant chemical defenses, has recently been reported 
9–20
(

; Suarez´et al., 2018).
</p>
         <p>
The biosynthetic route and the polyketide synthases involved in the biosynthesis of botcinin and its derivatives and botrylactones (compounds 
2–6
) have been described in the literature (

; 

). Biosynthesis was studied by using acetate and malonate units labelled with deuterium and carbon thirteen. It has been shown that the condensation of an acetate starter unit and four molecules of malonate yields a pentaketide (C10), with its four pendent methyl group originating from L-methylmethionine. The pentaketide losses the starter unit of the acetate to give botcinic and botcineric acid derivatives and their relatives botcinins (

).
</p>
         <p>
Moreover, the botrydial biosynthetic cluster consists of seven genes codifying for one sesquiterpene cyclase BcBOT2, three P450 monooxygenases, BcBOT1, BcBOT3 and BcBOT4, one acetyl transferase BcBOT5, one dehydrogenases BcBOT7, and the putative Zn(II) 
2
Cys 
6
transcription factor BcBOT6 (

; 

). The gene 
BcBOT4
encodes a cytochrome P450 monooxygenase that was shown to catalyse regio- and stereospecific hydroxylation at position C-4 of the presilphiperfolan-8-β- ol skeleton (

). The null mutant 

bcbot4
Δ

abolished the production of botrydial and its derivatives, and instead accumulated the tricyclic presilphiperfolane alcohol and overproduced a significant number of polyketides (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
A detailed study of the null mutant in the 
BcBOT 4
gene led us to characterize four undescribed botcinin derivatives and one cinbotolide, cinbotolide D. This paper addresses the structural characterization of the unreported polyketides and confirms the biosynthetic route to botrylactones and botcinins.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
A KO DNA cassette containing a nourseothricin resistance gene replacing the 
BcBOT4
gene, was constructed by PCR fusion and employed to transform protoplasts of the BO5.10 wild-type strains (

). The transformation resulted in two independent 

bcbot4
Δ

mutants and the integration of the replacement fragment at the targeted loci the genome was verified by PCR analysis.
</p>
         <p>
The null 

bcbot4
Δ

mutants, derived from the B05.10 strain, were grown on a solid malt agar medium as described in the experimental section. Broths were extracted with ethyl acetate (EtOAc) and the extracts separated by column chromatography using hexane:EtOAc mixtures of increasing polarity until reaching 100% of EtOAc. Both independent mutants displayed similar chemical patterns. 
1
H-NMR spectra of medium polarity fractions showed the presence of different mixtures of botcinins which were subjected to HPLC chromatography to obtain pure compounds which were then characterized by extensive NMR experiments.
</p>
         <p>
As expected, the null mutant accumulated the tricyclic presilphiperfolane-8β- ol, the key intermediate in botrydial biosynthesis (

; 

; 

). In addition to known polyketides previously reported, (

, 

; 

), compounds 
21–25
, 
Fig. 2
, were obtained and their structures were characterized by extensive mono- and bidimensional NMR experiments.
</p>
         <p>
The 
1
H-NMR spectrum of compound 
21
showed characteristic signals of the basic bicyclic skeleton of botcinin and signals corresponding to the side chain at C-7 were clearly missing. Thus, three signal doublets at δ 1.10, 1.20, 1.22, and one singlet (δ 1.22), integrating three protons each, were assigned to the four methyl groups on carbons C-2, C-6, C-8 and C-4, respectively. Two signals, one at δ 3.1 (dq, 
J
= 10, 7.0 Hz) and another at δ 2.0 (m), were assigned to protons H-2, and H-6 respectively. Also, four signals characteristic of protons germinal to oxygenated function at δ 3.50 (dq, 
J
= 9.7, 6.4 Hz), 3.7 (d, 
J
= 11 Hz), 2.9 (t, 
J
= 10 Hz), 5.4 (d, 
J
= 9.7 Hz), were assigned to protons H-8, H-5, H-7 and H-3. Lastly, a singlet at δ 2.1 corresponded to the methyl of the acetate group on carbon C-3. Spectroscopic constants were consistent with structure 
21
(
Fig. 2
), corresponding to the compound obtained from hydrogenation of the double bond in the side chain of botcinin A (
4
), and subsequent acid hydrolysis (HCl, 12 M) to remove the acyl portion (

). The absolute configuration of 
21
has been reported (

). This is the first time that this compound has been isolated and we have named it botcinin H.
</p>
         <p>
Compounds 
22–24
displayed a pattern of NMR signals characteristic of botcinins (

, 

). The 
13
C-NMR for compound 
22
contained 20 signals which, considered jointly with the HRMS, were consistent with the molecular formula C 
20
H 
30
O 
7
. These data, and the absence of NMR spectra signals corresponding to the acetyl group at C-3, indicated a side chain containing eight carbon atoms.
</p>
         <p>
The most significant differences were observed in the signals of the characteristic side chain. The multiplicity of vinylic signals at carbons C-2 
′
and C-3 
′
changed from two double doublets to two doublets. On the other hand, the absence of the signal in the 
1
H-NMR spectrum of the geminal proton to a hydroxyl group at C-4 
′
and instead the presence, in the 
13
C-NMR spectrum, of a carbonyl group, were observed. Thus the vinilic protons (H-2 
′
and H-3 
′
) signals appeared as two doublets at δ 6.7 and 7.11, 
J
= 16.0 Hz, indicating an 
E
geometry of the double bond, which along with the carbonyl signal to 199.5 ppm indicated that the compound 
22
possessed an octenoyl side chain with a carbonyl group at C-4 
′
. This proposed structure 
22
was confirmed by HMBC (supplementary Table S1) experiments showing correlations of H-2 
′
and H-3 
′
with C-1 
′
and with the carbonyl C-4 
′
, respectively; and of H-5 
′
with carbons C-4 
′
, C-6 
′
and C-7 
′
. The rest of the signals found in the NMR spectra and all the correlations in the HMBC and HSQC experiments were consistent with the basic structure 3- 
O
-deacetyl botcinin A (

), with a chain of (
E
)-4 
′
-oxooct-2 
′
-enoyloxy attached to the pyrane ring at C-7. This new chemical structure of botcinin was named botcinin I.
</p>
         <p>
The 
1
H-NMR signal pattern of compound 
23
resembled that of compound 
22
, the most notable differences being the presence of an acetyl group situated at C-3 and the coupling constants of the two doublet signals corresponding to the vinylic group at C-2 
′
-C-3 
′
, (
J
= 12.1 Hz), indicating a 
Z
geometry for the double bond.
</p>
         <p>
The HRMS supported by the 
13
C NMR spectrum showed that compound 
23
possessed a molecular formula of C 
24
H 
36
O 
8
indicating that, in addition to an acetyl group, compound 
23
had a side chain of ten carbon atoms. COSY, HSQC and HMBC spectra (supplementary Table S2) were consistent with a basic structure of botcinin A with a (
Z
)-4 
′
-oxodec-2 
′
- enoyloxy chain at the C-7 carbon which was named botcinin J.
</p>
         <p>
The HRMS and 
13
C-NMR of compound 
24
indicated a formula of C 
22
H 
34
O 
7
. The NMR spectra of this compound displayed a pattern of signals characteristic of a basic botcinin skeleton with a side chain of eight carbon atoms attached at C-7. The main differences observed in its 
1
H-NMR were the multiplicity of the signals corresponding to the double bond at C-2 
′
- C-3 
′
, the absence of the signal of a geminal proton to a hydroxyl group in the side chain, and the signals multiplicity of methyl groups which appeared as two doublets and two singlets instead of three doublets and one singlet.
</p>
         <p>
The multiplicity of vinylic signals at carbons C-2 
′
and C-3 
′
appeared as two double triplets at δ 5.8 (dt, 
J
= 15.6, 1.7 Hz) and 7.0 (dt, 
J
= 15.6, 7 Hz), indicating the absence of the characteristic hydroxyl group at C-4 
′
and, based on the coupling constant, an 
E
geometry for the double bond. Particularly interesting was the change observed in the multiplicity of one methyl group which changed to singlet, indicating the presence of a new organic function in the structure. The study of signals in the 
1
H and 
13
C-NMR spectra, along with HSQC and HMBC experiments, allowed us to assign protons H-3, H-5, H-6 and H-7, the methyl groups at C-2, C-4 and C-6, and all signals corresponding to side chain protons and carbons.
</p>
         <p>
The main differences were at carbon C-8 where the correlations observed in the HMBC of H-14 with C-7, C-8, C-9, and H-7α with C-1 
′
, C-9, C-13 and C-14, indicated the presence of a geminal acetyl group to the methyl at C-8. Examination of the HSQC, HMBC and COSY spectra enabled all the carbon and their associated 
1
H NMR signals to be assigned (Table S3).
</p>
         <p>
The stereochemistry of compound 
24
was deduced based on the absolute stereochemistry assigned to the basic skeleton of botcinin A (

), while the stereochemistry in the environment surrounding carbon C-8 was based on the interactions observed in the nOe experiments (Table S3). Thus, the β disposition for the methyl group at C-8 was deduced from the interactions of proton H-14 with H-6 and H-12; and those observed between H-11 and H-2, H-6 and H-14. The α stereochemistry assigned to the acetyl group was confirmed by interactions of H-7α with H-10, H-13 and H-5, and the nOe observed between H-3α and protons H-2, H-5, H-10. These nOe interactions allowed us to propose structure 
24
for this botcinin derivative which was named botcinin K.
</p>
         <p>
The botcinins and botrylactones, compounds 
2–6
and those described in this article 
21–23
, are polyketides biosynthesized by sequential assembly of a per-methylated pentaketide (C10) arising from the condensation of an acetate primer unit and four malonate molecules, leading to a botrylactone-like intermediate (
27
) yielding botrylactone (
6
) or botcinin derivatives 
2–5,
through “a” route, 
Fig. 3
, (

). Preliminary isotopic labelling experiments in which labelled sodium acetates, propionate and S-methylmethionine were fed to 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
cultures, clearly demonstrate that botcinin skeleton arise from an acetate-derived polyketide assembled from carbon C-8 to C-1, with its four pendent methyl groups originating from 
S
-adenosylmethylmethionine (

).
</p>
         <p>
These polyketides require the action of two polyketide synthases (PKS), BcBoa6 and BcBoa9 (
Fig. 3
). Deletion of either the 
bcboa6
or 
bcboa9
gene (

) showed that they act in concert to synthetize botcinic acid (
2
): 

Δ 
bcboa6

and 

Δ 
bcboa9

null mutants did not produce botcinic acid or its derivatives; interestingly 

Δ 
bcboa9

overproduced botrylactone (
6
) (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Further isotopic labelling experiments showed that BcBoa6 mediates the formation of the pentaketide core, common to both botcinins and botrylactones, whereas BcBoa9 is responsible for the 7- 
O
-acyltetraketide side chain of botcinic acid and its derivatives 
2–4
(

; 

). These results enabled us to propose the biosynthetic route showed in 
Fig. 3
, where the acetate starter unit in botcinins is lost through a retro-Claisen 
type
C–C bond cleavage of the botrylactone-like precursor 
26
. The starter unit remaining attached at position C-3 of the botcinin molecule. Therefore, the 3- 
O
-acetyl group in botcinins (4, 
5
) and 3-acetylbotcinic acid (
29
) is derived from the starter unit of the botrylactone precursors 
26
and 
27
(
Fig. 3
) (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Interestingly, the isolation of compound 
24
was relevant insofar as a study of its potential biosynthesis showed that it was apparently biosynthesized from the initial per-methylated pentaketide core, obtained by condensation of four malonate molecules and one acetate unit, without losing the starting acetate unit. Botcinin K has to be synthetized from pentaketide (C10) which, after methylation by S-adenosyl methyl methionine and adequate functionalization and cyclization, give the pyrane intermediate 
26
(
Fig. 3
). This key intermediate is apparently hydroxylated at C-5 giving intermediate 
28
, pathway “b”, and, after esterifications at C-5 and C-7, directly yields the botcinin K (
24
), where the acetate starter unit now appearing at carbon C-8, carbons C-9 and C-10.
</p>
         <p>
Lastly, the 
1
H NMR signals of compound 
25
resembled those of cinbotolide (
7
) (

). However, the molecular formula for this compound was established as C 
12
H 
18
O 
5
[M-H 
2
O] 
+
by HRMS indicating that 
25
is a tetraketide, with four methyl groups and two degrees of unsaturation, instead of a pentaketide. This was consistent with the 
13
C NMR and HSQC data. The 
13
C NMR revealed the presence of four methyl, five methine groups and three quaternary carbons, one corresponding to a carbonyl group at δ 176.5 ppm attributed to a γ- lactone, and two bore an oxygen function, one of which corresponds to a hemiketalic carbon at δ 106.0 ppm. The 
1
H NMR spectrum contained four, three-proton signals, two singlets (δ 1.35 (H-10) and 1.42 (H-12)) and two doublets (δ 1.23 (
J
= 7.1 Hz, H-9) and 1.34 (
J
= 7.2 Hz), H-11). There were three signals (doublets) in the 
1
H NMR that were assigned to protons geminal to hydroxyl groups at δ 4.09 (d, 
J
= 4.1 Hz), 4.25 (d, 
J
= 7.0 Hz) and 3.9 (d, 
J
= 5.9 Hz). Based on the HMBC correlations observed, the signals were attributed to protons H-3, H-5 and H-7, respectively (Table S4). Furthermore, the correlations observed in the HMBC, H-2 with C-1 and C-9; H-3 with the carbonyl C-1, C-4 and C-5; and H-9 with carbons C-1, C-2 and C-3, along with absorption in the IR 
1752 cm
1
and the signal at δ 
176.5 in
the 
13
C NMR, were consistent with a γ- lactone. In addition to the correlations of the protons H-10, H-6 and H-7, table S4, which let us to propose the polyketide chain, the correlations between H-5 and C-3, C-4, C-7, C-8 located the hemiketalic closing of the ring B, between C-5 and C-8. Moreover, correlations between H-6 and C-5, C-7, C-11, between H-11 and C-5, C-6, C-7, and H-12 and C-7, C-8 were observed, confirming the structure proposed for compound 
25
.
</p>
         <p>
Interestingly, the basic structure of cinbotolide of this compound corresponds with the same basic tetraketide of botcinins, which should be cyclized in different positions. Thus, attack of a hydroxyl group at C-5 to a keto group at C-8 would give ring B, followed by the simultaneous lactonization with the hydroxyl at C-4 to yield 
25
. Stereochemistry was then assigned on the basis of the absolute configuration previously assigned to the polyketides of botcinins (

) and cinbotolide A (

) and additional nOe experiments.
</p>
         <p>
When H-2 was irradiated, enhancements were observed in the signals corresponding to H-3, H-9 and H-10 and, interestingly, when H-3 was irradiated there were enhancements to the signals corresponding to H-2, H-10 and unexpectedly to H-7, which should have a β disposition. This was confirmed by irradiation of H-7 and then nOe effects were observed at H-3, H-11 and H-12. When H-5 and H-6 were irradiated enhancements of the signals corresponding to H-6 and H-10, and H-5, H-10 and H-11, were observed. The nOe for H-3, H-5, H-6, H-7 were contradictory and surprising and it became necessary to develop a study with molecular models and MM2 calculation of the more stable conformation. So, a plausible explanation of the nOe was obtained whether we consider an interaction of a hydrogen bond between the hydroxyl group at C-3 and the oxygen hemiketalic of the furan cycle. A conformational disposition as displayed in 
Fig. 4
was adopted for molecule 
25
, approaching proton H-3 and H- 
7 in
the β disposition along with H-11 and H-12. Protons H-5, H-6 and H-10 are situated on the same lateral face making nOe interactions between them possible. Proposed structure 
25
was consistent with HSQC, HMBC, COSY and NOE spectra (Table S4). This compound was isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
for the first time and is reported here as a new compound not previously described in the literature and has been named cinbotolide D.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
This detailed study of the null mutant 

Bcbot4
Δ

has shown that polyketides are overproduced when the biosynthesis of the sesquiterpene botrydial and its derivatives is abolished. The study led us to the isolation and characterization of five undescribed polyketides 
21–25
, three derived from botcinic and botcineric acids, botcinins H, I, J (
21–23
), one derived from the initial pentaketide, botcinin K (
24
), and one cinbotolide derivative, cinbotolide D (
25
). The isolation of compound 
24
has confirmed the proposed biosynthetic pathway to botcinins and also confirmed the initial synthesis of a pentaketide, by polyketide synthase BcBOA6, that lose the starter acetyl unit to yield botcinic acid and derivatives, (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. Fungal strains
</title>
         <p>
The parental strain of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Botrytis cinerea
Pers
</tp:taxon-name>
: Fr. (
<tp:taxon-name>Sclerotiniaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) used in this work, B05.10, was kindly supplied by P. Tudzinsky (

).
</p>
         <p>
4.2. Media and culture conditions
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
mutant was cultivated at 23 
◦
C with 24 h daylight. The culture was grown on malt agar medium (MA; 
20 g
/l. malt extract, 
5 g
/l yeast extract, 
15 g
/l Agar), and minimal medium (MMII; 
20 g
/l glucose, 
2 g
/l. NaNO 
3
, 
1 g
/l KH 
2
PO 

4
, 500 mg

/l MgSO 
4.
7H 
2
O, 
500 mg
/l KCl, 
10 mg
/l FeSO 
4.
7H 
2
O, 
15 g
/l Agar). The transformation media was a minimal medium supplemented with saccharose (MMV; 
20 g
/l glucose, 
200 g
/l saccharose, 
2 g
/l. NaNO 
3
, 
1 g
/l KH 
2
PO 

4
, 500 mg

/l MgSO 
4.
7H 
2
O, 
500 mg
/l KCl, 
10 mg
/l FeSO 
4.
7H 
2
O, 
15 g
/l Agar). Nourseothricin fungicide (Werner Bioagent, Germany- 70 μg/ml) was used to select 

bcbot4
Δ

mutants.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Standard molecular methods
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. Gene deletion of the cytochrome P450-encoding gene bcbot4
</title>
         <p>
The 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. cinerea
</tp:taxon-name>
gene 
bcbot4
(GenBank: AY277723.2) was deleted by homologous recombination following the methodology already reported for this mutant (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Chemical methods: Analysis of the Bcbot4
Δ 
metabolite profile
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.1. General procedure
</title>
         <p>
The 
Bcbot4
null mutant was grown on malt agar medium (

) at 25 
◦
C to produce mycelium plugs (
0.8 cm
) that were further used to inoculate the medium for metabolite production. The strain was fermented in solid malt agar medium following the reported protocol (

; 

). The solid agar malt medium was extracted with an ultrasonic bath using ethyl acetate (3 × 0.5 vol). The solvent was dried over Na 
2
SO 
4
and concentrated to dryness.
</p>
         <p>
Metabolites were purified by column chromatography (CC) and semipreparative and analytical HPLC (Su´arez et al., 2018; 

). HPLC was performed with a Hitachi/Merck L-6270 apparatus equipped with an UV-VIS detector (L 4250) and a differential refractometer detector (RI-7490). Lichrosfer Si 60 (5 μm) LichoCart (
250 mm
× 
4 mm
) and Lichrosfer Si 60 (10 μm) LichoCart (
250 mm
× 
10 mm
) columns were used for isolation experiments. Optical rotation was recorded with a digital polarimeter. IR spectra were determined on an FT-IR spectrophotometer and reported as wave number (cm 
1
) (

).
</p>
         <p>
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra were obtained on Agilent 400 and 500 MHz spectrometers with SiMe 
4
as the internal reference at 25 
ο
C. Mass Spectroscopy (MS) and High Resolution Mass Spectroscopy (HRMS) were performed on a Thermoquest Voyager spectrometer and QTOF mass spectrometer, respectively (

).
</p>
         <p>
4.4.2. Bcbot4
Δ 
metabolite analysis
</p>
         <p>
10 days after inoculation, the solid agar malt medium was extracted (

; 

) yielding a dense oil from the 

bcbot4
Δ

culture (
300 mg
) that was separated by column chromatography on silica gel, eluted with mixtures containing increasing percentages of ethyl acetate/hexane (10–100%) and methanol as solvents. The final purification of the metabolites of interest was carried out by means of semipreparative HPLC using 
n
-hexane (Hex)-ethyl acetate (EtOAc) – acetone (Me 
2
CO) (50:40:10) or Hex-EtOAc-Me 
2
CO (70:20:10) as the mobile phase and flow rate 0.8 or 2.5 ml min 
1
(

), yielding the metabolite presilphiperfolan-8β- ol (

) and a significant number of metabolites with a polyketide skeleton. In addition to the known polyketides: botcinic and botcineric acids (
2
, 
3
) (5.0, 
3.5 mg
), botcinins A (
4
), B (
5
), E and G (50.5, 30.4, 8.0, 6.0 mg), (

, 

), botrylactone (
6
) (
20 mg
) (

), cinbotolide (
7
) (
10 mg
) (

); the botrylactones 5-hydroxy-7-(4-hydroxydec-2 (3)-enoyl)botrylactone (
12.2 mg
), 5-hydroxy-7-(oct-2 (3)-enoyl) botrylactone (9.0 mg), 6-hydroxy-7-deoxybotrylactone (
8 mg
), as well as, cinbotolides B (2.0 mg) and C (
10.1 mg
) (

), and the metabolites botcinin H (
21
) (5.0 mg), botcinin I (
22
) (
6 mg
), botcinin J (
23
) (
3 mg
), botcinin K (
24
) and the new polyketide (
25
) (
5.5 mg
), were isolated and characterized.
</p>
         <p>
4.4.2.1. Botcinin H (21).
Colorless oil was isolated as indicated above and its spectroscopic constants were identical to those shown by a compound obtained by hydrolysis of botcinin An under treatment with 30 μl of HCl 12 M, (

).
</p>
         <p>
4.4.2.2. Botcinin I (22).
Colorless oil. Analytical HPLC: Hex-EtOAc-Me 
2
CO 70:20:10; flow 0.8 ml 
min-1
; 
tR
= 42 min. [
α
] 

D
21
-44 (0.23c, CHCl 
3
). 
IR
ν
max
(cm 
-1
)

:.3412, 2936, 1729, 1272, 1174 1047, 1003. 

1
H NMR

(500 MHz, CDCl 
3
): δ 0.93 (t, 3H, 
J
= 7.3 Hz, H-8 
′
); 1.06 (d, 3H, 
J
= 6.3 Hz, H-11), 1.12 (d, 3H, 
J
= 6.1 Hz, H-12), 1.24 (s, 3H, H-10), 1.29 (d, 3H, 
J
= 7.3 Hz, H-9), 1.36 (m, 2H, H-7 
′
), 1.63 (m, 2H, H-6 
′
), 2.2 (m, 1H, H-6β), 2.65 (t, 2H, 
J
= 7.4 Hz, H-5 
′
), 3.06 (dq, 1H, 
J
= 9.8, 7.3 Hz, H-2α), 3.7 (d, 1H, 
J
= 11 Hz, H-5α), 3.75 (dq, 1H, 
J
= 9.7, 6.1 Hz, H-8β), 4.15 (m, 1H, H-3α), 4.56 (dd, 1H, 
J
= 10.6, 9.7 Hz, H-7α), 6.7 (d, 1H, 
J
= 16.0 Hz, H-2 
′
) 7.11 (d, 1H, 
J
= 16.0 Hz, H-3 
′
). 

13
C NMR

(125 MHz, CDCl 
3
): δ 10.3 (
CH
3
, C-9), 11.0 (
CH
3
, C-10), 13.7 (
CH
3
, C-11), 13.8 (
CH
3
, C-8 
′
), 18.2 (
CH
3
, C-12), 22.2 (
CH
2
, C-7 
′
), 25.6 (
CH
2
, C-6 
′
), 35.5 (
CH
, C-6), 38.3 (
CH
, C-2), 41.5 (
CH
2
, C-5 
′
), 68.2 (
CH
, C-8), 74.0 (
CH
, C-3), 76.3 (C, C-4), 77.2 (
CH
, C-7), 78.2 (
CH
, C-5), 129.4 (
CH
, C-2 
′
), 140.4 (
CH
, C-3 
′
), 164.9 (C, C-1 
′
), 173.8 (C, C-1), 199.5 (C, C-4 
′
). HRMS(ESI 
+
): calcd. for C 
20
H 
30
O 
7
Na [M+ Na] 
+
405.1889, found 405.1895. calcd. for C 
20
H 
31
O 
7
[M+ H] 
+
383.2070, found 383.2076.
</p>
         <p>
4.4.2.3. Botcinin J (23).
Colorless oil. Semi-preparative HPLC: Hex-EtOAc-Me 
2
CO 70:20:10; flow 2.5 ml 
min-1
; 
tR
= 37.1 min. [
α
] 

D
21
-18 (0.01c, CHCl 
3
). 
IR
ν
max
(cm 
-1
)

: 3470, 2940, 1732, 1644, 1220, 1045. 

1
H NMR

(500 MHz, CDCl 
3
): δ 0.88 (t, 3H, 
J
= 7.1 Hz, H-10 
′
), 1.1 (d, 3H, 
J
= 6.3
</p>
         <p>
Hz, H-11), 1.12 (d, 3H, 
J
= 6.0 Hz, H-12), 1.12 (d (superimposed), 3H, H-9), 1.24 (s, 1H, H-10), 1.27 (m, 2H, H-9 
′
), 1.30 (m, 2H, H-8 
′
), 1.33 (m, 2H, H-7 
′
), 1.63 (m, 2H, H-6 
′
), 2.1 (s, 3H, 
CH
3
CO), 2.2 (m, 1H, H-6β), 2.6 (t, H-2, 
J
= 7.4 Hz, H-5 
′
), 3.1 (dq, 1H, 
J
= 10, 7.0 Hz, H-2α), 3.6 (dq, 1H, 
J
= 9.7, 6.2 Hz, H-8β), 3.8 (d, 1H, 
J
= 11 Hz, H-5α), 4.5 (dd, 1H, 
J
= 10.6, 9.7 Hz, H-7α), 5.4 (d, 1H, 
J
= 10 Hz, H-3α), 6.0 (d, 1H, 
J
= 12.1 Hz, H-2 
′
) 6.5 (d, 1H, 
J
= 12.1 Hz, H-3 
′
). 

13
C NMR

(125 MHz, CDCl 
3
): δ 10.2 (
CH
3
, C-9), 11.9 (
CH
3
, C-10), 13.7 (
CH
3
, C-11), 14.0 (
CH
3
, C-10 
′
), 18.2 (
CH
3
, C-12), 20.5 (
CH
3
, Ac), 22.4 (
CH
2
, C-8 
′
), 23.3 (
CH
2
, C-6 
′
), 28.7 (
CH
2
, C-7 
′
), 31.5 (
CH
2
, C-9 
′
), 35.3 (
CH
, C-6), 37.3 (
CH
, C-2), 42.7 (
CH
2
, C-5 
′
), 68.2 (
CH
, C-8), 74.2 (
CH
, C-3), 75.1 (C, C-4), 77.2 (
CH
, C-7), 78.4 (
CH
, C-5), 123.6 (
CH
, C-2 
′
), 142.6 (
CH
, C-3 
′
), 164.4 (C, C-1 
′
), 170.0 (C, Ac), 173.0 (C, C-1), 203.3 (C, C-4 
′
). HRMS(ESI 
+
): calcd. for C 
24
H 
37
O 
8
[M+ H] 
+
453.2488 found 453.2477.
</p>
         <p>
4.4.2.4. Botcinin K (24).
Colorless oil. Semi-preparative HPLC: Hex-EtOAc-Me 
2
CO 70:20:10; flow 2.5 ml 
min-1
; 
tR
= 25.2 min. [
α
] 

D
21
-7 (0.23c, CHCl 
3
). 
IR
ν
max
(cm 
-1
)

: 3457, 2928, 1723, 1219, 771. 

1
H NMR

(500 MHz, CDCl 
3
): δ 0.89 (t, 3H, 
J
= 7.1 Hz, H-8 
′
), 1.11 (d, 3H, 
J
= 6.3 Hz, H-13) 1.28 (s, 3H, H-12), 1.29 (d, 3H, 
J
= 6.3 Hz, H-11), 1.30 (m, 2H, H-6 
′
), 1.31 (m, 2H, H-7 
′
), 1.45 (m, 2H, H-5 
′
), 1.48 (s, 3H, H-14), 2.2 (m, 2H, H-4 
′
), 2.26 (s, 3H, H-10), 2.37 (m, 1H, H-6β), 3.1 (m, 1H, H-2α), 3.79 (d, 1H, 
J
= 11.1 Hz, H-5α), 4.26 (d, 1H, 
J
= 9.9 Hz, H-3α), 4.94 (d, 1H, 
J
= 10.7 Hz, H-7α), 5.8 (dt, 1H, 
J
= 15.6, 1.7 Hz, H-2 
′
), 7.0 (dt, 1H, 
J
= 15.6, 7 Hz, H-3 
′
). 

13
C NMR

(125 MHz, CDCl 
3
): δ 10.1 (
CH
3
, C-11), 13.0 (
CH
3
, C-13), 13.9 (
CH
3
, C-8 
′
), 15.8 (
CH
3
, C-12), 18.3 (
CH
3
, C-14), 22.4 (
CH
2
, C-7 
′
), 23.9 (
CH
3
, C-10), 27.5 (
CH
2
, C-5 
′
), 31.3 (
CH
2
, C-6 
′
), 31.7 (
CH
, C-6), 32.3 (
CH
2
, C-4 
′
), 38.4 (
CH
, C-2), 72.0 (
CH
, C-7), 75.4 (
CH
, C-3), 77.2 (C, C-4), 78.5 (
CH
, C-5), 82.2 (C, C-8), 119.8 (
CH
, C-2 
′
), 151.7 (
CH
, C-3 
′
), 165.2 (C, C-1 
′
), 173.6 (C, C-1), 206.9 (C, C-9). HRMS(ESI 
+
): calcd. for C 
22
H 
35
O 
7
[M+ H] 
+
411.2383, found 411.2392.
</p>
         <p>
4.4.2.5. Cinbotolide D (25).
Colorless oil. Semi-preparative HPLC: Hex-EtOAc-Me 
2
CO 50:40:10; flow 2.5 ml min 
-1
; 
tR
= 40.2 min. [
α
] 

D
21
-6.3 (0.24c, CHCl 
3
). IR 
vmax
(
cm-1
): 3422, 2942, 1752, 1450, 1390, 1181, 1084, 1039, 937. 
1
H NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 
3
): δ 1.23 (d, 3H, 
J
= 7.1 Hz, H-9), 1.35 (s, 3H, H-10), 1.34 (d, 3H, 
J
= 7.2 Hz, H-11), 1.42 (s, 3H, H-12), 2.40 (m, 1H, H-6), 2.87 (qd, 1H, 
J
= 7.1, 4.1 Hz, H-2), 3.9 (d, 1H, 
J
= 5.9 Hz, H-7), 4.09 (d, 1H, 
J
= 4.1 Hz, H-3), 4.25 (d, 1 H, 
J
= 7.0 Hz, H-5). 
13
C NMR (125 MHz, CDCl 
3
): δ 7.5 (
CH
3
, C-9), 13.4 (
CH
3
, C-11), 19.7 (
CH
3
, C-12), 20.9 (
CH
3
, C-10), 41.5 (
CH
, C-2), 45.9 (
CH
, C-6), 74.4 (
CH
, C-3), 79.0 (
CH
, C-5), 79.2 (C, C-4), 82.3 (
CH
, C-7), 106.0 (C, C-8), 176.5 (C, C-1). HRMS(ESI 
+
): calcd. for C 
12
H 
18
O 
5
Na [M+ Na-H 
2
O] 
+
265.1052, found 265.1049.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
This research was supported by a grant from MINECO-FEDER (RTI 2018-097356-B-C21). Use of NMR facilities at the Servicio Centralizado de Ciencia y Tecnología (SCCYT) of the University of C´adiz is acknowledged. 
BIOGER
benefits from the support of Saclay Plant Sciences-SPS (ANR-17-EUR-0007).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112627.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Agrios, G.N.
, 
2005
. 
Plant Pathology, fifth ed
. 
Elsevier Academic Press, San Diego, CA
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Botubol Ares, J.M.
, Duran-Pena ˜, M.J., Macías- S´anchez, A.J., 
Hanson, J.R.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, Hern´andez-Gal´an, R., 
2014
. 
The asymmetric total synthesis of cinbotolide: a revision of the original structure
. 
J. Org. Chem.
79
(
23
), 
11349–11358
. 

https://doi.org/ 10.1021/jo 
501471m

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Coley-Smith, J.R.
, 
Verhoeff, K.
, 
Jarvis, W.R.
, 
1980
. 

The Biology of 
Botrytis

. 
Academic Press, London
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Colmenares, A.J.
, 
Aleu, J.
, Dur´an-Patron´, R., 
Collado, I.G.
, Hern´andez-Gal´an, R., 
2002
. 

The putative role of botrydial and related metabolites in the infection mechanism of 
Botrytis cinerea

. 
J. Chem. Ecol.
28
, 
997–1005
. 
https://doi.org/10.1023/A: 1015209817830
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dalmais, B.
, 
Schumacher, J.
, 
Moraga, J.
, 
le Pecheur, P.
, 
Tudzynski, B.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, 
Viaud, M.
, 
2011
. 

The 
Botrytis cinerea
phytotoxin botcinic acid requires two polyketide synthases for production and has a redundant role in virulence

. 
Mol. Plant Pathol.
12
, 
564–579
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1364-3703.2010.00692.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elad, Y.
, 
Pertot, I.
, 
Cotes Prado, A.M.
, 
Stewart, A.
, 
2016
a. 
Plant Hosts of Botrytis spp
., in: 
Botrytis – the Fungus, the Pathogen and its Management in Agricultural Systems. Edit
. 
Springer International Publishing, Switzerland
, pp. 
413–486
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/978-3-319-23371-0_20
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elad, Y.
, 
Vivier, M.
, 
Fillinger, S.
, 
2016
b. 
Botrytis, the Good, the Bad and the Ugly
, in: 
Botrytis – the Fungus, the Pathogen and its Management in Agricultural Systems. Edit
. 
Springer International Publishing, Switzerland
, pp. 
1–15
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/978-3-319-23371-0_1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fillinger, S.
, 
Elad, Y.
, 
2016
. 
Botrytis – the Fungus, the Pathogen and its Management in Agricultural Systems
. 
Springer International Publishing, Switzerland
. 
https://doi. org/10.1007/978-3-319-23371-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Marumo, S.
, 
Katayama, M.
, 
Komori, E.
, 
Ozaki, Y.
, 
Natsume, M.
, 
Kondo, S.
, 
1982
. 

Microbial production of abscisic acid by 
Botrytis cinerea

. 
Agric. Biol. Chem.
46
, 
1967–1968
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/00021369.1982.10865367
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Massaroli, M.
, 
Moraga, J.
, 
Bastos Borges, K.
, Ramírez-Fern´andez, J., 
Viaud, M.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, Dur´an-Patron´, R., Hern´andez-Gal´an, R., 
2013
. 
A shared biosynthetic pathway for botcinins and botrylactones revealed through gene deletion
. 
Chembiochem
14
, 
132–136
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/cbic.201200487
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Micheli, P.A.
, Nova plantarun genera juxta tournefortii methodum disposita, 
1729
. 
Florentiae:Typis Bernardi Paperinii
, 
Florentia
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moraga, J.
, 
Pinedo, C.
, 
Duran-Patron, R.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, 
Hernandez-Galan, R.
, 
2011
. 
Botrylactone: new interest in an old molecule—review of its absolute configuration and related compounds
. 
Tetrahedron
67
, 
417–420
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. tet.2010.11.022
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moraga, J.
, 
Dalmais, B.
, 
Izquierdo-Bueno, I.
, 
Aleu, J.
, 
Hanson, J.R.
, Hernandez-Gal ´´an, R., 
Viaud, M.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, 
2016
. 
Genetic and molecular basis of botrydial biosynthesis: connecting cytochrome P450-encoding genes to biosynthetic intermediates
. 
ACS Chem. Biol.
11
(
10
), 
2838–2846
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acschembio.6b00581
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Persoon, C.H.
, 
1801
. 
Synopsis methodica fungarum
. 
Edit. H. Dieterich, G¨ottingen
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pinedo, C.
, 
Wang, C.-M.
, 
Pradier, J.-M.
, 
Dalmais, B.
, 
Choquer, M.
, 
Le Pecheur, P.
, 
Morgant, G.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, 
Cane, D.E.
, 
Viaud, M.
, 
2008
. 

Sesquiterpene synthase from the botrydial biosynthetic gene cluster of the phytopathogen 
Botrytis cinerea

. 
ACS Chem. Biol.
3
(
12
), 
791–801
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/cb800225v
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pinedo, C.
, 
Moraga, J.
, 
Barúa, J.
, Gonz´alez-Rodríguez, 
V.E
., 
Aleu, J.
, Dur´an-Patron´, R., Macías-S´anchez, A.J., 
Hanson, J.R.
, 
Viaud, M.
, Hern´andez-Gal´an, R., 
Garrido, C.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, 
2016
. 

Chemically induced cryptic sesquiterpenoids and expression of sesquiterpene cyclases in 
Botrytis cinerea
revealed new sporogenic (+)-4- epieremophil-9-en-11-ols

. 
ACS Chem. Biol.
11
, 
1391–1400
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acschembio.5b00931
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Porquier, A.
, 
Morgant, G.
, 
Moraga, J.
, 
Dalmais, B.
, 
Luytend, I.
, 
Simon, A.
, 
Pradier, J.-M.
, 
Amselem, J.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, 
Viaud, M.
, 
2016
. 

The botrydial biosynthetic gene cluster of 
Botrytis cinerea
displays a bipartite genomic structure and is positively regulated by the putative Zn(II)2Cys6 transcription factor BcBot6

. 
Fungal Genet. Biol.
96
, 
33–46
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fgb.2016.10.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Porquier, A.
, 
Moraga, J.
, 
Morgant, G.
, 
Dalmais, B.
, 
Simon, A.
, 
Sghyer, H.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, 
Viaud, M.
, 
2019
. 

Botcinic acid biosynthesis in 
Botrytis cinerea
relies on a subtelomeric gene cluster surrounded by relics of transposons and is regulated by the Zn2Cys6 transcription factor BcBoa13

. 
Curr. Genet.
65
, 
965–980
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s00294-019-00952-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Quidde, T.
, 
Osbourn, A.E.
, 
Tudzynski, P.
, 
1998
. 

Detoxification of α- tomatine by 
Botrytis cinerea

. 
Physiol. Mol. Plant Pathol.
52
, 
151–165
. 
https://doi.org/10.1006/ PMPP.1998.0142
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rossi, F.R.
, 
Garriz, A.
, 
Marina, M.
, 
Romero, F.M.
, 
Gonzalez, M.E.
, 
Collado, I.G.
, 
Pieckenstain, F.L.
, 
2011
. 

The sesquiterpene botrydial produced by 
Botrytis cinerea
induces the hypersensitive response on plant tissues and its action is modulated by salicylic acid and jasmonic acid signalling

. 
Mol. Plant Microbe Interact.
24
(
8
), 
888–896
. 
https://doi.org/10.1094/MPMI-10-10-0248
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Su´arez, I., 
da Silva Lima, G.
, 
Conti, R.
, 
Pinedo, C.
, 
Moraga, J.
, 
Barúa, J.
, 
de Oliveira, A.L. L.
, 
Aleu, J.
, Dur´an-Patr´on, R., Macías-S´anchez, A.J., 
Hanson, J.R.
, 
Tallarico Pupo, M.
, Hern´andez-Gal´an, R., 
Collado, I.G.
, 
2018
. 

Structural and biosynthetic studies on eremophilenols related to the phytoalexin capsidiol, produced by 
Botrytis cinerea

. 
Phytochemistry
154
, 
10–18
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.06.010
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tani, H.
, 
Koshino, H.
, 
Sakuno, E.
, 
Nakajima, H.
, 
2005
. 

Botcinins A, B, C, and D, metabolites produced by 
Botrytis cinerea
, and their antifungal activity against 
Magnaporthe grisea
, a pathogen of rice blast disease

. 
J. Nat. Prod
68
, 
1768–1772
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/NP0503855
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tani, H.
, 
Koshino, H.
, 
Sakuno, E.
, 
Cutler, H.G.
, 
Nakajima, H.
, 
2006
. 

Botcinins E and F and Botcinolide from 
Botrytis cinerea
and structural revision of botcinolides

. 
J. Nat. Prod
69
, 
722–725
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/NP060071X
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
