<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112908</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Anti-inflammatory and anti-proliferative activities of chemical constituents from fungus Biscogniauxia whalleyi SWUF13-085</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Xylariaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
(Graphostomataceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Anti-inflammatory and anti-proliferative activities of chemical constituents from fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
13-085

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Phongphan Jantaharn
a
, Wiyada Mongkolthanaruk
b
, Nuttika Suwannasai
c
,
Thanaset Senawong 
d
, Sarawut Tontapha
e
, Vittaya Amornkitbumrung
e, f
, Jaursup Boonmak
g
,
Sujittra Youngme 
g
, Sirirath McCloskey

a, 
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a

Natural Products Research Unit, Center of Excellence for Innovation in Chemistry (PERCH-CIC), Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, 
Khon Kaen
University,

Khon Kaen
, 40002, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Department of Microbiology
, 
Faculty of Science
, 
Khon Kaen
University, 
Khon Kaen
, 40002, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c
Department of Biology
, 
Faculty of Science
, 
Srinakharinwirot University
, 
Bangkok
, 10110, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
d
Department of Biochemistry
, 
Faculty of Science
, 
Khon Kaen
University, 
Khon Kaen
, 40002, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
e
Department of Physics
, 
Faculty of Science
, 
Khon Kaen
University, 
Khon Kaen
, 40002, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
f
Institute of Nanomaterials Research
and Innovation for Energy, 
Khon Kaen
University, 
Khon Kaen
, 40002, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
g

Materials Chemistry Research Center, Center of Excellence for Innovation in Chemistry (PERCH-CIC), Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, 
Khon Kaen
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
University
, 
Khon Kaen
, 40002, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Graphostomataceae</p>
         <p>Anti-proliferative activity Anti-inflammation</p>
         <p>NO production</p>
         <p>Bergamotene</p>
         <p>
α
-pyrone
</p>
         <p>Guaiane</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
The fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
13-085 from the Graphostomataceae family was studied for potential anti-inflammatory and anticancer agents. A diverse array of natural products was identified. Six of which were undescribed compounds, including xylariterpenoids L-N, (1 
R
,2 
S
,6 
R
,7 
S
)-1,2-dihydroxy- 
α
-bisabolol, 6-[(1 
R
)-1- hydroxy-1-methyl-2-propenyl]-4-methoxy-3-methyl-2 
H
-pyran-2-one and (1 
R
*,4 
S
*,5 
S
*,7 
S
*,10 
R
*)-guaia-11 (12)- en-7,10-diol. Several of the isolated compounds such as bergamotene, guaiane and phthalide derivatives showed activity in both the inhibition of nitric oxide (NO) production in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated RAW264.7 macrophage cells with IC 
50
values in the range of 2.48–10.82 
μ
g/mL and anti-proliferation against HeLa cells with IC 
50
values in the range of 8.64–31.16 
μ
g/mL. While compounds such as cerebrosides A and C only exhibited inhibitory effects on NO production with IC 
50
values in the range of 4.45–10.28 
μ
g/mL.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Cancer is the second leading cause of mortality in humans, globally. There are an estimated 18.1 million new cases each year and it accounted for 9.6 million deaths in 2018 (

). The treatment of cancer typically involves the removal of cancerous or tumor cells by surgery and radiation therapy, both of which are usually followed by chemotherapy (

). However, obstacles such as side effects of the cancer drugs, e.g. cardiotoxicity, pulmonary dysfunction, lymphedema, etc. (

; 

; 

) and the reoccurrence of cancerous cells, make this disease extremely difficult to completely eradicate, ultimately leading to the loss of life. A number of studies have demonstrated that chronic inflammation may cause several 
types
of cancer (

; 

; 

). The discovery of the link between inflammation and cancer has led to research into drugs that can target inflammatory mediators and cancerous cell growth. Therefore, we have explored natural products from fungi that have anti-inflammatory and anti-proliferative activities from fungi for chemoprevention and chemotherapy drug candidates.
</p>
         <p>
Fungi is one of the most significant sources for the discovery of potential drug candidates with research into their metabolites and compounds having produced a large number of well documented reports (

; 

; 

). The 
<tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia
</tp:taxon-name>
genus previously belonged to the wood-decaying fungi, the 
<tp:taxon-name>Xylariaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family. It was resurrected to the Graphostomataceae family in 2017, which comprises five genera that are made up of more than 136 species (

). Unlike Xylarials, for which there has been numerous reports on their bioactive compounds (

), there has only been a small number from this genus e.g. sesquiterpenoid analogues from 
Graphostoma
sp. that were found to have potent anti-inflammatory properties (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>
E-mail address:
sirsod@kku.ac.th (S. McCloskey).
</p>
         <p>
The chemical constituents of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
(Graphostomataceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
strain SWUF13-085 were isolated by chromatographic techniques, which resulted in the isolation of thirty-five compounds. The structure elucidation by the analysis of IR, NMR, MS, ECD and X-ray data revealed several classes of natural products e.g., bergamotene, 
α
-pyrone, guaiane, dipeptide, steroid, and cerebroside derivatives, six of which were undescribed. The isolated compounds were evaluated for anti-inflammatory activity in terms of the inhibitory effect on NO production in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated RAW264.7 cells and anti-proliferation against cervical cancer cells (HeLa), colon cancer cells (HT29 and HCT116), breast cancer cells (MCF-7) and normal Vero cells. Herein, we have described the isolation, structure elucidation and the results of an anti-inflammatory and anti-proliferative activity evaluation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
The separation of crude extracts from the culture of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
13-085 fungus yielded thirty-five compounds (1–35). The analysis of multiple data from IR, NMR, MS, ECD and X-ray crystallographic techniques and a comparison of those data with literature revealed a variety of natural products.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 1 was obtained as a yellow viscous oil and the molecular formula C 
15
H 
22
O 
2
was assigned by the positive ion peak in HRESIMS at 
m/z
257.1519 [M+Na] 
+
(calc. for C 
15
H 
22
O 
2
Na, 257.1517). The 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) displayed proton signals of one olefinic methine at 
δ
H
5.11 (t, 
J
= 6.8, H-10), three methines at 
δ
H
3.16 (s, H-4), 2.50 (br t, 
J
= 5.9, H-6) and 2.39 (t, 
J
= 5.9, H-2), three methylenes at 
δ
H
2.06 (d, 
J
= 10.5, H-1a) and 2.24 (dt, 
J
= 10.5, 5.9, H-1b), 1.97 (m, H-9), and 1.76 (dd, 
J
= 10.3, 6.9, H-8), and four methyls at 
δ
H
1.68 (s, H-12), 1.60 (s, H-13), 1.49 (s, H-15) and 1.00 (s, H-14). The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 2
) showed a carbonyl ketone signal at 
δ
C
206.1 (C-5) that corresponded with the strong absorption band of a carbonyl ketone at 
1711 cm
1
in

the IR spectrum, and two olefinic signals at 
δ
C
132.1 (C-11) and 123.7 (C-10). The COSY correlations of H-1 to H-2 and H- 
6 in
association with the key HMBC correlations of H-1 to C-2, C-3, C-5, C-6 and C-7, 
CH
3
-14 to C-2, C-6, C-7 and C-8, and 
CH
3
-15 to C-2, C-3 and C-4 suggested the presence of a bicyclo [3.1.1]heptane ring (
Fig. 2
), a core structure of the bergamotene-type sesquiterpenoid (

; 

; 

). This was supported by the multiplicity patterns of the bridge-ring protons, i.e. H-1, H-2 and H-6 (
Fig. 3
). The two bridgehead methine protons H-2 and H-6 that appeared as a triplet revealed the 
3
J
H2-H1b
, 
3
J
H6-H1b
and 
4
J
H2-H6
correlations with coupling constants of 5.9 Hz (

), which contributed to the doublet of triplet of H-1b (
3
J
H1b-H2
= 5.9 Hz, 
3
J
H1b-H6
= 5.9 Hz and 
2
J
H1b-H1a
= 10.5 Hz). However, the H-1a appeared as a doublet due to its coupling only with H-1b (
2
J
H1a-H1b
= 10.5 Hz). A possible explanation for this could be that the dihedral angle of H-1a to the adjacent protons H-2 and H-6 (
3
J
≈ 0 Hz) is around 90 
◦
thus there is no coupling among them. Signals from two high-field oxygenated carbons appeared at 
δ
C
59.8 (C-3) and 59.2 (C-4) and the HMBC correlation of 
CH
3
-15 to C-2, C-3 and C-4 that corresponds with the absence of an OH-stretching absorption band in the IR spectrum. This revealed a 3,4-epoxide ring which is different from the typical bergamotene-core structure. The 4-methylpent-3-en-1-yl moiety was deduced by the COSY correlation of H-9 to H-8 and H-10 and the HMBC correlations of 
CH
3
-12,13 to C-10 and C-11, H-8,9 to C-7 and 
CH
3
-14 to C-7 and C-8 that supported the connection at C-7 of the bicyclic ring. The key NOESY correlations (
Fig. 4
) of H-1b to H-8, and 
CH
3
-14 to H-4 indicated an 
exo
-face pentenyl-substituted chain on the tricyclic ring, suggesting the relative configuration of 2 
R
*, 3 
R
*, 4 
R
*, 6 
S
* and 7 
S
*. The comparison of experimental and calculated ECD spectra (
Fig. 5
), showing Cotton effects at 208 (Δ 
ε
= +0.03), 216 (Δ 
ε
= 0.03), 228 (Δ 
ε
= +0.01) and 324 (Δ 
ε
= +0.03) nm that were similar to the calculated spectrum for (2 
R
,3 
R
,4 
R
,6 
S
,7 
S
)-1, led to the assignment of the absolute configuration of 1. The structure of 1 was therefore depicted as shown in 
Fig. 1
and named as xylariterpenoid L (

).
</p>
         <p>
a
The mixture labeled as 2a and 2b.
</p>
         <p>
b
The overlapping signals of 2a and 2b.
</p>
         <p>
The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of 2–5 showed some degree of similarity to 1. Compound 2 was obtained as yellow viscous oil and the molecular formula C 
15
H 
24
O 
4
was determined according to the positive ion peak in HRESIMS at 
m/z
291.1573 [M+Na] 
+
(calc. for C 
15
H 
24
O 
4
Na, 291.1572). The shifted proton signal at 
δ
H
3.33 (br d, 
J
= 10.0, H-10), which corresponded to the carbon signals at 
δ
C
78.7 (C-10) and 73.2 (C-11), indicated the presence of a dihydroxy group instead of a double bond as in 1. This was supported by the absorption band of an OH-stretching at 
3403 cm
1
in

the IR spectrum. The 
13
C NMR data of 2 showed some splitting carbon signals such as at C-2, C-5, C-6, C-7 and C-14, which suggested the mixture of two diastereomers (2a and 2b). The diastereomeric ratio of 2a and 2b could not be assigned based on the overlapping of almost every 
1
H NMR signal. Nevertheless, the ratio of 1:0.7 of 2a and 2b was estimated from the integration of splitting 
13
C NMR signals (

). The key NOESY correlation of H-4 to 
CH
3
-14, 15 confirmed the 
exo
-face of the pentenyl group. The comparison of the ECD spectra with 1 (
Fig. 5
) suggested a similar absolute configuration on the tricyclic ring as 2 
R
, 3 
R
, 4 
R
, 6 
S
and 7 
S
. However, because they were isolated as a mixture, the configuration of C-10 could not be determined in this work. On the basis of the above data, 2 was identified as 10, 11-dihydroxy xylariterpenoid L, named as xylariterpenoid M.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
The mixture of 2a (major) and 2b (minor).

</p>
         <p>
Compound 3 was isolated as a colorless viscous oil. Its molecular formula was C 
15
H 
22
O, based on the positive ion peak at 
m/z
219.1743 [M+H] 
+
(calc. for C 
15
H 
23
O, 219.1749) in HRESIMS. When compared to 1, the 
1
H NMR data of 3 showed an additional olefinic proton signal at 
δ
H
5.73 (s, H-4). This corresponded to the 
13
C NMR signals at 170.0 (C-3) and 121.5 (C-4). The HMBC correlation of 
CH
3
-15 to C-2, C-3 and C-4 (
Fig. 2
) suggested that there was a double bond on the bicyclo [3.1.1] heptane ring instead of an epoxide ring. The key NOESY correlations of H-1b to H-8 and 
CH
3
-14 to H-4 (
Fig. 4
) suggested a pentenyl chain in the 
exo
-face of the bridge ring and the experimental ECD spectrum of 3 showed a similar pattern to the calculated ECD spectrum of (2 
S
,6 
S
,7 
S
)-3 (
Fig. 6
). According to the above data, 3 was an undescribed bergamotene, named as xylariterpenoid N. Compounds 4 and 5 were isolated as a mixture in this work. The NMR spectroscopic data suggested partially similar structures to that of 2 and 3. For example, the signals of an alkenyl group on the bicyclo [3.1.1]heptane ring and a 10,11-dihydroxy group on the pentenyl chain. An intensive comparison of the NMR and ECD data to those in literature revealed that they are known xylariterpenoids A (4) and B (5) (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Compound 6 was a yellow viscous oil. The IR spectrum displayed the strong absorption band of an OH stretching at 
3344 cm
1
and the weak absorption band of a C––C stretching at 
1707 cm
1
. At first glance, the 
1
H NMR data of 6 resembled 1 and 3, showing two olefinic signals at 
δ
H
5.71 (m, H-4) and 5.14 (t, 
J
= 6.6, H-10) and four methyl signals at 
δ
H
1.82 (s, H-15), 1.69 (s, H-12), 1.62 (s, H-13) and 1.22 (s, H-14). The 
13
C NMR data also displayed four olefinic signals at 
δ
C
132.1 (C-11), 131.2 (C-3), 126.0 (C-4) and 123.9 (C-10). Two oxygenated methine signals at 
δ
H
4.29 (br s, H-1) and 3.81 (s, H-2) corresponded to 
13
C NMR signals at 
δ
C
72.2 (C-2) and 70.8 (C-1). The COSY correlation of H-9 to H-8 and 
H-10 in
association with the HMBC correlations of 
CH
3
-12,13 to C-10 and C-11, and 
CH
3
-14 to C-6, C-7 and C-8 indicated a 2-hydroxy-6- methylhept-5-en-2-yl chain. The COSY correlations from H-1 to H-6 and the key HMBC correlations of 
CH
3
-15 to C-2, C-3 and C-4, H-1 to C-2, C-3, C-5, C-6 and C-7, H-2 to C-1, C-3, C-4, C-6 and C-15, H-4 to C-2, C-6 and C-15, and H-5 to C-3, C-4 and C-6 confirmed the 3-methylcyclohex-3-ene moiety. This data revealed that 6 was a bisabolol derivative with a substituted 1,2-dihydroxy group. Bisabolol is a precursor that goes through a C2–C7 ring closure to 
<tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
bergamotene (

). The key NOESY correlation of H-1 to H-2 and H-6 (
Fig. 4
), and the broad singlets of H-1 and H-2 (
3
J
H1-H2
≈ 
3
J
H1-H6
≈ 0 Hz), corresponding to the 
cis
form of the dihydroxy group (

), led to the assignment of the relative configuration of 6 as 1 
S
*, 2 
R
* and 6 
S
*. This was supported by a comparison of the multiplicity patterns of H-1 (br s), H-2 (s) and H-6 (m) with four known synthetic compounds with similar core structures (

; 

). It resembled (1 
S
,2 
R
,6 
R
)- 3-methyl-6-(prop-1-en-2-yl)cyclohex-3-ene-1, 2-diol (see Fig. S 
46 in
SI). The absolute configuration was indicated by comparing experimental and calculated ECD spectra (
Fig. 7
). The spectrum showed Cotton effects at 210 (Δ 
ε
= +0.35) and 223 (Δ 
ε
= +0.15) nm, which were similar to the calculated spectrum of (1 
R
,2 
S
,6 
R
, 7 
S
)-6. Based on the above data and the positive ion peak at 
m/z
277.1784 [M+Na] 
+
in HRESIMS accounting for the molecular formula C 
15
H 
22
O (calc. for C 
15
H 
26
O 
3
Na, 277.1784), compound 6 was determined as (1 
R
,2 
S
,6 
R
)-6-(( 
S
)-2-hydroxy-6-methylhept-5-en-2-yl)-3-met hylcyclohex-3-ene-1,2-diol, named (1 
R
,2 
S
,6 
R
,7 
S
)-1,2-dihydroxy- 
α
-bisa bolol.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 7 was identified as 
α
-pyrone derivative, named as 6- [(1 
R
)-1-hydroxy-1-methyl-2-propenyl]-4-methoxy-3-methyl-2 
H
-pyran-2-one. The molecular formula C 
11
H 
14
O 
4
was deduced from the HRESIMS ion peak at 
m/z
233.0791 [M+Na] 
+
(calc. for C 
11
H 
14
O 
4
Na, 233.0790). The IR spectrum showed the broad absorption band of an OH stretching at 
3393 cm
1
and the strong absorption band of an α,β- unsaturated carbonyl group of the 
α
-pyrone ring at 
1677 cm
1
(

). The 4-methoxy-3-methyl-2 
H
-pyran-2-one-6-yl ring was deduced from the 
1
H NMR signals of olefinic at 
δ
H
6.46 (s, H-5), methoxy at 
δ
H
3.91 (s, H-12) and methyl at 
δ
H
1.63 (s, H-7), together with the 
13
C NMR signals of carbonyl lactone at 
δ
C
165.9 (C-2) and olefinic carbons at 
δ
C
166.0 (C-4), 165.1 (C-6), 101.6 (C-3) and 91.7 (C-5). This was supported by HMBC correlations of 
CH
3
-7 to C-2, C-3 and C-4, H-5 to C-4 and C-6, and 
CH
3
O-12 to C-4. The 
1
H NMR data also exhibited a set of olefinic proton signals at 
δ
H
6.15 (dd, 
J
= 17.3, 10.7, H-9), 5.40 (d, 
J
= 17.3, H-10) and 5.24 (d, 
J
= 10.7, H-10), corresponding to 
13
C NMR signals at 
δ
C
140.5 (C-9) and 114.7 (C-10). An oxygenated carbon was observed at 
δ
C
73.7 (C-8). The COSY correlation of H-9 to H-10 and the HMBC correlations of H-10 to C-8 and C-9, and H-11 to C-6, C-8 and C-9 revealed the presence of a 2-hydroxybut-3-en-2-yl chain, substituted at C-6 of the 
α
-pyrone ring. When compared to compounds from literature, 7 closely resembled synthesized 6-[(1 
S
)-1-hydroxy-1-methyl-2-propenyl]-4-meth oxy-3,5-dimethyl-2 
H
-pyran-2-one, except for the lack of a methyl group at C-5 (

). The 8 
R
was assigned based on the [α] 
D
24.7
-99.0 (
c
0.60, CHCl 
3
), in contrast to the reported 
S
configuration ([α] 
D
+120.0, 
c
1.01 CHCl 
3
). The 
α
-pyrone derivatives 8–12 were recognized immediately from their NMR spectra and the data were compared to those in literature. The results showed that they were the known phomopyrone A (8) (

), gulypyrone B (9) (

), 6-(1 
′
,2 
′
-dimethyloxiran-1 
′
-yl)-4-methoxy-3-methyl-2 
H
-pyr an-2-one (10) (

), nectriapyrone (11) (

) and vermopyrone (12) (

).
</p>
         <p>
Nine guaiane-type sesquiterpenes (13–21) were promptly recognized from the NMR spectroscopic patterns as they have been frequently found throughout this Graphostomataceae fungi family (

; 

). There was one undescribed derivative (13) along with eight known compounds, including patchouliguaiol A (14) (

), pogostol (15) (

), xyralanone (16) (

), xylaranol A (17) (

), 
epi
-guaidiol A (18) (

), (1 
R
,4 
S
,5 
S
,7 
R
,10 
R
,11 
S
) -guaiane-10,11,12-triol (19) (

), (1 
R
,4 
S
,5 
S
,7 
R
,10 
R
,11 
R
)-guaiane-10,11,12-triol (20) (

) and graphostromane E (21) (

).
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
of the colorless needle crystals of 13 was deduced from the positive ion peak in HRESIMS at 
m/z
261.1823 [M+Na] 
+
(calc. for C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
Na, 261.1830). The 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) showed characteristic signals of a germinal alkene at 
δ
H
5.03 and 4.69 (1H each, s, H-12) that corresponded to 
13
C NMR signals at 
δ
C
153.3 (C-11) and 107.2 (C-12). Three methyl signals were observed at 
δ
H
1.77 (s, H-13), 1.17 (s, H-14) and 0.90 (d, 
J
= 6.9, H-15). The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 2
) revealed two additional signals of an oxygenated-quaternary carbon at 
δ
C
75.7 (C-7) and 74.1 (C-10). The HMBC correlations of H-12 to C-7 and C-13, and 
CH
3
-13 to C-7, C-11 and C-12 suggested a prop-1-en-2-yl fragment, substituted at the oxygenated C-7. The presence of a bicyclo [5.3.0]decane ring of a guaiane skeleton was demonstrated through the COSY correlations of H-3 to H-2 and H-4, H-5 to H-1 and H-6, and H-8 to H- 
9 in
association with HMBC correlations of H-1 to C-2 and C-10, H-6 to C-1, C-4, C-5, C-7 and C-8, 
CH
3
-14 to C-1, C-9 and C-10, and 
CH
3
-15 to C-3, C-4 and C-5. An intensive comparison of NMR data to those in literature showed that 13 was close to the known pogostol (15), apart from the presence of an additional hydroxy group at C- 
7 in
13. The relative configuration of 1 
R
*, 4 
S
*, 5 
S
*, 7 
S
* and 10 
R
* was confirmed by X-ray diffraction analysis (Mo Kα, see Supplementary data) (
Fig. 8
). Therefore, 13 was assigned as 7-hydroxyprogostol, named (1 
R
*,4 
S
*,5 
S
*,7 
S
*,10 
R
*)-guaia-11 (12)-en-7,10-diol.
</p>
         <p>
The intensive comparison of NMR data, specific optical rotation values, and MS data to those in literature showed that the other isolated compounds were 5-methylmellein (22) (

), 7-hydroxy-5-methoxy-4,6-dimethylphthalide (23) (

), 
p
-tyrosol (24) (

), and 5-hydroxy-2-prenylhydroquinone (25) (

), four cyclic dipeptides (diketopiperazine); cyclo (
ʟ
-Pro- 
ʟ
-Val) (26) (

), cyclo (
ʟ
-Pro-Gly) (27), cyclo (
ʟ
-Pro- 
ʟ
-Leu) (28) (

) and cyclo (
ʟ
-Pro- 
ʟ
-Phe) (29) (

), and four steroids; ergone (30) (

), ergosterol (31) (

), ergosterol peroxide (32) (

) and cerevisterol (33) (

). It is worth mentioning that a mixture of 34 and 35 was determined based on the HRESIMS displaying two major peaks at 
m/z
748.5397 (96.3) and 776.5675 (100) even though the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data suggested the existence of one cerebroside derivative. These ion peaks corresponded to [M+Na] 
+
of cerebroside A (calc. for C 
41
H 
75
NO 
9
Na, 748.5340) and cerebroside C (calc. for C 
43
H 
79
NO 
9
Na 776.5653) (

). To support the assumption, methanolysis of the mixture was performed to assign the C-2 
ʹ
configuration and the lengths of the fatty acid fragments (see Supplementary data). The HRESIMS results of the metanolysed products displayed two main ion peaks [M+Na] 
+
at 
m/z
327.0076 (89.7) and 335.2567 (100), which belonged to the sodium adduct ion of methyl 2-hydroxyhexadec-3-enoate (calc. for C 
17
H 
32
O 
3
Na, 327.2249, the fatty acid fragment of cerebroside A) and methyl 2-hydroxyoctadec-3-enoate (calc. for C 
19
H 
36
O 
3
Na, 335.2562, the fatty acid fragment of cerebroside C). Moreover, the specific optical rotation of the metanolysed products was [α] 
D
26.2
-3.0 (
c
0.60 CHCl 
3
), which corresponds to the 2 
R
configuration found in literature ([α] 
D
27
-5.1, CHCl 
3
) (

).
</p>
         <p>
The NO production inhibition and anti-proliferative activity against HeLa, HT116, HT29, and MCF-7 cancer cells, and normal Vero cell lines were evaluated (
Table 3
). The results showed that compounds 1, 3, 6, 15–17, 23 and a mixture of 34 and 35 exhibited a considerable inhibitory effect on NO production in the range of 2.48 ± 0.23 to 10.82 ± 1.3 
μ
g/mL. In addition, 1, 15, 17 and 23 were among the most toxic compounds against HeLa cells with an IC 
50
range between 8.64 ± 1.22 and 31.16 ± 4.12 
μ
g/mL, while some of the compounds showed a broad spectrum of toxicity towards all cancer cells.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
Thirty-five compounds were determined from fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
13-085. They were structurally categorized into bergamotenes (1–6), 
α
-pyrones (7–12), guaianoids (13–21), mullein (22), phthalide (23), phenolics (24–25), cyclic dipeptides (26–29), steroids (30–33) and cerebrosides (34 and 35). Among them, there were six undescribed compounds including xylariterpenoid L (1), xylariterpenoid M (2), xylariterpenoid N (3), (1 
R
,2 
S
,6 
R
,7 
S
)-1,2-dihydroxy-α- bisabolol (6), 6- [(1 
R
)-1-hydroxy-1-methyl-2-propenyl]-4-methoxy-3-methyl-2 
H
-pyran-2-one (7) and (1 
R
*,4 
S
*,5 
S
*,7 
S
*,10 
R
*)-guaia-11 (12)-en-7,10-diol (13). The evaluation of the inhibition of NO production and anti-proliferative activity revealed that the isolated compounds from this fungus such as 16 and 23 were potential anti-inflammatory agents for a number of known diseases. Compound 23 was most effective in decreasing NO levels and it was specifically toxic against HeLa cells, making it a possible candidate that could be developed specifically for this 
type
of cancer. Some of the compounds e.g. 1, 15, 17 and 23 exhibited both inhibition of NO production and anti-proliferative activity, which could be used to develop broad-spectrum anti-inflammatory and anti-cancer drugs. These results led to the conclusion that the fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia
</tp:taxon-name>
is a potential source of anti-inflammatory, chemopreventive and chemotherapeutic agents that should be further explored in terms of increasing the production of active compounds and molecular level studies.
</p>
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
Melting points were measured using a Sanyo/Gallenkamp MPD350. BM3.5 melting point apparatus. A JASCO DIP-1000 digital polarimeter was used to record optical rotation values. ECD and UV spectra were obtained from a JASCO J-810 circular dichroism spectropolarimeter. IR spectra were determined by a Bruker TENSOR27 FT-IR spectrometer. NMR spectra were recorded on Varian Mercury Plus 400 and Bruker 400 NMR spectrometers (400 MHz). High-resolution electrospray ionization mass spectra (HRESIMS) were measured on a micrOTOF Bruker mass spectrometer. The X-ray crystal data was collected on a Bruker D8 Quest PHOTON100 CMOS diffractometer with graphite-monochromated MoKα radiation (λ = 0.71073). For chromatographic separation, silica gel 60 (
0.063
–0.200
mm and 

0.040
–0.063
mm

, Merck, 
Germany
) were used for column chromatography (CC) and flash column chromatography (FCC). Sephadex LH-20 (Sigma-Aldrich, 
United States
) was used as the stationary phase for gel filtration chromatography. Preparative thin-layer chromatography (PLC) was performed using silica gel PF254 (Merck, 
Germany
) as the stationary phase.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Fungal material
</title>
         <p>

The fungal stromata were collected in 

August 2009

from corticated wood at 
Phu Khieo Wildlife Sanctuary
in 
Chaiyaphum Province
, 
Thailand
(

16 
◦
22 
ʹ
48.0 
ʺ
N


101 
◦
34 
ʹ
16.0 
ʺ
E

). The fungal strain was identified by the morphological characteristics and molecular data (see Supplementary data). The nucleotide sequence analysis of 5 loci, ITS (
MW403821
), LSU (
MZ452416
), α- actin (
MZ466385
), β- tubulin (
MZ466386
), rpb2 (
MZ466387
) confirmed that it is a new species and was named as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Biscogniauxia whalleyi
SWUF
</tp:taxon-name>
13-085. The specimen has been deposited in GenBank (accession number 
MW403821
) and MycroBank (accession number 
MB840293
). It is maintained at the Srinakharinwirot University Fungal Herbarium (SWUF) with the associated number of SWUF13-085

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Fermentation, extraction, and isolation
</title>
         <p>
The fungal stroma was cultivated on potato dextrose agar (PDA) for 45 days. The pure cultures were then cut into small pieces and inoculated into yeast-malt extract (YM) liquid medium (yeast extract (
3 g
/L), malt extract (
3 g
/L), peptone (
5 g
/L), and dextrose (
10 g
/L)) and kept at room temperature for 45 days. Next, the culture solution (71 L in total) was filtered to obtain the mycelium and the broth. The broth was repeatedly extracted 3 times by EtOAc and solvent was removed to yield crude EtOAc extract (
8.61 g
). The dried mycelium (
124.14 g
) was ground into a powder and extracted by hexane, EtOAc, and MeOH (1200 mL × 3 for each with reused solvent) to give crude hexane (
1.87 g
, 1.51%), EtOAc (
2.51 g
, 2.02%) and MeOH (
21.92 g
, wet weight) extracts.
</p>
         <p>
The separation procedures of the undescribed compounds (1–3, 6–7, and 13) are explained herein (for known compounds, see Supplementary data). The broth’ s EtOAc extract was fractionated on CC, eluted with a gradient system of hexane-EtOAc (stepwise from 100:0 to 0:100 v/v) and then EtOAc-MeOH (stepwise from 100:0 to 0:100 v/v) to yield 5 fractions (BE 
1
-BE 
5
). Fraction BE 
2
(
384.1 mg
) was separated on FCC, eluted with hexane-EtOAc (9.5:0.5 v/v) to obtain 
1 in
BE 
2.1
(
26.4 mg
) along with 8 fractions (BE 
2.2
-BE 
2.9
). The separation of BE 
2.6
(
92.1 mg
) was carried out on PLC, developed with hexane-acetone (4:1 v/v) to obtain BE 
2.6.1
and BE 
2.6.2
. Fraction BE 
2.6.1
(
20.5 mg
) was further purified by PLC, developed with hexane-CH 
2
Cl 
2
-EtOAc (5:4:1 v/v), which yielded 3 (
8.8 mg
). Fraction BE 
3
(
1.1678 g
) was chromatographed on FCC, eluted with hexane-EtOAc (stepwise from 100:0 to 0:100 v/v) followed by EtOAc-MeOH (stepwise from 100:0 to 0:100 v/v) to afford 9 fractions (BE 
3.1
-BE 
3.9
). Fraction BE 
3.5
(
363.2 mg
) was a mixture of white amorphous solid and yellow liquid. After filtration, the dried filtrate (
176.1 mg
) was subjected to FCC, eluted with acetone-hexane (1.5:8.5 v/v) to afford 8 fractions (BE 
3.5.1
-BE 
3.5.8
). Fraction BE 
3.5.6
(
16.9 mg
) appeared as a mixture of white amorphous solid and yellow liquid, from which the solid was then filtered out and recrystallized in MeOH– H 
2
O (20:1 v/v) to yield 13 (9.0 mg). Fraction BE 
3.7
(
283.3 mg
) was fractionated on FCC, eluted with hexane-CH 
2
Cl 
2
-acetone (5:4:1 v/v) to obtain BE 
3.7.1
-BE 
3.7.17
. Compound 7 (
5.5 mg
) was obtained from BE 
3.7.7
(
56.1 mg
), which was subjected to FCC, eluted with hexane-acetone (7:3 v/v) and then purified on Sephadex LH-20, eluted with MeOH. Fraction BE 
3.7.12
(43.0 g) was fractionated on FCC, eluted with hexane-acetone (3:1 v/v) to obtain 6 (
10.8 mg
). The fractionation of BE 
4
(
1.6349 g
) was carried out on FCC, eluted with hexane-EtOAc (stepwise from 100:0 to 0:100 v/v) and then EtOAc-MeOH (stepwise from 100:0 to 0:100 v/v) to afford BE 
4.1
-BE 
4.17
. Compound 2 (
17.2 mg
) was obtained from BE 
4.13.6
(
88.8 mg
) when purified on Sephadex LH-20, eluted with MeOH.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ND = not determined.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
(p 
&lt;
0.001 vs control).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
IC values referred to the concentration that cause 50% inhibition of NO production in LPS-induced RAW246.7 macrophage cells.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
50
b
IC values referred to the concentration that exhibited 50% of cell viability at 72 h, reported as mean ± SD (
μ
g/mL).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
50
c
Positive control for anti-proliferative activity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
d
Positive control for inhibitory effect on NO production.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.3.1. Xylariterpenoid L (1) [(1R,2R,4R,6S,7S)-2,7-dimethyl-7-(4- methylpent-3-en-1-yl)-3-oxatricyclo[
4.1.1.02

,4
]octan-5-one]
</title>
         <p>
Yellow viscous oil; [α] 
26.3
-116.9 (
c
0.60 EtOAc); UV (CHCl) 
λ
D 3 max
(log 
ε
) 220 (1.96), 324 (1.18) nm; ECD (CHCl 
3
) λ (Δ 
ε
) 324 (+0.03), 228 (+0.01), 216 (0.03), 208 (+0.03) nm; IR 
ν
max
2966, 2828, 1711, 1445, 1409, 1312, 
1274, 825, 785 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
257.1519 [M+Na] 
+
(calc. for C H O Na, 
15
22 2
257.1517).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.3.2. Xylariterpenoid M (2) [(1R,2R,4R,6S,7S)-7-(3,4-dihydroxy-4- methylpentyl)-2,7-dimethy-3-oxatricyclo[
4.1.1.02

,4
]octan-5-one]
</title>
         <p>
Yellow viscous oil; [α] 
27.3
-48.6 (
c
0.35, EtOAc); UV (CHCl) 
λ
D 3 max
(log 
ε
) 219 (2.60), 330 (1.90) nm; ECD (CHCl 
3
) λ (Δ 
ε
) 338 (+0.02), 224 (+0.01), 213 (0.03), 210 (+0.06) nm; IR 
ν
max
3403, 2969, 2931, 1705, 1446, 1381, 1159, 
1069, 825, 785 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
291.1573 [M+Na] 
+
(calc. for C 
15
H 
24
O 
4
Na, 291.1572).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. Xylariterpenoid N (3) [(1S,5S,6S)-4,6-dimethyl-6-(4-methylpent-3-
en-1-yl)bicyclo[3.1.1]hept-3-en-2-one]
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Colorless viscous oil; [α] 
26.2
-112.8 (
c
0.85, EtOAc); UV (CHCl) 
D 3
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 261 (2.10) nm; ECD (CHCl 
3
) λ (Δ 
ε
) 346 (0.28), 222 (+0.05), 210 (+0.14) nm; IR 
ν
max
2964, 2931, 1678, 1616, 1436, 
1377 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
219.1743 [M+H] 
+
(calc. for C H O, 219.1749). 
15
23
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.4. (1R,2S,6R,7S)-1,2-dihydroxy-α- bisabolol (6)
</title>
         <p>
Yellow viscous oil, [α] 
D
26.2
-37.4 (
c
0.65, EtOAc); UV (CHCl 
3
) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 217 (2.57) nm; ECD (CHCl 
3
) λ (Δ 
ε
) 210 (+0.35), 223 (+0.15) nm; IR 
ν
max
3344, 2967, 2917, 1707, 1441, 1376, 
1015, 909, 828 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
277.1784 [M+Na] 
+
(calc. for C 
15
H 
26
O 
3
Na, 277.1784).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.3.5. 6-[(1R)-1-Hydroxy-1-methyl-2-propenyl]-4-methoxy-3-methyl-2 
H-pyran-

2-one (7)
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
White waxy solid; [α] 
26.5
-59.5 (
c
0.85, EtOAc); UV (CHCl) 
λ
D 3 max
(log 
ε
) 299 (2.55) nm; ECD (CHCl 
3
) λ (Δ 
ε
) 204 (0.21), 216 (+0.06), 265 (0.04) nm; IR 
ν
max
3393, 2931, 1677, 1639, 1563, 1463, 1387, 1342, 1246, 
1154, 823 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
233.0791 [M+Na] 
+
(calc. for C H O Na, 233.0790). 
11 14
4
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.6. (1R*,4S*,5S*,7S*,10R*)-guaia-11(12)-en-7,10-diol (13)
</title>
         <p>
Colorless needle crystals; m. p. 109.0–111.0 
◦
C; [α] 
D
26.3
-68.9 (
c
0.60, EtOAc); UV (CHCl 
3
) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 257 (2.12) nm; ECD (CHCl 
3
) λ (Δ 
ε
) 204 (+0.12), 305 (0.07) nm; IR 
ν
max
3292, 2950, 2871, 1642, 1452, 1373, 1064, 
1050, 901 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
261.1823 [M+Na] 
+
(calc. for C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
Na, 261.1830).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. ECD calculation
</title>
         <p>
The conformational analysis of 1, 3 and 6 was performed using HyperChem software (HyperChem™ Professional 8.0.7, Hypercube, Inc., Gainesville, FL, 
USA
) under molecular mechanics force field through the Monte Carlo simulation protocol. Selected conformers with Boltzmann distribution higher than 10% distribution were optimized using the density functional theory (DFT) at the B3LYP/6-311G (d) basis set (

). The ECD calculations were carried out by Gaussian 09 software with the time-dependent density functional theory (TD-DFT) method using CAM-B3LYP/6–311++G (d,p) and the Conductor-like Polarizable Continuum Model (C-PCM) was used for solvent effects (CHCl 
3
and MeOH for ECD calculations) (

; 

; 

). The calculated ECD spectra were generated by the GaussSum program.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. X-ray crystallographic analysis
</title>
         <p>
Colorless needle crystals of 13 were obtained in MeOH: H 
2
O (20:1 v/ v). The diffraction data were integrated using SAINT (Bruker-AXS, 2000). The multiscan absorption corrections were conducted using the SADABS program (

). The structure was solved by intrinsic phasing using SHELXT (Apex2 program suite) (

) and refined by the full-matrix least-squares methods using SHELXTL (

), with the ShelXle user interface (

). All non-hydrogen atoms were refined anisotropically while the H-atoms were located on calculated positions. The crystallographic data was deposited with CCDC No. 2000936. These data can be obtained free of charge from the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre (CCDC) via http://www.ccdc.cam.ac.uk/data_request/cif.
</p>
         <p>
Crystallographic data for 13: C 
15
H 
26
O 
2
, M = 238.36, orthorhombic, 
a
= 8.994 (4) Å, 
b
= 16.191 (9) Å, c = 20.127 (11) Å, α = 90 
◦
, β = 90 
◦
, γ = 90 
◦
, V = 2931 (3) Å 
3
, 
T
= 298 (2) K, space group P 
212121
, Z = 8, 
D
calc
= 
1.080 g
/cm 
3
, F (000) = 1056.0, μ(Mo Kα) = 
0.069 mm
1
, 77,615 reflections collected, 5173 independent reflections (
Rint
= 0.5388). The goodness-of-fit on F 
2
was 0.982. The final 

R 
1

index was 0.0763 (I ≥ 2σ (I)). The final 

wR 
2

index was 0.1044 (I ≥ 2σ (I)). The final 

R 
1

index was 0.2616 (all data) and final 
wR2
index was 0.1485 (all data).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Cell culture
</title>
         <p>
HeLa, HT29, HCT116, MCF-7, Vero and RAW264.7 cells were cultured in RPMI-1640 medium, supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 
μ
g/mL streptomycin (Gibco-BRL). The cell culture was further incubated with an atmosphere of 95% air and 5% CO 
2
at 37 
◦
C in a humidified incubator.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Anti-proliferative activity against cancer cell lines
</title>
         <p>
The anti-proliferative activity against HeLa, HT29, HCT116, MCF-7 and Vero cells was carried out by MTT colorimetric assay, following a previously described protocol (

). The IC 
50
value was considered as the concentrations that exhibited 50% cell viability for 72 h. Cisplatin was used as a positive control.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Determination of NO production
</title>
         <p>
The cytotoxicity of compounds against RAW 264.7 cells was evaluated by MTT method to avoid a false result for the inhibition of NO production. The 85% cell viability result of the RAW 264.7 cells compared to the control (treated with only DMSO) allowed the compound to be used for further experimentation. Then, the RAW264.7 cells (2 × 
104
cells/well) were cultured on 96-well plates for 24 h and then treated with selected compounds for 2 h. Lipopolysaccharide (LPS, 1 
μ
g/ mL) was added to the culture media, which was then incubated for 24 h. The level of NO in the media was determined by measuring the accumulation of nitrite (NO 
2
ˉ
), a stable product of NO, using Griess reagent. The supernatant was mixed with an equal volume of Griess reagent (0.1% 
N
-(1-naphthyl)-ethylenediamine dihydrochloride and 1% sulfanilic acid in 5% phosphoric acid) in each well followed by incubation for 10 min; this was followed by the recording of UV absorbance at 
550 nm
. The concentration of nitrite was assessed by comparisons with a standard curve of sodium nitrite solution. The IC 
50
value was defined as the concentration that expressed 50% inhibition of NO production. 
N
G
- Monomethyl-L-arginine (L-NMMA), a nitric oxide synthase (NOS) inhibitor, was used as a positive control.
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgement
</p>
         <p>
We would like to gratefully acknowledge Graduate School, 
Khon Kaen
University and the Center of Excellence for Innovation in Chemistry (PERCH-CIC), Ministry of Higher Education, Science, Research and Innovation, for their financial support.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112908.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Amand, S.
, 
Langenfeld, A.
, 
Blond, A.
, 
Dupont, J.
, 
Nay, B.
, 
Prado, S.
, 
2012
. 

Guaiane sesquiterpenes from 
Biscogniauxia nummularia
featuring potent antigerminative activity

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
75
, 
798–801
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np2009913
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Andolfi, A.
, 
Boari, A.
, 
Evidente, M.
, 
Cimmino, A.
, 
Vurro, M.
, 
Ash, G.
, 
Evidente, A.
, 
2015
. 

Gulypyrones A and B and phomentrioloxins B and C produced by 
Diaporthe gulyae
, a potential mycoherbicide for saffron thistle (
Carthamus lanatus
)

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
78
, 
623–629
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np500570h
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ardashov, O.V.
, 
Pavlova, A.V.
, Il’ ina, I.V., 
Morozova, E.A.
, 
Korchagina, D.V.
, 
Karpova, E. V.
, 
Volcho, K.P.
, 
Tolstikova, T.G.
, 
Salakhutdinov, N.F.
, 
2011
. 

Highly potent activity of (1 
R
,2 
R
,6 
S
)-3-methyl-6-(prop-1-en-2-yl)cyclohex-3-ene-1,2-diol in animal models of Parkinson’ s disease

. 
J. Med. Chem.
54
, 
3866–3874
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ jm2001579
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Barra, L.
, 
Schulz, B.
, 
Dickschat, J.S.
, 
2014
. 

Pogostol biosynthesis by the endophytic fungus 
Geniculosporium

. 
Chembiochem
15
, 
2379–2383
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ cbic.201402298
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Becke, A.D.
, 
1993
. 
Density-functional thermochemistry. III. The role of exact exchange
. 
J. Chem. Phys.
98
, 
5648–5652
. 

https://doi.org/ 
10.1063
/ 
1.464913

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Becker, K.
, 
Stadler, M.
, 
2021
. 
Recent progress in biodiversity research on the Xylariales and their secondary metabolism. J
. 
Antibiot. (Tokyo)
74
, 
1–23
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1038/s41429-020-00376-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bruker-AXS, I., 
2000
. 
SAINT 4.0 Software Reference Manual
(
Madison, WI
, 
USA
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cai, R.
, 
Chen, S.
, 
Liu, Z.
, 
Tan, C.
, 
Huang, X.
, 
She, Z.
, 
2017
. 

A new 
α
-pyrone from the mangrove endophytic fungus 
Phomopsis
sp. HNY29-2B.

Nat. Prod. Res.
31
, 
124–130
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/14786419.2016.1214833
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Campbell, J.
, 
Lin, Q.
, 
Geske, G.D.
, 
Blackwell, H.E.
, 
2009
. 
New and unexpected insights into the modulation of LuxR-type quorum sensing by cyclic dipeptides
. 
ACS Chem. Biol.
4
, 
1051–1059
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/cb900165y
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chien, Y.C.
, 
Lin, C.H.
, 
Chiang, M.Y.
, 
Chang, H.S.
, 
Liao, C.H.
, 
Chen, I.S.
, 
Peng, C.F.
, 
Tsai, I. L.
, 
2012
. 

Secondary metabolites from the root of 
Ehretia longiflora
and their biological activities

. 
Phytochemistry
80
, 
50–57
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2012.04.013
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Choudhari, S.K.
, 
Chaudhary, M.
, 
Bagde, S.
, 
Gadbail, A.R.
, 
Joshi, V.
, 
2013
. 
Nitric oxide and cancer: a review. World J
. 
Surg. Oncol.
11
, 
118
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/1477- 7819-11-118
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cossi, M.
, 
Rega, N.
, 
Scalmani, G.
, 
Barone, V.
, 
2003
. 
Energies, structures, and electronic properties of molecules in solution with the C-PCM solvation model
. 
J. Comput. Chem.
24
, 
669–681
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/jcc.10189
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cragg, G.M.
, 
Pezzuto, J.M.
, 
2016
. 
Natural products as a vital source for the discovery of cancer chemotherapeutic and chemopreventive agents. Med. Princ. Pract. 25
(
Suppl.
2
), 
41–59
. 
https://doi.org/10.1159/000443404
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Elrayess, R.A.
, 
Gad El-Hak, H.N.
, 
2019
. 
Anticancer natural products: a review
. 
Cancer Stud. Mol. Med. Open J.
5
, 
11–22
. 
https://doi.org/10.17140/csmmoj-5-127
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frisch, M.J.
, 
Trucks, G.W.
, 
Schlegel, H.B.
, 
Scuseria, G.E.
, 
Robb, M.A.
, 
Cheeseman, J.R.
, 
Scalmani, G.
, 
Barone, V.
, 
Petersson, G.A.
, 
Nakatsuji, H.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Caricato, M.
, 
Marenich, A.
, 
Bloino, J.
, 
Janesko, B.G.
, 
Gomperts, R.
, 
Mennucci, B.
, 
Hratchian, H.P.
, 
Ortiz, J.V.
, 
Izmaylov, A.F.
, 
Sonnenberg, J.L.
, 
Williams-Young, D.
, 
Ding, F.
, 
Lipparini, F.
, 
Egidi, F.
, 
Goings, J.
, 
Peng, B.
, 
Petrone, A.
, 
Henderson, T.
, 
Ranasinghe, D.
, 
Zakrzewski, V.G.
, 
Gao, J.
, R, N., 
Zheng, G.
, 
Liang, W.
, 
Hada, M.
, 
Ehara, M.
, 
Toyota, K.
, 
Fukuda, R.
, 
Hasegawa, J.
, 
Ishida, M.
, 
Nakajima, T.
, 
Honda, Y.
, 
Kitao, O.
, 
Nakai, H.
, 
Vreven, T.
, 
Throssell, K.
, 
J A
Montgomery, J.
, 
Peralta, J.E.
, 
Ogliaro, F.
, 
Bearpark, M.
, 
Heyd, J.J.
, 
Brothers, E.
, 
Kudin, K.N.
, 
Staroverov, V.N.
, 
Keith, T.
, 
Kobayashi, R.
, 
Normand, J.
, 
Raghavachari, K.
, 
Rendell, A.
, 
Burant, J.C.
, 
Iyengar, S.S.
, 
Tomasi, J.
, 
Cossi, M.
, 
Millam, J.M.
, 
Klene, M.
, 
Adamo, C.
, 
Cammi, R.
, 
Ochterski, J.W.
, 
Martin, R.L.
, 
Morokuma, K.
, 
Farkas, O.
, 
Foresman, J.B.
, 
Fox, D.J.
, 
2010
. 
Gaussian 09, Revision B
. 01. 
Gaussian Inc., Wallingford, CT
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Furtadoa, N.A.J.C.
, 
Pupoa, M.T.
, 
Carvalhoa, I.
, 
Campoa, V.L.
, 
Duarteb, M.C.T.
, 
Bastos, J. K.
, 
2005
. 

Diketopiperazines produced by an 
Aspergillus fumigatus
Brazilian strain

. 
J. Braz. Chem. Soc.
16
, 
1448–1453
. 
https://doi.org/10.1590/S0103- 50532005000800026
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gegechkori, N.
, 
Haines, L.
, 
Lin, J.J.
, 
2017
. 
Long-term and latent side effects of specific cancer types
. 
Med. Clin.
101
, 
1053–1073
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. mcna.2017.06.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Geiseler, O.
, 
Podlech, J.
, 
2012
. 

Total synthesis of infectopyrone, aplysiopsenes A–C, 
ent
- aplysiopsene D, phomapyrones A and D, 8,9-dehydroxylarone, and nectriapyrone

. 
Tetrahedron
68
, 
7280–7287
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tet.2012.06.104
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Glynn, S.A.
, 
2019
. 
Emerging novel mechanisms of action for nitric oxide in cancer progression
. 
Curr. Opin. Physiol.
9
, 
18–25
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. cophys.2019.03.010
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gong, T.
, 
Zhen, X.
, 
Li, B.J.
, 
Yang, J.L.
, 
Zhu, P.
, 
2015
. 

Two new monoterpenoid 
α
-pyrones from a fungus 
Nectria
sp. HLS206 associated with the marine sponge 
Gelliodes carnosa
. J

. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
17
, 
633–637
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 10286020.2015.1040778
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Greten, F.R.
, 
Grivennikov, S.I.
, 
2019
. 
Inflammation and cancer: triggers, mechanisms, and consequences
. 
Immunity
51
, 
27–41
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. immuni.2019.06.025
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hatayama, S.
, 
Ochi, N.
, 
Takano, S.
, 
1993
. 

Enantioselective synthesis of the 
α
-pyrone subunit of verrucosidin

. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull. (Tokyo)
41
, 
1358–1361
. 
https://doi. org/10.1248/cpb.41.1358
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hubschle, C.B.
, 
Sheldrick, G.M.
, 
Dittrich, B.
, 
2011
. 
ShelXle: a Qt graphical user interface for SHELXL
. 
J. Appl. Crystallogr.
44
, 
1281–1284
. 
https://doi.org/10.1107/ S0021889811043202
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jia, Y.-L.
, 
Guan, F.-F.
, 
Ma, J.
, 
Wang, C.-Y.
, 
Shao, C.-L.
, 
2015
. 

Pestalotiolide A, a new antiviral phthalide derivative from a soft coral-derived fungus 
Pestalotiopsis
sp

. 
Nat. Prod. Sci.
21
, 
227–230
. 
https://doi.org/10.20307/nps.2015.21.4.227
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kaiser, J.
, 
2020
. 
New forms of ‘red devil’ cancer drug could spare hearts
. 
Science
. 
https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abd6024
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Khaopha, S.
, 
Jogloy, S.
, 
Patanothai, A.
, 
Senawong, T.
, 
2015
. 
Histone deacetylase inhibitory activity of peanut testa extracts against human cancer cell lines. J
. 
Food Biochem.
39
, 
263–273
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jfbc.12128
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kim, H.J.
, 
Su, L.
, 
Jung, H.
, 
Koo, S.
, 
2011
. 
Selective deoxygenation of allylic alcohol: stereocontrolled synthesis of lavandulol
. 
Org. Lett.
13
, 
2682–2685
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/ol200779y
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Koga, J.
, 
Yamauchi, T.
, 
Shimura, M.
, 
Ogawa, N.
, 
Oshima, K.
, 
Umemura, K.
, 
Kikuchi, M.
, 
Ogasawara, N.
, 
1998
. 
Cerebrosides A and C, sphingolipid elicitors of hypersensitive cell death and phytoalexin accumulation in rice plants
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
273
, 
31985–31991
. 
https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.273.48.31985
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kroschinsky, F.
, 
Stolzel, F.
, 
von Bonin, S.
, 
Beutel, G.
, 
Kochanek, M.
, 
Kiehl, M.
, 
Schellongowski, P.
, 
2017
. 
New drugs, new toxicities: severe side effects of modern targeted and immunotherapy of cancer and their management. Crit
. 
Care
21
, 
89
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/s13054-017-1678-1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Krzyczkowski, W.
, 
Malinowska, E.
, 
Suchocki, P.
, 
Kleps, J.
, 
Olejnik, M.
, 
Herold, F.
, 
2009
. 
Isolation and quantitative determination of ergosterol peroxide in various edible mushroom species
. 
Food Chem.
113
, 
351–355
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. foodchem.2008.06.075
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lee, W.Y.
, 
Park, Y.
, 
Ahn, J.-K.
, 
Park, S.-Y.
, 
Lee, H.-J.
, 
2005
. 

Cytotoxic activity of ergosta-4,6,8(14),22-tetraen-3-one from the sclerotia of 
Polyporus umbellatus

. 
Bull. Kor. Chem. Soc.
26
, 
1464–1466
. 
https://doi.org/10.5012/bkcs.2005.26.9.1464
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, Y.-Y.
, 
Hu, Z.-Y.
, 
Lu, C.-H.
, 
Shen, Y.-M.
, 
2010
. 

Four new terpenoids from 
Xylaria
sp

. 101. 
Helv. Chim. Acta
93
, 
796–802
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/hlca.200900296
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, Y.
, 
Zhang, F.
, 
Banakar, S.
, 
Li, Z.
, 
2019
. 

Bortezomib-induced new bergamotene derivatives xylariterpenoids H–K from sponge-derived fungus 
Pestalotiopsis maculans
16F-12

. 
RSC Adv.
9
, 
599–608
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/c8ra08209j
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lu, X.
, 
Xu, N.
, 
Dai, H.F.
, 
Mei, W.L.
, 
Yang, Z.X.
, 
Pei, Y.H.
, 
2009
. 

Three new compounds from endophytic fungus L10 of 
Cephalotaxus hainanensis
. J

. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
11
, 
397–400
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/10286020902819947
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Newman, D.J.
, 
Cragg, G.M.
, 
2020
. 
Natural products as sources of new drugs over the nearly four decades from 01/1981 to 09/2019
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
83
, 
770–803
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.9b01285
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niu, S.
, 
Xie, C.-L.
, 
Zhong, T.
, 
Xu, W.
, 
Luo, Z.-H.
, 
Shao, Z.
, 
Yang, X.-W.
, 
2017
. 

Sesquiterpenes from a deep-sea-derived fungus 
Graphostroma
sp. MCCC 3A00421.

Tetrahedron
73
, 
7267–7273
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tet.2017.11.013.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Niu, S.
, 
Xie, C.L.
, 
Xia, J.M.
, 
Luo, Z.H.
, 
Shao, Z.
, 
Yang, X.W.
, 
2018
. 

New anti-inflammatory guaianes from the Atlantic hydrotherm-derived fungus 
Graphostroma
sp. MCCC 3A00421

. 
Sci. Rep.
8
, 
530
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-18841-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Okuno, T.
, 
Oikawa, S.
, 
Goto, T.
, 
Sawai, K.
, 
Shirahama, H.
, 
Matsumoto, T.
, 
2014
. 

Structures and phytotoxicity of metabolites from 
Valsa ceratosperma
.

Agric. Biol. Chem.
50
, 
997–1001
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/00021369.1986.10867484
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Otte, D.A.
, 
Borchmann, D.E.
, 
Lin, C.
, 
Weck, M.
, 
Woerpel, K.A.
, 
2014
. 
13 C NMR spectroscopy for the quantitative determination of compound ratios and polymer end groups
. 
Org. Lett.
16
, 
1566–1569
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ol403776k
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Park, C.H.
, 
Kim, K.H.
, 
Lee, I.K.
, 
Lee, S.Y.
, 
Choi, S.U.
, 
Lee, J.H.
, 
Lee, K.R.
, 
2011
. 

Phenolic constituents of 
Acorus gramineus

. 
Arch Pharm. Res. (Seoul)
34
, 
1289–1296
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1007/s12272-011-0808-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ragasa, C.Y.
, 
Tan, S.
, C, M., 
Castro, M.E.D.
, 
Reyes, M.M.D.L.
, 
Oyong, G.G.
, 
Shen, C.-C.
, 
2018
. 

Sterols from 
Lentinus tigrinus

. 
Phcog. J.
10
, 
1079–1081
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.5530/pj.2018.6.182
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sheldrick, G.M.
, 
2000
. 
SADABS, Program for Empirical Absorption Correction of Area Detector Data
. 
University of G¨ottingen, G¨ottingen, Germany
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sheldrick, G.M.
, 
2015
. 
SHELXT - integrated space-group and crystal-structure determination
. 
Acta Crystallogr. A Found Adv
71
, 
3–8
. 
https://doi.org/10.1107/ S2053273314026370
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shu, R.G.
, 
Wang, F.W.
, 
Yang, Y.M.
, 
Liu, Y.X.
, 
Tan, R.X.
, 
2004
. 

Antibacterial and xanthine oxidase inhibitory cerebrosides from 
Fusarium
sp. IFB-121, an endophytic fungus in 
Quercus variabilis

. 
Lipids
39
, 
667–673
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11745-004-1280-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wendt, L.
, 
Sir, E.B.
, 
Kuhnert, E.
, Heitk¨amper, S., 
Lambert, C.
, 
Hladki, A.I.
, 
Romero, A.I.
, Luangsa-ard, J.J., 
Srikitikulchai, P.
, Perˇsoh, D., 
Stadler, M.
, 
2017
. 
Resurrection and emendation of the Hypoxylaceae, recognised from a multigene phylogeny of the Xylariales
. 
Mycol. Prog.
17
, 
115–154
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11557-017-1311-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
WHO
, 
2020
. 
WHO Report on Cancer: Setting Priorities, Investing Wisely and Providing Care for All
. 
World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wu, S.H.
, 
He, J.
, 
Li, X.N.
, 
Huang, R.
, 
Song, F.
, 
Chen, Y.W.
, 
Miao, C.P.
, 
2014
a. 

Guaiane sesquiterpenes and isopimarane diterpenes from an endophytic fungus 
Xylaria
sp

. 
Phytochemistry
105
, 
197–204
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2014.04.016
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wu, Z.-Y.
, 
Wu, Y.
, 
Chen, G.-D.
, 
Hu, D.
, 
Li, X.-X.
, 
Sun, X.
, 
Guo, L.-D.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
Yao, X.-S.
, 
Gao, H.
, 
2014
b. 
Xylariterpenoids A–D, four new sesquiterpenoids from the Xylariaceae fungus
. 
RSC Adv.
4
, 
54144–54148
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/ c4ra10365c
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, Y.
, 
Zhang, H.W.
, 
Wan, X.C.
, 
Zou, Z.M.
, 
2009
. 

Complete assignments of 1 H and 13 C NMR data for two new sesquiterpenes from 
Cyperus rotundus
L

. 
Magn. Reson. Chem.
47
, 
527–531
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/mrc.2416
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
