<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2023.113587</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Polyneurines A H, iboga alkaloids from Tabernaemontana polyneura</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2023</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Apocynaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana
(Apocynaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
(King &amp; Gamble) D.J. Middleton
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ervatamia polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
(King &amp; Gamble) D.J.Middleton (Apocynaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Polyneurines A H, iboga alkaloids from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Sin-Yee Tang
a
, Chun-Hoe Tan
b, d
, Kae-Shin Sim
b
, Kien-Thai Yong
b
, Kuan-Hon Lim
c
,
Yun-Yee Low 

a, 
**
, Siew-Huah Lim

a, 
*
</p>
         <p>
a
Department of Chemistry
, 
Faculty of Science
, 
Universiti Malaya
, 50603, 
Kuala Lumpur
, 
Malaysia
</p>
         <p>
b
Institute of Biological Sciences
, 
Faculty of Science
, 
Universiti Malaya
, 50603, 
Kuala Lumpur
, 
Malaysia
</p>
         <p>
c
School of Pharmacy
, 
University of Nottingham
Malaysia
, 
Jalan Broga
, 43500, 
Semenyih
, 
Selangor
, 
Malaysia
</p>
         <p>
d
Department of Biotechnology
, 
Faculty of Applied Science
, 
Lincoln University
, 47301, 
Petaling Jaya
, 
Selangor
, 
Malaysia
</p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Apocynaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Iboga</p>
         <p>Alkaloids</p>
         <p>ECD</p>
         <p>DP4+</p>
         <p>X-ray diffraction</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Eight undescribed iboga alkaloids, polyneurines A H, were isolated from the bark of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
. The structures of these alkaloids were established by interpretation of the MS and NMR data, while the configurations were determined using GIAO NMR calculations and DP4+probability analysis, TDDFT-ECD method, or X-ray diffraction analysis. Polyneurine A possesses a 
γ
-lactone unit embedded within the iboga skeleton, while polyneurines D and E incorporate a formylmethyl moiety at C-3 of the iboga skeleton. Biosynthetic pathways towards the formation of polyneurines A, C, D, and E were proposed.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana
(Apocynaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
has a broad distribution over the tropical and subtropical regions of the world, encompassing parts of America, Africa including 
Madagascar
, Asia, Oceania, and 
Australia
(

). Plants of this genus are used in Chinese, Ayurvedic and Thai traditional medicine for the treatment of dysentery, fever, and pain, as well as for the treatment of snakebites in 
Brazil
(

; 

). Previous studies on the chemical constituents of this genus have resulted in the discovery of many new alkaloids, particularly indole and bisindole alkaloids possessing structurally novel skeletons and useful biological activities (

; 

; 

; 

; 

; 

, 

; 

, 

; 

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
(King &amp; Gamble) D.J. Middleton
</tp:taxon-name>
(basionym: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ervatamia polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
) is endemic in Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

). A preliminary phytochemical investigation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
(sample collected at Genting Sempah, 
Selangor
, Peninsular 
Malaysia
) was first reported by Clivio et al., in 1990. Since no further studies of this plant have been reported and in view of our interest in probing the variation of alkaloid content as a function of geographical location in this genus, we initiated a larger scale study of a sample collected in a different location (Fraser’ s Hill, 
Pahang
, Peninsular 
Malaysia
), and herein report the results of the isolated compounds (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
         <p>
Polyneurine A (
1
) was obtained as a light orange oil, [α] 
D
25
44 (
c
0.2, CHCl 
3
). The UV spectrum showed absorption maxima at 226, 284, and 
291 nm
, indicating the presence of an indole chromophore, while the IR spectrum showed absorption bands at 3427 and 
1756 cm
1
, suggesting the presence of NH and 
γ
-lactone functions, respectively. The HRDARTMS data showed an [M + H] 
+
peak at 
m/z
323.1761 corresponding to the molecular formula C 
20
H 
22
N 
2
O 
2
. The 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) showed the presence of an indolic NH (
δ
H
9.59), four aromatic resonances (
δ
H
7.10–7.49) due to an unsubstituted indole moiety, as well as an ethyl side chain (
δ
H
1.03, t, 
J
= 7.5 Hz, Me-18; 
δ
H
1.80, dq, 
J
= 14.5, 7.5 Hz, H-19a; 
δ
H
1.98, dq, 
J
=14.5, 7.5 Hz, H-19 b). The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 2
) showed a total of 20 carbon resonances comprising one methyl, six methylenes, six methines, one ester carbonyl, one tertiary carbon linked to an ester oxygen, two tertiary carbons bonded to indolic nitrogen, and three quaternary carbon atoms. The COSY data revealed the presence of NCH 
2
CH
2
, 
CH
2
CHCH 
2
, and 
CH
2
CH
3
partial structures, corresponding to N–C-5 C-6, C-15 C-14 C-17 and C-19 C-18, respectively (
Fig. 2
). These structural features are reminiscent of the iboga skeleton, e.g., coronaridine (
9
) (

), except for the absence of signals due to H-20 and the ester methyl in 
1
. This is in agreement with the molecular formula of 
1
, which differs from that of 
9
by 16 mass units (
CH
3
+H). In addition, the 
13
C NMR data of 
1
displayed an upfield shift of the C-16 resonance from ca. 
δ
C
55 in
9 to 
δ
C
45.7 in
1
, whereas the signal of C-20 (usually observed at ca. 
δ
C
40 as in 
9
) was significantly shifted downfield to 
δ
C
88.1, likely due to being linked to an oxygen atom. These observations suggested the presence of a lactone bridge that connects C-16 and C-20 (
Fig. 1
), which was confirmed by the three-bond correlations observed from H-17 to 
C
OO, as well as from H-14 to C-16 and C- 
20 in
the HMBC spectrum (
Fig. 2
). The relative configuration of 
1
was deduced to resemble that of coronaridine (
9
) based on the NOE data (
Fig. 3
). The NOEs observed for H-21/H-5 
α
and H-9/H-6 
α
suggested that H-5 
α
, H-6 
α
, and H-21 occupied the same face, whereas the NOEs observed for H-3b/H-5 
β
, H-6 
β
, H-17 
β
and H-3a/H-15 
β
indicated that these protons were cofacial. Similarly, H-17 
α
and H-15 
α
were assigned based on the NOE observed between H-17 
α
and H-15 
α
.
</p>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>** Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>
E-mail addresses:
yylow@um.edu.my (Y.-Y. Low), shlim80@um.edu.my (S.-H. Lim).
</p>
         <p>
A search of the literature revealed that a compound similar to 
1
was obtained as a by-product during a total synthesis of vinblastine (

). Compound 
1
has similar 
1
H and 
13
C NMR, MS, and IR spectroscopic data compared to those of the synthetic compound (
10
) but showed opposite sign for the specific rotation ([α] 
D
25
44 for 

1 
vs

[α] 
D
22
+33 for 
10
), suggesting an enantiomeric relationship between 
1
and 
10
. In any case, the absolute configuration of 
1
was further confirmed by TDDFT-ECD method. The experimental ECD spectrum of 
1
showed high-amplitude negative Cotton effects at 220 and 
245 nm
and positive Cotton effects at 233 and 
288 nm
, which resemble the calculated ECD spectrum of 
1
(
Fig. 4
), leading to the assignment of the absolute configuration of 
1
as (14 
S
, 16 
S
, 20 
R
, 21 
R
). In addition, the experimental ECD data also matches with the experimental ECD data of voacangalactone (
11
), a 10-methoxy derivative of 
1
(

) and this provided further confirmation of the structure and absolute configuration of 
1
. A plausible biosynthetic pathway to 
1
from an iboga precursor, heyneanine (
12
), is shown in 
Fig. 5
. Generation of a secondary carbocation at C-19 followed by a 1,2-H shift provides a tertiary carbocation at C-20, which on nucleophilic attack by a water molecule leads to 
13
. A subsequent intramolecular transesterification furnishes compound 
1
.
</p>
         <p>
Polyneurine B (
2
) was initially isolated as a colorless oil, [α] 
D
25
44 (
c
0.5, CHCl 
3
), and subsequently as colorless plates from CCl 
4
/MeOH (mp 175–177 
ο
C). The UV spectrum showed absorption maxima at 217, 220, 285, and 
292 nm
, indicating the presence of an indole chromophore, while the IR spectrum showed absorption bands at 3258 and 
1716 cm
1
, suggesting the presence of NH/OH and ester carbonyl functions, respectively. The HRESIMS data showed an [M + H] 
+
peak at 
m/z
373.2139, which corresponds to the molecular formula, C 
21
H 
28
N 
2
O 
4
. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (
Tables 1
and 
2
) of 
2
were generally similar to those of 3-hydroxy-3,4- 
seco
coronaridine (
14
) (

), suggesting that they share a similar basic skeleton. The 
1
H NMR data of 
2
showed the presence of an indolic NH (
δ
H
8.55), four aromatic hydrogens (
δ
H
7.07–7.46) and a methyl ester (
δ
H
3.65), while the 
13
C NMR data showed a total of 21 resonances, including the notable downfield shift of the C-3 methylene resonance to 
δ
C
67.3 (which was commonly observed at ca. 
δ
C
52 in
9
), indicating a cleavage of the C-3 N-4 bond and substitution of an OH at C-3. The most pronounced difference in the NMR data between 
2
and 
14
was the presence of a hydroxyethyl group at C- 
20 in
2
, in place of the ethyl side chain in 
14
. This is consistent with the observed oxymethine resonance at 
δ
C
72.0 in the 
13
C NMR spectrum, as well as the signals due to a hydroxyethyl side chain (
δ
H
1.39, d, 
J
= 6.5 Hz, Me-18; 
δ
H
3.86, qd, 
J
= 6.5, 3.0 Hz, H-19) in the 
1
H NMR spectrum. Analysis of the COSY data also revealed the presence of a CHCHCH 
3
fragment in 
2
(
Fig. 2
), in place of the CHCH 
2
CH
3
fragment in 
14
, due to C-20 C-19 C-18. Attachment of the hydroxyethyl side chain at C-20 was further supported by the following three-bond correlations in the HMBC spectrum, viz., from H-19 (
δ
H
3.86) to C-15 (
δ
C
27.7) and C-21 (
δ
C
53.1), as well as from H-18 (
δ
H
1.39) to C-20 (
δ
C
42.3) (
Fig. 2
). The relative configurations at all the stereogenic centers in 
2
, except for C-19, were readily determined via analysis of the NOE data (
Fig. 3
). Since suitable crystals of 
2
were obtained, an X-ray diffraction analysis was carried out, which confirms the structure and the absolute configuration of 
2
as (14 
R
, 16 
S
, 19 
R
, 20 
S
, 21 
S
) (
Fig. 6
).
</p>
         <p>
Polyneurine C (
3
) was isolated as a light yellowish oil, [α] 
D
25
28 (
c
0.2, CHCl 
3
). The UV spectrum showed absorption maxima at 223 and 
286 nm
, indicating the presence of an indole chromophore, while the IR spectrum showed absorption bands at 3374 and 
1726 cm
1
, suggesting the presence of OH/NH and ester carbonyl functions, respectively. The HRESIMS data showed an [M + H] 
+
peak at 
m/z
385.2130, corresponding to the molecular formula, C 
22
H 
28
N 
2
O 
4
. The 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) showed the presence of an indolic NH (
δ
H
7.89), four aromatic resonances of an unsubstituted indole moiety (
δ
H
7.10–7.47), a methyl ester (
δ
H
3.72), and a hydroxyethyl side chain (
δ
H
1.27, d, 
J
= 6.4 Hz, Me-18; 
δ
H
3.88, qd, 
J
=6.4, 3.2 Hz, H-19). The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 2
) showed the presence of one methyl, five methylenes, nine methines, one methyl ester, one ester carbonyl, two tertiary carbons bonded to indolic NH, and three quaternary carbons, for a total of 22 carbon resonances. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data of 
3
showed features typical of iboga alkaloids with some differences, viz., the presence of a hydroxymethyl linked to C-3 and a hydroxyethyl side chain attached to C-20. These observations were supported by the presence of the corresponding oxymethylene (C-3) and oxymethine resonances (C-19), at 
δ
C
60.5 and 70.8, respectively. These assignments were also supported by the HMBC data which showed three-bond correlations from H-24 to C-14, H-15 and H-21 to C-19, and H-18 to C-20 (
Fig. 2
). The relative configuration was determined via analysis of the NOE data (
Fig. 3
) as well as from analysis of the vicinal coupling constants (
Table 1
). The configuration at C-3 was determined to be 
S
based on the NOEs observed between H-3 and H-5 
β
, H-6 
β
, H-17 
β
as well as between H-24 and H-15 
β
(
Fig. 3
). The 
β
-orientation of the hydroxyethyl side chain at C-20 was determined based on the H-15 
α
/H-20 NOE (
Fig. 3
) as well as the observed 
J

15 
α
–20

coupling value of 11.0 Hz, which requires the H-20 
α
/H-15 
α
dihedral angle to be ~0 
◦
(

). The 19 
R
configuration was assigned based on the chemical shifts of H-18 (
δ
H
1.27), H-19 (
δ
H
3.88), H-21 (
δ
H
4.18), and C-21 resonance (
δ
C
54.7), which correspond to those of the 19 
R
series of iboga alkaloids with a 
β
-substituted hydroxyethyl side chain at C-20 (

; 

; 

). The 19 
R
configuration was further confirmed by the Gauge-Including Atomic Orbital (GIAO) NMR calculations and DP4+ probability analysis (

). The experimental NMR data were compared with the calculated 
1
H and 
13
C NMR shifts of 
3
and its C-19 epimer 
3a
, using DP4+ probability analysis. As shown in 
Fig. 7
, compound 
3
with 19 
R
configuration showed DP4+probability score of 100% (based on all NMR data). Finally, the absolute configuration of 
3
was established as (3 
S
, 14 
R
, 16 
S
, 19 
R
, 20 
S
, 21 
S
) based on comparison of the experimental and calculated ECD spectra (
Fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Assignments based on COSY, HSQC, and 1D/2D NOESY; ‘m’ refers to multiplets or overlapped signals.
</p>
         <p>
b
CDCl, 600 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
c
CDCl, 400 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
</p>
         <p>
Polyneurine D (
4
) was isolated in minute amount as a light yellowish oil, [α] 
D
25
36 (
c
0.1, CHCl 
3
). The UV spectrum showed absorption maxima at 225, 285, and 
293 nm
, indicating the presence of an indole chromophore, while the IR spectrum showed absorption bands at 3376, 1725 and 
1718 cm
1
, suggesting the presence of OH/NH, ester, and aldehyde carbonyl functionalities, respectively. The HRESIMS data showed an [M + H] 
+
peak at 
m/z
397.2126, corresponding to the molecular formula, C 
23
H 
28
N 
2
O 
4
, which is 12 mass units higher than that of 
3
. The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 2
) accounted for all 23 carbon resonances, including one methyl, five methylenes, nine methines, one methyl ester, one ester carbonyl, one formyl, two tertiary carbons bonded to indolic NH, and three quaternary carbons. The 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) showed some common features with that of 
3
, viz., an indolic NH (
δ
H
7.85), an unsubstituted indole ring (
δ
H
7.11–7.47), a methyl ester (
δ
H
3.73), and a hydroxyethyl side chain (
δ
H
1.28, d, 
J
=7.0 Hz, Me-18; 
δ
H
3.89, qd, 
J
= 7.0, 2.8 Hz, H-19). However, unlike 
3
, a formylmethyl is attached at C- 
3 in
4
in

place of the hydroxymethyl in 
3
. This is evident from the presence of the aldehyde signal (
δ
H
9.76; 
δ
C
201.4) in 
4
, as well as the upfield shifts observed for C-3 (
δ
C
53.6 in

4 
vs δ
C
60.5 in
3
) and C-24 (
δ
C
46.3 in

4 
vs δ
C
62.0 in 
3
). Furthermore, the COSY data (
Fig. 2
) revealed an extended spin system NCHCH 
2
CHO, corresponding to the N-4 C-3 C-24 CHO partial structure. These observations were also consistent with the HMBC data which showed three-bond correlations from the formyl hydrogen to C-3 and from H-3 to the formyl carbon (
Fig. 2
). The relative configuration at C-3 was deduced to be 
R
based on the observed NOE interactions for H-24/H-15 
β
and H-3/H-5 
β
, H-17 
β
(
Fig. 3
). The relative configurations of the remaining stereogenic centers were similar to those in 
3
, based on comparison of the NOE as well as chemical shift data. Similar to 
3
, the 19 
R
configuration was assigned based on the chemical shifts of H-18 (
δ
H
1.28), H-19 (
δ
H
3.89), H-21 (
δ
H
4.14), and C-21 resonance (
δ
C
55.0) (
vide supra
). In addition, the GIAO NMR calculations and DP4+ analysis supported 
4
with 19 
R
configuration as the correct relative configuration, with 100% DP4+ probability (all data) (
Fig. 7
). Finally, the absolute configuration of 
4
was established as (3 
R
, 14 
R
, 16 
S
, 19 
R
, 20 
S
, 21 
S
) based on comparison of the experimental and calculated ECD spectra (
Fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
Polyneurine E (
5
) was obtained in minute amount as a light orange oil, [α] 
D
25
29 (
c
0.1, CHCl 
3
). The UV spectrum of 
5
showed typical indole absorption maxima at 227, 286, and 
293 nm
, while the IR spectrum showed absorption bands due to NH (
3378 cm
1
), ester (
1726 cm
1
), and aldehyde carbonyl (
1717 cm
1
) functions. The HRESIMS ([M +H] 
+
m/z
381.2174) data established the molecular formula of 
5
as C 
23
H 
28
N 
2
O 
3
, which is 16 mass units less than 
4
, suggesting a deoxy derivative of 
4
. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (
Tables 1
and 
2
) of 
5
showed similarities with those of 
4
, such as the presence of a formyl group (
δ
H
9.77; 
δ
C
202.5), an indolic NH (
δ
H
7.80), four aromatic hydrogens (
δ
H
7.09–7.47), and a methyl ester group (
δ
H
3.71; 
δ
C
52.7, 175.4). The only notable difference in the 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data between 
5
and 
4
was the replacement of signals due to the hydroxyethyl side chain present in 
4
with signals due to an ethyl side chain in 
5
. This observation was also consistent with the presence of a fragment, 
CH
2
CHCH 
2
CHCH 
2
CH
3
, which corresponds to the C-17 C-14 C-15 C-20 C-19 C-18 partial structure (
Fig. 2
). Ethyl side chain substitution at C-20 was also indicated from the HMBC data (
Fig. 2
), which showed the following three-bond correlations, H-18/C-20, H-15/C-19, and H-19/C-21. Examination of the NOE data (
Fig. 3
) of 
5
showed that its relative configuration was similar to those of 
3
and 
4
. The absolute configuration of 
5
was established as (3 
R
, 14 
R
, 16 
S
, 20 
S
, 21 
S
) based on comparison of the experimental and calculated ECD spectra (
Fig. 4
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
Assignments based on HSQC and HMBC.
</p>
         <p>
b
CDCl, 150 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
c
CDCl, 100 MHz.
</p>
         <p>
3
d–f
Interchangeable.
</p>
         <p>
A plausible biosynthetic pathway to 
3
, 
4
, and 
5
from an iboga precursor, 3(
S
)-cyanocoronaridine (
15
) (

) is shown in 
Fig. 8
. Hydrolysis of 
15
followed by reduction leads to ervatamine G (
16
) (

). Subsequent formation of the enamine 
17
, followed by an intermolecular enamine-formaldehyde reaction leads to the C-25 hydroxy intermediate, 
18
. Finally, oxidation of 
18
leads to 
5
. Compounds 
3
and 
4
may have formed from a similar biosynthetic pathway with the hypothetical 19 
R
-hydroxy derivative of 3 (
S
)-cyanocoronaridine 
19
.
</p>
         <p>
Polyneurine F
(
6
) 

was initially obtained as a light yellowish oil, [α] 
D
25
43 (
c
0.4, CHCl 
3
), and subsequently as light yellowish block crystals from EtOH (mp 153–154 
◦
C). The UV spectrum showed absorption maxima at 223, 285, and 
293 nm
, which were characteristic of an indole chromophore, while the IR spectrum showed the presence of NH/OH (
3331 cm
1
), ester (
1732 cm
1
), and lactam (
1657 cm
1
) functions. The HRESIMS data ([M + H] 
+
m/z
369.1817) established the molecular formula of 
6
as C 
21
H 
24
N 
2
O 
4
. The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 2
) displayed a total of 21 carbon resonances, comprising six methylenes, seven methines, one methyl ester, one ester carbonyl, one amide carbonyl, two tertiary carbons linked to indolic NH, and three quaternary carbons

, in 

agreement with the molecular formula. The 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) showed the presence of an indolic NH (
δ
H
8.12), an unsubstituted indole moiety (
δ
H
7.09–7.48), a methyl ester (
δ
H
3.72), and a 1-hydroxyethyl side chain (
δ
H
3.74, 3.81, H-18; 
δ
H
1.64, 1.77, H-19). The 
13
C NMR data showed the presence of an oxymethylene at 
δ
C
60.2 and a methylene at 
δ
C
37.5, which were attributed to C-18 and C-19, respectively from the HSQC and COSY data (
Fig. 2
). The COSY data indicated the presence of a CH 
2
CHCH 
2
CHCH 
2
CH 
2
partial structure, which corresponds to C-17 C-14 C-15 C-20 C-19 C- 
18 in
6
. This was further confirmed by the three-bond correlations from H-18 (
δ
H
3.74 and 3.81) to C-20 (
δ
C
30.6), and from H-20 (
δ
H
2.05) to C-18 (
δ
C
60.2) (
Fig. 2
). In addition, the presence of an amide carbonyl at C-3 was in agreement with the three-bond correlations observed from H-5, H-15, H-17, and H-21 to C-3 (
δ
C
176.3) (
Fig. 2
). Additionally, the presence of the C-3 carbonyl has resulted in a noticeable anisotropic deshielding of H-5 
β
(
δ
H
4.48) (


., 
2016
a), 

compared to 
δ
H
3.1–3.4 for H-5 
β
in

1

, 

3–5

. The NOE data (
Fig. 3
) also showed that the relative configuration of 
6
was similar to that of compounds 
1–5
. Since suitable crystals were obtained, an X-ray diffraction analysis was also carried out which confirmed the structure and provided the absolute configuration of 
6
(14 
R
, 16 
S
, 20 
R
, 21 
S
) (
Fig. 9
).
</p>
         <p>
Polyneurine G
(
7
) 

was isolated as an orange oil, [α] 
D
25
25 (
c
0.4, CHCl 
3
). The UV spectrum showed absorption maxima indicative of an indole chromophore at 225, 285, and 
293 nm
, while the IR spectrum showed the presence of NH/OH and ester groups at 3376 and

1728
cm
1
, respectively. The HRESIMS data ([M + H] 
+
m/z
371.1984) established the molecular formula of 
7
as C 
21
H 
26
N 
2
O 
4
. The 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) showed the presence of an indolic NH (
δ
H
8.13), four aromatic hydrogens (
δ
H
7.08–7.47), a methyl ester (
δ
H
3.73), and a 1,2-disubstituted ethyl side chain (
δ
H
3.61, 3.76, H-18; 
δ
H
3.78, H-19). The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 2
) indicated 21 carbon resonances, comprising six methylenes, eight methines, one methyl ester, one ester carbonyl, two tertiary carbons linked to indolic NH, and three quaternary carbons. The COSY and HMBC data (
Fig. 2
) led to the elucidation of the structure for the compound as the vicinally-dihydroxysubstituted coronaridine derivative (18,19-dihydroxycoronaridine). The oxymethylene and oxymethine resonances corresponding to the vicinally-dihydroxysubstituted C-18 C-19 were seen at 
δ
C
65.8 and 75.5, respectively. A search of the literature revealed that this 2D structure was previously assigned to 18,19-dihydroxycoronaridine (
20
) (

), which does not possess identical 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data to those of 
7
, suggesting 
7
to be an epimer of 
20
. Since the relative configurations at C-14, C-16, C-20, and C-21 were found to be identical to those of compounds 
1–6
(
Fig. 3
), the only stereochemical difference between compounds 
7
and 
20
must be at C-19. The stereochemistry at C-19 was assigned by comparing the 
13
C NMR data of 
7
and 
20
with those of 19 
R
- and 19 
S
-heyneanine (

; 

). In 
7
, 
C-
15
and C-21 were observed at 
δ
C
28.3 and 
δ
C
54.9, respectively, which correspond to the corresponding carbon shifts in the 19 
R
-hydroxyiboga alkaloid series such as 19- 
epi
-heyneanine (i.e., C-15 at ca. 
δ
C
29; C-21 at ca. 
δ
C
55). On the contrary, C-15 and C-21 of 
20
were found at 
δ
C
23.7 and 
δ
C
59.2, respectively (

), which are consistent with those found in the 19 
S
-hydroxyiboga alkaloid series such as heyneanine. We can therefore deduce that compound 
7
possesses an opposite relative configuration at C-19 (i.e., 
S
), compared to 
20
with a 19 
R
configuration (

). The deduction was further confirmed by GIAO NMR calculations and DP4+ analysis. The experimental NMR data were compared with the calculated 
1
H and 
13
C NMR shifts of 
7
and its C-19 epimer 
7a
using DP4+analysis. The DP4+results supported 
7
with 19 
S
configuration as the correct relative configuration, with 100% DP4+ probability (all data) (
Fig. 7
). Finally, the absolute configuration of 
7
was established as (14 
R
, 16 
S
, 19 
S
, 20 
S
, 21 
S
) based on comparison of the experimental and calculated ECD spectra (
Fig. 4
). Compound 
7
is thus identified as 18,19(
S
)-dihydroxycoronaridine.
</p>
         <p>
Polyneurine H
(
8
) 

was obtained as a yellowish oil, [α] 
D
25
30 (
c
0.1, CHCl 
3
). The UV spectrum exhibited absorption maxima indicative of a hydroxyindolenine chromophore at 223, 232 sh, 266, and 
292 nm
, while the IR spectrum showed the presence of OH and ester carbonyl groups at 3301 and

1732
cm

1
, respectively. The HRESIMS data ([M + H] 
+
m/z
371.1962) established the molecular formula of 
8
as C 
21
H 
26
N 
2
O 
4
. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (
Tables 1
and 
2
) revealed the presence of four aromatic resonances of an unsubstituted indole moiety (
δ
H
7.25–7.48), a methyl ester group (
δ
H
3.71; 
δ
C
53.4, 172.9), a hydroxyethyl side chain (
δ
H
1.24, 3.85; 
δ
C
22.2, 70.3), and a broad singlet at 
δ
H
3.26 due to an OH group (confirmed by D 
2
O exchange experiment). The imine function in 
8
was readily identified from the characteristic C-2 resonance observed at 
δ
C
188.6, in 

addition to the absence of an indolic NH signal in the 
1
H NMR spectrum

. 

The oxygenated tertiary carbon (C-7) associated with the hydroxyindolenine was clearly observed at 
δ
C
88.0. Examination of the COSY and HMBC data (
Fig. 2
) led to the structure as shown in 
8
. A search of the literature revealed that this 2D structure was previously assigned to heyneanine hydroxyindolenine (
21
) (

; 

), which does not have identical NMR data to those of 
8
, suggesting 
8
to be a diastereomer of 
21
. Since the relative configurations at C-14, C-16, C-20, and C-21 were established to be the same as those of compounds 
1–7
(
Fig. 3
), the stereochemical differences between compounds 
8
and 
21
must be at C-7 and/or C-19. As with compounds 
3
, 
4
, and 
7
, the C-19 configuration of 
8
was readily determined as 
R
from the observed carbon shifts of C-15 (
δ
C
28.5) and C-21 (
δ
C
54.2), which correspond to those of the 19 
R
-hydroxyiboga alkaloid series (
vide supra
) such as 19- 
epi
-heyneanine (C-15 at ca. 
δ
C
29 and C-21 at ca. 
δ
C
55) (

; 

). The 19 
R
configuration was also supported by the GIAO NMR calculations and DP4+ analysis of 
8
, which showed 100% probability (all data) (
Fig. 7
). The configuration at C-7 was assigned as 
S
based on the NOE interaction observed between H-21 and 7-OH (
Fig. 3
). Finally, the absolute configuration of 
8
was established as (7 
S
, 14 
R
, 16 
S
, 19 
R
, 20 
S
, 21 
S
) based on comparison of the experimental and calculated ECD spectra (
Fig. 4
). Compound 
8
is therefore the 7 
S
, 19 
R
diastereomer of 7 
R
, 19 
S
-heyneanine hydroxyindolenine

(

21

).
</p>
         <p>
Compounds 
1
, 
2
, 
6
, 
7
, and 
8
were tested for their cytotoxic effect against several human cancer cell lines (HT-29, HCT 116, MCF7, MDA-MB-231, A549, and PC-3) but were found to be inactive (IC 
50
&gt;
10 μM).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
The present study on the bark of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
</tp:taxon-name>
afforded eight previously undescribed iboga alkaloids (
1–8
). The structures of these compounds were established by interpretation of the MS and NMR data, GIAO NMR calculations and DP4+ probability analysis, TDDFT-ECD method, or X-ray diffraction analysis. A previous study of the same plant from a different location found only four new alkaloids in the stem bark extract, viz., two vobasine and two iboga alkaloids (

). The present study has resulted in the isolation of eight additional previously undescribed iboga alkaloids.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
         <p>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</p>
         <p>
Melting points were determined on an Electrothermal IA9100 digital melting point apparatus and are uncorrected. Optical rotations were measured on a JASCO P-1020 automatic digital polarimeter. UV spectra were obtained on a Shimadzu UV-2600 spectrophotometer. IR spectra were recorded on a PerkinElmer RX1 FT-IR spectrophotometer or Spectrum 400 FT-IR/FT-FIR spectrophotometer. HRDART-MS was recorded on a JEOL Accu TOF-DART mass spectrometer, and HRESIMS were obtained on an Agilent LC HR QTOF System Model G6530A or Agilent Technologies 6550 iFunnel Q-TOF LC/MS. 1D and 2D NMR spectra were recorded in CDCl 
3
using tetramethylsilane as internal standard on JEOL JNM (ECA 400 MHz) or Bruker Avance III (600 MHz) spectrometers and using a 
1.7 mm
microprobe for compound 
5
. ECD spectra were obtained using JASCO J-810 or JASCO J-815 circular dichroism spectrometers.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>

Bark of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tabernaemontana polyneura
(King &amp; Gamble) D.J.Middleton (Apocynaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
was collected in 

June 2016

from 
Fraser’ s Hill
, 
Pahang
, 
Malaysia
(

3.7249 
◦
N

, 

101.7143 
◦
E

), and was identified by 
Dr. K. T. Yong
(Institute of Biological Sciences, Universiti Malaya, Malaysia). A voucher specimen (
KLU49438
) was deposited at the 
Herbarium, Universiti
Malaya

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
Extraction of alkaloids from the ground bark material (
11.9 kg
) was carried out exhaustively with MeOH at room temperature to afford a viscous extract which was then acidified with 3% tartaric acid. Removal of non-alkaloidal material followed by basification with sodium carbonate and extraction with chloroform gave the crude alkaloidal mixture (
60 g
). The crude mixture was fractionated by column chromatography (SiO 
2
, hexanes/ 
CH
2
Cl 
2
; MeOH/ 
CH
2
Cl 
2
) to furnish eleven main fractions (F1–F11). Fraction F2 was rechromatographed (SiO 
2
, petroleum ether/EtOAc; MeOH/EtOAc) to give six subfractions (F2a F2f). Repeated purification of the subfraction F2c using preparative radial chromatography (Chromatotron) on SiO 
2
yielded compound 
1
. Rechromatography of fraction F3 over SiO 
2
(petroleum ether/CHCl 
3
; MeOH/CHCl 
3
) gave seven subfractions (F3a F 
3g
). Compounds 
5
and 
8
were obtained from the subfractions F3b and F3c, respectively, by repeated preparative radial chromatography. Further fractionation of fraction F5 by column chromatography (SiO 
2
, petroleum ether/EtOAc; MeOH/EtOAc) yielded ten subfractions (F5a F5j). Subfraction F 
5g
was further purified by repeated preparative radial chromatography to furnish compound 
4
. Column chromatography of F6 (SiO 
2
, petroleum ether/EtOAc; MeOH/EtOAc) gave 10 subfractions (F6a F6j). Compounds 
6
and 
7
were isolated from the subfractions F 
6g
and F6f, respectively, by repeated preparative radial chromatography over SiO 
2
. Gel permeation chromatography (Sephadex LH-20, MeOH) of fraction 7 yielded ten subfractions (F7a F7j). The combined subfraction F7c e was subjected to repetitive preparative radial chromatography to yield compound 
2
and 
3
. The solvent systems used for preparative radial chromatography were MeOH/Et 
2
O, petroleum ether/Et 
2
O, MeOH/ CHCl 
3
, petroleum ether/CHCl 
3
, MeOH/ 
CH
2
Cl 
2
, petroleum ether/ 
CH
2
Cl 
2
, 
CH
2
Cl 
2
, MeOH/EtOAc, and petroleum ether/EtOAc. All solvent systems used for preparative radial chromatography were NH 
3
-saturated. The yields (mg kg 
1
) of the alkaloids from the bark were as follows: 
1
(0.37), 
2
(0.59), 
3
(0.31), 
4
(0.14), 
5
(0.13), 
6
(0.59), 
7
(0.77), and 
8
(0.20).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Characterization data
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.1. Polyneurine A (1)
</title>
         <p>
Light orange oil; [α] 
D
25
44 (
c
0.2, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH), 
λ
max
(Δε) 220 (6.18), 233 (+1.66), 245 (3.27), 288 (+0.83) nm; UV (EtOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 226 (3.93), 284 (3.31), 291 (3.31) nm; IR (dry film) 
ν
max
3427, 
1756 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRDARTMS 
m/z
323.1761 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
20
H 
22
N 
2
O 
2
+ H, 323.1760).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.2. Polyneurine B (2)
</title>
         <p>
Colorless oil and subsequently colorless plates (CCl 
4
/MeOH); mp 175–177 
ο
C; [α] 
D
25
44 (
c
0.5, CHCl 
3
); UV (EtOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 217 (4.15), 220 (4.14), 285 (3.66), 292 (3.61) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3258, 
1716 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
373.2139 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
21
H 
28
N 
2
O 
4
+ H, 373.2122).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.3. Polyneurine C (3)
</title>
         <p>
Light yellowish oil; [α] 
D
25
28 (
c
0.2, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH), 
λ
max
(Δε) 205 (+2.95), 225 (1.33), 244 (+1.26), 275 (0.73) nm; UV (EtOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 223 (4.22), 286 (3.76) nm; IR (ATR) 
ν
max
3374, 
1726 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
385.2130 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
28
N 
2
O 
4
+ H, 385.2122).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.4. Polyneurine D (4)
</title>
         <p>
Light yellowish oil; [α] 
D
25
36 (
c
0.1, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH), 
λ
max
(Δε) 206 (+0.33), 214 (+10.49), 230 (4.89), 246 (+17.61), 280 (31.27) nm; UV (EtOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 225 (4.10), 285 (3.50), 293 (3.47) nm; IR (dry film) 
ν
max
3376, 1725, 
1718 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
397.2126 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for C 
23
H 
28
N 
2
O 
4
+H, 397.2122).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.5. Polyneurine E (5)
</title>
         <p>
Light orange oil; [α] 
D
25
29 (
c
0.1, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH), 
λ
max
(Δε) 203 (+5.56), 221 (1.06), 246 (+5.03), 279 (7.62), 315 (+0.62) nm; UV (EtOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 227 (4.18), 286 (3.66), 293 (3.63) nm; IR (dry film) 
ν
max
3378, 1726, 
1717 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
381.2174 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
23
H 
28
N 
2
O 
3
+ H, 381.2173).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.6. Polyneurine F (6)
</title>
         <p>
Light yellowish oil and subsequently light yellowish block crystals (EtOH); mp 153–154 
ο
C; [α] 
D
25
43 (
c
0.4, CHCl 
3
); UV (EtOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 223 (4.13), 285 (3.61), 293 (3.58) nm; IR (dry film) 
ν
max
3331, 1732, 
1657 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
369.1817 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for C 
21
H 
24
N 
2
O 
4
+ H, 369.1809).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.7. Polyneurine G (7)
</title>
         <p>
Orange oil; [α] 
D
25
25 (
c
0.4, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH), 
λ
max
(Δε) 203 (+7.32), 221 (+0.72), 243 (+4.84), 281 (5.92) nm; UV (EtOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 225 (4.69), 285 (4.11), 293 (4.07) nm; IR (dry film) 
ν
max
3376, 
1728 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
371.1984 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
21
H 
26
N 
2
O 
4
+ H, 371.1965).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.8. Polyneurine H (8)
</title>
         <p>
Yellowish oil; [α] 
D
25
30 (
c
0.1, CHCl 
3
); ECD (MeOH), 
λ
max
(Δε) 207 (8.68), 257 (+11.07), 293 (3.63) nm; UV (EtOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 223 (3.52), 232 sh (3.26), 266 (2.91), 292 (2.84) nm; IR (dry film) 
ν
max
3301, 
1732 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
371.1962 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
21
H 
26
N 
2
O 
4
+ H, 371.1965).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.9. Computational methods
</title>
         <p>
Conformational searches were performed by Spartan’14 software (

) using the MMFF94 force field. Conformers occurring within a 5 kcal mol 
1
energy window from the global minima were then imported into the Gaussian 09 software (

) for geometry optimization and frequency calculation at DFT level using the B3LYP functional with a basis set of 6–31G(d). TDDFT ECD calculations were performed on the optimized conformers at the B3LYP or 
ω
B97X-D/6-311G++(d,p) level using a PCM solvation model for MeOH. The ECD spectrum for each optimized conformer was weighted by Boltzmann distribution, and the overall ECD curves were produced by SpecDis (version 1.64) software (

) after UV correction. Gauge-Including Atomic Orbital (GIAO) NMR calculations were performed on the optimized conformers at the mPW1PW91/6-31 +G (d,p) level with PCM solvation model for CHCl 
3
. The Boltzmann-averaged magnetic shielding tensors were converted into chemical shifts (ppm) with TMS as the reference standard (

; 

). The DP4+ calculations were carried out using the Excel spreadsheet provided by the Sarotti group (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.10. X-ray crystallographic analysis of polyneurines B (2) and F (6)
</title>
         <p>
X-ray diffraction analyses were carried out on a Rigaku Oxford (formerly Agilent Technologies) SuperNova Dual diffractometer with Mo K 
α
(
λ
= 0.71073 Å) or Cu K 
α
(
λ
= 1.54184 Å) radiation at room temperature. Using Olex2, the structures were solved with SHELXT-2018/2 structure solution program using Intrinsic Phasing and refined with SHELXL-2018/3 refinement package using Least Square minimization. All non-hydrogen atoms were refined anisotropically, and all hydrogen atoms were placed in idealized positions and refined as riding atoms with the relative isotropic parameters. Crystallographic data for 
2
and 
6
had been deposited with the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre. Copies of the data can be obtained, free of charge, on application to the Director, CCDC, 12 Union Road, Cambridge CB2 1EZ, 
UK
(fax: +44 (0)1223–336033, or e-mail: deposit@ccdc.cam.ac.uk).
</p>
         <p>
Crystallographic Data of 
2
. Colorless plates (CCl 
4
/MeOH), mp 175–177 
◦
C, C 
21
H 
28
N 
2
O 
4
.CCl 
4
, 
M
r = 526.26, monoclinic, space group 
P
21
, 
a
=9.7036 (3) Å, 
b
=9.7698 (3) Å, 
c
=13.5325 (5) Å, 
β
=100.585 (3) 
◦
, 
V
=1261.08 (7) Å 
3
, 
Z
=2, 
D
calcd
= 
1.386 g
cm 
3
, crystal size 0.5 × 0.4 × 
0.01 mm
3
, 
F
(000) =548, Mo K 
α
radiation (
λ
= 0.71073 Å), 
T
= 293 (2) K. The final 
R
1
value is 0.0930 (w 
R
2
= 0.2790) for 6472 reflections [

I
&gt; 
2
σ(I)
], while the Flack, Hooft, and Parson’ s parameters were 
x
= 0.02 (3), 
y
= 0.05 (2), and 
z
=0.01 (3), respectively. For the inverted structure, the 
R
1
value is 0.0932 (w 
R
2
= 0.2796) for 6472 reflections [

I
&gt; 
2
σ(I)
], while the Flack, Hooft, and Parson’ s parameters were 
x
= 0.98 (3), 
y
= 0.95 (2), and 
z
= 0.99 (3), respectively, from which it follows that the correct enantiomer is the one depicted in 
Fig. 6
(14 
R
, 16 
S
, 19 
R
, 20 
S
, 21 
S
). CCDC number 2169029.
</p>
         <p>
Crystallographic Data of 
6
. Light yellowish block crystals (EtOH), mp 153–154 
◦
C, C 
21
H 
24
N 
2
O 
4
.H 
2
O, 
M
r =386.44, triclinic, space group 
P
1, 
a
=7.8152 (6) Å, 
b
=9.4777 (9) Å, 
c
=13.9307 (12) Å, 
α
=77.234 (7) 
◦
, 
β
=79.526 (7) 
◦
, 
γ
=89.595 (7) 
◦
, 
V
=988.98 (15) Å 
3
, 
Z
=2, 
D
calcd
= 
1.298 g
cm 
3
, crystal size 0.2 × 0.1 × 
0.03 mm
3
, 
F
(000) =412, Cu K 
α
radiation (
λ
=1.54184 Å), 
T
=293 (2) K. The final 
R
1
value is 0.0507 (w 
R
2
= 0.1071) for 7405 reflections [

I
&gt; 
2
σ(I)
], while the Flack, Hooft, and Parson’ s parameters were 
x
= 0.09 (19), 
y
= 0.10 (18), and 
z
= 0.1 (2), respectively. For the inverted structure, the 
R
1
value is 0.0508 (w 
R
2
= 0.1070) for 7405 reflections [

I
&gt; 
2
σ(I)
], while the Flack, Hooft, and Parson’ s parameters were 
x
=1.08 (19), 
y
=1.10 (18), and 
z
=1.1 (2), respectively, from which it follows that the correct enantiomer is the one depicted in 
Fig. 9
(14 
R
, 16 
S
, 20 
R
, 21 
S
). CCDC number 2169030.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Cytotoxicity assays
</title>
         <p>
Cytotoxicity assays were carried out following the published procedures (

).
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
         <p>
Data availability
</p>
         <p>Data will be made available on request.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>
We thank Universiti Malaya and MOHE 
Malaysia
(FRGS/1/2019/ STG01/UM/02/23) for financial support, and Data Intensive Computing Centre (DICC) Universiti Malaya for providing the high-performance computing facilities.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2023.113587.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Abubakar, I.B.
, 
Loh, H.S.
, 
2016
. 

A review on ethnobotany, pharmacology and phytochemistry of 
Tabernaemontana corymbosa

. 
J. Pharm. Pharmacol.
68
, 
423–432
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jphp.12523
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Azoug, M.
, 
Loukaci, A.
, 
Richard, B.
, 
Nuzillard, J.M.
, 
Moreti, C.
, 
Z`eches-Hanrot, M.
, 
Men-Olivier, L.L.
, 
1995
. 

Alkaloids from stem bark and leaves of 
Peschiera buchtieni

. 
Phytochemistry
39
(
5
), 
1223–1228
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(95)00050- H
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bruhn, T.
, 
SchaumlOffel ¨, A.
, 
Hemberger, Y.
, 
2015
. 
SpecDis, Version 1.64
. 

University of Wuerzburg, 
Germany

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Clivio, P.
, 
Richard, B.
, 
Hadi, H.A.
, 
David, B.
, 
Sevenet, T.
, 
Zeches, M.
, 
Men-Olivier, L.L.
, 
1990
. 

Alkaloids from leaves and stem bark of 
Ervatamia polyneura

. 
Phytochemistry
29
(
9
), 
3007–3011
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(90)87124-D
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Frisch, M.J.
, 
Trucks, G.W.
, 
Schlegel, H.B.
, 
Scuseria, G.E.
, 
Robb, M.A.
, 
Cheeseman, J.R.
, 
Scalmani, G.
, 
Barone, V.
, 
Mennucci, B.
, 
Petersson, G.A.
, 
Nakatsuji, H.
, 
Caricato, M.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Hratchian, H.P.
, 
Izmaylov, A.F.
, 
Bloino, J.
, 
Zheng, G.
, 
Sonnenberg, J.L.
, 
Hada, M.
, 
Ehara, M.
, 
Toyota, K.
, 
Fukuda, R.
, 
Hasegawa, J.
, 
Ishida, M.
, 
Nakajima, T.
, 
Honda, Y.
, 
Kitao, O.
, 
Nakai, H.
, 
Vreven, T.
, 
Montgomery Jr., J.A.
, 
Peralta, J.E.
, 
Ogliaro, F.
, 
Bearpark, M.
, 
Heyd, J.J.
, 
Brothers, E.
, 
Kudin, K.N.
, 

Staroverov, 

V.N.


, 
Keith, T.
, 
Kobayashi, R.
, 
Normand, J.
, 
Raghavachari, K.
, 
Rendell, A.
, 
Burant, J.C.
, 
Iyengar, S.S.
, 
Tomasi, J.
, 
Cossi, M.
, 
Rega, N.
, 
Millam, J.M.
, 
Klene, M.
, 
Knox, J.E.
, 
Cross, J.B.
, 
Bakken, V.
, 
Adamo, C.
, 
Jaramillo, J.
, 
Gomperts, R.
, 
Stratmann, R.E.
, 
Yazyev, O.
, 
Austin, A.J.
, 
Cammi, R.
, 
Pomelli, C.
, 
Ochterski, J.W.
, 
Martin, R.L.
, 
Morokuma, K.
, 
Zakrzewski, V.G.
, 
Voth, G.A.
, 

Salvador
, P.

, 
Dannenberg, J.J.
, 
Dapprich, S.
, 
Daniels, A.D.
, 
Farkas, O
¨., 
Foresman, J.B.
, 
Ortiz, J.V.
, 
Cioslowski, J.
, 
Fox, D.J.
, 
2010
. 

Gaussian 09
, Revision C.01.

Gaussian Inc., Wallingford, CT
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grimblat, N.
, 
Zanardi, M.M.
, 
Sarotti, A.M.
, 
2015
. 
Beyond DP4: improved probability for the stereochemical assignment of isomeric compounds using quantum chemical calculations of NMR shifts
. 
J. Org. Chem.
80
, 
12526–12534
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.joc.5b02396
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harada, M.
, 
Asaba, K.N.
, 
Iwai, M.
, 
Kogure, N.
, 
Kitajima, M.
, 
Takayama, H.
, 
2012
. 

Asymmetric total synthesis of an iboga-type indole alkaloid, voacangalactone, newly isolated from 
Voacanga africana

. 
Org. Lett.
14
(
22
), 
5800–5803
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/ol3027945
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ishikawa, H.
, 
Colby, D.A.
, 
Seto, S.
, 
Va, P.
, 
Tam, A.
, 
Kakei, H.
, 
Rayl, T.J.
, 
Hwang, I.
, 
Boger, D.L.
, 
2009
. 
Total synthesis of vinblastine, vincristine, related natural product, and key structural analogues
. 
J. Am. Chem. Soc.
131
, 
4904–4916
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/ja809842b
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kam, T.S.
, 
1999
. 
Alkaloids from Malaysian flora
. In: 
Pelletier, S.W.
(Ed.), 
Alkaloids: Chemical and Biological Perspectives, vol. 14
. 
Pergamon, Amsterdam
, pp. 
285–435
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kam, T.S.
, 
Pang, H.S.
, 
Choo, Y.M.
, 
Komiyama, K.
, 
2004
. 

Biologically active ibogan and vallesamine derivatives from 
Tabernaemontana divaricata

. 
Chem. Biodivers.
1
, 
646–656
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/cbdv.200490056
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kam, T.S.
, 
Choo, Y.M.
, 
2006
. 
Bisindole alkaloids
. In: 
Cordell, G.A.
(Ed.), 
The Alkaloids, vol. 63.
Academic Press, Amsterdam
, pp. 
181–337
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kam, T.S.
, 
Lim, K.H.
, 
2008
. 
Alkaloids of kopsia
. In: 
Cordell, G.A.
(Ed.), 
The Alkaloids: Chemistry and Biology, vol. 66
. 

Academic Press, 
The Netherlands

, pp. 
1–111
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Leeuwenberg, A.J.M.
, 
1991
. 
A Revision of Tabernaemontana: the Old World Species
. 

Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, 
U.

K.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lim, S.H.
, 
Low, Y.Y.
, 
Sinniah, S.K.
, 
Yong, K.T.
, 
Sim, K.S.
, 
Kam, T.S.
, 
2014
. 

Macroline, akuammiline, sarpagine, and ajmaline alkaloids from 
Alstonia macrophyll
a

. 
Phytochemistry
98
, 
204–215
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2013.11.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Middleton, D.J.
, 
2011
. 
Apocynaceae (subfamilies: rauvolfioideae and apocynoideae)
. In: 
Kiew, R.
, 
Chung, R.C.K.
, 
Saw, L.G.
, 
Soepadmo, E.
, 
Boyce, P.C.
(Eds.), 

Flora of Peninsular 
Malaysia
, Series II: Seed Plants, vol. 2

. 

Forest Research Institute 
Malaysia
, Kepong, 
Malaysia

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nge, C.E.
, 
Chong, K.W.
, 

Thomas, 
N.F.

, 
Lim, S.H.
, 
Low, Y.Y.
, 
Kam, T.S.
, 
2016
a. 

Ibogan, aspidosperman, vincamine, and bisindole alkaloids from a Malayan 
Tabernaemontana corymbosa
: iboga alkaloids with C-20 
α
substitution

. 
J. Nat. Prod. (Lloydia)
79
, 
1388–1399
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.6b00129
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nge, C.E.
, 
Sim, K.S.
, 
Lim, S.H.
, 

Thomas, 
N.F.

, 
Low, Y.Y.
, 
Kam, T.S.
, 
2016
b. 

Hexacyclic, iboga-derived monoterpenoid indole with a contracted tetrahydroazepine C-ring and incorporation of an isoxazolidine moiety, a 
seco
-corynanthean, an 
aspidospermaaspidosperma
bisindole with anticancer properties, and the absolute configuration of the pyridopyrimidine indole alkaloid, vernavosine

. 
J. Nat. Prod. (Lloydia)
79
, 
2709–2717
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.6b00674
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Santos, A.K.L.
, 
Magalh˜aes, T.S.
, 
Monte, F.J.Q.
, 
Carlos de Mattos, M.
, 
de Oliveira, M.C.F.
, 
Almeida, M.M.B.
, 
Lemos, T.L.G.
, 
Braz-Filho, R.
, 
2009
. 

Iboga alkaloids from 
Peschiera affinis
(Apocynaceae) unequivocal 1 H and 13C chemical shift assignments. Antioxidant activity

. 
Quim. Nova
32
(
7
), 
1834–1838
. 
https://doi.org/10.1590/ S0100-40422009000700028
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sharma, P.
, 
Cordell, G.A.
, 
1988
. 

Heyneanine hydroxyindolenine, a new indole alkaloid from 
Ervatamia coronaria
Var

. 
Plena. J. Nat. Prod.
51
(
3
), 
528–531
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/np50057a012
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sim, D.S.Y.
, 
Navanesan, S.
, 
Sim, K.S.
, 
Gurusamy, S.
, 
Lim, S.H.
, 
Low, Y.Y.
, 
Kam, T.S.
, 
2019
. 

Conolodinines A D, a 
spidosperma-aspidosperma
bisindole alkaloids with antiproliferative activity from 
Tabernaemontana corymbosa

. 
J. Nat. Prod. (Lloydia)
82
(
4
), 
850–858
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.8b00919
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sim, D.S.Y.
, 
Teoh, W.Y.
, 
Sim, K.S.
, 
Lim, S.H.
, 

Thomas, 
N.F.

, 
Low, Y.Y.
, 
Kam, T.S.
, 
2016
. 

Vobatensines A F, cytotoxic iboga-vobasine bisindoles from 
Tabernaemontana corymbosa

. 
J. Nat. Prod. (Lloydia)
79
, 
1048–1055
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. jnatprod.5b01117
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Spartan’14

, 
2014
. 
Wavefunction, Inc, Irvine, CA
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Takayama, H.
, 
Suda, S.
, 
Chen, I.S.
, 
Kitajima, M.
, 
Aimi, N.
, 
Sakai, S.
, 
1994
. 

Two new dimeric indole alkaloids from 
Tabernaemontana subglobosa
Merr. From 
Taiwan

. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull. (Tokyo)
42
(
2
), 
280–284
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/cpb.42.280
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Van Beek, T.A.
, 
Verpoorte, R.
, 
Svendsen, A.B.
, 
Leeuwenberg, A.J.M.
, 

Bisset, 
N.G.

, 
1984
. 

Tabernaemontana
L. (Apocynaceae): a review of its taxonomy, phytochemistry, ethnobotany and pharmacology. J

. 
Ethnopharmacol.
10
, 
101–156
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/0378-8741(84)90046-1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wenkert, E.
, 
Cochran, D.W.
, 
Gottlieb, H.E.
, 
Hagaman, E.W.
, 
Filho, R.B.
, 
Matos, F.J.A.
, 
Madruga, M.I.L.M.
, 
1976
. 
13C-NMR spectroscopy of naturally occurring substances. XLV. Iboga alkaloids
. 
Helv. Chim. Acta
59
(
7
), 
2437–2442
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ hlca.19760590719
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Willoughby, P.H.
, 
Jansma, M.J.
, 
Hoye, T.R.
, 
2014
. 
A guide to small-molecule structure assignment through computation of (1 H and 13C) NMR chemical shifts
. 
Nat. Protoc.
9
, 
643–660
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2014.042
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Willoughby, P.H.
, 
Jansma, M.J.
, 
Hoye, T.R.
, 
2020
. 
Addendum: a guide to small-molecule structure assignment through computation of (1 H and 13 C) NMR chemical shifts
. 
Nat. Protoc.
15
, 
2277
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41596-020-0293-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Z`eches-Hanrot, M.
, 
Nuzillard, J.M.
, 
Richard, B.
, 
Schaller, H.
, 
Hadi, H.A.
, 
S´evenet, T.
, 
Men-Olivier, L.L.
, 
1995
. 

Alkaloids from leaves and stem bark of 
Ervatamia peduncularis

. 
Phytochemistry
40
(
2
), 
587–591
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422 (95)00152-W
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, D.B.
, 
Yu, D.G.
, 
Sun, M.
, 
Zhu, X.X.
, 
Yao, X.J.
, 
Zhou, S.Y.
, 
Chen, J.J.
, 
Gao, K.
, 
2015
. 

Ervatamines A I, anti-inflammatory monoterpenoid indole alkaloids with diverse skeletons from 
Ervatamia hainanensis

. 
J. Nat. Prod. (Lloydia)
78
, 
1253–1261
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.5b00051
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
