<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113012</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Multioxidized aromatic polyketides produced by a soil-derived fungus Penicillium canescens</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichocomaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
Sopp O.J. (Trichocomaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. canescens
ATCC
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. canescens
CGMCC
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. canescens
CGMCC
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
Sopp O.J. (Trichocomaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
ATCC
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>nigrum</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium chrysogenum
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Multioxidized aromatic polyketides produced by a soil-derived fungus</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Yi Zang
a, b
, Yihua Gong
a
, Zhengyi Shi
a
, Changxing Qi
a
, Chunmei Chen
a
, Qingyi Tong
a
,
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Junjun Liu 
a
, Jianping Wang
a
, Hucheng Zhu

a, 
*
, Yonghui Zhang

a, 
**
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Hubei Key Laboratory of Natural Medicinal Chemistry and Resource Evaluation, School of Pharmacy, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan, 430030, People’ s Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Microbial Culture Collection and Application, Key Laboratory of Agricultural Microbiomics and Precision Application, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, State Key Laboratory of Applied Microbiology Southern China, Institute of Microbiology, Guangdong Academy of Sciences, Guangzhou, 510070, People’ s Republic of China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Keywords:
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Trichocomaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>OSMAC</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Aromatic polyketides Cytotoxicity</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Under OSMAC strategy, seven unreported multioxidized aromatic polyketides, penicanesins A‒G, were discovered from a soil-derived fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
along with seven known compounds. Their structures were assigned by extensive 1D and 2D NMR spectra in combination with HRESIMS and single crystal X-ray diffraction. Absolute stereochemistry of penicanesins A and D were elucidated by theoretical ECD calculation. (±)-Penicanesins A and B are two pairs of racemic aromatic polyketides with an unusual 6/6/6/6 heterotetracyclic ring core. In bioassay, ()-penicanesin A shows potential cytotoxicity against human cancer cell lines HL-60 and SW480 with IC 
50
values at 13.8 ± 0.6 and 12.5 ± 0.9 
μ
M, respectively, whereas the enantiomer (+)-penicanesin A is less active.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
1. Introduction
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
Sopp O.J. (Trichocomaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
, broadly distributed in natural sources such as soil, plants, and marine, is found to produce various bioactive secondary metabolites with diverse chemical structures. Although series of structurally complex aromatic polyketides, meroterpenoids, tetrapeptides, azaphilones, xanthones, and alkaloids have been isolated from this fungus derived from several special environments in previous reports (Bertinettia et al., 2009; Frank et al., 2019; Malik et al., 2020; Nicoletti et al., 2007; Yaegashi et al., 2015; Zang et al., 2019, 2020), it still has great potential for exploration of novel secondary metabolites as suggested by the whole genome sequencing of a soil-inhabiting 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. canescens
ATCC
</tp:taxon-name>
10419. Detailed analysis of the sequence in Joint Genome Institute (JGI) website pointed out kinds of secondary metabolism clusters, especially the presence of a large number of polyketide synthase (PKS) genes. Thus, in our recently chemical investigations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. canescens
CGMCC
</tp:taxon-name>
3.79658 (ATCC 10419), sets of novel dimeric polyketides comprising unprecedented chemical architectures were identified on the basis of one strain-many compounds (OSMAC) and MS/MS-based molecular networking strategies (Zang et al., 2019, 2020). Except for the identification of novel skeletons, partial dimeric polyketides exhibited potent PTP1B inhibition effect and cytotoxicity against human cancer cell lines.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
As part of continuing research for the discovery of bioactive polyketides, the fermentation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. canescens
CGMCC
</tp:taxon-name>
3.79658 under OSMAC method led to isolation of seven undescribed highly oxygenated aromatic polyketides (Fig. 1). Of these, two pairs of dimeric aromatic polyketide enantiomers (±)-penicanesins A (
1
) and B (
2
), two acyl phloroglucinol pyrones namely penicanesins C (
3
) and D (
4
), two pairs of phthalide-type derivatives called penicanesins E (
5
) and F (
6
), and a phenylacetic acid analogue penicanesin G (
7
), together with seven known ones including methyl 2-acetyl-3,5-dihydroxyphenylacetate (
8
) (Varma et al., 2006), 2-methyl-5-methoxycarbonylmethyl-7-hydroxychromone (
9
) (Xu et al., 2013), 15-deoxyoxalicine B (
10
) (Zhang et al., 2003), pseurotin E (
11
) (Breitenstein et al., 1981), griseofulvin (
12
) (Cacho et al., 2013), desmethyl-dehydrogriseofulvin A (
13
) (Cacho et al., 2013), and 3-chloro-6-hydroxy-2-(4-hydroxy-2-methoxy-6-methylphenoxy)-4-methoxy-benzoate (
14
) (Xia et al., 2011) were identified. Among them, compounds 
1
and 
2
are two pairs of racemic tetracyclic aromatic heterocycles with an unusual 6/6/6/6 ring system,
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
* Corresponding author. ** Corresponding author. 
E-mail addresses:
zhangyh@mails.tjmu.edu.cn (H. Zhu), zhuhucheng@hust.edu.cn (Y. Zhang).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>which is only presented in four examples produced by fungi (El Amrani et al., 2014; Singh et al., 2002; Talontsi et al., 2013). Their structures and absolute configurations are established by a combination of extensive spectroscopic data, X-ray diffraction (XRD), and electronic circle dichroism (ECD) calculation. Herein, we report the isolation, structure elucidation, and inhibition activity of human cancer cell lines.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
2. Results and discussion
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Compound 
1
was obtained as a yellow oil. The positive mode high resolution electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (HRESIMS) of 
1
exhibited an [M + Na] 
+
ion peak at 
m
/ 
z
411.0680 with a molecular formula of C 
19
H 
16
O 
9
Na (12 degrees of unsaturation). The IR absobtion bonds at 3381, 1686, 1605, and 1433 cm 
1
revealed the presence of the hydroxyl groups, carbonyl groups, and benzene rings. Analyses of 1D NMR and HSQC spectra (Table 1) showed nineteen carbons in 
1
, where comprised significant signals at 
δ
H
7.85 (1H, s, H-13) and 7.45 (1H, s, H- 6), 
δ
C
149.6 (C-5), 147.9 (C-13), 145.2 (C-15), 143.7 (C-4), 142.8 (C-14), 141.9 (C-3), 126.2 (C-11), 121.8 (C-2), 120.9 (C-7), 119.5 (C-10), 110.8 (C-12), and 101.7 (C-6) belonging to two highly substituted and oxygenated aromatic rings. Extra resonances were distributed to an aldehyde group at 
δ
H
11.01 (s, H-18) and 
δ
C
190.8 (C-18), a ketone carbonyl at 
δ
C
195.0 (C-8), a methoxyl group at 
δ
H
3.61 and 
δ
C
56.2 (Me- 19), and two singlet methyls at 
δ
H
2.54 (Me-16) and 2.24 (Me-17). That spectroscopic information including 2D NMR (Fig. 2) corroborated a skeleton of aromatic polyketide dimer for 
1
, which was structurally close to integrastatin B featuring a 6/6/6/6 heterotetracyclic ring core (Singh et al., 2002). The only difference between 
1
and integrastatin B was a decrease of the methyl (Me-20), whereas the HMBC correlation from Me-19 to C-5 suggested the keep of Me-19 (Fig. 2).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The evaluation of optical rotation (OR) and ECD spectra revealed compound 
1
was a racemic mixture. Subsequently, the separation of enantiomers was accomplished by a chiral column. Based on well matched experimental and calculated curves of (+)-(1 
S
,9 
S
)- 
1
and ()-(1 
R
,9 
R
)- 
1
as shown in Fig. 3, theoretical ECD calculation with timedependent density functional theory (TDDFT) method at B3LYP/6-31G
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
(d) level herein determined the absolute stereochemistry of (+)- 
1
and ()- 
1
. Therefore, compound 
1
was constructed as described and given a name penicanesin A.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Compound 
2
namely penicanesin B, was initially got as a yellow oil and with the same molecular formula (C 
19
H 
16
O 
9
) as 
1
corresponding to a positive ion peak at 
m
/ 
z
411.0676 [M + Na] 
+
in HRESIMS spectrum. The spectroscopic data of 
2
elucidated it was also an aromatic polyketide dimer with the same chemical architecture of 
1
, except for the location of a methoxyl group. The key HMBC correlation from Me-20 to C-13 (Fig. 2) suggested the location of the methoxy to be on C-13. Although, compound 
2
was also considered to be a pair of enantiomers according to the absence of Cotton effect and a OR value close to zero, the separation of the racemic mixture was unsuccessfully performed using different chiral columns.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Compound 
3
exhibited a molecular formula of C 
16
H 
16
O 
7
(requiring 9 degrees of unsaturation) determined by HRESIMS data with a molecular ion at 
m
/ 
z
343.0790 (calcd for C 
16
H 
16
O 
7
Na, 343.0788). Analyses of IR and NMR data (Table 1) demonstrated 
3
possessed an acyl 
α
-pyrone phloroglucinol scaffold similar to achyroclinopyrone A (Akaberi et al., 2019; Bohlmann et al., 1980). However, the presence of a conspicuous aromatic methine (7-CH) at 
δ
H
6.55 (s) and 
δ
C
105.1 in 
3
indicated it was not a full substituted aromatic ring, where key HMBC correlations from H-7 to C-3/C-5/C-6/C-8/C-9 and H-9 to C-3/C-7/C-8/C-10/C-11/C-15 identified an 
α
-pyrone moiety linked to C-8 of a pentasubstituted aromatic ring (Fig. 2). The position of methyl ketone and methoxyl groups on the benzene ring were respectively deduced from HMBC correlations of Me-1/C-3 and Me-17/C-6. Additionally, HMBC correlations from Me-16 to C-13/C-14 indicated the location of a methyl group (Me-16) at C-13. Thus, 
3
was firstly reported and designated penicanesin C.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Penicanesin D (
4
) showed a molecular formula of C 
18
H 
20
O 
8
(HRE- SIMS at 
m
/ 
z
387.1043 [M + Na] 
+
, calcd for C 
18
H 
20
O 
8
Na, 387.1050), The 1D and 2D NMR spectra of 
4
revealed an identical construction with compound 
3
. The observed change of a singlet methyl (Me-16) of 
3
to a doublet Me-18 [
δ
H
1.22 (d, 
J
= 6.3), 
δ
C
23.4] in 
4
and additional signals of an oxygenated methine at 
δ
H
4.10 (ddd, 
J
= 8.1, 6.3, 4.7, H-17) and 
δ
C
66.2 (C-17) and a methylene 16-CH 
2
[
δ
H
2.59 (dd, 
J
= 14.4, 4.7), 2.53
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fig. 1.
Chemical structures of compounds 
1–14
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Recorded in pyridine- 
d
5
. 
b
Recorded in methanol- 
d
4
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fig. 2.
Key HMBC, 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, and NOESY correlations of compounds 
1–4
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fig. 3.
Comparison of calculated and experimental ECD spectra of (±)- 
1
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
(dd, 
J
= 14.4, 8.1) and 
δ
C
44.0] combining with COSY cross-peaks of a spin system of –CH 
2
‒CH(OH)–CH 
3
as well as key HMBC correlations from H-16/H-17 to C-13 and H-16 to C-14 (Fig. 2), demonstrated a propan-2-ol group instead of the methyl (Me-16) in 
3
substituted on C-
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
13. The absolute configuration of the only chiral center C-17 was firstly assigned to be 
S
by comparison of OR value ([
α
] 
D
32.00) with a known pentaketide 
α
-pyrone ([
α
] 
D
20.3) reported by Tang and coworkers (Fujimoto et al., 2003; Zhou et al., 2010). Moreover, ECD calculation using TDDFT method at the PBE0-D3(BJ)/def2-SVP level also approved an 
S
configuration where experimental ECD spectrum was in good agreement with calculated ECD spectrum as shown (Fig. 4).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Penicanesin E (
5
), was obtained as a colorless crystal and its molecular formula was determined to be C 
10
H 
10
O 
6
by HRESIMS spectrum with a 
pseudo
-molecular ion at 
m
/ 
z
249.0373 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
10
H 
10
O 
6
Na, 249.0370). The obvious IR absorptions indicated hydroxyl groups at 3389 cm 
1
, ester carbonyl groups at 1741 cm 
1
, and a benzene ring at 1630 and 1502 cm 
1
. Data analysis of 
1
H and 
13
C NMR (Table 2) featured a characteristic proton at 
δ
H
6.83 (s) and eight carbons at 
δ
C
98.1 (C-8), 105.2 (C-3), 116.6 (C-9), 130.6 (C-4), 140.1 (C-6), 140.7 (C-5), 150.2 (C-7), and 168.5 (C-1) of an aromatic ring and a lactone ring, which showed a phthalide skeleton similar to a previously isolate penicichrysogenin D (Qi et al., 2017). The planar structure of 
5
was further identified by HMBC spectrum (Fig. 5), of which a correlation of Me-10/C-3 revealed a substituent C-3 with a methyl group (Me-10) in 
5
rather than a long alkyl chain in penicichrysogenin D. Additionally,
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fig. 4.
Comparison of calculated and experimental ECD spectra of 
4
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Table 2
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
1
H and 
13
C NMR Data of 
5 7
(
δ
in ppm, 
J
in Hz).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Recorded in methanol- 
d
4
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Recorded in DMSO‑ 
d
6
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c
Overlapped.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fig. 5.
Key HMBC correlations of compounds 
5–7
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
the absent signal of a methoxyl in 1D NMR spectrum suggested a hydroxyl at C-3 in 
5
. XRD results further confirmed the constructed structure for 
5
(CCDC, 1904336, Fig. S48). Although we got the crystal of 
5
, it also displayed a racemic mixture and the separation of enantiomers using chiral columns was failed due to the tautomerization of the hemiketone group (Fig. S49).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Compound 
6
namely penicanesin F, was also a phthalide derivative with a hydroxyisobenzofuranone core same to 
5
, illustrated by its molecular formula of C 
11
H 
12
O 
6
with a positive ion at 
m
/ 
z
263.0528 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
11
H 
12
O 
6
Na, 263.0526) in HRESIMS spectrum and analyses of 1D NMR data (Table 2). The structural distinction between them was a methoxyl group of C-3 in 
6
substituted the hydroxyl group in 
5
, which was recognized from HMBC correlations shown in Fig. 5 and XRD result (CCDC, 1978847, Fig. S50). However, an optical rotation value close to zero and a space group of crystallographic results pointed out a pair of enantiomers. The subsequently depuration of two enantiomers using a chiral column seemed like effective (Fig. S51), the recrystallization results still exhibited a mixture which may be caused by the presence of the acetal moiety leading to an unstable hydroxyfuranone ring.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Compound 
7
was classified as a phenylacetic acid derivative based on analyses of 1D and 2D NMR spectra (Table 2 and Fig. 5) and the HRESIMS spectrum, which was structurally similar to a known compound 
8
(Varma et al., 2006). The absence of carbon signals of a methyl and ketone carbonyl and the molecular formula (C 
10
H 
10
O 
6
) as well as a presence of a signal at 
δ
C
174.1 (C-9) of 
7
suggested that a carboxyl group located on C-8 of 
7
replaced an acetyl group in 
8
. Therefore, compound 
7
was determined and given a name penicanesin G.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The evaluation of cytotoxicity against human cancer cell lines including HL-60, A549, SMMC-7721, MCF-7, and SW480 for all compounds using MTS assay revealed that (±)- 
1
showed potent antitumor activities against HL-60, SMMC-7721, and SW480 with IC 
50
values ranging from 12.5 ± 0.9 to 17.2 ± 0.6 
μ
M, where cisplatin and taxol were used as positive control (Table 3). Intriguingly, the enantiomer of ()- 
1
displayed better activity than (+)- 
1
, which indicated a selection of optical activity for potential lead compounds. In addition, inhibition of NO production of all isolates was carried out and showed no activity. The screening of protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B (PTP1B) inhibitory activity exhibited that compound 
4
has weak inhibitory of PTP1B with a 58.7% inhibition at 50 
μ
M (Suramin was used as positive control with a 96.1% inhibition at 20 
μ
M).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
3. Conclusion
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
In summary, seven unreported highly oxygenated aromatic polyketide analogues, penicanesins A‒G (
1–7
), along with seven known products were isolated from two culture broths of the fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
uncovered by OSMAC strategy. Their structures including absolute configurations were established using detailed spectroscopic analysis and theoretical ECD calculations. Activity investigation of those products shows that ()- 
1
exhibits potential inhibition of human cancer cell lines HL-60 and SW480 with IC 
50
values at 13.8 ± 0.6 and 12.5 ± 0.9 
μ
M respectively, whereas the enantiomer (+)- 
1
shows less active.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4. Experimental section
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Optical rotations were determined with a Rudolph Autopol IV automatic polarimeter. The UV, IR, and ECD spectra were obtained on a PerkinElmer LAMBDA 35 UV/Vis spectrophotomer, a Bruker Vertex 70 instrument, and a JASCO-810 ECD spectrometer, respectively. Crystal Xray diffraction data were measured on a Rigaku SC-XRD diffractometer (XtaLAB PRO MM007HF) and Bruker D8 Venture Photon II through a graphite monochromatized Cu Kα radiation (
λ
= 1.54178 Å). NMR spectra were recorded on a Bruker AscendTM 400 and 600 MHz spectrometer, with 
1
H and 
13
C NMR chemical shifts referenced to the solvent or solvent impurity peaks for pyridine- 
d
5
(
δ
H
8.74, 7.58, 7.22 and 
δ
C
150.35, 135.91, 123.87), methanol- 
d
4
(
δ
H
3.31 and 
δ
C
49.0), and DMSO‑ 
d
6
(
δ
H
2.50 and 
δ
C
39.52). HRESIMS data were acquired using a Thermo Fisher LC-LTQ-Orbitrap XL spectrometer and an electrospray ionization (ESI) and a hybrid quadrupole time-of-flight (q-TOF) mass spectrometer (model 6540, Agilent). The measurement temperature was
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Table 3
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Cytotoxic activity (IC 
50
values in 
μ
M) of compounds 
1
, 
3
, 
4
, 
7–14
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
300 K. Semi-preparative HPLC utilized an Agilent 1200 quaternary system with a UV detector, using a reversed-phased C18 column (5 
μ
m, 10 × 250 mm, Welch Ultimate XB-C18) and chiral columns (5 
μ
m, 4.6 × 250 mm, DAICEL CHIRALPAK IG and IC). Column chromatography (CC) was performed using silica gel (Qingdao Marine Chemical Inc., China), ODS (50 
μ
m, Merck, Germany), Sephadex LH-20 (Merck, Germany), respectively. Thin-layer chromatography (TLC) was performed with silica gel 60 F 
254
(Yantai Chemical Industry Research Institute).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.2. Fungal material
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
Sopp O.J. (Trichocomaceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
, strain CGMCC 3.7958 (ATCC 10419) was bought from China general microbiological culture collection center (CGMCC). ITS-rDNA sequence amplified by conserved primer ITS1 and ITS4 shows 100% identity with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
ATCC
</tp:taxon-name>
10419 v1.0 by JGI BLAST (https:// mycocosm.jgi.doe.gov/pages/blast-query.jsf?db=Penca1).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.3. Fermentation and extraction
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The fungal strain was maintained on potato dextrose agar (PDA) medium at 28 
◦
C for 5 days used as the seed culture. The fermentation was carried out on solid rice medium at 25 
◦
C for 30 days, in 250 Erlenmeyer flasks (1 L) with 200.0 g rice and 200 mL distilled water for each flask. After incubation, the moldy rice was extracted with ethanol at room temperature. The entire crude extract was suspended in H 
2
O and extracted with ethyl acetate (EtOAc) to yield 350.0 g of residue. In addition, we also tried a liquid medium (10 g maltose, 10 g glucose, 5 g peptone, 10 g mannitol, 2.5 g yeast extract, 0.25 g K 
2
HPO 
4
, 0.25 g FeSO 
4
⋅7H 
2
O, and 500 mL distilled water per 1L Erlenmeyer flask) to culture this fungus under shaken for 9 days (27 
◦
C, 160 rpm).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.4. Isolation and purification
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The EtOAc extract was subjected to a flash column chromatography (CC) over silica gel with a gradient elution using petroleum ether/EtOAc (50:1 to EtOAc neat, v/v) and EtOAc/MeOH gradient (10:1 to MeOH, v/ v) to afford 5 fractions (Fr.1‒Fr.5). The Fr.3 was subjected to a RP-C18 gel column with a gradient elution using MeOH/H2O (20%–100%, v/v) to yield eight fractions (Fr.3A‒Fr.3J). Compound 
5
(20.0 mg) was isolated from Fr.3B by a recrystallization in MeOH. Fr.3D was separated by a silica CC using CH 
2
Cl 
2
/MeOH (60:1, v/v) to get 5 subfractions (Fr.3D1-5). From Fr.3D-1 and 3D-2, compounds 
6
(10.0 mg) and 
8
(11.0 mg) were respectively purified by semi-preparative HPLC (42% MeOH in H 
2
O for 40 min; flow rate: 2.0 mL/min; 
6
: 
t
R
= 28.5 min; 
8
: 
t
R
= 30.9 min). 
7
(1.8 mg) was further isolated from Fr.3D-5 using HPLC (45% MeOH in H 
2
O for 30 min; flow rate: 2.0 mL/min; 
7
: 
t
R
= 22.0 min). In Fr.3I, compound 
9
(7.5 mg) was separated with semi-preparative HPLC (43% MeOH in H 
2
O for 70 min; flow rate: 2.0 mL/min; 
9
: 
t
R
= 67.9 min). The Fr.4 was also subjected to a RP-C18 gel with a gradient elution using MeOH/H 
2
O (20%–100%, v/v) to yield eight fractions (Fr.4A‒Fr.4H). After a column chromatography using Sephadex LH-20 with CH 
2
Cl 
2
/ MeOH (1:1, v/v), Fr.4C was divided into 5 subfractions (Fr.4C-1‒Fr.4C- 5). From Fr. 4C-4, compounds 
1
(16.0 mg) and 
2
(5.0 mg) were purified by semi-preparative HPLC (52% MeOH in H 
2
O with 0.09% TFA for 50 min; flow rate: 2.0 mL/min; 
1
: 
t
R
= 41.0 min; 
2
: 
t
R
= 36.0 min). Racemic resolutions of 
1
and 
2
were performed by a chiral HPLC to yield pure enantiomers ()- 
1
(10.2 mg) and (+)- 
1
(4.5 mg) (88% hexane/isopropyl alcohol for 35 min; flow rate: 1 mL/min; ()- 
1
: 
t
R
= 21.0 min; (+)- 
1
: 
t
R
= 30.5 min). Fr.5 was subjected to a silica gel CC with a gradient elution using MeOH/H 
2
O (20%–100%, v/v) to yield eight fractions (Fr.5A–Fr.5E). Compound 
10
(2.4 mg) was purified from Fr.5D using semi-preparative HPLC (51% MeOH in H 
2
O for 30 min; flow rate: 2.0 mL/min; 
10
: 
t
R
= 24.5 min).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The whole broth of liquid medium was filtrated and then the aqueous solution was extracted with EtOAc at room temperature to yield 2.1 g</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
crude extract. The extract was subsequently subjected to CC over RPC18 gel with gradient elution using MeOH/H 
2
O (20–100%, v/v) to afford 10 fractions (Fr.1 Fr.10). Compounds 
3
(7.0 mg) and 
4
(2.8 mg) were isolated from Fr.2 by semi-preparative HPLC (44% MeOH in H 
2
O with 0.05% TFA for 60 min; flow rate: 2.0 mL/min; 
3
: 
t
R
= 50.5 min; 
4
: 
t
R
= 41.5 min). In Fr.5, 
11
(3.1 mg) was purified using HPLC (48% MeOH in H 
2
O for 60 min; flow rate: 2.0 mL/min; 
11
: 
t
R
= 53.1 min). From Fr.7, compounds 
12
(1.0 mg) and 
13
(1.5 mg) were further got with semi-preparative HPLC (52% ACN in H 
2
O for 55 min; flow rate: 2.0 mL/min; 
12
: 
t
R
= 43.3 min; 
13
: 
t
R
= 47.5 min). Compound 
14
(1.5 mg) was isolated from Fr.9 by semi-preparative HPLC (57% ACN in H 
2
O for 40 min; flow rate: 2.0 mL/min; 
14
: 
t
R
= 36.5 min).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.4.1. Penicanesin A (1)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil; (+)- 
1
: [
α
] 
D
25
.[
α
] 
D
25
[
α
] 
D
25
+38.2 (
c
0.11, MeOH); ()- 
1
: [
α
] 
D
25
33.5 (
c
0.05, MeOH); UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
nm (log 
ε
): 219 (4.1), 318 (3.7); IR (KBr) 
u
max
cm 
1
: 3381, 2923, 2854, 1686, 1605, 1453, 1434, 1121, 1034; 
1
H (400 MHz) and 
13
C (100 MHz) NMR data (pyridine- 
d
5
) see Table 1; (+) ESI-MS: 
m/z
411.0680 [M + Na] 
+
, (calcd. for C 
19
H 
16
NaO 
9
, 411.0687).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.4.2. Penicanesin B (2)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil; UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
nm (log 
ε
): 220 (4.5), 317 (4.1); IR (KBr) 
u
max
cm 
1
: 3437, 2930, 2859, 2858, 1676, 1634, 1497, 1468, 1372, 1329, 1198, 1143; 
1
H (400 MHz) and 
13
C (100 MHz) NMR data (pyridine- 
d
5
) see Table 1; (+) ESI-MS: 
m/z
411.0676 [M + Na] 
+
, (calcd. for C 
19
H 
16
NaO 
9
, 411.0687).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.4.3. Penicanesin C (3)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
nm (log 
ε
): 202 (4.2), 283 (3.8); IR (KBr) 
u
max
cm 
1
: 3427, 2939, 1744, 1680, 1630, 1500, 1460, 1380, 1359, 1313, 1187, 1146, 1108, 1072, 1034, 837, 801; 
1
H (400 MHz) and 
13
C (100 MHz) NMR data (methanol- 
d
4
) see Table 1; (+) ESI-MS: 
m/z
343.0790 [M + Na] 
+
, (calcd. for C 
16
H 
16
NaO 
7
, 343.0788).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.4.4. Penicanesin D (4)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
White amorphous powder; [
α
] 
D
25
32.0 (
c
0.025, MeOH); UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
nm (log 
ε
): 283 (3.8); IR (KBr) 
u
max
cm 
1
: 3424, 2926, 1683, 1636, 1435, 1384, 1208, 1188, 1138, 1029, 837, 802, 723; 
1
H (600 MHz) and 
13
C (150 MHz) NMR data (methanol- 
d
4
) see Table 2; (+) ESI-MS: 
m/z
387.1043 [M + Na] 
+
, (calcd. for C 
18
H 
20
NaO 
8
, 387.1050).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.4.5. Penicanesin E (5)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Colorless crystal; UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
nm (log 
ε
): 214 (4.3), 281 (3.8); IR (KBr) 
u
max
cm 
1
: 3382, 2943, 2850, 1741, 1630, 1502, 1462, 1358, 1306, 1208, 1164, 1142, 1101, 1053, 1025, 897, 839, 784, 692; 
1
H (400 MHz) and 
13
C (100 MHz) NMR data (DMSO‑ 
d
6
) see Table 2; (+) ESI-MS: 
m/z
249.0373 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. for C 
10
H 
10
NaO 
6
, 249.0370).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.4.6. Penicanesin F (6)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Colorless crystal; UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
nm (log 
ε
): 217 (4.3), 284 (3.9); IR (KBr) 
u
max
cm 
1
: 3427, 2939, 2852, 1745, 1631, 1501, 1460, 1380, 1359, 1312, 1187, 1147, 1108, 1072, 1035, 882, 838, 783, 684; 
1
H (600 MHz) and 
13
C (150 MHz) NMR data (methanol- 
d
4
) see Table 2; (+) ESIMS: 
m/z
263.0528 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd. for C 
11
H 
12
NaO 
6
, 263.0526).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.4.7. Penicanesin G (7)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Pale yellow oil; UV (MeCN) 
λ
max
nm (log 
ε
): 202 (4.1), 220 (4.0), 269 (3.8), 302 (3.7); IR (KBr) 
u
max
cm 
1
: 3418, 3210, 2956, 2924, 2853, 1708, 1610, 1593, 1384, 1352, 1270, 1170, 1022, 849; 
1
H (400 MHz) and 
13
C (100 MHz) NMR data (methanol- 
d
4
) see Table 2; () ESI-MS: 
m/ z
225.0400 [M H] (calcd. for C 
10
H 
9
O 
6
, 225.0393).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.5. X-ray crystal structure analysis
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Colorless crystals of 5 and 6 were obtained in MeOH. The crystal data were collected using a Rigaku SC-XRD with a graphite monochromator using Cu K 
α
radiation. The structures were refined with the SHELXTL refinement package using least squares minimization. The crystallographic data for 5 and 6 were deposited in the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre (CCDC deposition numbers: 5: 1904336; 6: 1978847). The data can be obtained freely from the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Centre by visiting sites of www.ccdc.cam.ac.uk/co nts/retrieving.html.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
X-ray crystallographic data for 
5
: C 
10
H 
10
O 
6
(
M
= 226.18): monoclinic, space group 
P
121/ 
c
1, a = 8.2975(7) Å, b = 14.8735(13) Å, c = 7.7147(7) Å, 
V
= 943.03(14) Å 
3
, 
Z
= 4, 
T
= 100.(2) K, 
μ
(Cu K 
α
) = 1.158 mm 
1
, 
Dcalc
= 1.593 g/cm 
3
, 12475 reflections measured (12.30 
◦
≤ 2 
θ
≤ 145.02 
◦
), 1852 independent reflections (
R
int
= 0.0384). The final 
R
1
values were 0.0349 (

I
&gt;

2 
σ
(
I
)). The final 
wR
(
F
2
) values were 0.1465 (

I
&gt;

2 
σ
(
I
)). The final 
R
1
values were 0.0354 (all data). The final 
wR
(
F
2
) values were 0.1475 (all data). The goodness of fit on 
F
2
was 1.399.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
X-ray crystallographic data for 
6
: C 
11
H 
12
O 
6
(
M
= 240.21): monoclinic, space group 
P
21/n, 
a
= 10.4924(3) Å, 
b
= 7.0255(2) Å, 
c
= 16.0752(4) Å, 
V
= 786.66(6) Å 
3
, 
Z
= 4, 
T
= 293.(2) K, 
μ
(Cu K 
α
) = 0.976 mm 
1
, 
Dcalc
= 1.381 g/cm 
3
, 10398 reflections measured (9.216 
◦
≤ 2 
θ
≤ 147.808 
◦
), 2304 independent reflections (
R
int
= 0.0515) which were used in all calculations. The final 
R
1
values were 0.0525 (

I
&gt;

2 
σ
(
I
)). The final 
wR
(
F
2
) values were 0.1513 (

I
&gt;

2 
σ
(
I
)). The final 
R
1
values were 0.0623 (all data). The final 
wR
(
F
2
) values were 0.1624 (all data). The goodness of fit on 
F
2
was 0.980.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.6. Computational method
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
In general, conformational analyses were carried out via random searching in the Sybyl-X 2.0 uing the MMFF94S force field with an energy cutoff of 2.5 kcal/mol. The optimized conformation geometries and thermodynamic parameters of all selected conformations were provided. For 
1
, the predominant conformers were optimized at the B3LYP/ 6-31G(d) level. Theoretical ECD calculations of all conformers were performed using Time Dependent Density Functional Theory (TDDFT) at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level in MeOH with the PCM model by the Gaussian 09 program(Frisch et al., 2009). For compound 
4
, the conformers were re-optimized using DFT at the PBE0-D3(BJ)/def2-SVP level in MeOH using the polarizable conductor calculation model (SMD) by the ORCA4.2.1 program(Neese, 2012, 2017). The energies, oscillator strengths, and rotational strengths (velocity) of the first 60 electronic excitations were calculated using the TDDFT methodology at the CAM-B3LYP/def2-TZVP level in MeOH. The ECD spectra were simulated by the overlapping Gaussian function (half the bandwidth at 1/e peak height, sigma = 0.30 for all)(Stephens and Harada, 2010). The ECD spectra of 
1
and 
4
were obtained by measuring the Boltzmann distribution rate of each geometric conformation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
4.7. Cytotoxicity assay
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The cytotoxicity was determined by the MTS assay. Colorimetric assays were performed to evaluate each compound’ s activity. HL-60 (Human promyelocytic leukemia cells), A549 (human lung cancer cells), SMMC-7721 (human hepatocellular carcinoma cells), MCF-7 (human breast adenocarcinoma cells), and SW480 (Human colon cancer cell) tumor cells were purchased from National Collection of Authenticated Cell Cultures of China. All cells were cultured in RPMI- 1640 or DMEM medium (Hyclone, Logan, UT) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Hyclone) at 37 
◦
C in a humidified atmosphere with 5% CO 
2
. Cell viability was assessed by conducting colorimetric measurements of the amount of insoluble formazan formed in living cells based on the reduction of 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-5(3-carboxymethoxyphenyl)-2-(4-sulfopheny)-2H-tetrazolium (MTS) (Sigma, St. Louis, MO). Briefly, 100 
μ
L of suspended adherent cells were seeded into each well of a 96-well cell culture plate and allowed to adhere for 12–24 h before drug addition. Suspended cells were seeded just before drug addition, with an initial density of 1 × 
105
cells/mL in 100 
μ
L of medium. Each tumor cell line was exposed to each test compound at various concentrations in triplicate for 48 h. After the incubation, MTS solution (20 
μ
L) was added to each well, and the incubation was continued for 2–4 h at 37 
◦
C. The optical density of the lysate was measured at 492 nm in a 96-well microtiter plate reader (MULTISKAN FC). The IC50 value of each compound was calculated by Reed and Muench’ s method. Cisplatin® (Sigma, purity
&gt;
95%) and taxol were used as positive control compounds. The purity of all compounds used for the biological assays was
&gt;
98% as assessed from the NMR spectra and HPLC traces.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Acknowledgments
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>We thank the Analytical and Testing Center at Huazhong University of Science and Technology for assistance in testing of ECD, UV, and IR analyses. This work was financially supported by the Program for Changjiang Scholars of Ministry of Education of People’ s Republic of China (No. T2016088); National Natural Science Foundation for Distinguished Young Scholars of China (No. 81725021); Innovative Research Groups of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81721005); National Natural Science Foundation for Young Scientists of China (No. 31800285); the Academic Frontier Youth Team of HUST; the Integrated Innovative Team for Major Human Diseases Program of Tongji Medical College (HUST).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113012.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
References
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Akaberi, M., Danton, O., Tayarani-Najaran, Z., Asili, J., Iranshahi, M., Emami, S.A., Hamburger, M., 2019. HPLC-based activity profiling for antiprotozoal compounds in the endemic Iranian medicinal plant 
Helichrysum oocephalum
. J. Nat. Prod. 82, 958–969. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.8b01031.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Bertinettia, B.V., Pen, N.I., Cabrera, G.M., 2009. An antifungal tetrapeptide from the culture of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
. Chem. Biodivers. 6, 1178–1184. https://doi.org/ 10.1002/cbdv.200800336.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Bohlmann, F., Abraham, W.-R., Robinson, H., King, R.M., 1980. A new labdane derivative and geranylphloroglucinols from 
Achyrocline alata
. Phytochemistry 19, 2475–2477. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(00)91058-6.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Breitenstein, W., Chexal, K.K., Mohr, P., Tamm, C., 1981. Pseurotin B, C, D, and E. Further new metabolites of 
Pseudeurotium ovalis
STOLK. Helv. Chim. Acta 64, 379–388. https://doi.org/10.1002/hlca.19810640203.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Cacho, R.A., Chooi, Y.H., Zhou, H., Tang, Y., 2013. Complexity generation in fungal polyketide biosynthesis: a spirocycle-forming P450 in the concise pathway to the antifungal drug griseofulvin. ACS Chem. Biol. 8, 2322–2330. https://doi.org/ 10.1021/cb400541z.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>El Amrani, M., Lai, D.W., Debbab, A., Aly, A.H., Siems, K., Seidel, C.,</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Schnekenburger, M., Gaigneaux, A., Diederich, M., Feger, D., Lin, W.H., Proksch, P., 2014. Protein kinase and HDAC inhibitors from the endophytic fungus 

Epicoccum 
<tp:taxon-name>nigrum</tp:taxon-name>

. J. Nat. Prod. 77, 49–56. https://doi.org/10.1021/np4005745.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Frank, M., Hartmann, R., Plenker, M., Mandi, A., Kurtan, T., Ozkaya, F.C., Muller, W.E. G., Kassack, M.U., Hamacher, A., Lin, W., Liu, Z., Proksch, P., 2019. Brominated azaphilones from the sponge-associated fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
strain 4.14.6a. J. Nat. Prod. 82, 2159–2166. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.9b00151.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Frisch, M.J., Trucks, G.W., Schlegel, H.B., Scuseria, G.E., Robb, M.A., Cheeseman, J.R., Scalmani, G., Barone, V., Mennucci, B., Petersson, G.A., Nakatsuji, H., Caricato, M., Li, X., Hratchian, H.P., Izmaylov, A.F., Bloino, J., Zheng, G., Sonnenberg, J.L., Hada, M., Ehara, M., Toyota, K., Fukuda, R., Hasegawa, J., Ishida, M., Nakajima, T., Honda, Y., Kitao, O., Nakai, H., Vreven, T., Montgomery Jr., J.A., Peralta, J.E., Ogliaro, F., Bearpark, M.J., Heyd, J., Brothers, E.N., Kudin, K.N., Staroverov, 
V.N.
, Kobayashi, R., Normand, J., Raghavachari, K., Rendell, A.P., Burant, J.C., Iyengar, S. S., Tomasi, J., Cossi, M., Rega, N., Millam, N.J., Klene, M., Knox, J.E., Cross, J.B., Bakken, V., Adamo, C., Jaramillo, J., Gomperts, R., Stratmann, R.E., Yazyev, O., Austin, A.J., Cammi, R., Pomelli, C., Ochterski, J.W., Martin, R.L., Morokuma, K.,
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Zakrzewski, V.G., Voth, G.A., Salvador, P., Dannenberg, J.J., Dapprich, S.,</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Daniels, A.D., Farkas, O ¨., Foresman, J.B., Ortiz, J.V., Cioslowski, J., Fox, D.J., 2009. Gaussian 09, Rev. E 01. Gaussian, Inc., Wallingford, CT, USA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Fujimoto, H., Nozawa, M., Okuyama, E., Ishibashi, M., 2003. Six new constituents from an ascomycete, 
Chaetomium quadrangulatum
, found in a screening study focused on monoamine oxidase inhibitory activity. Chem. Pharm. Bull. 51, 247–251. https:// doi.org/10.1002/chin.200334208.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Malik, A., Ardalani, H., Anam, S., McNair, L.M., Kromphardt, K.J.K., Frandsen, R.J.N., Franzyk, H., Staerk, D., Kongstad, K.T., 2020. Antidiabetic xanthones with alphaglucosidase inhibitory activities from an endophytic 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
. Fitoterapia 142, 104522. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2020.104522.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Neese, F., 2012. The ORCA program system. Wiley Interdiscip. Rev.: Comput. Mol. Sci. 2, 73–78. https://doi.org/10.1002/wcms.81.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Neese, F., 2017. Software update: the ORCA program system, version 4.0. Wiley Interdiscip. Rev.: Comput. Mol. Sci. 8, e1327. https://doi.org/10.1002/wcms.1327.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Nicoletti, R., Lopez-Gresa, M.P., Manzo, E., Carella, A., Ciavatta, M.L., 2007. Production and fungitoxic activity of Sch 642305, a secondary metabolite of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
. Mycopathologia 163, 295–301. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11046-007- 9015-x.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Qi, B., Liu, X., Mo, T., Li, S.S., Wang, J., Shi, X.P., Wang, X.H., Zhu, Z.X., Zhao, Y.F., Jin, H.W., Tu, P.F., Shi, S.P., 2017. Nitric oxide inhibitory polyketides from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium chrysogenum
</tp:taxon-name>
MT-12, an endophytic fungus isolated from 
Huperzia serrata
. Fitoterapia 123, 35–43. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fitote.2017.09.014.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Singh, S.B., Zink, D.L., Quamina, D.S., Pelaez, F., Teran, A., Felock, P., Hazuda, D.J., 2002. Integrastatins: structure and HIV-1 integrase inhibitory activities of two novel racemic tetracyclic aromatic heterocycles produced by two fungal species. Tetrahedron Lett. 43, 2351–2354. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040-4039(02)00265- 4.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Stephens, P.J., Harada, N., 2010. ECD cotton effect approximated by the Gaussian curve and other methods. Chirality 22, 229–233. https://doi.org/10.1002/chir.20733.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Talontsi, F.M., Dittrich, B., Schüffler, A., Sun, H., Laatsch, H., 2013. Epicoccolides: antimicrobial and antifungal polyketides from an endophytic fungus 
epicoccum
sp. associated with 
Theobroma cacao
. Eur. J. Org Chem. 3174–3180. https://doi.org/ 10.1002/ejoc.201300146, 2013.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Varma, G.B., Fatope, M.O., Marwah, R.G., Deadman, M.E., Al-Rawahi, F.K., 2006. Production of phenylacetic acid derivatives and 4-epiradicinol in culture by 
Curvularia lunata
. Phytochemistry 67, 1925–1930. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2006.05.032.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Xia, X.K., Li, Q., Li, J., Shao, C.L., Zhang, J.Y., Zhang, Y.G., Liu, X., Lin, Y.C., Liu, C.H., She, Z.G., 2011. Two new derivatives of griseofulvin from the mangrove endophytic fungus 
nigrospora
sp. (strain No. 1403) from 
Kandelia candel (L.) Druce
. Planta Med. 77, 1735–1738. https://doi.org/10.1055/s-0030-1271040.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Xu, W.F., Chen, G., Li, Z.Q., Lu, X., Pei, Y.H., 2013. Isolation and identification of chemical constituents from Rheum palmatum L. J. Shenyang Pharm. Univ. 30, 837–839. https://doi.org/10.14066/j.cnki.cn21-1349/r.2013.11.002.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Yaegashi, J., Romsdahl, J., Chiang, Y.M., Wang, C.C.C., 2015. Genome mining and molecular characterization of the biosynthetic gene cluster of a diterpenic meroterpenoid, 15-deoxyoxalicine B, in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
. Chem. Sci. 6, 6537–6544. https://doi.org/10.1039/C5SC01965F.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Zang, Y., Gong, Y.H., Gong, J.J., Liu, J.J., Chen, C.M., Gu, L.H., Zhou, Y., Wang, J.P., Zhu, H.C., Zhang, Y.H., 2020. Fungal polyketides with three distinctive ring skeletons from the fungus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
uncovered by OSMAC and molecular networking strategies. J. Org. Chem. 85, 4973–4980. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. joc.0c00147.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Zang, Y., Gong, Y.H., Li, X.W., Li, X.N., Liu, J.J., Chen, C.M., Zhou, Y., Gu, L.H., Luo, Z. W., Wang, J.P., Sun, W.G., Zhu, H.C., Zhang, Y.H., 2019. Canescones A–E: aromatic polyketide dimers with PTP1B inhibitory activity from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium canescens
</tp:taxon-name>
. Org. Chem. Front. 6, 3274–3281. https://doi.org/10.1039/c9qo00820a.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Zhang, Y.C., Li, C., Swenson, D.C., Gloer, J.B., Wicklow, D.T., Dowd, P.F., 2003. Novel antiinsectan oxalicine alkaloids from two undescribed fungicolous 
<tp:taxon-name>
Penicillium
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
Org. Lett. 5, 773–776. https://doi.org/10.1021/ol0340686.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Zhou, H., Qiao, K.J., Gao, Z.Z., Meehan, M.J., Li, J.W.-H., Zhao, X.L., Dorrestein, P.C., Vederas, J.C., Tang, Y., 2010. Enzymatic synthesis of resorcylic acid lactones by cooperation of fungal iterative polyketide synthases involved in hypothemycin biosynthesis. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 132, 4530–4531. https://doi.org/10.1021/ ja100060k.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
