<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113014</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Psilostachyins as trypanocidal compounds: Bioguided fractionation of Ambrosia tenuifolia chemically modified extract</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypanosoma cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia
spp. (Asteraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Medina Allende, Ciudad Universitaria, CP, X</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypanosoma cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
Spreng. (Asteraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trypanosoma cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
anti-T. cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
anti-T. cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
Spreng. (Asteraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trypanosoma cruzi parasites</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. cruzi
Tulahuen
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Psilostachyins as trypanocidal compounds: Bioguided fractionation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
chemically modified extract

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Tonino G. Adessi

a
,
b

, Yamile Ana
a, c
, Cinthia C. Stempin
a, c
, M´onica
C. García

a, d
,

Fabricio R. Bisogno 
a, e
, Viviana E. Nicotra
a, b
, Manuela E. García

a, b, 
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Facultad de Ciencias Químicas, Universidad Nacional de C´ordoba
(UNC), Ciudad Universitaria, X5000HUA, 

C´ordoba, 
Argentina
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
Instituto Multidisciplinario de Biología Vegetal (IMBIV), Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y T´ecnicas
(CONICET), 

C´ordoba, 
Argentina
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c
Centro de Investigaciones en Bioquímica Clínica e Inmunología (CIBICI-CONICET), C´ordoba
, 
Argentina
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
d
Unidad de Investigaci´on
y Desarrollo en Tecnología 
Farmac´eutica, (UNITEFA-CONICET), C´ordoba
, 
Argentina
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
e
Instituto de Investigaciones en Físico-Química de C´ordoba
(INFIQC-CONICET), 

C´ordoba, 
Argentina
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Bioguided fractionation</p>
         <p>Extract modifications</p>
         <p>Trypanocidal compounds</p>
         <p>Structure activity relationships</p>
         <p>Sesquiterpene lactones</p>
         <p>Psilostachyins</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
This work focusses on the chemical diversification of an 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
extract and its bioguided fractionation, aiming to unveil the chemical entity responsible for the trypanocidal activity. Besides, a revision of the phytochemical study of this species, based on previous reports of the antiparasitic psilostachyins A and C as main compounds, was conducted. To improve the biological properties of a plant extract through a simple chemical reaction, the oxidative diversification of the dichloromethane extract of this plant species was carried out. A bioguided fractionation of a chemically modified extract was performed by evaluating the inhibitory activity against 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypanosoma cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
trypomastigotes. This experiment led to the isolation of one of the most active compounds. In general terms, epoxidized metabolites were obtained as a result of the oxidation of the major metabolite of the species. The trypanocidal activity of some tested metabolites overperformed the reference drug, benznidazole, displaying no cytotoxicity at trypanocidal concentrations. Key structure-activity relationships were obtained for designing previously undescribed antiparasitic sesquiterpene lactones.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The structural diversity of compounds isolated from natural sources, together with the biological activity they present, is unquestionable. These metabolites have few rivals in any available synthetic screening library (

). It is well-documented that these privileged scaffolds serve as important platforms, as they are biologically pre-validated for library design in the search for new drug candidates (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Nowadays, natural products continue to have a great impact on human health. In addition, chemists have generated semisynthetic analogs that are often more successful than the original natural product in terms of clinical importance (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
In this sense, a large group of compounds of natural origin with a wide range of recognized biological activities is constituted by sesquiterpene lactones (SLs) (

). These represent one of the most relevant groups of metabolites isolated from the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
. Such C-15 terpenoidal compounds commonly have an α- methylene-γ- lactone group in their structure, which is considered essential for their activity (

, b). This chemical functionality is often responsible for biological effects and, in some cases, cytotoxic activity is attributed to this feature. Structural modifications in this group cause the loss of both cytotoxicity and tumor inhibition. Biological activity reports include anticancer, anti-inflammatory, and antiparasitic properties (

; 

; 

). Special mention should be made of anticancer agents, which have proved to have significant cytotoxic activity and selectivity against different tumor cell lines. This remarkable property of some of them and their semi-synthetic derivatives is currently being tested in clinical trials (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
In this sense, another important bioactivity reported for some pseudoguaianolide SL 
types
isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia
spp. (Asteraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
is the trypanocidal activity and its mechanisms (

; 

; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
* Corresponding author. IMBIV-CONICET, Dpto. de Química Org´anica, Facultad de Ciencias Químicas, Universidad Nacional de C´ordoba, Edificio de Ciencias Químicas 2, Haya de la Torre y 
<tp:taxon-name>Medina Allende, Ciudad Universitaria, CP, X</tp:taxon-name>
5000HUA, 
Cordoba
´, 
Argentina
.
</p>
         <p>
E-mail address:
manuelagarcia@unc.edu.ar (M.E. García).
</p>
         <p>
American trypanosomiasis, known as Chagas disease, is caused by infection with the protozoan parasite 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypanosoma cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
. It is endemic to 21 Latin American countries (

), and current treatments are based on benznidazole and nifurtimox, which are both effective, mainly in the acute phase of infection (P´erez-Molina and Molina, 2018). These drugs have severe side effects, and a low treatment adherence rate. In fact, they have been marketed for more than 50 years, are expensive, require long-term treatment, their efficacy to treat the chronic stage of the disease is still controversial, and can favor the development of drug-resistant parasites (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>Drug discovery, normally carried out by the pharmaceutical industry, involves a long and expensive process with an estimated duration of, at least, 15 years. Regarding diseases caused by trypanosomatids, such process is often neglected by the pharmaceutical industry. Therefore, the academy plays an essential role in the discovery, optimization, and development of trypanocidal therapeutic agents. It should be noted that these efforts are not currently underway; thus, more fruitful and cost-effective methodologies for obtaining safe compounds with significant trypanocidal activity are urgently required (Declaration of the Global Chagas Disease Coalition,).</p>
         <p>
Since the 1990s, there has been a renewed interest in herbal medicine, and research on the antiprotozoal effects of plants has been conducted. Several studies of extracts of raw plants, fractions, and pure compounds have allowed the identification of potential treatments for Chagas disease, reducing parasitemia, and showing low cytotoxicity for mammalian cells (

).
</p>
         <p>
One feasible technique for obtaining diversity in natural products, as demonstrated in recent reports, is to strengthen nature’ s biosynthetic machinery. This goal is accomplished by chemically modifying vegetal extracts to produce a wide range of previously unknown semi-synthetic chemicals in a single step (Lopez´et al., 2007; 

).
</p>
         <p>
The diversity of enhanced extracts is achieved through chemical modifications able to reshape the naturally occurring molecular scaffolds through a simple chemical reaction (

). As a result of the isolation of the modified compounds, natural product-like compounds with a dual outcome are obtained, on the one hand, for a strategy of expanding diversity and, on the other, for the fortuitous discovery of a natural product research (

).
</p>
         <p>
Through the chemical diversification of natural product mixtures, the resulting extracts have different composition, proportions, and biomolecular properties from those of their non-modified parents, depending on the 
type
of introduced functionality (M´endez et al., 2011). In terms of practical operation and scope, this is an appealing and alternative proposal for building molecules similar to natural products in one step.
</p>
         <p>
Due to the chemical complexity of the extracts (non-modified or modified) and their intended therapeutic applications, the bioguided fractionation model can be applied. In this regard, bioguided assays with extracts can provide relevant information as a guide for determining how to intensify fractionations and purifications. Furthermore, the discovery of previously undescribed bioactive compounds is inherent to these 
types
of studies. These metabolites are found in less quantity and are less likely to be isolated in a traditional phytochemical study. Besides, useful synergy, addition, and, in some cases, antagonistic interactions are observed. As a result, the overall process is more productive because only the most biologically relevant fractions are explored further (Alvarez´Touron, 2018; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Given the background of the trypanocidal activity of the main metabolites of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
Spreng. (Asteraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
species, and the possibility of improving the biological properties of a plant extract through a simple chemical reaction, the dichloromethane (
CH
2
Cl 
2
) extract of this plant was diversified. A bioguided fractionation of a modified extract was performed by analyzing the anti- 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypanosoma cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
activity. The pursued objective is to improve the trypanocidal effect through a simple oxidative modification that affects polarity, geometry, stereocenters, among other properties, as well as to identify and characterize the chemical entities responsible for the recorded activity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Phytochemical study
</title>
         <p>Performing a phytochemical review has two basic purposes. Firstly, it is well-known that species variability, together with factors such as season of collection, geographical location, and climate affect the content and relative quantity of specific metabolites of interest. Secondly, improving the biological properties through the derivatization of the extract requires prior knowledge of the chemical composition for comparative purposes.</p>
         <p>
The traditional phytochemical processing of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
extract resulted in previously reported different terpenoids (

; 

; 

; 

). In this study, the main isolated compound was psilostachyin B (Psi B) (

), in contrast to previous phytochemical studies in which psilostachyins A and C (Psi A and C) were the main isolated compounds (

). The structures of the isolated SLs (
Fig. 1
) were established based on their NMR data and by comparison with those previously reported (

), and the chemical structures of previously undescribed compounds were elucidated by a combination of 1- and 2-dimensional NMR experiments. The characterization of compounds was completed with other spectroscopic and spectropolarimetric methods (see experimental section).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Extract derivatization
</title>
         <p>
The analysis of the compounds present in the plant extract revealed that the reactive points of derivatization are, in general, hydroxyls, carbonyls and olefins. If a modification of reactive centers is pursued, 
meta
-chloroperbenzoic acid (
m
CPBA) could be used as chemical reagent (

). This is a versatile and inexpensive oxidant, easy to handle and capable of oxidizing an assortment of functional groups under generally mild and clean conditions. It produces stereoselective olefin epoxidation reactions, heteroatom oxidation reactions, oxidative rearrangements and cleavages, Baeyer-Villiger oxidations, among others. There are reports in which transannulation reactions also occurred as a consequence of opening reactions of epoxy rings, contributing to the diversification of compounds (

). In fact, epoxidation constitutes a new ring formation reaction, and this chemical functionality is an important heterocyclic unit found in various naturally occurring molecules. One may argue that oxirane rings are certainly electrophilic and reactive, which may be associated with possible toxicity, as exploited in antitumor cytotoxic agents. However, there are numerous reports of bioactive therapeutical compounds with more than one epoxide group in their structure (

). They are even derivatized or loaded into nanocarriers to avoid their low bioavailability or aqueous solubility, but these groups, which are responsible for their biological activity, are retained (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>Due to these characteristics, this oxidant was the reagent chosen to perform the oxygen enrichment of this plant species extract. In our experience, SLs are unstable at high temperatures and extreme pH, therefore a reagent enabling oxidation reactions under mild conditions is an essential requirement.</p>
         <p>
Before the modification of the extract, it was necessary to optimize the reaction conditions with a model and abundant compound (Psi B, as substrate). The reaction time and temperature varied in addition to the use of a mild base (NaHCO 
3
). The conversion was evaluated by 
1
H-NMR, monitoring the disappearance of key Psi B signals; total conversion was observed in all cases. The absence of base was determined to be the best condition, since no 
m
-chlorobenzoic acid residues were observed at the end of the work-up [
m
CPBA (2.4 eq), 24 h, 25 
◦
C in 
CH
2
Cl 
2
]. For more details, see figure S1 (Supporting information).
</p>
         <p>Usually, reactions on extracts result in an even more complex mixture, including unreacted reagents and unwanted products. In general, components are difficult to purify and, therefore, incompatible with any bioassay. In this case, the reaction was very clean, and pure compounds were easily obtained after a single purification step in all cases.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Bioguided fractionation of modified extract
</title>
         <p>
In a first step, the entire plant extract (
CH
2
Cl 
2
) was partitioned with solvents of increasing polarity, yielding 3 subextracts of different polarity (hexane, 
CH
2
Cl 
2
and EtOAc). From these, the 
CH
2
Cl 
2
extract contained the main part of its mass in SLs (evidenced by 
1
H-NMR). For this reason, extract derivatization with the previously reagent (
m
CPBA) was selected.
</p>
         <p>
The modified extract from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
was subjected to bioguided fractionation as depicted in 
Fig. 2A
, following their antiparasitic activity (as described in section 2.4). The resultant pools were subjected to chromatographic separation, and the pure compounds suitable for biological assays were obtained. From the purification of the different pools, only two major natural SLs, already present in the extract before being derivatized (Psi A and C), were isolated since they did not react with 
m
CPBA. Furthermore, the SLs paulitine and isopaulitin, which have been reported as components of another 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia
species
</tp:taxon-name>
, were also isolated (

). Interestingly, these SLs were not detectable components in the unmodified extract under the working conditions used and would have been obtained from Psi B by epoxidation and subsequent reactions. Finally, three previously undescribed derivatives were obtained, compounds 
1
, 
2
and 
3
. Compounds 
2
and 
3
, were formed as a result of the epoxidation of Psi B, which was consumed after the reaction. Compound 
1
was obtained presumably by the transesterification of compound 
2
, see 
Fig. 3
. For details regarding their structural elucidation, see the supplementary information (discussion and NMR spectra).
</p>
         <p>
2.4. Biological assays
</p>
         <p>
The effect of SLs on 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
trypomastigotes (the infective stage of the parasite) was evaluated 
in vitro
. The life cycle is divided into three stages; amastigotes and trypomastigotes are present in the mammalian host, whereas mainly infectious metacyclic epimastigotes are present in the insect vector. To calculate the inhibition percentage and IC 
50
values, live parasites were counted by optical direct microscopy after treatment, using the vehicle DMSO or benznidazole as negative and positive controls, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
Intriguingly, as shown in Figure S6 (see supplementary information), the total extract was inactive, and began to reveal trypanocidal activity as the amount of SLs present in the partition fractions increased (more specifically in the 
CH
2
Cl 
2
extract). This may be due to an antagonistic effect caused by other compounds present in the initial mixture or by a dilution effect.
</p>
         <p>
As observed in 
Fig. 2B
, three fractions (pools II, III and IV) exhibited higher antiparasitic activity compared to the other samples (pool I, V, VI). Interestingly, pool III exhibited the highest trypanocidal activity, which was similar to that of benznidazole (

p
&gt;

0.05).
</p>
         <p>
The isolated pure compounds after chemical modification of SLs extract were evaluated at concentrations of 1, 5 and 10 μg/mL (
Fig. 2C
). The IC 
50
values were calculated for those that showed the highest 
<tp:taxon-name>
anti-T. cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
activity (
Table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
In general terms, SLs showed an outstanding trypanocidal activity, in some cases comparable to or significantly higher than that exhibited by the reference drug, benznidazole (IC 
50
= 4.2 μM, 

p
&lt;

0.005). Nonetheless, the results can be organized into three groups. The first group includes the compounds that were inactive or had lower inhibitory activity than Psi B (the main chemical precursor of the obtained derivatives). 4- Oxobedfordia acid and compound 1 (which showed an inhibition 
&lt;
10 and 5%, respectively, at 5 μg/mL) were included in this group, as well as compound 2 and altamisin (% inhibition 
&lt;
5 and 
&lt;
10% at 1 and 5 μg/ mL, respectively, see Figure S7).
</p>
         <p>
Psi A, B, isopaulitin and altamisic acid (precursor of Psi B, by ring closure lactonization) belong to the second group, showing a moderate activity (% inhibition ≤ 80% at 5 μg/mL, IC 

50
in

the range 10–20 μM, 
Fig. 2C and S
7). The third group includes the most effective compounds (Psi C, paulitine and compound 3), which exhibited remarkable 
<tp:taxon-name>
anti-T. cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
activity (% inhibition
&gt;
75% at 5 μg/mL, IC 
50
&lt;
10 μM, 
Fig. 2C
).
</p>
         <p>
Although for Psi A and C there are promising 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. cruzi
</tp:taxon-name>
inhibition results previously reported (

), our findings on trypanocidal activity for Psi B suppose a starting point to find a better inhibition. This molecule differs from Psi C in a (C1–C10)-tetrasubstituted double bond, and though its activity is lower, it is a good and accessible precursor to other functionalities, both biosynthetically in nature and semi-synthetically in the laboratory.
</p>
         <p>
The most substantial results were those shown by isopaulitin and paulitin, compounds that were not detected in the phytochemical study and obtained in appreciable quantities after derivatization. This pair of isomers only differs in the configuration of the epoxide ring stereocenters present in their structures. Even though their trypanocidal activity was good, the α- epoxy-isomer (paulitin) exhibited a 9-fold higher activity than the β- epoxy-isomer, isopaulitin (

p
&lt;

0.005). At this point, it is logical to assume that 1,10-epoxy motif is a molecular enhancer for the trypanocidal activity that has been found in this family of compounds.
</p>
         <p>
After the chemical modification of the extract, compounds 1, 2 and 3 were obtained, presumably from the epoxidation of Psi B and subsequent reactions (

; Zhu et al., 2001), probably due to keto-enol tautomerism (see 
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
Compounds 
2
and 
3
also showed an inversion of the epoxy configuration between the C-1 and C-10 positions as the only difference in their structures. The trypanocidal activity demonstrated the same trend as paulitin and isopaulitin; α- epoxide had a better activity (10-fold higher, 

p
&lt;

0.005) than β- epoxide. It should be mentioned that the presence of conjugation in ring A on the lactone results in an improvement of the trypanocidal activity of epoxidized compounds.
</p>
         <p>
It is widely known that the α,β unsaturated lactone structural motif (with the double bond in exocyclic position) is a privileged scaffold for biological activity, not restricted to trypanocidal activity (

). Most SLs have shown cytotoxic activity 
in vitro
and 
in vivo
(

). In these structure-activity relationships (SAR) reports, it was shown that several cytotoxic SLs react with thiols (from cysteine residues of proteins) by Michael-type addition. These reactions are chemically mediated by the α,β- unsaturated carbonyl system present in SLs. These findings support the hypotheses that SLs inhibit numerous cell functions through the selective alkylation of key biological macromolecules. Differences in activity between individual SLs can be explained by different numbers of alkylating structural elements. Here, it is important to note that SLs activity can be also influenced by factors such as lipophilicity, chemical environment, molecular geometry, and target sulfhydryl, among others (

).
</p>
         <p>Our work contributes with the discovery of simple, but very valuable and previously unexplored structure-activity relationships. This means that the presence of ring A is important for parasite inhibition, since lactone compounds showed better activity than their open chain ester counterparts. In this case, esterification of free carboxylic acid decreased the efficacy. More importantly, in compounds bearing 1,10-epoxide along with the 2,3-olefinic-double bound, the spatial disposition of the epoxide turns out to be key for enhancing the trypanocidal activity.</p>
         <p>
As previously stated of lactones, the cytotoxic effect of some SLs is attributed to the exomethylene group. Even though this position was not chemically modified in our trypanocidal candidates, an evaluation of the impact of these structural changes on the cytotoxicity of the SLs was necessary. As discussed above, the addition of epoxide groups, in certain cases, may increase electrophilicity and reactivity. In consequence, the cytotoxicity of the compounds was evaluated on the macrophages cell line (
Table 1
). CC 
50
was measured for the most active compounds of the series (IC 
50
&lt;
7 μM) together with the positive control (benznidazol) and Psi B (the chemical precursor of the derivatives obtained). At 5 μg/mL, the concentration at which they exhibited high trypanocidal activity, the more active compounds (lower IC 
50
values) were non-toxic, according to ISO 10993-5 standards, since cell viabilities were higher than 75% (International Standards ISO, 2009). Therefore, this finding further broadens the horizons in the research for previously undescribed safe trypanocidal therapeutic agents.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>Apart from traditional phytochemical isolation, which yielded various bioactive compounds, in this contribution, a simple alternative was explored with remarkable results.</p>
         <p>
Through derivatization of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
extract and, consequently, its bioguided fractionation, naturally occurring bioactive metabolites (such as paulitin, the most active compound) were obtained, although they are not initially detectable in this species. Using a readily available and inexpensive oxidizing reagent, 
m
CPBA, derivatization was achieved under mild conditions, allowing simple purification with almost total isolated mass recovery.
</p>
         <p>
Epoxide-containing compounds, either naturally occurring or obtained by chemical modification, allowed arriving at a key structural motif regarding trypanocidal activity. As described in medicinal chemistry, a small structural change is capable of translating into an important change in biological activity (

). The configuration of the epoxy group (along with its intrinsic characteristic of being an electrophile capable of reacting with cellular nucleophiles as well as a hydrogen bond acceptor) proves to be a molecular determinant to increase parasite inhibition. To date, this is a novel finding that will serve as the foundation for future research aimed at the synthesis of more active and selective derivatives with less toxicity. Furthermore, it is the starting point for a mechanistic study of parasite growth inhibition at different stages, which may lead to finding the molecular target. This is still one of the biggest questions in this field of research and reaching consensus on it represents a difficult challenge.
</p>
         <p>
These data, together with an 
in silico
structural study of these molecules on biological targets of the parasite, would be very valuable to define their mechanism of action. In this regard, further molecular and biological evidence will allow a more efficient design of therapeutic trypanocidal agents.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General
</title>
         <p>
Optical rotation was measured on a JASCO P-1010 polarimeter. IR spectra were obtained in a Nicolet iZ10 ThermoScientific spectrophotometer (each compound was dissolved in a minimum amount of solvent, and a drop of solution was added to the AgCl IR plates). NMR experiments were performed on a Bruker AVANCE II 400 MHz instrument. Multiplicity determinations (HSQC-DEPT) and 2D spectra (COSY, HSQC, and HMBC) were obtained using standard Bruker software. Chemical shifts are expressed in ppm (δ) units using tetramethylsilane as the standard. Exact mass spectra were obtained on a Bruker microTOF-Q II mass spectrometer, equipped with an ESI source operating in positive mode. Chromatographic separations were performed by column chromatography and vacuum on silica gel 60 (
0.063
–0.200
mm), flash chromatography on Sepacore® X10 and X50, and preparative TLC on silica gel 60 F 
254
(
0.2 mm
thick) plates. The presence of compounds was revealed by an anisaldehyde reagent.
</p>
         <p>
Reagents used for derivatization were purchased in Sigma-Aldrich. Benznidazole (purity 99.2 ± 0.5% w/w) was extracted and purified from commercially available tablets (Radanil®, Roche, 
Argentina
), as reported in previous works (

).
</p>
         <p>
4.2. Plant material
</p>
         <p>

The aerial parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ambrosia tenuifolia
Spreng. (Asteraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected in 
Río de los Sauces
(
32.535932
; 
64.589681
), 
Calamuchita Department
, 
Cordoba
´, 
Argentina
, in 

February 2017

. The plant material was identified by 
Gloria Barboza
(IMBIV-CONICET, Cordoba´, Argentina), and a voucher specimen was deposited on the 
Museo Bot´anico de C´ordoba
(
CORD 00098343
), Universidad Nacional de C´ordoba

.
</p>
         <p>
4.3. Crude extracts
</p>
         <p>
The dried and powdered aerial parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
(
450 g
) were extracted with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
exhaustively at room temperature by five extraction cycles, and the solvent was evaporated under reduced pressure. This extract (40.0 g) was suspended in EtOH–H 
2
O (1:1) and washed with n-hexane (after extraction, 15.0 g), after which the EtOH was evaporated under reduced pressure. The residue was diluted with H 
2
O and extracted with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
(20.0 g), and finally with EtOAc (
1.2 g
). The combined 
CH
2
Cl 
2
phases were dried (Na 
2
SO 
4
), filtered, and evaporated to dryness.
</p>
         <p>
4.4. Extraction and isolation of control extract
</p>
         <p>
CH
2
Cl 
2
fraction (
19.4 g
) was purified by vacuum chromatography on silica gel (hexane-EtOAc gradient) to yield five fractions. Fraction 1 (hexane/EtOAc, 60:40) was repurified by column chromatography, so 
340.4 mg
of altamisin and 5, 
6 mg
of 4-oxobedfordia acid were obtained. Fraction 2 (hexane/EtOAc, 50:50) was repurified by column chromatography (hexane/EtOAc), so 
1.9 g
of altamisin, 
420.5 mg
of psilostachyin A (Psi A) and 
30.6 mg
of altamisic acid were obtained. Fraction 3 (hexane/EtOAc, 40:60) resulted in 
3.1 g
of pure Psi A. Fraction 4 (hexane/EtOAc, 25:75) resulted in 
7.6 g
of pure psilostachyin B (Psi B). Fraction 5 (100% EtOAc) resulted in 
2.8 g
of psilostachyin C (Psi C). All compounds were determined to be
&gt;
95% pure by 
1
H NMR spectroscopy.
</p>
         <p>
4.5. Extract derivatization
</p>
         <p>
To a solution of the 
CH
2
Cl 
2
fraction (
300 mg
) in 
CH
2
Cl 
2
(15 mL) at 0 
◦
C, 
m
-chloroperoxybenzoic acid 70% (
325 mg
, 1.32 mmol) was added, and the reaction was stirred for 24 h at room temperature. The reaction mixture was cooled in an ice bath, and the precipitated 
m-
chlorobenzoic acid was removed by filtration. The organic layer was washed with Na 
2
S 
2
O 
3
solution, then with NaHCO 
3
solution, and finally, with H 
2
O. The organic layer was dried with Na 
2
SO 
4
, filtered, and concentrated under reduced pressure, obtaining 
275 mg
of modified extract, which resulted in a recovery percentage of 92% SLs and their derivatives.
</p>
         <p>
4.5.1. Purification of the modified extract
</p>
         <p>
The modified 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tenuifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
extract was chromatographed on silica gel (hexane-EtOAc-MeOH gradient) to yield six pools. Pool I (hexane/ EtOAc, 70:30) resulted in 
12.5 mg
of pure compound 
1
, pool II (hexane/ EtOAc, 50:50) resulted in 
33.9 mg
of Psi A, pool III (hexane/EtOAc, 40:60) was repurified by column chromatography [
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (5%) gradient], so 3.0 mg Psi A, 
1.5 mg
of paulitine, and 
4.8 mg
of isopaulitine were obtained. Pool IV (hexane/EtOAc, 30:70) was repurified by column chromatography [
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (10%) gradient], so 
12.3 mg
of Psi C, 
20.4 mg
of compound 
2
, and 
26.1 mg
of compound 
3
were obtained. These compounds also were obtained from pool III in smaller proportions (
9.6 mg
and 
4.9 mg
, respectively). Pool V (hexane/EtOAc, 20:80) was repurified by column chromatography (
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (20%) gradient), so 
12.6 mg
Psi C and 
9.8 mg
of compound 
3
were obtained. Pool VI (EtOAc 100%) resulted in 
31.1 mg
of Psi C. All compounds were determined to be
&gt;
95% pure by 
1
H NMR spectroscopy. For more details on the structural elucidation and tables of assignments, see supplementary information.
</p>
         <p>
*n.m. Not measured.
</p>
         <p>
Methyl-1β,10β- epoxy-altamisoate (
1
): White amorphous powder; [α] 
25
D
: 8.9 (c 0.01, acetone); UV (acetonitrile) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 216 (3.78) nm, 206 (3.38) nm; IR (dry film) 
ν
max
: 3451, 2928, 1738, 1444, 1379, 
1004 cm
1
. HRESIMS m/z [M+ Na] 
+
333.1309 (calcd for C 
16
H 
22
NaO 
6
+
, 333.1309).
</p>
         <p>
1β,10β- epoxy-psilostachyin B (
2
): White amorphous powder; [α] 
25
D
: 59.9 (c 0.001, Acetone); UV (Acetonitrile) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 280 (2.27) nm, 206 (3.73) nm; IR (dry film) 
ν
max
: 2923, 1762, 1263, 1109, 
1062, 998 cm
1
. HRESIMS m/z [M+ Na] 
+
301.1039 (calcd for C 
15
H 
18
NaO 
5
+
, 301.1046).
</p>
         <p>
1α,10α- epoxy-psilostachyin B (
3
): White amorphous powder; [α] 
25
D
: 28.7 (c 0.002, acetone); UV (acetonitrile) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 282 (2.51) nm, 206 (3.86) nm; IR (dry film) 
ν
max
: 2925, 1766, 1264, 1110, 
1080, 996 cm
1
. HRESIMS m/z [M+ Na] 
+
301.1031 (calcd for C 
15
H 
18
NaO 
5
+
, 301.1046).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Trypanocidal activity
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.6.1. Obtention of 
<tp:taxon-name>Trypanosoma cruzi parasites</tp:taxon-name>
         </title>
         <p>
BALB/c mice, when 6–8 weeks old, were intraperitoneally infected with 1 × 10 
6
blood-derived trypomastigote forms of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. cruzi
Tulahuen
</tp:taxon-name>
strain, and the infection was maintained by intraperitoneal inoculation every 11 days. Then, trypomastigotes were used to infect Vero cell monolayers. After 7 days, supernatants were collected after centrifugation at 310× 
g
for 20 min and resuspended in complete Roswell Park Memorial Institute medium (RPMI, Gibco Invitrogen Corporation) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, Natocor), L-glutamine (2 mM, Gibco Invitrogen Corporation), and gentamicin (
40 g
/mL). Parasites were counted by direct microscopic observation using a Neubauer hemocytometer, and used for the 
in vitro
experiments as described below, or stored at 80 
◦
C (

).
</p>
         <p>
All animal experiments and procedures were carried out according to the guidelines of the Committee for Animal Care and Use of the Facultad de Ciencias Químicas, Universidad Nacional de C´ordoba, 
Argentina
(Ethical Committee Approval Number HCD 942/18) in strict accordance with the recommendation of the Guide to the Care and Use of Experimental Animals published by the Canadian Council on Animal Care.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6.2. In vitro evaluation of antiprotozoal activity
</title>
         <p>
Trypanocidal effects of natural compounds and derivatives were evaluated in trypomastigotes obtained as mentioned above. Parasites were resuspended in complete RPMI medium, and the concentration of parasites was adjusted to 1.5 × 10 
6
/mL. Parasites were seeded (100 μL/ well) in triplicates in a 96-well microplate, and 100 μL of each compound/well (1–100 μg/mL, final concentration) was added. Benznidazole or DMSO was used as a control. The plates were incubated at 37 
◦
C in a relative humidity of 95% with 5% of CO 
2
concentration for 24 h, and the remaining live parasites were counted in a Neubauer hemocytometer. Percent inhibition was calculated according to Equation (1) (

).
</p>
         <p>()</p>
         <p>live parasites in wells after treatment</p>
         <p>% inhibition = 100 × 100%</p>
         <p>live parasites in untreated wells</p>
         <p>Eq. 1</p>
         <p>
Half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC 
50
) was calculated by linear interpolation method using Equation (2) (

):
</p>
         <p>(50% low%) × (high[] low[])</p>
         <p>
IC 
50
= + low[] Eq. 2 high% low%
</p>
         <p>where low% represents the highest percent of inhibition less than 50%, high% represents the lowest percent of inhibition greater than or equal to 50%, low [] represents the concentration of test compound that gives the low%, and high [] represents the concentration of test compound that gives the high%.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. MTT assay
</title>
         <p>
RAW 264.7 macrophage cell line (ATCC) was seeded in 96-well microplates (3 × 
104
cells/well) and grown overnight in Dulbecco’ s modified Eagle’ s medium (DMEM, Gibco Invitrogen Corporation). Then, they were treated for 24 h with the compounds at the concentrations described above. DMEM medium was used as a control. After that, culture supernatant media was removed, and 100 μL of 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide (MTT) solution (Sigma-Aldrich, 
0.5 mg
/mL) prepared in DMEM medium were added to each well. Cells were incubated for 4 h at 37 
◦
C and 5% CO 
2.
Next, 100 μL of DMSO was added into each well, and the microplates were kept for 15 min on the shaker. Absorbance (optical density, OD) was measured at 
570 nm
using an ELISA reader (BioRad). The percentage of cell viability was calculated using Equation (3):
</p>
         <p>OD experiment sample % cell viability = × 100% Eq.3</p>
         <p>OD control</p>
         <p>
Cytotoxicity concentration 50% (CC 
50
) was calculated following Eq. (2).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Statistical analysis
</title>
         <p>
Prism (GraphPad Software) was used to perform the statistical analyses, with all data expressed as mean ± SD. Data were analyzed using Student’ s t-test, and one- and two-way ANOVA, followed by Dunnett’ s post-test for multiple comparisons. Values of p 
&lt;
0.05 were considered statistically significant.
</p>
         <p>
Funding
</p>
         <p>
This work has been financed by CONICET [grant number PIP 2015–2017, 11220150100208], ANPCYT [grant number PICT 2016- 2015], SeCyT-UNC [grant numbers 33620180100132CB, 33820180100152CB], ONR Global [Grant N62909- 
21-1-2052
, 
USA
].
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
This work has been funded by CONICET, ANPCYT, Ministerio de Ciencia y Tecnología de C´ordoba, SeCyT-UNC (
Argentine
agencies), and ONR Global, Office of Naval Research, 
USA
). T.A. and Y. A thank CONICET for the fellowships granted to conduct their Ph.D. programs. C. C.S., M.C.G., F.R.B, V.E.N., and M.E.G. are members of CONICET scientific career. The authors would like to thank CONICET and the Universidad Nacional de Cordoba´for providing their facilities for this work. The authors also thank G. Bonetto for NMR assistance, and Prof. G. Barboza for plant identification.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113014.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
´
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alvarez Touron, G.I.
, 
2018
. 
Bioguided design of trypanosomicidal compounds: a successful strategy in drug discovery
. In: 
Mavromoustakos, T.
, 
Kellici, T.F.
(Eds.), 
Rational Drug Design: Methods and Protocols
. 
Springer New York, New York,
pp. 
139–163
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Butler, M.S.
, 
2008
. 
Natural products to drugs: natural product-derived compounds in clinical trials
. 
Nat. Prod. Rep.
25
, 
475–516
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/B514294F
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Caldwell, G.W.
, 
Yan, Z.
, 
2014
. 
Rapidly distinguishing reversible and time-dependent CYP450 inhibition using human liver microsomes, Co-incubation, and continuous fluorometric kinetic analyses
. In: 
Caldwell, G.W.
, 
Yan, Z.
(Eds.), 
Optimization in Drug Discovery: in Vitro Methods
. 
Humana Press, Totowa, NJ
, pp. 
281–303
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chaturvedi, D.
, 
2011
. 
Sesquiterpene Lactones: Structural Diversity and Their Biological Activities, Opportunity, Challenge and Scope of Natural Products in Medicinal Chemistry
. 
Signpost, Kerala, India
, pp. 
313–334
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chaturvedi, D.
, 
Dwivedi, P.K.
, 
Mishra, M.
, 
2015
. 
Sesquiterpene lactones: a versatile class of structurally diverse natural products and their semisynthetic analogs as potential anticancer agent
. In: 
Goutam Brahmachari
(Ed.), 
Bioactive Natural Products, Chemistry and Biology
. 
Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Germany
, pp. 
321–342
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
da Silva, C.F.
, 
Batista, D.G.
, 
De Araújo, J.S.
, 
Batista, M.M.
, 
Lionel, J.
, 
de Souza, E.M.
, 
Hammer, E.R.
, 
da Silva, P.B.
, 
De Mieri, M.
, 
Adams, M.
, 
Zimmermann, S.
, 
Hamburger, M.
, 
Brun, R.
, 
Schühly, W.
, 
Soeiro
, 
Mde N.
, 
2013
. 

Activities of psilostachyin A and cynaropicrin against 
Trypanosoma cruzi in vitro
and 
in vivo

. 
Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
57
, 
5307–5314
. 
https://doi.org/10.1128/ AAC.00595-13
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
David, J.P.
, de, O., 
Santos, A.J.
, da, S., 
Guedes, M.L.
, 
David, J.M.
, 
Chai, H.-B.
, 
Pezzuto, J. M.
, 
Angerhofer, C.K.
, 
Cordell, G.A.
, 
1999
. 

Sesquiterpene lactones from 
Ambrosia artemisiaefolia
(asteraceae)

. 
Pharmaceut. Biol.
37
, 
165–168
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1076/phbi.37.2.165.6077
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Davison, E.K.
, 
Brimble, M.A.
, 
2019
. 
Natural product derived privileged scaffolds in drug discovery
. 
Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol.
52
, 
1–8
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. cbpa.2018.12.007
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Declaration of the Global Chagas Disease Coalition
. DNDi (Drugs for Neglegted Diseased Initiative), 
2013
Securing Access to Current Treatments while
Researching Better Options, PLOS
Neglected Tropical Diseases
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DeCorte, B.L.
, 
2016
. 
Underexplored opportunities for natural products in drug discovery
. 
J. Med. Chem.
59
, 
9295–9304
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jmedchem.6b00473
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fadel, H.
, 
Sifaoui, I.
, L´opez-Arencibia, A., 
Reyes-Batlle, M.
, 
Hajaji, S.
, 
Chiboub, O.
, Jim´enez, 
I.A
., 
Bazzocchi, I.L.
, 
Lorenzo-Morales, J.
, 
Benayache, S.
, Pinero ˜, J.E., 
2018
. 

Assessment of the antiprotozoal activity of 
Pulicaria inuloides
extracts, an Algerian medicinal plant: leishmanicidal bioguided fractionation

. 
Parasitol. Res.
117
, 
531–537
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00436-017-5731-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fidler, J.M.
, 
Li, K.
, 
Chung, C.
, 
Wei, K.
, 
Ross, J.A.
, 
Gao, M.
, 
Rosen, G.D.
, 
2003
. 
PG490-88, a derivative of triptolide, causes tumor regression and sensitizes tumors to chemotherapy
. 
Mol. Cancer Therapeut.
2
, 
855
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
García, M.C.
, 
Ponce, N.E.
, 
Sanmarco, L.M.
, 
Manzo, R.H.
, 
Jimenez-Kairuz, A.F.
, 
Aoki, M. P.
, 
2016
. 
Clomipramine and benznidazole act synergistically and ameliorate the outcome of experimental Chagas disease. Antimicrob
. 
Agents Chemother.
60
, 
3700–3708
. 
https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.00404-16
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
García, M.C.
, 
Martinelli, M.
, 
Ponce, N.E.
, 
Sanmarco, L.M.
, 
Aoki, M.P.
, 
Manzo, R.H.
, 
Jimenez-Kairuz, A.F.
, 
2018
. 
Multi-kinetic release of benznidazole-loaded multiparticulate drug delivery systems based on polymethacrylate interpolyelectrolyte complexes
. 
Eur. J. Pharmaceut. Sci.
120
, 
107–122
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.ejps.2018.04.034
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gardner, P.D.
, 
1956
. 
Organic peracid oxidation of some enol esters involving Rearrangement1
. 
J. Am. Chem. Soc.
78
, 
3421–3424
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ ja01595a043
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ghantous, A.
, 
Gali-Muhtasib, H.
, 
Vuorela, H.
, 
Saliba, N.A.
, 
Darwiche, N.
, 
2010
. 
What made sesquiterpene lactones reach cancer clinical trials? Drug Discov
. 
Today
15
, 
668–678
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drudis.2010.06.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gomes, A.R.
, 
Varela, C.L.
, 
Tavares-da-Silva, E.J.
, 
Roleira, F.M.F.
, 
2020
. 
Epoxide containing molecules: a good or a bad drug design approach
. 
Eur. J. Med. Chem.
201
, 
112327
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2020.112327
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guo, Z.
, 
2017
. 
The modification of natural products for medical use
. 
Acta Pharm. Sin. B
7
, 
119–136
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apsb.2016.06.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Herz, W.
, 
Anderson, G.
, 
Gibaja, S.
, 
Raulais, D.
, 
1969
. 

Sesquiterpene lactones of some 
Ambrosia
species

. 
Phytochemistry
8
, 
877–881
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422 (00)85877-X
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hussain, H.
, 
Al-Harrasi, A.
, 
Green, I.R.
, 
Ahmed, I.
, 
Abbas, G.
, 
Rehman, N.U.
, 
2014
. 
meta-Chloroperbenzoic acid (mCPBA): a versatile reagent in organic synthesis
. 
RSC Adv.
4
, 
12882–12917
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/C3RA45702H
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
International
standards ISO 10993-5, 
2009
. 
Tests for in Vitro Cytotoxicity, third ed. ed
. 
ISO copyright office Switzerland
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Izumi, E.
, 
Ueda-Nakamura, T.
, 
Dias Filho, B.P.
, 
Veiga Júnior, V.F.
, 
Nakamura, C.V.
, 
2011
. 

Natural products and Chagas’ disease: a review of plant compounds studied for activity against 
Trypanosoma cruzi

. 
Nat. Prod. Rep.
28
, 
809–823
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1039/C0NP00069H
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jimenez, V.
, 
Kemmerling, U.
, 
Paredes, R.
, 
Maya, J.D.
, 
Sosa, M.A.
, 
Galanti, N.
, 
2014
. 

Natural sesquiterpene lactones induce programmed cell death in 
Trypanosoma cruzi
: a new therapeutic target?

Phytomedicine
21
, 
1411–1418
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ j.phymed.2014.06.005
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kawamura, T.
, 
Matsubara, K.
, 
Otaka, H.
, 
Tashiro, E.
, 
Shindo, K.
, 
Yanagita, R.C.
, 
Irie, K.
, 
Imoto, M.
, 
2011
. 
Generation of ‘Unnatural Natural Product’ library and identification of a small molecule inhibitor of XIAP
. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem.
19
, 
4377–4385
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2011.05.009
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kimani, N.M.
, 
Matasyoh, J.C.
, 
Kaiser, M.
, 
Brun, R.
, 
Schmidt, T.J.
, 
2018
a. 

Antiprotozoal sesquiterpene lactones and other constituents from 
Tarchonanthus camphoratus
and 
Schkuhria pinnata

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
81
, 
124–130
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. jnatprod.7b00747
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kimani, N.M.
, 
Matasyoh, J.C.
, 
Kaiser, M.
, 
Brun, R.
, 
Schmidt, T.J.
, 
2018
b. 

Sesquiterpene lactones from 
Vernonia cinerascens
sch

. 
Bip. And their in vitro antitrypanosomal activity. Molecules
23
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules23020248
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
L´opez, S.N., 
Ramallo, I.A.
, 
Sierra, M.G.
, 
Zacchino, S.A.
, 
Furlan, R.L.E.
, 
2007
. 
Chemically engineered extracts as an alternative source of bioactive natural product-like compounds
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. Unit. States Am.
104
, 
441
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1073/pnas.0608438104
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mabry, T.
j., 
Kagan, H.B.
, 
Miller, H.E.
, 
1966
. 

Psilostachyin B, a new sesquiterpene dilactone from 
Ambrosia psilostachya
DC

. 
Tetrahedron
22
, 
1943–1948
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/S0040-4020(01)82268-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Martino, R.
, 
Beer, M.F.
, 
Elso, O.
, 
Donadel, O.
, 
Sülsen, V.
, 
Anesini, C.
, 
2015
. 

Sesquiterpene lactones from 
Ambrosia
spp. are active against a murine lymphoma cell line by inducing apoptosis and cell cycle arrest

. 
Toxicol. Vitro
29
, 
1529–1536
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.tiv.2015.06.011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
M´endez, L., 
Salazar, M.O.
, 
Ramallo, I.A.
, 
Furlan, R.L.E.
, 
2011
. 
Brominated extracts as source of bioactive compounds. ACS Comb
. 
Sci.
13
, 
200–204
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/co100073k
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Montes-Avila, J.
, 
Díaz-Camacho, S.P.
, 
Willms, K.
, de-la-Cruz-Otero, M.d.C., 
Robert, L.
, 
Rivero, I.A.
, 
Delgado-Vargas, F.
, 
2017
. 

Bioguided study of the in vitro parasitocidal effect on adult 
Hymenolepis nana
of the 
Psidium sartorianum
(O. Berg Nied.) fruit methanol extract

. 
Med. Chem. Res.
26
, 
2845–2852
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ s00044-017-1983-x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Muschietti, L.V.
, 
Ulloa, J.L.
, 
2016
. 
Natural sesquiterpene lactones as potential trypanocidal therapeutic agents: a review
. 
Natural Product Communications
11
. 
https://doi.org/10.1177/1934578X1601101036, 1934578X1601101036
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Newman, D.J.
, 
Cragg, G.M.
, 
2020
. 
Natural products as sources of new drugs over the nearly four decades from 01/1981 to 09/2019
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
83
, 
770–803
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.9b01285
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Oberti, J.C.
, 
Silva, G.L.
, 
Sosa, V.E.
, 
Kulanthaivel, P.
, 
Herz, W.
, 
1986
. 

Ambrosanolides and secoambrosanolides from 
Ambrosia tenuifolia

. 
Phytochemistry
25
, 
1355–1358
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(00)81289-3
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Olivaro, C.
, 
Rostan, V.
, 
Bandera, D.
, 
Moyna, G.
, 
Vazquez, A.
, 
2016
. 

Xanthane sesquiterpenoids from the roots and flowers of 
Xanthium cavanillesii

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
30
, 
2238–2242
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/14786419.2016.1149709
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
P´erez-Molina, 
J.A
., 
Molina, I.
, 
2018
. 
Chagas disease
. 
Lancet
391
, 
82–94
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/S0140-6736(17)31612-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Qiu, D.
, 
Kao, P.N.
, 
2003
. 

Immunosuppressive and anti-inflammatory mechanisms of triptolide, the principal active diterpenoid from the Chinese medicinal herb 
Tripterygium wilfordii
hook

. f. 
Drugs in R &amp; D
4
, 
1–18
. 
https://doi.org/10.2165/ 00126839-200304010-00001
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ramallo, I.A.
, 
Salazar, M.O.
, 
Mendez, L.
, 
Furlan, R.L.E.
, 
2011
. 
Chemically engineered extracts: source of bioactive compounds
. 
Accounts Chem. Res.
44
, 
241–250
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1021/ar100106n
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ramallo, I.A.
, 
Alonso, V.L.
, 
Rua, F.
, 
Serra, E.
, 
Furlan, R.L.E.
, 
2018
. 

A bioactive 
Trypanosoma cruzi
bromodomain inhibitor from chemically engineered extracts

. 
ACS Comb. Sci.
20
, 
220–228
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acscombsci.7b00172
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ren, Y.
, 
Yu, J.
, 
Kinghorn, A.D.
, 
2016
. 
Development of anticancer agents from plantderived sesquiterpene lactones
. 
Curr. Med. Chem.
23
, 
2397–2420
. 

https://doi.org/ 10.2174/ 
0929867323666160510123255

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ribeiro, V.
, 
Dias, N.
, 
Paiva, T.
, Hagstr¨om-Bex, L., 
Nitz, N.
, 
Pratesi, R.
, 
Hecht, M.
, 
2020
. 
Current trends in the pharmacological management of Chagas disease
. 
Int. J. Parasitol.: Drugs and Drug Resistance
12
, 
7–17
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. ijpddr.2019.11.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodrigues, T.
, 
Reker, D.
, 
Schneider, P.
, 
Schneider, G.
, 
2016
. 
Counting on natural products for drug design
. 
Nat. Chem.
8
, 
531–541
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/ nchem.2479
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Silva, G.L.
, 
Oberti, J.C.
, 
Herz, W.
, 
1992
. 

Sesquiterpene lactones and other constituents of argentine 
Ambrosia
species

. 
Phytochemistry
31
, 
859–861
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ 0031-9422(92)80029-E
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stempin, C.C.
, 
Rojas Marquez, J.D.
, 
Ana, Y.
, 
Cerban, F.M.
, 
2017
. 

GRAIL and otubain-1 are related to T cell hyporesponsiveness during 
Trypanosoma cruzi
infection

. 
PLoS Neglected Trop. Dis.
11
, e 
0005307
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005307
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sülsen, V.P.
, 
Frank, F.M.
, 
Cazorla, S.I.
, 
Anesini, C.A.
, 
Malchiodi, E.L.
, 
Freixa, B.
, 
Vila, R.
, 
Muschietti, L.V.
, 
Martino, V.S.
, 
2008
. 

Trypanocidal and leishmanicidal activities of sesquiterpene lactones from 
Ambrosia tenuifolia
Sprengel (Asteraceae)

. 
Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.
52
, 
2415–2419
. 
https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.01630-07
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sülsen, V.P.
, 
Frank, F.M.
, 
Cazorla, S.I.
, 
Barrera, P.
, 
Freixa, B.
, 
Vila, R.
, 
Sosa, M.A.
, 
Malchiodi, E.L.
, 
Muschietti, L.V.
, 
Martino, V.S.
, 
2011
. 
Psilostachyin C: a natural compound with trypanocidal activity
. 
Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents
37
, 
536–543
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2011.02.003
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sülsen, V.P.
, 
Cazorla, S.I.
, 
Frank, F.M.
, 
Laurella, L.C.
, 
Muschietti, L.V.
, Catal´an, 
C.A
., 
Martino, V.S.
, 
Malchiodi, E.L.
, 
2013
. 

Natural terpenoids from 
Ambrosia
species are active in vitro and in vivo against human pathogenic trypanosomatids

. 
PLoS Neglected Trop. Dis.
7
, e 
2494
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0002494
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sülsen, V.P.
, 
Puente, V.
, 
Papademetrio, D.
, 
Batlle, A.
, 
Martino, V.S.
, 
Frank, F.M.
, 
Lombardo, M.E.
, 
2016
. 
Mode of action of the sesquiterpene lactones psilostachyin and psilostachyin C on. Trypanosoma cruzi
. 
PLOS ONE
11
, e 
0150526
. 
https://doi. org/10.1371/journal.pone.0150526
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Sülsen, 
V P

, 
Martino, V.S.
, 
2018
. 
Sesquiterpene Lactones Advances in Their Chemistry and Biological Aspects
. 
Springer International Publishing AG, Switzerland
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tomohara, K.
, 
Ito, T.
, 
Hasegawa, N.
, 
Kato, A.
, 
Adachi, I.
, 
2016
. 
Direct chemical derivatization of natural plant extract: straightforward synthesis of natural plant-like hydantoin.
Tetrahedron Lett.
57
, 
924–927
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tetlet.2016.01.054.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
World Health Organization
, 
2021
. 
Chagas Disease (American Trypanosomiasis)
. Last Update date: April, 2021. 
http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs340/en/
. (Accessed 
10 May 2021
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhu, Y.
, 
Shu, L.
, 
Tu, Y.
, 
Shi, Y.
, 
2001
. 
Enantioselective synthesis and stereoselective rearrangements of enol ester epoxides
. 
J. Org. Chem.
66
, 
1818–1826
. 
https://doi. org/10.1021/jo001593z
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
