<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.10.005</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>In vitro cytotoxicity and structure-activity relationship approaches of entkaurenoic acid derivatives against human breast carcinoma cell line</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>12</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2018</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Copaifera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Copaifera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Copaifera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Copaifera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aspergillus terreus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus niger
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>oblongifolia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
In vitro
cytotoxicity and structure-activity relationship approaches of 
entkaurenoic
acid derivatives against human breast carcinoma cell line

</p>
         <p>
Ricardo M. da Costa
a,b

, Jairo 
K
. Bastos

c

, Maria 
C
.A. Costa

d

, Márcia M. 
C
. Ferreira

d
,
</p>
         <p>
Cássia S. Mizuno 
e
, Giovanni F. Caramori
f
, Gláucio R. Nagurniak
f
, Marília R. Simão
a
,
</p>
         <p>
Raquel A. dos Santos 
a

, Rodrigo 
C
.S. Veneziani

a
, Sérgio R. Ambrósio

a, 
∗∗
, Renato L.T. Parreira

a, 
∗
</p>
         <p>
a

Núcleo de Pesquisa em Ciências Exatas e Tecnológicas da Universidade de 
Franca
- UNIFRAN, 
Franca
, SP, 
Brazil
</p>
         <p>
b

Informática Aplicada às Ciências – IFSULDEMINAS, Muzambinho, MG, 
Brazil
</p>
         <p>
c

Faculdade de 
Ciências Farmacêuticas de Ribeirão Preto
, Universidade de 
São Paulo
, 
Ribeirão Preto
, SP, 
Brazil
</p>
         <p>
d

Theoretical and Applied Chemometrics Laboratory (LQTA), Institute of Chemistry, University of Campinas - Unicamp, Campinas, SP, 
Brazil
e

Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, University of New 
England
, College of Pharmacy, Portland, ME, 
USA
</p>
         <p>
f
Departamento de Química
, Universidade Federal de 
Santa Catarina
, 
Campos Universitário Trindade
, 
Florianópolis
, SC, 
Brazil
</p>
         <p>
A R T I 
C
L E I N F 
O
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Copaifera
</tp:taxon-name>
ssp (Fabaceae-caesalpinoiodidaeae) Multivariate QSAR analysis
</p>
         <p>Kaurenoic acid derivatives</p>
         <p>MCF-7 breast cancer cells</p>
         <p>PLS regression</p>
         <p>
A B S T R A 
C
T
</p>
         <p>
In this study, 
ent
-kaurenoic acid derivatives were obtained by microbial transformation methodologies and tested against breast cancer cell lines (MCF-7). A multivariate quantitative-structure activity relationship (QSAR) analysis was performed taking into account both microbial transformation derivatives and other analogues previously reported in literature to give some insight into the main features behind the cytotoxic activity displayed by kaurane-type diterpenes against MCF-7 cells. The partial least square regression (PLS) method was employed in the training set and the best PLS model was built with a factor describing 69.92% of variance and three descriptors (log 
P
, 
εHOMO
and 
εHOMO–1
) selected by the Ordered Predictors Selection (OPS) algorithm. The QSAR model provided reasonable regression (
Q
2
= 0.64, 
R
2
= 0.72, 
SEC
= 0.29 and 
SEV
= 0.33). The model was validated by leave- 
N
-out cross-validation, y-randomization and external validation (
R
2
pred
= 0.89 and 
SEP
= 0.27). The selected descriptors indicated that the activity was mainly related to electronic parameters (HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 molecular orbital energies), as well as to log 
P
. These findings suggest that higher activity values are directly related with both higher log 
P
and frontier orbital energy values. The positive relationship between these orbitals and the activity suggests that the 
ent
-kaurenoic acid analogues interaction with the target involves charge displacement, which is entirely consistent with the literature. Based on these findings, three compounds were proposed and one of them was synthesized and tested. The experimental result confirmed the activity predicted by the model.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Mother nature has been considered the most promising inspiration source for preparation of novel pharmacologically active chemical entities (

). Generally, natural compounds have been employed either in drug design processes or applied as starting scaffolds for structural modifications leading to the preparation of semisynthetic derivatives, which have demonstrated to be even more potent and/or less toxic in comparison with their parent structures (

; Simao et al., 2016).
</p>
         <p>
Nowadays, 
in silico
methods have become noticeable during the development of novel drugs, and quantitative-structure activity relationship (QSAR) studies have been employed to identify important chemical features and consequently propose descriptors related with the respective biological activity, thus assisting in the discovery of novel potential lead compounds (

; 

). In fact, QSAR has been considered an important tool in the rational development and discovery of new drugs (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Among a plethora of bioactive natural compounds, kaurenoic acid (
1
; 
ent
-kaur-16-en-19-oic acid; 
Fig. 1
), a kaurane-type diterpene, is found in high amounts in some Brazilian medicinal plants genera such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Copaifera
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Mikania
(

; Simao et al., 2016). Compound 
1
, in particular, has demonstrated to possess a wide spectrum of biological activities, displaying anti-inflamatory, analgesic, antispasmodic, antimicrobial, and antiparasitic activities (Batista et al., 2013; 

; 

; Tirapelli et al., 2005). Moreover, this diterpene has also attracted considerable attention from the scientific community because this natural compound and its structural derivatives exhibit significant 
in vitro
cytotoxic effects against several tumor cell lines (Batista et al., 2013; 

; 

; Simao et al., 2016).
</p>
         <p>
1
-R1 = COOH; R2 = 
H
; R3 = 
H
; R4 = 
H
</p>
         <p>
2
-R1 = COOH; R2 = OH; R3 = 
H
; R4 = 
H
</p>
         <p>
3
-R1 = COOH; R2 = 
H
; R3 = 
H
; R4 = OH
</p>
         <p>
5
-R1 = COOH; R2 = OH; R3 = OH; R4 = 
H
</p>
         <p>
6
-R1 = COOCH 
3
; R2 = OH; R3 = 
H
; R4 = 
H
</p>
         <p>
7
-R1 = COOH; R2 = 
H
; R3 = 
H
; R4 =
</p>
         <p>
O
</p>
         <p>
8
-R1 = 
CH
2
OH; R2 = 
H
; R3 = 
H
; R4 = 
H
</p>
         <p>
9
-R1 = COOCH 
3
; R2 = 
H
; R3 = 
H
; R4 = 
H
</p>
         <p>
OH R R 
H H
11
-R = N 
19
-R = N OC 
H
3
12
-R = N 
20
-R = 
H
21
-R = NH 
13
-R = N 
H
22
-R = N 
H
14
-R = N 
H
23
-R = N 
H
OCH 
15
-R = N 
3
OCH 
3
H
24
-R = N 
H
16
-R = N 
H
25
-R = N 
H
OH 
17
-R = N OH 
H
26
-R = N 
18
-R = 
H
27
-R = N N
</p>
         <p>
In 2010, Hueso-Falcon and coworkers (

) synthesized a series containing thirty-one 
ent
-kaurane derivatives, from which four were considered as potent apoptosis inducers in human tumor cells through a caspase-dependent mode of action. In another study, by Batista and coworkers (Batista et al., 2013), the 
in vitro
citotoxicity of oxidized/epoxidized kaurenoic acid analogues was assessed against ovary, breast, melanoma, lung, leukaemia, pancreas, colon and cervical cancer cells. From their results, two allylic alcohol derivatives showed to be the most potent ones, displaying very promising GI 
50
values, ranging from 0.71 to 8.90 μM (Batista et al., 2013). More recently, Simão and coworkers (Simao et al., 2016) investigated the ability of a series of amides and diols derivatives of compound 
1
to inhibit the growth of a human breast carcinoma cell line. Among the obtained analogues, one diterpene exhibited significant activity, displaying an IC 
50
value of 7.84 μM and a selectivity index of about 50.7. It was also observed in this study that the presence of an amide containing an aromatic moiety in kaurenoic acid, instead of the carboxylic acid group, significantly increased the activity and the selectivity of the obtained derivative (Simao et al., 2016). Such findings brought an insight to investigate the structure–activity relationship displayed by kaurenoic acid structural analogues against tumor cell lines.
</p>
         <p>
In the present study, kaurenoic acid derivatives were obtained through fungal transformation using 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
strains. Moreover, other kaurane-type diterpenes previously reported (

; Simao et al., 2016) were also employed to perform a multivariate data analysis (partial least squares regression - PLS), including QSAR studies against a human breast carcinoma cell line. Based upon the information obtained from QSAR analysis, three kaurenoic acid derivatives were proposed - one of them was synthesized and also evaluated against MCF-7 cell lines (compound 
27
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Microbial transformation of kaurenoic acid (compound 1)
</title>
         <p>
Fourteen-days incubation of compound 
1
, isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Copaifera
</tp:taxon-name>
ssp, with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
strains gave rise to four derivatives (
2, 3, 4
and 
5
), which were isolated with a yield ranging from 2.2 to 24.3% based on their weights relative to the starting substrate. Due to the high rate converting of diterpene 
2
from 
1
, this metabolite was used as substrate to obtain its respective methyl ester (
6
), which was also evaluated against MCF-7 cells. The spectral data of all compounds are in agreement with that previously reported in the literature, 
2
(Silva et al., 1999); 
3
(Vichnewski et al., 1977); 
4
(

); 
5
(

). The chemical structures of substrate (
1
) as well as of the derivatives obtained by microbial transformation are presented in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
As established in the scientific literature, microbial transformation is an area of great interest to the pharmaceutical and chemical industries, once it allows for the production of derivatives that are difficult to obtain by organic synthesis (

; 

). Biotransformation studies of natural products using 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus
species
</tp:taxon-name>
are commonly found in the scientific literature and hydroxylation is the major reaction produced by these microorganisms (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
In this work, we found that 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
catalyzed stereoselective hydroxylation of non-activated carbons of 
1
, mainly at C-7, C-11 and C-15 (
Fig. 1
). This strain also promoted the introduction of a hydroxyl moiety at C-16 (double bond), denoting its great versatility to obtain novel derivatives from kaurane-type diterpenes. The reactions performed by this fungus are particularly interesting as this kind of transformation is very difficult to achieve by classic synthetic methodologies, not to mention that it represents an important way of introducing a reactive center into the poorly functionalized kaurenoic acid skeleton.
</p>
         <p>
It is also noteworthy to mention that 
2
is the main metabolite obtained by microbial transformation of 
1
using 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
, a bioreaction that displayed a significant conversion yield (24.3%). This result is important, once 
ent
-7α-hydroxy-kaur-16-en-19-oic acid (
2
) can be used as substrate for chemical and microbiological synthesis of gibberellins (

), a group of tetracyclic diterpenes that has agricultural applications due to their effects on plant growth (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. QSAR results
</title>
         <p>
QSAR studies were performed using the compounds obtained from the microbial transformation study (
2
, 
3
, 
4
, 
5
and 
6
), derivatives from kaurenoic acid previously reported in the literature (

; Simao et al., 2016) and two diterpenes constituents of our chemical standard set (
7
and 
8
). These compounds are shown in 
Fig. 1
and the IC50 and 
p
IC50 values employed in the QSAR analyses are depicted in 
Table 1
. The biological results are well spread into the range of 3.06–5.11 for 
p
IC50 values (
Table 1
), indicating that the data set is adequate for a QSAR study (

).
</p>
         <p>
The data set consisting of selected descriptors (log 
P
, εHOMO and εHOMO- 
1 in
Supplementary information, 
Table S1
) was split into training (20 compounds) and test (5 compounds) sets, after removing compound 
7
. This compound is structurally different, as a large and different group to all other substituents was introduced at C-15 position.
</p>
         <p>
The dendrogram from hierarchical cluster analysis (HCA; 
Fig. 2a
) was obtained for all kaurenoic acid derivatives. The Ward's method, as highlighted by 

, was applied to construct the dendrogram. The selected compounds for the test set (
10
, 
15
, 
23
, 
24
, and 
25
) are highlighted, showing that all groups were well represented, considering the structural variability and IC50 range. Compounds 
23
and 
24
are the most active in the test set (IC50 = 66.47 and 68.01 μmol L −1, respectively), while compounds 
25
and 
10
are moderately active (94.32 and 151.60 μmol L −1) and compound 
15
presents low activity (288.00 μmol L −1). It is possible to observe from 
Fig. 1
that among all tested compounds four of them (
15
, 
23
, 
24
, and 
25
) are substituted at C-19 by different amide groups, whereas compound 
10
presents a carboxyl group at this position. Compounds 
23
, 
24
and 
25
present a double bond between C-16 and C-17, while a methoxy and hydroxyl groups were inserted at C- 
16 in
compounds 
10
and 
15
, respectively. The synthesized compound (
27
), of unknown biological activity, was included in this analysis in order to investigate its similarity to the other compounds in this series. Note that this compound was grouped with compound 
21
.
</p>
         <p>
The hierarchical cluster analysis performed for the training set (
Fig. 2b
) shows two groups, A and B. Group B is composed by the most active derivatives presenting, in most cases, IC50 values lower than 100.00 μmol L −1, except for compounds 
1
, 
9
and 
26
(IC50 = 145.40, 257.00 and 136.00 μmol L −1, respectively). Group A is mainly composed by the least active (
3
, 
4
, 
5
, 
16
, 
17
and 
18
) compounds, for which IC50 values are higher than 390.00 μmol L −1, and by the moderate activity derivatives 
2
, 
6
, 
8
, 
13
and 
14
presenting IC50 values ranging from 141.00 to 251.90 μmol L −1. Group A is further divided into two subgroups, A1 and A2, being the least active derivatives present in A2, while A1 is constituted by compounds with moderate (
2
, 
6
, 
13
and 
14
) and low (
3
and 
16
) activity. These two subgroups can be classified as presenting moderate (A1) or low (A2) activity, while group B can be classified as the most active. It can be inferred from these results that the selected descriptors are able to distinguish the compounds into three classes: high, low or moderate activity.
</p>
         <p>
The best PLS regression model for the training set was obtained with a factor describing a total variance of 69.92% and 3 descriptors (Supplementary information, 
Table S1
) according to Eq. (1), where log 
P
is the partition coefficient octanol/water, and εHOMO and εHOMO-1 are the energies of the highest and second highest occupied molecular orbitals:
</p>
         <p>
p
IC50 = 0.365(log 
P
) + 0.330 HOMO + 0.317 HOMO 1 (1)
</p>
         <p>where,</p>
         <p>
R
2 = 0.72; 
Q
2 = 0.64; 
SEC
= 0.29; 
SEV
= 0.33; 
PRESS
cal = 1.65; 
PRESS
val = 2.11).
</p>
         <p>
The resulting statistical parameters attend the minimum acceptable values for regression models in QSAR and satisfy the following conditions: 
Q
2&gt; 0.5, 
R
2&gt; 0.6 (

; Tropsha et al., 2003) and the difference between 
R
2 and 
Q
2 does not exceed 0.2–0.3, according to OECD (

) and Ericksson and coworkers (

). For the model proposed in this work, 
R2 – Q
2 = 0.08. The Pearson correlation coefficients between all descriptors and between descriptors and biological activity are exhibited in 
Table S2
(Supplementary information), together with the auto-scaled regression coefficients. The signals of the Pearson coefficients are in agreement with the signals from the regression coefficients, showing that the final PLS model is self-consistent and does not suffer from sign change problem (

). In addition, the low correlation between the variables shows that there is no information redundancy occurrence.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Leave- 
N
-out cross validation (LNO) and y-randomization were performed in order to validate the model. The results in 
Fig. 3
show that the randomized models are of poor quality, as expected. The intercepts were 0.0396 (
Fig. 3A
) and −0.4631 (
Fig. 3B
), and are below the acceptable values of αR &lt;0.3 and αQ &lt;0.05 proposed by Wold and Ericksson and coworkers (

; Wold et al., 1984). The correlation between 
p
IC50 and 
p
IC50randomized is below 0.4, showing no chance correlation (
Fig. 3A and B
). Furthermore, 
Q2
and 
R2
for randomized 
y
(
Fig. 3C
) are below 0.30, also indicating no chance correlation.
</p>
         <p>
The results for leave- 
N
-out cross validation (
Fig. 3D
) show that even after removing five compounds from the training set (20%), the 
Q
2 value remains close to 
Q
2 for Leave-one-out, with standard deviation not exceeding the limit of ± 0.05, indicating that the QSAR model is robust.
</p>
         <p>

a 
p
IC means –logIC (IC in mol L −1). 50 50 50 b Synthesized compound.

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a Average relative error of prediction. b coefficient of determination for external validation. c Standard error of prediction.
</p>
         <p>
External validation of the proposed PLS model was carried out using a test set consisting of compounds 
10
, 
15
, 
23
, 
24
and 
25
(
Fig. 1
). The results (
Table 2
) showed high prediction power, with the determination coefficient for external validation 
R
2 pred of 0.89 and the average relative error of prediction (
ARE
pred) of 6.40. The obtained 
R
2 pred was much higher than the 
R
2 pred&gt; 0.5 recommended value by Pratim and Kunal and Roy and coworkers (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
From the best PLS model built on the auto-scaled data (Eq. (1)), –log IC50 increases with the increasing descriptor values, once they are all positive. The regression coefficients in equation (1) are similar, indicating that the descriptors are almost equally important in describing the model; however, the coefficient for log 
P
is slightly higher than the others.
</p>
         <p>
The highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) and lowest unoccupied molecular orbital (LUMO), known as frontier orbitals, play an important role in the reactivity of molecules, considering the interaction between the outermost electrons of HOMO and the acceptor electron orbital, LUMO, of two reacting species. HOMO and LUMO energies are widely applied in drug-receptor interaction and structure-activity relationship studies (

; 

; 

; Silva et al., 2013; Zheng et al., 2013), as well as the difference between both (energy gap) that measures the molecule's stability. Molecules with a large energy gap present low chemical reactivity, while those with small energy gap can be easily excited favoring their bioactivity. In a drug-receptor system, the drug's HOMO interacts with the receptor's LUMO or vice-versa (Zheng et al., 2013).
</p>
         <p>
The analysis and energies of HOMO‒1 and LUMO+1, the second highest occupied molecular orbital and the second lowest unoccupied molecular orbital, respectively, are usually also employed in structure-activity relationship studies. Braga and coworkers (

) studied the carcinogenic activity of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons through a theoretical approach based on the local density of electronic states and the energy separation values between HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 orbitals. The authors found that the activity of these compounds is related to the HOMO and HOMO‒1 energies, as well as to the difference between them. Bexarotene is an FDA-approved drug, currently in limited use for cutaneous manifestations of T-cell lymphomas (CTCL). Misra and coworkers (

) synthesized the prodrug version of bexarotene and performed DFT (density functional theory) calculations of molecular orbitals, such as HOMO, LUMO, 
HOMO-
1 and LUMO+1 energies, in order to investigate the possibility of using a reengineered form of the drug to treat hepatocellular carcinoma. Comparing the prodrug and drug, the calculation predicts the prodrug to be less cytotoxic and more stable than the drug. 
Ben
Hadda and coworkers (

) investigated the anti-tumor activity of rutheniumstaurosporine complexes through density functional theory (DFT)-derived reactivity indexes and their study indicated that the activity is closely related to the orbital energies, HOMO–1 and HOMO–1-LUMO +1 gap.
</p>
         <p>
Among several electronic descriptors calculated in the present study, HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 energies were selected by the best PLS regression model and their coefficients, that were high in equation (1), suggesting that the interaction between the kaurenoic acid derivatives and the cell involves charge displacement and can occur by any kind of intermolecular interaction, even ionic or covalent bond. This finding seems to agree with the results from Duarte and coworkers (

) who pointed out that LUMO energies are an indicative of the interaction between the macrocyclic diterpenes and the receptor 
via
charge transfer from the receptor to the diterpenes. The HOMO energy values for that study could not help understand the activity differences; however, the present QSAR analysis including twenty six diterpenes derived from kaurenoic acid elucidated the importance of HOMO orbital in the intermolecular interaction of this class of compounds. Although kaurenoic acid derivatives act as antiproliferative in MCF-7 breast cells (

), while the effect of macrocyclic diterpenes is to reverse the multidrug resistance (MDR) observed in tumor cells, both studies show that charge transfer plays an important role in cytotoxic activity displayed by this class of natural compounds.
</p>
         <p>
The HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 molecular orbital surfaces are graphically represented in 
Table 3
for the three most active compounds, the three least active and for compound 
27
(synthesized compound). The molecular orbital surfaces were built from the distribution of electronic density on the molecule and their visualization helps understand which atomic orbitals are contributing to the formation of the molecular orbitals.
</p>
         <p>
It can be observed from the most active compounds of the training set (derivatives 
19
, 
20
and 
21
) that the HOMO molecular orbitals are mainly located in the portion of the molecule containing the R1 substituent, while for compounds 
4
and 
5
, which show low activity, the HOMO surface is distributed over other molecular regions. This indicates that substituent R1 is participating in the interactions with the receptor. The HOMO of molecule 
18
, the least active, also presents its HOMO surface on the R1 region, but log 
P
for this molecule is quite low if compared to that of the most active compounds; furthermore, the energies of HOMO and HOMO–1 for compound 
18
are also lower than that of most active compounds (Supplementary information, 
Table S1
).
</p>
         <p>
In addition, Eq. (1) shows that lipophilic groups in the kaurenoic acid derivatives favor the biological activity due to log 
P
value increase conferred by the substituent groups. This is also in agreement with the literature (

), where all studied diterpenes are lipophilic and the most active compounds present higher log 
P
values. The kaurenoic acid derivatives results indicate that drug transport by the biological system where these compounds act is facilitated by lipophilicity increase. According to several authors (

; 

, 

; Wermuth et al., 2015), the absorption and distribution process of the pharmaceuticals are regulated by lipophilicity, as for the drug to achieve the target it requires to dissolve and penetrate biological membranes that 
<tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
tissues and systems of living organisms.
</p>
         <p>
The increasing activity with log 
P
, εHOMO and εHOMO-1 values suggests that more active compounds could be designed by modifying the radical R 
1 in
order to obtain more lipophilic substituents, which at the same time provide increased HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 energy values. Based upon these findings, two compounds (
28
and 
29
) were proposed in this work (
Fig. 4
, 
B
and 

C

). The most active compound (
19
, 
Fig. 1
) was modified at R1 position in order to provide a more lipophilic derivative and in this way, the methoxy group (eOCH3) was substituted by a methyl group (eCH3) to generate compound 
28
and afterwards by an ethyl group (eCH2eCH3) to result in compound 
29
. The calculated log 
P
values for both compounds were higher than for compound 
19
, but HOMO and HOMO–1 energies were somewhat lower. The predicted 
p
IC50 for these compounds were close to the 
p
IC50 of the third most active compound, 
21
(
Table 4
). These results indicate that although log 
P
values were higher than that of the most active compound, the predicted activities were close to the compounds with similar HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 energies. Another kaurenoic derivative was proposed, synthesized and tested in this work (compound 

27
in

Table 4
). This compound was also modified in the R1 position, but with a completely different substituent from that of the most active compound, 
19
. Although this modification led to a logP value decrease, the HOMO energy of compound 
27
is closer to that of active compounds 
19
and 
20
when compared to those of compounds 
28
and 
29
(
Table 4
). All descriptor values for compound 
27
were similar to the values of compound 
21
and consequently, the estimated 
p
IC50 (4.49 mol L −1) was slightly higher than that of compound 
21
(
p
IC50 = 4.37 mol L −1). This compound was tested 
a posteriori
against MCF-7 breast cells and the experimental value for IC50 was 30.35 μmol L −1 (
p
IC50 = 4.52 mol L −1), confirming the activity predicted by the model (
p
IC50 observed – 
p
IC50 predicted = 0.03).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

(A) 27 (B) 28 (
C
) 29

</p>
         <p>
50 (
p
IC50pred
</p>
         <p>in mol L −1).</p>
         <p>
The biological response produced by bioactive compounds depends on a series of factors and conditions, including absorption and distribution mechanisms (

; 

; 

; Wermuth et al., 2015). The PLS model for this set of compounds indicate that HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 orbitals energies and log 
P
are related to activity against MCF-7 breast cells. A careful analysis of the results revealed that the interaction of this series of diterpenes derived from kaurenoic acid can occur by charge displacement, mainly from diterpenes to the target. However, when comparing with results from the literature for other series of diterpenes, it is suggested that the interaction with the receptor can also occur by charge displacement from the target to the diterpenes. The PLS regression model also indicated that lipophilic substituents increase the biological activity. In addition, through visualization of the HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 molecular orbitals surfaces, it was possible to identify the positions in which the substituents should be modified in order to increase their biological activity. The graphical representations of these orbitals for active compounds suggest that the intermolecular interaction occurs mainly from substituent R1.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
A QSAR analysis for a set of 26 kaurenoic acid derivatives was tested in this study against breast cancer cells through PLS regression analysis. The model was validated by y-randomization and leave- 
N
-out tests, in addition to external validation with a test set. Validation tests showed that the model is robust and presents a good prediction power. According to the PLS regression equation, the activity against MCF-7 breast cancer cells is related to log 
P
and HOMO and HOMO–1 energies, such that the higher log 
P
, HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 energies, the higher the activity. The positive relationship between these orbitals and the activity indicates that interaction with the target occurs mainly by charge displacement from the kaurenoic acid derivatives to the cell target. This finding corroborates with the literature in the sense that the drug-receptor interactions for this class of compounds with carcinogenic activity are predominantly guided by charge transfer or charge displacement. In addition, the graphical representations of the HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 molecular orbital for active compounds suggest that charge displacement occurs mainly from substituent R1. The activity increase in log 
P
, εHOMO and εHOMO-1 values indicates that more active compounds could be designed by modifying the radical R1 with more lipophilic substituents, which at the same time give the molecules higher HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 values. Based on these results, three compounds were proposed and one of them was synthesized and tested. The experimental result confirmed the activity predicted by the model.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General procedures
</title>
         <p>
NMR spectra were recorded either on a Bruker Avance DRX 400 or on a Jeol 300 MHz spectrometer. Samples were dissolved in CDCl3, pyridine-d or MeOD, and TMS was used as internal reference. The biotransformation procedures were performed on a Cientec CT-713 rotary shaker. All solvents were anhydrous and the reactions to obtain compound 
27
were performed under an inert atmosphere unless aqueous. All round-bottom flasks were kept dried in an oven under 100 ° 
C
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Kaurenoic acid isolation
</title>
         <p>
Kaurenoic acid was isolated from 150.0 g 
<tp:taxon-name>
Copaifera
</tp:taxon-name>
ssp oleoresin which was chromatographed through several chromatographic methods, as previously reported by Simão and coworkers (Simao et al., 2016). The identification of such compound was performed by spectroscopic analysis and compared with literature data (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

4.3. Microbial transformation of kaurenoic acid by 
<tp:taxon-name>Aspergillus terreus</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Prof. Dr. Suraia Said from the Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences of Ribeirão Preto, University of 
São Paulo
, 
Brazil
provided the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aspergillus terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
strain used in the biotransformation processes. This microorganism was maintained as a conidial suspension preparation on silica gel (6–12 mesh, grade 40, desiccant-activated), at 4 °C. The microbial transformation experiments were conducted using submerged shaken liquid culture and two-stage fermentation procedures. An inoculum of 1.73 × 10 7 conidia/mL was aseptically added to ten Erlenmeyer flasks (1000 mL) containing 500 mL of seed medium, as previously described in the literature (

). Cultures were incubated at 30 °C using a shaker operating at 120 rpm. After 24 h of incubation, the resulting mycelia were harvested, rinsed, and aseptically transferred to ten Erlenmeyer flasks (2000 mL) containing 1000 mL of sterile medium consisting of sucrose (3.0%), NaNO3 (0.2%), K2HPO4 (0.05%), MgSO4.7H2O (0.05%), KCl (0.05%), and FeSO4.7H2O (0.001%). After 24 h, 40 mL of 25.0 mg mL −1 of kaurenoic acid in dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) were equally distributed among the seven flasks, which were incubated again. Incubation was stopped after fourteen days and the cultures were filtered. The resulting aqueous layer was extracted with ethyl acetate (20 × 1000 mL) to yield the extract labeled AtE (
<tp:taxon-name>
A. terreus
</tp:taxon-name>
extract; 
2.24 g
) after solvent evaporation. Culture (culture medium containing microorganisms only incubated with DMSO) and substrate (sterile medium containing the same amount of kaurenoic acid incubated under the experimental condition) controls were also prepared for this strain

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Isolation of diterpenes obtained by microbial transformation
</title>
         <p>
Aiming to obtain a rich fraction of acid diterpenes from microbial transformation extract, AtE (
2.24 g
) was firstly submitted to an acidbase extraction, according to the methodology previously described by 

. The resulting organic phase from this procedure (AtEO; 
1.53 g
) was chromatographed over silica gel 60 
H
(Merck, art.7736) using VLC with increasing amounts of ethyl acetate in hexanes as eluent. This procedure furnished seven fractions (300 mL each): AtEO1 (12.0 mg; hexanes), AtEO2 (23.0 mg; 20% ethyl acetate), AtEO3 (
836.1 mg
; 40% ethyl acetate), AtEO4 (
96.2 mg
; 60% ethyl acetate), AtEO5 (
81.3 mg
; 80% ethyl acetate), AtEO6 (
45.1 mg
; ethyl acetate) and AtEO7 (
125.3 mg
; MeOH). AtEO3 was initially partitioned by classic chromatography (CC) using an isocratic hexanes/EtOAc 8:2 mobile phase; ten new fractions were obtained (AtEO3.1- AtEO3.10). Diterpene 
ent
-7α-hydroxy-kaur-16-en-19-oic acid (compound 
2
; 
Fig. 1
; 
256.4 mg
) was identified from AtEO3.5. TLC analysis (Whatman, 250.0 μm layer) of AtEO3.7 revealed a main spot that was purified by flash chromatography (hexanes/ethyl acetate/CHCl3 5:2:3), furnishing the derivative 
ent
-15β-hydroxy-kaur-16-en-19-oic acid (compound 
3
; 
Fig. 1
; 
39.7 mg
). AtEO4 and AtEO5 were combined on the basis of their quite similar TLC profile and designated AtEO4 (
177.5 mg
). This new fraction was first partitioned by CC (hexanes/ethyl acetate/CHCl3 4:3:3), leading to six additional fractions (AtEO4.1–AtEO4.6). Diterpene 
ent
-7α,11β-dihydroxy-kaur-16-en-19-oic acid (compound 
5
; 
Fig. 1
; 
12.1 mg
) was obtained from fraction AtEO4.6 after purification performed by washing with cold 
CH
2Cl2. Finally, analysis of AtEO7 by TLC revealed that the main metabolite present in this fraction afforded an extensive tail, which is a characteristic of compounds containing COOH groups in their structure. Aiming to facilitate its isolation, fraction AtEO7 was treated with ethereal diazomethane (Batista et al., 2007), and diterpene methyl 
ent
-7α,16β-dihydroxy-kaur-19-oate was later purified by CC (hexanes/ethyl acetate 1:1) as its methyl ester derivative (compound 
4
; 
Fig. 1
; 
25.2 mg
). This reaction was also performed with diterpene 
2
(50.0 mg) and its respective methyl ester (compound 
6
; 
Fig. 1
; 
34.6 mg
) was obtained after purification by CC (hexanes/ethyl acetate 8:2).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Synthesis of compound 27
</title>
         <p>
The synthesis of compound 
27
was performed according to published procedures (Simao et al., 2016). The crude product was purified by automated flash chromatography eluting with hexanes/ethyl acetate.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Cell viability assay - XTT
</title>
         <p>
The human breast carcinoma cell line (MCF-7 cells) was obtained from the Cell Bank of 
Rio de Janeiro
(BCRJ code 0069) and cultured. Diterpenes were dissolved in a 0.1% 
DMSO
solution (stock concentration of 0.1 M) and a serial dilution was performed to obtain concentrations ranging from 1000.0 to 0.975 μg mL −1. To determine the viability, cells were seeded in complete medium (1 × 10 4 cells/well) in 96 well plates and 24 h after treatment, plates were washed twice with phosphate buffer saline and incubated 4 h at 37 ° 
C
with DMEM without phenol red but containing XTT dye, as recommended by the manufacturer. Statistical analysis of experimental data was performed using the GraphPad InStat 3.0 software and IC50 values were calculated. Doxorubicin and 
DMSO
0.1% were employed as positive and solvent controls, respectively. Details to this procedure were previously described (Simao et al., 2016).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Computational methods
</title>
         <p>
Full geometry optimization and vibrational frequency calculations were carried out using the Gaussian09 program package (Gaussian Inc, Wallingford) using the B3LYP hybrid functional (

), and 6- 311 + G(d,p) basis set (

). The nature of the stationary point was determined through the eigenvalues obtained from the harmonic vibration analysis. The kaurenoic acid derivatives 
2
to 
26
were rotated around bonds 
a
and 
b
(
Fig. 5
) in order to adopt the same conformation of optimized geometry as the most active molecule (
1
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Multivariate data analysis (PLS) and QSAR studies
</title>
         <p>
A total of 659 descriptors were obtained, including topological properties calculated by the e-Dragon software (Tetko et al., 2005). The partition coefficient octanol/water (log 
P
), molecular volume and surface area were calculated using the Hyperchem software version 7.0 (Hypercube, Gainsville). The calculated descriptors for the 26 compounds from the training and test sets (
Table 1
) were organized in a matrix format 
X
(26,659), while IC50 values were arranged in a column vector 
y
, after data transformation into –log IC50 (or 
p
IC50, with IC 
50 in
mol L −1). The auto-scaled (mean-centered and unity variance scales) 
y
vector and descriptors matrix were correlated through the QSAR modeling software (

). Initially, those descriptors presenting a Pearson correlation coefficient with a 
p
IC50 lower than 0.3 were eliminated (

). Then, the ordered predictors selection (OPS) algorithm (Teofilo et al., 2009), implemented on QSAR modeling, was applied during a second variable selection step. In the OPS algorithm, PLS models are built on auto-scaled descriptors by rearranging the columns of the data matrix in such a way that the most important descriptors are placed in the first columns. Then, successive PLS regressions are performed with increasing number of descriptors in order to find the best PLS model (

). Leave-one-out cross-validation was applied to determine the number of factors (latent variables) in the regression model.
</p>
         <p>
The statistics of the final PLS model obtained, by taking into account the descriptors log 
P
, HOMO and 
HOMO-
1 energies, was assessed by the coefficient of multiple determination of calibration (R2), coefficient of multiple determination of cross validation, (
QLNO
2), standard error of calibration (
SEC
), standard error of cross validation (
SECV
) and average relative error of prediction (
ARE
pred) (Supplementary information, 
Table S3
). The final model obtained was validated applying y-randomization (

; 

) and leave- 
N
- out analyses. The y-randomization test was performed to investigate the possibility of chance correlation, where the y vector was scrambled 50 times. The robustness of the optimized model was examined by leave- 
N
- out cross validation (LNO, N = 1 to 5) procedure. This test was repeated twenty times for each N value, as explained by 

; 

; Baumann and Stiefl (2004) and 

(Baumann and Stiefl, 2004; 

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
An 
a priori
regression model was built to perform variable selection and investigate the presence of outliers. This model also allowed determining the number of latent variables in the model. The construction of the final model and external validation was carried out after splitting the total set of 26 compounds into training and test sets. Hierarchical cluster analysis built with the 
R
software version 3.2.1 (2015) shows that all groups were well represented in the selected test set, considering the structural variability and IC50 range. The predictive power of the PLS model was determined by the coefficient of multiple determination of prediction (
R2 pred
) and standard error of prediction (SEP).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgments
</title>
         <p>The authors are thankful to FAPESP (Processes number: 2007/ 54762-8, 2011/23028-2, 2011/07623-8 and 2011/13630-7), CAPES and CNPq for funds and grants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.10.005.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Batista, R.
, 
Garcia, P.A.
, 
Castro, M.A.
, 
del Corral, J.M.M.
, 
Speziali, N.L.
, 
Varotti, F.D.
, 

de Paula, R. 
C
.

, 
Garcia-Fernandez, L.F.
, 
Francesch, A.
, 
Feliciano, A.S.
, 
de Oliveira, A.B.
, 
2013
. 
Synthesis, cytotoxicity and antiplasmodial activity of novel ent-kaurane derivatives
. 
Eur. J. Med. Chem.
62
, 
168–176
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Batista, R.
, 
Humberto, J.L.
, 
Chiari, E.
, 
de Oliveira, A.B.
, 
2007
. 

Synthesis and trypanocidal activity of 
ent-
kaurane glycosides. Bioorg. Med. Chem. 15, 381–391. 

Baumann, 
K
., Stiefl, N., 2004. Validation tools for variable subset regression. 

J. Comput. 

Aided Mol. Des. 
18
, 
549–562
.




</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Becke, A.D.
, 
1993
. 
Density‐functional thermochemistry. III. The role of exact exchange
. 
J. Chem. Phys.
98
, 
5648–5652
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Braga, R.S.
, 
Barone, P.M.V.B.
, 
Galvao, D.S.
, 
2000
. 
Identifying carcinogenic activity of methylated and non-methylated polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) through electronic and topological indices
. 
Braz. J. Phys.
30
, 
560–568
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Carman, R.M.
, 
1964
. 

Agathis microstachya
oleoresin

. 
Aust. J. Chem.
17
, 
393–394
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Clark, R.D.
, 
Fox, P.C.
, 
2004
. 
Statistical variation in progressive scrambling
. 
J. Comput. Aided Mol. Des.
18
, 
563–576
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Costa-Lotufo, L.V.
, 
Cunha, G.M.A.
, 
Farias, P.A.M.
, 
Viana, G.S.B.
, 
Cunha, K.M.A.
, 
Pessoa, C.
, 
Moraes, M.O.
, 
Silveira, E.R.
, 
Gramosa, N.V.
, 
Rao, V.S.N.
, 
2002
. 

The cytotoxic and embryotoxic effects of kaurenoic acid, a diterpene isolated from 
Copaifera langsdorffii
oleo-resin

. 
Toxicon
40
, 
1231–1234
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Danishuddin
, 
Khan, A.U.
, 
2016
. 
Descriptors and their selection methods in QSAR analysis: paradigm for drug design. Drug Discov
. 
Today
21
, 
1291–1302
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
De Andrade, B.B.
, 
Moreira, M.R.
, 
Ambrosio, S.R.
, 
Furtado, N.A.J.C.
, 
Cunha, W.R.
, 
Martins, C.H.G.
, 
Veneziani, R.C.S.
, 
2011
. 

Evaluation of 
ent
-kaurenoic acid derivatives for their anticariogenic activity

. 
Nat. Prod. Commun.
6
, 
777–780
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Do Nascimento, A.M.
, 
De Oliveira, D.C.R.
, 
2001
. 

Kaurene diterpenes and other chemical constituents from 
Mikania stipulacea
(M. Vahl) willd

. 
J. Braz. Chem. Soc.
12
, 
552–555
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
dos Santos, G.F.
, 
da Silva Lima, G.
, 
Pereira de Oliveira, G.
, 
de Souza Filho, J.D.
, 
da Silva Amaral, L.
, 
Rodrigues-Filho, E.
, 
Takahashi, J.A.
, 
2018
. 

New AChE inhibitors from microbial transformation of trachyloban-19-oic acid by 
Syncephalastrum racemosum

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
79
, 
60–63
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Duarte, N.
, 
Jardanhazy, A.
, 
Molnar, J.
, 
Hilgeroth, A.
, 
Ferreira, M.J.U.
, 
2008
. 
Synergistic interaction between p-glycoprotein modulators and epirubicine on resistant cancer cells
. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem.
16
, 
9323–9330
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eriksson, L.
, 
Jaworska, J.
, 
Worth, A.P.
, 
Cronin, M.T.D.
, 
McDowell, R.M.
, 
Gramatica, P.
, 
2003
. 
Methods for reliability and uncertainty assessment and for applicability evaluations of classification- and regression-based QSARs. Environ
. 
Health Perspect.
111
, 
1361–1375
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ferreira, M.M.C.
, 
2015
. 
Quimiometria: Conceitos, Métodos e Aplicações
. 
Editora UNICAMP, Campinas
, pp. 496.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Foye, W.O.
, 
Lemke, T.L.
, 
Williams, D.A.
, 
1995
. 
Principles of Medicinal Chemistry
. 
Williams &amp; Wilkins, Philadelphia
, pp. 1489.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fraga, B.M.
, 
Bressa, C.
, 
Gonzalez-Vallejo, V.
, 
Gonzalez, P.
, 
Guillermo, R.
, 
2012
. 

Biotransforrnation of ent-kaur-16-ene and ent-trachylobane 7 beta-acetoxy derivatives by the fungus 
Gibberella fujikuroi
(
Fusarium fujikuroi
)

. 
Phytochemistry
81
, 
60–70
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fraga, B.M.
, 
Bressa, C.
, 
Gonzalez-Vallejo, V.
, 
Suarez, S.
, 
Guillermo, R.
, 
2011
. 
Neighbouring group participation in the reaction of 7-oxo-ent-kaur-16-ene derivatives with diacetoxyiodobenzene. Synthesis of gibberellin analogues
. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
52
, 
7138–7140
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Golbraikh, A.
, 
Tropsha, A.
, 
2002
. 
Beware of q
(2)!. 
J. Mol. Graph. Model.
20
, 
269–276
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hadda, T.B.
, 
Karagoz Genc, Z.
, 
Masand, V.H.
, 
Nebbache, N.
, 
Warad, I.
, 
Jodeh, S.
, 
Genc, M.
, 
Mabkhot, Y.N.
, 
Barakat, A.
, 
Zamora, H.S.
, 
2015
. 
Computational POM and DFT evaluation of experimental in-vitro cancer inhibition of staurosporine-ruthenium(II) complexes: the power force of organometallics in drug design
. 
Acta Chim. Slov.
62
, 
679–688
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hansch, C.
, 
Sammes, P.G.
, 
Taylor, J.B.
, 
1990
. 
Comprehensive Medicinal Chemistry: the Rational Design, Mechanistic Study &amp; Therapeutic Applications of Chemical Compounds
. 
Pergamon Press, Oxford
, pp. 6000.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hilgeroth, A.
, 
Molnar, A.
, 
Molnar, J.
, 
Voigt, B.
, 
2006
. 
Correlation of calculated molecular orbital energies of some phenothiazine compounds with MDR reversal properties
. 
Eur. J. Med. Chem.
41
, 
548–551
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hueso-Falcon, I.
, 
Giron, N.
, 
Velasco, P.
, 
Amaro-Luis, J.M.
, 
Ravelo, A.G.
, de las 
Heras, B.
, 
Hortelano, S.
, 
Estevez-Braun, A.
, 
2010
. 
Synthesis and induction of apoptosis signaling pathway of ent-kaurane derivatives
. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem.
18
, 
1724–1735
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jackson, M.
, 
Karwowski, J.P.
, 
Humphrey, P.E.
, 
Kohl, W.L.
, 
Barlow, G.J.
, 
Tanaka, S.K.
, 
1993
. 
Calbistrins, novel antifungal agents produced by penicillium-restrictum
.1. 
Production, taxonomy of the producing organism and biological-activity. J. Antibiot.
46
, 
34–38
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kiralj, R.
, 
Ferreira, M.M.C.
, 
2009
. 
Basic validation procedures for regression models in QSAR and QSPR studies: theory and application
. 
J. Braz. Chem. Soc.
20
, 
770–787
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kiralj, R.
, 
Ferreira, M.M.C.
, 
2010
. 
Is your QSAR/QSPR descriptor real or trash?
J. Chemometr.
24
, 
681–693
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Krishnan, R.
, 
Binkley, J.S.
, 
Seeger, R.
, 
Pople, J.A.
, 
1980
. 
Self‐consistent molecular orbital methods. XX. A basis set for correlated wave functions
. 
J. Chem. Phys.
72
, 
650–654
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kubinyi, H.
, 
1979
. 
Progress in Drug Research
. 
Birkhäuer Verlag, Basel
, pp. 101.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kubinyi, H.
, 
2008
. 
QSAR: Hansch Analysis and Related Approaches
. 
VCH Verlagsgesellschaft mbH, New York
, pp. 240.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lizarte Neto, F.S.
, 
Tirapelli, D.P.C.
, 
Ambrosio, S.R.
, 
Tirapelli, C.R.
, 
Oliveira, F.M.
, 
Novais, P.C.
, 
Peria, F.M.
, 
Oliveira, H.F.
, 
Carlotti Junior, C.G.
, 
Tirapelli, L.F.
, 
2013
. 
Kaurene diterpene induces apoptosis in U87 human malignant glioblastoma cells by suppression of anti-apoptotic signals and activation of cysteine proteases
. 
Braz. J. Med. Biol. Res.
46
, 
71–78
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Marquina, S.
, 
Parra, J.L.
, 
Gonzalez, M.
, 
Zamilpa, A.
, 
Escalante, J.
, 
Trejo-Hernandez, M.R.
, 
Alvarez, L.
, 
2009
. 

Hydroxylation of the diterpenes 
ent-
kaur-16-en-19-oic and 
entbeyer-
15-en-19-oic acids by the fungus 
Aspergillus niger

. 
Phytochemistry
70
, 
2017–2022
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Martinez, J.C.G.
, 
Andrada, M.F.
, 
Vega-Hissi, E.G.
, 
Garibotto, F.M.
, 
Nogueras, M.
, 
Rodriguez, R.
, 
Cobo, J.
, 
Enriz, R.D.
, 
Estrada, M.R.
, 
2017
. 
Dihydrofolate reductase inhibitors: a quantitative structure-activity relationship study using 2D-QSAR and 3D-QSAR methods
. 
Med. Chem. Res.
26
, 
247–261
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Martins, J.P.A.
, 
Ferreira, M.C.M.
, 
2013
. 
QSAR modeling: um novo pacote computacional open source para gerar e validar modelos QSAR. Quim
. 
Nova
36
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Misra, S.K.
, 
Ghoshal, G.
, 
Gartia, M.R.
, 
Wu, Z.
, 
De, A.K.
, 
Ye, M.
, 
Bromfield, C.R.
, 
Williams, E.M.
, 
Singh, K.
, 
Tangella, K.V.
, 
Rund, L.
, 
Schulten, K.
, 
Schook, L.B.
, 
Ray, P.S.
, 
Burdette, E.C.
, 
Pan, D.
, 
2015
. 
Trimodal therapy: combining hyperthermia with repurposed bexarotene and ultrasound for treating liver cancer
. 
ACS Nano
9
, 
10695–10718
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mizokami, S.S.
, 
Arakawa, N.S.
, 
Ambrosio, S.R.
, 
Zarpelon, A.C.
, 
Casagrande, R.
, 
Cunha, T.M.
, 
Ferreira, S.H.
, 
Cunha, F.Q.
, 
Verri, W.A.
, 
2012
. 

Kaurenoic acid from 
Sphagneticola trilobata
inhibits inflammatory pain: effect on cytokine production and activation of the NO-Cyclic GMP-Protein kinase G-ATP-Sensitive potassium channel signaling pathway

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
75
, 
896–904
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moreira, M.R.
, 
Souza, A.B.
, 
Soares, S.
, 
Bianchi, T.C.
, 
de Souza Eugenio, D.
, 
Lemes, D.C.
, 
Martins, C.H.
, 
da Silva Moraes, T.
, 
Tavares, D.C.
, 
Ferreira, N.H.
, 
Ambrosio, S.R.
, 
Veneziani, R.C.
, 
2016
. 

ent
-Kaurenoic acid-rich extract from 
Mikania glomerata
: in vitro activity against bacteria responsible for dental caries

. 
Fitoterapia
112
, 
211–216
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Newman, D.J.
, 
Cragg, G.M.
, 
2016
. 
Natural products as sources of new drugs from 1981 to 2014
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
79
, 
629–661
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
OECD
, 
O.F.E.C.-O.A.D
., 
2007
. 
Guidance document on validation of (quantitative structure-activity relationship [QSAR] models
. In: 
OECD
. vol. 
69
OECD, Paris.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Parshikov, I.A.
, 
Sutherland, J.B.
, 
2014
. 

The use of 
Aspergillus niger
cultures for biotransformation of terpenoids

. 
Process Biochem.
49
, 
2086–2100
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Porto, T.S.
, 
Simao, M.R.
, 
Carlos, L.Z.
, 
Martins, C.H.G.
, 
Furtado, N.A.J.C.
, 
Said, S.
, 
Arakawa, N.S.
, 
dos Santos, R.A.
, 
Veneziani, R.C.S.
, 
Ambrosio, S.R.
, 
2013
. 
Pimaranetype diterpenes obtained by biotransformation: antimicrobial properties against clinically isolated gram-positive multidrug-resistant bacteria
. 
Phytother Res.
27
, 
1502–1507
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pratim, R.P.
, 
Kunal, R.
, 
2008
. 
On some aspects of variable selection for partial least squares regression models. QSAR Comb
. 
Sci.
27
, 
302–313
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Roy, P.P.
, 
Leonard, J.T.
, 
Roy, K.
, 
2008
. 
Exploring the impact of size of training sets for the development of predictive QSAR models
. 
Chemometr. Intell. Lab. Syst.
90
, 
31–42
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rucker, C.
, 
Rucker, G.
, 
Meringer, M.
, 
2007
. 
y-Randomization and its variants in QSPR/ QSAR
. 
J. Chem. Inf. Model.
47
, 
2345–2357
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rudolf, J.D.
, 
Dong, L.B.
, 
Manoogian, K.
, 
Shen, B.
, 
2016
. 
Biosynthetic origin of the ether ring in platensimycin
. 
J. Am. Chem. Soc.
138
, 
16711–16721
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Severiano, M.E.
, 
Simao, M.R.
, 
Ramos, H.P.
, 
Parreira, R.L.
, 
Arakawa, N.S.
, 
Said, S.
, 
Furtado, N.A.
, 
de Oliveira, D.C.
, 
Gregorio, L.E.
, 
Tirapelli, C.R.
, 
Veneziani, R.C.
, 
Ambrosio, S.R.
, 
2013
. 
Biotransformation of ent-pimaradienoic acid by cell cultures of
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
