<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112538</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Mobilization of storage lipid reserve and expression analysis of lipase and lipoxygenase genes in rice (Oryza sativa var. Pusa Basmati 1) bran during germination</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Oryza sativa</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Oryza sativa</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oryza sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form phytoalexins</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
(
Thazar-Poulot et al., 2015
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
TAG
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
LOX
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
Information Resource
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oryza sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
LOX
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
Information Resource
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oryza sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis thaliana
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Oryza sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Indica</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
TAG
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
Information Resource
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Mobilization of storage lipid reserve and expression analysis of lipase and lipoxygenase genes in rice (

<tp:taxon-name>Oryza sativa</tp:taxon-name>
var. Pusa Basmati 1

) bran during germination

</p>
         <p>
Kshitija Sinha
a
, Ranjeet Kaur
b
, Nishu Singh
c
, Sumandeep Kaur
d
, Vikas Rishi
a
,
</p>
         <p>
Rupam Kumar Bhunia 

a, 
*
</p>
         <p>
a

National Agri-Food Biotechnology Institute (NABI), Plant Tissue Culture and 
Genetic Engineering
, 
Mohali
, 140306, 
Punjab
, 
India
</p>
         <p>
b

Department of Genetics, University of 
Delhi
South Campus, New 
Delhi
, 110026, 
India
</p>
         <p>
c
Department of Biotechnology
, 
Banasthali Vidyapith
, 
Vanasthali
, 304022, 
Rajasthan
, 
India
</p>
         <p>
d

Department of Biotechnology, Sector-25, 
Panjab
University, 
Chandigarh
, 160014, 
India
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Storage lipid mobilization by lipases and lipoxygenases (LOXs) in response to developmental cues take place during seed germination. After rice grain milling, the endogenous lipases and LOXs present in the bran fraction come in contact with the storage lipid reserve or triacylglycerol (TAG). Lipases catalyze the hydrolysis of TAGs to non-esterified fatty acids (NEFAs) and glycerol. The NEFAs, especially linoleic acid (18:2) produced, are further subjected to oxidative rancidity via peroxidation reaction catalyzed by LOXs. This results in the production of conjugated hydroperoxides of 18:2 that influence the off-flavors in rice bran lipids. The aim of this study is to understand how lipid mobilization and expression of lipase and LOX genes occur in the bran of germinating rice grains (

<tp:taxon-name>Oryza sativa</tp:taxon-name>
var. Pusa Basmati 1

). Our results show that the primary source of storage lipids in bran is TAG, and its mobilization starts at 4 days after imbibition (4 DAI). Using publically available RNA-seq data and phylogeny analyses, we selected a total of 18 lipase and 16 LOX genes in rice for their expression profiles during onset of lipid mobilization. Gene expression analyses revealed 
OsLip1
, 
OsLip9
, and 
OsLip13
; and 
OsLOX3
and 
OsLOX14
as the predominantly expressed genes in bran of germinating rice grains. This study explores two important events in the germinating rice grains, namely, mobilization of storage lipids and expression pattern of lipase and LOX genes. The information generated in this study can be used to efficiently manipulate the genes to enhance the shelf-stability of bran lipid reserve.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Oil-producing crops have been one of the most dynamic parts of agriculture. Worldwide, over the next thirty years, demand for vegetable oils is expected to double, with increasing requirements for food, feed, and fuel. Storage lipids are the major energy reserve stored in the form of triacylglycerols (TAGs) in oil-seed crops including cereals such as rice, oats, barley, and corn. Most of the cereal plants store carbohydrates and proteins in the endosperm; and TAGs and micronutrients in the bran layer, that is further used for oil extraction (

).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Oryza sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
(rice) belongs to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>
and is an important cereal crop due to the high starch content in endosperm along with lipids (3–4% of the grain), stored in the bran (Juliano and Tuano, 2019). Rice bran consists of a pericarp, seed coat, nucellus, and aleurone layer, the latter being high in TAGs, proteins, vitamins, and mineral content (

). TAGs stored in the rice bran are rich in palmitic (16:0), oleic (18:1), and linoleic (18:2) acids, that are also found in the rice bran oil (RBO) (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
TAGs are accumulated rapidly in rice grains between 5 and 12 days after pollination (
DAP
) (

) and stored as oil bodies (OBs) that are coated by oleosin proteins (oleosin 16 and oleosin 18) (

). During germination of rice grains, TAGs stored in bran are degraded by TAG lipases, releasing non-esterified FAs (NEFAs) and glycerol. The NEFAs are further degraded through the β- oxidation and glyoxylate pathway, and subsequently converted to transportable nutrient molecules (sugars) that are transferred through the absorptive scutellum to furnish energy for the growing embryo (

).
</p>
         <p>
Lipase activity is likely to be induced during post-germinative growth and a sharp decrease was observed as seedling growth progresses (

). Lipases contain the conserved GXSXG motif, where serine plays a role in the active site (

). Naturally, lipases hydrolyze the stored TAGs/DAGs (diacylglycerols)/MAGs (monoacylglycerols) in bran at 
Sn -1
, 
Sn
-3, or, sometimes, 
Sn
-2 position of the backbone. The generated NEFAs, especially the polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs), are prone to oxidation by the action of lipoxygenases (LOXs) (

). LOX is a non-heme and monomeric dioxygenase enzyme that catalyzes the peroxidation reaction in PUFAs (such as 18:2 and 18:3) containing 
cis
, 
cis
-1,4-pentadiene structure and generates conjugated unsaturated FA hydroperoxides (

). These hydroperoxy-FAs are the major factors influencing the stale flavors, which subsequently 
<tp:taxon-name>form phytoalexins</tp:taxon-name>
and signaling molecules via different metabolic pathways (

). Based on the substrate specificity at position 9 or 13 of the hydrocarbon backbone, LOXs are classified into 9-LOXs and 13-LOXs (

).
</p>
         <p>
In rice bran, compartmentalized TAGs are stored as OBs in the aleurone layer of bran fraction. However, during the rice milling individual cells are disrupted, thus exposing the TAG reserve to highly reactive endogenous lipases. This enables lipases to catalyze the hydrolysis of TAGs resulting in the release of NEFAs. This hydrolytic activity tends to continue during the prolonged storage of milled bran, reaching up to 40–60% of NEFAs (

). The liberated NEFAs, especially the 18:2, is further subjected to oxidative degradation catalyzed by LOX enzymes resulting in the production of hydroperoxides of 18:2 (

). These hydroperoxide molecules are the key metabolites responsible for the off-flavors of rice bran lipids (

).
</p>
         <p>Since the lipases and LOXs have a role in lipid mobilization and FA peroxidation, this research was aimed to comprehend the involvement of different lipases and LOXs in the mobilization of rice bran storage lipids during and after germination. This understanding of lipid mobilization and expression analysis of lipases and LOXs is crucial for the development of future genome editing approach to develop low rancid bran oil.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Lipid reserve mobilization during germination
</title>
         <p>
In order to study the mobilization of lipid reserves of bran in germinating rice grains, the four major lipid contents viz., TAGs, DAGs, NEFAs, and polar lipids (PLs) were analyzed between 2 h after imbibition (HAI) and 8 days after imbibition (DAI). The difference between the initial TAGs at 2 HAI and the remaining TAGs at 8 DAI was measured to indicate the TAG mobilization in rice bran. To begin with the TAG pool (
Fig. 1a
), it was observed that the abundance of TAGs in the rice bran tissue remained nearly unaltered between 2 HAI (58.0 μmol/g) and 4 DAI (54.4 μmol/g). Mobilization of TAG pool during germination of rice grain started at 4 DAI, as it was observed that at 6 DAI and 8 DAI, the TAG content declined to 36.2 μmol/g and 20.4 μmol/g, respectively (
Fig. 1a
). Compared with the TAG pool, other lipid classes (DAGs, NEFAs, and PLs) were found to be present in very low quantities in the bran fraction. The DAG pool of bran also showed a decline from 2 HAI (5.3 μmol/g) to 8 DAI (1.8 μmol/g), indicating that majority of the DAG pool was mobilized during this period (
Fig. 1a
). A relatively low mobilization pattern was observed for PLs, that showed a decline in its abundance from 2 HAI (7.2 μmol/g) to 8 DAI (5.1 μmol/g) (
Fig. 1a
). However, an increase in NEFA pool was observed from 2 HAI (0.4 μmol/ g) to 8 DAI (6.9 μmol/g).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Compositional changes in FA profiles of TAGs, DAGs, NEFAs and
</title>
         <p>
PLs during germination
</p>
         <p>
In order to obtain a holistic view of the lipid reserve mobilization events occurring in bran during different stages of rice grain germination, FA profiles of four bran lipid classes viz., TAGs, DAGs, NEFAs and PLs were also investigated (
Fig. 1b–e
). The FA profiles of the bran lipids consisted of three major FAs, 16:0, 18:1, and 18:2 along with other minor FAs, 16:1 (palmitoleic acid), 18:0 (stearic acid), 18:3 (α- linolenic acid), 20:0 (eicosanoic acid), and 20:1 (
cis
-11-eicosenoic acid). As expected 16:0, 18:1, and 18:2 FA of the TAG reserve showed a sharp decline between 4 DAI to 8 DAI from 10.5–4.3 μmol/g, 24.8–8.2 μmol/g and 14.0–5.9 μmol/g, respectively. In case of the DAG pool, 16:0 FA declined from 2.5 μmol/g at 2 HAI to 0.7 μmol/g at 8 DAI, but remained unchanged or slightly changed for other FAs during early germination (
Fig. 1c
). The NEFA pool showed an increasing proportion of 16:0, 18:1, and 18:2 FAs from 0.2–3.36 μmol/g, 0.07–1.27 μmol/g and 0.05–1.49 μmol/g, respectively from 2 HAI to 8 DAI (
Fig. 1d
), while the other FAs remained nearly unchanged. FAs of the PL pool started to accumulate in the bran tissues from 4 DAI onwards. The 16:0 and 18:1 FAs of PL pool were noted to accumulate from 0.76–1.28 μmol/g and 0.28–1.66 μmol/ g, respectively from 4 DAI to 8 DAI (
Fig. 1e
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Identification of rice lipase and LOX genes
</title>
         <p>
In order to identify the rice lipase and LOX genes for this study, data mining was performed using the Rice Genome Annotation Project (
RGAP
) public database. A query for the keyword “Lipase” in the putative function search tool resulted in a catalogue of 73 lipase genes (Table S3). Due to the large number of putative lipases obtained from the search, we grouped them based on their fragments per kilo base per million mapped reads (
FPKM
) expression. A maximum of five genes with highest 
FPKM
values in each of the four selected stages of the following tissues, viz., developing rice grain (5 and 10 
DAP
), endosperm (25 
DAP
) and leaves (20 
DAP
) were chosen for our study. After eliminating the duplicate gene entries from the shortlisted 20 genes, 11 lipases were selected for further analysis (
Table 1
). We would like to mention here that out of these 11 genes obtained from 
RGAP
data mining process, four genes were found to be devoid of lipase active site (
Table 1
). We studied their relative abundances in rice bran during the germination and postgermination stages.
</p>
         <p>
Apart from these 11 lipases, we also included 
sugar-dependent1
(
SDP1
, LOC_Os01g55650) as a candidate lipase for our study, taking the count to 12 lipases. 
SDP1
was identified as the major lipase involved in TAG reserve mobilization during seedling growth in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
(
Thazar-Poulot et al., 2015
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. In order to ensure that our study of rice lipases was exhaustive, a phylogenetic tree analysis of the 74 rice lipases was performed with the known 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
TAG
</tp:taxon-name>
lipases (
Fig. 2
).
</p>
         <p>
Based on the obtained results, the presence of lipase-conserved motif (GXSXG) and minimum expression (
FPKM
) profile of the lipases in any of the three tissues (Table S3), additional nine rice lipase genes were added to the list for further analysis. However, out of these nine selected rice lipases, three genes were found to be common with the previously selected 12 lipases and were removed from the list. This made the total number of candidate lipase genes as 18, and these were then named as 
OsLip1
to 
OsLip18
(
Table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
A similar search for LOX genes was also performed using the 
RGAP
database and 16 LOXs were identified, which were named as 
OsLOX1
to 
OsLOX16
(
Table 2
). Phylogenetic tree analysis of the identified rice LOXs showed them to possess homology with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
LOX
</tp:taxon-name>
family of proteins (
Fig. 3
). This led us to categorize them on the basis of a previously accepted classification of LOXs, i.e., 9-LOX and 13-LOX (

; 

). OsLOX1-4, 6, 9–10, and 13 were grouped as 9-LOX due to their close similarity with the biochemically-characterized 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
9-LOX family proteins (AtLOX1 and AtLOX5), while OsLOX5, 7–8, 11–12, and 14–16 were grouped as 13-LOX due to their high proximity with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
13-LOX family proteins (AtLOX2-4 and 6) (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.4. Structural analysis of rice lipase and LOX genes
</title>
         <p>
To decipher the detailed gene structure of the lipase and LOX genes, we performed the exon-intron analysis (
Fig. 4a and b
) and motif identification (
Fig. 5a and b
). By aligning the coding sequences of the candidate genes with their corresponding genomic DNA sequences using gene structure display server (
GSDS
2.0), we investigated the presence of variable number of exons and introns in each of them (
Fig. 4a and b
). Among the lipase genes, 
OsLip1
, 
OsLip2
, 
OsLip9
, and 
OsLip13
, were shown to possess ten exons and nine introns, while the rest of them have exons and introns ranging between 1-9 and 0–8, respectively. On the other hand, only one LOX gene, i.e., 
OsLOX4
, contained ten exons and nine introns, while 
OsLOX1
, 
OsLOX7
, and 
OsLOX9
were found to be composed of nine exons and eight introns.
</p>
         <p>
To reveal the conserved motifs that were identical among lipase and LOX protein sequences, structural motif annotation was performed. Primarily, 20 motifs were predicted in the rice lipase and LOX proteins (
Fig. 5
). OsLip1, OsLip2, OsLip9, and OsLip13 shared six motifs (motif-1- 6), OsLip-3 and OsLip15 shared seven motifs (motif-3, 7, 9, 14, 16, 18, and 20), OsLip4 and OsLip18 shared seven motifs (3, 11–13, 15, 17, and 20), and OsLip12 and OsLip17 shared three motifs (motif-8, 10, and 19) (
Fig. 5a
). None of the above 20 motifs were found in OsLip10 and OsLip14 protein sequences.
</p>
         <p>
On the other hand, OsLOX1-2, 4–5, 7, and 11–14 shared twenty identical motifs (motifs 1–20; 
Fig. 5b
). OsLOX3 and OsLOX9 consisted of eighteen and seventeen motifs, respectively (
Fig. 5b
). OsLOX6, 10, and 15–16 proteins consisted of different motif organization patterns compared to other LOXs. This observation suggesting functional similarities among lipase and LOX proteins within the same subfamily sharing the similar conserved motifs.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>DAP, Days after pollination; FPKM, fragments per kilo base per million mapped reads.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Active sites were identified using PROSITE (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.5. Transcript profiling of lipase genes during rice grain development and
germination
</title>
         <p>
To investigate the expression of 18 lipase genes in developing seeds (5 and 10 
DAP
), endosperm (25 
DAP
), and leaves (20 
DAP
), RNA-seq transcriptome data (obtained from 
RGAP
) in the form of differentially expressed values were analyzed (
Table 1
). Among the 18 lipase genes observed during rice grain development, 
OsLip8
(44.0 
FPKM
) and 
OsLip16
(63.1 
FPKM
), were observed to be the highly expressed lipase genes based on the 
FPKM
values. Similarly, in the case of endosperm, 
OsLip16
(152.9 
FPKM
) and 
OsLip11
(116.8 
FPKM
) were found to be highly expressed.
</p>
         <p>
In contrast to this observation, 
OsLip16
displayed relatively high expressions in the developing grains (5 
DAP
, 13.3 
FPKM
and 10 
DAP
, 63.1 
FPKM
) and endosperm (152.9 
FPKM
), suggesting that the function of this gene might be important to regulate rice grain and endosperm development. In leaves, 
OsLip3
(279.3 
FPKM
) and 
OsLip4
(66.7 
FPKM
) were highly expressed. Despite the high expression levels of 
OsLip3
and 
OsLip4
, these genes did not possess any lipase conserved active site motif.
</p>
         <p>
Next, in order to examine the expression pattern of the lipases during rice grain germination, we performed expression analysis of these selected 18 lipase genes by qRT PCR. Changes in gene expression during each germination stages were calculated as normalized log 
2
fold changes. One of the major events that determine the growth of the seedling is the lipolysis of storage TAGs by lipases present in seed grains during germination. The genes that were highly expressed after 2 HAI showed a subsequent reduction in their expression levels at the later stages. Amongst the 18 rice bran lipases studied, we found three of them viz., 
OsLip13
(5.0 fold change), 
OsLip9
(3.8 fold change), and 
OsLip1
(3.0 fold change) to be highly expressed during germination (
Fig. 6
).
</p>
         <p>
Lipase genes those were highly active during grain development showed low levels of transcript expression during germination (
Fig. 6
). Despite the high expression pattern of 
OsLip3-4
and 

6–7
in

leaves (
Table 1
), these genes showed relatively low expression in bran of germinating grains (
Fig. 6
). Although the expression profile of lipases in bran tissue is not available in the 
RGAP
database, the contrasting expression pattern of lipases indicates its involvement in lipid mobilization during grain development and germination.
</p>
         <p>
2.6. Transcript profiling of LOX genes during rice grain development and germination
</p>
         <p>
In order to understand the expression pattern of LOX genes, we mined the publicly available RNA-seq data from 
RGAP
. The analysis revealed that among the 16 selected LOX genes, 
OsLOX8
(10.0 
FPKM
), 
OsLOX3
(6.8 
FPKM
), and 
OsLOX1
(6.3 
FPKM
) were the genes that showed high expression at 5 
DAP
in rice grain. Interestingly, the expression level of all the genes greatly decreased at 10 
DAP
(
Table 2
). In the case of endosperm, 
OsLOX3
(10.8 
FPKM
) and 
OsLOX2
(5.9 
FPKM
) were noted to be the two abundantly expressed genes. 
OsLOX3
was found to be common and abundantly expressed in developing rice grain and endosperm, suggesting its role during grain development. Similarly, two LOX genes, 
OsLOX5
(702.7 
FPKM
) and 
OsLOX14
(277.4 
FPKM
), were found to be highly expressed in leaf tissues.
</p>
         <p>
To gain further insights into the LOX gene expression profiles in germinating rice grains, qRT PCR analysis was performed for the 16 candidate LOX genes (
Fig. 7
). The results indicated that most of the examined LOX genes obtained their highest expression peak at the initial stages of germination and then their expression levels decreased as the germination progressed. Upon inspection, we found that 
OsLOX3
(8.1 fold change) from 9-LOX and 
OsLOX14
(8.5 fold change) from 13-LOX class showed high expression at 1 DAI and 2 HAI, respectively. As shown in 
Table 2
and 
Fig. 7
, 
OsLOX4
also showed elevated expression in the developing (277.4 
FPKM
) and germinating (4.7 fold change) grains, suggesting its diverse role in rice grains.
</p>
         <p>
3. Discussion
</p>
         <p>
The standard practice of bran layer separation disrupts the physical barriers that sequester the cellular lipases and LOXs away from the lipids stored in bran. This, in turn, induces rapid hydrolysis of the bran lipids to high NEFAs. Several efforts have been made to reduce the rancidity and increase the shelf-life of lipids by adapting the pre-milling and postharvesting techniques. However, these techniques have negative impact on the quality of the bran micronutrients (

). Little attention was paid in understanding the causative genes responsible for the hydrolytic and oxidative rancidity of the bran lipids. Thus, it is imperative to target lipase and LOX genes in the grain to improve the quality of bran lipid with lower rancidity and longer shelf-life. The present study was aimed to fill this research gap and to unveil the process of TAG mobilization in rice bran during grain germination along with expression analysis of the lipase and LOX genes.
</p>
         <p>Our results show that TAGs were the primary lipid reserve stored in rice bran and were mobilized during the post-germinative process (4 HAI-8 DAI). In addition, a thorough examination of the expression pattern of the selected 18 lipases and 16 LOXs revealed that several among them were up-regulated during the period, suggesting these are the key causative genes responsible for the degradation and peroxidation of TAG products.</p>
         <p>
Storage lipid breakdown during seed germination starts with the hydrolysis of TAG reserves (

). In rice, 0–4 DAI is considered as the germination stage and 5–10 DAI as post-germinative growth (

). Mobilization of the TAG pool in the rice bran started at 4 DAI (
Fig. 1a
). However, degradation of TAGs did not coincide with the NEFA pool accumulated in bran tissues (
Fig. 1d
). The above discrepancy may be due to the catabolism of NEFAs through β- oxidation or amino acid biosynthesis pathway (

; 

). Meanwhile, a large proportion of the total DAGs were also utilized from 2 HAI to post-germinative growth at 8 DAI (
Fig. 1c
). On the other hand, the PL content remained mostly unaltered during the mobilization of TAGs and DAGs.
</p>
         <p>
Of the four lipid classes, 16:0, 18:1, and 18:2 are the three predominant FAs detected during germination and post-germinative growth (
Fig. 1b–e
). In TAGs, the contents of 16:0, 18:1, and 18:2 FAs decreased drastically from 4 DAI onward whereas, the NEFA content in the bran started to increase at the onset of 2 DAI (
Fig. 1c
). Although the accumulation of NEFAs started early, the loss of FAs from the TAG fraction was relatively much higher than the amount of NEFAs accumulated in the bran. The FA composition of 16:0, 18:1, and 18: 
2 in
the bran PL pool increased from 4 to 8 DAI (
Fig. 1d
). These results are in agreement with those reported earlier in germinating seeds (

).
</p>
         <p>
In order to investigate the expression pattern of the lipases in developing tissues, we mined the RNA-seq transcriptome data. The data obtained showed that the expression profiles of lipase genes differ across the examined tissues. For instance, 
OsLip3
and 
OsLip4
exhibited high levels of expression in leaves; 
OsLip7-8
, 
11
, and 

16
in

the developing endosperm; 
OsLip
8 and 
OsLip
16 in
the developing rice grains. To gain further insights into the expression pattern of the bran lipases in germinating rice grains, we performed qRT PCR analysis of the same 18 lipase genes. 
OsLip1
, 
OsLip9
, and 
OsLip13
were found to be highly expressed (
Fig. 6
), indicating to their involvement in lipid degradation. The results are in agreement with those reported earlier (

). Lipase expression and TAG degradation analysis, demonstrated that the mobilization of the TAG reserve coincides with the lipase expression during the post-germinative growth (
Fig. 1a
).
</p>
         <p>
After degradation of storage lipids by lipases in bran, LOXs are known to catalyze the peroxidation of the released PUFAs, leading to the formation of volatile compounds responsible for the off-flavors (

). Phylogenetic comparison between 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
and rice revealed 16 closely related LOX proteins. The OsLOX proteins were classified into two sub-families 9-LOX and 13-LOX. OsLOX1-4, 6, 9–10, and 13 were grouped in 9-LOX family proteins. The remaining OsLOX5, 7–8, 11–12, and 14–16 were placed in the 13-LOX group (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
In this study, members of the OsLOX gene family were found to share variable exon/intron organization (
Fig. 4b
). Most of the closely related members of LOX protein showed identical motif compositions (
Fig. 5b
). With the exception of OsLOX6, OsLOX10, and OsLOX15, all other LOX proteins consisted of motif-1 (
Fig. 4b
) with the family-specific conserved sequence His-(X) 
4
-His-(X) 
4
-His-(X) 
17
-His-(X) 
8
-His (

; 

). Previous study has shown that any substitution of conserved histidine amino acid residue alters the activity of the enzyme (

). Thus, closely related members of 9-LOX and 13-LOX with common conserved motifs and exon/intron organization, shall have functional similarities.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Since gene expression pattern should correlate with its function, we have analyzed the LOX gene expression profiles during lipid mobilization. Of the 16 genes analyzed, 13 were highly expressed, and among them 
OsLOX3, OsLOX4
and 
OsLOX14
genes known to be involved in lipid peroxidation and jasmonic acid signaling pathway, respectively (

; 

, 

, 

) showed more than 8 fold increased expression (
Fig. 7
). The suppression of 

OsLOX 
3

in rice grains has long been thought to enhance the seed longevity by catalyzing the peroxidation reaction (

). However,TALEN-mediated downregulation of 
OsLOX3
gene did not result in decreased peroxidation of PUFAs (

). Furthermore, it was reported that the downregulation of 
OsLOX3
or 

OsLOX 
4

in rice grains showed elevated expression of 
OsLOX14
transcripts. Results from the earlier studies suggest a functional redundancy among LOX genes. Given the possible biological redundancy among various LOX genes, it would be fruitful to target multiple LOXs to achieve rice bran stability.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>Overall, this study identifies the pattern of lipid mobilization and simultaneous expression analysis of lipase and LOX genes in rice bran. Insights were gained regarding the rice bran TAG reserve that remained static during early germination stages but began mobilizing during the post-germinative growth. Furthermore, a total of 18 lipase and 16 LOX genes were identified. In-depth expression analysis during rice grain germination exhibited the lipase and LOX gene expression profiles during the onset of lipid mobilization. High lipase and LOX expression levels in bran tissues revealed the molecular targets for downregulation to accomplish bran shelf-stability. The present work also provides a foundation for future functional studies involving other lipase and LOX genes to decipher their potential impact in oil rancidity.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.1. Plant material, germination conditions and sampling
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Oryza sativa
</tp:taxon-name>
L. subsp. 

<tp:taxon-name>Indica</tp:taxon-name>
var. Pusa Basmati 1

(family: 
<tp:taxon-name>Poaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) grains were dehusked manually before germination experiment. Grains were sterilized with 70% ethanol and 0.05% HgCl 
2
followed by stratification for 2 days at 4 
◦
C. Seed grains were further imbibed in moistened filter papers by placing in sterile Petri plates to provide the germination condition. The imbibed grains were kept in a growth chamber at 28 
◦
C. Bran tissue was manually dissected from embryo and endosperm at following time intervals: 0 HAI (0 day), 2 HAI (0 day), 1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 DAI of the rice grains. Dissected bran samples were frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at 80 
◦
C before lipid and qRT PCR analyses. Isolated bran fractions were pooled and three sub-pooled replicates were prepared for the analyses.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
5.2. In silico analysis of rice lipase and LOX genes
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Sequences of rice lipase and LOX genes were retrieved by the ‘putative function search’ in the RGAP database released by 
Michigan State
University, 
USA
(

). The identified genes were grouped on the basis of their FPKM expression values, derived from RGAP for the following rice tissues: developing rice grain (5 and 10 DAP), endosperm (25 DAP) and leaves (20 DAP). However, RGAP did not contain the expression data on rice lipase and LOX genes for bran tissue. The 15 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
TAG
</tp:taxon-name>
lipases were retrieved from The 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
Information Resource
</tp:taxon-name>
(TAIR) to establish the phylogenetic relationship of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
and rice lipase and LOX proteins. A phylogenetic tree was constructed using the neighbor-joining method in Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA X) tool (

; 

). Search for the active site motifs for lipase and LOX genes was done by using ExPASy PROSITE tool (Sigrist et al., 2012).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The exon/intron organization of rice lipase and LOX genes was identified using gene structure display server (GSDS 2.0) by sequence alignment of the coding sequence with their corresponding genomic DNA sequences (

). Conserved motif annotation of lipase and LOX genes was performed using the multiple EM for motif elicitation (MEME) suite (

). The maximum number of motifs screened was set at 20.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.3. Lipid analysis
</title>
         <p>
According to 

, rice grain dissected bran tissues (~ 
50 mg
) were used to extract the total lipid content. To determine the TAG, DAG, NEFA and PL content along with the FA composition of individual lipid classes, total bran lipids were extracted in chloroform: methanol (2:1, v/v) for 2 h at room temperature. To remove the polar fraction of the total lipid extract, it was treated with 0.88% (w/v) potassium chloride. The lower organic phase was collected in a fresh glass tube, concentrated in a Rotavapor R-300 (BUCHI, 
Germany
) and separated through thin layer chromatography (TLC) with a solvent system of hexane: diethyl ether: acetic acid (70:30:1, v/v). Individual lipid classes were exposed with iodine (CDH, 
India
) vapors to visualize the spots. Separated spots of individual lipid classes were scratched out from the TLC, eluted with chloroform and concentrated in a Rotavapor.
</p>
         <p>
Acid-catalyzed FA methyl esters (FAMEs) were prepared from the individual lipids using 4% (v/v) sulfuric acid in methanol (freshly prepared) along with 0.2 ml toluene (CDH, 
India
) and 10 μg of heptadecanoic acid (17:0, Sigma, 
USA
) as an internal standard. Transesterification reaction was carried out at 80 
◦
C for 2 h, followed by extraction of FAMEs with 4 ml of Hexane (CDH, 
India
) and 1 ml of 0.9% (w/v) of sodium chloride solution. The non-polar upper phase was collected and concentrated in the Rotavapor.
</p>
         <p>
Finally, the prepared FAMEs were analyzed in Agilent Technologies Model 7890B gas chromatography-flame ionization detector (GC-FID) with a capillary column (J&amp;W 123–5533, 
30 m
× 20 μm x 1 μm) and the parameters were set as follows: split less injection, injector, and flame ionization detector temperature at 260 
◦
C, oven temperature program at 110 
◦
C for 5 min, then increasing at 10 
◦
C min 
1
to 280 
◦
C and holding this temperature for 15 min. Samples were analyzed in three biological replicates and the individual concentrations of FA components were determined using the known concentration of 17:0 and represented as a μmoles/gram dry weight (μmol/g DW) of bran tissues. Unknown FAs present in bran lipids were identified using Supelco 37 component FAME Mix (Sigma, 
USA
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4. RNA isolation and complementary DNA (cDNA) synthesis
</title>
         <p>
Bran tissues were scraped from the imbibed rice grain using a sterile scalpel and placed at 80 
◦
C for long term-storage. The pooled bran samples were divided into three sub-pooled samples to extract RNA. Samples were then crushed in liquid nitrogen using mortar and pestle, and used to isolate total RNA using Spectrum plant total RNA extraction kit (Sigma-Aldrich, 
USA
). RNase-free DNase treatment (New 
England
Biolabs, MA, 
USA
) was employed to remove any residual contamination of genomic DNA using the manufacturer’ s protocol. Quantification and integrity of total RNA were examined using NanoDrop One microvolume UV–Vis spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, MA, 
USA
) and 1% agarose gel electrophoresis, respectively. First-strand cDNA was synthesized from 1 μg of total RNA extracted from the bran using iScript reverse transcription supermix (Bio-Rad, 
USA
) in a total reaction volume of 20 μl.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.5. Quantitative real time PCR (qRT PCR) analysis
</title>
         <p>
For qRT PCR, a CFX96 Touch Real-Time PCR machine (Bio-rad, 
California
, 
USA
) was used. Each reaction was set up using 1 μl of 
100 ng
cDNAs and iTaq universal SYBR green supermix (Bio-rad Inc., 
USA
) at following parameters: 2 min of initial denaturation at 94 
◦
C followed by 40 cycles of 94 
◦
C for 30 s, 55 
◦
C for 15 s, and 68 
◦
C for 30 s. Lipase (
Table S1
) and LOX (
Table S2
)-specific qRT PCR primers were designed using NCBI-Primer BLAST tool and synthesized by Eurofins Scientific (Bengaluru, 
India
). The qRT PCR assays were conducted in three replicates. The specificity of each primer was determined by melting curve analysis and 1.5% agarose gel electrophoresis of the amplified qRT PCR product. Relative gene expression of lipase and LOX genes in germinating bran was measured using the 2 
–ΔΔ
CT method (

), using the average CT (cycle threshold) values for both reference and target genes. Normalization of each reaction was done using the 
elongation factor 1-alpha
(
EF1A
, accession no.: XM_015774317.2) as the reference gene. The qRT PCR analysis of lipase and LOX genes was represented as fold change.
</p>
         <p>
Author contributions statement
</p>
         <p>RKB conceived and designed the study. KS, NS, SK and RKB did the experimental work. KS, RK and RKB analyzed the results. RKB, RK and VR wrote and edit the final version of the revised manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this research paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
We thank Executive Director, National Agri-Food Biotechnology Institute (NABI), Mohali for research facilities. RKB acknowledges the research funding from Department of Science &amp; Technology (DST), New 
Delhi
, 
India
in the form of INSPIRE Faculty award (DST/INSPIRE/04/ 2017/000484).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112538.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Amarasinghe, B.M.W.P.K.
, 
Kumarasiri, M.P.M.
, 
Gangodavilage, N.C.
, 
2009
. 
Effect of method of stabilization on aqueous extraction of rice bran oil
. 
Food Bioprod. Process.
87
, 
108–114
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbp.2008.08.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bailey, T.L.
, 
Williams, N.
, 
Misleh, C.
, 
Li, W.W.
, 
2006
. 
MEME: discovering and analyzing DNA and protein sequence motifs
. 
Nucleic Acids Res
. 34 
https://doi.org/10.1093/ nar/gkl198
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bannenberg, G.
, 
Martínez, M.
, 
Hamberg, M.
, 
Castresana, C.
, 
2009
. 
Diversity of the enzymatic activity in the lipoxygenase gene family of arabidopsis thaliana
. 
Lipids
44
, 
85–95
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11745-008-3245-7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bhunia, R.K.
, 
Chakraborty, A.
, 
Kaur, R.
, 
Maiti, M.K.
, 
Sen, S.K.
, 
2016
. 
Enhancement of α- linolenic acid content in transgenic tobacco seeds by targeting a plastidial ω-3 fatty acid desaturase (fad7) gene of Sesamum indicum to ER
. 
Plant Cell Rep.
35
, 
213–226
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00299-015-1880-z
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Borek, S.
, 
Ratajczak, W.
, 
Ratajczak, L.
, 
2015
. 
Regulation of storage lipid metabolism in developing and germinating lupin (Lupinus spp.) seeds
. 
Acta Physiol. Plant.
37
, 
119
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11738-015-1871-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Borek, Sł
, 
Ratajczak, L.
, 
2010
. 
Storage lipids as a source of carbon skeletons for asparagine synthesis in germinating seeds of yellow lupine (Lupinus luteus L.). J
. 
Plant Physiol.
167
, 
717–724
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jplph.2009.12.010
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Brash, A.R.
, 
1999
. 
Lipoxygenases: occurrence, functions, catalysis, and acquisition of substrate
. 
J. Biol. Chem.
274
, 
23679–23682
. 
https://doi.org/10.1074/ jbc.274.34.23679
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Burlando, B.
, 
Cornara, L.
, 
2014
. 
Therapeutic properties of rice constituents and derivatives (Oryza sativa L.): a review update
. 
Trends Food Sci. Technol.
40
, 
82–98
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tifs.2014.08.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, Z.
, 
Chen, X.
, 
Yan, H.
, 
Li, W.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
Cai, R.
, 
Xiang, Y.
, 
2015
. 
The Lipoxygenase gene family in poplar: identification, classification, and expression in response to MeJA treatment
. 
PloS One
10
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0125526
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chuang, R.L.C.
, 
Chen, J.C.F.
, 
Chu, J.
, 
Tzen, J.T.C.
, 
1996
. 
Characterization of seed oil bodies and their surface oleosin isoforms from rice embryos
. 
J. Biochem.
120
, 
74–81
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordjournals.jbchem.a021396
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dunford, N.T.
, 
2019
. 
Chemistry of rice bran oil
. In: 
Rice Bran and Rice Bran Oil
. 
AOCS Press
, pp. 
1–18
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Feussner, I.
, 
Wasternack, C.
, 
2002
. 
The lipoxygenase pathway
. 
Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.
53
, 
275–297
. 
https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.arplant.53.100301.135248
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Goffman, F.D.
, 
Pinson, S.
, 
Bergman, C.
, 
2003
. 
Genetic diversity for lipid content and fatty acid profile in rice bran. JAOCS, J. Am. Oil Chem
. 
Soc.
80
, 
485–490
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s11746-003-0725-x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Graham, I.A.
, 
2008
. 
Seed storage oil mobilization
. 
Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.
59
, 
115–142
. 
https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.arplant.59.032607.092938
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gul, K.
, 
Yousuf, B.
, 
Singh, A.K.
, 
Singh, P.
, 
Wani, A.A.
, 
2015
. 
Rice bran: nutritional values and its emerging potential for development of functional food - a review. Bioact. Carbohydrates Diet
. 
Fibre.
6
, 
24–30
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcdf.2015.06.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hall, B.G.
, 
2013
. 
Building phylogenetic trees from molecular data with MEGA
. 
Mol. Biol. Evol.
30
, 
1229–1235
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst012
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hu, B.
, 
Jin, J.
, 
Guo, A.Y.
, 
Zhang, H.
, 
Luo, J.
, 
Gao, G.
, 
2015
. 
GSDS 2.0: an upgraded gene feature visualization server
. 
Bioinformatics
31
, 
1296–1297
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1093/bioinformatics/btu817
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ichihara, K.
, 
Kobayashi, N.
, 
Saito, K.
, 
2003
. 
Lipid synthesis and acyl-CoA synthetase in developing rice seeds
. 
Lipids
38
, 
881–884
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11745-003- 1139-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Juliano, B.O.
, 
Tua˜no, A.P.P.
, 
2019
. 
Gross structure and composition of the rice grain
. 
Rice
, pp. 
31–53
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/b978-0-12-811508-4.00002-2
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kawahara, Y.
, 
de la Bastide, M.
, 
Hamilton, J.P.
, 
Kanamori, H.
, 
Mccombie, W.R.
, 
Ouyang, S.
, 
Schwartz, D.C.
, 
Tanaka, T.
, 
Wu, J.
, 
Zhou, S.
, 
Childs, K.L.
, 
Davidson, R. M.
, 
Lin, H.
, 
Quesada-Ocampo, L.
, 
Vaillancourt, B.
, 
Sakai, H.
, 
Lee, S.S.
, 
Kim, J.
, 
Numa, H.
, 
Itoh, T.
, 
Buell, C.R.
, 
Matsumoto, T.
, 
2013
. 
Improvement of the oryza sativa nipponbare reference genome using next generation sequence and optical map data
. 
Rice
6
, 
3–10
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/1939-8433-6-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Khan, F.I.
, 
Lan, D.
, 
Durrani, R.
, 
Huan, W.
, 
Zhao, Z.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
2017
. 
The lid domain in lipases: structural and functional determinant of enzymatic properties
. 
Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol
5
, 
16
. 
https://doi.org/10.3389/fbioe.2017.00016
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kumar, S.
, 
Stecher, G.
, 
Li, M.
, 
Knyaz, C.
, 
Tamura, K.
, 
2018
. 
MEGA X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms
. 
Mol. Biol. Evol.
35
, 
1547–1549
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msy096
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Livak, K.J.
, 
Schmittgen, T.D.
, 
2001
. 
Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2-ΔΔCT method
. 
Methods
25
, 
402–408
. 
https://doi. org/10.1006/meth.2001.1262
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ma, L.
, 
Zhu, F.
, 
Li, Z.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Dong, J.
, 
Wang, T.
, 
2015
. 
TALEN-Based mutagenesis of lipoxygenase LOX3 enhances the storage tolerance of rice (Oryza sativa) Seeds
. 
PloS One
10
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0143877
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Malekian, F.
, 
Rao, R.M.
, 
Prinyawiwatkul, W.
, 
Marshall, W.E.
, 
Windhauser, M.
, 
Ahmedna, M.
, 
2000
. 
Lipase and Lipoxygenase Activity, Functionality, and Nutrient Losses in Rice Bran during Storage
. 
Louisiana State Univ. Agric. Cent
. 
https://doi. org/10.1002/fsn3.86
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Porta, H.
, 
Rocha-Sosa, M.
, 
2002
. 
Plant lipoxygenases
. 
Physiological and molecular features. Plant Physiol
130
, 
15–21
. 
https://doi.org/10.1104/pp.010787
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rondanini, D.P.
, Borr´as, L., 
Savin, R.
, 
2019
. 
Improving grain quality in oil and cereal crops
. In: 
Meyers, R.
(Ed.), 
Encyclopedia of Sustainability Science and Technology
. 
Springer, New York, NY
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
RoyChowdhury, M.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Qi, H.
, 
Li, W.
, 
Sun, J.
, 
Huang, C.
, 
Wu, D.
, 
2016
. 
Functional characterization of 9-/13-LOXs in rice and silencing their expressions to improve grain qualities
. 
BioMed Res. Int.
2016
, 
4275904
https://doi.org/10.1155/2016/ 4275904
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schaffrath, U.
, 
Zabbai, F.
, 
Dudler, R.
, 
2000
. 
Characterization of RCI-1, a chloroplastic rice lipoxygenase whose synthesis is induced by chemical plant resistance activators
. 
Eur. J. Biochem.
267
, 
5935–5942
. 
https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1432- 1327.2000.01660.x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shirasawa, K.
, 
Takeuchi, Y.
, 
Ebitani, T.
, 
Suzuki, Y.
, 
2008
. 
Identification of gene for rice (Oryza sativa) seed lipoxygenase-3 involved in the generation of stale flavor and development of SNP markers for lipoxygenase-3 deficiency
. 
Breed Sci.
58
, 
169–176
. 
https://doi.org/10.1270/jsbbs.58.169
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shrestha, P.
, 
Callahan, D.L.
, 
Singh, S.P.
, 
Petrie, J.R.
, 
Zhou, X.R.
, 
2016
. 
Reduced triacylglycerol mobilization during seed germination and early seedling growth in Arabidopsis containing nutritionally important polyunsaturated fatty acids. Front
. 
Plant Sci
. 7 
https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2016.01402
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sigrist, C.J.A.
, 
De Castro, E.
, 
Cerutti, L.
, 
Cuche, B.A.
, 
Hulo, N.
, 
Bridge, A.
, 
Bougueleret, L.
, 
Xenarios, I.
, 
2013
. 
New and continuing developments at PROSITE
. 
Nucleic Acids Res
. 41 
https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gks1067
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Steczko, J.
, 
Donoho, G.P.
, 
Axelrod, B.
, 
Clemens, J.C.
, 
Dixon, J.E.
, 
1992
. 
Conserved histidine residues in soybean lipoxygenase: functional consequences of their replacement
. 
Biochemistry
31
, 
4053–4057
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/bi00131a022
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Thazar-Poulot, N.
, 
Miquel, M.
, 
Fobis-Loisy, I.
, 
Gaude, T.
, 
2015
. 
Peroxisome extensions deliver the Arabidopsis SDP1 lipase to oil bodies
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A
112
, 
4158–4163
. 
https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1403322112
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tiwari, G.J.
, 
Chiang, M.Y.
, 
De Silva, J.R.
, 
Song, B.K.
, 
Lau, Y.L.
, 
Rahman, S.
, 
2016
. 

Lipase genes expressed in rice bran: LOC_Os 
11g
43510 encodes a novel rice lipase

. 
J. Cereal. Sci.
71
, 
43–52
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcs.2016.07.008
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vijayakumar, K.R.
, 
Gowda, L.R.
, 
2012
. 
Temporal expression profiling of lipase during germination and rice caryopsis development
. 
Plant Physiol. Biochem.
57
, 
245–253
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2012.05.028
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Viswanath, K.K.
, 
Varakumar, P.
, 
Pamuru, R.R.
, 
Basha, S.J.
, 
Mehta, S.
, 
Rao, A.D.
, 
2020
. 
Plant lipoxygenases and their role in plant physiology. J
. 
Plant Biol.
63
, 
83–95
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s12374-020-09241-x
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, H.
, 
Wei, Y.
, 
Zhu, Y.
, 
Lian, L.
, 
Xie, Hongguang
, 
Cai, Q.
, 
Chen, Q.
, 
Lin, Z.
, 
Wang, Z.
, 
Xie, Huaan
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
2015
. 
Antisense suppression of LOX3 gene expression in rice endosperm enhances seed longevity
. 
Plant Biotechnol. J.
13
, 
526–539
. 
https://doi. org/10.1111/pbi.12277
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
