<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113023</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>13,13a-seco-protoberberines from the tubers of Corydalis yanhusuo and their anti-inflammatory activity</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>28</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
W.T. Wang
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Papaveraceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis
(Papaveraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
W.T. Wang
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis
species
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
W.T. Wang (Papaveraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

13,13a- 
seco
-protoberberines from the tubers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
and their anti-inflammatory activity

</p>
         <p>
Gui-Yang Xia
a, 1
, Dong-Jie Fang
b, 1
, Ling-Yan Wang
a
, Huan Xia
a
, Ya-Nan Wang
b
,
Hong-Cai Shang 

a, 
**
, Sheng Lin

a, 
*
</p>
         <p>
a

Key Laboratory of 
Chinese Internal Medicine

of 
Ministry of Education
and 
Beijing
, Dongzhimen Hospital, 
Beijing
University of Chinese Medicine
, 
Beijing
, 100700, 
China
b
State Key Laboratory of Bioactive Substance
and 
Function of Natural Medicines
, 
Institute of Materia Medica
, 
Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences
and 
Peking
Union Medical College, 
Beijing
, 100050, 
China
</p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
W.T. Wang
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Papaveraceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
13,13a- 
seco
-protoberberines
</p>
         <p>Yanhusanines G-L</p>
         <p>Anti-inflammatory</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Six undescribed protoberberine derivatives including two pairs of enantiomers, named yanhusanines G-L, along with fifteen reported protoberberine alkaloids, were isolated from the tubers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
. Among them, yanhusanines H-L feature a unique 13,13a- 
seco
skeleton which is rare in nature. Their structural elucidations were achieved by extensive spectroscopic analysis and quantum chemistry calculations. A biogenetic route for yanhusanines H-L was proposed. Bioassay results showed that yanhusanine J exhibited potent inhibitory effect against the nitric oxide (NO) production in lipopolysaccharide (LPS) induced RAW 264.7 cells (IC 
50
= 2.25 ± 1.32 
μ
M). Western blot analysis demonstrated that yanhusanine J exerted its anti-inflammatory effect 
via
suppressing the nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κB) pathway, together with the decrease of the inflammatory factors TNF- 
α
, IL-6 and IL-1 
β
. Furthermore, molecular simulation docking indicated that yanhusanine J had strong interaction with the active site of the inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) protein.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis
(Papaveraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
, comprising about 470 species, is widely distributed throughout the world among which 290 species are native to 
China
. Eleven species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis
</tp:taxon-name>
have applications in folk medicine in 
China
(

). More specifically, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
W.T. Wang
</tp:taxon-name>
is an important medicinal plant and has been traditionally used in 
China
. The dried tuber of this plant, known as “ 
yan-hu-suo
”, is included in the Chinese Pharmacopoeia and has been traditionally used for treatment of menstrual, spastic, and abdominal pain, rheumatism, dysmenorrhea, cardiac arrhythmias, and cardiodynia (

), most of which are closely related to inflammation. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
mainly produces 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis
</tp:taxon-name>
alkaloids including palmatine, tetrahydropalmatine, corydaline, and dehydrocorydaline which have been considered as the index components this species (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
In mammalian species, inflammation is a natural defensive cellular mechanism against harmful factors such as physical or noxious chemical stimuli and pathogens. During the inflammation process, macrophage cells have been considered as the key component of the host immune system (

; Moghaddam et al., 2018). However, the uncontrolled inflammatory response of macrophages to pathogenic substances such as bacterial lipopolysaccharides (LPS) can lead to multiple inflammatory diseases, such as cardiovascular disease (

; 

), arthritis (

), and asthma (

; 

), 
via
expression of pro-inflammatory enzymes. For example, the inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) catalyzes the production of excessive NO, and pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as tumor necrosis factor (TNF- 
α
), interleukin 6 (IL-6) and interleukin 1β (IL-1β) which cause cell damage (

). These inflammatory factors are induced by the nuclear factor κB (NF-κB), which is an important dimeric transcription factor involved in the inflammatory responses. The NF-κB complexes, consisting of NF-κB and the inhibitor of NF-κB (IκB), may be degraded via phosphorylation triggered by interaction with IκB kinase (IκK), thus inducing NF-κB translocation to the nucleus (

; Karin et al., 2000). Therefore, the NF-κB signaling cascade may be an important target for preventing inflammatory diseases.
</p>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>** Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>
E-mail addresses:
shanghongcai@126.com (H.-C. Shang), lsznn@126.com (S. Lin).
</p>
         <p>
1
These authors contributed equally to this work.
</p>
         <p>
In our continuing search for biological alkaloids from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
(

; 

), six previously undescribed protoberberine derivatives (
1–6
), including two pairs of enantiomers, and fifteen known ones (
7–21
) have been isolated and identified. Among them, compounds 
2–6
contained a unique 13,13a- 
seco
skeleton which is rare in nature (
Fig. 1
). We describe the isolation, structural elucidation, proposed biosynthetic pathways, and anti-inflammatory activities studies of these compounds.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Structural elucidation
</title>
         <p>
The aqueous extracts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
tubers (
50 kg
), which have been processed with 6% acetic acid, were systematically separated by ODS column, Sephadex LH-20, and HPLC to yield yanhusanines G-L (
1–6
).
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine G (
1
) was obtained as white powder with the molecular formula of C 
22
H 
24
NO 
5
based on the (+)-HRESIMS data at 
m/z
382.1647 [M] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
24
NO 
5
, 382.1649), which indicated 12 degrees of unsaturation. The 
1
H NMR data of 
1
(
Table 1
) revealed the presence of a 1,2,3,4-tetrasubstituted aromatic ring, with signals at 
δ
H
8.23 (1H, d, 
J
=9.4 Hz, H-11) and 8.20 (1H, d, 
J
=9.4 Hz, H-12). The conjoint analysis of 
1
H NMR and 
1
H– 
1
H COSY spectra suggested a spin system consisting of an oxymethine 5.02 (1H, dd, 
J
=4.9, 2.1 Hz, H-5), and a methylene moiety at 
δ
H
5.00 (1H, dd, 
J
=13.1, 4.9 Hz, 
Ha-
6) and 4.77 (1H, brd, 
J
= 13.1 Hz, 
Hb-
6). The 
1
H NMR spectrum also provided three aromatic proton singlets at 
δ
H
9.96 (1H, s, H-8), 7.42 (1H, s, H-1), and 7.26 (1H, s, H-4); four methoxy group resonances at 
δ
H
3.87 (3H, s, 2-OMe), 3.91 (3H, s, 3-OMe), 4.11 (3H, s, 9-OMe), and 4.09 (3H, s, 10-OMe); as well as a methyl singlet at 
δ
H
3.01 (3H, s, H 
3
-14). With the aid of the DEPT and HSQC spectra, the 22 carbon signals in the 
13
C NMR spectrum of 
1
were assigned to fifteen aromatic and/or olefinic carbons, one oxygenated tertiary carbon, one methylene, one methyl, and four methoxy groups. The above spectroscopic data indicated that 
1
contained a protoberberine skeleton with four methoxy groups similar to the concomitantly isolated compound, dehydrocorydaline (
7
) (

). The main difference between 
1
and 
7
was the disappearance of a methylene group in 
7
and the presence of an oxymethine group in 
1
, suggesting that 
1
is a hydroxy derivative of 
7
. This was supported by the HRESIMS data which showed a 16 amu difference between 
1
and 
7
. In addition, the HMBC correlations from H-5 to C-4 and C-13b, from H 
2
-6 to C-8, and from H-4 to C-5, incorporation with the NOESY correlations of H-5/H-4 and H-8/H 
2
-6 established that the hydroxy group is located at C-5 (
Fig. 2
).
</p>
         <p>
a
NMR data were measured in DMSO‑ 
d
at 600 MHz for 
1
H NMR and at 150 
6
MHz for 
13
C NMR. Proton coupling constants (
J
) in Hz are given in parentheses.
</p>
         <p>
b
NMR data were measured in CDCl at 600 MHz for 
1
H NMR and at 150 MHz 
3
for 
13
C NMR. Proton coupling constants (
J
) in Hz are given in parentheses.
</p>
         <p>
Considering the only one chiral center of C-5 and the teeny optical rotation of yanhusanine G (
1
), it was speculated that 
1
might be a partial racemic mixture. This was verified by the chiral-phase HPLC resolution [Chiralpak IG, acetonitrile–H 
2
O–trifluoroacetic acid (ACN–H 
2
O–TFA), 37:63:0.01], which yielded two well-separated enantiomers, 

(
þ
)-1

(
t
R
= 5.3 min, 
0.6 mg
) and () 
-1
(
t
R
= 5.9 min, 
0.3 mg
) in a near 2:1 ratio (Figure S11, Supporting Information). Comparing the calculated and experimental ECD curves demonstrated that the absolute configurations of (+)- 
1
and ()- 
1
were 5 
S
and 5 
R
, respectively (
Fig. 3
). Because TFA was used in the HPLC purification process, (+)- 
1
and ()- 
1
were eluted as their TFA salts. This was verified by the characteristic signals of the carbonyl carbon of TFA at around 
δC
158.2 in
the 
13
C-NMR spectra of 
1
. Therefore, the structures of this pair of enantiomers were elucidated as shown (
Fig. 1
) and given the trivial names, (+)-(5 
S
)-yanhusanine G and ()-(5 
R
)-yanhusanine G, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine H (
2
) was isolated as white powder with a molecular formula of C 
21
H 
21
NO 
7
, comprising 12 degrees of unsaturation, as verified by HRESIMS at 
m/z
400.1388 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
21
H 
22
NO 
7
, 400.1391). The IR spectrum suggested the presence of carbonyl (1683 
cm-1
) and aromatic ring (1606 and 
1501 cm
1
) functional groups. The 
1
H NMR spectrum of 

2
in

CDCl 
3
showed characteristic signals attributable to a 1,6,7-trisubstituted dihydroisoquinoline moiety [
δ
H
7.66 (1H, s, H-1), 6.62 (1H, s, H-4), 2.85 (2H, m H 
2
-5), 3.24, 3.02 (each 1H, brs, H 
2
-6)] and 1,2,3,4-tetrasubstituted aromatic group [
δ
H
7.15 (1H, d, 
J
= 8.4 Hz, H-11), 7.67 (1H, d, 
J
= 8.4 Hz, H-12)]. In addition, a proton signal at 
δ
H
8.03 (1H, brs, H-8) that was assigned to one oxymethine based on the HSQC spectrum. Four aromatic methoxy moieties at 
δ
H
3.97 (3H, s, OMe-10), 3.95 (3H, s, OMe-2), 3.92 (3H, s, OMe-3), and 3.88 (3H, s, OMe-9) were also observed in the 
1
H NMR spectrum. The 
13
C NMR data analyzed with the aid of HSQC data showed that 
2
contained 21 carbon resonances corresponding to the above units and two carbonyl carbons at 
δ
C
165.1 (C-13a) and 168.6 (C-13) (
Table 1
). The 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlations from H 
2
-5 to H 
2
-6 and HMBC correlations from H-4 to C-2, C-5, and C-1a, from H-1 to C-3, C-4a, and C-13a, from H 
2
-5 to C-4 and C-1a, from H 
2
-6 to C-4a and C-13a, and from two methoxy protons to C-2 and C-3, respectively, along with their chemical shift values, indicated the presence of a 3,4-dihydro-6,7-dimethoxy-1- oxo-isoquinolinone moiety in 
2
. In addition, a 1,3-dihydro-6,7-dimethoxy-3-oxo-1-isobenzofuranyl group was proposed by comparing the NMR data with those previously reported (

), which was affirmed by the IR absorption band of lactone (
1767 cm
1
), and from the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlation from H-11 to H-12 and HMBC correlations from H-11 to C-9 and C-12a, from H-12 to C-10, C-13, and C-8a, and from two methoxy protons to C-9 and C-10, respectively. Although there were no observed HMBC cross-peaks between H-8 and C-6 and C-13a or between H 
2
-6 and C-8, the NOSEY correlations of H-8/H 
2
-6 and H-8/OMe-9 (
Fig. 2
) suggested that the 1,3-dihydro-6,7-dimethoxy-3-oxo-1-isobenzofuranyl group was attached to the nitrogen atom of the 3, 4-dihydro-6,7-dimethoxy-1-oxo-isoquinolinone moiety. The computationally calculated 
13
C NMR data matched well with the NMR experimental data, in full support of the proposed planar structure of 
2
(Figure S64, Supporting Information).
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine H (
2
) was a racemic mixture according to its optical rotation ([
α
]20D 0) and the lacking of Cotton effect in the ECD spectrum. Consequently, the expected pair of enantiomers, (+)- 
2
([
α
]20D +138.7, t 

R

=42.1 min) and ()- 
2
([
α
]20D 149.3, t 

R

=44.8 min), was successfully separated using the CHIRALPAK IB-N 
3
chiral column (Figure S29, Supporting Information). Comparative analysis of the computationally calculated and experimental ECD spectra established the absolute configurations of (+)- 
2
and ()- 
2
as 8 
S
and 8 
R
, respectively (
Fig. 3
). Therefore, the structures of this pair of enantiomers were elucidated as shown (
Fig. 1
) and given the trivial names, (+)-(8 
S
)-yanhusanine H and ()-(8 
R
)-yanhusanine H, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine I (
3
) was isolated as white powder, with the molecular formula of C 
22
H 
25
NO 
6
as confirmed by use of HRESIMS data at 
m/z
400.1764 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
26
NO 
6
, 400.1755), indicating 11 degrees of unsaturation. Compounds 
3
and 
2
displayed similar NMR spectroscopic features, where both compounds contained a 1,6,7-trisubstituted dihydroisoquinoline moiety. The main difference between the two compounds was that the 1,3-dihydro-6,7-dimethoxy-3-oxo-1-isobenzofuranyl group in 
2
was replaced with an 
N
-methylene-3,4-dimethoxy-acetophenone moiety in 
3
[
δ
H
7.09 (1H, d, 
J
=8.4 Hz, H-11), 7.54 (1H, d, 
J
= 8.4 Hz, H-12), 4.79 (2H, s, H 
2
-8), 2.51 (3H, s, H 
3
-14), 3.72 (3H, s, OMe-9), and 3.87 (3H, s, OMe-10); 
δ
C
41.5 (C-8), 129.9 (C-8a), 148.1 (C-9), 154,5 (C-10), 111.2 (C-11), 125.2 (C-12), 133.3 (C-12a), 163.4 (C-13a), and 29.7 (C-14)]. This was confirmed by interpretation of the 2D NMR data of 
3
, particularly from the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlation between H-11 and H-12, and HMBC correlations from H-11 to C-9 and C-12a, from H 
3
-14 to C-12, from H-12 to C-10, C-13, and C-8a, and from two methoxy protons to C-9 and C-10. Finally, HMBC correlations from H 
2
-8 to C-6, C-13a, C-9, and C-12a, and from H 
2
-6 to C-9 revealed the connection of the two moieties (
Fig. 4
). Consequently, the structure of 
3
was elucidated as 2-(6-acetyl-2,3-dimethoxybenzyl)-6,7-dimethoxy-1 (
4H
)-isoquinolinone and was given the trivial name, yanhusanine I.
</p>
         <p>
The HRESIMS of yanhusanine J (
4
) displayed a protonated molecular ion at 
m/z
398.1600 [M +H] 
+
, as consistent with the molecular formula C 
22
H 
24
NO 
6
. The 1D NMR data of 
4
closely resembled those of 
3
excepted for the presence of a disubstituted double bond [
δH
7.08 (1H, d, 
J
=7.4 Hz, H-6) and 6.44 (1H, d, 
J
=7.4 Hz, H-5); 
δC
131.7 (C-6) and 104.3 (C-5)] instead of two adjacent methylenes in 
3
. The 2D NMR data of 
4
, especially the 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlation of H-5/H-6, HMBC cross-peaks of H-5/C-4, H-5/C-1a, H-6/C-13a, H-6/C-4a, and H-6/C-8, as well as the NOESY correlation of H-4/H-5, confirmed the presence of a double bond at C-5-C-6. Therefore, the structure of 
4
was established as 2-(6-acetyl-2,3-dimethoxybenzyl)-6,7-dimethoxy-1(
2H
)-isoquinolinone and was given the trivial name, yanhusanine J.
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine K (
5
) had a molecular formula of C 
21
H 
23
NO 
6
based on a protonated molecular ion at 
m/z
386.1589 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
21
H 
24
NO 
6
, 386.1598). The molecular formula implied the loss of a 
CH
2
group as compared to 
3
, and the close NMR data indicated a strong similarity between the two compounds. However, the main differences were the absence of a methoxy group and presence of an extra OH group in 
3
. The OH proton at 
δ
H
10.19 showed a strong HMBC correlation with C-10 and a NOESY correlation with H-11, confirming the above observation and locating the OH group to C-10. Therefore, 
5
was identified as the 10- 
O
-demethyl analogue of 
3
, 2-(6-acetyl-3-hydroxy-2-methoxybenzyl)-6,7-dimethoxy-1(
4H
)-isoquinolinone, and was given the trivial name, yanhusanine K.
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine L (
6
) was separated as white powder and its molecular formula C 
22
H 
23
NO 
7
, with 14 mass units more than compound 
3
, was deduced from the HRESIMS at 
m/z
414.1539 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
24
NO 
7
, 414.1547). The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra of 
6
displayed resonances similar to those of 
3
, but also disclosed that the isolated methylene in 
3
was in place of a carbonyl group at 
δ
C
168.4 in
6
. These observations, coupled with analysis of the 2D NMR data, indicated that 
6
was an 8-oxo derivative of 
3
. Thus, the structure of 
6
was identified as 2- (6-acetyl-2,3-dimethoxybenzoyl)-6,7-dimethoxy-1(
4H
)-isoquinolinone and was named trivially as yanhusanine L.
</p>
         <p>
By comparing the spectroscopic data with those reported in the literatures, structures of the known compounds were identified as dehydrocorydaline trifluoroacetate (
7
) (

), dehydrocorybulbine trifluoroacetate (
8
) (

), 13-methylcolumbamine trifluoroacetate (
9
) (

), 13-methyl-palmatrubine trifluoroacetate (
10
) (

), 13-methyldehydrocorydalmine trifluoroacetate (
11
) (

), worenine trifluoroacetate (
12
) (

), palmatine trifluoroacetate (
13
) (

), jatrorrhizine trifluoroacetate (
14
) (

), columbamine trifluoroacetate (
15
) (

), dehydrocorydalmine trifluoroacetate (
16
) (

), berberine trifluoroacetate (
17
) (

), coptisine trifluoroacetate (
18
) (

), (+)-(13 
S
,13a 
R
)-corydaline (
19
) (

), (+)-(13 
S
,13a 
R
)-9- 
O
-desmethylcorydaline (
20
) (

), and (+)-(13 
S
,13a 
R
)-corybulbine (
21
) (

), respectively.
</p>
         <p>
The 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis
species
</tp:taxon-name>
have been reported as rich in protoberberinetype alkaloids, such as dehydrocorydaline and palmatine. Yanhusanines H-L (
2–6
) are oxidatively ring-opened derivatives with a unique 13,13a- 
seco
protoberberine skeleton, which are different from the common benzylisoquinoline alkaloids. To our knowledge, only few of the alkaloids with this skeleton, such as chingazumianine (

), tomentellines C and D (

), and 6,7-methylenedioxy-2-(6-acetyl-2,3-methylenedioxybenzyl)-1(2 
H
)-isoquinolinone (

), have been reported as natural products. During the extract fractionation process in this study, dehydrocorydaline and palmatine were isolated from the 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
tubers in large quantities. These compounds might be biosynthetic precursors for these rare 13, 13a- 
seco
-protoberberines. The proposed biosynthetic pathway for 
2–6
is shown in 
Fig. 5
. Dehydrocorydaline and palmatine undergo an oxidative cleavage of the C13–C13a bond to generate the putative precursors 
a
and 
b
, respectively, which continued to undergo nucleophilic addition to give rise to 
c
and 
d
, respectively. Then, a lactone ring closure 
via
the loss of a molecule of H 
2
O from 
c
or oxidation reaction in 
d
, generates 
2
and 
6,
respectively. 
3
is probably biosynthesized from 
b
after reduction. 
4
and 
5
are presumably derived from 

3 
via

dehydrogenation and demethylation, respectively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Anti-inflammatory effects
</title>
         <p>
The isolated compounds were preliminarily screened for their effects on the viability of RAW264.7 cells. The results indicated that the cell viability was not obviously affected by any of the tested compounds at concentrations up to 40 
μ
M for a treatment period of 48 h. Consequently, the isolates were evaluated for their inhibitory effect against NO production in LPS-induced RAW264.7 macrophage cells using indomethacin as a positive control (
Table 2
). Compounds 
3–6
exhibited inhibitory effects on NO production with IC 
50
values ranging from 2.25 ±1.32 to 25.55 ±1.40 
μ
M, suggesting that these compounds were more effective than indomethacin (IC 
50
= 34.91 ± 3.04 
μ
M). However, compounds 
1
, 
2
, and 
7–21
were uneffective against NO production at a concentration of 40 
μ
M. The preliminary structure-activity relationships indicated that the 13,13a- 
seco
protoberberine skeleton plays an important role in the inhibition of NO production. Among the active compounds, yanhusanine J (
4
) exhibited the most potent IC 
50
value (2.25 ±1.32 
μ
M), that is about 15-fold increase in potency compared to that of indomethacin and around 6–10-fold higher potency compared to compounds 
3
, 
5
, and 
6
(
Table 2
), suggesting strongly that the Δ 
5,6
double bond is essential for the inhibitory activity against NO production. Remarkably, the complete absence of activity of 
2
compared to compounds 
3–6
indicates that the lactonization at C-13 and C-8 could reduce the bioactivity. Based on the above IC 
50
data, yanhusanine J (
4
) was given priority for studying of the 
in vitro
mechanism of its anti-inflammatory action.
</p>
         <p>
Previous reports have demonstrated that overproduction of NO in the macrophage inflammatory cascade is usually the consequence of the aberrant expression or the inhibited efficiency of iNOS (

). As expected, the LPS-induced RAW264.7 macrophage cells showed an obviously increased expression of iNOS. However, pretreatment with 
4
notably attenuated theLPS induction of high expression of iNOS at concentrations of 5 and 10 
μ
M (
Fig. 6A
). To understand the inhibition effect of 
4
on the efficiency of iNOS, the possible affinity interaction between 
4
and iNOS was predicted using molecular docking studies. As shown in 
Fig. 6B and C
, the molecular docking of 
4
into the active site pocket of iNOS suggested its interactions with the residues which interacted directly with the reported inhibitors. It not only exhibited H-bond interactions between the two carbonyl units and Gln 263, but also displayed π- π interactions between the conjugated isoquinolinone moiety of 
4
and the key active site residue Glu 377 of iNOS. In addition, π- π interactions were also observed between aromatic ring and Arg 388. The above results indicated that 
4
may exert the inhibitory effect against NO production by dual inhibition of the expression level and efficiency of iNOS (

).
</p>
         <p>
In view of the biological relevance of the molecules for inflammatory responses, the effects of 
4
on the release of pro-inflammatory cytokines (TNF- 
α
, IL-6, and IL-1 
β
) were examined using ELISA. As shown in 
Fig. 7
, LPS treatment significantly induced the secretion of TNF-a, IL-6 and IL-1 
β
as compared to the control group. However, pretreatment of cells with 
4
inhibited the release of TNF- 
α
, IL-1 
β
, and IL-6 into the media, suggesting that 
4
could inhibit the LPS-induced activation of macrophage cells.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
a
The assignments were based on 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HSQC, HMBC and NOESY experiments.

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Various lines of evidence support the importance of the NF-κB pathway in the regulation of pro-inflammatory mediator production, thereby playing a key role in inflammation. The p65 component contains the main trans-activating domain responsible for NF-κB transcription factor function. Phosphorylation of IκB 
α
(p-IκB 
α
) plays an important role in the process of nuclear translocation and activation of NF-κB. The IκB kinase (IκK), which is responsible for phosphorylation of IκB, is the key to NF-κB activation (

; 

; 

). Therefore, Western blot analyses of the expression levels of p-p65 NF-κB, p65 NF-κB, p-IκB 
α
, IκB 
α
, p-IκK, and IκK proteins were carried out to further disclose the mechanism of anti-inflammatory action of 
4
. As shown in 
Fig. 8
, the expression of the phosphorylated IκB 
α
, IκK, and p65 NF-κB was obviously increased in LPS-induced RAW264.7 cells, which indicates the activation of NF-κB signaling pathway. Whereas, pretreatment with 
4
diminished the expression of p-IκB 
α
, p-IκK, and p-p65 NF-κB. These data confirm that 
4
could regulate the inflammatory response by inhibiting the NF-κB signaling pathway.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>
In the present study, we identified the undescribed protoberberine alkaloid (yanhusanine G, 
1
) and protoberberine derivatives with a unique 13,13a- 
seco
skeleton (yanhusanines H-L, 
2–6
), along with 15 known protoberberine alkaloids (
7–21)
, from the tubers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
. Among them, (±)- 
1
and (±)- 
2
were two pairs of enantiomers, which were successfully separated and unambiguously identified. The inhibitory activities of all the isolates toward the production of NO stimulated by LPS in mouse RAW264.7 macrophages were evaluated. Yanhusanine J (
4
) exhibited the most potent anti-inflammatory effect involved in the inhibition of the expression of iNOS and the downregulation of the activation of NF-κB signaling pathway, resulting in decreasing the expression of p-IκB 
α
, p-IκK, and p-p65 NF-κB. Moreover, yanhusanine J inhibited the generation of inflammatory cytokines, such as TNF- 
α
, IL-1 
β
, and IL-6. Inhibiting these inflammatory mediators by preventing their production could be an effective treatment strategy for various inflammation-mediated diseases. Apart from enrichment of the chemical diversity of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. yanhusuo
</tp:taxon-name>
, a potential structural motif for future anti-inflammatory drug development was provided by the current study.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental section
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
NMR spectra, consisting of 2D data were recorded by Bruker 600 MHz (
1
H, 600 MHz; 
13
C, 150 MHz) spectrometers and the chemical shifts were reported as 
δ
values using internal standard TMS (measured in DMSO‑ 
d
6
). UV spectra were obtained on a Cary 300 spectrometer. IR spectra were acquired on a Nicolet Impact 400 FT-IR Spectrophotometer. High-resolution electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (HR-ESI-MS) was performed on an Agilent 6520 HPLC-Q-TOF. Column chromatography was carried out with ODS-A (YMC, 
Japan
), Sephadex LH-20 (Amersham Biosciences, 
Sweden
), and silica gel (200–300 mesh, Qingdao Marine Chemical Inc., 
China
). Analytical HPLC was performed with Agilent 
1260II
coupled 6125B mass spectrometer using a Titank column (Guangzhou FLM Scientific Instrument Co., Ltd) packed with C 
18
(250 × 
4.6 mm
, 5 
μ
m). HPLC separation, consisted of a CXTH 3000 controller, a LC3000 pump, a CXTH LC3000N absorbance detector, using the following columns: SHISEIDO MGII ODS C 
18
column (250 × 
10 mm
, 5 
μ
m).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>

The tubers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Corydalis yanhusuo
W.T. Wang (Papaveraceae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected in 
Pan’ an
, 
Jiangsu Province
, People’ s 
Republic of China
, in 

2015

. The materials were identified by Prof. 
Hai-yu Xu
, Institute of Chinese Materia Medica, China Academy of Chinese Medical Sciences. The voucher specimens have been deposited in 
Dongzhimen Hospital
, Beijing University of Chinese Medicine (no. 
DZMH-2015-10-15
)


and 
Institute of Materia Medica
, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College (no. 
IMM-2015-10-15
)

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>
For extraction and partition separation of the extract to obtain the fractions A-I, see our previous work (

). Separation of fraction B (14.0 g) was performed on reversed phase medium pressure column chromatography (CC) with methanol-water (5%→95%, 2 h, ODS), yielding three subfractions (B1–B3) and 
19
(
450 mg
). Fraction B1 (
1.5 g
) was subjected to Sephadex LH-20 CC (5 × 
120 cm
) eluting with petroleum ether (PE)- 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (
v
: 
v
: 
v
5:5:1) to afford four subfractions (B1-1 B1-4). Subfraction B1-2 was fractionated by Sephadex LH-20 column using MeOH as eluent to obtain B1-2-1 and B1-2-2. B1-2-2 (
705 mg
) was separated by HPLC to give subfractions (B1-2-2-1 B1-2-2-3) and 
7
[RP C 
18
, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, ACN–H 
2
O–TFA (43:57:0.1), 
tR
= 26.3 min, 
209 mg
]. B1-2-2-1 (290.0 mg) was further separated by HPLC [RP C 
18
, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, ACN–H 
2
O–TFA (34:66:0.1)] to afford 
20
(
tR
= 11.0 min, 136.0 mg), 
8
(
tR
= 13.9 min, 4.0 mg), 
21
(
tR
= 20.3 min, 45.0 mg), and 
11
(
tR
=25.0 min, 4.0 mg). Separation on B1-2-2-2 (
24.1 mg
) by HPLC [RP C 
18
, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, MeOH–H 
2
O-TFA (51:49:0.1)] gave 
18
(
tR
=24.6 min, 2.0 mg), 
10
(
tR
= 26.6 min, 4.0 mg), and 
9
(
tR
= 28.0 min, 3.0 mg). B1-2-2-3 (14.0 mg) was further separated by HPLC [RP XB-CN, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, MeOH–H 
2
O-TFA (42:58:0.2)] to give 
12
(
tR
= 20.3 min, 2.0 mg). Subfractions B1-3 was further purified by HPLC to yield 
6
[RP C 
18
, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, ACN–H 
2
O–TFA (50:50:0.1), 
tR
= 10.3 min, 
0.6 mg
].
</p>
         <p>
Fraction B2 (
2.2 g
) was separated by Sephadex LH-20 CC [5 × 
120 cm
, PE-CH 
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (
v
: 
v
: 
v
5:5:1)] to afford four subfractions (B2- 1 B2-4). Subfractions B2-1 was further separated by HPLC to give 
3
[RP C 
18
, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, ACN–H 
2
O–TFA (43:57:0.2), 
tR
=28.5 min, 1.0 mg]. Subfraction B2-2 was further separated by HPLC [RP C 
18
, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, ACN–H 
2
O–TFA (40:60:0.2)] to give 
5
tR
=34.0 min, 
1.1 mg
) and 
1
(
tR
=28.9 min, 
1.2 mg
). 
1
was separated using a CHIRALPAK IG chiral column (ACN–H 
2
O–TFA, 37:63:0.01) to give (+)- 
1
(
t
R
= 5.3 min, 
0.6 mg
) and ()- 
1
(
t
R
= 5.9 min, 
0.3 mg
).
</p>
         <p>
Fraction B3 was separated by CC on flash inverting medium voltage and eluted with MeOH–H 
2
O (40%→95%, 2h, RP C 
18
120g
), to give five subfractions (B3-1 B3-5). Subfraction B3-3 was further separated by HPLC [RP 
18
, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, ACN–H 
2
O–TFA (45:65:0.1)] to give 
4
(
tR
=24.0 min, 2.0 mg) and 
2
(
tR
=26.0 min, 
2.5 mg
). 
2
was separated by HPLC (CHIRALPAK IB-N3 chiral column, ACN–H 
2
O–TFA, 37:63:0.01) to give (+)- 
2
(
t
R
=33.3 min, 
0.54 mg
) and ()- 
2
(
t
R
=34.8 min, 
0.60 mg
).
</p>
         <p>
Fraction I (
12.1 g
) was separated by Sephadex LH-20 CC (5 × 
120 cm
) using MeOH as eluent to furnish eight subfractions (I1–I8). Subfraction I7 (
1.6 g
) was subsequently separated by C18 reverse phase silica gel column (MeOH–H 
2
O gradient: 20:80 → 100:0) to produce four fractions (I7-1 I7-4). Subfraction I7-2 (
580 mg
) was separated by HPLC [RP C 
18
, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, MeOH–H 
2
O-TFA (54:46:0.1)] to give 
13
(
9 mg
, 
tR
=20.4 min), 
15
(
4 mg
, 
tR
=24.0 min), and 
14
(
4 mg
, 
tR
=24.5 min). Subfraction I7-3 (
470 mg
) was separated by HPLC [RP C 
18
, 5 
μ
m, 250 × 
10 mm
, MeOH–H 
2
O-TFA (53:47:0.1)] to give 
16
(
4 mg
, 
tR
=13.9 min) and 
17
(
4 mg
, 
tR
=17.0 min).
</p>
         <p>
TFA Salt of 
Yanhusanine G (1)
: 
w
hite powder; [
α
]20D +6.0 (c 0.05, MeOH); UV (MeOH, 0.001) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 203 (4.23), 229 (4.10), 266 (4.08), 336 (3.98), 422 (3.41) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3403, 2945, 2851, 1686, 1604, 1522, 1447, 1209, 1141, 1093, 
1026, 845, 803, 726 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR (600 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) and 
13
C NMR (150 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) data, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
382.1647 [M] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
24
NO 
5
, 382.1649).
</p>
         <p>
TFA Salt of 

(
+
)Yanhusanine G [(
+
)-1]

: [
α
]20D + 16.0 (c 0.05, MeOH); CD (MeOH, 0.25): 222 (
Δε
3.49), 246 (
Δε
+7.87), 284 (
Δε
1.07), 333 (
Δε
3.02).
</p>
         <p>
TFA Salt of 
()Yanhusanine G [()-1]
: [
α
]20D - 15.8 (c 0.04, MeOH); CD (MeOH, 0.25): 222 (
Δε
+1.93), 246 (
Δε
4.38), 284 (
Δε
+0.59), 333 (
Δε
+1.73).
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine H (2)
: 
w
hite powder; [
α
]20D 0 (c 0.05, MeOH); UV (MeOH, 0.001) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 206 (4.50), 221 (4.41), 265 (3.95) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3447, 2959, 2917, 2850, 1767, 1683, 1606, 1501, 1438, 1346, 1279, 1208, 1139, 1075, 
1028, 843, 802, 725 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR (600 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
), 
1
H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl 
3
), 
13
C NMR (150 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
), and 
13
C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl 
3
) data, see 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
400.1388 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
21
H 
22
NO 
7
, 400.1391).
</p>
         <p>
(
+
)Yanhusanine H [(
+
)-2]

: [
α
]20D + 138.7 (c 0.04, MeOH); CD (MeOH, 0.25): 205 (
Δε
+31.21), 224 (
Δε
15.78), 252 (
Δε
10.45), 275 (+7.03), 301 (
Δε
+7.82).
</p>
         <p>
()Yanhusanine H [()-2]
: [
α
]20D -149.3 (c 0.04, MeOH); CD (MeOH, 0.25): 205 (
Δε
34.44), 224 (
Δε
+19.18), 252 (
Δε
+12.10), 275 (
Δε
6.95), 301 (
Δε
7.99).
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine I (3)
: 
w
hite powder; UV (MeOH, 0.002) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 224 (4.35), 263 (4.06), 297 (3.91) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3431, 3084, 2999, 2935, 2849, 1729, 1679, 1642, 1601, 1512, 1482, 1453, 1340, 1276,1222, 1174, 1099, 
1077, 980, 951, 877, 800 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR (600 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) and 
13
C NMR (150 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) data, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
400.1764 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
26
NO 
6
, 400.1755).
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine J (4)
: white powder; UV (MeOH, 0.0003) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 210 (4.75), 231 (4.79), 248 (4.92), 256 (4.81) nm, 272 (4.45), 293 (4.34), 323 (3.89), 338 (3.72); IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3433, 2941, 2841, 1676, 1646, 1593, 1507, 1269, 1221, 1171, 1079, 
1029, 982, 808 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR (600 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) and 
13
C NMR (150 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) data, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
398.1600 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
24
NO 
6
, 398.1598).
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine K(5)
: yellowish powder; UV (MeOH, 0.002) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 208 (4.22), 222 (4.23), 267 (3.85), 295 (3.72) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3067, 3000, 2967, 2936, 2872, 2836, 2712, 2647, 1668, 1620, 1599, 1563, 1515, 1484, 1442, 1383, 1345, 1305, 1285, 1206, 1175, 1138, 1097, 
1015, 978, 877, 822, 802, 724 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR (600 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) and 
13
C NMR (150 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) data, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
386.1589 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for C 
21
H 
24
NO 
6
, 386.1598).
</p>
         <p>
Yanhusanine
L 
(6)
: white powder; UV (MeOH, 0.001) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 205 (4.46), 229 (4.38), 275 (4.17) nm, 308 (3.95) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3345, 3079, 3006, 2977, 2951, 2922, 2840, 1727, 1678, 1601, 1572, 1514, 1493, 1460, 1420, 1383, 1346, 1317, 
1020, 980, 926, 882, 814, 771, 717 cm
1
; 
1
H NMR (600 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) and 
13
C NMR (150 MHz, DMSO‑ 
d
6
) data, see 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
414.1539 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
24
NO 
7
, 414.1547).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Anti-inflammatory assay and cell viability
</title>
         <p>The anti-inflammatory activities of the isolated compounds were evaluated using LPS-induced NO production in RAW264.7 macrophages. The detailed process is described in the Supporting Information.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Enzyme linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)
</title>
         <p>
The levels of the released pro-inflammatory cytokines (TNF- 
α
, IL-6, and IL-1 
β
) were examined using ELISA kits according to the manufacturer’ s protocols. The detailed process is described in the Supporting Information.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Western blot analysis
</title>
         <p>
The protein expression levels of iNOS, IκB 
α
, p-IκB 
α
, IκK, p-IκK, p65 NF-κB, and p-p65 NF-κB were evaluated by performing western blotting according to our previous report (

), as detailed in the Supporting Information.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Molecular docking studies
</title>
         <p>
The possible affinity interaction between 
4
and iNOS was predicted by molecular docking using the crystal structure of iNOS (PDB: 3E7G) (

) as receptor. The detailed process is described in the Supporting Information.
</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
This research was financially supported by 
Beijing
Natural Science Foundation (Grant No. JQ18026), the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(NNSFC; Grant No. 82073978, 81522050), and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (Grant No.2021-BUCMXJKY007).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.113023.</p>
         <p>
The assignments were based on 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HSQC, HMBC and NOESY experiments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chan, S.C.
, 
2000
. 

Chingazumianine, a novel dichlorinated alkaloid from 
Corydalis koidzumiana

. 
Helv. Chim. Acta
83
, 
2993–2999
. 

https://doi.org/10.1002/1522-2675 (20001108)83:11 
&lt;
2993::AID-HLCA2993
&gt;
3.0.CO;2-A

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cheng, X.Y.
, 
Shi, Y.
, 
Zheng, S.L.
, 
Jin, W.
, 
Sun, H.
, 
2008
. 

Two new protoberberine quaternary alkaloids from 
Corydalis yanhusuo
. J

. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
10
, 
1117–1121
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/10286020802410615
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Colombo, M.L.
, 
Bugatti, C.
, 
Mossa, A.
, 
Pescalli, N.
, 
Piazzoni, L.
, 
Pezzoni, G.
, 
Menta, E.
, 
Spinelli, S.
, 
Johnson, F.
, 
Gupta, R.C.
, 
Dasaradhi, L.
, 
2002
. 
Cytotoxicity evaluation of natural coptisine and synthesis of coptisine from berberine
. 
Il Farmaco
56
, 
403–409
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0014-827X(01)01121-1
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Deng, A.P.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Zhou, L.
, 
Kang, C.Z.
, Lv, C.G., 
Kang, L.P.
, 
Nan, T.G.
, 
Zhan, Z.L.
, 
Guo, L.P.
, 
Huang, L.Q.
, 
2021
. 

Systematic review of the alkaloid constituents in several important medicinal plants of the genus 
Corydalis

. 
Phytochemistry
183
, 
112644
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112644
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fricker, M.
, 
Gibson, P.G.
, 
2017
. 
Macrophage dysfunction in the pathogenesis and treatment of asthma
. 
Eur. Respir. J.
50
, 
1700196
. 
https://doi.org/10.1183/ 13993003.00196-2017
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Garcin, E.D.
, 
Arvai, A.S.
, 
Rosenfeld, R.J.
, 
Kroeger, M.D.
, 
Crane, B.R.
, 
Andersson, G.
, 
Andrews, G.
, 
Hamley, P.J.
, 
Mallinder, P.R.
, 
Nicholls, D.J.
, 
St-Gallay, S.A.
, 
Tinker, A. C.
, 
Gensmantel, N.P.
, 
Mete, A.
, 
Cheshire, D.R.
, 
Connolly, S.
, 
Stuehr, D.J.
, 
Aberg, A.
, 
Wallace, A.V.
, 
Tainer, J.A.
, 
Getzoff, E.D.
, 
2008
. 
Anchored plasticity opens doors for selective inhibitor design in nitric oxide synthase
. 
Nat. Chem. Biol.
4
, 
700–707
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/nchembio.115
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Karimov, A.
, 
Faskhutdinov, M.F.
, 
Abdullaev, N.D.
, 
Levkovich, M.G.
, Mil’ grom, E.G., 
Rashkes, Y.V.
, 
Shakirov, R.
, 
1993
. 

Berberis
alkaloids XXXII. berberal-A new alkaloid from 
Berberis heterobotrys

. 
Chem. Nat. Compd.
29
(
6
), 
774–777
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1007/BF00629649
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Karin, M.
, 
Ben-Neriah, Y.
, 
2000
. 
Phosphorylation meets ubiquitination: the control of NF-κB activity
. 
Annu. Rev. Immunol.
18
, 
621–663
. 
https://doi.org/10.1146/ annurev.immunol.18.1.621
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kim, J.H.
, 
Ryu, Y.B.
, 
Lee, W.S.
, 
Kim, Y.H.
, 
2014
. 

Neuraminidase inhibitory activities of quaternary isoquinoline alkaloids from 
Corydalis turtschaninovii
rhizome

. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem.
22
, 
6047–6052
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2014.09.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kwon, I.S.
, 
Kwak, J.H.
, 
Pyo, S.
, 
Lee, H.W.
, 
Kim, A.
, 
Schmitz, F.J.
, 
2017
. 

Oscarellin, an anthranilic acid derivative from a philippine sponge, 
Oscarella stillans
, as an inhibitor of inflammatory cytokines in macrophages

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
80
, 
149–155
. 
https://doi. org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.6b00787
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, S.H.
, 
Li, L.
, 
Yang, R.N.
, 
Liang, S.D.
, 
2020
. 
Compounds of traditional Chinese medicine and neuropathic pain
. 
Chin. J. Nat. Med.
18
, 
28–35
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ S1875-5364(20)30002-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Y.
, 
Fang, S.
, 
Li, X.
, 
Feng, J.
, 
Du, J.
, 
Guo, L.
, 
Su, Y.
, 
Zhou, J.
, 
Ding, G.
, 
Bai, Y.
, 
Wang, S.
, 
Wang, H.
, 
Liu, Y.
, 
2017
. 
Aspirin inhibits LPS-induced macrophage activation via the NF-κB pathway
. 
Sci. Rep.
7
, 
11549
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/ s41598-017-10720-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ma, B.L.
, 
Ma, Y.M.
, 
Shi, R.
, 
Wang, T.M.
, 
Zhang, N.
, 
Wang, C.H.
, 
Yang, Y.
, 
2010
. 

Identification of the toxic constituents in 
rhizoma coptidis
.

J. Ethnopharmacol.
128
, 
357–364
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2010.01.047.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Medzhitov, R.
, 
2010
. 
Inflammation 2010: new adventures of an old flame
. 
Cell
140
, 
771–776
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2010.03.006
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Miyazawa, M.
, 
Yoshio, K.
, 
Ishikawa, Y.
, 
Kameoka, H.
, 
1998
. 

Insecticidal alkaloids from 
Corydalis bulbosa
against 
Drosophila melanogaster

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
46
, 
1914–1919
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jf9701897
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moghaddam, A.S.
, 
Mohammadian, S.
, 
Vazini, H.
, 
Taghadosi, M.
, 
Esmaeili, S.
, 
Mardani, F.
, 
Seifi, B.
, 
Mohammadi, A.
, 
Afshari, J.T.
, 
Sahebkar, A.
, 
2018
. 
Macrophage plasticity, polarization, and function in health and disease
. 
J. Cell. Physiol.
233
, 
6425–6440
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/jcp.26429
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Okamoto, T.
, 
Sanda, T.
, 
Asamitsu, K.
, 
2007
. 
NF-kappa B signaling and carcinogenesis
. 
Curr. Pharmaceut. Des.
13
, 
447–462
. 
https://doi.org/10.2174/ 138161207780162944.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ruan, Q.F.
, 
Pan, W.C.
, 
Zhao, M.
, 
Tang, Y.Q.
, 
Chen, X.J.
, 
Bai, J.Y.
, 
Jin, J.
, 
Cui, H.
, 
Zhao, Z. X.
, 
2021
. 

Butyrolactone and sesquiterpene derivatives as inhibitors of iNOS from the roots of 
Lindera glauca

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
111
, 
104871
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. bioorg.2021.104871
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Saradna, A.
, 
Do, D.C.
, 
Kumar, S.
, 
Fu, Q.L.
, 
Gao, P.
, 
2018
. 
Macrophage polarization and allergic asthma
. 
Transl. Res.
191
, 
1–14
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trsl.2017.09.002
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sener, B.
, 
Temizer, H.
, 
1988
. 

Chemical study on protoberberine alkaloids from 
Corydalis solida
ssp. 
Brachyloba

. 
Planta Med.
54
, 
584
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2006- 962602
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Singh, S.
, 
Singh, T.D.
, 
Singh, V.P.
, 
Pandey, V.B.
, 
2010
. 

Quaternary alkaloids of 
Argemone mexicana

. 
Pharm. Biol.
48
, 
158–160
. 
https://doi.org/10.3109/ 13880200903062622
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Skeoch, S.
, 
Bruce, I.N.
, 
2015
. 
Atherosclerosis in rheumatoid arthritis: is it all about inflammation?
Nat. Rev. Rheumatol.
11
, 
390–400
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/ nrrheum.2015.40
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Soysal, P.
, 
Arik, F.
, 
Smith, L.
, 
Jackson, S.E.
, 
Isik, A.T.
, 
2020
. 
Inflammation, frailty and cardiovascular disease
. 
Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.
1216
, 
55–64
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ 978-3-030-33330-0_7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tang, Y.
, 
Li, S.
, 
Li, S.
, 
Yang, X.J.
, 
Qin, Y.
, 
Liu, C.M.
, 
Zhang, Y.C.
, 
2017
. 

Screening and isolating potential 
α
-glucosidase inhibitors from 
Rhizoma Coptidis
by ultrafiltration LC-PDA-ESI/MS combined with high-speed countercurrent chromatography and reverse-phase medium-pressure liquid chromatography

. 
Med. Chem. Res.
26
, 
3384–3394
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00044-017-2031-6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tran, Q.T.N.
, 
Fred Wong, W.S.
, 
Chai, C.L.L.
, 
2019
. 
The identification of naturally occurring labdane diterpenoid calcaratarin D as a potential anti-inflammatory agent
. 
Eur. J. Med. Chem.
174
, 
33–44
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2019.04.023
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, L.Y.
, 
Qiu, B.L.
, 
Xia, H.
, 
Xia, G.Y.
, 
Xiao, B.B.
, 
Zhang, J.F.
, 
Zhong, W.C.
, 
Lin, S.
, 
2020
. 

Yanhusanines A F, Isoquinoline-derived alkaloid enantiomers from 
Corydalis yanhusuo
and their biological activity

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
83
, 
489
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1021/acs.jnatprod.9b01155
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, Y.J.
, 
Wang, D.D.
, 
Zhang, J.H.
, 
Liu, D.
, 
Wang, Z.H.
, 
Meng, D.L.
, 
2018
. 

Isoquinolines from 
Corydalis tomentella
from Tibet

, 
China, possess hepatoprotective activities
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wu, L.
, 
Wang, G.C.
, 
Shen, T.
, 
Qiang, Q.
, 
Xue, Q.
, 
Chen, M.
, 
Zhang, J.M.
, 
Luo, Y.Y.
, 
Hong, Y.M.
, 
Si, C.L.
, 
Hu, W.C.
, 
2018
. 

Chemical constituents of leaves of 
Mahonia bealei

. 
Chem. Nat. Compd.
54
, 
210–212
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10600-018-2302- 6
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xia, H.
, 
Liu, Y.T.
, 
Xia, G.Y.
, 
Liu, Y.
, 
Lin, S.
, 
Guo, L.J.
, 
2021
. 
Novel isoquinoline alkaloid Litcubanine A - a potential anti-inflammatory candidate
. 
Front. Immunol.
12
, 
685556
. 
https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2021.685556
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xiao, B.B.
, 
Xia, G.Y.
, 
Wang, L.Y.
, 
Qiu, B.L.
, 
Xia, H.
, 
Zhong, W.C.
, 
Tian, G.H.
, 
Lin, S.
, 
2020
. (±)- 

Bicoryanhunine A, dimeric benzylisoquinoline alkaloid atropo-enantiomers from 
Corydalis yanhusuo

. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
61
, 
151890
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. tetlet.2020.151890
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xie, C.
, 
Veitch, N.C.
, 
Houghton, P.J.
, 
Simmonds, M.S.J.
, 
2004
. 

Flavonoid glycosides and isoquinolinone alkaloids from 
Corydalis bungeana

. 
Phytochemistry
65
, 
3041–3047
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2004.09.009
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, J.
, 
He, S.
, 
Wang, J.
, 
Wang, C.
, 
Wu, J.
, 
Wang, W.
, 
Li, F.
, 
Li, S.
, 
Zhao, C.
, 
Li, F.
, 
2020
. 

A Review of the traditional uses, botany, phytochemistry, pharmacology, pharmacokinetics, and toxicology of 
Corydalis yanhusuo

. 
Nat. Prod. Commun.
15
, 
1–19
. 
https://doi.org/10.1177/1934578X20957752
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhu, H.
, 
Wang, D.
, 
Wen, L.
, 
Yu, J.Q.
, 
Geng, Y.L.
, 
Zhao, H.Q.
, 
Zhao, R.X.
, 
Wang, X.
, 
2016
. 
Preparative separation of quaternary ammonium alkaloids from Caulis Mahoniae by conventional and pH-zone-refining counter-current chromatography
. 
RSC Adv.
6
, 
83343
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/C6RA14056D
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
