<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112509</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The effect of β-cyclocitral treatment on the carotenoid content of transgenic Marsh grapefruit (Citrus paradisi Macf.) suspension-cultured cells</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rutaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rutaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Artemisia annua
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rutaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
(
Ramel et al., 2012
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rutaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Erwinia uredovora Crt
B
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

The effect of β- cyclocitral treatment on the carotenoid content of transgenic Marsh grapefruit (
Citrus paradisi
Macf.) suspension-cultured cells

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Xiongjie Zheng
a, 1
, Kaijie Zhu
a, 1
, Junli Ye
a
, Elliott J. Price
b, c, d
, Xiuxin Deng

a, 
**
,
Paul D. Fraser 
b, *
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a

Key Laboratory of Horticultural Plant Biology (Ministry of Education), Huazhong Agricultural University, Wuhan, 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
b
School of Biological Sciences
, 
Royal Holloway
, 
University of London
, 
Egham Hill
, 
Egham
, 
Surrey
, TW20 0EX, 
UK
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
c

Faculty of Sports Studies, Masaryk University, Brno, 
Czech Republic
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
d

RECETOX Centre, Masaryk University, Brno, 
Czech Republic
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ARTICLE INFO</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
Citrus paradis
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Rutaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Citrus</p>
         <p>Suspension-cultured cells Chemical elicitor β- yclocitral</p>
         <p>Carotenoid</p>
         <p>Provitamin A</p>
         <p>ABSTRACT</p>
         <p>
This work reports the development of suspension culture system of transgenic Marsh grapefruit (
Citrus paradisi
Macf., 
<tp:taxon-name>Rutaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) callus overexpressing bacterial phytoene synthase; and the use of this suspension culture to investigate the effects of β- cyclocitral on carotenoid content and composition. At a β- cyclocitral concentration of 0.5 mM and after ten days cultivation, analysis of the carotenoids showed a significant increase in the content of β-, α- carotene, and phytoene predominantly. The maximal increase in total provitamin A carotenoids content following β- cyclocitral application was ~2-fold higher than the control, reaching 245.8 μg/g DW. The trend for increased transcript levels of biosynthetic genes PSY and ZDS correlated with the enhancement of the content of these carotenes following β- cyclocitral treatment and GC-MS based metabolite profiling showed significant changes of metabolite levels across intermediary metabolism. These findings suggest that β- cyclocitral can act as a chemical elicitor, to enhance the formation of carotenes in citrus suspension-cultured cells (SCC), which could be utilized in studying the regulation of carotenoid biosynthesis and biotechnological application to the renewable production of nutritional carotenoids.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Carotenoids are chemically diverse natural pigments, which are synthesized 
de novo
in all photosynthetic organisms, as well as some microorganisms (

). In plant, carotenoids are derived from isopentenyl pyrophosphate (IPP) formed from the methylerythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathway in the plastid. IPP is condensed into geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGPP; C 
20
), a common precursor for several groups of plastidial isoprenoids (

; Ruiz-Sola and Rodríguez-Concepcion´, 2012). The tail-to-tail condensation of two molecules of GGPP form 15- 
cis
-phytoene (C 
40
), which represents the first dedicated step in carotenoid biosynthesis and is catalyzed by phytoene synthase (PSY) (
Fig. 1
). This is also generally accepted to be the “rate-limiting step” of the carotenoid pathway (

; 

). Phytoene desaturase (PDS), ζ- carotene isomerase (Z-ISO), ζ- carotene desaturase (ZDS) and carotenoid isomerase (CRTISO) are required to convert 15- 
cis
-phytoene into the red coloured lycopene (

; 

; 

). Cyclization of lycopene, catalyzed by lycopene β- cyclase (LCYb) and/or ε- cyclase (LCYe), converts the acyclic carotenes into cyclic carotenoids, including β- carotene (with two β- ionone rings) and α- carotene (with one β- and ε- ionone rings) (

; 

). These cyclic carotenoids are then converted into various oxygen-containing xanthophylls, by hydroxylation and epoxidation reactions decorating the β and/or α- rings. These modifications are catalyzed by β- carotene hydroxylases (BCH) and zeaxanthin epoxidase (ZEP) enzymes (
Fig. 1
) (

; Ruiz-Sola and Rodríguez-Concepci´on, 2012).
</p>
         <p>
In plants, various volatile and non-volatile apocarotenoids are derived from carotenoids through enzymatic reaction, catalyzed by a gene family of carotenoid cleavage dioxygenases (CCDs) (

; 

; 

; 

; Zheng et al., 2019), or non-enzymatic degradation (

; 

). Some apocarotenoids are precursors for signaling molecules, such as strigolactones (SLs) and abscisic acid (ABA) (

; 

); and serve as bioactive molecules involved in regulating plant growth, stress responses and signaling (e.g. zaxinone, β- cyclocitral and anchorene) (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
In addition to their diverse functions in plant processes, carotenoids have nutritional and industrial uses. For example, in human, where carotenoids cannot be synthesized 
de novo
, β- carotene acts as provitamin A and is thus an essential dietary component. A lack of β- carotene and other provitamin A carotenoids (e.g. α- carotene) in the diet will lead to vitamin A deficiency (VAD). VAD is a public health problem which impacts the lives of over 125–130 million preschool-aged children and is the leading cause of preventable pediatric blindness in low-income developing countries (

). This has prompted the development of a series of biotechnology strategies toward biofortification of provitamin A carotenoids (mainly β- carotene) in crops (

; 

; 

). In addition, many carotenoids are commercially produced for use as nutritional supplements for health, colorants and additives for the cosmetic industry, feed, and pharma sectors.
</p>
         <p>
Plants are exploitable ‘green’ chemical factories with potential to produce various high-value compounds. Use of plant cell suspension culture platforms has been proposed as a sustainable strategy to produce high-value bioactive compounds or pharmaceuticals, such as taxol, isoflavone and artemisinin (Cusido et al., 2014; 

; 

). In addition, many pharmaceuticals derived plant cell suspension cultures are already commercially viable (

). One feature of metabolite production in plant tissue culture has been the use of various chemical inducers/elicitors, such as mineral nutrients, fine chemicals &amp; phytohormones (

; 

). For example, the 50 mM 2, 6-dimethyl-β- cyclodextrins treatment enhanced production of intracellular lutein and quinone contents from SCC of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Artemisia annua
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (

). However, to date, there are no reports related to the application of elicitor/inducers on enhancing production yield of provitamin A carotenoids in citrus SCC. β- Cyclocitral is a volatile apocarotenoid derived from oxidative cleavage of β- ring containing carotenoids (e.g. β- carotene) (
Fig. 1
). It has been shown to regulate the plant response to oxidative stress and excess light, as well as root growth (

; 

). However, the effect of this compound on the production of carotenoids in SCC, when applied exogenously, remains unknown.
</p>
         <p>
Previous works have reported the solid medium culture of a transgenic citrus (
Citrus paradisi
Macf., 
<tp:taxon-name>Rutaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) callus line overexpressing a bacterial phytoene synthase (CrtB) which produces high content of provitamin A carotenoids, mainly β- carotene (

; 

). In the present study, the suspension culture system of this carotenoid-biofortified transgenic callus line is established; the obtained transgenic suspension-cultured cells are used to investigate the effect of β- cyclocitral on carotenoid production, gene expression of the carotenoid biosynthetic pathway and metabolite levels across intermediary metabolism.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Effect of β- cyclocitral treatment on the carotenoids content and
composition of citrus suspension-cultured cells
</title>
         <p>
Most citrus callus tissues have a very low-level carotenoids content (

). Therefore, the effects of β- cyclocitral were investigated by using transgenic citrus callus which produce abundant carotenoids, due to the overexpression of a bacterial phytoene synthase gene (

). In the present study, SCC of this transgenic calli line were developed and β- cc tested as a chemical elicitor of carotenoid production in this biological system. SCC were firstly treated with different concentrations of β- cc for twelve days. The total carotenoid content of SCC was significantly increased under 0.1 mM and 0.5 mM β- cc treatment (
Fig. 2
). However, further dosage increase (1 mM) did not lead to significant increase of total carotenoids content (
Fig. 2A
), instead, it had stronger negative effect on growth index of SCC compared with 0.5 mM β- cc (
Fig. 3
). Moreover, 2 mM β- cc concentration had a lethal effect on the citrus SCC, producing white-coloured callus cells (
Fig. S1A
). This suggests that excessive β- cc is toxic for plant cells. Specifically, the provitamin A carotenoids 
trans
-β- carotene (referred to as β- carotene throughout) and α- carotene showed highest content enhancement under β- cc treatment. Other carotenes, such as 
cis
-β- carotene and the colorless phytofluene and phytoene also showed a significant increase after β- cc treatment. In contrast, the xanthophylls (i. e. violaxanthin and lutein) were slightly decreased under β- cc treatment, indicating a specific effect of β- cc on carotenes accumulation in SCC (
Fig. 2A
). The highest content of β- carotene and α- carotene was observed when citrus SCC were treated with 0.5 mM β- cc, increasing ~2-fold compared to the control samples. Treatment with 0.1 mM β- cc also resulted in significant increases of provitamin A carotenoids but showed less effect compared to 0.5 mM β- cc (
Fig. 2A
, 
Fig. S1B
). This suggests a dose dependent response to β- cc treatment, but further studies are required to fully establish the nature of the effect. Consistent with increased provitamin A carotenoids content, the citrus SCC visually turns to a redder coloration after 12 days of 0.5 mM β- cc treatment compared to the control material (
Fig. 2B
).
</p>
         <p>
Once it was known which β- cc concentration induced the maximal levels of provitamin A carotenoids, the time course of provitamin A carotenoids production was analyzed in citrus SCC elicited with 0.5 mM β- cc. As shown in 
Fig. 4
, the content of all carotenoids, expect phytoene, was decreased from day 0 to 4th day. However, significantly increased accumulation of total and provitamin A carotenoids was observed by day 10. In contrast, the content of xanthophylls (violaxanthin and lutein) was always lower under β- cc treatment than control.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. The effect of β- cyclocitral on the expression of genes involved in
carotenoid formation and degradation in citrus suspension-cultured cells
</title>
         <p>
Transcriptional regulation of carotenoid biosynthetic genes is a major molecular mechanism for carotenoid accumulation in plant (

; 

). As such, carotenoid pathway gene expression was profiled at 4th, 7th and 10th day of 0.5 mM β- cc treatment. As shown in 
Fig. 5
, at four days post treatment only 
CitZDS
was significantly altered by β- cc treatment being up-regulated, in comparison to control. At 7th day, the expression of genes upstream of α/β- carotene biosynthesis (
CitDXS
, 
CitPSY
and 
CitZDS
) alongside the downstream gene 
CitZEP,
was increased in SCC under β- cc treatment. At 10th day, expression of 
CitGGPPS
and 
CitBCH
was significantly increased, in addition to all genes that exhibited significant upregulation at 7th day. The trend for increased expression of key carotenoid biosynthetic genes correlated with the enhancement of carotene contents in SCC observed at 7th and 10th day under β- cc treatment.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Changes in intermediary metabolite pools associated with
</title>
         <p>
β- cyclocitral treatment of citrus transgenic suspension-cultured cells
</p>
         <p>
In order to assess the global effects of β- cc treatment across the metabolome of the citrus SCC, GC-MS based metabolite profiling was performed on SCC following fourteen days treatment at 0.5 mM β- cc concurrently with their control. Fifty-four metabolites were identified and quantified in a relative manner. Significant changes in metabolite levels were found across multiple sectors of intermediary metabolism (
Fig. 6
). Most notably, the sugar levels were significantly higher in response to β- cc treatment compared with control and core monosaccharides (e.g. fructose, glucose, inositol, sedoheptulose) plus cellwall related sugars/derivatives (e.g. arabinofuranose, gluconic acid) were increased under β- cc treatment. Furthermore, over 60% of the organic acids quantified, were elevated under β- cc treatment. In particular, the relative concentration of citric acid and ribonic acid showed a greater than two-fold and six-fold increase respectively. Numerous amino acids displayed significantly greater content under β- cc treatment, whilst pyroglutamic acid and ornithine showed reduction in level. The levels of phytosterols, campesterol and β- sitosterol showed reduction in levels, whilst several triterpenoids (e.g. squalene, cycloartenol and 24-methylenecycloartenol) showed a significant increase under β- cc treatment. GABA displayed a significant alteration with a greater than three-fold increase under β- cc treatment, suggesting that the β- cc had triggered a stress response in the SCC (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Discussion
</title>
         <p>
Carotenoids are antioxidant compounds and/or vitamin A precursors that are indispensable for human health. In particular, vitamin A deficiency (VAD) is still one of the most severe health problems impacting the lives of millions in low-income countries (

). The demand for plant derived natural provitamin A carotenoids creates a need for development of platforms and strategies to increase their production in plant cell factories. Previous study reported that metabolic engineering of carotenoid biosynthesis by overexpression of a bacterial phytoene synthase gene resulted in enrichment of carotenoids, consisting predominantly of β- carotene, in solid medium-cultured citrus callus (

). In the present study, we develop the suspension culture of this transgenic citrus callus line, which allows faster growth of callus cells than that in the solid culture and rapid studying in vitro the biological function of small molecule/elicitor. Our results showed that 0.5 mM β- cc treatment effectively improves the production yield of provitamin A carotenoids content in transgenic SCC after 10 days cultivation (
Fig. 4
and 
Fig. S1
), which reveals the use of chemical elicitor for cell suspension cultures has a great potential to improve the production of valuable carotenoids.
</p>
         <p>
In addition, results suggest that the effect of β- cc on production yield of provitamin A carotenoids could be concentration dependent. The SCC with 0.5 mM treatment of β- cc showed the highest content of the provitamin A carotenoids. Further increase in β- cc dose (1 mM) did not show a significant positive effect on total carotenoids production; instead, it strongly hindered the growth of SCC (
Fig. 3
). Although the 0.5 mM treatment also had negative effect on growth index of SCC compared with 0.1 mM β- cc, which had no significant negative effect on growth index (
Fig. 3
), the increased total provitamin A production in 60 mL suspension culture are still significantly higher in 0.5 mM β- cc treatment than 0.1 mM (
Figs. S1B and C
). As the β and α- carotene concentration of SCC is much higher under 0.5 mM β- cc application (
Fig. 2A
), 0.5 mM treatment would be more economically viable to extract target provitamin A carotenoids. Future work in bioreactor is suggested to determine the optimal concentration between 0.1 mM and 0.5 mM, to achieve maximal production of provitamin A carotenoids with respect to cell culture growth index.
</p>
         <p>
β- cc has been demonstrated to be a stress signal which modulates photosynthesis and root growth (

; 

) whilst β- ionone (another β- carotene derived volatile apocarotenoid) treatment did not elicit similar response to excess light stress in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
(
Ramel et al., 2012
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. In addition, our result showed that the same concentration of β- ionone cannot mimic β- cc effect on content of carotenoids in citrus SCC (
Fig. S2
), suggesting that β- cc plays a specific role on both induction of stress signal in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arabidopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
and modulation of carotenoid formation in citrus SCC. Moreover, β- cc treatment increased expression of upstream carotenoid biosynthetic genes 
DXS
, 
PSY
and 
ZDS
gene after seven days (
Fig. 5
), which is consistent with the enhancement of carotenoids content. Thus, one can speculate a possible mechanism is that high concentration of β- cc mediated stress signal plays a feedback role in the transcriptional regulation of carotenoid biosynthesis, thereby increased carotenoids content in citrus SCC. Among the carotenoids, α- carotene, β- carotene, 
cis
-β- carotene, phytoene and phytofluene were increased in citrus SCC by β- cc application. In contrast, the xanthophylls, lutein and violaxanthin, showed a slight reduction following β- cc treatment (
Figs. 2
and 
4
). Thus, β- cc shows a specific positive effect on production yield of all carotenes. Alongside the provitamin A carotenoids the colorless carotenes, phytoene and phytofluene are themselves valuable bioactive widely used in many skin care products due to their antioxidant properties and harboring several purported beneficial effects on human health (

). Previous studies in non-green tissues have demonstrated that pushing metabolic flux to carotenoids by gene manipulation results in a more predominant accumulation of β- carotene, phytoene and phytofluene than xanthophylls (

), likely due to the lower carotenoid hydroxylase activity than in green tissues. It is plausible that in the citrus SCC β- cc may act directly on the hydroxylase enzymes as an inhibitor. Limiting the pathway at this step could create multiple feedback/forward loops in an attempt to bring homeostasis to the pathway. For example, the absence of end product xanthophyll could stimulate the earlier steps in the pathway to increase flux through the pathway and thus expression of these early pathway genes arises (
Fig. 5
). Expression levels of genes subsequent to cyclization and involved in xanthophyll formation were increased concurrently in an attempt to overcome the inhibition at the enzyme level.
</p>
         <p>
To further understand how β- cc affects carotenoid concentrations in a holistic manner across metabolism, metabolite pools associated with intermediary metabolism were analyzed. Previous studies have demonstrated the interconnectivity of primary and secondary metabolism. For example, the steady state level of many diverse metabolites in transgenic tomato fruit was shown to be significantly perturbed (

, 

). The β- cc treatment in the transgenic SCC had broad effects across the metabolome (
Fig. 6
). An increase in sugars, amino acids, and organic acids suggests that the β- cc lead to increase the carbon source in cell cultures. The decreases of overall triterpenes following β- cc treatment support increased flux of precursor isoprenoids towards carotenoid biosynthesis. However, the most prominent metabolic perturbation was the increase in signaling compounds GABA and dopamine, indicating that the modulatory effects of β- cc were far reaching across metabolism.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Conclusions
</title>
         <p>In the present study, we report that β- cc treatment can be applied to enhance the contents of provitamin A carotenoids, phytoene and phytofluene in carotenoid-biofortified transgenic citrus SCC. These changes in carotenes contents were accompanied by increases in the expression of genes upstream of α/β- carotene biosynthesis and altered intermediary metabolite contents. These results highlight that the chemical elicitation strategy has a great potential to be utilized in improving valuable carotenoids production in plant cell factory. Furthermore, the suspension culture of carotenoid-biofortified transgenic citrus callus has a potential as a fundamental tool for the study of carotenoid regulation and small molecule/elicitor modulation of the pathway.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Experimental
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.1. Plant materials and plant cell culture conditions
</title>
         <p>
The establishment of transgenic Marsh grapefruit (
Citrus paradisi
Macf., 
<tp:taxon-name>Rutaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) callus lines overexpressing the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Erwinia uredovora Crt
B
</tp:taxon-name>
gene have been reported earlier (

). The stable transgenic line was sub-cultured into fresh solid medium every 2 weeks as previously described (

; 

). To establish suspension cultures, friable calli grown on solid medium were transferred into a Murashige and Skoog (MS) liquid medium (containing vitamin B5) supplemented with sucrose (
50 g
/L), 4-morpholineethanesulfonic acid (MES, 
0.5 g
/L), Vitamin C (
0.5 g
/L), malt extract (
0.5 g
/L) and L-glutamine (
1.5 g
/L). The pH of the suspension medium was 5.85. Sixty mL of suspension-cultured cells were cultivated in sterile flasks (200 mL) placed on a horizontal orbital shaker set to 120 rpm, and at a temperature of 25 

◦

C under darkness. The callus cells were sub-cultured into fresh suspension medium every two weeks.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.2. β- Cyclocitral treatments
</title>
         <p>
Suspension-cultured cells were pre-cultivated in liquid media for 4 days prior to β- cyclocitral (β- cc) treatments. These suspension cells were cultured in 60 mL media containing 0 mM (control), 0.1 mM, 0.5 mM or 1 mM β- cc and harvested at 12 days after β- cc treatment. In addition, the suspension cells with 0.5 mM β- cc treatment were harvested at 0 days, 4th day, 7th day, 10th day and 14th day. Growth index (GI) of suspension-cultured cells under different treatment conditions was defined as GI 
=
(final fresh weight of biomass - initial fresh weight of biomass)/initial fresh weight of biomass (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.3. Carotenoid profile
</title>
         <p>
The extraction of carotenoids was carried out according to the method described in (

). In brief, the carotenoids were extracted from samples that had been lyophilized and ground into a powder (
20 mg
) by using chloroform (500 μL) and methanol (250 μL). Then 100 mM Tris-HCl (250 μL, pH: 7.5) was added to the crude extract to remove the water-soluble impurities and create a discrete partition. The separation and detection of carotenoids were performed using high-performance liquid chromatography with photodiode array detection (HPLC-PDA). The carotenoids were eluted from a C 
30
reverse-phase column (250 
×
4.6 mm
; YMC, Wilmington, NC, 
USA
) at a flow rate of 1 mL/min using mobile phase A (100% methanol), phase B (methanol with 20% (v/v) water) and mobile phase C (tert-methyl butyl ether, MTBE) with UV-VIS continuous detection (from 
200 to 600 nm
). The gradient was 95% A/5% B for 6 min stepped a linear gradient to 80% A/5% B/15% C by 7 min, held until 12 min, followed by a linear gradient to 30% A/5% B/65% C by 32 min, held until 48 min, and then was returned to 95% A/5% B by the end of analysis (60 min) (

). The carotenoids were identified by a comparison of spectral properties and the retention times with authentic standards and &amp; spectra from literature (

; 

). The contents of carotenoids were measured by comparison with calibration curves of authentic standards.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.4. Quantitative Real-time PCR
</title>
         <p>
Extraction of total RNA was performed by using Qiagen RNeasy plant mini kit (Qiagen Ltd. Crawley 
UK
) following the manufacturer’ s instructions. The total RNA was treated with on-column DNaseI digestion. The first-strand cDNA synthesis and Quantitative Real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) were performed by using a Rotor-Gene 3000 thermocycler (Qiagen, Ltd., Crawley, 
UK
) with QuantiTect SYBR Green, one-step real-time RT-PCR kit (Qiagen, Ltd., Crawley, 
UK
) as previously reported (

). Gene-specific primers used for Quantitative Real-time PCR are listed in Table S1.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.5. GC-MS based metabolite profiling
</title>
         <p>
Metabolite extraction, derivatization and GC-MS analysis were performed as previously described (

; 

). Briefly, freeze-dried callus powder (
20 mg
) was used and the metabolites were extracted using methanol (400 μL; HPLC grade), water (400 μL; HPLC grade) and chloroform (800 μL). An aliquot of the polar phase (20 μL) to which the internal standard d 
4
-succinic acid (10 μg) was added and the non-polar extract (700 μL) to which the internal standard d 
27
-myristic acid (10 μg) was added and dried. Derivatization was performed immediately using methoxyamine hydrochloride (30 μL of a 
20 mg
/mL solution, in pyridine) and N-methyl-N-trimethylsilyltrifluoroacetamide (70 μL; MSTFA, Sigma-Aldrich) prior to injection. Three biological and three technical replicates were analyzed. The GC-MS analysis was performed on an Agilent HP6890 gas chromatograph with a 5973MSD by using a 10:1 split injector mode as previously described (

). Peaks were only used for analyses if identified in all three biological and technical replicates of any samples. Identification of metabolites was based on a retention-indexed spectral library constructed from authentic standards (

) and comparison to NIST 14 MS library. Quantification of metabolites was carried out using AMDIS software (v2.71; NIST). Each compound was assigned a representative ion and integrated peak response areas were expressed relative to internal standard (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5.6. Statistical analysis
</title>
         <p>
All the data are presented as the mean 
±
SE (standard deviation of the mean) of three biological replications unless stated otherwise. The statistical analysis of data was carried out using the Microsoft Excel program. One-way ANOVA and Student’ s t-tests were used to calculate significant difference of expression level of carotenoid pathway genes in suspension-cultured cells between treatment and control. Multiple comparisons of carotenoid content were performed by using SAS version 8 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC). The Heml 1.0 software was used for heatmap displaying of the metabolites data from GC-MS analysis.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest
</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
This work was supported in part through the National Key Research and Development Program of 
China
(2018YFD1000200), European Union Framework Program DISCO (from DISCOvery to products: a nextgeneration pipeline for the sustainable generation of high-value plant products; Project 613513), the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council OPTICAR Project (optimisation of tomato fruit carotenoid content for nutritional improvement and industrial exploitation), National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(No. 31930095, 31630065) and a 
China
council scholarship. We greatly appreciate Hongbo Cao, Kit Liew, Rapacz Elzbieta, Chris Gerrish and Karl Crosby for their excellent technical assistance.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112509.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Al-Babili, S.
, 
Bouwmeester, H.J.
, 
2015
. 
Strigolactones, a novel carotenoid-derived plant hormone
. 
Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.
66
, 
161–186
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alder, A.
, 
Jamil, M.
, 
Marzorati, M.
, 
Bruno, M.
, 
Vermathen, M.
, 
Bigler, P.
, et al., 
2012
. 
The path from β- carotene to carlactone, a strigolactone-like plant hormone
. 
Science
335
, 
1348–1351
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Arano-Varela, H.
, 
Fern´andez, F.
, 
Estrada-Zúniga ˜, M.
, 
Cruz-Sosa, F.
, 
2020
. 

Verbascoside production in long-term 
Buddleja cordata
Kunth cell suspension cultures

. 3 
Biotech
10
, 
245-245
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bown, A.W.
, 
Shelp, B.J.
, 
2016
. 
Plant GABA: not just a metabolite
. 
Trends Plant Sci.
21
, 
811–813
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Breitenbach, J.
, 
Sandmann, G.
, 
2005
. 

ζ- Carotene 
cis
isomers as products and substrates in the plant poly- 
cis
carotenoid biosynthetic pathway to lycopene

. 
Planta
220
, 
785–793
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Britton, G.
, 
Liaaen-Jensen, S.
, 
Pfander, H.
, 
2012
. 
Carotenoids: Handbook
. 
Birkh¨auser
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cao, H.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Xu, J.
, 
Ye, J.
, 
Yun, Z.
, 
Xu, Q.
, et al., 
2012
. 
Comprehending crystalline β- carotene accumulation by comparing engineered cell models and the natural carotenoid-rich system of citrus
. 
J. Exp. Bot.
63
, 
4403–4417
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cunningham, F.X.
, 
Gantt, E.
, 
2001
. 
One ring or two? Determination of ring number in carotenoids by lycopene ϵ- cyclases
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
98
, 
2905–2910
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cusido, R.M.
, 
Onrubia, M.
, 
Sabater-Jara, A.B.
, 
Moyano, E.
, 
Bonfill, M.
, 
Goossens, A.
, et al., 
2014
. 

A rational approach to improving the biotechnological production of taxanes in plant cell cultures of 
Taxus
spp

. 
Biotechnol. Adv.
32
, 
1157–1167
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dickinson, A.J.
, 
Lehner, K.
, 
Mi, J.
, 
Jia, K.-P.
, 
Mijar, M.
, 
Dinneny, J.
, et al., 
2019
. 
β- Cyclocitral is a conserved root growth regulator
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
116
, 
10563–10567
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Diretto, G.
, 
Al-Babili, S.
, 
Tavazza, R.
, 
Papacchioli, V.
, 
Beyer, P.
, 
Giuliano, G.
, 
2007
. 
Metabolic engineering of potato carotenoid content through tuber-specific overexpression of a bacterial mini-pathway
. 
PloS One
2
, e 
350
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Drapal, M.
, 
Barros de Carvalho, E.
, 
Ovalle Rivera, T.M.
, 
Becerra Lopez-Lavalle, L.A.
, 
Fraser, P.D.
, 
2018
. 

Capturing biochemical diversity in cassava (
Manihot esculenta
Crantz) through the application of metabolite profiling

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
67
, 
986–993
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Enfissi, E.M.
, 
Barneche, F.
, 
Ahmed, I.
, Lichtl´e, C., 
Gerrish, C.
, 
McQuinn, R.P.
, et al., 
2010
. 
Integrative transcript and metabolite analysis of nutritionally enhanced DEETIOLATED1 downregulated tomato fruit
. 
Plant Cell
22
, 
1190–1215
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Enfissi, E.M.
, 
Nogueira, M.
, 
Bramley, P.M.
, 
Fraser, P.D.
, 
2017
. 
The regulation of carotenoid formation in tomato fruit
. 
Plant J.
89
, 
774–788
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Enfissi, E.M.
, 
Nogueira, M.
, 
D’ Ambrosio, C.
, 
Stigliani, A.L.
, 
Giorio, G.
, 
Misawa, N.
, et al., 
2019
. 
The road to astaxanthin production in tomato fruit reveals plastid and metabolic adaptation resulting in an unintended high lycopene genotype with delayed over-ripening properties
. 
Plant Biotechnol. J.
17
, 
1501–1513
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fraser, P.D.
, 
Bramley, P.M.
, 
2004
. 
The biosynthesis and nutritional uses of carotenoids
. 
Prog. Lipid Res.
43
, 
228–265
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fraser, P.D.
, 
Enfissi, E.M.
, 
Halket, J.M.
, 
Truesdale, M.R.
, 
Yu, D.
, 
Gerrish, C.
, et al., 
2007
. 
Manipulation of phytoene levels in tomato fruit: effects on isoprenoids, plastids, and intermediary metabolism
. 
Plant Cell
19
, 
3194–3211
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fraser, P.D.
, 
Pinto, M.E.S.
, 
Holloway, D.E.
, 
Bramley, P.M.
, 
2000
. 
Application of high-performance liquid chromatography with photodiode array detection to the metabolic profiling of plant isoprenoids
. 
Plant J.
24
, 
551–558
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Giri, C.C.
, 
Zaheer, M.
, 
2016
. 
Chemical elicitors versus secondary metabolite production in vitro using plant cell, tissue and organ cultures: recent trends and a sky eye view appraisal
. 
Plant Cell Tiss Org
126
, 
1–18
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Giuliano, G.
, 
Giliberto, L.
, 
Rosati, C.
, 
2002
. 
Carotenoid isomerase: a tale of light and isomers
. 
Trends Plant Sci.
7
, 
427–429
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Isaacson, T.
, 
Ohad, I.
, 
Beyer, P.
, 
Hirschberg, J.
, 
2004
. 
Analysis in vitro of the enzyme CRTISO establishes a poly-cis-carotenoid biosynthesis pathway in plants
. 
Plant Physiol.
136
, 
4246–4255
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jia, K.-P.
, 
Dickinson, A.J.
, 
Mi, J.
, 
Cui, G.
, 
Xiao, T.T.
, 
Kharbatia, N.M.
, et al., 
2019
. 
Anchorene is a carotenoid-derived regulatory metabolite required for anchor root formation in Arabidopsis
. 
Sci. Adv.
5
, eaaw 
6787
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ma, G.
, 
Zhang, L.
, 
Matsuta, A.
, 
Matsutani, K.
, 
Yamawaki, K.
, 
Yahata, M.
, et al., 
2013
. 

Enzymatic formation of β- citraurin from β- cryptoxanthin and Zeaxanthin by carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase 
4 in
the flavedo of citrus fruit

. 
Plant Physiol.
163
, 
682–695
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Miras-Moreno, B.
, 
Pedre˜no, M.A.
, 
Fraser, P.D.
, 
Sabater-Jara, A.B.
, 
Almagro, L.
, 
2019
. 
Effect of diflufenican on total carotenoid and phytoene production in carrot suspension-cultured cells
. 
Planta
249
, 
113–122
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nisar, N.
, 
Li, L.
, 
Lu, S.
, 
Khin, N.C.
, 
Pogson, B.J.
, 
2015
. 
Carotenoid metabolism in plants
. 
Mol. Plant
8
, 
68–82
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nogueira, M.
, 
Enfissi, E.M.
, 
Almeida, J.
, 
Fraser, P.D.
, 
2018
. 
Creating plant molecular factories for industrial and nutritional isoprenoid production
. 
Curr. Opin. Biotechnol.
49
, 
80–87
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nogueira, M.
, 
Mora, L.
, 
Enfissi, E.M.
, 
Bramley, P.M.
, 
Fraser, P.D.
, 
2013
. 
Subchromoplast sequestration of carotenoids affects regulatory mechanisms in tomato lines expressing different carotenoid gene combinations
. 
Plant Cell
25
, 
4560–4579
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ochoa-Villarreal, M.
, 
Howat, S.
, 
Hong, S.
, 
Jang, M.O.
, 
Jin, Y.-W.
, 
Lee, E.-K.
, et al., 
2016
. 
Plant cell culture strategies for the production of natural products
. 
BMB Rep.
49
, 
149
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Price, E.J.
, 
Bhattacharjee, R.
, 
Lopez-Montes, A.
, 
Fraser, P.D.
, 
2017
. 

Metabolite profiling of yam (
Dioscorea spp.
) accessions for use in crop improvement programmes

. 
Metabolomics
13
, 
144
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Price, E.J.
, 
Wilkin, P.
, 
Sarasan, V.
, 
Fraser, P.D.
, 
2016
. 

Metabolite profiling of 
Dioscorea
(yam) species reveals underutilised biodiversity and renewable sources for high-value compounds

. 
Sci. Rep.
6
, 
29136
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ramel, F.
, 
Birtic, S.
, 
Ginies, C.
, 
Soubigou-Taconnat, L.
, 
Triantaphylides, C.
, 
Havaux, M.
, 
2012
. 
Carotenoid oxidation products are stress signals that mediate gene responses to singlet oxygen in plants
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
109
, 
5535–5540
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ramirez-Estrada, K.
, 
Vidal-Limon, H.
, 
Hidalgo, D.
, 
Moyano, E.
, 
Golenioswki, M.
, Cusido´, R., et al., 
2016
. 
Elicitation, an effective strategy for the biotechnological production of bioactive high-added value compounds in plant cell factories
. 
Molecules
21
, 
182
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rizzello, F.
, 
De Paolis, A.
, 
Durante, M.
, 
Blando, F.
, 
Mita, G.
, 
Caretto, S.
, 
2014
. 

Enhanced production of bioactive isoprenoid compounds from cell suspension cultures of 
Artemisia annua
L. using β- cyclodextrins

. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
15
, 
19092–19105
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rodrigo, M.J.
, 
Alquezar, B.
, 
Alos, E.
, 
Medina, V.
, 
Carmona, L.
, 
Bruno, M.
, et al., 
2013
. 

A novel carotenoid cleavage activity involved in the biosynthesis of 
Citrus
fruitspecific apocarotenoid pigments

. 
J. Exp. Bot.
64
, 
4461–4478
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ronen, G.
, 
Carmel-Goren, L.
, 
Zamir, D.
, 
Hirschberg, J.
, 
2000
. 
An alternative pathway to β- carotene formation in plant chromoplasts discovered by map-based cloning of Beta and old-gold color mutations in tomato
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
97
, 
11102–11107
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Ruiz-Sola, M
.A

´., Rodríguez-Concepci´on, M., 
2012
. 
Carotenoid Biosynthesis in Arabidopsis: a Colorful Pathway
, vol. 
10
. The Arabidopsis book/American Society of Plant Biologists.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Santos, R.B.
, 
Abranches, R.
, 
Fischer, R.
, 
Sack, M.
, 
Holland, T.
, 
2016
. 
Putting the spotlight back on plant suspension cultures
. 
Front. Plant Sci.
7
, 
297
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Schaub, P.
, 
Wust, F.
, 
Koschmieder, J.
, 
Yu, Q.
, 
Virk, P.
, 
Tohme, J.
, et al., 
2017
. 
Nonenzymatic β- carotene degradation in provitamin A-biofortified crop plants
. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
65
, 
6588–6598
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Simkin, A.J.
, 
Schwartz, S.H.
, 
Auldridge, M.
, 
Taylor, M.G.
, 
Klee, H.J.
, 
2004
. 
The tomato carotenoid cleavage dioxygenase 1 genes contribute to the formation of the flavor volatiles β- ionone, pseudoionone, and geranylacetone
. 
Plant J.
40
, 
882–892
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sun, T.
, 
Yuan, H.
, 
Cao, H.
, 
Yazdani, M.
, 
Tadmor, Y.
, 
Li, L.
, 
2018
. 
Carotenoid metabolism in plants: the role of plastids
. 
Mol. Plant
11
, 
58–74
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tan, B.C.
, 
Joseph, L.M.
, 
Deng, W.T.
, 
Liu, L.
, 
Li, Q.B.
, 
Cline, K.
, et al., 
2003
. 
Molecular characterization of the Arabidopsis 9-cis epoxycarotenoid dioxygenase gene family
. 
Plant J.
35
, 
44–56
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, C.
, 
Zeng, J.
, 
Li, Y.
, 
Hu, W.
, 
Chen, L.
, 
Miao, Y.
, et al., 
2014
. 

Enrichment of provitamin A content in wheat (
Triticum aestivum
L.) by introduction of the bacterial carotenoid biosynthetic genes CrtB and CrtI

. 
J. Exp. Biol.
65
, 
2545–2556
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, J.Y.
, 
Haider, I.
, 
Jamil, M.
, 
Fiorilli, V.
, 
Saito, Y.
, 
Mi, J.
, et al., 
2019
. 
The apocarotenoid metabolite zaxinone regulates growth and strigolactone biosynthesis in rice
. 
Nat. Commun.
10
, 
810
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
West, K.P.
, 
Darnton-Hill, I.
, 
2008
. 
Vitamin A Deficiency. Nutrition and Health in Developing Countries
. 
Springer
, pp. 
377–433
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wilson, S.A.
, 
Roberts, S.C.
, 
2012
. 
Recent advances towards development and commercialization of plant cell culture processes for the synthesis of biomolecules
. 
Plant Biotechnol. J.
10
, 
249–268
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, C.-J.
, 
Fraser, P.D.
, 
Wang, W.-J.
, 
Bramley, P.M.
, 
2006
. 
Differences in the carotenoid content of ordinary citrus and lycopene-accumulating mutants
. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
54
, 
5474–5481
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ye, X.
, 
Al-Babili, S.
, Kloti ¨, A., 
Zhang, J.
, 
Lucca, P.
, 
Beyer, P.
, et al., 
2000
. 
Engineering the provitamin A (β- carotene) biosynthetic pathway into (carotenoid-free) rice endosperm
. 
Science
287
, 
303–305
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zheng, X.
, 
Giuliano, G.
, 
Al-Babili, S.
, 
2020
. 

Carotenoid biofortification in crop plants: 
citius, altius, fortius

. 
Biochim. Biophys. Acta Mol. Cell Biol. Lipids
, 158664. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.bbalip.2020.158664
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zheng, X.
, 
Zhu, K.
, 
Sun, Q.
, 
Zhang, W.
, 
Wang, X.
, 
Cao, H.
, et al., 
2019
. 

Natural variation in 
CCD4
promoter underpins species-specific evolution of red coloration in citrus peel

. 
Mol. Plant
12
, 
1294–1307
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
