<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113085</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Constituents promoting osteogenesis from the fruits of Psoralea corylifolia and their structure-activity relationship study</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form compounds</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form dihydrofuran</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Constituents promoting osteogenesis from the fruits of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
and their structure-activity relationship study

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Qingxia Xu, Youbo Zhang, Zichao He, Zhenyu Liu, Yingtao Zhang, Wei Xu, XiuWei Yang
*
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

State Key Laboratory of Natural and Biomimetic Drugs (
Peking
University), 
Department of Natural Medicines
, 
School of Pharmaceutical Sciences
, 
Peking
University Health Science Center, 
Peking
University, 
Beijing
, 100191, PR 
China
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:
</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Leguminosae</p>
         <p>Phytoestrogen</p>
         <p>Promoting osteogenesis</p>
         <p>MC3T3-E1 cells</p>
         <p>Structure-activity relationship</p>
         <p>Surface plasmon resonance</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
The mature fruit of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
L. is a common traditional Chinese medicine used to tonify the kidney and yang, and as well as to treat osteoporosis. Systematic phytochemical investigations have established the most comprehensive constituent library to date, covering over 180 compounds. In this study, 109 chemical constituents containing 37 undescribed compounds were reported and incorrect structures of four known coumarins were corrected. The structures of these undescribed compounds were elucidated using spectroscopic methods, single-crystal X-ray diffraction, Rh 
2
(OCOCF 
3
) 
4
and Mo 
2
(OAc) 
4
-induced circular dichroism spectra. To identify potentially active compounds and investigate their structure-activity relationship (SAR), 89 constituents in the library were evaluated for their osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation activities in MC3T3-E1 cells. We found that coumarins, isoflavones, flavonones, and meroterpenoids were the material basis for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
-based treatment of osteoporosis, with some compounds exhibiting excellent activities. These compounds function via the estrogen receptor (ER) pathway and were natural phytoestrogen. Further SAR analysis showed that compounds with an intact isopentenyl replacement possessed superior activities, which was explained by their improved affinity with the ER.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
Osteoporosis is a systemic bone disease characterised by reduced bone mass, impaired bone quality, and decreased bone strength, which causes bone fragility and fracture (

). Osteoporosis is a common disease among older women (

); indeed, one third of women over the age of 50 will suffer from osteoporosis (

). owing to its insidious onset, symptoms of osteoporosis do not manifest until the fracture occurs, thus posing a serious threat to women’ s health (

). Osteoporosis is associated with decreased estrogen levels in postmenopausal women (

). Estrogen plays important roles in bone resorption and formation in many ways (

). It activates the Wnt/β- catenin signalling pathway, which promotes the differentiation and maturation of bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells (BMSCs) into osteoblasts (

; 

). Moreover, estrogen inhibits the levels of osteoclast differentiation factors IL-1, IL-6, IL-7, and TNF-α, and induces osteoclast apoptosis through the Fasl pathway (

). And estrogen affects differentiation by regulating the ratio of RANKL/OPG (

). Therefore, estrogen replacement therapy (ERT) is the preferred treatment for early menopause. ERT supplements help relieve menopause-associated symptoms, but simultaneously bring some adverse effects, such as the increasing risk of breast cancer and stroke (

). For this reason, researchers are committed to seeking estrogen substitutes, among which phytoestrogen (PE), a mild estrogen analogue, has become a research hotspot (

).
</p>
         <p>
The mature fruit of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (Leguminosae) is a common traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) used to tonify the kidney and yang, and to treat colitis, pollakiuria, osteoporosis, eczema and leucoderma (

). It is also used as a natural food additive (

). Kidney-tonifying TCM is used for the treatment of osteoporosis, based on the TCM theory that bone growth depends on the nourishment of kidney essence (

). PE from fruits of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
. is the material basis for anti-osteoporosis. For example, psoralidin promotes osteogenesis and inhibits the adipogenesis of BMSCs, while suppressing bone loss in ovariectomised rats (

; 

). Meanwhile neobavaisoflavone inhibits osteoclastogenesis, promotes osteogenesis, and ameliorates bone loss in ovariectomised mice (

).
</p>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>
E-mail address:
xwyang@bjmu.edu.cn (X. Yang).
</p>
         <p>
However, studies on the anti-osteoporosis effects of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
have mostly focused on its main constituents, such as psoralen, isopsoralen, psoralidin, neobavaisoflavone, bavachin, bavachalcone, and isobavachalcone. Systematic studies on anti-osteoporosis compounds from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
and their structure-activity relationship (SAR) are lacking. Thus, this study aimed to carry out a systematic phytochemical analysis on 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
to establish a comprehensive constituent library and evaluate the effects of chemical constituents on differentiation and mineralisation of MC3T3-E1 cells. Furthermore, SAR was discussed, which was explained by surface plasmon resonance (SPR) experiments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Structure elucidation
</title>
         <p>
With the aim of identifying the anti-osteoporosis constituents of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
, a systematic phytochemical study was carried out. Plant material (
47.9 kg
) was extracted with 70% ethanol. The crude extract was partitioned successively with cyclohexane (cHe), ethyl acetate (EtOAc), and normal butanol (
n
-BuOH). The EtOAc extract was separated using various column chromatography methods. Fortunately, diverse structures were obtained. In our previous study, four flavonones and chalcones (

), 17 heterodimers of meroterpene phenol (

), and 22 meroterpene phenols (

) were identified. In this study, we report a further109 compounds (
1–109
) (
Fig. S1
), containing 37 undescribed compounds (1–6, 18–33, 53–60, 74–75, 94, 103–105, 106) (
Fig. 1
). The identified compounds included 17 coumarins (
1–17
), 35 isoflavones (18–52), 21 flavonones (53–73), 20 chalcones (74–93), 6 flavones (94–99), 3 benzofurans (
100–102
), 3 chromones (
103–105
), 2 isoflavanols (106 and 107), and 2 glycosides (108 and 109). Herein, the structures of undescribed compounds were elucidated and the structures of some coumarins (
7–10
) were corrected.
</p>
         <p>
Bavacoumestan F (
1
) was obtained as a white amorphous powder, and its molecular formula was established as C 
20
H 
14
O 
6
via negative HRESIMS at 
m/z
349.0709 [M – H] 
–
(calcd for 349.0712), indicating 14 degrees of unsaturation. The 
1
H NMR data (Table S1) showed an ABX coupled system at 
δ
H
7.20 (s), 6.98 (d, 8.4) and 7.74 (d, 8.4), and three aromatic protons at 
δ
H
8.20 (s), 7.86 (s) and 6.86 (s). The 
13
C NMR (Table S2) and 2D NMR spectra revealed 20 carbons, including 17 olefinic carbons, two methyl carbons, and one oxygenated quaternary carbon. NMR and HR-ESI-MS analyses revealed a coumarin structure derived from psoralidin (
13
). The key HMBC correlation (
Fig. 2
) was reported from H-8 at 
δ
H
7.86 to C-10 at 
δ
C
108.7, rather than C-1 
′
at 
δ
C
114.5 (

), and confined the connection position of the isopentenyl group at C-6. The isopentenyl group was cyclised to generate a furan ring via chemical shifts at 
δ
C
167.4 for C-2 
′′
and at 
δ
C
100.3 for C-3 
′′
. The HMBC correlations from H-5 
′′
/H-6 
′′
at 
δ
H
1.55 to C-4 
′′
at 
δ
C
67.8 suggested a hydroxyl group at C-4 
′′
. Thus, the structure was successfully constructed (
Fig. 1
), which was supported by X-ray crystallographic data (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
Bavacoumestan G (
2
), a white amorphous powder, possessed the molecular formula C 
22
H 
20
O 
7
. Its 
1
H and 
13
C NMR spectra (Tables S1 and S2) showed similar signals and splitting patterns to those of bavacoumestan C (

) and 
epi
-bavacoumestan C (

). However, signals of the ethyl group at 
δ
H
3.73 and 
δ
H
1.17 were observed, and it was combined to C-3 
′′
by key HMBC correlations from H–OCH 
2
CH
3
at 
δ
H
3.73 to C-3 
′′
at 
δ
C
77.9 (
Fig. 2
). The key HMBC correlation from H-8 at 
δ
H
7.12 to C-10 at 
δ
C
105.5 indicated that the isopentenyl group was located at C-6. Accordingly, the structure of compound 2 was established. The relative configurations of C-2 
′′
and C-3 
′′
were constructed as 
trans
by the small coupling constant (
J
′′ 
2,3
′′ = 2.8 Hz) (

; 

). Interestingly, the NMR data of compounds 8 and 9 were the same as those of bavacoumestan C and 
epi
-bavacoumestan C, respectively (Table S13). However, further HMBC analysis showed cross-peaks of H-8 (
δ
H
7.06 for 8, 
δ
H
7.06 for 9) and C-10 (
δ
C
105.6 for 8, 
δ
C
105.8 for 9), indicating that their isopentenyl groups were combined on C-6 instead of C-5’. We found that the chemical shifts at C-10 and C-1 
′
were mistakenly assigned to bavacoumestan C and 
epi
-bavacoumestan C (

; 

). In fact, the chemical shifts of C-10 were 105.3 and 106.1 ppm, and the chemical shifts of C-1 
′
were 
δ
C
114.5 and 115.0 ppm. This indicated that the isopentenyl groups were located at C- 
6 in
bavacoumestan C and 
epi
-bavacoumestan C (
Fig. 1
). In the same manner, we redefined the structures of compounds 7 (bavacoumestan B) and 10 using HMBC experiments. We first reported the 
13
C NMR data of 10 and named it bavacoumestan L. Fortunately, we could successfully cultivate crystals of 7 and 8, and their crystal structures (
Fig. 3
) were undoubtedly consistent with the above-mentioned analysis. Ultimately, the absolute configuration of 2 was confirmed as 2 
′′
S
,3 
′′
S
based on its biosynthesis relationship with bavacoumestan B (
7
).
</p>
         <p>
Bavacoumestan H (
3
) and bavacoumestan I (
4
) were assigned the molecular formula C 
20
H 
16
O 
7
on the basis of HR-ESI-MS at 
m/z
367.0816 [M – H] 
–
(calcd for 367.0818) and at 
m/z
369.0968 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for 369.0974), revealing 13 degrees of unsaturation. Their 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR spectra (Tables S1 and S2) highly overlapped with those of psoralidin (
13
), indicating their similar coumarin structures. The isopentenyl groups were located at C-6, as proved by the key HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
) from H-8 (
δ
H
6.99 for 3; 
δ
H
7.14 for 4) to C-10 (
δ
C
105.1 for 3; 
δ
C
108.1 for 4), and were cyclised based on their degrees of unsaturation. The presence of a dihydrofuran ring in 3 was confirmed by the C-2 
′′
chemical shift at 
δ
C
87.9, and 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlation between H-2 
′′
at 
δ
H
4.93 and H-3 
′′
at 
δ
H
3.35/3.22. However, only one methyl group at 
δ
H
1.14 was observed, along with a hydroxyl methylene group at 
δ
H
3.35. Accordingly, the structure of 3 was constructed as shown in 
Fig. 1
. The configuration of C-2 
′′
was assigned as 
S
by its biosynthesis relationship with bavacoumestan B. The positive Cotton effect at 
295 nm
and 
393 nm
(
Fig. S6
) assigned the chirality of C-4 
′′
as 
S
based on the Mo 
2
(OAc) 
4
-induced circular dichroism (ICD) method (

). Thus, the absolute configuration of 3 was determined as 2 
′′
S
,4 
′′
S
. Similarly, a hydroxyl methylene group replaced a methyl group in 4 based on its’ NMR data, but the methylene group was linked to C-7 by an ether bond, which was supported by key HMBC correlations from H-2 
′′
at 
δ
H
3.84 (d, 12.0) and 3.69 (d, 12.0) to C-7 at 
δ
H
162.2. In the NOESY spectrum of 4, the correlation of 
CH
3
-6 
′′
at 
δ
H
1.25 and H-4 
′′
at 
δ
H
3.59 indicated their 
cis
orientations (
Fig. S2
). Furthermore, the absolute configuration of 4 was assigned as 3 
′′
R
,4 
′′
S
by the positive Cotton effect on 
291 nm
and 
372 nm
in the Mo 
2
(OAc) 
4
-ICD spectrum (
Fig. S6
). Thus, the structure of 4 was established as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of bavacoumestan J (
5
), a white amorphous powder, was confirmed to be C 
20
H 
16
O 
6.
NMR data (Tables S1 and S2) analysis showed a coumarin skeleton. However, a terminal double bond replaced the methyl group of the isopentenyl group, and a hydroxylation reaction occurred at C-2 
′′
via HMBC cross-peaks between H-4 
′′
at 
δ
H
4.83/4.72 and C-2 
′′
at 
δ
C
73.5. The isopentenyl moiety was linked to C-6 via the HMBC correlation from H-8 at 
δ
H
6.90 to C-10 at 
δ
C
103.6 (
Fig. 2
). The absolute configuration of 2 
′′
S
was assigned by positive Cotton effect at 
302 nm
(Fig. S7) in the Rh 
2
(OCOCF 
3
) 
4
-ICD spectrum (

). Accordingly, we established the structure of 5.
</p>
         <p>
Bavacoumestan K (
6
) possessed the molecular formula C 
20
H 
18
O 
8
and was also a coumarin. Three hydroxyl groups were combined at C-1 
′′
, C-2 
′′
and C-3 
′′
via chemical shifts at 
δ
C
68.9, 79.2 and 73.5 (Tables S1 and S2) and HMBC correlations from H-4 
′′
at 
δ
H
1.21 to C-2 
′′
/C-3 
′′
. However, the isopentenyl group was not cyclised based on 12 degrees of unsaturation. Similarly, based on HMBC analysis, it was connected to the C-6 position. Furthermore, the coupling constant value (
J
′′ 
1,2
′′ =7.9 Hz) (

) assigned 
threo
configuration of OH-1 
′′
and OH-2 
′′
. Thus, we established the structure of 6.
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavone A (
18
), a white amorphous powder, was assigned the molecular formula C 
17
H 
10
O 
4
on the basis of HR-ESI-MS data at 
m/z
277.0501 [M – H] (calcd for 277.0503), indicating 13 degrees of unsaturation. The 
1
H NMR data (Table S3) of this compound contained two groups of ABX coupling system, which were 
δ
H
7.91 (1H, d, 
J
=9.0 Hz, H-5), 6.75 (1H, dd, 
J
=9.0, 2.2 Hz, H-6) and 6.56 (1H, d, 
J
=2.2 Hz, H-8); and 
δ
H
7.76 (1H, d, 
J
=1.8 Hz, H-2 
′
), 7.53 (1H, d, 
J
=8.5 Hz, H-5 
′
) and 7.44 (1H, dd, 
J
= 8.5, 1.8 Hz, H-6 
′
). The 
13
C NMR data (Table S4) and HSQC spectra showed the presence of a carbonyl carbon at 
δ
C
178.4 and an alkenyl carbon at 
δ
C
154.7. Based on the above-mentioned analysis, this compound was considered an isoflavone. The H–H COSY spectrum showed two coupled protons (
J
= 2.2 Hz) at 7.76 (H-2 
′′
) and 6.87 (H-3 
′′
), which indicated a benzofuran ring. Thus, the structure of compound 18, named bavaisoflavone A, was established, as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of bavaisoflavone B (
19
) was determined to be C 
20
H 
14
O 
4
based on the HR-ESI-MS ion at 
m/z
319.0966 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for 319.0970). The 
1
H NMR and the 
13
C NMR data (Tables S3 and S4) of this compound were higly similar to those of compound 18, which suggested the same isoflavone skeleton of compound 19. Their differences were the presence of an allyl group, which was connected to the furan ring on the basis of the HMBC correlation (
Fig. 2
) from H-5 
′′
at 
δ
H
5.77 to C-2 
′′
at 134.4. Finally, the structure of compound 19 was confirmed, and it was named bavaisoflavone B. Bavaisoflavone C (
20
) and bavaisoflavone D (
21
) were assigned the molecular formulas C 
20
H 
16
O 
5
and C 
21
H 
18
O 
5
, respectively. NMR data (Tables S3 and S4) showed that they shared the same furan-containing prenylated isoflavone as compound 19. Based on two methyl signals at 
δ
C
29.3 in
compound 20 or 
δ
C
25.3 in
compound 21, a propyl fragment was added on C-2 
′′
. The C-4 
′′
carbons were hydroxylated via key HMBC correlations from 
CH
3
to C-4 
′′
at 
δ
C
67.9 (
20
) or 
δ
C
73.1 (
21
) (
Fig. 2
). Furthermore, a methoxy group was combined to C-4 
′′
via the HMBC correlation from OCH 
3
at 
δ
H
3.01 to C-4 
′′
at 
73.1 in
compound 21. Therefore, the structures of the two compounds were determined, as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavone E (
22
) was assigned the molecular formula C 
20
H 
18
O 
6
, indicating 12 degrees of unsaturation. With NMR data (Tables S3 and S4), the compound was identified as a prenylated isoflavone with dihydrofuran, and it had a planar structure similar to that of corylifol E (
34
) (

). However, the coupling constant (
J
′′ 
2,3
′′ =6.1 Hz) of compound 22 was different from that (
J
′′ 
2,3"
=3.7 Hz) of corylifol E (
34
), indicating a 
cis
configuration of the two protons (

; 

). The chiral centre of compound 35 (Corylifol D) at the C-2 
′′
position was deduced to be 
R
by the negative optical value ([
α
]25 D 16.00) (

). Therefore, the absolute configuration of 22 was established as 2 
′′
R
,3 
′′
S
based on their biogenetic synthesis relationships.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of bavaisoflavone F (
23
) was identified as C 
20
H 
18
O 
5
based on HR-ESI-MS analysis, indicating 12 degrees of unsaturation. Similarly, the presence of a carbonyl carbon at 
δ
C
175.3 and an alkenyl carbon at 
δ
C
153.1 (Tables S3 and S4) suggested the isoflavone skeleton of compound 23. However, there was only one ABX coupling system, where 
δ
H
7.05 (1H, d, 
J
=2.0 Hz, H-2 
′
), 6.83 (1H, dd, 
J
= 8.0, 2.0 Hz, H-6 
′
) and 6.78 (1H, d, 
J
=8.0 Hz, H-5 
′
) were observed. And 
δ
C
at 145.0 and 145.6 seemingly indicated a group of adjacent dihydroxy in the B-ring. Furthermore, there was another group of aromatic orthocoupled protons (
J
= 8.8 Hz) for 
δ
H
7.85 (H-5) and 7.00 (H-6), whose HMBC correlations to C-4 at 
δ
C
175.3 were observed (
Fig. 2
). An isopentenyl group was attached to C-8 via the HMBC correlation from H-1 
′′
at 
δ
H
3.46 to C-7 at 
δ
C
159.9. Thus, the structure of 23 was established, as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavone G (
24
) was assigned the molecular formula C 
20
H 
18
O 
5
based on the HR-ESI-MS ion at 
m/z
339.1230 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for 339.1232). Its NMR data (Tables S3 and S4) were similar to those of daidzein (
44
) (

) except for an isopentenyl group at C-8, by HMBC cross-peaks between H-3 
′′
at 
δ
H
3.32 and C-7 at 
δ
C
165.0. However, isopentenyl was cyclised to form a dihydrofuran ring by 
1
H NMR signals at 
δ
H
4.83 (1H, t, 
J
=8.9 Hz, H-2 
′′
) and 3.32 (2H, d, 
J
=8.9 Hz, H-3 
′′
), and 
13
C NMR signals at 
δ
C
91.6 for C-2 
′′
and 27.0 for C-3 
′′
. Thus, the planar structure of 24 was constructed. The absolute configuration assigned at C-2 
′′
was 
R
by the negative optical value ([
α
]25 D 16.00) (

).
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of bavaisoflavone H (
25
) was determined to be C 
23
H 
24
O 
7
using the HR-ESI-MS ion at 
m/z
413.1595 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for 413.1600). The NMR spectra (Tables S3 and S4) of 25 showed representative isoflavone NMR signals for a carbonyl carbon at 
δ
C
178.0 and an alkenyl carbon at 
δ
C
154.7. Two equivalent aromatic protons at 
δ
H
6.82 (2H, s) and two equivalent methoxy groups at 
δ
H
3.86 (6H, s) provided crucial evidence for the conclusion that the B-ring was 1,3,4,5- substituted. Further analysis of the 2D NMR spectra indicated that isopentenyl was linked to C-8 and cyclised to form a dihydrofuran ring, and that one methoxy group at 
δ
H
3.78 combined with C-4’. However, only one methyl group of isopentenyl was observed in the NMR spectra. H–H COSY and HSQC analyses also indicated the presence of 
CH
3
– 
CH
– 
CH
2
OH. Therefore, compound 25 was identified as 4 
′
-methoxy bavarigenin.
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavone I (
26
) was assigned the molecular formula C 
25
H 
28
O 
6
by the HR-ESI-MS ion at m/z 423.1808 [M – H] (calcd for 423.1808), revealing that the compound was a variant of corylifol A (
49
) (

). In the NMR spectra (Tables S5 and S6), signals of the fragment between C-1 
′′
and C-5 
′′
highly overlapped with those of corylifol A (
49
), indicating their same structural units. However, the HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
) from 
CH
3
-8 
′′
at 
δ
H
1.09 to C-6 
′′
at 
δ
C
79.1 and C-7 
′′
at 
δ
C
74.1 determined a 6 
′′
, 7 
′′
-dihydroxyl fragment, which replaced one group of double-bond signals between C-6 
′′
and C-7 
′′
. The absolute configuration of 6 
′′
S
was assigned by a positive Cotton effect at 
305 nm
(

) in Rh 
2
(OCOCF 
3
) 
4
-ICD spectrum (Fig. S7). Therefore, the structure of compound 26 was established successfully (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
The molecular formula of bavaisoflavone J (
27
) was deduced to be C 
25
H 
26
O 
6
based on the HR-ESI-MS ion at m/z 423.1800 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for 423.1808). Further analysis of the 
1
H NMR and 
13
C NMR data (Tables S5 and S6) of 27 showed similar resonances to those of 26. The obvious differences between 26 and 27 were two groups of terminal double bonds at 
δ
H
4.93 (s) and 4.81 (s); at 
δ
H
5.05 (s) and 4.93 (s) in 27. The hydroxyl replacements were situated at C-2 
′′
and C-6 
′′
on the basis of HMBC correlations from H-10 
′′
to C-2 
′′
at 
δ
C
76.3; and from H-8 
′′
to C-6 
′′
at 
δ
C
76.6 (
Fig. 2
). However, the attempt to determine the configurations at C-2 
′′
and C-6 
′′
using Mosher’ method, was unsuccessful (
Fig. S4
). Therefore, the planar structure of 27 was proposed.
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavone K (
28
) was isolated as a yellowish amorphous powder with the molecular formula C 
25
H 
26
O 
5
based on positive HR-ESI-MS. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (Tables S5 and S6) implied that the skeleton of 28 was similar to that of neocorylin (
37
), except for the absence of the double bond at C-3 
′′
=C-4 
′′
in the pyranoid ring. The chemical shift at C-3 
′′
(
δ
C
68.9) and the HMBC correlation (
Fig. 2
) from H-3 
′′
at 
δ
H
3.84 to C-3 
′
at 121.6 showed that a hydroxyl group was located on C-3 
′′
. According to 
1
H– 
1
H COSY between H-3 
′′
and H-4 
′′
(
δ
H
3.02, 2.77), assignment of a methylene group at C-4 
′′
was obtained. The absolute configuration of C-3 
′′
was assigned as 
S
based on the positive Cotton effect at 
308 nm
(

) in the Rh 
2
(OCOCF 
3
) 
4
-ICD spectrum (Fig. S7). Finally, the structure of compound 28 was established, as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavone L (
29
) was assigned the molecular formula C 
25
H 
26
O 
6
. The NMR data (Tables S5 and S6) of 29 highly overlapped with those of 28, indicating similar planar structures. The only difference was that a hydroxyl group at C-4 
′′
was observed via 
1
H– 
1
H COSY correlation (
Fig. 2
) between H-3 
′′
at 
δ
H
3.51 and H-4 
′′
at 
δ
H
4.41, and a down-field chemical shift at 
δ
C
68.2 for C-4 
′′
. The relative configurations of OH-3 
′′
and OH-4 
′′
were assigned 
trans
on the basis of coupling constants (
J
′′ 
3,4
′′ =8.2 Hz) (

). In the NOESY spectrum of 29, the cross-peaks between H-4 
′′
and 
CH
3
-11 
′′
at 
δ
H
1.13 suggested a 
cis
-orientation (
Fig. S2
). Finally, the absolute configuration of 29 was determined as 2 
′′
R
,3 
′′
S
,4 
′′
R
according to the chirality at C-3 
′′
. Thus, the structure of 29 was established as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavone M (
30
) was obtained as yellowish amorphous powders, and its molecular formula was determined to be C 
25
H 
26
O 
6
based on HR-ESI-MS ion at 
m/z
423.1805 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for 423.1808). Similar 
1
H and 
13
C NMR signals (Tables S5 and S6) between 30 and 29 were observed with the exception of the carbon chemical shift at C-2 
′′
(
δ
C
96.3 for 30; 
δ
C
80.2 for 29). The downfield chemical shift at C-2 
′′
indicated that the geranyl moiety in corylifol A (
49
) was cyclised to form a dihydrofuran ring. The small coupling constant (
J
′′ 
2,3
′′ = 4.8 Hz) determined that the relative configurations of C-2 
′′
and C-3 
′′
were 
trans
(

; 

). The NOE correlations between H-2 
′′
at 
δ
H
4.23 and 
CH
3
-11 
′′
at 
δ
H
1.13 indicated the relative position of the methyl group (
Fig. S2
). Accordingly, the structure of 30 was constructed (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavone N (
31
) and bavaisoflavone O (
32
) shared the same molecular formulas as C 
25
H 
24
O 
5
. Their NMR data (Tables S5 and S6) were highly similar to those of neocorylin (
37
) (

), with the exception of the terminal isopentenyl group. The HMBC correlations from 
CH
3
-9 
′′
/10 
′′
at 
δ
H
1.21 to C-8 
′′
at 
δ
C
71.5 suggested the presence of a hydroxyl group on C-8 
′′
in compound 31 (
Fig. 2
). The presence of a double bond at C-6 
′′
and C-7 
′′
was supported by their carbon chemical shifts at 
δ
C
122.4 and 143.4, and the key HMBC correlation from H-6 
′′
at 
δ
H
5.66 to C-8 
′′
. Therefore, the structure of 31 was established in 
Fig. 1
. However, one terminal double bond replaced a methyl group at C-9 
′′
in compound 32, via key HMBC correlations from H-9 
′′
at 
δ
H
4.90 and 4.80 to C-10 
′′
at 
δ
C
17.9. A hydroxyl replacement at C-7 
′′
occurred via HMBC cross-peaks from H-9 
′′
to C-7 
′′
at 
δ
C
77.0. The absolute configuration of C-7 
′′
was assigned as 
S
based on the positive Cotton effect at 
300 nm
(

) in the Rh 
2
(OCOCF 
3
) 
4
-ICD spectrum (Fig. S7). Accordingly, the structure of 32 was constructed.
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavone P (
33
), a white amorphous powder, possessed the molecular formula C 
25
H 
26
O 
5
, as determined via positive HR-ESI-MS. The typical aromatic 
1
H and 
13
C NMR signals (Tables S5 and S6) suggested an isoflavone skeleton. However, the geranyl moiety NMR signals showed great differences from those of corylifol A (
49
) (

), where ten sp 
3
hybridised carbons remained, except for 15 aromatic carbons. The 
13
C and HSQC spectra indicated that ten sp 
3
hybridised carbons contained three methyls, three methylenes, two methenyls and two quaternary carbons. The key HMBC cross-peaks (
Fig. 2
) from H-8 
′′
at 
δ
H
0.94 to C-2 
′′
at 
δ
C
53.6; from H-1 
′′
at 
δ
H
2.53 to C-7 
′′
at 
δ
C
45.6, established the connection bond from C-7 
′′
to C-2 
′′
. However, an additional degree of unsaturation was in accordance with the molecular formula of 33, which indicated the presence of another ring. Further analysis showed that the epoxy bridge between C-3 
′′
at 
δ
C
86.6 and C-6 
′′
at 
δ
C
85.4 was required to meet 13 degrees of unsaturation and two rings. Thus, a structure was proposed. Fortunately, needle crystals of 33 could be cultivated from a mixed solvent of 
CH
3
OH and H 
2
O after various attempts. Then X-ray diffraction analysis defined the absolutely configuration of 33 as 2 
′′
R
,3 
′′
S
,6 
′′
R
. (
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>
Bavachinone C (
53
) was isolated as a white amorphous powder. Its molecular formula was C 
20
H 
18
O 
5
as determined via HR-ESI-MS at 
m/z
339.1227 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for 339.1232). Upon analyzing its NMR data (Tables S7 and S8), 
1
H NMR signals at 
δ
H
5.51 (1H, dd, 
J
=13.0, 3.0 Hz), 
δ
H
3.27 (1H, dd, 
J
= 17.0, 13.0 Hz) and 
δ
H
2.77 (1H, dd, 
J
= 17.0, 3.0 Hz), and the carbonyl signal at 
δ
C
192.0 indicated the flavonone skeleton of 53. Singlet proton signals at 
δ
H
8.03 (1H, s) and 
δ
H
7.21 (1H, s) assigned to the A ring, showed that the isopentenyl group was combined with C-6. The key HMBC correlations (
Fig. 2
) from 
CH
3
-5 
′′
/ 
CH
3
-6 
′′
at 
δ
H
1.50 to C-2 
′′
at 
δ
C
166.1 suggested the presence of a furan ring, along with 12 degrees of unsaturation. Therefore, the structure of compound 53 was established as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Bavachinone D (
54
) was assigned the molecular formula C 
17
H 
12
O 
4
based on HR-ESI-MS at 
m/z
279.0660 [M – H] 
–
(calcd for 279.0657). Representative 
1
H and 
13
C NMR patterns (Tables S7 and S8) of 54 showed a flavonone structure. However, methyl groups from the isopentenyl group were not observed. As elucidated from its molecular formula, compound 54 lost a propyl group, and an unsubstituted furan ring remained. Ortho-coupling protons (
J
= 8.8 Hz) at 
δ
H
7.82 and 
δ
H
7.20 in
ring A, made the furan ring locate on C-8. Thus, the structure of 54 was constructed and named bavachinone D.
</p>
         <p>
Bavachinone E (
55
), a white amorphous powder, possessed the molecular formula C 
20
H 
20
O 
6
, as determined via HR-ESI-MS at 
m/z
357.1333 [M +H] 
+
(calcd for 357.1338). The NMR data (Tables S7 and S8) of 55 were highly similar to those of bavachinone A (
63
) (

), except for the 3 
′′
-hydroxyl group. The protons at C-2 
′′
and C-3 
′′
were at a 
trans
orientation by the small coupling constant (
J
′′ 
2,3
′′ = 4.0 Hz) (

; 

). Furthermore, the absolute configuration of 55 was assigned 2 
′′
S
,3 
′′
S
based on the configuration of bavachinone A (
63
). In summary, the structure of 55 was determined, as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Bavachinone F (
56
) was isolated as a white amorphous powder with a molecular formula of C 
20
H 
18
O 
5
, indicating 12 degrees of unsaturation. NMR data analysis (Tables S7 and S8) showed that its structure was similar to that of anhydrobavachinone A (

). However, a hydroxyl group at C-5 was observed via key HMBC correlations from H-3 
′′
at 
δ
H
2.90 and 
δ
H
2.77 to C-5 at 
δ
C
163.4 (
Fig. 2
). The absolute configuration was determined as 2 
′′
S
from biogenetic synthesis. Accordingly, the structure of compound 56 was established. The molecular formula of bavachinone G (
57
), a white amorphous powder, was confirmed to be C 
20
H 
18
O 
5
. Based on NMR data (Tables S7 and S8), the structure of 57 was similar to that of 56, except for isopentenyl cyclisation. Undoubtedly, a pyranoid ring was formed by the coupling constant value (
J
′′ 
3,4
′′ = 10.1 Hz) and corresponding chemical shifts (
δ
C
127.3 at C-3 
′′
and 
δ
C
115.7 at C-4 
′′
). Therefore, the structure of 57 was constructed, and named bavachinone G.
</p>
         <p>
Bavachinone H (
58
) was obtained as a white amorphous powder, and its molecular formula was determined to be C 
21
H 
22
O 
5
. As elucidated from NMR data (Tables S7 and S8), 58 was derived from bavachinin (
111
) (

). The main differences in the NMR signals of these two compounds were the presence of two ortho coupling protons (
J
= 11.9 Hz) at 
δ
H
5.00 and 
δ
H
4.51, and a down-field chemical shift value at 
δ
C
74.8 for C- 
3 in
58. The NMR analysis indicated that compound 58 was a flavanonol. According to the coupling constant values (
J
2,3
=11.9 Hz) (

), the 3-hydroxyl group and 2-phenyl group were in the 
trans
orientation. Accordingly, the absolute configuration of 58 was determined as 2 
R
,3 
R
and it was named bavachinone G.
</p>
         <p>
Bavachinone I (
59
) possessed the molecular formula C 
17
H 
16
O 
5
, revealing 10 degrees of unsaturation. The NMR spectra (Tables S7 and S8) showed the classical flavonone signals. However, NMR signals of the isopentenyl group were not observed. Further analysis showed that a methyl group was added on C-7 via the HMBC correlation from 
CH
3
at 
δ
H
3.88 to C-7 at 
δ
C
165.5 (
Fig. 2
). The cross-peaks between 
CH
2
OH at 
δ
H
4.55 and C-5 at 
δ
C
126.0/C-7 indicated that a hydroxymethyl group was linked to C-6. Thus, the structure of 59 was established, as shown in 
Fig. 1
.
</p>
         <p>
Bavachinone J (
60
) had the molecular formula C 
21
H 
24
O 
7
. Upon combining its NMR data (Tables S7 and S8), it was inferred that compound 60 was a flavonone. A methyl group was combined on C-7 by the key HMBC correlation from 
CH
3
at 
δ
H
3.83 to C-7 at 
δ
C
165.1 (
Fig. 2
). Three hydroxyl groups were added at C-1 
′′
, C-2 
′′
, and C-3 
′′
via chemical shifts at 
δ
C
68.0, 78.5, and 75.1 and HMBC correlations. According to the coupling constant value (
J
′′ 
1,2
′′ = 3.7 Hz) (

), the configurations of OH-1 
′′
and OH-2 
′′
were assigned 
erythro
. In this way, we established the structure of 60, and named it bavachinone J.
</p>
         <p>
Psorachalcone B (
74
) was isolated as a yellow amorphous powder, and its molecular formula was determined to be C 
21
H 
22
O 
6
based on HR-ESI-MS at 
m/z
369.1340 [M – H] 
–
(calcd for 369.1338). In theNMR spectra (Table S9) of 74, a group of signals of 
trans
double bond (
J
= 15.2 Hz) at 
δ
H
7.81 and 7.61 was observed, along with a carbonyl signal at 
δ
C
194.3, indicating a chalcone structure (

). The remaining aromatic signals contained two groups of ortho coupling proton, namely 
δ
H
7.62 (
J
= 8.6 Hz) and 
δ
H
6.84 assigned to ring B, as well as 
δ
H
8.11 (
J
= 8.9 Hz) and 
δ
H
6.50 assigned to ring A. The above analysis showed the presence of an isopentenyl group on C-3’. The isopentenyl group was cyclised to form a dihydrofuran ring with hydroxyl substitutions at C-3 
′′
and C-4 
′′
on the basis of their chemical shift values at 
δ
C
80.8 and 
δ
C
71.9. The HMBC correlation (
Fig. 2
) from 
CH
3
at 
δ
H
3.52 to C-3 
′′
at 
δ
C
80.8 showed the linkage position of the methyl group at C-3 
′′
. Then, the relative configurations of C-2 
′′
and C-3 
′′
were assigned 
trans
by the coupling constant values (
J
′′ 
2,3
′′ =2.3 Hz) (

; 

). Thus, the structure of 74 was established.
</p>
         <p>
Psorachalcone C (
75
), a yellow amorphous powder, was assigned the molecular formula C 
21
H 
24
O 
7
. The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data (Table S9) showed that compound 75 was a chalcone. Singlet proton signals at 
δ
H
8.17 (1H, s) and 
δ
H
6.24 (1H, s) assigned to the A ring determined it as a 1,2,4,5-tetrasubstituted benzene ring. A methyl group was added on C-4 
′
via HMBC cross-peaks between 
CH
3
at 
δ
H
3.70 and C-4 
′
at 
δ
C
167.0 (
Fig. 2
). Hydroxyl substitutions occurred at C-1 
′′
, C-2 
′′
and C-3 
′′
by their chemical shifts at 
δ
C
68.5, 78.5 and 75.3, respectively. The configurations of OH-1 
′′
and OH-2 
′′
were determined to be 
erythro
based on the broad single peak characteristics (

) of H-1 
′′
and H-2 
′′
in the 
1
H NMR spectrum. Accordingly, the structure of 75 was constructed.
</p>
         <p>
Bavaflavone A (
94
) was isolated as a yellow amorphous powder and assigned the molecular formula C 
20
H 
18
O 
6
on the basis of HR-ESI-MS at m/z 355.1186 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for 355.1182). The flavone nature of compound 94 was supported by representative NMR signals (Table S10) at 
δ
C
184.7 for C-4 and 
δ
C
148.2 for C-2. Ortho-coupling proton signals (
J
= 8.5 Hz) at 
δ
H
7.58 and 
δ
H
6.70 were assigned to ring A, which was supported by the key HMBC correlation between H-5 at 
δ
H
7.58 and C-4 at 
δ
C
184.7 (
Fig. 2
). Additionally, we also observed a group of 1,3,4- trisubstituted benzene ring signals at 
δ
H
7.52, 
δ
H
7.22 and 
δ
H
6.83 belonging to ring B. Furthermore, HMBC correlations from H-1 
′′
at 
δ
H
3.38 to C-9 at 
δ
C
164.3 indicated that an isopentenyl group was added on C-8. Isopentenyl was cyclised to a dihydrofuran ring through C 
2
′′–O–C 
7
on the basis of carbon chemical shifts (
δ
C
93.5 at C-2 
′′
and 
δ
C
27.7 at C-3 
′′
) and 12 degrees of unsaturation. A hydroxyl group was added on C-4 
′′
via HMBC correlations between 
CH
3
-5 
′′
/6 
′′
at 
δ
H
1.33/1.28 and C-4 
′′
at 
δ
C
72.6. Accordingly, the structure of 94 was established and its’ absolutely configuration was confirmed as 2 
′′
R
by the optical value ([
α
]25 D 74.4) (

).
</p>
         <p>
Bavachromone A (
103
), a white amorphous powder, possessed the molecular formula C 
14
H 
14
O 
3
, as determined via HR-ESI-MS at 
m/z
229.0866 [M – H] 
–
(calcd for 229.0865), indicating 8 degrees of unsaturation. A pair of coupling protons (
J
2,3
=6.0 Hz) (Table S11) at 
δ
H
8.00 for H-2 and 
δ
H
6.23 for H-3 were shown in 
1
H NMR spectrum, and their cross-peaks with C-4 at 
δ
C
179.8 revealed the presence of pyrone. Upon combining its molecular formula, compound 103 was found to be a chromone with an isopentenyl group, which was linked to C-6 via the key HMBC correlation between H-1 
′
at 
δ
H
3.34 and C-5 at 
δ
C
126.4 (
Fig. 2
). Thus, the structure of 103 was determined, as shown in 
Fig. 1
. The molecular formula of bavachromone B (
104
) and bavachromone C (
105
) was determined to be C 
14
H 
14
O 
4
. Further NMR analysis suggested the same chromone skeletons as that of bavachromone A (
103
). Their structures were then established from 1D and 2D NMR spectra. A terminal double bond at C-4 
′
and a hydroxyl replacement at C-2 
′
were observed in compound 104, which was proved by chemical shifts of H-4 
′
at 
δ
H
4.85/4.76 and C-2 
′
at 
δ
C
76.5. The absolute configuration of C-2 
′
was assigned as 
R
on the basis of the negative Cotton effect at 
318 nm
(

) in the Rh 
2
(OCOCF 
3
) 
4
-ICD spectrum (Fig. S7). A dihydrofuran ring formed by isopentenyl cyclisation appeared in compound 105 according to carbon chemical shifts (
δ
C
93.1 at C-2 
′
, 
δ
C
30.5 at C-3 
′
and 
δ
C
72.5 at C-4 
′
) and 8 degrees of unsaturation. Similarly, the negative optical value ([
α
]25 D 24) of 105 assigned the chiral centre at C-2 
′
as 
R
(

).
</p>
         <p>
Bavaisoflavanol (
106
) was isolated as a white amorphous powder, and its’ molecular formula was determined to be C 
20
H 
22
O 
5
via HR-ESI-MS at 
m/z
341.1402 [M – H] 
–
(calcd for 341.1389). A set of NMR signals (Table S12) for the – 
CH
2
- 
CH
– 
CH
– fragment at 
δ
H
4.20 (1H, dd, 
J
=17.5, 11.0 Hz), 
δ
H
3.50 (1H, dd, 
J
=17.5, 11.0 Hz), 
δ
H
3.50 (1H, dd, 
J
=11.0, 5.6 Hz) and 
δ
H
5.44 (1H, br d, 
J
=5.6 Hz) were present in the 
1
H NMR spectrum, except for aromatic and isopentenyl signals. However, no carbonyl signal was observed. Therefore, the above NMR analysis indicated an isoflavanol skeleton for compound 106. Two singlet signals at 
δ
H
7.17 and 
δ
H
6.40 assigned to the A ring revealed the presence of an isopentenyl group on C-6. In addition, 1,2,4-trisubstituted aromatic ring signals were observed, and hydroxyl substitutions occurred at C-2 
′
and C-4 
′
on the basis of their chemical shifts at 
δ
C
161.8 and 
δ
C
159.6. Thus, the structure of 106 was established as shown in 
Fig. 1
. The absolute configuration was assigned as 3 
S
,4 
R
from positive Cotton effects in the CD curve at 
238 nm
(Δ 
ε
8.74) and 
290 nm
(Δ 
ε
+2.95) (
Fig. S5
) (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation activities of MC3T3-E1
</title>
         <p>
After the separation of the three extracts was completed, the isolation of more than 180 chemical constituents from the fruits of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
, allowed us to establish a rich compound library, which is the broadest coverage of the constituent library to date. Next, to identify the active compounds and investigate their SAR, 89 chemical constituents (
Fig. S1
; 
Fig. S3
and Table S16) in the library, covering all 
types
of compounds and consisting of two ones (122 and 123) from 
n
-BuOH extract (

), 80 ones from EtOAc extracts and 7 ones (
114–120
) from cHe extract (Lv et al., 2020; 

), were evaluated for their osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation activities of MC3T3-E1 cells.
</p>
         <p>
The cell viability of 89 compounds was assessed using the MTT method. As shown in Table S15, most compounds showed noncytotoxicity in the range of 0.001–20 
μ
M after 48 h of administration. According to the results of preliminary screening, the compounds were effective at 0.1, 1, and 10 
μ
M. Therefore, we chose the three concentrations for activity evaluation, and selected E2 at 0.1 
μ
M as the positive control. However, compounds 51, 115 and 116 showed cytotoxicity after 7 or 16 days of induction, as determined from low total protein concentrations and poor cell morphologies under a microscope.
</p>
         <p>
We evaluated the effects of 17 coumarins on osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation. As shown in 
Fig. 4
, Fig. S12 and Table S16, compounds 16 (psoralen) and 17 (isopsoralen) led to a two-fold increase of the amount of calcium nodules at concentrations of 1 and 10 
μ
M. Further, the activity (240.72 ± 9.43%; 224.59 ± 10.19% activation compared with control) of compound 17 was stronger than that of compound 16 (203.17 ±10.52%; 196.98 ±6.36% activation compared with control), which was probably due to similar structures between angular furanocoumarin and estrogen. However, only compound 16 increased ALP expression at 0.1 
μ
M at day 7. When the lactone ring was opened to 
<tp:taxon-name>form compounds</tp:taxon-name>
101 and 102, or compounds 122 and 123 by further glycosylation (Fig. S11), the mineralisation activity disappeared. This indicated that the furanocoumarin skeleton was necessary for activity. Compound 11 (coumestrol) significantly promoted the osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation of MC3T3-E1 cell at 10 
μ
M. However, a methoxyl substitution (
12
) at C-5 
′
of 11 resulted in reduction in its mineralisation ability. Interestingly, the replacement of the isopentenyl group at C-5 
′
to produce compound 13 (psoralidin) resulted in a two-fold increase in ALP and calcium nodules at 0.1 
μ
M. However, changes at the isopentenyl group, including, but not limited to, hydroxylation and cyclisation, led to a decreased or an absent activity. Hydroxylation substituents (
6
) and cyclisation to 
<tp:taxon-name>form dihydrofuran</tp:taxon-name>
(7, 8, 9 and 2), resulted in a reduced activities. When forming furan (
1
), six-membered (14 and 15) and seven-membered rings (
4
), showed no activity, possibly due to larger molecule sizes preventing access to the estrogen-binding pocket. In summary, compared with that in 11, isopentenyl replacement for 13 contributed to a strong activity.
</p>
         <p>
The abilities of 28 isoflavones to induce osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation were assessed. As indicated in Fig. S8, Fig. S13 and Table S16, compound 44 (daidzein) showed a significant effect at 10 
μ
M, but a hydroxyl group (
45
) at C-3 
′
was unfavorable for the activity. It was noteworthy that a methoxyl (46, 3 
′
-methoxydaidzein) or an isopentenyl group (42, neobavaisoflavone) replacement at C-3 
′
promoted osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation at 0.1 and 1 
μ
M. However, structural changes in the isopentenyl group displayed a decreased or no activity. Compound 47, a hydroxylation product, was still able to increase the number of calcium nodules and the expression of ALP at 0.1 and 1 
μ
M, cyclised compounds (19, 20, 18, 35, 22, 20, 34, 41, 38, and 40) were almost inactive. When the isopentenyl group was combined with C-6 or C-8 (36, 23, 24, and 52), their activities disappeared or only ALP expression was increased, suggesting that the position of isopentenyl played a key role in osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation activities. Compared with 44, the introduced geranyl group (49, corylifol A) at C-3 
′
resulted in a stronger activity at 0.1 and 1 
μ
M. When a hydroxyl group was connected to the C-5 position of 49, the activity of 48 was retained at 1 
μ
M. Remarkably, when the geranyl group was hydroxylated or cyclised, and the terminal isopentenyl group remained intact, compounds 37 (neocorylin), 29, and 30 still promoted osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation at 0.1 and 1 
μ
M. These results showed that the terminal isopentenyl group of the geranyl moiety was conducive to their activity. However, simultaneous introduction of two isopentenyl groups at C-3 
′
and C-5’ (
51
) did not increase the activity, but increased cytotoxicity at 10 
μ
M, probably due to the larger molecular size and stronger adsorption to biofilms. In brief, compounds with methoxyl, intact isopentenyl or geranyl groups introduced at C-3 
′
displayed improved activities. Moreover, compound 108 (Fig. S11), an isoflavone glycoside, also showed a better activity at 0.1–10 
μ
M.
</p>
         <p>
We investigated the effects of 14 flavonones on the osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation of MC3T3-E1cells. As indicated in Fig. S9, Fig. S14 and Table S16, compound 110 (bavachin) enhanced ALP expression and the amount of calcium nodules at 0.1 
μ
M. A methyl group introduced on 7-OH (111, bavachinin) showed a little effect on activity. However, the hydroxyl substituent at C-3, C-5 or C-3 
′
resulted in a decreased activity for compounds 58, 64, and 69. Similar results were obtained upon hydroxylation and cyclisation (72, 60, 56, 63, 55 and 53) of the isopentenyl group. When isopentenyl was combined with C-8 (70 and 68) or C-3’ (
67
), activities were weaker than those of compounds with the isopentenyl group at C-6. This indicated that flavonones with an isopentenyl replacement at C-6 exhibited a strong activity.
</p>
         <p>
In addition, the activities of 14 chalcones, five flavones and one chromone (
103
) were evaluated. As shown in Fig. S10, Fig. S11 and Table S16, these 
types
of compounds exhibited a weak activity. Among chalcones, only compound 112 (isobavachalcone), promoted the osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation of MC3T3-E1 cells at 0.1 
μ
M. Most flavones enhanced the expression of ALP at 10 
μ
M, and at the same time showed no effect or limitation on the formation of calcium nodules. However, flavone glycoside (
109
) (Fig. S11) could increase ALP expression and the amount of calcium nodules at 10 
μ
M. Unfortunately, there were insufficient data to further explain the SAR.
</p>
         <p>
Furthermore, the activities of the eight meroterpenoids were investigated. Compound 114 (bakuchiol) significantly increase the formation (183.82 ±19.45% activation compared with control) of calcium nodules at 10 
μ
M (Fig. S11, Fig. S15 and Table S16). In most cases, structural changes in the monoterpene chain (115, 116, 117, 119 and 120) caused the activity to decrease or disappear. However, compound 118 (12- oxobakuchiol) exhibited a stronger activity with a 3-fold increased calcium nodules (300.69 ±15.26% at 10 
μ
M and 326.85 ±14.18% at 1 
μ
M), and enhanced ALP activities, which was probably contributed by the ketone group. Interestingly, compound 121, a cyclisation product, still showed effects on osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation at 10 
μ
M, which was attributed to the similarity between its 6/5/6 tricyclic system and that of estrogen structure.
</p>
         <p>
2.3. Psoralidin and neobavaisoflavone work via ER pathway
</p>
         <p>
To verify whether these compounds functioned via the ER pathway, representative compounds psoralidin (
13
) and neobavaisoflavone (
42
) were added to cells with ICI (0.1 
μ
M) treatment, an ER antagonist. As indicated in 
Fig. 5
, ICI decreased ALP activities and the calcium nodule formation in MC3T3-E1 cells exposed to E2 (0.1 
μ
M), psoralidin (
13
) (0.1 
μ
M) and neobavaisoflavone (
42
) (0.1 
μ
M). The above-mentioned results showed that these compounds promoted osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation of MC3T3-E1 cells via the ER pathway.
</p>
         <p>
2.4. SPR analysis
</p>
         <p>
Estrogen binding to ER alpha and beta (ERα and ERβ), plays a key role in bone metabolism (

). The expression of ERβ in bone tissue is higher than that of ERα (

; 

). Consequently, in order to explain their SAR in depth, we evaluated the binding affinities of eight compounds and ERβ by SPR technology. The affinity values of the eight compounds and ERβ were shown in 
Fig. 6
. The KD values of most compounds were analyzed using a kinetic model, whereas the KD values of E2, neobavaisoflavone (
42
) and neocorylin (
37
) were obtained using the affinity model. For two coumarins, psoralidin (
13
) (12.4 
μ
M) exhibited a stronger affinity than coumestrol (
11
) (25.0 
μ
M). When it comes to six isoflavones, the KD values of 3 
′
-methoxydaidzein (
46
) and neobavaisoflavone (
42
) were 8.81 and 7.28 
μ
M respectively, indicating stronger affinities than that of daidzein (
44
) (28 
μ
M). In contrast, the affinities of corylifol A (
49
) (54.4 
μ
M), neocorylin (
37
) (96.1 
μ
M) and bakuisoflavone (
47
) (92.8 
μ
M) were weaker than that of daidzein (
44
). Remarkably, compared with E2 (13.9 
μ
M), psoralidin (
13
), neobavaisofalvone (
42
), and 3 
′
-methoxydaidzein (
46
) showed better affinities. The above-mentioned results showed that compounds with an intact isopentenyl replacement possessed a stronger affinity for ERβ than the compounds without isopentenyl substitution or compounds with altered isopentenyl group. Moreover, when a methoxyl group was introduced on C-3 
′
of daidzein, the compound also exhibited a better affinity than daidzein (
44
). Based on the above-mentioned reasons, psoralidin (
13
), neobavaisofalvone (
42
) and 3 
′
-methoxydaidzein (
46
) showed improved results at the cellular level.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusion
</title>
         <p>
In summary, diverse structures were obtained from the fruits of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 109 chemical constituents, containing 37 undescribed compounds, were reported in this study. The structures of undescribed compounds were elucidated via spectroscopic methods, single-crystal Xray diffraction, Rh 
2
(OCOCF 
3
) 
4
and Mo 
2
(OAc) 
4
-ICD spectra. In addition, the wrong structures of the four known coumarins were corrected following X-ray crystallographic analysis. Systematic phytochemical investigations enabled us to establish the most comprehensive constituent library to date, covering over 180 compounds.
</p>
         <p>
Based on the traditional role of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
in the treatment of osteoporosis, 89 library constituents were evaluated for their osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation activities of MC3T3-E1 cells, to identify potentially active compounds and investigate their SAR. We found that coumarins, isoflavones, flavonones and meroterpenoids were the basis for the role of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
in osteoporosis treatment. Among these constituents, psoralen (
16
), isopsoralen (
17
), coumestrol (
11
), psoralidin (
13
), daidzein (
44
), 3 
′
-methoxydaidzein (
46
), neobavaisoflavone (
42
), corylifol A (
49
), neocorylin (
37
), bavachin (
110
), bavachinin (
111
), bakuchiol (
114
), 12-oxobakuchiol (
118
), corypsoriol A (
121
), genistin (
108
) and astragaline (
109
) exhibited excellent activities. The activities of the representative compounds, psoralidin (
13
) and neobavaisoflavone (
42
), were decreased by the ER antagonist ICI, indicating that these compounds functioned via the ER pathway and were natural PE. Therefore, these compounds could serve as potential drugs or health foods for relieving menopausal symptoms and for the treatment of postmenopausal osteoporosis.
</p>
         <p>
Further SAR analysis showed that compounds with intact isopentenyl replacement possessed superior activities than compounds without isopentenyl substitution, or compounds with an altered isopentenyl group. This was because the isopentenyl group increased their affinity for ER. Moreover, isoflavones with an isopentenyl group at C-3 
′
and flavonones with an isopentenyl group at C-6 exhibited better activities than compounds with isopentenyl groups at other positions.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Materials and methods
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures
</title>
         <p>
HRESIMS data were recorded on a Waters Xevo G2 QTOF spectrometer. Infrared spectra were collected using a Thermo Nicolet Nexus 470 FT-IR spectrometer. Ultraviolet spectra were acquired by an Mapada UV-6100 double beam spectrophotometer. NMR spectra were obtained by a Bruker AVANCE III HD 400 or 600 NMR spectrometer. Optical rotations were measured by a Rudolph Autopol IV automatic polarimeter. ECD data were obtained on a JASCO J-810 spectropolarimeter. Solvents used for column chromatography (CC), cHe, EtOAc, chloroform (CHCl 
3
), 
n
-BuOH, methanol (MeOH), and acetonitrile (ACN), were purchased from 
Beijing
Chemical Works (
Beijing
, 
China
). HPLC grade solvents, MeOH and ACN, were purchased from Fisher Scientific (Pittsburgh, PA, 
USA
). Slica gel (200–300 mesh, Marine Chemical Ltd., Qingdao, 
China
), Sephadex LH-20 gel (Pharmacia Biotek, 
Denmark
), polyamide (100–200 mesh, 
Shanghai
Yuanye Biotechnology Co. Ltd., 
China
), were used for CC. Alpha modifications minimum essential medium (α- MEM), fetal bovine serum (FBS), trypsin, penicillinstreptomycin solution (PS), and phosphate buffered saline (PBS) were obtained from Gibco® (Life Technologies Inc., Grand Island, NY, 
USA
). ICI182,780 (ICI) from Abcam (
UK
); 17β- estradiol (E2), β- glycerol phosphate, ascorbic acid, dexamethasone and cetylpyridinium chloride monohydrate from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, 
USA
); Alizarin Red S from Solarbios Life Science (
Beijing
, 
China
); bicinchoninic acid assay (BCA) protein assay kit, alkaline phosphatase (ALP) activity test kit, cell lysis buffer for Western and IP without inhibitors, and 4% paraformaldehyde fix solution from Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology (
Jiangsu
, 
China
) were used for osteogenic differentiation and mineralisation experiments of MC3T3-E1. Recombinant Human Estrogen Receptor β were purchased from SAB (CollegePark, 
USA
). MC3T3-E1 cells were obtained from the Cell Resource Center, Peking Union Medical College (which is the headquarter of National Infrastructure of Cell Line Resource, NSTI).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material
</title>
         <p>

The mature fruits of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Psoralea corylifolia
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (Leguminosae) was harvested in 
Yunnan Province
(GPS coordinates: 

23 
◦
32 
′
N

, 

99 
◦
23 
′
E

), People’ s 
Republic of China
in 

October 2016

, and authenticated by 
Prof. XiuWei Yang
of the School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Peking University. A voucher specimen (NO: 
BGZ201610
) of the fruits was deposited at the 
State Key Laboratory of Natural Medicines

and 
Biomimetic Drugs of Peking University

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation
</title>
         <p>Detailed extraction and isolation processes could be viewed in Supplementary data. Spectroscopic data of 37 undescribed compounds and NMR data of 72 known compounds were shown in Supplementary data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

4.4. Mo 
2
(OAc) 
4
and Rh 
2
(OCOCF 
3
) 
4
-induced CD spectra

</title>
         <p>
Compounds (
0.6 mg
) were dissolved in anhydrous DMSO solution of 
1 mg
/mL Mo 
2
(OAc) 
4
or Rh 
2
(OCOCF 
3
) 
4
. After mixing, the ICD spectrum was immediately collected from 
250 nm
to 
500 nm
until a stable state.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. X-ray crystallographic analysis
</title>
         <p>
The X-ray crystallographic data was collected on a Rigaku Micro Max 003+ single crystal diffractometer with 
CuK
α
radiation and a XtaLAB Synergy R, HyPix diffractometer with 
CuK
α
radiation. Crystallographic data for 1 (No. CCDC 2102008), 7 (No. CCDC 2102007), 8 (No. CCDC 2102009) and 33 (No. CCDC 2102010) have been deposited at the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Center (the detailed X-ray Crystallographic analysis data see Table S14). These data can be obtained free of charge via http://www.ccdc.cam.ac.uk/conts/retrieving.html.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Cultivation and osteogenic differentiation of MC3T3-E1 cells
</title>
         <p>
MC3T3-E1 cells were maintained in α- MEM containing 10% FBS and 1% PS (growth medium), in a constant humidity atmosphere of 5% CO 
2
at 37 C. Cells were seeded in 12-well culture plates at a density of 1 × 
105
cells/well for 24 h. When cells reached 100% confluence, the growth medium was replaced with osteogenic differentiation medium (growth medium with 10 mM β- glycerol phosphate, 50 μg/ml ascorbic acid and 100 nM dexamethasone) for 7 or 16 days (

; 

). The osteogenic differentiation medium was refreshed every two days.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Cell viability
</title>
         <p>
MC3T3-E1 cells were seeded in 96-well culture plates at a density of 1 × 10 
4
cells/well for 24 h. And then, cells were treated with compounds at various concentrations (20, 10, 1.0, 0.1, 0.01 and 0.001 
μ
M) in the osteogenic differentiation medium. After 48 h, cell viability was assessed by the MTT method.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. ALP activity assay
</title>
         <p>
MC3T3-E1 cells were cultivated in osteogenic differentiation medium with compounds (10.0, 1.0 and 0.1 
μ
M) and E2 (0.1 
μ
M) for 7 days. Cell lysis buffer for Western and IP without inhibitors (100 μL) was added into each well and the cells were lysed on ice for 10 min. The total protein collection was obtained after centrifugation at 12,000× 
g
for 3 min and was diluted five times for ALP activity assay. The concentration of the total protein collection was measured by BCA method.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.9. Calcium nodules staining and quantitation
</title>
         <p>
MC3T3-E1 cells were cultivated in osteogenic differentiation medium with compounds (10.0, 1.0 and 0.1 
μ
M) and E2 (0.1 
μ
M) for 16 days. The cells were fixed by 4% paraformaldehyde fix solution (1 mL) for 30 min. Next, calcium nodules were stained by Alizarin Red S (ARS) for 5 min. Pictures of staining sample were taken by an inverted optical microscope and a digital camera. Finally, calcium nodules were dissolved for 30 min at room temperature by 10% cetylpyridinium chloride monohydrate, and the amount was quantified by absorbance values at 
570 nm
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.10. SPR analysis for binding affinity
</title>
         <p>SPR experiment was performed by Biacore 8K (GE Healthcare). Recombinant Human Estrogen Receptor β protein was diluted to 20 μg/mL with sodium acetate solution. The PSP-P buffer was used for mobile phase. According to standard operation, the diluted protein was coupled to CM5 sensor chip. At flow rate at 20 μL/min, the binding time was 60 s and the dissociation time was 130 s. The sensor chip surface was regenerated with 10 mM NaOH. Finally, data was analyzed using Biacore 8K software.</p>
         <p>
Declaration of competing interest
</p>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(81773865).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data
</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113085.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Almeida, M.
, 
Laurent, M.R.
, 
Dubois, V.
, 
Claessens, F.
, O’ 
Brien, C.A.
, 
Bouillon, R.
, 
Vanderschueren, D.
, 
Manolagas, S.C.
, 
2017
. 
Estrogens and androgens in skeletal physiology and pathophysiology
. 
Physiol. Rev.
97
, 
135–187
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1152/physrev.00033.2015
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
An, J.
, 
Yang, H.
, 
Zhang, Q.
, 
Liu, C.C.
, 
Zhao, J.J.
, 
Zhang, L.L.
, 
Chen, B.
, 
2016
. 
Natural products for treatment of osteoporosis: the effects and mechanisms on promoting osteoblast-mediated bone formation
. 
Life Sci.
147
, 
46–58
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ j.lfs.2016.01.024
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bado, I.
, 
Gugala, Z.
, 
Fuqua, S.A.W.
, 
Zhang, X.H.
, 
2017
. 
Estrogen receptors in breast and bone: from virtue of remodeling to vileness of metastasis
. 
Oncogene
36
, 
4527–4537
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/onc.2017.94
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Cao, H.J.
, 
Li, C.R.
, 
Wang, L.Y.
, 
Ziadlou, R.
, 
Grad, S.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Cheng, Y.
, 
Lai, Y.X.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
Alini, M.
, 
Qin, L.
, 
Wang, X.L.
, 
2019
. 
Effect and mechanism of psoralidin on promoting osteogenesis and inhibiting adipogenesis
. 
Phytomedicine
61
, 
152860
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phymed.2019.152860
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, H.W.
, 
Fang, C.
, 
Zhi, X.
, 
Song, S.J.
, 
Gu, Y.Q.
, 
Chen, X.F.
, 
Cui, J.
, 
Hu, Y.
, 
Weng, W.Z.
, 
Zhou, Q.R.
, 
Wang, Y.J.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
Jiang, H.
, 
Li, X.Q.
, 
Cao, L.H.
, 
Chen, X.
, 
Su, J.C.
, 
2020
. 
Neobavaisoflavone inhibits osteoclastogenesis through blocking RANKL signalling-mediated TRAF6 and c-Src recruitment and NF-kappaB, MAPK and Akt pathways. J
. 
Cell Mol. Med.
24
, 
9067–9084
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jcmm.15543
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen, S.N.
, 
Chu, B.X.
, 
Chen, Y.
, 
Cheng, X.
, 
Guo, D.
, 
Chen, L.H.
, 
Wang, J.C.
, 
Li, Z.Y.
, 
Hong, Z.H.
, 
Hong, D.
, 
2019
. 
Neferine suppresses osteoclast differentiation through suppressing NF-kappaB signal pathway but not MAPKs and promote osteogenesis
. 
J. Cell. Physiol.
234
, 
22960–22971
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/jcp.28857
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chino, M.
, 
Sato, K.
, 
Yamazaki, T.
, 
Maitani, T.
, 
2002
. 
Constituent of natural food additive hokosshi extract and an analytical method for the additive in foods. Shokuhinseigaku Zasshi J. Food Hyg
. 
Soc. Japan
43
, 
352
. 
https://doi.org/10.3358/ shokueishi.43.352
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Choi, Y.H.
, 
Yon, G.H.
, 
Hong, K.S.
, 
Yoo, D.S.
, 
Choi, C.W.
, 
Park, W.-K.
, 
Kong, J.Y.
, 
Kim, Y. S.
, 
Ryu, S.Y.
, 
2008
. In 

vitro BACE-1 inhibitory phenolic components from the seeds of 
Psoralea corylifolia

. 
Planta Med.
74
, 
1405–1408
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2008- 1081301
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dai, J.
, 
Shen, D.
, 
Yoshida, W.Y.
, 
Parrish, S.M.
, 
Williams, P.G.
, 
2012
. 

Isoflavonoids from 
Ficus benjamina
and their inhibitory activity on BACE1

. 
Planta Med.
78
, 
1357–1362
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-0032-1315001
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Di Bari, L.
, 
Pescitelli, G.
, 
Pratelli, C.
, 
Pini, D.
, 
Salvadori, P.
, 
2001
. 
Determination of absolute configuration of acyclic 1,2-diols with Mo2(OAc)4
. 
J. Org. Chem.
66
, 
4819–4825
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/jo010136v
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Foger-Samwald, U.
, 
Dovjak, P.
, 
Azizi-Semrad, U.
, 
Kerschan-Schindl, K.
, 
Pietschmann, P.
, 
2020
. 
Osteoporosis: pathophysiology and therapeutic options
. 
EXCLI J
19
, 
1017–1037
. 
https://doi.org/10.17179/excli2020-2591
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gerards, M.
, 
Snatzke, G.
, 
1990
. 
Circular dichroism, XCIII determination of the absolute configuration of alcohols, olefins, epoxides, and ethers from the CD of their “in situ” complexes with [Rh2(O2CCF3)4]
. 
Tetrahedron: Asymmetry
1
, 
221–236
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/S0957-4166(00)86328-4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guo, J.M.
, 
Weng, X.C.
, 
Wu, H.
, 
Li, Q.H.
, 
Bi, K.S.
, 
2005
. 

Antioxidants from a Chinese medicinal herb - 
Psoralea corylifolia
L

. 
Food Chem.
91
, 
287–292
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.foodchem.2004.04.029
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Harper-Harrison, G.
, 
Shanahan, M.M.
, 
2021
. 
Hormone Replacement Therapy. StatPearls
. 
StatPearls Publishing Copyright © 2021, StatPearls Publishing LLC., Treasure Island (FL
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Herz, W.
, 
Kulanthaivel, P.
, 
1984
. 
Ent-pimaranes, ent-kauranes, Heliangolides and other Constituents of three Helianthus species
. 
Phytochemistry
23
, 
1453–1459
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(00)80485-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
He, Z.C.
, 
Xu, Q.X.
, 
Yang, X.W.
, 
Wang, Z.J.
, 
Xu, W.
, 
2021
. 

The benzofuran glycosides from the fruits of 
Psoralea corylifolia
L

. 
Fitoterapia
155
, 
105057
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/ j.fitote.2021.105057
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Johnston, C.B.
, 
Dagar, M.
, 
2020
. 
Osteoporosis in older adults
. 
Med. Clin.
104
, 
873–884
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mcna.2020.06.004
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kanis, J.A.
, 
Johnell, O.
, 
Oden, A.
, 
Sernbo, I.
, 
Redlund-Johnell, I.
, 
Dawson, A.
, 
De Laet, C.
, 
Jonsson, B.
, 
2000
. 
Long-term risk of osteoporotic fracture in Malmo. Osteoporos
. 
Int.
11
, 
669–674
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s001980070064
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Khalid, A.B.
, 
Krum, S.A.
, 
2016
. 
Estrogen receptors alpha and beta in bone
. 
Bone
87
, 
130–135
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bone.2016.03.016
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Khosla, S.
, 
Oursler, M.J.
, 
Monroe, D.G.
, 
2012
. 
Estrogen and the skeleton
. 
Trends Endocrinol. Metabol.
23
, 
576–581
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-59259-157-2_13
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kim, M.
, 
Won, D.
, 
Han, J.
, 
2010
. 
Absolute configuration determination of isoflavan-4-ol stereoisomers
. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett
20
, 
4337–4341
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. bmcl.2010.06.074
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Koul, B.
, 
Taak, P.
, 
Kumar, A.
, 
Kumar, A.
, 
Sanyal, I.
, 
2019
. 

Genus 
Psoralea
: a review of the traditional and modern uses, phytochemistry and pharmacology. J

. 
Ethnopharmacol.
232
, 
201–226
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2018.11.036
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, S.R.
, 
Chen, P.Y.
, 
Chen, L.Y.
, 
Lo, Y.F.
, 
Tsai, I.L.
, 
Wang, E.C.
, 
2009
. 
Synthesis of haginin E, equol, daidzein, and formononetin from resorcinol via an isoflavene intermediate
. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
50
, 
2121–2123
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tetlet.2009.02.159
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, Y.
, 
Yang, F.
, 
Gao, M.Q.
, 
Gong, R.
, 
Jin, M.Y.
, 
Liu, T.Y.
, 
Sun, Y.
, 
Fu, Y.T.
, 
Huang, Q.
, 
Zhang, W.W.
, 
Liu, S.Z.
, 
Yu, M.X.
, 
Yan, G.G.
, 
Feng, C.
, 
He, M.Y.
, 
Zhang, L.
, 
Ding, F.Z.
, 
Ma, W.Y.
, 
Bi, Z.G.
, 
Xu, C.Q.
, 
Yuan, Y.
, 
Cai, B.Z.
, 
Yang, L.
, 
2019
. 
miR-149
- 
3p
regulates the switch between adipogenic and osteogenic differentiation of BMSCs by targeting FTO. 
Mol. Ther. Nucleic Acids
17
, 
590–600
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. omtn.2019.06.023
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, J.H.
, 
Xu, S.X.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
Kobayashi, H.
, 
1995
. 

Two new 6-alkylcoumarins from 
Angelica pubescens f. biserrata

. 
Planta Med.
61
, 
482–484
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2006-958145. PMID: 17238102
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, X.Y.
, 
Yang, J.
, 
Yu, H.J.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Du, J.
, 
Wang, X.H.
, 
Wang, Y.F.
, 
Chai, X.
, 
2021
. 

Chemical constituents from the fruits of 
Cullen corylifolium
(L.) Medik. by the targeted separation mode

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
35
, 
1071–1076
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 14786419.2019.1638382
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Liu, Y.
, 
Xu, Z.J.
, 
Wang, Q.Q.
, 
Jiang, Y.Y.
, 
Wang, R.
, 
Chen, S.Y.
, 
Zhu, J.Y.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Chen, J.H.
, 
2020
. 
Selective regulation of RANKL/RANK/OPG pathway by heparan sulfate through the binding with estrogen receptor beta in MC3T3-E1 cells
. 
Int. J. Biol. Macromol.
161
, 
1526–1534
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2020.07.308
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lv, Q.
, 
Xu, Q.X.
, 
Zhang, Y.T.
, 
Yang, X.W.
, 
2020
. 

Inhibition of bakuchiol and its derivatives in 
Psoraleae Fructus
on nitric oxide production in lipopolysaccharideactivated RAW 264.7 cell lines.

Chin. Tradit. Herb. Drugs
51
, 
307–314
. In Chinese.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Noh, J.Y.
, 
Yang, Y.
, 
Jung, H.
, 
2020
. 
Molecular mechanisms and emerging therapeutics for osteoporosis
. 
Int. J. Mol. Sci.
21
, 
7623
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms21207623
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Petrine, J.C.P.
, 
Del Bianco-Borges, B.
, 
2021
. 
The influence of phytoestrogens on different physiological and pathological processes: an overview
. 
Phytother Res.
35
, 
180–197
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ptr.6816
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Reutrakul, V.
, 
Ningnuek, N.
, 
Pohmakotr, M.
, 
Yoosook, C.
, 
Napaswad, C.
, 
Kasisit, J.
, 
Santisuk, T.
, 
Tuchinda, P.
, 
2007
. 
Anti HIV-1 flavonoid glycosides from Ochna integerrima
. 
Planta Med.
73
, 
683–688
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2007-981538
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sigstad, E.E.
, 
Catalan, C.A.N.
, 
Diaz, J.G.
, 
Herz, W.
, 
1996
. 
Chromanones, benzofurans and other constituents from Ophryosporus lorentzii
. 
Phytochemistry
42
, 
1443–1445
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0031-9422(96)00106-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Song, P.
, 
Yang, X.Z.
, 
Yuan, J.Q.
, 
2013
. 

Cytotoxic constituents from 
Psoralea corylifolia

. 
J. Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
15
, 
624–630
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/ 10286020.2013.793181
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Won, T.H.
, 
Song, I.H.
, 
Kim, K.H.
, 
Yang, W.Y.
, 
Lee, S.K.
, 
Oh, D.C.
, 
Oh, W.K.
, 
Oh, K.B.
, 
Shin, J.
, 
2015
. 

Bioactive metabolites from the fruits of 
Psoralea corylifolia

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
78
, 
666–673
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np500834d
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, Q.X.
, 
Xu, W.
, 
Yang, X.W.
, 
2020
a. 

Meroterpenoids from the fruits of 
Psoralea corylifolia

. 
Tetrahedron
76
, 
131343
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tet.2020.131343
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, Q.X.
, 
Hu, Y.
, 
Li, G.Y.
, 
Xu, W.
, 
Zhang, Y.T.
, 
Yang, X.W.
, 
2018
. 

Multi-target antialzheimer activities of four prenylated compounds from 
Psoralea fructus

. 
Molecules
23
, 
614
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules23030614
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, Q.X.
, 
Zhang, Y.B.
, 
Liu, X.Y.
, 
Xu, W.
, 
Yang, X.W.
, 
2020
b. 

Cytotoxic heterodimers of meroterpene phenol from the fruits of 
Psoralea corylifolia

. 
Phytochemistry
176
, 
112394
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112394
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, Q.X.
, 
Lv, Q.
, 
Liu, L.
, 
Zhang, Y.T.
, 
Yang, X.W.
, 
2021
. 

New bakuchiol dimers from 
Psoraleae Fructus
and their inhibitory activities on nitric oxide production

. 
Chin. Med.
16
, 
98
. https://doi: 
10.1186/s13020-021-00499-y
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yin, S.
, 
Fan, C.Q.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
Dong, L.
, 
Yue, J.M.
, 
2004
. 

Antibacterial prenylflavone derivatives from 
Psoralea corylifolia
, and their structure-activity relationship study

. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem.
12
, 
4387–4392
. https://doi: 
10.1016/j.bmc.2004.06.014
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhai, Y.K.
, 
Wang, Q.F.
, 
Li, Y.Y.
, 
Cui, J.W.
, 
Feng, K.
, 
Kong, X.J.
, 
Xian, C.J.
, 
2018
. 
The higher osteoprotective activity of psoralidin in vivo than coumestrol is attributed by its presence of an isopentenyl group and through activated PI3K/Akt axis
. 
Biomed. Pharmacother.
102
, 
1015–1024
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopha.2018.03.166
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
