<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.03.009</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Corrigendum to “Bioactive carbazole and quinoline alkaloids from Clausena dunniana” [Phytochemistry 151 (2018) 1-8]</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2018</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group/>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Corrigendum</p>
         <p>
Corrigendum

to “Bioactive carbazole and quinoline alkaloids from 
Clausena dunniana

” [
Phytochemistry
151
(
2018
) 
1–8
]

</p>
         <p>
Nankai Cao, Yuemei Chen, Xiaoli Ma, Kewu Zeng, Mingbo Zhao, Pengfei Tu, Jun Li
∗∗
,
</p>
         <p>
Yong Jiang 

∗
</p>
         <p>

State Key Laboratory of Natural and Biomimetic Drugs, School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, 
Peking
University, 

Beijing
, 100191, PR 
China
</p>
         <p>
In the original publication of this paper, the biphenyl configurations of four pairs of carbazole atropisomer (
1–3
, 
6
) were determined as (
aS
) for 
1a–3a
and 
6a
, and (
aR
) for 
1b–3b
and 
6b
, respectively. However, in following up this research, we found that it not appropriate to determine the stereochemistry of dimeric carbazoles by comparison of their ECD data with those of biphenyl lignanoids (Chen et al., 2006; Shen et al., 2007), even though their ECD curves match well. We have therefore reinvestigated the configurations of the carbazole atropisomers by ECD exciton coupling and comparison of the calculated and experimental ECD data. This has led us to propose a redefinition of the configurations.
</p>
         <p>
The ECD spectrum of 
1a
exhibited sequential negative and positive Cotton effects at 240 and 
218 nm
, i.e., a negative couplet derived from the electronic transition of the two carbazole monomers as shown in 
Fig. 1
. Therefore, the absolute configuration of (−)-dunnine A (
1a
) was determined as (
aR
), and correspondingly, that of (+)-dunnine B (
1b
) was assigned as (
aS
). Further support for this conclusion was obtained when the ECD spectra of (
aR
)- and (
aS
)- 
1
(
Fig. 2
) were calculated using the TDDFT method at the B3LYP/6-311+G(d) level: this confirmed the results of ECD exciton coupling. Then, the absolute configurations of 
2a/3a
/ 
6a
and 
2b
/ 
3b/6b
were defined as (
aR
) and (
aS
), respectively, by comparison of their specific rotations and ECD data with those of 
1a
and 
1b
. Their structures were corrected as shown in 
Fig. 3
. The authors apologize for any inconvenience caused.
</p>
         <p>
DOI of original article: https://doi.org/ 
10.1016/j.phytochem.2018.03.009
</p>
         <p>
∗

Corresponding author. 
State Key Laboratory of Natural
and Biomimetic Drugs, 
School of Pharmaceutical Sciences
, 
Peking
University, No.
38 Xueyuan Road, 
Haidian District
, 
Beijing
, 100191, PR 
China

.
</p>
         <p>
∗∗

Corresponding author.
</p>
         <p>
E-mail addresses:
lijun@bjmu.edu.cn (J. Li), yongjiang@bjmu.edu.cn (Y. Jiang).
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.04.009</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References
</title>
         <p>
Chen, M., Kilgore, N., Lee, K.H., Chen, D.F., 2006. Rubrisandrins A and B, lignans and related anti HIV compounds from 
Schisandra rubriflora
. J. Nat. Prod. 69, 1697–1701.
</p>
         <p>
Shen, Y.C., Cheng, Y.B., Lan, T.W., Liaw, C.C., Liou, S.S., Kuo, Y.H., Khalil, A.T., 2007. Kadsuphilols A–H, oxygenated lignans from 
Kadsura philippinensis
. J. Nat. Prod. 70, 1139–1145.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
