<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document ID-DOI="http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5374866" ID-ISSN="1638-9395" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5374866" checkinTime="1630277031466" checkinUser="marcus" docAuthor="Cao, Nathanaël &amp; Bagils, René Zaragüeta &amp; Vignes-Lebbe, Régine" docDate="2007" docId="0051FFF11A19FFD45D35314C0656E876" docName="Geodiversitas.2007.29.1.5-15.pdf" docOrigin="Geodiversitas 29 (1)" docStyle="DocumentStyle:94524207C6714CF92F879FE43E306202.1:Geodiversitas.2000-2008.journal_article.type2" docStyleId="94524207C6714CF92F879FE43E306202" docStyleName="Geodiversitas.2000-2008.journal_article.type2" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Hierarchical representation of hypotheses of homology" docVersion="2" lastPageNumber="15" pageNumber="5" updateTime="1630562433925" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CC0-1.0" zenodo-license-figures="CC0-1.0">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Hierarchical representation of hypotheses of homology</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Cao, Nathanaël</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>CNRS, UMR 5143, Équipe Paléodiversité, systématique et évolution des embryophytes, Université Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris 6, Laboratoire Paléobotanique et Paléoécologie, 12 rue Cuvier, F-75231 Paris cedex 05 (France) ncao@snv.jussieu.fr</mods:affiliation>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Bagils, René Zaragüeta</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Vignes-Lebbe, Régine</mods:namePart>
<mods:affiliation>CNRS, UMR 5143, Équipe Systématique, recherche informatique et structuration des cladogrammes, Université Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris 6, Laboratoire Informatique et Systématique, 12 rue Cuvier, F-75231 Paris cedex 05 (France) rzb@ccr.jussieu.fr vignes@ccr.jussieu.fr</mods:affiliation>
<mods:nameIdentifier type="email">fr@ccr.jussieu.fr</mods:nameIdentifier>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Geodiversitas</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2007</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>29</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:detail type="issue">
<mods:number>1</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>5</mods:start>
<mods:end>15</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5374866</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1638-9395</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5374866</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<subSection _generate="added" pageId="0" pageNumber="5" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="0.[212,1064,332,425]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">
<!--emphasis removed-->
<docTitle pageId="0" pageNumber="5">Hierarchical representation of hypotheses of homology</docTitle>

</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="0.[735,1211,508,708]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">
<!--emphasis removed-->
<docAuthor box="[1014,1210,508,533]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">Nathanaël CAO</docAuthor>

<docAuthorAffiliation pageId="0" pageNumber="5">
CNRS, UMR 5143, Équipe Paléodiversité, systématique et évolution des embryophytes, Université Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris 6, Laboratoire Paléobotanique et Paléoécologie, 12 rue Cuvier, F-75231 Paris cedex 05 (
<collectingCountry box="[1133,1204,658,679]" name="France" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">France</collectingCountry>
) ncao@snv.jussieu.fr
</docAuthorAffiliation>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="0.[609,1211,741,1000]" lastBlockId="0.[217,417,1528,1699]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">
<!--emphasis removed-->
<docAuthor pageId="0" pageNumber="5">René ZARAGÜETA BAGILS Régine VIGNES-LEBBE</docAuthor>

<docAuthorAffiliation pageId="0" pageNumber="5">
CNRS, UMR 5143, Équipe Systématique, recherche informatique et structuration des cladogrammes, Université Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris 6, Laboratoire Informatique et Systématique, 12 rue Cuvier, F-75231 Paris cedex 05 (
<collectingCountry box="[1133,1204,921,942]" name="France" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">France</collectingCountry>
) rzb@ccr.jussieu.fr vignes@ccr.jussieu.fr
</docAuthorAffiliation>
<!--emphasis removed-->KEY WORDS
Data matrix, homology, character,
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="0.[217,417,1528,1699]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">classificatory structure, hierarchy, formalization, cladistic analysis.</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection _generate="added" pageId="0" pageNumber="5" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="0.[454,1210,1277,1314]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">
<docRef accuracy="0.8120301" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">
Cao N., Zaragüeta Bagils R. &amp; Vignes-Lebbe R. 2007. — Hierarchical representation of hypotheses of homology. 
<!--emphasis removed-->
<docJournal box="[649,762,1297,1314]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">Geodiversitas</docJournal>

29 (1): 
<docPagination box="[825,867,1297,1314]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">5-15</docPagination>
.
</docRef>
</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection _generate="added" pageId="0" pageNumber="5" type="abstract">
<paragraph blockId="0.[454,585,1354,1378]" box="[454,585,1354,1378]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">
<heading bold="true" box="[454,585,1354,1378]" fontSize="10" level="1" pageId="0" pageNumber="5" reason="4">
<!--emphasis removed-->ABSTRACT
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="0.[454,1211,1382,1699]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5">
Tables (usually called data matrices) are currently used to represent hypotheses of homology in cladistic analysis because they are easily readable and concise. 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." box="[454,713,1440,1465]" pageId="0" pageNumber="5" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006)</bibRefCitation>
have recently criticized their use. They argue that tables are unable to represent nested relationships and the underlying homologies. We agree with their point of view and we supplement their argumentation. We identify the formal reasons of the inadequacy of this kind of representation in systematics and cladistic biogeography. We propose a solution that has the advantage of being easily understandable and concise as well. In order to guarantee consistency in the representation proposed herein, we provide precise definitions of the concepts of “component”, “character”, “character-state”, and “homologue”.
</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection _generate="added" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" type="abstract">
<paragraph blockId="1.[213,1210,216,621]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">
<!--emphasis removed-->RÉSUMÉ
<!--emphasis removed-->Représentation hiérarchique des hypothèses d’homologie.
La représentation des hypothèses d’homologie sous forme de tableaux (appelés couramment matrices de données) est classiquement utilisée en analyse cladistique grâce à la grande lisibilité et concision. 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." box="[923,1179,332,356]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006)</bibRefCitation>
en ont récemment fait la critique. Ils fondent leur argumentation sur le fait que les tableaux sont incapables de représenter des relations de parenté, c’est-à-dire les homologies sous-jacentes. Nous sommes d’accord avec leur point de vue et 
<!--emphasis removed-->MOTS CLÉS
complétons ici leur argumentation. Nous identifions les raisons formelles de Matrice de données, l’inadéquation de cette forme de représentation pour les hypothèses d’homolohomologie, caractère, gies en systématique et biogéographie cladistique. Nous proposons également structure classificatoire, une solution qui a pour avantage de rester claire et concise. Afin de garantir la hiérarchie, formalisation, cohérence de la nouvelle représentation, nous précisons les concepts de « comanalyse cladistique. posante», «caractère », « état de caractère » et « homologue ».
</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection _generate="added" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" type="introduction">
<paragraph blockId="1.[114,342,818,844]" box="[114,342,818,844]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">
<heading allCaps="true" box="[114,342,818,844]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" reason="1">INTRODUCTION</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[113,647,881,1446]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">
Recently, 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." box="[218,501,881,908]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006)</bibRefCitation>
criticized the use of data matrices in phylogenetics (cladistics) and historical biogeography. Their main point is that data matrices are unable to represent hypotheses of homology. We agree with these authors. However, although they point out what we understand as the main problem in phylogenetics, i.e. the discovery of relationships with a device that cannot represent them, they do not assess the proper reasons for the impossibility of representing relationships by a two dimensional table, nor do they give a relevant alternative for coding hypotheses of homology.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[113,647,881,1446]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">Here we provide formal reasons for the failure of data matrices and present a simple, relevant alternative representation of hypotheses of homology. Before introducing our new representation, formalization of a number of concepts is required in order to clarify the rationale of cladistic analysis.</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection _generate="added" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="1.[114,458,1515,1572]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">
<heading allCaps="true" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" reason="1">FORMALIZATION VERSUS TERMINOLOGY</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[113,646,1610,1700]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">Before discussing some terminological points introduced by Williams &amp; Ebach, we describe some formal entities and structures.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[677,1210,818,939]" box="[677,853,818,844]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">FORMALIZATION</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[677,1210,818,939]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">Formalization is the expression of a message in a language that conveys no ambiguity (Lebbe 1991). In general, the language used is mathematics or logic.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[677,1210,976,1700]" box="[677,915,976,1002]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">
<!--emphasis removed-->Classificatory structures
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[677,1210,976,1700]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">
A classificatory structure is a covering set of classes (
<bibRefCitation author="CELEUX G. &amp; DIDAY E. &amp; GOVAERT G. &amp; LECHEVALLIER Y. &amp; RALAMBONDRAINY H." box="[684,925,1039,1066]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" refId="ref6062" refString="CELEUX G., DIDAY E., GOVAERT G., LECHEVALLIER Y. &amp; RALAMBONDRAINY H. 1989. - Classification automatique des donnees. Dunod Informatique; Bordas, Paris, 285 p." type="book" year="1989">
Celeux 
<!--emphasis removed-->et al.
1989: 65
</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="DIDAY E." box="[936,1070,1039,1066]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" refId="ref6228" refString="DIDAY E. 1991. - Des objets de l'analyse des donnees a ceux de l'analyse des connaissances, in KODRATOFF Y. &amp; DIDAY E. (eds), Induction symbolique numerique a partir de donnees. Cepadues, Toulouse, 460 p." type="book" year="1991">Diday 1991</bibRefCitation>
). This means that, given a set of individuals to classify, each individual belongs to at least one class and that there are no empty classes. There exist a number of kinds of classificatory structures. We will focus on two of them: partitions and hierarchies.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[677,1210,976,1700]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">
A partition is a classificatory structure that verifies an additional property: the intersection between two classes is always empty (
<bibRefCitation author="BARTHELEMY J. - P. &amp; GUENOCHE A." pageId="1" pageNumber="6" refId="ref6034" refString="BARTHELEMY J. - P. &amp; GUENOCHE A. 1988. - Les arbres et les representations des proximites. Masson, Paris, 239 p." type="book" year="1988">Barthélemy &amp; Guénoche 1988</bibRefCitation>
). Partitions admit a constraint of order. That is, any two classes can be sorted following one or several criteria.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[677,1210,976,1700]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">
A hierarchy is a classificatory structure that verifies three conditions (
<bibRefCitation author="BARTHELEMY J. - P. &amp; GUENOCHE A." box="[862,1197,1451,1477]" pageId="1" pageNumber="6" refId="ref6034" refString="BARTHELEMY J. - P. &amp; GUENOCHE A. 1988. - Les arbres et les representations des proximites. Masson, Paris, 239 p." type="book" year="1988">Barthélemy &amp; Guénoche 1988</bibRefCitation>
): 1. There is a class that contains all the individuals. This class is equivalent to the root of a rooted tree. 2. There is a class that contains a single individual, for each individual. These classes are called singletons.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="1.[677,1210,976,1700]" lastBlockId="2.[113,647,216,623]" lastPageId="2" lastPageNumber="7" pageId="1" pageNumber="6">3. The intersection between two classes is either empty or is one of the classes; that is, classes either do not intersect or one is included in the other.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[113,647,216,623]" pageId="2" pageNumber="7">Only classes different from the root and the singletons may be informative in systematics and biogeography.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[113,647,216,623]" pageId="2" pageNumber="7">
Hierarchies and rooted trees are mathematically isomorphic (
<bibRefCitation author="DIDAY E." box="[248,381,374,400]" pageId="2" pageNumber="7" refId="ref6228" refString="DIDAY E. 1991. - Des objets de l'analyse des donnees a ceux de l'analyse des connaissances, in KODRATOFF Y. &amp; DIDAY E. (eds), Induction symbolique numerique a partir de donnees. Cepadues, Toulouse, 460 p." type="book" year="1991">Diday 1991</bibRefCitation>
). For the purposes of this paper, we consider them simply equivalent.Note that hierarchies and unrooted trees are not isomorphic: an unrooted tree does not define a hierarchy.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[113,647,216,623]" pageId="2" pageNumber="7">In order to formally explain the difference between the transformational and the taxic approaches, we also need to reassess the definition of a methodological term.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[113,647,659,1700]" box="[113,195,659,685]" pageId="2" pageNumber="7">
<!--emphasis removed-->Analysis
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[113,647,659,1700]" pageId="2" pageNumber="7">
Cladistic analysis, in phylogenetics and biogeography, is not called analysis by chance. The analytical method has roots very deep in time (
<bibRefCitation author="DESCARTES R." pageId="2" pageNumber="7" refId="ref6176" refString="DESCARTES R. 1637. - Discours de la methode pour bien conduire sa raison et chercher la verite dans les sciences, plus la Dioptrique, les Meteores et la Geometrie qui sont des essais de cette methode. De l'imprimerie de I. Maire, Leyde, 79 p." type="book" year="1637">Descartes 1637</bibRefCitation>
). It has a precise definition, requirements and constraints. In his “ 
<!--emphasis removed-->Discours de la méthode pour bien conduire sa raison et chercher la vérité dans les sciences, plus la Dioptrique, les Météores et la Géométrie qui sont des essais de cette méthode
”, René Descartes gives the methodological principles that let him redefine correct formal reasoning. Among them, his second principle states that one has “to divide each of the difficulties under examination into as many parts as possible, and as might be necessary for its adequate solution” and the third, “to conduct my thoughts in such order that, by commencing with objects the simplest and easiest to know, I might ascend by little and little, and, as it were, step by step, to the knowledge of the more complex”. We can reformulate the analytical method as follows: when facing a problem that is too complex, the only way to solve it is to decompose it into a set of simpler problems. If the complex problem is how to “find the relationships of a set of taxa”, the simpler problem is how to decompose it? The only way that has gained some success is to decompose it into a suite of characters. This means that the parts that compose taxic relationships are characters (
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J." pageId="2" pageNumber="7" refId="ref6800" refString="NELSON G. J. 1994 a. - Homology and systematics, in HALL B. K. (ed.), The Hierarchical Basis of Comparative Biology. Academic Press, San Diego: 101 - 149." type="book" year="1994">Nelson 1994a</bibRefCitation>
), structured by hypotheses of homology.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[113,647,659,1700]" lastBlockId="2.[677,1210,216,1383]" pageId="2" pageNumber="7">
We will not discuss here why all systematicists dealing with phylogenetics search for hierarchies of taxa. Nevertheless, if characters are the parts of taxa relationships, it follows that characters have a hierarchical structure. All systematicists use Descartes’ analytical method to accomplish their task. Some method of historical biogeography (e.g., BPA, PAE, etc.) use the same 
<!--emphasis removed-->modus operandi
: biogeographical areas are decomposed into hierarchical distributions of taxa structured by a concept of area homology.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[677,1210,216,1383]" pageId="2" pageNumber="7">
However, there is a constraint when using this method. As stated by Descartes’ second principle, the analytical method uses an ascending reasoning, i.e. what is known about the whole (taxa or areas) is nothing more than the combination, addition or congruence of the solutions to the partial problems. In other words, what is known about the relationships of taxa is no more than the combination of our knowledge concerning characters. As a consequence, nothing can be learned about characters (or taxa in biogeography) from the relationships of taxa (or areas in biogeography). Nevertheless, this is exactly what parsimony analysis (and almost any other matrix-based phylogenetic or biogeographic method) does: characters lack a hierarchical structure, and their combination always leads to an unrooted tree. Outgroups are added in order to obtain the hierarchical structure and to “polarize” characters. This is a violation of the Cartesian analytical method, since something is learned about the characters (the parts) from the taxa (the whole). Nevertheless, everything that is known about taxa is nothing more that the combination or addition of what is hypothesized about their parts, i.e. characters. The need for this inconsistent, circular reasoning follows from the use of the data matrix. Indeed, the data matrix cannot represent what it is supposed to represent, i.e. hypotheses of relationships (
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." pageId="2" pageNumber="7" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach 2006</bibRefCitation>
). Before discussing this point, we will clarify our use of “character”.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[677,1210,1420,1700]" box="[677,826,1420,1445]" pageId="2" pageNumber="7">
<!--emphasis removed-->Representation
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[677,1210,1420,1700]" lastBlockId="3.[113,647,216,1700]" lastPageId="3" lastPageNumber="8" pageId="2" pageNumber="7">Systematics is concerned with organisms and taxa, their description, discrimination, identification and phylogenetic and biogeographical relationships. The concepts of taxa, character and state belong to systematics. However, as each set of problems is conceptually different, these concepts have different meanings. There is a requirement of consistency: different meanings of the same concepts cannot be incompatible. We will focus in the differences needed for identification and classification purposes.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[113,647,216,1700]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8">
Identification is the procedure that assigns a specimen to a previously established classification (
<bibRefCitation author="PANKHURST R. J." box="[121,303,342,369]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6972" refString="PANKHURST R. J. 1978. - Biological Identification. The Principles and Practice of Identification Methods in Biology. Edward Arnold, London, 104 p." type="book" year="1978">Pankhurst 1978</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="LEBBE J. &amp; VIGNES R." box="[316,568,342,369]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6674" refString="LEBBE J. &amp; VIGNES R. 1991. - Generation de graphes d'identification a partir de descriptions de concepts, in KODRATOFF Y. &amp; DIDAY E. (eds), Induction symbolique et numerique. Cepadues, Toulouse: 193 - 239." type="book" year="1991">Lebbe &amp; Vignes 1991</bibRefCitation>
). Most identification methods proceed by a recursive partitioning of the initial taxonomic sampling in order to isolate a candidate by discriminating classes: its rationale is “divisive”. Identification proceeds by recursively excluding parts of the candidates. On the other hand, the goal of phylogenetics is to propose a natural classification.Its rationale is “agglomerative” (
<bibRefCitation author="JARDINE N. &amp; SIBSON D." box="[120,371,596,622]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6467" refString="JARDINE N. &amp; SIBSON D. 1971. - Mathematical Taxonomy. Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd., London, 286 p." type="book" year="1971">Jardine &amp; Sibson 1971</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="LECOINTRE G. &amp; LE GUYADER H." pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6720" refString="LECOINTRE G. &amp; LE GUYADER H. 2001. - Classification phylogenetique du vivant. Belin, Paris, 543 p." type="book" year="2001">Lecointre &amp; Le Guyader 2001</bibRefCitation>
). Systematics and cladistic biogeography is concerned with the initial problem of grouping two observations, organisms, taxa or distributions as being more closely related than they are to a third (
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J." box="[121,268,754,781]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" pagination="1 - 21" refId="ref6743" refString="NELSON G. J. 1979. - Cladistic analysis and synthesis: Principles and definitions, with a historical note on Adanson's Familles des Plantes (1763 - 1764). Systematic Zoology 28: 1 - 21." type="journal article" year="1979">Nelson 1979</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J." box="[281,353,755,781]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6800" refString="NELSON G. J. 1994 a. - Homology and systematics, in HALL B. K. (ed.), The Hierarchical Basis of Comparative Biology. Academic Press, San Diego: 101 - 149." type="book" year="1994">1994a</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="PLATNICK N. I." box="[366,523,754,781]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" pagination="537 - 546" refId="ref7026" refString="PLATNICK N. I. 1979. - Philosophy and the transformation of cladistics. Systematic Zoology 28: 537 - 546." type="journal article" year="1979">Platnick 1979</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J. &amp; PLATNICK N. I." pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6940" refString="NELSON G. J. &amp; PLATNICK N. I. 1981. - Systematics and Biogeography: Cladistics and Vicariance. Columbia University Press, New York, 567 p." type="book" year="1981">Nelson &amp; Platnick 1981</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="KITCHING I. J. &amp; FOREY P. L. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; LIAMS D. W." box="[274,486,786,812]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6492" refString="KITCHING I. J., FOREY P. L., HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; WIL- LIAMS D. W. 1998. - Cladistics: the Theory and Practice of Parsimony Analysis. Second edition. The Oxford University Press, Oxford, 228 p." type="book" year="1998">
Kitching 
<!--emphasis removed-->et al.
1998
</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; PARENTI L. R." pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6430" refString="HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; PARENTI L. R. 1999. - Cladistic Biogeography: Interpreting Patterns of Plant and Animal Distributions. Second edition. Oxford University Press, Oxford, 187 p." type="book" year="1999">Humphries &amp; Parenti 1999</bibRefCitation>
). The rationale of cladistics leads to the construction of hierarchies, or rooted trees, whereas in order to assign a specimen to a taxon, identification methods choose a class in a pre-established partition. Note that a particular pathway through an identification key (e.g., a printed key) may take a hierarchical appearance; however, the ensemble of the possible pathways of an identification key (the key) is not supposed to be hierarchical. The differences between both procedures and the issue of giving a particular formal structure to each of these concepts are essential to the relevance of the results. The structure of characters used in identification, i.e. descriptors plus attributes (Vignes-Lebbe 2000), and in phylogenetics, i.e. hypotheses of homology (
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J. &amp; PLATNICK N. I." box="[121,380,1293,1319]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6940" refString="NELSON G. J. &amp; PLATNICK N. I. 1981. - Systematics and Biogeography: Cladistics and Vicariance. Columbia University Press, New York, 567 p." type="book" year="1981">Nelson &amp; Platnick 1981</bibRefCitation>
) or relationships (
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J." pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6800" refString="NELSON G. J. 1994 a. - Homology and systematics, in HALL B. K. (ed.), The Hierarchical Basis of Comparative Biology. Academic Press, San Diego: 101 - 149." type="book" year="1994">Nelson 1994a</bibRefCitation>
, b), is different. Identification characters are best represented as partitions, while cladistic relationships are best represented as hierarchies.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[113,647,216,1700]" lastBlockId="3.[677,1210,216,1700]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8">
Is the data matrix able to represent cladistic relationships, i.e. hierarchies? The data matrix is nothing more than a two-dimension table. It is not a matrix, in the mathematical sense. It represents, or it is supposed to represent, hypotheses of homology. Thus, ironically, the data “matrix” contains no data (
<bibRefCitation author="VIGNES R." box="[123,264,1610,1636]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref7117" refString="VIGNES R. 1991. - Caracterisation automatique de groupes biologiques. These de doctorat, Universite Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris 6, Paris, France, 268 p." type="book" year="1991">Vignes 1991</bibRefCitation>
). Data refers to what can be measured. Therefore, it is linked to a single object and explains only what has been observed. In the data matrix, several observations are represented by the same symbol. Thus, they are not data, but concepts (
<bibRefCitation author="FREGE G." box="[683,806,279,305]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6386" refString="FREGE G. 1971. - Ecrits logiques et philosophiques. Editions du Seuil, Paris, 234 p." type="book" year="1971">Frege 1971</bibRefCitation>
; Lebbe 1991; 
<bibRefCitation author="VIGNES R." box="[954,1090,279,305]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref7117" refString="VIGNES R. 1991. - Caracterisation automatique de groupes biologiques. These de doctorat, Universite Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris 6, Paris, France, 268 p." type="book" year="1991">Vignes 1991</bibRefCitation>
). Concepts express more than what has been observed, but are linked to more than the object. 
<bibRefCitation author="HENNIG W." box="[1014,1176,342,369]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6406" refString="HENNIG W. 1968. - Elementos de una sistematica filogenetica. Editorial Universitaria de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, 353 p." type="book" year="1968">Hennig (1968)</bibRefCitation>
already made the distinction in phylogenetics between semaphoronts, from which data can be observed, and holomorphs, the concepts that have semaphoronts as instances or the “lowest taxonomic level”. What does the “data” “matrix” represent? As pointed out by Williams &amp; Ebach, the “data” “matrix” represents classes of cells coded with the same symbol. The “data” “matrix” does not represent homology, i.e. the hierarchical relationship between classes, but the classes of homologues themselves. These classes define a partition, a classificatory structure suitable for identification purposes but not for Cladistics 
<!--emphasis removed-->sensu
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." box="[737,1028,754,781]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006)</bibRefCitation>
. For this reason, no method, except three-item analysis and some versions of compatibility analysis (implicit in 
<bibRefCitation author="LE QUESNE W. J." pageId="3" pageNumber="8" pagination="201 - 205" refId="ref6571" refString="LE QUESNE W. J. 1969. - A method of selection of characters in numerical taxonomy. Systematic Zoology 18: 201 - 205." type="journal article" year="1969">Le Quesne 1969</bibRefCitation>
, 
<bibRefCitation author="LE QUESNE W. J." box="[840,897,850,876]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" pagination="92 - 94" refId="ref6598" refString="LE QUESNE W. J. 1979. - Compatibility analysis and the uniquely derived character concept. Systematic Zoology 28: 92 - 94." type="journal article" year="1979">1979</bibRefCitation>
) finds the target, i.e. a hierarchy of taxa. All current methods find unrooted trees, which are irrelevant, as they were never the target of investigation. In order to root the trees, the addition of several outgroups is required, and hence the analytical rationale violated. Note that even with the addition of outgroups, homologies will not necessarily have a hierarchical structure. They do not even represent partitions. Characters “polarized” by outgroup rooting, rather than having a formal structure, have a narrative one.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[677,1210,216,1700]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8">
The influence of the “data” “matrix” and the confusion between identification and phylogenetics (but see 
<bibRefCitation author="KITCHING I. J. &amp; FOREY P. L. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; LIAMS D. W." box="[802,1062,1261,1287]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6492" refString="KITCHING I. J., FOREY P. L., HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; WIL- LIAMS D. W. 1998. - Cladistics: the Theory and Practice of Parsimony Analysis. Second edition. The Oxford University Press, Oxford, 228 p." type="book" year="1998">
Kitching 
<!--emphasis removed-->et al.
1998: 27
</bibRefCitation>
), i.e. between partitions and hierarchies, is so deep that most authors have tried to adapt their definitions of characters to justify the use of partitions. 
<bibRefCitation author="COLLESS D. H." pageId="3" pageNumber="8" pagination="229 - 233" refId="ref6099" refString="COLLESS D. H. 1985. - On &#34; character &#34; and related terms. Systematic Zoology 34: 229 - 233." type="journal article" year="1985">Colless (1985)</bibRefCitation>
considers a character as a mutually exclusive set of attributes. However, mutually exclusive sets of attributes define partitions, not hierarchies. 
<bibRefCitation author="PIMENTEL R. A. &amp; RIGGINS R." box="[677,965,1483,1509]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" pagination="201 - 209" refId="ref7001" refString="PIMENTEL R. A. &amp; RIGGINS R. 1987. - The nature of cladistic data. Cladistics 3: 201 - 209." type="journal article" year="1987">Pimentel &amp; Riggins (1987)</bibRefCitation>
define cladistic characters as linear morphoclines. Again, morphoclines or series of transformations (
<bibRefCitation author="HENNIG W." box="[984,1133,1546,1572]" pageId="3" pageNumber="8" refId="ref6406" refString="HENNIG W. 1968. - Elementos de una sistematica filogenetica. Editorial Universitaria de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, 353 p." type="book" year="1968">Hennig 1968</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="POGUE M. G. &amp; MICKEVICH M. F." pageId="3" pageNumber="8" pagination="319 - 361" refId="ref7049" refString="POGUE M. G. &amp; MICKEVICH M. F. 1990. - Character definitions and character state delineation: the bete noire of phylogenetic inference. Cladistics 6: 319 - 361." type="journal article" year="1990">Pogue &amp; Mickevich 1990</bibRefCitation>
) define ordered partitions, not hierarchies, with a constraint of order. Cladistic programs may use 
<!--emphasis removed-->ordered
or 
<!--emphasis removed-->additive
characters, which applies to partitions and not to hierarchies.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[143,160,218,243]" box="[143,160,218,243]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">A</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[143,159,973,998]" box="[143,159,973,998]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">E</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[732,750,218,243]" box="[732,750,218,243]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">B</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[732,1062,317,578]" box="[890,914,317,337]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">n1</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[732,1062,317,578]" box="[890,914,384,404]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">n3</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[732,1062,317,578]" box="[890,914,449,469]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">n2</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[732,1062,317,578]" box="[890,914,515,535]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">n4</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[732,1062,317,578]" box="[732,751,553,578]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">D</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[734,749,973,998]" box="[734,749,973,998]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">F</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[113,1210,1371,1478]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">
F 
<!--emphasis removed-->ig
. 1. — 
<!--emphasis removed-->A
, a hierarchical character of six OTUs; 
<!--emphasis removed-->B
, states of the character shown in A; 
<!--emphasis removed-->C -F
, components of the character showed in A; the nodes of a tree correspond to the informative classes of its isomorphic hierarchy. Thus, a rooted tree can be separated into a series of components (trees with a single internal node) or classes (states). However, when interpreted as an ensemble of classes (states), part of the information is lost. When coded as a matrix, almost all of the information is lost; for example, state n1 cannot be coded in a matrix as a state of the same character.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[113,646,1546,1700]" lastBlockId="5.[113,647,216,496]" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="10" pageId="4" pageNumber="9">
<bibRefCitation author="DARLU P. &amp; TASSY P." box="[113,357,1546,1573]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9" refId="ref6123" refString="DARLU P. &amp; TASSY P. 1993. - La reconstruction phylogenetique. Concepts et methodes. Masson, Paris, 245 p." type="book" year="1993">Darlu &amp; Tassy (1993)</bibRefCitation>
define a character as “any observable attribute in an organism”, a definition that does not define relationships, but belongs to a “divisive” rationale. Some recent work (
<bibRefCitation author="WAGNER G. P." box="[501,643,1642,1668]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9" refId="ref7189" refString="WAGNER G. P. (ed.) 2001. - The Character Concept in Evolutionary Biology. Academic Press, San Diego, 622 p." type="book" year="2001">Wagner 2001</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="WIENS J. J." box="[113,239,1673,1699]" pageId="4" pageNumber="9" pagination="689 - 699" refId="ref7217" refString="WIENS J. J. 2001. - Character analysis in morphological phylogenetics: problems and solutions. Systematic Biology 50: 689 - 699." type="journal article" year="2001">Wiens 2001</bibRefCitation>
) gives a certain number of definitions of characters, none of which produces hierarchies.More evidence of the confusion between identification and phylogenetics is the consideration of the diagnostic properties of synapomorphies (see 
<bibRefCitation author="KITCHING I. J. &amp; FOREY P. L. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; LIAMS D. W." pageId="4" pageNumber="9" refId="ref6492" refString="KITCHING I. J., FOREY P. L., HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; WIL- LIAMS D. W. 1998. - Cladistics: the Theory and Practice of Parsimony Analysis. Second edition. The Oxford University Press, Oxford, 228 p." type="book" year="1998">
Kitching 
<!--emphasis removed-->et al.
1998: 24
</bibRefCitation>
, for examples). Some authors have even judged the relevance of phylogenetic methods considering their “diagnostic performance” (
<bibRefCitation author="FARRIS J. S." pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="403 - 410" refId="ref6365" refString="FARRIS J. S. 2000. - Diagnostic efficiency of three-taxon analysis. Cladistics 16: 403 - 410." type="journal article" year="2000">Farris 2000</bibRefCitation>
). None of them has succeeded in explaining why we search for hierarchies of taxa and why the methods they use are unable to find them. If multistate characters can be decomposed into a series of components, it follows that components are also hierarchies. We redefine components as hierarchies having a single internal node (Fig. 1).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[113,647,533,781]" box="[113,273,533,559]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">TERMINOLOGY</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[113,647,533,781]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." box="[113,456,564,590]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006: 410)</bibRefCitation>
introduce, under their section “Terminology”, some new terms to describe a data matrix. They use these terms to redefine some concepts. However, for some of the concepts they use, we think that the difficulty is formal or logical rather than terminological. We focus here on the notion of “component” to illustrate it.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[113,647,818,1700]" box="[113,240,818,844]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">
<!--emphasis removed-->Components
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[113,647,818,1700]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">
Following 
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J." box="[224,404,849,876]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="1 - 21" refId="ref6743" refString="NELSON G. J. 1979. - Cladistic analysis and synthesis: Principles and definitions, with a historical note on Adanson's Familles des Plantes (1763 - 1764). Systematic Zoology 28: 1 - 21." type="journal article" year="1979">Nelson (1979: 5)</bibRefCitation>
, “cladistic components are branch points. A particular branch point is defined by the branch tips (terminals, or terms) to which it leads”.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[113,647,818,1700]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">
<bibRefCitation author="WILKINSON M." box="[136,384,976,1002]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="343 - 368" refId="ref7265" refString="WILKINSON M. 1994. - Common cladistic information and its consensus representation: reduced Adams and reduced cladistic consensus trees and profiles. Systematic Biology 43: 343 - 368." type="journal article" year="1994">Wilkinson (1994: 344)</bibRefCitation>
considers that “Components (= clades, monophyletic groups, holophyletic groups, clusters) are statements of relationships that apply, through inclusion or exclusion, to all taxa under consideration”. The first part of the sentence (clades, monophyletic groups, holophyletic groups or clusters) seems to deal with classes, the second (statements of relationships) clearly with hierarchies (he also states that “components are the most inclusive unambiguous single statements of cladistic information that might be shared by a set of fundamental trees” and the third (inclusion or exclusion) with partitions. The rest of our paper considers components either as classes or as partitions.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[113,647,818,1700]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">
<bibRefCitation author="KITCHING I. J. &amp; FOREY P. L. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; LIAMS D. W." box="[136,425,1420,1446]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" refId="ref6492" refString="KITCHING I. J., FOREY P. L., HUMPHRIES C. J. &amp; WIL- LIAMS D. W. 1998. - Cladistics: the Theory and Practice of Parsimony Analysis. Second edition. The Oxford University Press, Oxford, 228 p." type="book" year="1998">
Kitching 
<!--emphasis removed-->et al.
(1998: 203)
</bibRefCitation>
define a component as “a group of taxa as determined by the branching pattern of a cladogram. For example, in a group comprising three taxa A, B, and C, where B and C are more closely related to each other than either is to A, there are two components, ABC and BC”.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[113,647,818,1700]" lastBlockId="5.[677,1210,216,1700]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J." box="[136,495,1610,1636]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="259 - 271" refId="ref7378" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J. 2003. - Component coding, three-item coding, and consensus methods. Systematic Biology 52: 259 - 271." type="journal article" year="2003">Williams &amp; Humphries (2003)</bibRefCitation>
analyzed the asymmetry that exists between a data matrix and a cladogram. The asymmetry comes from the difference that exists between components, represented by binary characters in a data matrix, and a cladogram, represented by a single multistate character in a data matrix. This difference is only detected by the conversion of both data matrix and characters into three-item statements. The conversion from a cladogram to a data matrix, called component coding, means that components can be associated to columns of a data matrix, or character points 
<!--emphasis removed-->sensu
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." box="[735,1021,501,528]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006)</bibRefCitation>
:
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[677,1210,216,1700]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">
“Component coding follows each internal node in a cladogram to all its tips and enters those data with scores of 
<quantity box="[832,876,596,622]" metricMagnitude="-2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.54" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" unit="in" value="1.0">1 in</quantity>
the matrix. All remaining taxa not supported by that node are scored with a 0. If a cladogram has more than one node, then one component is coded for each node” (
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J." pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="259 - 271" refId="ref7378" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J. 2003. - Component coding, three-item coding, and consensus methods. Systematic Biology 52: 259 - 271." type="journal article" year="2003">Williams &amp; Humphries 2003</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[677,1210,216,1700]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">
It results from their statement that components are synonyms of binary characters (“[…] three binary characters (three components) […]”) and they are represented as hierarchies: A(BCDE), AB(CDE), ABC(DE) (
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J." box="[805,1144,881,907]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="259 - 271" refId="ref7378" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J. 2003. - Component coding, three-item coding, and consensus methods. Systematic Biology 52: 259 - 271." type="journal article" year="2003">Williams &amp; Humphries 2003</bibRefCitation>
: table 2). In fact, a correct hierarchical representation should be ([A]([B][C][D][E])), ([A][B]([C][D][E])), ([A][B][C]([D][E])). The classes represented by the brackets (“[
<!--emphasis removed-->x
]”) are singletons. In order to simplify the notion, we will not represent singletons. However, we consider essential the representation of the root, i.e. the class that contains all the individuals: (A(BCDE)), (AB(CDE)), (ABC(DE)).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[677,1210,216,1700]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J." box="[699,1032,1166,1192]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="259 - 271" refId="ref7378" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J. 2003. - Component coding, three-item coding, and consensus methods. Systematic Biology 52: 259 - 271." type="journal article" year="2003">Williams &amp; Humphries (2003)</bibRefCitation>
and 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006)</bibRefCitation>
extend the use of component to the data matrix. In their description of the data matrix, 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." box="[677,964,1261,1288]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006)</bibRefCitation>
define components as the class of the terminal taxa that have the same “character-state”. This use implies a new meaning of component: the representation of a class of a primary homology hypothesis (
<!--emphasis removed-->sensu
<bibRefCitation author="DE PINNA M. C. C." box="[1025,1175,1388,1414]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="367 - 394" refId="ref6148" refString="DE PINNA M. C. C. 1991. - Concepts and tests of homology in the cladistic paradigm. Cladistics 7: 367 - 394." type="journal article" year="1991">de Pinna 1991</bibRefCitation>
) in a data matrix. 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." box="[826,1156,1420,1446]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006: 411)</bibRefCitation>
state that they follow 
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J." box="[852,1008,1451,1477]" pageId="5" pageNumber="10" pagination="1 - 21" refId="ref6743" refString="NELSON G. J. 1979. - Cladistic analysis and synthesis: Principles and definitions, with a historical note on Adanson's Familles des Plantes (1763 - 1764). Systematic Zoology 28: 1 - 21." type="journal article" year="1979">Nelson (1979)</bibRefCitation>
when they refer to components. In their table 5 they refer to positive and negative components without any allusion to a cladogram. Nevertheless, if components are “branching points”, they should be linked to cladograms.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[677,1210,216,1700]" lastBlockId="6.[113,647,216,812]" lastPageId="6" lastPageNumber="11" pageId="5" pageNumber="10">Nelson’s definition, however, contains some ambiguity. In its first part, components are considered branching points [of trees]. Branching points may be identified by a rooted tree with a single chosen node with all the less inclusive terminals collapsed on to the chosen node (branch point) and the remaining terminals collapsed at the root. In the second part of the same definition, Nelson states that a branching point is defined by “the branch tips (terminals, or terms) to which it leads”. Then, a branching point is not a tree with a single internal node but a single class, or group.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[113,647,216,812]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11">Since Nelson’s definition, components have either been considered hierarchies, partitions or groups (i.e. classes) of terminal taxa. Only the former requires a cladogram. The reason for the confusion generated is, in our opinion, the intrinsic ambiguity of what the data matrix is actually representing, compared to what it is supposed to represent. In order to clarify the concept of component, we need to introduce some formal, or mathematical, classificatory notions.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[113,647,849,1700]" box="[113,283,849,875]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11">
<!--emphasis removed-->Character points
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[113,647,849,1700]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11">
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." box="[113,395,881,908]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006)</bibRefCitation>
call 
<!--emphasis removed-->character points
the columns of a data matrix. They do not call them simply characters because, from their point of view, characters are relationships, while the columns of a data matrix are not. Whereas we agree with their viewpoint that characters and homology are relationships and that the data matrix cannot represent them (see below). We also agree with Williams &amp; Ebach that homology defines a relationship between homologues. What, then, are the homologues? 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." pageId="6" pageNumber="11" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006: 412)</bibRefCitation>
state that: “A cell might be more conventionally understood as equivalent to a homologue, a part of an organism”, following 
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J." box="[113,286,1293,1319]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11" refId="ref6800" refString="NELSON G. J. 1994 a. - Homology and systematics, in HALL B. K. (ed.), The Hierarchical Basis of Comparative Biology. Academic Press, San Diego: 101 - 149." type="book" year="1994">Nelson (1994a)</bibRefCitation>
and 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W." box="[344,530,1293,1319]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11" pagination="191 - 224" refId="ref7297" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. 2004. - Homologues and homology, phenetics and cladistics: 150 years of progress, in WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; FOREY P. L. (eds), Milestones in Systematics. CRC, The Systematics Association, London: 191 - 224." type="book chapter" year="2004">Williams (2004)</bibRefCitation>
. They also maintain that “a relationship might be usefully understood as the relation of homology, based on shared homologues” (2006: 413). Later they declare that “if our knowledge is rather better and we are able to say that the homologues of feathers are lizard scales then this might be construed as a multistate character point, with increased complexity”.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[113,647,849,1700]" lastBlockId="6.[677,1210,216,876]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11">
Let us admit that homologues are part of organisms. Are organisms formally individuals? For Hennig organisms, seen as holomorphs, are classes (
<bibRefCitation author="HENNIG W." pageId="6" pageNumber="11" refId="ref6406" refString="HENNIG W. 1968. - Elementos de una sistematica filogenetica. Editorial Universitaria de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, 353 p." type="book" year="1968">Hennig 1968: 86</bibRefCitation>
). He states that organisms can be seen as “the lowest taxonomic unit of a group”, whereas the formal individuals, the “elements of systematics” are the semaphoronts, i.e. an organism during a very short period of its life. Are homologues parts of semaphoronts or parts of holomorphs? In order to deal with these different approaches, operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were defined (
<bibRefCitation author="SOKAL R. R. &amp; SNEATH P. H. A." pageId="6" pageNumber="11" refId="ref7084" refString="SOKAL R. R. &amp; SNEATH P. H. A. 1963. - Principles of Numerical Taxonomy. W. H. Freeman, San Francisco, 573 p." type="book" year="1963">Sokal &amp; Sneath 1963</bibRefCitation>
). OTUs allow an operational treatment of classes, i.e. holomorphs, as if they were formal individuals, i.e. semaphoronts.Homologues are parts of holomorphs and cannot be seen as observations or specimens. This allows the representation in a hierarchy of multistate relationships of homology and the use of any taxon as a terminal. Homologues, then, can be seen as the parts of the OTUs, whatever their nomenclatural or taxonomic rank may be, related by homology. Our definition does not contradict Williams &amp; Ebach approach, because their taxic point can refer to any taxa, not only to organisms. If a cell represents a homologue, it can instantiate any OTU. A homologue may not only be a part of an organism but a part of any OTU.
</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection _generate="added" lastPageId="9" lastPageNumber="14" pageId="6" pageNumber="11" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="6.[677,869,945,971]" box="[677,869,945,971]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11">
<heading allCaps="true" box="[677,869,945,971]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="6" pageNumber="11" reason="1">PROPOSITION</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="6.[677,1210,1008,1699]" lastBlockId="7.[113,647,216,1700]" lastPageId="7" lastPageNumber="12" pageId="6" pageNumber="11">
We have shown that characters necessarily need to have a hierarchical structure, as a requirement of consistency of the method. We have also shown that a matrix cannot represent hierarchical hypotheses of primary homology (
<bibRefCitation author="DE PINNA M. C. C." box="[986,1147,1134,1161]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11" pagination="367 - 394" refId="ref6148" refString="DE PINNA M. C. C. 1991. - Concepts and tests of homology in the cladistic paradigm. Cladistics 7: 367 - 394." type="journal article" year="1991">de Pinna 1991</bibRefCitation>
). Can a different representation be found? Hierarchies are usually represented in phylogenetics and biogeography with Venn diagrams (e.g., 
<bibRefCitation author="HENNIG W." box="[1051,1206,1229,1255]" pageId="6" pageNumber="11" refId="ref6406" refString="HENNIG W. 1968. - Elementos de una sistematica filogenetica. Editorial Universitaria de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires, 353 p." type="book" year="1968">Hennig 1968</bibRefCitation>
: figs 18, 19). Venn diagrams can be transcribed to a series of taxon names in parentheses, where each pair of parentheses indicates a class. However, using parentheses has a drawback: a character coded in 50 taxa, drawn in parentheses, will occupy a lot of space and not be easily readable. One hundred hypotheses of relationships for 50 terminal taxa may require many pages to be written, leading to an incomprehensible message. A system where the names of taxa are replaced by a code, e.g., a single letter, as in the computer program MATRIX (
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J. &amp; LADIGES P. Y." pageId="6" pageNumber="11" refId="ref6880" refString="NELSON G. J. &amp; LADIGES P. Y. 1993. - Matrix 1.0. Published by the authors, New York; Melbourne." type="book" year="1993">Nelson &amp; Ladiges 1993</bibRefCitation>
), could be imagined. From a programmer’s viewpoint, parsing such a file is easier. Nevertheless, understanding hypotheses of homology becomes extremely difficult with such a representation. Another way of representing primary hypotheses of homology could be by directly drawing the characters as rooted trees. This straightforward representation is easily readable and explicit. But again, whereas a data matrix can summarize a vast quantity of information (even if it is an extremely inadequate way) in a compact way, a huge number of trees will require a lot of space. We propose a new representation of hierarchies that, while correcting the inadequacy of the data matrix, preserves its advantages, mainly of concision.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="7.[113,647,216,1700]" pageId="7" pageNumber="12">
Our proposition intends to guarantee all the advantages of the representation of conjectures of primary homology in the form of a table, while enhancing it by expressing the relationships among homologues. The way relationships are usually expressed is by applying the same symbols, e.g., numbers, or, for aligned molecular sequences, the symbols “A”, “T”/“U”, “C”, “G”, and “gap”, to the taxa presenting them. Each symbol represents a character-state or the intension of a class (a “component” in the terminology used by 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." pageId="7" pageNumber="12" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach 2006</bibRefCitation>
). The hierarchical structure of characters is built by placing each state (or “positive components”) inside another, more general state or into the root (negative components 
<!--emphasis removed-->sensu
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." pageId="7" pageNumber="12" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach 2006</bibRefCitation>
). If this hierarchy of components is explicit in the data matrix, then the representation would become relevant, while remaining concise and readable by anyone who is used to reading such tables. We propose to add an additional row with the hierarchy of character states given in parentheses (Fig. 2). This simple improvement of the data matrix converts it into a representation for the analysis of hierarchical relationships. It also allows the representation of states that cannot be coded in a matrix, that is, states with no instances (Fig. 2). This is because our representation constitutes an isomorphism with hierarchies. Note that a state, as defined here, is an informative class of a hierarchical character.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="7.[113,647,216,1700]" lastBlockId="7.[677,1210,216,1700]" pageId="7" pageNumber="12">
Our proposition, as simple as it may appear, has some important consequences. The line we propose to add to the matrix, i.e. the hierarchy of states, represents only a hypothesis of homology, without reference to the homologues. In the original matrix, only the different classes of homologues are represented. Our solution clearly distinguishes, and explicitly separates, the extension of the structure of concepts (the matrix) and its intension (the subordination of characters states). As a result, homologies (relationships) are coded separate from groups of homologues – the components of 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." pageId="7" pageNumber="12" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006</bibRefCitation>
: fig. 1). With our enhancement, the systematist, rather than the algorithms or outgroups, decide on the hypotheses of homology.Such hypotheses can be changed should new knowledge become available, independently of the homologues; they can also modify the hypotheses of primary homology without changing the representation of homologues, e.g., after an analysis and a re-examination of the hypothesis. This is achieved simply by changing the hierarchy of character-states in the enhanced matrix (Fig. 2). Our notation allows the coding of complex characters, i.e. characters with two or more states. Complex hypotheses of homology cannot be simply represented in the matrix. This is the case for cladistic biogeography. Biogeographic analysis uses cladograms of taxa as the primary hypothesis of area homology (
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J. &amp; PLATNICK N. I." box="[872,1133,944,971]" pageId="7" pageNumber="12" refId="ref6940" refString="NELSON G. J. &amp; PLATNICK N. I. 1981. - Systematics and Biogeography: Cladistics and Vicariance. Columbia University Press, New York, 567 p." type="book" year="1981">Nelson &amp; Platnick 1981</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="EBACH M. C." pageId="7" pageNumber="12" pagination="169 - 172" refId="ref6274" refString="EBACH M. C. 2003. - Area cladistics. Biologist 50: 169 - 172." type="journal article" year="2003">Ebach 2003</bibRefCitation>
). Each hypothesis of hierarchical relationships among areas corresponds to the paralogy-free subtrees extracted from the cladograms of taxa (
<bibRefCitation author="NELSON G. J. &amp; LADIGES P. Y." pageId="7" pageNumber="12" pagination="1 - 58" refId="ref6907" refString="NELSON G. J. &amp; LADIGES P. Y. 1996. - Paralogy in cladistic biogeography and analysis of paralogy-free subtrees. American Museum Novitates 3167: 1 - 58." type="journal article" year="1996">Nelson &amp; Ladiges 1996</bibRefCitation>
; 
<bibRefCitation author="EBACH M. C. &amp; NEWMAN R. A. &amp; WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; WALSH S. A." box="[864,1056,1071,1098]" pageId="7" pageNumber="12" pagination="781 - 787" refId="ref6323" refString="EBACH M. C., NEWMAN R. A., WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; WALSH S. A. 2005. - Assumption 2: opaque to intuition? Journal of Biogeography 32: 781 - 787." type="journal article" year="2005">
Ebach 
<!--emphasis removed-->et al.
2005
</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="7.[677,1210,216,1700]" pageId="7" pageNumber="12">
The matrix shown in Figure 2 illustrates that tables are unable to represent even relatively simple hypotheses of primary homology. The only solution for representing complex hypotheses of homology in a “data” “matrix” is to transform them into a series of additive binary characters. However, it has been shown (Nelson 1993) that coding the hypothesis as separate binary, independent, characters, is not equivalent to coding it as states of the same character, as asserted by some authors (
<bibRefCitation author="KLUGE A. G." box="[986,1118,1388,1414]" pageId="7" pageNumber="12" pagination="246 - 259" refId="ref6542" refString="KLUGE A. G. 1993. - Three-taxon transformation in phylogenetic inference: ambiguity and distortion as regards explanatory power. Cladistics 9: 246 - 259." type="journal article" year="1993">Kluge 1993</bibRefCitation>
).
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="7.[677,1210,216,1700]" pageId="7" pageNumber="12">
It is impossible to represent these complex trees in a matrix, but straightforward using the method presented herein. The hierarchical account allows the representation of any phylogenetic or biogeographic hypotheses. In biogeography, the impossibility of representing this kind of information has led to the development of methods, such as BPA (
<bibRefCitation author="WILEY E. O." pageId="7" pageNumber="12" pagination="271 - 290" refId="ref7243" refString="WILEY E. O. 1988. - Parsimony analysis and vicariance biogeography. Systematic Zoology 37: 271 - 290." type="journal article" year="1988">Wiley 1988</bibRefCitation>
), that are defective (
<bibRefCitation author="EBACH M. C. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J." pageId="7" pageNumber="12" pagination="427 - 444" refId="ref6292" refString="EBACH M. C. &amp; HUMPHRIES C. J. 2002. - Cladistic biogeography and the art of discovery. Journal of Biogeography 29: 427 - 444." type="journal article" year="2002">Ebach &amp; Humphries 2002</bibRefCitation>
). However, with the notation we propose
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="8.[113,1210,1567,1700]" pageId="8" pageNumber="13">
F 
<!--emphasis removed-->ig
. 2. — The inadequacy of the matrix for representing hierarchical relationships: 
<!--emphasis removed-->A
, the usual matrix coding where characters are represented as partitions (see the partition C 
<subScript attach="left" box="[481,488,1597,1609]" fontSize="5" pageId="8" pageNumber="13">0</subScript>
at right); this poor representation introduces a high amount of ambiguity often resulting in a parsimony analysis, in a high number of most parsimonious trees leading to unresolved relationships when a consensus method is applied; 
<!--emphasis removed-->B
, the formal coding proposed here: characters are represented as hierarchies; the hierarchical structure is given by the upper line, with the character-states in parentheses. Note that character C 
<subScript attach="left" box="[725,732,1665,1677]" fontSize="5" pageId="8" pageNumber="13">0</subScript>
is extremely ambiguous: four hierarchical representations of the same character are shown (characters C 
<subScript attach="left" box="[504,511,1688,1700]" fontSize="5" pageId="8" pageNumber="13">1</subScript>
to C 
<quantity box="[551,579,1680,1700]" metricMagnitude="-1" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.016" pageId="8" pageNumber="13" unit="in" value="4.0">
<subScript attach="left" box="[551,558,1688,1700]" fontSize="5" pageId="8" pageNumber="13">4</subScript>
in
</quantity>
B) implying very different assumptions concerning homology.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[113,647,216,305]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">the source trees are coded directly, independent from the number of areas of distribution and the complexity of relationships.</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection _generate="added" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="9.[114,304,374,400]" box="[114,304,374,400]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<heading allCaps="true" box="[114,304,374,400]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" reason="1">CONCLUSION</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[113,648,437,1478]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Cladistics is an analytical method of reasoning. There is a widely accepted consensus that the best representation of phylogenetic and biogeographic relationships is hierarchical. Our formalization of classificatory structures, as is generally done in the knowledge analysis field, and the analytical method, following Descartes, implies that characters (or relationships of distributions of taxa) must have a hierarchical structure in order to be consistent.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[113,648,437,1478]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
Cladistics can be seen as a method of combination of hierarchies. However, as shown by 
<bibRefCitation author="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C." pageId="9" pageNumber="14" pagination="409 - 420" refId="ref7350" refString="WILLIAMS D. W. &amp; EBACH M. C. 2006. - The data matrix. Geodiversitas 28 (3): 409 - 420." type="journal article" year="2006">Williams &amp; Ebach (2006)</bibRefCitation>
, the “data” “matrix” is an inadequate way of representing hierarchies. We have shown that this is the main reason that explains why all current methods do not find hierarchies of taxa but, instead, unrooted trees.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[113,648,437,1478]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Our proposal allows the representation of hierarchical hypotheses of taxon or area homology. It allows the explicit representation of the extension and the intension of the hypothesis, the latter being absent from current “data” “matrix” representation. Our proposition is of no help to systematists until it can be implemented in a computer program that is able to read and “understand” (i.e. that is able to preserve the sense of) the new representation. We are currently developing such a program that will manipulate, decompose and combine hierarchies or rooted trees using three-item analysis, the only cladistic method that can use our representation, for it is the only method to explicitly require hierarchical hypotheses of homology. In short, we will be able to go out of the matrix.</paragraph>
</subSection>
<subSection _generate="added" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="15" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="acknowledgments">
<paragraph blockId="9.[113,327,1546,1572]" box="[113,327,1546,1572]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<heading bold="true" box="[113,327,1546,1572]" fontSize="11" level="1" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" reason="5">
<!--emphasis removed-->Acknowledgements
</heading>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[113,646,1578,1700]" lastBlockId="9.[677,1210,216,368]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">D. M. Williams and L. Parenti contributed to the improvement of the text. We acknowledge our colleagues in the SRISC (Systematics, Research in Informatics and Structure of Cladograms) and in the Systematics and Evolution of Embryophyte of the UMR 5143 for useful discussions. We specially acknowledge D. M. Williams and M. C. Ebach for identifying a fundamental problem in phylogenetic systematics and cladistic biogeography.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" box="[677,852,438,464]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">REFERENCES</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6034" type="book">
<author box="[677,849,484,508]" case="AC" fns="I" in="J.-P." ins="D" ln="BARTHELEMY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">BARTHÉLEMY J.-P.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[879,1020,484,509]" case="AC" fns="I" in="A." ins="D" ln="GUENOCHE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">GUÉNOCHE A.</author>
<year box="[1026,1080,485,509]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1988</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.07669055" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Les arbres et les représentations des proximités
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[1063,1206,510,534]" jopScore="2.9239483" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Masson, Paris</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[707,770,537,561]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">239 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6062" type="book">
<author box="[677,786,564,589]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G." ins="D" ln="CELEUX" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">CELEUX G.</author>
, 
<author box="[800,891,564,587]" case="AC" fns="I" in="E." ins="D" ln="DIDAY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">DIDAY E.</author>
, 
<author box="[906,1030,564,589]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G." ins="D" ln="GOVAERT" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">GOVAERT G.</author>
, 
<author box="[1045,1209,564,587]" case="AC" fns="I" in="Y." ins="D" ln="LECHEVALLIER" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">LECHEVALLIER Y.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[733,947,590,613]" case="AC" fns="I" in="H." ins="D" ln="RALAMBONDRAINY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">RALAMBONDRAINY H.</author>
<year box="[953,1007,591,615]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1989</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.07769013" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Classification automatique des données
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="2.2160244" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Dunod Informatique; Bordas, Paris</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[766,829,643,667]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">285 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6099" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,832,670,695]" case="AC" fns="I" in="D. H." ins="D" ln="COLLESS" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">COLLESS D. H.</author>
<year box="[840,895,671,695]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1985</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.2981846" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">On “character” and related terms</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[774,948,696,720]" jopScore="1.4714147" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematic Zoology
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[955,983,696,720]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="volume">34</part>
: 
<pagination box="[993,1080,696,720]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="pagination">229-233</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6123" type="book">
<author box="[677,763,723,746]" case="AC" fns="I" in="P." ins="D" ln="DARLU" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">DARLU P.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[790,866,723,746]" case="AC" fns="I" in="P." ins="D" ln="TASSY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">TASSY P.</author>
<year box="[869,921,723,747]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1993</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.10853157" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->La reconstruction phylogénétique. Concepts et méthodes
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[974,1111,748,772]" jopScore="2.9239483" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Masson, Paris</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[1121,1184,748,772]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">245 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6148" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,880,775,800]" case="AC" fns="I" in="M. C. C." ins="D" ln="DE PINNA" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<subScript attach="left" box="[677,703,781,797]" fontSize="7" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">DE</subScript>
PINNA M. C. C.
</author>
<year box="[888,943,776,800]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1991</year>
. — 
<title pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Concepts and tests of homology in the cladistic paradigm</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[1088,1181,801,825]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Cladistics
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[1190,1206,802,825]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="volume">7</part>
: 
<pagination box="[707,794,828,852]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="pagination">367-394</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6176" type="book">
<author box="[677,812,855,878]" case="AC" fns="I" in="R." ins="D" ln="DESCARTES" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">DESCARTES R.</author>
<year box="[817,870,856,880]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1637</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.1451533" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Discours de la méthode pour bien conduire sa raison et chercher la vérité dans les sciences, plus la Dioptrique, les Météores et la Géométrie qui sont des essais de cette méthode
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="0.24033704" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">De l’imprimerie de I. Maire, Leyde</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[848,899,960,984]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">79 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6228" type="book">
<author box="[677,764,987,1010]" case="AC" fns="I" in="E." ins="D" ln="DIDAY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">DIDAY E.</author>
<year box="[769,822,988,1012]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1991</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.14564969" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Des objets de l’analyse des données à ceux de l’analyse des connaissances</title>
, 
<!--emphasis removed-->in
<volumeTitle box="[1071,1203,1014,1037]" jopScore="0.09859527" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">KODRATOFF Y</volumeTitle>
. &amp; 
<editor box="[733,822,1040,1063]" case="AC" fns="I" in="E." ins="D" ln="DIDAY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">DIDAY E.</editor>
(eds), 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="2.157419" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Induction symbolique numérique à partir de données.
Cépadués, Toulouse
</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[1087,1150,1066,1090]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">460 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6274" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,818,1093,1118]" case="AC" fns="I" in="M. C." ins="D" ln="EBACH" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">EBACH M. C.</author>
<year box="[826,882,1094,1118]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">2003</year>
. — 
<title box="[926,1075,1092,1117]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Area cladistics</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[1086,1169,1092,1116]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Biologist
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[1177,1206,1092,1116]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="volume">50</part>
: 
<pagination box="[707,794,1119,1143]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="pagination">169-172</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6292" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,812,1146,1171]" case="AC" fns="I" in="M. C." ins="D" ln="EBACH" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">EBACH M. C.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[848,1020,1146,1171]" case="AC" fns="I" in="C. J." ins="D" ln="HUMPHRIES" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">HUMPHRIES C. J.</author>
<year box="[1027,1081,1147,1171]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">2002</year>
. — 
<title pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Cladistic biogeography and the art of discovery</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Journal of Biogeography
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[835,863,1198,1222]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="volume">29</part>
: 
<pagination box="[873,961,1198,1222]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="pagination">427-444</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6323" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,799,1225,1250]" case="AC" fns="I" in="M. C." ins="D" ln="EBACH" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">EBACH M. C.</author>
, 
<author box="[810,950,1225,1250]" case="AC" fns="I" in="R. A." ins="D" ln="NEWMAN" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">NEWMAN R. A.</author>
, 
<author box="[960,1113,1225,1248]" case="AC" fns="I" in="D. W." ins="D" ln="WILLIAMS" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">WILLIAMS D. W.</author>
&amp; 
<author case="AC" fns="I" in="S. A." ins="D" ln="WALSH" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">WALSH S. A.</author>
<year box="[762,816,1253,1277]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">2005</year>
. — 
<title box="[858,1210,1251,1275]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Assumption 2: opaque to intuition?</title>
<journalOrPublisher box="[707,928,1278,1302]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Journal of Biogeography
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[934,962,1278,1302]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="volume">32</part>
: 
<pagination box="[972,1060,1278,1302]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="pagination">781-787</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6365" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,782,1305,1329]" case="AC" fns="I" in="J. S." ins="D" ln="FARRIS" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">FARRIS J. S.</author>
<year box="[786,839,1305,1329]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">2000</year>
. — 
<title pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Diagnostic efficiency of three-taxon analysis</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[793,882,1331,1355]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Cladistics
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[889,917,1330,1354]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="volume">16</part>
: 
<pagination box="[927,1014,1331,1355]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" type="pagination">403-410</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6386" type="book">
<author box="[677,768,1358,1382]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G." ins="D" ln="FREGE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">FREGE G.</author>
<year box="[774,828,1358,1382]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1971</year>
. — 
<title box="[867,1156,1357,1383]" jopScore="0.055333335" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Écrits logiques et philosophiques
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="2.185265" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Éditions du Seuil, Paris</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[913,976,1384,1408]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">234 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6406" type="book">
<author box="[677,792,1410,1433]" case="AC" fns="I" in="W." ins="D" ln="HENNIG" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">HENNIG W.</author>
<year box="[799,853,1411,1435]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1968</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.110171795" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Elementos de una sistemática filogenética
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="1.7357671" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Editorial Universitaria de Buenos Aires, Buenos Aires</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[846,910,1463,1487]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">353 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6430" type="book">
<author box="[677,847,1490,1515]" case="AC" fns="I" in="C. J." ins="D" ln="HUMPHRIES" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">HUMPHRIES C. J.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[883,1023,1490,1513]" case="AC" fns="I" in="L. R." ins="D" ln="PARENTI" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">PARENTI L. R.</author>
<year box="[1031,1085,1491,1515]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1999</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.3770699" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Cladistic Biogeography: Interpreting Patterns of Plant and Animal Distributions
. Second edition
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="2.9524856" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Oxford University Press, Oxford</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[852,915,1569,1593]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">187 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6467" type="book">
<author box="[677,789,1596,1619]" case="AC" fns="I" in="N." ins="D" ln="JARDINE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">JARDINE N.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[824,927,1596,1621]" case="AC" fns="I" in="D." ins="D" ln="SIBSON" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">SIBSON D.</author>
<year box="[934,988,1597,1621]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1971</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.49961686" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Mathematical Taxonomy
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[780,1065,1622,1646]" jopScore="3.7254214" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd., London</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[1074,1138,1622,1646]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">286 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="9.[677,1210,438,1700]" lastBlockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="15" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="15" pageId="9" pageNumber="14" refId="ref6492" type="book">
<author box="[677,821,1649,1672]" case="AC" fns="I" in="I. J." ins="D" ln="KITCHING" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">KITCHING I. J.</author>
, 
<author box="[832,944,1649,1672]" case="AC" fns="I" in="P. L." ins="D" ln="FOREY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">FOREY P. L.</author>
, 
<author box="[958,1127,1649,1673]" case="AC" fns="I" in="C. J." ins="D" ln="HUMPHRIES" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">HUMPHRIES C. J.</author>
&amp; WIL- 
<author box="[707,839,1675,1698]" case="AC" fns="I" in="D. W." ins="D" ln="LIAMS" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">LIAMS D. W.</author>
<year box="[847,903,1676,1700]" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">1998</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.41897798" lastPageId="10" lastPageNumber="15" pageId="9" pageNumber="14">
<!--emphasis removed-->Cladistics: the Theory and Practice of Parsimony Analysis.
Second edition
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="2.5982885" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">The Oxford University Press, Oxford</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[475,538,241,265]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">228 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6542" type="journal article">
<author box="[115,244,268,293]" case="AC" fns="I" in="A. G." ins="D" ln="KLUGE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">KLUGE A. G.</author>
<year box="[252,306,269,293]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1993</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Three-taxon transformation in phylogenetic inference: ambiguity and distortion as regards explanatory power</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[411,500,321,345]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Cladistics
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[507,522,321,345]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">9</part>
: 
<pagination box="[532,619,321,345]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">246-259</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6571" type="journal article">
<author box="[115,290,348,373]" case="AC" fns="I" in="W. J." ins="D" ln="LE QUESNE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LE QUESNE W. J.</author>
<year box="[298,353,349,373]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1969</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">A method of selection of characters in numerical taxonomy</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematic Zoology
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[182,210,400,424]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">18</part>
: 
<pagination box="[220,307,400,424]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">201-205</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6598" type="journal article">
<author box="[115,284,427,452]" case="AC" fns="I" in="W. J." ins="D" ln="LE QUESNE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LE QUESNE W. J.</author>
<year box="[290,344,428,452]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1979</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Compatibility analysis and the uniquely derived character concept</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematic Zoology
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[224,252,480,504]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">28</part>
: 
<pagination box="[262,323,480,504]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">92-94</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6624" type="book">
<author box="[115,195,506,529]" case="AC" fns="I" in="J." ins="D" ln="LEBBE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LEBBE J.</author>
<year box="[201,255,507,531]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1991</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.10899285" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Représentation des concepts en biologie et médecine. Introduction à l’analyse des connaissances et à l’identification assistée par ordinateur
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="4.2036977" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Thèse de doctorat, spécialité Sciences de la vie, Université Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris 6, Paris, France</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[511,574,612,636]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">281 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6674" type="book">
<author box="[115,195,639,662]" case="AC" fns="I" in="J." ins="D" ln="LEBBE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LEBBE J.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[227,328,639,662]" case="AC" fns="I" in="R." ins="D" ln="VIGNES" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">VIGNES R.</author>
<year box="[334,388,640,664]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1991</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.13485412" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Génération de graphes d’identification à partir de descriptions de concepts</title>
, 
<!--emphasis removed-->in
<volumeTitle box="[145,275,692,715]" jopScore="0.0683329" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">KODRATOFF Y</volumeTitle>
. &amp; 
<editor box="[310,396,692,715]" case="AC" fns="I" in="E." ins="D" ln="DIDAY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">DIDAY E.</editor>
(eds), 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="1.2448035" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Induction symbolique et numérique
. Cépadués, Toulouse: 193
</journalOrPublisher>
-239.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6720" type="book">
<author box="[115,251,745,769]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G." ins="D" ln="LECOINTRE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LECOINTRE G.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[281,432,745,769]" case="AC" fns="I" in="H." ins="D" ln="LE GUYADER" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LE GUYADER H.</author>
<year box="[436,488,745,769]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">2001</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.07678236" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Classification phylogénétique du vivant
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[391,504,770,794]" jopScore="2.062959" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Belin, Paris</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[514,577,770,794]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">543 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6743" type="journal article">
<author box="[115,246,797,822]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G. J." ins="D" ln="NELSON" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">NELSON G. J.</author>
<year box="[250,304,798,822]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1979</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.109145686" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
Cladistic analysis and synthesis: Principles and definitions, with a historical note on Adanson’s 
<!--emphasis removed-->Familles des Plantes
(1763-1764)
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="1.4714147" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematic Zoology
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[224,252,876,900]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">28</part>
: 
<pagination box="[262,310,876,900]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">1-21</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" box="[115,628,903,928]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" box="[115,628,903,928]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6783" type="journal article">
<author box="[115,249,903,928]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G. J." ins="D" ln="NELSON" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">NELSON G. J.</author>
<year box="[255,309,904,928]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1993</year>
. — 
<title box="[350,408,903,927]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Reply</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[417,506,903,927]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Cladistics
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[512,527,903,927]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">9</part>
: 
<pagination box="[537,625,903,927]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">261-265</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6800" type="book">
<author box="[115,247,930,955]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G. J." ins="D" ln="NELSON" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">NELSON G. J.</author>
<year box="[252,303,931,955]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1994</year>
a. — 
<title box="[356,619,929,953]" jopScore="0.18639328" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Homology and systematics</title>
, 
<!--emphasis removed-->in
<editor box="[145,249,956,979]" case="AC" fns="I" in="B. K." ins="D" ln="HALL" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">HALL B. K.</editor>
(ed.), 
<!--emphasis removed-->
<volumeTitle jopScore="0.34878853" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">The Hierarchical Basis of Comparative Biology</volumeTitle>

. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[226,541,982,1006]" jopScore="1.5442349" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Academic Press, San Diego: 101</journalOrPublisher>
-149.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6841" type="book">
<author box="[115,243,1009,1034]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G. J." ins="D" ln="NELSON" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">NELSON G. J.</author>
<year box="[247,297,1010,1034]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1994</year>
b. — 
<title box="[351,644,1009,1033]" jopScore="0.16279736" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">La systématique et l’homologie</title>
, 
<!--emphasis removed-->in
<volumeTitle box="[171,242,1036,1059]" jopScore="0.123915456" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">TASSY P</volumeTitle>
. &amp; 
<editor box="[282,404,1036,1059]" case="AC" fns="I" in="H." ins="D" ln="LELIEVRE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LELIÈVRE H.</editor>
(eds), 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="1.5720191" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Caractères
. Société française de Systématique, Paris: 5
</journalOrPublisher>
-28.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6880" type="book">
<author box="[115,255,1088,1113]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G. J." ins="D" ln="NELSON" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">NELSON G. J.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[292,427,1088,1111]" case="AC" fns="I" in="P. Y." ins="D" ln="LADIGES" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LADIGES P. Y.</author>
<year box="[434,489,1089,1113]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1993</year>
. — 
<!--emphasis removed-->
<title box="[533,644,1088,1112]" jopScore="0.36770886" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="_" typeScore="42">Matrix 1.0</title>
.

Published by the authors, 
<journalOrPublisher box="[400,621,1114,1138]" jopScore="2.3775418" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">New York; Melbourne</journalOrPublisher>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6907" type="journal article">
<author box="[115,255,1141,1166]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G. J." ins="D" ln="NELSON" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">NELSON G. J.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[292,428,1141,1164]" case="AC" fns="I" in="P. Y." ins="D" ln="LADIGES" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LADIGES P. Y.</author>
<year box="[436,491,1142,1166]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1996</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Paralogy in cladistic biogeography and analysis of paralogy-free subtrees</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[236,506,1194,1218]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->American Museum Novitates
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[512,566,1194,1218]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">3167</part>
: 
<pagination box="[575,624,1194,1218]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">1-58</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6940" type="book">
<author box="[115,252,1221,1246]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G. J." ins="D" ln="NELSON" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">NELSON G. J.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[288,440,1221,1244]" case="AC" fns="I" in="N. I." ins="D" ln="PLATNICK" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">PLATNICK N. I.</author>
<year box="[448,502,1222,1246]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1981</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.26964667" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematics and Biogeography: Cladistics and Vicariance
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="1.8789043" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Columbia University Press, New York</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[422,485,1273,1297]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">567 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[115,649,215,1325]" lastBlockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref6972" type="book">
<author box="[115,281,1300,1323]" case="AC" fns="I" in="R. J." ins="D" ln="PANKHURST" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">PANKHURST R. J.</author>
<year box="[286,340,1301,1325]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1978</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.2744834" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Biological Identification. The Principles and Practice of Identification Methods in Biology
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[788,1032,241,265]" jopScore="2.0851016" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Edward Arnold, London</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[1042,1106,242,266]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">104 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7001" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,832,268,293]" case="AC" fns="I" in="R. A." ins="D" ln="PIMENTEL" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">PIMENTEL R. A.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[865,976,268,291]" case="AC" fns="I" in="R." ins="D" ln="RIGGINS" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">RIGGINS R.</author>
<year box="[983,1037,269,293]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1987</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">The nature of cladistic data</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[846,935,294,318]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Cladistics
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[941,956,295,319]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">3</part>
: 
<pagination box="[966,1053,295,319]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">201-209</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7026" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,818,321,344]" case="AC" fns="I" in="N. I." ins="D" ln="PLATNICK" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">PLATNICK N. I.</author>
<year box="[822,874,322,346]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1979</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Philosophy and the transformation of cladistics</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[878,1053,347,371]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematic Zoology
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[1059,1087,347,371]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">28</part>
: 
<pagination box="[1097,1184,347,371]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">537-546</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7049" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,815,374,399]" case="AC" fns="I" in="M. G." ins="D" ln="POGUE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">POGUE M. G.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[852,1029,374,397]" case="AC" fns="I" in="M. F." ins="D" ln="MICKEVICH" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">MICKEVICH M. F.</author>
<year box="[1035,1089,375,399]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1990</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Character definitions and character state delineation: the bête noire of phylogenetic inference</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[1090,1182,427,451]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Cladistics
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[1190,1205,427,451]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">6</part>
: 
<pagination box="[707,794,453,477]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">319-361</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7084" type="book">
<author box="[677,804,480,505]" case="AC" fns="I" in="R. R." ins="D" ln="SOKAL" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">SOKAL R. R.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[841,1010,480,505]" case="AC" fns="I" in="P. H. A." ins="D" ln="SNEATH" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">SNEATH P. H. A.</author>
<year box="[1018,1073,481,505]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1963</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.11899502" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Principles of Numerical Taxonomy
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="0.7147411" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">W. H. Freeman, San Francisco</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[767,830,532,556]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">573 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7117" type="book">
<author box="[677,772,559,582]" case="AC" fns="I" in="R." ins="D" ln="VIGNES" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">VIGNES R.</author>
<year box="[776,827,560,584]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1991</year>
. — 
<!--emphasis removed-->
<title jopScore="0.28850514" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Caractérisation automatique de groupes biologiques</title>
.

<journalOrPublisher jopScore="3.706749" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Thèse de doctorat, Université Pierre et Marie Curie-Paris 6, Paris, France</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[1048,1112,612,636]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">268 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7147" type="book chapter">
VIGNES- 
<author box="[761,854,639,662]" case="AC" fns="I" in="R." ins="D" ln="LEBBE" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">LEBBE R.</author>
<year box="[862,918,640,664]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">2000</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.09361766" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="_" typeScore="42">Caractère pour le biologiste, caractère pour l’informaticien</title>
, 
<!--emphasis removed-->in
<volumeTitle box="[1080,1178,665,688]" jopScore="0.14052574" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">BARRIEL V</volumeTitle>
. &amp; 
<editor box="[707,840,692,715]" case="AC" fns="I" in="T." ins="D" ln="BOURGOIN" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">BOURGOIN T.</editor>
(eds), 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="2.29532" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Biosystema 18
. Société française de Systématique, Paris
</journalOrPublisher>
: 
<pagination box="[937,999,718,742]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">61-70</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7189" type="book">
<author box="[677,826,745,770]" case="AC" fns="I" in="G. P." ins="D" ln="WAGNER" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">WAGNER G. P.</author>
(ed.) 
<year box="[888,943,746,770]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">2001</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.26773837" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->The Character Concept in Evolutionary Biology
</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[940,1205,771,795]" jopScore="1.6019272" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Academic Press, San Diego</journalOrPublisher>
, 
<bookContentInfo box="[707,770,797,821]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">622 p.</bookContentInfo>
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7217" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,783,824,847]" case="AC" fns="I" in="J. J." ins="D" ln="WIENS" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">WIENS J. J.</author>
<year box="[788,842,825,849]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">2001</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Character analysis in morphological phylogenetics: problems and solutions</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematic Biology
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[782,810,876,900]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">50</part>
: 
<pagination box="[820,907,876,900]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">689-699</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7243" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,794,903,928]" case="AC" fns="I" in="E. O." ins="D" ln="WILEY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">WILEY E. O.</author>
<year box="[799,852,904,928]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1988</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Parsimony analysis and vicariance biogeography</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[849,1024,929,953]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematic Zoology
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[1030,1058,929,953]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">37</part>
: 
<pagination box="[1068,1155,929,953]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">271-290</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7265" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,828,956,979]" case="AC" fns="I" in="M." ins="D" ln="WILKINSON" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">WILKINSON M.</author>
<year box="[837,891,957,981]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">1994</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Common cladistic information and its consensus representation: reduced Adams and reduced cladistic consensus trees and profiles</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[707,877,1035,1059]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematic Biology
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[884,912,1035,1059]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">43</part>
: 
<pagination box="[922,1009,1035,1059]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">343-368</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7297" type="book chapter">
<author box="[677,847,1062,1085]" case="AC" fns="I" in="D. W." ins="D" ln="WILLIAMS" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">WILLIAMS D. W.</author>
<year box="[855,910,1063,1087]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">2004</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.33045402" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Homologues and homology, phenetics and cladistics: 150 years of progress</title>
, 
<!--emphasis removed-->in
<volumeTitle box="[734,891,1115,1138]" jopScore="0.2119883" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">WILLIAMS D. W</volumeTitle>
. &amp; 
<editor box="[933,1045,1115,1138]" case="AC" fns="I" in="P. L." ins="D" ln="FOREY" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">FOREY P. L.</editor>
(eds), 
<journalOrPublisher jopScore="3.6361184" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Milestones in Systematics
. CRC, The Systematics Association, London
</journalOrPublisher>
: 
<pagination box="[798,884,1168,1192]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">191-224</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7350" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,843,1194,1217]" case="AC" fns="I" in="D. W." ins="D" ln="WILLIAMS" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">WILLIAMS D. W.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[881,1017,1194,1219]" case="AC" fns="I" in="M. C." ins="D" ln="EBACH" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">EBACH M. C.</author>
<year box="[1025,1079,1195,1219]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">2006</year>
. — 
<title pageId="10" pageNumber="15">The data matrix</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[783,905,1220,1244]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Geodiversitas
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[912,937,1221,1245]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">28</part>
(
<part box="[952,965,1221,1245]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="issue">3</part>
): 
<pagination box="[985,1073,1221,1245]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">409-420</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[677,1211,215,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList|year" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" refId="ref7378" type="journal article">
<author box="[677,841,1247,1270]" case="AC" fns="I" in="D. W." ins="D" ln="WILLIAMS" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">WILLIAMS D. W.</author>
&amp; 
<author box="[877,1048,1247,1272]" case="AC" fns="I" in="C. J." ins="D" ln="HUMPHRIES" lnc="AC" npo="LnIn" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">HUMPHRIES C. J.</author>
<year box="[1055,1109,1248,1272]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">2003</year>
. — 
<title jopScore="0.35354373" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">Component coding, three-item coding, and consensus methods</title>
. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[804,974,1300,1324]" jopScore="1.1826997" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
<!--emphasis removed-->Systematic Biology
</journalOrPublisher>
<part box="[981,1009,1300,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="volume">52</part>
: 
<pagination box="[1019,1106,1300,1324]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" type="pagination">259-271</pagination>
.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="10.[909,1210,1379,1430]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15">
Submitted on 
<date box="[1041,1203,1379,1403]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" value="2006-10-20">20 October 2006</date>
; accepted on 
<date box="[1041,1206,1406,1430]" pageId="10" pageNumber="15" value="2007-01-25">25 January 2007</date>
.
</paragraph>
</subSection>
</document>