<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document ID-DOI="10.4232/1.3262" ID-ISSN="1464-5262" ID-Zenodo-Dep="5279762" checkinTime="1630027597062" checkinUser="felipe" docAuthor="Berger, Manfred &amp; Jung, Matthias &amp; Roth, Dieter" docDate="2000" docId="012AFFDEFFECC2060C6FFFD7FF8FFFB9" docName="JNatHist.34.6.953-956.pdf" docOrigin="Journal of Natural History 34" docSource="http://dx.doi.org/10.4232/1.3262" docStyle="DocumentStyle:B6EF65DE5B4D2965D4D236BA736D172F.1:JNatHist.2000-2002.journal_article.2cover" docStyleId="B6EF65DE5B4D2965D4D236BA736D172F" docStyleName="JNatHist.2000-2002.journal_article.2cover" docStyleVersion="1" docTitle="Politbarometer Ost 1999 (Kumulierter Datensatz)" docVersion="2" lastPageNumber="956" pageNumber="953" updateTime="1630054695672" updateUser="ExternalLinkService" zenodo-license-document="CLOSED">
<mods:mods xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Politbarometer Ost 1999 (Kumulierter Datensatz)</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Berger, Manfred</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Jung, Matthias</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:name type="personal">
<mods:role>
<mods:roleTerm>Author</mods:roleTerm>
</mods:role>
<mods:namePart>Roth, Dieter</mods:namePart>
</mods:name>
<mods:typeOfResource>text</mods:typeOfResource>
<mods:relatedItem type="host">
<mods:titleInfo>
<mods:title>Journal of Natural History</mods:title>
</mods:titleInfo>
<mods:part>
<mods:date>2000</mods:date>
<mods:detail type="volume">
<mods:number>34</mods:number>
</mods:detail>
<mods:extent unit="page">
<mods:start>953</mods:start>
<mods:end>956</mods:end>
</mods:extent>
</mods:part>
</mods:relatedItem>
<mods:location>
<mods:url>http://dx.doi.org/10.4232/1.3262</mods:url>
</mods:location>
<mods:classification>journal article</mods:classification>
<mods:identifier type="DOI">10.4232/1.3262</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="ISSN">1464-5262</mods:identifier>
<mods:identifier type="Zenodo-Dep">5279762</mods:identifier>
</mods:mods>
<subSection _generate="added" lastPageId="5" lastPageNumber="956" pageId="2" pageNumber="953" type="multiple">
<paragraph blockId="2.[454,660,210,244]" box="[454,660,210,244]" pageId="2" pageNumber="953">
<!--emphasis removed-->Book reviews
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[79,1034,297,346]" pageId="2" pageNumber="953">
<bibRef _evidence="authorList" pageId="2" pageNumber="953" refId="ref2" type="book">
<!--emphasis removed-->Parasites in Social Insects
. Monographs in Behavior and Ecology. 
<author box="[792,852,298,319]" case="TC" fns="I" in="P." ins="D" ln="By" lnc="TC" npo="LnIn" pageId="2" pageNumber="953">By P.</author>
SCHMID-HEMPEL, 
<year box="[111,159,324,346]" pageId="2" pageNumber="953">1998</year>
(Princeton University Press) [Pp. 409]. 
<journalOrPublisher box="[573,832,324,346]" jopScore="0.4182127" pageId="2" pageNumber="953">Price US$ 35.00. ISBN 0</journalOrPublisher>
-691-05923-3.
</bibRef>
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[79,1036,364,1502]" pageId="2" pageNumber="953">Wherever organisms live together in societies, other organisms have found means to exploit the bene®ts of the society. Many monographs on social insects also contain short chapters concerned with their parasites. In this book, Schmid-Hempel has compiled all available information and attempted to synthesize the present knowledge on parasites of social insects. The results are presented in eight chapters each with a short summary at the end. In the ®rst chapter, the biology of social insects is recapitulated in order to lay the foundation necessary for those of us who are not on every-day terms with this group of organisms. All major groups of parasites and their respective biology are introduced in the second chapter followed by a chapter entitled`Breaking into the fortress’. In this latter chapter it becomes clear that infestation of the social group is achieved by various pathways usually via the brood but also via adult workers. The following two chapters explore how the organization of the colony aOEects the parasite’s population dynamics (Chapter 4) and how genetic variability of social insects inūences their susceptibility to parasites (Chapter 5). While the author identi®es some traits, he emphasizes that these topics are complex and much more future research is necessary. Similarly, in the next two chapters on`Host±parasite dynamics’ and`Virulence and resistance’, many questions need to be answered in the future. How are the dynamics of host and parasite populations linked, and how do parasites achieve virulence and hosts resistance? In Chapter 7 it becomes evident that many hosts and their respective parasites co-evolve and that a continuous arms-race is proceeding between them. In the ®nal chapter, which is more like a discussion in character than the previous chapters, Schmid-Hempel brilliantly examines the evolution of sociality from the perspective of a parasitologist. The continuing conīct for social cohabitants of recognizing members and discriminating against non-members (yet conspeci®cs) has provided many opportunities for parasites to`get a foot in the door’. To point out the importance of understanding and acknowledging the role of parasites in the continuing evolution of social insects is one of the most important achievements of Schmid- Hempel’s book. Beyond this, the author introduces new concepts and ideas, many of which will have to be put to a thorough test in future studies. Anybody interested in the topic will appreciate the extensive reference section spanning more than 50 pages. Additionally, the book includes an extensive appendix presenting tables with long lists of parasites of social insects, a resource that will be most useful to all scholars of social insects. The glossary is unfortunately short, and I found myself several times consulting it without success. Since the author provides a relatively basic introduction, he must have had in mind that his book will be read by non-specialists who do not immediately know what dysentry, dulosis or inquilinism mean, just to name a few. Furthermore, the book contains a few typographical errors, for which exclusively the publishers would be to blame. Most of these typos are of the following kind:`or’ instead of`of ’,`...of of ...’,`adults’ instead of`adult’, and I only emphasize them to demonstrate that computer programs are still not smart enough to replace a thorough proof-reader. Without any further nit-picking, I like to conclude by congratulating the author who has provided the ®rst complete synthesis on Parasites in Social Insects. The role of parasites in ecological interactions becomes increasingly acknowledged, and this book will do its share to foster this knowledge. Its modest price should allow a high prevalence of this book in institutional and personal libraries.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="2.[79,1036,364,1502]" box="[886,1035,1480,1502]" pageId="2" pageNumber="953">MARTIN THIEL</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[79,1034,120,168]" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">
<!--emphasis removed-->The Liverwort Flora of the British Isles
. By JEAN A. PATON, 1999 (Colchester: Harley Books) [Pp. 626]. Price £52.50 (hbk). ISBN 0 946589 60 7.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[79,1036,187,1423]" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">
The British Isles contain a very signi®cant proportion of the bryophyte ¯ora of Europe, and the importance of this group of organisms in the biodiversity and biogeography of Britain and 
<collectingCountry box="[125,199,241,263]" name="Ireland" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">Ireland</collectingCountry>
is being recognized increasingly by ecologists. Fortunately, since the inception of the Moss Exchange Club in 1896 (latterly the British Bryological Society), there has been a dedicated (if albeit small) army of British bryologists whose members have collected, identi®ed and catalogued these small plants. Consequently, the content and distribution of the bryophyte ¯ora of the British Isles is probably better known than any area of comparable size in the world. This has been possible only as a result of the availability of a small number of excellent descriptive ¯oras (and distribution atlases), which have been published in succession during this century, each building on the accumulation of knowledge and experience gained from their predecessors.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[79,1036,187,1423]" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">
Jean Paton’s impressive book builds on S. M. Macvicar’s 
<!--emphasis removed-->Student’s Handbook of British Hepatics
(1912) and A. J. E. Smith’s 
<!--emphasis removed-->
The Liverworts of Britain and 
<collectingCountry box="[779,850,511,533]" name="Ireland" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">Ireland</collectingCountry>

(1990) and is the result of 30 years dedicated to the study of liverworts in Britain and 
<collectingCountry box="[812,886,537,559]" name="Ireland" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">Ireland</collectingCountry>
. Remarkably, she has observed all but ®ve of the 296 species in their natural habitats in the ®eld and is widely recognized as an authority on this rather di cult group. The book includes 20 introductory pages that deal with the collection and examination of specimens, together with helpful notes on important identi®cation features. Under the heading of`Habitats and Distribution’ there are lists indicating the preferences that certain species show for particular habitats. I always liked this feature in E. V. Watson’s 
<!--emphasis removed-->British Mosses and Liverworts
(1968) since it is so useful for non-experts to have some idea of what they may expect to ®nd. In the`Conspectus of Classi®cation’, the 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="class" box="[474,649,753,775]" class="Marchantiopsida" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Plantae" pageId="3" pageNumber="954" phylum="Marchantiophyta" rank="class">Marchantiopsida</taxonomicName>
and the Anthocerotopsida have been treated as classes within the division Bryophyta. Within the 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="class" box="[803,978,780,802]" class="Marchantiopsida" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Plantae" pageId="3" pageNumber="954" phylum="Marchantiophyta" rank="class">Marchantiopsida</taxonomicName>
, the 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="family" box="[79,220,808,830]" class="Jungermanniopsida" family="Lophoziaceae" kingdom="Plantae" order="Jungermanniales" pageId="3" pageNumber="954" phylum="Marchantiophyta" rank="family">Lophoziaceae</taxonomicName>
is given family status separate from the 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="family" box="[665,853,808,830]" class="Jungermanniopsida" family="Jungermanniaceae" kingdom="Plantae" order="Jungermanniales" pageId="3" pageNumber="954" phylum="Marchantiophyta" rank="family">Jungermanniaceae</taxonomicName>
and 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="genera" box="[912,1008,808,830]" class="Jungermanniopsida" family="Jungermanniaceae" genus="Leiocolea" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Plantae" order="Jungermanniales" pageId="3" pageNumber="954" phylum="Marchantiophyta" rank="genus">
<!--emphasis removed-->Leiocolea
</taxonomicName>
is separated as a genus from 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="genera" authorityName="M.-A.Libert" authorityYear="1820" box="[358,448,835,856]" class="Jungermanniopsida" family="Lejeuneaceae" genus="Lejeunea" kingdom="Plantae" order="Porellales" pageId="3" pageNumber="954" phylum="Marchantiophyta" rank="genus">
<!--emphasis removed-->Lejeunea
</taxonomicName>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[79,1036,187,1423]" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">The main part of the ¯ora, of course, deals with description and identi®cation. There are detailed dichotomous keys that will traumatize novices such as undergraduate students in the age-old fashion, but as far as I could tell, all of the technical terms are adequately de®ned in a glossary which is cross-referenced with a series of ®gures illustrating features such as leaf insertion, shape and surface characters. All the species of liverworts known in the British Isles are described with invaluable information (where available) on chromosome numbers, largely thanks to studies by Dr Martha Newton. In addition, there are useful notes on ecology and distribution. Each species is illustrated by excellent line drawings and given a separate ®gure showing habit and details of key features. For many, myself included, this will be one of the most important features of this book. At the back, there is a map and list of Vice Counties in the British Isles followed by a comprehensive bibliography.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[79,1036,187,1423]" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">I write this review as someone who needs to identify liverworts occasionally, sometimes in the course of vegetation surveys, but also during the supervision of undergraduate ®eld and project work. I am not a bryologist; however, the identi®cation of lower plants is now regarded as essential in ecological surveys, whether the agenda centres on biodiversity, vegetation classi®cation or environmental impact assessment. This book will be particularly helpful to the growing numbers of us who have to deal with those things and will allow us to move up a notch in our bryophyte identi®cation skills. It will become one of the most important descriptive ¯oras of the British Isles and is an essential acquisition for anyone interested in bryophytes.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[79,1036,187,1423]" box="[864,1034,1401,1423]" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">CHARLES HIPKIN</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[79,1035,1479,1583]" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">
<!--emphasis removed-->ReÂsultats des Campagne s MUSORSTOM
, 
<!--emphasis removed-->Volume 20
. Coordinated by ALAIN CROSNIER, 1999. 
<!--emphasis removed-->MeÂmoires du MuseÂum national d’Histoire naturelle
<!--emphasis removed-->180
: 588, 192 ®gures (Paris: MuseÂum national d’Histoire naturelle and ORSTOM). Price 600 FF (hbk). ISBN 2 85653 520 8, ISNN 1243 4442.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="3.[79,1035,1601,1677]" lastBlockId="4.[79,1037,120,1677]" lastPageId="4" lastPageNumber="955" pageId="3" pageNumber="954">
Potentially, reviewing Volume 20 of the 
<!--emphasis removed-->ReÂsultats des Campagnes MUSORSTOM
appeared to be a straightforward task that would at most take a couple of hours after which I could place the tome into my book case. The only challenging part to writing a short snappy review would be the inclusion of a topical humorous reference to the purchase of a certain British agricultural product. But such a cheap book review would most certainly go down in the annals of oceanography as one of the greatest misjudgements of the 20th century because I would have completely devalued the outstanding scienti®c contribution made by MUSORSTOM. This remarkable deep-sea exploration programme must now rank alongside the truly great marine expeditions such as 
<!--emphasis removed-->Challenger
, 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="genera" authority=", la Voyage" authorityName="la Voyage" box="[644,880,253,275]" class="Actinopterygii" family="Nemichthyidae" genus="Investigator" kingdom="Animalia" order="Anguilliformes" pageId="4" pageNumber="955" phylum="Chordata" rank="genus">
<!--emphasis removed-->Investigator
, la Voyage
</taxonomicName>
au poÃle sud et dans l’ OceÂanie sur les corvettes 
<!--emphasis removed-->l’ Astrolabe
et 
<!--emphasis removed-->la ZeÂleÂe
, and 
<collectingCountry box="[673,810,280,302]" name="United States of America" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">United States</collectingCountry>
Exploring Expedition under the Command of Charles Wilkes, to name but a few. And yet the marine biological achievements of this French project appear to have sailed past the scienti®c community virtually unnoticed.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[79,1037,120,1677]" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">
<materialsCitation collectorName="le DeAveloppement CoopeAration &amp; de Recherche &amp; le DeAveloppement" country="Philippines" elevation="200" location="l'Institut FrancEais de Recherche Scienti" municipality="Institut de Recherche" pageId="4" pageNumber="955" specimenCount="1">
In 1976, two French Institutions with a world-renowned reputation for scienti®c excellence, the MuseÂum national d’Histoire naturelle (MNHN) and 
<location country="Philippines" municipality="Institut de Recherche" name="l'Institut FrancEais de Recherche Scienti" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">l’Institut FrancËais de Recherche Scienti</location>
®que pour 
<collectorName box="[273,605,441,463]" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">le DeÂveloppement CoopeÂration</collectorName>
(ORSTOM), now renamed 
<collectingMunicipality pageId="4" pageNumber="955">
Institut 
<collectorName pageId="4" pageNumber="955">de Recherche</collectorName>
</collectingMunicipality>
pour 
<collectorName box="[251,436,468,490]" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">le DeÂveloppement</collectorName>
(IRD), organized a 10-day cruise to the 
<collectingCountry box="[868,981,468,490]" name="Philippines" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">Philippines</collectingCountry>
. The aim of this expedition was to collect samples of a glypheid crustacean. This`living fossil’ is known only from a single specimen that is in poor condition and was originally captured in the 
<collectingCountry box="[116,229,550,572]" name="Philippines" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">Philippines</collectingCountry>
area at a depth of about 
<quantity box="[483,541,550,572]" metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.0" pageId="4" pageNumber="955" unit="m" value="200.0">
<elevation box="[483,541,550,572]" metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="2.0" pageId="4" pageNumber="955" unit="m" value="200.0">200 m</elevation>
</quantity>
during 1908 by the US research vessel 
<!--emphasis removed-->Albatross
. The French deep-sea cruise was successful because ORSTOM research vessel 
<!--emphasis removed-->Vauban
collected 
<specimenCount box="[79,242,603,625]" pageId="4" pageNumber="955" type="generic">eight specimens</specimenCount>
of the wanted glypheid. Two further cruises in the same area were carried out in 1980 and 1985 with the aim of collecting more specimens of the`living fossil’
</materialsCitation>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[79,1037,120,1677]" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">
Following these three cruises in the 
<collectingCountry box="[496,609,657,679]" name="Philippines" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">Philippines</collectingCountry>
, a new ambitious programme known as MUSORSTOM extended the research to other archipelagos in the Indo-West Paci®c with a view to sampling the bathyal depths for a better knowledge of the tropical deep-water fauna. These expeditions became known as les campagnes MUSORSTOM.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[79,1037,120,1677]" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">
To date, 11 cruises have been undertaken, including cruise 1 (1976), 2 (1980) 3 (1985) to the 
<collectingCountry box="[118,231,792,814]" name="Philippines" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">Philippines</collectingCountry>
Islands; 4 (1985), 5 (1986), 6 (1989) to 
<collectingCountry box="[643,800,792,814]" name="New Caledonia" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">New Caledonia</collectingCountry>
; 7 (1992) to the 
<collectingCountry name="Wallis and Futuna" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">Wallis and Futuna</collectingCountry>
Islands; 8 (1994) to 
<collectingCountry box="[419,506,820,841]" name="Vanuatu" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">Vanuatu</collectingCountry>
; 9 (1997) to the Marquesas Islands and 10 (1998), 11 (1998) to 
<collectingCountry box="[217,252,846,868]" name="Fiji" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">Fiji</collectingCountry>
. Other deep-sea cruises, engaged in bio-prospecting, also contributed additional samples and information about the deep sea. During all these investigations, a total of 764 days were spent at sea with over 2800 trawls and dredges collecting marine life from depths of 
<quantity box="[182,240,927,949]" metricMagnitude="2" metricUnit="m" metricValue="1.0" pageId="4" pageNumber="955" unit="m" value="100.0">100 m</quantity>
down to 
<quantity box="[340,415,927,949]" metricMagnitude="3" metricUnit="m" metricValue="3.7" pageId="4" pageNumber="955" unit="m" value="3700.0">3700 m</quantity>
. Each station is accompanied by a meticulously documented set of ®eld data. To put this programme into perspective, the MUSORSTOM cruises to 
<collectingCountry name="New Caledonia" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">New Caledonia</collectingCountry>
alone collected more samples than all the great international expeditions since the 19th century. Of the 1600 invertebrate species currently recorded from the economic zone of 
<collectingCountry box="[79,239,1035,1057]" name="New Caledonia" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">New Caledonia</collectingCountry>
, 60% were described as new. However, the MUSORSTOM cruises have not ®nished; in 2000 an expedition to the 
<collectingCountry box="[472,537,1062,1083]" name="Tonga" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">Tonga</collectingCountry>
Islands is scheduled.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[79,1037,120,1677]" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">
The material from the expeditions was sent to the 
<collectingRegion box="[657,740,1089,1110]" country="Ireland" name="Monaghan" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">MNHN</collectingRegion>
for sorting and is still only partly studied. At the Museum the MUSORSTOM project has been a truly international eOEort because since 1976, 181 scientists from 92 research institutes and representing 24 countries have taken part in the taxonomic studies of MUSORTOM specimens. Many scientists have visited the collections in Paris with the assistance of generous ®nancial support from ORSTOM, MNHM and the French Foreign AOEairs Ministry.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[79,1037,120,1677]" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">
Most of the results are published in a series 
<!--emphasis removed-->ReÂsultats des Campagnes MUSORSTOM
in the 
<!--emphasis removed-->MeÂmoires of the MuseÂum national d’Histoire naturelle
. Initially only 12 volumes were envisaged but today I am reviewing Volume 20 and I know that two more volumes are in preparation for publication in 2000. This series of volumes comprises some 200 contributions (approximately 50% of papers are in English, the other half are in French), about 9100 pages of taxonomic revisions and biogeography, and contains descriptions of 4587 species of which 1324 are new to science, as well as several new families and 126 new genera. Detailed cruise narratives are reported in French and English. Apart from the 20 MUSORSTOM volumes, about 500 notes and short papers have been accepted for publication. To underline the international concord of this project further, a proportion of the identi®ed biological specimens have been donated and deposited in various museums around the globe.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="4.[79,1037,120,1677]" pageId="4" pageNumber="955">To save publishing costs, these MUSORTOM volumes have been prepared as cameraready copy for the printers using desktop publishing and this has not compromised the quality of the series. Further, the series has received sponsorship from a number of sources for the production costs of these tomes. Since Volume 15 and at very little extra expense, the series has been produced with hard covers.</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[79,1036,120,1018]" pageId="5" pageNumber="956">
The editor of Volume 20 is Alain Crosnier and he has been the scienti®c editor for 11 other 
<!--emphasis removed-->MUSORSTOM
volumes including 6, 8±16 and 18. Volume 20 is typical of the international collaboration described in this review with 11 authors representing 
<collectingCountry box="[820,880,173,194]" name="Japan" pageId="5" pageNumber="956">Japan</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[892,1027,173,195]" name="New Zealand" pageId="5" pageNumber="956">New Zealand</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[79,131,199,221]" name="United States of America" pageId="5" pageNumber="956">USA</collectingCountry>
and Europe, covering the following zoological groups of deep-sea corals, Bryozoa, Crustacea and snake eels. One subfamily, ®ve genera and 60 species are described as new to science, and new data are presented on an additional 250 species. One paper in this volume records a living example of the bryozoan genus 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="genera" authorityName="Labracherie" authorityYear="1975" box="[578,747,279,301]" class="Gymnolaemata" family="Bryopastoridae" genus="Pseudothyracella" kingdom="Animalia" order="Cheilostomatida" pageId="5" pageNumber="956" phylum="Bryozoa" rank="genus">
<!--emphasis removed-->Pseudothyracella
</taxonomicName>
, which was only previously known as a Palaeogene fossil from Europe and North America; this highlights just how inadequately the tropical deep sea has been sampled. However, there are three lengthy taxonomic studies that represent a considerable amount of investment by the authors concerned. The deep-water Scleractinia paper by Stephen Cairns reports on 134 species from 
<collectingCountry box="[79,166,412,433]" name="Vanuatu" pageId="5" pageNumber="956">Vanuatu</collectingCountry>
, 
<collectingCountry box="[182,376,411,433]" name="Wallis and Futuna" pageId="5" pageNumber="956">Wallis and Futuna</collectingCountry>
Islands. All but one species is a new record for the region, 16 are described as new to science, examples of commensal/parasite relationships are reported and 22 ®gures of black and white photographs accompany the text. This is a substantial contribution to anthozoan taxonomy. The review of the pagurid crustacean genus 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="genera" authorityName="Smith" authorityYear="1879" box="[909,1035,492,513]" class="Malacostraca" family="Parapaguridae" genus="Parapagurus" higherTaxonomySource="GBIF" kingdom="Animalia" order="Decapoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="956" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<!--emphasis removed-->Parapagurus
</taxonomicName>
by Rafael Lemaitre comprises 75 pages of text supported by well-illustrated ®gures and a comprehensive key to the Paci®c and Indian Ocean species. With the description of seven new parapagurids, the genus now contains 17 species of which only three are known from the Atlantic Ocean. The author also summarizes bathymetric distribution data for all species assigned to the genus. Paper nine in Volume 20 is a revision of the 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="order" box="[853,957,624,646]" class="Malacostraca" kingdom="Animalia" order="Decapoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="956" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="order">Decapoda</taxonomicName>
family 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="family" authorityName="Ortmann" authorityYear="1892" box="[79,222,651,673]" class="Malacostraca" family="Dynomenidae" kingdom="Animalia" order="Decapoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="956" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="family">Dynomenidae</taxonomicName>
, a group of small primitive crabs often associated with corals. All the genera and species of the family are revised and redescribed with the genus 
<taxonomicName _evidence="catalogs" _step="genera" authorityName="Desmarest" authorityYear="1823" box="[797,901,679,700]" class="Malacostraca" family="Dynomenidae" genus="Dynomene" kingdom="Animalia" order="Decapoda" pageId="5" pageNumber="956" phylum="Arthropoda" rank="genus">
<!--emphasis removed-->Dynomene
</taxonomicName>
divided into two genera. Forty-one ®gures illustrate the text and these include photographs of specimens, pictures taken with a scanning electron microscope, excellent line drawings, several cladograms and maps displaying geographical distributions. The author, Colin McLay, also provides a key to the species of the family. Volume 20 comprises 588 pages, 192 ®gures, two colour photographs which are all printed on acid-free paper at a cost of only 600 French francs plus postage. However, if your Institution is not subscribing to this major on-going zoological series on tropical deep-sea benthos make contact with email address dhenry@mnhn.fr for details.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[79,1036,120,1018]" pageId="5" pageNumber="956">
The MUSORSTOM marine biological project with its vision of unsel®sh international scienti®c collaboration is probably unrivalled in our modern era. May its tropical deep-sea programme continued to be funded by the French Government. Vive la 
<collectingCountry box="[831,902,970,991]" name="France" pageId="5" pageNumber="956">France</collectingCountry>
.
</paragraph>
<paragraph blockId="5.[79,1036,120,1018]" box="[872,1035,996,1018]" pageId="5" pageNumber="956">PAUL F. CLARK</paragraph>
</subSection>
</document>