<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1038/nature21072</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Meiofaunal deuterostomes from the basal Cambrian of Shaanxi (China)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2017</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
LETTER 

doi:10.1038/ 
nature
21072
</p>
         <p>Meiofaunal deuterostomes from the basal Cambrian of Shaanxi (China)</p>
         <p>Jian Han1
, 
Simon Conway Morris2
, 
Qiang Ou3
, 
4
, 
Degan Shu1
&amp; 
Hai Huang5</p>
         <p>Deuterostomes1include the group we belong to (vertebrates) as well as an array of disparate forms that include echinoderms2, hemichordates3and more problematic groups such as vetulicolians4and vetulocystids5
. The Cambrian fossil record is well-populated 
<p>
with representative examples, but possible intermediates 
6
, 
7
are controversial and the nature of the original deuterostome remains idealized. Here we report millimetric fossils, 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
coronarius

nov. gen., nov. sp., from an Orsten-like Lagerstätte from the earliest Cambrian period of South China, which stratigraphically are amongst the earliest of deuterostomes. The bag-like body bears a prominent mouth and associated folds, and behind them up to four conical openings on either side of the body as well as possible sensory structures. An anus may have been absent, and correspondingly the lateral openings probably served to expel water and waste material. This new form has similarities to both the vetulicolians
4and vetulocystids5and collectively these findings suggest that a key step in deuterostome evolution was the development of lateral openings that subsequently were co-opted as pharyngeal gills2
– 
4
, 
8
. Depending on its exact phylogenetic position, the meiofaunal habit of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
may help to explain the major gap between divergence times seen in the fossil record and estimates based on molecular clocks
9.</p>
         </p>
         <p>
Insights into the early evolution of deuterostomes 
1
are critically dependent on the Cambrian fossil record, notably from Burgess Shaletype and Orsten-style Lagerstätten. By Cambrian Series 2–3 (around 510–520 million years ago (Ma)), this superphylum had diversified into echinoderms 
2
, hemichordates 
3
, tunicates 
10
and vertebrates 
11
, as well as the more problematic cambroernids 
6
, vetulicolians 
4
, 
12
, vetulocystids 
5
, 
13
and yunnanozoans 
7
. This degree of disparity, combined with apparently rapid divergences, renders the identification of the various stem groups problematic and also frustrates reconstruction of the ur-deuterostome. Here we describe a suite of phosphatized microfossils from the earliest Cambrian period of South China (Extended Data 

). These fossils throw new light on what appears to be an early stage in deuterostome evolution and reiterate the importance of Örsten-style Lagerstätten 
14
– 
17
as a source of insights into the Cambrian metazoan radiations.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Deuterostomia Grobben, 1908</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Saccorhytida (new stem group) Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 
2017</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Saccorhytidae (
new family
) Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytusgen. nov.
Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronariusgen et sp. nov
. Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronarius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>data</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pomatrum</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Xidazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Data</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronarius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronarius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Meiofaunal deuterostomes from the basal Cambrian of Shaanxi (China)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/nature21072</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1D24282A9B47FFE5F56CFFEE5841FFA4</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature21072</pub-id>
               <source>Nature</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Saccorhytidae (
new family
) Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytusgen. nov.
Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronariusgen et sp. nov
. Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Millimetric, ellipsoidal body, ventral mouth and multiple lateral openings.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Generic name reference to bag-like body (L. 
saccus
) and wrinkled preservation (Gr. 
rhytis
). Specific name in reference to crownlike mouth.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Hemi-ellipsoidal, bilaterally symmetrical body. Integument bears chevron pattern. Ventral mouth defined by two circlets of radial folds, inner circlet with associated protuberances. Aborally and dorsally up to four nodulate rugae. Eight body openings, conical, defined by radial folds. In mid-region anteriorly directed spines. Smaller pores parallel to body cones and in posterior region, possibly housed setae. 
Holotype.
XX45-20.
</p>
            <p>Other material.
XX25-62 and another 43 specimens (Supplementary Table 1).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Locality.
Zhangjiagou section, Hexi, Xixiang County, Shaanxi, China.
</p>
            <p>Stratigraphy.
Kuanchuanpu Formation, Fortunian Stage of Terreneuvian Series.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Forty-five phosphatized specimens are available (

, 

, Extended Data 

–6 and Supplementary Table 1). As with similar material from this horizon 
14
– 
16
and co-eval deposits 
17
, the phosphatic composition of the specimens is evidently the result of very early diagenesis. Extensive folding suggests that in life the integument was thin, flexible and only slightly sclerotized. The integument consists of two layers (Extended Data 

b, c, h, 3c, g, 5k, 6c, d), and frequently exhibits a fine-scale, densely spaced chevron-like folding on both external and internal surfaces (

b, Extended Data 

f–i, 3h, 4g and Supplementary Table 1). If original, this suggests that the integument was bi-layered.
</p>
            <p>
The body is hemi-ellipsoidal, with a maximum length of 1,300μm, width 800μm and height 900μm (Extended Data Fig. 7). Most material is crushed but several specimens (

g, h and Extended Data Figs 5g, h, 6a) confirm original bilateral symmetry. Otherwise, body orientations depend principally on identification of the mouth, and presumably the more dorsal and posterior location of the body cones and possibly sensory pores. Post-mortem deformation makes the precise dispositions of other structures more difficult to interpret. The most parsimonious conclusion, however, is that these features were also arranged bilaterally (

g, h and Extended Data Figs 4f, h 6a).
</p>
            <p>
The largest of the body openings (approximately 300–500 μm) is defined by a double circlet with prominent radial folds. The folds of the inner circlet are somewhat finer and this circlet also bears a series of oral protrusions, each consisting of an outer sheath and an inner peg-like structure (

a, d, e, g–i, 2a, b, d, e and Extended Data 

c, 3f, 4a, c, f, 5a, c, d, g, i). This double circlet is interpreted as the oral region, while the protrusions, notably the most anterior pair (Extended Data Figs 5g, i, 6f, g), may represent sensilla. The flexibility of the oral region is evident from both its lateral compression and dorsal arching (

a, d, e, i, 2d and Extended Data Figs 4a, e, 5a, c, d, g).
</p>
            <p>
Anterior to the oral region, the dorsal integument consists of up to four rugae with a nodular appearance (

a, d, 2a, b, d and Extended Data 

d, 4a, c, 5a, f). These may be separated by intervening integument or (presumably as a result of contraction) are closely adpressed with the nodular regions interlocked. Behind the rugae, the integument grades into a zone with longitudinal folds, but the posterior body is relatively smooth. Otherwise the most prominent structures are a series of body cones (

a, d, g, i, 2a, d, f, g and Extended Data 

a, b, d, h, 3a, c, d, g, 4b, d, f, h, 5a–c, e, g, k, 6). These vary in size (56–328 μm across), but all are formed of a series of ribs radiating from an unoccluded aperture. Up to eight body cones are visible, with the four body cones on the left and right sides extending in a more dorsal direction (

a). The first body cone is located immediately behind the oral region, and the body cone behind it is somewhat larger. The third body cone is the largest, and the most dorsal one is smaller. There are also two sets of small circular pores (30 μm across). One set is widely separated and runs parallel to the body cones (

a, g and Extended Data Figs 4f, h, 5g). The other set is more dorsal and consists of sub-linear arrays (

a, b, f, 2a, c, f, g and Extended Data 

a, d, e, j, 3a, d, e, 4f, h, 5b, h, j). Finally there are occasional conspicuous spines, with a wide base and elongate anterior taper (

c, 2h and Extended Data 

d, 5a, b, f, 6a). Strong folding makes the conclusion tentative, but no anus is evident (

a).
</p>
            <p>1State Key Laboratory of Continental Dynamics, Department of Geology, Northwest University, Xi’an 710069, China. 2Department of Earth Sciences, University of Cambridge, Downing Street, Cambridge CB2 3EQ, UK. 3State Key Laboratory of Biogeology and Environmental Geology, China University of Geosciences, Beijing 100083, China. 4Department of Zoology, University of Kassel, Kassel 34132, Germany. 5College of Petroleum Engineering, Xi’an Shiyou University, Xi’an 710065, China.</p>
            <p>0 0 M O N T H 2 0 1 7 | V O L 0 0 0 | N A T U R E | 1</p>
            <p>
The oral region could evidently distend, with its pleated arrangement accommodating changes in size. This, combined with dorsal arching, would allow ingestion of food particles and possibly somewhat larger prey 
18
. The size of mouth also suggests that water was swallowed, with the body cones being interpreted as exhalant structures. The dorsal extension of the body cones suggests that the corresponding oral cavity was also elongate. The more dorsal set of circular pores may represent the insertion points of setae. The other set adjacent to the body cones may have had a sensory function, although alternatively they could have released internal contents such as adhesive mucus or gametes.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
The millimetric size of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
does not preclude a planktonic location, but its globular shape is consistent with a meiofaunal habit within what is now a phosphatic shelly limestone 
16
. Although we did not find exact counterparts amongst extant meiobenthic taxa, 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
shows a suite of features consistent with an interstitial habitat 
18
. These include a thick but flexible cuticle, suitable for mechanical protection and wriggling between sediment grains, respectively (Extended Data 

c, d). The postulated setae, especially those towards the dorsal side, could perform a haptic role, including temporary attachment. Many meiofaunal taxa are progenetic and deciding whether 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
is best interpreted as a miniaturized adult or a larval stage has important implications for both potential life cycles and phylogenetic relationships. Evidence in favour of the former includes the observation that, despite a size range of 548–1,326 μm, the morphology is effectively invariant. More notable is that most extant larvae 
19
are ciliated and, although a few groups such as the bryozoans (cyphonautes) and loriciferans have thin cuticular coverings, they are unlike the relatively massive coat of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
Irrespective of whether 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
is a progenetic relative of unknown macroscopic taxa, its closest relationships appear to lie with the vetulicolians and possibly vetulocystids. Forming part of a highly disparate suite of taxa, collectively they appear to represent early deuterostomes 
1
, 
20
, albeit ones not easily assigned to particular stem groups 
21
. Our phylogenetic analysis (

b, Extended Data Fig. 8 and Supplementary Information) confirms both the monophyly of the deuterostomes 
22
and component groups including vetulicolians plus banffiids and vetulocystids, but the position of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
remains less well constrained.
</p>
            <p>
With respect to vetulicolians, similarities with 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
include the circum-oral radial structures and the body openings, interpreted as pharyngeal gills in the former group. In forms such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>12
the gills also have a convex exterior, although here the openings are directed posteriorly. Moreover, in 
<tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
the relative size of the openings in the posterior direction is similar to that seen in 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
, notably with the third opening being conspicuously larger. In 
<tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>12
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pomatrum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Xidazoon</tp:taxon-name>1
, 
12
and 
Banffia23
the oral region shows variably developed pleating (Extended 
<tp:taxon-name>Data</tp:taxon-name>
Fig. 9), similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
. Similarities to the vetulocystids 
5
include body openings defined as truncated cones with well-developed radial ribs, albeit more numerous. The anterior body of vetulocystids is also strongly convoluted, and so reminiscent of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
Very few characters unite the deuterostomes 
8
, 
22
, 
24
, and only the pharyngeal openings are potentially fossilizable. In this context the body cones of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
are more similar to the apparently equivalent structures found in the vetulicolians and vetulocystids than they are to the pharyngeal structures of other deuterostomes 
1
, 
3
, 
7
, 
11
. Early deuterostomes have a through gut, so the apparent absence of an anus in 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
could be secondary, as in brachiopods and ophiuroids. It remains possible, however, that this feature was inherited from more primitive bilaterians 
25
, possibly linked to the acoels and xenoturbellids 
24
, 
26
.
</p>
            <p>
We draw two main conclusions. First, some of the earliest deuterostomes were meiofaunal, and this finding complements proposals that such animals were benthic worms 
27
. In contrast, however, to the suggestions that early deuterostomes possessed an indirect life cycle with a feeding larva 
24
, the biology of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
seems more consistent with direct development 
28
. Previous work had emphasized the possible importance of the first stages of metazoan evolution occurring in a meiofaunal context 
29
. The discrepancy between the known fossil record of early metazoans and their estimated times of divergence 
30
as based on molecular clocks suggests that such miniaturized forms could slip through the nets of most fossilization pathways and so help to explain this cryptic history 
9
. Second, the body cone openings of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
are consistent with deuterostome body openings being very primitive 
8
, 
24
. In 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
, however, diffusion across the body surface would have met any respiratory needs, suggesting that a transformation to specifically pharyngeal gills was linked to an increase in body size. If 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
lacked an anus, body openings may have originated to dispose of waste material.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Saccorhytidae (
new family
) Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytusgen. nov.
Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronariusgen et sp. nov
. Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronarius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>data</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pomatrum</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Xidazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Data</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronarius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronarius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Meiofaunal deuterostomes from the basal Cambrian of Shaanxi (China)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/nature21072</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1D24282A9B47FFE5F56CFFEE5841FFA4</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature21072</pub-id>
               <source>Nature</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Saccorhytidae (
new family
) Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytusgen. nov.
Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronariusgen et sp. nov
. Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Millimetric, ellipsoidal body, ventral mouth and multiple lateral openings.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Generic name reference to bag-like body (L. 
saccus
) and wrinkled preservation (Gr. 
rhytis
). Specific name in reference to crownlike mouth.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Hemi-ellipsoidal, bilaterally symmetrical body. Integument bears chevron pattern. Ventral mouth defined by two circlets of radial folds, inner circlet with associated protuberances. Aborally and dorsally up to four nodulate rugae. Eight body openings, conical, defined by radial folds. In mid-region anteriorly directed spines. Smaller pores parallel to body cones and in posterior region, possibly housed setae. 
Holotype.
XX45-20.
</p>
            <p>Other material.
XX25-62 and another 43 specimens (Supplementary Table 1).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Locality.
Zhangjiagou section, Hexi, Xixiang County, Shaanxi, China.
</p>
            <p>Stratigraphy.
Kuanchuanpu Formation, Fortunian Stage of Terreneuvian Series.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Forty-five phosphatized specimens are available (

, 

, Extended Data 

–6 and Supplementary Table 1). As with similar material from this horizon 
14
– 
16
and co-eval deposits 
17
, the phosphatic composition of the specimens is evidently the result of very early diagenesis. Extensive folding suggests that in life the integument was thin, flexible and only slightly sclerotized. The integument consists of two layers (Extended Data 

b, c, h, 3c, g, 5k, 6c, d), and frequently exhibits a fine-scale, densely spaced chevron-like folding on both external and internal surfaces (

b, Extended Data 

f–i, 3h, 4g and Supplementary Table 1). If original, this suggests that the integument was bi-layered.
</p>
            <p>
The body is hemi-ellipsoidal, with a maximum length of 1,300μm, width 800μm and height 900μm (Extended Data Fig. 7). Most material is crushed but several specimens (

g, h and Extended Data Figs 5g, h, 6a) confirm original bilateral symmetry. Otherwise, body orientations depend principally on identification of the mouth, and presumably the more dorsal and posterior location of the body cones and possibly sensory pores. Post-mortem deformation makes the precise dispositions of other structures more difficult to interpret. The most parsimonious conclusion, however, is that these features were also arranged bilaterally (

g, h and Extended Data Figs 4f, h 6a).
</p>
            <p>
The largest of the body openings (approximately 300–500 μm) is defined by a double circlet with prominent radial folds. The folds of the inner circlet are somewhat finer and this circlet also bears a series of oral protrusions, each consisting of an outer sheath and an inner peg-like structure (

a, d, e, g–i, 2a, b, d, e and Extended Data 

c, 3f, 4a, c, f, 5a, c, d, g, i). This double circlet is interpreted as the oral region, while the protrusions, notably the most anterior pair (Extended Data Figs 5g, i, 6f, g), may represent sensilla. The flexibility of the oral region is evident from both its lateral compression and dorsal arching (

a, d, e, i, 2d and Extended Data Figs 4a, e, 5a, c, d, g).
</p>
            <p>
Anterior to the oral region, the dorsal integument consists of up to four rugae with a nodular appearance (

a, d, 2a, b, d and Extended Data 

d, 4a, c, 5a, f). These may be separated by intervening integument or (presumably as a result of contraction) are closely adpressed with the nodular regions interlocked. Behind the rugae, the integument grades into a zone with longitudinal folds, but the posterior body is relatively smooth. Otherwise the most prominent structures are a series of body cones (

a, d, g, i, 2a, d, f, g and Extended Data 

a, b, d, h, 3a, c, d, g, 4b, d, f, h, 5a–c, e, g, k, 6). These vary in size (56–328 μm across), but all are formed of a series of ribs radiating from an unoccluded aperture. Up to eight body cones are visible, with the four body cones on the left and right sides extending in a more dorsal direction (

a). The first body cone is located immediately behind the oral region, and the body cone behind it is somewhat larger. The third body cone is the largest, and the most dorsal one is smaller. There are also two sets of small circular pores (30 μm across). One set is widely separated and runs parallel to the body cones (

a, g and Extended Data Figs 4f, h, 5g). The other set is more dorsal and consists of sub-linear arrays (

a, b, f, 2a, c, f, g and Extended Data 

a, d, e, j, 3a, d, e, 4f, h, 5b, h, j). Finally there are occasional conspicuous spines, with a wide base and elongate anterior taper (

c, 2h and Extended Data 

d, 5a, b, f, 6a). Strong folding makes the conclusion tentative, but no anus is evident (

a).
</p>
            <p>1State Key Laboratory of Continental Dynamics, Department of Geology, Northwest University, Xi’an 710069, China. 2Department of Earth Sciences, University of Cambridge, Downing Street, Cambridge CB2 3EQ, UK. 3State Key Laboratory of Biogeology and Environmental Geology, China University of Geosciences, Beijing 100083, China. 4Department of Zoology, University of Kassel, Kassel 34132, Germany. 5College of Petroleum Engineering, Xi’an Shiyou University, Xi’an 710065, China.</p>
            <p>0 0 M O N T H 2 0 1 7 | V O L 0 0 0 | N A T U R E | 1</p>
            <p>
The oral region could evidently distend, with its pleated arrangement accommodating changes in size. This, combined with dorsal arching, would allow ingestion of food particles and possibly somewhat larger prey 
18
. The size of mouth also suggests that water was swallowed, with the body cones being interpreted as exhalant structures. The dorsal extension of the body cones suggests that the corresponding oral cavity was also elongate. The more dorsal set of circular pores may represent the insertion points of setae. The other set adjacent to the body cones may have had a sensory function, although alternatively they could have released internal contents such as adhesive mucus or gametes.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
The millimetric size of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
does not preclude a planktonic location, but its globular shape is consistent with a meiofaunal habit within what is now a phosphatic shelly limestone 
16
. Although we did not find exact counterparts amongst extant meiobenthic taxa, 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
shows a suite of features consistent with an interstitial habitat 
18
. These include a thick but flexible cuticle, suitable for mechanical protection and wriggling between sediment grains, respectively (Extended Data 

c, d). The postulated setae, especially those towards the dorsal side, could perform a haptic role, including temporary attachment. Many meiofaunal taxa are progenetic and deciding whether 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
is best interpreted as a miniaturized adult or a larval stage has important implications for both potential life cycles and phylogenetic relationships. Evidence in favour of the former includes the observation that, despite a size range of 548–1,326 μm, the morphology is effectively invariant. More notable is that most extant larvae 
19
are ciliated and, although a few groups such as the bryozoans (cyphonautes) and loriciferans have thin cuticular coverings, they are unlike the relatively massive coat of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
Irrespective of whether 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
is a progenetic relative of unknown macroscopic taxa, its closest relationships appear to lie with the vetulicolians and possibly vetulocystids. Forming part of a highly disparate suite of taxa, collectively they appear to represent early deuterostomes 
1
, 
20
, albeit ones not easily assigned to particular stem groups 
21
. Our phylogenetic analysis (

b, Extended Data Fig. 8 and Supplementary Information) confirms both the monophyly of the deuterostomes 
22
and component groups including vetulicolians plus banffiids and vetulocystids, but the position of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
remains less well constrained.
</p>
            <p>
With respect to vetulicolians, similarities with 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
include the circum-oral radial structures and the body openings, interpreted as pharyngeal gills in the former group. In forms such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>12
the gills also have a convex exterior, although here the openings are directed posteriorly. Moreover, in 
<tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
the relative size of the openings in the posterior direction is similar to that seen in 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
, notably with the third opening being conspicuously larger. In 
<tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>12
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pomatrum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Xidazoon</tp:taxon-name>1
, 
12
and 
Banffia23
the oral region shows variably developed pleating (Extended 
<tp:taxon-name>Data</tp:taxon-name>
Fig. 9), similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
. Similarities to the vetulocystids 
5
include body openings defined as truncated cones with well-developed radial ribs, albeit more numerous. The anterior body of vetulocystids is also strongly convoluted, and so reminiscent of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
Very few characters unite the deuterostomes 
8
, 
22
, 
24
, and only the pharyngeal openings are potentially fossilizable. In this context the body cones of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
are more similar to the apparently equivalent structures found in the vetulicolians and vetulocystids than they are to the pharyngeal structures of other deuterostomes 
1
, 
3
, 
7
, 
11
. Early deuterostomes have a through gut, so the apparent absence of an anus in 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
could be secondary, as in brachiopods and ophiuroids. It remains possible, however, that this feature was inherited from more primitive bilaterians 
25
, possibly linked to the acoels and xenoturbellids 
24
, 
26
.
</p>
            <p>
We draw two main conclusions. First, some of the earliest deuterostomes were meiofaunal, and this finding complements proposals that such animals were benthic worms 
27
. In contrast, however, to the suggestions that early deuterostomes possessed an indirect life cycle with a feeding larva 
24
, the biology of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
seems more consistent with direct development 
28
. Previous work had emphasized the possible importance of the first stages of metazoan evolution occurring in a meiofaunal context 
29
. The discrepancy between the known fossil record of early metazoans and their estimated times of divergence 
30
as based on molecular clocks suggests that such miniaturized forms could slip through the nets of most fossilization pathways and so help to explain this cryptic history 
9
. Second, the body cone openings of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
are consistent with deuterostome body openings being very primitive 
8
, 
24
. In 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
, however, diffusion across the body surface would have met any respiratory needs, suggesting that a transformation to specifically pharyngeal gills was linked to an increase in body size. If 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
lacked an anus, body openings may have originated to dispose of waste material.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Saccorhytidae (
new family
) Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytusgen. nov.
Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronariusgen et sp. nov
. Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronarius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>data</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pomatrum</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Xidazoon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Data</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronarius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronarius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Meiofaunal deuterostomes from the basal Cambrian of Shaanxi (China)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/nature21072</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1D24282A9B47FFE5F56CFFEE5841FFA4</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature21072</pub-id>
               <source>Nature</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Saccorhytidae (
new family
) Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytusgen. nov.
Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus coronariusgen et sp. nov
. Han, Shu, Ou and Conway Morris, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Millimetric, ellipsoidal body, ventral mouth and multiple lateral openings.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Generic name reference to bag-like body (L. 
saccus
) and wrinkled preservation (Gr. 
rhytis
). Specific name in reference to crownlike mouth.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Hemi-ellipsoidal, bilaterally symmetrical body. Integument bears chevron pattern. Ventral mouth defined by two circlets of radial folds, inner circlet with associated protuberances. Aborally and dorsally up to four nodulate rugae. Eight body openings, conical, defined by radial folds. In mid-region anteriorly directed spines. Smaller pores parallel to body cones and in posterior region, possibly housed setae. 
Holotype.
XX45-20.
</p>
            <p>Other material.
XX25-62 and another 43 specimens (Supplementary Table 1).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Locality.
Zhangjiagou section, Hexi, Xixiang County, Shaanxi, China.
</p>
            <p>Stratigraphy.
Kuanchuanpu Formation, Fortunian Stage of Terreneuvian Series.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Forty-five phosphatized specimens are available (

, 

, Extended Data 

–6 and Supplementary Table 1). As with similar material from this horizon 
14
– 
16
and co-eval deposits 
17
, the phosphatic composition of the specimens is evidently the result of very early diagenesis. Extensive folding suggests that in life the integument was thin, flexible and only slightly sclerotized. The integument consists of two layers (Extended Data 

b, c, h, 3c, g, 5k, 6c, d), and frequently exhibits a fine-scale, densely spaced chevron-like folding on both external and internal surfaces (

b, Extended Data 

f–i, 3h, 4g and Supplementary Table 1). If original, this suggests that the integument was bi-layered.
</p>
            <p>
The body is hemi-ellipsoidal, with a maximum length of 1,300μm, width 800μm and height 900μm (Extended Data Fig. 7). Most material is crushed but several specimens (

g, h and Extended Data Figs 5g, h, 6a) confirm original bilateral symmetry. Otherwise, body orientations depend principally on identification of the mouth, and presumably the more dorsal and posterior location of the body cones and possibly sensory pores. Post-mortem deformation makes the precise dispositions of other structures more difficult to interpret. The most parsimonious conclusion, however, is that these features were also arranged bilaterally (

g, h and Extended Data Figs 4f, h 6a).
</p>
            <p>
The largest of the body openings (approximately 300–500 μm) is defined by a double circlet with prominent radial folds. The folds of the inner circlet are somewhat finer and this circlet also bears a series of oral protrusions, each consisting of an outer sheath and an inner peg-like structure (

a, d, e, g–i, 2a, b, d, e and Extended Data 

c, 3f, 4a, c, f, 5a, c, d, g, i). This double circlet is interpreted as the oral region, while the protrusions, notably the most anterior pair (Extended Data Figs 5g, i, 6f, g), may represent sensilla. The flexibility of the oral region is evident from both its lateral compression and dorsal arching (

a, d, e, i, 2d and Extended Data Figs 4a, e, 5a, c, d, g).
</p>
            <p>
Anterior to the oral region, the dorsal integument consists of up to four rugae with a nodular appearance (

a, d, 2a, b, d and Extended Data 

d, 4a, c, 5a, f). These may be separated by intervening integument or (presumably as a result of contraction) are closely adpressed with the nodular regions interlocked. Behind the rugae, the integument grades into a zone with longitudinal folds, but the posterior body is relatively smooth. Otherwise the most prominent structures are a series of body cones (

a, d, g, i, 2a, d, f, g and Extended Data 

a, b, d, h, 3a, c, d, g, 4b, d, f, h, 5a–c, e, g, k, 6). These vary in size (56–328 μm across), but all are formed of a series of ribs radiating from an unoccluded aperture. Up to eight body cones are visible, with the four body cones on the left and right sides extending in a more dorsal direction (

a). The first body cone is located immediately behind the oral region, and the body cone behind it is somewhat larger. The third body cone is the largest, and the most dorsal one is smaller. There are also two sets of small circular pores (30 μm across). One set is widely separated and runs parallel to the body cones (

a, g and Extended Data Figs 4f, h, 5g). The other set is more dorsal and consists of sub-linear arrays (

a, b, f, 2a, c, f, g and Extended Data 

a, d, e, j, 3a, d, e, 4f, h, 5b, h, j). Finally there are occasional conspicuous spines, with a wide base and elongate anterior taper (

c, 2h and Extended Data 

d, 5a, b, f, 6a). Strong folding makes the conclusion tentative, but no anus is evident (

a).
</p>
            <p>1State Key Laboratory of Continental Dynamics, Department of Geology, Northwest University, Xi’an 710069, China. 2Department of Earth Sciences, University of Cambridge, Downing Street, Cambridge CB2 3EQ, UK. 3State Key Laboratory of Biogeology and Environmental Geology, China University of Geosciences, Beijing 100083, China. 4Department of Zoology, University of Kassel, Kassel 34132, Germany. 5College of Petroleum Engineering, Xi’an Shiyou University, Xi’an 710065, China.</p>
            <p>0 0 M O N T H 2 0 1 7 | V O L 0 0 0 | N A T U R E | 1</p>
            <p>
The oral region could evidently distend, with its pleated arrangement accommodating changes in size. This, combined with dorsal arching, would allow ingestion of food particles and possibly somewhat larger prey 
18
. The size of mouth also suggests that water was swallowed, with the body cones being interpreted as exhalant structures. The dorsal extension of the body cones suggests that the corresponding oral cavity was also elongate. The more dorsal set of circular pores may represent the insertion points of setae. The other set adjacent to the body cones may have had a sensory function, although alternatively they could have released internal contents such as adhesive mucus or gametes.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
The millimetric size of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
does not preclude a planktonic location, but its globular shape is consistent with a meiofaunal habit within what is now a phosphatic shelly limestone 
16
. Although we did not find exact counterparts amongst extant meiobenthic taxa, 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
shows a suite of features consistent with an interstitial habitat 
18
. These include a thick but flexible cuticle, suitable for mechanical protection and wriggling between sediment grains, respectively (Extended Data 

c, d). The postulated setae, especially those towards the dorsal side, could perform a haptic role, including temporary attachment. Many meiofaunal taxa are progenetic and deciding whether 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
is best interpreted as a miniaturized adult or a larval stage has important implications for both potential life cycles and phylogenetic relationships. Evidence in favour of the former includes the observation that, despite a size range of 548–1,326 μm, the morphology is effectively invariant. More notable is that most extant larvae 
19
are ciliated and, although a few groups such as the bryozoans (cyphonautes) and loriciferans have thin cuticular coverings, they are unlike the relatively massive coat of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
Irrespective of whether 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
is a progenetic relative of unknown macroscopic taxa, its closest relationships appear to lie with the vetulicolians and possibly vetulocystids. Forming part of a highly disparate suite of taxa, collectively they appear to represent early deuterostomes 
1
, 
20
, albeit ones not easily assigned to particular stem groups 
21
. Our phylogenetic analysis (

b, Extended Data Fig. 8 and Supplementary Information) confirms both the monophyly of the deuterostomes 
22
and component groups including vetulicolians plus banffiids and vetulocystids, but the position of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
remains less well constrained.
</p>
            <p>
With respect to vetulicolians, similarities with 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
include the circum-oral radial structures and the body openings, interpreted as pharyngeal gills in the former group. In forms such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>12
the gills also have a convex exterior, although here the openings are directed posteriorly. Moreover, in 
<tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>
the relative size of the openings in the posterior direction is similar to that seen in 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
, notably with the third opening being conspicuously larger. In 
<tp:taxon-name>Didazoon</tp:taxon-name>12
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pomatrum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Xidazoon</tp:taxon-name>1
, 
12
and 
Banffia23
the oral region shows variably developed pleating (Extended 
<tp:taxon-name>Data</tp:taxon-name>
Fig. 9), similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
. Similarities to the vetulocystids 
5
include body openings defined as truncated cones with well-developed radial ribs, albeit more numerous. The anterior body of vetulocystids is also strongly convoluted, and so reminiscent of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
Very few characters unite the deuterostomes 
8
, 
22
, 
24
, and only the pharyngeal openings are potentially fossilizable. In this context the body cones of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
are more similar to the apparently equivalent structures found in the vetulicolians and vetulocystids than they are to the pharyngeal structures of other deuterostomes 
1
, 
3
, 
7
, 
11
. Early deuterostomes have a through gut, so the apparent absence of an anus in 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
could be secondary, as in brachiopods and ophiuroids. It remains possible, however, that this feature was inherited from more primitive bilaterians 
25
, possibly linked to the acoels and xenoturbellids 
24
, 
26
.
</p>
            <p>
We draw two main conclusions. First, some of the earliest deuterostomes were meiofaunal, and this finding complements proposals that such animals were benthic worms 
27
. In contrast, however, to the suggestions that early deuterostomes possessed an indirect life cycle with a feeding larva 
24
, the biology of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
seems more consistent with direct development 
28
. Previous work had emphasized the possible importance of the first stages of metazoan evolution occurring in a meiofaunal context 
29
. The discrepancy between the known fossil record of early metazoans and their estimated times of divergence 
30
as based on molecular clocks suggests that such miniaturized forms could slip through the nets of most fossilization pathways and so help to explain this cryptic history 
9
. Second, the body cone openings of 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
are consistent with deuterostome body openings being very primitive 
8
, 
24
. In 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
, however, diffusion across the body surface would have met any respiratory needs, suggesting that a transformation to specifically pharyngeal gills was linked to an increase in body size. If 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
lacked an anus, body openings may have originated to dispose of waste material.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>Online Content
Methods,along with any additional Extended Data display items and Source Data, are available in the online version of the paper; references unique to these sections appear only in the online paper.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Received 15 August; accepted 22 December 2016.</title>
         <p>Published online 30 January 2017.</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Supplementary Information
is available in the online version of the paper.
</p>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <p>
1. 
Shu, D.-G.
, 
Conway Morris, S.
, 
Zhang,Z. F.
&amp; 
Han, J.The earliest history of the deuterostomes: the importance of the Chengjiang Fossil-Lagerstatte
. 
Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B277
,
165–174
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>Acknowledgements
Supported by Natural Science Foundation of China (nos 41621003, 41272019, 41572017, 41672009), Ministry of Science and Technology of China (D.S., J.H.) (no. 2013CB835002), Alexander von Humboldt Foundation (Q.O.), Program for New Century Excellent Talents, Ministry of Education of China (Q.O.), Department of Earth Sciences, University of Cambridge and St. John’s College,Cambridge (S.C.M.). We thank V.Brown, J. Luo, J. Sun, M. Cheng, and H. Gong for technical assistance and D.-H. Yang for the reconstruction.
</p>
         <p>
2. 
Zamora, S.
, 
Rahman, I. A.
&amp; 
Smith, A. B.Plated Cambrian bilaterians reveal the earliest stages of echinoderm evolution
. 
PLoS One7
,

e 
38296
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
3. 
Nanglu, K.
, 
Caron, J. -B.
, 
Conway Morris, S.
&amp; 
Cameron, C. B.Cambrian suspension-feeding tubicolous hemichordates
. 
BMC Biol
. 
14
,
56
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
4. 
Ou, Q.et al.
Evidence for gill slits and a pharynx in Cambrian vetulicolians: implications for the early evolution of deuterostomes

. 
BMC Biol
. 
10
,
81
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>Author Contributions
J.H. and D.S. conceived the project.J.H., S.C.M. and Q.O. wrote early drafts of paper and assessed initial results.J.H. prepared photographs and phylogenetic analysis.H.H. undertook computerized tomography restoration.All authors discussed results, and developed observations and conclusions.
</p>
         <p>
5. 
Shu, D.-G.
, 
Conway Morris, S.
, 
Han,J.
, 
Zhang, Z.F.
&amp; 
Liu, J. N.Ancestral echinoderms from the Chengjiang deposits of China
. 
Nature430
,
422–428
(
2004
).
</p>
         <p>
6. 
Caron, J.-B.
, 
Conway Morris, S.
&amp; 
Shu, D.Tentaculate fossils from the Cambrian of Canada (British Columbia) and China (Yunnan) interpreted as primitive deuterostomes
. 
PLoS One5
,

e 
9586
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>Author Information
Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. The authors declare no competing financial interests.Readers are welcome to comment on the online version of the paper. Publisher’s note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to D.S. (elidgshu@nwu.edu.cn) or S.C.M. (sc113@cam.ac.uk).
</p>
         <p>
7. 
Shu, D.et al.
A new species of yunnanozoan with implications for deuterostome evolution

. 
Science299
,
1380–1384
(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
8. 
Gillis, J. A.
, 
Fritzenwanker, J. H.
&amp; 
Lowe, C. J. Astem-deuterostome origin of the vertebrate pharyngeal transcriptional network
. 
Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B279
,
237–246
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
9. 
Wray,G. A.Molecular clocks and the early evolution of metazoan nervous systems
. 
Phil. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B370
,
20150046
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
10. 
Shu, D.-G.
, 
Chen, L.
, 
Han, J.
&amp; 
Zhang, X. L.An Early Cambrian tunicate from China
. 
Nature411
,
472–473
(
2001
).
</p>
         <p>
11. 
Conway Morris, S.
&amp; 
Caron, J.-B. Aprimitive fish from the Cambrian of North America
. 
Nature512
,
419–422
(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
12. 
Shu, D.-G.et al.
Primitive deuterostomes from the Chengjiang Lagerstätte (Lower Cambrian, China)

. 
Nature414
,
419–424
(
2001
).
</p>
         <p>
13. 
Conway Morris, S.
, 
Halgedahl, S. L.
, 
Selden, P.
&amp; 
Jarrard, R. D.
Rare primitive deuterostomes from the Cambrian (Series 3) of Utah. 

J. 
Paleontol
. 
89
,
631–636
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
14. 
Dong, X.-P.et al.
Embryos, polyps and medusae of the Early Cambrian scyphozoan 
Olivooides
. 
Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B280
,
20130071
(
2013
).
</p>
         <p>
15. 
Han, J.et al.
Early Cambrian pentamerous cubozoan embryos from South China

. 
PLoS One8
,

e 
70741
(
2013
).
</p>
         <p>
16. 
Liu, Y.
, 
Xiao, S.
, 
Shao, T.
, 
Broce, J.
&amp; 
Zhang, H.The oldest known priapulid-like scalidophoran animal and its implications for the early evolution of cycloneuralians and ecdysozoans
. 
Evol. Dev
.
16
,
155–165
(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
17. 
Zhang,H.et al.
Armored kinorhynch-like scalidophoran animals from the early Cambrian

. 
Sci. Rep
.
5
,
16521
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
18. 
Giere, O.Meiobenthology: The microscopic fauna in aquatic sediments
(Springer-Verlag, 1993)

.
</p>
         <p>
19. 
Young, C. M.
, 
Sewell, M. A.
&amp; 
Rice, M. E.
(eds) 
Atlas of Marine Invertebrate Life
(Academic,2002)

.
</p>
         <p>
20. 
Peterson, K. J.
&amp; 
Eernisse, D. J.The phylogeny, evolutionary developmental biology, and paleobiology of the Deuterostomia:25 years of new techniques, new discoveries, and new ideas
. 
Org. Divers. Evol
.
16
,
401–418
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
21. 
Smith, A. B.Cambrian problematica and the diversification of deuterostomes
. 
BMC Biol
. 
10
,
79
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
22. 
Simakov, O.et al.
Hemichordate genomes and deuterostome origins

. 
Nature527
,
459–465
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
23. 
Caron, J.-B.Banffia constricta
, a putative vetulicolid from the Middle Cambrian Burgess Shale

. 
Trans. R. Soc. Edinb. Earth Sci
. 
96
,
95–111
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
24. 
Lowe, C. J.
, 
Clarke, D. N.
, 
Medeiros, D. M.
, 
Rokhsar, D. S.
&amp; 
Gerhart, J.The deuterostome context of chordate origins
. 
Nature520
,
456–465
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
25. 
Hejnol, A.
&amp; 
Martín-Durán,J.Getting to the bottom of anal evolution
. 
Zool. Anz
.
256
,
61–74
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
26. 
Hejnol, A.
&amp; 
Pang, K.Xenacoelomorpha’s significance for understanding bilaterian evolution
. 
Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev
.
39
,
48–54
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
27. 
Brown, F. D.
, 
Prendergast, A.
&amp; 
Swalla, B. J.Man is but a worm: chordate origins
. 
Genesis46
,
605–613
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
28. 
Sly, B. J.
, 
Snoke, M. S.
&amp; 
Raff, R. A.Who came first—larvae or adults? origins of bilaterian metazoan larvae
. 
Int. J. Dev. Biol.47
,
623–632
(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
29. 
Boaden, P.Meiofauna and the origins of the Metazoa
. 
Zool. J. Linn. Soc.96
,
217–227
(
1989
).
</p>
         <p>
30. 
Erwin, D. H.et al.
The Cambrian conundrum:early divergence and later ecological success in the early history of animals

. 
Science334
,
1091–1097
(
2011
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Reviewer InformationNature
thanks A.Hejnol, I. Rahman and J. Vannier for their contribution to the peer review of this work.
</p>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <p>
Most of the rock samples were treated with 8% acetic acid solution, with the insoluble component being examined with a binocular microscope. Coated with gold, the specimens were imaged under high vacuum in a scanning mode using secondary electrons with an of FEI Quanta 400 FEG scanning electron microscope. Internal anatomy of specimens was examined using microcomputed tomography (micro-CT) with a ZEISS Xradia-510 in Xian Shiyou University, China with settings: source voltage 
~
40 kV,target current 
~
74μA.For a single microfossil we acquired 990 successive pictures each with a resolution of 1,013×1,013 pixels, and each pixel was about 1 μm.Micro-CT 
<tp:taxon-name>data</tp:taxon-name>
were processed using VG Studio 2.2 Max for 3D reconstructions.All specimens are deposited at the Early Life Institute (ELI), Northwest University, Xi’an, China. Forty-five specimens are assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
coronarius

gen. nov., sp. nov.:XX23-248, XX25-62, XX26-170, XX26- 168, XX34-298, XX35-228, XX36-22, and so on.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <p>Data availability.
Source 
<tp:taxon-name>data</tp:taxon-name>
for all figures are provided with the paper. The phylogeny in 

is provided in the Supplementary Information.
</p>
         <p>
31. 
Shu, D.-G.et al.
A pipiscid–like fossil from the Lower Cambrian of south China

. 
Nature400
,
746–749
(
1999
).
</p>
         <p>
32. 
Luo, H.et al
. 
Early Cambrian Chengjiang Fauna from Kunming Region, China. (Yunnan Sci. &amp; Tech. Press,1999)
.
</p>
         <p>
33. 
Shu, D.-G.On the phylum Vetulicolia
. 
Chin. Sci. Bull
.
50
,
2342–2354
(
2005
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Extended Data 

| 
Geographical location of horizon and its</p>
         <p>petrography. a
, Locality map of the Zhangjiagou section, Xixiang, Shaanxi Province, China. In addition to 
<tp:taxon-name>Saccorhytus</tp:taxon-name>
, the phosphatic limestone of Bed 2 of the Kuanchuanpu Formation in the Zhangjiagou section 
</p>
      </sec>
      <p/>
   </body>
</article>
