<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1126/science.1137614</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Protein sequences from mastodon and Tyrannosaurus rex revealed by mass spectrometry</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2007</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>
Protein Sequences 
from
Mastodon and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus Rex</tp:taxon-name>
Revealed by Mass Spectrometry
</p>
      <p>John M.Asara
,1 
'
2 

* Mary 
H
. Schweitzer,3 
Lisa
M. Freimark,1 Matthew Phillips,1 Lewis 
C
. 
Cantley
1 
'4</p>
      <p>
Fossilized bones from extinct taxa harbor the potential for obtaining protein or 
DNA
sequences that could reveal evolutionary links to extant 
species
. We used mass spectrometry to obtain protein sequences from bones of 
a
160,000- to 600,000-year-old 
extinct
mastodon 
Wlammut americanum)
and a 68-million-year-old dinosaur 

(
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus rex</tp:taxon-name>
).

The presence of 
T. rex
sequences indicates that their peptide bonds were remarkably stable. 
Mass
spectrometry can thus be used to determine unique sequences from ancient organisms from peptide fragmentation patterns, a valuable tool to study the evolution and adaptation of ancient taxa from which genomic sequences are unlikely to be obtained
</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>
Obtaining genome sequences from a 
number of
taxa has dramatically enhanced our abilities to study the 
evolution
and adaptation of organisms. However, difficulties 
in
the acquisition of DNA or RNA 
from ancient
extinct 
taxa limit
the ability 
to examine
molecular evolution. Recent 
advances
in mass spectrometry (MS) technologies have made it possible to obtain sequence information from subpicomolar quantities of fragmented proteins and peptides (
7
, 
2
), but the 
conversion
of these fragmentation patterns (MS/MS spectra) into peptide sequences in the absence of genomic and protein sequences from publicly available databases has been a challenge. If the unknown peptide 
is
identical in sequence to a protein region from an organism whose genes or proteins have previously been sequenced, then the fragmentation pattern (the mass/charge ratios and relative intensities of peaks) will match a theoretical fragmentation pattern from a sequence 
in
publicly available protein databases or from the fragmentation pattern of a synthetically derived peptide, to confirm its identity.
</p>
      <p>
Using this approach, tryptic peptide sequences of collagen have been identified from a 100,000- to 300,000-year-old mammoth skull, and these matched collagen fragments of extant mammalian taxa including bovine, a result that was also supported by immunological methods (
5
). MS has also been used to report protein sequences from younger fossil specimens 

(
4
- 
6
).

However, sequence data from very old (1 million years or older) fossils has been hindered by protein concentrations below the limits of detection by most analytical methods, and by theoretical limits based on predicted rates of degradation (
7
, 
8
).

In addition, most commercial software for identifying peptide sequences by MS relies on the peptide fragmentation pattern matching identically to that of a peptide/protein sequence 
in
existing sequence databases. Here we show that these hindrances can be overcome by a two-step proteomics approach to obtain sequences from ion-trap MS fragmentation patterns.
</p>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus rex</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Protein sequences from mastodon and Tyrannosaurus rex revealed by mass spectrometry</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1126/science.1137614</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/360F4F73FFCCFFD6F475FFCDFFE5FF8C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1137614</pub-id>
               <source>Science</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
We sequenced collagen protein fragments derived from fossilized bones of two extinct taxa: a 160,000- to 600,000-year-old mastodon [specimen number Museum of the Rockies (MOR) 605] (
9
) and a 68-million-year-old dinosaur 

(
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus rex</tp:taxon-name>
,
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
) 

(
10
),
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
results that are supported by immunological and molecular analyses published in this issue by Schweitzer 

et al. (
11
).

We first looked for tryptic peptide fragments from extracts of fossilized bone that matched identically with sequences from an orthologous protein or proteins from extant taxa, thereby identifying the protein(s) of interest. This is a common procedure for conserved proteins from taxa that share genomic information. Next, we generated a protein sequence database of likely drifts in amino acids in other tryptic peptides by comparing amino acid sequences ofthe orthologs from multiple related extant taxa. This approach produced a manageable number of theoretical protein sequences. The predicted peptide fragmentation pattern from these theoretical protein sequences were then compared with the fragmentation patterns of additional peptides derived from extracts of fossilized bone that did not match peptides in public sequence databases (fig. S1).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <p>
division of Signal Transduction, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, Boston, 
MA
02115, USA. department of Pathology, Harvard Medical School, Boston, 
MA
02115, USA; North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences, Raleigh, NC 27601, USA; and Museum of the Rockies, Montana State University, Bozeman, MT 59717, USA. department of Marine, Earth and Atmospheric Sciences, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC 27695, USA. department of Systems Biology, Harvard Medical School, Boston, 
MA
02115, USA.
</p>
      <p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: jasara@bidmc.harvard.edu</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>
As a proof of concept for this approach, we investigated collagen sequences from femur bone extracts of an ostrich 
{Struthio camelus),
an extant organism whose genomic sequence has not yet been evaluated and whose protein sequences are not available in protein databases. Collagens are the most abundant proteins in bone (&gt;90%) and have specific posttranslational modifications (72, 73), and their longevity has already been demonstrated in fossils (
3
, 
14
).

Collagen proteins are also highly conserved. For example, the sequence identity for collagen al type 1 (α1tl) from human 
{Homo sapiens)
to frog 
{Xenopus laevis)
is 81%, and the sequence identity between human and bovine 
{Bos taurus)
is 97%, an extraordinarily high similarity. Using the Sequest algorithm (75), we identified 87 tryptic peptide spectra by microcapillary LC/MS/ MS (LC, liquid chromatography) representing peptide sequence matches to extant related organisms in protein databases, primarily collagen α1tl from chicken 
{Gallusgallus)
(table S1). In addition to obtaining sequence data, a further benefit of using MS is that posttranslational modifications 

(
16
)

of the proteins can be determined. Approximately 50% of proline residues, 15% of lysines, and 10% of glycines in the collagen peptides were hydroxylated. Hydroxyproline stabilizes the triple helical confirmation of collagen in fibrillar structures (
12
), and hydroxylysine cross-links individual collagen molecules (
13
), although the function of glycine hydroxylation has not been reported. In some cases, the technology used here could not determine posttranslational modifications resulting in very small mass shifts nor could it distinguish isobaric amino acid residues. Approximately 33% ofthe sequence for collagen αltl and 16% for collagen α2t1 were identified from ostrich bone extracts through identical matches to collagen in taxa whose sequences are present in protein databases. Many experimental factors can result in a failure to obtain complete protein coverage, including proteolysis, chromatography, and ionization efficiency; however, some peptide sequences could have been missed because ofthe evolutionary divergence ofamino acids from sequences of taxa in current protein databases.
</p>
      <p>Protein nameOrganism identityNumber of peptide spectraAmino acid coverageCollagen α1(l)-chain precursorDog
, bovine, human, chimp
2420%Similar to α2t1 collagenDog
, human
1510%Similar to α2t1 collagenElephant129%Similar to collagen α1(IV)-chain precursorBovine34%α1tl collagenHuman22%α1t2 collagen isoform 1Human34%Collagen α2(l) chainHuman46%Similar to collagen α1t1Elephant23%Collagen α1(l) chainMouse22%α1t2 collagenNewt25%Similar to α2tl1collagenChicken34%Similar to collagen α1(l)-chain precursorChimp22%α1t1 collagenNewt23%</p>
      <p>
To address this latter possibility, we generated aligned sequences obtained from chicken collagen altl (the most closely related sequence to that of ostrich in the public database) with those from frog and Japanese newt 
(Cynops pyrrhogaster)
(the next most closely related sequences in the database). For predicted tryptic fragments where one or more of these three taxa diverged at more than one residue, we generated a set of theoretical peptide/protein sequences that included the exact sequence in regions where all three species were identical and various combinations of the observed variant amino acids at residues where the three species diverged (

A). We assumed that differences between chicken and ostrich are most likely to occur at residues that have been observed to drift from chicken to frog and newt. Because chicken is phylogenetically closer to ostrich than frog or newt, we chose the residue observed in chicken as the most likely residue when all three species differed at a location but chose the majority residue where two out of three were identical at a given position. For this example, we predicted a theoretical drift from chicken that was likely to be observed in a related species such as ostrich. This sequence (as well as other sequences predicted in an analogous manner) matched MS/MS fragmentation patterns from ostrich bone extract as well as a synthetic peptide created for sequence validation (
Fig
. 1, B and C).
</p>
      <p>Peptide sequenceProteinOrganism identityXcorrSpGATGAP*GIAGAPG*FP*GARCollagen α1t1Chicken, frog3.771099
G* 
AAGPP
*GATGFP*GAAGR
Collagen α1t1Newt, fish, mouse3.74797GVQGPP*GPQGPRCollagen α1t1Chicken2.54865GLPGESGAVGPAGPIGSRCollagen α2t1Chicken2.99479GVVGLP*GQRCollagen α1t1Multiple organisms2.55500GLVGAPGLRGLPGKCollagen α1t2Frog2.28410GAPGPQG*PAGAP*GPKCollagen α1t1Newt2.14272</p>
      <p>
Additional theoretical sequences were generated for misaligned residues by using point-assisted mutation (
PAM
) matrices that predict changes in amino acid residues through evolution (
17
), rather than choosing a residue from one of the three initial organisms 
(18).
In addition to sequence matches to related organisms, the approach found six additional collagen peptide sequences that were unique to extant ostrich and had been missed in the comparison with public databases (table S2). Of these six sequences, four were determined using the organism weightedconsensus method and two were determined using the PAM weighted-consensus method. Although this approach only increased the total sequence coverage of ostrich collagen from -33% to -39%, it revealed sequences 
in
ostrich collagen that differed from those 
in
chicken or 
in
other species in the database, thus providing a means to assess evolutionary divergences between these species.
</p>
      <p>
For mastodon sequences, we sampled extracts from mastodon long-bone fragments dating to 160,000 to 600,000 years ago that preserved soft tissues (
9
, 
19
).

74 tryptic peptide MS/MS spectra matched collagen sequences from extant mammalian organisms 
in
the protein database (Table 1). The sequence matches resulted 
in
approximately 32% coverage for collagen αlt1 and 29% for collagen 
a
2tl. The fraction of glycine with hydroxylation 
in
the mastodon collagen peptides was somewhat higher (-50%) than that observed 
in
ostrich collagen, whereas the fraction of hydroxylated proline and lysine residues was similar to that in ostrich. It is possible that the subset of peptides with hydroxylation on glycine 
is
resistant to proteolysis, thus explaining the enrichment. Alternatively, enzymatic glycine hydroxylation may be more active 
in
the mastodon than 
in
the ostrich, or the oxidation may have occurred nonenzymatically over hundreds of thousands of years. The mastodon sequences obtained were more closely related to collagen sequences from dog, bovine, human, and elephant than to nonmammalian taxa, as expected.
</p>
      <p>
We used the same approach as for ostrich to identify collagen peptide sequences unique to mastodon. We compared drifts 
in
sequences between vertebrate mammals, including human, dog 
(Canis familiaris),
and mouse 
(Mus musculus)
as well as PAM to generate additional theoretical collagen sequences centered on extant mammalian species and added them to our protein database containing theoretical ostrich sequences. Elephant 
(Loxodonta africana),
the most closely related extant taxon 

(
20
),

was not used to generate predicted collagen sequences because incomplete peptide sequence fragments translated from genomic data are available in public protein databases. Other combinations ofmammalian organisms such as bovine were also used to generate additional predictions. Four additional mastodon peptide sequences from fragmentation patterns matched the theoretical sequences; two from the organism weighted-consensus method and two from the PAM weighted-consensus method (

). Those sequences were confirmed by comparing their fragmentation patterns to those obtained with synthetic peptides (

, B and C).
</p>
      <p>
The additional sequences increased the amino acid coverage of mastodon collagen αltl from approximately 32% to 37%, a comparable 
increase
to that for the ostrich collagen. We thus obtained nearly as much coverage of collagen sequence from the 160,000- to 600,000-year-old fossilized bone (37%) as from a freshly collected ostrich bone (39%).
</p>
      <p>
For 
T. rex
sequences, we analyzed proteins from the femur of a 68-million-year-old 
T. rex
(MOR 1125) recovered from the base of the Hell Creek Formation. This bone preserves soft tissues 

(
10
).

Previous attempts to obtain protein or DNA sequences from such ancient fossils have failed because of extremely low concentrations of organic material remaining after extraction and because of degradation or modification of the remaining organic materials (
7
). Protein extracts from the 
T. rex
were prepared as for ostrich and mastodon; however, the tryptic peptides required multiple purification steps (solid-phase extraction, strong cation exchange, and reversed-phase microchromatography) 
in
order to eliminate a rust-colored coextracting contaminant and to increase the concentration of peptidic material. Three sequences from initial LC/MS/MS experiments from the 
T. rex
samples indicated the presence of the iron-containing metalloenzyme nitrile hydratase beta, derived from soil bacteria 
Rhodococcus sp.
and involved 
in
biodegradation 

(
21
).

Two peptides from a collagen adhesion protein from 
Solibacter usitatis
were also sequenced. Microbial contamination was not significant, most likely because of the deep burial of the fossilized bones 
in
the strata of the Hell Creek Formation.
</p>
      <p>
The MS/MS spectra obtained from processed 
T. rex
bone extracts revealed seven total collagen peptide sequences that could be aligned with predicted fragmentation patterns of collagen α1tl, α2tl, or α1t2 sequences from extant vertebrate taxa 
in
the public protein database (
Table 2
). These sequences could be reproduced from multiple LC/MS/MS experiments; however, different peptides were sequenced from five different sample preparations of 
T. rex
protein extract over a 1.5-year period. The last two extractions yielded less sequence information than earlier extractions, probably because of degradation of the fossil over time after removal from its well-preserved native environment 

(
22
).

As in the extant ostrich and extinct mastodon, most of the peptides contained hydroxyl modifications on proline, lysine, or glycine residues. Sediment and buffer control samples were analyzed, and no sequences from collagen were found, although bacterial peptides were also present in sediment.
</p>
      <p>
A BLAST alignment and similarity search 

(
23
)

of the five 
T. rex
peptides from collagen αltl as a group against the all-taxa protein database showed 58% sequence identity to chicken, followed by frog (51% identity) and newt (51% identity). The small group of peptide sequence data reported here support phylogenetic hypotheses suggesting that 
T. rex is
most closely related to birds among living organisms whose collagen sequence 
is
present 
in
protein databases 

(
24
- 
26
).

The collagen sequences from other closely related extant taxa such as alligator 
(Alligator sinensis)
and crocodile 
(Crocodylus acutus)
are not present in current protein databases. If all sequences were consistent with a single extant organism, it might indicate that the samples or our experiments were contaminated. However, we identified regions of sequence that align uniquely with multiple related vertebrate taxa in protein databases. The highly conserved nature of collagen proteins results in very limited regions that do not overlap, and the sequence alignments vary by only one or two amino acids, even 
in
distantly related organisms. Because these peptides are all derived from the same bone matrix, one would have to make the argument for multiple contamination events from organisms, such as newt, that are not native to Hell Creek environments and have never been inside the buildings that have housed these bone samples. For further validation of the sequence 
data
, 

shows one of the experimental 
T. rex
sequences, GVQGPP(
OH
) 

GPQGPR (
27
),

that matched to chicken collagen altl and the synthetic 
version
of the peptide. The experimental spectrum shows lower signal intensity and more chemical noise than the synthetic peptide, which 
is
not surprising because the 
spectra
were derived from 68-million-year-old endogenous proteins. The signal intensities of the mass spectra indicate that only low or subfemtomole levels of peptides were produced from tryptic digestions of approximately 30 mg of bone protein extract. Peptide sequences unique to 
T. rex
were not found, most likely because few peptides were available for sequencing as compared to the ostrich and mastodon samples. In support of these results and data shown here and by Schweitzer 
et al.
(
11
), 
in
situ localization with avian antibodies to collagen type 1 shows the presence of collagen, which disappears after treatment with collagenase (
11
).
</p>
      <p>
The ability to sequence intact peptides from a 68-million-year-old source is attributed to several factors, including the exceptional preservation of the soft tissues from the Hell Creek 
environment
, the fresh preparation of the fossil samples without curation or preservation 

(
22
),

and the advancements in the sensitivity of MS technology over the past decade. The fact that sequenceable collagen was very abundant in the mastodon sample, which could be approximately half a million years old, also sheds light on the fact that sequenceable protein lasts much longer than 1 million years.
</p>
      <p>
As technologies become more refined and protein extraction techniques are optimized, more informative material may be recovered. This holds promise for future work on other fossil material showing similar preservation, but also demonstrates a method for obtaining protein sequences from rare or endangered extant organisms whose genomes have note been sequenced. The MS- and bioinformatics-based approach we have used can be applied not only to obtain sequences from extinct organisms, but also to obtain protein sequences from extant organisms whose genomes have not been sequenced and to discover mutations 
in
diseased tissues such as cancers.
</p>
      <p>REPORTS
I
</p>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References and Notes</title>
         <p>
1. 
M. Mann
, 
0. N. Jensen
, 
Nat. Biotechnol.21
,
255
(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
2. 
B. Domon
, 
R. Aebersold
, 
Science312
,
212
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
3. 
M. H. Schweitzer
et al., 
J. Mol. Evol.55
,
696
(
2002
).
</p>
         <p>
4. 

C. 
M
. Nielsen-Marsh
et
al., 
Proc. Natl. Acad.
Sci. 
U.S.A.102
,
4409
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
5. 

C. 
M
. Nielsen-Marsh

et al., 
Geology30
,
1099
(
2002
).
</p>
         <p>
6. 
P
. H. Ostrom

et al., 

Geochim. Cosmochim. 
Acta70
, 
2034
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
7. 
T. Lindahl
, 
Nature362
,
709
(
1993
).
</p>
         <p>
8. 
M
. J. Collins

et al., 
Geology28
,
1139
(
2000
).
</p>
         <p>
9. 
C. L. Hill
, 
Quat. Int.142-143
,
87
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
10. 
M. H. Schweitzer
, 
J. L. Wittmeyer
, 
J. R. Horner
, 
J. K. Toporski
, 
Science307
,
1952
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
11. 
M. H. Schweitzer
et al., 
Science316
,
277
(
2007
).
</p>
         <p>
12. 
A
. Bhattacharjee

, 
M
. Bansal

, 
Int. U. Biochem. Mol. Biol. Life57
,
161
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
13. 
L. Knott
, 
A. J. Bailey
, 
Bone22
,
181
(
1998
).
</p>
         <p>
14. 
N. Tuross
, 
M. L. Fogel
, 
P. E. Hare
, 

Geochim. Cosmochim. 
Acta52
,
929
(
1988
).
</p>
         <p>
15. 
J. K. Eng
, 
A
. L. McCormack

, 

J. R. Yates 
III
, 

J. 
Am. Soc. Mass Spectrom.5
,
976
(
1994
).
</p>
         <p>
16. 
M. Mann
, 
O
. N. Jensen

, 
Nat.
Biotechnol.
21
,
255
(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
17. 

M. 
O
. Dayhoff
et al.,
Atlas 
of
Protein Sequence 
and
Structure

, 
vol. 5, suppl. 3
(
National Biomedical Research Foundation, Washington, DC
, 
1978
).
</p>
         <p>
18. A complete 
description
of the predicted sequence generation is available as supporting material on 
Science
Online.
</p>
         <p>
19. 
M
. 
H
. Schweitzer

, 
J. L. Wittmeyer
, 
J. R. Horner
, 
Proc. R.
Soc. 
London Ser. B274
, 
183
(
2007
).
</p>
         <p>
20. 

H. 
Yang
, 
E
. 
M
. Golenberg

, 
J. Shoshani
, 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A
.
93
,
1190
(
1996
).
</p>
         <p>
21. 

M. 
M
. Tauber

et al., 
Appl. Environ. Microbiol
.
66
, 
1634
(
2000
).
</p>
         <p>
22. 
M
. Pruvost

et al., 

Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 
U.S.A.104
,
739
(
2007
).
</p>
         <p>
23. 
S
. F. Altschul

, 
W
. Gish

, 
W
. Miller

, 
E
. 
W
. Myers

, 

D. J. 
Lipman
, 
J. Mol
. 
Biol
.
215
,
403
(
1990
).
</p>
         <p>
24. 
P
. M. 
O'Connor
, 
L. P. Claessens
, 
Nature436
,
253
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
25. 
F. V. Mariani
, 
G
. R. Martin

, 
Nature423
, 
319
(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
26. 
M. H. Schweitzer
, 
J. L. Wittmeyer
, 
J. R. Horner
, 
Science308
,
1456
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
27. Single-letter abbreviations for the amino acid residues are as follows: 
A
, Ala; C, Cys; D, Asp; E, Glu; F, Phe;
</p>
         <p>
G, Gly; H, His; I, Ile; K, 
Lys
; L, Leu; M, Met; N, 
Asn
; 
P
, Pro; 0, Gln; R, 
Arg
; S, Ser; T, Thr; V, Val; 
W
, Trp; and Y, 
Tyr
.
</p>
         <p>
28. We thank J. Wittmeyer, J. Luo, R. Mecham, M. Berne, M. Vander Heiden, H. Christofk, and B. Zheng for experimental help and helpful discussions; 
W
. Lane and S. Nagpal for software help; J. R. Horner for providing 
T.
rex and mastodon fossils; and C. Hill for taphonomic data for mastodon. We also thank NSF (awards EAR- 0634136 and 
EAR-
0541744), the Paul F. Glenn Foundation, and the David and Lucile Packard Foundation for providing funds.
</p>
         <p>SupportingOnline Material
www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/316/5822/280/DCl
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Materials and Methods</p>
      <p>SOM Text</p>
      <p>Fig. S1</p>
      <p>Tables S1 and S2</p>
      <p>Reference</p>
      <p>15 November 2006; accepted 16 March 2007</p>
      <p>10.1126/science.1137614</p>
      <p>
www.sciencemag.org SCIENCE VOL 316 13 
APRIL
2007
</p>
      <p>This content downloaded from 154.59.124.40 on Tue, 07 Apr 2020 11:06:44 UTC All use subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms</p>
   </body>
</article>
