<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1371/journal.pone.0115021</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Amphibious Shelter-Builder Oniscidea Species from the New World with Description of a New Subfamily</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>
Amphibious Shelter-Builder Oniscidea Species from the New World with Description of a New Subfamily, a New Genus and a New Species from Brazilian Cave (
<tp:taxon-name>Isopoda</tp:taxon-name>
,
</p>
      <p>
Synocheta, 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Leila A. Souza</tp:taxon-name>1
☯ 
*
, 
Rodrigo L. Ferreira2
☯, 
André R. Senna3
☯ 
1
Universidade Estadual do Ceará (
UECE
), Campus do Itaperi, Instituto Superior de Ciências Biomédicas, Laboratório de Carcinicultura/ 
LACAR
, Fortaleza, CE, 
Brasil
, 
2
Universidade Federal de Lavras (
UFLA
), Departamento de Biologia, Setor de Zoologia, Laboratório de Ecologia Subterrânea, Lavras, MG, 
Brasil
, 
3
Universidade Federal da Bahia (
UFBA
), Instituto de Biologia, Laboratório de Invertebrados Marinhos: Crustacea, Cnidaria &amp; Fauna Associada (LABIMAR), 
Salvador
, BA, 
Brasil</p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. 
*
leila.souza@uece.br
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>OPEN
ACCESS
</p>
      <p>Citation:Souza LA
, 
Ferreira RL
, 
Senna AR
(
2015
) 
Amphibious Shelter-Builder Oniscidea Species from the New World with Description of a New Subfamily
, a New Genus and a New Species from Brazilian Cave (
<tp:taxon-name>Isopoda, Synocheta</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
). 
PLoS ONE10
(
5
): e0115021. doi: 
10.1371
/journal.pone.0115021
</p>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>
The new subfamily Iuiuniscinae, 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, is erected for the new genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus</tp:taxon-name>
and the new species 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
, which is described from cave of the State of Bahia, Northeastern 
Brazil
. 
A
special ecological character is shown here for the first time for a New World Oniscidea: the construction of mud shelters. An introduction addressing the systematics of Synocheta with emphasis on 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae
Vandel, 
1952</tp:taxon-name>
is provided, as well as general comments about the dependence of water in some Oniscidea and ecological traits of amphibious Synocheta. The problems referring to nomenclature, taxonomy and the interrelationships in 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
are discussed.
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Academic Editor:
Sebastien Duperron, Université Pierre et Marie Curie, 
FRANCE</p>
      <p>Received:May 22, 2014</p>
      <p>Accepted:November 17, 2014</p>
      <p>Published:May 20, 2015</p>
      <p>Copyright:
© 
2015
Souza et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.
</p>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Data Availability Statement:
All relevant data are within the paper.
</p>
         <p>
According to Schmidt [
1
], the Synocheta Legrand, 
1946
comprise about 
630
species and they are adapted to endogeous or cave habitats, all of them confined to quite moist environments. Schmalfuss [
2
] distinguished two phyletic lines in Synocheta: 
1
. Pleopod 
1
endopodite of male is elongated in relation to that of the female, and simple, without any “individualized setae” or other appendages; exopodite shows specializations related to the copulation behavior. 
2
. Pleopod 
1
endopodite of male is elongated and bears an individualized long seta, which in some groups evolved into an apparent second article of this appendage. The male pleopod 
1
exopodite is not—or only slightly modified. This group includes " 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
s. str." [
1
], 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae
Vandel

, 
1952</tp:taxon-name>
, as well as Haplophthalminae, 
<tp:taxon-name>Buddelundiella
Silvestri

, 
1897</tp:taxon-name>
,
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Funding:
Funding was provided by the Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e
</p>
      <p>
Tecnológico (CNPq), process nº 
477712
/ 
2006
– 
1
, and to R. L. F. (CNPq grant nr. 
301061
/ 
2011
– 
4
), and by Fundação Carlos Chagas Filho de Amparo à
</p>
      <p>
Pesquisa do Estado do Rio de Janeiro (FAPERJ) to A. R. S., by grant, process nr. E- 
26
/ 
110.773
/ 
2012
. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.
</p>
      <p>
“ 
<tp:taxon-name>Turanoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
”, Titanidae, 
<tp:taxon-name>Schoebliidae</tp:taxon-name>
, and several holarctic genera.
</p>
      <p>Competing Interests:
The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.
</p>
      <p>
The current section Synocheta used to correspond to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichoniscidae Sars, 
1899</tp:taxon-name>
. Smaller families kept being described, increasing the group’s complexity. The monophyly of Synocheta and their relation with Crinocheta as their sister group were established by Schmalfuss [
3
]. Synocheta, previously named “complexe trichoniscoide” [4,5], were divided by Vandel into two superfamilies—called “series styloniscienne” and “series trichoniscienne” [
5
] and, later, Styloniscoidea and Trichoniscoidea [
6
]—defined by the structure of the copulatory apparatus of the male and by the geographical distribution. This division was adopted by some authors [
7–10
], but ignored by others [
3
]. Vandel himself [
11
] viewed the differences between the two groups as “quantitative” and not “qualitative”, because the strong pleopodal musculature of 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
was supposed to have been reduced in 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, in a scenario of {
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
⊣ 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
} defined by him.
</p>
      <p>
Verhoeff [
12
] was the first to mention that 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
did not occur in the Neotropical Region. In "Landisopoden aus Südamerika", submitted to publication in 
1939
and only actually published 
12
years later, Verhoeff [
13
] created the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Patagoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
with the species 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
iheringi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
nordenskjoldi</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
pallidus</tp:taxon-name>
from Patagonia and 
Falkland Islands
. In a second article, prepared in the same period but published earlier, on the fauna of Synocheta from Southern 
Chile
[
12
], the author described three more species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Patagoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
— 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. 
schwabei</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
araucanicus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
simrothi</tp:taxon-name>
. According to Verhoeff [
13
], 
<tp:taxon-name>Patagoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscus
Brandt, 
1833 in</tp:taxon-name>
many aspects, but differs mainly in having only four pairs of fully developed pleopods in both sexes and strong musculature in the first pleonal segment of the male. Verhoeff considered these characters essential to justifying making this genus the 
type
of a new family Pata- goniscidae. In this family, he also included many other 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
from South 
America
, and concluded that 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
was absent in South and Central 
America
and in a large portion of North 
America
, not taking artificially introduced species into account.
</p>
      <p>
Vandel [
5
] published a study on “Les trichoniscides (crustaces—isopodes) de l’hemisphere austral...” (although this was the title of the paper, the author suggested a new family for these species), confirming the Verhoeff’s hypothesis [
13
] that the concerned " 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
" (
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
) have musculature in the first pleonal segment of the male different from all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
of the Northern Hemisphere. Thus, Vandel saw reasons to support Verhoeff’s opinion [
13
] that 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
from South 
America
should be separated from the ones of the Northern Hemisphere as a new family. Vandel [
5
] didn’t examine Verhoeff’s species, but claimed that he must have misinterpreted his material in many aspects. He considered 
<tp:taxon-name>Patagoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
as junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscus
Dana, 
1852</tp:taxon-name>
, and claimed that both genus and 
type
species, 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
magellanicus
Dana, 
1852</tp:taxon-name>
, are valid, despite Dana’s incomplete description [
14
]. He also preferred not to keep Verhoeff’s name, and named this new family 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
. The family name created by Vandel, though more recent, was kept instead of Patagoniscidae, because it was established before 
1961
and received general acceptance according to article 
40
of 
ICZN
[
10
].
</p>
      <p>
Besides 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, there are two other small families included by Vandel [
5
] in Styloniscoidea, both endemic from Southern Africa: 
<tp:taxon-name>Schoebliidae</tp:taxon-name>
and Titanidae. Their species are exclusively termitary dwellers of depressed body [
5
]. Information about regressive characters probably connected to the microhabitat of termitaries can be found in Kensley [
8
]. Borutzky [
7
], based on a termitary dwelling species of 
Uzbekistan
of which only females are known, described a fourth family in Styloniscoidea 
<tp:taxon-name>Turanoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Schmalfuss [
3
] didn’t recognize the superfamilies Styloniscoidea and Trichoniscoidea because he didn’t find evidences of their monophyly or of a sister group relation between them. This author included 
<tp:taxon-name>
Olibrinidae Budde-Lund, 
1913</tp:taxon-name>
, a small group of halophile Oniscidea, in the infraorder Synocheta, besides the families recognized by Vandel. But 
<tp:taxon-name>Olibrinidae</tp:taxon-name>
has at least one possible synapomorphy with the Crinocheta—tuft of penicillia (and not teeth) in the molar process of mandible—so that such inclusion would need more convincing backing.
</p>
      <p>
Schmölzer [
15
] and Tabacaru [
16
] approached 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
systematics, giving formal names to the tribes of Trichoniscinae called “legions” by Vandel [
6
]. Tabacaru [
16
] recognized the two traditional subfamilies, Trichoniscinae and Haplophthalminae Verhoeff, 
1908
. He elevated a tribe poorly described not long before—Thaumatoniscellini—to the rank of subfamily; but this was done in the last line of his article, in a not very explicit way, and was not even referred in the abstract. He also recognized the proximity of Buddellundiellidae Verhoeff, 
1930
to Haplophthalminae and Trichoniscinae Trichoniscini, as had already been proposed by Vandel. Neither of the authors, however, passed this phylogenetic idea to their classifications, keeping 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
as a concededly paraphyletic group.
</p>
      <p>
According to Schmidt [
1
]: “the 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
are a paraphyletic basal group including all species not having the apomorphies of the other families”.
</p>
      <p>
Classification scheme for the 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
of Vandel/Schmölzer/Tabacaru:
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoniscidae Sars, 
1899</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
Trichoniscinae Sars, 
1899</p>
      <p>
Première Division = Typhlotricholigioidini Rioja, 
1959
Deuxième Division
</p>
      <p>
Légions I + II = Spelaeonethini Schmölzer, 
1965
Légion III = Androniscini Tabacaru, 
1993
Légion IV = Oritoniscini Tabacaru, 
1993
Légion V = Trichoniscoidini Schmölzer, 
1965
Troisième Division = Trichoniscini Sars, 
1899</p>
      <p>
Haplophthalminae Verhoeff, 
1908</p>
      <p>
Thaumatoniscellinae Tabacaru, 
1993</p>
      <p>
doi: 
10.1371
/journal.pone.0115021.t001
</p>
      <p>
The family 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
was divided by Vandel [
5
] into two subfamilies: Styloniscinae and Notoniscinae. The first, which seems to be defined only by symplesiomorphies, is characterized by smooth or tuberculated dorsum and pleon-epimera 
1–5
reduced opening a gap between pereon and pleon. The Notoniscinae are a small group of species with well-developed neopleurons 
3–5
or 
4–5
and tergal ornamentation similar to the one found in Haplophthalminae (
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
), with tubercles or longitudinal ribs and sometimes pleonites with protrusions. Strouhal [
17
] described a third subfamily Kuscheloniscinae from the Juan Fernández Islands (
Chile
), monotypic and defined by the absence of an interruption in the pereon-pleon outline, pleon-epimera 
3–5
very reduced and by having pereonites with protrusions and lateral ribs.
</p>
      <p>Until the present study, Styloniscinae was grouped the following genera [18, 19]:</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Clavigeroniscus
Arcangeli, 
1930</tp:taxon-name>
, groups five species (only four, according to Tabacaru [
16
]) with pantropical distribution. One of them— 
<tp:taxon-name>C
. 
orghidani
Vandel, 
1981</tp:taxon-name>
, from 
Cuba
, is troglobiotic.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Cordioniscus
Graeve, 
1914</tp:taxon-name>
(maybe a synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscus</tp:taxon-name>
[
20
]), includes 
15
species. Among them, 
<tp:taxon-name>C
. 
stebbing
(Patience, 
1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
is cosmopolitan and “ 
<tp:taxon-name>Cordioniscus</tp:taxon-name>
” 
leleupi
Vandel, 
1968
is exclusive from 
Ecuador
[
21
]. Of the remaining species, two are troglobiotic from 
Bulgaria
: 
<tp:taxon-name>C
. 
bulgaricus
Andreev, 
1986</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>C
. 
schmalfussi
Andreev, 
2002</tp:taxon-name>
and the rest from mediterranean countries, mainly 
Greece
[
22
], of which at least six are troglobiotic.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Indoniscus
Vandel, 
1952</tp:taxon-name>
, presents three species from regions surrounding the Indian Ocean. One of them, 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
deharvengi
Dalens, 
1987</tp:taxon-name>
, from 
Thailand
, is troglobiotic.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Pectenoniscus
Andersson, 
1960</tp:taxon-name>
is monotypic, from Southern 
Brazil
.
</p>
      <p>Trogloniscus
Taiti &amp; Xue, 
2012
(includes 
<tp:taxon-name>Sinoniscus
Schultz, 
1995</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Guiliniscus
Dixon, 
2013
) has five troglobiotic species from the Chinese provinces of Guangxi and Guizhou (although the largest part of the Chinese territory belongs to the Palearctic Region, these provinces lie in the Oriental Region).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Styloniscus
Dana, 
1852</tp:taxon-name>
, groups about 
40
species of mainly circum-antarctic distribution, some of them troglobiotic.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Thailandoniscus
Dalens, 
1989</tp:taxon-name>
is monotypic, with one troglobiotic species from 
Thailand
.
</p>
      <p>Spelunconiscus
Campos-Filho, Araújo &amp; Taiti, 
2014
, monotypic, with one troglobiotic species (
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
castroi</tp:taxon-name>
) from state of Minas Gerais, 
Brazil
.
</p>
      <p>Xangoniscus
Campos-Filho, Araújo &amp; Taiti, 
2014
, monotypic, with one troglobiotic species (
X
. 
aganju
) from state of Bahia, 
Brazil
.
</p>
      <p>
The subfamily Notoniscinae groups two genera, 
<tp:taxon-name>Notoniscus
Chilton, 
1915</tp:taxon-name>
, from the Australian Region, and 
<tp:taxon-name>Paranotoniscus
Barnard, 
1932</tp:taxon-name>
, from 
South Africa
, both without regressive characters.
</p>
      <p>
On the other hand, Kuscheloniscinae includes a single monotypic genus, 
<tp:taxon-name>Kuscheloniscus
Strouhal, 
1961</tp:taxon-name>
, with one species from Southern Neotropics, without regressive characters.
</p>
      <p>
Considering the diagnostic characters pointed to by Vandel [
5
] and Schmalfuss [
2
], the new genus and new species described here belong to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, but their inclusion in one of the previously established subfamilies is impossible. A comprehensive analysis of Brazilian 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, started by Souza-Kury [
23
] and still in progress, reveals the need for the creation of a new subfamily for these 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
. Thus, a new subfamily is herein erected based on the new genus and new species herein described. Recently Campos-Filho 
et al
. [
19
] published an article on Brazilian cave terrestrial isopods, in which they described two monotypic genera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
. Campos-Filho 
et al
. [
19
] noted that the taxonomic impediment has been a problem in the description of Oniscidea species. The present paper contributes to solving this problem.
</p>
      <p>
This is the first paper of a series which the authors intend to publish on the Brazilian troglobiotic 
<tp:taxon-name>Isopoda</tp:taxon-name>
, particularly 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, in the BIS Research Group (

Biodiversidade de 
<tp:taxon-name>Isopoda Subterrâneos</tp:taxon-name>
) registered in 
Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico
(CNPq), 
Brazil
.
</p>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Material and Methods</title>
         <p>
No specific permissions were required for these locations/activities (it's not a Conservation Unit). However, we have a permission from Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade (ICMBio)— 
Brazil
, because the collection was made in a cave (license nº 
14783
– 
1
). The field studies did not involve endangered or protected species. It is a new invertebrate species described in this study. Location of the study: “Lapa do Baixão” cave (
14
º 
23
´
8.13
´´S

,
</p>
         <p>43
º 
3735.06
´´W), located in 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiu</tp:taxon-name>
municipality (Bahia state, 
Brazil
).
</p>
         <p>
The specimens were found in “Lapa do Baixão” cave (
14
º 
23
´
8.13
´´S

, 
43
º 
3735.06
´´W), locat- ed in 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiu</tp:taxon-name>
municipality (Bahia state, 
Brazil
). The cave was not totally explored, since part of its inner chambers is flooded during rainy periods. However, the known conduits extend over 
500
meters. The only known entrance to the cave is located at the bottom of a subsidence sinkhole, which receives epigean water, especially during the rainy season. The external area is severely impacted, mainly by human activities such as agriculture and extensive breeding of cattle and goats. Fortunately, it seems the cave has not been visited by anyone except the research team.
</p>
         <p>
A visual search for specimens was conducted throughout the base and walls of the “Lapa do Baixão” cave. Special attention was paid to water ponds, which were more common in deeper areas of the cave, although some ponds were also observed near the entrance. Specimens were captured with a fine brush and placed in vials containing ethanol 
70
%. The specimens were dissected under a Leica stereoscopic microscope and their appendages were mounted in glycerol gel slides. The illustrations were made under an optic microscope, Motic BA- 
310
, with camera lucida, and digitally prepared with CorelDraw 

X 
6
, with support of a tablet, Wacon Intuos 
4
. The 
type
material is preserved in ethanol 
70
% and housed at the Crustacea Collection of 
Museu de Zoologia
, 
Universidade Federal da Bahia
(
UFBA
), and the Collection of Subterranean Invertebrates, 
Universidade Federal de Lavras
(ISLA). Nomenclature of characters is mainly based on Schmidt [
24
].
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Nomenclatural Acts</title>
         <p>
The electronic edition of this article conforms to the requirements of the amended International Code of Zoological Nomenclature, and hence the new names contained herein are available under that Code from the electronic edition of this article. This published work and the nomenclatural acts it contains have been registered in ZooBank, the online registration system for the 
ICZN
. The ZooBank LSIDs (Life Science Identifiers) can be resolved and the associated information viewed through any standard web browser by appending the 
LSID
to the prefix “http://zoobank.org/”. The 
LSID
for this publication is: urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:F 
5155225
- 
9832
- 
41
AA-A 
476-97041
BD 
837
B 
3
. The electronic edition of this work was published in a journal with an 
ISSN
, and has been archived and is available from the following digital repositories: PubMed Central, LOCKSS.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>
Order 
<tp:taxon-name>
Isopoda Latreille, 
1817</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Section Synocheta Legrand, 
1946</p>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>
Styloniscidae Vandel, 
1952</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amphibious Shelter-Builder Oniscidea Species from the New World with Description of a New Subfamily</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0115021</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/467BFFCAE735FFF3FF8EF6230D58FFF9</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0115021</pub-id>
               <source>PLoS ONE</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscinae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>subfam. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>Type
species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>
gen. 
et
sp. nov.
</tp:taxon-status>
, by monotypy.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>gen
. et 
sp
. 
nov
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>Subfamily name based on genus name.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Large, amphibious troglobiotic 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
about 
10 mm
long; flexible body capable of folding; dorsal integument smooth or without ribs or large protrusions (
versus
with tubercles or longitudinal ribs in Notoniscinae and 
versus
protrusions and lateral ribs in Kuscheloniscinae); enlarged coxal plates; pereopod 
1
much shorter than the others, flanking the head; pleon-epimera 
3–5
well developed (
versus
pleon-epimera 
1–5
reduced in Styloniscinae and 
versus
pleonepimera 
3–5
very reduced in Kuscheloniscinae), forming acute tips; telson distal half is lower than the proximal half. This subfamily includes shelter-builder species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
Genus name is arbitrary, from 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, name of the 
type
locality + the ending (o)niscus used for oniscideans. Gender masculine.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Blind and unpigmented. Amphibious, can be found inside water bodies in the cave. Also in the cave, it can be found in special habitats: semi-spheric clay formations on the walls, or natural holes sealed with clay, where it hides. Broad enlarged and acute coxal plates; pleon-epimera 
3–5
with exceptionally long and acute tips. First antenna with ten aesthetascs. First maxilla outer endite with 
4
+ 
3
simple tooth setae, one slender seta in the inner corner and two long bipectinate setae in the inner group of teeth. Telson with acute apex. Second antennae have a 
7
-jointed flagellum. Pereopods 
2–4
of male with stout protrusion proximally on the frontal face of the merus.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D 
5
A 
719
D 
3-51
BE- 
4
D 
85
-AB 
2
A- 
93
A011F 
58
EFD (

)
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined</p>
            <p>Holotype
: male, dissected and drawn, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
.VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., 
UFBA1603
.
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
: 
1
female

, dissected and drawn, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
.VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., 
UFBA1604
; 
7
males

and 
1
female

, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
. VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., 
UFBA1605
; 
3
males

and 
1
female

, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
.VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., ISLA 
4993
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The species name is an adjective derived from the 
type
locality name, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>Same as the genus.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Based in the 
holotype
. Measurements: length— 
9.2 mm
from anterior margin of the head to the apex of telson; width— 
5 mm
, from one tip to another of the pereon coxal plate 
4
. Cephalon semiquadrangular, fully inserted in the first pereonite; there is a line on the vertex which runs along the back of the posterior deep furrows which hold the second antennae, forming a "V" whose tip is positioned medially between the insertion of the antennae. Without eyes and pigment, with convex body. Dorsal integument smooth, not very thin, with setae and more sclerotized on the tips of coxal plates that are all fused with tergites; posterior margins of tergites of pereonites with different kinds of setae. Flexible body capable of folding. Convex pereon tergites, coxal plates of pereonites 
1–7
outwardly extended and widely separated, apically acute. Pereonite 
1
is of smaller width, but of greater length, coxal plates go down and then fold up and form a concave area in the anterior end; coxal plates of pereonites 
1–7
form lateral-distal ends that become progressively more acute, and are especially developed and acute from pereonite 
5–7
. Sternum of pereonites deeply grooved at the sites of insertion of pereopods (minor groove is at the insertion of pereopod 
1
). Pleonites 
1
and 
2
distinct in dorsal view, without apparent pleon-epimera. Pleon-epimera 
3–5
with exceptionally long tips; the tips of the fifth are longer than exopods of uropods. Telson distal half depressed in relation to the proximal half, lateral margin slightly sinuous, with acute apex.
</p>
            <p>
First antenna (

A) 
3
-jointed with nine apical and one lateral aesthetascs on the third article; the three articles are subequal in length. Second antenna (

B) thin; when stretched, it reaches the edge of coxal plate of the pereonite 
3
; the last article of peduncle is the largest; flagellum with 
7
articles, the first one the biggest, the apical one the smallest, with a tuft of free sensory hairs. Mandibles with a pars molaris with a large masticatory surface; left mandible (

C) with three slender penicils between the pars incisiva and the pars molaris, 
lacinia mobilis
robust and apically 
3
-cuspidate; right mandible (

D) with one slender penicil between the pars incisiva and the pars molaris, 
lacinia mobilis
slender and bipectinate. First maxilla (

E) inner endite with three penicils, two of them are almost equal and the third is the biggest; without laterodistal corner; outer endite with outer group with four strong and simple tooth setae; inner group with three simple tooth setae + one slender and differentiated seta in the inner corner; there are also two long setae wholly and conspicuously bipectinate, that emerge from the inner group of teeth. Second maxilla (

F) apically rounded, with many sensilla and outer lobe not apparent. Maxilliped (

G) with a large basis narrowed in its proximal portion; maxilliped palp with 
3
indistinctly delimited distal articles, each of them with a tuft of setae, there is a single setae located below the proximal article; endite distally acute, hairy.
</p>
            <p>
Pereopods 
1–3
(

A– 
2
E) pointing to the proximal region of the body; pereopods 
4–7
(

F), longer, to the distal; spines on margins of pereopods with an accessory seta each. Pereopod 
1
much shorter than the others, flanking the head; dactylus with an outer claw big but slender, with a brownish tip indicating heavy sclerotization. Merus of pereopods 
2–4
with protrusion at its frontal face, proximally; merus 
6
with dilated and truncated distal part. Dactylus of pereopods 
1–7
without conspicuous inner claw. Genital papilla (

A) swollen in the medial part, with extremity constituted of a basal region with folds and a long tip. Pleopod 
1</p>
            <p>
(

A) sympodite large; endopodite biarticulate, 
2
nd article flagelliform, tiny, slender, barely visible 
in situ
. Pleopod 
2
(

B) exopodite without marginal setae; endopodite biarticulate,
</p>
            <p>
enlarged, bifurcate at the apex, forming two long tips. Exopodites of pleopods 
1
and 
2
smaller and 
3–5
bigger, but among the latter, the fifth is the smallest; they all close like blades over the endopods. Sympodites of uropods small. Endopodites of uropods about 
2
/ 
3
the length of exopodites.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amphibious Shelter-Builder Oniscidea Species from the New World with Description of a New Subfamily</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0115021</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/467BFFCAE735FFF3FF8EF6230D58FFF9</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0115021</pub-id>
               <source>PLoS ONE</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscinae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>subfam. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>Type
species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>
gen. 
et
sp. nov.
</tp:taxon-status>
, by monotypy.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>gen
. et 
sp
. 
nov
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>Subfamily name based on genus name.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Large, amphibious troglobiotic 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
about 
10 mm
long; flexible body capable of folding; dorsal integument smooth or without ribs or large protrusions (
versus
with tubercles or longitudinal ribs in Notoniscinae and 
versus
protrusions and lateral ribs in Kuscheloniscinae); enlarged coxal plates; pereopod 
1
much shorter than the others, flanking the head; pleon-epimera 
3–5
well developed (
versus
pleon-epimera 
1–5
reduced in Styloniscinae and 
versus
pleonepimera 
3–5
very reduced in Kuscheloniscinae), forming acute tips; telson distal half is lower than the proximal half. This subfamily includes shelter-builder species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
Genus name is arbitrary, from 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, name of the 
type
locality + the ending (o)niscus used for oniscideans. Gender masculine.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Blind and unpigmented. Amphibious, can be found inside water bodies in the cave. Also in the cave, it can be found in special habitats: semi-spheric clay formations on the walls, or natural holes sealed with clay, where it hides. Broad enlarged and acute coxal plates; pleon-epimera 
3–5
with exceptionally long and acute tips. First antenna with ten aesthetascs. First maxilla outer endite with 
4
+ 
3
simple tooth setae, one slender seta in the inner corner and two long bipectinate setae in the inner group of teeth. Telson with acute apex. Second antennae have a 
7
-jointed flagellum. Pereopods 
2–4
of male with stout protrusion proximally on the frontal face of the merus.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D 
5
A 
719
D 
3-51
BE- 
4
D 
85
-AB 
2
A- 
93
A011F 
58
EFD (

)
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined</p>
            <p>Holotype
: male, dissected and drawn, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
.VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., 
UFBA1603
.
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
: 
1
female

, dissected and drawn, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
.VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., 
UFBA1604
; 
7
males

and 
1
female

, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
. VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., 
UFBA1605
; 
3
males

and 
1
female

, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
.VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., ISLA 
4993
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The species name is an adjective derived from the 
type
locality name, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>Same as the genus.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Based in the 
holotype
. Measurements: length— 
9.2 mm
from anterior margin of the head to the apex of telson; width— 
5 mm
, from one tip to another of the pereon coxal plate 
4
. Cephalon semiquadrangular, fully inserted in the first pereonite; there is a line on the vertex which runs along the back of the posterior deep furrows which hold the second antennae, forming a "V" whose tip is positioned medially between the insertion of the antennae. Without eyes and pigment, with convex body. Dorsal integument smooth, not very thin, with setae and more sclerotized on the tips of coxal plates that are all fused with tergites; posterior margins of tergites of pereonites with different kinds of setae. Flexible body capable of folding. Convex pereon tergites, coxal plates of pereonites 
1–7
outwardly extended and widely separated, apically acute. Pereonite 
1
is of smaller width, but of greater length, coxal plates go down and then fold up and form a concave area in the anterior end; coxal plates of pereonites 
1–7
form lateral-distal ends that become progressively more acute, and are especially developed and acute from pereonite 
5–7
. Sternum of pereonites deeply grooved at the sites of insertion of pereopods (minor groove is at the insertion of pereopod 
1
). Pleonites 
1
and 
2
distinct in dorsal view, without apparent pleon-epimera. Pleon-epimera 
3–5
with exceptionally long tips; the tips of the fifth are longer than exopods of uropods. Telson distal half depressed in relation to the proximal half, lateral margin slightly sinuous, with acute apex.
</p>
            <p>
First antenna (

A) 
3
-jointed with nine apical and one lateral aesthetascs on the third article; the three articles are subequal in length. Second antenna (

B) thin; when stretched, it reaches the edge of coxal plate of the pereonite 
3
; the last article of peduncle is the largest; flagellum with 
7
articles, the first one the biggest, the apical one the smallest, with a tuft of free sensory hairs. Mandibles with a pars molaris with a large masticatory surface; left mandible (

C) with three slender penicils between the pars incisiva and the pars molaris, 
lacinia mobilis
robust and apically 
3
-cuspidate; right mandible (

D) with one slender penicil between the pars incisiva and the pars molaris, 
lacinia mobilis
slender and bipectinate. First maxilla (

E) inner endite with three penicils, two of them are almost equal and the third is the biggest; without laterodistal corner; outer endite with outer group with four strong and simple tooth setae; inner group with three simple tooth setae + one slender and differentiated seta in the inner corner; there are also two long setae wholly and conspicuously bipectinate, that emerge from the inner group of teeth. Second maxilla (

F) apically rounded, with many sensilla and outer lobe not apparent. Maxilliped (

G) with a large basis narrowed in its proximal portion; maxilliped palp with 
3
indistinctly delimited distal articles, each of them with a tuft of setae, there is a single setae located below the proximal article; endite distally acute, hairy.
</p>
            <p>
Pereopods 
1–3
(

A– 
2
E) pointing to the proximal region of the body; pereopods 
4–7
(

F), longer, to the distal; spines on margins of pereopods with an accessory seta each. Pereopod 
1
much shorter than the others, flanking the head; dactylus with an outer claw big but slender, with a brownish tip indicating heavy sclerotization. Merus of pereopods 
2–4
with protrusion at its frontal face, proximally; merus 
6
with dilated and truncated distal part. Dactylus of pereopods 
1–7
without conspicuous inner claw. Genital papilla (

A) swollen in the medial part, with extremity constituted of a basal region with folds and a long tip. Pleopod 
1</p>
            <p>
(

A) sympodite large; endopodite biarticulate, 
2
nd article flagelliform, tiny, slender, barely visible 
in situ
. Pleopod 
2
(

B) exopodite without marginal setae; endopodite biarticulate,
</p>
            <p>
enlarged, bifurcate at the apex, forming two long tips. Exopodites of pleopods 
1
and 
2
smaller and 
3–5
bigger, but among the latter, the fifth is the smallest; they all close like blades over the endopods. Sympodites of uropods small. Endopodites of uropods about 
2
/ 
3
the length of exopodites.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amphibious Shelter-Builder Oniscidea Species from the New World with Description of a New Subfamily</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0115021</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/467BFFCAE735FFF3FF8EF6230D58FFF9</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0115021</pub-id>
               <source>PLoS ONE</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscinae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>subfam. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>Type
species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>
gen. 
et
sp. nov.
</tp:taxon-status>
, by monotypy.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>gen
. et 
sp
. 
nov
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>Subfamily name based on genus name.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Large, amphibious troglobiotic 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
about 
10 mm
long; flexible body capable of folding; dorsal integument smooth or without ribs or large protrusions (
versus
with tubercles or longitudinal ribs in Notoniscinae and 
versus
protrusions and lateral ribs in Kuscheloniscinae); enlarged coxal plates; pereopod 
1
much shorter than the others, flanking the head; pleon-epimera 
3–5
well developed (
versus
pleon-epimera 
1–5
reduced in Styloniscinae and 
versus
pleonepimera 
3–5
very reduced in Kuscheloniscinae), forming acute tips; telson distal half is lower than the proximal half. This subfamily includes shelter-builder species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
Genus name is arbitrary, from 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, name of the 
type
locality + the ending (o)niscus used for oniscideans. Gender masculine.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Blind and unpigmented. Amphibious, can be found inside water bodies in the cave. Also in the cave, it can be found in special habitats: semi-spheric clay formations on the walls, or natural holes sealed with clay, where it hides. Broad enlarged and acute coxal plates; pleon-epimera 
3–5
with exceptionally long and acute tips. First antenna with ten aesthetascs. First maxilla outer endite with 
4
+ 
3
simple tooth setae, one slender seta in the inner corner and two long bipectinate setae in the inner group of teeth. Telson with acute apex. Second antennae have a 
7
-jointed flagellum. Pereopods 
2–4
of male with stout protrusion proximally on the frontal face of the merus.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:D 
5
A 
719
D 
3-51
BE- 
4
D 
85
-AB 
2
A- 
93
A011F 
58
EFD (

)
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined</p>
            <p>Holotype
: male, dissected and drawn, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
.VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., 
UFBA1603
.
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
: 
1
female

, dissected and drawn, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
.VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., 
UFBA1604
; 
7
males

and 
1
female

, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
. VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., 
UFBA1605
; 
3
males

and 
1
female

, Lapa do Baixão, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
, BA, 
Brazil
, 
20
.VII. 
2007
, R. L. Ferreira col., ISLA 
4993
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The species name is an adjective derived from the 
type
locality name, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiú</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>Same as the genus.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Based in the 
holotype
. Measurements: length— 
9.2 mm
from anterior margin of the head to the apex of telson; width— 
5 mm
, from one tip to another of the pereon coxal plate 
4
. Cephalon semiquadrangular, fully inserted in the first pereonite; there is a line on the vertex which runs along the back of the posterior deep furrows which hold the second antennae, forming a "V" whose tip is positioned medially between the insertion of the antennae. Without eyes and pigment, with convex body. Dorsal integument smooth, not very thin, with setae and more sclerotized on the tips of coxal plates that are all fused with tergites; posterior margins of tergites of pereonites with different kinds of setae. Flexible body capable of folding. Convex pereon tergites, coxal plates of pereonites 
1–7
outwardly extended and widely separated, apically acute. Pereonite 
1
is of smaller width, but of greater length, coxal plates go down and then fold up and form a concave area in the anterior end; coxal plates of pereonites 
1–7
form lateral-distal ends that become progressively more acute, and are especially developed and acute from pereonite 
5–7
. Sternum of pereonites deeply grooved at the sites of insertion of pereopods (minor groove is at the insertion of pereopod 
1
). Pleonites 
1
and 
2
distinct in dorsal view, without apparent pleon-epimera. Pleon-epimera 
3–5
with exceptionally long tips; the tips of the fifth are longer than exopods of uropods. Telson distal half depressed in relation to the proximal half, lateral margin slightly sinuous, with acute apex.
</p>
            <p>
First antenna (

A) 
3
-jointed with nine apical and one lateral aesthetascs on the third article; the three articles are subequal in length. Second antenna (

B) thin; when stretched, it reaches the edge of coxal plate of the pereonite 
3
; the last article of peduncle is the largest; flagellum with 
7
articles, the first one the biggest, the apical one the smallest, with a tuft of free sensory hairs. Mandibles with a pars molaris with a large masticatory surface; left mandible (

C) with three slender penicils between the pars incisiva and the pars molaris, 
lacinia mobilis
robust and apically 
3
-cuspidate; right mandible (

D) with one slender penicil between the pars incisiva and the pars molaris, 
lacinia mobilis
slender and bipectinate. First maxilla (

E) inner endite with three penicils, two of them are almost equal and the third is the biggest; without laterodistal corner; outer endite with outer group with four strong and simple tooth setae; inner group with three simple tooth setae + one slender and differentiated seta in the inner corner; there are also two long setae wholly and conspicuously bipectinate, that emerge from the inner group of teeth. Second maxilla (

F) apically rounded, with many sensilla and outer lobe not apparent. Maxilliped (

G) with a large basis narrowed in its proximal portion; maxilliped palp with 
3
indistinctly delimited distal articles, each of them with a tuft of setae, there is a single setae located below the proximal article; endite distally acute, hairy.
</p>
            <p>
Pereopods 
1–3
(

A– 
2
E) pointing to the proximal region of the body; pereopods 
4–7
(

F), longer, to the distal; spines on margins of pereopods with an accessory seta each. Pereopod 
1
much shorter than the others, flanking the head; dactylus with an outer claw big but slender, with a brownish tip indicating heavy sclerotization. Merus of pereopods 
2–4
with protrusion at its frontal face, proximally; merus 
6
with dilated and truncated distal part. Dactylus of pereopods 
1–7
without conspicuous inner claw. Genital papilla (

A) swollen in the medial part, with extremity constituted of a basal region with folds and a long tip. Pleopod 
1</p>
            <p>
(

A) sympodite large; endopodite biarticulate, 
2
nd article flagelliform, tiny, slender, barely visible 
in situ
. Pleopod 
2
(

B) exopodite without marginal setae; endopodite biarticulate,
</p>
            <p>
enlarged, bifurcate at the apex, forming two long tips. Exopodites of pleopods 
1
and 
2
smaller and 
3–5
bigger, but among the latter, the fifth is the smallest; they all close like blades over the endopods. Sympodites of uropods small. Endopodites of uropods about 
2
/ 
3
the length of exopodites.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Sexual dimorphism</title>
         <p>
Dactylus of pereopod 
1
of male with very small and acute inner claw; inner claw of dactylus of pereopod 
1
of female bigger. Female pleopod 
1
sympodite (
B
), with setae surrounding the entire outer margin of its outer part, which is large and oval, continuing as a rectangular piece that joins the exopodite to form a single piece. In the junction of female pleopod 
1
exopodites, in the midline, they form two small lobes at a height of half their length and distally form two larger lobes; endopodites weren’t observed in 
2
female

specimens dissected.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Remarks</title>
         <p>
In the 
sein
of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, the new subfamily Iuiuniscinae is distiguished from Styloniscinae by very developed pleon-epimera 
3–5
; from Notoniscinae by not having longitudinal ribs; and from Kuscheolinicinae by very developed pleon-epimera 
3–5
and by not having protrusions and ribs on the lateral parts of the pereon. It can be distinguished from Notoniscinae and Kuscheolinicinae by being larger and by including only troglobiotic species (Styloniscinae contains genera with troglobiotic species and 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscus</tp:taxon-name>
includes species of up to 
14
mm

), as shall be confirmed in the coming papers on the description of new genera and species. It can be distinguished from all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
subfamilies by all the other characteristics mentioned in the subfamily diagnosis herein provided. Some of these characteristics are synapomorphies (e. g. enlarged coxal plates; pleon-epimera 
3–5
well developed). Campos-Filho 
et al
. [
19
] include the two monotypic genera they described, 
Spelunconiscus
and 
Xangoniscus
, in Styloniscinae. In the diagnosis for 
Spelunconiscus
, they mark the main characteristic that discriminates Styloniscinae from the other subfamilies (“pleonites 
3
–5

with epimera reduced, adpressed, without visible posterior points.”). Conversely, in the diagnosis of the genus 
Xangoniscus
, these authors refer to pleonites 
3–5
as showing “epimera well developed, with visible posterior points.” Considering the description of this character state for 
X
. 
aganju
(“Pleonites 

3– 
5
(Fig 
9
F) with falciform epimera.”) and the corresponding illustration, the insertion of this genus in Styloniscinae remains appropriate, since small variations in the poorly-developed pleon-epimera 

1– 
5 may
be interpreted as the same state, which is plesiomorphic (see some comments on the interrelationships in 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
in the Discussion below). In 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, the morphology of the distal part of pleopod 
2
endopodite of male has been a character of interest for analysis. Campos-
</p>
         <p>
Filho 
et al
. [
19
] point to the resemblance between 
Xangoniscus
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Clavigeroniscus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Thailandoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
and their difference from 
Spelunconiscus
in relation to this character. Souza-Kury [
23
] had already shown this resemblance between 
<tp:taxon-name>Clavigeroniscus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Thailandoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
, and separated this character in two. Considering the morphology of the distal part of pleopod 
2
endopodite of male, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. is in part similar to 
Spelunconiscus
, but not to 
Xangoniscus
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. and 
Xangoniscus aganju
occur in caves in different cities of the Brazilian state of Bahia.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Natural History</title>
         <p>
Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. were only found inside Lapa do Baixão cave, 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiu</tp:taxon-name>
municipality (Bahia state, 
Brazil
) (

A), although other caves have been sampled in the region of the Caatinga, the only xeric biome of the country with xeromorph, decidual vegetation (

B). Our research team went to eight other caves near Lapa do Baixão cave, and found no specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. what indicates that the species could be endemic to this cave. Many roots were observed inside the cave, an important nourishment source to the hypogean fauna (

C). The organisms were observed mostly inside water bodies, particularly in places far from the entrance. The cave has a water table level that oscillates over the year (water stains of different levels were found on the walls). The fluctuation of the phreatic level produces puddles that teem with specimens. Few were observed directly in the phreatic level, in comparison to the dense groups found in puddles. However, the small volume of the puddles must have led to the specimens being crowded in small areas (which doesn’t happen in the phreatic level, which encompasses a great flooded conduit) (

D). 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. cohabits puddles with specimens of another species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, also troglobiotic (

). This sympatric species, which will be described in a future paper, doesn’t have the big acute 
3–5
pleon-epimera typical of 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. It dwells mainly in areas near the entrance, and wasn’t observed in the deeper regions (including the phreatic level), unlike 
I
.
</p>
         <p>
Fig 4. 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sP. nov.

(A) 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiu</tp:taxon-name>
municipality (Bahia state, Brazil), (B) Surroundings of Lapa do Baixão cave, (C) Inside the cave, showing roots, (D) Puddles where specimens were collected, (E) Habitus.
</p>
         <p>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0115021.g004</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. Although a large part has been observed in puddles, some specimens of both species were found walking on the moist substratum of the cave, both on the ground and on the walls. This clearly demonstrates that they are capable of dispersing when the puddles dry out.
</p>
         <p>
Fig 5. 
<tp:taxon-name>Iuiuniscus iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sP. nov. cohabiting Puddle with another sPecies.

Red point: sympatric species. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0115021.g005
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. shows a special ecological character recorded for the first time in 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
species. In several areas of the innermost part of the cave, semispherical struc-
</p>
         <p>
tures made of clay (

C) were observed on the walls. Such structures sometimes possessed irregular shapes (

A). Some of them were opened, revealing specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. inside (

B and 
6
D). The specimens use the clay present on the floor for building
</p>
         <p>
the shelter’s walls, since old eroded shelters (without the covering) showed a depression from where the clay used on the walls was extracted (

E). The specimens also use natural holes in the rock as shelters, using clay for sealing these cavities (

A and 
6
B). Among millipedes (Diplopoda), special molting chambers are usually constructed, differing from one order to another [
25
]. Similarly, the clay structures built by 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. are also molting
</p>
         <p>chambers, used as shelter during the process, when the specimens are vulnerable. The molting specimens of Oniscidea consume the exuvia to obtain its minerals [26, 27] and some not yet</p>
         <p>
consumed exuvias were observed within the chambers, near the specimens under molting (

G). After the hardening of the new exoskeleton, the specimens leave the shelter by a small
</p>
         <p>
opening made by themselves (

F). The behavior of building shelters for molting could be related to: 
i)
desiccation avoidance or 
ii)
predation avoidance. The fact that the chambers aim at protecting the specimens from drying is unlikely, because they re located in very humid areas. However, in the terrestrial habitats of this cave there is a potential predator: a relatively big troglobiotic pseudoscorpion species (
<tp:taxon-name>Spelaeobochica iuiu
Ratton, Mahnert &amp; Ferreira, 
2012</tp:taxon-name>
). This species is well distributed along the cave, especially in the areas where 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. occurs. Although this predator cannot offer risks for “regular” specimens, it certainly can offer risks for molting specimens, due to their exoskeleton fragility. Accordingly, the sheltering behavior could prevent their predation during molting.
</p>
         <p>
Fig 6. SemisPherical and irregular shelters made of clay, built by sPecimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sP. nov., and used by them as molting chambers.
</p>
         <p>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0115021.g006</p>
         <p>
Among Oniscidea, the behavior of building shelters was observed to serve not only for molting, but also for mating and birth giving. It was mentioned by few authors, in very succinct papers: [
28–31
]. The “logettes de mue et parturition”, as the shelters were called by the French authors, were recorded for six genera and ten species of Oniscidea—one genus and species of Crinocheta 
<tp:taxon-name>Platyarthridae</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Platyarthrus hoffmannseggii
Brandt, 
1833</tp:taxon-name>
—and five genera and nine species of Synocheta 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Metatrichoniscoides fouresi
Vandel, 
1950</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Nesiotoniscus corsicus
Racovitza, 
1908</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Scotoniscus macromelos
Racovitza, 
1908</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscoides albidus
(Budde-Lund, 
1880
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscoides albigensis
Dalens, 
1966</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscoides modestus
Racovitza, 
1908</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscoides sarsi
Patience, 
1908</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscoides vandeli
Dalens, 
1966</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscus pygmaeus
Sars, 
1898</tp:taxon-name>
. All species but 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
hoffmannseggii</tp:taxon-name>
, which is myrmecophilous, are either endogenous or cave-dwelling. Dalens [
30
] pointed to the fact that the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscoides</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Metatrichoniscoides</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Scotoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
are considered to be closely related and to belong to the “Légion V” of Trichoniscinae (Légion V = Trichoniscoidini Schmölzer, 
1965
, Deuxième Division, see classification above).
</p>
         <p>
Dalens [
31
] accentuated that two shelters, occupied by one male and one female each, were observed for 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscoides albidus</tp:taxon-name>
, commented the possibility of this fact reflecting the usage of the shelter during copulation, which was confirmed in his paper on 
<tp:taxon-name>Nesiotoniscus corsicus</tp:taxon-name>
[
31
].
</p>
         <p>
The desert Crinocheta 
<tp:taxon-name>Agnaridae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Hemilepistus reaumuri
(Milne-Edwards, 
1840
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, which lives in burrows, only digs a shelter for survival under harsh conditions, but does not construct any 
loget de mue et parturition
[
32
].
</p>
         <p>
All Oniscidea species that build shelters occur typically in the Palearctic. 
<tp:taxon-name>Platyarthrus hoffmannseggii</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscoides sarsi</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscus pygmaeus</tp:taxon-name>
were introduced in North 
America
[
21
]. The species herein described is the first New World native cave-dwelling shelterbuilder, since none of the Brazilian cave-dwelling species described or recorded in Campos- Filho 
et al
. [
19
] was noted as presenting shelter-building behavior.
</p>
         <p>
Also deserving of mention is the notably differentiated morphology of 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. in comparison to the other Brazilian troglobiotic 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
. This difference involves the presence of tapering coxal plates of pereonites and pleon-epimera 
3–5
, so that the habitus could be interpreted as spiny. In no other cave-dwelling species of this family are these tips of pereon and pleon so prominent.
</p>
         <p>
Many troglobiotic 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Brazil
dwell in specific microhabitats, especially puddles formed inside dams of travertines. The species that inhabit small streams never occur in places where there are large predators, like fish. However, contrasting to all other know species, 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. inhabits a phreatic level in which fishes of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichomycteridae</tp:taxon-name>
have been observed. This family is quite common in Brazilian caves; 
12
out of the 
25
Brazilian troglobiotic fishes belong to this family [
33
].
</p>
         <p>
Morphological modifications, apparently evolved in response to this predation pressure, have already been noticed in other subterranean crustaceans [
34
]. In the case of some 
<tp:taxon-name>Troglocaris</tp:taxon-name>
species, some species/populations consistently co-occurring with their predator, 
<tp:taxon-name>Proteus anguinus
Laurenti, 
1768</tp:taxon-name>
(Amphibia: 
<tp:taxon-name>Caudata</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Proteidae</tp:taxon-name>
), have longer rostra than species/populations living in a 
<tp:taxon-name>Proteus</tp:taxon-name>
-free locality [
34
].
</p>
         <p>
Terrestrial isopods have responded to predation pressure by developing a variety of antipredator strategies, which include a combination of behavioral and morphological traits, as said by Schmalfuss [
35
].
</p>
         <p>
Although this is still speculation, it’s plausible to consider that the “spines” of 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
iuiuensis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. 
et
sp. nov. have been selected because of predation pressure, different from what occurs with other Brazilian species. These tips probably hinder their being eaten by fish. Besides, the second troglobiotic species of the cave (with no prominent tips) only inhabits areas far from the phreatic level, not in contact with predators. This hypothesis must be
</p>
         <p>tested experimentally.</p>
         <p>
An aquatic life habit, as found in various species of Synocheta and a few Crinocheta, summarized by Tabacaru [
36
], is regarded as a secondary condition that evolved several times within the Oniscidea [
1
].
</p>
         <p>
The first amphibious Synocheta were described by Rioja [
37
], which called the species 
<tp:taxon-name>Typhlotricholigioides aquaticus</tp:taxon-name>
. The “ligioides” part of the name means 
<tp:taxon-name>Ligia</tp:taxon-name>
-like, not in the morphological sense (as already shown by Schultz [
38
]), but surely in the aquatic habits. Rioja, based on the observations of the collector, said that the isopods have been found in the remains of puddles, and that this was not accidental, but their normal way of living. Vandel [
39
] stated that 
<tp:taxon-name>Titanethes albus
(Koch, 
1841
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, a cave dwelling trichoniscid of the Western Balkan peninsula, lives on the moist clay of the caves, often entering water puddles and passing easily from one milieu to another. Vandel [
40
] described a second amphibious Synocheta 
<tp:taxon-name>Cantabroniscus primitivus</tp:taxon-name>
, from caves in Spain—and started a series of papers [41, 42] suggesting that 
<tp:taxon-name>Typhlotricholigioides
Rioja, 
1952</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cantabroniscus
Vandel, 
1965</tp:taxon-name>
were relics of the most primitive Synocheta, still in the amphibious state, and took their existence as a proof of the polyphyly of the terrestrial 
<tp:taxon-name>Isopoda</tp:taxon-name>
. Other authors, however, did not find evidence that the amphibious habit was a conservation of an ancestral condition, and stated that this could be better explained by secondary acquisition [16, 38].
</p>
         <p>
Karaman [
43
] cites species from the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscoides
Sars, 
1899</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Brackenridgia
Ulrich, 
1902</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Alpioniscus
Racovitza, 
1908</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Scotoniscus
Racovitza, 
1908</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Bureschia
Verhoeff, 
1926</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyphonethes
Verhoeff, 
1926</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cretoniscellus
Vandel, 
1958</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>Graeconiscus
Strouhal, 
1940</tp:taxon-name>
) [22, 44], 
<tp:taxon-name>Mexiconiscus
Schultz, 
1964</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>Balearonethes
Dalens, 
1977</tp:taxon-name>
already referred as amphibious. He adds that he himself knows two undescribed species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyphoniscellus
Verhoeff, 
1901</tp:taxon-name>
that are also amphibious. All these genera belong to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
In the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
, only five species, 
<tp:taxon-name>Thailandoniscus annae
Dalens, 
1989</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Trogloniscus clarkei
Taiti &amp; Xue, 
2012
, 
Trogloniscus trilobatus
Taiti &amp; Xue, 
2012
, 

Spelunconiscus 
<tp:taxon-name>
castroi Campos-Filho, Araújo &amp; Taiti, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Xangoniscus aganju
Campos-Filho, Araújo &amp; Taiti, 
2014
are known to occur in subterranean waters.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
A thorough reanalysis of the interrelationships in Synocheta and 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
is beyond the scope of the present paper, but some comments are due: the 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscidae</tp:taxon-name>
can be considered a monophyletic family only if the highly specialized termitariophilous Titanidae and 
<tp:taxon-name>Schoebliidae</tp:taxon-name>
are also included. A striking synapomorphy for uniting the three supposed families—the structure of the protopodal musculature of pleopod 
1
—was recognized long ago. Of the three currently accepted subfamilies, Kuscheloniscinae is monotypic and Notoniscinae is a well defined small group. On the other hand, the nominal subfamily Styloniscinae is based only on negative traits.
</p>
         <p>
The definition of the 
type
species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Indoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
offers some problems. This genus was defined for the species 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoniscus mauritiensis
Barnard, 
1932</tp:taxon-name>
, poorly described, which Vandel [
45
] re-described thoroughly. The author, however, didn’t examine the 
type
material of Barnard and cast some doubts over his own identification of the examined specimens; this suggests that the material might correspond to a new species. Later, Barnard [
46
] discovered that the specimens of Vandel really didn’t correspond to 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mauritiensis</tp:taxon-name>
, and described a new species, 
<tp:taxon-name>Indoniscus vandeli</tp:taxon-name>
, for this material. Taiti &amp; Ferrara [
47
] examined the 
type
material of 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mauritiensis</tp:taxon-name>
and suggested to include the species in 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscus</tp:taxon-name>
, providing a few additional illustrations, as well as a discussion in which they defend the view that the only species that
</p>
         <p>
should stay in 
<tp:taxon-name>Indoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
is 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
vandeli</tp:taxon-name>
, while all the other ones should be included in 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscus</tp:taxon-name>
. By original designation and by monotypy, the 
type
species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Indoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
must be 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mauritiensis</tp:taxon-name>
, in spite of all the diagnosis of 
<tp:taxon-name>Indoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
by Vandel and Taiti &amp; Ferrara being based on 
I
.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>vandeli</tp:taxon-name>
. According to the standard procedure ruled by the 
ICZN
, if any author considers that 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
vandeli</tp:taxon-name>
(but not 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mauritiensis</tp:taxon-name>
) belongs to a genus different from 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscus</tp:taxon-name>
, he should describe a new genus to include this species, while 
<tp:taxon-name>Indoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
would become a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Styloniscus</tp:taxon-name>
. In our opinion, this procedure would lead to the creation of one more superfluous name, and an alternative would be to formally propose that the International Comission of
</p>
         <p>
Zoological Nomenclature use its plenary powers to fix 
<tp:taxon-name>I
. 
vandeli</tp:taxon-name>
as 
type
species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Indoniscus</tp:taxon-name>
. This way, in spite of the mistakes (
1
) of Vandel [
45
], who didn’t identify the species 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mauritiensis</tp:taxon-name>
correctly, and (
2
) of Taiti &amp; Ferrara [
47
], who excluded the 
type
species of the genus,
</p>
         <p>keeping its name, the general concept according to the use of the authors would be kept.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgments</title>
         <p>
The authors thank Dr. Célia de Souza Sampaio, 
Laboratório de Carcinicultura
(
LACAR
) of 
Universidade Estadual do Ceará
(
UECE
), for the acquisition of Leica microscopes used in this study, MSc Arthur Vinícius L. Ferreira (
LACAR
/ 
UECE
) for the orientation on the use of the Leica Application Suite (LAS) software, which integrates Leica automated microscope and digital camera, Dr. Manoel Paiva (
LACAR
/ 
UECE
) for sharing knowledge on the use of Leica microscopes, Prof. Bruno Edson Chaves from 
Laboratório de Botânica
(LABOTAN/ 
UECE
) for teaching the use of the software IPWin 
4
Program Image Pró-plus, version 
4.5
, Adriana Petrelli from 
Fundação Oswaldo Cruz
(FIOCRUZ) and M.Sc. Joafrâncio. P. Araújo from 
Universidade Federal da Paraíba
(
UFPB
) for sending some papers, Dr. Adriano B. Kury from 
Museu Nacional da Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro
(
MNRJ
) for scientific advice, and Dr. Nelson Papavero from 
Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo
(
MZUSP
) for suggesting the names for genus and species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Author Contributions</title>
         <p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LAS RLF ARS. Performed the experiments: LAS RLF ARS. Analyzed the data: LAS RLF ARS. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: LAS RLF ARS. Wrote the paper: LAS RLF ARS.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>1
.
Schmidt C
(
2008
) 
Phylogeny of terrestrial Isopoda (Oniscidea): a review
.— 

Arthropod Systematics &amp; Phylogeny, 
66
(
2
): 
191–226
.
</p>
         <p>2
.
Schmalfuss H
(
2005
) 
Utopioniscus kuehni
n. gen., n. sp. (Isopoda: Oniscidea: Synocheta) from submarine caves in Sardinia

. 
Stuttgarter Beiträge zur Naturkunde Serie A (Biologie)
, 
677
: 
1–21
.
</p>
         <p>3
.
Schmalfuss H
(
1989
) 
Phylogenetics in Oniscidea
.— 
Monitore zoologico italiano, Nuova Serie, Monografia4
: 
3–27
.
</p>
         <p>4
.
Vandel A
(
1946
) 
Especes francaises, nouvelles ou peu connues de Trichoniscidae (isopodes terrestres) (deuxieme partie)
. 

Bulletin de la Societe zoologique de 
France71
: 
53–72
.
</p>
         <p>5
.
Vandel A
(
1952
) 
La repartition du complexe trichoniscoide (isopodes terrestres) et les theories geologiques
. 
Comptes rendus hebdomadaire des Seances de l'Academie des Sciences (Paris)235
: 
997– 999
.
</p>
         <p>6
.
Vandel A
(
1960
) 
Isopodes terrestres (Première Partie)
. In: 
Fédération Française des Sociétes de Sciences Naturelles
, 

(ed.) Faune de 
France64
: Paris: Lechevalier

, pp. 
1–416
.
</p>
         <p>7
.
Borutzky E
(
1969
) 
A new family Turanoniscidae fam. n. (Isopoda, Oniscoidea) from termitaria of Middle Asia [Russian with English summary]
. 
Zoologicheskii Zhurnal48
: 
499–504
.
</p>
         <p>8
.
Kensley B
(
1971
) 
Termitophilous isopods from southern Africa
. 
Annals of the South African Museum57
: 
131–147
.
</p>
         <p>9
.
Bowman TE
, 
Abele LG
(
1982
) 
Classification of the Recent Crustacea
. In: 
Abele L. G.
(ed.), 
Systematics, the fossil record, and biogeography
, vol. 
I of Bliss, D. E. (ed.), The Biology of Crustacea. New York, Academic Press
. pp. 
1–27
. 
<p>10
.
Holdich D
, 
Lincoln R
, 
Ellis J
(
1984
) 
The biology of terrestrial isopods: Terminology and classification
. 
Symposia of the Zoological Society of London53
: 
1–6
. 
<p>11
.
Vandel A
(
1975
) 
Les isopodes terrestres et le Gondwana
. 
Memoires du Museum national d'Histoire naturelle, Nouvelle Serie, Serie A88
: 
197
– 
133
.
</p>
            </p>
         </p>
         <p>12
.
Verhoeff K
(
1939
) 

Von Dr. G. H. Schwabe in 
Chile
gesammelte Isopoda terrestria, Diplopoda und Chilopoda

.— 
Archiv fur Naturgeschichte, Neue Folge
, 
8
: 
301–324
.
</p>
         <p>13
.
Verhoeff K
(
1951
) 
Land-Isopoden aus Sudamerika
.—In: 

Further zoological Results of the Swedish 
Antarctic
Expedition 

1901– 
1903
, vol. 
4
: 
1–19
; Stockholm.
</p>
         <p>14
.
Dana JD
(
1852
) 
On the classification of the Crustacea Choristopoda or Tetradecapoda
. 
Amer. Jour. Sc. Arts
, (
2
:) XIV: 
297–316
.
</p>
         <p>15
.
Schmölzer K
(
1965
) 
Bestimmungsbucher zur Bodenfauna Europas
. 

Ordnung Isopoda (Landasseln). Lieferung 
4
and 
5
: 
468
pp.

; Berlin.
</p>
         <p>16
.
Tabacaru I
(
1993
) 

Sur la classification des Trichoniscidae et la position systematique de Thaumatoniscellus orghidani Tabacaru, 
1973
(Crustacea, Isopoda, Oniscidea)

. 
Travaux de l'Institut de Speologie "Emile Racovitza
" 
32
: 
43–85
.
</p>
         <p>17
.
Strouhal H
(
1961
) 
Die Oniscoideen-Fauna der Juan Fernandez-Inseln (Crustacea, Isopoda terrestria)
. 
Annalen des Naturhistorischen Museums in Wien64
: 
185–244
.
</p>
         <p>18
.
Taiti S
, 
Xue Z
(
2012
) 

The cavernicolous genus 
Trogloniscus
nomen novum, with descriptions of four new species from southern 
China
(Crustacea, Oniscidea, Styloniscidae)

. 
Tropical Zoology25
: 
183– 209
.
</p>
         <p>19
.
Campos-Filho IS
, 
Araujo PB
, 
Bichuette ME
, 
Trajano E
, 
Taiti S
(
2014
) 
Terrestrial isopods (Crustacea: Isopoda: Oniscidea) from Brazilian caves
. 
Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society172
: 
360–425
.
</p>
         <p>20
.
Schmalfuss H
, 
Erhard F
(
1998
) 

Die Land-Isopoden (Oniscidea) Griechenlands. 
19
. Beitrag: Gattung 
<tp:taxon-name>Cordioniscus</tp:taxon-name>
(Styloniscidae)

. 

Stuttgarter Beitrage zur Naturkunde, Serie A, 
582
: 
20
pp.
</p>
         <p>21
.
Schmalfuss H
(
2003
) 
World catalog of terrestrial isopods (Isopoda: Oniscidea)
. 

Stuttgarter Beitrage zur Naturkunde, Serie A, Nr. 
654
: 
341
pp.
</p>
         <p>22
.

Alexiou 
S
, 

Sfenthourakis 
S
(
2013
) 

The terrestrial Isopods (
<tp:taxon-name>Isopoda</tp:taxon-name>
: Oniscidea) of 
Greece
. 
Parnassiana1
: 
3–50
.
</p>
         <p>23
.

Souza-Kury 
LA
(
1997
) 

Estudo sistemático de Oniscidea (Crustacea, 
<tp:taxon-name>Isopoda</tp:taxon-name>
) cavernícolas brasileiros

. 
D. Sc. Thesis, Instituto de Biociências, Universidade de São Paulo
.
</p>
         <p>24
.
Schmidt C.
(
2002
) 

Contribution to the phylogenetic system of the Crinocheta (Crustacea, Isopoda). Part 
1
(Olibrinidae to Scyphaidae s. str.)

. 
Mitteilungen aus dem Museum fur Naturkunde in Berlin (Zoologische Reihe)78
: 
275–352
.
</p>
         <p>25
.
Golovatch SI
, 
Kime RD
(
2009
) 
Millipede (Diplopoda) distributions: A review
. 
Soil Organisms81
(
3
): 
565–597
.
</p>
         <p>26
.

Steel 
CGH
(
1993
) 

Storage and translocation of integumentary calcium during the moult cycle of the terrestrial isopod 
Oniscus asellus
(L.)

. 
Canadian Journal of Zoology71
: 
4–10
. 
<p>27
.
Hornung E
(
2011
) 
Evolutionary adaptation of oniscidean isopods to terrestrial life: structure, physiology and behavior
. 
Terrestrial Arthropod Reviews4
(
2
): 
95–130
.
</p>
         </p>
         <p>28
.
Crawley C
(
1910
) 

Ants and 
Platyarthrus hoffmannseggi
. 
Entomologist's Record and Journal of Variation22
: 
129–130
.
</p>
         <p>29
.
Vandel A
(
1958
) 
Sur l'édification de logettes de mue et de parturition chez lez isopodes terrestres troglobies, et sur certains phénoménes de convergence observés dans le comportment des animaux cavernicoles
. 
Comptes rendus hebdomadaire des Seances de l'Academie des Sciences (Paris)247
: 
1538–1540
.
</p>
         <p>30
.
Dalens H
(
1967
) 
Observations relatives a l'edifications de logettes de mue et de parturition chez les isopodes terrestres
. 
Comptes rendus hebdomadaire des Seances de l'Academie des Sciences (Paris), Serie D265
: 
701–703
.
</p>
         <p>31
.
Dalens H
(
1977
) 

Comportement constructeur chez l’isopode 
Nesiotoniscus corsicus
Racovitza

. 
Bulletin de la Societe d’Histoire Naturelle de Toulouse113
: 
181–182
. 
PMID
: 
15095733</p>
         <p>32
.

Duffy 
JE
(
2010
) 
Crustacean Social Evolution
. In: 

Breed 
M
.D.

and 

Moore 
J
.

, (eds.) 
Encyclopedia of Animal Behavior
, volume 
1
, pp. 
421–429Oxford: Academic Press
.
</p>
         <p>33
.

Trajano 
E
, 
Bichuette ME
, 

Kapoor 
BG
(
2010
) 
Biology of Subterranean Fishes
. 
Science Publishers
, 
460
p.
</p>
         <p>34
.

Jugovic 
J
, 

Prevorcnik 
S
, 

Aljancic 
G
, 

Sket 
B
(
2010
) 
The atyid shrimp (Crustacea, Decapoda, Atyidae) rostrum: Phylogeny versus adaptation, taxonomy versus trophic ecology
. 
Journal of Natural History44
: 
2509–2533
.
</p>
         <p>35
.

Schmalfuss 
H
(
1984
) 
Eco-morphological strategies in terrestrial isopods
. 
Symposia of the Zoological Society of London53
: 
49–63
.
</p>
         <p>36
.

Tabacaru 
I
(
1999
) 

L'adaptation a la vie aquatique d'un remarquable trichoniscide cavernicole, 
Cantabroniscus primitivus
Vandel, et le probleme de la monophylie des isopodes terrestres

. 

Travaux de l'Institut de Speologie "Emile Racovitza" 
37–38
: 
115–131
.
</p>
         <p>37
.

Rioja 
E
(
1952
) 
Un nuevo genero de isopodo triconiscido de la Cueva de Ojo de Agua Grande, Paraje Nuevo, Cordoba
. 

Anales del Instituto de Biologia, Universidad de 
Mexico23
: 
227–241
.
</p>
         <p>38
.

Schultz 
G
(
1994
) 
Typhlotricholigioides
and 
Mexiconiscus
from 
Mexico
and 
Cylindroniscus
from North 
America
(Isopoda: Oniscidea: Trichoniscidae)

. 
Journal of Crustacean Biology14
: 
763–770
.
</p>
         <p>39
.

Vandel 
A
(
1964
) 

Les isopodes cavernicoles recoltes en 
Grece
par le Docteur 
H
. Henrot

. 
Annales de Speleologie19
: 
729–740
.
</p>
         <p>40
.

Vandel 
A
(
1965
) 
Sur l´existence d´oniscoides tres primitifs menant une vie aquatique et sur le polyphyletisme des isopodes terrestres
. 
Annales de Speleologie20
: 
489–518
.
</p>
         <p>41
.

Vandel 
A
(
1965
) 

Les “Trichoniscidae” cavernicoles (
<tp:taxon-name>Isopoda</tp:taxon-name>
terrestria; Crustacea) de l´Amerique du Nord

. 
Annales de Speleologie20
: 
347–389
.
</p>
         <p>42
.

Vandel 
A
(
1966
) 

Observations complementaires sur 
Cantabroniscus primitivus
Vandel (crustaces; isopodes; Oniscoidea; Trichoniscidae)

. 
Annales de Speleologie21
: 
643–650
.
</p>
         <p>43
.

Karaman 
I
(
2003
) 
Macedonethes stankoi
n. sp., a rhithral oniscidean isopod (Isopoda: Oniscidea: Trichoniscidae) from 
Macedonia
. Organisms Diversity &amp; Evolution 
3
(
3
): 

Electronic Supplement 
8
: 
1–15
. 
<p>44
.
Schmalfuss H
, 

Paragamian 
K
, 
Sfenthourakis S
(
2004
) 
The terrestrial isopods (Isopoda: Oniscidea) of Crete and the surrounding islands
. 

Stuttgarter Beiträge zur Naturkunde, Serie 
A662
: 
74
pp.
</p>
         </p>
         <p>45
.

Vandel 
A
(
1952
) 
Les trichoniscides (crustaces—isopodes) de lemisphere austral
. 

Memoires du Museum National d'Histoire naturelle, Serie 
A
, 
6
: 
1–116
.
</p>
         <p>46
.
Barnard K
(
1958
) 

Terrestrial isopods and amphipods from 
Madagascar
. 

Memoires de l‘Institute Scientifique de 
Madagascar
, Serie 
A12
: 
67–111
. 

doi: 
10.1007
/s00402-009-0884-y
PMID
: 
19440728</p>
         <p>47
.
Taiti S
, 
Ferrara F
(
1983
) 

Su alcuni isopodi terrestri della 
Reunion
, di 
Mauritius
e delle 
Seychelles
. 
Revue suisse de Zoologie90
: 
199–231
.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
