<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.5281/zenodo.202017</journal-id>
         <issn>1175-5326</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Two nematode species of the family Tobrilidae (Enoplida) De Coninck, 1965 from Lake Baikal, Russia</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Two nematode species of the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Tobrilidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Enoplida</tp:taxon-name>
) De Coninck, 
1965
from Lake Baikal, 
Russia</p>
         <p>
VLADIMIR G. GAGARIN 
1
&amp; TATYANA V. NAUMOVA 
2</p>
         <p>1
Institute of Inland Waters Biology, Russian Academy of Sciences, Borok, 
152742
, Yaroslavl Province, 
Russia
. E-mail: gagarin@ibiw.yaroslavl.ru
</p>
         <p>2
Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences, Irkutsk, 
664033
, 
Russia
. E-mail: tvnaum@lin.irk.ru
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>
Two nematode species found in Lake Baikal, Gorevoi Utes (
Russia
) are presented. 
<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. n.</named-content>
differs from all other species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
by the markedly anterior position of the vulva (V= 
26–31
%). The new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi
Altherr, 
1963</tp:taxon-name>
in body size and stoma structure but differs in the comparatively thicker body (males, 
a
= 
32–45versus a
= 
60–75
), shorter stoma (males, 
26–27
µm long 
versus35–40
µm long), longer spicules (
48–53
µm 
versus40
µm), and absence of crystalloids. A redescription and new illustrations of 
<tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus
(

Shoshin, 
1988
) 

Andrássy, 
2007</tp:taxon-name>
, including a description of the previously unknown females, are also given.
</p>
         <p>Key words:
Lake Baikal, descriptions, 
<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
, free-living freshwater nematodes, new species, 
<tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
, taxonomy
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>
Lake Baikal in 
Russia
, the deepest lake on Earth, is a unique freshwater body inhabited by endemic fauna. Recently, 
68
nematode species representing 
27
genera have been reported from this lake (

Gagarin, 
2003
; 

Gagarin &amp; Naumova, 
2010
a

, 
b
, 
c
, 
d
, 
2011
; 

Shoshin, 
2010
; 

Shoshin &amp; Tsalolikhin, 
2001
; 

Shoshina, 
2003
; 

Tsalolikhin, 
1980
). Among these, 
30
species from 
9
genera belong to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Tobrilidae</tp:taxon-name>
. Eight species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
have been described from Lake Baikal, most of them found in the littoral zone (

Shoshin &amp; Tsalolikhin, 
2001
). Prof. T.Ya. 

Sitnikova (Khlystov 
et al.,2009
)

discovered a bitumen-associated biotope, where new nematode species were found confined to oil seepage localities— 
<tp:taxon-name>Monhystera naphthera
Gagarin &amp; Naumova, 
2010</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. n.</named-content>
, described here. 
<tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
was originally described on the basis of three males from Peschanaya Bay, Baikal (

Shoshin, 
1988
). Females of this species, not present in the original population, are described herein.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Material and methods</title>
         <p>
Nematodes were collected by Prof. T.Ya. Sitnikova and Dr. T.V. Naumova (Limnological Institute of Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences, Irkutsk, 
Russia
) in Lake Baikal, Cape Gorevoi Utes, on 
19–20
August 
2009
. Two samples were collected using submersible “MIR- 
2
”, at 
884 m
and 
897 m
depth respectively, both consisting of bitumen (

Khlystov 
et al
., 
2009
). One additional sand sample was collected by bottom-dredge “Ocean” 
2 km
from the coast and at 
20 m
depth. The samples contained numerous free-living nematodes, including the two species described herein. Nematodes were fixed by standard methods, and mounted in glycerin-jelly on permanent slides (

Tsalolikhin, 
1980
). All observations were made using an Olympus CX- 
21
light microscope. Photographs were taken using an Axiovert 
200ZEISS
light microscope fitted with a Pixera Penguin 
600
CL camera, located in the Collective Instrumental Center of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences.
</p>
         <p>Abbreviations</p>
         <p>a.d.—anal or cloacal body diameter, in µm;</p>
         <p>am.w.—width of the amphid (amphidial fovea), in µm; c.s.—length of cephalic setae (third ring), in µm; diam.c.s.—body diameter at the level of cephalic setae, in µm; diam.midb.—mid-body diameter, in µm;</p>
         <p>dis.am.—distance from the cephalic apex to the anterior rim of the amphid, in µm; dis.ph.cl.—distance from the pharynx base to the cloaca, in µm; dis.ph.v.—distance from the pharynx base to the vulva, in µm; dis.v.a.—distance from the vulva to the anus, in µm; gub.l.—gubernaculum length, in µm;</p>
         <p>l.sup.r.—length of supplement row, in µm;</p>
         <p>n.eg.—number of eggs;</p>
         <p>n.sup.—number of supplements;</p>
         <p>o.l.s.—length of outer labial setae (second ring), in µm; ph.l.—pharyngeal length, in µm;</p>
         <p>spic.—spicula length along the arc, in µm;</p>
         <p>spic.cl.—spicule length divided by cloaca diameter, st.l.—total stoma length, in µm;</p>
         <p>st.w.—stoma width, in µm;</p>
         <p>t.l.—tail length, in µm</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Descriptions</title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus
Tsalolikhin, 
1981</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi
Altherr, 
1963</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus
Micoletzky, 
1922</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus
(

Shoshin, 
1988
) 

Andrássy, 
2007</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988)

Andrássy, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy

, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Two nematode species of the family Tobrilidae (Enoplida) De Coninck, 1965 from Lake Baikal, Russia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.5281/zenodo.202017</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5D2A7A73FFF09E522E7AFFD4FFEB690F</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.202017</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus
Tsalolikhin, 
1981</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
(

, 

; 

Table 
1
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus
Micoletzky, 
1922</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus
(

Shoshin, 
1988
) 

Andrássy, 
2007</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs 3,4; 

Table 
2
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
1.2–4.5 mm
long. Crystalloids present or absent. Outer labial and cephalic sensilla setiform. Outer labial sensilla long, usually 
40–55
% of labial region diameter. Stoma usually with two subventral pockets, stomatal teeth 
2–10
µm apart. Vaginal musculature well-developed. Male supplements 
5–7 in
number (usually 
6
), protruding, echinate, separated into two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. First and last supplements are often smaller than the others. Spicules comparatively short and wide, with bifurcated apex.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
material.
Holotype
male, slide reference number 
213
, deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
)
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
.

One male and three females deposited in the collection of the Institute of Inland Waters Biology, Russian Academy of Sciences (Borok, Yaroslavl Province, 
Russia
); six males and four females deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Measurements.
Table 
1
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
locality.

Cape Gorevoi Utes, Lake Baikal, Siberia, 
Russia
, depth 
884–897 m
, bitumen sediment. Collected by submersible “MIR- 
2
”, 
19–20
August 
2009
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The species name means “amazing”, “wonderful”.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description. 
Male
. Body cylindrical, tapering toward both extremities. Cuticle finely annulated, 
1.3–1.7
µm thick at mid-body. Crystalloids absent. Somatic setae short and scarce anteriorly; becoming longer and denser in the posterior part of the body, level with supplements and on the tail. Lips well developed, high. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Outer labial sensilla and cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, thin and articulated, arranged in a single circle. Six outer labial sensilla 
11–13
µm long, about 
38–43
% of labial region width. Cephalic sensilla 
7–8
µm long. Cheilostom spacious; pharyngostom narrow, funnel-shaped, 
12–14
µm long. Dorsal pocket and dorsal tooth not visible. Both subventral pockets, separate, located far apart. Teeth in pockets are comparatively small. Stoma 
25–27
µm long, 
0.7–0.9
labial region width. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphid aperture located at the level of stoma pockets. Cervical setae absent. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Nerve ring encircles pharynx at 
43–48
% of pharyngeal length. Cardia small, surrounded by 
3
oval glands. Renette, renette canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Testes paired, opposed, situated to the left of intestine; anterior testis outstretched, posterior testis reflexed. Vas deferens well developed. Spicules 1.0– 
1.2
times as long as the cloacal body diameter, slender, slightly ventrally curved, with elongate-oval capitulum. Apical end of spicules bifurcated. Gubernaculum short, 
14–16
µm long, with apical expansion. Precloacal supplementary organs echinate, 
6 to 7 in
number. Supplement ampullae slightly flattened, contents concentrated at ampulla basis. Supplement pads armed with small thorns (approximately 
40–50
things) and one longer and thicker thorn, which protrude from the cuticle. Supplements arranged in two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. Row of supplements 
221–300
µm long. Tail slender, long, with proximal conical and distal cylindrical portions, gradually merging into one another. Distal portion 
1.5–1.7
times longer than proximal portion. Caudal setae 
8–10
µm long, arranged in 
5–6
subventral and 
3–4
subdorsal pairs. Three caudal glands present, opening through short spinneret. Tail terminus with subterminal setae.
</p>
            <p>CharacterHolotype male Paratype males (n = 8)Paratype females (n = 7)L arange mean 2743 2358–3146 2756 39 32–45 38range mean 2959–3706 3236 31–48 39b c c’ V,% diam.c.s. diam.midb.6.0 5.1–6.0 5.5 15.1 13.4–20.2 16.5 4.0 3.4–4.4 3.9 – – – 29 29–31 30 71 64–78 715.8–7.1 6.3 9.1–12.0 10.8 5.0–8.8 7.2 25.7–30.8 28.7 31–34 32 73–100 84a.d. o.l.s.46 39–46 42 12 10–12 1137–52 42 11–13 12c.s. st.l.7 7–8 7 27 25–27 267–9 8 26–31 28st.w.10 9–10 1011–12 12am.w.9 8–9 88–10 9
dis.am. ph.l. dis.ph.cl. dis.ph. 
<tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
.v.a.
19 15–25 21 455 455–520 486 2106 1742–2470 2106 – – – – – –20–25 23 445–572 515 – – 364–494 416 1807–2340 2005Q1 Q2 n.eg. spic.– – – – – – – – – 51 48–53 51247–390 299 398–546 460 1–5 2 – –spic.cl gub.l. n.sup. l.sup.r. t.l.1.1 1.1–1.3 1.2 22 20–22 21 6 6–7 6 226 219–300 162 182 150–182 164– – – – – – – – 255–338 300</p>
            <p>Female.
General morphology is similar to that of males in structure of cuticle and anterior body end. Cuticle finely annulated. Somatic setae short and scarce. Crystalloids and cervical setae absent. Labial region comparatively wide. Lips well developed, high. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Six outer labial sensilla and four cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, thin and articulate, arranged in a single circle. Outer labial sensilla are longer than cephalic sensilla; outer labial sensilla as long as 
38–42
% of labial region width. Cheilostom is comparatively small. Buccal cavity narrow, funnel-shaped; somewhat longer than the labial region diameter. Dorsal pocket and dorsal tooth not visible. Both subventral pockets small, separated and located far apart. Teeth in the pockets are comparatively small. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphidial opening located at the level of buccal cavity. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Cardiac glands large, 
30–35
µm long. Renette and canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Rectum 1.0– 
1.2
times as long as the anal body diameter. Reproductive system didelphic, amphidelphic. Ovaries situated to the left of intestine, reflexed and comparatively short. Oocytes numerous. Vulva a transverse slit, situated anterior to midbody, relatively close to anterior body end. Vulval lips sclerotized, protruding outside the body contour. Vulval glands not seen. Vagina short, its walls thin, not muscular. Uterus spacious, containing numerous spindle–shaped spermatozoa and 
3–8
intrauterine eggs, measuring 
71–107
× 
40–61
µm. Tail long and slender, gradually narrowing towards the terminus. Caudal glands and spinneret well developed. Tail terminus with subterminal setae.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
2.36–3.15 mm
long in male, 
2.96–3.71 mm
long in female. Cuticle finely annulated. Crystalloids absent. Outer labial setae and cephalic setae arranged in single circle. Outer labial setae longer than cephalic setae and as long as 
38–43
% of labial region width. Cheilostom comparatively small. Buccal cavity narrow, funnelshaped. Dorsal pocket absent. Subventral pockets separate, with small teeth. Vulva a transverse slit, situated relatively anterior along the body length. Uterus with numerous spermatozoa and 
3–8
intrauterine eggs, measuring 
71– 107
x 
40
–61 µm. Males with comparatively short, slightly curved spicules and short gubernaculum. Precloacal supplements 
6 to 7 in
number, echinate, separated in two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. Tail slender, comparatively long, with subterminal setae.
</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. n.</named-content>
differs from all species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
by its markedly anterior vulva position (V = 
26–31
% 
versus39–55
% in other species of the genus). The new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi
Altherr, 
1963</tp:taxon-name>
in body size and stoma structure, but differs from it in the absence of crystalloids, comparatively thicker body (males, 
a
= 
32–45versus a
= 
60–75 in<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
), shorter stoma (males, stoma 
26– 27
µm 
versus35–40
µm in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
) and longer spicules (
48–53
µm 
versus40
µm in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Altherr 
1963
; 
Tsalolikhin 1983
, 
2005
; 

Gagarin 
2009
; 

Zullini, 
2006
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
1.8–2.8 mm
long. Outer labial sensilla and cephalic sensilla setiform. Stoma large, barrel- or funnel-shaped. Stomatal pockets merged with the buccal cavity, with two or three teeth. Male supplements 
6–8 in
number, large, protruding, echinate, with pad and cap.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material.
Ten mature males and 
18
mature females. All slides are deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
).
</p>
            <p>Locality.
Gorevoi Utes, Lake Baikal, Siberia, 
Russia
, depth 
20 m
, 
2 km
from coast.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Female.
Body long, elongate, tapering toward both extremities. Cuticle finely annulated, 
1.5
µm thick at midbody. Somatic setae short, scarce. Crystalloids present, bacilliform in shape. Cervical setae absent. Labial region high, offset from the adjacent body; lips well developed. Body diameter at the base of the pharynx 
2.2–2.6
times as wide as the labial region diameter. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Six outer labial sensilla and four cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, long and thin, arranged in a single circle. Outer labial sensilla longer than cephalic sensilla, extending 
40–45
% of labial region width. Stoma funnel-shaped, slightly curved ventrally. Cheilostom spacious; pharyngostom funnel-shaped with comparatively thick walls. Dorsal pocket and its tooth are absent. Subventral pockets slightly separated from the buccal cavity, overlapping each other, and each with a single tooth. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphidial opening is located at the level of buccal cavity. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Cardiac glands large, oval, 
30–35
µm in diameter. Renette, its canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Reproductive system didelphic, amphidelphic. Ovaries comparatively short, situated to the left of intestine. Oocytes numerous, first in two rows, then as a single row. Vulva a transverse slit, situated slightly anterior to mid-body. Vulval lips sclerotized, not protruding past the body contour. Prevulval glands not observed. Vagina comparatively short, with thick walls. Uterus spacious, containing numerous spindleshaped spermatozoa and one or two intrauterine eggs, measuring 
135–146
× 
50–55
µm. Rectum 
0.9–1.1
times as long as the anal body diameter. Tail slender, comparatively long, gradually narrowing to its terminus. Caudal glands and spinneret well developed.
</p>
            <p>Males.
General morphology is similar to that of females, in structure of cuticle and anterior part of the body. Testes paired, opposed, situated to the left of intestine; anterior testis outstretched, posterior testis reflexed. Vas deferens well developed. Spicules 
1.4–1.5
times as long as cloacal body diameter, slender, curved ventrally, with developed capitulum. Gubernaculum short, with distal swelling. Precloacal supplements six in number, strongly protruding, echinate.
</p>
            <p>
Character Male (n = 
10
) Female (n = 
10
)
</p>
            <p>Lrange 2125–2790mean 2547range 2333–2794mean 2551a b c c’32–43 4.7–5.8 14.8–20.4 3.1–4.339 5.3 17.3 3.732–37 4.7–5.4 11.2–15.4 4.5–5.934 5.0 13.7 4.9V,% diam.c.s.– 26–30– 2841.5–47.0 30–3444.3 32diam.midb. a.d. o.l.s.63–67 39–47 11–1465 41 1370–81 35–41 11–1473 38 13c.s. st.l. st.w.7–10 26–31 15–178 28 167–10 27–31 17–198 29 18
am.w. dis.am. ph.l. dis.ph.cl. dis.ph. 
<tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
.v.a.
8–10 8–12 458–588 1717–2165 – –9 10 464 1930 – –10–12 10–14 470–558 – 461–698 1080–144011 12 510 – 619 1235Q1 Q2 n.eg.– – –– – –230–338 196–339 0–2289 277 1spic. spic.cl gub.l. n.sup. l.sup.r. t.l.59–62 1.3–1.6 19–21 6 225–331 125–17060 1.5 20 6 181 153– – – – – 176–208– – – – – 187</p>
            <p>
Supplement ampulla slightly flattened, its contents concentrated at ampulla basis. Supplement pad large, armed with small thorns (approximately 
40–50
things); cap is comparatively small, with large central thorn. Supplement array 
250–331
µm long. Tail slender, long. Caudal setae 
8–11
µm long, numerous. Three caudal glands open through short spinneret.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
was described on the basis of three males from Peschanaya Bay, Baikal (

Shoshin, 
1988
). Females in the original population were not found. This is the second record of this species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus
Tsalolikhin, 
1981</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi
Altherr, 
1963</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus
Micoletzky, 
1922</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus
(

Shoshin, 
1988
) 

Andrássy, 
2007</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988)

Andrássy, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy

, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Two nematode species of the family Tobrilidae (Enoplida) De Coninck, 1965 from Lake Baikal, Russia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.5281/zenodo.202017</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5D2A7A73FFF09E522E7AFFD4FFEB690F</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.202017</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus
Tsalolikhin, 
1981</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
(

, 

; 

Table 
1
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus
Micoletzky, 
1922</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus
(

Shoshin, 
1988
) 

Andrássy, 
2007</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs 3,4; 

Table 
2
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
1.2–4.5 mm
long. Crystalloids present or absent. Outer labial and cephalic sensilla setiform. Outer labial sensilla long, usually 
40–55
% of labial region diameter. Stoma usually with two subventral pockets, stomatal teeth 
2–10
µm apart. Vaginal musculature well-developed. Male supplements 
5–7 in
number (usually 
6
), protruding, echinate, separated into two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. First and last supplements are often smaller than the others. Spicules comparatively short and wide, with bifurcated apex.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
material.
Holotype
male, slide reference number 
213
, deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
)
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
.

One male and three females deposited in the collection of the Institute of Inland Waters Biology, Russian Academy of Sciences (Borok, Yaroslavl Province, 
Russia
); six males and four females deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Measurements.
Table 
1
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
locality.

Cape Gorevoi Utes, Lake Baikal, Siberia, 
Russia
, depth 
884–897 m
, bitumen sediment. Collected by submersible “MIR- 
2
”, 
19–20
August 
2009
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The species name means “amazing”, “wonderful”.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description. 
Male
. Body cylindrical, tapering toward both extremities. Cuticle finely annulated, 
1.3–1.7
µm thick at mid-body. Crystalloids absent. Somatic setae short and scarce anteriorly; becoming longer and denser in the posterior part of the body, level with supplements and on the tail. Lips well developed, high. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Outer labial sensilla and cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, thin and articulated, arranged in a single circle. Six outer labial sensilla 
11–13
µm long, about 
38–43
% of labial region width. Cephalic sensilla 
7–8
µm long. Cheilostom spacious; pharyngostom narrow, funnel-shaped, 
12–14
µm long. Dorsal pocket and dorsal tooth not visible. Both subventral pockets, separate, located far apart. Teeth in pockets are comparatively small. Stoma 
25–27
µm long, 
0.7–0.9
labial region width. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphid aperture located at the level of stoma pockets. Cervical setae absent. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Nerve ring encircles pharynx at 
43–48
% of pharyngeal length. Cardia small, surrounded by 
3
oval glands. Renette, renette canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Testes paired, opposed, situated to the left of intestine; anterior testis outstretched, posterior testis reflexed. Vas deferens well developed. Spicules 1.0– 
1.2
times as long as the cloacal body diameter, slender, slightly ventrally curved, with elongate-oval capitulum. Apical end of spicules bifurcated. Gubernaculum short, 
14–16
µm long, with apical expansion. Precloacal supplementary organs echinate, 
6 to 7 in
number. Supplement ampullae slightly flattened, contents concentrated at ampulla basis. Supplement pads armed with small thorns (approximately 
40–50
things) and one longer and thicker thorn, which protrude from the cuticle. Supplements arranged in two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. Row of supplements 
221–300
µm long. Tail slender, long, with proximal conical and distal cylindrical portions, gradually merging into one another. Distal portion 
1.5–1.7
times longer than proximal portion. Caudal setae 
8–10
µm long, arranged in 
5–6
subventral and 
3–4
subdorsal pairs. Three caudal glands present, opening through short spinneret. Tail terminus with subterminal setae.
</p>
            <p>CharacterHolotype male Paratype males (n = 8)Paratype females (n = 7)L arange mean 2743 2358–3146 2756 39 32–45 38range mean 2959–3706 3236 31–48 39b c c’ V,% diam.c.s. diam.midb.6.0 5.1–6.0 5.5 15.1 13.4–20.2 16.5 4.0 3.4–4.4 3.9 – – – 29 29–31 30 71 64–78 715.8–7.1 6.3 9.1–12.0 10.8 5.0–8.8 7.2 25.7–30.8 28.7 31–34 32 73–100 84a.d. o.l.s.46 39–46 42 12 10–12 1137–52 42 11–13 12c.s. st.l.7 7–8 7 27 25–27 267–9 8 26–31 28st.w.10 9–10 1011–12 12am.w.9 8–9 88–10 9
dis.am. ph.l. dis.ph.cl. dis.ph. 
<tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
.v.a.
19 15–25 21 455 455–520 486 2106 1742–2470 2106 – – – – – –20–25 23 445–572 515 – – 364–494 416 1807–2340 2005Q1 Q2 n.eg. spic.– – – – – – – – – 51 48–53 51247–390 299 398–546 460 1–5 2 – –spic.cl gub.l. n.sup. l.sup.r. t.l.1.1 1.1–1.3 1.2 22 20–22 21 6 6–7 6 226 219–300 162 182 150–182 164– – – – – – – – 255–338 300</p>
            <p>Female.
General morphology is similar to that of males in structure of cuticle and anterior body end. Cuticle finely annulated. Somatic setae short and scarce. Crystalloids and cervical setae absent. Labial region comparatively wide. Lips well developed, high. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Six outer labial sensilla and four cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, thin and articulate, arranged in a single circle. Outer labial sensilla are longer than cephalic sensilla; outer labial sensilla as long as 
38–42
% of labial region width. Cheilostom is comparatively small. Buccal cavity narrow, funnel-shaped; somewhat longer than the labial region diameter. Dorsal pocket and dorsal tooth not visible. Both subventral pockets small, separated and located far apart. Teeth in the pockets are comparatively small. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphidial opening located at the level of buccal cavity. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Cardiac glands large, 
30–35
µm long. Renette and canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Rectum 1.0– 
1.2
times as long as the anal body diameter. Reproductive system didelphic, amphidelphic. Ovaries situated to the left of intestine, reflexed and comparatively short. Oocytes numerous. Vulva a transverse slit, situated anterior to midbody, relatively close to anterior body end. Vulval lips sclerotized, protruding outside the body contour. Vulval glands not seen. Vagina short, its walls thin, not muscular. Uterus spacious, containing numerous spindle–shaped spermatozoa and 
3–8
intrauterine eggs, measuring 
71–107
× 
40–61
µm. Tail long and slender, gradually narrowing towards the terminus. Caudal glands and spinneret well developed. Tail terminus with subterminal setae.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
2.36–3.15 mm
long in male, 
2.96–3.71 mm
long in female. Cuticle finely annulated. Crystalloids absent. Outer labial setae and cephalic setae arranged in single circle. Outer labial setae longer than cephalic setae and as long as 
38–43
% of labial region width. Cheilostom comparatively small. Buccal cavity narrow, funnelshaped. Dorsal pocket absent. Subventral pockets separate, with small teeth. Vulva a transverse slit, situated relatively anterior along the body length. Uterus with numerous spermatozoa and 
3–8
intrauterine eggs, measuring 
71– 107
x 
40
–61 µm. Males with comparatively short, slightly curved spicules and short gubernaculum. Precloacal supplements 
6 to 7 in
number, echinate, separated in two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. Tail slender, comparatively long, with subterminal setae.
</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. n.</named-content>
differs from all species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
by its markedly anterior vulva position (V = 
26–31
% 
versus39–55
% in other species of the genus). The new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi
Altherr, 
1963</tp:taxon-name>
in body size and stoma structure, but differs from it in the absence of crystalloids, comparatively thicker body (males, 
a
= 
32–45versus a
= 
60–75 in<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
), shorter stoma (males, stoma 
26– 27
µm 
versus35–40
µm in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
) and longer spicules (
48–53
µm 
versus40
µm in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Altherr 
1963
; 
Tsalolikhin 1983
, 
2005
; 

Gagarin 
2009
; 

Zullini, 
2006
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
1.8–2.8 mm
long. Outer labial sensilla and cephalic sensilla setiform. Stoma large, barrel- or funnel-shaped. Stomatal pockets merged with the buccal cavity, with two or three teeth. Male supplements 
6–8 in
number, large, protruding, echinate, with pad and cap.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material.
Ten mature males and 
18
mature females. All slides are deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
).
</p>
            <p>Locality.
Gorevoi Utes, Lake Baikal, Siberia, 
Russia
, depth 
20 m
, 
2 km
from coast.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Female.
Body long, elongate, tapering toward both extremities. Cuticle finely annulated, 
1.5
µm thick at midbody. Somatic setae short, scarce. Crystalloids present, bacilliform in shape. Cervical setae absent. Labial region high, offset from the adjacent body; lips well developed. Body diameter at the base of the pharynx 
2.2–2.6
times as wide as the labial region diameter. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Six outer labial sensilla and four cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, long and thin, arranged in a single circle. Outer labial sensilla longer than cephalic sensilla, extending 
40–45
% of labial region width. Stoma funnel-shaped, slightly curved ventrally. Cheilostom spacious; pharyngostom funnel-shaped with comparatively thick walls. Dorsal pocket and its tooth are absent. Subventral pockets slightly separated from the buccal cavity, overlapping each other, and each with a single tooth. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphidial opening is located at the level of buccal cavity. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Cardiac glands large, oval, 
30–35
µm in diameter. Renette, its canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Reproductive system didelphic, amphidelphic. Ovaries comparatively short, situated to the left of intestine. Oocytes numerous, first in two rows, then as a single row. Vulva a transverse slit, situated slightly anterior to mid-body. Vulval lips sclerotized, not protruding past the body contour. Prevulval glands not observed. Vagina comparatively short, with thick walls. Uterus spacious, containing numerous spindleshaped spermatozoa and one or two intrauterine eggs, measuring 
135–146
× 
50–55
µm. Rectum 
0.9–1.1
times as long as the anal body diameter. Tail slender, comparatively long, gradually narrowing to its terminus. Caudal glands and spinneret well developed.
</p>
            <p>Males.
General morphology is similar to that of females, in structure of cuticle and anterior part of the body. Testes paired, opposed, situated to the left of intestine; anterior testis outstretched, posterior testis reflexed. Vas deferens well developed. Spicules 
1.4–1.5
times as long as cloacal body diameter, slender, curved ventrally, with developed capitulum. Gubernaculum short, with distal swelling. Precloacal supplements six in number, strongly protruding, echinate.
</p>
            <p>
Character Male (n = 
10
) Female (n = 
10
)
</p>
            <p>Lrange 2125–2790mean 2547range 2333–2794mean 2551a b c c’32–43 4.7–5.8 14.8–20.4 3.1–4.339 5.3 17.3 3.732–37 4.7–5.4 11.2–15.4 4.5–5.934 5.0 13.7 4.9V,% diam.c.s.– 26–30– 2841.5–47.0 30–3444.3 32diam.midb. a.d. o.l.s.63–67 39–47 11–1465 41 1370–81 35–41 11–1473 38 13c.s. st.l. st.w.7–10 26–31 15–178 28 167–10 27–31 17–198 29 18
am.w. dis.am. ph.l. dis.ph.cl. dis.ph. 
<tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
.v.a.
8–10 8–12 458–588 1717–2165 – –9 10 464 1930 – –10–12 10–14 470–558 – 461–698 1080–144011 12 510 – 619 1235Q1 Q2 n.eg.– – –– – –230–338 196–339 0–2289 277 1spic. spic.cl gub.l. n.sup. l.sup.r. t.l.59–62 1.3–1.6 19–21 6 225–331 125–17060 1.5 20 6 181 153– – – – – 176–208– – – – – 187</p>
            <p>
Supplement ampulla slightly flattened, its contents concentrated at ampulla basis. Supplement pad large, armed with small thorns (approximately 
40–50
things); cap is comparatively small, with large central thorn. Supplement array 
250–331
µm long. Tail slender, long. Caudal setae 
8–11
µm long, numerous. Three caudal glands open through short spinneret.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
was described on the basis of three males from Peschanaya Bay, Baikal (

Shoshin, 
1988
). Females in the original population were not found. This is the second record of this species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus
Tsalolikhin, 
1981</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi
Altherr, 
1963</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus
Micoletzky, 
1922</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus
(

Shoshin, 
1988
) 

Andrássy, 
2007</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988)

Andrássy, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy

, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Two nematode species of the family Tobrilidae (Enoplida) De Coninck, 1965 from Lake Baikal, Russia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.5281/zenodo.202017</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5D2A7A73FFF09E522E7AFFD4FFEB690F</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.202017</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus
Tsalolikhin, 
1981</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
(

, 

; 

Table 
1
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus
Micoletzky, 
1922</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus
(

Shoshin, 
1988
) 

Andrássy, 
2007</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs 3,4; 

Table 
2
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
1.2–4.5 mm
long. Crystalloids present or absent. Outer labial and cephalic sensilla setiform. Outer labial sensilla long, usually 
40–55
% of labial region diameter. Stoma usually with two subventral pockets, stomatal teeth 
2–10
µm apart. Vaginal musculature well-developed. Male supplements 
5–7 in
number (usually 
6
), protruding, echinate, separated into two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. First and last supplements are often smaller than the others. Spicules comparatively short and wide, with bifurcated apex.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
material.
Holotype
male, slide reference number 
213
, deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
)
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
.

One male and three females deposited in the collection of the Institute of Inland Waters Biology, Russian Academy of Sciences (Borok, Yaroslavl Province, 
Russia
); six males and four females deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Measurements.
Table 
1
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
locality.

Cape Gorevoi Utes, Lake Baikal, Siberia, 
Russia
, depth 
884–897 m
, bitumen sediment. Collected by submersible “MIR- 
2
”, 
19–20
August 
2009
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The species name means “amazing”, “wonderful”.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description. 
Male
. Body cylindrical, tapering toward both extremities. Cuticle finely annulated, 
1.3–1.7
µm thick at mid-body. Crystalloids absent. Somatic setae short and scarce anteriorly; becoming longer and denser in the posterior part of the body, level with supplements and on the tail. Lips well developed, high. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Outer labial sensilla and cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, thin and articulated, arranged in a single circle. Six outer labial sensilla 
11–13
µm long, about 
38–43
% of labial region width. Cephalic sensilla 
7–8
µm long. Cheilostom spacious; pharyngostom narrow, funnel-shaped, 
12–14
µm long. Dorsal pocket and dorsal tooth not visible. Both subventral pockets, separate, located far apart. Teeth in pockets are comparatively small. Stoma 
25–27
µm long, 
0.7–0.9
labial region width. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphid aperture located at the level of stoma pockets. Cervical setae absent. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Nerve ring encircles pharynx at 
43–48
% of pharyngeal length. Cardia small, surrounded by 
3
oval glands. Renette, renette canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Testes paired, opposed, situated to the left of intestine; anterior testis outstretched, posterior testis reflexed. Vas deferens well developed. Spicules 1.0– 
1.2
times as long as the cloacal body diameter, slender, slightly ventrally curved, with elongate-oval capitulum. Apical end of spicules bifurcated. Gubernaculum short, 
14–16
µm long, with apical expansion. Precloacal supplementary organs echinate, 
6 to 7 in
number. Supplement ampullae slightly flattened, contents concentrated at ampulla basis. Supplement pads armed with small thorns (approximately 
40–50
things) and one longer and thicker thorn, which protrude from the cuticle. Supplements arranged in two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. Row of supplements 
221–300
µm long. Tail slender, long, with proximal conical and distal cylindrical portions, gradually merging into one another. Distal portion 
1.5–1.7
times longer than proximal portion. Caudal setae 
8–10
µm long, arranged in 
5–6
subventral and 
3–4
subdorsal pairs. Three caudal glands present, opening through short spinneret. Tail terminus with subterminal setae.
</p>
            <p>CharacterHolotype male Paratype males (n = 8)Paratype females (n = 7)L arange mean 2743 2358–3146 2756 39 32–45 38range mean 2959–3706 3236 31–48 39b c c’ V,% diam.c.s. diam.midb.6.0 5.1–6.0 5.5 15.1 13.4–20.2 16.5 4.0 3.4–4.4 3.9 – – – 29 29–31 30 71 64–78 715.8–7.1 6.3 9.1–12.0 10.8 5.0–8.8 7.2 25.7–30.8 28.7 31–34 32 73–100 84a.d. o.l.s.46 39–46 42 12 10–12 1137–52 42 11–13 12c.s. st.l.7 7–8 7 27 25–27 267–9 8 26–31 28st.w.10 9–10 1011–12 12am.w.9 8–9 88–10 9
dis.am. ph.l. dis.ph.cl. dis.ph. 
<tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
.v.a.
19 15–25 21 455 455–520 486 2106 1742–2470 2106 – – – – – –20–25 23 445–572 515 – – 364–494 416 1807–2340 2005Q1 Q2 n.eg. spic.– – – – – – – – – 51 48–53 51247–390 299 398–546 460 1–5 2 – –spic.cl gub.l. n.sup. l.sup.r. t.l.1.1 1.1–1.3 1.2 22 20–22 21 6 6–7 6 226 219–300 162 182 150–182 164– – – – – – – – 255–338 300</p>
            <p>Female.
General morphology is similar to that of males in structure of cuticle and anterior body end. Cuticle finely annulated. Somatic setae short and scarce. Crystalloids and cervical setae absent. Labial region comparatively wide. Lips well developed, high. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Six outer labial sensilla and four cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, thin and articulate, arranged in a single circle. Outer labial sensilla are longer than cephalic sensilla; outer labial sensilla as long as 
38–42
% of labial region width. Cheilostom is comparatively small. Buccal cavity narrow, funnel-shaped; somewhat longer than the labial region diameter. Dorsal pocket and dorsal tooth not visible. Both subventral pockets small, separated and located far apart. Teeth in the pockets are comparatively small. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphidial opening located at the level of buccal cavity. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Cardiac glands large, 
30–35
µm long. Renette and canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Rectum 1.0– 
1.2
times as long as the anal body diameter. Reproductive system didelphic, amphidelphic. Ovaries situated to the left of intestine, reflexed and comparatively short. Oocytes numerous. Vulva a transverse slit, situated anterior to midbody, relatively close to anterior body end. Vulval lips sclerotized, protruding outside the body contour. Vulval glands not seen. Vagina short, its walls thin, not muscular. Uterus spacious, containing numerous spindle–shaped spermatozoa and 
3–8
intrauterine eggs, measuring 
71–107
× 
40–61
µm. Tail long and slender, gradually narrowing towards the terminus. Caudal glands and spinneret well developed. Tail terminus with subterminal setae.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
2.36–3.15 mm
long in male, 
2.96–3.71 mm
long in female. Cuticle finely annulated. Crystalloids absent. Outer labial setae and cephalic setae arranged in single circle. Outer labial setae longer than cephalic setae and as long as 
38–43
% of labial region width. Cheilostom comparatively small. Buccal cavity narrow, funnelshaped. Dorsal pocket absent. Subventral pockets separate, with small teeth. Vulva a transverse slit, situated relatively anterior along the body length. Uterus with numerous spermatozoa and 
3–8
intrauterine eggs, measuring 
71– 107
x 
40
–61 µm. Males with comparatively short, slightly curved spicules and short gubernaculum. Precloacal supplements 
6 to 7 in
number, echinate, separated in two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. Tail slender, comparatively long, with subterminal setae.
</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. n.</named-content>
differs from all species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
by its markedly anterior vulva position (V = 
26–31
% 
versus39–55
% in other species of the genus). The new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi
Altherr, 
1963</tp:taxon-name>
in body size and stoma structure, but differs from it in the absence of crystalloids, comparatively thicker body (males, 
a
= 
32–45versus a
= 
60–75 in<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
), shorter stoma (males, stoma 
26– 27
µm 
versus35–40
µm in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
) and longer spicules (
48–53
µm 
versus40
µm in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Altherr 
1963
; 
Tsalolikhin 1983
, 
2005
; 

Gagarin 
2009
; 

Zullini, 
2006
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
1.8–2.8 mm
long. Outer labial sensilla and cephalic sensilla setiform. Stoma large, barrel- or funnel-shaped. Stomatal pockets merged with the buccal cavity, with two or three teeth. Male supplements 
6–8 in
number, large, protruding, echinate, with pad and cap.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material.
Ten mature males and 
18
mature females. All slides are deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
).
</p>
            <p>Locality.
Gorevoi Utes, Lake Baikal, Siberia, 
Russia
, depth 
20 m
, 
2 km
from coast.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Female.
Body long, elongate, tapering toward both extremities. Cuticle finely annulated, 
1.5
µm thick at midbody. Somatic setae short, scarce. Crystalloids present, bacilliform in shape. Cervical setae absent. Labial region high, offset from the adjacent body; lips well developed. Body diameter at the base of the pharynx 
2.2–2.6
times as wide as the labial region diameter. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Six outer labial sensilla and four cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, long and thin, arranged in a single circle. Outer labial sensilla longer than cephalic sensilla, extending 
40–45
% of labial region width. Stoma funnel-shaped, slightly curved ventrally. Cheilostom spacious; pharyngostom funnel-shaped with comparatively thick walls. Dorsal pocket and its tooth are absent. Subventral pockets slightly separated from the buccal cavity, overlapping each other, and each with a single tooth. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphidial opening is located at the level of buccal cavity. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Cardiac glands large, oval, 
30–35
µm in diameter. Renette, its canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Reproductive system didelphic, amphidelphic. Ovaries comparatively short, situated to the left of intestine. Oocytes numerous, first in two rows, then as a single row. Vulva a transverse slit, situated slightly anterior to mid-body. Vulval lips sclerotized, not protruding past the body contour. Prevulval glands not observed. Vagina comparatively short, with thick walls. Uterus spacious, containing numerous spindleshaped spermatozoa and one or two intrauterine eggs, measuring 
135–146
× 
50–55
µm. Rectum 
0.9–1.1
times as long as the anal body diameter. Tail slender, comparatively long, gradually narrowing to its terminus. Caudal glands and spinneret well developed.
</p>
            <p>Males.
General morphology is similar to that of females, in structure of cuticle and anterior part of the body. Testes paired, opposed, situated to the left of intestine; anterior testis outstretched, posterior testis reflexed. Vas deferens well developed. Spicules 
1.4–1.5
times as long as cloacal body diameter, slender, curved ventrally, with developed capitulum. Gubernaculum short, with distal swelling. Precloacal supplements six in number, strongly protruding, echinate.
</p>
            <p>
Character Male (n = 
10
) Female (n = 
10
)
</p>
            <p>Lrange 2125–2790mean 2547range 2333–2794mean 2551a b c c’32–43 4.7–5.8 14.8–20.4 3.1–4.339 5.3 17.3 3.732–37 4.7–5.4 11.2–15.4 4.5–5.934 5.0 13.7 4.9V,% diam.c.s.– 26–30– 2841.5–47.0 30–3444.3 32diam.midb. a.d. o.l.s.63–67 39–47 11–1465 41 1370–81 35–41 11–1473 38 13c.s. st.l. st.w.7–10 26–31 15–178 28 167–10 27–31 17–198 29 18
am.w. dis.am. ph.l. dis.ph.cl. dis.ph. 
<tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
.v.a.
8–10 8–12 458–588 1717–2165 – –9 10 464 1930 – –10–12 10–14 470–558 – 461–698 1080–144011 12 510 – 619 1235Q1 Q2 n.eg.– – –– – –230–338 196–339 0–2289 277 1spic. spic.cl gub.l. n.sup. l.sup.r. t.l.59–62 1.3–1.6 19–21 6 225–331 125–17060 1.5 20 6 181 153– – – – – 176–208– – – – – 187</p>
            <p>
Supplement ampulla slightly flattened, its contents concentrated at ampulla basis. Supplement pad large, armed with small thorns (approximately 
40–50
things); cap is comparatively small, with large central thorn. Supplement array 
250–331
µm long. Tail slender, long. Caudal setae 
8–11
µm long, numerous. Three caudal glands open through short spinneret.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
was described on the basis of three males from Peschanaya Bay, Baikal (

Shoshin, 
1988
). Females in the original population were not found. This is the second record of this species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus
Tsalolikhin, 
1981</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi
Altherr, 
1963</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus
Micoletzky, 
1922</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus
(

Shoshin, 
1988
) 

Andrássy, 
2007</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988)

Andrássy, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy

, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Paratrilobus 
delicatus
(Shoshin, 1988) Andrássy
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Two nematode species of the family Tobrilidae (Enoplida) De Coninck, 1965 from Lake Baikal, Russia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.5281/zenodo.202017</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5D2A7A73FFF09E522E7AFFD4FFEB690F</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.202017</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus
Tsalolikhin, 
1981</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. n.</tp:taxon-status>
(

, 

; 

Table 
1
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus
Micoletzky, 
1922</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus
(

Shoshin, 
1988
) 

Andrássy, 
2007</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs 3,4; 

Table 
2
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
1.2–4.5 mm
long. Crystalloids present or absent. Outer labial and cephalic sensilla setiform. Outer labial sensilla long, usually 
40–55
% of labial region diameter. Stoma usually with two subventral pockets, stomatal teeth 
2–10
µm apart. Vaginal musculature well-developed. Male supplements 
5–7 in
number (usually 
6
), protruding, echinate, separated into two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. First and last supplements are often smaller than the others. Spicules comparatively short and wide, with bifurcated apex.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
material.
Holotype
male, slide reference number 
213
, deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
)
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
.

One male and three females deposited in the collection of the Institute of Inland Waters Biology, Russian Academy of Sciences (Borok, Yaroslavl Province, 
Russia
); six males and four females deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Measurements.
Table 
1
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
locality.

Cape Gorevoi Utes, Lake Baikal, Siberia, 
Russia
, depth 
884–897 m
, bitumen sediment. Collected by submersible “MIR- 
2
”, 
19–20
August 
2009
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The species name means “amazing”, “wonderful”.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description. 
Male
. Body cylindrical, tapering toward both extremities. Cuticle finely annulated, 
1.3–1.7
µm thick at mid-body. Crystalloids absent. Somatic setae short and scarce anteriorly; becoming longer and denser in the posterior part of the body, level with supplements and on the tail. Lips well developed, high. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Outer labial sensilla and cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, thin and articulated, arranged in a single circle. Six outer labial sensilla 
11–13
µm long, about 
38–43
% of labial region width. Cephalic sensilla 
7–8
µm long. Cheilostom spacious; pharyngostom narrow, funnel-shaped, 
12–14
µm long. Dorsal pocket and dorsal tooth not visible. Both subventral pockets, separate, located far apart. Teeth in pockets are comparatively small. Stoma 
25–27
µm long, 
0.7–0.9
labial region width. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphid aperture located at the level of stoma pockets. Cervical setae absent. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Nerve ring encircles pharynx at 
43–48
% of pharyngeal length. Cardia small, surrounded by 
3
oval glands. Renette, renette canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Testes paired, opposed, situated to the left of intestine; anterior testis outstretched, posterior testis reflexed. Vas deferens well developed. Spicules 1.0– 
1.2
times as long as the cloacal body diameter, slender, slightly ventrally curved, with elongate-oval capitulum. Apical end of spicules bifurcated. Gubernaculum short, 
14–16
µm long, with apical expansion. Precloacal supplementary organs echinate, 
6 to 7 in
number. Supplement ampullae slightly flattened, contents concentrated at ampulla basis. Supplement pads armed with small thorns (approximately 
40–50
things) and one longer and thicker thorn, which protrude from the cuticle. Supplements arranged in two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. Row of supplements 
221–300
µm long. Tail slender, long, with proximal conical and distal cylindrical portions, gradually merging into one another. Distal portion 
1.5–1.7
times longer than proximal portion. Caudal setae 
8–10
µm long, arranged in 
5–6
subventral and 
3–4
subdorsal pairs. Three caudal glands present, opening through short spinneret. Tail terminus with subterminal setae.
</p>
            <p>CharacterHolotype male Paratype males (n = 8)Paratype females (n = 7)L arange mean 2743 2358–3146 2756 39 32–45 38range mean 2959–3706 3236 31–48 39b c c’ V,% diam.c.s. diam.midb.6.0 5.1–6.0 5.5 15.1 13.4–20.2 16.5 4.0 3.4–4.4 3.9 – – – 29 29–31 30 71 64–78 715.8–7.1 6.3 9.1–12.0 10.8 5.0–8.8 7.2 25.7–30.8 28.7 31–34 32 73–100 84a.d. o.l.s.46 39–46 42 12 10–12 1137–52 42 11–13 12c.s. st.l.7 7–8 7 27 25–27 267–9 8 26–31 28st.w.10 9–10 1011–12 12am.w.9 8–9 88–10 9
dis.am. ph.l. dis.ph.cl. dis.ph. 
<tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
.v.a.
19 15–25 21 455 455–520 486 2106 1742–2470 2106 – – – – – –20–25 23 445–572 515 – – 364–494 416 1807–2340 2005Q1 Q2 n.eg. spic.– – – – – – – – – 51 48–53 51247–390 299 398–546 460 1–5 2 – –spic.cl gub.l. n.sup. l.sup.r. t.l.1.1 1.1–1.3 1.2 22 20–22 21 6 6–7 6 226 219–300 162 182 150–182 164– – – – – – – – 255–338 300</p>
            <p>Female.
General morphology is similar to that of males in structure of cuticle and anterior body end. Cuticle finely annulated. Somatic setae short and scarce. Crystalloids and cervical setae absent. Labial region comparatively wide. Lips well developed, high. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Six outer labial sensilla and four cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, thin and articulate, arranged in a single circle. Outer labial sensilla are longer than cephalic sensilla; outer labial sensilla as long as 
38–42
% of labial region width. Cheilostom is comparatively small. Buccal cavity narrow, funnel-shaped; somewhat longer than the labial region diameter. Dorsal pocket and dorsal tooth not visible. Both subventral pockets small, separated and located far apart. Teeth in the pockets are comparatively small. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphidial opening located at the level of buccal cavity. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Cardiac glands large, 
30–35
µm long. Renette and canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Rectum 1.0– 
1.2
times as long as the anal body diameter. Reproductive system didelphic, amphidelphic. Ovaries situated to the left of intestine, reflexed and comparatively short. Oocytes numerous. Vulva a transverse slit, situated anterior to midbody, relatively close to anterior body end. Vulval lips sclerotized, protruding outside the body contour. Vulval glands not seen. Vagina short, its walls thin, not muscular. Uterus spacious, containing numerous spindle–shaped spermatozoa and 
3–8
intrauterine eggs, measuring 
71–107
× 
40–61
µm. Tail long and slender, gradually narrowing towards the terminus. Caudal glands and spinneret well developed. Tail terminus with subterminal setae.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
2.36–3.15 mm
long in male, 
2.96–3.71 mm
long in female. Cuticle finely annulated. Crystalloids absent. Outer labial setae and cephalic setae arranged in single circle. Outer labial setae longer than cephalic setae and as long as 
38–43
% of labial region width. Cheilostom comparatively small. Buccal cavity narrow, funnelshaped. Dorsal pocket absent. Subventral pockets separate, with small teeth. Vulva a transverse slit, situated relatively anterior along the body length. Uterus with numerous spermatozoa and 
3–8
intrauterine eggs, measuring 
71– 107
x 
40
–61 µm. Males with comparatively short, slightly curved spicules and short gubernaculum. Precloacal supplements 
6 to 7 in
number, echinate, separated in two groups [
2
+ 
4
(
5
)]. Tail slender, comparatively long, with subterminal setae.
</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus mirandus</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. n.</named-content>
differs from all species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Eutobrilus</tp:taxon-name>
by its markedly anterior vulva position (V = 
26–31
% 
versus39–55
% in other species of the genus). The new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi
Altherr, 
1963</tp:taxon-name>
in body size and stoma structure, but differs from it in the absence of crystalloids, comparatively thicker body (males, 
a
= 
32–45versus a
= 
60–75 in<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
), shorter stoma (males, stoma 
26– 27
µm 
versus35–40
µm in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
) and longer spicules (
48–53
µm 
versus40
µm in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. andrassyi</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Altherr 
1963
; 
Tsalolikhin 1983
, 
2005
; 

Gagarin 
2009
; 

Zullini, 
2006
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Body 
1.8–2.8 mm
long. Outer labial sensilla and cephalic sensilla setiform. Stoma large, barrel- or funnel-shaped. Stomatal pockets merged with the buccal cavity, with two or three teeth. Male supplements 
6–8 in
number, large, protruding, echinate, with pad and cap.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material.
Ten mature males and 
18
mature females. All slides are deposited in the collection of the Limnological Institute, Siberian Branch of the Russian Academy of Sciences (Irkutsk, 
Russia
).
</p>
            <p>Locality.
Gorevoi Utes, Lake Baikal, Siberia, 
Russia
, depth 
20 m
, 
2 km
from coast.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Female.
Body long, elongate, tapering toward both extremities. Cuticle finely annulated, 
1.5
µm thick at midbody. Somatic setae short, scarce. Crystalloids present, bacilliform in shape. Cervical setae absent. Labial region high, offset from the adjacent body; lips well developed. Body diameter at the base of the pharynx 
2.2–2.6
times as wide as the labial region diameter. Inner labial sensilla papilliform. Six outer labial sensilla and four cephalic sensilla setiform in shape, long and thin, arranged in a single circle. Outer labial sensilla longer than cephalic sensilla, extending 
40–45
% of labial region width. Stoma funnel-shaped, slightly curved ventrally. Cheilostom spacious; pharyngostom funnel-shaped with comparatively thick walls. Dorsal pocket and its tooth are absent. Subventral pockets slightly separated from the buccal cavity, overlapping each other, and each with a single tooth. Amphidial fovea cup-shaped, amphidial opening is located at the level of buccal cavity. Pharynx muscular, comparatively long, expanding gradually towards its base. Cardiac glands large, oval, 
30–35
µm in diameter. Renette, its canal, ampulla and excretory pore not observed. Reproductive system didelphic, amphidelphic. Ovaries comparatively short, situated to the left of intestine. Oocytes numerous, first in two rows, then as a single row. Vulva a transverse slit, situated slightly anterior to mid-body. Vulval lips sclerotized, not protruding past the body contour. Prevulval glands not observed. Vagina comparatively short, with thick walls. Uterus spacious, containing numerous spindleshaped spermatozoa and one or two intrauterine eggs, measuring 
135–146
× 
50–55
µm. Rectum 
0.9–1.1
times as long as the anal body diameter. Tail slender, comparatively long, gradually narrowing to its terminus. Caudal glands and spinneret well developed.
</p>
            <p>Males.
General morphology is similar to that of females, in structure of cuticle and anterior part of the body. Testes paired, opposed, situated to the left of intestine; anterior testis outstretched, posterior testis reflexed. Vas deferens well developed. Spicules 
1.4–1.5
times as long as cloacal body diameter, slender, curved ventrally, with developed capitulum. Gubernaculum short, with distal swelling. Precloacal supplements six in number, strongly protruding, echinate.
</p>
            <p>
Character Male (n = 
10
) Female (n = 
10
)
</p>
            <p>Lrange 2125–2790mean 2547range 2333–2794mean 2551a b c c’32–43 4.7–5.8 14.8–20.4 3.1–4.339 5.3 17.3 3.732–37 4.7–5.4 11.2–15.4 4.5–5.934 5.0 13.7 4.9V,% diam.c.s.– 26–30– 2841.5–47.0 30–3444.3 32diam.midb. a.d. o.l.s.63–67 39–47 11–1465 41 1370–81 35–41 11–1473 38 13c.s. st.l. st.w.7–10 26–31 15–178 28 167–10 27–31 17–198 29 18
am.w. dis.am. ph.l. dis.ph.cl. dis.ph. 
<tp:taxon-name>v. dis</tp:taxon-name>
.v.a.
8–10 8–12 458–588 1717–2165 – –9 10 464 1930 – –10–12 10–14 470–558 – 461–698 1080–144011 12 510 – 619 1235Q1 Q2 n.eg.– – –– – –230–338 196–339 0–2289 277 1spic. spic.cl gub.l. n.sup. l.sup.r. t.l.59–62 1.3–1.6 19–21 6 225–331 125–17060 1.5 20 6 181 153– – – – – 176–208– – – – – 187</p>
            <p>
Supplement ampulla slightly flattened, its contents concentrated at ampulla basis. Supplement pad large, armed with small thorns (approximately 
40–50
things); cap is comparatively small, with large central thorn. Supplement array 
250–331
µm long. Tail slender, long. Caudal setae 
8–11
µm long, numerous. Three caudal glands open through short spinneret.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Paratrilobus delicatus</tp:taxon-name>
was described on the basis of three males from Peschanaya Bay, Baikal (

Shoshin, 
1988
). Females in the original population were not found. This is the second record of this species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>
Authors thank Prof. T.Ya. Sitnikova, who kindly collected and provided the material for this study. Several samples were collected by a submersible “MIR- 
2
”, operated and financed by the Foundation of Lake Baikal Conservation and a “Metropol” Group. Sincere thanks are due to the crew of Scientific-research vessel «G.Yu. Vereshchagin» (Capt. A.G. Palevich) for their assistance in sampling. Specimens were photographed in the Collective Instrumental Center LIN SB RAS (headed by Prof. Ye.V. Likhoshway). This work was supported by a 
RFBR
Grant No. 09-04- 0 0 
781
, Integration Project of SB RAS No. 27, 49, Program of RAS Presidium No. 
20.9
and State Projects No. 

VII- 
62
- 
1-4
.

The authors are grateful both to the anonymous reviewers and to Dr. Oleksandr Holovachov for improving the manuscript.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Altherr, E.
(
1963
) 
Contribution à la connaissance de la faune des sables submergés en Lorraine. Nematodes
. 
Annales de Speleologie
,
18
, 

53– 
98
.
</p>
         <p>Andrássy, I.
(
2007
) 

Free-living nematodes of 
Hungary
(Nematoda errantia), II

. In: 
Pedozoologica Hungarica
, 

Budapest, No. 
4
, 
496 pp.</p>
         <p>Gagarin, V.G.
(
2003
) 
Review of the fauna of free-living nematodes in the ancient lakes of Asia
. 
Inland Water Biology
,
2
, 

15– 
19
. (In Russian).
</p>
         <p>Gagarin, V.G.
(
2009
) 

The revision of the genus 
Eutobrilus
Tsalolikhin, 
1981
(Nematoda, Triplonchida)

. 
Zoologicheskii Zhurnal
, 
3
, 

17– 
24
. (In Russian).
</p>
         <p>Gagarin, V.G.
&amp; 
Naumova, T.V.
(
2010
a) 

Two new species of the genus 
Hofmaenneria
Schneider, 
1940
(Nematoda, Monhysterida) from Lake Baikal

, 
Russia
. 
International Journal of Nematology
, 
20
, 

7– 
12
.
</p>
         <p>Gagarin, V.G.
&amp; 
Naumova, T.V.
(
2010
b) 
Monhystera naphthera
sp.n. (Nematoda, Monhysteridae) from a bitumen biotope of Lake Baikal abyssal

. 
Zoologicheskii Zhurnal
, 
89
, 

1264– 
1267
(In Russian).
</p>
         <p>Gagarin, V.G.
&amp; 
Naumova, T.V.
(
2010
c) 
Two new species of free-living nematodes from Lake Baikal
, 
Russia
. 
Russian Journal of Nematology
, 
18
, 
103
– 
110
.
</p>
         <p>Gagarin, V.G
.. &amp; Naumova, T.V. (
2010
d) 
Three new species of free-living nematodes from Lake Baikal
, 
Russia
. 
International Journal of Nematology
, 
20
, 
185
– 
193
.
</p>
         <p>Gagarin, V.G.
&amp; 
Naumova, T.V.
(
2011
) 
Two new species of Dorylaimids (Nematoda, Dorylaimida) from Lake Baikal
. 
Inland Water Biology
, 
4
, 

28– 
33
.
</p>
         <p>Khlystov, O.M.
, 
Zemskaya, T.I.
, 
Sitnikova, T.
Ya., Mekhanikova, I.V., Kaigorodova, I.A., Gorshkov, A.G., Timoshkin, O.A., Shubenkova, O.V., Chernitsyna, S.M., Lomakina, A.V., Likhoshvai, A.V., Sagalevich, A.M., Moskvin, V.I., Peresypkin, V.I., Belyaev, N.A., Slipenchuk, M.V., Tulokhonov, A.K. &amp; Grachev, M.A. (
2009
) 

Bottom Bituminous Constructions and Biota Inhabiting Them According to Investigation of Lake Baikal with the 
Mir
Submersible

. 
Doklady Earth Sciences
,

429, 

1333– 
1336
.
</p>
         <p>Shoshin, A.V.
(
1988
) 
New species of nematodes of family Tobrilidae from the Baikal Lake
. 

Proceedings of the Zoological Institute 
USSR
Academy of Sciences

, 
80
, 

43– 
58
. (In Russian).
</p>
         <p>Shoshin, A.V.
(
2010
) 

A new species of diatom-feeding 
Asperotobrilus
(Nematoda: Triplonchida: Tobrilidae) from Lake Baikal

. 
Zoosystematica Rossica
, 
19
, 

18– 
22
.
</p>
         <p>Shoshin, A.V.
&amp; 
Tsalolikhin, S.
Ja. (
2001
) 
Free-living nematodes (Nemathelminthes: Nematoda)
. 
In
: 
Timoshkin, O.A.
(Eds.), 
Index of animal species inhabiting Lake Baikal and its catchments area
. 

Vol. 
1
. Lake Baikal, Book
1
. Novosibirsk, 
Russia
, Nauka, pp. 
305–320
. 
(In Russian)
.
</p>
         <p>Shoshina, A.A.
(
2003
) 

A new trident tobrilid, 
Setsalia mirabilis
gen. et sp.n., from Lake Baikal (Nematoda: Enoplida)

. 
Zoosystematica Rossica14
, 

15– 
18
.
</p>
         <p>Tsalolikhin, S.
Ya. (
1980
) 
Free-living nematodes of the Baikal Lake
. 

Novosibirsk. 
Russia
. Nauka.
120
pp.
</p>
         <p>Tsalolikhin, S.
Ya. (
1983
) 
Nematodes of the families Tobrilidae and Tripylidae of the World Fauna
.

Nauka, Leningrad, 
Russia
, 
232
pp.

(In Russian).
</p>
         <p>Tsalolikhin S.Ya
. (
2005
) 

A review of the genus 
Eutobrilus
(Nematoda, Enoplida, Tobrilidae) 
Zoologicheskii Zhurnal84
, 
914
– 
921
. (In Russian).
</p>
         <p>Zullini, A.
(
2006
) 
Order Triplonchida
. 
In:Eyualem-Abebe, I.
Andrássy, &amp; W. Traunspurger (Eds) 
Freshwater nematodes
. 
Ecology and Taxonomy
. 
CABI
Publishing, Wallingford, 
UK
, pp. 
293–325
.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
