<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1126/science.aab2625</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Miocene small-bodied ape from Eurasia sheds light on hominoid evolution</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>◥</p>
         <p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E S U M M A R Y</p>
         <p>PRIMATE EVOLUTION</p>
         <p>Miocene small-bodied ape from Eurasia sheds light on hominoid evolution</p>
         <p>David M. Alba
,

* 
<tp:taxon-name>Sergio Almécija
, 
Daniel DeMiguel
, 
Josep Fortuny
,
Miriam Pérez
de los Ríos, 
Marta Pina
, 
Josep M. Robles
, 
Salvador Moyà-Solà</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <p>INTRODUCTION:
Reconstructing the ancestral morphotype from which extant hominoids (apes and humans) evolved is complicated by the mosaic nature of ape evolution, the confounding effects of independently evolved features (homoplasy), and the virtual lack of hylobatids (gibbons and siamangs) in the Miocene fossil record. For several decades, small-bodied anthropoid primates from Africa and Eurasia have not played an important role in this debate, because they generally lack the shared derived features of extant catarrhines (hominoids and Old World monkeys) and are thus considered to precede their divergence. Even some small-bodied catarrhines from Africa (dendropithecids), considered to be stem hominoids by some authors, are viewed as more primitive than the larger-bodied stem ape 
Proconsul
. This has led to the assumption that hylobatids are a dwarfed lineage that evolved from a larger-bodied and more great ape–like common ancestor with hominids (great apes and humans).
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>2016, 25 May on / org. sciencemag. science //: http from Downloaded ◥</p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>RATIONALE:
Here we describe a new genus of small-bodied (4 to 5 kg) ape from the Miocene (11.6 Ma), discovered in the Abocador de Can Mata stratigraphic series (Vallès-Penedès Basin, northeast Iberian Peninsula), that challenges current views on the last common ancestor of extant hominoids. This genus is based on a partial skeleton that enables a reliable reconstruction of cranial morphology and a detailed assessment of elbow and 
Cranial reconstruction and life appearance.
Artist’s representation of the cranial recon- struction (in frontal view) and of the life appearance (in lateral oblique view) of the new genus of small-bodied ape from the Iberian Miocene. [Artwork by M. Palmero] wrist anatomy. It exhibits a mosaic of primitive (stem catarrhine–like) and derived (extant hominoid–like) features that forces us to reevaluate the role played by small-bodied catarrhines in ape evolution.
</p>
         <p>RESULTS:
The new genus retains some features that are suggestive of generalized abovebranch quadrupedalism, but it possesses more extensive hominoid-like postcranial features (mostly related to enhanced forearm rotation and ulnar deviation capabilities) than those convergently displayed by atelids. Its overall body plan is more compatible with an emphasis on cautious and eclectic climbing, combined with some degree of below-branch forelimbdominated suspension (although less acrobatic than in extant gibbons). Its relative brain ◥ size implies a monkey-like 
ON OUR WEB SITE
degree of encephalization Read the full article (similar to that of hyloat http://dx.doi. batids but below that of org/10.1126/ great apes), and dental science.aab2625 microwear indicates a fru- 
..................................................
givorous diet. From a phylogenetic viewpoint, the new genus combines craniodental and postcranial primitive features (similar to those of dendropithecids) with multiple derived cranial and postcranial features shared with extant hominoids. Some cranial similarities with gibbons would support a closer phylogenetic link between the new genus and hylobatids. However, this possibility is not supported by the total evidence. A cladistic analysis based on more than 300 craniodental and postcranial features reveals that the new genus is a stem hominoid (preceding the divergence between hylobatids and hominids), although more derived than previously known small catarrhines and 
Proconsul
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>CONCLUSION:
As the first known Miocene small-bodied catarrhine to share abundant derived features with extant hominoids, the new genus indicates a greater morphological diversity than previously recognized among this heterogeneous group, and it provides key insight into the last common ancestor of hylobatids and hominids. Our cladistic results, coupled with the chronology and location of the new genus, suggest that it represents a late-surviving offshoot of a small African stem hominoid that is more closely related to crown hominoids than 
Proconsul
is. These results suggest that, at least in size and cranial morphology, the last common ancestor of extant hominoids might have been more gibbon-like (less great ape–like) than generally assumed. ▪
</p>
      <p>
The list of author affiliations is available in the full article online. 
*Corresponding author. E-mail: david.alba@icp.cat</p>
      <p>
Cite this article as D. M. Alba 
et al
., 
Science350
, aab2625

(
2015
). DOI: 
10.1126/science.aab2625</p>
      <p>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E</p>
      <p>PRIMATE EVOLUTION</p>
      <p>Miocene small-bodied ape from Eurasia sheds light on hominoid evolution</p>
      <p>David M. Alba,1
* 
Sergio Almécija,2,1Daniel DeMiguel,1Josep Fortuny,1</p>
      <p>Miriam Pérez de los Ríos,1Marta Pina,1Josep M. Robles,1,3Salvador Moyà-Solà4</p>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Miocene small-bodied anthropoid primates from Africa and Eurasia are generally considered to precede the divergence between the two groups of extant catarrhines—hominoids (apes and humans) and Old World monkeys—and are thus viewed as more primitive than the stem ape 
Proconsul
. Here we describe 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.,
</title>
         <p>
a small-bodied (4 to 5 kilograms) primate from the Iberian Miocene (11.6 million years ago) that displays a mosaic of primitive characteristics coupled with multiple cranial and postcranial shared derived features of extant hominoids. Our cladistic analyses show that 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is a stem hominoid that is more derived than previously described small catarrhines and 
Proconsul
. This forces us to reevaluate the role played by small-bodied catarrhines in ape evolution and provides key insight into the last common ancestor of hylobatids (gibbons) and hominids (great apes and humans).
</p>
         <p>
pes and humans (hominoids) diverged from Old World monkeys (cercopithecoids) by 
A
the Oligocene [
≥
25 million years ago (Ma)] (
1
, 
2
) and subsequently diversified in both Africa and Eurasia during the Miocene (23 to ~5 Ma) (
3
). They are currently represented by crown hominoids (
4
)—i.e., the small-bodied hylobatids (gibbons and siamangs) and the largerbodied hominids (great apes and humans), which diverged from one another by the early Miocene (~17 Ma) (
1
). Reconstructing the ancestral morphotype from which extant apes and humans evolved is a challenging task (
5–7
), given the mosaic nature of evolution (
8
), the confounding effects of independently evolved features (homoplasy) (
5
, 
9
), the conflicting evidence provided by Miocene great apes (
6
, 
9
), and the incomplete and fragmentary nature of the hominoid fossil record [in particular, the virtual lack of fossil gibbons until at least the latest Miocene (
10
, 
11
)]. Thus, although extant hominoids share numerous derived features, particularly in the trunk and forelimb, it is uncertain to what extent these characteristics were inherited from their last common ancestor, whose morphotype is still under discussion (
5
, 
6
, 
11
, 
12
).
</p>
         <p>
The earliest hypotheses postulated a smallbodied gibbon-like ancestor (
13
), and for many
</p>
         <p>
years, fossil small-bodied catarrhines (anthropoid primates from Africa and Eurasia) were considered to be broadly ancestral to gibbons (
14
, 
15
). Today, hylobatids are generally considered to be a specialized and probably dwarfed lineage, evolved from a larger and more great ape–like last common ancestor with hominids (
6
, 
16
). This is because known small-bodied extinct catarrhines, such as the African dendropithecids (including at least 
Dendropithecus
, 
Simiolus
, and 
Micropithecus
) and the Eurasian pliopithecoids (
Pliopithecus
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
, and allied genera), lack most of the synapomorphies (shared derived features) of crown catarrhines (
17–21
). Even dendropithecids, which are more derived than pliopithecoids and are currently interpreted by some authors as stem hominoids (preceding the hylobatid-hominid divergence) (
3
, 
8
, 
22
), are considered to be more basal than the stem ape 
Proconsul
(
8
, 
21–23
). Here we describe a new Miocene small-bodied ape from Spain, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pliobates 
cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov. (
24
). In some primitive features, this new primate resembles previously known small-bodied catarrhines such as dendropithecids, but it differs from them and from 
Proconsul
by displaying multiple crownhominoid derived features. This mosaic provides key insight into ape evolution by forcing us to reevaluate the role played by small-bodied catarrhines in the emergence of crown hominoids.
</p>
         <p>1Institut Català de Paleontologia Miquel Crusafont (ICP), Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona (UAB), Edifici ICTA-ICP, Carrer de les Columnes sense número, Campus de la UAB, 0 8193 Cerdanyola del Vallès, Barcelona, Spain. 2Center for the Advanced Study of Human Paleobiology, Department of Anthropology, The George Washington University,</p>
         <p>Provenance</p>
         <p>The new taxon is described on the basis of a partial skeleton (IPS58443; table S1) that is permanently housed in the collections of the Institut Català de Paleontologia Miquel Crusafont (ICP) in Sabadell, Spain. The main cranial fragments were initially discovered on 3 January 2011 by a team of paleontologists from the company FOSSILIA Serveis Paleontològics i Geològics, directed by one of the authors (J.M.R.), while overseeing the excavation works performed by digging machines at the Can Mata landfill (els Hostalets de Pierola, Catalonia, Spain). In the following days, postcranial elements were found at the field during excavation of the same stratigraphic level, and the remaining postcranial small bones and other small fragments were subsequently recovered by screen-washing the excavated sediments. All the fossils therefore come from a single horizon, which was labeled ACM/C8-A4 (Abocador de Can Mata, Cell 8, sector A, locality 4).</p>
         <p>
The ACM local stratigraphic composite series (
25–27
) is located in the Vallès-Penedès Basin (northeast Iberian Peninsula), a half-graben trending north-northeast–south-southwest and limited by the Catalan Coastal Ranges; this structure was generated by the rifting of the northwest Mediterranean during the Neogene (
28
, 
29
). The basin infill mostly consists of marginal alluvial fan sediments that have provided a rich fossil record of Miocene terrestrial vertebrates (
30
). The area of els Hostalets de Pierola has thick middle to late Miocene sequences that were deposited in distalto-marginal inter-fan zones of coalescing alluvial fan systems (
27
). The ACM composite series, about 250 m in thickness, includes more than 200 formally defined localities that can be accurately dated based on lithostratigraphic, magnetostratigraphic, and biostratigraphic correlation (
26
, 
27
, 
31
). The whole series is late Aragonian, and, based on updated chron boundaries (
32
), it spans from ~12.6 to 11.5 Ma. Locality ACM/C8-A4 is correlated to chron C5r.2n (11.657 to 11.592 Ma) with an interpolated age of 11.628 Ma, which is close to the middle/late Miocene boundary, as defined by the base of the Tortonian and currently dated to 11.625 Ma (
32
).
</p>
         <title>Methods</title>
         <p>Cranial reconstruction</p>
         <p>
The cranium was preserved in a main piece (IPS58443.1) with parts of the neurocranium, basicranium, muzzle, and right maxilla (

, A to C); a medium-sized fragment with the left maxilla (IPS58443.2); and other smaller fragments that were found in close spatial association or recovered by screen-washing the surrounding sediments. These other fragments include part of the occipital and right parietal (IPS58443.3), the right glenoid region (IPS58443.4), the right occipital condyle (IPS58443.5), a fragment of the right orbital margin (IPS58443.6), the left orbital margin and temporal process of the zygomatic (IPS58443.12), a parietal fragment (IPS58443.11), and several other minor fragments whose location cannot be determined (IPS58443.7 to IPS58443.10, IPS58443.13, and IPS58443.37). The mandible was not preserved, except for a fragment of the right ramus with the condyle (IPS58443.14). The main fragment (IPS58443.1) is composed of several bone fragments that are crushed against each other and somewhat displaced from their anatomical position, but (like the remaining specimens) not plastically distorted.
</p>
         <p>Washington, DC 20052, USA. 3FOSSILIA Serveis</p>
         <p>Paleontològics i Geològics, Jaume I 87, 5è 1a, 0 8470 Sant Celoni, Barcelona, Spain. 4Institució Catalana de Recerca i Estudis Avançats at ICP and Unitat d’Antropologia Biològica (Department de Biologia Animal, de Biologia Vegetal i</p>
         <p>
d'Ecologia), Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona, Edifici ICTA-ICP, Carrer de les Columnes sense número, Campus de la UAB, 0 8193 Cerdanyola del Vallès, Barcelona, Spain. 
*Corresponding author. E-mail: david.alba@icp.cat</p>
         <p>Several bone fragments of IPS58443.1 were individualized through careful mechanical preparation, but for many other bone fragments, their fragility and state of preservation precluded a complete isolation from each other and/or from the embedding matrix. Therefore, for conservational reasons, no complete preparation of the specimen was performed, and a virtual threedimensional (3D) reconstruction was undertaken instead. The larger specimens (IPS58443.1 and IPS58443.2) were scanned at the American Museum of Natural History (New York) with a highresolution computed tomograph (CT) system (Phoenix v|tome|x s180, General Electric Measurement &amp; Control Solutions, Hanover, Germany), using a nanofocus x-ray tube. Different protocols were used for these two cranial fragments: 160 kV voltage, 1.4 mA current, 0.2 mm Cu filter, and magnification of 2.10013075, obtaining 1600 slices (virtual cross-sectional images) of 0.2 mm in thickness and a pixel size of 0.09523217 mm (IPS58443.1); and 145 kV voltage, 1.3 mA current, 0.1 mm Cu filter, and a magnification of 2.93159482, obtaining 1500 slices of 0.2 mm in thickness and a pixel size of 0.06822225 mm (IPS58443.2). Raw CT data were imported into VGStudio Max 2.1 and exported (as a stack of TIFF files) to Avizo 7.0 and Geomagic 2012 for segmentation, repositioning, mirroring, and/or visualization. CT-scanned bone fragments were segmented slice by slice by digitally removing the matrix with the aid of differential bone and sediment densities, using the semiautomatic thresholding tools of Avizo 7.0. Additional small isolated bone fragments not surrounded by matrix were scanned with a 3D desktop laser scanner (NextEngine) at high definition and with a dimensional accuracy of 0.13 mm (Macro Mode); the resulting 3D models were exported to Geomagic 2012 to align and repair the meshes. The preserved bone fragments generally had clean fractures that allowed them to be easily matched with other fragments. Up to 39 3D virtual models of bone fragments, including pieces of the premaxillae and maxillae with teeth, lacrimals, zygomatics, frontal, parietals, temporals, occipital, and pterygoids, were thus digitally assembled and repositioned using Avizo 7.0 and Geomagic 2012 on the basis of preserved morphology, fracture congruence, and bilateral symmetry. Once the preserved fragments were adequately positioned, areas preserved only in one side of the cranium were mirrored. The individual models were then merged to obtain the definitive 3D virtual model, which was also 3D-printed with a ZPrinter 450 at the Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona for visualization and comparative purposes.</p>
         <p>To reconstruct the muzzle area, we primarily relied on IPS58443.1, in which the right premaxilla (with the alveoli for I1 to C1) and the maxilla (with P3 to M3, the lower portion of the nasal aperture, most of the palatine process, and the intermaxillary suture) are almost completely preserved. The left maxillary specimen (IPS58443.2) is less complete and only includes the M2 to M3 series and a smaller portion of the intermaxillary suture, as well as the zygomatic root. Palate width and shape were thus reconstructed by mirroring the right fragment onto the left one, then further adjusting it based on the fit onto the left portion of the intermaxillary suture and the alignment with the left molars. With regard to the orbital area, although the orbits are not completely preserved on either side, their profile can be reconstructed with reasonable accuracy based on the available fragments: IPS58443.1 includes, in several fragments, most of the interorbital area of the frontal and the superior orbital rims, the maxillary portion of the right inferior orbital rim, a zygomatic portion of the right lateral orbital rim, and both lacrimals; IPS58443.12 includes a larger lateral portion of the left orbit that encompasses part of the temporal process of the zygomatic arch and the frontomaxillary suture. Although the zygomaticomaxillary suture is not preserved on either side, the missing portion of the zygomatic process of the maxilla on the left side is minimal. Therefore, it is possible to situate the left orbit relative to the muzzle, on the basis of the orientation between the zygomatic process of IPS58443.12 and the zygomatic root preserved in IPS58443.2. Similarly, although the frontozygomatic suture is not preserved at the end of the left zygomatic process of IPS58443.1, only a very small portion is missing; thus, the preservation of the suture in the zygomatic portion of the lateral orbital rim in IPS58443.12 enables a reliable reconstruction of the superolateral aspect of the orbit, based on the curvature of these two fragments. The inferior orbital rim can be also reconstructed using its right maxillary portion, which is preserved in IPS58443.1, by mirroring onto the left side. Moreover, the preservation of both superior orbital rims in the frontal fragments of IPS58443.1 further allows the right orbit to be positioned relative to the muzzle, in spite of the fact that the right zygomaticomaxillary suture is not preserved. Overall, although the missing fragments of the orbital rims introduce some degree of uncertainty, the curvature of the various preserved portions enables a confident reconstruction of orbital size and shape. The preserved portions of the zygomatic and maxilla further enable reliable positioning of the orbits relative to the muzzle. Because the missing portions are very small, other possible reconstructions do not differ substantially from the one provided here.</p>
         <p>Fig. 1. Cranium and dentition.
(
A
to 
C
) Cranium of the holotype (IPS58443) of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.The main cranial fragments, including the basicranium and the right palate, are shown in basal view (A); details of the right palatal fragment are shown in left-lateral (B) and right-lateral (C) views. (
D
) Detail of the right postcanine teeth, in occlusal view (mesial is to the right).
</p>
         <p>To reconstruct the neurocranium, we relied on the relative spatial position of the braincase fragments in the crushed main specimen (IPS58443.1). Because these fragments are not plastically deformed, they show the original curvature of the braincase, which considerably facilitated the reconstruction of its overall shape. The frontals are preserved in six fragments that enable the reconstruction of most of the braincase morphology (including the whole supraorbital area and the connection with the parietals on the left side). The parietals are preserved in 19 fragments, which have well-preserved sutures and neat fractures. The latter fact, together with the spatial association among the various fragments, enables the reconstruction of the posterior contour of the cranial vault. Large portions of both temporals, including the tympanic bullae, are also preserved in IPS58443.1. The right temporal is more completely preserved than the left one; it includes not only the glenoid fossa and the temporal process of the zygomatic arch, but also the suture with the parietal. These preserved pieces, mirrored onto the left side, enabled the reconstruction of the lateral aspects of the neurocranium. The occipitals are less completely preserved, being restricted to three basioccipital fragments and one occipital fragment, which include the occipital condyles and enable a reliable orientation of the preserved profile of the foramen magnum. One of these fragments connects with the left temporal, thereby enabling the reconstruction of the basicranium. Only minor displacements, caused by diagenesis, had to be corrected; these included displacements between the left bulla and the left occipital condyle and basioccipital, and the artifactual separation of the occipital-temporal suture. Once these elements were slightly repositioned into their correct anatomical place, they fit congruently with the surrounding elements. Last, the pterygoid wings are also preserved on the right side, attached to the palatine but slightly crushed, so that some realignment of this bone was necessary. The connection of the braincase with the superior portion of the face is possible through the frontal fragments, which on the left side are continuous with the parietal fragments. The connection between the braincase and the lower portion of the face is possible, not only because of the preservation of the superior orbital rims in the frontal and of a maxillary portion of the right inferior orbital rim, but also because part of the right pterygoid wing (anatomically adjacent to the palatine) was preserved in its original anatomical position, attached to one of the bone fragments of IPS58443.1 (which includes a large portion of the basicranium and temporal). This pterygoid fragment enables a reliable reconstruction of the relative position of the muzzle and the neurocranium via the basicranium, and it further confirms the correctness of the reconstruction of orbital shape and position. The position of the muzzle was further tested on the basis of the congruent alignment on the right side between the temporal process of the zygomatic in IPS58443.12 and the zygomatic process of the temporal in IPS58443.4.</p>
         <p>Dental measurements and bodymass estimation</p>
         <p>
Standard dental measurements of mesiodistal length (MD) and maximum buccolingual breadth (BL) were taken (in millimeters) to assess dental size and proportions by means of comparative bivariate plots of log-transformed BL versus MD for each of the upper molars. Data for extant and extinct small-bodied catarrhines were taken from the literature (
17
, 
33–46
) or measured by one of the authors (D.M.A.). Based on MD and BL measurements, tooth square area (A, in square millimeters) was computed for postcanine teeth to estimate the body mass (BM, in kilograms) of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, using allometric equations of BM versus A (
47
). BM of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
and, for comparative purposes, of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus
vindobonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
was also estimated based on allometric equations, using postcranial estimators (
48
) separately for samples of hominoids and catarrhines (i.e., hominoids plus cercopithecoids), based on sex-species mean data. Six postcranial BM estimators were used (
49
), including three surface areas (for the tibia, humerus, and radius) and three linear measurements (for the humerus and radius; tables S2 and S3).
</p>
         <p>Humeral torsion and arm angle</p>
         <p>
Humeral torsion, or the orientation of the humeral head relative to the mediolateral axis of the distal humerus (
50
), cannot be directly computed in the described skeleton because the humeral head is missing. Accordingly, humeral torsion was kindly estimated by S. Larson, following her methodology (
50
) for incomplete humeri lacking the proximal end (based on the bisector of the bicipital groove, indicating the orientation of the humeral head), as well as using the posterior buttress for the humeral head (as a reference for the head axis). Measurements were obtained from a cast of the two humeral diaphyseal fragments of the holotype specimen. This humerus was originally preserved as a single specimen, with a crack filled with sediment at about midshaft level, the two fragments being slightly crushed against each other in the proximodistal direction. After manual separation of the matrix, the original shape of the diaphysis was reconstructed by correctly aligning casts of the two fragments.
</p>
         <p>
The arm angle (or carrying angle at the elbow joint), which is the angle between the long axes of the humerus and ulna (arm angles &lt;0° imply medial deviation of the ulna) (
51
), was computed from a photograph of the rearticulated original specimens.
</p>
         <p>Postcranial proportions</p>
         <p>
The degree of elongation of the forearm, the arm, and the forelimb as a whole were assessed by means of allometric regressions of radius, humerus, and radius-plus-humerus length (in millimeters), respectively, relative to BM (in kilograms). Allometric equations (table S4) were derived based on data taken from the literature (
48
, 
52–54
) or kindly provided by E. Sarmiento to S.M.S. Regressions for anthropoid primates were based on 
n
= 54 sex-species means, corresponding to 31 species from 17 genera; hylobatids, orangutans, 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachyteles</tp:taxon-name>
were excluded from the regressions because they are clear outliers. Allometric residuals were computed for the studied sample as well as for 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
; humeral length in the former, given the lack of the humeral head, was estimated by taking into account the proportions of the humerus of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
To assess the size of the triquetrum relative to the hamate, the size of each bone was computed as the geometric mean of three measurements representing their maximum dimensions: maximum mediolateral breadth, dorsopalmar height, and proximodistal length for the triquetrum; and maximum proximodistal length, dorsopalmar height, and mediolateral breadth for the hamate. Comparative data were kindly provided by T. Kivell; her metrics and sample (including 28 anthropoid species from 16 genera) are described in the literature (
55
, 
56
).
</p>
         <p>Cranial capacity and encephalization</p>
         <p>
For preservational reasons, it was not possible to compute cranial capacity (CC, in cubic centimeters) from the virtual endocast. Therefore, CC was estimated using published allometric equations based on various external neurocranial measurements (
57
): maximum width of the braincase base (CW, in millimeters); vertical height of braincase (CH, in millimeters); chord of the midline suture through occipitals, parietals, and frontals (CL, in millimeters); modulus of the above-mentioned linear measurements (CO, in millimeters), computed as CO = CW + CH + CL; the product of the above-mentioned linear dimensions (PR, in cubic millimeters), computed as PR = CW × CH × CL; and foramen magnum area (FMA, in square centimeters), computed as FMA = (π/4) × FMW × FML, where FMW is foramen magnum width, and FML is foramen magnum length (both in millimeters). To assess encephalization, we relied on lower taxonomic–level metrics of relative brain size, which are significantly correlated with general domain cognitive abilities in primates (
58
, 
59
). Encephalization residuals (ER) were computed as ER = ln CCobserved – ln CCpredicted, by using the ordinary least-squares cercopithecoid allometric regression (ln CC = 0.4778 ln BM + 3.457), whereas encephalization constants (EC) were computed as EC = CC / BM0.28 (
58
, 
59
). Sex-species mean data for extant species were taken from the literature (
58
). In addition to the estimates derived for 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
in this study, published data for various extinct catarrhines (female 
Aegyptopithecus zeuxis
, male 
Victoriapithecus macinnesi
, female 
Proconsul nyanzae
, male 
Oreopithecus bambolii
, and female 
Hispanopithecus hungaricus
) were also included in the analyses (
37
, 
58
, 
60–62
).
</p>
         <p>Dental microwear</p>
         <p>
Paleodietary reconstruction was based on dental microwear analysis (
63
). The M1 of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
was selected, because it exhibits clearer and larger phase II crushing and grinding facets than the remaining molars. Occlusal surfaces were examined through an environmental scanning electron microscope at ×500 magnification in secondary emissions mode and at 20 kV, following established procedures (
63
). An area of standardized size, corresponding to 0.02 mm2 on the original facet (
64
), was analyzed using the custom software package Microware 4.02 (
65
). Three microscopic variables were measured: percentage of pits, breadth of striations, and breadth of pits. Striations and pits were categorized by following an arbitrarily set length-to-width ratio of 4:1 (
63
, 
66–68
). We compared our results with those previously derived for a sample of 11 extant anthropoids with well-known diets (
63
, 
69
, 
70
), partitioned into three distinct dietary categories (
66
), as well as with those reported for extinct catarrhines (
64
, 
66–68
, 
71
), including both pliopithecoids and hominoids. Microwear data were analyzed by means of canonical variates analysis, using SPSS Statistics 19 software.
</p>
         <p>Phylogenetic analysis</p>
         <p>
A cladistic analysis based on maximum parsimony was performed with PAUP* (Phylogenetic Analysis Using Parsimony) version 4.0 for Unix (
72
), with the search command “branch-and-bound,” based on a taxon-character data matrix of 319 characters and 20 taxa (tables S5 and S6). This matrix was coded anew by the authors, although it was partially based on character statements taken from the literature (
8
, 
22
, 
73–76
). All but 10 characters were treated as unordered, whereas inapplicable characters were treated as missing data. Clade robusticity was assessed by means of bootstrap analysis (10,000 replicates) and Bremer support indices. For the most-parsimonious cladograms, the following metrics were computed: consistency index (excluding uninformative characters), retention index, and rescaled consistency index. Character polarity was determined using the outgroup method, with the stem catarrhine 
Aegyptopithecus
being used as such. Ingroup taxa include the stem catarrhine 
Saadanius
, two cercopithecoids (the extant 
<tp:taxon-name>Macaca</tp:taxon-name>
and the extinct 
Victoriapithecus
), extant hylobatids, extant (
<tp:taxon-name>Pongo</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Gorilla</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>Pan</tp:taxon-name>
) and extinct (
Pierolapithecus
and 
Hispanopithecus
) great apes, and a wide representation of small-bodied fossil catarrhines from Africa [two dendropithecids, including 
Micropithecus
and 
Dendropithecus
-plus- 
Simiolus
(coded simultaneously)] and Eurasia (six pliopithecoids,including 
Pliopithecus
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Dionysopithecus
, 
Barberapithecus
, 
Anapithecus
, and 
Plesiopliopithecus
). The phylogenetic placement of 
Saadanius
, 
Micropithecus
, and most pliopithecoids (except 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
) should be considered with caution, because they have a large proportion of missing data. For this reason, the analysis was also performed with these taxa removed.
</p>
         <p>Table 1. Dental measurements.
Standard dental measurements to assess dental size and proportions were taken to the nearest 0.1 mm in the holotype (IPS58443) of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov. MD, mesiodistal length (in millimeters); BL, buccolingual width (in millimeters); BLI, breadth/length index (in percent), computed as BL/MD × 100. Dashes indicate lack of data due to incomplete preservation.
</p>
         <p>Catalog no. Tooth Side MD BL BLI
IPS58443.1 P3 Right .....................................................................................................................................................................................................................&gt;2.8&gt;4.5 — IPS58443.1 P4 Right 3.2 5.3 165.6 ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... IPS58443.1 M1 Right 5.0 5.9 118.0 ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... IPS58443.1 M2 Right 5.3 6.5 122.6 ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... IPS58443.1 M3 Right 4.6 6.4 139.1 ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... IPS58443.2 M2 Left&gt;5.0 — — ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... IPS58443.2 M3 Left 4.5 6.7 148.9 .....................................................................................................................................................................................................................
</p>
         <p>Systematic paleontology</p>
      </sec>
      <p>
Order Primates Linnaeus, 1758. Suborder Haplorrhini Pocock, 1918. Infraorder Anthropoidea Mivart, 1864. Parvorder 
<tp:taxon-name>Catarrhini</tp:taxon-name>
É. Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, 1812. Superfamily Hominoidea Gray, 1821.
</p>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobatidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pan troglodytes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Papio cynocephalus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus
vindobonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus
vindobonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachyteles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pongo</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pan</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecusvindobonensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobatesmoloch</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>H. moloch</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>H. moloch</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles
paniscus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus
aethiops
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miocene small-bodied ape from Eurasia sheds light on hominoid evolution</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1126/science.aab2625</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6E78FF8EFA7A8A155848FFBAFFA9A57C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aab2625</pub-id>
               <source>Science</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobatidae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>fam. nov.</tp:taxon-status>Type genus:<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
,
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. et sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>whose diagnosis is as for its type (and only) species, described below.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Holotype: IPS58443, a partial skeleton with an associated skull (

and movie S1), housed at the ICP. It is composed of 70 bones and bone fragments (table S1) found in close spatial association, which, given the lack of repeated elements, are attributed to a single adult female individual (based on the small canine alveolus), with an estimated body mass of 4 to 5 kg (tables S7 and S8). It includes large portions of the cranium with postcanine maxillary teeth (
Table 1
), a mandibular fragment, a partial left forelimb (nearly complete humerus, radius, partial ulna, carpals, and bones of the manual rays), more fragmentary elements of the right forelimb, and bones from the hind limb.
</p>
            <p>Type locality: ACM/C8-A4 (els Hostalets de Pierola, Catalonia, Spain), in the ACM stratigraphic series (Vallès-Penedès Basin, northeast Iberian Peninsula).</p>
            <p>
Age, stratigraphic position, and distribution: Only known from the type locality, which has an estimated age of 11.6 Ma (middle/late Miocene boundary) and is thus somewhat younger than all other ACM hominoid- and pliopithecoid-bearing localities (
9
, 
31
, 
33
, 
77
, 
78
), the latter of which have been dated to 11.7 to 11.9 Ma [updated from (
77
, 
78
)].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>
Etymology: Genus name from the Latin 
plio-
(itself from the Greek, meaning “greater in extent”) and from the Greek 
bates
(meaning “the one that walks or haunts”). The name is a contraction of the genus names 
Pliopithecus
(“more ape”) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
(“the one that walks in the woods or in the trees”), in allusion to the small body size and the mosaic of primitive (stem catarrhine–like) and derived (crown hominoid) features displayed by the new taxon. The species epithet is the genitive of the female substantive “Catalonia,” the Latin name of Catalunya (in which the type locality is situated).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>Small-bodied catarrhine primate (estimated female BM of 4 to 5 kg). Dental formula 2.1.2.3.</p>
            <p>Female upper canines moderately compressed. Upper cheek teeth low-crowned and with subpyramidal, moderately peripheral, and inflated cusps. Upper premolars relatively broad and ovoid, P4 smaller than P3, both with heteromorphic cusps, a markedly convex lingual contour and a distinct lingual cingulum (more developed in the P4), a distinct transverse crest separating the restricted mesial fovea from the extensive trigon basin, and the postparacrista forming an abrupt angle with the distal marginal ridge. Upper molars only moderately broader than long, with markedly convex lingual profiles; buccal cusps quite peripheral and buccal cingula discontinuous; lingual cingula relatively well developed, shelf-like, and C-shaped, but not surrounding the hypocone (which is distinct and more peripheral than the protocone); mesial fovea restricted, with an obliquely directed preprotocrista, and trigon basin extensive, being separated by a continuous crista obliqua from the slightly smaller distal fovea, which displays no hypocone-metacone crest. M2 slightly larger than the M1, and M3 shorter and trapezoidal (due to the oblique buccal margin, with a centrally situated metacone and a rudimentary hypocone).</p>
            <p>Face small but with a distinct snout, the anterior portion of the nasals being almost parallel to the palate. Maxillary sinus large and frontal sinus present but small. Nasal aperture narrow. Nasoalveolar clivus short, with an open palatine fenestra. Anteriorly slightly narrow palate with somewhat convergent upper tooth rows. Zygomatic root moderately high. Orbits subcircular, large, and frontated, with telescopic orbital rims located over the P4. Estimated cranial capacity (69 to 75 cm3) indicating a monkey-like degree of encephalization. External auditory meatus tubular but short and not completely ossified, with a V-shaped end and its anterior portion fused with the postglenoid process. Carotid foramen perforating the bulla posterodistally, and carotid canal horizontally and anteriorly oriented. Spinosum and postglenoid foramina absent. Jugular foramen large and ventrally visible.</p>
            <p>Humerus without entepicondylar foramen and capitular tail, with a well-developed capitulum, and a narrow and deep zona conoidea.Radial head rounded and not very tilted, with a markedly beveled surface for articulation with the humeral zona conoidea, the articular surface for the ulnar radial notch extending along a large portion of the radial head, and a laterally facing bicipital tuberosity. Distal radioulnar joint fully diarthrodial, with an expanded and two-faceted semilunar articulation on the ulnar head, and a partially developed ulnar fovea. Ulnar styloid process with reduced girth and not articulating with the short pisiform. Triquetrum small and with a reduced articular surface for the ulnar styloid process. Hamate relatively long proximodistally, with a steep triquetrum facet, a relatively large head and a distally projecting hamulus. Capitate with a relatively small and oblong head and a divided facet for the second metacarpal on its radial side.</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis</p>
            <p>
The new taxon differs from pliopithecoids and dendropithecids in its lack of a humeral capitular tail, its hominoid-like proximal radial morphology, its expanded ulnar head with a two-faceted semilunar articulation, and its partially developed ulnar fovea. It further differs from these taxa and proconsulids in its more hominoid-like carpal morphology (including the lack of a pisiform facet for the styloid process, a capitate facet for the second metacarpal divided by a deep ligamentary notch, and a distally projecting hamulus in the hamate), and particularly from pliopithecoids in its overall larger muzzle, more horizontal nasals anteriorly, some details of the upper molars, and (at least compared with 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
) the lack of an entepicondylar foramen in the humerus. It also differs from all of the above-mentioned taxa in its fused ectotympanic and postglenoid process, and from these taxa and hominids in its horizontal and anteriorly oriented carotid canal. Last, it differs from crown hominoids (hylobatids and hominids) in its incompletely ossified ectotympanic and in its more primitive dentition and forelimb morphology (particularly in the humeroulnar articulation).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description, comparisons, and paleobiology 
Dental morphology and diet</p>
            <p>
Although the lack of lower dentition precludes comparisons with some taxa, the upper cheek teeth of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
(

D and 
Table 1
) generally resemble those of other small-bodied Miocene catarrhines in both occlusal morphology and proportions (figs. S1 and S2). In contrast, they display a more primitive morphology than those of extant hominoids, including the similarly sized gibbons. Hylobatids possess more elongated cheek teeth with more peripheralized cusps, less developed cingula, and a much more extensive central fovea. Compared with Miocene small-bodied catarrhines from Eurasia and Africa (fig. S1), the upper molars of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
more closely resemble those of the dendropithecid 
Micropithecus
(
21
, 
34
, 
35
, 
79
) in several features, such as the markedly convex lingual profiles and moderately developed buccal cingula (albeit to a lesser extent than in 
Micropithecus
), the C-shaped lingual cingulum that is mostly restricted to the protocone (not surrounding the hypocone), the well-developed and lingually situated hypocone, and the relatively narrow M1 and M2. Nevertheless, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
differs in several features from 
Micropithecus
, which has more restricted buccal cingula, a hypocone-metacone crest, and a relatively longer and less trapezoidal M3. The dentition of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
more clearly differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
and other pliopithecoids (fig. S1), including from 
Barberapithecus
[also recorded at the Vallès-Penedès Basin (
36
)] and 
Pliopithecus
[previously recorded at ACM (
33
)] in several features, such as the more convex lingual profile, the more peripheral buccal cusps, the less developed cingula of the molars, the narrower M1 and M2, and the M3 occlusal morphology and proportions (fig. S2).
</p>
            <p>
With regard to microwear features, the M1 displays a pitting percentage of 30.0%, a pit breadth of 5.67 μm, and a striation breadth of 1.98 μm. Based on pitting incidence (

, A and B), which is the most useful metric for distinguishing among dietary categories (
70
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
closely resembles extant frugivores (
<tp:taxon-name>Pan troglodytes</tp:taxon-name>
) and eclectic feeders (
<tp:taxon-name>Papio cynocephalus</tp:taxon-name>
) that largely rely on ripe fruit. In contrast, the pitting incidence of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is higher than in extant folivores and much lower than in extant hard-object feeders (including orangutans). Compared with other extinct catarrhines from Western Europe, the pitting percentage of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is somewhat lower than in most pliopithecoids and hominoids, for which some degree of sclerocarpy has been inferred (
66
, 
68
). This low pitting incidence is consistent with the pit- and striation-breadth measurements (which show no sign of extreme folivory or specialized hard-object feeding) and most closely approaches that of the fossil hominoids 
Anoiapithecus brevirostris
and 
Hispanopithecus laietanus
, previously interpreted as soft frugivores (
68
). These results are confirmed by a multivariate analysis that simultaneously examined the three microwear variables (

C and tables S9 to S11), in which 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
falls closer to the extant frugivorous–mixed-feeder centroid for the first and second canonical axes and is classified as a frugivore. Dental microwear analyses therefore indicate a mainly frugivorous diet for 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, compatible with a high consumption of ripe fruit and a low sclerocarpic component.
</p>
            <p>Body mass</p>
            <p>
Dental BM estimates for the female holotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
(table S7) range from 2.9 to 4.8 kg, with an average BM estimate of 3.9 kg and an uncertainty degree (based on the combined 95% confidence intervals for each dental locus) of 2.5 to 5.7 kg. Postcranial BM estimates (table S8) are on average 4.8 kg (range: 4.0 to 5.6 kg), based on catarrhine regressions, and 4.3 kg (range: 2.6 to 6.3 kg), based on hominoid regressions (estimates for each postcranial estimator and their confidence intervals are given in table S8). Given that the size of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is in the lower range for extant hominoids, the catarrhine regressions probably yield more accurate estimates, although the hominoid-based estimates are closer to the dental ones. Overall, the body mass of the holotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
can be estimated at ~4 to 5 kg (much lower than that estimated for 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus
vindobonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, ~11 to 12 kg; table S8).
</p>
            <p>Cranial morphology and encephalization</p>
            <p>
A 3D virtual reconstruction of the cranium, based on the preserved specimens, is shown in fig. S3, whereas the final reconstruction (including mirrored portions) is shown in 

and movie S1. Based on this reconstruction, the cranium of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
differs from the primitive catarrhine condition (
22
, 
37
, 
60
) by being short, wide, and high. However, the tubular ectotympanic is short and incompletely ossified—i.e., less developed than in 
Saadanius
and extant crown catarrhines (
20–22
). The maxillary sinus is extensive, as in stem catarrhines and hominoids (
22
, 
80
), and there is also a small frontal sinus, as in stem hominoids but unlike in stem catarrhines, cercopithecoids, hylobatids, and pongines (
22
, 
37
, 
80
). The face is short and displays anteriorly situated orbits, as in hylobatids, colobines, and some extinct small-bodied catarrhines such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Micropithecus
, and 
Lomorupithecus
(
19
, 
21
, 
38
, 
76
, 
79
). However, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
differs from these taxa (and more closely resembles hylobatids) by displaying a more well-defined muzzle (especially compared with 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
) with long and more horizontal nasals, a higher zygomatic root (moderately high as in hylobatids, but less so than in hominids), an interorbital pillar nearly orthogonal to the frontal squama (as in hylobatids and chimpanzees), a high degree of orbital convergence and frontation (as in all extant hominoids), and thin and anteriorly projecting (telescopic) orbital rims [to a greater extent than in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
(
38
), and thus most closely resembling hylobatids and, as far as it can be ascertained with incomplete preservation, 
Micropithecus
(
79
)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
also displays derived hominoid features in the basicranium (

A), including the absence of a postglenoid foramen with a large and ventrally visible jugular foramen (as in all extant hominoids), the foramen ovale situated anteriorly and laterally to the Eusta- chian aperture (as in hylobatids and African and African apes), and the horizontal and anapes), the fusion between the auditory meatus teriorly directed carotid canal in the petrosal bone and the postglenoid process (as in hylobatids (as in hylobatids).
</p>
            <p>
Braincase measurements yield an average cranial capacity estimate of 69.0 cm3 (range: 41.4 to 110.7 cm3; table S12), which is close to the estimates of 60.1 and 65.3 cm3 delivered by the two most reliable estimators (
57
) and only slightly lower than the estimate of 75.1 cm3 obtained from foramen magnum area (table S12). According to our estimates of body mass (4.5 kg) and cranial capacity [72 cm3 (average of cranial and foramen magnum estimates)], 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
would display a monkey-like degree of encephalization extensively overlapping with extant cercopithecoids (fig. S4 and table S13), being much more encephalized than the stem catarrhine 
Aegyptopithecus
, slightly more so than the stem cercopithecoid 
Victoriapithecus
, and only slightly less so than hylobatids and the extinct hominoids 
Proconsul
and 
Oreopithecus
. All these taxa, like cercopithecoids, are less encephalized than the extinct hominoid 
Hispanopithecus
(
Rudapithecus
) and the extant great apes. Although humans are outliers in brain size–body size allometric regressions, great apes further display an allometric grade shift compared with hylobatids (and 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
), which are only slightly more encephalized on average than cercopithecoids (
58
).
</p>
            <p>Postcranial morphology and locomotion</p>
            <p>
The humerus (

) resembles that of extant crown catarrhines, proconsulids, and dendropithecids by lacking (unlike 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
) an entepicondylar foramen (
17
, 
20
, 
21
, 
38
, 
79
, 
81
, 
82
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
more closely resembles extant hominoids in the laterally facing bicipital tuberosity in the radius (
81
, 
83
) (

), as well as in the configuration of the humeroradial articulation (
81
, 
82
, 
84
) (

), including: in the humerus, the lack of capitular tail [present in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
, dendropithecids, and cercopithecoids (
84
)] and the moderately globulous (although not posterolaterally expanded) capitulum with a well-developed zona conoidea [lacking in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
and dendropithecids (
81–84
)]; and, in the radius, the only slightly tilted and almost circular radial head with a small and flat area, a reduced lateral lip, and a beveled surface for the humeral zona conoidea. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
also has a hominoid-like diarthrodial distal radioulnar joint (
85–87
), with a two-faceted expanded semilunar articulation in the ulnar head (

). In this regard, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
departs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
, dendropithecids, and cercopithecoids (
17
, 
38
, 
82
) and more closely resembles 
Proconsul
(
88
), although the ulnar head is less extensive than in extant hominoids. In contrast with these derived features, the humeral shaft and humeroulnar joint are plesiomorphic: The former (

) is anteriorly straight and somewhat proximally retroflexed; the latter (

) lacks the stabilizing features of extant hominoids (
83
, 
89
), as shown by the narrow ulnar trochlear notch without a median keel (in agreement with the absence of spooling and the poorly defined trochlear lateral keel in the humerus of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
            <p>
Humeral torsion in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is estimated at 101°, irrespective of the method employed (based on the posterior buttress for the humeral head or the bisector of the bicipital groove), with a confidence interval spanning 95.7° to 106.3° [based on the prediction error (5.23%) for the bicipital groove method (
50
)]. This degree of torsion is moderate, higher than that estimated for 
Proconsul heseloni
(92°), but comparable to estimates for 
Dryopithecus fontani
(102°) and 
Dendropithecus macinnesi
(103.5°), and only slightly below the value estimated for 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus
vindobonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(109°). The humeral torsion of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is thus most comparable to that of non-atelid platyrrhines and lower than that of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
and extant hominoids, especially African great apes and humans [although the high degree of humeral torsion of extant hominoids is related to increased mobility at the glenohumeral joint, the higher values of great apes and humans appear related to knucklewalking and enhanced manipulation, respectively, rather than suspensory behaviors (
50
)]. In contrast to the moderate humeral torsion, the forelimb of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
appears somewhat elongated relative to its body size (fig. S5). Allometric computations of relative forelimb length in fossils (residuals are given in table S14) must be considered with caution, because they are dependent on the accuracy of body-size estimates. However, the forelimb of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
(based on our BM estimate of 4.5 kg) appears more elongated than that of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
(based on our estimate of 11.5 kg). The latter taxon, contrary to previous assertions (
81
, 
83
), has the generalized proportions of quadrupedal monkeys. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, in contrast, has a forelimb elongation similar to that of female orangutans and 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachyteles</tp:taxon-name>
, although it is less extreme than in 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
and especially than in hylobatids. The same pattern holds when the humerus and radius are analyzed separately, although in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, relative length is somewhat higher for the radius than for the humerus. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
further displays a high arm angle (8°), which is considerably greater than the average in most anthropoids, except 
<tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
(9.8°), 
<tp:taxon-name>Pongo</tp:taxon-name>
(6.3°), and 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
(6.5°) (
51
).
</p>
            <p>
The ulnocarpal articulation of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is completely different from that of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
and dendropithecids (
17
, 
38
, 
90
), including a partially developed ulnar fovea (

), which, in extant hominoids, is the attachment area of the triangular disc ligament and the intra-articular meniscus (
85–87
). The ulnar styloid process is relatively long and slender, with no discernible articular surfaces for the pisiform or triquetrum. This agrees with the lack of an articular facet for the styloid process on the pisiform, like extant hominoids but unlike monkeys and 
Proconsul
(
91
). However, in contrast to 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
), the triquetrum of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
shows a proximal articular facet, which is more developed than that present in hylobatids and sometimes 
<tp:taxon-name>Pan</tp:taxon-name>
(
51
, 
87
) but less developed than in monkeys. This suggests that ulnotriquetral contact might have been reduced by some kind of intra-articular tissue, similarly to some 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
species (
93
). Moreover, as in apes, the triquetrum of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is small relative to hamate size (fig. S6), indicating a reduced loading on the ulnar side of the wrist. However, as in monkeys and 
Proconsul
, the triquetrum of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
differs from that of extant apes and 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
) by possessing a proximally protruding beak-like process (

). The hamate of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is “Miocene ape– like” (
91
, 
92
), although it more closely resembles that of hylobatids by possessing a dorsopalmarly narrow and proximodistally long triquetral articular surface that is proximally globular, as well as a distally projecting hamulus (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
further resembles hylobatids and 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
by having an oblong and mediolaterally narrow capitate head that, like the facet for the hamate, is proximodistally aligned. This morphology contrasts with the more globulous, wider, and ulnarly inclined capitate head of other catarrhines, including 
Proconsul
(
88
, 
91
) and 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
); in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, though, it is not radially inclined, as it is in hylobatids. Moreover, the capitate facet for the second metacarpal is divided by a deep ligamentary notch (

), as in extant hominoids and 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
) but not in other catarrhines (including 
Proconsul
), in which the facet for the second metacarpal is dorsopalmarly continuous and occupies the whole lateral aspect of the capitate (

) (
91
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
has a complex articulation between the third metacarpal and capitate, as in extant apes but not in 
Proconsul
(
91
); however, as in 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
), the capitate of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
lacks a hook-like process.
</p>
            <p>
Regarding positional behaviors, although the primitive morphology of the proximal humerus of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is suggestive of generalized abovebranch quadrupedalism (
94
), its overall postcranial body plan is more compatible with a locomotor repertoire that includes a large amount of cautious and eclectic climbing (
87
, 
95
). This inference is supported by the emphasis on pronation and supination capabilities, the reduced compressive forces transferred across the ulnar side of the wrist, and the important ulnar deviation and rotatory capabilities. It agrees with previous hypotheses on the original locomotor adaptations of hominoids (
95
, 
96
) and with recent interpretations of 
Proconsul
that similarly depict this taxon as an arboreal quadruped with adaptations for cautious climbing and clambering (
12
, 
88
), including an incipient distal radioulnar diarthrosis that (unlike in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
) is still associated to a nonretreated ulnar styloid process (
88
). The reduced ulnocarpal articulation of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
thus more closely foreshadows the condition of extant hominoids, although to a lesser extent than in the stem great ape 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
), indicating a decreased emphasis on forearm use under weight-bearing conditions relative to 
Proconsul
(
88
). Several characteristics of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
(particularly the elongated forearm, the high arm angle, and the laterally facing bicipital tuberosity) further suggest some degree of below-branch forelimbdominated suspensory behaviors (
51
). However, the lack of hominoid-like elbow-stabilizing features in the humeroulnar joint (
83
, 
89
), the generalized metacarpophalangeal proportions, and the lack of marked phalangeal curvature suggest that 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
was not specifically adapted to perform the acrobatic suspensory behaviors (ricochetal brachiation) displayed by extant gibbons.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobatidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pan troglodytes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Papio cynocephalus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus
vindobonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus
vindobonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachyteles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pongo</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pan</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecusvindobonensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobatesmoloch</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>H. moloch</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>H. moloch</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles
paniscus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus
aethiops
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miocene small-bodied ape from Eurasia sheds light on hominoid evolution</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1126/science.aab2625</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6E78FF8EFA7A8A155848FFBAFFA9A57C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aab2625</pub-id>
               <source>Science</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobatidae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>fam. nov.</tp:taxon-status>Type genus:<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
,
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. et sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>whose diagnosis is as for its type (and only) species, described below.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Holotype: IPS58443, a partial skeleton with an associated skull (

and movie S1), housed at the ICP. It is composed of 70 bones and bone fragments (table S1) found in close spatial association, which, given the lack of repeated elements, are attributed to a single adult female individual (based on the small canine alveolus), with an estimated body mass of 4 to 5 kg (tables S7 and S8). It includes large portions of the cranium with postcanine maxillary teeth (
Table 1
), a mandibular fragment, a partial left forelimb (nearly complete humerus, radius, partial ulna, carpals, and bones of the manual rays), more fragmentary elements of the right forelimb, and bones from the hind limb.
</p>
            <p>Type locality: ACM/C8-A4 (els Hostalets de Pierola, Catalonia, Spain), in the ACM stratigraphic series (Vallès-Penedès Basin, northeast Iberian Peninsula).</p>
            <p>
Age, stratigraphic position, and distribution: Only known from the type locality, which has an estimated age of 11.6 Ma (middle/late Miocene boundary) and is thus somewhat younger than all other ACM hominoid- and pliopithecoid-bearing localities (
9
, 
31
, 
33
, 
77
, 
78
), the latter of which have been dated to 11.7 to 11.9 Ma [updated from (
77
, 
78
)].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>
Etymology: Genus name from the Latin 
plio-
(itself from the Greek, meaning “greater in extent”) and from the Greek 
bates
(meaning “the one that walks or haunts”). The name is a contraction of the genus names 
Pliopithecus
(“more ape”) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
(“the one that walks in the woods or in the trees”), in allusion to the small body size and the mosaic of primitive (stem catarrhine–like) and derived (crown hominoid) features displayed by the new taxon. The species epithet is the genitive of the female substantive “Catalonia,” the Latin name of Catalunya (in which the type locality is situated).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>Small-bodied catarrhine primate (estimated female BM of 4 to 5 kg). Dental formula 2.1.2.3.</p>
            <p>Female upper canines moderately compressed. Upper cheek teeth low-crowned and with subpyramidal, moderately peripheral, and inflated cusps. Upper premolars relatively broad and ovoid, P4 smaller than P3, both with heteromorphic cusps, a markedly convex lingual contour and a distinct lingual cingulum (more developed in the P4), a distinct transverse crest separating the restricted mesial fovea from the extensive trigon basin, and the postparacrista forming an abrupt angle with the distal marginal ridge. Upper molars only moderately broader than long, with markedly convex lingual profiles; buccal cusps quite peripheral and buccal cingula discontinuous; lingual cingula relatively well developed, shelf-like, and C-shaped, but not surrounding the hypocone (which is distinct and more peripheral than the protocone); mesial fovea restricted, with an obliquely directed preprotocrista, and trigon basin extensive, being separated by a continuous crista obliqua from the slightly smaller distal fovea, which displays no hypocone-metacone crest. M2 slightly larger than the M1, and M3 shorter and trapezoidal (due to the oblique buccal margin, with a centrally situated metacone and a rudimentary hypocone).</p>
            <p>Face small but with a distinct snout, the anterior portion of the nasals being almost parallel to the palate. Maxillary sinus large and frontal sinus present but small. Nasal aperture narrow. Nasoalveolar clivus short, with an open palatine fenestra. Anteriorly slightly narrow palate with somewhat convergent upper tooth rows. Zygomatic root moderately high. Orbits subcircular, large, and frontated, with telescopic orbital rims located over the P4. Estimated cranial capacity (69 to 75 cm3) indicating a monkey-like degree of encephalization. External auditory meatus tubular but short and not completely ossified, with a V-shaped end and its anterior portion fused with the postglenoid process. Carotid foramen perforating the bulla posterodistally, and carotid canal horizontally and anteriorly oriented. Spinosum and postglenoid foramina absent. Jugular foramen large and ventrally visible.</p>
            <p>Humerus without entepicondylar foramen and capitular tail, with a well-developed capitulum, and a narrow and deep zona conoidea.Radial head rounded and not very tilted, with a markedly beveled surface for articulation with the humeral zona conoidea, the articular surface for the ulnar radial notch extending along a large portion of the radial head, and a laterally facing bicipital tuberosity. Distal radioulnar joint fully diarthrodial, with an expanded and two-faceted semilunar articulation on the ulnar head, and a partially developed ulnar fovea. Ulnar styloid process with reduced girth and not articulating with the short pisiform. Triquetrum small and with a reduced articular surface for the ulnar styloid process. Hamate relatively long proximodistally, with a steep triquetrum facet, a relatively large head and a distally projecting hamulus. Capitate with a relatively small and oblong head and a divided facet for the second metacarpal on its radial side.</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis</p>
            <p>
The new taxon differs from pliopithecoids and dendropithecids in its lack of a humeral capitular tail, its hominoid-like proximal radial morphology, its expanded ulnar head with a two-faceted semilunar articulation, and its partially developed ulnar fovea. It further differs from these taxa and proconsulids in its more hominoid-like carpal morphology (including the lack of a pisiform facet for the styloid process, a capitate facet for the second metacarpal divided by a deep ligamentary notch, and a distally projecting hamulus in the hamate), and particularly from pliopithecoids in its overall larger muzzle, more horizontal nasals anteriorly, some details of the upper molars, and (at least compared with 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
) the lack of an entepicondylar foramen in the humerus. It also differs from all of the above-mentioned taxa in its fused ectotympanic and postglenoid process, and from these taxa and hominids in its horizontal and anteriorly oriented carotid canal. Last, it differs from crown hominoids (hylobatids and hominids) in its incompletely ossified ectotympanic and in its more primitive dentition and forelimb morphology (particularly in the humeroulnar articulation).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description, comparisons, and paleobiology 
Dental morphology and diet</p>
            <p>
Although the lack of lower dentition precludes comparisons with some taxa, the upper cheek teeth of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
(

D and 
Table 1
) generally resemble those of other small-bodied Miocene catarrhines in both occlusal morphology and proportions (figs. S1 and S2). In contrast, they display a more primitive morphology than those of extant hominoids, including the similarly sized gibbons. Hylobatids possess more elongated cheek teeth with more peripheralized cusps, less developed cingula, and a much more extensive central fovea. Compared with Miocene small-bodied catarrhines from Eurasia and Africa (fig. S1), the upper molars of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
more closely resemble those of the dendropithecid 
Micropithecus
(
21
, 
34
, 
35
, 
79
) in several features, such as the markedly convex lingual profiles and moderately developed buccal cingula (albeit to a lesser extent than in 
Micropithecus
), the C-shaped lingual cingulum that is mostly restricted to the protocone (not surrounding the hypocone), the well-developed and lingually situated hypocone, and the relatively narrow M1 and M2. Nevertheless, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
differs in several features from 
Micropithecus
, which has more restricted buccal cingula, a hypocone-metacone crest, and a relatively longer and less trapezoidal M3. The dentition of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
more clearly differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
and other pliopithecoids (fig. S1), including from 
Barberapithecus
[also recorded at the Vallès-Penedès Basin (
36
)] and 
Pliopithecus
[previously recorded at ACM (
33
)] in several features, such as the more convex lingual profile, the more peripheral buccal cusps, the less developed cingula of the molars, the narrower M1 and M2, and the M3 occlusal morphology and proportions (fig. S2).
</p>
            <p>
With regard to microwear features, the M1 displays a pitting percentage of 30.0%, a pit breadth of 5.67 μm, and a striation breadth of 1.98 μm. Based on pitting incidence (

, A and B), which is the most useful metric for distinguishing among dietary categories (
70
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
closely resembles extant frugivores (
<tp:taxon-name>Pan troglodytes</tp:taxon-name>
) and eclectic feeders (
<tp:taxon-name>Papio cynocephalus</tp:taxon-name>
) that largely rely on ripe fruit. In contrast, the pitting incidence of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is higher than in extant folivores and much lower than in extant hard-object feeders (including orangutans). Compared with other extinct catarrhines from Western Europe, the pitting percentage of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is somewhat lower than in most pliopithecoids and hominoids, for which some degree of sclerocarpy has been inferred (
66
, 
68
). This low pitting incidence is consistent with the pit- and striation-breadth measurements (which show no sign of extreme folivory or specialized hard-object feeding) and most closely approaches that of the fossil hominoids 
Anoiapithecus brevirostris
and 
Hispanopithecus laietanus
, previously interpreted as soft frugivores (
68
). These results are confirmed by a multivariate analysis that simultaneously examined the three microwear variables (

C and tables S9 to S11), in which 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
falls closer to the extant frugivorous–mixed-feeder centroid for the first and second canonical axes and is classified as a frugivore. Dental microwear analyses therefore indicate a mainly frugivorous diet for 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, compatible with a high consumption of ripe fruit and a low sclerocarpic component.
</p>
            <p>Body mass</p>
            <p>
Dental BM estimates for the female holotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
(table S7) range from 2.9 to 4.8 kg, with an average BM estimate of 3.9 kg and an uncertainty degree (based on the combined 95% confidence intervals for each dental locus) of 2.5 to 5.7 kg. Postcranial BM estimates (table S8) are on average 4.8 kg (range: 4.0 to 5.6 kg), based on catarrhine regressions, and 4.3 kg (range: 2.6 to 6.3 kg), based on hominoid regressions (estimates for each postcranial estimator and their confidence intervals are given in table S8). Given that the size of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is in the lower range for extant hominoids, the catarrhine regressions probably yield more accurate estimates, although the hominoid-based estimates are closer to the dental ones. Overall, the body mass of the holotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates cataloniae</tp:taxon-name>
can be estimated at ~4 to 5 kg (much lower than that estimated for 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus
vindobonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, ~11 to 12 kg; table S8).
</p>
            <p>Cranial morphology and encephalization</p>
            <p>
A 3D virtual reconstruction of the cranium, based on the preserved specimens, is shown in fig. S3, whereas the final reconstruction (including mirrored portions) is shown in 

and movie S1. Based on this reconstruction, the cranium of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
differs from the primitive catarrhine condition (
22
, 
37
, 
60
) by being short, wide, and high. However, the tubular ectotympanic is short and incompletely ossified—i.e., less developed than in 
Saadanius
and extant crown catarrhines (
20–22
). The maxillary sinus is extensive, as in stem catarrhines and hominoids (
22
, 
80
), and there is also a small frontal sinus, as in stem hominoids but unlike in stem catarrhines, cercopithecoids, hylobatids, and pongines (
22
, 
37
, 
80
). The face is short and displays anteriorly situated orbits, as in hylobatids, colobines, and some extinct small-bodied catarrhines such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Micropithecus
, and 
Lomorupithecus
(
19
, 
21
, 
38
, 
76
, 
79
). However, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
differs from these taxa (and more closely resembles hylobatids) by displaying a more well-defined muzzle (especially compared with 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
) with long and more horizontal nasals, a higher zygomatic root (moderately high as in hylobatids, but less so than in hominids), an interorbital pillar nearly orthogonal to the frontal squama (as in hylobatids and chimpanzees), a high degree of orbital convergence and frontation (as in all extant hominoids), and thin and anteriorly projecting (telescopic) orbital rims [to a greater extent than in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
(
38
), and thus most closely resembling hylobatids and, as far as it can be ascertained with incomplete preservation, 
Micropithecus
(
79
)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
also displays derived hominoid features in the basicranium (

A), including the absence of a postglenoid foramen with a large and ventrally visible jugular foramen (as in all extant hominoids), the foramen ovale situated anteriorly and laterally to the Eusta- chian aperture (as in hylobatids and African and African apes), and the horizontal and anapes), the fusion between the auditory meatus teriorly directed carotid canal in the petrosal bone and the postglenoid process (as in hylobatids (as in hylobatids).
</p>
            <p>
Braincase measurements yield an average cranial capacity estimate of 69.0 cm3 (range: 41.4 to 110.7 cm3; table S12), which is close to the estimates of 60.1 and 65.3 cm3 delivered by the two most reliable estimators (
57
) and only slightly lower than the estimate of 75.1 cm3 obtained from foramen magnum area (table S12). According to our estimates of body mass (4.5 kg) and cranial capacity [72 cm3 (average of cranial and foramen magnum estimates)], 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
would display a monkey-like degree of encephalization extensively overlapping with extant cercopithecoids (fig. S4 and table S13), being much more encephalized than the stem catarrhine 
Aegyptopithecus
, slightly more so than the stem cercopithecoid 
Victoriapithecus
, and only slightly less so than hylobatids and the extinct hominoids 
Proconsul
and 
Oreopithecus
. All these taxa, like cercopithecoids, are less encephalized than the extinct hominoid 
Hispanopithecus
(
Rudapithecus
) and the extant great apes. Although humans are outliers in brain size–body size allometric regressions, great apes further display an allometric grade shift compared with hylobatids (and 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
), which are only slightly more encephalized on average than cercopithecoids (
58
).
</p>
            <p>Postcranial morphology and locomotion</p>
            <p>
The humerus (

) resembles that of extant crown catarrhines, proconsulids, and dendropithecids by lacking (unlike 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
) an entepicondylar foramen (
17
, 
20
, 
21
, 
38
, 
79
, 
81
, 
82
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
more closely resembles extant hominoids in the laterally facing bicipital tuberosity in the radius (
81
, 
83
) (

), as well as in the configuration of the humeroradial articulation (
81
, 
82
, 
84
) (

), including: in the humerus, the lack of capitular tail [present in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
, dendropithecids, and cercopithecoids (
84
)] and the moderately globulous (although not posterolaterally expanded) capitulum with a well-developed zona conoidea [lacking in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
and dendropithecids (
81–84
)]; and, in the radius, the only slightly tilted and almost circular radial head with a small and flat area, a reduced lateral lip, and a beveled surface for the humeral zona conoidea. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
also has a hominoid-like diarthrodial distal radioulnar joint (
85–87
), with a two-faceted expanded semilunar articulation in the ulnar head (

). In this regard, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
departs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
, dendropithecids, and cercopithecoids (
17
, 
38
, 
82
) and more closely resembles 
Proconsul
(
88
), although the ulnar head is less extensive than in extant hominoids. In contrast with these derived features, the humeral shaft and humeroulnar joint are plesiomorphic: The former (

) is anteriorly straight and somewhat proximally retroflexed; the latter (

) lacks the stabilizing features of extant hominoids (
83
, 
89
), as shown by the narrow ulnar trochlear notch without a median keel (in agreement with the absence of spooling and the poorly defined trochlear lateral keel in the humerus of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
            <p>
Humeral torsion in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is estimated at 101°, irrespective of the method employed (based on the posterior buttress for the humeral head or the bisector of the bicipital groove), with a confidence interval spanning 95.7° to 106.3° [based on the prediction error (5.23%) for the bicipital groove method (
50
)]. This degree of torsion is moderate, higher than that estimated for 
Proconsul heseloni
(92°), but comparable to estimates for 
Dryopithecus fontani
(102°) and 
Dendropithecus macinnesi
(103.5°), and only slightly below the value estimated for 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus
vindobonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(109°). The humeral torsion of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is thus most comparable to that of non-atelid platyrrhines and lower than that of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
and extant hominoids, especially African great apes and humans [although the high degree of humeral torsion of extant hominoids is related to increased mobility at the glenohumeral joint, the higher values of great apes and humans appear related to knucklewalking and enhanced manipulation, respectively, rather than suspensory behaviors (
50
)]. In contrast to the moderate humeral torsion, the forelimb of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
appears somewhat elongated relative to its body size (fig. S5). Allometric computations of relative forelimb length in fossils (residuals are given in table S14) must be considered with caution, because they are dependent on the accuracy of body-size estimates. However, the forelimb of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
(based on our BM estimate of 4.5 kg) appears more elongated than that of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
(based on our estimate of 11.5 kg). The latter taxon, contrary to previous assertions (
81
, 
83
), has the generalized proportions of quadrupedal monkeys. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, in contrast, has a forelimb elongation similar to that of female orangutans and 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachyteles</tp:taxon-name>
, although it is less extreme than in 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
and especially than in hylobatids. The same pattern holds when the humerus and radius are analyzed separately, although in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, relative length is somewhat higher for the radius than for the humerus. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
further displays a high arm angle (8°), which is considerably greater than the average in most anthropoids, except 
<tp:taxon-name>Hylobates</tp:taxon-name>
(9.8°), 
<tp:taxon-name>Pongo</tp:taxon-name>
(6.3°), and 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
(6.5°) (
51
).
</p>
            <p>
The ulnocarpal articulation of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is completely different from that of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
and dendropithecids (
17
, 
38
, 
90
), including a partially developed ulnar fovea (

), which, in extant hominoids, is the attachment area of the triangular disc ligament and the intra-articular meniscus (
85–87
). The ulnar styloid process is relatively long and slender, with no discernible articular surfaces for the pisiform or triquetrum. This agrees with the lack of an articular facet for the styloid process on the pisiform, like extant hominoids but unlike monkeys and 
Proconsul
(
91
). However, in contrast to 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
), the triquetrum of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
shows a proximal articular facet, which is more developed than that present in hylobatids and sometimes 
<tp:taxon-name>Pan</tp:taxon-name>
(
51
, 
87
) but less developed than in monkeys. This suggests that ulnotriquetral contact might have been reduced by some kind of intra-articular tissue, similarly to some 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
species (
93
). Moreover, as in apes, the triquetrum of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is small relative to hamate size (fig. S6), indicating a reduced loading on the ulnar side of the wrist. However, as in monkeys and 
Proconsul
, the triquetrum of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
differs from that of extant apes and 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
) by possessing a proximally protruding beak-like process (

). The hamate of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is “Miocene ape– like” (
91
, 
92
), although it more closely resembles that of hylobatids by possessing a dorsopalmarly narrow and proximodistally long triquetral articular surface that is proximally globular, as well as a distally projecting hamulus (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
further resembles hylobatids and 
<tp:taxon-name>Ateles</tp:taxon-name>
by having an oblong and mediolaterally narrow capitate head that, like the facet for the hamate, is proximodistally aligned. This morphology contrasts with the more globulous, wider, and ulnarly inclined capitate head of other catarrhines, including 
Proconsul
(
88
, 
91
) and 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
); in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, though, it is not radially inclined, as it is in hylobatids. Moreover, the capitate facet for the second metacarpal is divided by a deep ligamentary notch (

), as in extant hominoids and 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
) but not in other catarrhines (including 
Proconsul
), in which the facet for the second metacarpal is dorsopalmarly continuous and occupies the whole lateral aspect of the capitate (

) (
91
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
has a complex articulation between the third metacarpal and capitate, as in extant apes but not in 
Proconsul
(
91
); however, as in 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
), the capitate of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
lacks a hook-like process.
</p>
            <p>
Regarding positional behaviors, although the primitive morphology of the proximal humerus of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is suggestive of generalized abovebranch quadrupedalism (
94
), its overall postcranial body plan is more compatible with a locomotor repertoire that includes a large amount of cautious and eclectic climbing (
87
, 
95
). This inference is supported by the emphasis on pronation and supination capabilities, the reduced compressive forces transferred across the ulnar side of the wrist, and the important ulnar deviation and rotatory capabilities. It agrees with previous hypotheses on the original locomotor adaptations of hominoids (
95
, 
96
) and with recent interpretations of 
Proconsul
that similarly depict this taxon as an arboreal quadruped with adaptations for cautious climbing and clambering (
12
, 
88
), including an incipient distal radioulnar diarthrosis that (unlike in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
) is still associated to a nonretreated ulnar styloid process (
88
). The reduced ulnocarpal articulation of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
thus more closely foreshadows the condition of extant hominoids, although to a lesser extent than in the stem great ape 
Pierolapithecus
(
92
), indicating a decreased emphasis on forearm use under weight-bearing conditions relative to 
Proconsul
(
88
). Several characteristics of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
(particularly the elongated forearm, the high arm angle, and the laterally facing bicipital tuberosity) further suggest some degree of below-branch forelimbdominated suspensory behaviors (
51
). However, the lack of hominoid-like elbow-stabilizing features in the humeroulnar joint (
83
, 
89
), the generalized metacarpophalangeal proportions, and the lack of marked phalangeal curvature suggest that 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
was not specifically adapted to perform the acrobatic suspensory behaviors (ricochetal brachiation) displayed by extant gibbons.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <p>Phylogeny and evolutionary implications</p>
      <p>
Our cladistic analysis, based on both craniodental and postcranial characters, recovers a single most-parsimonious tree (Fig. 8 and table S15), indicating that 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is more closely related to crown hominoids than other Miocene smallbodied catarrhines and 
Proconsul
are. With moderate support (bootstrap 71%, Bremer index 3), our results contradict the view of some authors that all of these taxa are stem catarrhines (preceding the divergence between hominoids and Old World monkeys) (
17
, 
21
) and concur instead with some previous cladistic analyses indicating a hominoid status for both 
Proconsul
(
2
, 
8
, 
22
) and, at least, dendropithecids (
8
, 
22
). Our analysis is inconsistent with the current consensus that 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
is a pliopithecoid (
20, 66, 76, 78
); however, the internal phylogeny of pliopithecoids and dendropithecids is not settled by our results (it is recovered by the most-parsimonious tree but not by the bootstrap 50%-majority-rule consensus). Similarly, the phylogenetic relationships between the analyzed dryopithecines (
Hispanopithecus
and 
Pierolapithecus
) are not well resolved (the closer link between 
Pierolapithecus
and crown hominids has a Bremer index of 1 and bootstrap support of 56%). In contrast, our analysis recovers, with very high support (bootstrap 93 to 100%, Bremer indices 7 to 11), both the molecular phylogeny of extant hominoids (
1
, 
6
) and the stem hominid status of 
Pierolapithecus
and 
Hispanopithecus
(
9
, 
92
). The position of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
as a stem hominoid more derived than 
Proconsul
is relatively well supported (bootstrap 78%, Bremer index 2). When the analysis is repeated excluding all fossil taxa with large amounts of missing data (fig. S7), the position of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
as a stem hominoid more derived than 
Proconsul
is much better supported (bootstrap 100%, Bremer index 20); it is even more robust than the monophyly of crown hominoids (bootstrap 98%, Bremer index 11) and than the great-ape status of 
Pierolapithecus
and 
Hispanopithecus
(bootstrap 100%, Bremer index 13).
</p>
      <p>
Given that our analyses support 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
as a stem hominoid more derived than 
Proconsul
, the mosaic of primitive and derived features displayed by the former taxon is of utmost relevance for interpreting the evolution of several key features among catarrhine primates. Many authors agree that homoplasy has played an important role in hominoid postcranial evolution (
5
, 
9
, 
12
, 
92
), but 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
shows a mosaic of primitive and derived features both in the cranium and the postcranium. For the cranium, this is best illustrated by the short tubular (but incompletely ossified) external auditory meatus with a V-shaped end, which would imply the independent acquisition of a more completely ossified ectotympanic in cercopithecoids and hominoids. This has previously been posited by some authors (
20
), and it is suggested to some extent by the stem catarrhine 
Saadanius
(
22
), the stem Old World monkey 
Victoriapithecus
(
60
), and the stem ape 
Proconsul
(
97
); in these taxa, the ectotympanic, albeit slightly more developed, is still short, does not laterally exceed the postglenoid process, and lacks a completely closed terminal ventral tip (

). In contrast, several other cranial features of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
are derived toward the crown-hominoid condition, generally more closely resembling hylobatids than hominids. Some of the similarities with gibbons (e.g., short face with a distinct muzzle and anteriorly situated telescopic orbits) may be size-related to a large extent (
98
), but others (horizontal and anteriorly directed carotid canal) are otherwise only known in hylobatids. Coupled with the fact that 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
chronologically fits within the long ghost lineage of hylobatids, from their divergence from hominids at ~17 Ma (
1
) until their putative oldest record (
Yuanmoupithecus
) at 8 to 7 Ma (
10
, 
39
), these similarities raise the possibility that 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
might be a stem hylobatid. This hypothesis is not favored by our total (craniodental plus postcranial) evidence–based cladistic analyses, which support instead a stem hominoid status for 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
, mostly because of the lack of various crownhominoid postcranial synapomorphies. However, its hylobatid cranial features and small body size suggest that, at least in some respects, the last common ancestor of crown hominoids might have been more gibbon-like (or less great ape–like) than generally assumed (
6
, 
16
).
</p>
      <p>
Furthermore, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
supports the view that some small-bodied catarrhines played a more important role in the emergence of crown hominoids than has generally been assumed over the past decades. The postcranial evidence provided by Miocene great apes such as 
Pierolapithecus
and 
Sivapithecus
(
9
, 
92
, 
99
) indicates that the last common ancestor of crown hominoids must have been postcranially more primitive than it would be inferred to be exclusively on the basis of extant forms. This supports some degree of parallel evolution in the postcranium between extant hylobatids and hominids (
5
), although not to such a great extent as if 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
was interpreted as a crown hominoid. As a stem ape, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
cannot resolve whether many of the postcranial derived features shared by extant hylobatids and hominids are homologous (
6
) or homoplastic (
5
), although 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
does suggest that a suite of features in the humeroradial and wrist joints might be homolgous. In these anatomical regions, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
displays much more extensive postcranial synapomorphies of crown hominoids than those convergently displayed by atelids, including a diarthrodial radioulnar joint, an expanded ulnar head, an incipient ulnar fovea, a long and thin styloid process with reduced contact with the relatively small triquetrum, and a distally projecting hamulus on the hamate. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
also displays incipient suspensory adaptations, although, based on currently available evidence, it is not possible to conclusively ascertain whether these were inherited by the last common ancestor of crown hominoids (and later secondarily lost in some fossil great apes such as 
Sivapithecus
and 
Pierolapithecus
) or whether they merely represent an independent acquisition of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
’s.
</p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Conclusions</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
provides the first evidence of crownhominoid postcranial synapomorphies in a Miocene small-bodied catarrhine, thus demonstrating a greater diversity in postcranial morphology and positional behaviors than previously recognized among this paraphyletic assemblage of taxa. Three decades ago, the degree of parallel evolution required to evolve hylobatids from small-bodied catarrhines such as dendropithecids, albeit conceivable, was considered unlikely in light of the available evidence (
18
), because of the numerous parallelisms that would be required in crownhominoid (and even crown-catarrhine) features between hylobatids and hominids. Although the evidence provided by 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
reduces this morphological gap, this taxon still falls short of being supported as a hylobatid by our cladistic analyses, which strongly favor instead the monophyly of extant hominoids with all fossil smallbodied catarrhines excluded. However, unlike dendropithecids, which are currently interpreted as stem catarrhines (
21
) or hominoids more basal than 
Proconsul
(
22
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is unambiguously interpreted as more closely related to crown hominoids. Given its chronology and geographic location, as well as the retention of plesiomorphic dental and some postcranial features that resemble those of small-bodied catarrhines such as dendropithecids, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pliobates</tp:taxon-name>
is likely to be a latesurviving offshoot of a small African stem hominoid more closely related to crown hominoids than 
Proconsul
is. This has important implications for reconstructing the ancestral morphotype from which extant hominoids evolved: It suggests that some small-bodied catarrhines could have played a much more remarkable role in ape evolution than previously thought, and that the last common ancestor of crown hominoids was not necessarily great ape–like.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>REFERENCES AND NOTES</title>
         <p>
1. M. S. Springer 
et al
., Macroevolutionary dynamics and historical biogeography of primate diversification inferred from a species supermatrix. 
PLOS ONE7
, e49521 (2012). doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0049521; pmid: 23166696
</p>
         <p>
2. N. J. Stevens 
et al
., Palaeontological evidence for an Oligocene divergence between Old World monkeys and apes. 
Nature497
, 611–614 (2013). doi: 10.1038/nature12161; pmid: 23676680
</p>
         <p>3
. 
D. R. Begun
, in 
Handbook of Paleoanthropology
,
W. Henke
, 
I. Tattersall
, Eds. (
Springer, Heidelberg, Germany, ed
. 
2
, 
2015
), pp. 1261–1332.
</p>
         <p>
4. In the systematic scheme used here (
9
), hominoids are defined as including both the crown group (extant hominids and hylobatids, plus extinct taxa closely related to either) and the stem lineage (extinct taxa more closely related to crown hominoids than to Old World monkeys, but preceding the hylobatid-hominid divergence).
</p>
         <p>
5. 
S. G. Larson
, 
Parallel evolution in the hominoid trunk and forelimb
. 
Evol. Anthropol.6
, 
87–99
(
1998
). doi: 10.1002/ (SICI)1520-6505(1998)6:3&lt;87::AID-EVAN3&gt;3.0.CO;2-T
</p>
         <p>
6. 
D. Pilbeam
, 
Genetic and morphological records of the Hominoidea and hominid origins: A synthesis
. 
Mol. Phylogenet. Evol
.
5
, 
155–168
(
1996
). doi: 10.1006/ mpev.1996.0010; pmid: 8673283
</p>
         <p>
7. 
P. Andrews
, 
T. Harrison
, 

in 
Interpreting the Past: Essays on Human, Primate and Mammal Evolution in Honor of David Pilbeam
, D. Lieberman, R. Smith, J. Kelley, Eds

. (
Brill Academic Publishers, The Hague, Netherlands
, 
2005
), pp. 103–121.
</p>
         <p>
8. 
T. C. Rae
, 
Mosaic evolution in the origin of the Hominoidea
. 
Folia Primatol. (Basel)70
, 
125–135
(
1999
). doi: 10.1159/ 0 0 0 0 21685; pmid: 10394061
</p>
         <p>
9. 
D. M. Alba
, 
Fossil apes from the Vallès-Penedès Basin
. 
Evol. Anthropol.21
, 
254–269
(
2012
). 
doi: 10.1002/evan.21312;
pmid: 23280922
</p>
         <p>
10. T. Harrison, X. Ji, L. Zheng, Renewed investigations at the late Miocene hominoid locality of Leilao, Yunnan, China. 
Am.J. Phys
. 
Anthropol
. 
135
(suppl. 
46
), 113 (
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
11. 
J. G. Fleagle
, 
Primate Adaptation and Evolution
(
Academic Press, San Diego, CA, ed
. 
3
, 
2013
).
</p>
         <p>12
. 
C. Ward
, in 
Handbook of Paleoanthropology
, 
W. Henke
, 
I. Tattersall
, Eds., (
Springer, Heidelberg, Germany, ed
. 
2
, 
2015
), pp. 1011–1030.
</p>
         <p>13
. 
A. Keith
, 

Hunterian lecture’s on man’s posture: Its evolution and disorders. 
BMJ1
, 
451–454
(
1923
). doi: 10.1136/ bmj.1.3246.451; pmid: 20771052
</p>
         <p>
14. 
E. L. Simons
, 
J. Fleagle
, 
The history of extinct gibbon-like primates
. 
Gibbon Siamang2
, 
121–148
(
1973
).
</p>
         <p>
15. 
P. Andrews
, 
E. Simons
, 

A new Arican Miocene gibbon-like genus, 
Dendropithecus
(Hominoidea, Primates) with distinctive postcranial adaptations: Its significance to origin of Hylobatidae

. 
Folia Primatol. (Basel)28
, 
161–169
(
1977
). 
doi: 10.1159/000155807;
pmid: 914128
</p>
         <p>
16. 
N. M. Young
, 
A reassessment of living hominoid postcranial variability: Implications for ape evolution
. 
J. Hum. Evol.45
, 
441–464
(
2003
). 
doi: 10.1016/j.jhevol.2003.09.001
pmid: 14643673
</p>
         <p>
17. 
T. Harrison
, 
thesis
, 
University College London, London
(
1982
).
</p>
         <p>
18. 
J. G. Fleagle
, 

in 
The Lesser Apes: Evolutionary and Behavioral Biology
, H. Preuschoft, D. J. Chivers, W. Y. Brockelman, N. Creel, Eds

. (
Edinburgh Univ. Press, Edinburgh
, 
1984
), pp. 431–447.
</p>
         <p>
19. 
T. Harrison
, 
The phylogenetic relationships of the early catarrhine primates: A review of the current evidence
. 
J. Hum. Evol.16
, 
41–80
(
1987
). 
doi: 10.1016/0047-2484(87)90060-1</p>
         <p>20
. 
D. R. Begun
, in 
The Primate Fossil Record
, 
W. C. Hartwig
, Eds. (Cambridge Univ. Press, Cambridge, 
2002
), 
pp. 221–240
.
</p>
         <p>21
. 
T. Harrison
, in 
Cenozoic Mammals of Africa
, 
L. Werdelin
, 
W. J. Sanders
, Eds. (Univ. of California Press, Berkeley, CA, 
2010
), 
pp. 429–469
.
</p>
         <p>
22. I. S. Zalmout 
et al
., New Oligocene primate from Saudi Arabia and the divergence of apes and Old World monkeys. 
Nature466
, 360–364 (2010). doi: 10.1038/nature09094 pmid: 20631798
</p>
         <p>
23. The genus 
Proconsul
was recently split into two
</p>
         <p>
distinct genera (
100
), but throughout the paper, this genus name is used in a broad sense (including both 
Proconsul
s.s. and 
Ekembo
).
</p>
         <p>
24. The new names published here are nomenclaturally available according to the requirements of the amended 
International Code of Zoological Nomenclature
, including registration of the work in ZooBank (http://zoobank.org) with the following Life Science Identifier: urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:4A5EC1F1-29BD- 4925-8CC6-04AB083C61DA.
</p>
         <p>
25. D. M. Alba 
et al
., Los vertebrados fósiles del Abocador de Can Mata (els Hostalets de Pierola, l’Anoia, Cataluña), una sucesión de localidades del Aragoniense superior (MN6 y MN7+8) de la cuenca del Vallès-Penedès. Campañas 2002- 2003, 2004 y 2005. 
Estudios Geol.62
, 295–312 (2006). doi: 10.3989/egeol.0662127
</p>
         <p>
26. 
D. M. Alba
, 
I. Casanovas-Vilar
, 
J. M. Robles
, 
S. Moyà-Solà
, 
Parada 3. El Aragoniense superior y la transición con el Vallesiense: Can Mata y la exposición paleontológica de els Hostalets de Pierola
. 
Paleontol. Evol. Mem. Esp.6
, 
95–109
(
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
27. S. Moyà-Solà 
et al
., First partial face and upper dentition of the Middle Miocene hominoid 
Dryopithecus fontani
from Abocador de Can Mata (Vallès-Penedès Basin, Catalonia, NE Spain): Taxonomic and phylogenetic implications. 
Am
. 
J. Phys
. 
Anthropol
. 
139
, 
126–145
(
2009
). doi: 10.1002/ ajpa.20891; pmid: 19278017
</p>
         <p>28
. 
L. Cabrera
, 
E. Roca
, 
M. Garcés
, 
J. de Porta
, in 
Geología de España
, 
J. A. Vera
, Ed. (Sociedad Geológica de España–Instituto Geológico y Minero de España, Madrid, 
2004
), 
pp. 569–573
.
</p>
         <p>
29. 
J. M. de Gibert
, 
I. Casanovas-Vilar
, 
Contexto geológico del Mioceno de la cuenca del Vallès-Penedès
. 
Paleontol. Evol. Mem. Esp.6
, 
39–45
(
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
30. 
I. Casanovas-Vilar
, 
D. M. Alba
, 
J. M. Robles
, 
S. Moyà-Solà
, 
Registro paleontológico continental del Mioceno de la cuenca del Vallès-Penedès
. 
Paleontol.Evol. Mem. Esp.6
, 
55–80
(
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
31. 
I. Casanovas-Vilar
, 
D. M. Alba
, 
M. Garcés
, 
J. M. Robles
, 
S. Moyà-Solà
, 
Updated chronology for the Miocene hominoid radiation in Western Eurasia
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.108
, 
5554–5559
(
2011
). 
doi: 10.1073/pnas.1018562108</p>
         <p>pmid: 21436034</p>
         <p>
32. F. J. Hilgen 
et al.
, in 
The Geologic Time Scale 2012, Volume 2
, F. M. Gradstein, J. G. Ogg, M. D. Schmitz, G. M. Ogg, Eds. (Elsevier, Amsterdam, 2012), pp. 923–978.
</p>
         <p>
33. D. M. Alba 
et al
., A new species of 
Pliopithecus
Gervais, 1849 (Primates: Pliopithecidae) from the Middle Miocene (MN8) of Abocador de Can Mata (els Hostalets de Pierola, Catalonia, Spain). 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.141
, 52–75
</p>
         <p>
(
2010
). 
pmid
: 
19544577</p>
         <p>
34. 
T. Harrison
, 

A new species of 
Micropithecus
from the middle Miocene of Kenya

. 
J. Hum. Evol.18
, 
537–557
(
1989
). 
doi: 10.1016/0047-2484(89)90017-1</p>
         <p>
35. 
M. Pickford
, 
S. Musalizi
, 
B. Senut
, 
D. Gommery
, 
E. Musiime
, 

Small apes from the Early Miocene of Napak, Uganda. 
Geo.
- 
Pal. Uganda3
, 
1–111
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>
36. 
D. M. Alba
, 
S. Moyà-Solà
, 
A new pliopithecid genus (Primates: Pliopithecoidea) from Castell de Barberà (Vallès-Penedès Basin, Catalonia, Spain)
. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.147
, 
88–112
(
2012
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.21630;
pmid: 22101732
</p>
         <p>37. E. L. Simons, E. R. Seiffert, T. M. Ryan, Y. Attia, A remarkable female cranium of the early Oligocene anthropoid</p>
         <p>Aegyptopithecus zeuxis
(Catarrhini, Propliopithecidae)

. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.104
, 
8731–8736
(
2007
). doi: 10.1073/ pnas.0703129104; pmid: 17517628
</p>
         <p>38. H. Zapfe, Die Primatenfunde aus der miozänen Spaltenfüllung von Neudorf an der March (Děvínská Nová Ves),</p>
         <p>
Tschechoslowakei. 
Schweiz. Paläontol
. 
Abh
. 
78
, 
1–293
(
1961
).
</p>
         <p>
39. 
Y. Pan
, 

in Lufengpithecus hudiensis 
Site
, G. Qi, W. Dong, Eds

. (
Science Press, Beijing
, 
2006
). pp. 131–148.
</p>
         <p>
40. 
L. Ginsburg
, 
Le Pliopithèque des faluns Helvétiens de la Touraine et de l’Anjou
. 
Colloq. Int. CNRS218
, 
877–886
(
1975
).
</p>
         <p>
41. 
R. F. Kay
, 
J. G. Fleagle
, 
E. L. Simons
, 
A revision of the Oligocene apes from the Fayum Province
, 

Egypt. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.55
, 
293–322
(
1981
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.1330550305</p>
         <p>
42. 
R. E. F. Leakey
, 
M. G. Leakey
, 
A new Miocene small-bodied ape from Kenya
. 
J. Hum. Evol.16
, 
369–387
(
1987
). 
doi: 10.1016/0047-2484(87)90067-4</p>
         <p>
43. 
Y. Pan
, 
D. M. Waddle
, 
J. G. Fleagle
, 

Sexual dimorphism in 
Laccopithecus robustus
, a late Miocene hominoid from China

. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.79
, 
137–158
(
1989
). doi: 10.1002/ ajpa.1330790203; pmid: 2742002
</p>
         <p>
44. 
T. Harrison
, 
E. Delson
, 
G. Jian
, 

A new species of 
Pliopithecus
from the middle Miocene of China and its implications for early catarrhine zoogeography

. 
J. Hum. Evol.21
, 
329–361
(
1991
). 
doi: 10.1016/0047-2484(91)90112-9</p>
         <p>
45. 
T. Harrison
, 
Y. Gu
, 
Taxonomy and phylogenetic relationships of early Miocene catarrhines from Sihong
, 

China. 
J. Hum. Evol.37
, 
225–277
(
1999
). 
doi: 10.1006/jhev.1999.0310;
pmid: 10444352
</p>
         <p>
46. 
M. Pickford
, 
Y. Kunimatsu
, 

Catarrhines from the Middle Miocene (ca. 14.5 Ma) of Kipsaraman, Tugen Hills, Kenya. 
Anthropol. Sci.113
, 189–224 (2005)

. 
doi: 10.1537/ase.113.189
47. P. D. Gingerich, B. H. Smith, K. Rosenberg, Allometric scaling in the dentition of primates and prediction of body weight from tooth size in fossils. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.58
, 
81–100
(
1982
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.1330580110;
pmid: 7124918
</p>
         <p>
48. 
C. B. Ruff
, 
Long bone articular and diaphyseal structure in Old World monkeys and apes
. 

II: Estimation of body mass. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.120
, 
16–37
(
2003
). doi: 10.1002/ ajpa.10118; pmid: 12489135
</p>
         <p>
49. 
C. B. Ruff
, 
Long bone articular and diaphyseal structure in old world monkeys and apes. I: Locomotor effects
. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.119
, 
305–342
(
2002
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.10117;
pmid: 12448016
</p>
         <p>
50. 
S. G. Larson
, 
Estimating humeral torsion on incomplete fossil anthropoid humeri
. 
J. Hum. Evol.31
, 
239–257
(
1996
). 
doi: 10.1006/jhev.1996.0059</p>
         <p>
51. 
E. E. Sarmiento
, 
thesis, New York University
, 
New York
(
1985
).
</p>
         <p>
52. 
L. C. Aiello
, 
The allometry of primate body proportions
. 
Symp. Zool. Soc. London48
, 
331–358
(
1981
).
</p>
         <p>
53. 
R. S. Jabbour
, 
thesis, The City University of New York
, 
New York
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
54. 
R. J. Smith
, 
W. L. Jungers
, 
Body mass in comparative primatology
. 
J. Hum. Evol.32
, 
523–559
(
1997
). doi: 10.1006/ jhev.1996.0122; pmid: 9210017
</p>
         <p>
55. 
T. L. Kivell
, 
A comparative analysis of the hominin triquetrum (SKX 3498) from Swartkrans
, 

South Africa. 
S. Afr. J. Sci.107
, 
515
(
2011
). 
doi: 10.4102/sajs.v107i5/6.515</p>
         <p>
56. 
T. L. Kivell
, 
D. R. Begun
, 
New primate carpal bones from Rudabánya (late Miocene, Hungary): Taxonomic and functional implications
. 
J. Hum. Evol.57
, 
697–709
(
2009
). 
doi: 10.1016/j.jhevol.2009.05.011;
pmid: 19709719
</p>
         <p>
57. 
R. D. Martin
, 
Primate Origins and Evolution. A Phylogenetic Reconstruction
(
Princeton Univ. Press, Princeton, NJ
, 
1990
).
</p>
         <p>
58. 
D. M. Alba
, 
Cognitive inferences in fossil apes (Primates, Hominoidea): Does encephalization reflect intelligence
? 
J. Anthropol. Sci.88
, 
11–48
(
2010
). pmid: 20834049
</p>
         <p>
59. 
M. F. Williams
, 
Primate encephalization and intelligence
. 
Med. Hypotheses58
, 
284–290
(
2002
). doi: 10.1054/
</p>
         <p>mehy.2001.1516; pmid: 12027521</p>
         <p>
60. 
B. R. Benefit
, 
M. L. McCrossin
, 
Earliest known Old World monkey skull
. 
Nature388
, 
368–371
(
1997
). doi: 10.1038/ 41078; pmid: 9237753
</p>
         <p>
61. 
D. R. Begun
, 
L. Kordos
, 

in 
The Evolution of Thought. Evolutionary Origins of Great Ape Intelligence
, A.E. Russon, D. R. Begun, Eds

. (
Cambridge Univ. Press, Cambridge
, 
2004
), pp. 260–279.
</p>
         <p>
62. 
E. L. Simons
, 

New endocasts of 
Aegyptopithecus:
Oldest wellpreserved record of the brain in Anthropoidea

. 
Am. J. Sci.293
, 
383–390
(
1993
). 
doi: 10.2475/ajs.293.A.383</p>
         <p>
63. 
M. F.Teaford
, 
A review of dental microwear and diet in modern mammals
. 
Scanning Microsc
.
2
, 
1149–1166
(
1988
). pmid: 3041572
</p>
         <p>
64. 
P. S. Ungar
, 

Dental evidence for the diets of fossil primates from Rudabánya northeastern Hungary with comments on extant primate analogs and “noncompetitive” sympatry. 
Palaeontogr
. 
Ital
. 
90
, 
97–111
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
65. 
P. S. Ungar
, 

in 
Reconstructing Behavior in the Primate Fossil Record
, J. M. Plavcan, R. F. Kay, W. L. Jungers, C. P. Van Schaik, Eds

. (
Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers, New York
, 
2002
), pp. 261–296.
</p>
         <p>
66. 
D.DeMiguel
, 
D.M.Alba
, 
S.Moyà-Solà
, 

European pliopithecid diets revised in the light of dental microwear in 
Pliopithecus canmatensis
and 
Barberapithecus huerzeleri
. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.151
, 
573–582
(
2013
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.22299;
pmid: 23868170
</p>
         <p>
67. 
P. S. Ungar
, 
Dental microwear of European Miocene catarrhines: Evidence for diets and tooth use
. 
J. Hum. Evol.31
, 
335–366
(
1996
). 
doi: 10.1006/jhev.1996.0065</p>
         <p>
68. 
D. DeMiguel
, 
D. M. Alba
, 
S. Moyà-Solà
, 
Dietary specialization during the evolution of Western Eurasian hominoids and the extinction of European Great Apes
. 
PLOS ONE9
, e 
97442
(
2014
). 
doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0097442;
pmid: 24848272
</p>
         <p>
69. 
M. F. Teaford
, 

Molar microwear and diet in the genus 
Cebus
. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.66
, 
363–370
(
1985
). doi: 10.1002/ ajpa.1330660403; pmid: 3993762
</p>
         <p>70. S. El-Zaatari, F. E. Grine, M. F. Teaford, H. F. Smith, Molar microwear and dietary reconstructions of fossil</p>
         <p>Cercopithecoidea from the Plio-Pleistocene deposits of South Africa
. 
J. Hum
. 
Evol
.
49
, 
180–205
(
2005
). 
doi: 10.1016/j.
jhevol.2005.03.005; pmid: 15964607
</p>
         <p>
71. 
T. King
, 
L. C. Aiello
, 
P. Andrews
, 

Dental microwear of 
Griphopithecus alpani
. 
J. Hum. Evol.36
, 
3–31
(
1999
). 
doi: 10.1006/jhev.1998.0258;
pmid: 9924132
</p>
         <p>
72. 
D. Swofford
, 
PAUP
* 
4.0
(
Sinauer Associates, Sunderland, MA
, 
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
73. 
D. R. Begun
, 
C. V. Ward
, 
M. D. Rose
, 

in 
Function, Phylogeny and Fossils: Miocene Hominoid Evolution and Adaptation
, D. R. Begun, C. V. Ward, M. D. Rose, Eds

. (
Plenum Press, New York
, 
1997
), pp. 389–415.
</p>
         <p>
74. 
D. W. Cameron
, 
A revised systematic scheme for the Eurasian Miocene fossil Hominidae
. 
J. Hum. Evol.33
, 
449–477
(
1997
). 
doi: 10.1006/jhev.1997.0145;
pmid: 9361253
</p>
         <p>
75. 
J. A. Finarelli
, 
W. C. Clyde
, 
Reassessing hominoid phylogeny: Evaluating congruence in the morphological and temporal data
. 
Paleobiology30
, 
614–651
(
2004
). 
doi: 10.1666/0094-
8373(2004)030&lt;0614:RHPECI&gt;2.0.CO;2
</p>
         <p>
76. 
J. B. Rossie
, 
L. MacLatchy
, 
A new pliopithecoid genus from the early Miocene of Uganda
. 
J. Hum. Evol.50
, 
568–586
(
2006
). 
doi: 10.1016/j.jhevol.2005.12.007;
pmid: 16472841
</p>
         <p>
77. 
D. M. Alba
, 
S. Moyà-Solà
, 
J. M. Robles
, 
J. Galindo
, 
Brief communication: The oldest pliopithecid record in the Iberian Peninsula based on new material from the Vallès-Penedès Basin
. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.147
, 
135–140
(
2012
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.21631;
pmid: 22170401
</p>
         <p>
78. D. M. Alba, S. Moyà-Solà, New fossil remains of 
Pliopithecus canmatensis
from Abocador de Can Mata, and their
</p>
         <p>
implications for the taxonomic validity and phylogenetic position of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epipliopithecus</tp:taxon-name>
(Primates, Pliopithecidae). 
Am
. 
J. Phys
. 
Anthropol
. 
153
(suppl. 
58
), 64 (
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
79. 
J. G. Fleagle
, 
E. L. Simons
, 
Micropithecus clarki
, a small ape from the Miocene of Uganda

. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.49
, 
427–440
(
1978
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.1330490402;
pmid: 367175
</p>
         <p>
80. 
J. B. Rossie
, 
The phylogenetic significance of anthropoid paranasal sinuses
. 
Anat. Rec.291
, 
1485–1498
(
2008
). 
doi: 10.1002/ar.20781;
pmid: 18951494
</p>
         <p>
81. 
M. D. Rose
, 

in 
Postcranial Adaptation in Nonhuman Primates
, 
D. L. Gebo, Ed. (Northern Illinois Univ. Press, DeKalb, IL
, 
1993
), pp. 252–272.
</p>
         <p>
82. 
M. D. Rose
, 
M. G. Leakey
, 
R. E. F. Leakey
, 
A. C. Walker
, 

Postcranial specimens of 
Simiolus enjiessi
and other primitive catarrhines from the early Miocene of Lake Turkana

, 

Kenya. 
J. Hum. Evol.22
, 
171–237
(
1992
). 
doi: 10.1016/S0047-2484(05)80006-5</p>
         <p>
83. 
M. D. Rose
, 

in 
Postcranial Adaptation in Nonhuman Primates
, 
D. L. Gebo, Ed. (Northern Illinois Univ. Press, DeKalb, IL
, 
1993
), pp. 70–95.
</p>
         <p>
84. 
M. D. Rose
, 
Quadrupedalism in some Miocene catarrhines
. 
J. Hum. Evol.26
, 
387–411
(
1994
). 
doi: 10.1006/jhev.1994.1025</p>
         <p>
85. 
O. J. Lewis
, 
The hominoid wrist joint
. 
Am. J.Phys. Anthropol.30
, 
251–267
(
1969
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.1330300211;
pmid: 5772045
</p>
         <p>
86. 
O. J. Lewis
, 
The contrasting morphology found in the wrist joints of semibrachiating monkeys and brachiating apes
. 
Folia Primatol. (Basel)16
, 
248–256
(
1971
). doi: 10.1159/
</p>
         <p>0 0 0 155406; pmid: 5004213</p>
         <p>
87. 
E. E. Sarmiento
, 
Anatomy of the hominoid wrist joint: Its evolutionary and functional implications
. 
Int. J. Primatol.9
, 
281–345
(
1988
). 
doi: 10.1007/BF02737381</p>
         <p>
88. 
G. Daver
, 
M. Nakatsukasa
, 
Proconsul heseloni
distal radial and ulnar epiphyses from the Kaswanga Primate Site, Rusinga Island

, 

Kenya. 
J. Hum. Evol.80
, 
17–33
(
2015
). doi: 10.1016/ j.jhevol.2014.06.021; pmid: 25577018
</p>
         <p>
89. 
D. M. Alba
, 
S. Moyà-Solà
, 
S. Almécija
, 
A partial hominoid humerus from the middle miocene of Castell de Barberà (Vallès- Penedès Basin, Catalonia, Spain)
. 
Am. J.Phys. Anthropol.144
, 
365–381
(
2011
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.21417;
pmid: 21302264
</p>
         <p>
90. 
J. B. Rossie
, 
M. Gutierrez
, 
E. Goble
, 

Fossil forelimbs of 
Simiolus
from Moruorot

, 

Kenya. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.147
, 
252
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
91. 
K. C. Beard
, 
M. F. Teaford
, 
A. Walker
, 

New wrist bones of 
Proconsul africanus
and 
P. nyanzae
from Rusinga Island

, 

Kenya. 
Folia Primatol. (Basel)47
, 
97–118
(
1986
).
</p>
         <p>doi: 10.1159/000156268; pmid: 3108122</p>
         <p>
92. 
S. Moyà-Solà
, 
M. Köhler
, 
D. M. Alba
, 
I. Casanovas-Vilar
, 
J. Galindo
, 
Pierolapithecus catalaunicus
, a new Middle Miocene great ape from Spain

. 
Science306
, 
1339–1344
(
2004
). 
doi: 10.1126/science.1103094;
pmid: 15550663
</p>
         <p>
93. 
D. Youlatos
, 
Atelines, apes and wrist joints
. 
Folia Primatol. (Basel)67
, 
193–198
(
1996
). 
doi: 10.1159/000157222;
pmid: 9159919 94. M. D. Rose, in 
Function, Phylogeny and Fossils: Miocene Hominoid Evolution and Adaptation
, D. R. Begun, C. V. Ward, M. D. Rose, Eds. (Plenum Press, New York, 1997), pp. 79–100.
</p>
         <p>
95. 
M. Cartmill
, 
K. Milton
, 
The lorisiform wrist joint and the evolution of “brachiating” adaptations in the Hominoidea
. 
Am. J. Phys. Anthropol.47
, 
249–272
(
1977
). 
doi: 10.1002/ajpa.1330470206;
pmid: 410307
</p>
         <p>
96. 
E. E. Sarmiento
, 
Cautious climbing and folivory: A model of hominoid differentiation
. 
Hum. Evol.10
, 
289–321
(
1995
). 
doi: 10.1007/BF02438967</p>
         <p>
97. 
J. R. Napier
, 
P. R. David
, 

The fore-limb skeleton and associated remains of 

Proconsul 
<tp:taxon-name>africanus</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Foss. Mamm.Afr.16
, 
1–69
(
1959
).
</p>
         <p>98
. 
B. T. Shea
, in 
A Companion to Paleoanthropology
, 
D. R. Begun
, Ed. (Blackwell Publishing, Chichester, UK, 
2013
), 
pp. 119–135
.
</p>
         <p>
99. M. E. Morgan 
et al
., A partial hominoid innominate from the Miocene of Pakistan: Description and preliminary analyses. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.112
, 82–87 (2015). doi: 10.1073/
</p>
         <p>pnas.1420275111; pmid: 25489095</p>
         <p>
100. 
K. P. McNulty
, 
D. R. Begun
, 
J. Kelley
, 
F. K. Manthi
, 
E. N. Mbua
, 

A systematic revision of 
Proconsul
with the description of a new genus of early Miocene hominoid

. 
J. Hum. Evol.84
, 
42–61
(
2015
). 
doi: 10.1016/j.jhevol.2015.03.009;
pmid: 25962549
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</p>
      <p>This work has been supported by the Spanish Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad (projects CGL2014-54373-P,</p>
      <p>CGL2011-27343, and CGL0211-28681; contracts RYC-2009-04533 to D.M.A. and JCI-2011-11697 to D.DM.; and grant BES-2009- 0 20612 to M.P.R.), the Spanish Ministerio de Educación (grant AP2010-4579 to M.P.), the Generalitat de Catalunya (research groups 2014 SGR 416 GRC and 2014/100609; and grant 2011 BE-DGR 0 0 310 to D.M.A.),NSF (grant 1316947 to S.A.), and the AAPA Professional Development Grant (to S.A.). We further acknowledge the support of the Servei d’Arqueologia i Paleontologia of the</p>
      <p>Generalitat de Catalunya. Fieldwork was defrayed by CESPA Gestión de Residuos. The authors thank S. Larson for the</p>
      <p>estimation of humeral torsion; J. Arias-Martorell for discussion on the fossil material; M. Palmero for scientific artwork; E. Delson, D. Pilbeam, L. Costeur, U. Gölich, and E. Mbua for access to casts and original fossil specimens; I. Sucarrats for assistance in data gathering; E. Sarmiento and T. Kivell for sharing measurements; the staff of the Preparation Division of the ICP for the preparation of the specimens; J. Thostenson and M. Hill for assistance with using the Microscopy and Imaging Facility of the American</p>
      <p>Museum of Natural History; S. Llàcer for assistance in processing the movie; S. Grau for philological advice; M. Köhler for comments on the manuscript; and three anonymous reviewers for helpful and constructive suggestions. We are also grateful to the staff of the following museums for access to comparative specimens:</p>
      <p>American Museum of Natural History, New York; Museum of Comparative Zoology, Harvard; Kenyan National Museums;</p>
      <p>Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris; Naturhistorisches Museum Wien; and Naturhistorisches Museum Basel. Author contributions were as follows: D.M.A. and S.M.-S. designed the study and wrote the paper with input from other authors; D.M.A., S.A., M.P.R., M.P., and S.M.-S. performed the descriptions and comparisons; J.F., M.P.R., and S.M.-S. made the virtual cranial reconstruction; D.DM. carried out the microwear analyses; J.M.R. directed the fieldwork and performed the stratigraphic</p>
      <p>correlations; D.M.A., S.A., M.P.R., M.P., and S.M.-S. assembled the cladistic data matrix; and D.M.A. and J.F. performed the</p>
      <p>phylogenetic analyses. All authors approved the final manuscript and declare that all data reported here are fully and freely available from the date of publication. The new fossils described in this paper are curated at the ICP with catalog number IPS58443. Supporting data for this paper are presented in the supplementary materials.</p>
      <p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</p>
      <p>www.sciencemag.org/content/350/6260/aab2625/suppl/DC1 Figs. S1 to S7</p>
      <p>Tables S1 to S15</p>
      <p>Movie S1</p>
      <p>1 April 2015; accepted 21 September 2015 10.1126/science.aab2625</p>
      <p>2016
, 
25May on / org
. 
sciencemag. science //: http from Downloaded</p>
      <p>Miocene small-bodied ape from Eurasia sheds light on hominoid evolution</p>
      <p>
David M. Alba, 
<tp:taxon-name>Sergio Almécija, Daniel DeMiguel, Josep Fortuny, Miriam Pérez</tp:taxon-name>
de los Ríos, Marta Pina, Josep M. Robles and Salvador Moyà-Solà (October 29, 2015)
</p>
      <p>Science350
(6260),. [doi: 10.1126/science.aab2625]
</p>
      <p>Editor's Summary</p>
      <p>Meet your gibbon cousin</p>
      <p>
Apes are divided into two groups: larger-bodied apes, or hominoids, such as humans, chimps, and gorillas; and smaller-bodied hylobatids, such as gibbons. These two lineages are thought to have diverged rather cleanly, sharing few similarities after the emergence of crown hominoids. Alba 
et al.
describe a new ape from the Miocene era that contains characteristics from both hominoids and small-bodied apes (see the Perspective by Benefit and McCrossin). Thus, early small-bodied apes may have contributed more to the evolution of the hominoid lineage than previously assumed.
</p>
      <p>Science
, this issue p. 10.1126/science.aab2625; see also p. 515
</p>
      <p>This copy is for your personal, non-commercial use only.</p>
      <p>Article Tools</p>
      <p>Permissions</p>
      <p>Visit the online version of this article to access the personalization and article tools:</p>
      <p>http://science.sciencemag.org/content/350/6260/aab2625</p>
      <p>
Obtain information about reproducing this article: http://www.sciencemag.org/about/permissions.dtl 
Science
(print ISSN 0036-8075; online ISSN 1095-9203) is published weekly, except the last week in December, by the American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1200 New York
</p>
      <p>Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20005. Copyright 2016 by the American Association for the</p>
      <p>
Advancement of Science; all rights reserved. The title 
Science
is a registered trademark of AAAS.
</p>
      <p>2016
, 25 May on / org. 
sciencemag. science //: http from Downloaded</p>
   </body>
</article>
