<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1126/science.abc1490</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Manta-like planktivorous sharks in Late Cretaceous oceans</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>Supplementary Materials for</p>
         <p>Manta-like planktivorous sharks in Late Cretaceous oceans</p>
         <p>Romain Vullo
*, 
Eberhard Frey
, 
Christina Ifrim
, 
Margarito A. González González
, 
Eva S. Stinnesbeck
, 
Wolfgang Stinnesbeck</p>
         <p>*Corresponding author. Email: romain.vullo@univ-rennes1.fr</p>
         <p>
Published 19 March 
2021
, 
Science371
, 1253 (2021) DOI: 
10.1126/science.abc1490</p>
         <p>This PDF file includes:</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <p>Materials and Methods</p>
         <p>Supplementary Text</p>
         <p>
to S11
</p>
         <p>Tables S1
to S6
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <p>References</p>
         <p>Other Supplementary Material for this manuscript includes the following:</p>
         <p>(available at science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6535/1253/suppl/DC1)</p>
         <p>MDAR Reproducibility Checklist (.pdf)</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Materials and Methods</title>
         <p>Authenticity and provenance of the specimen</p>
         <p>The fossil shark specimen described here was discovered in 2012 in situ in the Vallecillo quarry area (Nuevo León State, northeastern Mexico) by an unknown quarryman, then secured, collected and prepared by one of us (M.A.G.G.). Finally, Mauricio Fernandez Garza (San Pedro Garza García) purchased the specimen in order to assign it an Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia (INAH) registration number and to house and display it in a new public museum (Museo La Milarca in San Pedro Garza García MMSP, Nuevo León State, Mexico; scheduled opening in 2021), where it will be accessible upon request. All of us intensively and thoroughly checked the specimen and the limestone surface by direct investigation with a hand lens (e.g., to look for teeth) and macrophotography; therefore, we can formally state that the specimen is 1) authentic and not a composite fossil, and 2) originates from one of the Vallecillo quarries located in the western part of the limestone exploitation area.</p>
         <p>The Vallecillo plattenkalk and stratigraphic position of the specimen</p>
         <p>
Uppermost Cenomanian to basal middle Turonian (lower Upper Cretaceous) strata are exposed in the Vallecillo quarry area. The holotype and only known specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnamilarcae</tp:taxon-name>
(INAH 2544 P.F.17) comes from the Vallecillo Member of the Agua Nueva Formation, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudaspidoceras flexuosum</tp:taxon-name>
Zone, lower Turonian (

) (
32
). The stratigraphic position of the specimen is indicated by the presence of the same slab of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudaspidoceras pseudonodosoides</tp:taxon-name>
(

), an ammonite species which occurs only in the middle -upper 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudaspidocerasflexuosum</tp:taxon-name>
Zone at Vallecillo (
33
).
</p>
         <p>
At Vallecillo, lower Turonian platy limestone (plattenkalk) has yielded many other open marine vertebrates, including elasmobranchs (
<tp:taxon-name>Ptychodus</tp:taxon-name>
sp., 
<tp:taxon-name>Cretoxyrhina mantelli</tp:taxon-name>
), actinopterygians (
<tp:taxon-name>Araripichthys</tp:taxon-name>
sp., 
<tp:taxon-name>Tselfatia formosa</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Vallecillichthys multivertebratum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Robertichthys riograndensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhynchodercetis regio</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pachycormidae</tp:taxon-name>
indet., 
<tp:taxon-name>Pachyrhizodontidae</tp:taxon-name>
indet.), indeterminate sea turtles, plesiosaurs (cf. 
<tp:taxon-name>Polycotylodon</tp:taxon-name>
sp., 
<tp:taxon-name>Mauriciosaurus fernandezi</tp:taxon-name>
) and aigialosaurs (
<tp:taxon-name>Vallecillosaurus donrobertoi</tp:taxon-name>
) (
32
, 
34
- 
36
). Many of these fossils show exquisite soft tissue preservation. For further information on the geological, paleontological and paleoecological setting of the Vallecillo Lagerstätte, see (
32
- 
34
, 
37
, 
38
).
</p>
         <p>Taphonomy</p>
         <p>
Several organisms, including the ammonite 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudaspidoceras pseudonodosoides</tp:taxon-name>
and various actinopterygian fishes (
<tp:taxon-name>Paranursallia gutturosa</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Goulmimichthys roberti</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhynchodercetis regio</tp:taxon-name>
), are preserved on the slab along with the holotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnamilarcae</tp:taxon-name>
(

). Specimen INAH 2544 P.F.17 shows some disarticulation of skeletal elements, notably jaw and pectoral girdle elements. Such moderate disarticulation is common at Vallecillo and mostly related to gas release during the decay process. No teeth can be observed in INAH 2544 P.F.17, possibly due to rapid post-mortem disarticulation and scattering affecting the dentition. Unlike in 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
, the dentitions can be observed in the few articulated specimens of other elasmobranch taxa (i.e., 
<tp:taxon-name>Ptychodus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cretoxyrhina</tp:taxon-name>
) found at Vallecillo; however, these dentitions, preserved in slight to moderate disarticulation, consist of small to rather large teeth (~5 to 25 mm in maximum dimension). This taphonomic observation supports the hypothesis that 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
had a dentition with very small (&lt;5 mm) dental elements that may have been winnowed.
</p>
         <p>
Vallecillo vertebrate fossils show all stages of decay from complete specimens with skin shadow to isolated primary fragments. The loss or finding of isolated body parts like the tail and other fins, or elements of the skull, is explained by a failure of mechanically weak articulations due to progressive decay, because body parts are missing as a whole, without bite marks or traces of violent disruption. Slight dislocation of ribs is most plausibly explained by the disruption of the swim bladder or escape of decay gas from the body cavity, and not from currents or scavengers. Most missing body parts were lost during post-mortem drifting. There is no evidence for scavenger activities at the sea floor. Some carcasses sank to the sea bottom prior to decay, and disintegrated there out of the reach of other animals. Bite marks or broken bones were not identified among the Vallecillo vertebrate fossils, suggesting that scavenging upon carcasses at the sea-floor was uncommon or absent (
32
, 
34
, 
39
). The absence of scavengers and benthic life, with the exception of inoceramid bivalves, is explained by the anoxic conditions at the Vallecillo sea floor due to persistence of Oceanic Anoxic Event 2 (
33
, 
34
, 
38
). Apparently, carcasses were buried outside the reach of scavengers within the oxygen minimum zone.
</p>
         <p>Comparison with modern neoselachians</p>
         <p>
The measurement data for the extant species (
Tables S1
and S 
2
) used to assess the ecomorphotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
were assembled from the literature (
17
, 
40
- 
50
). We followed Sternes and Shimadaʾs (
51
) strategy by using illustrations of reference books (i.e., FAO publications, authored by experts of international renown) to determine some morphometric measurements usually not provided in the literature and thus not available for all species. Interestingly, Sternes and Shimada (
51
) demonstrated the high degree of similarity between the book illustrations and actual shark samples, thus showing that such drawings can be reliably used for interspecific morphometric analyses. For each shark species included in the present analysis, illustrations in lateral and ventral views allowed to assess body proportions and to calculate the precaudal length (PCL), caudal fin length (CFL) and pectoral fin span (PFS) on the basis of the known maximum total length (TL). For each batoid species (except rhinopristiform species) included in the present analysis, we used either the known maximum disc width (DW, which corresponds to the PFS of sharks and rhinopristiform batoids) to calculate the disc length (DL), or the known maximum TL to calculate the disc length and disc width (using illustrations in dorsal view). In addition to the measurements of specimen 
INAH
2544 P.F.17, hypothetical measurements inferred from a 250 cm hypothetical maximum TL were used for 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
. All measurements were log 
10
-transformed in order to improve normality and homogeneity of variance. All analyses described below were performed using PAleontological STatistics (PAST software, version 4.04) (
52
).
</p>
         <p>
In a first analysis, we compared 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
to 26 modern shark species belonging to the four specialized pelagic ecomorphotypes (i.e., bathic, microceanic, macroceanic, and tachypelagic) and to the specialized benthic ecomorphotype characterized by enlarged pectoral fins (i.e., squatinobenthic) (
1
) (
Table S1
). For each ecomorphotype, we selected several species representative of the size range and body proportions of the category. As a multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) revealed significant differences in the multivariate means of the five ecomorphotypesconsideredtogether (Pillaiʾs trace = 1.826, 
F12, 63
= 8.169, 
p
&lt;0.0001) andin pairs (
Table S3
), a linear discriminant analysis (LDA) was performed to compare the body proportions of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
to those of modern sharks and to determine whether 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
falls into any of the ecomorphotypes. This method maximizes the separation between groups while minimizing the within-group variance. Here, the LDA matrix consists of three quantitative variables (PCL, CFL and PFS, all log 
10
-transformed) and one qualitative variable (ecomorphotype category, here used as grouping variable) scored for 26 modern shark species (assigned to five given groups) plus 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
(with no given group). As the ecomorphotype of the latter is unknown, a "?" was scored in the group column; thus, 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
was not included in the discriminant analysis itself, but was classified.
</p>
         <p>
In a second analysis, 27 modern batoid species belonging to the three main ecomorphotypes (i.e., aquilopelagic, rajobenthic, and rhinobenthic) (
1
) (
Table S2
) were added to the previous data set. The taxonomy and maximum size of some species were updated following the 2016 book "Rays of the World" (
53
). As the slender tails (short to extremely long, sometimes whiplike with no caudal fin) of the batoids belonging to the rajobenthic and aquilopelagic ecomorphotypes cannot be compared with the caudal fins of sharks, the variable "CFL" was removed from this analysis. For each of the three added ecomorphotypes, we selected several species representative of the size range and body proportions of the category. As a multivariate analysis of variance (MANOVA) revealed significant differences in the multivariate means of the eight ecomorphotypes consideredtogether (Pillaiʾs trace = 1.537, 
F14, 90
= 21.32, 
p
&lt;0.0001) and in pairs (
Table S4
), a linear discriminant analysis (LDA) was performed to compare the body proportions of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
to those of modern neoselachians and to determine whether 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
falls into any of the ecomorphotypes. Here, the LDA matrix consists of two quantitative variables (PCL or DL, and PFS or DW, all log 
10
-transformed) and one qualitative variable (ecomorphotype category, here used as grouping variable) scored for 53 modern neoselachian species (26 sharks and 27 batoids assigned to eight given groups) plus 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
(with no given group). As the ecomorphotype of the latter is unknown, a "?" was scored in the group column; thus, 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
was not included in the discriminant analysis itself, but was classified.
</p>
         <p>Supplementary Text</p>
         <p>Systematic paleontology</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Chondrichthyes Huxley, 1880</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Elasmobranchii Bonaparte, 1838</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Neoselachii Compagno, 1977</p>
         <p>Selachimorpha Nelson, 1984</p>
         <p>
? 
<tp:taxon-name>Lamniformes Berg, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">fam. nov.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudaspidoceras flexuosum</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cretomanta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Platylithophycus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cretomanta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Megachasmidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Odontaspididae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Carcharhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Squaliformes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Megachasma</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lamniformes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinus maximus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Megachasma pelagios</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Megachasma</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Megachasma</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rhinopteridae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Myliobatidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Mobulidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rhincodontidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Megachasmidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Mobulidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Platylithophycus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>A.milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Gymnura</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rhina ancylostoma</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>R. ancylostoma</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Manta-like planktivorous sharks in Late Cretaceous oceans</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1126/science.abc1490</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8E483A0EFFAF3F05FA62FFB1B636FFFF</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abc1490</pub-id>
               <source>Science</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. et sp. nov</tp:taxon-status>Etymology</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>
Generic name combines ʿ 
Aquila
ʾ (
Latin
, eagle), and the shark genus name ʿ 
Lamna
ʾ, in reference to the wing-shaped pectoral fins and aquilopelagic ecomorphotype of this probable lamniform. Specific epithet refers to the Museo La Milarca (San Pedro Garza García, 
Nuevo León State
, 
Mexico
), where the 
holotype
is housed and exhibited. Proposed vernacular name: eagle shark.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Holotype
and only known specimen
<tp:material-citation>
Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia (
INAH
) 
2544 P.
F.17

, an articulated and nearly complete skeleton with associated soft tissue (

and 

and 

to S6)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Locality and horizon</p>
            <p>
Vallecillo quarry area, 
Nuevo León State
, 
Mexico
(

26.655° 
N
, 

100.044° 
W
); Vallecillo Member of the Agua Nueva Formation, middle -upper 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudaspidoceras flexuosum</tp:taxon-name>
Zone, lower Turonian, Upper Cretaceous (

) (
32
). This stratigraphic level is ca. 93 million years in age.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis of family, genus and species</p>
            <p>Medium-sized neoselachian shark that differs from all other selachimorphs in having hypertrophied, scythe-shaped plesodic pectoral fins whose span exceeds the total length of the animal. High number (~70) of anteriorly directed pectoral radials. Head short and broad, with wide and near-terminal mouth. Caudal fin markedly heterocercal. Caudal fin skeleton showing a high hypochordal ray angle (i.e., ventrally directed hypochordal rays). Caudal tip slender with no (or strongly reduced?) terminal lobe. Squamation strongly reduced (or completely absent?).</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
Remark on 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
The family 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
type
and only known genus: 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
) possibly includes the enigmatic, poorly known Late Cretaceous genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Cretomanta</tp:taxon-name>
(
24
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Platylithophycus</tp:taxon-name>
(
27
). Systematic and paleoecological assumptions combined with stratigraphic evidence (see main text) suggest that the tooth-based genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Cretomanta</tp:taxon-name>
is a suitable candidate for being the dental elements of the skeleton-based genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
(for which teeth are unknown in the sole specimen available to date) and thus may be a senior synonym of the latter; however, both taxa must be considered distinct pending the discovery of overlapping material.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
The 
holotype
is a 166-cm-long (total length TL) holomorphic specimen with a precaudal length (PCL) of 
122 cm
and an estimated pectoral fin span (PFS) of about 
190 cm
(
158 cm
as preserved) (PFS about 1.1 times TL and 1.6 times PCL)
</tp:material-citation>
; 
<tp:material-citation>
the specimen is preserved flattened dorsoventrally, with the exception of the tail exposed in lateral view (

)
</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>The vertebral column consists of about 225 asterospondylic vertebrae, with the caudal vertebral count (~120) higher than the precaudal vertebral count (~105)</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
Anteriorly, there is no synarcual element, indicating that this specimen cannot be classified as a batoid (
9
)
</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
Tessellated prismatic calcified cartilage is well preserved in various parts of the specimen, with tesserae showing the sub-hexagonal close-packing arrangement typical of chondrichthyans (
27
)
</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
Soft-tissue imprints (skin, muscles) are preserved, providing information on the body outline (

and 

and 

to S6)
</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
The skin seems to be overall devoid of dermal denticles, as in many myliobatiform rays (
54
)
</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>The head is severely crushed dorsoventrally</tp:material-citation>
; 
<tp:material-citation>
it is short, with an indistinct snout and a wide mouth (

and 

)
</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
As indicated by the position of the anteriormost vertebra, the poorly preserved chondrocranium represents about 10% of the precaudal length. The overall outline of the chondrocranium is not recognizable, although some structures can be tentatively interpreted as rostral cartilages and nasal capsules. The jaws are long, extending posterior to the occiput. With the exception of a disarticulated and displaced Meckelʾs cartilage (
259 mm
in length), jaw elements cannot be identified with certainty, as those of hyoid and branchial arches. No teeth are preserved, possibly due to rapid post-mortem disarticulation and scattering affecting the dentition, like in fossil skeletons of cetorhinid sharks (
55
, 
56
)
</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
The hyper-elongate pectoral fins are rather broad at their bases, slightly forward-directed, and gently recurved at their ends (

and 

)
</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>They show an extremely increased number of radial cartilages. At least 70 radials are present</tp:material-citation>
, probably supported by several rodlike metapterygial elements. These radials are directed towards the anterior margin of the pectoral fin and some of them are bifurcated anteriorly (

), as in the megamouth shark (
7
). The trunk is moderately slender. No stomach/gut contents are preserved. There are no traces of dorsal, pelvic or anal fins; this reflects either original morphology (true phylogenetic absence) or taphonomic loss (post-mortem disarticulation and degradation). The caudal fin skeleton is characterized by ventrally directed hypochordal rays (hypochordal ray angle = 120°). The heterocercal caudal fin shows an elongate and slender dorsal lobe (dorsal margin length = 
51 cm
) at a moderate angle above the body axis (heterocercal angle = 27°), and a rather strong ventral lobe (preventral margin length = 
21 cm
) at a high angle below the body axis (hypocercal angle = 55°) ["lamniform caudal fin 
type
2" sensu (
13
)]. No terminal lobe can be discerned at the caudal tip (

and 

).
</p>
            <p>Remark on the caudal fin shape</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Interestingly, the caudal fin shape of sharks is generally related to their primary habitat and lifestyle (
1
, 
57
). Among modern sharks, four main 
types
of caudal fin shape can be identified (
57
). The caudal fin 
type
observed in 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
is present in most active-swimming littoral and oceanic species (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>Megachasmidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Odontaspididae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Carcharhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
) (
1
, 
13
, 
57
). High-speed pelagic sharks with a tuna-like morphology (
<tp:taxon-name>Lamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
) have a crescentic, rather symmetrical caudal fin (i.e., high heterocercal and hypocercal angles) (
1
, 
13
, 
57
). Deepwater sharks such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Squaliformes</tp:taxon-name>
generally have a caudal fin with a moderate to low heterocercal angle, a well-developed epichordal (= epicaudal) lobe, and a large terminal lobe (
1
, 
57
). Lastly, bottom-dwelling sharks usually have a caudal fin characterized by a very low heterocercal angle and a poorly defined (or no separate) ventral lobe (
1
, 
57
) (

).
</p>
            <p>
In conclusion, the 
<tp:taxon-name>Megachasma</tp:taxon-name>
-like caudal fin shape of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
, well distinct from that of benthic species, strongly indicates that this shark was an active-swimming pelagic form (although not capable of high swimming speeds) (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Remark on the presence/absence of dorsal, pelvic and anal fins</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
As mentioned above, the apparent absence of dorsal, pelvic and anal fins in 
INAH 2544 P.F.17
reflects either original morphology or taphonomic loss. In modern sharks, the first dorsal fin is more or less developed (
1
, 
9
). Among filter-feeding 
<tp:taxon-name>Lamniformes</tp:taxon-name>
, the basking shark
</tp:material-citation>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinus maximus</tp:taxon-name>
; derived tachypelagic form) has a high, well-developed first dorsal fin, whereas the megamouth shark (
<tp:taxon-name>Megachasma pelagios</tp:taxon-name>
; macroceanic form) has a low, moderately large first dorsal fin (
16
). Interestingly, this is inversely proportional to the development of their pectoral fins. In 
<tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Megachasma</tp:taxon-name>
, the pectoral fin span represents 54% and 70% of the precaudal length, respectively (see 

Table 
S
1

). Furthermore, the pectoral area is about equal to the first dorsal fin area in 
<tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinus</tp:taxon-name>
, whereas the pectoral area is about triple the first dorsal fin area in 
<tp:taxon-name>Megachasma</tp:taxon-name>
(
16
). Similarly, pelagic cownose, eagle and devil rays (
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinopteridae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Myliobatidae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Mobulidae</tp:taxon-name>
; aquilopelagic forms) have enlarged winglike pectoral fins and a small dorsal fin (despite the lack of caudal fin) (
1
, 
9
). In analogy with modern elasmobranchs, the hyper-elongate pectoral fins of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
would suggest that the first dorsal fin, if present, might have been small.
</p>
            <p>8</p>
            <p>
Whereas the anal fin was secondarily lost in many living sharks and all living batoids, pelvic fins are present in all modern elasmobranchs (
9
, 
10
). Pelvic fins were not secondary lost because males have paired copulatory organs (claspers) whose cartilaginous elements correspond to a modified portion of the pelvic fin skeleton (
9
). Therefore, the apparent lack of pelvic fins in the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
is most likely due to taphonomic loss. Only the discovery of new material may help determine whether 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
actually possessed dorsal, pelvic and anal fins.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Remark on the body size</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
The 
holotype
and single known specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
is a medium-sized individual; however, it is not possible to determine 1) whether this specimen represents a juvenile, subadult or adult individual, and 2) the maximum size attainable by this species. Unfortunately, the origin and evolutionary history of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
are undocumented, and we do not know if these putative lamniform sharks could reach gigantic sizes like in the four modern lineages of filter-feeding elasmobranchs (i.e., 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhincodontidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Megachasmidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Mobulidae</tp:taxon-name>
) (
3
). If the enigmatic genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Platylithophycus</tp:taxon-name>
(known by a single specimen representing a large individual) (
27
) can be proven to be actually an aquilolamnid, this would suggest an evolutionary pathway toward gigantism in this lineage of Late Cretaceous sharks.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Similarly, it is not possible, based on the current knowledge, to assess whether aquilolamnids arose from medium-sized benthic ancestors (as did rhincodontids and mobulids) (
3
), large-sized pelagic ancestors (as did megachasmatids and cetorhinids) (
3
), or medium-sized pelagic ancestors.
</p>
            <p>LDA results</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
The first LDA including only shark species (correct classification = 88.5%; 

Table 
S
5

) shows that 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
clearly falls outside the five specialized ecomorphotypes considered here (

). This is also true when a 
250 cm
hypothetical maximum total length is used for 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
. This strongly suggests that the body proportions of 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna</tp:taxon-name>
are distinctive among selachimorphs.
</p>
            <p>
The second LDA including both shark and batoid species (correct classification = 73.6%; 

Table 
S
6

) shows that 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
falls in the overlapping area between the aquilopelagic and rajobenthic ecomorphotypes (

and 

). However, the LDA classifier assigns 
<tp:taxon-name>A.milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
to the aquilopelagic group based on the minimal Mahalanobis distanceto the group mean. This is confirmed when a 
250 cm
hypothetical maximum total length is used for 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
, with a new position located within the aquilopelagic ecomorphotype but outside the rajobenthic ecomorphotype. The partial overlap observed between the aquilopelagic and rajobenthic ecomorphotypes is due to the aquilopelagic-like disc proportions (i.e., disc markedly wider than long) of the butterfly rays (
<tp:taxon-name>Gymnura</tp:taxon-name>
spp.) (
21
, 
58
). Gymnurids were originally categorized as bottom-dwelling, undulatory rajobenthic rays (
1
) (ecomorphotype assignment followed here; 

Table 
S
2

), but subsequently studies demonstrated that this group actually use fin movements intermediate between undulatory (like in typical rajobenthic forms) and oscillatory (like in typical aquilopelagic forms) locomotion (
21
, 
58
). Gymnurids exhibit an undulatory-based swimming mode near the sea bottom, whereas their locomotion is more oscillatory in the water column (
21
). Therefore, gymnurids should not be considered as a rajobenthic group sensu stricto. Arajobenthic ecomorphotype can be ruled out for 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
, as the latter was likely an active-swimming pelagic form (see above) characterized by pectoral fins with a narrowly angular shape and gently recurved distal tips (unlike gymnurids but like aquilopelagic myliobatiforms). With the exception of its typical shark caudal fin, 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
shows aquilopelagic-like morphology and proportions, clearly distinct from those observed in selachimorphs. Interestingly, the living demersal species 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhina ancylostoma</tp:taxon-name>
(shark ray), which is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
in having a shark -ray mixed appearance, is a rhinobenthic batoid that falls between the macroceanic and squatinobenthic shark species. Whereas the body of 
<tp:taxon-name>A. milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
is wider than long, that of 
<tp:taxon-name>R. ancylostoma</tp:taxon-name>
is clearly longer than wide, with precaudal length about 0.6 and 1.5 times pectoral fin span, respectively.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <p>Species (Order) (vernacular name)PCL (cm)CFL (cm)PFS (cm)
Ecomorphotype sensu (
1
)
Reference<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamna milarcae</tp:taxon-name>
(?La) (Eagle shark)
122 (184)44 (66)190 (286)UnknownThis study<tp:taxon-name>Euprotomicrus bispinatus
(Sq)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Pygmy shark)
2347Microceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Heteroscymnoides marleyi
(Sq)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Longnose pygmy shark)
3078Microceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Isistius brasiliensis
(Sq)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Cookiecutter shark)
42810Microceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocarcharias kamoharai
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Crocodile shark)
962635Microceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Scymnodalatias albicauda
(Sq)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Whitefin dogfish)
902042Microceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Zameus squamulosus
(Sq)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Velvet dogfish)
691518Microceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Heptranchias perlo
(He)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Sharpnose sevengill shark)
1013934Bathic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Hexanchus griseus
(He)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Bluntnose sixgill shark)
387163192Bathic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Odontaspis noronhai
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Bigeye sandtiger shark)
309118135Bathic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Somniosus antarcticus
(Sq)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Southern sleeper shark)
38373135Bathic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Mitsukurina owstoni
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Goblin shark)
25413064Bathic (Rhynchobathic)
Compagno (2001) (
17
)
<tp:taxon-name>Alopias pelagicus
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Pelagic thresher)
173202133Macroceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Carcharhinus falciformis
(Ca)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Silky shark)
25278162Macroceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Carcharhinus longimanus
(Ca)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Oceanic whitetip shark)
247103215Macroceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Isurus paucus
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Longfin mako shark)
34387280Macroceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Megachasma pelagios
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Megamouth shark)
379171267Macroceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Prionace glauca
(Ca)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Blue shark)
28694156Macroceanic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Carcharodon carcharias
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Great white shark)
523117273Tachypelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinus maximus
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Basking shark)
795205432Tachypelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Isurus oxyrinchus
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Shortfin mako shark)
32971173Tachypelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Lamna nasus
(La)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Porbeagle shark)
27476168Tachypelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Rhincodon typus
(Or)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Whale shark)
932268624Tachypelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Eucrossorhinus dasypogon
(Or)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Tasselled wobbegong)
1032258Squatinobenthic
Compagno (2001) (
17
)
<tp:taxon-name>Orectolobus ornatus
(Or)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Ornate wobbegong)
24741108Squatinobenthic
Compagno (2001) (
17
)
<tp:taxon-name>Squatina aculeata
(St)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Sawback angel shark)
1622675Squatinobenthic
Compagno (1984) (
40
)
<tp:taxon-name>Squatina japonica
(St)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Japanese angel shark)
17030106Squatinobenthic
Compagno (1984) (
40
)
</p>
      <p>Species (Order) (vernacular name)DL (or PCL) (cm)DW (or PFS) (cm)
Ecomorphotype sensu (
1
)
Reference<tp:taxon-name>Aetobatus flagellum
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Longhead eagle ray)
6390Aquilopelagic
Compagno and Last (1999c) (
43
)
<tp:taxon-name>Aetobatus narinari
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Spotted eagle ray)
133230Aquilopelagic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002d) (
48
)
<tp:taxon-name>Mobula alfredi
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Reef manta ray)
258550Aquilopelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Mobula birostris
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Giant manta ray)
296700Aquilopelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Mobula kuhlii</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>M. eregoodootenkee</tp:taxon-name>
) (My) (K uhl ʾ s devil ra y)
56100Aquilopelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Mobula mobular</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>M. japanica</tp:taxon-name>
) (My) (Spinetail devil ray)
237520Aquilopelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Mobula tarapacana
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Chilean devil ray)
197305Aquilopelagic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002f) (
50
)
<tp:taxon-name>Mobula thurstoni
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Bentfin devil ray)
98190Aquilopelagic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Myliobatis freminvillei
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Bullnose eagle ray)
5386Aquilopelagic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002d) (
48
)
<tp:taxon-name>Myliobatis goodei
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Southern eagle ray)
6099Aquilopelagic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002d) (
48
)
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinoptera brasiliensis
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Ticon cownose ray)
5291Aquilopelagic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002e) (
49
)
<tp:taxon-name>Dipturus olseni
(Ra)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Spreadfin skate)
3239Rajobenthic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002a) (
45
)
<tp:taxon-name>Gymnura altavela
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Spiny butterfly ray)
105208Rajobenthic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002c) (
47
)
<tp:taxon-name>Gymnura micrura
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Smooth butterfly ray)
64110Rajobenthic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002c) (
47
)
<tp:taxon-name>Hexatrygon bickelli
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Sixgill stingray)
11290Rajobenthic
Compagno and Last (1999b) (
42
)
<tp:taxon-name>Hypanus guttatus
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Longnose stingray)
163180Rajobenthic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002b) (
46
)
<tp:taxon-name>Malacoraja senta
(Ra)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Smooth skate)
3340Rajobenthic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002a) (
45
)
<tp:taxon-name>Pteroplatytrygon violacea
(My)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Pelagic stingray)
6280Rajobenthic
Ebert (2014) (
44
)
<tp:taxon-name>Rostroraja eglanteria
(Ra)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Clearnose skate)
4352Rajobenthic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002a) (
45
)
<tp:taxon-name>Springeria longirostris
(Ra)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Longnose legskate)
5043Rajobenthic
McEachran and Carvalho (2002a) (
45
)
<tp:taxon-name>Aptychotrema rostrata
(Rh)
</tp:taxon-name>
(East Australian shovelnose ray)
10441Rhinobenthic
Compagno and Last (1999a) (
41
)
<tp:taxon-name>Glaucostegus granulatus
(Rh)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Sharpnose guitarfish)
18469Rhinobenthic
Compagno and Last (1999a) (
41
)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Glaucostegus halavi</tp:taxon-name>13145RhinobenthicCompagno and Last(Rh) (Halavi guitarfish)
(1999a) (
41
)
<tp:taxon-name>Glaucostegus thouin</tp:taxon-name>26898RhinobenthicCompagno and Last(Rh) (Clubnose guitarfish)
(1999a) (
41
)
<tp:taxon-name>Rhina ancylostoma</tp:taxon-name>219143RhinobenthicCompagno and Last(Rh) (Shark ray)
(1999a) (
41
)
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinobatos schlegelii</tp:taxon-name>6824RhinobenthicCompagno and Last(Rh) (Brown guitarfish)
(1999a) (
41
)
<tp:taxon-name>Rhynchobatus australiae</tp:taxon-name>15463RhinobenthicCompagno and Last(Rh) (Whitespotted
(1999a) (
41
)
wedgefish)</p>
      <p>BathicMacroceanicTachypelagicMicroceanicMacroceanic0.013404Tachypelagic0.0611360.071804Microceanic0.00443450.000411570.0010423Squatinobenthic0.0376810.0318410.0819710.038937</p>
      <p>BathicMacro-Tachy-Micro-Squatino-Aquilo-RajoceanicpelagicceanicbenthicpelagicbenthicMacro-0.0028346ceanicTachy-0.0335490.065032pelagicMicro-0.00549680.000221590.00039197ceanicSquatino-0.0575090.149180.0747380.015781benthicAquilo-7.5659E-096.4895E-078.2444E-082.173E-091.4995E-06pelagicRajo-4.4227E-072.5054E-052.3143E-063.4836E-076.7734E-050.0039309benthicRhino-0.125810.00443530.0107490.0179560.306141.7872E-092.3962E-07benthic</p>
      <p>BathicMacro- ceanicTachy- pelagicMicro- ceanicSquatino- benthicTotalBathic500005/5 (100%)Macroceanic051005/6 (83.3%)Tachypelagic014004/5 (80%)Microceanic000515/6 (83.3%)Squatinobenthic000044/4 (100%)Total5655523/26 (88.5%)</p>
      <p>BathicMacro- ceanicTachy- pelagicMicro- ceanicSquatino -benthicAquilo- pelagicRajo- benthicRhino- benthicTotal correct/ TotalBathic301000013/5 (60%)Macro- ceanic050010005/6 (83.3%)Tachy- pelagic014000004/5 (80%)Micro- ceanic000410014/6 (66.7%)Squatino- benthic000030013/4 (75%)Aquilo- pelagic00000101010/11 (90.9%)Rajo- benthic010002606/9 (66.7%)Rhino- benthic110100044/7 (57.1%)Total48555127739/53 (73.6%)</p>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References and Notes</title>
         <p>
1. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 
Alternative life-history styles of cartilaginous fishes in time and space
. 
Environ. Biol. Fishes28
, 
33
- 
75
(
1990
). 
doi:10.1007/BF00751027</p>
         <p>
2. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 
"Pelagic elasmobranch diversity" inSharks of the Open Ocean: Biology, Fisheries and Conservation
, 
M. D. Camhi, E. K. Pikitch, E. A. Babcock
, Eds. (
Blackwell
, 
2008
), pp. 14-23.
</p>
         <p>
3. 
C. Pimiento
, 
J. L. Cantalapiedra
, 
K. Shimada
, 
D. J. Field
, 
J. B. Smaers
, 
Evolutionary pathways toward gigantism in sharks and rays
. 
Evolution73
, 
588
- 
599
(
2019
). 
doi:10.1111/evo.13680
Medline
</p>
         <p>
4. M. 
Friedman, K.Shimada, L. D.Martin, M. J.Everhart, J.Liston, A.Maltese, M.Triebold, 100-million-year dynasty of giant planktivorous bony fishes in the Mesozoic seas
. 
Science327
, 
990
- 
993
(
2010
). 
doi:10.1126/science.1184743
Medline
</p>
         <p>
5. 
C. J. Underwood
, 
M. A. Kolmann
, 
D. J. Ward
, 
Paleogene origin of planktivory in the Batoidea
. 
J. Vertebr. Paleontol.37
, e 
1293068
(
2017
). 
doi:10.1080/02724634.2017.1293068</p>
         <p>
6. 
S. Adnet
, 
H. Cappetta
, 
G. Guinot
, 
G. Notarbartolo di Sciara
, 
Evolutionary history of the devilrays (Chondrichthyes: Myliobatiformes) from fossil and morphological inference
. 
Zool. J. Linn. Soc.166
, 
132
- 
159
(
2012
). 
doi:10.1111/j.1096-3642.2012.00844.x</p>
         <p>
7. 
T. Tomita
, 
S. Tanaka
, 
K. Sato
, 
K. Nakaya
, 
Pectoral fin of the megamouth shark: Skeletal and muscular systems, skin histology, and functional morphology
. 
PLOS ONE9
, e 
86205
(
2014
). 
doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0086205
Medline
</p>
         <p>
8. 
C. J. Duffin
, 
Ostenoselache stenosoma
n. g. n. sp., a new neoselachian shark from the Sinemurian (Early Jurassic) of Osteno (Lombardy, Italy)

. 
Paleontologia Lombarda9
, 
3
- 
27
(
1998
).
</p>
         <p>
9. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 
Phyletic relationships of living sharks and rays
. 
Am. Zool.17
, 
303
- 
322
(
1977
). 
doi:10.1093/icb/17.2.303</p>
         <p>
10. 
O. Larouche
, 
M. L. Zelditch
, 
R. Cloutier
, 
Fin modules: An evolutionary perspective on appendage disparity in basal vertebrates
. 
BMC Biol.15
, 
32
(
2017
). 
doi:10.1186/s12915-
017-0370-x Medline
</p>
         <p>
11. 
R. Lund
, 
R. Zangerl
, 
Squatinactis caudispinatus
, a new elasmobranch from the Upper Mississippian of Montana

. 
Ann. Carnegie Mus.45
, 
43
- 
55
(
1974
).
</p>
         <p>
12. 
E. G. White
, 
Interrelationships of the elasmobranchs with a key to the order Galea
. 
Bull. Am. Mus. Nat. Hist.74
, 
25
- 
138
(
1937
).
</p>
         <p>
13. 
S. H. Kim
, 
K. Shimada
, 
C. K. Rigsby
, 
Anatomy and evolution of heterocercal tail in lamniform sharks
. 
Anat. Rec.296
, 
433
- 
442
(
2013
). 
doi:10.1002/ar.22647
Medline
</p>
         <p>
14. 
C. J. Underwood
, 
Diversification of the Neoselachii (Chondrichthyes) during the Jurassic and Cretaceous.Paleobiology32
, 
215
- 
235
(
2006
). 
doi:10.1666/04069.1</p>
         <p>
15. G. 
Guinot, L.Cavin, ʿFishʾ (Actinopterygii and Elasmobranchii) diversification patterns through deep time
. 
Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc.91
, 
950
- 
981
(
2016
). 
doi:10.1111/brv.12203
Medline
</p>
         <p>
16. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 

Relationships of the megamouth shark, 
Megachasma pelagios
(Lamniformes: Megachasmidae), with comments on its feeding habits

. 
NOAA Tech. Rep.
NMFS
90
, 
357
- 
379
(
1990
).
</p>
         <p>
17. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 
Sharks of the world. An annotated and illustrated catalogue of shark species known to date. Volume 2. Bullhead, mackerel and carpet sharks (Heterodontiformes, Lamniformes and Orectolobiformes)
. 
FAO Species Cat. Fish.
Purp.
1
, 
1
- 
269
(
2001
).
</p>
         <p>
18. 
R. Vullo
, 
G. Guinot
, 
G. Barbe
, 

The first articulated specimen of the Cretaceous mackerel shark 
Haimirichia amonensis
gen. nov. (Haimirichiidae fam. nov.) reveals a novel ecomorphological adaptation within the Lamniformes (Elasmobranchii)

. 
J. Syst. Palaeontol.14
, 
1003
- 
1024
(
2016
). 
doi:10.1080/14772019.2015.1137983</p>
         <p>
19. 
F. L. Condamine
, 
J. Romieu
, 
G. Guinot
, 
Climate cooling and clade competition likely drove the decline of lamniform sharks
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.116
, 
20584
- 
20590
(
2019
). 
doi:10.1073/pnas.1902693116
Medline
</p>
         <p>
20. 
D. W. Sims
, 
Filter-feeding and cruising swimming speeds of basking sharks compared with optimal models: They filter-feed slower than predicted for their size
. 
J. Exp. Mar. Biol. Ecol
.
249
, 
65
- 
76
(
2000
). 
doi:10.1016/S0022-0981(00)00183-0
Medline
</p>
         <p>
21. 
L. J. Rosenberger
, 

Pectoral fin locomotion in batoid fishes: Undulation 
versus
oscillation

. 
J. Exp. Biol.204
, 
379
- 
394
(
2001
). Medline
</p>
         <p>
22. 
C. A. D. Wilga
, 
G. V. Lauder
, 

"Biomechanics of locomotion in sharks, rays, and chimeras" in 
Biology of Sharks and Their Relatives
, J. C. Carrier, J. A. Musick, M. R. Heithaus, Eds

. (
CRC Press
, 
2004
), pp. 
139
- 
164
.
</p>
         <p>
23. 
B. J. Welton
, 
R. F. Farish
, 
T he C ollector 's G uide to F ossil S harks and R a y s fromthe Cretaceous of Texas
(Before Time, 
1993
).
</p>
         <p>
24. 
G. R. Case
, 
T. T. Tokaryk
, 
D. Baird
, 
Selachians from the Niobrara Formation of the Upper Cretaceous (Coniacian) of Carrot River, Saskatchewan
, 

Canada. 
Can. J. Earth Sci.27
, 
1084
- 
1094
(
1990
). 
doi:10.1139/e90-112</p>
         <p>
25. 
A. Noubhani
, 
H. Cappetta
, 
Les Orectolobiformes, Carcharhiniformes et Myliobatiformes (Elasmobranchii, Neoselachii) des Bassins à phosphate du Maroc (Maastrichtien - Lutétien basal)
. 
Palaeo Ichthyologica8
, 
1
- 
327
(
1997
).
</p>
         <p>
26. 
S. Enault
, 
H. Cappetta
, 
S. Adnet
, 
Simplification of the enameloid microstructure of large stingrays (Chondrichthyes: Myliobatiformes): a functional approach
. 
Zool. J. Linn. Soc.169
, 
144
- 
155
(
2013
). 
doi:10.1111/zoj.12059</p>
         <p>
27. 
A. W. Bronson
, 
J. G. Maisey
, 

Resolving the identity of 
Platylithophycus
, an enigmatic fossil from the Niobrara Chalk (Upper Cretaceous, Coniacian -Campanian)

. 
J. Paleontol.92
, 
743
- 
750
(
2018
). 
doi:10.1017/jpa.2018.14</p>
         <p>
28. 
K. Shimada
, 
E. V. Popov
, 
M. Siversson
, 
B. J. Welton
, 
D. J. Long
, 
Anew clade of putative plankton-feeding sharks from the Upper Cretaceous of Russia and the United States
. 
J. Vertebr. Paleontol.35
, e 
981335
(
2015
). 
doi:10.1080/02724634.2015.981335</p>
         <p>
29. 
L. Alegret
, 
E. Thomas
, 
K. C. Lohmann
, 
End-Cretaceous marine mass extinction not caused by productivity collapse
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.109
, 
728
- 
732
(
2012
). 
doi:10.1073/pnas.1110601109
Medline
</p>
         <p>
30. 
A. Tajika
, 
A. Nützel
, 
C. Klug
, 
The old and the new plankton: Ecological replacement of associations of mollusc plankton and giant filter feeders after the Cretaceous?PeerJ6
, e 
4219
(
2018
). 
doi:10.7717/peerj.4219
Medline
</p>
         <p>
31. 
M. J. Henehan
, 
A. Ridgwell
, 
E. Thomas
, 
S. Zhang
, 
L. Alegret
, 
D. N. Schmidt
, 
J. W. B. Rae
, 
J. D. Witts
, 
N. H. Landman
, 
S. E. Greene
, 
B. T. Huber
, 
J. R. Super
, 
N. J. Planavsky
, 
P. M. Hull
, 
Rapid ocean acidification and protracted Earth system recovery followed the end-Cretaceous Chicxulub impact
. 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.116
, 
22500
- 
22504
(
2019
). 
doi:10.1073/pnas.1905989116
Medline
</p>
         <p>
32. 
C. Ifrim
, 
W. Stinnesbeck
, 
E. Frey
, 
Upper Cretaceous (Cenomanian -Turonian and Turonian -Coniacian) open marine plattenkalk deposits in NE Mexico
. 
N. Jb. Geol. Paläont. Abh.245
, 
71
- 
81
(
2007
). 
doi:10.1127/0077-7749/2007/0245-0071</p>
         <p>
33. 
C. Ifrim
, 
Fluctuations of the oxygen minimum zone at the end of Oceanic Anoxic Event 2 in the Gulf of Mexico and the response of ammonites
. 
Swiss J. Palaeontol.134
, 
217
- 
225
(
2015
). 
doi:10.1007/s13358-015-0089-7</p>
         <p>
34. 
C. Ifrim
, 
"TheFossil Lagerstätte at Vallecillo, North- Eastern Mexico: Pelagic Plattenkalks Related to Cenomanian -Turonian Boundary Anoxia", thesis, University of K arlsruhe
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
35. 
K. T. Smith
, 
M.-C. Buchy
, 
Anew aigialosaur (Squamata: Anguimorpha) with soft tissue remains from the Upper Cretaceous of Nuevo León
, 

Mexico. 
J. Vertebr. Paleontol.28
, 
85
- 
94
(
2008
). 
doi:10.1671/0272-4634(2008)28[85:ANASAW]2.0.CO;2</p>
         <p>
36. 
E. Frey
, 
E. W. A. Mulder
, 
W. Stinnesbeck
, 
H. E. Rivera-Sylva
, 
J. M. Padilla-Gutiérrez
, 
A. H. González-González
, 
Anew polycotylid plesiosaur with extensive soft tissue preservation from the early Late Cretaceous of northeast Mexico
. 
Bol. Soc. Geol. Mex.69
, 
87
- 
134
(
2017
). 
doi:10.18268/BSGM2017v69n1a5</p>
         <p>
37. 
A. Blanco-Piñón
, 
E. Frey
, 
W. Stinnesbeck
, 
J. G. López Oliva
, 
Late Cretaceous (Turonian) fish assemblage from Vallecillo, Northeastern Mexico.N. Jb. Geol. Paläontol. Abh
.
225
, 
39
- 
54
(
2002
). 
doi:10.1127/njgpa/225/2002/39</p>
         <p>
38. 
C. Ifrim
, 
S. Götz
, 
S. W. Stinnesbeck
, 
Fluctuations of the oxygen minimum zone at the end of Oceanic Anoxic Event 2 reflected by benthic and planktic fossils
. 
Geology39
, 
1043
- 
1046
(
2011
). 
doi:10.1130/G32161.1</p>
         <p>
39. 
E. S. Stinnesbeck
, 
J. Rust
, 
F. Herder
, 

Paleobiology and taphonomy of the pycnodont fish 
Nursallia gutturosum
, based on material from the Latest-Cenomanian-Middle Turonian Vallecillo platy limestone, Mexico

. 
PalZ93
, 
659
- 
668
(
2019
). 
doi:10.1007/s12542-019-
00461-2
</p>
         <p>
40. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 
Sharks of the world. An annotated and illustrated catalogue of shark species known to date
. Volume 4, Part 1. Hexanchiformes to Lamniformes. 
FAO Fish Synop.125
, 1- 
249
(
1984
).
</p>
         <p>
41. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 
P. R. Last
, "Rhinidae (= Rhynchobatidae): Wedgefishes" in 
The Living Marine Resources of the Western Central Pacific
. FAO Species Identification Guide for Fishery Purposes. Volume 3. Batoid fishes, chimaeras and bony fishes part 1 (Elopidae to Linophrynidae)

, 
K. E. Carpenter, V. H. Niem
, Eds. (FAO, 
1999
), pp. 1418-1430.
</p>
         <p>
42. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 
P. R. Last
, "Hexatrygonidae: Sixgill Stingray" in 
The Living Marine Resources of the Western Central Pacific. FAO Species Identification Guide for Fishery Purposes
. Volume 3. Batoid fishes, chimaeras and bony fishes part 1 (Elopidae to Linophrynidae)

, 
K. E. Carpenter, V. H. Niem
, Eds. (FAO, 
1999
), pp. 1477-1478.
</p>
         <p>
43. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 
P. R. Last
, "Myliobatidae: Eagle Rays" in 
The Living Marine Resources of the Western Central Pacific. FAO Species Identification Guide for Fishery Purposes
. Volume 3. Batoid fishes, chimaeras and bony fishes part 1 (Elopidae to Linophrynidae)

, 
K. E. Carpenter, V. H. Niem
, Eds. (
FAO
, 
1999
), pp. 
1511
- 
1519
.
</p>
         <p>
44. 
D. A. Ebert
, 
"On board guide for the identification of pelagic sharks and rays of the Western Indian Ocean"
(
FAO
, 
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
45. 
J. D. McEachran
, 
M. R. de Carvalho
, "Rajidae: Skates" in 
The Living Marine Resources of the Western Central Atlantic. FAO Species Identification Guide for Fishery Purposes
. Volume 1. Introduction, molluscs, crustaceans, hagfishes, sharks, batoid fishes and chimaeras

, 
K. E. Carpenter
, Ed. (
FAO
, 
2002
), pp. 531-561.
</p>
         <p>
46. 
J. D. McEachran
, 
M. R. de Carvalho
, "Dasyatidae: Stingrays" in 
The Living Marine Resources of the Western Central Atlantic. FAO Species Identification Guide for Fishery Purposes
. Volume 1. Introduction, molluscs, crustaceans, hagfishes, sharks, batoid fishes and chimaeras

, 
K. E. Carpenter
, Ed. (FAO, 
2002
), pp. 562-571.
</p>
         <p>
47. 
J. D. McEachran
, 
M. R. de Carvalho
, "Gymnuridae: Butterfly Rays" in 
The Living Marine Resources of the Western Central Atlantic. FAO Species Identification Guide for Fishery Purposes
. Volume 1. Introduction, molluscs, crustaceans, hagfishes, sharks, batoid fishes and chimaeras

, 
K. E. Carpenter
, Ed. (FAO, 
2002
), pp. 575-577.
</p>
         <p>
48. 
J. D. McEachran
, 
M. R. de Carvalho
, "Myliobatidae: Eagle Rays" in 
The Living Marine Resources of the Western Central Atlantic. FAO Species Identification Guide for Fishery Purposes. Volume 1. Introduction, molluscs, crustaceans, hagfishes, sharks, batoid fishes and chimaeras
, 
K. E. Carpenter
, Ed. (
FAO
, 
2002
), pp. 578-582.
</p>
         <p>
49. 
J. D. McEachran
, 
M. R. de Carvalho
, "Rhinopteridae: Cownose Rays" in 
The Living Marine Resources of the Western Central Atlantic. FAO Species Identification Guide for Fishery Purposes
. Volume 1. Introduction, molluscs, crustaceans, hagfishes, sharks, batoid fishes and chimaeras

, 
K. E. Carpenter
, Ed. (FAO, 
2002
), pp. 583-585.
</p>
         <p>
50. 
J. D. McEachran
, 
M. R. de Carvalho
, "Mobulidae: Devil 
Rays
or Mantas" in 
The Living Marine Resources of the Western Central Atlantic. FAO Species Identification Guide for Fishery Purposes
. Volume 1. Introduction, molluscs, crustaceans, hagfishes, sharks, batoid fishes and chimaeras

, 
K. E. Carpenter
, Ed. (
FAO
, 
2002
), pp. 586-589.
</p>
         <p>
51. 
P. C. Sternes
, 
K. Shimada
, 
Body forms in sharks (Chondrichthyes: Elasmobranchii) and their functional, ecological, and evolutionary implications
. 
Zoology140
, 
125799
(
2020
). 
doi:10.1016/j.zool.2020.125799
Medline
</p>
         <p>
52. 
Ø. Hammer
, 
D. A. T. Harper
, 
P. D. Ryan
, 
PAST: Paleontological statistics software package for education and data analysis
. 
Palaeontol. Electronica4
, 
1
- 
9
(
2001
).
</p>
         <p>
53. 
P. R. Last, W. T. White, M. R. de Carvalho, B. Séret, M. F. W. Stehmann, G. J. P. Naylor
, Eds., 
Rays of the World
(
CSIRO Publishing
, 
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
54. 
W. Meyer
, 
U. Seegers
, 
Basics of skin structure and function in elasmobranchs: A review
. 
J. Fish Biol.80
, 
1940
- 
1967
(
2012
). 
doi:10.1111/j.1095-8649.2011.03207.x
Medline
</p>
         <p>
55. 
D. C. Hovestadt
, 
M. Hovestadt-Euler
, 

Apartial skeleton of 
Cetorhinus parvus
Leriche, 1910 (Chondrichthyes, Cetorhinidae) from the Oligocene of Germany

. 
Paläontol. Z.86
, 
71
- 
83
(
2012
). 
doi:10.1007/s12542-011-0118-9</p>
         <p>
56. 
A. M. Prokofiev
, 
E. K. Sychevskaya
, 
Basking shark (Lamniformes: Cetorhinidae) from the lower Oligocene of the Caucasus
. 
J. Ichthyol
.
58
, 
127
- 
138
(
2018
). 
doi:10.1134/S0032945218020121</p>
         <p>
57. 
K. S. Thomson
, 
D. E. Simanek
, 
Body form and locomotion in sharks
. 
Am. Zool.17
, 
343
- 
354
(
1977
). 
doi:10.1093/icb/17.2.343</p>
         <p>
58. 
O. Franklin
, 
C. Palmer
, 
G. Dyke
, 
Pectoral fin morphology of batoid fishes (Chondrichthyes: Batoidea): Explaining phylogenetic variation with geometric morphometrics
. 
J. Morphol.275
, 
1173
- 
1186
(
2014
). 
doi:10.1002/jmor.20294
Medline
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
