<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1038/nature06966</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Live birth in the Devonian period</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2008</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>LETTERS</p>
      <p>Live birth in the Devonian period</p>
      <p>John A. Long1,2,3, Kate Trinajstic4, Gavin C. Young2 &amp; Tim Senden5</p>
      <p>The extinct placoderm fishes were the dominant group of verte-brates throughout the Middle Palaeozoic era1, yet controversyabout their relationships within the gnathostomes (jawed verte-brates) is partly due to different interpretations of their repro-ductive biology2–5. Here we document the oldest record of alive-bearing vertebrate in a new ptyctodontid placoderm,<tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis attenboroughi</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov., from the Late
Devonian Gogo Formation of Australia (approximately 380 millionyears ago)6. The new specimen, remarkably preserved in threedimensions, contains a single, intra-uterine embryo connected bya permineralized umbilical cord. An amorphous crystalline massnear the umbilical cord possibly represents the recrystallized yolk
sac. Another ptyctodont from the Gogo Formation, 
<tp:taxon-name>Austroptyctodus</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>gardineri</tp:taxon-name>7, also shows three small embryos inside it in the sameposition. Ptyctodontids have already provided the oldest definiteevidence for vertebrate copulation8, and the new specimens confirmthat some placoderms had a remarkably advanced reproductivebiology, comparable to that of some modern sharks and rays. Thenew discovery points to internal fertilization and viviparity invertebrates as originating earliest within placoderms.</p>
      <p>Placodermi McCoy, 1848</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Ptyctodontida Gross, 1932</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis attenboroughi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Austroptyctodus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Austroptyctodus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>gardineri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Austroptyctodus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asterolepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis attenboroughi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Austroptyctodus gardineri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis
attenboroughi
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Live birth in the Devonian period</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/nature06966</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EE53F11DFF9F7618FFBCBE39FFD7FFA4</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06966</pub-id>
               <source>Nature</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis attenboroughi</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et 
<tp:taxon-status>sp. nov</tp:taxon-status>
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Generic name from the Latin meaning ‘mother fish’; species name in honour of Sir David Attenborough, who first drew attention to the Gogo fish sites in his 
1979
series 
Life on Earth
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Holotype
.
WAM 07.12
. 
1
(
Western Australian Museum, Perth
)

. 
Age and locality.
From the 
Stromatoporoid camp locality, Gogo Station, near Fitzroy Crossing
, 
Western Australia
(Late Devonian, early Frasnian)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.A
small aspinothoracid ptyctodontid fish having an ante- riorly pointed nuchal plate that participates in the posterior margin of the skull roof, broad roughly triangular-shaped preorbitals that meet mesially; the marginal plate has a large postorbital region with parallel rows of tubercles adorning it; the submarginal is strap-like and strongly curved mesially; robust triturating tooth plates that meet only at anterior tips, superognathals with moderately high anterior dorsal process. The body is scaleless.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description.<tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. nov.</named-content>
(

) is readily distinguished from all other known ptyctodontids by the combination of lacking a spinal plate with anteriorly pointed nuchal plate (

e), and a much-expanded postorbital region on the marginal plate (

f). The nuchal plate participates in the posterior margin of the skull roof and the centrals are unusually broad (

e). The skull roof is unusual in having prominent raised ridges for the main sensory-line canals (

e). The tooth plates can be moved against each other as in life. This shows that only the anterior-most biting edges of the jaws met in full occlusion (

). The trunk shield plates do not differ significantly from those of many other aspinothoracid ptyctodontids, in particular 
<tp:taxon-name>Austroptyctodus</tp:taxon-name>7
, except for proportions and ornamentation, the median dorsal having a low median crest. A restoration of the dermal armour is shown in 

h. 
A
detailed description of the dermal and axial skeleton, braincase and dentition of 
<tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. nov.</named-content>
, and its embryonic skeletal morphology, will be published elsewhere.
</p>
            <p>
The Gogo Formation has yielded the earliest phosphatized gnathostome muscle tissues and nerve fibres 
9
, and the new specimen shows additional soft-tissue preservation never before recorded in any fossil. The new specimen is exceptional in revealing a small partial skeleton located within the upper body cavity of a pregnant, adult female ptyctodontid placoderm (

a–d). The relatively complete adult skeleton includes much of the tail (

a). The single, partially ossified juvenile skeleton inside the body cavity of the adult clearly belongs to the same species based on characteristic tooth-plate and marginal plate morphology (

c, d). The small internal individual must be an embryo, rather than an ingested prey item, because the delicate bones show no breakage or etching from stomach acids, and the dentition is of similar gross morphology to that of the adult. The location of the preserved embryo close to the vertebral column suggests that it is in the uterus rather than the gut, a view supported by the presence of mineralized soft tissue forming a placental connection between embryo and mother. Furthermore, a second specimen from Gogo, previously described as 
<tp:taxon-name>Austroptyctodus</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>gardineri</tp:taxon-name>7
, has been re-examined and we have identified three small embryos in the same position posterior to the adult anterior lateral plate as in 
<tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. nov.</named-content>
(

). Cases demonstrating viviparity in the fossil record are extremely rare, the best being Mesozoic ichthyosaurs 
10,11
and mosasauroids 
12
. Presumed fetal specimens of a holocephalan fish from the Lower Carboniferous of Montana 
13
may

extend the record of viviparity back into the Palaeozoic era, but were not found in or near the body cavity of the mother. Our new example extends the definite record of vertebrate viviparity back by some 
200
million years.
</p>
            <p>
The embryos of 
<tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. nov.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Austroptyctodus</tp:taxon-name>
are about 
25
% of the adult size, based on proportions of the anterior lateral plate. The embryonic bones are remarkably thin and fragile, yet perfectly preserved, with the upper and lower dentition still in occlusion in 
<tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. nov.</named-content>
(

b–d and 
2g
). The skull bones of this specimen are oriented posteriorly, indicating that the embryo was curled. Only some dermal plates are represented in the embryos. Absence of certain bones at an early developmental stage is also recorded in tiny (
14–16 mm
) juvenile skeletons of the antiarch placoderm 
<tp:taxon-name>Asterolepis</tp:taxon-name>14
. Identified embryonic bones comprise paired preorbitals, a paranuchal, anterior dorsolateral, anterior lateral and a marginal plate, and both sets of tooth plates in articulation (

b–d, g and 
2g
, f). The supragnathals of 
<tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov. meet at a distinct medially directed symphysis (sym, 

), lending increased structural support for biting ability immediately after birth.
</p>
            <p>1Museum Victoria,Melbourne, PO Box 666,Melbourne 3001, Australia.2Research School of Earth Sciences, The Australian National University, Canberra 0 200, Australia. 3School of Geosciences,Monash University,Clayton,Victoria 3800, Australia.4School of Earth and Geographical Sciences,The University of Western Australia,Perth 6009, Western Australia, Australia. 5Department of Applied Mathematics, Research School of Physical Sciences and Engineering, The Australian National University, Canberra 0 200, Australia.</p>
            <p>
A thin tube of mineralized white material with slight helical twisting (umb, 

c, d) connects the 
<tp:taxon-name>Materpiscis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. nov.</named-content>
embryo to a region within the upper body cavity of the female, marked by an ovoid mass of coarsely crystalline calcite, possibly the position of the yolk sac (

c, d). In modern sharks, the umbilical cord wall comprises multiple small vessels, capillaries and a dense spongy
</p>
            <p>
connective tissue 
15
. The fossilized tube has similar external shape and position as the umbilical cord in chondrichthyans. High-resolution scanning electron microscopy 

(
SEM
)

imaging and high-resolution computer tomography scanning of this specimen revealed that the cord loops underneath the adult dorsal fin basal plate (

h and Supplementary Information). Its surface is covered with a thin layer of epithelium (

e) and has a series of pits of varying sizes (

c, d), with the wall of the umbilical cord made up of a series of vessels and a dense matrix of tissue. The path of one major vessel could be determined running through the cord (

b). Branching off from the umbilical cord are the remains of filamentous processes equivalent to the appendiculae in extant sharks (app, 

d). Thus, ptyctodonts apparently evolved beyond the first live-bearing stage (oviviparity, in which the mother retains her eggs inside her body, providing only protection, with the yolk sac providing all nutrition) to matrotrophy. The relative size and position of the embryo and yolk sac in relation to the mother fish is shown in 

a, with an attempted restoration of the fish giving birth shown in 

b, based on the observation that several viviparous sharks give birth tail-first to their young. Further discussion of the significance of viviparity and evolution can be found in the Supplementary Information.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <p>METHODS SUMMARY</p>
      <p>Preparation followed the standard acid etching technique using dilute (10%) acetic acid, although fine-resolution acid bathing for short time intervals was used for revealing the very delicate bones of the embryo.</p>
      <p>Full Methods
and any associated references are available in the online version of the paper at www.nature.com/nature.
</p>
      <p>Received 10 January; accepted 3 April 2008.</p>
      <p>
1. 
Denison, R.Handbook of Paleoichthyology. Placodermi128
(
Gustav Fischer, Stuttgart
, 
1978
).
</p>
      <p>
2. 
Gardiner, B. G.The relationships of placoderms
. 
J.Vert. Paleo.4
, 
379–395
(
1984
).
</p>
      <p>
3. 
Young, G. C.The relationships of placoderm fishes
. 
Zool. J. Linn. Soc.88
, 
1–57
(
1986
).
</p>
      <p>
4. 
Goujet, D.
&amp; 
Young, G. C.
in 
Recent Advances in the Origin and Early Radiation of Vertebrates
(eds Arratia, G., Wilson, M. &amp; Cloutier, R.)
109–126
(
Dr Freiderich Pfeil, Munich
, 
2004
).
</p>
      <p>
5. 
Miles, R. S.
&amp; 
Young, G. C.
in 
Problems in Vertebrate Evolution
(eds Andrews, S. M., Miles, R. S. &amp; Walker, A. D.)
123–198
(
Linnean Soc. Symp. Series 4
, 
1977
).
</p>
      <p>
6. 
Long, J. A.Swimming in Stone—the Amazing Gogo Fossils of the Kimberley320
(
Fremantle Arts Centre, Perth
, 
2006
).
</p>
      <p>
7. 
Long, J. A.
Ptyctodontid fishes (Vertebrata, Placodermi) from the Late Devonian Gogo Formation, Western Australia, with a revision of the European genus 
Ctenurella
Ørvig, 1960

. 
Geodiversitas19
, 
515–555
(
1997
).
</p>
      <p>
8. 
Miles, R. S.
Observations on the ptyctodont fish, 
Rhamphodopsis
Watson

. 
J. Linn. Soc. Zool.47
, 
99–120
(
1967
).
</p>
      <p>
9. 
Trinajstic, K.
, 
Marshall, E.
, 
Long, J.
&amp; 
Bifield, K.Exceptional preservation of nerve and muscle tissues in Devonian placoderm fish and their phylogenetic implications
. 
Biol. Lett.3
, 
197–200
(
2007
).
</p>
      <p>
10. 
Böttcher, R.Neue Erkenntnisse über die Fortpflanzungsbiologie der Ichthyosaurier (Reptilia)
. 
Stuttgarter Beitr. Nat. B164
, 
1–51
(
1990
).
</p>
      <p>
11. 
Maxwell, E. E.
&amp; 
Caldwell, M. W.First record of live birth in Cretaceous ichthyosaurs: closing an 80 million year gap
. 
Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B
270 (Suppl. 1), S104–S107

(
2003
).
</p>
      <p>
12. 
Caldwell, M. W.
&amp; 
Lee, M. S. Y.Live birth in marine lizards (mosasauroids)
. 
Proc.R. Soc. Lond. B268
, 
2397–2401
(
2001
).
</p>
      <p>
13. 
Lund, R.Viviparity and interuterine feeding in a new holocephalan fish from the Lower Carboniferous of Montana
. 
Science209
, 
697–699
(
1980
).
</p>
      <p>
14. 
Upeniece, I.The unique fossil assemblage from the Lode Quarry (Upper Devonian, Latvia)
. 
Mitt. Mus. Natkd. Berl. Geowiss.4
, 
101–119
(
2001
).
</p>
      <p>
15. 
Wourms, J.
Maximization of evolutionary trends for placental viviparity in the spadenose shark, 

Scoliodon laticaudus. 
Env. Biol. Fish.38
, 
269–294
(
1993
).
</p>
      <p>Supplementary Information
is linked to the online version of the paper at www.nature.com/nature.
</p>
      <p>Acknowledgements
We thank M. Gomon and M. Lee for discussion of the material, and M. Caldwell for comments on the paper. P. Lillywhite assisted with photography. J.A.L., K.T. and G.C.Y. are supported by an Australian Research Council Discovery Grant. We thank L. Hatcher for finding the specimen on the 2005 Museum Victoria Gogo Expedition. The specimen was partially prepared by D. Pickering.
</p>
      <p>Author Contributions
The fine preparation of the new specimen was done by J.A.L., and it was described by J.A.L., K.T. and G.C.Y.; T.S. participated in the 2005 Gogo expedition and analysed the specimen using XCT scan imagery.
</p>
      <p>Author Information
Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to J.A.L. (jlong@museum.vic.gov.au).
</p>
      <p>METHODS</p>
      <p>Specimen preparation.
The acid immersion procedure (in 10% acetic acid for 2 days, washed in running water for a day, air-dried, all exposed bones then hardened with Mowital B30 consolidant dissolved in pure ethanol) was repeated over 2 months to extract fully the adult dermal plates of the head and trunk shields. The first part of the initial preparation was carried out by D. Pickering. Once enough of the skeleton was revealed to show that it was a ptyctodontid placoderm, the specimen was handed over to J.A.L. who continued preparation, taking photographs of the specimen after every acid bath cycle to record exact positions of individual skeletal elements.
</p>
      <p>
The remaining elongate section of rock contained what we originally thought was just the tail vertebrae and parts of the axial skeleton, so preparation was halted to retain a high degree of articulation in the tail for study of the articulated vertebral units. However, during a visit to Museum Victoria in November 2007 by K.T., it was decided to prepare the tail section of the specimen one more time to clarify details of the anterior axial skeleton,so the specimen was placed in weak acetic acid (7%) for one night. The following day the embryonic bones were first revealed. From that point on we decided to take much more caution with preparation. We noted from the previous photographs that some delicate embryonic bones were already exposed previously and missed by us, dismissed as possibly being thin body scales as occur on the flank of 
<tp:taxon-name>Campbellodus</tp:taxon-name>
7. After the acid bath the delicate preorbital plates of the embryo were now missing, but in the process the rest of the embryonic skeleton,and the umbilical cord and yolk sac, had been revealed. A search of the kept residue from the last acid bath revealed the missing embryonic preorbital plates, which were so fragile that one was severely damaged trying to lift it onto a slide mount.
</p>
      <p>One more attempt was made to prepare the specimen further to reveal more of the embryonic skeleton. This time the specimen was placed in very dilute acetic acid (5%) for 1 h at each immersion. The wet specimen was then carefully examined under a microscope and re-immersed in acid until the desired level of detail was exposed, after three more immersions, as is shown in the illustrations of our paper. During this time the thin layer of limestone holding the articulate tail together dissolved through, dividing the specimen into two sections: one containing embryo, umbilicus and yolk sac with parts of the adult axial skeleton and dermal trunk shield, and a smaller elongate section containing the distal axial skeleton.</p>
      <p>Tomogram of specimen.
High-resolution X-ray tomography was conducted in-house to explore the relationship between external and internal structures at a spatial resolution of 13 µm16,17. The included animation (Supplementary Movie) shows the specimen rotating to reveal parts of the umbilicus not visible on the surface, which are looped underneath a flat-lying dorsal fin basal plate from the mother fish.
</p>
      <p>All volume rendering and animation was done using the freeware package, Drishti (http://anusf.anu.edu.au/Vizlab/drishti).</p>
      <p>Scanning electron microscopy.
Scanning electron micrographs were taken at The Centre for Microscopy, Characterization and Analysis, University of Western Australia. Small portions of the umbilicus were removed from the specimen and imaged using a Zeiss 1555 VP-FESEM. Samples were first coated in carbon and then gold. SEM was chosen as it gave finer resolution for external surface detail than the XCT scans.
</p>
      <p>
16. 
Sakellariou, A.
, 
Sawkins, T. J.
, 
Senden, T. J.
&amp; 
Limaye, A.X-ray tomography for mesoscale physics applications
. 
Physica A339
, 
152–158
(
2004
).
</p>
      <p>
17. 

Sakellariou, A. 
et al.An x-ray tomography facility for quantitative predictions of mechanical and transport properties in geological, biological and synthetic systems
. In 
Development in X-Ray Tomography IV
(ed. 
Bonse, U.
) 
Proc. SPIE
Vol. 
5535473–484
(SPIE, Bellingham, Western Australia, 
2004
).
</p>
   </body>
</article>
