<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2017.381</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Integrative description of two new species of Malagasy chirping giant pill-millipedes, genus Sphaeromimus (Diplopoda: Sphaerotheriida: Arthrosphaeridae)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2017</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Integrative description of two new species of Malagasy chirping giant pill-millipedes, genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
(Diplopoda: 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaeridae</tp:taxon-name>
)
</title>
         <p>Leif MORITZ 1,* &amp; Thomas WESENER 2</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1,2 Zoologisches Forschungsmuseum Alexander Koenig, Leibniz Institute for Animal Biodiversity, Adenauerallee 160, D-53113 Bonn, 
Germany
.
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>* Corresponding author: moritz.leif@gmail.com</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>2 Email: t.wesener@zfmk.de</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>1 urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:89921EE8-F015-4FED-AB5C-1D17F2C2F8F6 2 urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author:86DEA7CD-988C-43EC-B9D6-C51000595B47</title>
         <p>Abstract.
The species-rich giant pill-millipedes (
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
) often represent a microendemic component of Madagascar’s mega-invertebrate fauna. Of the chirping genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
, ten species have been described. Here, we describe two new species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
integratively, combining light microscopy, scanning electron microscopy, 
DNA
barcoding and micro-CT technology for the first time in a taxonomic description of a giant pillmillipede. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp.nov.</named-content>
are the first giant pill-millipedes collected and described from the mountainous rainforests of Kalambatritra and Midongy. Both species show island gigantism compared to their congeners. Our analysis of the mitochondrial 
COI
gene shows that the two species are related to one another with a moderate genetic distance (9.4%), while they are more closely related to an undetermined specimen from the forest of Vevembe (6.3% and 8.4%). They stand in a basal position with 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibeWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus
(de Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
. The four aforementioned species share a high number of stridulation ribs on the male harp. Our micro- CT analysis provides a look into the head of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and shows that non-destructive CT methods are a useful tool for studying the inner morphology of giant pill-millipedes.
</p>
         <p>Keywords.
Biodiversity, 
COI
, island gigantism, Kalambatritra, Midongy.
</p>
         <p>
Moritz L. &amp; Wesener T. 
2017
. Integrative description of two new species of Malagasy chirping giant pillmillipedes, genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
(Diplopoda: 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaeridae</tp:taxon-name>
). 
European Journal of Taxonomy381
: 1–25. https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2017.381
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Madagascar
, the world’s 4th largest island, lies in the Indian Ocean east of Africa and has a tropical climate (
Moat &amp; Smith 2007
). While its center and west is mainly covered by dry savanna and dry forest, its east is covered by dense humid rainforests (
Moat &amp; Smith 2007
). 
Madagascar
is considered one of the world’s hottest biodiversity hotspots (

Myers 
et al.
2000

; 

Ganzhorn 
et al.
2001

) and provides shelter to a high
</p>
         <p>
diversity of endemic species. This high degree of endemism is probably due to its early isolation from Africa more than 150 Ma years ago and from 
India
more than 80 Ma years ago (
Wells 2003
). Thus 99% of the amphibian species (
Glaw &amp; Verdes 2003
) and 90% of all species of reptiles (
Raxworthy 2003
) and mammals (

Goodman 
et al.
2003

) in 
Madagascar
are endemic. Since the arrival of humans ca 2000 years ago (
Dewar &amp; Wright 1993
), the landscape of 
Madagascar
has undergone tremendous changes resulting in only 9.9% of the primary vegetation remaining (

Myers 
et al.
2000

). A key thread to Madagascar’s biodiversity is the fast rate of deforestation of habitat (

Harper 
et al.
2007

). Although several projects and action plans were established in the last decades to protect Madagascar’s rich nature, deforestation and fragmentation still takes place at an increasing rate (
Horning 2012
; 

Waeber 
et al.
2016

). Thus, from 
1950 to 2000
the area covered by forests decreased by 40% (
Green &amp; Sussman 1990
).
</p>
         <p>
One of the highly endemic faunal groups of 
Madagascar
are the millipedes, class Diplopoda (
Enghoff 2003
). Millipedes play an important role in terrestrial ecosystems as detritivores (Cárcamo 
et al.
2000) and were among the first terrestrial animals, with fossils dating back to the middle Silurian (
Shear &amp; Edgecombe 2010
). Sixteen extant orders of Diplopoda are known (
Blanke &amp; Wesener 2014
), of which eight occur naturally on 
Madagascar
(
Shelley &amp; Golovatch 2011
), with two of them, Polyzoniida (
Wesener 2014a
) and Siphonophorida (
Wesener 2014b
), being only recently recorded from the island. 
Madagascar
is host to some of the most spectacular millipedes: different genera of large-bodied pitchblack/bloodred so called “Fire-Millipedes” of the order Spirobolida (

Wesener 
et al.
2009a

, 
2009b
, 
2011
), as well as the world’s largest giant pill-millipedes, order 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
(see 
Wesener &amp; Wägele 2008
; 
Wesener 2009
), showing island gigantism. All giant pill-millipedes of 
Madagascar
belong to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaeridae</tp:taxon-name>
, otherwise only found in 
India
(
Wesener &amp; VandenSpiegel 2009
; 

Wesener 
et al.
2010

) and are an example of the interesting biogeographical history of the Malagasy fauna. All species of the family are characterized by unique stridulation organs present in both sexes (see also 
Wesener 2014c
), the male harp and the female washboard. On 
Madagascar
, three genera with altogether 77 species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaeridae</tp:taxon-name>
, all endemic, can be found (
Wesener 2016
): the species-rich genus 
Zoosphaerium
Pocock, 1895, the dwarfed species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Microsphaerotherium
Wesener &amp; VandenSpiegel, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
and the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
, whose members have especially well-developed stridulation organs (
Wesener &amp; Sierwald 2005
). Until 2005 only known from a single specimen, 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
was thought to be based on a mislabeled Indian specimen (
Jeekel 1999
), but then two new species and many specimens were described from SE 
Madagascar
(
Wesener &amp; Sierwald 2005
). Morphological (
Wesener &amp; VandenSpiegel 2009
) and molecular (

Wesener 
et al.
2010

) studies suggest that 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
is more closely related to the Indian genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaera
Pocock, 1895
</tp:taxon-name>
than to the other genera in 
Madagascar
. Seven additional species were described integratively in 2014, including the first gigantic species of the genus, reaching the size of a ping-pong ball (

Wesener 
et al.
2014

). All specimens found so far are from south and south-east 
Madagascar
(
Wesener 2016
), and inhabit humid lowland, littoral, or montane rainforests, apart from a single species (
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897))
</tp:taxon-name>
which is widespread in the spiny forest ecosystem.
</p>
         <p>
Here, we describe two new species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
, both of them “giants”. The species come from previously unsampled regions, the quite remote (only approachable via a hike of&gt; 
30 km
) uniquely transitional forest of Kalambatritra (

Irwin 
et al.
2001

) and its nearest neighbour, the eastern montane rainforest of Midongy-Sud (

Bora 
et al.
2007

). We chose to describe both species integratively (

Padial 
et al.
2010

), using drawings and scanning-electron microscopy (

Oatley 
et al.
1966

) combined with genetic barcoding (Hebert 
et al.
2003; Hebert &amp; Gregory 2005). For only the second time in Diplopoda taxonomy (

Akkari 
et al.
2015

), we also use micro-CT technology (
Ritman 2004
) to study and visualize internal structures non-invasively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Material and methods</title>
         <p>Abbreviations:</p>
         <p>CAS
= 
California
Academy of Sciences, San Francisco, 
USA</p>
         <p>FMNH
= Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, 
USA</p>
         <p>ZFMK
= Zoologisches Forschungsmuseum Alexander Koenig, Leibniz Institute of Terrestrial Biodiversity, Bonn, 
Germany</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Specimen collection and conservation</title>
         <p>
The described specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
were all obtained from natural history collections and collected by hand during general inventory programs by American museums. The single specimen of the species collected in Midongy (
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
) by V. Soramalaia in 
February 2008
, was provided by the 
FMNH
. The four specimens from Kalambatritra (
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
; 

), collected by B.L. Fisher and colleagues in 
February 2009
, are from the collection of the 
CAS
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Dissection and illustrations</title>
         <p>
The left or the right 1st, 2nd and 9th legs, the anterior and the posterior telopods of the male 
holotype
, and the left or right 2nd leg and the subanal plate of female 
paratypes
(if present) were dissected for drawings. Pencil-drawings were made using a camera lucida mounted on a Zeiss Discovery 
V8
(Carl Zeiss AG). For both species the antennae and a part of the endotergum of a mid-body segment were dissected for SEM-imaging. From the species found in Kalambatritra, where more specimens were available, the mandible and the gnathochilarium were dissected as well. All objects were dehydrated in an alcohol series (96%, 96%, 100%) and dried overnight. The parts were mounted on stubs and sputter-coated with gold. Objects were removed from the stubs and returned to alcohol after study. SEM-images were obtained with a Supra VR 300VP scanning electron microscope (Carl Zeiss AG) using the SmartSEM V05.00 software (Carl Zeiss AG).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Micro-CT imaging</title>
         <p>
For a non-invasive visualization of internal structures a micro-CT-scan was performed. The head of the female 
paratype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
was dehydrated via an ascending ethanol series (96%, 100%) and critical point dried. A micro-CT-scan was conducted using the SKYSCAN 1272 micro- CT-scanner (Brucker microCT, Kontich, 
Belgium
) and the accompanying Control Software v. 1.1.7 (Brucker microCT) with the following settings: source voltage = 60 kV, source current = 166 µA, exposure = 915 ms, rotation of 180° in rotation steps of 0.2°, frame averaging = 6, random movement = 15, flat field correction ON,geometrical correction ON,filter = Al 
0.25mm
. Reconstruction and thermal drift correction was performed in NRecon v. 1.7.0.4 (Brucker microCT) and the images were converted to 8bit grayscale images via 
Fiji
ImageJ v. 1.49k (

Schindelin 
et al.
2012

). Volume rendering of the dataset for three-dimensional exploration and visualization was done in Drishti v. 2.6.3 (
Limaye 2012
). The tentorium and nebententorium were segmented automatically and corrected manually in ITK-SNAP v. 3.4.0 (

Yushkevich 
et al.
2006

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>DNA-extraction and sequencing</title>
         <p>
Muscle tissue was taken from the male 
holotypes
stored in 80% ethanol and transferred to 95% ethanol. For 
DNA
extraction the DNeasy Blood &amp; Tissue Kit (Qiagen Sample &amp; Assay Technologies) was used. A fragment of the cytochrome 
c
oxidase subunit I (
CO1
) mitochondrial gene was amplified with the primers HCO2198-JJ and 
LCO
1490-JJ (
Astrin &amp; Stüben 2008
) using the Multiplex PCR Kit (Qiagen Sample &amp; Assay Technologies) and the Thermocycler Biometra 
TRIO
(Biometra GmbH). The PCR protocol and other methods are the same as those used in earlier studies (
Wesener 2015
). The PCRproduct was enzymatically purified with the Illustra ExoProStar PCR and Sequence Reaction Clean- up Kit (GE Healthcare Life Sciences). Double-strand Sanger sequencing (

Sanger 
et al.
1977

) of the cleaned PCR product was performed by Macrogen, 
Netherlands
. Sequences were concatenated using Seqman (DNASTAR Inc.). 
BLAST
searches (

Altschul 
et al.
1990

) were used to check the sequences for contaminations. Sequences were translated into amino acids to rule out the accidental amplification of pseudogenes. New sequences were uploaded to Genbank (see 
Table 1
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Species<tp:taxon-name>Procyliosoma leae</tp:taxon-name>
*
Zoosphaerium neptunus
*
Z. alluaudi
*
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaera brandtii</tp:taxon-name>
*
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
01*
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
02*
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
03*
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
04*
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
0 5 (red)*
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
0 6 (red)*
<tp:taxon-name>S. splendidus</tp:taxon-name>
A*
<tp:taxon-name>S. splendidus</tp:taxon-name>
B*
<tp:taxon-name>S. inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name>
A*
<tp:taxon-name>S. inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name>
B*
<tp:taxon-name>S. titanus</tp:taxon-name>
*
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
*
<tp:taxon-name>S. lavasoa</tp:taxon-name>
B*
<tp:taxon-name>S. lavasoa</tp:taxon-name>
C*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
01*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
02*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
03*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
04*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
05*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
06*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
07*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
08*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
09*
<tp:taxon-name>S. saintelucei</tp:taxon-name>
*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andrahomana
Cave
</tp:taxon-name>
*
<tp:taxon-name>S. andrahomana</tp:taxon-name>
*
S.
sp. ‚Vevembe‘*
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
         <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
         <tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
         <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>Specimen Catalog #QVMAG
23:45801
FMNH-INS 56005FMNH-INS 56000FMNH-INS 8650FMNH-INS 56016FMNH-INS 56016FMNH-INS 56008FMNH-INS 56212ZFMK MYR 2273ZFMK MYR 2276FMNH-INS 6702FMNH-INS 56031FMNH-INS 56033FMNH-INS 61090CASENT 9032789FMNH-INS 8184FMNH-INS 61143FMNH-INS 61142FMNH-INS 61135FMNH-INS 61137ZFMK MYR 2322FMNH-INS 61136FMNH-INS 61132FMNH-INS 61138FMNH-INS 56210FMNH-INS 56210ZFMK MYR 2323ZFMK MYR 889FMNH-INS 56211FMNH-INS 56214CASENT 9032816CASENT 9068297-AFMNH-INS 3119888LocalityTasmaniaMadagascar, AndasibeMadagascar, PetrikyTanzania, Usambara HillsMadagascar, AndrahomanaMadagascar, AndrahomanaMadagascar, MangatsiakaMadagascar, TsimelahyMadagascar, TsimelahyMadagascar, TsimelahyMadagascar, Sainte Luce S9Madagascar, Sainte Luce S9Madagascar, EnatoMadagascar, EnatoMadagascar, ManomboMadagascar, IvohibeMadagascar, Gr. LavasoaMadagascar, Gr. LavasoaMadagascar, Isaka-IvondroMadagascar, Isaka-IvondroMadagascar, Isaka-IvondroMadagascar, Isaka-IvondroMadagascar, ManantantelyMadagascar, ManantantelyMadagascar, MalioMadagascar, MalioMadagascar, MalioMadagascar, Sainte Luce S8Madagascar, AndrahomanaMadagascar, Ankapaky PlateauMadagascar, VevembeMadagascar, KalambatritraMadagascar, Midongy-BefotakaGenbank #FJ409910
*
FJ409929*FJ409926*FJ409915*FJ409919*FJ409920*FJ409921*FJ409922*KJ13244*KJ13245*FJ409918*FJ409917*FJ409916*KJ13246*KJ13247*KJ13248*KJ13249*KJ13250*KJ13251*KJ13252*KJ13253*KJ13254*KJ13255*KJ13256*FJ409923*KJ13257*KJ13258*KJ13259*FJ409924*KJ13260*KJ13261*KY417112KY417113GenSeqgenseq-4genseq-4genseq-3genseq-4genseq-4genseq-4genseq-4genseq-4genseq-4genseq-4genseq-3genseq-3genseq-4genseq-4genseq-1genseq-1genseq-2genseq-2genseq-2genseq-2genseq-1genseq-2genseq-4genseq-4genseq-4genseq-4genseq-4genseq-1genseq-4genseq-1genseq-4genseq-1genseq-1</p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Sequence processing and DNA-analysis</title>
         <p>
Sequences were aligned by hand in Bioedit (
Hall 1999
). The final dataset consisted of 33 sequences for 15 species; two of the sequences were newly sequenced and 31 obtained from GenBank (see 
Table 1
), which had been part of two earlier studies (

Wesener 
et al.
2010

, 
2014
). The final dataset included 33 sequences with 674 positions. Distance analysis was performed in Mega 6 (

Tamura 
et al.
2013

) using the uncorrected p-distance model. Variation among sites was modeled with gamma distribution with shape parameter = 1. Included were codon positions 1st+2nd+3rd. Genetic distances are displayed in matrix format (
Table2
). The best fitting substitution-model for maximum likelihood analysis was calculated with Modeltest (
Tamura &amp; Nei 1993
) as implemented in Mega 6. Codon positions included were 1st+2nd+3rd. The best fitting model was the General Time Reversal (GTR)-Model (

Tavaré 
1986
) with gamma distribution and Invariant sites (GTR+ 
G
+ 
I
) (lnL = -4010.400, Invariant = 0.5302, Gamma = 1.4196, 
R
= 3.75520307816161; Freq 
A
: 0.2640, 
T
: 0.3345, 
C
: 0.2287, 
G
: 0.1726). Phylogenetic analysis was performed in Mega 6 based on the GTR+ 
G
+ 
I
model. 
A
species tree was reconstructed using the maximum likelihood method with gamma-distribution of 5 categories. Initial trees were made automatically using 
NJ
/BioNJ. The bootstrap consensus tree was calculated from 
1000
replicates (Felsenstein 
1985
). The obtained tree was edited in Adobe Illustrator 
CS
2.
</p>
         <p>Table 2.
Genetic p-distances between species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
. Variation among sites was modeled with gamma distribution with shape parameter = 1. Included were codon positions 1st+2nd+3rd.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Procyliosoma leae</tp:taxon-name>
(
QVMAG
23:45801)
Zoosphaerium neptunusFMNH-INS
56005)
Zoosphaerium alluaudi
(
FMNH
_ 
INS86000
)
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaera brandtii</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
8650)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. musicus
</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
56016)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. andohahela
</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
61135)
<tp:taxon-name>S
.lavasoa
</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
61143)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. lavasoa
</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
61142)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. andrahomana
</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
56211)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. inexpectatus
</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
56033)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. saintelucei
</tp:taxon-name>
(
ZFMK-MYR
889)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. splendidus
</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
56031)
S
. sp.

Vevembe (CAS-ENT9032816)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
8184)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanus</tp:taxon-name>
(CAS-ENT9032789)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
midongy</tp:taxon-name>
(
FMNH-INS
3119888)
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
(CAS-ENT9068297- 
A
)
0.1990.1850.2310.2440.2200.2220.2230.2300.2420.2270.2230.2300.2230.2430.2380.2350.1480.1900.1820.2150.2210.2210.2280.2050.1850.2280.2030.1780.2000.2020.2020.1780.1690.2100.2010.2010.2110.1960.1810.2130.2070.1890.1870.2170.1980.1930.2180.2090.2110.2150.2170.2020.2230.1990.1910.1970.2110.2070.1990.1990.2000.2080.1860.1660.2120.1490.1530.1630.1630.1540.0830.0850.1010.1880.1810.0770.1810.1910.2030.2110.1900.0010.1080.1880.1720.0740.1780.1910.1900.1910.1810.1100.1890.1730.0760.1790.1910.1910.1930.1830.1750.1700.1100.1900.2020.1850.1970.1810.0540.2000.1920.1830.1840.1890.1900.1810.1800.1640.1630.1750.1780.1790.1900.2030.1960.1830.1510.1660.0630.0840.1710.1570.1580.1650.1800.094</p>
         <p>Distribution map</p>
         <p>
The localities of specimens were mapped in the free software 
DIVA-GIS
v. 7.5.0.0 (

Hijmans 
et al.2001
) on spatial information made freely available by the 
GADM
database v. 1.0 and the 
Madagascar
Vegetation mapping project (

Moat &amp; Smith 
2007
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Results</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Order<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaerotheriida Brandt, 
1833</tp:taxon-name>
         </title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arthrosphaeridae Jeekel, 
1974</tp:taxon-name>
         </title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure

&amp; Zehntner

, 
1902</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure

&amp; Zehntner
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>saintelucei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andrahomana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>musicus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>lavasoa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>vatovavy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. midongy
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. musicus

(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. vatovavy
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>st left</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibeWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>st left</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Integrative description of two new species of Malagasy chirping giant pill-millipedes, genus Sphaeromimus (Diplopoda: Sphaerotheriida: Arthrosphaeridae)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2017.381</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F42B3452FFF1FF88FF9FFFAFFFD5557C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2017.381</pub-id>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure

&amp; Zehntner

, 
1902</tp:taxon-name>
For a recent revision, see 

Wesener 
et al.
(
2014
)

.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>Key to the species of<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
:
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
            <sec sec-type="multiple">
               <title>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:620 
CAD
6B-DAB4-4FFC-8556-61357C75AF40 

, 
</title>
            </sec>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FA9166CE-73E5-41FE-A203-E4C999D2C0EE 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>1. Male harp on the anterior telopod with 3 stridulation ribs …………………………………………2 – Male harp on the anterior telopod with 4–6 stridulation ribs ………………………………………7</p>
            <p>
2. Body length &lt;
20 mm
. Mid-body legs without a coxal lobe. Endotergum with single row of marginal bristles. Immovable finger of posterior telopod slender, apically strongly curved like a hook. Colour pink or brown ………………………………………………………………………………………3
</p>
            <p>
– Body length&gt; 
20 mm
. Mid-body legs at least with a weak coxal lobe. Endotergum usually with at least two, rarely only one 

(
<tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
) row of marginal bristles. Immovable finger of posterior telopod at least basally wide. Colour black or brown …………4
</p>
            <p>
3. Colour pink, surface shiny. Process of telopoditomere 2 of anterior telopods in anterior view visible laterally. Littoral forest of Mandena and rainforest of Enato …………………………… …………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Colour light brown, surface dull. Process of telopoditomere 2 of anterior telopods in anterior view not visible. Littoral forest of Sainte Luce, fragment S8 ……………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
4. Body length&gt; 
30mm
, light brown. Endotergum with single row of marginal bristles. Movable finger of posterior telopod straight (

). Lowland forest of Manombo …… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Body length 
21–28 mm
, black or dark brown. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles. Movable finger of posterior telopod curved ………………………………………………………5
</p>
            <p>
5. Mid-body legs with strongly developed coxal process. Tergite surface shiny. Littoral forest of Sainte Luce, fragment 
S
9 ………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>– Mid-body legs with barely developed coxal process. Tergite surface dull …………………………6</p>
            <p>
6. Endotergum with strongly developed cuticular patterns. Movable finger of posterior telopod without small pits, carrying 20–22 crenulated teeth. Andohahela mountain chain, Manantantely, Malio and Isaka-Ivondro …………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Endotergum with weakly developed cuticular patterns. Movable finger of posterior telopod covered with small pits, carrying 23 or 24 crenulated teeth. Inside Grotte d’Andrahomana and in deep ravines 
N
of Ankapaky …………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
7. Unique black pattern on orange-reddish basic colour. Harp with 5 ribs. Endotergum with three rows of marginal bristles. Widespread in the SW spiny forest …… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>– Colour different, either uniformly black or brown. Rainforest species ……………………………8</p>
            <p>
8. Harp with 4 stridulation ribs. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles, not reaching tergite margin. Operculum well-rounded. Dark brown to black species. Lavasoa Mountain ……… …………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>– Harp with 5 or 6 stridulation ribs. Endotergum with one to three rows of marginal bristles …9</p>
            <p>
9. Harp with 5 stridulation ribs (

). Movable finger of posterior telopod with one or two membranous lobes. Marginal bristles of endotergum protruding beyond tergite margin (

) …10
</p>
            <p>
– Harp with 6 stridulation ribs (

). Movable finger of posterior telopod with two membranous lobes (

) ……………………………………………………………………………………11
</p>
            <p>
10. Operculum apically recessed. Medium-sized species. Movable finger of posterior telopod with single membranous lobe and 26 crenulated teeth. Eyes with&gt;60 ocelli. Rudimentary lateral palpi consisting of 3 sensilla. Vevembe-Vatovavy area … 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Operculum well-rounded, typical for genus (

). Gigantic species (&gt; 
50 mm
). Movable finger of posterior telopod with two membranous lobes and 30 crenulated teeth (

). Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli. Rudimentary lateral palpi consisting of 4 sensilla (

). Kalambatritra Rainforest ………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">
sp. 

nov. 
<p>
11. Small, black species, red legs. Endotergum with single sparse row of very short marginal bristles. Posterior telopod with four spines and 36 crenulated teeth. Ivohibe Mountain ………… …………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
                  </p>
               </named-content>
            </p>
            <p>
– Gigantic (&gt; 
50 mm
), brown species. Endotergum with two dense rows of long marginal bristles (

). Posterior telopod with two spines and 32 crenulated teeth (

). Midongy Rainforest … ………………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. midongy
</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Large, massive, brown 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
,&gt; 
50 mm
long. Differing from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
in having five stridulation ribs on the male harp (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. musicus

(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. vatovavy
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
) in the following characters: tarsus of leg 3 without an apical spine, coxal process almost absent, posterior telopod with two membranous lobes.&gt;80 ocelli.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The specific epithet ‘kalambatritra’, noun in apposition, refers to the type-locality, the Réserve Spéciale de Kalambatritra (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
(3 ♂♂, 1 ♀)
</p>
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>Holotype</p>
               <p>MADAGASCAR
: 
♂
, 
Toliaria, Réserve Spéciale Kalambatritra, Befarara
, 
BLF21330
, 
23°25′04″ S
, 
46°26′52″ E
,alt. 
1390m
, 
montane rainforest
, 

7 
Feb.2009
, 
B.L. Fisheret al.
leg., 
general collecting
(
CASENT 9068297-A
).
</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
            <p>Paratypes</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>MADAGASCAR
: 
1♂
, same collection data as for holotype (
ZFMKMYR06125
);
</tp:material-citation>
               <tp:material-citation>
1 
♂
, same collection data as for holotype (
CASENT 9068297-C
);
</tp:material-citation>
               <tp:material-citation>
1 
♀
, 
Toliaria, Réserve Spéciale Kalambatritra, Ampanihy
, 
BLF21565
, 
23°27′49″S
, 
46°27′47″ E
,alt. 
1270m
, 
montane rainforest
, 

9–10 
Feb.2009
, 
B.L. Fisheret al.
leg., 
general collecting
(
CASENT 9058301
).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Male 
holotype
ca 
51.5 mm
long, 
24.4 mm
(2nd segment) up to 
28.2 mm
(10th segment = widest) wide, 
14 mm
(2nd segment) high. Female ca 
52 mm
long, 
24.7 mm
(2nd segment) wide, 
15.1 mm
(2nd segment) high (

).
</p>
            <p>
COLORATION OF PRESERVED SPECIMEN (

). Tergites in anterior half dark brown, posterior half light brown, posterior margin with thin dark brown band. Paratergites light brown with dark brown to blackish tips. Paratergite impressions and groove of thoracic shield light brown. Antennae brown, and legs and pleurites light brown to grey. Head laterally around eyes and at posterior margin dark brown, frontally light brown. Collum dark brown. Eyes green.
</p>
            <p>HEAD
. Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli, median ocelli small and increasing in size towards lateral and posterior part of eyes (

), several larger ocelli on lateral margin clearly separated from eye. Organ of Tömösváry positioned in antennal-groove (

). Antennae short, protruding to coxa of third leg, not reaching margin of thoracic shield. Antennomere 1 as long as 2+3; antennomeres 2–5 of similar length; antennomere 6 as long as 4+5, but shorter than 1. Antennomeres 1–6 and antennal groove densely pubescent (

). Antennomere 6 towards disc with single row of sensilla basiconica (

). Disc in female with 33/31, in male with 53/55 apical cones, as well as several setae shorter, or as long as, apical cones (

). Margin of labrum with setae.
</p>
            <p>
GNATHOCHILARIUM. Gnathochilarium typical for members of the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
, stipes and lamellamentum densely pubescent (

, 

). Lateral palpi rudimentary, not distinctly projecting over level of surrounding cuticle, consisting of four sensillae (

). Inner palpi well developed, with field of sensory-cones and scale-like structures (

). 
Central
pads (protuberance of endochilarium) with field of sensory-cones and smaller scale-like structures (

). Endochilarium with deep triangular incision between central pads, central pads projecting lamella-mentum nearly to base of inner palpi.
</p>
            <p>
Lateral endochilarium with densely packed median-pointing setae. Hypopharynx with single row of teeth lateral on both sides, anterior distinctly separated row of 8 teeth (

).
</p>
            <p>
MANDIBLE. Mandible with typical shape of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
(

), inner tooth 3-combed, with 6 long pectinate lamellae (

), condylus with a single, lower step at its apex (

). Condylus of mandible mounted against cuticular thickening on lateral margin of labrum, anteriorly of antennae (

). Tentorium lacking connection to head capsule via transverse bar. Posterior process triangular and plate-like, laying parallel to plate-like gnathal lobe sclerite. Epipharyngeal bar broad and laminar, running within epipahryngeal wall in direction of mandible condylus, broadening distally. Epipharyngeal bar with short lateral offshoot. Hypopharyngeal bar rod-like, curved within hypopharyngeal wall. Distal tip of hypopharyngeal bar reaches plate-like nebententorium. Nebententorium oriented at right angle to hypopharyngeal bar (

).
</p>
            <p>COLLUM. Collum glabrous except for few setae at margins.</p>
            <p>
THORACIC 
SHIELD
. Thoracic shield glabrous, with a chagrinated (leather-like) surface, few setae in grooves. Grooves deep (

).
</p>
            <p>BODYRINGS
. Tergites 3–12 with a chagrinated surface, small hair only present at posterior margin and in grooves, paratergite tips of mid-body tergites strongly projecting posteriorly (

). Tergites with single black locking carina.
</p>
            <p>ANALSHIELD
. Anal shield large, with a steep edge, entirely glabrous, with lighter and darker patches (

). Underside with single black locking carina, located closer to tergite margins than to pleurite.
</p>
            <p>
ENDOTERGUM. Endotergum inner section with loose field of short, cone-shaped spines and long setae (

). Externally 2–3 dense rows of long marginal bristles, slightly protruding above margin of tergite. Bristles covered with small, triangular spines, apically increasing in density (

).
</p>
            <p>
STIGMATIC PLATES. First stigma-carrying plate with a well-rounded projecting apex, apex covered with tiny spines and setae (

). Second plate (

) without apex and spines.
</p>
            <p>FIRST PLEURITE. First pleurite laterally well-rounded, without extensions.</p>
            <p>LEGS
. Leg 1 with 2, 2 with 4, 3 with 10 ventral spines and no apical spine. Leg pairs 4–21 with 12–16 ventral spines and an apical spine. Small coxa process developed, covered with field of spines (

). Femur 2.0, tarsus 3.3 times as long as wide. All podomeres with few setae (

). Toothed ridge (cleaning comb?) of femur with&gt;40 teeth, reaching ca. 0.8 times length of femur. Coxa in anterior aspect basally with a row of teeth, similar to “cleaning comb” on femur. Pronounced coxal process absent.
</p>
            <p>MALEGONOPORE
. Male gonopore typical for genus, plate glabrous, surrounded by relative large membranous area, few small spines basally of gonopore (

).
</p>
            <p>
ANTERIOR TELOPOD. Harp carrying five well-developed stridulation ribs (

). Shape usual for genus, with setae and tiny teeth at apical margin. Telopoditomere 4 with one large, triangular, apically weakly sclerotized spine and 2 smaller ones (

); basally on its anterior side with several tiny teeth. Telopoditomere 3 with triangular hump laterally, located close to border to telopoditomere 4 and juxtaposed to process of telopoditomere 2 (

).
</p>
            <p>
POSTERIOR TELOPOD. Podomere 3 slightly curved, 3.3 times as long as wide, slightly longer than immovable finger (

). Hollowed-out inner margin with two lobes and two spines, posterior aspect with ca 30 small crenulated teeth. Immovable finger straight, basally wide, apically tapering, only apical tip strongly curved towards podomere 3. Podomere 1 with few setae on lateral margin (

), podomere 2 only with few setae at anterior side, posterior side glabrous (

). Podomere 3 with only few marginal setae.
</p>
            <p>
FEMALE SEXUAL CHARACTERS. Vulva massive. Operculum well-rounded, protruding up to apical third of prefemur, with few marginal setae (

). Subanal plate large, with shallow invagination at apical margin (shape typical for genus). Washboard with ten stridulation ribs on each side, median in anterior half with black triangular field (

). The female carried several hundred eggs with a diameter of 
1.5–1.6 mm
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Only known from the type-locality, the Réserve Spéciale de Kalambatritra, which is a mountainous rainforest (

). In the same habitat, two undetermined giant pill-millipede species of the genus 
Zoosphaerium
occur sympatrically.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Large, massive, dark brown 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
,&gt; 
50 mm
long. Differing from the only known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
with six stridulation ribs on the male harp (
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibeWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
), with which it also shares the two lobes on the movable finger of the posterior telopod, in the following characters: large difference in size and colour pattern, a densely pubescent male gonopore, legs 4–21 with 14 or 15 ventral spines (
12 in<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
), and endotergum with two dense rows of long marginal bristles (single row in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>The specific epithet ‘midongy’, noun in apposition, refers to the type-locality, the Parc National de Midongy.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
(1 ♂)
</p>
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>Holotype</p>
               <p>MADAGASCAR
: 1 
♂
, Province de 
Fianarantsoa
, 

Parc National de Midongy-Befotaka, 
11.5km
SW of Befotaka village, VS-1536

, 
23°53.3′ S
, 
46°53.8′ E
, 
1055m
alt., 
dense humid transitional lowland and montane forest
, 
27 Feb. 2008
, 
V. Soarimalaia
leg. (
FMNH-INS 3119888
).
</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Male 
holotype
ca 
51.5 mm
long, 
24.1 mm
(2nd segment) and 
26.1 mm
(9th segment) wide, 
14.2 mm
(2nd segment) high.
</p>
            <p>COLORATION OF PRESERVED SPECIMEN. Tergites dark brown with black tips, posterior margin with a light brown band which is bordered anteriorly and posteriorly by thinner black bands. Paratergite impressions and groove of thoracic shield lighter brown. Legs, antennae, pleurites, head and collum brown, eyes green.</p>
            <p>HEAD
. Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli. Antennae short, protruding to third leg pair. Antennomere 1 as long as 2+3; 2 shorter than 3; 3–5 of similar length; 6 slightly shorter than 4+5. Antennomeres 1–6 densely pubescent (

). Antennomere 6 towards disc with single row of sensilla basiconica (

). Disc of male with 50/49 apical cones as well as several sensillae shorter or as long as sensory cones (

). Organ of Tömösváry in antennal groove close to eye. Margin of labrum with setae.
</p>
            <p>MOUTHPARTS. Not dissected.</p>
            <p>COLLUM. Collum glabrous except for few setae at margins.</p>
            <p>
THORACIC 
SHIELD
. Thoracic shield chagrinated (leather-like). Grooves deep, covered with setae.
</p>
            <p>BODYRINGS
. Paratergites 3–12 with posterior margin smooth, rest chagrinated, with hairs on posterior and anterior margin, paratergite tips of mid-body tergites strongly projecting posteriorly.
</p>
            <p>ANALSHIELD
. Anal shield massive, well-rounded, lacking pubescent area. Underside with single black locking carina, located closer to tergite margins than to pleurite.
</p>
            <p>
ENDOTERGUM. Endotergum inner section with setae and triangular spines (

). Between margin and inner area with single row of large, elliptical cuticular patterns. Externally two row of marginal bristles. Bristles protruding weakly above tergite margin. Bristles with small triangular spines, apically increasing in density (

).
</p>
            <p>
STIGMATIC PLATES. First stigma-carrying plate with a well-rounded, projecting apex covered by hairs (

). Second plate without apex, but with field of teeth opposite of coxa (

).
</p>
            <p>FIRST PLEURITE. First pleurite laterally well-rounded, without extensions.</p>
            <sec sec-type="multiple">
               <title>LEGS
. Leg 1 with 4, 2 with 5 ventral spines and no apical spine; leg 3 with 10 ventral spines and a short apical spine. Leg pairs 4–21 with 14 or 15 ventral spines. Coxa process weakly developed, with small, black, triangular spines (

). Femur 1.5, tarsus 3.5 times as long as wide. All podomeres
</title>
            </sec>
            <p>
densely pubescent (

). Toothed ridge of femur ca ⅔ length of femur, with 40 small teeth, distally increasing in size. Coxa in anterior aspect basally with a row of teeth, similar to toothed ridge on femur.
</p>
            <p>
MALE GONOPORE. Male gonopore densely pubescent, shape typical for genus (

).
</p>
            <p>
ANTERIOR TELOPOD. Harp with six stridulation ribs (

), all ribs of similar length. Shape usual for genus, telopoditomere 4 with one large triangular spine with sclerotized tip and 2 smaller spines (

). Telopoditomeres 3 and 4 with sclerotized spots.
</p>
            <p>
POSTERIOR TELOPOD. Podomere 3 slightly curved, 3 times longer than wide, slightly longer than immovable finger (

). Hollowed-out inner margin with two lobes and two spines, posterior aspect with ca32 small crenulated teeth (

). Immovable finger constant in width, only apically tapering, tip weakly curved towards podomere 3. Podomere 1 with setae, podomere 2 with few setae on anterior and posterior side. Podomere 3 and immovable finger with only few marginal setae (

).
</p>
            <p>Female sexual characters</p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Only known from the type-locality, the Parc National de Midongy (

). Mountainous rainforest.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="key">
         <title>Key to the species of<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
:
</title>
         <p>1. Male harp on the anterior telopod with 3 stridulation ribs …………………………………………2 – Male harp on the anterior telopod with 4–6 stridulation ribs ………………………………………7</p>
         <p>
2. Body length &lt;
20 mm
. Mid-body legs without a coxal lobe. Endotergum with single row of marginal bristles. Immovable finger of posterior telopod slender, apically strongly curved like a hook. Colour pink or brown ………………………………………………………………………………………3
</p>
         <p>
– Body length&gt; 
20 mm
. Mid-body legs at least with a weak coxal lobe. Endotergum usually with at least two, rarely only one 

(
<tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
) row of marginal bristles. Immovable finger of posterior telopod at least basally wide. Colour black or brown …………4
</p>
         <p>
3. Colour pink, surface shiny. Process of telopoditomere 2 of anterior telopods in anterior view visible laterally. Littoral forest of Mandena and rainforest of Enato …………………………… …………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
– Colour light brown, surface dull. Process of telopoditomere 2 of anterior telopods in anterior view not visible. Littoral forest of Sainte Luce, fragment S8 ……………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
4. Body length&gt; 
30mm
, light brown. Endotergum with single row of marginal bristles. Movable finger of posterior telopod straight (

). Lowland forest of Manombo …… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
– Body length 
21–28 mm
, black or dark brown. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles. Movable finger of posterior telopod curved ………………………………………………………5
</p>
         <p>
5. Mid-body legs with strongly developed coxal process. Tergite surface shiny. Littoral forest of Sainte Luce, fragment 
S
9 ………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>– Mid-body legs with barely developed coxal process. Tergite surface dull …………………………6</p>
         <p>
6. Endotergum with strongly developed cuticular patterns. Movable finger of posterior telopod without small pits, carrying 20–22 crenulated teeth. Andohahela mountain chain, Manantantely, Malio and Isaka-Ivondro …………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
– Endotergum with weakly developed cuticular patterns. Movable finger of posterior telopod covered with small pits, carrying 23 or 24 crenulated teeth. Inside Grotte d’Andrahomana and in deep ravines 
N
of Ankapaky …………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
7. Unique black pattern on orange-reddish basic colour. Harp with 5 ribs. Endotergum with three rows of marginal bristles. Widespread in the SW spiny forest …… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>– Colour different, either uniformly black or brown. Rainforest species ……………………………8</p>
         <p>
8. Harp with 4 stridulation ribs. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles, not reaching tergite margin. Operculum well-rounded. Dark brown to black species. Lavasoa Mountain ……… …………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>– Harp with 5 or 6 stridulation ribs. Endotergum with one to three rows of marginal bristles …9</p>
         <p>
9. Harp with 5 stridulation ribs (

). Movable finger of posterior telopod with one or two membranous lobes. Marginal bristles of endotergum protruding beyond tergite margin (

) …10
</p>
         <p>
– Harp with 6 stridulation ribs (

). Movable finger of posterior telopod with two membranous lobes (

) ……………………………………………………………………………………11
</p>
         <p>
10. Operculum apically recessed. Medium-sized species. Movable finger of posterior telopod with single membranous lobe and 26 crenulated teeth. Eyes with&gt;60 ocelli. Rudimentary lateral palpi consisting of 3 sensilla. Vevembe-Vatovavy area … 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
– Operculum well-rounded, typical for genus (

). Gigantic species (&gt; 
50 mm
). Movable finger of posterior telopod with two membranous lobes and 30 crenulated teeth (

). Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli. Rudimentary lateral palpi consisting of 4 sensilla (

). Kalambatritra Rainforest ………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">
sp. 

nov. 
<p>
11. Small, black species, red legs. Endotergum with single sparse row of very short marginal bristles. Posterior telopod with four spines and 36 crenulated teeth. Ivohibe Mountain ………… …………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </p>
            </named-content>
         </p>
         <p>
– Gigantic (&gt; 
50 mm
), brown species. Endotergum with two dense rows of long marginal bristles (

). Posterior telopod with two spines and 32 crenulated teeth (

). Midongy Rainforest … ………………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. midongy
</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure

&amp; Zehntner

, 
1902</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure

&amp; Zehntner
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>saintelucei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andrahomana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>musicus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>lavasoa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>vatovavy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. midongy
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. musicus

(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. vatovavy
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>st left</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibeWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>st left</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Integrative description of two new species of Malagasy chirping giant pill-millipedes, genus Sphaeromimus (Diplopoda: Sphaerotheriida: Arthrosphaeridae)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2017.381</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F42B3452FFF1FF88FF9FFFAFFFD5557C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2017.381</pub-id>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure

&amp; Zehntner

, 
1902</tp:taxon-name>
For a recent revision, see 

Wesener 
et al.
(
2014
)

.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>Key to the species of<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
:
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
            <sec sec-type="multiple">
               <title>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:620 
CAD
6B-DAB4-4FFC-8556-61357C75AF40 

, 
</title>
            </sec>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FA9166CE-73E5-41FE-A203-E4C999D2C0EE 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>1. Male harp on the anterior telopod with 3 stridulation ribs …………………………………………2 – Male harp on the anterior telopod with 4–6 stridulation ribs ………………………………………7</p>
            <p>
2. Body length &lt;
20 mm
. Mid-body legs without a coxal lobe. Endotergum with single row of marginal bristles. Immovable finger of posterior telopod slender, apically strongly curved like a hook. Colour pink or brown ………………………………………………………………………………………3
</p>
            <p>
– Body length&gt; 
20 mm
. Mid-body legs at least with a weak coxal lobe. Endotergum usually with at least two, rarely only one 

(
<tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
) row of marginal bristles. Immovable finger of posterior telopod at least basally wide. Colour black or brown …………4
</p>
            <p>
3. Colour pink, surface shiny. Process of telopoditomere 2 of anterior telopods in anterior view visible laterally. Littoral forest of Mandena and rainforest of Enato …………………………… …………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Colour light brown, surface dull. Process of telopoditomere 2 of anterior telopods in anterior view not visible. Littoral forest of Sainte Luce, fragment S8 ……………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
4. Body length&gt; 
30mm
, light brown. Endotergum with single row of marginal bristles. Movable finger of posterior telopod straight (

). Lowland forest of Manombo …… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Body length 
21–28 mm
, black or dark brown. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles. Movable finger of posterior telopod curved ………………………………………………………5
</p>
            <p>
5. Mid-body legs with strongly developed coxal process. Tergite surface shiny. Littoral forest of Sainte Luce, fragment 
S
9 ………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>– Mid-body legs with barely developed coxal process. Tergite surface dull …………………………6</p>
            <p>
6. Endotergum with strongly developed cuticular patterns. Movable finger of posterior telopod without small pits, carrying 20–22 crenulated teeth. Andohahela mountain chain, Manantantely, Malio and Isaka-Ivondro …………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Endotergum with weakly developed cuticular patterns. Movable finger of posterior telopod covered with small pits, carrying 23 or 24 crenulated teeth. Inside Grotte d’Andrahomana and in deep ravines 
N
of Ankapaky …………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
7. Unique black pattern on orange-reddish basic colour. Harp with 5 ribs. Endotergum with three rows of marginal bristles. Widespread in the SW spiny forest …… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>– Colour different, either uniformly black or brown. Rainforest species ……………………………8</p>
            <p>
8. Harp with 4 stridulation ribs. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles, not reaching tergite margin. Operculum well-rounded. Dark brown to black species. Lavasoa Mountain ……… …………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>– Harp with 5 or 6 stridulation ribs. Endotergum with one to three rows of marginal bristles …9</p>
            <p>
9. Harp with 5 stridulation ribs (

). Movable finger of posterior telopod with one or two membranous lobes. Marginal bristles of endotergum protruding beyond tergite margin (

) …10
</p>
            <p>
– Harp with 6 stridulation ribs (

). Movable finger of posterior telopod with two membranous lobes (

) ……………………………………………………………………………………11
</p>
            <p>
10. Operculum apically recessed. Medium-sized species. Movable finger of posterior telopod with single membranous lobe and 26 crenulated teeth. Eyes with&gt;60 ocelli. Rudimentary lateral palpi consisting of 3 sensilla. Vevembe-Vatovavy area … 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Operculum well-rounded, typical for genus (

). Gigantic species (&gt; 
50 mm
). Movable finger of posterior telopod with two membranous lobes and 30 crenulated teeth (

). Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli. Rudimentary lateral palpi consisting of 4 sensilla (

). Kalambatritra Rainforest ………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">
sp. 

nov. 
<p>
11. Small, black species, red legs. Endotergum with single sparse row of very short marginal bristles. Posterior telopod with four spines and 36 crenulated teeth. Ivohibe Mountain ………… …………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
                  </p>
               </named-content>
            </p>
            <p>
– Gigantic (&gt; 
50 mm
), brown species. Endotergum with two dense rows of long marginal bristles (

). Posterior telopod with two spines and 32 crenulated teeth (

). Midongy Rainforest … ………………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. midongy
</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Large, massive, brown 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
,&gt; 
50 mm
long. Differing from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
in having five stridulation ribs on the male harp (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. musicus

(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. vatovavy
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
) in the following characters: tarsus of leg 3 without an apical spine, coxal process almost absent, posterior telopod with two membranous lobes.&gt;80 ocelli.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The specific epithet ‘kalambatritra’, noun in apposition, refers to the type-locality, the Réserve Spéciale de Kalambatritra (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
(3 ♂♂, 1 ♀)
</p>
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>Holotype</p>
               <p>MADAGASCAR
: 
♂
, 
Toliaria, Réserve Spéciale Kalambatritra, Befarara
, 
BLF21330
, 
23°25′04″ S
, 
46°26′52″ E
,alt. 
1390m
, 
montane rainforest
, 

7 
Feb.2009
, 
B.L. Fisheret al.
leg., 
general collecting
(
CASENT 9068297-A
).
</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
            <p>Paratypes</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>MADAGASCAR
: 
1♂
, same collection data as for holotype (
ZFMKMYR06125
);
</tp:material-citation>
               <tp:material-citation>
1 
♂
, same collection data as for holotype (
CASENT 9068297-C
);
</tp:material-citation>
               <tp:material-citation>
1 
♀
, 
Toliaria, Réserve Spéciale Kalambatritra, Ampanihy
, 
BLF21565
, 
23°27′49″S
, 
46°27′47″ E
,alt. 
1270m
, 
montane rainforest
, 

9–10 
Feb.2009
, 
B.L. Fisheret al.
leg., 
general collecting
(
CASENT 9058301
).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Male 
holotype
ca 
51.5 mm
long, 
24.4 mm
(2nd segment) up to 
28.2 mm
(10th segment = widest) wide, 
14 mm
(2nd segment) high. Female ca 
52 mm
long, 
24.7 mm
(2nd segment) wide, 
15.1 mm
(2nd segment) high (

).
</p>
            <p>
COLORATION OF PRESERVED SPECIMEN (

). Tergites in anterior half dark brown, posterior half light brown, posterior margin with thin dark brown band. Paratergites light brown with dark brown to blackish tips. Paratergite impressions and groove of thoracic shield light brown. Antennae brown, and legs and pleurites light brown to grey. Head laterally around eyes and at posterior margin dark brown, frontally light brown. Collum dark brown. Eyes green.
</p>
            <p>HEAD
. Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli, median ocelli small and increasing in size towards lateral and posterior part of eyes (

), several larger ocelli on lateral margin clearly separated from eye. Organ of Tömösváry positioned in antennal-groove (

). Antennae short, protruding to coxa of third leg, not reaching margin of thoracic shield. Antennomere 1 as long as 2+3; antennomeres 2–5 of similar length; antennomere 6 as long as 4+5, but shorter than 1. Antennomeres 1–6 and antennal groove densely pubescent (

). Antennomere 6 towards disc with single row of sensilla basiconica (

). Disc in female with 33/31, in male with 53/55 apical cones, as well as several setae shorter, or as long as, apical cones (

). Margin of labrum with setae.
</p>
            <p>
GNATHOCHILARIUM. Gnathochilarium typical for members of the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
, stipes and lamellamentum densely pubescent (

, 

). Lateral palpi rudimentary, not distinctly projecting over level of surrounding cuticle, consisting of four sensillae (

). Inner palpi well developed, with field of sensory-cones and scale-like structures (

). 
Central
pads (protuberance of endochilarium) with field of sensory-cones and smaller scale-like structures (

). Endochilarium with deep triangular incision between central pads, central pads projecting lamella-mentum nearly to base of inner palpi.
</p>
            <p>
Lateral endochilarium with densely packed median-pointing setae. Hypopharynx with single row of teeth lateral on both sides, anterior distinctly separated row of 8 teeth (

).
</p>
            <p>
MANDIBLE. Mandible with typical shape of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
(

), inner tooth 3-combed, with 6 long pectinate lamellae (

), condylus with a single, lower step at its apex (

). Condylus of mandible mounted against cuticular thickening on lateral margin of labrum, anteriorly of antennae (

). Tentorium lacking connection to head capsule via transverse bar. Posterior process triangular and plate-like, laying parallel to plate-like gnathal lobe sclerite. Epipharyngeal bar broad and laminar, running within epipahryngeal wall in direction of mandible condylus, broadening distally. Epipharyngeal bar with short lateral offshoot. Hypopharyngeal bar rod-like, curved within hypopharyngeal wall. Distal tip of hypopharyngeal bar reaches plate-like nebententorium. Nebententorium oriented at right angle to hypopharyngeal bar (

).
</p>
            <p>COLLUM. Collum glabrous except for few setae at margins.</p>
            <p>
THORACIC 
SHIELD
. Thoracic shield glabrous, with a chagrinated (leather-like) surface, few setae in grooves. Grooves deep (

).
</p>
            <p>BODYRINGS
. Tergites 3–12 with a chagrinated surface, small hair only present at posterior margin and in grooves, paratergite tips of mid-body tergites strongly projecting posteriorly (

). Tergites with single black locking carina.
</p>
            <p>ANALSHIELD
. Anal shield large, with a steep edge, entirely glabrous, with lighter and darker patches (

). Underside with single black locking carina, located closer to tergite margins than to pleurite.
</p>
            <p>
ENDOTERGUM. Endotergum inner section with loose field of short, cone-shaped spines and long setae (

). Externally 2–3 dense rows of long marginal bristles, slightly protruding above margin of tergite. Bristles covered with small, triangular spines, apically increasing in density (

).
</p>
            <p>
STIGMATIC PLATES. First stigma-carrying plate with a well-rounded projecting apex, apex covered with tiny spines and setae (

). Second plate (

) without apex and spines.
</p>
            <p>FIRST PLEURITE. First pleurite laterally well-rounded, without extensions.</p>
            <p>LEGS
. Leg 1 with 2, 2 with 4, 3 with 10 ventral spines and no apical spine. Leg pairs 4–21 with 12–16 ventral spines and an apical spine. Small coxa process developed, covered with field of spines (

). Femur 2.0, tarsus 3.3 times as long as wide. All podomeres with few setae (

). Toothed ridge (cleaning comb?) of femur with&gt;40 teeth, reaching ca. 0.8 times length of femur. Coxa in anterior aspect basally with a row of teeth, similar to “cleaning comb” on femur. Pronounced coxal process absent.
</p>
            <p>MALEGONOPORE
. Male gonopore typical for genus, plate glabrous, surrounded by relative large membranous area, few small spines basally of gonopore (

).
</p>
            <p>
ANTERIOR TELOPOD. Harp carrying five well-developed stridulation ribs (

). Shape usual for genus, with setae and tiny teeth at apical margin. Telopoditomere 4 with one large, triangular, apically weakly sclerotized spine and 2 smaller ones (

); basally on its anterior side with several tiny teeth. Telopoditomere 3 with triangular hump laterally, located close to border to telopoditomere 4 and juxtaposed to process of telopoditomere 2 (

).
</p>
            <p>
POSTERIOR TELOPOD. Podomere 3 slightly curved, 3.3 times as long as wide, slightly longer than immovable finger (

). Hollowed-out inner margin with two lobes and two spines, posterior aspect with ca 30 small crenulated teeth. Immovable finger straight, basally wide, apically tapering, only apical tip strongly curved towards podomere 3. Podomere 1 with few setae on lateral margin (

), podomere 2 only with few setae at anterior side, posterior side glabrous (

). Podomere 3 with only few marginal setae.
</p>
            <p>
FEMALE SEXUAL CHARACTERS. Vulva massive. Operculum well-rounded, protruding up to apical third of prefemur, with few marginal setae (

). Subanal plate large, with shallow invagination at apical margin (shape typical for genus). Washboard with ten stridulation ribs on each side, median in anterior half with black triangular field (

). The female carried several hundred eggs with a diameter of 
1.5–1.6 mm
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Only known from the type-locality, the Réserve Spéciale de Kalambatritra, which is a mountainous rainforest (

). In the same habitat, two undetermined giant pill-millipede species of the genus 
Zoosphaerium
occur sympatrically.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Large, massive, dark brown 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
,&gt; 
50 mm
long. Differing from the only known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
with six stridulation ribs on the male harp (
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibeWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
), with which it also shares the two lobes on the movable finger of the posterior telopod, in the following characters: large difference in size and colour pattern, a densely pubescent male gonopore, legs 4–21 with 14 or 15 ventral spines (
12 in<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
), and endotergum with two dense rows of long marginal bristles (single row in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>The specific epithet ‘midongy’, noun in apposition, refers to the type-locality, the Parc National de Midongy.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
(1 ♂)
</p>
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>Holotype</p>
               <p>MADAGASCAR
: 1 
♂
, Province de 
Fianarantsoa
, 

Parc National de Midongy-Befotaka, 
11.5km
SW of Befotaka village, VS-1536

, 
23°53.3′ S
, 
46°53.8′ E
, 
1055m
alt., 
dense humid transitional lowland and montane forest
, 
27 Feb. 2008
, 
V. Soarimalaia
leg. (
FMNH-INS 3119888
).
</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Male 
holotype
ca 
51.5 mm
long, 
24.1 mm
(2nd segment) and 
26.1 mm
(9th segment) wide, 
14.2 mm
(2nd segment) high.
</p>
            <p>COLORATION OF PRESERVED SPECIMEN. Tergites dark brown with black tips, posterior margin with a light brown band which is bordered anteriorly and posteriorly by thinner black bands. Paratergite impressions and groove of thoracic shield lighter brown. Legs, antennae, pleurites, head and collum brown, eyes green.</p>
            <p>HEAD
. Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli. Antennae short, protruding to third leg pair. Antennomere 1 as long as 2+3; 2 shorter than 3; 3–5 of similar length; 6 slightly shorter than 4+5. Antennomeres 1–6 densely pubescent (

). Antennomere 6 towards disc with single row of sensilla basiconica (

). Disc of male with 50/49 apical cones as well as several sensillae shorter or as long as sensory cones (

). Organ of Tömösváry in antennal groove close to eye. Margin of labrum with setae.
</p>
            <p>MOUTHPARTS. Not dissected.</p>
            <p>COLLUM. Collum glabrous except for few setae at margins.</p>
            <p>
THORACIC 
SHIELD
. Thoracic shield chagrinated (leather-like). Grooves deep, covered with setae.
</p>
            <p>BODYRINGS
. Paratergites 3–12 with posterior margin smooth, rest chagrinated, with hairs on posterior and anterior margin, paratergite tips of mid-body tergites strongly projecting posteriorly.
</p>
            <p>ANALSHIELD
. Anal shield massive, well-rounded, lacking pubescent area. Underside with single black locking carina, located closer to tergite margins than to pleurite.
</p>
            <p>
ENDOTERGUM. Endotergum inner section with setae and triangular spines (

). Between margin and inner area with single row of large, elliptical cuticular patterns. Externally two row of marginal bristles. Bristles protruding weakly above tergite margin. Bristles with small triangular spines, apically increasing in density (

).
</p>
            <p>
STIGMATIC PLATES. First stigma-carrying plate with a well-rounded, projecting apex covered by hairs (

). Second plate without apex, but with field of teeth opposite of coxa (

).
</p>
            <p>FIRST PLEURITE. First pleurite laterally well-rounded, without extensions.</p>
            <sec sec-type="multiple">
               <title>LEGS
. Leg 1 with 4, 2 with 5 ventral spines and no apical spine; leg 3 with 10 ventral spines and a short apical spine. Leg pairs 4–21 with 14 or 15 ventral spines. Coxa process weakly developed, with small, black, triangular spines (

). Femur 1.5, tarsus 3.5 times as long as wide. All podomeres
</title>
            </sec>
            <p>
densely pubescent (

). Toothed ridge of femur ca ⅔ length of femur, with 40 small teeth, distally increasing in size. Coxa in anterior aspect basally with a row of teeth, similar to toothed ridge on femur.
</p>
            <p>
MALE GONOPORE. Male gonopore densely pubescent, shape typical for genus (

).
</p>
            <p>
ANTERIOR TELOPOD. Harp with six stridulation ribs (

), all ribs of similar length. Shape usual for genus, telopoditomere 4 with one large triangular spine with sclerotized tip and 2 smaller spines (

). Telopoditomeres 3 and 4 with sclerotized spots.
</p>
            <p>
POSTERIOR TELOPOD. Podomere 3 slightly curved, 3 times longer than wide, slightly longer than immovable finger (

). Hollowed-out inner margin with two lobes and two spines, posterior aspect with ca32 small crenulated teeth (

). Immovable finger constant in width, only apically tapering, tip weakly curved towards podomere 3. Podomere 1 with setae, podomere 2 with few setae on anterior and posterior side. Podomere 3 and immovable finger with only few marginal setae (

).
</p>
            <p>Female sexual characters</p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Only known from the type-locality, the Parc National de Midongy (

). Mountainous rainforest.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure

&amp; Zehntner

, 
1902</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure

&amp; Zehntner
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>saintelucei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>titanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>splendidus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>andrahomana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>musicus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>lavasoa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>vatovavy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. midongy
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. musicus

(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S
. vatovavy
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>st left</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibeWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>st left</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Integrative description of two new species of Malagasy chirping giant pill-millipedes, genus Sphaeromimus (Diplopoda: Sphaerotheriida: Arthrosphaeridae)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2017.381</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F42B3452FFF1FF88FF9FFFAFFFD5557C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2017.381</pub-id>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
de Saussure

&amp; Zehntner

, 
1902</tp:taxon-name>
For a recent revision, see 

Wesener 
et al.
(
2014
)

.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>Key to the species of<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
:
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus
kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
            <sec sec-type="multiple">
               <title>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:620 
CAD
6B-DAB4-4FFC-8556-61357C75AF40 

, 
</title>
            </sec>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:FA9166CE-73E5-41FE-A203-E4C999D2C0EE 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>1. Male harp on the anterior telopod with 3 stridulation ribs …………………………………………2 – Male harp on the anterior telopod with 4–6 stridulation ribs ………………………………………7</p>
            <p>
2. Body length &lt;
20 mm
. Mid-body legs without a coxal lobe. Endotergum with single row of marginal bristles. Immovable finger of posterior telopod slender, apically strongly curved like a hook. Colour pink or brown ………………………………………………………………………………………3
</p>
            <p>
– Body length&gt; 
20 mm
. Mid-body legs at least with a weak coxal lobe. Endotergum usually with at least two, rarely only one 

(
<tp:taxon-name>
S. 
titanus
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
) row of marginal bristles. Immovable finger of posterior telopod at least basally wide. Colour black or brown …………4
</p>
            <p>
3. Colour pink, surface shiny. Process of telopoditomere 2 of anterior telopods in anterior view visible laterally. Littoral forest of Mandena and rainforest of Enato …………………………… …………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. 
inexpectatus
Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Colour light brown, surface dull. Process of telopoditomere 2 of anterior telopods in anterior view not visible. Littoral forest of Sainte Luce, fragment S8 ……………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
saintelucei
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
4. Body length&gt; 
30mm
, light brown. Endotergum with single row of marginal bristles. Movable finger of posterior telopod straight (

). Lowland forest of Manombo …… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
titanusWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Body length 
21–28 mm
, black or dark brown. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles. Movable finger of posterior telopod curved ………………………………………………………5
</p>
            <p>
5. Mid-body legs with strongly developed coxal process. Tergite surface shiny. Littoral forest of Sainte Luce, fragment 
S
9 ………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
splendidus
Wesener &amp; 
Sierwald, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>– Mid-body legs with barely developed coxal process. Tergite surface dull …………………………6</p>
            <p>
6. Endotergum with strongly developed cuticular patterns. Movable finger of posterior telopod without small pits, carrying 20–22 crenulated teeth. Andohahela mountain chain, Manantantely, Malio and Isaka-Ivondro …………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andohahela
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Endotergum with weakly developed cuticular patterns. Movable finger of posterior telopod covered with small pits, carrying 23 or 24 crenulated teeth. Inside Grotte d’Andrahomana and in deep ravines 
N
of Ankapaky …………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
andrahomana
Wesener, 
2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
7. Unique black pattern on orange-reddish basic colour. Harp with 5 ribs. Endotergum with three rows of marginal bristles. Widespread in the SW spiny forest …… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
musicus
(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 
1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>– Colour different, either uniformly black or brown. Rainforest species ……………………………8</p>
            <p>
8. Harp with 4 stridulation ribs. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles, not reaching tergite margin. Operculum well-rounded. Dark brown to black species. Lavasoa Mountain ……… …………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
lavasoaWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>– Harp with 5 or 6 stridulation ribs. Endotergum with one to three rows of marginal bristles …9</p>
            <p>
9. Harp with 5 stridulation ribs (

). Movable finger of posterior telopod with one or two membranous lobes. Marginal bristles of endotergum protruding beyond tergite margin (

) …10
</p>
            <p>
– Harp with 6 stridulation ribs (

). Movable finger of posterior telopod with two membranous lobes (

) ……………………………………………………………………………………11
</p>
            <p>
10. Operculum apically recessed. Medium-sized species. Movable finger of posterior telopod with single membranous lobe and 26 crenulated teeth. Eyes with&gt;60 ocelli. Rudimentary lateral palpi consisting of 3 sensilla. Vevembe-Vatovavy area … 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
vatovavyWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Operculum well-rounded, typical for genus (

). Gigantic species (&gt; 
50 mm
). Movable finger of posterior telopod with two membranous lobes and 30 crenulated teeth (

). Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli. Rudimentary lateral palpi consisting of 4 sensilla (

). Kalambatritra Rainforest ………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. kalambatritra
</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">
sp. 

nov. 
<p>
11. Small, black species, red legs. Endotergum with single sparse row of very short marginal bristles. Posterior telopod with four spines and 36 crenulated teeth. Ivohibe Mountain ………… …………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. ivohibe
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
                  </p>
               </named-content>
            </p>
            <p>
– Gigantic (&gt; 
50 mm
), brown species. Endotergum with two dense rows of long marginal bristles (

). Posterior telopod with two spines and 32 crenulated teeth (

). Midongy Rainforest … ………………………………………………………………………………… 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. midongy
</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Large, massive, brown 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
,&gt; 
50 mm
long. Differing from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
in having five stridulation ribs on the male harp (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. musicus

(Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. vatovavy
Wesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
) in the following characters: tarsus of leg 3 without an apical spine, coxal process almost absent, posterior telopod with two membranous lobes.&gt;80 ocelli.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The specific epithet ‘kalambatritra’, noun in apposition, refers to the type-locality, the Réserve Spéciale de Kalambatritra (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
(3 ♂♂, 1 ♀)
</p>
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>Holotype</p>
               <p>MADAGASCAR
: 
♂
, 
Toliaria, Réserve Spéciale Kalambatritra, Befarara
, 
BLF21330
, 
23°25′04″ S
, 
46°26′52″ E
,alt. 
1390m
, 
montane rainforest
, 

7 
Feb.2009
, 
B.L. Fisheret al.
leg., 
general collecting
(
CASENT 9068297-A
).
</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
            <p>Paratypes</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>MADAGASCAR
: 
1♂
, same collection data as for holotype (
ZFMKMYR06125
);
</tp:material-citation>
               <tp:material-citation>
1 
♂
, same collection data as for holotype (
CASENT 9068297-C
);
</tp:material-citation>
               <tp:material-citation>
1 
♀
, 
Toliaria, Réserve Spéciale Kalambatritra, Ampanihy
, 
BLF21565
, 
23°27′49″S
, 
46°27′47″ E
,alt. 
1270m
, 
montane rainforest
, 

9–10 
Feb.2009
, 
B.L. Fisheret al.
leg., 
general collecting
(
CASENT 9058301
).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Male 
holotype
ca 
51.5 mm
long, 
24.4 mm
(2nd segment) up to 
28.2 mm
(10th segment = widest) wide, 
14 mm
(2nd segment) high. Female ca 
52 mm
long, 
24.7 mm
(2nd segment) wide, 
15.1 mm
(2nd segment) high (

).
</p>
            <p>
COLORATION OF PRESERVED SPECIMEN (

). Tergites in anterior half dark brown, posterior half light brown, posterior margin with thin dark brown band. Paratergites light brown with dark brown to blackish tips. Paratergite impressions and groove of thoracic shield light brown. Antennae brown, and legs and pleurites light brown to grey. Head laterally around eyes and at posterior margin dark brown, frontally light brown. Collum dark brown. Eyes green.
</p>
            <p>HEAD
. Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli, median ocelli small and increasing in size towards lateral and posterior part of eyes (

), several larger ocelli on lateral margin clearly separated from eye. Organ of Tömösváry positioned in antennal-groove (

). Antennae short, protruding to coxa of third leg, not reaching margin of thoracic shield. Antennomere 1 as long as 2+3; antennomeres 2–5 of similar length; antennomere 6 as long as 4+5, but shorter than 1. Antennomeres 1–6 and antennal groove densely pubescent (

). Antennomere 6 towards disc with single row of sensilla basiconica (

). Disc in female with 33/31, in male with 53/55 apical cones, as well as several setae shorter, or as long as, apical cones (

). Margin of labrum with setae.
</p>
            <p>
GNATHOCHILARIUM. Gnathochilarium typical for members of the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
, stipes and lamellamentum densely pubescent (

, 

). Lateral palpi rudimentary, not distinctly projecting over level of surrounding cuticle, consisting of four sensillae (

). Inner palpi well developed, with field of sensory-cones and scale-like structures (

). 
Central
pads (protuberance of endochilarium) with field of sensory-cones and smaller scale-like structures (

). Endochilarium with deep triangular incision between central pads, central pads projecting lamella-mentum nearly to base of inner palpi.
</p>
            <p>
Lateral endochilarium with densely packed median-pointing setae. Hypopharynx with single row of teeth lateral on both sides, anterior distinctly separated row of 8 teeth (

).
</p>
            <p>
MANDIBLE. Mandible with typical shape of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
(

), inner tooth 3-combed, with 6 long pectinate lamellae (

), condylus with a single, lower step at its apex (

). Condylus of mandible mounted against cuticular thickening on lateral margin of labrum, anteriorly of antennae (

). Tentorium lacking connection to head capsule via transverse bar. Posterior process triangular and plate-like, laying parallel to plate-like gnathal lobe sclerite. Epipharyngeal bar broad and laminar, running within epipahryngeal wall in direction of mandible condylus, broadening distally. Epipharyngeal bar with short lateral offshoot. Hypopharyngeal bar rod-like, curved within hypopharyngeal wall. Distal tip of hypopharyngeal bar reaches plate-like nebententorium. Nebententorium oriented at right angle to hypopharyngeal bar (

).
</p>
            <p>COLLUM. Collum glabrous except for few setae at margins.</p>
            <p>
THORACIC 
SHIELD
. Thoracic shield glabrous, with a chagrinated (leather-like) surface, few setae in grooves. Grooves deep (

).
</p>
            <p>BODYRINGS
. Tergites 3–12 with a chagrinated surface, small hair only present at posterior margin and in grooves, paratergite tips of mid-body tergites strongly projecting posteriorly (

). Tergites with single black locking carina.
</p>
            <p>ANALSHIELD
. Anal shield large, with a steep edge, entirely glabrous, with lighter and darker patches (

). Underside with single black locking carina, located closer to tergite margins than to pleurite.
</p>
            <p>
ENDOTERGUM. Endotergum inner section with loose field of short, cone-shaped spines and long setae (

). Externally 2–3 dense rows of long marginal bristles, slightly protruding above margin of tergite. Bristles covered with small, triangular spines, apically increasing in density (

).
</p>
            <p>
STIGMATIC PLATES. First stigma-carrying plate with a well-rounded projecting apex, apex covered with tiny spines and setae (

). Second plate (

) without apex and spines.
</p>
            <p>FIRST PLEURITE. First pleurite laterally well-rounded, without extensions.</p>
            <p>LEGS
. Leg 1 with 2, 2 with 4, 3 with 10 ventral spines and no apical spine. Leg pairs 4–21 with 12–16 ventral spines and an apical spine. Small coxa process developed, covered with field of spines (

). Femur 2.0, tarsus 3.3 times as long as wide. All podomeres with few setae (

). Toothed ridge (cleaning comb?) of femur with&gt;40 teeth, reaching ca. 0.8 times length of femur. Coxa in anterior aspect basally with a row of teeth, similar to “cleaning comb” on femur. Pronounced coxal process absent.
</p>
            <p>MALEGONOPORE
. Male gonopore typical for genus, plate glabrous, surrounded by relative large membranous area, few small spines basally of gonopore (

).
</p>
            <p>
ANTERIOR TELOPOD. Harp carrying five well-developed stridulation ribs (

). Shape usual for genus, with setae and tiny teeth at apical margin. Telopoditomere 4 with one large, triangular, apically weakly sclerotized spine and 2 smaller ones (

); basally on its anterior side with several tiny teeth. Telopoditomere 3 with triangular hump laterally, located close to border to telopoditomere 4 and juxtaposed to process of telopoditomere 2 (

).
</p>
            <p>
POSTERIOR TELOPOD. Podomere 3 slightly curved, 3.3 times as long as wide, slightly longer than immovable finger (

). Hollowed-out inner margin with two lobes and two spines, posterior aspect with ca 30 small crenulated teeth. Immovable finger straight, basally wide, apically tapering, only apical tip strongly curved towards podomere 3. Podomere 1 with few setae on lateral margin (

), podomere 2 only with few setae at anterior side, posterior side glabrous (

). Podomere 3 with only few marginal setae.
</p>
            <p>
FEMALE SEXUAL CHARACTERS. Vulva massive. Operculum well-rounded, protruding up to apical third of prefemur, with few marginal setae (

). Subanal plate large, with shallow invagination at apical margin (shape typical for genus). Washboard with ten stridulation ribs on each side, median in anterior half with black triangular field (

). The female carried several hundred eggs with a diameter of 
1.5–1.6 mm
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Only known from the type-locality, the Réserve Spéciale de Kalambatritra, which is a mountainous rainforest (

). In the same habitat, two undetermined giant pill-millipede species of the genus 
Zoosphaerium
occur sympatrically.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
Large, massive, dark brown 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
,&gt; 
50 mm
long. Differing from the only known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
with six stridulation ribs on the male harp (
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibeWesener, 2014</tp:taxon-name>
), with which it also shares the two lobes on the movable finger of the posterior telopod, in the following characters: large difference in size and colour pattern, a densely pubescent male gonopore, legs 4–21 with 14 or 15 ventral spines (
12 in<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
), and endotergum with two dense rows of long marginal bristles (single row in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>The specific epithet ‘midongy’, noun in apposition, refers to the type-locality, the Parc National de Midongy.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
(1 ♂)
</p>
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>Holotype</p>
               <p>MADAGASCAR
: 1 
♂
, Province de 
Fianarantsoa
, 

Parc National de Midongy-Befotaka, 
11.5km
SW of Befotaka village, VS-1536

, 
23°53.3′ S
, 
46°53.8′ E
, 
1055m
alt., 
dense humid transitional lowland and montane forest
, 
27 Feb. 2008
, 
V. Soarimalaia
leg. (
FMNH-INS 3119888
).
</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Male 
holotype
ca 
51.5 mm
long, 
24.1 mm
(2nd segment) and 
26.1 mm
(9th segment) wide, 
14.2 mm
(2nd segment) high.
</p>
            <p>COLORATION OF PRESERVED SPECIMEN. Tergites dark brown with black tips, posterior margin with a light brown band which is bordered anteriorly and posteriorly by thinner black bands. Paratergite impressions and groove of thoracic shield lighter brown. Legs, antennae, pleurites, head and collum brown, eyes green.</p>
            <p>HEAD
. Eyes with&gt;80 ocelli. Antennae short, protruding to third leg pair. Antennomere 1 as long as 2+3; 2 shorter than 3; 3–5 of similar length; 6 slightly shorter than 4+5. Antennomeres 1–6 densely pubescent (

). Antennomere 6 towards disc with single row of sensilla basiconica (

). Disc of male with 50/49 apical cones as well as several sensillae shorter or as long as sensory cones (

). Organ of Tömösváry in antennal groove close to eye. Margin of labrum with setae.
</p>
            <p>MOUTHPARTS. Not dissected.</p>
            <p>COLLUM. Collum glabrous except for few setae at margins.</p>
            <p>
THORACIC 
SHIELD
. Thoracic shield chagrinated (leather-like). Grooves deep, covered with setae.
</p>
            <p>BODYRINGS
. Paratergites 3–12 with posterior margin smooth, rest chagrinated, with hairs on posterior and anterior margin, paratergite tips of mid-body tergites strongly projecting posteriorly.
</p>
            <p>ANALSHIELD
. Anal shield massive, well-rounded, lacking pubescent area. Underside with single black locking carina, located closer to tergite margins than to pleurite.
</p>
            <p>
ENDOTERGUM. Endotergum inner section with setae and triangular spines (

). Between margin and inner area with single row of large, elliptical cuticular patterns. Externally two row of marginal bristles. Bristles protruding weakly above tergite margin. Bristles with small triangular spines, apically increasing in density (

).
</p>
            <p>
STIGMATIC PLATES. First stigma-carrying plate with a well-rounded, projecting apex covered by hairs (

). Second plate without apex, but with field of teeth opposite of coxa (

).
</p>
            <p>FIRST PLEURITE. First pleurite laterally well-rounded, without extensions.</p>
            <sec sec-type="multiple">
               <title>LEGS
. Leg 1 with 4, 2 with 5 ventral spines and no apical spine; leg 3 with 10 ventral spines and a short apical spine. Leg pairs 4–21 with 14 or 15 ventral spines. Coxa process weakly developed, with small, black, triangular spines (

). Femur 1.5, tarsus 3.5 times as long as wide. All podomeres
</title>
            </sec>
            <p>
densely pubescent (

). Toothed ridge of femur ca ⅔ length of femur, with 40 small teeth, distally increasing in size. Coxa in anterior aspect basally with a row of teeth, similar to toothed ridge on femur.
</p>
            <p>
MALE GONOPORE. Male gonopore densely pubescent, shape typical for genus (

).
</p>
            <p>
ANTERIOR TELOPOD. Harp with six stridulation ribs (

), all ribs of similar length. Shape usual for genus, telopoditomere 4 with one large triangular spine with sclerotized tip and 2 smaller spines (

). Telopoditomeres 3 and 4 with sclerotized spots.
</p>
            <p>
POSTERIOR TELOPOD. Podomere 3 slightly curved, 3 times longer than wide, slightly longer than immovable finger (

). Hollowed-out inner margin with two lobes and two spines, posterior aspect with ca32 small crenulated teeth (

). Immovable finger constant in width, only apically tapering, tip weakly curved towards podomere 3. Podomere 1 with setae, podomere 2 with few setae on anterior and posterior side. Podomere 3 and immovable finger with only few marginal setae (

).
</p>
            <p>Female sexual characters</p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Only known from the type-locality, the Parc National de Midongy (

). Mountainous rainforest.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Barcoding results</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
shows the lowest genetic distance to the undetermined specimen from Vevembe (

), with a 8.4% divergence. The distance of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from the only rainforest located close-by is 9.4%. The highest distance of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
within 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
is 19% to both 
<tp:taxon-name>S. inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
(
Table 2
). 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
also has the lowest pairwise distance to the undetermined Vevembe specimen, with 6.3%, and the highest to 
<tp:taxon-name>S. andohahela</tp:taxon-name>
with 21.1% (
Table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
The maximum likelihood tree receives high support for nodes at the species level (e.g., 100% for 
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
) and shallower nodes (e.g., 100% for 
<tp:taxon-name>S. saintelucei</tp:taxon-name>
+ 
<tp:taxon-name>S. inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name>
), while deeper nodes receive no support (e.g., 39% for 
<tp:taxon-name>S. titanus</tp:taxon-name>
+ (
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
+ (
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
+ Specimen from Vevembe)) + (
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
+ 
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
)). Branches separating taxa are relatively long (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
is recovered as a monophyletic group with 74% bootstrap support. A sistergroup relationship of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
with the undetermined specimen from Vevembe receives high support (99%) (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
as the sister-group to 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
+ the undetermined specimen from Vevembe receives 100% bootstrap support. This clade is separated by a long branch from a group comprising 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
. Monophyly of those four taxa is supported with 63% bootstrap support (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
Updated distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Including the two newly described species, the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
is still restricted to southeastern 
Madagascar
. With 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, we record the western-most distribution of a rainforest species (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
was, as all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
, found to live in direct sympatry with at least one species of 
Zoosphaerium
.
</p>
         <p>Micro-CT in taxonomy and phylogeny</p>
         <p>
Already 

Akkari 
et al.
(2015)

showed the great potential of micro-CT in millipede taxonomy. It can be used to visualize and infer internal morphological characters, which can be exploited not only for the species description itself, but also for subsequent morphological phylogenetic reconstruction as demonstrated by 
Blanke &amp; Wesener (2014)
. Here, we show that micro-CT is not only a useful tool to examine hard sclerotized structures like the head capsule, the gnathal lobe sclerite and the tentorium (

), but also to visualize soft parts like the collagenous tendon and single muscles (

).
</p>
         <p>Fig. 10.
Maximum likelihood tree based on the COI sequence after 1000 bootstrap replicates under the GTR+G+I model. Branch length indicates genetic distance. Numbers on branches indicate bootstrap support. Schematic drawing shows right anterior telopod of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
Numbers in circles indicate number of stridulation ribs on the male harp.
</p>
         <p>
The advantage of micro-CT compared to conventional invasive methods is that it does not damage the specimen. This is especially important, because many new species are found in museum collections and are only represented by a few or a single specimen, like the species described in this study. These specimens cannot be examined without permission and should not be damaged. This makes it nearly impossible to study internal features by dissection or histological sectioning. Furthermore, it makes it possible to share morphological information via public databases, which otherwise opens up a variety of new possibilities, as outlined by 

Akkari 
et al.
(2015)

. Therefore, we suggest considering the use of micro-CT in taxonomic studies if it seems advantageous to include internal characters. For the first time we add internal characters to the taxonomic description of a member of the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
. We describe the structure of the tentorium and the articulation of the mandible condylus. At this point, it is not possible to state which of these characters show inter- or intraspecific variations, because there is no data available yet for other species, except the descriptions of the tentorium of 
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaera dentigera
(Verhoeff 1930)
</tp:taxon-name>
by 
Verhoeff (1932)
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeropoeus modiglianii
Silvestri, 1895
</tp:taxon-name>
, a 
<tp:taxon-name>Zephroniidae</tp:taxon-name>
, by 
Silvestri (1903)
. Future studies will elaborate whether any useful taxonomic characters can be collected from these inner morphological features. The structure of the tentorium of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
corresponds to the state described for 
<tp:taxon-name>A. dentigera</tp:taxon-name>
. The hypopharnygeal bar of the tentorium of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
is elongated, while the nebententorium is more stout compared to the state depicted by 
Silvestri (1903)
for the 
<tp:taxon-name>Zephroniidae</tp:taxon-name>
. Furthermore, the posterior process of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
seems larger than in 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeropoeus</tp:taxon-name>
, although this could be due to the perspective Silvestri chose to depict the tentorium. The shape of the epipharyngeal bar shows a high similarity in both.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Genetic analysis</title>
         <p>
The high genetic distances between the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
suggest an early speciation event, as previously suggested by 

Wesener 
et al.
(2010

, 
2014
). The 
COI
gene probably lost its resolution due to the accumulation of reverse substitutions over time. 

Klopfstein 
et al.
(2010)

and 
Townsend &amp; Leuenberger (2011)
showed that the ‘informativeness’ of the 
COI
gene declines in older splits.
</p>
         <p>
As shown in several studies on giant pill-millipedes (e.g., 

Wesener 
et al.
2010

for 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
; 

Wongthamwanich 
et al.
2012

and 

Golovatch 
et al.
2012

for 
<tp:taxon-name>Zephroniidae</tp:taxon-name>
), the 
COI
gene remains nevertheless a powerful tool for the taxonomy and identification of giant pill-millipede species. It makes it possible to assign specimens of different stages, gender or with high morphological intraspecific variation to a species. Otherwise, it is not necessarily possible to assign such specimens to a species based solely on morphological evidence (see 

Wesener 
et al.
2014

). The 
COI
barcode shows a close and well-supported relationship between 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and the undetermined (female) specimen from Vevembe (

). In previous studies, the specimen from Vevembe was separated from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
+ 
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
by a long branch and with weak support (see 

Wesener 
et al.
2014

). With a genetic distance of 6.3% between 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and the specimen from Vevembe, they cannot be assigned to the same species based on 
COI
data alone until morphological characters of the male of the Vevembe population become available. Thus, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. inexpectatus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. saintelucei</tp:taxon-name>
show a genetic distance of only 4.1% in our analysis and 4.0% in the study conducted by 

Wesener 
et al.
(2014)

, and are regarded as separate species based on morphological characters. Nevertheless, the genetic distance of the 
COI
sequence fragment in 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
is usually 8–20% between two species (

Wesener 
et al.
2014

). Therefore, it cannot be ruled out that the specimen from Vevembe belongs to 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp.nov.</named-content>
To draw sufficiently supported conclusions, further studies and sampling of these areas are needed.A comparison of the genetic distance and the geographical distance reveal an interesting biogeographic pattern. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
and the specimen from Vevembe, which are separated by ca 
43 km
(

), show a genetic distance of 15.1% while 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and the specimen from Vevembe are separated by 
125 km
(

), and have a genetic distance of 6.3%. The genetic distance between 
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
is 9.4%, although the geographical distance is only 
65 km
(

). This demonstrates that species endemic to geographically close habitats are not necessarily closely related (see also 

Wesener 
et al.
2014

).
</title>
         <p>Number of stridulation ribs of the male harp</p>
         <p>
Comparing the number of stridulation ribs on the male harp to the species-tree, there seems to be one clade with an increased number of stridulation ribs (

). While most known 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
have three stridulation ribs (
4 in<tp:taxon-name>S. lavasoa</tp:taxon-name>
) the clade (
<tp:taxon-name>S. kalambatritra</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
+ (
<tp:taxon-name>S. midongy</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
+ specimen from Vevembe)) + (
<tp:taxon-name>S. musicus</tp:taxon-name>
+ 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ivohibe</tp:taxon-name>
) has five or six stridulation ribs. However, it has to be noted that there is no information on the number in the specimen from Vevembe, since we know a single female only. We can assume that the ancestral state is a low number of stridulation ribs on the male harp, as seen in other representatives of the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaeridae</tp:taxon-name>
. In 
<tp:taxon-name>Arthrosphaera</tp:taxon-name>
the number of stridulation ribs can vary between none and 2 ribs, 
<tp:taxon-name>Microsphaerotherium</tp:taxon-name>
has one rib and 
Zoosphaerium
has one or two (
Wesener &amp; VandenSpiegel 2009
). The advantage of a high number of stridulation ribs remains unclear. Thus, the habitats of species with high or low numbers of stridulation ribs overlap. Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeromimus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Zoosphaerium
usually occur in sympatry (

Wesener 
et al.
2014

). The number of ribs might have an impact on the sound production, but only for South African species information about the produced sounds is available (

Wesener 
et al.
2011

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>
This work is the result of a study class conducted in the course of the international Master OEP program based at the University of Bonn. The examined material was kindly provided by Petra Sierwald, Crystal Maier (both 
FMNH
) and Darrel Ubick (
CAS
). We especially thank the collectors Brian L. Fisher (
CAS
) and Steve M. Goodman (
FMNH
), as well as V. Soarimalaia, for their continuous inventorying efforts on 
Madagascar
, unearthing numerous undescribed species. Claudia Etzbauer (
ZFMK
) is thanked for assistance in the molecular laboratory. Karen Ulmen and Hans-Joachim Krammer (both 
ZFMK
) provided help at the SEM. Claudia Koch and Peter Rühr (
ZFMK
) are thanked for assistance at the micro-CT. Thorsten Klug made habitus pictures. Christina Sagorny is thanked for advice and help during the whole project. Brian L. Fisher, Mitch Irwin (
NorthernIllinois
University) and Jörg Ganzhorn (University of 
Hamburg
) kindly provided information about the sampling sites. Futhermore, we thank the two anonymous reviewers and the editor Rudy C.A.M. Jocqué for their comments and suggestions.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Akkari N.
, 
Enghoff H.
&amp; 
Metscher B.D.2015
. 
A new dimension in documenting new species: highdetail imaging for myriapod taxonomy and first 3D cybertype of a new millipede species (Diplopoda, Julida, Julidae)
. 
PloS One10
(
8
): e 
0135243
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0135243</p>
         <p>Altschul S.F.
, 
Gish W.
, 
Miller W.
, 
Myers E.W.
&amp; 
Lipman D.J.1990
. 
Basic local alignment search tool
. 
Journal of Molecular Biology215
(
3
): 
403–410
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2</p>
         <p>Astrin J.J.
&amp; 
Stüben P.E.2008
. 
Phylogeny in cryptic weevils: molecules, morphology and new genera of western Palaearctic Cryptorhynchinae (Coleoptera: Curculionidae)
. 
Invertebrate Systematics22
(
5
): 
503–522
. 
https://doi.org/10.1071/IS07057</p>
         <p>Blanke A.
&amp; 
Wesener T.2014
. 
Revival of forgotten characters and modern imaging techniques help to produce a robust phylogeny of the Diplopoda (Arthropoda, Myriapoda)
. 
Arthropod Structure &amp; Development43
: 
63–75
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.asd.2013.10.003</p>
         <p>Bora P.
, 
Randriambahiniarime M.O.
, 
Rabemananjara F.C.E.
, 
Ramilijaona O.R.
, 
Glaw F.
&amp; 
Vences M.2007
. 

A rapid assessment survey of the herpetofauna at Befotaka-Midongy National Park, south-eastern 
Madagascar
. 
Zoosystematics and Evolution83
(
2
): 
170–178
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/mmnz.200700007</p>
         <p>
Cárcamo H.A., Abe T.A., Prescott 
C
. 
E
., Holl F.B.&amp; Chanway 
C.P
. 
2000
. 

Influence of millipedes on litter decomposition, N mineralization, and microbial communities in a coastal forest in 
British Columbia
, 
Canada
. 
Canadian Journal of Forest Research
30

(
5
): 
817–826
. 

https://doi.org/10.1139/ 
x00
-014
</p>
         <p>Dewar R.E.
&amp; 
Wright H.T.1993
. 

The culture history of 
Madagascar
. 
Journal of World Prehistory7
(
4
): 
417–466
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00997802</p>
         <p>Enghoff H.2003
. 
Diplopoda, millipedes
. 
In
: 
Goodman S.M.
&amp; 
Benstead J.P.
(eds) 

Natural History of 
Madagascar
: 
617–627
. 
University of Chicago Press, Chicago
.
</p>
         <p>Felsenstein J
. 
1985
. 

Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap. 
Evolution39
(
4
): 
783–791
. 
https://doi.org/10.2307/2408678</p>
         <p>Ganzhorn J.U.
, 
Lowry P.P.
, 
Schatz G.E.
&amp; 
Sommer S.2001
. 

The biodiversity of 
Madagascar
: one of the world’s hottest hotspots on its way out

. 
Oryx35
(
4
): 
346–348
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-3008.2001.00201.x</p>
         <p>Glaw F.
&amp; 
Verdes M.2003
. 
Introduction to amphibians
. 
In
: 
Goodman S.M.
&amp; 
Benstead J.P.
(eds) 

Natural History of 
Madagascar
: 
883–898
. 
University of Chicago Press, Chicago
.
</p>
         <p>Golovatch S.
I., 
Wesener T.
, 
Mauriès J.P.
&amp; 

Semenyuk I. 

I. 
2012
. 

On the identities of 
Cryxus
Leach, 1814 and 
Zephronia
Gray, 1832, the oldest generic names in the millipede order Sphaerotheriida (Diplopoda)

. 
Arthropoda Selecta21
(
4
): 
273–294
.
</p>
         <p>Goodman S.M.
, 
Ganzhorn J.U.
&amp; 
Rakotondravony D.2003
. 
Introduction to mammals
. 
In
: 
Goodman S.M.
&amp; 
Benstead J.P.
(eds) 

Natural History of 
Madagascar
: 
1159–1186
. 
University of Chicago Press, Chicago
.
</p>
         <p>Green G.M.
&amp; 
Sussman R.W.1990
. 

Deforestation history of the eastern rain forests of 
Madagascar
from satellite images

. 
Science248
(
4952
): 
212–215
. 
https://doi.org/10.1126/science.248.4952.212</p>
         <p>Hall T.A.1999
. 
BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT
. 
Nucleic Acids Sympsoium41
: 
95–98
.
</p>
         <p>Harper G.J.
, 
Steininger M.K.
, 
Tucker C.J.
, 
Juhn D.
&amp; 
Hawkins F.2007
. 

Fifty years of deforestation and forest fragmentation in 
Madagascar
. 
Environmental Conservation
34 (4): 325–333

. 
https://doi.org/10.1017/S0376892907004262
Hebert P.D. &amp; Gregory T.R. 2005. The promise of 
DNA
barcoding for taxonomy. 
Systematic Biology54
(
5
): 
852–859
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/10635150500354886</p>
         <p>Hebert P
. 
D., Cywinska A. &amp; Ball S.L
. 
2003
. 

Biological identifications through DNA barcodes. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences270
(
1512
): 
313–321
. 
https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2002.2218</p>
         <p>Hijmans R.J.
, 
Guarino L.
, 
Cruz M.
&amp; 
Rojas E.2001
. 

Computer tools for spatial analysis of plant genetic resources data: 1. 
DIVA-GIS
. 
Plant Genetic Resources Newsletter127
: 
15–19
.
</p>
         <p>Horning N.R.2012
. 
Debunking three myths about Madagascar’s deforestation
. 
Madagascar
Conservation and Development
7
(
3
): 
116–119
. 

https://doi.org/10.4314/mcd. 
v7
i3.3
</p>
         <p>Irwin M.T.
, 
Samonds K.E.
&amp; 
Raharison J.L.2001
. 

A biological inventory of the lemur community of Réserve Spéciale de Kalambatritra, South-Central 
Madagascar
. 
Lemur News6
: 
24–28
.
</p>
         <p>Jeekel C.A.W.1999
. 

A new pill-millipede from 
Madagascar
, with a catalogue of the species hitherto described from the island (Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida)

. 
Myriapod Memoranda1
: 5–20
</p>
         <p>Klopfstein S.
, 
Kropf C.
&amp; 
Quicke D.L.J.2010
. 
An evaluation of phylogenetic informativeness profiles and the molecular phylogeny of Diplazontinae (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae)
. 
Systematic Biology59
(
2
): 
226–241
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syp105</p>
         <p>Limaye A.2012
. 
Drishti: a volume exploration and presentation tool
. 
SPIE
Proceedings Developments in X-Ray Tomography
885060
X. 
https://doi.org/10.1117/12.935640</p>
         <p>Moat J.
&amp; 
Smith P.2007
. 

Atlas of the Vegetation of 
Madagascar
. 

Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, Richmond, 
Surrey
.
</p>
         <p>Myers N.
, 
Mittermeier R.A.
, 
Mittermeier C.G.
, 
da Fonseca A.B.
&amp; 
Kent
J.
2000
. 
Biodiversity hotspots for conservation priorities
. 
Nature491
(
333
): 
853–858
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/35002501</p>
         <p>Oatley C.W.
, 
Nixon W.C.
&amp; 
Pease R.F.W.1966
. 
Scanning electron microscopy
. 
Advances in Electronics and Electron Physics21
: 
181–247
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0065-2539(08)61010-0</p>
         <p>Padial J.M.
, 
Miralles A.
, 
De La Riva I
. &amp; 
Vences M.2010
. 
The integrative future of taxonomy
. 
Frontiers in Zoology7
(
1
): 
1–14
. 
https://doi.org/10.1186/1742-9994-7-16</p>
         <p>Raxworthy C.J.2003
. 
Introduction to reptiles
. 
In
: 
Goodman S.M.
&amp; 
Benstead J.P.
(eds) 

Natural History of 
Madagascar
: 
934–949
. 
University of Chicago Press, Chicago
.
</p>
         <p>Ritman E.L.2004
. 
Micro-computed tomography – current status and developments
. 
Annual Review of Biomedical Engineering6
: 
185–208
. 
https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.bioeng.6.040803.140130</p>
         <p>Sanger F.
, 
Nicklen S.
&amp; 
Coulson A.R.1977
. 
DNA
sequencing with chain-terminating inhibitors

. 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences74
(
12
): 
5463–5467
. 
https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.74.12.5463</p>
         <p>Schindelin J.
, 
Arganda-Carreras I
., 
Frise
E.

, 
Kaynig V
., 
Longair M.
, 
Pietzsch T.
, 
Preibisch S.
, 
Rueden C.
, 
Saalfeld S.
, 
Schmid B.
, 
Tinevez J.
, 
White D.J.
, 
Hartenstein V
., 
Eliceiri K.
, 
Tomancak P.
&amp; 
Cardona A.2012
. 
Fiji
: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis

. 
Nature Methods9
(
7
): 
676–682
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/nmeth.2019</p>
         <p>Shear W.A.
&amp; 
Edgecombe G.D.2010
. 
The geological record and phylogeny of the Myriapoda
. 
Arthropod Structure &amp; Development39
: 
174–190
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.asd.2009.11.002</p>
         <p>Shelley R.M.
&amp; 

Golavatch S. 

I. 
2011
. 
Atlas of myriapod biogeography. I. Indigenous ordinal and supraordinal distributions in the Diplopoda: Perspectives on taxon origins and ages, and a hypothesis on the origin and early evolution of the class
. 
Insecta Mundi158
: 
1–134
.
</p>
         <p>Silvestri F.1903
. 
Classis Diplopoda
. Vol. 
1
, 

Anatome. Pars 1a, Segmenta, Tegumentum, Musculi. Della Torre, Portici, 
Italy
.
</p>
         <p>Tamura K.
&amp; 
Nei M.1993
. 

Estimation of the number of nucleotide substitutions in the control region of mitochondrial 
DNA
in humans and chimpanzees

. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution10
: 
512–526
.
</p>
         <p>Tamura K.
, 
Stecher G.
, 
Peterson D.
, 
Filipski A.
&amp; 
Kumar S.2013
. 
MEGA
6: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 6.0

. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution30
: 
2725–2729
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst197</p>
         <p>Tavaré S.1986
. 

Some probabilistic and statistical problems in the analysis of 
DNA
sequences

. 
Lectures on Mathematics in the Life Sciences17
: 
57–86
.
</p>
         <p>Townsend J.P.
&amp; 
Leuenberger C.2011
. 
Taxon sampling and the optimal rates of evolution for phylogenetic inference
. 
Systematic Biology60
(
3
): 
358–365
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syq097</p>
         <p>Verhoeff K.1932
. 
Diplopoda
. 
In
: 
Verhoeff K.
(ed.) 

Bronns Klassen und Ordnungen des Tierreichs, Bd. 
5/II.Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft, Leipzig
.
</p>
         <p>Waeber P.O.
, 
Wilmé L.
, 
Mercier J.R.
, 
Camara C.
&amp; 
Lowry II P.P.2016
. 

How effective have thirty years of internationally driven conservation and development efforts been in 
Madagascar
? 
PloS One
11 (8): e0161115

. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0161115</p>
         <p>Wells N.A.2003
. 

Some hypotheses on the Mesozoic and Cenozoic paleoenvironmental history of 
Madagascar
. 
In
: 
Goodman S.M.
&amp; 
Benstead J.P.
(eds) 

Natural History of 
Madagascar
: 
16–34
. 
University of Chicago Press, Chicago
.
</p>
         <p>Wesener T.2009
. 

Unexplored richness: discovery of 31 new species of giant pill-millipedes endemic to 
Madagascar
, with a special emphasis on microendemism (Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida)

. 
Zootaxa2097
: 
1–131
.
</p>
         <p>Wesener T.2014
a. 

Redescription of 
Polyzonium malagassum
, a new synonym of 
Rhinotus purpureus
(Pocock, 1894), with notes about the occurrence of the order Polyzoniida on 
Madagascar
(Diplopoda)

. 
Zootaxa3790
(
4
): 
587–594
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3790.4.7</p>
         <p>Wesener T.2014
b. 

First records of the order Siphonophorida from 
Madagascar
and 
Mauritius
(Diplopoda)

. 

Revue 
Suisse
de Zoologie
121
(
3
): 
415–423
. 
Available fromhttps://biodiversitylibrary.org/page/52965457
[accessed 
14 Nov. 2017
].
</p>
         <p>Wesener T.2014
c. 
A new phylogenetic analysis of the Sphaerotheriida (Diplopoda) with a revision of the Australian giant pill-millipedes
. 
Invertebrate Systematics28
(
2
): 
196–213
. 
https://doi.org/10.1071/IS13048</p>
         <p>Wesener T.2015
. 

No millipede endemics north of the Alps? DNA-barcoding reveals 
Glomeris malmivaga
Verhoeff, 1912 as a synonym of 
G. ornata
Koch, 1847 (Diplopoda, Glomerida, Glomeridae)

. 
Zootaxa3999
(
4
): 
571–580
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3999.4.7</p>
         <p>Wesener T.2016
. 
The giant pill-millipedes, order Sphaerotheriida – An annotated species catalogue with morphological atlas and list of apomorphies (Arthropoda: Diplopoda)
. 
Bonn Zoological Bulletin Supplementum63
: 
1–104
.
</p>
         <p>Wesener T.
&amp; 
Sierwald P.2005
. 

The giant pill-millipedes of 
Madagascar
- Revision of the genus 
Sphaeromimus
. 

Proceedings of the 
California
Academy of Science
56
: 
557–599
.
</p>
         <p>Wesener T.&amp; VandenSpiegel D
. 
2009
. 
A first phylogenetic analysis of giant pill-millipedes (Diplopoda: Sphaerotheriida), a new model Gondwanan taxon, with special emphasis on island gigantism
. 
Cladistics25
: 
545–573
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-0031.2009.00267.x</p>
         <p>Wesener T.
&amp; 
Wägele J.W.2008
. 

The giant pill-millipedes of 
Madagascar
: revision of the genus 
Zoosphaerium
(Myriapoda, Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida)

. 
Zoosystema30
(
1
): 
5–82
.
</p>
         <p>Wesener T.
, 
Enghoff H.
&amp; 
Sierwald P.2009
a. 

Review of the Spirobolida on 
Madagascar
, 

with descriptions of twelve new genera, including three genera of ‘fire millipedes’ (Diplopoda). 
Zookeys19
: 
1–128
. 
https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.19.221</p>
         <p>Wesener T.
, 
Enghoff H.
, 
Hoffmann R.L.
, 
Wägele J.W.
&amp; 
Sierwald P.2009
b. 

Revision of the endemic giant fire millipedes of 
Madagascar
, genus 
Aphistogoniulus
(Diplopoda: Spirobolida: Pachybolidae)

. 
International Journal of Myriapodology2
(
1
): 
15–52
. 
https://doi.org/10.1163/187525409X462403</p>
         <p>Wesener T.
, 
Raupach M.J.
&amp; 
Sierwald P.2010
. 

The origins of the giant pill-millipedes from 
Madagascar
(Diplopoda: Sphaerotheriida: Arthrosphaeridae)

. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution57
(
3
): 
1184– 1193
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2010.08.023</p>
         <p>Wesener T.
, 
Köhler J.
, 
Fuchs S.
&amp; 
VandenSpiegel D.2011
. 
How to uncoil your partner—“mating songs” in giant pill-millipedes (Diplopoda: Sphaerotheriida)
. 
Naturwissenschaften98
(
11
): 
967–975
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s00114-011-0850-8</p>
         <p>Wesener T.
, 
Minh-Tu Le D.
&amp; 
Loria S.F.2014
. 

Integrative revision of the giant pill-millipede genus 
Sphaeromimus
, with the description of seven new species (Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida, Arthrosphaeridae)

. 
ZooKeys414
: 
67–104
. 
https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.414.7730</p>
         <p>Wongthamwanich N.
, 
Panha S.
, 
Sierwald P.
, 
Wesener T.
&amp; 
Thirakhupt K.2012
. 

A new species of the giant pill-millipede genus 
Sphaerobelum
Verhoeff, 1924 from northern 
Thailand
, with an extensive description and molecular characters (Diplopoda: Sphaerotheriida: Zephroniidae)

. 
Zootaxa3220
: 
29–43
.
</p>
         <p>Yushkevich P.A.
, 
Piven J.
, 
Hazlett H.C.
, 
Smith R.G.
, 
Ho S.
, 
James C.
, 
Gee J.C.
&amp; 
Gerig G.2006
. 
Userguided 3D active contour segmentation of anatomical structures: Significantly improved efficiency and reliability
. 
Neuroimage31
(
3
): 
1116–1128
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2006.01.015</p>
         <p>
Manuscript received: 
2 January 2017
Manuscript accepted: 
28 March 2017
Published on: 
15 December 2017
Topic editor: Rudy Jocqué
</p>
         <p>Desk editor: Kristiaan Hoedemakers
Printed versions of all papers are also deposited in the libraries of the institutes that are members of the 
EJT
consortium: Muséum national d’Histoire naturelle, Paris, 
France
; Botanic Garden Meise, 
Belgium
; Royal Museum for 
Central
Africa, Tervuren, 
Belgium
; Natural History Museum, London, 
United Kingdom
; Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences, 
Brussels
, 
Belgium
; Natural History Museum of 
Denmark
, Copenhagen, 
Denmark
; Naturalis Biodiversity 
Center
, Leiden, 
the Netherlands
; Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales-CSIC, 
Madrid
, 
Spain
; Real Jardín Botánico de 
MadridCSIC
, 
Spain
.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
