<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1206/3877.1</journal-id>
         <issn>0003-0082</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Discovery of the Bee Tribe Tarsaliini in Arabia (Hymenoptera: Apidae), with the Description of a New Species</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2017</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A M E R I C A N M U S E U M N O 
V
I TAT E S
</title>
         <p>
Number 
3877
, 28 pp. 

March 20, 
2017</p>
         <p>
Discovery of the Bee Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>
in Arabia (
<tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Apidae</tp:taxon-name>
), with the Description of a New Species
</p>
         <p>MICHAEL S. ENGEL
, 
1ABDULAZIZ S. ALQARNI,2
AND MOHAMED A. SHEBL 
3</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>ABSTRACT</title>
         <p>
The uncommonly encountered bee tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Apinae</tp:taxon-name>
) is recorded from the Arabian Peninsula for the first time, and based on a new species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz. The
</tp:taxon-name>
tribes 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>
are diagnosed and their differences highlighted. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
, is described and figured from the eastern portion of the Najd of central-eastern 
Saudi Arabia
(Qassim and 
Riyadh
regions). The new species is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
, known only from 
Egypt
and 
Sudan
, as well as the larger 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Iran
. These three species are morphologically and largely geographically distinct from the remainder of the genus, and are segregated into a new subgenus, 
Astibomelissa
Engel. An updated and corrected checklist of the genera and subgenera of bees recorded from 
Saudi Arabia
is appended.
</p>
         <p>1Division of Invertebrate Zoology (Entomology), American Museum of Natural History; Division of Entomology, Natural History Museum, and Department of Ecology
&amp; 

Evolutionary Biology, University of 
Kansas
, Lawrence.
</p>
         <p>2
Department of Plant Protection, College of Food and Agriculture Sciences, King Saud University, 
Riyadh
, 
Saudi Arabia
.
</p>
         <p>3
Department of Plant Protection, College of Food and Agriculture Sciences, King Saud University, 
Riyadh
,
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>2 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
         <p>
The bee species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
are some of the more uncommonly encountered and little studied among Eurasian and northeastern African Anthophila. The genus was first described by 
Morawitz (1895)
from material collected by explorer naturalist Dmitry K. Glazunov (1869–1913) in 
Razavi Khorasan Province
, 
Iran
(at the time a southern part of “Greater 
Khorasan
” of 
Persia
), and near the present-day borders of 
Turkmenistan
and 
Afghanistan
. Subsequently, 
Popov (1935)
described a related species from southern 
Tajikistan
(eastern 
Khatlon Province
), and 
Baker (1971)
a species from southern 
India
(
Karaikal
), while subspecific forms of Morawitz’s and Popov’s species were documented from the eastern Mediterranean (
Pittioni, 1950
; 
Mavromoustakis, 1952
). 
Popov (1935)
also noted a similarity between 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
and the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
Lepeletier de Saint Fargeau
</tp:taxon-name>
, considering that some species of the latter may eventually prove to belong within the former. Nearly a half century later, 
Warncke (1977)
took this similarity a step further and united 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyla</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
as subgenera within a single genus, and subsequently provided a revision for the combined group (
Warncke, 1979
). 
Baker (1998)
corrected some errors of previous authors when describing another Indian species (Konkan), as well as transferring a further two overlooked taxa described in other genera, and thereby bringing the known fauna at the time to seven species (table 1). For nearly the last 20 years no further taxonomic treatments have considered species of the genus in any detail, nor has considerable material improved our impoverished understanding of the distribution or biology of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The general placement of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
among other groups of 
<tp:taxon-name>Apidae</tp:taxon-name>
has also been challenging for several reasons, not the least of which is a dearth of material. Subsequent to 
Morawitz’s (1895)
description, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
were rarely considered by melittologists, usually overlooked (e.g., 
Ashmead, 1899
) or mentioned only in passing as a genus of anthophorines (e.g., 
Friese, 1896
: under his concept of “Podaliriinae”). 
Cockerell (1933)
noted a general similarity between a species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
and the New World tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Exomalopsini</tp:taxon-name>
, although he did not recognize his species as congeneric with Morawitz’s genus and instead placed the Sudanese taxon in 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetralonia
Spinola
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Eucerini</tp:taxon-name>
). This same author again noted a similarity between 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
and the 
<tp:taxon-name>Exomalopsini</tp:taxon-name>
, as well as 
<tp:taxon-name>Emphorini</tp:taxon-name>
, when describing a species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyla</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Algeria
, but again wrongly attributed its genus—this time to 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyloscelis
Latreille. It
</tp:taxon-name>
was 
Popov (1935)
who first drew clearer attention to the affinities between 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyla</tp:taxon-name>
, and documented the peculiar asymmetry in the male seventh metasomal sternum of the former. In his world classification of bees, 
Michener (1944)
brought 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyla</tp:taxon-name>
together formally into a tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>4
(
Michener, 1944
), although the characters purportedly shared between these genera were problematic and applied only to one or the other of the two (
Baker, 1998
). 
Michener (1944)
did not have material from which to base his character assessments, relying on generally inadequate published descriptions, and even excluded the tribe from his final phylogenetic scheme due to the dearth of substantive information. 
Popov (1949)
subsequently suggested a relationship between 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Exomalopsini</tp:taxon-name>
(echoing the notion of 
Cockerell, 1933
), as well as 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucerini</tp:taxon-name>
. The tribe has remained little understood (e.g., 
Michener and Moure, 1957
), and attempts to place 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
among other apine bees have given varied results but consistently place 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyla</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
near 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucerini</tp:taxon-name>
, though they are not always as a monophyletic group (
Roig-Alsina and Michener, 1993
; 

Silveira, 1993 
a
, 1995; 
Baker, 1998
; 
Praz and Packer, 2014
; 
Plant and Paulus, 2016
). 
Baker (1998)
went so far as to constrain 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
to only its 
type
genus, removing 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
as a basal branch within 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucerini</tp:taxon-name>
and noting the birecurved gradulus on the female second metasomal sternum in both. Nonetheless, 
Michener (2000
, 
2007
) retained 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
in its traditional sense, correctly noting that several of 
Baker’s (1998)
characters were questionably defined or coded. Recently, the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
was again removed from 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
, although this time placed within its own tribe, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>
, and as a putative sister group to 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucerini</tp:taxon-name>
(
Engel, 2015
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>4
The tribe was originally established as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ancylini (
Michener, 1944
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, but was emended to 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
to remove homonymy with a family group among the 
<tp:taxon-name>Gastropoda</tp:taxon-name>
(
Engel et al., 2008
; 
ICZN, 2010
).
</p>
      <p>
2017 ENGEL ET AL.: ARABIAN 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
3
</p>
      <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIINI</tp:taxon-name>Engel, 2015
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Engel</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. subgen.</named-content>
         <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>Saudi Arabia
: Najd
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(
Cockerell, 1933
)
</tp:taxon-name>Egypt
, 
Sudan<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(
Warncke, 1979
)
</tp:taxon-name>Iran
: 
Khuzestan
, 
Fars
Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
         <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.str
.
</named-content>
         <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformisPopov, 1935</tp:taxon-name>Turkey
, 
Israel
, 
Turkmenistan
, 
Uzbekistan
, 
Tajikistan
= 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformis mediterraneaPittioni, 1950</tp:taxon-name>Cyprus
, Sardinia
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
cellularis
(
Cameron, 1898
)
</tp:taxon-name>India
: Deccan Plateau
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
deccanaBaker, 1971</tp:taxon-name>
[1972]
India
: Eastern and Western ghats
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
hirtipesMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>Turkey
, 
Uzbekistan
, 
Iran
: 
Razavi Khorasan
, 
Fars
,
Khuzestan
= 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
hirtipes cyriacaMavromoustakis, 1952</tp:taxon-name>Cyprus<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
strobilanthaeBaker, 1998</tp:taxon-name>India
: Konkan Coast

Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>
ANCYLAINI 
Michener, 1944</tp:taxon-name>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>AncylaLepeletier de Saint Fargeau, 1841</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>A
. 
asiaticaFriese, 1922</tp:taxon-name>Lebanon
, 
Turkey<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
brevisDours, 1873</tp:taxon-name>Algeria
= 
<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
punicaFriese, 1922</tp:taxon-name>Tunisia<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
cretensisFriese, 1902</tp:taxon-name>Crete
= 
<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
cretensis kilikiaWarncke, 1979</tp:taxon-name>Turkey<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
holtziFriese, 1902</tp:taxon-name>Bulgaria
, 
Cyprus
, 
Greece
, 
Iraq
, 
Iran
: 
Fars
= 
<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
holtzi anatolicaWarncke, 1979</tp:taxon-name>Turkey<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
nitidaFriese, 1902</tp:taxon-name>Armenia
, 
Azerbaijan
, 
Greece
, 
Turkey
= 
<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
nitida nigricornisFriese, 1902</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>A
. 
oraniensisLepeletier de Saint Fargeau, 1841</tp:taxon-name>Algeria
, 
Morocco
, 
Tunisia
= 
<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
flavilabris
(
Lucas, 1849
)
</tp:taxon-name>
= 
<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
heterodoxa
(
Cockerell, 1937
)
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>A
. 
orientalicaWarncke, 1979</tp:taxon-name>Greece
, 
Iraq
, 
Syria
, 
Turkey<tp:taxon-name>A
. 
stolliFriese, 1922</tp:taxon-name>Iran
: 
Fars
, 
Lebanon
, 
Syria
, 
Turkey</p>
      <p>
Including a species established herein, the 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
each consist of eight, uncommonly encountered species (table 1), the latter occurring in Mediterranean Europe, Western Asia, and northern Africa, while the former encompasses roughly the same area although more restricted in northeastern Africa and extending into Central Asia and 
India
. The known records of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
reveal a rather disjunct distribution—the European/Western and Central Asian occurrences, the Indian species, and those species in northeastern Africa. Here we report the discovery of the tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>
for the first time from the Arabian Peninsula, expanding the distribution of this lineage into the region and closing the otherwise purported gap between those taxa in northeastern Africa and the Asiatic fauna. In addition, we provide revised diagnoses of the tribes 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>
, highlighting their distinctive traits. An initial survey of the supraspecific groups of bees occurring in 
Saudi Arabia
was outlined by 
Engel et al. (2013)
with the intention of encouraging further collecting throughout the peninsula. Subsequently, several genera have been newly recorded for the country, or even the entire peninsula, much as is done here with 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
, and we accordingly append an updated list (appendix).
</p>
      <p>4 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</p>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
         <p>
Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
were taken at two localities in central 
Saudi Arabia
during the 2011 and 2013 field seasons, while other attempts to locate individuals and nests were unsuccessful. The available material is deposited in the Division of Entomology (Snow Entomological Collections), University of Kansas Natural History Museum, Lawrence, Kansas (SEMC), and the King Saud University Museum of Arthropods, Plant Protection Department, College of Food and Agriculture Sciences, King Saud University, 
Riyadh
, 
Saudi Arabia
(KSMA). Comparative material of all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
, with the exception of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia cellularis
(Cameron)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and diverse 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyla</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucerini</tp:taxon-name>
were examined from the collections of SEMC.
</p>
         <p>
Descriptions are provided in the context of improving identifications of and species-level treatments of bees (
Engel, 2011
; 
Gonzalez et al., 2013
). For the descriptive sections, the morphological terminology is largely adapted from 
Michener (2007)
and 
Engel (2001)
, and from 
Snelling (1981)
in terms of setal orientation. However, we have used a slightly revised terminology for tibial spurs, particularly the protibial calcar (= “fibula” sensu 
Snodgrass, 1956
). Following 
Engel (2009)
we use the term 
rachis
for the main, longitudinal body of the spur along its entire length, and as commonly employed in biology for any spine or shaft forming the principle axis. For the protibial calcar, which forms a portion of the foreleg strigilis or “antenna cleaner,” we restrict the term 
malus5
(in Latin referring to a mast) to that apical portion of the rachis beyond the primary velum (and, when present, the secondary, anterior velum: 
Schönitzer and Renner, 1980
; 
Schönitzer, 1986
). The anterior velum is often lacking, but variably represented among different lineages by a carina, thin lamella, or a reduced, lamellate lobe (
Schönitzer, 1986
).
</p>
         <p>
Microphotographs were prepared through the combination of consecutive images at successive focal plans, all shot using a Canon 7D digital camera attached to an Infinity K-2 longdistance microscope lens. Measurements of specimens relied upon an ocular micrometer and an Olympus SZX-12 stereomicroscope, those of the 
paratype
male in parentheses.
</p>
         <p>5
The term 
malus
as used by 
Michener (1944
, 
2007
), 
Eickwort (1969)
, and 
Engel (2000
, 
2001
) is equivalent to 
rachis,
but the latter term is more broadly applicable to the axial length of all tibial spurs.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2017 ENGEL ET AL.: ARABIAN 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
5
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>SYSTEMATICS</title>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>
Apinae 
Latreille, 1802</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ancylaini 
Michener, 1944</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Ancylini 
Michener, 1944: 273</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Type
genus: 
<tp:taxon-name>AncylaLepeletier de Saint Fargeau, 1841</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini Michener</tp:taxon-name>
, nomen emendatum; 
Engel et al., 2008: 199
; ICZN, 2011: 116.
</p>
         <p>
DIAGNOSIS: Bees of small to moderate size (
5–10 mm
in length); head about as wide as long to wider than long and face comparatively narrow, interocular distance less than compound eye length; vertex comparatively straight, not uniformly convex nor excavated between compound eyes and ocelli in facial view. Lower face often without maculation (see sexes below); clypeus flat to weakly protuberant in profile, scarcely bent back at side of labrum. Labrum broader than long. Malar space linear, nearly lacking with mandibular base abutting lower compound eye margin. Mandible simple, without distinct subapical tooth; articulations equidistant from compound eye, posterior articulation behind mediolongitudinal axis of compound eye. Postpalpal portion of galea broad proximally, then attenuate and with weakly sclerotized strip extending to apex; maxillary palpus with six palpomeres. Glossa and labial palpus much shorter than prementum; submental spine present; paraglossa short; labial palpus with four palpomeres, first two palpomeres similar in shape to apical two palpomeres, not flattened; submental spine absent. Pronotum without transverse carina. Propodeum basally declivitous, basal area impunctate, not covered by setae. Protibial calcar of strigilis with anterior carina or thin lamella on rachis bordering primary velum but lacking anterior, secondary velum; primary velum rectangular with inner margin rounded, with inner apical corner projected as acutely pointed process; malus short, often shorter than velum, with apex straight, inner margin minutely ciliate. Mesotibial spur long, serrate, apex slightly incurved; mesobasitarsal comb absent. Metabasitibial plate short, wider than long, apically weakly and broadly rounded; metatibial spurs long, serrate, apices straight or slightly incurved. Pretarsal arolium present. Forewing with pterostigma small, longer than wide, scarcely wider than prestigma; pterostigmal margin inside marginal cell convex, sometimes weakly so; marginal cell apex not truncate, bent away from anterior wing margin; three submarginal cells present; membrane with setae throughout. Hind wing with 2M+Cu about one-half as long as M, or slightly more; cu-a transverse, one-half length or more of M; jugal lobe short, slightly less than one-half length of vannal lobe. Metasomal tergum I without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces, at most sharply angulate in some males.
</p>
         <p>
FEMALE: Face without maculation; probasitarsus without anterior or posterior combs; metatibial and metabasitarsal scopa large, dense, composed of long, plumose setae, without oil-collecting structures; metabasitibial plate surface bare and smooth; pretarsal claws with small basal tooth; metasomal tergum 
VI
with narrow pygidial plate; gradulus of metasomal sternum II simple; sterna II–V with scattered long, subdecumbent setae apically, but not forming scopa.
</p>
         <p>MALE
: Clypeus, supraclypeal area, paraocular area, and antennal scape with maculation; apical margin of clypeus with linear patch of distinctive setae; ventral surface of mandible and usually postgena near mandibular base with characteristic patch of dense setae; flagellum crenulate; mesobasitarsus, metatibia, metabasitarsus, and metatibial spurs frequently greatly modified (e.g., mesobasitarsus swollen with dense setae; metatibia swollen, with modified setae; metabasitarsus thickened and arched, with concave inner surface and modified; metatibial spurs elongate and broadly curved); metabasitibial plate covered with appressed setae; pretarsal claws deeply cleft; tergum VII setose, with pygidial plate present; sternum 
V
with subapical, paramedial setal patches and apical, paramedial, thumblike processes bordering medial concavity; sternum 
VI
with medial tubercle extending between processes of sternum 
V
, and variously with broadly concave areas laterally and medially, with mediolongitudinal ridge or carina and medioapical margin various modified; sternum VII with lateral and apical lobes; sternum VIII with apical lobes; gonostylus without setigerous parapenial lobe; spatha present.
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>6 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</p>
      <p>
COMMENTS: The presently included species, all in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyla</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>PlistotrichiaMorawitz, 1874</tp:taxon-name>
), and their distributions are summarized in table 1. The nesting biology and immature stages have been reported for two species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
(
Straka and Rozen, 2012
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and the species are generally considered specialists of 
<tp:taxon-name>Apiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
and has mouthparts similar to short-tongued bees (
Silveira, 1993b
; 
Straka and Rozen, 2012
).
</p>
      <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>Engel, 2015</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>Engel, 2015: 4
. 
Type
genus: 
<tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
DIAGNOSIS (modified and expanded from 
Engel, 2015
): Bees of small to moderate size (
5.5–13 mm
in length); head wider than long, but face comparatively narrow, interocular distance less than compound eye length; vertex comparatively straight, not uniformly convex nor excavated between compound eyes and ocelli in facial view (fig. 1D). Lower face often with maculation (see sexes below); clypeus weakly to moderately protuberant in profile, strongly bent back at side of labrum. Labrum broader than long. Malar space linear, nearly lacking with mandibular base abutting lower compound eye margin. Mandible simple, without distinct subapical tooth; articulations equidistant from compound eye, posterior articulation behind mediolongitudinal axis of compound eye. Postpalpal portion of galea broad proximally, then attenuate and with weakly sclerotized strip extending to apex; maxillary palpus with six palpomeres. Glossa and labial palpus longer than prementum; submental spine present; paraglossa short, not exceeding first labial palpomere; labial palpus with four palpomeres, first two palpomeres long, sheathlike (contrasting with condition in 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
where first two palpomeres are similar in shape to apical two palpomeres); submental spine present. Pronotum without transverse carina. Propodeum basally with subhorizontal area, subhorizontal area punctate and setose. Protibial calcar of strigilis with anterior carina or thin lamella on rachis bordering primary velum but lacking anterior, secondary velum; primary velum rectangular with inner margin blunt, straight, with inner apical corner projected as acutely pointed process (as in most 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucerini</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Exomalopsini</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>Emphorini</tp:taxon-name>
: 
Schönitzer, 1986
); malus elongate, as long as or longer than velum, with apex straight or slightly incurved, inner margin minutely ciliate. Mesotibial spur long, serrate, apex slightly incurved; mesobasitarsal comb absent. Metabasitibial plate short, wider than long, apically weakly and broadly rounded; metatibial spurs long, serrate, apices slightly incurved. Pretarsal arolium present. Forewing with pterostigma small (fig. 1A), as long as wide, scarcely wider than prestigma; pterostigmal margin inside marginal cell weakly or not convex; marginal cell apex not truncate, bent away from anterior wing margin; three submarginal cells present; membrane with setae throughout. Hind wing with 2M+Cu one-half as long as M or less; cu-a transverse, more than one-half length of M; jugal lobe short, slightly less than one-half length of vannal lobe. Metasomal tergum I with or without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsalfacing surfaces (absent in two species).
</p>
      <p>
2017 ENGEL ET AL.: ARABIAN 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
7
</p>
      <p>
FEMALE: Labrum, clypeus, and supraclypeal area usually with maculation (fig. 1D) (absent in one species); paraocular area usually without maculation (present in one species); antennal scape usually without maculation (present in one species); probasitarsus without anterior or posterior combs; metatibial and metabasitarsal scopa large, dense, composed of long, plumose setae, without oil-collecting structures; metabasitibial plate surface bare and smooth; pretarsal claws with minute basal tooth; metasomal tergum 
VI
with narrow pygidial plate; gradulus of metasomal sternum II weakly birecurved (similar to condition in some 
<tp:taxon-name>Thygater
Holmberg
</tp:taxon-name>
); sterna II–V with scopa composed of long, dense setae, such setae often apically wavy or sinuous (similar to 
type
IV of 
Pasteels and Pasteels, 1974
).
</p>
      <p>MALE
: Labrum with maculation (reduced to a medioapical spot in one species); clypeus and supraclypeal area usually with maculation (absent in one species); paraocular area with maculation; antennal scape usually without maculation (absent in one species), flagellum not crenulate nor elongate; metabasitibial plate often shorter than in female, covered with appressed setae; pretarsal claws deeply cleft; tergum VII setose, with true pygidial plate absent (no raised pygidial plate, instead surface continuous with disc and uniformly covered with setae), instead with distinct lateral carina and apicomedially produced and truncate to weakly bilobate (broadly and shallowly emarginate), medial projected area rounded and deflexed in two species; apical margin sternum 
V
straight to medially lobate; sternum 
VI
narrowed apically, apical margin usually characteristic (truncate, rounded, or medially emarginate), with lateral marginal areas broadly concave and typically smooth, producing narrow medial area usually bearing a medial tubercle or carina; sternum VII with lateral and apical lobes; sternum VIII with apical lobes; gonostylus with parapenial lobe bearing thickened setae; spatha present (absent in one species); hidden sterna and genitalia asymmetrical (sternum VII usually strongly asymmetrical; sternum VIII less dramatically so; sometimes with penis valves strongly asymmetrical).
</p>
      <p>
COMMENTS: Recently, the tribe was proposed as “new” again in 
Plant and Paulus (2016)
, despite having already been made available a year prior to this. The name as employed by these authors has no nomenclatural standing.
</p>
      <p>Baker (1998)
speculated that the characteristic sternal setae functioned as a scopa. However, conclusive evidence demonstrating the use of the sternal setae for pollen transport is lacking, and both 
Michener (2007)
and 
Plant and Paulus (2016)
indicated that specimens with copious pollen in the hind-leg scopae lacked pollen on the sterna. However, we’ve followed 
Baker (1998)
in considering the sternal setae as a metasomal scopa as the female of the new species described below has appreciable pollen in only two places on the body: the hind-leg scopae and the sternal setae. It is hoped that biological studies will someday be possible to permit an evaluation of the true functional significance of the dense sternal setae of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>8 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</p>
      <p>
The chiral form of the male terminalia is unique among bees. The asymmetry of the male sternum VII, and to a lesser degree sternum VIII, along with the sometimes hypertrophy of one penis valve, is immediately distinctive and peculiar. The purpose for this consistent chirality is unclear and, as noted by 
Baker (1998)
, does not correspond to any asymmetry in the female terminal sclerites. Until such time as the mating behavior of these bees is discovered, the function of these asymmetries shall remain a mystery, but in the meantime they represent a strong synapomorphy for the tribe.
</p>
      <p>
We have considered the males of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
to lack a true pygidial plate. It is definitive that a pygidial plate as traditionally defined (
Michener, 1944
) is lacking in males of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
. However, the seventh tergum is medioapically produced with the tergal apical margin carinate, suggestive of a plate, and leading some to speculate that the majority of the tergal apical dorsum is equivalent to a pygidial plate (
Michener, 2007
). However, this apical surface is continuous on all sides with the remainder of the tergal disc, as well as identically sculptured and uniformly covered with setae, in stark contrast to the distinctly raised surface of a pygidial plate which also almost invariably differently sculptured and either lacking in setae or with such setae distinctly differing from those of the surrounding disc. Thus, from a strictly morphological standpoint we do not consider a true pygidial plate to be present in 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
, and the form of the seventh tergum in these bees should not be confused with those lineages in which such a plate is present (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>Ancylaini</tp:taxon-name>
). Even if the apical protrusion of the seventh tergum of male 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
should be shown later to be developmentally homologous to the pygidial plate, it still remains a fundamentally different structure of uncertain function and such a character state should not be equated or confused with the pygidial plate in other bees. Referring to the present character state as a “pygidial plate” obscures the uniqueness of the condition found among 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
, as well as misleads others, we believe, as to its morphological identity (i.e., that a true pygidial plate is lacking).
</p>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895: 9</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia hirtipesMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
(
Tarsalia
) Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Tarsalia
) 
ancyliformis
Popov
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
(
T
.) 
hirtipes
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
(
T
.) 
deccana
Baker
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
deccana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
hirtipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz. 
A.
Open
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Tarsalia
) 
ancyliformis
Popov. 
B.
Dense
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. (
Astibomelissa
) 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa
Engel
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Astibomelissa
) 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulate</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asteroideae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella
(
Tetraloniella
) 
persiciformisAlqarni et al. (2012)</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Discovery of the Bee Tribe Tarsaliini in Arabia (Hymenoptera: Apidae), with the Description of a New Species</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1206/3877.1</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFAD740C0B409454DC78FFE0FFF6FFE7</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1206/3877.1</pub-id>
               <issn>0003-0082</issn>
               <source>American Museum Novitates</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa
Engel
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new subgenus</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Astibomelissa
) 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895: 9</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia hirtipesMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
, by monotypy. 
Friese, 1896: 211
; 
Baker, 1998: 837
; 
Michener, 2000: 666
; 
Michener, 2007: 686
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
(
Tarsalia
) Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Warncke, 1977: 58
; 
Warncke, 1979: 192
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>DIAGNOSIS: As for tribe (above).</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
COMMENTS: The genus currently includes two rather distinct groups, one with three species in northeastern Africa, Arabia, and 
Iran
, while the other has five species in Western and Central Asia, south into 
India
, and west on the Mediterranean islands of 
Cyprus
and Sardinia (table 1).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
Key to Subgenera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
1.Metasoma and mesosoma dark reddish brown to black (fig. 1); metatibial scopa open (fig. 2A); subtriangular patch of distinctive, squamiform setae on outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate (Sardinia, 
Cyprus
, Western and Central Asia, 
India
)......................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str
.
</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>
—Metasoma and majority of mesosoma light castaneous to testaceous (figs. 3, 4); metatibial scopa densely closed (fig. 2B); outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate without patch of distinctive setae, area similar to remainder of scopal setae (northeastern Africa, Arabia, 
Iran
)...................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. subgen.</named-content>
closed (fig. 2B); outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate without patch of distinctive setae, area similar to remainder of scopal setae. Metasomal tergum I with or without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces (all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str.</named-content>
with carina, albeit sometimes weakly so).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TYPESPECIES
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
               </tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>DIAGNOSIS: Body length approximately 5.5–9.0 mm; integument pale castaneous to testaceous on metasoma and majority of mesosoma (figs. 3–5, 6). Female metatibial scopa densely</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
1.Mesoscutum with numerous appressed to decumbent, plumose setae (usually missing on central disc, presumably due to abrasion), setae longer, not squamiform; outer surface of probasitarsus with fine, erect to suberect setae with distinctly sinuate or wavy apices (= 
type
IV of 
Pasteels and Pasteels, 1974
); inner setae of metabasitarsus white to pale yellow and similar to setae of scopa; metasomal tergum I without transverse carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces; smaller species, 
5.5–7.5 mm
in total length (
Saudi Arabia
; 
northeastern Africa
).................................................... 2
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
—Mesoscutum tomentose, with dense covering of appressed, minute (typically about 0.50× ocellar diameter), squamiform setae; outer surface of probasitarsus with fine, subdecumbent setae tapering to straight apices; inner setae of metabasitarsus fuscous, contrasting with surrounding white to pale yellow setae of scopa; metasomal tergum I with transverse carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces; larger species, 
7.9–8.8 mm
in length [
Iran
]............................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
2.Female with yellow facial maculation confined to labrum, clypeus, and supraclypeal area (fig. 3C); metasomal scopa dense, with setae greatly elongate and subdecumbent to suberect; small species, approximately 
5.5–6.5 mm
in length (male unknown) [
Egypt
, 
Sudan
].................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
—Female with yellow facial maculation extending to paraocular area and scape (fig. 6C); metasomal scopa not so dense, with setae long and largely decumbent to subdecumbent; moderate-sized species, approximately 
6.7–7.5 mm
in length (central 
Saudi Arabia
)........................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p/>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>
DIAGNOSIS: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
can be recognized by combination of largely pale castaneous to light testaceous integument on metasoma, legs, and sometimes large portions of mesosoma although nota and much of pleura darker (figs. 4, 6); outer surface of female probasitarsus with dense, long, suberect setae with sinuate or wavy apices; metasomal tergum I without transverse dorsal carina; female metasomal scopa with long, subdecumbant setae with sinuate or wavy apices; male tergum VII with medioapical produced margin weakly bilobate (fig. 5A); male sternum VI apically truncate and with medial tubercle (fig. 5B); male hidden sterna asymmetrical and of characteristic form (fig. 5C); left penis valve hypertrophied (figs. 5E, 5G); and unique possession of yellow facial maculation on female paraocular area and scape, in addition to labrum, clypeus, and supraclypeal area (fig. 6C).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
DESCRIPTION: MALE: Total body length 
6.72 mm
(
7.14 mm
); forewing length 
4.70 mm
(
5.18 mm
). Head wider than long, length 
1.69 mm
(
1.94 mm
), width 
2.28 mm
(
2.34 mm
); inner margins of compound eyes comparatively straight, parallel in lower two-thirds, slightly diverging in upper third, upper interorbital distance 
1.31 mm
(
1.37 mm
), lower interorbital distance 
1.16 mm
(
1.22 mm
); apex of clypeus slightly below lower tangent of compound eyes; clypeus weakly protuberant and convex; ocelli at upper tangent of compound eyes; lateral ocelli separated from median ocellus by about one-half median ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from eye by about 1.6× lateral ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from posterior of head by about its diameter; scape short, extending at most to lower border of median ocellus; FI slightly longer than apical width, longer than FII. Intertegular distance 
1.41 mm
(
1.53 mm
). Basal area of propodeum weakly defined, about as long as metanotum. Legs without special modifications; mesobasitarsus elongate, straight, spur extending to slightly basad basitarsal midlength; metafemur slightly thicker than mesofemur; metabasitarsus elongate. Forewing with basal vein basad cu-a by 2–3 times vein width; 1m-cu entering second submarginal cell; second submarginal cell shortest, narrowed toward anterior wing margin; 2rs-m arcuate. Hind wing with nine distal hamuli. Metasomal tergum I without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces (similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
); tergum VII gradulus medially pointed posteriorly, without lateral gradular teeth (sensu 
Baker, 1998
), but lateral area instead angulate, apical margin projected, deflexed medially, margin shallowly and broadly emarginate (fig. 5A); sternum V with medioapical margin produced with broad, apically blunt lobe; sternum VI narrowed apically, medioapical margin truncate, with broadly concave, smooth ovoid areas laterally along margin producing narrow medial disc bearing a medial tubercle (fig. 5B); hidden sterna VII and VIII asymmetrical and as in figures 5C and 5D; genitalia as in figures 5E–G, with penis valves markedly asymmetrical (figs. 5E, 5G).
</p>
            <p>Integument somewhat shining. Labrum with coarse, shallow, contiguous punctures, otherwise smooth. Clypeus with coarse, faint, shallow punctures separated by less than a puncture width, except slightly more spaced along borders and more oblique, approximately separated by a puncture width or sometimes slightly more, integument between punctures smooth. Supraclypeal area with smaller, more well-defined punctures, separated by a puncture width, except medially slightly more separated, integument otherwise smooth. Face below level of antennae with small, faint, scattered punctures, separated by less than a puncture width along border with clypeus and subantennal sulcus, then becoming sparser toward inner margin of compound eye such that paraocular margin impunctate, integument between punctures smooth. Face above level of antennae with small, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, integument between punctures faintly imbricate; punctures sparse in short, broad triangular patch immediate anterior to median ocellus and absent in paraocular margin where integument is strongly imbricate; ocellocular space medially as on upper face but with punctures absent along outer border of lateral ocellus and in paraocular margin bordering compound eye, former patch smooth, latter strongly imbricate; vertex as on upper face; gena as on upper face except punctures smaller and becoming gradually more widely spaced ventrally such that on lower gena punctures separated by 2–3 times a puncture width, integument between punctures smooth; postgena with minute punctures similar to those on lower gena except sparse, integument otherwise smooth. Pronotum with sparse, minute punctures, integument otherwise smooth. Mesoscutum with small, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, with some posteromedially separated by about a puncture width, integument between punctures; tegula generally smooth to faintly imbricate, with sparse, minute punctures; mesoscutellum with punctures as on mesoscutum except somewhat larger and coarser. Metanotum finely imbricate with scattered, shallow, faint punctures. Pleura with small, well-defined punctures, integument otherwise smooth except more imbricate in area of mesepisternal border with metepisternum; punctures on hypoepimeral area becoming oblique ventrally, nearly contiguous, except sparse along scrobal sulcus; punctures on preepisternal area smaller, becoming shallower, fainter, and oblique toward anterior margin; punctures on mesepisternum below scrobal sulcus becoming fainter along posterior border and on ventral-facing surface; metepisternum imbricate with sparse punctures. Basal area of propodeum largely obscured by setae, integument apparently imbricate and coarsely punctate; posterior and lateral surfaces of propodeum faintly imbricate to smooth, with scattered, small punctures. Metasomal terga with minute, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, except anterior-facing depression of tergum I largely smooth and narrow apical margins of terga smooth, integument between punctures smooth; sterna as on terga except punctures coarser and integument otherwise more imbricate.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
Coloration of head generally testaceous to black (lighter in 
holotype
male, darker in 
paratype
male), except labrum entirely yellow; mandible largely yellow except dark reddish brown to black apically; clypeus and supraclypeal area entirely yellow; paraocular area yellow below level of antennae and broadly along compound eye in lower half of upper face; paraocular area in upper half of face above antennae dark brown to testaceous; scape yellow, pedicel and flagellomeres I and II yellowish brown; remainder of flagellum orange. Pronotum dark reddish brown to testaceous (testaceous in 
holotype
male, dark testaceous along borders blending to dark reddish brown posteriorly in 
paratype
male). Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum dark testaceous to black; tegula semitranslucent; metanotum testaceous to dark reddish brown; pleura
</tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">testaceous to dark reddish brown; basal area of propodeum dark testaceous to black, remainder of propodeum testaceous to dark reddish brown. Legs testaceous. Wing membranes hyaline, faintly parchment colored; veins yellowish brown to dark brown. Metasoma testaceous.</tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Pubescence white and often obscuring integument on frons, vertex, gena, mesosoma, tibiae, tarsi, and metasomal terga where such setae usually appressed to decumbent and plumose (setae with numerous, minute branches along length of rachis, giving feathered appearance: similar to short-branched setal forms described by 
Saunders, 1878
, and 
Braue, 1913
), setae of mesoscutum not squamiform, typically as long as or slightly longer than ocellar diameter (setae abraded from large areas of mesosoma and anterior metasomal terga on 
paratype
male, allowing view of integumental sculpture); labrum with transverse, medial patch of short, erect, branched setae; setae below level of antennae typically sparse, suberect to erect, long, and minutely branched, similar setae on postgena; mesosoma with setae less prominent on preepisternal area and posteroventrally on mesepisternum and anteroventrally on lateral propodeal surface; tergal setae largely short and appressed; sternal setae longer, suberect, and posteriorly directed.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
FEMALE: As described for male, except as follows: total body length 
7.50 mm
; forewing length 5.00 mm. Head wider than long, length 
1.81 mm
, width 
2.44 mm
; inner margins of compound eyes comparatively straight, slightly convergent below, upper interorbital distance 
1.51 mm
, lower interorbital distance 
1.33 mm
; lateral ocelli separated from median ocellus by about one-half median ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from eye by about 2.0× lateral ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from posterior of head by about its diameter; scape short, extending to slightly less than distance to lower border of median ocellus; FI elongate, length about twice apical width, about twice as long as FII. Intertegular distance 
1.56 mm
.
</p>
            <p>Coloration as in darker male (above) (fig. 6).</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Pubescence as in male except for sex differences: probasitarsus with fine, erect to suberect setae with distinctly sinuate or wavy apices; metatibial and metabasitarsal scopa composed of dense, elongate, plumose setae; metasomal sterna II–V with rows of elongate, subdecumbent setae with sinuate or wavy apices, forming distinct scopa; sternum 
VI
with medioapical patch of dense, short, erect setae.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>HOLOTYPE
: 
♂
, 
Saudi Arabia
: 
Riyadh
, al-Amariah [al-‘ 
Amāriah
, a locality about 
12 km
west of 
Riyadh
], 
Majra
[Mazra‘ah] al-Gasim [
al-Qasim
, farm], 
23.v.2011
[
23 May 2011
], 
M.A. Hannan
(
KSMA
).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>PARATYPES
: 
1♀
, 
Saudi Arabia
: 
Riyadh
, al-Amariah [al-‘Amāriah], Majra [Mazra‘ah] alGasim [
al-Qasim
, farm], 
19.vi.2011
[
19 June 2011
], M.A. Hannan &amp; I. Naser (SEMC); 
1♂
, 
Saudi Arabia
: Qassim [
al-Qassim
], Unizah [Unayzah], al-Watania Farm, Rowdah, 
29.v.2013
[
29 May 2013
], M.A. Hannan; 
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulate</tp:taxon-name>
[sic] [
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
] (SEMC).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
FLORAL RECORD: The 
paratype
male was taken while visiting flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) C.A. Mey (
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteroideae</tp:taxon-name>
: Helianthodea: Inuleae), a rather common annual herb in the region, known as false fleabane or regionally as “Jethjath” and used in medicinal tea. Regional beekeepers consider 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
as a good source for pollen and nectar during the spring.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>
ETYMOLOGY: The specific epithet refers to the ancient kingdom of Kindah, which occupied, among other areas, large portions of the Najd, encompassing the 
type
localities.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
COMMENTS: There is variation in color of the head and mesosoma between the two males, the one from Qassim being darker and similar to the female from al-‘Amāriah, while the male from al-‘Amāriah is distinctly lighter. The lighter male is more testaceous in those areas where the Qassim male is dark testaceous to dark reddish brown, and dark testaceous to reddish brown in those places where the female and male from Qassim are dark reddish brown to black. However, despite these color differences, the integumental, structural, and genitalic traits are identical between the males. The male of 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
superficially resembles to some degree the male of the sympatric 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella
(
Tetraloniella
) 
persiciformisAlqarni et al. (2012)</tp:taxon-name>
, a eucerine that has also been taken visiting flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895: 9</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia hirtipesMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
(
Tarsalia
) Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Tarsalia
) 
ancyliformis
Popov
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
(
T
.) 
hirtipes
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
(
T
.) 
deccana
Baker
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
deccana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
hirtipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz. 
A.
Open
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Tarsalia
) 
ancyliformis
Popov. 
B.
Dense
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. (
Astibomelissa
) 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa
Engel
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Astibomelissa
) 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulate</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asteroideae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella
(
Tetraloniella
) 
persiciformisAlqarni et al. (2012)</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Discovery of the Bee Tribe Tarsaliini in Arabia (Hymenoptera: Apidae), with the Description of a New Species</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1206/3877.1</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFAD740C0B409454DC78FFE0FFF6FFE7</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1206/3877.1</pub-id>
               <issn>0003-0082</issn>
               <source>American Museum Novitates</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa
Engel
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new subgenus</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Astibomelissa
) 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895: 9</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia hirtipesMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
, by monotypy. 
Friese, 1896: 211
; 
Baker, 1998: 837
; 
Michener, 2000: 666
; 
Michener, 2007: 686
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
(
Tarsalia
) Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Warncke, 1977: 58
; 
Warncke, 1979: 192
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>DIAGNOSIS: As for tribe (above).</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
COMMENTS: The genus currently includes two rather distinct groups, one with three species in northeastern Africa, Arabia, and 
Iran
, while the other has five species in Western and Central Asia, south into 
India
, and west on the Mediterranean islands of 
Cyprus
and Sardinia (table 1).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
Key to Subgenera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
1.Metasoma and mesosoma dark reddish brown to black (fig. 1); metatibial scopa open (fig. 2A); subtriangular patch of distinctive, squamiform setae on outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate (Sardinia, 
Cyprus
, Western and Central Asia, 
India
)......................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str
.
</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>
—Metasoma and majority of mesosoma light castaneous to testaceous (figs. 3, 4); metatibial scopa densely closed (fig. 2B); outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate without patch of distinctive setae, area similar to remainder of scopal setae (northeastern Africa, Arabia, 
Iran
)...................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. subgen.</named-content>
closed (fig. 2B); outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate without patch of distinctive setae, area similar to remainder of scopal setae. Metasomal tergum I with or without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces (all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str.</named-content>
with carina, albeit sometimes weakly so).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TYPESPECIES
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
               </tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>DIAGNOSIS: Body length approximately 5.5–9.0 mm; integument pale castaneous to testaceous on metasoma and majority of mesosoma (figs. 3–5, 6). Female metatibial scopa densely</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
1.Mesoscutum with numerous appressed to decumbent, plumose setae (usually missing on central disc, presumably due to abrasion), setae longer, not squamiform; outer surface of probasitarsus with fine, erect to suberect setae with distinctly sinuate or wavy apices (= 
type
IV of 
Pasteels and Pasteels, 1974
); inner setae of metabasitarsus white to pale yellow and similar to setae of scopa; metasomal tergum I without transverse carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces; smaller species, 
5.5–7.5 mm
in total length (
Saudi Arabia
; 
northeastern Africa
).................................................... 2
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
—Mesoscutum tomentose, with dense covering of appressed, minute (typically about 0.50× ocellar diameter), squamiform setae; outer surface of probasitarsus with fine, subdecumbent setae tapering to straight apices; inner setae of metabasitarsus fuscous, contrasting with surrounding white to pale yellow setae of scopa; metasomal tergum I with transverse carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces; larger species, 
7.9–8.8 mm
in length [
Iran
]............................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
2.Female with yellow facial maculation confined to labrum, clypeus, and supraclypeal area (fig. 3C); metasomal scopa dense, with setae greatly elongate and subdecumbent to suberect; small species, approximately 
5.5–6.5 mm
in length (male unknown) [
Egypt
, 
Sudan
].................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
—Female with yellow facial maculation extending to paraocular area and scape (fig. 6C); metasomal scopa not so dense, with setae long and largely decumbent to subdecumbent; moderate-sized species, approximately 
6.7–7.5 mm
in length (central 
Saudi Arabia
)........................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p/>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>
DIAGNOSIS: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
can be recognized by combination of largely pale castaneous to light testaceous integument on metasoma, legs, and sometimes large portions of mesosoma although nota and much of pleura darker (figs. 4, 6); outer surface of female probasitarsus with dense, long, suberect setae with sinuate or wavy apices; metasomal tergum I without transverse dorsal carina; female metasomal scopa with long, subdecumbant setae with sinuate or wavy apices; male tergum VII with medioapical produced margin weakly bilobate (fig. 5A); male sternum VI apically truncate and with medial tubercle (fig. 5B); male hidden sterna asymmetrical and of characteristic form (fig. 5C); left penis valve hypertrophied (figs. 5E, 5G); and unique possession of yellow facial maculation on female paraocular area and scape, in addition to labrum, clypeus, and supraclypeal area (fig. 6C).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
DESCRIPTION: MALE: Total body length 
6.72 mm
(
7.14 mm
); forewing length 
4.70 mm
(
5.18 mm
). Head wider than long, length 
1.69 mm
(
1.94 mm
), width 
2.28 mm
(
2.34 mm
); inner margins of compound eyes comparatively straight, parallel in lower two-thirds, slightly diverging in upper third, upper interorbital distance 
1.31 mm
(
1.37 mm
), lower interorbital distance 
1.16 mm
(
1.22 mm
); apex of clypeus slightly below lower tangent of compound eyes; clypeus weakly protuberant and convex; ocelli at upper tangent of compound eyes; lateral ocelli separated from median ocellus by about one-half median ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from eye by about 1.6× lateral ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from posterior of head by about its diameter; scape short, extending at most to lower border of median ocellus; FI slightly longer than apical width, longer than FII. Intertegular distance 
1.41 mm
(
1.53 mm
). Basal area of propodeum weakly defined, about as long as metanotum. Legs without special modifications; mesobasitarsus elongate, straight, spur extending to slightly basad basitarsal midlength; metafemur slightly thicker than mesofemur; metabasitarsus elongate. Forewing with basal vein basad cu-a by 2–3 times vein width; 1m-cu entering second submarginal cell; second submarginal cell shortest, narrowed toward anterior wing margin; 2rs-m arcuate. Hind wing with nine distal hamuli. Metasomal tergum I without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces (similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
); tergum VII gradulus medially pointed posteriorly, without lateral gradular teeth (sensu 
Baker, 1998
), but lateral area instead angulate, apical margin projected, deflexed medially, margin shallowly and broadly emarginate (fig. 5A); sternum V with medioapical margin produced with broad, apically blunt lobe; sternum VI narrowed apically, medioapical margin truncate, with broadly concave, smooth ovoid areas laterally along margin producing narrow medial disc bearing a medial tubercle (fig. 5B); hidden sterna VII and VIII asymmetrical and as in figures 5C and 5D; genitalia as in figures 5E–G, with penis valves markedly asymmetrical (figs. 5E, 5G).
</p>
            <p>Integument somewhat shining. Labrum with coarse, shallow, contiguous punctures, otherwise smooth. Clypeus with coarse, faint, shallow punctures separated by less than a puncture width, except slightly more spaced along borders and more oblique, approximately separated by a puncture width or sometimes slightly more, integument between punctures smooth. Supraclypeal area with smaller, more well-defined punctures, separated by a puncture width, except medially slightly more separated, integument otherwise smooth. Face below level of antennae with small, faint, scattered punctures, separated by less than a puncture width along border with clypeus and subantennal sulcus, then becoming sparser toward inner margin of compound eye such that paraocular margin impunctate, integument between punctures smooth. Face above level of antennae with small, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, integument between punctures faintly imbricate; punctures sparse in short, broad triangular patch immediate anterior to median ocellus and absent in paraocular margin where integument is strongly imbricate; ocellocular space medially as on upper face but with punctures absent along outer border of lateral ocellus and in paraocular margin bordering compound eye, former patch smooth, latter strongly imbricate; vertex as on upper face; gena as on upper face except punctures smaller and becoming gradually more widely spaced ventrally such that on lower gena punctures separated by 2–3 times a puncture width, integument between punctures smooth; postgena with minute punctures similar to those on lower gena except sparse, integument otherwise smooth. Pronotum with sparse, minute punctures, integument otherwise smooth. Mesoscutum with small, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, with some posteromedially separated by about a puncture width, integument between punctures; tegula generally smooth to faintly imbricate, with sparse, minute punctures; mesoscutellum with punctures as on mesoscutum except somewhat larger and coarser. Metanotum finely imbricate with scattered, shallow, faint punctures. Pleura with small, well-defined punctures, integument otherwise smooth except more imbricate in area of mesepisternal border with metepisternum; punctures on hypoepimeral area becoming oblique ventrally, nearly contiguous, except sparse along scrobal sulcus; punctures on preepisternal area smaller, becoming shallower, fainter, and oblique toward anterior margin; punctures on mesepisternum below scrobal sulcus becoming fainter along posterior border and on ventral-facing surface; metepisternum imbricate with sparse punctures. Basal area of propodeum largely obscured by setae, integument apparently imbricate and coarsely punctate; posterior and lateral surfaces of propodeum faintly imbricate to smooth, with scattered, small punctures. Metasomal terga with minute, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, except anterior-facing depression of tergum I largely smooth and narrow apical margins of terga smooth, integument between punctures smooth; sterna as on terga except punctures coarser and integument otherwise more imbricate.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
Coloration of head generally testaceous to black (lighter in 
holotype
male, darker in 
paratype
male), except labrum entirely yellow; mandible largely yellow except dark reddish brown to black apically; clypeus and supraclypeal area entirely yellow; paraocular area yellow below level of antennae and broadly along compound eye in lower half of upper face; paraocular area in upper half of face above antennae dark brown to testaceous; scape yellow, pedicel and flagellomeres I and II yellowish brown; remainder of flagellum orange. Pronotum dark reddish brown to testaceous (testaceous in 
holotype
male, dark testaceous along borders blending to dark reddish brown posteriorly in 
paratype
male). Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum dark testaceous to black; tegula semitranslucent; metanotum testaceous to dark reddish brown; pleura
</tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">testaceous to dark reddish brown; basal area of propodeum dark testaceous to black, remainder of propodeum testaceous to dark reddish brown. Legs testaceous. Wing membranes hyaline, faintly parchment colored; veins yellowish brown to dark brown. Metasoma testaceous.</tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Pubescence white and often obscuring integument on frons, vertex, gena, mesosoma, tibiae, tarsi, and metasomal terga where such setae usually appressed to decumbent and plumose (setae with numerous, minute branches along length of rachis, giving feathered appearance: similar to short-branched setal forms described by 
Saunders, 1878
, and 
Braue, 1913
), setae of mesoscutum not squamiform, typically as long as or slightly longer than ocellar diameter (setae abraded from large areas of mesosoma and anterior metasomal terga on 
paratype
male, allowing view of integumental sculpture); labrum with transverse, medial patch of short, erect, branched setae; setae below level of antennae typically sparse, suberect to erect, long, and minutely branched, similar setae on postgena; mesosoma with setae less prominent on preepisternal area and posteroventrally on mesepisternum and anteroventrally on lateral propodeal surface; tergal setae largely short and appressed; sternal setae longer, suberect, and posteriorly directed.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
FEMALE: As described for male, except as follows: total body length 
7.50 mm
; forewing length 5.00 mm. Head wider than long, length 
1.81 mm
, width 
2.44 mm
; inner margins of compound eyes comparatively straight, slightly convergent below, upper interorbital distance 
1.51 mm
, lower interorbital distance 
1.33 mm
; lateral ocelli separated from median ocellus by about one-half median ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from eye by about 2.0× lateral ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from posterior of head by about its diameter; scape short, extending to slightly less than distance to lower border of median ocellus; FI elongate, length about twice apical width, about twice as long as FII. Intertegular distance 
1.56 mm
.
</p>
            <p>Coloration as in darker male (above) (fig. 6).</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Pubescence as in male except for sex differences: probasitarsus with fine, erect to suberect setae with distinctly sinuate or wavy apices; metatibial and metabasitarsal scopa composed of dense, elongate, plumose setae; metasomal sterna II–V with rows of elongate, subdecumbent setae with sinuate or wavy apices, forming distinct scopa; sternum 
VI
with medioapical patch of dense, short, erect setae.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>HOLOTYPE
: 
♂
, 
Saudi Arabia
: 
Riyadh
, al-Amariah [al-‘ 
Amāriah
, a locality about 
12 km
west of 
Riyadh
], 
Majra
[Mazra‘ah] al-Gasim [
al-Qasim
, farm], 
23.v.2011
[
23 May 2011
], 
M.A. Hannan
(
KSMA
).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>PARATYPES
: 
1♀
, 
Saudi Arabia
: 
Riyadh
, al-Amariah [al-‘Amāriah], Majra [Mazra‘ah] alGasim [
al-Qasim
, farm], 
19.vi.2011
[
19 June 2011
], M.A. Hannan &amp; I. Naser (SEMC); 
1♂
, 
Saudi Arabia
: Qassim [
al-Qassim
], Unizah [Unayzah], al-Watania Farm, Rowdah, 
29.v.2013
[
29 May 2013
], M.A. Hannan; 
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulate</tp:taxon-name>
[sic] [
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
] (SEMC).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
FLORAL RECORD: The 
paratype
male was taken while visiting flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) C.A. Mey (
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteroideae</tp:taxon-name>
: Helianthodea: Inuleae), a rather common annual herb in the region, known as false fleabane or regionally as “Jethjath” and used in medicinal tea. Regional beekeepers consider 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
as a good source for pollen and nectar during the spring.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>
ETYMOLOGY: The specific epithet refers to the ancient kingdom of Kindah, which occupied, among other areas, large portions of the Najd, encompassing the 
type
localities.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
COMMENTS: There is variation in color of the head and mesosoma between the two males, the one from Qassim being darker and similar to the female from al-‘Amāriah, while the male from al-‘Amāriah is distinctly lighter. The lighter male is more testaceous in those areas where the Qassim male is dark testaceous to dark reddish brown, and dark testaceous to reddish brown in those places where the female and male from Qassim are dark reddish brown to black. However, despite these color differences, the integumental, structural, and genitalic traits are identical between the males. The male of 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
superficially resembles to some degree the male of the sympatric 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella
(
Tetraloniella
) 
persiciformisAlqarni et al. (2012)</tp:taxon-name>
, a eucerine that has also been taken visiting flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2017 ENGEL ET AL.: ARABIAN 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
11
</title>
      </sec>
      <p>12 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</p>
      <p>
ETYMOLOGY: The new subgeneric name is a combination of the Greek 
astibes
(meaning, “untrodden,” hence “desert”) and 
melissa
(meaning, “bee”). The gender of the name is considered feminine.
</p>
      <p>
INCLUDED 
SPECIES
: The subgenus presently includes three species: 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
from forest steppes and semidesert regions of 
Iran
to either side of the Zagros Mountains (
Warncke, 1979
; 
Baker, 1998
); 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
from Upper 
Egypt
and 
the Sudan
(
Cockerell, 1933
; 
Baker, 1998
); and 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
, from the Najd Plateau of 
Saudi Arabia
(east of the Hejaz and immediately west of the ad-Dahna Erg or Desert), with records from near Unayzah and separated by the Thuwayrat dunes from the others southeast near al-‘Amāriah on the Tuwayq escarpment, 
Riyadh
.
</p>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895: 9</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia hirtipesMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
(
Tarsalia
) Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Tarsalia
) 
ancyliformis
Popov
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
(
T
.) 
hirtipes
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
(
T
.) 
deccana
Baker
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
deccana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
hirtipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz. 
A.
Open
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Tarsalia
) 
ancyliformis
Popov. 
B.
Dense
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. (
Astibomelissa
) 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa
Engel
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Astibomelissa
) 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulate</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asteroideae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella
(
Tetraloniella
) 
persiciformisAlqarni et al. (2012)</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Discovery of the Bee Tribe Tarsaliini in Arabia (Hymenoptera: Apidae), with the Description of a New Species</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1206/3877.1</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFAD740C0B409454DC78FFE0FFF6FFE7</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1206/3877.1</pub-id>
               <issn>0003-0082</issn>
               <source>American Museum Novitates</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa
Engel
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new subgenus</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Astibomelissa
) 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895: 9</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia hirtipesMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
, by monotypy. 
Friese, 1896: 211
; 
Baker, 1998: 837
; 
Michener, 2000: 666
; 
Michener, 2007: 686
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
(
Tarsalia
) Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Warncke, 1977: 58
; 
Warncke, 1979: 192
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>DIAGNOSIS: As for tribe (above).</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
COMMENTS: The genus currently includes two rather distinct groups, one with three species in northeastern Africa, Arabia, and 
Iran
, while the other has five species in Western and Central Asia, south into 
India
, and west on the Mediterranean islands of 
Cyprus
and Sardinia (table 1).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
Key to Subgenera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
1.Metasoma and mesosoma dark reddish brown to black (fig. 1); metatibial scopa open (fig. 2A); subtriangular patch of distinctive, squamiform setae on outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate (Sardinia, 
Cyprus
, Western and Central Asia, 
India
)......................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str
.
</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>
—Metasoma and majority of mesosoma light castaneous to testaceous (figs. 3, 4); metatibial scopa densely closed (fig. 2B); outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate without patch of distinctive setae, area similar to remainder of scopal setae (northeastern Africa, Arabia, 
Iran
)...................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. subgen.</named-content>
closed (fig. 2B); outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate without patch of distinctive setae, area similar to remainder of scopal setae. Metasomal tergum I with or without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces (all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str.</named-content>
with carina, albeit sometimes weakly so).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TYPESPECIES
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
               </tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>DIAGNOSIS: Body length approximately 5.5–9.0 mm; integument pale castaneous to testaceous on metasoma and majority of mesosoma (figs. 3–5, 6). Female metatibial scopa densely</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
1.Mesoscutum with numerous appressed to decumbent, plumose setae (usually missing on central disc, presumably due to abrasion), setae longer, not squamiform; outer surface of probasitarsus with fine, erect to suberect setae with distinctly sinuate or wavy apices (= 
type
IV of 
Pasteels and Pasteels, 1974
); inner setae of metabasitarsus white to pale yellow and similar to setae of scopa; metasomal tergum I without transverse carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces; smaller species, 
5.5–7.5 mm
in total length (
Saudi Arabia
; 
northeastern Africa
).................................................... 2
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
—Mesoscutum tomentose, with dense covering of appressed, minute (typically about 0.50× ocellar diameter), squamiform setae; outer surface of probasitarsus with fine, subdecumbent setae tapering to straight apices; inner setae of metabasitarsus fuscous, contrasting with surrounding white to pale yellow setae of scopa; metasomal tergum I with transverse carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces; larger species, 
7.9–8.8 mm
in length [
Iran
]............................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
2.Female with yellow facial maculation confined to labrum, clypeus, and supraclypeal area (fig. 3C); metasomal scopa dense, with setae greatly elongate and subdecumbent to suberect; small species, approximately 
5.5–6.5 mm
in length (male unknown) [
Egypt
, 
Sudan
].................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
—Female with yellow facial maculation extending to paraocular area and scape (fig. 6C); metasomal scopa not so dense, with setae long and largely decumbent to subdecumbent; moderate-sized species, approximately 
6.7–7.5 mm
in length (central 
Saudi Arabia
)........................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p/>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>
DIAGNOSIS: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
can be recognized by combination of largely pale castaneous to light testaceous integument on metasoma, legs, and sometimes large portions of mesosoma although nota and much of pleura darker (figs. 4, 6); outer surface of female probasitarsus with dense, long, suberect setae with sinuate or wavy apices; metasomal tergum I without transverse dorsal carina; female metasomal scopa with long, subdecumbant setae with sinuate or wavy apices; male tergum VII with medioapical produced margin weakly bilobate (fig. 5A); male sternum VI apically truncate and with medial tubercle (fig. 5B); male hidden sterna asymmetrical and of characteristic form (fig. 5C); left penis valve hypertrophied (figs. 5E, 5G); and unique possession of yellow facial maculation on female paraocular area and scape, in addition to labrum, clypeus, and supraclypeal area (fig. 6C).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
DESCRIPTION: MALE: Total body length 
6.72 mm
(
7.14 mm
); forewing length 
4.70 mm
(
5.18 mm
). Head wider than long, length 
1.69 mm
(
1.94 mm
), width 
2.28 mm
(
2.34 mm
); inner margins of compound eyes comparatively straight, parallel in lower two-thirds, slightly diverging in upper third, upper interorbital distance 
1.31 mm
(
1.37 mm
), lower interorbital distance 
1.16 mm
(
1.22 mm
); apex of clypeus slightly below lower tangent of compound eyes; clypeus weakly protuberant and convex; ocelli at upper tangent of compound eyes; lateral ocelli separated from median ocellus by about one-half median ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from eye by about 1.6× lateral ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from posterior of head by about its diameter; scape short, extending at most to lower border of median ocellus; FI slightly longer than apical width, longer than FII. Intertegular distance 
1.41 mm
(
1.53 mm
). Basal area of propodeum weakly defined, about as long as metanotum. Legs without special modifications; mesobasitarsus elongate, straight, spur extending to slightly basad basitarsal midlength; metafemur slightly thicker than mesofemur; metabasitarsus elongate. Forewing with basal vein basad cu-a by 2–3 times vein width; 1m-cu entering second submarginal cell; second submarginal cell shortest, narrowed toward anterior wing margin; 2rs-m arcuate. Hind wing with nine distal hamuli. Metasomal tergum I without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces (similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
); tergum VII gradulus medially pointed posteriorly, without lateral gradular teeth (sensu 
Baker, 1998
), but lateral area instead angulate, apical margin projected, deflexed medially, margin shallowly and broadly emarginate (fig. 5A); sternum V with medioapical margin produced with broad, apically blunt lobe; sternum VI narrowed apically, medioapical margin truncate, with broadly concave, smooth ovoid areas laterally along margin producing narrow medial disc bearing a medial tubercle (fig. 5B); hidden sterna VII and VIII asymmetrical and as in figures 5C and 5D; genitalia as in figures 5E–G, with penis valves markedly asymmetrical (figs. 5E, 5G).
</p>
            <p>Integument somewhat shining. Labrum with coarse, shallow, contiguous punctures, otherwise smooth. Clypeus with coarse, faint, shallow punctures separated by less than a puncture width, except slightly more spaced along borders and more oblique, approximately separated by a puncture width or sometimes slightly more, integument between punctures smooth. Supraclypeal area with smaller, more well-defined punctures, separated by a puncture width, except medially slightly more separated, integument otherwise smooth. Face below level of antennae with small, faint, scattered punctures, separated by less than a puncture width along border with clypeus and subantennal sulcus, then becoming sparser toward inner margin of compound eye such that paraocular margin impunctate, integument between punctures smooth. Face above level of antennae with small, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, integument between punctures faintly imbricate; punctures sparse in short, broad triangular patch immediate anterior to median ocellus and absent in paraocular margin where integument is strongly imbricate; ocellocular space medially as on upper face but with punctures absent along outer border of lateral ocellus and in paraocular margin bordering compound eye, former patch smooth, latter strongly imbricate; vertex as on upper face; gena as on upper face except punctures smaller and becoming gradually more widely spaced ventrally such that on lower gena punctures separated by 2–3 times a puncture width, integument between punctures smooth; postgena with minute punctures similar to those on lower gena except sparse, integument otherwise smooth. Pronotum with sparse, minute punctures, integument otherwise smooth. Mesoscutum with small, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, with some posteromedially separated by about a puncture width, integument between punctures; tegula generally smooth to faintly imbricate, with sparse, minute punctures; mesoscutellum with punctures as on mesoscutum except somewhat larger and coarser. Metanotum finely imbricate with scattered, shallow, faint punctures. Pleura with small, well-defined punctures, integument otherwise smooth except more imbricate in area of mesepisternal border with metepisternum; punctures on hypoepimeral area becoming oblique ventrally, nearly contiguous, except sparse along scrobal sulcus; punctures on preepisternal area smaller, becoming shallower, fainter, and oblique toward anterior margin; punctures on mesepisternum below scrobal sulcus becoming fainter along posterior border and on ventral-facing surface; metepisternum imbricate with sparse punctures. Basal area of propodeum largely obscured by setae, integument apparently imbricate and coarsely punctate; posterior and lateral surfaces of propodeum faintly imbricate to smooth, with scattered, small punctures. Metasomal terga with minute, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, except anterior-facing depression of tergum I largely smooth and narrow apical margins of terga smooth, integument between punctures smooth; sterna as on terga except punctures coarser and integument otherwise more imbricate.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
Coloration of head generally testaceous to black (lighter in 
holotype
male, darker in 
paratype
male), except labrum entirely yellow; mandible largely yellow except dark reddish brown to black apically; clypeus and supraclypeal area entirely yellow; paraocular area yellow below level of antennae and broadly along compound eye in lower half of upper face; paraocular area in upper half of face above antennae dark brown to testaceous; scape yellow, pedicel and flagellomeres I and II yellowish brown; remainder of flagellum orange. Pronotum dark reddish brown to testaceous (testaceous in 
holotype
male, dark testaceous along borders blending to dark reddish brown posteriorly in 
paratype
male). Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum dark testaceous to black; tegula semitranslucent; metanotum testaceous to dark reddish brown; pleura
</tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">testaceous to dark reddish brown; basal area of propodeum dark testaceous to black, remainder of propodeum testaceous to dark reddish brown. Legs testaceous. Wing membranes hyaline, faintly parchment colored; veins yellowish brown to dark brown. Metasoma testaceous.</tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Pubescence white and often obscuring integument on frons, vertex, gena, mesosoma, tibiae, tarsi, and metasomal terga where such setae usually appressed to decumbent and plumose (setae with numerous, minute branches along length of rachis, giving feathered appearance: similar to short-branched setal forms described by 
Saunders, 1878
, and 
Braue, 1913
), setae of mesoscutum not squamiform, typically as long as or slightly longer than ocellar diameter (setae abraded from large areas of mesosoma and anterior metasomal terga on 
paratype
male, allowing view of integumental sculpture); labrum with transverse, medial patch of short, erect, branched setae; setae below level of antennae typically sparse, suberect to erect, long, and minutely branched, similar setae on postgena; mesosoma with setae less prominent on preepisternal area and posteroventrally on mesepisternum and anteroventrally on lateral propodeal surface; tergal setae largely short and appressed; sternal setae longer, suberect, and posteriorly directed.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
FEMALE: As described for male, except as follows: total body length 
7.50 mm
; forewing length 5.00 mm. Head wider than long, length 
1.81 mm
, width 
2.44 mm
; inner margins of compound eyes comparatively straight, slightly convergent below, upper interorbital distance 
1.51 mm
, lower interorbital distance 
1.33 mm
; lateral ocelli separated from median ocellus by about one-half median ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from eye by about 2.0× lateral ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from posterior of head by about its diameter; scape short, extending to slightly less than distance to lower border of median ocellus; FI elongate, length about twice apical width, about twice as long as FII. Intertegular distance 
1.56 mm
.
</p>
            <p>Coloration as in darker male (above) (fig. 6).</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Pubescence as in male except for sex differences: probasitarsus with fine, erect to suberect setae with distinctly sinuate or wavy apices; metatibial and metabasitarsal scopa composed of dense, elongate, plumose setae; metasomal sterna II–V with rows of elongate, subdecumbent setae with sinuate or wavy apices, forming distinct scopa; sternum 
VI
with medioapical patch of dense, short, erect setae.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>HOLOTYPE
: 
♂
, 
Saudi Arabia
: 
Riyadh
, al-Amariah [al-‘ 
Amāriah
, a locality about 
12 km
west of 
Riyadh
], 
Majra
[Mazra‘ah] al-Gasim [
al-Qasim
, farm], 
23.v.2011
[
23 May 2011
], 
M.A. Hannan
(
KSMA
).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>PARATYPES
: 
1♀
, 
Saudi Arabia
: 
Riyadh
, al-Amariah [al-‘Amāriah], Majra [Mazra‘ah] alGasim [
al-Qasim
, farm], 
19.vi.2011
[
19 June 2011
], M.A. Hannan &amp; I. Naser (SEMC); 
1♂
, 
Saudi Arabia
: Qassim [
al-Qassim
], Unizah [Unayzah], al-Watania Farm, Rowdah, 
29.v.2013
[
29 May 2013
], M.A. Hannan; 
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulate</tp:taxon-name>
[sic] [
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
] (SEMC).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
FLORAL RECORD: The 
paratype
male was taken while visiting flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) C.A. Mey (
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteroideae</tp:taxon-name>
: Helianthodea: Inuleae), a rather common annual herb in the region, known as false fleabane or regionally as “Jethjath” and used in medicinal tea. Regional beekeepers consider 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
as a good source for pollen and nectar during the spring.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>
ETYMOLOGY: The specific epithet refers to the ancient kingdom of Kindah, which occupied, among other areas, large portions of the Najd, encompassing the 
type
localities.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
COMMENTS: There is variation in color of the head and mesosoma between the two males, the one from Qassim being darker and similar to the female from al-‘Amāriah, while the male from al-‘Amāriah is distinctly lighter. The lighter male is more testaceous in those areas where the Qassim male is dark testaceous to dark reddish brown, and dark testaceous to reddish brown in those places where the female and male from Qassim are dark reddish brown to black. However, despite these color differences, the integumental, structural, and genitalic traits are identical between the males. The male of 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
superficially resembles to some degree the male of the sympatric 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella
(
Tetraloniella
) 
persiciformisAlqarni et al. (2012)</tp:taxon-name>
, a eucerine that has also been taken visiting flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2017 ENGEL ET AL.: ARABIAN 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
13
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>14 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2017 ENGEL ET AL.: ARABIAN 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
15
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>16 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895: 9</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia hirtipesMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
(
Tarsalia
) Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Tarsalia
) 
ancyliformis
Popov
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
(
T
.) 
hirtipes
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
(
T
.) 
deccana
Baker
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
deccana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
hirtipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz. 
A.
Open
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Tarsalia
) 
ancyliformis
Popov. 
B.
Dense
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. (
Astibomelissa
) 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa
Engel
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Astibomelissa
) 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulate</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asteroideae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella
(
Tetraloniella
) 
persiciformisAlqarni et al. (2012)</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Discovery of the Bee Tribe Tarsaliini in Arabia (Hymenoptera: Apidae), with the Description of a New Species</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1206/3877.1</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFAD740C0B409454DC78FFE0FFF6FFE7</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1206/3877.1</pub-id>
               <issn>0003-0082</issn>
               <source>American Museum Novitates</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa
Engel
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new subgenus</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
(
Astibomelissa
) 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>TarsaliaMorawitz, 1895: 9</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia hirtipesMorawitz, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
, by monotypy. 
Friese, 1896: 211
; 
Baker, 1998: 837
; 
Michener, 2000: 666
; 
Michener, 2007: 686
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Ancyla
(
Tarsalia
) Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Warncke, 1977: 58
; 
Warncke, 1979: 192
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>DIAGNOSIS: As for tribe (above).</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
COMMENTS: The genus currently includes two rather distinct groups, one with three species in northeastern Africa, Arabia, and 
Iran
, while the other has five species in Western and Central Asia, south into 
India
, and west on the Mediterranean islands of 
Cyprus
and Sardinia (table 1).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
Key to Subgenera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
1.Metasoma and mesosoma dark reddish brown to black (fig. 1); metatibial scopa open (fig. 2A); subtriangular patch of distinctive, squamiform setae on outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate (Sardinia, 
Cyprus
, Western and Central Asia, 
India
)......................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str
.
</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>
—Metasoma and majority of mesosoma light castaneous to testaceous (figs. 3, 4); metatibial scopa densely closed (fig. 2B); outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate without patch of distinctive setae, area similar to remainder of scopal setae (northeastern Africa, Arabia, 
Iran
)...................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. subgen.</named-content>
closed (fig. 2B); outer surface of metatibia apical to metabasitibial plate without patch of distinctive setae, area similar to remainder of scopal setae. Metasomal tergum I with or without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces (all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str.</named-content>
with carina, albeit sometimes weakly so).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TYPESPECIES
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
               </tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>DIAGNOSIS: Body length approximately 5.5–9.0 mm; integument pale castaneous to testaceous on metasoma and majority of mesosoma (figs. 3–5, 6). Female metatibial scopa densely</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
1.Mesoscutum with numerous appressed to decumbent, plumose setae (usually missing on central disc, presumably due to abrasion), setae longer, not squamiform; outer surface of probasitarsus with fine, erect to suberect setae with distinctly sinuate or wavy apices (= 
type
IV of 
Pasteels and Pasteels, 1974
); inner setae of metabasitarsus white to pale yellow and similar to setae of scopa; metasomal tergum I without transverse carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces; smaller species, 
5.5–7.5 mm
in total length (
Saudi Arabia
; 
northeastern Africa
).................................................... 2
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
—Mesoscutum tomentose, with dense covering of appressed, minute (typically about 0.50× ocellar diameter), squamiform setae; outer surface of probasitarsus with fine, subdecumbent setae tapering to straight apices; inner setae of metabasitarsus fuscous, contrasting with surrounding white to pale yellow setae of scopa; metasomal tergum I with transverse carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces; larger species, 
7.9–8.8 mm
in length [
Iran
]............................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica
(Warncke)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
2.Female with yellow facial maculation confined to labrum, clypeus, and supraclypeal area (fig. 3C); metasomal scopa dense, with setae greatly elongate and subdecumbent to suberect; small species, approximately 
5.5–6.5 mm
in length (male unknown) [
Egypt
, 
Sudan
].................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes
(Cockerell)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
—Female with yellow facial maculation extending to paraocular area and scape (fig. 6C); metasomal scopa not so dense, with setae long and largely decumbent to subdecumbent; moderate-sized species, approximately 
6.7–7.5 mm
in length (central 
Saudi Arabia
)........................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
Engel, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p/>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>
DIAGNOSIS: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
can be recognized by combination of largely pale castaneous to light testaceous integument on metasoma, legs, and sometimes large portions of mesosoma although nota and much of pleura darker (figs. 4, 6); outer surface of female probasitarsus with dense, long, suberect setae with sinuate or wavy apices; metasomal tergum I without transverse dorsal carina; female metasomal scopa with long, subdecumbant setae with sinuate or wavy apices; male tergum VII with medioapical produced margin weakly bilobate (fig. 5A); male sternum VI apically truncate and with medial tubercle (fig. 5B); male hidden sterna asymmetrical and of characteristic form (fig. 5C); left penis valve hypertrophied (figs. 5E, 5G); and unique possession of yellow facial maculation on female paraocular area and scape, in addition to labrum, clypeus, and supraclypeal area (fig. 6C).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
DESCRIPTION: MALE: Total body length 
6.72 mm
(
7.14 mm
); forewing length 
4.70 mm
(
5.18 mm
). Head wider than long, length 
1.69 mm
(
1.94 mm
), width 
2.28 mm
(
2.34 mm
); inner margins of compound eyes comparatively straight, parallel in lower two-thirds, slightly diverging in upper third, upper interorbital distance 
1.31 mm
(
1.37 mm
), lower interorbital distance 
1.16 mm
(
1.22 mm
); apex of clypeus slightly below lower tangent of compound eyes; clypeus weakly protuberant and convex; ocelli at upper tangent of compound eyes; lateral ocelli separated from median ocellus by about one-half median ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from eye by about 1.6× lateral ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from posterior of head by about its diameter; scape short, extending at most to lower border of median ocellus; FI slightly longer than apical width, longer than FII. Intertegular distance 
1.41 mm
(
1.53 mm
). Basal area of propodeum weakly defined, about as long as metanotum. Legs without special modifications; mesobasitarsus elongate, straight, spur extending to slightly basad basitarsal midlength; metafemur slightly thicker than mesofemur; metabasitarsus elongate. Forewing with basal vein basad cu-a by 2–3 times vein width; 1m-cu entering second submarginal cell; second submarginal cell shortest, narrowed toward anterior wing margin; 2rs-m arcuate. Hind wing with nine distal hamuli. Metasomal tergum I without carina at angle of anterior- and dorsal-facing surfaces (similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
); tergum VII gradulus medially pointed posteriorly, without lateral gradular teeth (sensu 
Baker, 1998
), but lateral area instead angulate, apical margin projected, deflexed medially, margin shallowly and broadly emarginate (fig. 5A); sternum V with medioapical margin produced with broad, apically blunt lobe; sternum VI narrowed apically, medioapical margin truncate, with broadly concave, smooth ovoid areas laterally along margin producing narrow medial disc bearing a medial tubercle (fig. 5B); hidden sterna VII and VIII asymmetrical and as in figures 5C and 5D; genitalia as in figures 5E–G, with penis valves markedly asymmetrical (figs. 5E, 5G).
</p>
            <p>Integument somewhat shining. Labrum with coarse, shallow, contiguous punctures, otherwise smooth. Clypeus with coarse, faint, shallow punctures separated by less than a puncture width, except slightly more spaced along borders and more oblique, approximately separated by a puncture width or sometimes slightly more, integument between punctures smooth. Supraclypeal area with smaller, more well-defined punctures, separated by a puncture width, except medially slightly more separated, integument otherwise smooth. Face below level of antennae with small, faint, scattered punctures, separated by less than a puncture width along border with clypeus and subantennal sulcus, then becoming sparser toward inner margin of compound eye such that paraocular margin impunctate, integument between punctures smooth. Face above level of antennae with small, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, integument between punctures faintly imbricate; punctures sparse in short, broad triangular patch immediate anterior to median ocellus and absent in paraocular margin where integument is strongly imbricate; ocellocular space medially as on upper face but with punctures absent along outer border of lateral ocellus and in paraocular margin bordering compound eye, former patch smooth, latter strongly imbricate; vertex as on upper face; gena as on upper face except punctures smaller and becoming gradually more widely spaced ventrally such that on lower gena punctures separated by 2–3 times a puncture width, integument between punctures smooth; postgena with minute punctures similar to those on lower gena except sparse, integument otherwise smooth. Pronotum with sparse, minute punctures, integument otherwise smooth. Mesoscutum with small, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, with some posteromedially separated by about a puncture width, integument between punctures; tegula generally smooth to faintly imbricate, with sparse, minute punctures; mesoscutellum with punctures as on mesoscutum except somewhat larger and coarser. Metanotum finely imbricate with scattered, shallow, faint punctures. Pleura with small, well-defined punctures, integument otherwise smooth except more imbricate in area of mesepisternal border with metepisternum; punctures on hypoepimeral area becoming oblique ventrally, nearly contiguous, except sparse along scrobal sulcus; punctures on preepisternal area smaller, becoming shallower, fainter, and oblique toward anterior margin; punctures on mesepisternum below scrobal sulcus becoming fainter along posterior border and on ventral-facing surface; metepisternum imbricate with sparse punctures. Basal area of propodeum largely obscured by setae, integument apparently imbricate and coarsely punctate; posterior and lateral surfaces of propodeum faintly imbricate to smooth, with scattered, small punctures. Metasomal terga with minute, well-defined punctures separated by less than a puncture width, except anterior-facing depression of tergum I largely smooth and narrow apical margins of terga smooth, integument between punctures smooth; sterna as on terga except punctures coarser and integument otherwise more imbricate.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
Coloration of head generally testaceous to black (lighter in 
holotype
male, darker in 
paratype
male), except labrum entirely yellow; mandible largely yellow except dark reddish brown to black apically; clypeus and supraclypeal area entirely yellow; paraocular area yellow below level of antennae and broadly along compound eye in lower half of upper face; paraocular area in upper half of face above antennae dark brown to testaceous; scape yellow, pedicel and flagellomeres I and II yellowish brown; remainder of flagellum orange. Pronotum dark reddish brown to testaceous (testaceous in 
holotype
male, dark testaceous along borders blending to dark reddish brown posteriorly in 
paratype
male). Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum dark testaceous to black; tegula semitranslucent; metanotum testaceous to dark reddish brown; pleura
</tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">testaceous to dark reddish brown; basal area of propodeum dark testaceous to black, remainder of propodeum testaceous to dark reddish brown. Legs testaceous. Wing membranes hyaline, faintly parchment colored; veins yellowish brown to dark brown. Metasoma testaceous.</tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Pubescence white and often obscuring integument on frons, vertex, gena, mesosoma, tibiae, tarsi, and metasomal terga where such setae usually appressed to decumbent and plumose (setae with numerous, minute branches along length of rachis, giving feathered appearance: similar to short-branched setal forms described by 
Saunders, 1878
, and 
Braue, 1913
), setae of mesoscutum not squamiform, typically as long as or slightly longer than ocellar diameter (setae abraded from large areas of mesosoma and anterior metasomal terga on 
paratype
male, allowing view of integumental sculpture); labrum with transverse, medial patch of short, erect, branched setae; setae below level of antennae typically sparse, suberect to erect, long, and minutely branched, similar setae on postgena; mesosoma with setae less prominent on preepisternal area and posteroventrally on mesepisternum and anteroventrally on lateral propodeal surface; tergal setae largely short and appressed; sternal setae longer, suberect, and posteriorly directed.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
FEMALE: As described for male, except as follows: total body length 
7.50 mm
; forewing length 5.00 mm. Head wider than long, length 
1.81 mm
, width 
2.44 mm
; inner margins of compound eyes comparatively straight, slightly convergent below, upper interorbital distance 
1.51 mm
, lower interorbital distance 
1.33 mm
; lateral ocelli separated from median ocellus by about one-half median ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from eye by about 2.0× lateral ocellar diameter; lateral ocellus separated from posterior of head by about its diameter; scape short, extending to slightly less than distance to lower border of median ocellus; FI elongate, length about twice apical width, about twice as long as FII. Intertegular distance 
1.56 mm
.
</p>
            <p>Coloration as in darker male (above) (fig. 6).</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Pubescence as in male except for sex differences: probasitarsus with fine, erect to suberect setae with distinctly sinuate or wavy apices; metatibial and metabasitarsal scopa composed of dense, elongate, plumose setae; metasomal sterna II–V with rows of elongate, subdecumbent setae with sinuate or wavy apices, forming distinct scopa; sternum 
VI
with medioapical patch of dense, short, erect setae.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>HOLOTYPE
: 
♂
, 
Saudi Arabia
: 
Riyadh
, al-Amariah [al-‘ 
Amāriah
, a locality about 
12 km
west of 
Riyadh
], 
Majra
[Mazra‘ah] al-Gasim [
al-Qasim
, farm], 
23.v.2011
[
23 May 2011
], 
M.A. Hannan
(
KSMA
).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>PARATYPES
: 
1♀
, 
Saudi Arabia
: 
Riyadh
, al-Amariah [al-‘Amāriah], Majra [Mazra‘ah] alGasim [
al-Qasim
, farm], 
19.vi.2011
[
19 June 2011
], M.A. Hannan &amp; I. Naser (SEMC); 
1♂
, 
Saudi Arabia
: Qassim [
al-Qassim
], Unizah [Unayzah], al-Watania Farm, Rowdah, 
29.v.2013
[
29 May 2013
], M.A. Hannan; 
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulate</tp:taxon-name>
[sic] [
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
] (SEMC).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
FLORAL RECORD: The 
paratype
male was taken while visiting flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) C.A. Mey (
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteroideae</tp:taxon-name>
: Helianthodea: Inuleae), a rather common annual herb in the region, known as false fleabane or regionally as “Jethjath” and used in medicinal tea. Regional beekeepers consider 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
as a good source for pollen and nectar during the spring.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>
ETYMOLOGY: The specific epithet refers to the ancient kingdom of Kindah, which occupied, among other areas, large portions of the Najd, encompassing the 
type
localities.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
COMMENTS: There is variation in color of the head and mesosoma between the two males, the one from Qassim being darker and similar to the female from al-‘Amāriah, while the male from al-‘Amāriah is distinctly lighter. The lighter male is more testaceous in those areas where the Qassim male is dark testaceous to dark reddish brown, and dark testaceous to reddish brown in those places where the female and male from Qassim are dark reddish brown to black. However, despite these color differences, the integumental, structural, and genitalic traits are identical between the males. The male of 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
superficially resembles to some degree the male of the sympatric 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella
(
Tetraloniella
) 
persiciformisAlqarni et al. (2012)</tp:taxon-name>
, a eucerine that has also been taken visiting flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
undulata</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>DISCUSSION</title>
         <p>
The new species described here is most similar to the African 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
, a rare species known only at present from the female. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
are both smaller species that lack the characteristic matt of mesoscutal tomentum of 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica</tp:taxon-name>
, and also share distinctive setae on the outer surface of the probasitarsi, have fully concolorous white to pale yellow scopal setae, and lack a dorsal carina on the first metasomal tergum. Aside from the aforementioned characters, 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
also differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
persica</tp:taxon-name>
in the form of the male terminalia, particularly noticeable in the more dramatically hypertrophied left penis valve, and from all other species in the genus by the unique presence of yellow maculation on the female scape and paraocular area. The specialized setae on the probasitarsus of 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
mimetes</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
suggest some kind of interesting association or use, either in preparing the nest or for collecting pollen, although anterior and posterior probasitarsal combs are lacking in 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
. In the female of 
<tp:taxon-name>T
. 
kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
, although there is abundant pollen in the scopa, there are no grains within the setae of the probasitarsi. It would be revealing to discover more about the pollen-collecting behavior of these species. Unfortunately, nothing is known of the biology of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
, although several floral records have been documented across a wide range of families but principally among the 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
(table 2).
</p>
         <p>
The two groups of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia</tp:taxon-name>
, considered here as subgenera, are as distinctive as many genera among the closely related 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucerini</tp:taxon-name>
(e.g., 
Moure and Michener, 1955
; 
Michener et al., 1955
; 
LaBerge, 1957
, 
1970
; 
Pesenko and Sitdikov, 1988
; 
Baker, 1998
, 
2003
; 
Michener, 2007
), and could therefore be considered as such. We have retained them as subgenera for the time being as considerable sampling of these rare bees is needed in order to more fully understand their diversity, distribution, and unique characters. In particular, extensive biological data are needed from the various groups in order to ascertain their floral associations and the significance of differences in the scopal setae and patches bordering the metabasitibial plates, to say nothing about their nesting biology and the anatomy of their developmental stages. There are also great gaps in the available occurrence data for many species, particularly throughout 
Egypt
, 
Sudan
, and the Arabian Peninsula, and bordering areas where seemingly similar and suitable habitat occurs, not to overlook the similar gaps across Central Asia, South Asia, and the Mashriq (Levant + 
Iraq
). As presently understood, the two subgenera overlap only within 
Iran
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>20 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</title>
      </sec>
      <p>CLADE ROSIDS
ORDER 
<tp:taxon-name>CUCURBITALES</tp:taxon-name>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Cucurbitaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Citrullus vulgaris
Schrad.
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>T. hirtipes</tp:taxon-name>
ORDER 
<tp:taxon-name>FABALES</tp:taxon-name>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Alhagi kirghisorum
Schrenk
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. hirtipes</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Cullen drupaceum
(Bunge) C.H. Stirt.
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
ORDER 
<tp:taxon-name>MALPIGHIALES</tp:taxon-name>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Euphorbiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Chrosophora tinctoria</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) A. Juss. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. hirtipes</tp:taxon-name>CLADE ASTERIDS
ORDER 
<tp:taxon-name>APIALES</tp:taxon-name>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Apiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Carum carvi</tp:taxon-name>
L. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Eryngium caucasicum
Trautv.
</tp:taxon-name>1<tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
ORDER 
<tp:taxon-name>ASTERALES</tp:taxon-name>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Blumea</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. deccana</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Centaurea iberica
Trevir. &amp; Spreng.
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>C. solstitialis</tp:taxon-name>
L. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>C. triumfettii
All.
</tp:taxon-name>2<tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. hirtipes</tp:taxon-name>C.
sp. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Cynara scolymus</tp:taxon-name>
L. T. ancyliformis
<tp:taxon-name>Onopordon</tp:taxon-name>
acanthium

L. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. hirtipes</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Pulicaria undulata</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) C.A. Mey 
<tp:taxon-name>T. kindahensis</tp:taxon-name>
ORDER 
<tp:taxon-name>DIPSACALES</tp:taxon-name>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Caprifoliaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Dipsacus laciniatus</tp:taxon-name>
L. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>
ORDER 
<tp:taxon-name>LAMIALES</tp:taxon-name>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Acanthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Strobilanthes</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. strobilanthae</tp:taxon-name>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Verbenaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>Vitex agnus-castus</tp:taxon-name>
L. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. ancyliformis</tp:taxon-name>1
Reported by 
Popov (1967)
under the junior synonym 
<tp:taxon-name>E
. 
caeruleum
M. Bieb.
</tp:taxon-name>2
Reported by 
Popov (1967)
under the junior synonym 
<tp:taxon-name>C
. 
squarrosa
Willd.
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2017 ENGEL ET AL.: ARABIAN 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
21
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
         <p>
We extend our appreciation to the Deanship of Scientific Research at King Saud University for funding this work through research group project No. RGP 189. We are thankful to Chulwoo Shin, Victor H. Gonzalez, and Laura C. 
V
. Breitkreuz for assistance with microphotography; to 
Mary
Knight for her editorial help and expert assistance in transliterating Arabic; and to two anonymous reviewers for their constructive commentary. This is a contribution of the Division of Entomology, University of 
Kansas
Natural History Museum.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>REFERENCES</title>
         <p>Alqarni, A.S.
, 
M.A. Hannan
, and 
M.S. Engel
. 
2012
. 

A new wild, pollinating bee species of the genus 
Tetraloniella
from the Arabian Peninsula (Hymenoptera, Apidae)

. 
ZooKeys172
: 
89–96
.
</p>
         <p>Alqarni, A.S.
, 
M.A. Hannan
, 
I.A. Hinojosa-Díaz
, and 
M.S. Engel
. 
2013
. 

First record of 
Chiasmognathus
from the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Hymenoptera, Apidae)

. 
Journal of Hymenoptera Research35
: 
83–89
.
</p>
         <p>Alqarni, A.S.
, 
M.A. Hannan
, and 
M.S. Engel
. 
2014
a. 
New records of nomiine and halictine bees in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Hymenoptera: Halictidae)
. 
Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society87
(
3
): 
312–317
.
</p>
         <p>Alqarni, A.S.
, 
M.A. Hannan
, and 
M.S. Engel
. 
2014
b. 

First record of the bee genus 
Compsomelissa
in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Hymenoptera: Apidae)

. 
Pan-Pacific Entomologist90
(
1
): 
37–39
.
</p>
         <p>Ashmead, W.H.1899
. 
Classification of the bees, or the superfamily Apoidea
. 
Transactions of the American Entomological Society26
: 
49–100
.
</p>
         <p>Baker, D.B.1971
[1972]. A new 
Tarsalia
(Hym., Apoidea) from southern India

. 
Entomologist’s Monthly Magazine107
(1289– 
1291
): 
246–248
.
</p>
         <p>Baker, D.B.1994
. 

The date of the Hymenoptera section of the 
Exploration scientifique de l’Algérie
. 
Archives of Natural History21
(
3
): 
345–350
.
</p>
         <p>Baker, D.B.1998
. 

Taxonomic and phylogenetic problems in Old World eucerine bees, with special reference to the genus 
Tarsalia
Morawitz, 1895 (Hymenoptera: Apoidea: Anthophoridae)

. 
Journal of Natural History32
(
6
): 
823–860
.
</p>
         <p>Baker, D.B.2003
. 
Ulugombakia
, a new eucerine bee from Malaya (Hymenoptera: Apoidea: Apidae)

. 
Beiträge zur Entomologie53
(
1
): 
123–129
.
</p>
         <p>Braue, A.1913
. 
Die Pollensammelapparate der beinsammelnden Bienen
. 
Jenaische Zeitschrift für Naturwissenschaft50
(
1
): 
1–96
, + 
4 pls.</p>
         <p>Cameron, P.1898
. 
Hymenoptera Orientalia, or contributions to a knowledge of the Hymenoptera of the Oriental Zoological Region. Part VII
. 
Memoirs and Proceedings of the Manchester Literary and Philosophical Society42
(
11
): 
1–84
, +1 pl.
</p>
         <p>Cockerell, T.D.A.1933
. 
Descriptions and records of bees — CXLV
. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History, Tenth
Series 12 (
67
): 
126–136
.
</p>
         <p>Cockerell, T.D.A.1937
. 
Descriptions and records of bees — CLXIV
. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History, Tenth
Series 20 (
117
): 
280–286
.
</p>
         <p>Dours, J.A.1873
. 

Hyménoptères du bassin Méditerranéen / 
Andrena
(suite)

. 
Revue et Magasin de Zoologie Pure et Appliquée1
(
3
): 
274–325
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>22 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</title>
         <p>Eickwort, G.C.1969
. 
A comparative morphological study and generic revision of the augochlorine bees (Hymenoptera: Halictidae)
. 
University of Kansas Science Bulletin48
(
13
): 
325–524
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.2000
. 
Classification of the bee tribe Augochlorini (Hymenoptera: Halictidae)
. 
Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History250
: 
1–89
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.2001
. 
A monograph of the Baltic amber bees and evolution of the Apoidea (Hymenoptera)
. 
Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History259
: 
1–192
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.2005
. 
Family-group names for bees (Hymenoptera: Apoidea)
. 
American Museum Novitates3476
: 
1–33
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.2009
. 

Revision of the bee genus 
Chlerogella
(Hymenoptera, Halictidae), Part I: Central American species

. 
ZooKeys23
: 
47–75
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.2011
. 
Systematic melittology: where to from here?Systematic Entomology36
(
1
): 
2–15
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.2015
. 
Notes on family-group names for bees (Hymenoptera: Apoidea)
. 
Journal of Melittology46
: 
1–7
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.
, 
J.S. Ascher
, and 
D.A. Yanega
. 
2008
. 
Ancylini Michener, 1944 (Insecta, Hymenoptera): proposed emendation of spelling to Ancylaini, to remove homonymy with Ancylini Rafinesque, 1815 (Mollusca, Gastropoda) [Case 3461]
. 
Bulletin of Zoological Nomenclature65
(
3
): 
198–201
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.
, 
M.A. Hannan
, and 
A.S. Alqarni
. 
2012
. 
Systropha androsthenes
in Saudi Arabia (Hymenoptera: Halictidae)

. 
Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society85
(
1
): 
62–64
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.
, 
A.S. Alqarni
, and 
M.A. Hannan
. 
2013
. 
A preliminary list of bee genera in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia (Hymenoptera: Apoidea)
. 
Journal of the Saudi Society of Agricultural Sciences12
(
1
): 
85–89
.
</p>
         <p>Engel, M.S.
, 
A.S. Alqarni
, 
M.A. Hannan
, 
I.A. Hinojosa-Díaz
, and 
C.D. Michener
. 
2014
. 

Allodapine bees in the Arabian Peninsula (Hymenoptera: Apidae): a new species of 
Braunsapis
from the Sarawat Mountains, with an overview of the Arabian fauna

. 
American Museum Novitates3801
: 
1–15
.
</p>
         <p>Friese, H.1896
. 

Die Bienen Europa’s (Apidae europaeae) nach ihren Gattungen, Arten und Varietäten auf vergleichend morphologisch-biologischer Grundlage. Theil II. Solitäre Apiden. Genus 
Eucera
. 
Berlin: Friedländer &amp; Sohn
, 
216 pp.</p>
         <p>Friese, H.1902
. 
Neue Bienen-Arten aus Griechenland. (Hym.)
. 
Zeitschrift für Systematische Hymenopterologie und Dipterologie2
(
2
): 
105–108
.
</p>
         <p>Friese, H.1922
. 
Neue Arten der Anthophorinae (Hym.)
. 
Konowia1
(1– 
2
): 
59–66
.
</p>
         <p>Gonzalez, V.H.
, 
T. Griswold
, and 
M.S. Engel
. 
2013
. 
Obtaining a better taxonomic understanding of native bees: where do we start?Systematic Entomology38
(
4
): 
645–653
.
</p>
         <p>Griswold, T.L.2013
. 

New Palearctic bee species of 
Protosmia
subgenus 
Nanosmia
(Hymenoptera: Megachilidae)

. 
Journal of Melittology20
: 
1–9
.
</p>
         <p>Hinojosa-Díaz, I.A.
, 
A.S. Alqarni
, 
A. Lira-Noriega
, and 
M.S. Engel
. 
2016
. 

Ecological niche modeling of the rare bee 
Promelitta alboclypeata
reveals possible cryptic differentiation across northern Africa and Arabia (Hymenoptera: Melittidae)

. 
Apidologie47
(
4
): 
509–514
.
</p>
         <p>ICZN
[
International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature
]. 
2010
. 
Ancylini Michener, 1944 (Insecta, Hymenoptera): spelling emended to Ancylaini to remove homonymy with Ancylini Rafinesque, 1815 (Mollusca, Gastropoda) [Opinion 2246 (Case 3461)]
. 
Bulletin of Zoological Nomenclature67
(
1
): 
116–117
.
</p>
         <p>LaBerge, W.E.1957
. 
The genera of bees of the tribe Eucerini in North and Central America (Hymenoptera, Apoidea)
. 
American Museum Novitates1837
: 
1–44
.
</p>
         <p>LaBerge, W.E.1970
. 
A new genus with three new species of eucerine bees from Mexico (Hymenoptera: Anthophoridae)
. 
Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society43
(
3
): 
321–328
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>2017ENGEL ET AL
.: 

ARABIAN 
TARSALIA23</title>
         <p>Latreille, P.A.1802
. 
Histoire naturelle des fourmis, et recueil de memoires et d’observations sur les abeilles, les araignées, les faucheurs, et autres insectes
. 
Paris: Crapelet
, xvi + 
445 pp.</p>
         <p>Lepeletier de Saint Fargeau, A.L.M.1841
. 
Histoire naturelle des insectes — Hyménoptères, vol
. 2. 
Paris: Roret
, 
680 pp.</p>
         <p>Lucas, P.H.1849
. 
Cinquième classe.—Insectes. Cinquième ordre. Les Hyménoptères
. 
InExploration scientifique de l’Algérie pendant les années1840
, 1841, 1842 publiée par ordre du gouvernement et avec le concours d’une commission académique. Sciences physiques. Zoologie, histoire naturelle des animaux articulés [troisième partie: insectes (suite)]: 141–344, +1 pl. [pl. 19]. Paris: Imprimerie Royale, 
527 pp.
[Refer to Baker (1994) for details on the dating of livraisons comprising the third part of Lucas’ work on the arthropods; all 122 arthropod plates were also issued as a separate quarto Atlas in June 1849.]
</p>
         <p>Mavromoustakis, G.A.1952
. 
On the bees (Hymenoptera, Apoidea) of Cyprus.—Part III
. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History (12)5
(
57
): 
814–843
.
</p>
         <p>Michener, C.D.1944
. 
Comparative external morphology, phylogeny, and a classification of the bees (Hymenoptera)
. 
Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History82
(
6
): 
151–326
.
</p>
         <p>Michener, C.D.1999
. 
Genus-group names of bees and supplemental family-group names
. 
Scientific Papers, Natural History Museum, University of Kansas1
: 
1–81
.
</p>
         <p>Michener, C.D.2000
. 
The bees of the world
. 
Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press
, xiv+[i]+ 
913 pp.
, + 
16 pls.</p>
         <p>Michener, C.D.2007
. 
The bees of the world, 2nd ed
. 
Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press
, xvi+[i]+ 
953 pp.
, + 
20 pls.</p>
         <p>Michener, C.D.
, and 
J.S. Moure
. 
1957
. 
A study of the classification of the more primitive non-parasitic anthophorine bees (Hymenoptera, Apoidea)
. 
Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History112
(
5
): 
395–451
.
</p>
         <p>Michener, C.D.
, 
W.E. LaBerge
, and 
J.S. Moure
. 
1955
. 
Some American Eucerini bees
. 
Dusenia6
(
6
): 
213–230
.
</p>
         <p>Moore, M.J.
, 
P.S. Soltis
, 
C.D. Bell
, 
J.G. Burleigh
, and 
D.E. Soltis
. 
2010
. 
Phylogenetic analysis of 83 plastid genes further resolves the early diversification of eudicots
. 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America107
(
10
): 
4623–4628
.
</p>
         <p>Morawitz, F.F.1874
. 
Die Bienen Daghestans
. 
Horae Societatis Entomologicae Rossicae10
(2– 
4
): 
129– 189
.
</p>
         <p>Morawitz, F.F.1895
. 
Beitrag zur Bienenfauna Turkmeniens
. 
Horae Societatis Entomologicae Rossicae29
: 
1–76
.
</p>
         <p>Moure, J.S.
, and 
C.D. Michener
. 
1955
. 
A contribution toward the classification of neotropical Eucerini (Hymenoptera, Apoidea)
. 
Dusenia6
(
6
): 
239–331
.
</p>
         <p>Pasteels, J.J.
, and 
J.M. Pasteels
. 
1974
. 
Étude au microscope électronique à balayage des scopas abdominales chez de nombreuses espèces d’abeilles (Apoidea, Megachilidae)
. 
Tissue and Cell6
(
1
): 
65–83
.
</p>
         <p>Pesenko, Y.A.
, and 
A.A. Sitdikov
. 
1988
. 
Classification and phylogenetic relations of the genera of the tribe Eucerini (Hymenoptera, Anthophoridae) with two submarginal cells
. 
Entomologicheskoe Obozrenie67
(4): 846–860. [in Russian, with English translation in Entomological Review (1990) 
69
(
1
): 
88–104
.]
</p>
         <p>Pittioni, B.1950
. 
On the insect fauna of Cyprus. Results of the expedition of 1938 by Harald, Håkan and P.H. Lindberg. V. Hymenoptera Aculeata I. Diploptera, Fossores und Apoidea der Insel Cypern
. 
Commentationes Biologicae10
(
12
): 
1–94
.
</p>
         <p>Plant, J.D.
, and 
H. Paulus
. 
2016
. 
Evolution and phylogeny of bees: review and cladistic analysis in light of morphological evidence (Hymenoptera, Apoidea)
. 
Zoologica161
: 
1–364
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>24 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</title>
         <p>Popov, V.V.1935
. 
Beiträge zur Bienenfauna von Tadjikistan (Hymenoptera, Apodea [sic])
. 
Travaux de la Filiale de l’Académie des Sciences de l’URSS au Tadjikistan5
: 
351–408
. [in Russian, with German summary]
</p>
         <p>Popov, V.V.1944
. 
Tarsalia ancyliformis
Popov as an oligolectic bee

. 
Travaux de la Filiale de l’Académie des Sciences de l’URSS au Tadjikistan5
: 
155–160
. [in Russian]
</p>
         <p>Popov, V.V.1949
. 
Tribe Pararhophitini (Hymenoptera, Anthophorinae) as an Early Tertiary element of the contemporary fauna of the desert of Central Asia and Egypt
. 
Doklady Akademii Nauk SSSR66
(
3
): 
507–510
. [in Russian]
</p>
         <p>Popov, V.V.1967
. 
Bees (Hymenoptera, Apoidea) of Central Asia and their distribution on flowering plants
. 
Trudy Zoologicheskogo Instituta Akademii Nauk SSSR38
: 
11–381
. [in Russian]
</p>
         <p>Praz, C.J.
, and 
L. Packer
. 
2014
. 

Phylogenetic position of the bee genera 
Ancyla
and 
Tarsalia
(Hymenoptera: Apidae): a remarkable base compositional bias and an early Paleogene geodispersal from North America to the Old World

. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution81
: 
258–270
.
</p>
         <p>Roig-Alsina, A.
, and 
C.D. Michener
. 
1993
. 
Studies of the phylogeny and classification of long-tongued bees (Hymenoptera: Apoidea)
. 
University of Kansas Science Bulletin55
(
4
): 
123–162
.
</p>
         <p>Saunders, E.1878
. 
Remarks on the hairs of some of our British Hymenoptera
. 
Transactions of the Entomological Society of London1878
(
2
): 
169–172
, +1 pl.
</p>
         <p>Schönitzer, K.1986
. 
Comparative morphology of the antenna cleaner in bees (Apoidea)
. 
Zeitschrift für Zoologische Systematik und Evolutionsforschung24
(
1
): 
35–51
.
</p>
         <p>Schönitzer, K.
, and 
M. Renner
. 
1980
. 
Morphologie der Antennenputzapparate bei Apoidea
. 
Apidologie11
(
2
): 
113–120
.
</p>
         <p>Shebl, M.A.
, 
A.S. Alqarni
, and 
M.S. Engel
. 
2016
. 

First record of the bee genus 
Melitta
from the Arabian Peninsula (Hymenoptera: Apoidea: Melittidae)

. 
Zoology in the Middle East62
(
4
): 
352–357
.
</p>
         <p>Silveira, F.A.1993
a. 
Phylogenetic relationships of the Exomalopsini and Ancylini (Hymenoptera: Apoidea)
. 
University of Kansas Science Bulletin55
(
5
): 
163–173
.
</p>
         <p>Silveira, F.A.1993
b. 

The mouthparts of 
Ancyla
and the reduction of the labiomaxillary complex among long-tongued bees (Hymenoptera: Apoidea)

. 
Entomologica Scandinavica24
(
3
): 
293–300
.
</p>
         <p>Silveira, F.A.1995
. 
Phylogenetic relationships and classification of Exomalopsini with a new tribe Teratognathini (Hymenoptera: Apoidea)
. 
University of Kansas Science Bulletin55
(
12
): 
425–454
.
</p>
         <p>Snelling, R.R.1981
. 
Systematics of social Hymenoptera
. 
InH.R. Hermann
(editor), 
Social insects
, vol. 
2
: 
369–453
. 
New York: Academic Press
, xiii + 
491 pp.</p>
         <p>Snodgrass, R.E.1956
. 
Anatomy of the honey bee
. 
Ithaca: Cornell University Press
, xiv + [i] + 
334 pp.</p>
         <p>Soltis, D.E.
, 
P.S. Soltis
, 
P.K. Endress
, and 
M.W. Chase
. 
2005
. 
Phylogeny and evolution of angiosperms
. 
Sunderland: Sinauer
, x + 
370 pp.</p>
         <p>Straka, J.
, and 
J.G. Rozen, Jr.2012
. 

First observations on nesting and immatures of the bee genus 
Ancyla
(Apoidea: Apidae: Apinae: Ancylaini)

. 
American Museum Novitates3749
: 
1–24
.
</p>
         <p>Warncke, K.1977
. 
Ideen zum natürlichen System der Bienen (Hymenoptera, Apoidea)
. 
Mitteilungen der Münchner Entomologischen Gesellschaft67
: 
39–63
.
</p>
         <p>Warncke, K.1979
. 

Beiträge zur Bienenfauna des Iran: 10. Die Gattung 
Ancyla
Lep., mit einer revision der Bienengattung 
Ancyla
Lep

. 
Bolletino del Museo Civico di Storia Naturale di Venezia30
: 
183–195
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2017 ENGEL ET AL.: ARABIAN 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
25
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>APPENDIX</title>
         <p>
HIERARCHICAL CHECKLIST Of BEE GENERA AND SUBGENERA IN 
SAUDI ARABIA</p>
         <p>The following builds upon our earlier list (Engel et al., 2013), from which we are developing a guide to the Arabian bee fauna (Engel and Alqarni, in prep.). As in our earlier list, cleptoparasitic groups are denoted with an asterisk. Dates and citations for family- and genus-groups names within this list can be found in Engel (2005, 2015) and Michener (1999, 2007), respectively, and are not included here. Citations for recent records are appended.</p>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>COLLETIDAE Lepeletier de Saint Fargeau</tp:taxon-name>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>COLLETINAE Lepeletier de Saint Fargeau</tp:taxon-name>
Genus 
Colletes
Latreille Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>HYLAEINAE Viereck</tp:taxon-name>
Genus 
Hylaeus
Fabricius Subgenus 
Hylaeus
s. str. (Engel, unpubl. data) Subgenus 
Nothylaeus
Bridwell (Engel, unpubl. data) Subgenus 
Paraprosopis
Popov
</p>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>ANDRENIDAE Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>ANDRENINAE Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Andrena
Fabricius
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Chrysandrena
Hedicke
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Graecandrena
Warncke
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Melanapis
Cameron
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Suandrena
Warncke
</p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>PANURGINAE Leach</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Melitturgini Newman</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Borgatomelissa
Patiny
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Meliturgulini</tp:taxon-name>
Engel
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Meliturgula
Friese
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Panurgini Leach</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Panurginus
Nylander (Shebl and Engel, unpubl. data)
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Panurgus
Panzer
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Panurgus
s. str.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>26 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</title>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>HALICTIDAE Thomson</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>ROPHITINAE Schenck</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Rophitini Schenck</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Dufourea
Lepeletier de Saint Fargeau
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Dufourea
s. str.
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Systropha
Illiger (Engel et al., 2012)
</p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>NOMIINAE Robertson</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Nomiini Robertson</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Lipotriches
Gerstaecker
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Rhopalomelissa
Alfflen (Alqarni et al., 2014a)
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Nomia
Latreille
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Crocisaspidia
Ashmead
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Pseudapis
Kirby
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Pseudapis
s. str.
</p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>HALICTINAE Thomson</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Nomioidini Börner</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Ceylalictus
Strand
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Ceylalictus
s. str.
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Nomioides
Schenck
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Nomioides
s. str.
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Halictini Thomson</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Halictus
Latreille
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Argalictus
Pesenko (Alqarni et al., 2014a)
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Seladonia
Robertson
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Vestitohalictus
Blüthgen
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Lasioglossum
Curtis
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Afrodialictus
Pauly
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Ctenonomia
Cameron
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Evylaeus
Robertson
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Lasioglossum
s. str.
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Sphecodes
Latreille (Engel, unpubl. data)
</p>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>MELITTIDAE Kawall</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>MELITTINAE Kawall</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Melittini Kawall</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Melitta
Kirby (Shebl et al., 2016)
</p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>DASYPODAINAE Börner</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Promelittini Michener</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Promelitta
Warncke (Hinojosa-Díaz et al., 2016)
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Dasypodaini Börner</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Dasypoda
Latreille
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2017 ENGEL ET AL.: ARABIAN 
<tp:taxon-name>TARSALIA</tp:taxon-name>
27
</title>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>MEGACHILIDAE Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>MEGACHILINAE Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Anthidiini Ashmead</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Afranthidium
Michener
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Mesanthidium
Popov
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Anthidium
Fabricius
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Anthidium
s. str.
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Proanthidium
Friese
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Icteranthidium
Michener
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Pachyanthidium
Friese
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Trichanthidiodes
Michener and Griswold
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Pseudoanthidium
Friese
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Pseudoanthidium
s. str.
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Osmiini Newman</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Osmia
Panzer
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Helicosmia
Thomson
</p>
         <p>Genus Protosmia Ducke</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Nanosmia
Griswold (Griswold, 2013)
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Pseudoheriades
Peters
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Megachilini Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
Chalicodoma
Lepeletier de Saint Fargeau
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Chalicodoma
s. str.
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Pseudomegachile
Friese
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Coelioxys
Latreille*
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Allocoelioxys
Tkalců*
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
Megachile
Latreille
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Creightonella
Cockerell
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Eutricharaea
Thomson
</p>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>APIDAE Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>XYLOCOPINAE Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Xylocopini Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Xylocopa
Latreille
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Koptortosoma
Gribodo
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Ctenoxylocopa
Michener
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Ceratinini Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Ceratina
Latreille
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Dalyatina
Terzo et al.
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Euceratina
Hirashima et al.
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Pithitis
Klug
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Allodapini Cockerell</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Compsomelissa
Alfflen (Alqarni et al., 2014b)
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Braunsapis
Michener
</tp:taxon-name>
(Engel et al., 2014)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>28 AMERICAN MUSEUM NOVITATES NO. 3877</title>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>NOMADINAE Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
*
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Ammobatini Handlirsch</tp:taxon-name>
*
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Ammobates
Latreille
</tp:taxon-name>
*
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>Ammobates</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str.</named-content>
*
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Chiasmognathus</tp:taxon-name>
Engel* (Alqarni et al., 2013)
</p>
         <p>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>APINAE Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucerini Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucera
Scopoli
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Synhalonia
Patton
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella
Ashmead
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraloniella</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str.</named-content>
(Alqarni et al., 2012)
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsaliini</tp:taxon-name>
Engel
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tarsalia
Morawitz
</tp:taxon-name>
(reported herein)
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>Astibomelissa</tp:taxon-name>
Engel
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Anthophorini Dahlbom</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Amegilla
Friese
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>Amegilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Micramegilla
Brooks
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Zebramegilla
Brooks
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Anthophora
Latreille
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Heliophila
Klug
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Paramegilla
Friese
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Petalosternon
Brooks
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Pyganthophora
Brooks
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Melectini Westwood</tp:taxon-name>
*
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Melecta
Latreille
</tp:taxon-name>
*
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Paracrocisa
Alfflen*
</p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Thyreus
Panzer
</tp:taxon-name>
*
</p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Apini Latreille</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Apis
Linnaeus
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
Micrapis
Ashmead
</p>
         <p>
Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>Apis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str.</named-content>
         </p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
