<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4254.1.3</journal-id>
         <issn>1175-5326</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A new species of habitat – forming Suberites (Porifera, Demospongiae, Suberitida) in the Benguela upwelling region (South Africa)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2017</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
A new species of habitat–forming 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
(Porifera, Demospongiae, Suberitida) in the Benguela upwelling region (
South
Africa

)
</p>
         <p>
TOUFIEK SAMAAI 
1
,2,5, SESHNEE MADURAY1,3, LIESL JANSON1, 
MARK
J 
GIBBONS
3, BENEDICTA NGWAKUM4 &amp; PETER R TESKE4
</p>
         <p>1
Department of Environmental Affairs, Oceans &amp; Coasts Branch, Oceans &amp; Coasts Chief Research, Marine Biodiversity and Coastal Directorate, Marine Biodiversity and Ecosystems Research, Private Bag 
X2
, Roggebaai, 8012, 
Cape
Town, 
Western
Cape

, 
South
Africa

.
</p>
         <p>2
Marine Research Institute (MA–RE), University of 
Cape
Town, Private Bag 
X 3
, Rondebosch 7701, 
Cape
Town, 
South
Africa
3
Department of Biodiversity and Conservation, University of the 
Western
Cape

, Bellville, 
Cape
Town, 
South
Africa
4
Molecular Zoology Lab, Department of Zoology, University of Johannesburg, 
Auckland
Park 2006, 
South
Africa
5Corresponding author. E-mail: (tsamaai@environment.gov.za; toufiek.samaai@gmail.com); Tel. +27 21 819 5047 or +27 (0) 83 2479485</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is described from the west coast of 
South
Africa

and occurs at depths of 
80–500 m
among unconsolidated sediments. Specimens can reach 
40 cm
in length and in some areas off 
South
Africa

, up to 
18 tons
/km2 can be collected in a single demersal trawl. Morphologically, the sponge is straw yellow, massive with rounded lobes and has a velvety surface: it is characterized by subradiate, irregular reticulation of bundles of tylostyles and tylostrongyles. Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
have three size classes of tylostyles with the largest tylostyle lengths being 516 µm (441– 614 µm), medium tylostyle lengths being 352 µm (307–422 µm) and the shortest tylostyle lengths being 215 µm (153– 288 µm). Apart from the presence of tylostyles, some specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
also possess centrotylostongyles/oxeas, tylostrongyles and microacanthostrongyles spicules. We have used morphological characters to distinguish this species and a molecular marker (cox1) to conform that all specimens are the same species. At the spicular level, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is characterized by a complex of spicule 
types
that vary with specimen size. Following a histological investigation and re–description of the 
holotypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus
(
Johnston, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
, and comparisons with 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus
(
Johnston, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. stilensis
Burton, 1933
</tp:taxon-name>
, and other 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species described from the African region, it is clear that the new species is different in spicule morphology, spicule size and external morphology. For example, microacanthostrongyles are not present in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
, whilst 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
possesses a second, non–spinose category of microstrongyles. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
has tylostyles that are sometimes polytylote, with heads either well formed, pear shaped or reduced, in only one size catogory. The 'tylobtuse' condition of the tylostyles is also different to the kidney–shaped and centrotylostrongyles found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites stilensis
Burton, 1933
</tp:taxon-name>
has larger and thicker tylostyles (800 µm length 
x 10
µm thick) than those of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
A comparative analysis of partial cox1 sequences from morphologically diverse specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
with published material indicates that all specimens comprise a monophyletic clade. The combined morphological and genetic data support the designation of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>Key words
: Porifera; 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
; new species; 
South
Africa

; sponges; taxonomy; Vulnerable Marine Ecosystem (VME)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>
Large accumulations of sponges can be found over unconsolidated seabed habitats at depths of 
80–500 m
off the west coast of southern Africa (see also 

Uriz 
et al
. 1988

, 
1990
). These sponges form beds or facies (

Uriz 
et al.
1988

, 
1990
), and they are dominated by what 
Uriz (1988)
identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
, on the basis of their tylobtuse and kidney–shaped strongyles. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
was first described from the 
Red Sea
and, because it had not been recorded as bycatch in the local trawl fishery prior to 1960 (see 
Ridley &amp; Dendy 1887
; 
Kirkpatrick 1902
, 
1903a
&amp; 
b
; 
Stephens 1915
; 
Burton 1926
, 
1931
, 
1933a
&amp; 
b
, 
1936
), 
Uriz (1990)
suggested that this species was translocated to southern Africa some time between 
1960 and 1984
by fisheries and shipping activities (see also 

Mead 
et al
. 2011

). She added that “trawling seems to play an important role in the spread of the species” (
Uriz 1990, pp. 310
).
</p>
         <p>
Following 
Uriz (1988
, 
1990
), all large specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
collected over the continental shelf of the southern Benguela ecosystem have, until now, been uncritically identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
, although never thoroughly examined. However, a recent, more detailed examination of a large number of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
specimens revealed considerable variations in spicule composition outside the range hitherto considered normal for 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus
(
Maduray 2014
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Typically, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
has tylostyles and tylostrongyles in one size catogory, it lacks microacanthostrongyles and furthermore has (thicker) spicular widths of up to 25 µm (see 
Lévi, 1958
). The west coast 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
specimens however, possessed three distinct 
types
of megascleres; specimens could be distinguished that possessed tylobtuse strongyles and microstrongyles; those that lacked tylobtuse strongyles but possessed microacanthostrongyles; and those that lacked both tylobtuse strongyles and microacanthostrongyles. When 
Maduray (2014)
compared the “tylobtuse” tylostrongyles of the west coast specimens to those of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
described from the 
Red Sea
, they were not conspecific.
</p>
         <p>
On the west coast of 
South
Africa

, 
Uriz (1987
, 
1988
) and 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons (2005)
have identified 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
sponges as either 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus
(
Johnston, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, which lacks tylostrongyles but possesses microacanthostrongyles, or 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus
(
Johnston, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Samaai &amp; Gibbons 2005
, 
Uriz 1987
), which lacks both spicule 
types
. Both of these species were first described from the NE Atlantic, and locally they have hitherto been found on hard substrata at shallow depths (&lt;
20 m
) and on unconsolidated sediments at deeper depths (&lt;
80 m
) (see 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons 2005
, 
Uriz 1988
). The occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
in 
South
Africa

however, is considered dubious (Van 

Soest 
et al
. 2016

). This is because at least three distinct cryptic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
with microacanthostrongyles similar to those found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
have been described from the Celtic Sea around the 
Isle of Man
(Solé– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe 1986
); the 
type
location of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
. These species, including 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
,

currently have distributions that are restricted to the Northern Hemisphere (Van 

Soest 
et al.
2016

). Furthermore 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
was reported with a single variable category of tylostyles whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
were described with additional diactines (Van 
Soest 2002
; Hajdu 
et al
. 2013). It is also highly unlikely that the Northern Hemisphere species would spread across the entire Northern and Southern Atlantic Ocean.
</p>
         <p>
Three other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
have been recorded from 
South
Africa

, including the Benguela region and Prince Edwards Islands (PEIs)— 
<tp:taxon-name>S. axiatusRidley and Dendy, 1886</tp:taxon-name>
(
Namibia
), 
<tp:taxon-name>S. stilensis
Burton, 1933 (Still Bay)
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 
Uriz, 1987
, 
1988
, 
1990
; 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. caminatusRidley &amp; Dendy, 1886</tp:taxon-name>
(PEIs).
</p>
         <p>
The discrepancies that exist between published accounts of the ecology of the described 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species from the Benguela region (and 
South
Africa

), and the present material, have prompted us to re–examine in detail the specimens collected from the sponge beds off the west coast of southern Africa, using a combination of morphological characters and molecular data (cox1). Though the spicular composition and growth forms vary greatly between the west coast specimens, we have concluded that they are indeed the same species based on a closer examination of the morphology and the molecular marker. We have surveyed both the west and south coasts of 
South
Africa

and have not encountered this species on the south coast. After examination of the 
holotype
materials of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
, and through literature–based comparisons with 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. stilensis</tp:taxon-name>
and other 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species (including those from the African region), we conclude that this species is new to science.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Materials and methods</title>
         <p>Study area.
Specimens of sponges were collected along both the west and the south coasts of 
South
Africa

(

). The west coast is strongly influenced by the cool Benguela Current, and is characterised by a narrow continental shelf and coastal upwelling, which makes it a hydrodynamically active and productive region (

Hutchings 
et al
. 2009

). The shelf along the south coast is much broader. Coastal upwelling occurs seasonally at capes and peninsulas, and shelf–edge upwelling occurs along the edge of the Agulhas Bank (

Hutchings 
et al
. 2009

). Offshore, the warm Agulhas Current, which retroflects to flow eastwards south of 
Cape
Agulhas, strongly influences water temperatures in the region. Whilst the Agulhas Current itself is not very productive, the waters over the Agulhas Bank are (

Hutchings 
et al
. 2009

).
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 1
. Locator map of study the area, with trawl stations (points) conducted during 2010/11 used to display the typical distribution of sampling.
</p>
         <p>Specimen collection.
Sponges were obtained from demersal research trawl surveys conducted over the period 
April 2007
– 
January 2011
on the 
FRS
Africana

. Trawl locations were determined in a pseudo–random manner across a depth range of 
30–800 m
(
Fairweather &amp; Leslie 2008
; Atkinson 
et al
. 2011). A 
55 m
German otter trawl fitted with a 
75 mm
mesh cod end lined with a 
35 mm
mesh was used to collect the samples. The mouth of the net was 
26 m
wide. The net was trawled at a speed of 3 knots for 30 mins. Catches (kg) were converted to density (tons/km2), with the area swept by each trawl being 0.0246 nautical miles2. Catch data were imported into Q Geographic Information System 
QGIS
and mapped (

). The sponge specimens examined here were located in the Namaqua inner shelf, Southwestern 
Cape
inner shelf, southern Benguela outer shelf and southern Benguela shelf–edge benthic biozones (

Sink 
et al
. 2011

). In addition, we examined a trawl collected specimen from 
1970 in
the collections of the Iziko Museum, 
South
Africa

. All specimens were preserved in 96% ethanol upon collection.
</p>
         <p>Morphology.
Histological sections of the sponges were prepared by embedding a small piece in paraffin wax and then sectioning with a microtome at 70 µm and 100 µm. Spicule slides and Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM) spicule preparations were made following Boury– 
Esnault &amp; Rützler (1997)
. Clean spicules for SEM examination were spread on a plastic disc, air–dried, and coated with gold palladium for 20 minutes. The SEM used was a LEO S440 Microscope at 5 and 10 kV at the University of 
Cape
Town. Spicule dimensions are given as the mean length (range) x mean width (range) of 20 spicule measurements. Gross morphology, spicules and skeletal organization were carefully observed in all specimens.
</p>
         <p>Genetic analyses.DNA
was extracted from tissue samples using the cetyltrimethyl ammonium bromide (
CTAB
) method (
Doyle &amp; Doyle 1987
; 
1990
). A portion of the mitochondrial cytochrome 
c
oxidase subunit I (cox1) was amplified using primers 
LCO
–1490 (5’– 
GGTCAACAAATCATAAAGATATTG
G–3’) and HCO– 2198 (5’– 
TAAACTTCAGGGTGACCAAAAAAT
CA–3’) (

Folmer 
et al.
1994

). Polymerase chain reactions (PCR) were performed in volumes of 20 µl containing 3 mM MgCl2, 2 µl of 10× buffer (Promega), 20 mM of dNTP mixture (Sigma-Aldrich), 0.4 µl of each primer (10 mM), 0.24 µl of 
BSA
, 0.5 U of Super-Therm Taq polymerase (Separation Scientific, 
South
Africa

), and 5 µl of 
DNA
template. The cycling profile included an initial denaturation step (3 min at 94°C), 40 cycles of denaturation (30 s at 94°C), annealing (45 s at 50°C) and extension (45 s at 94°C), and a final extension step (20 min at 94°C). PCR products were purified using the QiagenQIAquick kit, amplified using BigDye v. 3.1 (AppliedBiosystems) and sequenced in both directions on an. Applied Biosystems 3730xl 
DNA
Analyzer (see 

Teske 
et al
. 2015

for Standard protocols). A total of 20 new cox1 sequences were generated while amplification failed repeatedly in 18 additional specimens, likely due to problems with 
DNA
preservation. Despite substantial efforts, we did not succeed in obtaining 
DNA
from a number of other collected specimens, likely due to problems with 
DNA
preservation.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 2
. Sponge species distribution (red dot) trawls (black dots).
</p>
         <p>
Cox1 sequences obtained were 580 bp long after contig assembly. To determine the placement of these among sequence data from all published sequences available from species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
, we jointly analysed our samples with cox1 sequences from fourteen other species (
Table 1
) in 
MEGA
version 6.06 (

Tamura 
et al
. 2013

). In addition, as a 
BLAST
search (Altshul 
et al
. 1990) on GenBank (

Benson 
et al
. 2009

) revealed that sequences from some other genera were more similar to the new species than some of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
sequences, we included representatives from the following genera in the alignment: 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudosuberites</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Protosuberites</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Hymeniacidon</tp:taxon-name>
. As there were no length differences between samples, these could be readily aligned by eye. The alignment of the cox1 sequences was checked for the potential occurrence of nuclear pseudogenes using the genetic code for invertebrate mitochondria, and no frame–shift mutations, which would indicate that these sequences originate from a non–functional gene region, were identified. To determine whether the 
South
African samples formed a distinct monophyletic clade relative to the other species, we reconstructed a phylogenetic tree using the neighbour–joining method (
Saitou &amp; Nei 1987
) in 
MEGA
. Evolutionary distances were computed using the Kimura 2–parameter (K2P) method (
Kimura 1980
), and support for individual nodes was based on 1000 non– parametric bootstrap estimates (
Felsenstein 1985
). The K2P distances were also used to compare levels of genetic differentiation between the sequences generated in this study and the published 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
sequences.
</p>
         <p>Material and acquisition.
Primary 
type
material of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
(
MNHNDCL
1301) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
, (
BMNH
1847.9.7.51) were obtained from the Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle, Paris and Natural History Museum, London respectively. All recently collected voucher samples are in the collection of Toufiek Samaai (TS) at Oceans and Coasts Research of the Department of Environmental Affairs. Accession numbers will be provided by the 
South
African Museum, Iziko Museums of 
Cape
Town, and specimens will be deposited into their Natural History collection. Abbreviations used in the text: TS (personalised number for collection of Toufiek Samaai); 
SAMC
(Iziko Museum catalogue number); 
MNHN
(Paris Museum catalogue number); 
BMNH
(London Museum catalogue number). The taxonomic authority for the new species described in this paper is restricted to authors Toufiek Samaai and Seshnee Maduray.
</p>
         <p>TABLE 1
. A list of species whose cox1 sequences were used in this study, with collecting localities. The cox1 sequences are shown with their GenBank accession numbers.
</p>
         <p>Species name Locality Voucher cox1 Sequences Reference(s)</p>
         <p>#</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
Benguela Region - 
South
see 
Holotype
and
</p>
         <p>
Africa 
Paratypes</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites aurantiacus</tp:taxon-name>CaribbeanSTAIIFP4EF519680
Erpenbeck 
et a
l. 2008
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites cf. caminatus</tp:taxon-name>Ross Sea—AntarcticaNIWA52801LN850254
Vargas 
et al
. 2015
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites diversicolor</tp:taxon-name>Kakaban Marine Lake— IndonesiaRMNH POR 6400KF568960
Becking 
et al
. 2013
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
*
Adriatic Sea (Croatia)UnknownAM690374
Lukic-Bilela 
et al
. 2008; Morrow 
et al
. 2012
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula</tp:taxon-name>Adriatic seaMCZ:DNA105717JX999078
Riesgo 
et al
. 2014
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites cf. ficus</tp:taxon-name>IrelandBELUM Mc4322HQ379429
Morrow 
et al
. 2012; Morrow 
et al
. 2013
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus</tp:taxon-name>MassachusettsNo VoucherAJ843891
Hess 
et al
. unpublished
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>IrelandBELUM Mc4043KC869422
Morrow 
et al.
2013
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites topsenti</tp:taxon-name>Ross Sea - AntarcticaNIWA28884LN850246
Vargas 
et al
. 2015
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria panicea</tp:taxon-name>IrelandBELUM Mc4070KC869423
Morrow 
et al
. 2013
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudosuberites nudus</tp:taxon-name>AntarcticaNIWA28874LN850223
Vargas 
et al
. 2015
<tp:taxon-name>Hymeniacidon sinapium</tp:taxon-name>Daecheon Beach, KoreaNo VoucherKF192342
Jun 
et al
. 2015

Aff. 
<tp:taxon-name>Protosuberites</tp:taxon-name>
sp.
Australia190513-06KJ620404Yang, unpublished<tp:taxon-name>Protosuberites</tp:taxon-name>
sp.
AustraliaPOR14649AY561979Nichols, 2005Results</p>
         <p>West coast
specimen identification.

A total of 
62 specimens
of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
spp. were collected and examined (
Table 2
). We also examined the 
holotypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
(
MNHNDCL
1301), 
<tp:taxon-name>H. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
(
BMNH
1847.9.7.51) and Iziko museum specimens 
SAM
–H4897 and 
SAM
–H4898, which were previously identified by 
Samaai and Gibbons (2005)
as 
<tp:taxon-name>S.
aff. 
carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. aff. 
ficus</tp:taxon-name>,
respectively. Most of the west coast specimens possess microacanthostrongyles, a spicule not mentioned in the original descriptions of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
, but described in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
. New spicule preparations of the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>H. fícus</tp:taxon-name>
–
BMNH
1847.9.7.51) revealed the presence of a second, non–spinose category of microstrongyles that was 24–48 µm in length. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus</tp:taxon-name>
also had curved styles (heads having a slight bump) and long thin sinuous styles with rounded heads, as oppose to the normal tylostyles present in our specimens. The 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
(
MNHNDCL
1301) has tylostyles that are sometimes polytylote, with heads either well formed, pear shaped or reduced, in only one size catogory. The 'tylobtuse' condition of the tylostyles, as found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
, is different to the kidney–shaped and centrotylostrongyles found in the west coast specimens. Microacanthostrongyles are absent in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and were also not recorded in the original description by 
Lévi (1958)
. The west coast specimens have tylostyles, which are thicker ¾ way from the head. Morphologically and skeletally, the west coast specimens are distinct from the 
Red Sea
species 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
(
MNHNDCL
1301) and from the north Atlantic 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Table 3
lists the main morphological differences between them. The known distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
is currently restricted to the 
Red Sea
(
Lévi 1958
; Van 

Soest 
et al
. 2016

) and the environmental conditions in the 
Red Sea
are very different to the southern Benguela to suggest that 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
has a broad ecological adaptability.
</p>
         <p>West coast
morphological and genetic variation.
DNA
was extracted from a total of 
38 specimens
of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
, but only 
20 specimens
produced sequences of sufficiently good quality for analysis. 
<tp:taxon-name>A posteriori</tp:taxon-name>
morphological examination of the 20 sequenced specimens indicated that these could be grouped into individuals possessing tylobtuse tylostyles and microstrongyles; those that lack the tylobtuse tylostyles but possess microstrongyles; and those that lack both the tylobtuse tylostyles and microstrongyles (

). The cox1 sequences of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
specimens from the 
South
African west coast formed a distinct but weakly supported (boostrap support: 62%) phylogenetic cluster and were characterised by a single polymorphic position, which defined two distinct haplotypes (

). A single representive of each haplotype was submitted to GenBank. The two haplotypes were part of a strongly supported genetic cluster (bootstrap support: 99%) that included previously published sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula
(
Olivi 1792
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites pagurorum
Solé
</tp:taxon-name>
– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe, 1986
(see 

). We could not sequence the two 
holotype
species (
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
) examined morphologically. Genetic differentiation (based on K2P distances) with published cox1 sequences were very low in some cases; e.g. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>JX999078
: 0.004; 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>AM690374
: 0.005; 
<tp:taxon-name>S. pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>KC869422
: 0.005. However, levels of differentiation between some of the published sequences from different species were similarly low, e.g. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>JX999078
vs. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>KC869422
: 0.000; and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>AM690374
vs. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>KC869422
: 0.005. The phylogenetic tree supports previous findings that 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
is not a monophyletic group (

Redmond 
et al
. 2013

), as several species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
were not recovered as sister to the ingroup cluster.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 3
. Three specimen groups for west coast 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>TABLE 2
. Comparative measurements of west coast 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
specimens (n.sp) with holotypes 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
anđ 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>Specimen Material Examineđ Acantho Thin Large Large Tylostyles Large sinuous styles Međium Tylostyles Small Tylostyles</p>
         <p>microstrongyles Tylostyles</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>MNHNDCL
1301 519 µm
</p>
         <p>type
specimen) (441 µm.556 µm)
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus</tp:taxon-name>
(
TypeBMNH
1847.9.7.51 23 µm (16.28 µm) 318.7 µm 212 µm
</p>
         <p>specimen) (288 µm.345 µm) (153 µm.268 µm)</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
(Type specimen)
Not Examineđ288.345 µm153.268 µm<tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus sensu
Ackers 
et al.
1992
</tp:taxon-name>Not Examineđ320.420 µm100.225 µm<tp:taxon-name>Suberites stilensis</tp:taxon-name>BMNH 1932.7.25.35 - not examineđup to 800 µmEctosomal tylostyles smaller (Burton đoes not proviđe measurements)<tp:taxon-name>Suberites stilensis</tp:taxon-name>SAM-H4899788 µm (728 µm.865 µm)542 µm 237 µm (455 µm.610 µm) (200 µm.264 µm)</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 1625 (Holotype)18 µm (16.19 µm)458 µm (441 µm.490 µm)389 µm (345 µm.403 µm)224 µm (211 µm.259 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 158618 µm (16 µm.19 µm)519 µm (480 µm.547 µm)331 µm (316 µm.422 µm)209 µm (163 µm.288 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 1592516 µm (441 µm.614 µm)352 µm (307 µm.422 µm)200 µm (153 µm.240 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 1584551 µm (480 µm.604 µm)352 µm (307 µm.384 µm)251 µm (192 µm.288 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 158717 µm (16 µm.19 µm)505 µm (412 µm.576 µm)351 µm (288 µm.384 µm)226 µm (163 µm.288 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
            <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 1602 Ts 161118 µm (14 µm.21 µm)537 µm (508 µm.585 µm) 527 µm (489 µm.585 µm)418 µm (355 µm.480 µm) 384 µm (316 µm.451 µm)216 µm (161 µm.284 µm) 217 µm (144 µm.288 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 161419 µm (16 µm.21 µm)490 µm (441 µm.528 µm)369 µm (326 µm.412 µm)159 µm (144 µm.172 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 181018 µm (16 µm.21 µm)502 µm (451 µm.537 µm)276 µm (230 µm.336 µm)150 µm (144 µm.163 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 180718 µm (16 µm.21 µm)506 µm (470 µm.576 µm)373 µm (288 µm.441 µm)213 µm (182 µm.240 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 181518 µm (16 µm.19 µm)503 µm (441 µm.595 µm)338 µm (288 µm.274 µm)161 µm (144 µm.172 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 181617 µm (14 µm.21 µm)560 µm (518 µm.614 µm)369 µm (307 µm.432 µm)182 µm (144 µm.249 µm)<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>Ts 182820 µm (16 µm.24 µm)556 µm (508 µm.595 µm)359 µm (307 µm.412 µm)215 µm (153 µm.288 µm)</p>
         <p>……continued on the next page</p>
         <p>TABLE 2.
(Continueđ)
</p>
         <p>Specimen Centrotylostongyles/ Large Tylostrongyles Small Tylostrongyles Small Tylostrongyles Relative abunđance COX1 Comments</p>
         <p>oxeas/styles (Kiđney-shape) acanthomicrostrongyles Gene</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
(
type
256 µm 188 µm No
</p>
         <p>specimen) (240 µm.297 µm) (182 µm.192 µm)</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus</tp:taxon-name>
(
Type
Common No
</p>
         <p>specimen)</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
(
Type
No
</p>
         <p>specimen)</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus sensu
No
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Ackers 
et al.
1992
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites stilensis
No
</tp:taxon-name>Holotype
not examineđ - see Burton 1933
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites stilensis
No
</tp:taxon-name>Holotype
not examineđ - see Burton 1933
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
327 µm (288 µm.366 µm) 264 µm 188 µm Commom Yes (240 µm.288 µm) (182 µm.192 µm)
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
265 µm Rare No Observeđ only three (259.2 µm.278 µm) Large tylostrongyle spicules
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
Yes
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
211 µm Yes Observeđ only one Large tylostrongyle spicules
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
Large Centrotyloxeas 413 307 µm 163 µm 86 µm Rare No µm (364 µm.518 µm) (259 µm.345 µm) (115 µm.192 µm) (76 µm.96 µm)
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
214 µm (182 µm.240 µm); 243 µm 163 µm Common Yes Large Centrotyloxeas 348 (201 µm.297 µm) (144 µm.182 µm)
</p>
         <p>µm (307 µm.451 µm)</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
None observeđ Yes
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
321 µm (288 µm.355 µm) 245 µm 182 µm Rare Yes (230 µm.259 µm) (172 µm.192 µm)
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
Rare Yes
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
Rare Yes
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
Common Yes
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
Common Yes
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
Rare Yes
</p>
         <p>TABLE 3
. Table summarising the morphological đifferences between 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
anđ 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>
Characters 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>S. stilensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>nov</p>
         <p>Texture when Unknown If fully expanđeđ very Firm even when fully expanđeđ Unknown Unknown (texture Unknown unđisturbeđ soft, đoes not sink when anđ sinks when broken off. compressable anđ soft -</p>
         <p>unđerwater broken off. above water)</p>
         <p>ContractionUnknownContracts to 1/4 of fully expanđeđ size when prođđeđ.Contracts to 3/4 of fully expanđeđ size when prođđeđ.UnknownUnknownUnknownShapeEllipsoiđ-oval (small to međium)Usually fig-shapeđ or spherical; often stalkeđ.Usually lobeđ, not stalkeđ; occasionally fig- shapeđ.Massive, usually lobeđRegularly massiveMassive, usually lobeđ or elongatesSurfaceVelvetly smoothSlight velvety feel to tongue. This is not always obvious.Surface lacks velvety feel to tongue,but there is high friction đue to the palisađe.Velvety anđ smoothSurface even, harsh to the touchSanđpapery anđ smoothSkeleton ectosomePlumose bunđles arranges in bouquettesPlumose bunđles of spicules at surface.Bunđles unite at the surface to form a palisađe.UnknownBunđles unite at surface forming a palisađe.Rađially arangeđSkeleton choanosomeRađiating architecture becoming confuseđ below the ectosome (Halichonđroiđ)Less đense, confuseđ, no tenđency to form a multi- spicular net: less of a size range in any one specimen.More đense, more orđeređ, tenđs to form bunđles arrangeđ in a net (use a stereo microscope on cleaređ section); greater size range in any one specimen.Irregular anđ tenđs to form bunđles anđ seperateđ by slenđer spiculesplumose reticulation, branching anđ anastomosing towarđs the surfaceSubrađiate, confuseđ irreguar reticulationCentrotylote microscleresAbsentAbsentPresent amongst the tips of the palisađe spicules. Seconđ smooth catogory also presentAbsentAbsentRough centrotylotes</p>
         <p>
Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
from the west coast showed no phenotypic differences with respect to external morphology or skeletal architecture, although variation occurred in spicule composition (

&amp; 

). Cox1 haplotypes in the phylogenetic tree (

) show no relationship with sampling location or spicule variation. Overall, this evidence suggests that all west coast 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
specimens collected and examined represent a single species with variable spicule composition. We therefore consider all the west coast specimens to be conspecific, and to represent a new species that is distinct from both 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
. The specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
previously identified by 
Uriz (1988)
and 
Samaai and Gibbons (2005)
from the same region are here considered to be variants of this new species. The 
type
species of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
are redescribed on the basis of morphological characters, and we describe a new species, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, for the west coast samples. Table S1 highlights the different morphological characters.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 4
. Cladogram constructed from cox1 sequences. Tree topology is based on the neighbour–joining method. Numbers next to nodes are bootstrap support values. The cox1 sequences of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
specimens from the South African west coast formed a distinct but weakly supported (bootstrap support: 62%) phylogenetic cluster (red line).
</p>
         <p>Species comparisons.
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
consists of approximately 80 valid species (
Table 4
; Van 

Soest 
et al
. 2016

). However most of them are described from temperate seas and only three species are described from the African region, of which two are from 
South
Africa

[including the Prince Edward Islands (PEIs)] (
Table 4
; Van 

Soest 
et al
. 2016

). Other regional species described from the Atlantic or 
Western
Indian Ocean (WIO) are from 
India
(one species), the 
Red Sea
(three species), the Azores archipelago (two species), the Southern Ocean Islands (three species) and the Atlantic coast of 
South
America (two species) (see 
Table 4
). We will discuss and compare, these species, by region, as well as contrast the 
holotypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>
The description from Still Bay, 
South
Africa

, of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. stilensis</tp:taxon-name>
is brief and vague. The largest tylostyle recorded by Burton (1933) was 800 µm length 
x 10
µm thick. Burton (1933) made no mention of any other spicule 
types
nor indicate the dimensions of the of the smaller tylostyles found in the ectosome. We did not examine Burton’s material at the Natural History Museum, London (
BMNH
). According to Burton (1933), the sponge is massive, surface harsh to the touch with a radial–anastomosing and branching choanosomal architecture. The specimen described by 
Samaai and Gibbons (2005)
from the west coast of 
South
Africa

had similar tylostyles dimensions for the largest tylostyles [788 µm (728–865 µm)] as described by Burton (1933). 
Samaai and Gibbons (2005)
however, recorded three catogories of tylostyles (
Table 2
; Table S1). We have made measurements in specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from a variety of size classes (
5 cm
– 
20 cm
in length) (
Tables 2
&amp; Table S1), across its biogeographical range (

) and from the three identified specimen groups (

&amp; 

). All of the 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
specimens examined have three size classes of tylostyles with the largest tylostyles length being 516 µm (441–614 µm), medium tylostyle lengths being 352 µm (307–422 µm) and the shortest tylostyle lengths being 215 µm (153–288 µm), which is much smaller to the maximum length reported for 
<tp:taxon-name>S. stilensis</tp:taxon-name>
recorded from Still Bay and Elands Bay (west coast). The west coast specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
were also thinner in width to that of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. stilensis</tp:taxon-name>
(see Burton 1933; see 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons 2005
). Apart from the presence of tylostyles, some specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
also possess centrotylostongyles/oxeas, tylostrongyles and microacanthostrongyles spicules (see 
Table 2
). We consider the spicule length and width of the tylostyles, the halichondroid architecture and yellowish colour and distinct deep sea habit of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov
.
</named-content>
as strong distinguishing characters.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 5
. Comparative gross morphology for west coast specimens and holotypes of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The singular description of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites caminatusRidley &amp; Dendy, 1886</tp:taxon-name>
from the PEIs is brief. The largest tylostyle in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. caminatus</tp:taxon-name>
is 1200 µm and there is no mention of any microacanthostrongyles being observed. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites caminatus</tp:taxon-name>
also differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in having a hemispherical growth form and containing chimney like oscules and lacking microacanthostrongyles.
</p>
         <p>
Seven deep sea species (
<tp:taxon-name>S. bengalensisLévi, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus
var. 
depressusTopsent, 1904</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. gibbosicepsTopsent, 1904</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. axiatusRidley &amp; Dendy, 1886</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. mollisRidley &amp; Dendy, 1886</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. microstomusRidley &amp; Dendy, 1887</tp:taxon-name>
) have been described from the Southern and Northern Hemispheres respectively (
Table 4
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from the deep water 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites bengalensis</tp:taxon-name>
not only in its distinct cold temperate upwelling habitat, but also in its gross morphology (massive lobate vs. massive tubular), colour (yellow hue vs. pinkish gray), location (Atlantic 
South
Africa

vs. 
India
) by the fact that it possesses substantially smaller tylostyles in three size categories (
<tp:taxon-name>S. bengalensis</tp:taxon-name>
—280–1000 µm × 7–20 µm and 1200–1600 µm × 30–32 µm) (Table S1).
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 6
. Comparative skeletal morphology for west coast specimens, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
type species.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites axiatus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from the 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in having tylostyles that are spinulate, fusiform, with subglobular heads occuring in two size classes; larger tylostyles 1750 × 30 µm and smaller tylostyles 700 µm × 12 µm. The choanosomal architecture of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. axiatus</tp:taxon-name>
also has a thick central axis of longitudinally and closely–placed spicules, from which bands of spiculo–fibre radiate to the surface, where they diverge. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
has a halichondroid reticulation of densely packed tylostyles forming brushes that pierce the surface (Table S1). 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites axiatus</tp:taxon-name>
is described from 
Uruguay
(
Table 4
).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites mollisRidley &amp; Dendy, 1886</tp:taxon-name>
from the Crozet Islands in the Southern Ocean, differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in being stipitate and having extremely large tylostyles (2000 × 30 µm), similar to those found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. axiatus</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Topsent (1904)
reported 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus
var. 
depressus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. gibbosiceps</tp:taxon-name>
from the Azores. The latter species has a cream coloration with tylostyles that are twice as large as in the new species (see Table S1). There are no subsequent reports of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus
var. 
depressus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. gibbosiceps</tp:taxon-name>
. All the deep water species listed above are set apart from the new species by their possession of tylostyles that can be much larger (±1000 µm) than those of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
(see Table S1).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites clavatusKeller, 1891</tp:taxon-name>
from the Eritrean 
Red Sea
, has tylostyles measuring between 300–530 µm 
x 5
– 9.8–15 µm (
Table 4
; Table S1). These are shorter than those of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
Similar spicule dimensions for 
<tp:taxon-name>S. clavatus</tp:taxon-name>
were reported by Lévi (1965) from the island of Abu Latt, in the 
Red Sea
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites microstomusRidley &amp; Dendy, 1887</tp:taxon-name>
can be differentiated from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in the following ways: 1) the sponge is hemispherical with raised oscules; 2) it has a thick cortex; 3) the size and form of the tylostyles, which are much larger and thicker than in the new species; it occurs in the Northern Hemisphere (Azores).
</p>
         <p>
Another Eritrean 
Red Sea
species, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites kelleri
Burton, 1930
</tp:taxon-name>
, is encrusting and dark brown. The average length of tylostyles is shorter and thinner than either the new species or 
<tp:taxon-name>S. clavatus</tp:taxon-name>
and they occur only in one size catogory (Table S1). 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites kelleri</tp:taxon-name>
has been observed from the 
South
African east coast and 
Kenya
(personal observation). 
Lévi (1959)
reported 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tortuosusLévi, 1959</tp:taxon-name>
, from Soa Tome, Gulf of 
Guinea
. The specimen described by 
Lévi (1959)
had a large number of branches but unfortunately the live colour was not recorded. The tylostyles found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tortuosus</tp:taxon-name>
ranged widely in size (150–900 µm × 15 µm), with the average tylostyles length of this species (Lévi’s, 1959) being much larger in length than the tylostyles found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(Table S1). There are no subsequent reports of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tortuosus</tp:taxon-name>
, which is otherwise restricted to the Gulf of 
Guinea
. Finally, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
also possess microacanthoxeas in various degrees of abundance, a character not mentioned in any of the above species.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 7
. Geographical distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
along the west coast of South Africa (Green dots); Red dots—other sponge species distributions collected during trawl surveys.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tortuosus
sensu Cuartas
</tp:taxon-name>
(1986a; as 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tortuosa
var. 
austral</tp:taxon-name>
), described from 
Argentina
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in possessing styles in addition to tylostyles, it is massive–ridged like, as oppose to lobe shaped, and has two size categories of tylostyles, both smaller in size than the largest tylostyles found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(
Table 4
; Table S1). Three Chilean 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species, two described by 
Thiele (1905)
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites puncturatusThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ruberThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
and one described by Hajdu 
et al
. (2013), 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites cranium
Hajdu, Desqueyroux
</tp:taxon-name>
–Faúndez, Carvalho, Lôbo– 
Hajdu &amp; Willenz, 2013
, all have tylostyles in the size catogory of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
But they differ in the their spicules, habit and colour. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
has three size categories of tylostyles; it posses microacanthostrongyles and tylobtuse tylostyles as oppose to only two 
types
of tylostyles in the chilean species; 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is not encrusting (
<tp:taxon-name>S. puncturatus</tp:taxon-name>
), cushion–like or hemisperical (
<tp:taxon-name>S. cranium</tp:taxon-name>
); 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is not reddish in colour but yellowish–beige in colour (see Hajdu 
et al
. 2013) (Table S1).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites affinis
Brøndsted, 1924
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. anastomosus
Brøndsted, 1924
</tp:taxon-name>
(both described from 
New zealand
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
(described from the Northern Hemisphere) were reported with a single variable category of tylostyles (Table S1; see also Hajdu 
et al
. 2013). It is highly unlikely that these species would be spread across the entire southern Pacific Ocean or the Atlantic Ocean to 
South
Africa

. Hajdu 
et al
. (2013) reached a similar conclusion when they decribed 
<tp:taxon-name>S. cranium</tp:taxon-name>
from the Chilean Fjords. Furthermore, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. affinis</tp:taxon-name>
is attached to the substratum through a narrow base, being pear or club–shaped [(similar habit of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
(sensu 

Ackers 
et al
. 1992

)], while all the specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
are lobed–shaped. The habit of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. anastomosus</tp:taxon-name>
is also branched like with the ectosome clearly discernable, a character not visible in any specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>FIGURE 8
. Geographical distribution of the various groups within 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
along the west coast of South Africa.
</p>
         <p>
Three shallow water 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species with microacanthostrongyles (
<tp:taxon-name>S. rubrus Solé</tp:taxon-name>
– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe, 1986
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. pagurorum
Solé
</tp:taxon-name>
– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe, 1986
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. luridus
Solé
</tp:taxon-name>
– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe, 1986
) have been described from the Celtic Sea (Northern Hemispheres) (see Table S1 and 
Table 4
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from the shallow water 
<tp:taxon-name>S. rubrus</tp:taxon-name>
in its gross morphology (massive lobate vs. thinly ecrusting), colour (yellow hue vs. red– orange), location (Atlantic 
South
Africa

vs. Celtic Sea), it has larger tylostyles, in three size categories (
<tp:taxon-name>S. rubrus</tp:taxon-name>
— 250 × 7 µm, one size category) and substantially smaller microacanthostrongyles (
<tp:taxon-name>S. rubrus</tp:taxon-name>
— 
31 x
2.2 µm). 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>
and S. 
<tp:taxon-name>luridus</tp:taxon-name>
differ from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in having one size catory of tylostyles (
<tp:taxon-name>S. pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>
—252 × 8 µm; 
<tp:taxon-name>S. luridus</tp:taxon-name>
—249 × 8 µm) and also larger microcentrostrongyles (
<tp:taxon-name>S. pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>
— 
29 x 3
µm; 
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
luridus</tp:taxon-name>
— 
30 x 2
µm). All three species are found to be epibionts on 
<tp:taxon-name>Chlamys opercularis</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
rubrus</tp:taxon-name>&amp;<tp:taxon-name>S
. 
luridus</tp:taxon-name>
) or the gastropod 
<tp:taxon-name>Pagurus bernhardus</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>S. pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>
)

.
</p>
         <p>
It is clear that 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
is something of a “dustbin assemblage” that has been recorded from all corners of the globe (Van 

Soest 
et al
. 2016

). As indicated by Van 
Soest (2002)
and Hajdu 
et al
. (2013) this species is in need of a taxonomic revision as it may well contain a series of cryptic species, as noted for 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
(Solé– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe, 1986
). 

Ackers 
et al
. (1992)

describe 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
as being massive–fig shape, attached by a stalk to the substrate with long thin tylostyles of one category.
</p>
         <p>
The new species reported here is considered well differentiated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
occurring both in in the Benguela region but also in other regions (south-eastern/western Pacific, south–western Atlantic and Northern Atlantic/Mediterranean regions) have traditionally been regarded as possibly sharing faunistic elements with the marine temperate 
South
African biota.
</p>
         <p>TABLE 4.
The table briefly summarises the descriptive information available for all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
thus far recorded.
</p>
         <p>
Genus Species Taxonomic Authority accepted Country 
Type
Location Range distribution Hemisphere Comments Status distribution
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites affinis</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Brøndsted, 1924 
New ZealandAuckland
Is, New 
New Zealand
Southern
</p>
         <p>Zealand Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites anastomosus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Brøndsted, 1924 
New ZealandAuckland
Is &amp; 
New Zealand
Southern
</p>
         <p>Campbell Is, New Hemisphere</p>
         <p>Zealand</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites aurantiacus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (Duchassaing &amp; Carribean 
Eastern
Caribbean Caribbean; 
Panama
Northern
</p>
         <p>
Michelotti, 1864) Bight; 
Bermuda
; Hemisphere
</p>
         <p>Brazil</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites australiensis</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Bergquist, 1968 
New Zealand
Cuviar 
Island
, New 
New Zealand
Southern
</p>
         <p>Zealand Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites axiatus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Ridley &amp; Dendy, 
UruguayUruguay
- Buenos 
Uruguay
- Buenos Southern The record of this species occuring
</p>
         <p>
1886 Aires Shelf Aires Shelf Hemisphere in 
Namibia
is inaccurate
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites axinelloides</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Brøndsted, 1924 
New Zealand
Three Kings - New 
New Zealand
Southern
</p>
         <p>Zealand Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites baffini</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Brøndsted, 1933 
Canada
Baffin 
Island
- 
CanadaCanada
Northern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites bengalensis</tp:taxon-name>
accepted 
Lévi, 1964
Bay of Bengal Indian part of the Bay Indian part of the Bay Northern
</p>
         <p>of Bengal of Bengal Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites caminatus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Ridley &amp; Dendy, 
South
Africa

Prince Edward Islands Prince Edward Southern The records of this species 1886 Islands, Southeastern Hemisphere occuring in the the Azores and 
Brazil
and Uraguay 
South
Newfoundland is inaccurate; The records from 
Brazil
and 
Uruguay
is also questionable
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (
Johnston, 1842
) 
United KingdomUnited KingdomUnited Kingdom
, Northern The records of this species from 
Western
Hemisphere the WIO, 
South
Africa

, New Mediterranean, Zealand and 
Red Sea
are Azores, Canary inaccurate Islands
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>var.
accepted 
Topsent, 1904
Azores Canaries Azores Canaries Azores Canaries
</tp:taxon-name>
Northern
</p>
         <p>depressus
Madeira Madeira Madeira Hemisphere
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>var.
accepted Topsent, 1900
</tp:taxon-name>France
North Sea North Sea Northern The cccurrence of the species 
incrustans
Hemisphere occuring in the Mediterranean is
</p>
         <p>questanable</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>var.
accepted Dendy, 1924
</tp:taxon-name>New ZealandNew ZealandNew Zealand
Southern
</p>
         <p>novaezealandiae
Hemisphere
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>var.
accepted Topsent, 1900
</tp:taxon-name>
Mediterranean 
WesternWestern
Northern The cccurrence of the species 
ramosus
Mediterranean Mediterranean, Hemisphere occuring in 
Norway
questionable. Northern 
Norway
and This variety may be similar to the 
Finnmark
, encrusting North Sea specimen 

……continued on the next page 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>var.
accepted (
Olivi, 1792
)
</tp:taxon-name>
Mediterranean Adriatic Sea Mediterranean Northern
</p>
         <p>TABLE 4.
(Continued)
</p>
         <p>GenusSpeciesTaxonomic StatusAuthority acceptedCountryType LocationRange distributionHemisphere distributionComments<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>clavatus</tp:taxon-name>acceptedKeller, 1891Red SeaSouthern Red SeaRed SeaNorthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>compactusacceptedVerrill, 1873FloridaFlorida Woods HoleFloridaNorthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>concinnusacceptedLambe, 1895CanadaCanada (Arctic)Canada (Arctic),Northern HemisphereThe record of this species occuring in the North Atlantic is inaccurate<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>cranium</tp:taxon-name>acceptedHajdu, Desqueyroux- Faúndez, Carvalho, Lôbo-Hajdu &amp; Willenz, 2013ChileChiloense (Chile)ChileanSouthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>crelloidesacceptedMarenzeller, 1886RussiaRussianRussianNorthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>cupuloidesacceptedBergquist, 1961New ZealandNorthern New Zealand, Rangitoto &amp; Onetangi BeachNew ZealandSouthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>difficilisacceptedDendy, 1897AustraliaSouth AustraliaSouth AustraliaSouthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>distortusacceptedSchmidt, 1870CarribeanEastern CaribbeanEastern CaribbeanNorthern HemisphereThe records of this species occuring in the North Atlantic are inaccurate<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>diversicolor</tp:taxon-name>acceptedBecking &amp; Lim, 2009IndonesiaPapua/IndonesiaIndonesianSouthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>domuncula</tp:taxon-name>accepted(Olivi, 1792)MediterraneanAdriatic SeaMediterranean, AzoresNorthern HemisphereThe records of this species occuring Mexico and the Sea of Okhotsk (western Pacific Ocean) are inaccurate</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
Hemisphere
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites excellens</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (Thiele, 1898) 
JapanJapanJapan
Northern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (
Johnston, 1842
) 
United KingdomUnited KingdomUnited Kingdom
, Northern The records of this species
</p>
         <p>
Meditteranean, Hemisphere occuring in 
Namibia
, 
South</p>
         <p>
Africa, North America, 
New</p>
         <p>Zealand and Possibly the Azores</p>
         <p>
are inaccurate 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites flabellatus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Carter, 1886 
AustraliaAustralia
- Port Phillip 
Australia
Southern
</p>
         <p>Heads Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites gibbosiceps</tp:taxon-name>
accepted 
Topsent, 1904
Azores Canaries Azores Canaries Azores Canaries Northern
</p>
         <p>Madeira Madeira Madeira Hemisphere</p>
         <p>……continued on the next page
Genus Species Taxonomic Authority accepted Country 
Type
Location Range distribution Hemisphere Comments Status distribution
</p>
         <p>TABLE 4.
(Continued)
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites glaber</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Hansen, 1885 
NorwayNorwayNorway
Northern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites glasenappii</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Merejkowski, 1878 
Russia
Russian 
Russia
Northern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites globosus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Carter, 1886 
AustraliaAustralia
- Port Phillip 
Australia
Southern
</p>
         <p>Heads Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites heros</tp:taxon-name>
accepted 
Schmidt, 1870
Caribbean 
Eastern
Caribbean 
Eastern
Caribbean Northern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites hirsutus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Topsent, 1927 Azores Azores Canaries Azores Canaries Northern
</p>
         <p>Madeira Madeira Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites hystrix</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Schmidt, 1868 Mediterranean 
WesternWestern
Northern
</p>
         <p>Mediterranean Mediterranean Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites insignis</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Carter, 1886 
AustraliaAustralia
- Port Phillip 
Australia
Southern
</p>
         <p>Heads Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites japonicus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Thiele, 1898 
JapanJapanJapan
Northern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites kelleri</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Burton, 1930 
EritreaEritreaEritrea
, 
Kenya
, 
South
Northern This species occurs within the
</p>
         <p>
African East 
Coast
Hemisphere WIO (person obs.)
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites lambei</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Austin, Ott, 
CanadaOregon
, 
Washington
, 
Oregon
, 
Washington
, Northern
</p>
         <p>
Reiswig, Romagosa Vancouver 
Coast
and Vancouver 
Coast
and Hemisphere
</p>
         <p>&amp; McDaniel, 2014 Shelf Shelf</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites laticeps</tp:taxon-name>
accepted 
Topsent, 1904
Azores Canaries Azores Canaries Azores Canaries Northern
</p>
         <p>Madeira Madeira Madeira Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites latus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Lambe, 1893 
Canada
Pacific 
Coast
of Pacific 
Coast
of Northern
</p>
         <p>CanadaCanada
&amp; 
USA
Hemisphere
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites lobatus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (Wilson, 1902) Caribbean Caribbean - Greater Caribbean Northern The records of this species Antilles Hemisphere occuring in the North Atlantic Ocean is inaccurate
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites luridus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Solé-Cava &amp; 
United Kingdom
Celtic Sea - United 
United Kingdom
Northern
</p>
         <p>Thorpe, 1986
Kingdom Hemisphere
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites lutea</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Sole-Cava &amp; 
United Kingdom
Celtic Sea - United 
United Kingdom
Northern
</p>
         <p>Thorpe, 1986
Kingdom Hemisphere
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites mammilaris</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Sim &amp; Kim, 1994 
KoreaKoreaIslandKorea
Northern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites massa</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Nardo, 1847 Mediterranean Adriatic Sea 
Eastern
Mediterranean Northern The records of this species Hemisphere occuring in the United Kingdon is questionable
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites microstomus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Ridley &amp; Dendy, Kerguelen Kerguelen Islands Kerguelen Islands Southern This species, as for 
<tp:taxon-name>S. caminatus</tp:taxon-name>
, 1887 Islands Hemisphere is also recorded from the East Antarctic Wilkes Land 
……continued on the next page ……continued on the next page
Genus Species Taxonomic Authority accepted Country 
Type
Location Range distribution Hemisphere Comments Status distribution
</p>
         <p>TABLE 4.
(Continued)
</p>
         <p>GenusSpeciesTaxonomic StatusAuthority acceptedCountryType LocationRange distributionHemisphere distributionComments<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>microstomus var. stellatus</tp:taxon-name>
mineri
accepted acceptedKirkpatrick, 1908 (de Laubenfels, 1935)Antarctica MexicoRoss Sea, Antarctica Mexican Tropical PacificRoss Sea - Antarctica Mexican Tropical Pacific &amp; SouthernSouthern Hemisphere Northern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>mollis</tp:taxon-name>
montalbidus
accepted acceptedRidley &amp; Dendy, 1886 Carter, 1880Crozet Islands EEZ Barents SeaCrozet Islands Barents SeaCalifornia bight Crozet Islands EEZ North and East Barents Sea, North Sea, Greenland ShelfSouthern Hemisphere Northern HemisphereThe records of this species occuring in the Aleutian Islands (North Pacific) is questionable<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>acceptedSolé-Cava &amp; Thorpe, 1986United KingdomCeltic Sea - United KingdomUnited KingdomNorthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>paludumacceptedSchmidt, 1868MediterraneanWestern MediterraneanWestern MediterraneanNorthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>paradoxus perfectusaccepted acceptedWilson, 1931 Ridley &amp; Dendy, 1886North America AustraliaChesapeake Bay Port Jackson, South AustraliaNorth America - Chesapeake Bay East Australia, Malay Archipelago, Northeastern New ZealandNorthern Hemisphere Southern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>pisiformisacceptedLévi, 1993New CaledoniaNew CaledoniaNew Caledonia, New ZealandSouthern HemisphereThe record of this species occuring in New Zealand is questionable<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>placentaacceptedThiele, 1898JapanJapanJapanNorthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>prototypusacceptedCzerniavsky, 1880Black SeaBlack SeaBlack SeaNorthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>puncturatus</tp:taxon-name>acceptedThiele, 1905ChileChiloense (Chile)ChileSouthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>radiatusacceptedKieschnick, 1896IndonesiaTernate - IndonesiaIndonesiaSouthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
ramosus rhaphidiophorus 
<tp:taxon-name>ruber</tp:taxon-name>accepted accepted acceptedBrøndsted, 1924 (Brøndsted, 1924) Thiele, 1905New Zealand New Zealand ChileCampbell Island - New Zealand Auckland Island - New Zealand ChileNew Zealand New Zealand ChileSouthern Hemisphere Southern Hemisphere Southern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>rubrus</tp:taxon-name>acceptedSole-Cava &amp; Thorpe, 1986United KingdomCeltic SeaUnited KingdomNorthern Hemisphere<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>senilisacceptedRidley &amp; Dendy, 1886HawaiiNorth Pacific - HawaiiHawaiiNorthern Hemisphere</p>
         <p>TABLE 4.
(Continued)
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites sericeus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Thiele, 1898 
JapanJapanJapan
Northern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites spermatozoon</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (Schmidt, 1875) Barents Sea Lindesnes - Barents Barents Sea &amp; North Northern
</p>
         <p>Sea Sea Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites spirastrelloides</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Dendy, 1897 
AustraliaSouthAustraliaSouthAustralia
Southern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites spongiosus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Schmidt, 1868 Mediterranean 
WesternWestern
Northern
</p>
         <p>Mediterranean Mediterranean Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites stilensis</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Burton, 1933 
South
Africa
South
Africa

- Still 
South
Africa

Southern
</p>
         <p>Bay Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites strongylatus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Sarà, 1978 
ChileTierra del Fuego
- 
Chile
Southern
</p>
         <p>Chile
Hemisphere
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites suberia</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (Montagu, 1814) 
United Kingdom
Celtic Sea - United 
United Kingdom
Northern
</p>
         <p>Kingdom Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites syringella</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (Schmidt, 1868) Mediterranean 
Western
Mediterranean Northern
</p>
         <p>Mediterranean Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites topsenti</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (
Burton, 1929
) Ross Sea Ross Sea, 
Antarctica
Ross Sea, Falkland Southern The records of this species Islands, Weddell Sea, Hemisphere occuring in the 
Falkland Islands
, Antarctic Peninsula Weddell Sea &amp; Antarctic Peninsula are questionable
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tortuosus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted 
Lévi, 1959Guinea
Gulf of 
Guinea
Islands Gulf of 
Guinea
Northern
</p>
         <p>Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tortuosus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>var.
accepted Cuartas, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>ArgentinaArgentinaArgentina
Southern This species should be compared 
austral
Hemisphere with the specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. topsenti</tp:taxon-name>
recorded from the 
Falkland Islands</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted 
Lévi, 1958Red SeaSouthern Red SeaSouthern Red Sea
Northern The records of this species Hemisphere occuring in 
Namibia
is inaccurate. This Benguela species is considered as the new species, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites villosus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted Schmidt, 1868 Mediterranean 
WesternWestern
Northern
</p>
         <p>Mediterranean Mediterranean Hemisphere</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites virgultosus</tp:taxon-name>
accepted (
Johnston, 1842
) 
United KingdomUnited Kingdom
North and East Northern The record of this species occuring Barents Sea, North Hemisphere on the east 
Greenland
shelf is Sea, 
Greenland
Shelf questionable
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites bursa</tp:taxon-name>
taxon Schmidt, 1862 Adriatic Sea Adriatic Sea Adriatic Sea Northern The validity of this species need
</p>
         <p>inquirendum Hemisphere further investigation</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites hirsutus</tp:taxon-name>
taxon (Fleming, 1828) 
United KingdomUnited KingdomUnited Kingdom
Northern The validity of this species need
</p>
         <p>inquirendum Hemisphere further investigation</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites maculans</tp:taxon-name>
taxon (
Johnston, 1842
) 
United KingdomUnited KingdomUnited Kingdom
Northern The validity of this species need
</p>
         <p>inquirendum Hemisphere further investigation</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Taxonomy—Species descriptions</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Phylum Porifera 
Grant, 1836</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Class Demospongiae 
Sollas, 1885</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Subclass Heteroscleromorpha Cárdenas, Perez &amp; Boury–Esnault, 2012</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Order
Suberitida Chombard &amp; Boury–Esnault, 1999
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>
Suberitidae 
Schmidt, 1870</tp:taxon-name>
         </title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>FiculinaGray, 1867</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberanthusLendenfeld, 1898</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberellaThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>CarnleiaBurton, 1930a</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>LaxosuberellaBurton, 1930b</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaUriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium ficus
sensu 
Linnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ficulina ficusLinnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium bulbosumEsper, 1806</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula
von 
Lendenfeld, 1888</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
Ackers 
et al.,
1992
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnson, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusa
sensu 
Uriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria fícusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Suberites 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelanae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Erylus, Geodia
(
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Crambe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new species of habitat – forming Suberites (Porifera, Demospongiae, Suberitida) in the Benguela upwelling region (South Africa)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4254.1.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFEDEE1CE740FFC6FF97A02311720F30</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4254.1.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>Restricted synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 523. 
<tp:taxon-name>FiculinaGray, 1867</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 523. 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberanthusLendenfeld, 1898</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 144. 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberellaThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 416. [
<tp:taxon-name>Suberella</tp:taxon-name>
] 
Burton, 1929
, pg. 446. 
<tp:taxon-name>CarnleiaBurton, 1930a</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 519; 
<tp:taxon-name>LaxosuberellaBurton, 1930b</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 675.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–f; 
Table 2
; Table S1)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–d; 
Table 2
; Table S1)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
(

; 11a–h; 
Table 2
; 
Table 3
; Table S1).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type species
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
(by original description).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
(from van 
Soest 2002
). Massive, compact, usually with velvety smooth surface caused by dense ectosomal arrangement of tylostyles oriented perpendicularly to the sponge surface, points outward; peripheral choanosomal skeleton consists of closely packed strands of tylostyles distinctly larger than ectosomal ones, with interior skeleton of densely packed tylostyles in confusion. Centrotylote, minutely spined microstrongyles may be present in a few species and if so are concentrated at the surface. Approximately 80 species have been described (obvious synonyms and invalid genus assignments omitted). The genus is cosmopolitan in distribution but is most common in cold or temperate waters.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Original description.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Synonymy.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 24, fig. 20; 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaUriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 38, fig. 15.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
. Holotype MNHN DCL 1301, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Small fragments of 
type
material (

a). 
Lévi (1958)
however, described the sponge as massive with rounded lobes. Surface smooth, irregular and velvety to the touch. Oscules not visible. Consistency soft and fleshy. Colour in life bright orange.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. Megascleres are tylostyles and tylostrongyles in one size catogory. Tylostyles 1, smooth, slightly curved sometimes polytylote; head either well rounded or pear shaped, or reduced to resemble styles. Distally fusiform, or with mucronate or rounded ends. One size category (440–556 µm 
x 15
µm) (maximum length 600 µm 
x 15–25
µm) (

b, c, d). Tylostyles 2, more slender than the previous ones in length, gently curved with well formed heads, sometimes slightly fusiform, 350–450 µm 
x 10–11
µm thick. Tylostrongyles short and stocky 182– 297 µm 
x 8
µm (maximum length 450 µm 
x 15
) (

e) (please refer to 
Table 2
for comparative measurements).
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Absent.
</p>
            <p>Skeleton
. The skeletal architecture is irregular and includes packages of radial megasclere pointing in every direction and separated by more slender spicules (

f). There is no recognisable ectosome. Ectosomal skeleton consists of densly packed tylostyles
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Type
locality

. Abu Latt 
Island
, 
Red Sea
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Habitat
. Coral reefs.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Original description.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; see also van 
Soest &amp; Hooper 2002
, pg. 242.
</p>
            <p>Synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium ficus
sensu 
Linnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 1295; 
<tp:taxon-name>Ficulina ficusLinnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 1295 (see 
Uriz 1984
, pg. 58); 
<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium bulbosumEsper, 1806</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 235; 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 144; 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula
von 
Lendenfeld, 1888</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 65 (not 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 241); 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
Ackers 
et al.,
1992
</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 68.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
. Lectotype BMNH 1847.9.7.51, 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnson, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Bulbous, or pear–shaped, sometimes bulging from a narrow stalk, 
2.5–8 cm
in length (

a). Van 
Soest (2002)
described the species as lobate, occasionally cylindrical and may include specimens enveloping gastropod shells and encrusting scallops, 
10–40 cm
in length. Surface smooth with a velvety appearance with one or more conspicuous, large oscules. Consistency firm and incompressible. Colour in life russet red; in dried state cream/white.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. Styles, two types (

b). Type I, slightly curved, heads rounded and having a slight bump. Distally fusiform, sometimes mucronate, 288–345 µm 
x 7
µm (Van 
Soest, 2002
, measurements 350–500 µm 
x 10
µm). Type II, very thin, sinuous, heads rounded having a slight bump. Distally fusiform, 153–268 µm 
x 2
µm (Van 
Soest, 2002
, measurements 100–250 µm 
x 5
µm) (please refer to 
Table 2
for comparative measurements).
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Microrhabds (

c)—microspined microstrongyles, usually centrotylote, common, 16–28 µm. Smooth microstrongyles, usually centrotylote (

d), common, 24–48 µm.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Skeleton
. The skeletal architecture is confused, almost halichondroid, being radial near the surface. The ectosomal skeleton is made up of smaller tylostyles arranged pendicularly forming a dense palisade at the surface. 
Type
locality

. 
Scarborough
, 
England
, 
North Atlantic.</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Habitat
. Deep water.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusa
sensu 
Uriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
, pg 38 (Not 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
); 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 28, figs. 3A, 21 a–e. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 27, figs. 2O, 20 a–d.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Material
examined

. 
Holotype
.
SAMC
–A088677 (cross ref. TS 1625), 
West coast
, Station 
A29477
(
30°26'0"S
, 
16°48'59"E
), depth 
180 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
Other Material examined 
Holotype
MNHN DCL 1301, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Holotype
BMNH 1847.9.7.51, 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria fícusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Paratypes
.
SAMC
–A088678 (cross ref. TS 1815), 
West coast
, Station 
A30349
(
31°47'58"S
, 
17°54'29"E
), depth 
114 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>SAMC
–A088679 (cross ref. TS 1592), 
West coast
, Station 
A29471
(
29°12'0"S
, 
15°59'0"E
), depth 
166 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1586, 
West coast
, Station 
A29444
(
30°58'0"S
, 
17°27'0"E
), depth 
134 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1587, 
West coast
, Station 
A29442
(
30°30'59"S
, 
17°19'0"E
), depth 
111 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1599, 
West coast
, Station 
A29478
(
30°19'0"S
, 
16°54'59"E
), depth 
154 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1602, 
West coast
, Station 
A29482
(
29°37'59"S
, 
16°20'0"E
), depth 
157 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1612, 
West coast
, Station 
A29481
(
29°40'59"S
, 
16°12'59"E
), depth 
166 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1614, 
West coast
, Station 
A29480
(
29°53'0"S
, 
16°18'0"E
), depth 
182 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1631, 
West coast
, Station 
A29439
(
30°50'0"S
, 
16°52'0"E
), depth 
198 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1633, 
West coast
, Station 
A29479
(
30°0'0"S
, 
16°20'59"E
), depth 
187 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1640, 
West coast
, Station 
A27448
(
32°0'24"S
, 
17°24'59"E
), depth 
160 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1783, 
West coast
, Station 
A30328
(
32°17'52"S
, 
16°53'53"E
), depth 
296 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1787, 
West coast
, Station 
A30382
(
29°32'13"S
, 
15°45'14"E
), depth 
175 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1794, 
West coast
, Station 
A30389
(
29°20'13"S
, 
16°0'58"E
), depth 
168 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1798, 
West coast
, Station 
A30340
(
31°58'46"S
, 
16°52'10"E
), depth 
282 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1830, 
West coast
, Station 
A31415
(
31°22'5"S
, 
17°30'56"E
), depth 
147 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1836, 
West coast
, Station 
A31460
(
29°20'11"S
, 
16°1'1"E
), depth 
168 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1850, 
West coast
, Station 
A31406
(
32°7'32"S
, 
17°19'11"E
), depth 
184 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1859, 
West coast
, Station 
A31417
(
31°43'30"S
, 
17°1'30"E
), depth 
256 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1828, 
West coast
, Station 
A30350
(
31°34'58"S
, 
17°48'2"E
), depth 
118 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1876, 
West coast
, Station 
A31405
(
32°7'55"S
, 
17°12'7"E
), depth 
211 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1807, 
West coast
, Station 
A30351
(
31°19'47"S
, 
17°35'8"E
), depth 
133 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1810, 
West coast
, Station 
A30357
(
30°42'58"S
, 
16°53'19"E
), depth 
191 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1816, 
West coast
, Station 
A30403
(
31°8'38"S
, 
17°41'41"E
), depth 
89 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Other
voucher specimens.

TS 1584, 
West coast
, Station 
A29490
(
30°16'59"S
, 
15°43'59"E
), depth 
235 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1585, 
West coast
, Station 
A29500
(
31°29'0"S
, 
17°40'59"E
), depth 
125 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1589, 
West coast
, Station 
A29443
(
30°54'59"S
, 
17°20'0"E
), depth 
147 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1594, 
West coast
, Station 
A29507
(
33°22'0"S
, 
17°44'0"E
), depth 
183 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1601, 
West coast
, Station 
A29501
(
31°38'59"S
, 
17°47'59"E
), depth 
120 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1604, 
West coast
, Station 
A29483
(
29°29'59"S
, 
16°16'59"E
), depth 
155 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1611, 
West coast
, Station 
A29502
(
31°30'59"S
, 
17°58'0"E
), depth 
95 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1623, 
West coast
, Station 
A29475
(
30°22'59"S
, 
16°34'0"E
), depth 
208 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1628, 
West coast
, Station 
A29461
(
31°16'59"S
, 
17°12'59"E
), depth 
206 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1644, 
West coast
, Station 
A29455
(
32°18'59"S
, 
18°0'59"E
), depth 
103 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1784, 
West coast
, Station 
A30359
(
31°0'5"S
, 
16°0'52"E
), depth 
320 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1786, 
West coast
, Station 
A30392
(
29°8'33"S
, 
16°19'49"E
), depth 
138 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1789, 
West coast
, Station 
A30341
(
31°52'39"S
, 
17°7'3"E
), depth 
211 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1795, 
West coast
, Station 
A30383
(
29°36'57"S
, 
15°55'19"E
), depth 
178 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1797, 
West coast
, Station 
A30392
(
29°8'33"S
, 
16°19'49"E
), depth 
138 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1809, 
West coast
, Station 
A30356
(
30°49'35"S
, 
16°39'34"E
), depth 
239 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1813, 
West coast
, Station 
A30385
(
29°18'43"S
, 
16°33'41"E
), depth 
126 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1817, 
West coast
, Station 
A30384
(
29°46'46"S
, 
16°0'46"E
), depth 
185 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1819, 
West coast
, Station 
A30395
(
29°44'59"S
, 
16°29'17"E
), depth 
156 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1823, 
West coast
, Station 
A30325
(
32°48'44"S
, 
17°42'33"E
), depth 
142 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1826, 
West coast
, Station 
A30352
(
31°10'23"S
, 
17°20'33"E
), depth 
178 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1877, 
West coast
, Station 
A31438
(
30°38'19"S
, 
16°53'37"E
), depth 
186 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1621, 
West coast
, Station 
A29470
(
29°7'59"S
, 
16°5'59"E
), depth 
163 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1805, 
West coast
, Station 
A30353
(
30°54'52"S
, 
17°3'18"E
), depth 
197 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1806, 
West coast
, Station 
A30399
(
30°21'1"S
, 
16°48'2"E
), depth 
179 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1812, 
West coast
, Station 
A30381
(
29°24'13"S
, 
15°30'20"E
), depth 
181 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1814, 
West coast
, Station 
A30391
(
29°28'59"S
, 
16°20'25"E
), depth 
151 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1837, 
West coast
, Station 
A31413
(
31°38'59"S
, 
17°39'16"E
), depth 
130 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1840, 
West coast
, Station 
A31446
(
29°0'26"S
, 
16°15'34"E
), depth 
141 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1841, 
West coast
, Station 
A31439
(
30°38'23"S
, 
17°9'20"E
), depth 
150 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1848, 
West coast
, Station 
A31440
(
30°40'43"S
, 
17°25'5"E
), depth 
98 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1849, 
West coast
, Station 
A31441
(
30°23'34"S
, 
16°59'47"E
), depth 
150 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1862, 
West coast
, Station 
A31462
(
29°39'28"S
, 
16°2'58"E
), depth 
181 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1868, 
West coast
, Station 
A31437
(
30°33'26"S
, 
16°50'0"E
), depth 
186 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
Other 
South
African &amp; Namibian material examined

. 
SAM
–H4898 (Ts 330), 
Elands Bay
(
32°20’S
, 
18°20’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M. J. Gibbons
, 
7 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
343a, 
Elands Bay
(
32°20’S
, 
18°20’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M.J. Gibbons
, 
7 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
344, 
Ts
346, 
Ts
348, 
Ts
355, 
St Helena Bay
(
32°40’S
, 
18°10’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M.J. Gibbons
, 
9 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
412, 
Black Rock
, 
Lüderitz
, 
Namibia
(
24°50’S
, 
14°40’E
), depth 
12 m
, collected by 
NSFRI
, 
20 March 1998</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>SAM
– H4897 (Ts 540), 
Oranjemund
(
26°31’S
, 
15°01’E
), depth 
78 m
, collected by 
A. Goosen
, from ‘ 
Jago’
submersible, 
April 1999</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
541, 
Oranjemund
(
26°31’S
, 
15°01’E
), depth 
78 m
, collected by 
A. Goosen
, from ‘ 
Jago’
submersible, 
April 1999</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Massive sponge with rounded lobes and apical oscula (

a). Two morphotypes are distinguishable: (a) globulous, widest at the base, with one large apical osculum terminally, and (b) elongate, with compressed base from where a few globular lobes rise, each widest in the middle and terminating in a small osculum. Varied size, up to 
40 cm
in diameter. Surface smooth, microscopically hirsute, not velvety. Oscules 
1–2 cm
in diameter on the apical end of the lobe; ostia 
0.1 mm
in diameter. Consistency spongy, soft, depending on the degree of contraction. Ectosome not discernable. Colour in life straw orange brown with some having tinges of yellow, choanosome orange–yellow internally; in preservative light brown or straw yellow to khaki. Mud encrusted specimens are greyish brown.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. 
Type
I Tylostyles. Thin, long, straight or curved, with a sharp gradually tapering end, heads well rounded, distally fusiform, 505 (413–576) × 7 (7) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–I). 
Type
II Tylostyles. More robust, thickened and somewhat curved, head well defined and rounded, distally fusiform, 351 (307–413) × 19 (14–24) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–II). 
Type
III Tylostyles. Thick, straight, head well defined and rounded 465 (451–490) ×14 (9.6–19) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–III). Large tylostrongyles (tylobtuse strongyles). Thick, variable size, head poorly defined, but round, often somewhat wider than opposite rounded end, 271 (240–307) × 24 (19–29) µm, 
n
= 10 (

c). Centrotylostrongyles. Thick, variable size, straight or slightly curved, with bulbous centre, end not fusiform but hastately rounded 307 (259–346) ×14 (9.6–19) µm, 
n
= 10 (

d). Centrotyloxeas. Thick, variable size, sinuous or slightly curved, with bulbous centre, end fusiform, but some forms are centrotylostrongyles, 414 (365–518) ×16 (14–19) µm, 
n
= 10. Small tylostrongyles (tylobtuse strongyles). Thick, variable size, head well defined, and rounded, 163 (115–201) ×24 (19–29) µm, 
n
= 10 (

e). Small mutant tylostrongyles (kidney–shaped) also present with size approximately 86 (76–96) 
x 19
µm, 
n
= 10 (

f). Some specimens e.g. TS 1815 and TS 1592 lack the tylobtuse strongyles (see 

). These megascleres are present in variable proportions in all the specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Microrhabds (microacanthostrongyles, usually centrotylote), rare in some specimens or even absent (e.g. 

—specimen TS 1592), 10–15 µm (

g). The morphology of the microacanthostrongyles is similar to that found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
. It is present in variable proportions in all the specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>Skeleton
. Choanosomal skeleton consists of a subradiate, composed of a confused irregular reticulation of bundles of tylostyles, which meander vertically through the choanosome. Spicules radially arranged near the surface, and the internal skeleton confused, almost halichondroid (

h). The ectosome consists of a distinct, compact, radially disposed layer of small dermal tylostyles, 200–400 µm wide. Distal ends of tylostyles project slightly beyond the ectosomal surface.
</p>
            <p>DNA barcodes
. Two unique cox1 haplotypes were identified among a total of 20 specimens. GenBank accession nos. KY463455 (haplotype 1) and KY463456 (haplotype 2).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
. Named after Ms Dandelene Reynolds, a technician in DEA, who passed away in 2010.
</p>
            <p>Phenotypic variation
. The species variability is limited to the sponge size with a uniform straw orange brown.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
locality

. The 
type
material was collected from the west coast of 
South
Africa

, from unconsolidated sediment in a region with seasonal cold-water upwelling.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.South
African and Namibian west coast (
BCLME
) (

&amp; 

)
</p>
            <p>Ecology
. 
Uriz (1988
, 
1990
) proposed that 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
(
Red Sea
sponge) was translocated by fisheries activities to the continental shelf off southern Africa between 
1960 and 1984
, as earlier surveys conducted over many decades had failed to detect it. These earlier surveys however, were not comprehensive or thorough, and focused their efforts around 
Cape
Town, Saldanha Bay, Still Bay and Durban, all of which fall outside its distributional range.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is particularly abundant at depths ranging between 
80–500 m
, on the continental plateau of the west coast of South Africa and Namibia (
Samaai &amp; Gibbons 2005
; 
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
) (

&amp; 

) where it may dominate epibenthic communities in terms of biomass, forming “sponge beds or facies” (
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
). During various trawl surveys on the west coast of South Africa (with the Research Vessels Dr Fridjof Nansen and RV Africana), more than 
6 tons
/km2 of sponge material were obtained during several hauls within depths ranging 

120– 
275 m
. The greatest mass of sponges collected was 
18 tons
/km2, from a depth near 
138 m
off Doring Bay (2006–Cruise 402, Station 1250). The three localities off Port Nolloth produced 
3–3.5 tons
/km2 of sponges collected on average, while 
6 tons
/km2 of sponges were obtained from one site at a depth of 
195 m
in the proposed Namaqualand MPA (Nansen Cruise 402, Station 1196, 2006) (

). The commercial trawler fleet generally fishes in water that is deeper (
200–1000 m
) than that of the sponge beds, but there is an overlap in the distribution of the sponge and diamond mining and oil and gas operations (Atkinson 
et al
. 2011; 

Sink 
et al
. 2012

). The potential threats of these activities on the filter feeding sponge community have yet to be assessed.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is not a reef builder, but it can be habitat forming and occurs in soft sediment environments. The sponge beds constitute an ecologically important habitat of great complexity for fishes and both motile and sessile invertebrates, and they may play an important role in the ecology and diversity of the west coast region. Indeed, their presence could constitute a Vulnerable Marine Ecosystem (VME) or an Ecologically and Biologically Significant Area (
EBSA
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks
. The identification of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
at the species level based on morphological features is difficult, because species of this genus are highly polymorphic and have a simple skeleton and spicular structures, which are more or less homogeneous (Solé– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe 1986
; Van 
Soest 2002
). Having said that, it has been argued that the use of qualitative characters such as the presence or absence of microscleres (microstrongyles) is helpful in distinguishing species, e.g. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
(
Hartman 1958
; 

Hiscock 
et al.
1983

). However, it is clear from the present results (Table S1) that although there are taxonomically useful spicule differences between specimens, these qualitative and quantitative differences can be misleading in defining a species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
specimens show considerable variation in the relative proportion or presence of different spicule 
types
.
</p>
            <p>
Typically, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
has three distinct 
types
of megascleres, but some specimens (see 
Table 2
) possess only tylobtuse strongyles and microstrongyles, or they lack tylobtuse strongyles but possess microstrongyles, and some specimens lack both tylobtuse strongyles and microstrongyles (see also 

). This exemplifies the importance of studying a range of specimens to find phenotypic and histological characters that are useful in fitting the puzzle to correctly identify or separate species. Differences only become evident when the specimens are studied together (
Tables 2
&amp; Table S1). The new species exhibits a number of affinities with 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
(see 
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
), both in terms of external morphology and in the structure of the centrotylote microscleres. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
in external morphology, having centrotylote microscleres and generally larger megaslere spicules (see 
Tables 3
&amp; Table S1).
</p>
            <p>
The absence of centrotylote microscleres, tylostrongyle megascleres and the poorly developed tylostyle megascleres in some specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
illustrates that secondary loss of spicules can occur readily. Sponge taxonomy is largely based on spicule morphology, but spicules have already been shown to be potentially unreliable for phylogenetics due to their high level of morphological homoplasy (
Fromont &amp; Bergquist 1990
; 

Manuel 
et al
. 2003

; 

Cárdenas 
et al
. 2011

), as well as for alpha–taxonomy due to intra–specific variation (
Schönberg &amp; Barthel 1998
).
</p>
            <p>Zea (1987)
found that spicules, especially microscleres, can be present or absent in sponge specimens depending on their location, and that variations in megascleres are rare. Maldonando 
et al.
(1999) showed that variation in spicule 
type
and shape can also be explained by silicon limitation. Although there is considerable latitudinal variability in the frequency, intensity and seasonality of upwelling in the Benguela ecosystem, the region is not generally considered to be silicon–poor in deeper water. It is worth noting here that whilst surface waters may become stripped of silica by diatoms in upwelling areas, the same is not true of bottom waters where the sponges are found owing to remineralisation (

Pitcher 
et al
. 1992

). Location and seawater chemistry are unlikely to be responsible for the considerable variation in spicule 
types
found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
as samples collected from the same trawl often had different spicule complements (

).
</p>
            <p>
The magnitude between depth differences in concentration of dissolved silicate (and temperature), have been examined in order to assess their potential relevance in the development and/or maintenance of the sponge aggregations. The mean concentration of silicate, a crucial nutrient used by sponges to build their silica skeleton, ranges from 12.22 to 17.36 µM over the year between 
100–400 m
depth, being only approximately 20 µM lower on average than values deeper than 
400 m
.
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is most abundant between the 
100–200 m
depth range. Temperature values decrease towards the deeper depths.
</p>
            <p>
It remains unclear what the particular conditions are that have favored the impressive aggregation of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
between 
100–200 m
depth range. As this sponge is characterized by a well–developed organic body by having a massive silica skeleton, it would be expected to require large amounts of dissolved silicon for growth and build its skeletal framework. However, average silicate concentrations where the sponges are found were stable, even in areas where the sponge occurs in far lower abundance. The data suggest that dissolved silicon availability in the southern Benguela may not be particularly responsible for the occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelanae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
. Intra–specific variation in spicule complement can often be the result of phenotypic plasticity due to the influence of environmental factors. Our study, like that of 
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp (2013)
presents another case of intra– specific spicule variation, most probably as a consequence due to sponge size (or age), as opposed to reflecting changes due to environmental conditions or latitudinal/bathymetric variations (

). However, little more than mere speculation can be offered at the current stage of knowledge, because virtually nothing is known both about the reproductive biology and dispersal ability of this new 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species. This study reiterates the point by 
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp (2013)
that taxonomist should be careful when delinating species only by the presence or abundance of one 
type
of spicule. A few examples of such inappropriate use of spicules as morphological characters exist in the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Erylus, Geodia
(
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Crambe</tp:taxon-name>
(
Maldonadoet al
. 1999

).
</p>
            <p>
Based on the above considerations, megasclere 
type
may not be a stable or valid taxonomic character for species discrimination within the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
. The structure and presence of centrotylote microscleres, as a trait for species identification, should also be considered carefully due to the rarity and possible inconsistent occurrence of this 
type
of microsclere in the new species. Nevertheless, the present species is clearly distinct from other 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species (Table S1), and any uncertainties regarding this particular trait are irrelevant in its recognition as a new species.
</p>
            <p>
Further studies are needed to fully document the population dynamics of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in light of our conclusions that the species has a restricted geographical range in the southern Benguela upwelling region, and it is critical to understand the species' ecological role in the region’s coastal and continental shelf marine ecosystems.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>FiculinaGray, 1867</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberanthusLendenfeld, 1898</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberellaThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>CarnleiaBurton, 1930a</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>LaxosuberellaBurton, 1930b</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaUriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium ficus
sensu 
Linnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ficulina ficusLinnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium bulbosumEsper, 1806</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula
von 
Lendenfeld, 1888</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
Ackers 
et al.,
1992
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnson, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusa
sensu 
Uriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria fícusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Suberites 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelanae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Erylus, Geodia
(
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Crambe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new species of habitat – forming Suberites (Porifera, Demospongiae, Suberitida) in the Benguela upwelling region (South Africa)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4254.1.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFEDEE1CE740FFC6FF97A02311720F30</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4254.1.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>Restricted synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 523. 
<tp:taxon-name>FiculinaGray, 1867</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 523. 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberanthusLendenfeld, 1898</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 144. 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberellaThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 416. [
<tp:taxon-name>Suberella</tp:taxon-name>
] 
Burton, 1929
, pg. 446. 
<tp:taxon-name>CarnleiaBurton, 1930a</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 519; 
<tp:taxon-name>LaxosuberellaBurton, 1930b</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 675.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–f; 
Table 2
; Table S1)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–d; 
Table 2
; Table S1)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
(

; 11a–h; 
Table 2
; 
Table 3
; Table S1).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type species
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
(by original description).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
(from van 
Soest 2002
). Massive, compact, usually with velvety smooth surface caused by dense ectosomal arrangement of tylostyles oriented perpendicularly to the sponge surface, points outward; peripheral choanosomal skeleton consists of closely packed strands of tylostyles distinctly larger than ectosomal ones, with interior skeleton of densely packed tylostyles in confusion. Centrotylote, minutely spined microstrongyles may be present in a few species and if so are concentrated at the surface. Approximately 80 species have been described (obvious synonyms and invalid genus assignments omitted). The genus is cosmopolitan in distribution but is most common in cold or temperate waters.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Original description.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Synonymy.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 24, fig. 20; 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaUriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 38, fig. 15.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
. Holotype MNHN DCL 1301, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Small fragments of 
type
material (

a). 
Lévi (1958)
however, described the sponge as massive with rounded lobes. Surface smooth, irregular and velvety to the touch. Oscules not visible. Consistency soft and fleshy. Colour in life bright orange.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. Megascleres are tylostyles and tylostrongyles in one size catogory. Tylostyles 1, smooth, slightly curved sometimes polytylote; head either well rounded or pear shaped, or reduced to resemble styles. Distally fusiform, or with mucronate or rounded ends. One size category (440–556 µm 
x 15
µm) (maximum length 600 µm 
x 15–25
µm) (

b, c, d). Tylostyles 2, more slender than the previous ones in length, gently curved with well formed heads, sometimes slightly fusiform, 350–450 µm 
x 10–11
µm thick. Tylostrongyles short and stocky 182– 297 µm 
x 8
µm (maximum length 450 µm 
x 15
) (

e) (please refer to 
Table 2
for comparative measurements).
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Absent.
</p>
            <p>Skeleton
. The skeletal architecture is irregular and includes packages of radial megasclere pointing in every direction and separated by more slender spicules (

f). There is no recognisable ectosome. Ectosomal skeleton consists of densly packed tylostyles
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Type
locality

. Abu Latt 
Island
, 
Red Sea
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Habitat
. Coral reefs.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Original description.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; see also van 
Soest &amp; Hooper 2002
, pg. 242.
</p>
            <p>Synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium ficus
sensu 
Linnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 1295; 
<tp:taxon-name>Ficulina ficusLinnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 1295 (see 
Uriz 1984
, pg. 58); 
<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium bulbosumEsper, 1806</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 235; 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 144; 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula
von 
Lendenfeld, 1888</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 65 (not 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 241); 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
Ackers 
et al.,
1992
</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 68.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
. Lectotype BMNH 1847.9.7.51, 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnson, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Bulbous, or pear–shaped, sometimes bulging from a narrow stalk, 
2.5–8 cm
in length (

a). Van 
Soest (2002)
described the species as lobate, occasionally cylindrical and may include specimens enveloping gastropod shells and encrusting scallops, 
10–40 cm
in length. Surface smooth with a velvety appearance with one or more conspicuous, large oscules. Consistency firm and incompressible. Colour in life russet red; in dried state cream/white.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. Styles, two types (

b). Type I, slightly curved, heads rounded and having a slight bump. Distally fusiform, sometimes mucronate, 288–345 µm 
x 7
µm (Van 
Soest, 2002
, measurements 350–500 µm 
x 10
µm). Type II, very thin, sinuous, heads rounded having a slight bump. Distally fusiform, 153–268 µm 
x 2
µm (Van 
Soest, 2002
, measurements 100–250 µm 
x 5
µm) (please refer to 
Table 2
for comparative measurements).
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Microrhabds (

c)—microspined microstrongyles, usually centrotylote, common, 16–28 µm. Smooth microstrongyles, usually centrotylote (

d), common, 24–48 µm.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Skeleton
. The skeletal architecture is confused, almost halichondroid, being radial near the surface. The ectosomal skeleton is made up of smaller tylostyles arranged pendicularly forming a dense palisade at the surface. 
Type
locality

. 
Scarborough
, 
England
, 
North Atlantic.</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Habitat
. Deep water.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusa
sensu 
Uriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
, pg 38 (Not 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
); 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 28, figs. 3A, 21 a–e. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 27, figs. 2O, 20 a–d.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Material
examined

. 
Holotype
.
SAMC
–A088677 (cross ref. TS 1625), 
West coast
, Station 
A29477
(
30°26'0"S
, 
16°48'59"E
), depth 
180 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
Other Material examined 
Holotype
MNHN DCL 1301, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Holotype
BMNH 1847.9.7.51, 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria fícusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Paratypes
.
SAMC
–A088678 (cross ref. TS 1815), 
West coast
, Station 
A30349
(
31°47'58"S
, 
17°54'29"E
), depth 
114 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>SAMC
–A088679 (cross ref. TS 1592), 
West coast
, Station 
A29471
(
29°12'0"S
, 
15°59'0"E
), depth 
166 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1586, 
West coast
, Station 
A29444
(
30°58'0"S
, 
17°27'0"E
), depth 
134 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1587, 
West coast
, Station 
A29442
(
30°30'59"S
, 
17°19'0"E
), depth 
111 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1599, 
West coast
, Station 
A29478
(
30°19'0"S
, 
16°54'59"E
), depth 
154 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1602, 
West coast
, Station 
A29482
(
29°37'59"S
, 
16°20'0"E
), depth 
157 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1612, 
West coast
, Station 
A29481
(
29°40'59"S
, 
16°12'59"E
), depth 
166 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1614, 
West coast
, Station 
A29480
(
29°53'0"S
, 
16°18'0"E
), depth 
182 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1631, 
West coast
, Station 
A29439
(
30°50'0"S
, 
16°52'0"E
), depth 
198 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1633, 
West coast
, Station 
A29479
(
30°0'0"S
, 
16°20'59"E
), depth 
187 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1640, 
West coast
, Station 
A27448
(
32°0'24"S
, 
17°24'59"E
), depth 
160 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1783, 
West coast
, Station 
A30328
(
32°17'52"S
, 
16°53'53"E
), depth 
296 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1787, 
West coast
, Station 
A30382
(
29°32'13"S
, 
15°45'14"E
), depth 
175 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1794, 
West coast
, Station 
A30389
(
29°20'13"S
, 
16°0'58"E
), depth 
168 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1798, 
West coast
, Station 
A30340
(
31°58'46"S
, 
16°52'10"E
), depth 
282 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1830, 
West coast
, Station 
A31415
(
31°22'5"S
, 
17°30'56"E
), depth 
147 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1836, 
West coast
, Station 
A31460
(
29°20'11"S
, 
16°1'1"E
), depth 
168 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1850, 
West coast
, Station 
A31406
(
32°7'32"S
, 
17°19'11"E
), depth 
184 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1859, 
West coast
, Station 
A31417
(
31°43'30"S
, 
17°1'30"E
), depth 
256 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1828, 
West coast
, Station 
A30350
(
31°34'58"S
, 
17°48'2"E
), depth 
118 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1876, 
West coast
, Station 
A31405
(
32°7'55"S
, 
17°12'7"E
), depth 
211 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1807, 
West coast
, Station 
A30351
(
31°19'47"S
, 
17°35'8"E
), depth 
133 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1810, 
West coast
, Station 
A30357
(
30°42'58"S
, 
16°53'19"E
), depth 
191 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1816, 
West coast
, Station 
A30403
(
31°8'38"S
, 
17°41'41"E
), depth 
89 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Other
voucher specimens.

TS 1584, 
West coast
, Station 
A29490
(
30°16'59"S
, 
15°43'59"E
), depth 
235 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1585, 
West coast
, Station 
A29500
(
31°29'0"S
, 
17°40'59"E
), depth 
125 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1589, 
West coast
, Station 
A29443
(
30°54'59"S
, 
17°20'0"E
), depth 
147 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1594, 
West coast
, Station 
A29507
(
33°22'0"S
, 
17°44'0"E
), depth 
183 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1601, 
West coast
, Station 
A29501
(
31°38'59"S
, 
17°47'59"E
), depth 
120 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1604, 
West coast
, Station 
A29483
(
29°29'59"S
, 
16°16'59"E
), depth 
155 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1611, 
West coast
, Station 
A29502
(
31°30'59"S
, 
17°58'0"E
), depth 
95 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1623, 
West coast
, Station 
A29475
(
30°22'59"S
, 
16°34'0"E
), depth 
208 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1628, 
West coast
, Station 
A29461
(
31°16'59"S
, 
17°12'59"E
), depth 
206 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1644, 
West coast
, Station 
A29455
(
32°18'59"S
, 
18°0'59"E
), depth 
103 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1784, 
West coast
, Station 
A30359
(
31°0'5"S
, 
16°0'52"E
), depth 
320 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1786, 
West coast
, Station 
A30392
(
29°8'33"S
, 
16°19'49"E
), depth 
138 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1789, 
West coast
, Station 
A30341
(
31°52'39"S
, 
17°7'3"E
), depth 
211 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1795, 
West coast
, Station 
A30383
(
29°36'57"S
, 
15°55'19"E
), depth 
178 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1797, 
West coast
, Station 
A30392
(
29°8'33"S
, 
16°19'49"E
), depth 
138 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1809, 
West coast
, Station 
A30356
(
30°49'35"S
, 
16°39'34"E
), depth 
239 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1813, 
West coast
, Station 
A30385
(
29°18'43"S
, 
16°33'41"E
), depth 
126 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1817, 
West coast
, Station 
A30384
(
29°46'46"S
, 
16°0'46"E
), depth 
185 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1819, 
West coast
, Station 
A30395
(
29°44'59"S
, 
16°29'17"E
), depth 
156 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1823, 
West coast
, Station 
A30325
(
32°48'44"S
, 
17°42'33"E
), depth 
142 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1826, 
West coast
, Station 
A30352
(
31°10'23"S
, 
17°20'33"E
), depth 
178 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1877, 
West coast
, Station 
A31438
(
30°38'19"S
, 
16°53'37"E
), depth 
186 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1621, 
West coast
, Station 
A29470
(
29°7'59"S
, 
16°5'59"E
), depth 
163 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1805, 
West coast
, Station 
A30353
(
30°54'52"S
, 
17°3'18"E
), depth 
197 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1806, 
West coast
, Station 
A30399
(
30°21'1"S
, 
16°48'2"E
), depth 
179 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1812, 
West coast
, Station 
A30381
(
29°24'13"S
, 
15°30'20"E
), depth 
181 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1814, 
West coast
, Station 
A30391
(
29°28'59"S
, 
16°20'25"E
), depth 
151 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1837, 
West coast
, Station 
A31413
(
31°38'59"S
, 
17°39'16"E
), depth 
130 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1840, 
West coast
, Station 
A31446
(
29°0'26"S
, 
16°15'34"E
), depth 
141 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1841, 
West coast
, Station 
A31439
(
30°38'23"S
, 
17°9'20"E
), depth 
150 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1848, 
West coast
, Station 
A31440
(
30°40'43"S
, 
17°25'5"E
), depth 
98 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1849, 
West coast
, Station 
A31441
(
30°23'34"S
, 
16°59'47"E
), depth 
150 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1862, 
West coast
, Station 
A31462
(
29°39'28"S
, 
16°2'58"E
), depth 
181 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1868, 
West coast
, Station 
A31437
(
30°33'26"S
, 
16°50'0"E
), depth 
186 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
Other 
South
African &amp; Namibian material examined

. 
SAM
–H4898 (Ts 330), 
Elands Bay
(
32°20’S
, 
18°20’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M. J. Gibbons
, 
7 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
343a, 
Elands Bay
(
32°20’S
, 
18°20’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M.J. Gibbons
, 
7 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
344, 
Ts
346, 
Ts
348, 
Ts
355, 
St Helena Bay
(
32°40’S
, 
18°10’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M.J. Gibbons
, 
9 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
412, 
Black Rock
, 
Lüderitz
, 
Namibia
(
24°50’S
, 
14°40’E
), depth 
12 m
, collected by 
NSFRI
, 
20 March 1998</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>SAM
– H4897 (Ts 540), 
Oranjemund
(
26°31’S
, 
15°01’E
), depth 
78 m
, collected by 
A. Goosen
, from ‘ 
Jago’
submersible, 
April 1999</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
541, 
Oranjemund
(
26°31’S
, 
15°01’E
), depth 
78 m
, collected by 
A. Goosen
, from ‘ 
Jago’
submersible, 
April 1999</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Massive sponge with rounded lobes and apical oscula (

a). Two morphotypes are distinguishable: (a) globulous, widest at the base, with one large apical osculum terminally, and (b) elongate, with compressed base from where a few globular lobes rise, each widest in the middle and terminating in a small osculum. Varied size, up to 
40 cm
in diameter. Surface smooth, microscopically hirsute, not velvety. Oscules 
1–2 cm
in diameter on the apical end of the lobe; ostia 
0.1 mm
in diameter. Consistency spongy, soft, depending on the degree of contraction. Ectosome not discernable. Colour in life straw orange brown with some having tinges of yellow, choanosome orange–yellow internally; in preservative light brown or straw yellow to khaki. Mud encrusted specimens are greyish brown.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. 
Type
I Tylostyles. Thin, long, straight or curved, with a sharp gradually tapering end, heads well rounded, distally fusiform, 505 (413–576) × 7 (7) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–I). 
Type
II Tylostyles. More robust, thickened and somewhat curved, head well defined and rounded, distally fusiform, 351 (307–413) × 19 (14–24) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–II). 
Type
III Tylostyles. Thick, straight, head well defined and rounded 465 (451–490) ×14 (9.6–19) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–III). Large tylostrongyles (tylobtuse strongyles). Thick, variable size, head poorly defined, but round, often somewhat wider than opposite rounded end, 271 (240–307) × 24 (19–29) µm, 
n
= 10 (

c). Centrotylostrongyles. Thick, variable size, straight or slightly curved, with bulbous centre, end not fusiform but hastately rounded 307 (259–346) ×14 (9.6–19) µm, 
n
= 10 (

d). Centrotyloxeas. Thick, variable size, sinuous or slightly curved, with bulbous centre, end fusiform, but some forms are centrotylostrongyles, 414 (365–518) ×16 (14–19) µm, 
n
= 10. Small tylostrongyles (tylobtuse strongyles). Thick, variable size, head well defined, and rounded, 163 (115–201) ×24 (19–29) µm, 
n
= 10 (

e). Small mutant tylostrongyles (kidney–shaped) also present with size approximately 86 (76–96) 
x 19
µm, 
n
= 10 (

f). Some specimens e.g. TS 1815 and TS 1592 lack the tylobtuse strongyles (see 

). These megascleres are present in variable proportions in all the specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Microrhabds (microacanthostrongyles, usually centrotylote), rare in some specimens or even absent (e.g. 

—specimen TS 1592), 10–15 µm (

g). The morphology of the microacanthostrongyles is similar to that found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
. It is present in variable proportions in all the specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>Skeleton
. Choanosomal skeleton consists of a subradiate, composed of a confused irregular reticulation of bundles of tylostyles, which meander vertically through the choanosome. Spicules radially arranged near the surface, and the internal skeleton confused, almost halichondroid (

h). The ectosome consists of a distinct, compact, radially disposed layer of small dermal tylostyles, 200–400 µm wide. Distal ends of tylostyles project slightly beyond the ectosomal surface.
</p>
            <p>DNA barcodes
. Two unique cox1 haplotypes were identified among a total of 20 specimens. GenBank accession nos. KY463455 (haplotype 1) and KY463456 (haplotype 2).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
. Named after Ms Dandelene Reynolds, a technician in DEA, who passed away in 2010.
</p>
            <p>Phenotypic variation
. The species variability is limited to the sponge size with a uniform straw orange brown.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
locality

. The 
type
material was collected from the west coast of 
South
Africa

, from unconsolidated sediment in a region with seasonal cold-water upwelling.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.South
African and Namibian west coast (
BCLME
) (

&amp; 

)
</p>
            <p>Ecology
. 
Uriz (1988
, 
1990
) proposed that 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
(
Red Sea
sponge) was translocated by fisheries activities to the continental shelf off southern Africa between 
1960 and 1984
, as earlier surveys conducted over many decades had failed to detect it. These earlier surveys however, were not comprehensive or thorough, and focused their efforts around 
Cape
Town, Saldanha Bay, Still Bay and Durban, all of which fall outside its distributional range.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is particularly abundant at depths ranging between 
80–500 m
, on the continental plateau of the west coast of South Africa and Namibia (
Samaai &amp; Gibbons 2005
; 
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
) (

&amp; 

) where it may dominate epibenthic communities in terms of biomass, forming “sponge beds or facies” (
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
). During various trawl surveys on the west coast of South Africa (with the Research Vessels Dr Fridjof Nansen and RV Africana), more than 
6 tons
/km2 of sponge material were obtained during several hauls within depths ranging 

120– 
275 m
. The greatest mass of sponges collected was 
18 tons
/km2, from a depth near 
138 m
off Doring Bay (2006–Cruise 402, Station 1250). The three localities off Port Nolloth produced 
3–3.5 tons
/km2 of sponges collected on average, while 
6 tons
/km2 of sponges were obtained from one site at a depth of 
195 m
in the proposed Namaqualand MPA (Nansen Cruise 402, Station 1196, 2006) (

). The commercial trawler fleet generally fishes in water that is deeper (
200–1000 m
) than that of the sponge beds, but there is an overlap in the distribution of the sponge and diamond mining and oil and gas operations (Atkinson 
et al
. 2011; 

Sink 
et al
. 2012

). The potential threats of these activities on the filter feeding sponge community have yet to be assessed.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is not a reef builder, but it can be habitat forming and occurs in soft sediment environments. The sponge beds constitute an ecologically important habitat of great complexity for fishes and both motile and sessile invertebrates, and they may play an important role in the ecology and diversity of the west coast region. Indeed, their presence could constitute a Vulnerable Marine Ecosystem (VME) or an Ecologically and Biologically Significant Area (
EBSA
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks
. The identification of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
at the species level based on morphological features is difficult, because species of this genus are highly polymorphic and have a simple skeleton and spicular structures, which are more or less homogeneous (Solé– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe 1986
; Van 
Soest 2002
). Having said that, it has been argued that the use of qualitative characters such as the presence or absence of microscleres (microstrongyles) is helpful in distinguishing species, e.g. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
(
Hartman 1958
; 

Hiscock 
et al.
1983

). However, it is clear from the present results (Table S1) that although there are taxonomically useful spicule differences between specimens, these qualitative and quantitative differences can be misleading in defining a species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
specimens show considerable variation in the relative proportion or presence of different spicule 
types
.
</p>
            <p>
Typically, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
has three distinct 
types
of megascleres, but some specimens (see 
Table 2
) possess only tylobtuse strongyles and microstrongyles, or they lack tylobtuse strongyles but possess microstrongyles, and some specimens lack both tylobtuse strongyles and microstrongyles (see also 

). This exemplifies the importance of studying a range of specimens to find phenotypic and histological characters that are useful in fitting the puzzle to correctly identify or separate species. Differences only become evident when the specimens are studied together (
Tables 2
&amp; Table S1). The new species exhibits a number of affinities with 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
(see 
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
), both in terms of external morphology and in the structure of the centrotylote microscleres. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
in external morphology, having centrotylote microscleres and generally larger megaslere spicules (see 
Tables 3
&amp; Table S1).
</p>
            <p>
The absence of centrotylote microscleres, tylostrongyle megascleres and the poorly developed tylostyle megascleres in some specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
illustrates that secondary loss of spicules can occur readily. Sponge taxonomy is largely based on spicule morphology, but spicules have already been shown to be potentially unreliable for phylogenetics due to their high level of morphological homoplasy (
Fromont &amp; Bergquist 1990
; 

Manuel 
et al
. 2003

; 

Cárdenas 
et al
. 2011

), as well as for alpha–taxonomy due to intra–specific variation (
Schönberg &amp; Barthel 1998
).
</p>
            <p>Zea (1987)
found that spicules, especially microscleres, can be present or absent in sponge specimens depending on their location, and that variations in megascleres are rare. Maldonando 
et al.
(1999) showed that variation in spicule 
type
and shape can also be explained by silicon limitation. Although there is considerable latitudinal variability in the frequency, intensity and seasonality of upwelling in the Benguela ecosystem, the region is not generally considered to be silicon–poor in deeper water. It is worth noting here that whilst surface waters may become stripped of silica by diatoms in upwelling areas, the same is not true of bottom waters where the sponges are found owing to remineralisation (

Pitcher 
et al
. 1992

). Location and seawater chemistry are unlikely to be responsible for the considerable variation in spicule 
types
found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
as samples collected from the same trawl often had different spicule complements (

).
</p>
            <p>
The magnitude between depth differences in concentration of dissolved silicate (and temperature), have been examined in order to assess their potential relevance in the development and/or maintenance of the sponge aggregations. The mean concentration of silicate, a crucial nutrient used by sponges to build their silica skeleton, ranges from 12.22 to 17.36 µM over the year between 
100–400 m
depth, being only approximately 20 µM lower on average than values deeper than 
400 m
.
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is most abundant between the 
100–200 m
depth range. Temperature values decrease towards the deeper depths.
</p>
            <p>
It remains unclear what the particular conditions are that have favored the impressive aggregation of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
between 
100–200 m
depth range. As this sponge is characterized by a well–developed organic body by having a massive silica skeleton, it would be expected to require large amounts of dissolved silicon for growth and build its skeletal framework. However, average silicate concentrations where the sponges are found were stable, even in areas where the sponge occurs in far lower abundance. The data suggest that dissolved silicon availability in the southern Benguela may not be particularly responsible for the occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelanae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
. Intra–specific variation in spicule complement can often be the result of phenotypic plasticity due to the influence of environmental factors. Our study, like that of 
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp (2013)
presents another case of intra– specific spicule variation, most probably as a consequence due to sponge size (or age), as opposed to reflecting changes due to environmental conditions or latitudinal/bathymetric variations (

). However, little more than mere speculation can be offered at the current stage of knowledge, because virtually nothing is known both about the reproductive biology and dispersal ability of this new 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species. This study reiterates the point by 
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp (2013)
that taxonomist should be careful when delinating species only by the presence or abundance of one 
type
of spicule. A few examples of such inappropriate use of spicules as morphological characters exist in the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Erylus, Geodia
(
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Crambe</tp:taxon-name>
(
Maldonadoet al
. 1999

).
</p>
            <p>
Based on the above considerations, megasclere 
type
may not be a stable or valid taxonomic character for species discrimination within the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
. The structure and presence of centrotylote microscleres, as a trait for species identification, should also be considered carefully due to the rarity and possible inconsistent occurrence of this 
type
of microsclere in the new species. Nevertheless, the present species is clearly distinct from other 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species (Table S1), and any uncertainties regarding this particular trait are irrelevant in its recognition as a new species.
</p>
            <p>
Further studies are needed to fully document the population dynamics of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in light of our conclusions that the species has a restricted geographical range in the southern Benguela upwelling region, and it is critical to understand the species' ecological role in the region’s coastal and continental shelf marine ecosystems.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>FiculinaGray, 1867</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberanthusLendenfeld, 1898</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberellaThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>CarnleiaBurton, 1930a</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>LaxosuberellaBurton, 1930b</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaUriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium ficus
sensu 
Linnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ficulina ficusLinnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium bulbosumEsper, 1806</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula
von 
Lendenfeld, 1888</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
Ackers 
et al.,
1992
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnson, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusa
sensu 
Uriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria fícusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Suberites 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelanae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Erylus, Geodia
(
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Crambe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new species of habitat – forming Suberites (Porifera, Demospongiae, Suberitida) in the Benguela upwelling region (South Africa)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4254.1.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFEDEE1CE740FFC6FF97A02311720F30</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4254.1.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>Restricted synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 523. 
<tp:taxon-name>FiculinaGray, 1867</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 523. 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberanthusLendenfeld, 1898</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 144. 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberellaThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 416. [
<tp:taxon-name>Suberella</tp:taxon-name>
] 
Burton, 1929
, pg. 446. 
<tp:taxon-name>CarnleiaBurton, 1930a</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 519; 
<tp:taxon-name>LaxosuberellaBurton, 1930b</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 675.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–f; 
Table 2
; Table S1)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–d; 
Table 2
; Table S1)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
(

; 11a–h; 
Table 2
; 
Table 3
; Table S1).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type species
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
(by original description).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
(from van 
Soest 2002
). Massive, compact, usually with velvety smooth surface caused by dense ectosomal arrangement of tylostyles oriented perpendicularly to the sponge surface, points outward; peripheral choanosomal skeleton consists of closely packed strands of tylostyles distinctly larger than ectosomal ones, with interior skeleton of densely packed tylostyles in confusion. Centrotylote, minutely spined microstrongyles may be present in a few species and if so are concentrated at the surface. Approximately 80 species have been described (obvious synonyms and invalid genus assignments omitted). The genus is cosmopolitan in distribution but is most common in cold or temperate waters.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Original description.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Synonymy.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 24, fig. 20; 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaUriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 38, fig. 15.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
. Holotype MNHN DCL 1301, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Small fragments of 
type
material (

a). 
Lévi (1958)
however, described the sponge as massive with rounded lobes. Surface smooth, irregular and velvety to the touch. Oscules not visible. Consistency soft and fleshy. Colour in life bright orange.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. Megascleres are tylostyles and tylostrongyles in one size catogory. Tylostyles 1, smooth, slightly curved sometimes polytylote; head either well rounded or pear shaped, or reduced to resemble styles. Distally fusiform, or with mucronate or rounded ends. One size category (440–556 µm 
x 15
µm) (maximum length 600 µm 
x 15–25
µm) (

b, c, d). Tylostyles 2, more slender than the previous ones in length, gently curved with well formed heads, sometimes slightly fusiform, 350–450 µm 
x 10–11
µm thick. Tylostrongyles short and stocky 182– 297 µm 
x 8
µm (maximum length 450 µm 
x 15
) (

e) (please refer to 
Table 2
for comparative measurements).
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Absent.
</p>
            <p>Skeleton
. The skeletal architecture is irregular and includes packages of radial megasclere pointing in every direction and separated by more slender spicules (

f). There is no recognisable ectosome. Ectosomal skeleton consists of densly packed tylostyles
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Type
locality

. Abu Latt 
Island
, 
Red Sea
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Habitat
. Coral reefs.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Original description.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; see also van 
Soest &amp; Hooper 2002
, pg. 242.
</p>
            <p>Synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium ficus
sensu 
Linnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 1295; 
<tp:taxon-name>Ficulina ficusLinnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 1295 (see 
Uriz 1984
, pg. 58); 
<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium bulbosumEsper, 1806</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 235; 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 144; 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula
von 
Lendenfeld, 1888</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 65 (not 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 241); 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
Ackers 
et al.,
1992
</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 68.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
. Lectotype BMNH 1847.9.7.51, 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnson, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Bulbous, or pear–shaped, sometimes bulging from a narrow stalk, 
2.5–8 cm
in length (

a). Van 
Soest (2002)
described the species as lobate, occasionally cylindrical and may include specimens enveloping gastropod shells and encrusting scallops, 
10–40 cm
in length. Surface smooth with a velvety appearance with one or more conspicuous, large oscules. Consistency firm and incompressible. Colour in life russet red; in dried state cream/white.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. Styles, two types (

b). Type I, slightly curved, heads rounded and having a slight bump. Distally fusiform, sometimes mucronate, 288–345 µm 
x 7
µm (Van 
Soest, 2002
, measurements 350–500 µm 
x 10
µm). Type II, very thin, sinuous, heads rounded having a slight bump. Distally fusiform, 153–268 µm 
x 2
µm (Van 
Soest, 2002
, measurements 100–250 µm 
x 5
µm) (please refer to 
Table 2
for comparative measurements).
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Microrhabds (

c)—microspined microstrongyles, usually centrotylote, common, 16–28 µm. Smooth microstrongyles, usually centrotylote (

d), common, 24–48 µm.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Skeleton
. The skeletal architecture is confused, almost halichondroid, being radial near the surface. The ectosomal skeleton is made up of smaller tylostyles arranged pendicularly forming a dense palisade at the surface. 
Type
locality

. 
Scarborough
, 
England
, 
North Atlantic.</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Habitat
. Deep water.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusa
sensu 
Uriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
, pg 38 (Not 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
); 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 28, figs. 3A, 21 a–e. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 27, figs. 2O, 20 a–d.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Material
examined

. 
Holotype
.
SAMC
–A088677 (cross ref. TS 1625), 
West coast
, Station 
A29477
(
30°26'0"S
, 
16°48'59"E
), depth 
180 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
Other Material examined 
Holotype
MNHN DCL 1301, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Holotype
BMNH 1847.9.7.51, 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria fícusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Paratypes
.
SAMC
–A088678 (cross ref. TS 1815), 
West coast
, Station 
A30349
(
31°47'58"S
, 
17°54'29"E
), depth 
114 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>SAMC
–A088679 (cross ref. TS 1592), 
West coast
, Station 
A29471
(
29°12'0"S
, 
15°59'0"E
), depth 
166 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1586, 
West coast
, Station 
A29444
(
30°58'0"S
, 
17°27'0"E
), depth 
134 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1587, 
West coast
, Station 
A29442
(
30°30'59"S
, 
17°19'0"E
), depth 
111 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1599, 
West coast
, Station 
A29478
(
30°19'0"S
, 
16°54'59"E
), depth 
154 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1602, 
West coast
, Station 
A29482
(
29°37'59"S
, 
16°20'0"E
), depth 
157 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1612, 
West coast
, Station 
A29481
(
29°40'59"S
, 
16°12'59"E
), depth 
166 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1614, 
West coast
, Station 
A29480
(
29°53'0"S
, 
16°18'0"E
), depth 
182 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1631, 
West coast
, Station 
A29439
(
30°50'0"S
, 
16°52'0"E
), depth 
198 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1633, 
West coast
, Station 
A29479
(
30°0'0"S
, 
16°20'59"E
), depth 
187 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1640, 
West coast
, Station 
A27448
(
32°0'24"S
, 
17°24'59"E
), depth 
160 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1783, 
West coast
, Station 
A30328
(
32°17'52"S
, 
16°53'53"E
), depth 
296 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1787, 
West coast
, Station 
A30382
(
29°32'13"S
, 
15°45'14"E
), depth 
175 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1794, 
West coast
, Station 
A30389
(
29°20'13"S
, 
16°0'58"E
), depth 
168 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1798, 
West coast
, Station 
A30340
(
31°58'46"S
, 
16°52'10"E
), depth 
282 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1830, 
West coast
, Station 
A31415
(
31°22'5"S
, 
17°30'56"E
), depth 
147 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1836, 
West coast
, Station 
A31460
(
29°20'11"S
, 
16°1'1"E
), depth 
168 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1850, 
West coast
, Station 
A31406
(
32°7'32"S
, 
17°19'11"E
), depth 
184 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1859, 
West coast
, Station 
A31417
(
31°43'30"S
, 
17°1'30"E
), depth 
256 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1828, 
West coast
, Station 
A30350
(
31°34'58"S
, 
17°48'2"E
), depth 
118 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1876, 
West coast
, Station 
A31405
(
32°7'55"S
, 
17°12'7"E
), depth 
211 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1807, 
West coast
, Station 
A30351
(
31°19'47"S
, 
17°35'8"E
), depth 
133 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1810, 
West coast
, Station 
A30357
(
30°42'58"S
, 
16°53'19"E
), depth 
191 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1816, 
West coast
, Station 
A30403
(
31°8'38"S
, 
17°41'41"E
), depth 
89 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Other
voucher specimens.

TS 1584, 
West coast
, Station 
A29490
(
30°16'59"S
, 
15°43'59"E
), depth 
235 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1585, 
West coast
, Station 
A29500
(
31°29'0"S
, 
17°40'59"E
), depth 
125 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1589, 
West coast
, Station 
A29443
(
30°54'59"S
, 
17°20'0"E
), depth 
147 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1594, 
West coast
, Station 
A29507
(
33°22'0"S
, 
17°44'0"E
), depth 
183 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1601, 
West coast
, Station 
A29501
(
31°38'59"S
, 
17°47'59"E
), depth 
120 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1604, 
West coast
, Station 
A29483
(
29°29'59"S
, 
16°16'59"E
), depth 
155 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1611, 
West coast
, Station 
A29502
(
31°30'59"S
, 
17°58'0"E
), depth 
95 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1623, 
West coast
, Station 
A29475
(
30°22'59"S
, 
16°34'0"E
), depth 
208 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1628, 
West coast
, Station 
A29461
(
31°16'59"S
, 
17°12'59"E
), depth 
206 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1644, 
West coast
, Station 
A29455
(
32°18'59"S
, 
18°0'59"E
), depth 
103 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1784, 
West coast
, Station 
A30359
(
31°0'5"S
, 
16°0'52"E
), depth 
320 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1786, 
West coast
, Station 
A30392
(
29°8'33"S
, 
16°19'49"E
), depth 
138 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1789, 
West coast
, Station 
A30341
(
31°52'39"S
, 
17°7'3"E
), depth 
211 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1795, 
West coast
, Station 
A30383
(
29°36'57"S
, 
15°55'19"E
), depth 
178 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1797, 
West coast
, Station 
A30392
(
29°8'33"S
, 
16°19'49"E
), depth 
138 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1809, 
West coast
, Station 
A30356
(
30°49'35"S
, 
16°39'34"E
), depth 
239 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1813, 
West coast
, Station 
A30385
(
29°18'43"S
, 
16°33'41"E
), depth 
126 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1817, 
West coast
, Station 
A30384
(
29°46'46"S
, 
16°0'46"E
), depth 
185 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1819, 
West coast
, Station 
A30395
(
29°44'59"S
, 
16°29'17"E
), depth 
156 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1823, 
West coast
, Station 
A30325
(
32°48'44"S
, 
17°42'33"E
), depth 
142 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1826, 
West coast
, Station 
A30352
(
31°10'23"S
, 
17°20'33"E
), depth 
178 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1877, 
West coast
, Station 
A31438
(
30°38'19"S
, 
16°53'37"E
), depth 
186 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1621, 
West coast
, Station 
A29470
(
29°7'59"S
, 
16°5'59"E
), depth 
163 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1805, 
West coast
, Station 
A30353
(
30°54'52"S
, 
17°3'18"E
), depth 
197 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1806, 
West coast
, Station 
A30399
(
30°21'1"S
, 
16°48'2"E
), depth 
179 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1812, 
West coast
, Station 
A30381
(
29°24'13"S
, 
15°30'20"E
), depth 
181 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1814, 
West coast
, Station 
A30391
(
29°28'59"S
, 
16°20'25"E
), depth 
151 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1837, 
West coast
, Station 
A31413
(
31°38'59"S
, 
17°39'16"E
), depth 
130 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1840, 
West coast
, Station 
A31446
(
29°0'26"S
, 
16°15'34"E
), depth 
141 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1841, 
West coast
, Station 
A31439
(
30°38'23"S
, 
17°9'20"E
), depth 
150 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1848, 
West coast
, Station 
A31440
(
30°40'43"S
, 
17°25'5"E
), depth 
98 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1849, 
West coast
, Station 
A31441
(
30°23'34"S
, 
16°59'47"E
), depth 
150 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1862, 
West coast
, Station 
A31462
(
29°39'28"S
, 
16°2'58"E
), depth 
181 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1868, 
West coast
, Station 
A31437
(
30°33'26"S
, 
16°50'0"E
), depth 
186 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
Other 
South
African &amp; Namibian material examined

. 
SAM
–H4898 (Ts 330), 
Elands Bay
(
32°20’S
, 
18°20’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M. J. Gibbons
, 
7 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
343a, 
Elands Bay
(
32°20’S
, 
18°20’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M.J. Gibbons
, 
7 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
344, 
Ts
346, 
Ts
348, 
Ts
355, 
St Helena Bay
(
32°40’S
, 
18°10’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M.J. Gibbons
, 
9 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
412, 
Black Rock
, 
Lüderitz
, 
Namibia
(
24°50’S
, 
14°40’E
), depth 
12 m
, collected by 
NSFRI
, 
20 March 1998</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>SAM
– H4897 (Ts 540), 
Oranjemund
(
26°31’S
, 
15°01’E
), depth 
78 m
, collected by 
A. Goosen
, from ‘ 
Jago’
submersible, 
April 1999</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
541, 
Oranjemund
(
26°31’S
, 
15°01’E
), depth 
78 m
, collected by 
A. Goosen
, from ‘ 
Jago’
submersible, 
April 1999</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Massive sponge with rounded lobes and apical oscula (

a). Two morphotypes are distinguishable: (a) globulous, widest at the base, with one large apical osculum terminally, and (b) elongate, with compressed base from where a few globular lobes rise, each widest in the middle and terminating in a small osculum. Varied size, up to 
40 cm
in diameter. Surface smooth, microscopically hirsute, not velvety. Oscules 
1–2 cm
in diameter on the apical end of the lobe; ostia 
0.1 mm
in diameter. Consistency spongy, soft, depending on the degree of contraction. Ectosome not discernable. Colour in life straw orange brown with some having tinges of yellow, choanosome orange–yellow internally; in preservative light brown or straw yellow to khaki. Mud encrusted specimens are greyish brown.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. 
Type
I Tylostyles. Thin, long, straight or curved, with a sharp gradually tapering end, heads well rounded, distally fusiform, 505 (413–576) × 7 (7) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–I). 
Type
II Tylostyles. More robust, thickened and somewhat curved, head well defined and rounded, distally fusiform, 351 (307–413) × 19 (14–24) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–II). 
Type
III Tylostyles. Thick, straight, head well defined and rounded 465 (451–490) ×14 (9.6–19) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–III). Large tylostrongyles (tylobtuse strongyles). Thick, variable size, head poorly defined, but round, often somewhat wider than opposite rounded end, 271 (240–307) × 24 (19–29) µm, 
n
= 10 (

c). Centrotylostrongyles. Thick, variable size, straight or slightly curved, with bulbous centre, end not fusiform but hastately rounded 307 (259–346) ×14 (9.6–19) µm, 
n
= 10 (

d). Centrotyloxeas. Thick, variable size, sinuous or slightly curved, with bulbous centre, end fusiform, but some forms are centrotylostrongyles, 414 (365–518) ×16 (14–19) µm, 
n
= 10. Small tylostrongyles (tylobtuse strongyles). Thick, variable size, head well defined, and rounded, 163 (115–201) ×24 (19–29) µm, 
n
= 10 (

e). Small mutant tylostrongyles (kidney–shaped) also present with size approximately 86 (76–96) 
x 19
µm, 
n
= 10 (

f). Some specimens e.g. TS 1815 and TS 1592 lack the tylobtuse strongyles (see 

). These megascleres are present in variable proportions in all the specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Microrhabds (microacanthostrongyles, usually centrotylote), rare in some specimens or even absent (e.g. 

—specimen TS 1592), 10–15 µm (

g). The morphology of the microacanthostrongyles is similar to that found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
. It is present in variable proportions in all the specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>Skeleton
. Choanosomal skeleton consists of a subradiate, composed of a confused irregular reticulation of bundles of tylostyles, which meander vertically through the choanosome. Spicules radially arranged near the surface, and the internal skeleton confused, almost halichondroid (

h). The ectosome consists of a distinct, compact, radially disposed layer of small dermal tylostyles, 200–400 µm wide. Distal ends of tylostyles project slightly beyond the ectosomal surface.
</p>
            <p>DNA barcodes
. Two unique cox1 haplotypes were identified among a total of 20 specimens. GenBank accession nos. KY463455 (haplotype 1) and KY463456 (haplotype 2).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
. Named after Ms Dandelene Reynolds, a technician in DEA, who passed away in 2010.
</p>
            <p>Phenotypic variation
. The species variability is limited to the sponge size with a uniform straw orange brown.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
locality

. The 
type
material was collected from the west coast of 
South
Africa

, from unconsolidated sediment in a region with seasonal cold-water upwelling.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.South
African and Namibian west coast (
BCLME
) (

&amp; 

)
</p>
            <p>Ecology
. 
Uriz (1988
, 
1990
) proposed that 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
(
Red Sea
sponge) was translocated by fisheries activities to the continental shelf off southern Africa between 
1960 and 1984
, as earlier surveys conducted over many decades had failed to detect it. These earlier surveys however, were not comprehensive or thorough, and focused their efforts around 
Cape
Town, Saldanha Bay, Still Bay and Durban, all of which fall outside its distributional range.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is particularly abundant at depths ranging between 
80–500 m
, on the continental plateau of the west coast of South Africa and Namibia (
Samaai &amp; Gibbons 2005
; 
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
) (

&amp; 

) where it may dominate epibenthic communities in terms of biomass, forming “sponge beds or facies” (
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
). During various trawl surveys on the west coast of South Africa (with the Research Vessels Dr Fridjof Nansen and RV Africana), more than 
6 tons
/km2 of sponge material were obtained during several hauls within depths ranging 

120– 
275 m
. The greatest mass of sponges collected was 
18 tons
/km2, from a depth near 
138 m
off Doring Bay (2006–Cruise 402, Station 1250). The three localities off Port Nolloth produced 
3–3.5 tons
/km2 of sponges collected on average, while 
6 tons
/km2 of sponges were obtained from one site at a depth of 
195 m
in the proposed Namaqualand MPA (Nansen Cruise 402, Station 1196, 2006) (

). The commercial trawler fleet generally fishes in water that is deeper (
200–1000 m
) than that of the sponge beds, but there is an overlap in the distribution of the sponge and diamond mining and oil and gas operations (Atkinson 
et al
. 2011; 

Sink 
et al
. 2012

). The potential threats of these activities on the filter feeding sponge community have yet to be assessed.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is not a reef builder, but it can be habitat forming and occurs in soft sediment environments. The sponge beds constitute an ecologically important habitat of great complexity for fishes and both motile and sessile invertebrates, and they may play an important role in the ecology and diversity of the west coast region. Indeed, their presence could constitute a Vulnerable Marine Ecosystem (VME) or an Ecologically and Biologically Significant Area (
EBSA
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks
. The identification of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
at the species level based on morphological features is difficult, because species of this genus are highly polymorphic and have a simple skeleton and spicular structures, which are more or less homogeneous (Solé– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe 1986
; Van 
Soest 2002
). Having said that, it has been argued that the use of qualitative characters such as the presence or absence of microscleres (microstrongyles) is helpful in distinguishing species, e.g. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
(
Hartman 1958
; 

Hiscock 
et al.
1983

). However, it is clear from the present results (Table S1) that although there are taxonomically useful spicule differences between specimens, these qualitative and quantitative differences can be misleading in defining a species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
specimens show considerable variation in the relative proportion or presence of different spicule 
types
.
</p>
            <p>
Typically, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
has three distinct 
types
of megascleres, but some specimens (see 
Table 2
) possess only tylobtuse strongyles and microstrongyles, or they lack tylobtuse strongyles but possess microstrongyles, and some specimens lack both tylobtuse strongyles and microstrongyles (see also 

). This exemplifies the importance of studying a range of specimens to find phenotypic and histological characters that are useful in fitting the puzzle to correctly identify or separate species. Differences only become evident when the specimens are studied together (
Tables 2
&amp; Table S1). The new species exhibits a number of affinities with 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
(see 
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
), both in terms of external morphology and in the structure of the centrotylote microscleres. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
in external morphology, having centrotylote microscleres and generally larger megaslere spicules (see 
Tables 3
&amp; Table S1).
</p>
            <p>
The absence of centrotylote microscleres, tylostrongyle megascleres and the poorly developed tylostyle megascleres in some specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
illustrates that secondary loss of spicules can occur readily. Sponge taxonomy is largely based on spicule morphology, but spicules have already been shown to be potentially unreliable for phylogenetics due to their high level of morphological homoplasy (
Fromont &amp; Bergquist 1990
; 

Manuel 
et al
. 2003

; 

Cárdenas 
et al
. 2011

), as well as for alpha–taxonomy due to intra–specific variation (
Schönberg &amp; Barthel 1998
).
</p>
            <p>Zea (1987)
found that spicules, especially microscleres, can be present or absent in sponge specimens depending on their location, and that variations in megascleres are rare. Maldonando 
et al.
(1999) showed that variation in spicule 
type
and shape can also be explained by silicon limitation. Although there is considerable latitudinal variability in the frequency, intensity and seasonality of upwelling in the Benguela ecosystem, the region is not generally considered to be silicon–poor in deeper water. It is worth noting here that whilst surface waters may become stripped of silica by diatoms in upwelling areas, the same is not true of bottom waters where the sponges are found owing to remineralisation (

Pitcher 
et al
. 1992

). Location and seawater chemistry are unlikely to be responsible for the considerable variation in spicule 
types
found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
as samples collected from the same trawl often had different spicule complements (

).
</p>
            <p>
The magnitude between depth differences in concentration of dissolved silicate (and temperature), have been examined in order to assess their potential relevance in the development and/or maintenance of the sponge aggregations. The mean concentration of silicate, a crucial nutrient used by sponges to build their silica skeleton, ranges from 12.22 to 17.36 µM over the year between 
100–400 m
depth, being only approximately 20 µM lower on average than values deeper than 
400 m
.
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is most abundant between the 
100–200 m
depth range. Temperature values decrease towards the deeper depths.
</p>
            <p>
It remains unclear what the particular conditions are that have favored the impressive aggregation of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
between 
100–200 m
depth range. As this sponge is characterized by a well–developed organic body by having a massive silica skeleton, it would be expected to require large amounts of dissolved silicon for growth and build its skeletal framework. However, average silicate concentrations where the sponges are found were stable, even in areas where the sponge occurs in far lower abundance. The data suggest that dissolved silicon availability in the southern Benguela may not be particularly responsible for the occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelanae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
. Intra–specific variation in spicule complement can often be the result of phenotypic plasticity due to the influence of environmental factors. Our study, like that of 
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp (2013)
presents another case of intra– specific spicule variation, most probably as a consequence due to sponge size (or age), as opposed to reflecting changes due to environmental conditions or latitudinal/bathymetric variations (

). However, little more than mere speculation can be offered at the current stage of knowledge, because virtually nothing is known both about the reproductive biology and dispersal ability of this new 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species. This study reiterates the point by 
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp (2013)
that taxonomist should be careful when delinating species only by the presence or abundance of one 
type
of spicule. A few examples of such inappropriate use of spicules as morphological characters exist in the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Erylus, Geodia
(
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Crambe</tp:taxon-name>
(
Maldonadoet al
. 1999

).
</p>
            <p>
Based on the above considerations, megasclere 
type
may not be a stable or valid taxonomic character for species discrimination within the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
. The structure and presence of centrotylote microscleres, as a trait for species identification, should also be considered carefully due to the rarity and possible inconsistent occurrence of this 
type
of microsclere in the new species. Nevertheless, the present species is clearly distinct from other 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species (Table S1), and any uncertainties regarding this particular trait are irrelevant in its recognition as a new species.
</p>
            <p>
Further studies are needed to fully document the population dynamics of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in light of our conclusions that the species has a restricted geographical range in the southern Benguela upwelling region, and it is critical to understand the species' ecological role in the region’s coastal and continental shelf marine ecosystems.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>FiculinaGray, 1867</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberanthusLendenfeld, 1898</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>SuberellaThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>CarnleiaBurton, 1930a</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>LaxosuberellaBurton, 1930b</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaUriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium ficus
sensu 
Linnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Ficulina ficusLinnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium bulbosumEsper, 1806</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula
von 
Lendenfeld, 1888</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
Ackers 
et al.,
1992
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnson, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusa
sensu 
Uriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Halichondria fícusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Suberites 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
S. 
dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelanae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Erylus, Geodia
(
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Crambe</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new species of habitat – forming Suberites (Porifera, Demospongiae, Suberitida) in the Benguela upwelling region (South Africa)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4254.1.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFEDEE1CE740FFC6FF97A02311720F30</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4254.1.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>Restricted synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>SuberitesNardo, 1833</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 523. 
<tp:taxon-name>FiculinaGray, 1867</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 523. 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberanthusLendenfeld, 1898</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 144. 
<tp:taxon-name>SuberellaThiele, 1905</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 416. [
<tp:taxon-name>Suberella</tp:taxon-name>
] 
Burton, 1929
, pg. 446. 
<tp:taxon-name>CarnleiaBurton, 1930a</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 519; 
<tp:taxon-name>LaxosuberellaBurton, 1930b</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 675.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–f; 
Table 2
; Table S1)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–d; 
Table 2
; Table S1)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
(

; 11a–h; 
Table 2
; 
Table 3
; Table S1).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type species
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
(by original description).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
(from van 
Soest 2002
). Massive, compact, usually with velvety smooth surface caused by dense ectosomal arrangement of tylostyles oriented perpendicularly to the sponge surface, points outward; peripheral choanosomal skeleton consists of closely packed strands of tylostyles distinctly larger than ectosomal ones, with interior skeleton of densely packed tylostyles in confusion. Centrotylote, minutely spined microstrongyles may be present in a few species and if so are concentrated at the surface. Approximately 80 species have been described (obvious synonyms and invalid genus assignments omitted). The genus is cosmopolitan in distribution but is most common in cold or temperate waters.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Original description.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtususLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Synonymy.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 24, fig. 20; 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaUriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 38, fig. 15.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
. Holotype MNHN DCL 1301, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Small fragments of 
type
material (

a). 
Lévi (1958)
however, described the sponge as massive with rounded lobes. Surface smooth, irregular and velvety to the touch. Oscules not visible. Consistency soft and fleshy. Colour in life bright orange.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. Megascleres are tylostyles and tylostrongyles in one size catogory. Tylostyles 1, smooth, slightly curved sometimes polytylote; head either well rounded or pear shaped, or reduced to resemble styles. Distally fusiform, or with mucronate or rounded ends. One size category (440–556 µm 
x 15
µm) (maximum length 600 µm 
x 15–25
µm) (

b, c, d). Tylostyles 2, more slender than the previous ones in length, gently curved with well formed heads, sometimes slightly fusiform, 350–450 µm 
x 10–11
µm thick. Tylostrongyles short and stocky 182– 297 µm 
x 8
µm (maximum length 450 µm 
x 15
) (

e) (please refer to 
Table 2
for comparative measurements).
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Absent.
</p>
            <p>Skeleton
. The skeletal architecture is irregular and includes packages of radial megasclere pointing in every direction and separated by more slender spicules (

f). There is no recognisable ectosome. Ectosomal skeleton consists of densly packed tylostyles
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Type
locality

. Abu Latt 
Island
, 
Red Sea
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Habitat
. Coral reefs.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Original description.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
(
Johnson, 1842
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; see also van 
Soest &amp; Hooper 2002
, pg. 242.
</p>
            <p>Synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium ficus
sensu 
Linnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 1295; 
<tp:taxon-name>Ficulina ficusLinnaeus, 1767</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 1295 (see 
Uriz 1984
, pg. 58); 
<tp:taxon-name>Alcyonium bulbosumEsper, 1806</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 235; 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 144; 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domuncula
von 
Lendenfeld, 1888</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 65 (not 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites domunculaOlivi, 1792</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 241); 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
Ackers 
et al.,
1992
</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 68.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
. Lectotype BMNH 1847.9.7.51, 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria ficusJohnson, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Bulbous, or pear–shaped, sometimes bulging from a narrow stalk, 
2.5–8 cm
in length (

a). Van 
Soest (2002)
described the species as lobate, occasionally cylindrical and may include specimens enveloping gastropod shells and encrusting scallops, 
10–40 cm
in length. Surface smooth with a velvety appearance with one or more conspicuous, large oscules. Consistency firm and incompressible. Colour in life russet red; in dried state cream/white.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. Styles, two types (

b). Type I, slightly curved, heads rounded and having a slight bump. Distally fusiform, sometimes mucronate, 288–345 µm 
x 7
µm (Van 
Soest, 2002
, measurements 350–500 µm 
x 10
µm). Type II, very thin, sinuous, heads rounded having a slight bump. Distally fusiform, 153–268 µm 
x 2
µm (Van 
Soest, 2002
, measurements 100–250 µm 
x 5
µm) (please refer to 
Table 2
for comparative measurements).
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Microrhabds (

c)—microspined microstrongyles, usually centrotylote, common, 16–28 µm. Smooth microstrongyles, usually centrotylote (

d), common, 24–48 µm.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Skeleton
. The skeletal architecture is confused, almost halichondroid, being radial near the surface. The ectosomal skeleton is made up of smaller tylostyles arranged pendicularly forming a dense palisade at the surface. 
Type
locality

. 
Scarborough
, 
England
, 
North Atlantic.</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Habitat
. Deep water.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Synonomy.<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusa
sensu 
Uriz, 1988</tp:taxon-name>
, pg 38 (Not 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
); 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites ficus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 28, figs. 3A, 21 a–e. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites carnosus
sensu 
Samaai &amp; Gibbons, 2005</tp:taxon-name>
, pg. 27, figs. 2O, 20 a–d.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Material
examined

. 
Holotype
.
SAMC
–A088677 (cross ref. TS 1625), 
West coast
, Station 
A29477
(
30°26'0"S
, 
16°48'59"E
), depth 
180 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
Other Material examined 
Holotype
MNHN DCL 1301, 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites tylobtusaLévi, 1958</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Holotype
BMNH 1847.9.7.51, 
<tp:taxon-name>Halichondria fícusJohnston, 1842</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Paratypes
.
SAMC
–A088678 (cross ref. TS 1815), 
West coast
, Station 
A30349
(
31°47'58"S
, 
17°54'29"E
), depth 
114 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>SAMC
–A088679 (cross ref. TS 1592), 
West coast
, Station 
A29471
(
29°12'0"S
, 
15°59'0"E
), depth 
166 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1586, 
West coast
, Station 
A29444
(
30°58'0"S
, 
17°27'0"E
), depth 
134 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1587, 
West coast
, Station 
A29442
(
30°30'59"S
, 
17°19'0"E
), depth 
111 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1599, 
West coast
, Station 
A29478
(
30°19'0"S
, 
16°54'59"E
), depth 
154 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1602, 
West coast
, Station 
A29482
(
29°37'59"S
, 
16°20'0"E
), depth 
157 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1612, 
West coast
, Station 
A29481
(
29°40'59"S
, 
16°12'59"E
), depth 
166 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1614, 
West coast
, Station 
A29480
(
29°53'0"S
, 
16°18'0"E
), depth 
182 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1631, 
West coast
, Station 
A29439
(
30°50'0"S
, 
16°52'0"E
), depth 
198 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1633, 
West coast
, Station 
A29479
(
30°0'0"S
, 
16°20'59"E
), depth 
187 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1640, 
West coast
, Station 
A27448
(
32°0'24"S
, 
17°24'59"E
), depth 
160 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1783, 
West coast
, Station 
A30328
(
32°17'52"S
, 
16°53'53"E
), depth 
296 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1787, 
West coast
, Station 
A30382
(
29°32'13"S
, 
15°45'14"E
), depth 
175 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1794, 
West coast
, Station 
A30389
(
29°20'13"S
, 
16°0'58"E
), depth 
168 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1798, 
West coast
, Station 
A30340
(
31°58'46"S
, 
16°52'10"E
), depth 
282 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1830, 
West coast
, Station 
A31415
(
31°22'5"S
, 
17°30'56"E
), depth 
147 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1836, 
West coast
, Station 
A31460
(
29°20'11"S
, 
16°1'1"E
), depth 
168 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1850, 
West coast
, Station 
A31406
(
32°7'32"S
, 
17°19'11"E
), depth 
184 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1859, 
West coast
, Station 
A31417
(
31°43'30"S
, 
17°1'30"E
), depth 
256 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1828, 
West coast
, Station 
A30350
(
31°34'58"S
, 
17°48'2"E
), depth 
118 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1876, 
West coast
, Station 
A31405
(
32°7'55"S
, 
17°12'7"E
), depth 
211 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1807, 
West coast
, Station 
A30351
(
31°19'47"S
, 
17°35'8"E
), depth 
133 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1810, 
West coast
, Station 
A30357
(
30°42'58"S
, 
16°53'19"E
), depth 
191 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1816, 
West coast
, Station 
A30403
(
31°8'38"S
, 
17°41'41"E
), depth 
89 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Other
voucher specimens.

TS 1584, 
West coast
, Station 
A29490
(
30°16'59"S
, 
15°43'59"E
), depth 
235 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1585, 
West coast
, Station 
A29500
(
31°29'0"S
, 
17°40'59"E
), depth 
125 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1589, 
West coast
, Station 
A29443
(
30°54'59"S
, 
17°20'0"E
), depth 
147 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1594, 
West coast
, Station 
A29507
(
33°22'0"S
, 
17°44'0"E
), depth 
183 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1601, 
West coast
, Station 
A29501
(
31°38'59"S
, 
17°47'59"E
), depth 
120 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1604, 
West coast
, Station 
A29483
(
29°29'59"S
, 
16°16'59"E
), depth 
155 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1611, 
West coast
, Station 
A29502
(
31°30'59"S
, 
17°58'0"E
), depth 
95 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1623, 
West coast
, Station 
A29475
(
30°22'59"S
, 
16°34'0"E
), depth 
208 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1628, 
West coast
, Station 
A29461
(
31°16'59"S
, 
17°12'59"E
), depth 
206 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1644, 
West coast
, Station 
A29455
(
32°18'59"S
, 
18°0'59"E
), depth 
103 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1784, 
West coast
, Station 
A30359
(
31°0'5"S
, 
16°0'52"E
), depth 
320 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1786, 
West coast
, Station 
A30392
(
29°8'33"S
, 
16°19'49"E
), depth 
138 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1789, 
West coast
, Station 
A30341
(
31°52'39"S
, 
17°7'3"E
), depth 
211 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1795, 
West coast
, Station 
A30383
(
29°36'57"S
, 
15°55'19"E
), depth 
178 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1797, 
West coast
, Station 
A30392
(
29°8'33"S
, 
16°19'49"E
), depth 
138 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1809, 
West coast
, Station 
A30356
(
30°49'35"S
, 
16°39'34"E
), depth 
239 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1813, 
West coast
, Station 
A30385
(
29°18'43"S
, 
16°33'41"E
), depth 
126 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1817, 
West coast
, Station 
A30384
(
29°46'46"S
, 
16°0'46"E
), depth 
185 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1819, 
West coast
, Station 
A30395
(
29°44'59"S
, 
16°29'17"E
), depth 
156 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1823, 
West coast
, Station 
A30325
(
32°48'44"S
, 
17°42'33"E
), depth 
142 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1826, 
West coast
, Station 
A30352
(
31°10'23"S
, 
17°20'33"E
), depth 
178 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1877, 
West coast
, Station 
A31438
(
30°38'19"S
, 
16°53'37"E
), depth 
186 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1621, 
West coast
, Station 
A29470
(
29°7'59"S
, 
16°5'59"E
), depth 
163 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2009</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
TS 1805, 
West coast
, Station 
A30353
(
30°54'52"S
, 
17°3'18"E
), depth 
197 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1806, 
West coast
, Station 
A30399
(
30°21'1"S
, 
16°48'2"E
), depth 
179 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1812, 
West coast
, Station 
A30381
(
29°24'13"S
, 
15°30'20"E
), depth 
181 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1814, 
West coast
, Station 
A30391
(
29°28'59"S
, 
16°20'25"E
), depth 
151 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2010</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1837, 
West coast
, Station 
A31413
(
31°38'59"S
, 
17°39'16"E
), depth 
130 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1840, 
West coast
, Station 
A31446
(
29°0'26"S
, 
16°15'34"E
), depth 
141 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1841, 
West coast
, Station 
A31439
(
30°38'23"S
, 
17°9'20"E
), depth 
150 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1848, 
West coast
, Station 
A31440
(
30°40'43"S
, 
17°25'5"E
), depth 
98 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1849, 
West coast
, Station 
A31441
(
30°23'34"S
, 
16°59'47"E
), depth 
150 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1862, 
West coast
, Station 
A31462
(
29°39'28"S
, 
16°2'58"E
), depth 
181 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
TS 1868, 
West coast
, Station 
A31437
(
30°33'26"S
, 
16°50'0"E
), depth 
186 m
, collected by 
FRS
Africana, 
January 2011</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
Other 
South
African &amp; Namibian material examined

. 
SAM
–H4898 (Ts 330), 
Elands Bay
(
32°20’S
, 
18°20’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M. J. Gibbons
, 
7 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
343a, 
Elands Bay
(
32°20’S
, 
18°20’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M.J. Gibbons
, 
7 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
344, 
Ts
346, 
Ts
348, 
Ts
355, 
St Helena Bay
(
32°40’S
, 
18°10’E
), depth 
2–5 m
, collected by 
T. Samaai
and 
M.J. Gibbons
, 
9 April 1997</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
412, 
Black Rock
, 
Lüderitz
, 
Namibia
(
24°50’S
, 
14°40’E
), depth 
12 m
, collected by 
NSFRI
, 
20 March 1998</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>SAM
– H4897 (Ts 540), 
Oranjemund
(
26°31’S
, 
15°01’E
), depth 
78 m
, collected by 
A. Goosen
, from ‘ 
Jago’
submersible, 
April 1999</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>Ts
541, 
Oranjemund
(
26°31’S
, 
15°01’E
), depth 
78 m
, collected by 
A. Goosen
, from ‘ 
Jago’
submersible, 
April 1999</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of gross morphology
. Massive sponge with rounded lobes and apical oscula (

a). Two morphotypes are distinguishable: (a) globulous, widest at the base, with one large apical osculum terminally, and (b) elongate, with compressed base from where a few globular lobes rise, each widest in the middle and terminating in a small osculum. Varied size, up to 
40 cm
in diameter. Surface smooth, microscopically hirsute, not velvety. Oscules 
1–2 cm
in diameter on the apical end of the lobe; ostia 
0.1 mm
in diameter. Consistency spongy, soft, depending on the degree of contraction. Ectosome not discernable. Colour in life straw orange brown with some having tinges of yellow, choanosome orange–yellow internally; in preservative light brown or straw yellow to khaki. Mud encrusted specimens are greyish brown.
</p>
            <p>Megascleres
. 
Type
I Tylostyles. Thin, long, straight or curved, with a sharp gradually tapering end, heads well rounded, distally fusiform, 505 (413–576) × 7 (7) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–I). 
Type
II Tylostyles. More robust, thickened and somewhat curved, head well defined and rounded, distally fusiform, 351 (307–413) × 19 (14–24) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–II). 
Type
III Tylostyles. Thick, straight, head well defined and rounded 465 (451–490) ×14 (9.6–19) µm, 
n
= 10 (

b–III). Large tylostrongyles (tylobtuse strongyles). Thick, variable size, head poorly defined, but round, often somewhat wider than opposite rounded end, 271 (240–307) × 24 (19–29) µm, 
n
= 10 (

c). Centrotylostrongyles. Thick, variable size, straight or slightly curved, with bulbous centre, end not fusiform but hastately rounded 307 (259–346) ×14 (9.6–19) µm, 
n
= 10 (

d). Centrotyloxeas. Thick, variable size, sinuous or slightly curved, with bulbous centre, end fusiform, but some forms are centrotylostrongyles, 414 (365–518) ×16 (14–19) µm, 
n
= 10. Small tylostrongyles (tylobtuse strongyles). Thick, variable size, head well defined, and rounded, 163 (115–201) ×24 (19–29) µm, 
n
= 10 (

e). Small mutant tylostrongyles (kidney–shaped) also present with size approximately 86 (76–96) 
x 19
µm, 
n
= 10 (

f). Some specimens e.g. TS 1815 and TS 1592 lack the tylobtuse strongyles (see 

). These megascleres are present in variable proportions in all the specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>Microscleres
. Microrhabds (microacanthostrongyles, usually centrotylote), rare in some specimens or even absent (e.g. 

—specimen TS 1592), 10–15 µm (

g). The morphology of the microacanthostrongyles is similar to that found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
. It is present in variable proportions in all the specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>Skeleton
. Choanosomal skeleton consists of a subradiate, composed of a confused irregular reticulation of bundles of tylostyles, which meander vertically through the choanosome. Spicules radially arranged near the surface, and the internal skeleton confused, almost halichondroid (

h). The ectosome consists of a distinct, compact, radially disposed layer of small dermal tylostyles, 200–400 µm wide. Distal ends of tylostyles project slightly beyond the ectosomal surface.
</p>
            <p>DNA barcodes
. Two unique cox1 haplotypes were identified among a total of 20 specimens. GenBank accession nos. KY463455 (haplotype 1) and KY463456 (haplotype 2).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
. Named after Ms Dandelene Reynolds, a technician in DEA, who passed away in 2010.
</p>
            <p>Phenotypic variation
. The species variability is limited to the sponge size with a uniform straw orange brown.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
locality

. The 
type
material was collected from the west coast of 
South
Africa

, from unconsolidated sediment in a region with seasonal cold-water upwelling.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.South
African and Namibian west coast (
BCLME
) (

&amp; 

)
</p>
            <p>Ecology
. 
Uriz (1988
, 
1990
) proposed that 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
(
Red Sea
sponge) was translocated by fisheries activities to the continental shelf off southern Africa between 
1960 and 1984
, as earlier surveys conducted over many decades had failed to detect it. These earlier surveys however, were not comprehensive or thorough, and focused their efforts around 
Cape
Town, Saldanha Bay, Still Bay and Durban, all of which fall outside its distributional range.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is particularly abundant at depths ranging between 
80–500 m
, on the continental plateau of the west coast of South Africa and Namibia (
Samaai &amp; Gibbons 2005
; 
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
) (

&amp; 

) where it may dominate epibenthic communities in terms of biomass, forming “sponge beds or facies” (
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
). During various trawl surveys on the west coast of South Africa (with the Research Vessels Dr Fridjof Nansen and RV Africana), more than 
6 tons
/km2 of sponge material were obtained during several hauls within depths ranging 

120– 
275 m
. The greatest mass of sponges collected was 
18 tons
/km2, from a depth near 
138 m
off Doring Bay (2006–Cruise 402, Station 1250). The three localities off Port Nolloth produced 
3–3.5 tons
/km2 of sponges collected on average, while 
6 tons
/km2 of sponges were obtained from one site at a depth of 
195 m
in the proposed Namaqualand MPA (Nansen Cruise 402, Station 1196, 2006) (

). The commercial trawler fleet generally fishes in water that is deeper (
200–1000 m
) than that of the sponge beds, but there is an overlap in the distribution of the sponge and diamond mining and oil and gas operations (Atkinson 
et al
. 2011; 

Sink 
et al
. 2012

). The potential threats of these activities on the filter feeding sponge community have yet to be assessed.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is not a reef builder, but it can be habitat forming and occurs in soft sediment environments. The sponge beds constitute an ecologically important habitat of great complexity for fishes and both motile and sessile invertebrates, and they may play an important role in the ecology and diversity of the west coast region. Indeed, their presence could constitute a Vulnerable Marine Ecosystem (VME) or an Ecologically and Biologically Significant Area (
EBSA
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks
. The identification of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
at the species level based on morphological features is difficult, because species of this genus are highly polymorphic and have a simple skeleton and spicular structures, which are more or less homogeneous (Solé– 
Cava &amp; Thorpe 1986
; Van 
Soest 2002
). Having said that, it has been argued that the use of qualitative characters such as the presence or absence of microscleres (microstrongyles) is helpful in distinguishing species, e.g. 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
(
Hartman 1958
; 

Hiscock 
et al.
1983

). However, it is clear from the present results (Table S1) that although there are taxonomically useful spicule differences between specimens, these qualitative and quantitative differences can be misleading in defining a species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
specimens show considerable variation in the relative proportion or presence of different spicule 
types
.
</p>
            <p>
Typically, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
has three distinct 
types
of megascleres, but some specimens (see 
Table 2
) possess only tylobtuse strongyles and microstrongyles, or they lack tylobtuse strongyles but possess microstrongyles, and some specimens lack both tylobtuse strongyles and microstrongyles (see also 

). This exemplifies the importance of studying a range of specimens to find phenotypic and histological characters that are useful in fitting the puzzle to correctly identify or separate species. Differences only become evident when the specimens are studied together (
Tables 2
&amp; Table S1). The new species exhibits a number of affinities with 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
(see 
Uriz 1988
, 
1990
), both in terms of external morphology and in the structure of the centrotylote microscleres. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. carnosus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. tylobtusus</tp:taxon-name>
in external morphology, having centrotylote microscleres and generally larger megaslere spicules (see 
Tables 3
&amp; Table S1).
</p>
            <p>
The absence of centrotylote microscleres, tylostrongyle megascleres and the poorly developed tylostyle megascleres in some specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
illustrates that secondary loss of spicules can occur readily. Sponge taxonomy is largely based on spicule morphology, but spicules have already been shown to be potentially unreliable for phylogenetics due to their high level of morphological homoplasy (
Fromont &amp; Bergquist 1990
; 

Manuel 
et al
. 2003

; 

Cárdenas 
et al
. 2011

), as well as for alpha–taxonomy due to intra–specific variation (
Schönberg &amp; Barthel 1998
).
</p>
            <p>Zea (1987)
found that spicules, especially microscleres, can be present or absent in sponge specimens depending on their location, and that variations in megascleres are rare. Maldonando 
et al.
(1999) showed that variation in spicule 
type
and shape can also be explained by silicon limitation. Although there is considerable latitudinal variability in the frequency, intensity and seasonality of upwelling in the Benguela ecosystem, the region is not generally considered to be silicon–poor in deeper water. It is worth noting here that whilst surface waters may become stripped of silica by diatoms in upwelling areas, the same is not true of bottom waters where the sponges are found owing to remineralisation (

Pitcher 
et al
. 1992

). Location and seawater chemistry are unlikely to be responsible for the considerable variation in spicule 
types
found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
as samples collected from the same trawl often had different spicule complements (

).
</p>
            <p>
The magnitude between depth differences in concentration of dissolved silicate (and temperature), have been examined in order to assess their potential relevance in the development and/or maintenance of the sponge aggregations. The mean concentration of silicate, a crucial nutrient used by sponges to build their silica skeleton, ranges from 12.22 to 17.36 µM over the year between 
100–400 m
depth, being only approximately 20 µM lower on average than values deeper than 
400 m
.
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is most abundant between the 
100–200 m
depth range. Temperature values decrease towards the deeper depths.
</p>
            <p>
It remains unclear what the particular conditions are that have favored the impressive aggregation of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
between 
100–200 m
depth range. As this sponge is characterized by a well–developed organic body by having a massive silica skeleton, it would be expected to require large amounts of dissolved silicon for growth and build its skeletal framework. However, average silicate concentrations where the sponges are found were stable, even in areas where the sponge occurs in far lower abundance. The data suggest that dissolved silicon availability in the southern Benguela may not be particularly responsible for the occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelanae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
. Intra–specific variation in spicule complement can often be the result of phenotypic plasticity due to the influence of environmental factors. Our study, like that of 
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp (2013)
presents another case of intra– specific spicule variation, most probably as a consequence due to sponge size (or age), as opposed to reflecting changes due to environmental conditions or latitudinal/bathymetric variations (

). However, little more than mere speculation can be offered at the current stage of knowledge, because virtually nothing is known both about the reproductive biology and dispersal ability of this new 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species. This study reiterates the point by 
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp (2013)
that taxonomist should be careful when delinating species only by the presence or abundance of one 
type
of spicule. A few examples of such inappropriate use of spicules as morphological characters exist in the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Erylus, Geodia
(
Cárdenas &amp; Rapp 2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Crambe</tp:taxon-name>
(
Maldonadoet al
. 1999

).
</p>
            <p>
Based on the above considerations, megasclere 
type
may not be a stable or valid taxonomic character for species discrimination within the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
. The structure and presence of centrotylote microscleres, as a trait for species identification, should also be considered carefully due to the rarity and possible inconsistent occurrence of this 
type
of microsclere in the new species. Nevertheless, the present species is clearly distinct from other 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species (Table S1), and any uncertainties regarding this particular trait are irrelevant in its recognition as a new species.
</p>
            <p>
Further studies are needed to fully document the population dynamics of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
in light of our conclusions that the species has a restricted geographical range in the southern Benguela upwelling region, and it is critical to understand the species' ecological role in the region’s coastal and continental shelf marine ecosystems.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Summary</title>
         <p>
The present study demonstrates that cox1 sequences performed sufficiently well as a molecular markers to confirm that considerable intraspecific spicular variability found in 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
occurred within a species that has not previously been sequenced. In contrast to this taxonomically misleading variability, there was no conflict in the genetic results. The high genetic similarity among sequences of S. 
<tp:taxon-name>dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and the fact that all haplotypes generated are novel, indicate that all specimens sequenced belong to the new species. The new 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species is closely related to 
<tp:taxon-name>S. pagurorum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>S. domuncula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. ficus</tp:taxon-name>
. Although genetic differentiation is minimal, this is not unexpected because cox1 sequence data often fails to separate congeneric sponge species (

Wörheide 
et al
. 2006

) because mitochondrial 
DNA
in sponge evolves much more slowly than in most other metazoans (

Shearer 
et al
. 2002

). Phylogenetic studies of sponges typically require more genetic information in the form of additional portions of the cox1 gene, or of more quickly evolving nuclear genetic markers such as the internal transcribed spacers (Wörheide 
et al.
2002, Becking 
et al.
2013). However, such a strategy would not have been informative in the present case because no sequences from such markers are available for the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
that formed a monophyletic cluster with 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
Moreoever, the value of 
ad hoc
sequence similarity thresholds is increasingly being questioned (

Lin 
et al
. 2015

), and species status is instead based on reciprocal monophyly of a group of sequences, as this indicates that sufficient time has passed since speciation to complete lineage sorting, and to permit the genetic identification of species (Kapli 
et al
. in press). On the basis of this biologically more meaningful approach, our finding that all individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
for which the cox1 gene was sequenced share a common ancestor presents strong support for its species status. This study thus reinforces the utility of molecular information for taxonomic clarity, especially when morphological characters are in conflict, which can often lead to species misidentifications. The results also show that a revised phylogenetic tree that includes additional markers for both the new species and all its congeners would be desirable in order to resolve genetic relationships within this taxonomic group, and clarify the taxonomic placement of 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
Several sequences of what are supposedly conspecific species did not cluster together in the phylogenetic tree reconstructed here, which suggests either potential mis–identifications or cryptic speciation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>
We thank the Oceans and Coasts Research Chief Directorate, Department of Environmental Affairs (DEA), 
Cape
Town, for logistic support under their Marine Biodiversity &amp; Ecosystems Research section, and the National Research Foundation, 
South
Africa

, for financial support to the senior author. We also thank the DEA for collection permits. We are also grateful to Dr Lara Atkinson, Ms. Liese Swart, Dr Kerry Sink and Dr Louise Lange for assistance with specimen collections. We are grateful to the University of 
Cape
Town Electron Microscopy Unit for access to their Scanning Electron Microscope. The seniour author is grateful for the assistance, advice and guidance provided by Dr Gisele Lôbo Hajdu, Thiago de Paula, Prof. Channing (
UWC
), Dr Harkins (
UWC
) and Dr Tolley (
SANBI
). Ongoing research support to TS through funding to the Marine Biodiversity Programme, from Oceans and Coasts Research, is gratefully acknowledged.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Ackers, R.G
., Moss, D. &amp; Picton. B.E. (
1992
) 
Sponges of the British Isles (“Sponges Ƒ”): A colour guide and working document
.
Marine Conservation Society, Ross on Wye
, 
175 pp.</p>
         <p>Altschul, S.F.
, 
Gish, W.
, 
Miller, W.
, 
Myers, E.W.
&amp; 
Lipman, D.J.
(
1990
) 
Basic local alignment search tool
. 
Journal of Molecular Biology
, 
215
, 
403–410
.
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2</p>
         <p>Atkinson, L.J.
, 
Leslie, R.W.
, 
Field, J.G.
&amp; 
Jarre, A.
(
2011
) 

Changes in demersal fish assemblages on the west coast of 
South
Africa

, 
1986–2009
. 
African Journal of Marine Science
, 
33
, 
157–170
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.2989/1814232X.2011.572378</p>
         <p>Benson, D.A.
, 
Karsch-Mizrachi, I
., 
Lipman, D.J.
, 
Ostell, J.
&amp; 
Sayers, E.W.
(
2009
) 
GenBank
. 
Nucleic Acids Research
, 
37
(Database Issue), 26–31. [D 
26–31
]
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkn723</p>
         <p>Boury-Esnault, N.
&amp; 
Rützler, K.
(Eds.) (
1997
) 
Thesaurus of Sponge Morphology
. 

Smithsonian. 
Contributions to Zoology
, 
596
, 
1–55
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.5479/si.00810282.596</p>
         <p>Burton, M.
(
1930
a) 
Norwegian Sponges from the Norman Collection
. 
Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London
, 1930

(
2
), 
487–546
, pls. I–II.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.10963642.1930.tb00989.x</p>
         <p>Burton, M.
(
1930
b) 
Additions to the sponge fauna of the Gulf of Manaar
. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History
, Series 10

, 
5
(
30
), 
665–676
.
</p>
         <p>Burton, M.
(
1931
a) 

On a Collection of Marine Sponges mostly from the Natal 
Coast
. 
Annals of the Natal Museum
, 
6
(
3
), 
337– 358
, pl. XXIII.
</p>
         <p>Burton, M.
(
1926
) 

Description of 
South
African sponges collected in the 
South
African Marine Survey. Part I. Myxospongia and Astrotetraxonida

. 
Fisheries Bulletin. Fisheries and marine biological survey division
, 

Union of 
South
Africa

Report

, 
4
, (Special Report 9), 
1–29
, pls 6.
</p>
         <p>Burton, M.
(
1929
) 
Porifera. Part II. Antarctic sponges. British Antarctic ('Terra Nova') Expedition, 1910
. 
Natural History Report
, 
London
, 
British Museum (Natural History)
, 
Zoology
, 
6
(
4
), 
393–458
, pls. I–V.
</p>
         <p>Burton, M.
(
1933
a) 
Four new marine sponges from Natal
. 
Annals of the Natal Museum
, 
7
(
2
), 
249
.
</p>
         <p>Burton, M.
(
1933
b) 

Report on a small collection of sponges from Stil Bay, 
South
Africa

. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History
, Series 10

, 
11
, 
235–244
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1080/00222933308673651</p>
         <p>Burton, M.
(
1936
) 

Notes on sponges from 
South
Africa

, with descriptions of new species

. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History
, Series 10

, 
17
(
97
), 
141–147
.
</p>
         <p>Cárdenas, P.
, 
Xavier, J.R.
, 
Reveillaud, J.
, 
Schander, C.
&amp; 
Rapp, H.T.
(
2011
) 
Molecular phylogeny of the Astrophorida (Porifera, Demospongiae) reveals an unexpected high level of spicule homoplasy
. 
Plos One
, 
6
(
4
), e18318. https://doi.org/ 
10.1371/journal.pone.0018318</p>
         <p>Cárdenas,P.
, 
Pérez,T.
&amp; 
Boury-Esnault, N.
(
2012
). 
Sponge systematics facing new challenges
. 
Advances in marine biology
, 
61
, 
79–209
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-12-387787-1.00010-6</p>
         <p>Cárdenas, P.
&amp; 
Tore Rapp, H.
(
2013
) 
Disrupted spiculogenesis in deep-water Geodiidae (Porifera, Demospongiae) growing in shallow waters
. 
Invertebrate Biology
, 
132
(
3
), 
173–194
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1111/ivb.12027</p>
         <p>Chombard, C.
&amp; 
Boury-Esnault, N.
(
1999
) 
Good congruence between morphology and molecular phylogeny of Hadromerida, or how to bother sponge taxonomists
. 

Memoirs of the 
Queensland
Museum

, 
44
, 
100
.
</p>
         <p>Doyle, J.J.
&amp; 
Doyle J.L.
(
1987
) 

A rapid 
DNA
isolation procedure for small quatities of fresh leaf tissue

. 
Phytochemical Bulletin
, 
19
, 
11–15
.
</p>
         <p>Doyle, J.J
&amp; 
Doyle, J.L.
(
1990
) 

Isolation of plant 
DNA
from fresh tissue

. 
Focus
, 
12
, 
13–15
.
</p>
         <p>Esper, E.J.C.
(
1806
) 
Fortsetzungen der Pflanzenthiere in Abbildungen nach der Natur mit Farben erleuchtet nebst Beschreibungen
. 
Zweyter Theil
. 
Raspe, Nürnberg
, pp. 
25–48
, pls. LXV–LXX.
</p>
         <p>Fairweather, T.
&amp; 
Leslie, R.W.
(
2008
) 
Merluccius capensis and M. paradoxus length at 50% maturity based on research survey biological data
. 

Unpublished report, Marine and Coastal Management, 
South
Africa

, 
MCM
/2008/JUL/SWG-DEM/42

, 
5 pp.</p>
         <p>Felsenstein, J.
(
1985
) 
Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap
. 
Evolution
, 
39
, 
783–791
. https://doi.org/ 
10.2307/2408678</p>
         <p>Folmer, O.
, 
Black, M.
, 
Hoeh, W.
, 
Lutz, R.
&amp; 
Vrijenhoek, R.
(
1994
) 
DNA
primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit I from diverse metazoan invertebrates

. 
Molecular Marine Biology and Biotechnology
, 
3
, 
294–299
.
</p>
         <p>Fromont, J.
&amp; 
Bergquist, P.R.
(
1990
) 
Structural characters and their use in sponge taxonomy: when is a sigma not a sigma
? 
In
: 
Rützler, K.
(Ed.), 
New perspectives in sponge biology
. 
Proceedings 3rdInternational Sponge Conference
. Wood Hole, Smithsonian Institution Press, 
Washington
, pp. 
273–278
.
</p>
         <p>Grant, R.E.
(
1836
) 
Animal Kingdom
. 
In:Todd, R.B.
(Ed.), 
The Cyclopaedia of Anatomy and Physiology
. Ƒol. 1.

Sherwood, Gilbert &amp; Piper, London, pp. 
107–118
, 
1–813
.
</p>
         <p>Gray, J.E.
(
1867
) 
Notes on the arrangement of sponges, with the descriptions of some new Genera
. 
Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London
, 1867

(
2
), 
492–558
, pls. XXVII–XXVIII.
</p>
         <p>Hajdu, E.
, 
Desqueyroux-Faúndez, R.
, 
Carvalho, M.D.S.
, 
Lôbo-Hajdu, G.
&amp; 
Willenz, P.
(
2013
) 
Twelve new Demospongiae (Porifera) from Chilean fjords, with remarks upon sponge-derived biogeographic compartments in the SE Pacific
. 
Zootaxa
, 
3744
(
1
), 
1–64
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3744.1.1</p>
         <p>Hartman, W.D.
(
1958
) 

Natural History of the Marine Sponges of Southern New 
England
. 
Bulletin of the Peabody Museum of Natural History
, 
12
, 
1–155
.
</p>
         <p>Hiscock, K.
, 
Stone, S.M.K.
&amp; 
George, J.D.
(
1983
) 
The marine fauna of Lundy. Porifera (sponges)
. 
Report Lundy Field Society
, 
34
, 
16–35
.
</p>
         <p>Hutchings, L.
, 
Augustyn, C.J.
, 
Cockcroft, A.
, 
van der Lingen, C.
, 
Coetzee, J.
, 
Leslie, R.W.
, 
Tarr, R.J.
, 
Oosthuizen, H.
, 
Lipinski, M.R.
, 
Roberts, M.R.
, 
Wilke, C.
, 
Crawford, R.
, 
Shannon, L.J.
&amp; 
Mayekiso, M.
(
2009
) 

Marine fisheries monitoring programmes in 
South
Africa

. 
South
African Journal of Science

, 
105
, 
182–192
.
</p>
         <p>Johnston, G.
(
1842
) 
A History of British Sponges and Lithophytes
. 

W.H. Lizars, 
Edinburgh
, i–xii

, 
1–264
, pls. I–XXV.
</p>
         <p>Kapli, P.
, 
Lutteropp, S.
, 
Zhang, J.
, 
Kobert, K.
, 
Pavlidis, P.
, 
Stamatakis, A.
&amp; 
Flouri, T.
(
2016
) 

Multi-rate Poisson Tree Processes for single-locus species delimitation under Maximum Likelihood and Markov Chain 
Monte Carlo
. 
bioRxiv
, 
2016
, 0 
63875
.
</p>
         <p>[published online]</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1101/063875</p>
         <p>Keller, C.
(
1891
) 
Die Spongienfauna des Rothen Meeres (II. Halfte)
. 
Zeitschrift für wissenschaftliche Zoologie
, 
52
, 
294–368
, pls. XVI–XX, pp. 316–317.
</p>
         <p>Kimura, M.
(
1980
) 
A simple method for estimating evolutionary rate of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences
. 
Journal of Molecular Evolution
, 
16
, 
111–120
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01731581</p>
         <p>Kirkpatrick, R.
(
1902
) 

Descriptions of 
South
African Sponges. Part I

. 

Marine Investigations in 
South
Africa

, 
1
, 
219–232
, pls. I– III.
</p>
         <p>Kirkpatrick, R.
(
1903
a) 

Descriptions of 
South
African Sponges. Part II

. 

Marine Investigations in 
South
Africa

, 
2
(
14
), 
171–180
, pl. IV.
</p>
         <p>Kirkpatrick, R.
(
1903
b) 

Descriptions of 
South
African Sponges. Part III

. 

Marine Investigations in 
South
Africa

, 
2
(
14
), 
233– 264
, pls. V–VI.
</p>
         <p>Lendenfeld, R.
Von (
1888
) 
Descriptive Catalogue of the Sponges in the Australian Museum
, 
Sidney
. 
Taylor &amp; Francis, London, I–xiv, 1–260, pls1–12
.
</p>
         <p>Lendenfeld, R. von
(
1898
) 
Die Clavulina der Adria
. 
Nova acta Academiae Caesareae Leopoldino Carolinae germanicae naturaecuriosorum
, 
69
, 
1–251
, pls. I–XII. page(s), 144.
</p>
         <p>Lévi, C.
(
1958
) 

Résultats scientifiques des Campagnes de la ‘Calypso’.Campagne 
1951–1952
en 
Mer Rouge
(suite). 11. Spongiaires de 
Mer Rouge
recueillis par la ‘Calypso’ (
1951–1952
)

. 
Annales de l’Institut océanographique
, 
34
(
3
), 
3–46
.
</p>
         <p>Lévi, C.
(
1959
) 

Résultats scientifiques des Campagnes de la ‘Calypso’. Campagne de la ‘Calypso’ dans le Golfe de 
Guinée
et aux îles 
Principe
, 
São Tomé
et 
Annobon
. 5. Spongiaires

. 
Annales de l’Institut océanographique
, 
37
(
4
), 
115–141
, pls. 5–6, 125, fig.14, pl. 5, fig. 4.
</p>
         <p>Lévi, C.
(
1964
) 
Spongiaires des zones bathyale
, 

abyssale et hadale. 
Galathea Report
. 
Scientific Results of The Danish Deep- Sea Expedition Round the World
, 
1950–52
, 
7
, 
63–112
, pls. II–XI.
</p>
         <p>Linnaeus, C.
(
1767
) 
Systema naturae sive regna tria naturae
, 
secundum classes
, 
ordines
, 
genera
, 
species
, 
cum characteribus
, 
differentiis
, 
synonymis
, 
locis
. 
Ƒol
. 
1
. 

Part 2. 12 
thEdition.
Laurentii Salvii, Holmiae

, 
795 pp.
[pp. 
533–1327
]
</p>
         <p>Lin, X.
, 
Stur, E.
&amp; 
Ekrem, T.
(
2015
). 

Exploring genetic divergence in a species-rich insect genus using 2790 
DNA
Barcodes

. 
Plos One
, 
10
(
9
), e0138993.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0138993</p>
         <p>Maduray, S.
(
2014
) 

Studies on the diversity and spatial distribution of deep water sponges along the west and south coasts of 
South
Africa

. 

MSc Thesis (unpublished), University of the 
Western
Cape

, 
Cape
Town, pp

. 
117
.
</p>
         <p>Maldonado
, M.

, 
Carmona, M.C.
, 
Uriz, M.J.
&amp; 
Cruzado, A.
(
1999
) 
Decline in Mesozoic reef-building sponges explained by silicon limitation
. 
Nature
, 
401
, 
785–788
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1038/44560</p>
         <p>Manuel, M.
, 
Borchiellini, C.
, 
Alivon, E.
, 
Le Parco, Y.
, 
Vacelet, J.
&amp; 
Boury-Esnault, N.
(
2003
) 
Phylogeny and evolution of calcareous sponges: monophyly of calcinea and calcaronea, high level of morphological homoplasy, and the primitive nature of axial symmetry
. 
Systematic Biology
, 
52
, 
311–333
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1080/10635150390196966</p>
         <p>Mead, A.
, 
Carlton, J.T.
, 
Griffiths, C.L.
&amp; 
Rius, M.
(
2011
) 

Introduced and cryptogenic marine and estuarine species in 
South
Africa

. 
Journal of Natural History
, 
45
, 
2463–2524
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1080/00222933.2011.595836</p>
         <p>Nardo, G.D.
(
1833
) 
Auszug aus einem neuen System der Spongiarien,wonach bereits die Aufstellung in der Universitäts- Sammlung zu Padua gemacht ist
. 
In:Isis
. 
Oder Encyclopädische Zeitung Coll.
Oken, Jena

, pp. 
519–523
.
</p>
         <p>Olivi, G.
(
1792
) 
Alcyonium
and 
Spongia
. 
Zoologia Adriatica
, 
1792
, 
235–254
&amp; 262–273.
</p>
         <p>Pitcher, G.C.
, 
Brown, P.C.
&amp; 
Mitchell-Innes, B.A.
(
1992
) 
Spatio-temporal variability of phytoplankton in the southern Benguela upwelling system
. 
South
African Journal of Marine Science

, 
12
, 
439–456
. https://doi.org/ 
10.2989/02577619209504717</p>
         <p>Redmond, N.E.
, 
Morrow, C.C.
, 
Thacker, R.W.
, 
Diaz, M.C.
, 
Boury-Esnault, N.
, 
Cárdenas, P.
, 
Hajdu, E.
, 
Lôbo-Hajdu, G.
, 
Picton, B.E.
, 
Pomponi, S.A.
&amp; 
Kayal, E.
(
2013
) 

Phylogeny and systematics of Demospongiae in light of new small-subunit ribosomal 
DNA
(18S) sequences

. 
Integrative and Comparative Biology
, 
53
, 
388–415
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1093/icb/ict078</p>
         <p>Ridley, S.O.
&amp; 
Dendy, A.
(
1886
) 
Preliminary Report on the Monaxonida collected by H.M.S. ‘Challenger’
. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History
, Series 5

, 
18
, 
325–351
, 470–493.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1080/00222938609459982</p>
         <p>Ridley, S.O.
&amp; 
Dendy, A.
(
1887
) 

Report on the Monaxonida collected by H.M.S. ‘Challenger’ during the years 
1873–1876
. Report on the Scientific Results of the Voyage of H.M.S. ‘Challenger’, 
1873–1876
. 
Zoology
, 20

(
59
), i–lxviii, 
1–275
, pls. I–LI, 
1 map
.
</p>
         <p>Saitou, N.
&amp; 
Nei, M.
(
1987
) 
The neighbor-joining method: A new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees
. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
, 
4
, 
406–425
.
</p>
         <p>Samaai, T.
&amp; 
Gibbons, M.J.
(
2005
) 

Demospongiae taxonomy and biodiversity of the Benguela region on the west coast of 
South
Africa

. 
African Natural History
, 
1
, 
1–96
.
</p>
         <p>Schönberg, C.H.L.
&amp; 
Barthel, D.
(
1998
) 

Unreliability of Demosponge skeletal characters: the example of 
Halichondria panicea
. 
In:Watanabe, Y
. &amp; Fusetani, N. (Eds.), 
Sponge Sciences. Multidisciplinary Perspectives
. 

Springer, 
Tokyo
, pp. 
41–53
.
</p>
         <p>Schmidt, O.
(
1870
) 
Grundzüge einer Spongien-Fauna des atlantischen Gebietes
. 
Wilhelm Engelmann, Leipzig, ii
+ 
88 pp.
, VI pls. [pp. iii–iv, 
1–88
, pls. I–VI]
</p>
         <p>Shearer, T.L.
, 
van Oppen, M.J.H.
, 
Romano, S.L.
&amp; 
Wörheide, G.
(
2002
) 

Slow mitochondrial 
DNA
sequence evolution in the Anthozoa (Cnidaria)

. 
Molecular Ecology
, 
11
(
12
), 
2475–2487
.
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.1046/j.1365-294X.2002.01652.x</p>
         <p>Solé-Cava, A.M.
&amp; 
Thorpe, J.P.
(
1986
) 

Genetic differentiation between morphotypes of the marine sponge 
Suberites ficus
(Demospongiae: Hadromerida)

. 
Marine Biology
, 
93
, 
247–253
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00508262</p>
         <p>Sink, K.J.
, 
Attwood, C.G.
, 
Lombard, A.T.
, 
Grantham, H.
, 
Leslie, R.
, 
Samaai, T.
, 
Kerwath, S.
, 
Majiedt, P.
, 
Fairweather, T.
, 
Hutchings, L.
, 
van der Lingen, C.
, 
Atkinson, L.J.
, 
Wilkinson, S.
, 
Holness, S
. &amp; Wolf, T. (
2011
) 

Spatial planning to identify focus areas for offshore biodiversity protection in 
South
Africa

. Final Report for the Offshore Marine Protected Area Project

.
South
African National Biodiversity Institute, 
Cape
Town, pp

. 
66
.
</p>
         <p>Sink, K.
, 
Holness, S.
, 
Harris, L.
, 
Majiedt, P.
, 
Atkinson, L.
, 
Robinson, T.
, 
Kirkman, S.
, 
Hutchings, L.
, 
Leslie, R.
, 
Lamberth, S.
, 
Kerwath, S.
, 
von der Heyden, S.
, 
Lombard, A.
, 
Attwood, C.
, 
Branch, G.
, 
Fairweather, T.
, 
Taljaard, S.
, 
Weerts, S.
, 
Cowley, P.
, 
Awad, A.
, 
Halpern, B.
, 
Grantham, H
. &amp; 
Wolf, T
. (
2012
) 
National Biodiversity Assessment2011
. Technical Report. Ƒol. 4. Marine and Coastal Component

. 
South
African National Biodiversity Institute, Pretoria, pp. 
325
.
</p>
         <p>Soest, R.W.M. van
(
2002
) 
Family Suberitidae
. 
In
: 
Hooper, J.N.A
&amp; 
van Soest, R.W.M.
(Eds.), 
Systema Porifera
, 
a guide to the classification of the sponges
. 

Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers, 

New 
York
, pp. 
227–244
.
</p>
         <p>Soest, R.W.M. van
, 
Boury-Esnault, N.
, 
Hooper, J.N.A.
, 
Rützler, K.
, 
de Voogd, N.J.
, 
Alvarez de Glasby, B.
, 
Hajdu, E.
, 
Pisera, A.B.
, 
Manconi, R.
, 
Schoenberg, C.
, 
Klautau, M.
, 
Picton, B.
, 
Kelly, M.
, 
Vacelet, J.
, 
Dohrmann, M.
, 
Díaz, M.C.
, 
Cárdenas, P.
&amp; 
Carballo, J. L.
(
2016
) 
World Porifera database
. 
Available from
: 
http://www.marinespecies.org/porifera
/ porifera.php?p=taxdetails&amp;id= 
170877
(accessed 
11
October 
2016
)
</p>
         <p>Sollas, W.J.
(
1885
) 
A Classification of the Sponges
. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History
, Series 5

, 
16
(
95
), 395. https://doi.org/ 
10.1080/00222938509459901</p>
         <p>Stephens, J.
(
1915
) 
Atlantic Sponges collected by the Scottish National Antarctic Expedition
. 

Transactions of the Royal Society of 
Edinburgh
, 
50
(
2
), 
423–467
, pls. XXXVIII–XL.
</p>
         <p>Tamura, K.
, 
Stecher, G.
, 
Peterson, D.
, 
Filipski, A.
&amp; 
Kumar, S.
(
2013
) 
MEGA
6: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 6

. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
, 
30
, 
2725–2729
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst197</p>
         <p>Teske, P.R.
, 
Bader, S.
&amp; 
Golla, T.R.
(
2015
) 
Passive dispersal against an ocean current
. 
Marine Ecology Progress Series
, 
539
, 
153–163
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.3354/meps11516</p>
         <p>Thiele, J.
(
1905
) 
Die Kiesel-und Hornschwämme der Sammlung Plate
. 
Zoologische Jahrbücher Supplement6
(Fauna Chilensis III)

, 407–496, pls. 
27–33
.
</p>
         <p>Topsent, E.
(
1904
) 
Spongiaires des Açores
. 
Résultats des campagnes scientifiques accomplies par le Prince Albert I
, 
Monaco
, 
25
, 
1–280
, pls. 1–18, pp. 124.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.61852</p>
         <p>Uriz, M.J.
(
1984
b) 

Descripción de nuevas esponjas del litoral de 
Namibia
(sudoeste de África)

. 
Resultados Expediciones Científicas
, 
12
, 
107–116
.
</p>
         <p>Uriz, M.J.
(
1987
) 
Sponges from the South-West of Africa: description of species
. 
In
: 
Jones, W.C.
(Ed.), 
European Contributions to the Taxonomy of Sponges
. 

Sherkin 
Island
Marine Station, Sherkin 
Island
, County Cork, pp. 54–73

, pp. 
1– 140
.
</p>
         <p>Uriz, M.J.
(
1988
) 

Deep-water sponges from the continental shelf and slope off 
Namibia
(
Southwest Africa
): Classses Hexactinellida and Demospongia

. 
Monografías de Zoología Marina
, 
3
, 
9–157
.
</p>
         <p>Uriz, M.J.
(
1990
) 

Possible influence of trawl fishery on recent expansion in the range of 
Suberites tylobtusa
in the Southeast Atlantic

. 
In:Rützler, K.
(Ed.), 
New perspective in Sponge Biology
. 

Smithsonian Institute Press, 
Washington D.C
., 
309– 315
.
</p>
         <p>Wörheide, G.
(
2006
) 

Low variation in partial cytochrome oxidase subunit I (
COI
) mitochondrial sequences in the coralline demosponge 
Astrosclera willeyana
across the Indo-Pacific

. 
Marine Biology
, 
148
(
5
), 
907–912
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1007/s00227-005-0134-y</p>
         <p>Wörheide, G.
, 
Hooper, J.N.A.
&amp; 
Degnan, B.M.
(
2002
) 

Phylogeography of western Pacific 
Leucetta
‘ 
chagosensis
’ (Porifera: Calcarea) from ribosomal 
DNA
sequences: implications for population history and conservation of the Great Barrier Reef World Heritage Area (
Australia
)

. 
Molecular Ecology
, 
11
, 
1753–1768
.
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.1046/j.1365-294X.2002.01570.x</p>
         <p>Zea, S.
(
1987
) 
Esponjas del Caribe Colombiano
. 
Catálogo Cientifico, Bogotá
, 
286 pp.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Supporting Information</title>
         <p>TABLE
S1

. Main morphological characters of 
<tp:taxon-name>Suberites</tp:taxon-name>
species, including 
<tp:taxon-name>S. dandelenae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
specimens. (Microsoft Excel File)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Deposition of specimens</title>
         <p>Holotype
and 
paratype
specimens were deposited into the collection at the Iziko museum, 
Cape
Town. Voucher specimens are housed at DEA–O&amp;C in TS collection. Registration numbers were provided for the 
holotype
and two 
paratype
specimens from the collections manager, Dr Wayne Florence.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Sequences</title>
         <p>Sequences were deposited into GenBank.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
         <p>
All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files, except sequences, which are available from the 
NCBI
database.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
