<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1126/science.aag2737</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Eocene lantern fruits from Gondwanan Patagonia and the early origins of Solanaceae</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2017</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>PLANT EVOLUTION</p>
         <p>
Eocene lantern fruits from Gondwanan Patagonia and the early origins of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Peter Wilf
,
1
* 
<tp:taxon-name>Mónica R. Carvalho</tp:taxon-name>
,
2<tp:taxon-name>María A. Gandolfo</tp:taxon-name>
,
2N. Rubén Cúneo3
The nightshade family 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
holds exceptional economic and cultural importance. The early diversification of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
is thought to have occurred in South America during its separation from Gondwana, but the family’ s sparse fossil record provides few insights. We report 52.2-million-year-old lantern fruits from terminal-Gondwanan Patagonia, featuring highly inflated, five-lobed calyces, as a newly identified species of the derived, diverse New World genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
(e.g., groundcherries and tomatillos). The fossils are considerably older than corresponding molecular divergence dates and demonstrate an ancient history for the inflated calyx syndrome. The derived position of these early Eocene fossils shows that 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
were well diversified long before final Gondwanan breakup.
</p>
         <p>
he 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
, an angiosperm family of ~2500 species and 100 genera, include some of the world’ s most economically valuable and historically important crops such as potatoes, tobacco, tomatoes, eggplants, and peppers (
1
). The family is a source of pharmaceutical compounds and model organisms (e.g., tobacco, tomato, and petunia) and is known for its diverse reproductive structures (
2
– 
5
). One well-studied feature found in several 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
genera is the inflated calyx syndrome (ICS), in which complex signaling pathways cause the calyx to expand after fertilization and surround the fruit (
6
, 
7
), as in tomatillos and other lantern fruits.
</p>
         <p>
Despite increasing interest in the timing and biogeography of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
evolution (
8
), the family’ s poor fossil record provides little information. There are no valid previous records of fossil flowers, fruits, or leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
(
9
). Several Eocene-Pliocene isolated seeds are known, but except for some Oligocene and younger specimens assigned to the large 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanoideae</tp:taxon-name>
clade, they cannot be placed in derived groups (
10
). Molecular divergence estimates for the crown group of the family range from ~3 5 to 5 1 million years ago (Ma) (
11
) and, most recently, ~30 Ma, based on intensive taxon sampling and critical use of the available fossils for temporal calibrations (
10
). Recent estimates of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
divergence from 
<tp:taxon-name>Convolvulaceae</tp:taxon-name>
vary from ~49 to 67 Ma (
10
, 
12
, 
13
). The 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
are thought to have evolved and diversified on late- or post-Gondwanan South America (
11
, 
14
), which is the family’ s center of diversity today (
1
). Nevertheless, Miocene wood from Argentina (
15
) has been the only physical evidence of its South American history.
</p>
         <p>
We present here two compressed fossil lantern fruits (

) with angled, five-lobed, inflated calyces from terminal-Gondwanan South America that preserve diagnostic features of the derived, diverse (&gt;120 species) New World 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
. One fossil (

, A to C) is elongate and preserves a slender pedicel, one meridional primary vein per lobe, and four of the five lobe tips; the coalified remains of the berry fill the width of the calyx, revealed by the cleavage plane cutting just under part of the calyx surface. The second specimen (

, G and H) is more rounded, is basally well invaginated, and preserves five lobes; it has lost the pedicel and the berry. As in living 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
fruits, there are no corolla elements in these specimens; what appear superficially to be corolla components near the bases are instead compressed calycine vein remnants that project into the matrix behind the pedicel, similar to the preservation of some flattened herbarium specimens (

I). The two fossils have an identical venation pattern, and comparable variation in aspect ratio and calyx closure is found in several 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
species (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>P. angustifolia</tp:taxon-name>
) (

, D and I). Therefore, we consider the two fossil specimens to belong to the same newly identified species.
</p>
         <p>
We discovered these fossils at Laguna del Hunco in Chubut, Patagonia, Argentina, an early Eocene caldera-lake, fossil rainforest locality that represents the terminal phase of Gondwana and the global warmth of the early Eocene climatic optimum (
16
, 
17
). The assemblage is dominated by Gondwanic taxa with fossil and extant Austral- asian affinities (
17
– 
19
). There are few reliable previous records from the site of characteristically New World taxa, suggesting minimal linkage of late-Gondwanan and extant South American floras due to cooling and regional extinctions since the late Eocene (
19
). The minimum age of the fossils is 52.22 ± 0.22 Ma, based on three 40Ar-39Ar dates from closely associated tuffs and two paleomagnetic reversals from the local stratigraphic section (
16
, 
20
).
</p>
         <p>
Inflated, five-angled calyces and other features of fruiting 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
help make it one of the most recognizable angiosperm genera, although calyx expansion, by itself, is plesiomorphic within the family (
7
, 
21
, 
22
). However, several more detailed characters of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
fruiting calyces are noted for their systematic value (
21
, 
23
– 
25
). To assess the phylogenetic position of the fossils, we scored a 16-character morphological matrix (table S 
1
) for the fossils and for 109 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
species from 39 genera that have available genetic data (
10
, 
20
) and mostly have inflated or accrescent fruiting calyces (data table S 
1
). We used these morphological data first for a standard taxonomic treatment, then combined them with the species’ DNA sequences (
10
) to construct a matrix for total evidence analyses using maximum parsimony (MP) (

) and maximum likelihood (ML) (fig. S 
1
) (
20
). We also mapped the morphological characters individually on the strict consensus MP tree (figs. S 
2
to S 
17
). Limitations of the phylogenetic analysis included the specialized set of morphological characters appropriate for the fossil fruits (without complementary data preserved from other organs) and the proportionally small (~ 
10
%) and phylogenetically nonrandom selection of the species in (
10
) that had suitable calyx features for comparison (
20
).
</p>
         <p>Systematic paleontology:</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae Jussieu 1789</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Physalis
Linnaeus 1753
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis infinemundi
Wilf
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis infinemundi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. infinemundi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. angustifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. glutinosa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. infinemundi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. angustifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis infinemundi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Deprea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Nicandra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanum</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Withania</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Juanulloeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Alkekengi officinarum</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Iochrominae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Deprea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Nicandra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Deprea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis infinemundi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae in Gondwanan</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Eocene lantern fruits from Gondwanan Patagonia and the early origins of Solanaceae</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1126/science.aag2737</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFEF0A4FFF81FF91B239FF89FFEFE12C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aag2737</pub-id>
               <source>Science</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Physalis infinemundi
Wilf
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology:
Latin, 
in fine mundi
, “at the end of the world,” reflecting provenance from the last stages of the Gondwanan supercontinent and from Patagonia, popularly known as “the end of the world.”
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type material:<tp:material-citation>
repository 
Museo Paleontológico Egidio Feruglio, Trelew, Argentina
(MPEF-Pb); 
holotypus
hic designatus 
MPEF-Pb 6434a,b
(

, A to C) (lowercase letters indicate part and counterpart), from 
Laguna del Hunco, Huitrera Formation, early Eocene
, 
Chubut Province
, 
Argentina
, 
quarry LH13
(
16
), collected 
7 December 2002
(fig. 
S18
);
</tp:material-citation>
               <tp:material-citation>paratypeMPEF-Pb 6435a,b
(

, G and H), 
Laguna del Hunco quarry LH04
(
16
), 
21 November 2006
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description:
based on two dispersed, apparently mature, compressed fruiting calyces; only the holotype preserves berry and pedicel remains. Pedicel preserved length 18.8 mm, width 1 mm at inflection point of insertion. Calyx basally invaginated, highly inflated to completely surround the berry, five-lobed, angled, partly open at apex, length by width 2 5.2 mm by 1 3.2 mm (
1
. 
9
: 
1
) on holotype, 21.6 mm by 17.6 mm (ratio 1.2: 
1
) on paratype. Calyx lobes equally sized, sinuses angular and incised one-quarter to half the total calyx length, tips acute triangular. Venation with one robust primary meridional vein per lobe, terminating at lobe apex and alternating with secondary veins.
</p>
            <p>
1Department of Geosciences, Pennsylvania State University, University Park,PA 16802, USA. 2L. H. Bailey Hortorium, Plant Biology Section, School of Integrative Plant 
Science
, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853,USA. 3Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas (CONICET), Museo PaleontolÓgico Egidio Feruglio,9100 Trelew, Chubut, Argentina. *Corresponding author. Email: pwilf@psu.edu
</p>
            <p>
Secondary veins arising near the base, visually distinct from the primaries and other vein orders, and bifurcating close to the lobe sinuses (

C). Intersecondary veins arising near the base, visually distinct from secondaries and tertiaries, dichotomizing into the random, irregular reticulum of tertiary through at least quinternary veins that fill most of the vein field. Some basal veins compressed into partial detachment from the calyx body, the remnants visible against the matrix. Berry round, flattened and coalified from fossilization, filling the full width of the calyx and appearing by surface relief to extend apically almost to the lobe sinuses; seeds not preserved.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>
The fossils preserve several features that, together, are diagnostic of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
clade of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
(
20
, 
21
, 
23
, 
25
). These include the highly inflated, lantern-shaped, pedicellate, five-parted, angled, regular calyces covering a large, fleshy berry, along with the combination of (i) invaginated base, (ii) robust primary veins that terminate in the lobe tips (not the lobe sinuses), and (iii) secondary veins that fork before the sinus. Nonphysaline species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
with ICS lack some or all of these three features (e.g., those in 
<tp:taxon-name>Deprea</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Nicandra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Withania</tp:taxon-name>
, and the 
<tp:taxon-name>Juanulloeae</tp:taxon-name>
clade) (figs. S 
5
, S 
11
, and S 
13
) (
23
, 
24
). Within 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
, there are several problematic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
and other genera that diverge below the core 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
clade (

) (equivalent to 
P.
subgenus 
Rydbergis
) of relatively homogeneous species (
13
, 
23
– 
25
). Among these taxa, 
<tp:taxon-name>Alkekengi officinarum</tp:taxon-name>
calyces are the most similar to the fossils, but they have a much larger size, consistently rounded shape, and nearly closed apex. Otherwise, each of these basal physaline species structurally differs from the fossils and core 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
(
20
, 
24
, 
25
) (figs. S 
2
to S 
17
). All these observations highlight the close relationship of the fossils with core 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
Both the MP and ML results (

and fig. S 
1
) support the fossils’ affinity with 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
. The newly identified species is placed in 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
with strong support in both MP and ML analyses and at a basal polytomy of (MP, weak support) or within (ML, strong support) the crown of core 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
. Both the MP and ML topologies are generally consistent with and reproduced most major clades from (
10
), with robust support of the critical 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
clade. However, each tree recovered the closely related (
10
) 
<tp:taxon-name>Iochrominae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Deprea</tp:taxon-name>
as collapsed into a single clade that also included 
<tp:taxon-name>Nicandra</tp:taxon-name>
, which has 
<tp:taxon-name>Deprea</tp:taxon-name>
-like calyx morphology but is not closely related to that genus. Nevertheless, the overall agreement of the MP and ML tree topologies with (
10
) is notable in light of the limitations of the analysis. Notably, no species from outside 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
were misplaced among 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
, and no 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
species were misplaced into other clades. Considering the unknown additional organs of this extinct species, the incomplete knowledge of calyx morphology in extant 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
, and problematic resolution among extant basal species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
(
13
, 
25
), we suggest that the newly identified species can be used, conservatively, to constrain the divergence of 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
to a minimum of 52.2 Ma.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Physalis infinemundi</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
represents a derived lineage of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae in Gondwanan</tp:taxon-name>
South America at 52.2 Ma, pushing back considerably the evolutionary timing of the family. Compared with recent molecular divergence estimates (
10
), these fossils are considerably older than the ~30 Ma crown for the entire 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family as well as the ~11 Ma divergence of 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
. A second recent study similarly placed the 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalinae</tp:taxon-name>
divergence at only ~9 Ma (
13
).
</p>
            <p>
Our results reinforce the emerging pattern wherein numerous fossil plant taxa from Gondwanan Patagonia and Antarctica are substantially older than their corresponding molecular dates (
26
, 
27
), demonstrating Gondwanan history for groups conjectured to have post-Gondwanan origins under entirely different paleogeographic and paleoclimatic scenarios. Likewise, the derived position of the newly identified fossil species shows that the origins and diversification of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
must have taken place at a much earlier time than previously thought, considerably before final Gondwanan breakup. Other regions of Gondwana are also likely to have played prominent roles in 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
evolution, especially Antarctica, which has produced other important asterid fossils (
27
). Moreover, the newly identified fossils directly help to resolve temporal inconsistencies between the evolutionary timing of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solanaceae</tp:taxon-name>
and its herbivores and mutualists (
28
). The large fossil berry strongly implicates trophic associations with animals, as seen in extant 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
(
29
). Today, 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
inhabits South, Central, and North America, and Mexico is its center of diversity (
2
). Thus, the fossils establish a rare link to extant New World floras from late-Gondwanan Patagonian assemblages, whose living relatives are mostly concentrated in the Old World tropics and subtropics.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p>
The discovery of 52.2-Ma fossil inflated calyces demonstrates an ancient history for ICS and implies that the Eocene world was already populated with derived solanaceous reproductive structures. The potential adaptive functions of the inflated calyx are scarcely discussed in the literature (
30
), but the lakeside rainforest paleoenvironment led us to consider flotation dispersal and protective drying for the berry. Simple kitchen-sink and stream experiments on several 
<tp:taxon-name>Physalis</tp:taxon-name>
species confirmed that intact calyces hold stable air pockets around the berry, enabling flotation for several days in water and preventing wetting of the berry during rains. These insights suggest potential origins of ICS in ancient humid, riparian environments.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>REFERENCES AND NOTES</title>
         <p>
1. 

W. G. D 
’
Arcy

, in 
Solanaceae Ill
: 
Taxonomy, Chemistry, Evolution, J. G. Hawkes, R. N. Lester, M. Nee, N. Estrada, Eds
. (
Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, UK
, 
1991
), pp. 

75 
–
137

.
</p>
         <p>2
. 
A. T. Hunziker
, 
The Genera of Solanaceae
(A. R. G. Gantner Verlag K.-G., Ruggell, Lichtenstein

, 
2001
).
</p>
         <p>3
. 
S. Knapp
, 
Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B365
, 

449 
–
460

(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>4
. 
G. A. GarzÓn-Martínez
, 
Z. I. Zhu
, 
D. Landsman
, 
L. S. Barrero
, 
L. Mariño-Ramírez
, 
BMC Genomics13
, 
151
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
5. 
K. Kindscheret al
., 
Econ. Bot.66
, 

298 
–
310

(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>6
. 
C. He
, 
H. Saedler
, 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.102
, 5 7 7 

9 
–
5784

(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>7
. 
J. Y. Hu
, 
H. Saedler
, 
Mol. Biol. Evol.24
, 

2443 
–
2453

(
2007
).
</p>
         <p>8
. 
S. R. Manchester
, 
F. Grímsson
, 
R. Zetter
, 
Ann. Mo. Bot. Gard.100
, 

329 
–
363

(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>9
. 
M. Millán
, 
W. Crepet
, 
Bot. Rev.80
, 7 

3 
–
106

(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>10
. 
T. Särkinen
, 
L. Bohs
, 
R. G. Olmstead
, 
S. Knapp
, 
BMC Evol
. 
Biol
.
13
, 
214
(
2013
).
</p>
         <p>11
. 
R. G. Olmstead
, 
Bot. J. Linn. Soc.171
, 
8
0 
–
102 (
2013
).
</p>
         <p>12
. 
S. MagallÓn
, 
S. GÓmez-Acevedo
, 
L. L. Sánchez-Reyes
, 
T. Hernández-Hernández
, 
New Phytol
.
207
, 

437 
–
453

(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>13
. 
M. P. Zamora-Tavares
, 
M. Martínez
, 
S. MagallÓn
, 
L. Guzmán-Dávalos
, 
O. Vargas-Ponce
, 
Mol. Phyl. Evol.100
, 

41 
–
50

(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
14. 
R. G. Olmsteadet al
., 
Taxon57
, 

1159 
–
1181

(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>15
. 
M. J. Franco
, 
M. Brea
, 
Ameghiniana45
, 

699 
–
717

(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
16. 
P. Wilfet al
., 
Science300
, 

122 
–
125

(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
17. 
P. Wilf
, 
N. R. Cúneo
, 
I. H. Escapa
, 
D. Pol
, 
M. O. Woodburne
, 
Annu. Rev. Earth Planet
. 
Sci
.
41
, 

561 
–
603

(
2013
)

.
</p>
         <p>
18. 
M. A. Gandolfoet al
.

, 
PLOS ONE6
, e 
21084
(
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
19. 
R. M. Kooymanet al
.

, 
Am. J. Bot.101
, 

2121 
–
2135

(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>20. Materials and methods are available as supplementary materials.</p>
         <p>21
. 
B. Axelius
, 
Am. J. Bot.83
, 

118 
–
124

(
1996
).
</p>
         <p>
22. 
J. E. Averett
, 

W. G. D 
’
Arcy

, 
Phytologia80
, 

273 
–
275

(
1996
).
</p>
         <p>23
. 
E. Estrada
, 
M. Martínez
, in 
Solanaceae IV: Advances in Biology and Utilization
, 
M. Nee
, 
D. E. Symon
, 
R. N. Lester
, 
J. P. Jessop
, Eds. (
Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, UK
, 
1999
), pp. 

139 
–
159

.
</p>
         <p>24
. 
G. E. Barboza
, 
Kurtziana28
, 6 

9 
–
79

(
2000
).
</p>
         <p>25
. 
M. Whitson
, 
P. S. Manos
, 
Syst. Bot.30
, 

216 
–
230

(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>26
. 
P. Wilf
, 
I. H. Escapa
, 
New Phytol
.
207
, 

283 
–
290

(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
27. 
V. D. Barredaet al
., 
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.112
, 

10989 
–
10994

(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>28
. 
I. J. GarzÓn-Orduña
, 
K. L. Silva-Brandão
, 
K. R. Willmott
, 
A. V. L. Freitas
, 
A. V. Z. Brower
, 
Syst. Biol.64
, 

752 
–
767

(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>29
. 
M. F. Willson
, 
Oikos67
, 

159 
–
176

(
1993
).
</p>
         <p>30
. 
J. Zhang
, 
Y. Tian
, 
L. Wang
, 
C. He
, 
J. Syst
. 
Evol
.
48
, 9 

4 
–
101

(
2010
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
         <p>This work was supported by NSF grants DEB-1556666 and DEB-1556136, National Geographic Society grant 7337-02, and the David and Lucile Packard Foundation. We thank M. Donovan, I. Escapa, E. Hermsen, K. Johnson, P. Puerta, L. Reiner,</p>
         <p>A. Reznicek, E. Ruigomez, M. Smith, T. Su, J. Svitko, E. Wilf, the Nahueltripay family, and many others for field and laboratory assistance; S. Knapp and R. Olmstead for helpful discussions; and two anonymous reviewers for very useful comments. The fossil specimens are curated at Museo PaleontolÓgico Egidio Feruglio, Trelew, Argentina. The morphological matrix developed in this paper is tabulated in the supplementary materials.</p>
      </sec>
      <p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</p>
      <p>www.sciencemag.org/content/355/6320/71/suppl/DC1 Materials and Methods Figs. S1 to S18</p>
      <p>Table S1</p>
      <p>Database S1</p>
      <p>
References (
31–75
)
</p>
      <p>1 June 2016; resubmitted 15 October 2016 Accepted 18 November 2016</p>
      <p>10.1126/science.aag2737</p>
   </body>
</article>
