<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <kwd-group>
         <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
            <tp:taxon-name>Takiyaella sexguttata ( Chiamolera &amp; Cavichioli, 2003 )</tp:taxon-name>
         </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Takiyaella sexguttata Gonçalves &amp; Domahovski 2021, gen. et comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5579014</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B087EA791CFFE4FED9FA7A0E7AFD54</uri>
         <article-title>A new genus and five new species of Neocoelidiinae leafhoppers from Brazil (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadellidae) with a key to males</article-title>
         <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.775.1545</pub-id>
         <issn>2118-9773</issn>
         <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Takiyaella sexguttata
(
Chiamolera &amp; Cavichioli, 2003
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      <tp:taxon-status>gen. et comb. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 10–11
, 
12K–M
, 
13
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Xenocoelidia sexguttata
Chiamolera &amp; Cavichioli, 2003: 199
</tp:taxon-name>

: figs 1–7.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Male pygofer (
Fig. 10D
) expanded apically, dorsal margin with small rounded lobe, caudal margin with ventral rounded lobe. Aedeagus (
Fig. 10I–K
) with atrial processes slender, curved dorsally, not following the curvature of shaft; shaft expanded apically, spatulate, with small lateral spiniform projections; anal tube (
Fig. 10L
) with basiventral process triangular.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Rio de Janeiro
, 
Silva Jardim
; 

Mar. 1974

; 
F.M. Oliveira
leg.; 
DZUP-082927
; 
DZUP
.
</tp:material-citation>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
– 

Rio de Janeiro

• 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
DZUP-492337
; 
DZUP
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 

VIII.1975

; 
DZUP-492336
; 
DZUP
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS (mm). 
Holotype
(
♂
): total length 6.1. 
Paratypes
(
♂
): 6.1 (n = 1); (
♀
) 6.7 (n = 1). COLORATION. Pale yellow (
Fig. 12K–L
). Forewing (
Fig. 12K–L
) translucent, with three dark maculae on claval comissure: first, between base and second anal vein; second, between anal veins and third on apex of clavus and extending to brachial cell.
</p>
      <p>HEAD AND THORAX. External morphological characters as in generic description.</p>
      <p>
MALE TERMINALIA. Pygofer, in lateral view (
Fig. 10D
), 1.7 × as long as maximum height, expanded apically; dorsal margin concave medially with small preapical rounded lobe; caudal margin truncated with small ventral rounded lobe; ventral tooth slightly rounded; apical portion with inner integument thickening. Subgenital plate, in lateral view (
Fig. 10E
), subtriangular, 3.6 × as long as maximum height, narrowing at apical fourth; in ventral view (
Fig. 10F
), subrhomboid, lateral margins converging towards apex; ventral surface with pair of uniseriate rows of 4–5 macrosetae; apex acutely rounded. Connective (
Fig. 10G
) V-shaped, total length approximately ⅔ length of style; stem short. Style (
Fig. 10G–H
) with dorsal margin of apodeme rounded; apophysis elongated and robust. Aedeagus (
Fig. 10I–K
) with pair of atrial processes curved dorsally, with ⅓ length of shaft, anterior to curvature of shaft and not following its curvature broad at base and tapering towards apex; shaft slightly flattened dorsoventrally, apical portion expanded laterally, spatulate, lateral margins with some small spiniform projections. Anal tube (
Fig. 10L
) with sternite X long and tubular, basal portion with basiventral process triangular, with few denticles.
</p>
      <p>
FEMALE TERMINALIA. Sternite VII (
Fig. 11A
) slightly wider than long; lateral margins constricted medially; posterior margin slightly emarginated. First valvula of ovipositor (
Fig. 11D
) with dorsal sculptured area areolate-strigate. Other characters as in generic description.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Xenocoelidia sexguttata
</tp:taxon-name>
was described by 
Chiamolera &amp; Cavichioli (2003)
based on 
two males
and 
one female
from 
Rio de Janeiro
, 
Brazil
. Our study of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
X. sexguttata
</tp:taxon-name>
types
(
Figs 10–11
, 
12K–L
) indicated the following morphological incongruities with the other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenocoelidia
</tp:taxon-name>
: (1) male pygofer with caudal margin with small lobe without robust setae (
Fig. 10D
), whereas in other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenocoelidia
</tp:taxon-name>
the caudal margin of pygofer is broadly rounded bearing several small and robust setae; (2) subgenital plates fused to each other in the basal two-thirds, with only the apical third being free (
Fig. 10F
), while in other species the subgenital plates are fused only at base, being free for most of its length; (3) connective with stem short (
Fig. 10G
), while in other species the connective is Y-shaped, with stem long; (4) style with preapical lobe moderately developed and slightly produced posterad (
Fig. 10H
), whereas other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenocoelidia
</tp:taxon-name>
have the preapical lobe strongly developed and expanded laterally; and (5) aedeagus with shaft moderately long, wider at base, bearing atrial processes (
Fig. 10I
), while in other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenocoelidia
</tp:taxon-name>
the aedeagus lacks atrial process, and the aedeagal shaft is very long and narrow in almost all its length. Based on these differences, we propose the transfer of 
<tp:taxon-name>
X
. 
sexguttata
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Takiyaella
</tp:taxon-name>
gen nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
