<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Zootaxa</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.2946.1.12</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Complementary Approaches to Systematic Ichthyology</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>08</day>
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2011</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Scorpaeniformes</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ekemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Teleostei, Blennioidei</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Chaenopsidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Acanthemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ekemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hemiemblemaria simulus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ekemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Acanthemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ekemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hemiemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cetomimidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Mirapinnidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Megalomycteridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Complementary Approaches to Systematic Ichthyology

*
</p>
         <p>
PHILIP A. HASTINGS
</p>
         <p>

Professor and Curator of Marine Vertebrates, Marine Biology Research Division, Scripps Institution of Oceanography, University of 
California
San Diego, 9500 Gilman Drive, La Jolla CA 92093-0208, 
U.S.A.
E-mail: phastings@ucsd.edu

</p>
         <p>
* 
In
: Carvalho, M.R. de &amp; Craig, M.T. (Eds) (2007) Morphological and Molecular Approaches to the Phylogeny of Fishes: Integration or Conflict?. 
Zootaxa
, 2946, 
1
–142.
</p>
         <p>
All systematists should be just as comfortable examining and comparing museum specimens as they are at examining and comparing DNA sequences; ...... the future will favor ..... researchers who are not afraid to choose the best approach for any given phylogenetic puzzle – whether it means studying morphological or molecular variation, or both.
— 

, p. 15.
</p>
         <p>
The molecular revolution in phylogenetic biology and its widespread application to fishes has in some ways complicated the task of teaching my craft of ichthyology. Beginning students know nothing of the history of fish classifications, how they were created, how they have changed over the years or how and why they continue to change. On the first day of class I typically bring in the four editions of Joe Nelson’s classic 
Fishes of the World
(

, 

, 

, 

) to show students that systematic ichthyology is a vibrant and dynamic science and that these are exciting times. Then I add that the latest of these encyclopedias of our current knowledge has for the most part not incorporated the more radical changes in our understanding of fish relationships suggested by many recent analyses of molecular data. It is not difficult to imagine students’ frustration when one moment I tell them that the 
<tp:taxon-name>Scorpaeniformes</tp:taxon-name>
is a long-recognized lineage of fishes, show them the distinctive morphological features shared by the group, then go on to say that the group is likely not monophyletic and that the character homologies upon which traditional diagnoses of the group were based are homoplasious (

, 

; 

; 

). That realization may be exciting to some but must be nothing short of maddening to a novice. But in time, if my students and I do our jobs well, they too will learn to relish the vibrant science that systematic ichthyology continues to be.
</p>
         <p>
It is common knowledge that the basis of virtually all phylogenetic hypotheses is morphology (

; 

) and that the exponential growth in molecular phylogenies relies on this foundation. The tension between practitioners of morphological and molecular methods of phylogenetic analysis has been thoroughly discussed and debated (e.g., 

; 

; 

) and in the minds of many, a consensus has been reached. Most have achieved a realization that while neither approach provides infallible proof of relationships, they are complementary, having their own strengths and weaknesses, but with much to contribute to one another (

).
</p>
         <p>

remain unconvinced and seemingly have overlooked many of the contributions of molecular data. Rather they see a crisis in systematic biology because hypotheses of relationships based on molecular data are often not grounded in thorough (or even cursory) morphological analyses and clades lacking morphological synapomorphies are routinely proposed. Rather than viewing this lack of morphological character support for hypothesized clades as a crisis, I see it as a growing pain of the science. In time, if we continue to train and adequately support students of morphology (an uncertain prospect to be sure), the molecular hypotheses will for the most part have their day in the court of morphology.
</p>
         <p>
Rather than critique the many points raised by 

, a task left to others in this volume, I wish to present my own views, similar to those of 

, that morphological and molecular data should be viewed as complementary, each providing potentially novel insights, and that practitioners of both should be knowledgeable of the methods and welcome the results of the other. Coming as I do from a morphologist’s background, I illustrate two examples in which molecular data can inform morphology, namely that molecular analyses can guide 
a posteriori
examination of morphology, renewing the search for morphological synapomorphies, and genetic data can relatively easily identify “cryptic” variation that has been overlooked by morphologists.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Novel relationships suggested by molecular data

</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Ekemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
is a curious genus of only three species of tube blennies (
<tp:taxon-name>Teleostei, Blennioidei</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Chaenopsidae</tp:taxon-name>
). John Stephens, who described the genus in 1963, hypothesized its relationships with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acanthemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
(1963, 1970), an hypothesis later supported by three morphological synapomorphies (

, 

). However, recent phylogenetic analysis of one mitochrondial and four nuclear genes totaling 3,544 base pairs, surprisingly placed 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ekemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
with the wrasse blenny, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hemiemblemaria simulus
</tp:taxon-name>
, with strong statistical support in Bayesian, maximum likelihood and parsimony analyses (Lin, 2009; 

). Inclusion of a data matrix of 148 morphological characters, including the three putative synapomorphies of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ekemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acanthemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
, in a “total evidence” analysis did not change the result. The molecular signal out-weighed the signal in the morphological data.
</p>
         <p>
This new and unanticipated hypothesis of relationships stimulated a search for corroborating morphological support. Subsequent examination revealed two novel morphological synapomorphies for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ekemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hemiemblemaria
</tp:taxon-name>
and two others that were in the original morphological data set but assumed to be homoplasious (

. In this case, the detailed and highly sophisticated statistical analyses of molecular data stimulated a successful search for supporting morphological evidence (synapomorphies).
</p>
         <p>
Other, more dramatic examples of unanticipated relationships for which molecular data have provided early clues could be cited. One of the most extraordinary is the recent demonstration that three families of fishes, the whalefishes (
<tp:taxon-name>Cetomimidae</tp:taxon-name>
), hairyfishes and tapetails (
<tp:taxon-name>Mirapinnidae</tp:taxon-name>
) and bignose fishes (
<tp:taxon-name>Megalomycteridae</tp:taxon-name>
) are in fact different life history stages of a single lineage (

). This hypothesis had been suggested in part by a few early morphological systematists, but more recently by ecological data (

) and by the sequence similarity of their mitochondrial genomes (

). This change in our understanding of relationships of these extraordinary fishes, signaled by molecular data, has since been well-supported by detailed morphological analyses, enriching the science of ichthyology.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Cryptic diversity

</title>
         <p>
A second innovative role that molecular data play is the discovery of so-called “cryptic” diversity, variation within presumed species that has been overlooked or unappreciated by morphologists. Many examples could be cited from guitarfishes (Sandoval-Castillo et al., 2004) to bonefishes (

) to blennies (

). Most such hypotheses of cryptic diversity have not been adequately evaluated using traditional morphological methods. A notable exception is a recent study (

) that carefully documented morphological variation in a lineage of shiners. This work was stimulated by variation identified by molecular markers that turned out to be mirrored by congruent morphological variation. It is doubtful that the detailed and painstaking morphological analyses would have been undertaken had not the molecular data been available.
</p>
         <p>Rather than fearing that our science is taking a turn for the worse and bemoaning the inevitable march of molecular biology into systematic biology, I suggest that all systematists embrace new analytical methods and new data sets to inform and guide their own research while remaining grounded in the scientific tradition that they know best. I too am sometimes frustrated when envisioning, studying and teaching about clades without known morphological synapomorphies. But I am also excited by the fresh hypotheses and refinements of long-standing ideas of relationships that molecular data inevitably bring. Our science will be best served when we fully embrace new data sources and refined analytical methods and incorporate them with more traditional methods to gain an ever-clearer picture of the tree of life.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References

</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Berendzen, P.B.
, 
Olson, W.M.
&amp; 
Barron, S.M.
(
2009
) 

The utility of molecular hypotheses for uncovering morphological diversity in the 
Notropis rubellus
species complex (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae)

. 

Copeia

, 
2009
, 
661–673
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hastings, P.A.
(
1990
) 

Phylogenetic relationships of tube blennies of the genus 
Acanthemblemaria
(Pisces, Blennioidei)

. 

Bulletin of Marine Science

, 
47
, 
725–738
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hastings, P.A.
(
1992
) 

Ekemblemaria lira
, a new blennioid fish from Ecuador, with comments on sexual dimorphism and relationships in 
Ekemblemaria
(Teleostei, Chaenopsidae)

. 

Copeia

, 
1992
, 
769–776
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hillis, D.M.
&amp; 
Weins, J.J.
(
2000
) 
Molecules versus morphology in systematics. Conflicts, artifacts, and misconceptions
. 
In
: 
Weins, J.J.
(ed). 

Phylogenetic Analysis of Morphological Data

. 
Smithsonian Institution Press. Washington D.C
., pp. 
1–19
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Imamura, H.
&amp; 
Shinohara, G.
(
1997
) 
Phylogenetic studies of the order Scorpaeniformes (Pisces: Acanthopterygii): progress, present condition and problems
. 

Bulletin of the National Science Museum, Tokyo
, Series A

, 
24
, 
185–212
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Imamura, H.
&amp; 
Shinohara, G.
(
1998
) 
Scorpaeniform fish phylogeny: an overview
. 

Bulletin of the National Science Museum (Tokyo)

, 
24
, 
185–212
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Jenner, R.A.
(
2004
) 
Accepting partnership by submission? Morphological phylogenetics in a molecular millennium
. 

Systematic Biology

, 
53
, 
333–342
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Johnson, G.D.
, 
Paxton, J.R.
, 
Sutton, T.T.
, 
Satoh, T.P.
, 
Sado, T.
, 
Nishida, M.
&amp; 
Miya, M.
(
2009
) 
Deep-sea mystery solved: astonishing larval transformations and extreme sexual dimorphism unite three fish families
. 

Biology Letters. Evolutionary Biology

, 
5
, 
235–239
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lin, H.-C.
(
2009
) 

Evolution of the Suborder Blennioidei: Phylogeny and Phylogeography of a Shallow Water Fish Clade
.

Unpublished PhD Dissertation, 
University of California San Diego
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lin, H.-C.
&amp; 
Hastings, P.A.
(
2011
) 
Evolution of a Neotropical marine fish lineage (Subfamily Chaenopsinae, Suborder Blennioidei) based on phylogenetic analysis of combined molecular and morphological data
. 

Molecular Phylogenetics &amp; Evolution
(2011)

, 
doi:10.1016/j.ympev.2011.04.018
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lin, H.-C.
, 
Sanchez-Ortiz, C.
&amp; 
Hastings, P.A.
(
2009
) 
Colour variation is incongruent with mitochondrial lineages: Cryptic speciation and subsequent diversification in a Gulf of California reef fish (Teleostei: Blennioidei)
. 

Molecular Ecology

, 
18
, 
2476–2488
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Miya, M.
, 
Takeshima, H.
, 
Endo, H.
, 
Ishiguro, N.B.
, 
Inoue, J.G.
, 
Mukai, T.
, 
Satoh, T.P.
, 
Yamaguchi, M.
, 
Kawaguchi, A.
, 
Mabuchi, K.
, 
Shirai, S.M.
&amp; 
Nishida, M.
(
2003
) 
Major patterns of higher teleostean phylogenies: a new perspective based on 100 complete mitochondrial DNA sequences
. 

Molecular Phylogenetics &amp; Evolution

, 
26
, 
121–138
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mooi, R.
&amp; 
Gill, A.
(
2010
) 
Phylogenies without synapomorphies – a crisis in fish systematics: Time to show some character
. 

Zootaxa

, 
2450
, 
26–40
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nelson, J.S.
(
1976
) 

Fishes of the World
.

Wiley-Interscience, New York
. 
416 pp.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nelson, J.S.
(
1984
) 

Fishes of the World
.


John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York, 2 
nd
edition

. 
523 pp.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nelson, J.S.
(
1994
) 

Fishes of the World

. 

John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. New York, 3 
rd
edition

. 
600 pp.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nelson, J.S.
(
2006
) 

Fishes of the World
.


John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc. New York, 4 
th
edition

. 
601 pp.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Patterson, C.
(Ed). (
1987
) 

Molecules and Morphology in Evolution: Conflict or Compromise?
Cambridge University Press

, 
Cambridge
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Patterson, C.
, 
Williams, D.M.
&amp; 
Humphries, C.J.
(
1993
) 
Congruence between molecular and morphological phylogenies
. 

Annual Review of Ecology &amp; Systematics

24
, 
153–188
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pfeiler, E.
, 
Bitler, B.G.
, 
Ulloa, R.
, 
van der Heiden, A.M.
&amp; 
Hastings, P.A.
(
2008
) 

Molecular identification of the bonefish 
Albula esuncula
(Albuliformes: Albulidae) from the Tropical Eastern Pacific, with comments on distribution and morphology

. 

Copeia

, 
2008
, 
763–770
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sandoval-Castillo, 
Rocha-Olivares, A.
, 
Villavicencio-Garayzar, C.
&amp; 
Balart, E.
(
2004
) 
Cryptic isolation of Gulf of California shovelnose guitarfish evidenced by mitochondrial DNA
. 

Marine Biology

, 
145
, 
983–988
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Scottland, R.W.
, 
Olmstead, R.G.
&amp; 
Bennett, J.R.
(
2003
) 
Phylogeny reconstruction; the role of morphology
. 

Systematic Biology

, 
52
, 
539–548
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shinohara, G.
&amp; 
Imamura, H.
(
2007
) 
Revisiting recent phylogenetic studies of "Scorpaeniformes
". 

Ichthyological Research

, 
54
, 
92–99
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Smith, W.L.
&amp; 
Wheeler, W.C.
(
2004
) 
Polyphyly of the mail-cheeked fishes (Teleostei: Scorpaeniformes): evidence from mitochondrial and nuclear sequence data
. 

Molecular Phylogenetics &amp; Evolution

, 
32
, 
627–646
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stephens, J.S.
(
1963
) 
A revised classification of the blennioid fishes of the American family Chaenopsidae
. 

University of California Publications in Zoology

, 
68
, 
1–165
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Stephens, J.S.
(
1970
) 
Seven new chaenopsid blennies from the western Atlantic
. 

Copeia

, 
1970
, 
280–309
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Weins, J.J.
(
2004
) 
The role of morphological data in phylogeny reconstruction
. 

Systematic Biology

, 
53
, 
653–661
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
