<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112414</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Phenolics from Archidendron clypearia (Jack) I.C.Nielsen protect SH-SY5Y cells against H O -induced oxidative stress</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>08</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Chinese Materia Medica</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Chinese</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen Leguminosae
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen. Their
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>A. clypearia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Chinese Materia Medica</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. clypearia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. clypearia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen (Leguminosae)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
A. clypearia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Archidendron clypearia (Jack) I.C.Nielsen.</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Phenolics from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen
</tp:taxon-name>
protect SH-SY5Y cells against H 
2
O 
2
-induced oxidative stress

</p>
         <p>
Yu-Xi Wang
a,1
, Feng-Ying Han
a,1
, Zhi-Kang Duan
a
, Ye Chang
a
, Bin Lin
b
, Xiao-Bo Wang
c
,
</p>
         <p>
Xiao-Xiao Huang 

a,c, 
∗∗
, Guo-Dong Yao

a, 
∗∗∗
, Shao-Jiang Song

a, 
∗
</p>
         <p>
a

Key Laboratory of Computational 
Chemistry-Based Natural Antitumor Drug

Research

&amp; 

Development
, 
School of Traditional
<tp:taxon-name>Chinese Materia Medica</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Liaoning province
,
</p>
         <p>
People's Republic of China

</p>
         <p>
b
School of Pharmaceutical Engineering
, Shenyang Pharmaceutical University, Shenyang, 110016



, 

People's Republic of China

</p>
         <p>
c
<tp:taxon-name>Chinese</tp:taxon-name>
People's Liberation Army Logistics Support Force No. 967 Hospital, Dalian, 116021, 
People's Republic of China

</p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:

</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen Leguminosae
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Phenolics</p>
         <p>Neuroprotective activity</p>
         <p>Apoptosis</p>
         <p>Oxidative stress</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
Five undescribed phenolics named pithecellobiumin C-G, along with thirteen known ones were isolated from the twigs and leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen. Their
</tp:taxon-name>
structures were elucidated based on comprehensive spectroscopic analyses, combined with computer-assisted structure elucidation software (ACD/ Structure Elucidator) and gauge-independent atomic orbitals (GIAO) NMR chemical shift calculations. The absolute configurations were determined by comparison of experimental and calculated specific rotation and ECD curves. These compounds were tested for their neuroprotective activities against H 
2
O 
2
-induced injury in human neuroblastoma SH-SY5Y cells by MTT assay. Pithecellobiumin C-E exhibited noticeable neuroprotective effect. Further pharmacological study demonstrated that they could prevent cell death through inhibiting the apoptosis induction. Flow cytometry assays also proved that these compounds could attenuate reactive oxygen species (ROS) level and mitochondrial dysfunction in SH-SY5Y cells.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction

</title>
         <p>
Phenolics exist widely in nature as natural products, and they possess multiple biological properties (

). As one of the most typical botanic phenolics, gallic acid is commonly used in the esterification reaction of many bioactive compounds (

). The galloylation of phenolics could significantly change their biological activities. These compounds were usually reported to exhibit better activity compared with the parent molecule. (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen.
</tp:taxon-name>
is a tree widely distributed in many areas of tropical Asia (

). Systematic phytochemical studies led to the discovery of diverse structures including polyphenols, flavonoids, lignans and terpenoids (

; 

, 2018). Among them, various 
types
of galloyl substituted phenolics are the most characteristic constituents of this plant, and some of them have been reported with high potential for neurodegenerative treatments (

; 

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Oxidative stress has been generally considered as one of the major causes of the neurodegenerative diseases (

; 

). Excessive free radicals in the body can damage various biomolecules including protein, lipid and nucleic acids, leading to cellular function disorder and apoptosis (

). Therefore, it is of utmost importance to explore anti-oxidative candidates to quench the elevated ROS and alleviate the symptoms of neurodegeneration conditions. As part of a continuous investigation of the twigs and leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>A. clypearia</tp:taxon-name>
, five undescribed galloylated phenolics (
1–5
) together with thirteen known ones (
6–18
) were isolated and identified. All isolates were tested for their protective effects to reverse H 
2
O 
2
-induced damage in human neuroblastoma SH-SY5Y cells. In addition, the possible mechanism of the top three potent compounds (
1–3
) were also investigated in this study.
</p>
         <p>
∗
Corresponding author.
</p>
         <p>
∗∗
Corresponding author. Key Laboratory of Computational Chemistry-Based Natural Antitumor Drug Research &amp; Development, School of Traditional 
<tp:taxon-name>Chinese Materia Medica</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Liaoning province
, 
People's Republic of China
.
</p>
         <p>
∗∗∗
Corresponding author.
</p>
         <p>
E-mail addresses:
xiaoxiao270@163.com (X.-X. Huang), guodong_yao@126.com (G.-D. Yao), songsj99@163.com (S.-J. Song).
</p>
         <p>
1
These author contributed equally.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Compounds 
1
and 
3–5
were recorded in DMSO‑ 
d
. 
2
was recorded in
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
6
methanol- 
d
4
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.1. Structure elucidation of compounds 1–5

</title>
         <p>
Compound 
1
, a deep yellow gum, possessed the molecular formula C 
17
H 
16
O 
8
, as determined by a HRESIMS ion at 
m/z
349.0918 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
17
H 
17
O 
8
, 349.0918), corresponding to 10 degrees of unsaturation. In the 
1
H NMR spectrum of 
1
, two sets of aromatic resonances were observed at 
δ
Η
6.20 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.2 Hz, H-6), 
δ
H
6.13 (1H, d, 
J
= 2.2 Hz, H-8) and 
δ
H
7.05 (2H, s, H-3′, H-7′) indicating an asymmetry 4,5,7,9-tetrasubstituted and a symmetrical 2′,4′,5′,6′-tetrasubstituted aromatic ring system, respectively. The resonances at 
δ
H
1.97 (1H, m, H-3a), 
δ
H
1.81 (1H, m, H-3b) and 
δ
H
2.55 (1H, m, H-4a), 
δ
H
2.43 (1H, m, H-4b) exhibited the existence of two methylene groups. Moreover, a methoxy groups at 
δ
H
3.38 (3H, s) and a dioxymethine proton at 
δ
H
5.51 (1H, t, 
J
= 2.7 Hz, H-2) were also observed. The 
13
C NMR data (
Table 1
) showed 17 carbon signals, including 12 aromatic carbons (
δ
C
101.1–155.6), one ester carbonyl carbons (
δ
C
164.4), two methylenes (
δ
C
14.5–25.2), one dioxygenated methine (
δ
C
97.6) and one methoxy group (
δ
C
55.3). The HMBC (
Fig. 2
) correlations of H-2,4/ C-9, H-8/C-6,10 and H-6/C-10 were indicative of a chromanyl fragment. The cross peak between OCH 
3
and C-2 proved the methoxy group at C-2. Furthermore, the signals of H-3′/C-1′, 5′ and H-7′/C-1′, 5′ revealed the presence of a galloyl group. In the 
13
C-NMR of 
1
, the signal of C-7 (149.7) was found to have an upfield shift compared to the normal meta-trisubstituded benzene ring, indicating the galloyl group was placed at C-7 of the chromanyl group (

). However, this assumption was based on empirical NMR chemical shift prediction due to the paucity of long-range 
1
H– 
13
C HMBC correlations between these fragments. Hence, ACD/Structure Elucidator (Struc_Eluc; ACD/ Labs, Toronto, ON, 
Canada
), a computer-assisted structure elucidation software, was used to solve this problem.
</p>
         <p>
After analyzing the spectroscopic data of 
1
, two substructures of the galloyl and the chromanyl groups were added manually to accelerate the generation time, and two molecules (ID = 1 and ID = 2) were generated by Correlation Spectroscopy Based Generator. Deviations 
dN
were calculated for chemical shift prediction based on the artificial neural net algorithm. As shown in 
Fig. S8
, the molecule (ID = 2) with smaller values represented the more acceptable structure for 
1
. Additionally, 
13
C NMR calculations based on density functional theory (DFT) were performed at the mPW1PW91/6-311 + G (d, p) level with the polarizable continuum model (PCM) in DMSO‑ 
d
6
solvent. As shown in 
Fig. 3A
, the DP4+ application suggested the most probable structure was the molecule with 100% probability.
</p>
         <p>
The absolute configuration of 
1
was elucidated by comparison between the experimental and calculated ECD and the specific rotation value using quantum mechanical calculations. The observation of a positive Cotton effect at 
213 nm
in the experimental ECD spectrum matched well with the calculated one for the 1 
S
configuration (
Fig. 4
), which was consistent with the conclusion drawn by comparison of its specific rotation [
α
]20 
D
+10.0 (
c
0.5, MeOH) with the calculated value [
α
]20 
D
+102.5 (
c
0.5, MeOH). Thus, compound 
1
was determined and named as (1 
S
)-pithecellobiumin C (
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
2
possessed the molecular formula C 
18
H 
16
O 
8
based on the HRESIMS data of 383.0739 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
18
H 
16
O 
8
Na, 383.0737). Detailed comparison between the NMR data of 
1
and 
2
revealed their structural similarity. The 
1
H NMR of 
2
showed the absence of a methoxy and the existence of a methyl at 
δ
H
2.25 (3H, s, H- 2″). The 
13
C NMR showed the existence of a methyl [C-2′′ (
δ
C
26.2)], a ketone [C-1′′ (
δ
C
210.0)] and an oxygenated methine [C-2 (
δ
C
81.5)] in 
2
rather than the methoxy group (
δ
C
55.3) and the dioxygenated methine (
δ
C
97.6) in 
1
. This evidence combined with the key HMBC crosspeaks from H-2″ to C-2 and H-3 to C-1″ indicated that an acetyl group was linked to C- 
2 in
2
. The position of the galloyl ester group was elucidated by the combination of Struc-Eluc (Fig. S20) and DFT calculations of NMR chemical shifts (
Fig. 3B
). The structure of ID = 2 showed better similarity to the experimental data and suggested that the galloyl unit was placed at C-7 (
δ
C
151.7). By comparing the calculated and experimental ECD spectra, the absolute configuration of 
2
was determined to be 3 
S
(
Fig. 4
). Additionally, the observed specific rotation [
α
]20 
D
-16.0 (
c
0.1, MeOH) and calculated value [
α
]20 
D
-33.0 (
c
0.1, MeOH) displayed the same result as ECD experiment. Thus, 
2
was asigned as (3 
S
)-pithecellobiumin D.
</p>
         <p>
Pithecellobiumin E (
3
) showed a sodium adduct ion at 481.0741 [M + Na] 
+
in HRESIMS, corresponding to a molecular formula of C 
22
H 
18
O 
11
(calcd for C 
22
H 
18
O 
11
Na, 481.0741). The NMR data (
Tables 1
and 
2
) at 
δ
H
7.05 (2H, s, H-3′, H-7′), 6.12 (2H, s, H-3, 5) and 
δ
C
100.1 (C-3, 5), 111.4 (C-1), 149.4 (C-4), 156.4 (C-2, 6), 109.0 (C-3′, 7′), 118.4 (C-2′), 139.3 (C-5′), 
δ
C
145.8 (C-4′, 6′) showed typical signals of a galloyl segment and a 5,9-dihydroxy-benzene. In addition, two ortho-coupling signals at 
δ
H
2.76 (2H, t, 
J
= 8.4 Hz, H-7), 2.92 (2H, t, 
J
= 8.4 Hz, H-8) and 
δ
H
6.98 (2H, s, H-2″, H-6″) indicated two adjacent methylenes and a symmetrical 1″,3″,4″,5″-tetrasubstituted aromatic ring system, respectively. In HMBC spectrum, correlations of H-8/C-1, H-7/C-9 and H-2″, 6′′/C-9 indicated the substituent group at C-1 of 
3
as shown in 
Fig. 2
. The three aromatic rings in 
3
were symmetrical, which suggested the location of galloyl moiety might be C-4 or C-9. The Struc-Eluc and 
13
C NMR calculations experiments suggested the certain placement of galloyl at C-7 (Figs. S28 and 3C) is consistent with the observed 
13
C NMR upfield diamagnetic shift. Therefore, the structure of compound 3 was determined.
</p>
         <p>
Pithecellobiumin F (
4
) was ascertained to have a molecule at 
m/z
387.0674 [M + Na] 
+
in the HRESIMS data, which consist with the molecular formula, C 
17
H 
16
O 
9
(calcd for C 
17
H 
16
O 
9
Na, 387.0687). Its NMR data (
Tables 1
and 
2
) was found to be similar to that of 
3
. The difference is the presence of a methoxy at 
δ
H
3.60 (3H, s, 9-OCH 
3
) in 
4
instead of the phenyl moiety in 
3
. Moreover, an ester carbonyl at 
δ
C
173.3 in
4
was instead of the ketone carbon (
δ
C
198.5) in 
3
, which indicated that the methoxy group might connect to C-9 and formed a methyl ester. The result was further confirmed by the HMBC crosspeaks of OCH 
3
/C-9, H-8/C-1 and H-7/C-2, 6, 9. The galloyl group was located at C-4 due to the both symmetrical benzene rings.
</p>
         <p>
The HRESIMS spectrum of compound 
5
exhibited a sodium adduct ion at 
m/z
373.0532 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
16
H 
14
O 
9
Na, 373.0530) corresponding to the molecular formula of C 
16
H 
14
O 
9
. The NMR data were similar to those of 
4
except for the peaks in the high field, which only showed a singlet [
δ
H
3.48 (2H, s, H-7)] in 
5
rather than the two ortho-coupling methylenes signals in 
4
. These observations indicated a methylene unit reduced from 
4
and was further confirmed by the HMBC correlations of H-7/C-2 and OCH 
3
/C-8. The downfield chemical shifts of H-7 indicated that the methylene located between the benzene ring and the methoxyacyl group. As a result, compound 
5
was determined and named as pithecellobiumin G.
</p>
         <p>
Thirteen known compounds were determined based on comparison of their spectroscopic data with those in the literature. They were identified as (2 
R
,3 
R
)-catechin-7- 
O
-gallate (
6
) (

), (2 
R
,3 
R
)-gallocatechin-7- 
O
-gallate (
7
) (

), 5-methoxygallocatechin (
8
) (

), (2 
R
,3 
S
)-gallocatechin-4′- 
O
- gallate (
9
) (

), isookanin (
10
) (

), 5′-hydroxyeriodictyol (
11
) (

), 7,3′,4′-trihydroxyflavone (
12
) (

), myricetin (
13
) (

), melanoxetin (
14
) (

), 7-methoxymelanoxetin (
15
) (

), falloconvolin B (
16
) (

), 3,4,5-trimethoxyphenol-1- 
O -β
-D-(6′- 
O
-galloyl)glucopyranoside (
17
) (

) and phlorizin (
18
) (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.2. Neuroprotective effect of compounds in SH-SY5Y cells

</title>
         <p>
As an important ROS contributor, hydrogen peroxide (H 
2
O 
2
) was used to induce injury in SH-SY5Y cells, which offered a suitable model system 
in vitro
to evaluate neuroprotective activity. As depicted in 
Fig. 5
, H 

2
O 
2

decreased the cell viability to 63.6%, compared with the control. After co-cultureing with compounds at different concentrations, the H 
2
O 
2
-decreaced cell viability was generally restored. Among them, compounds 
1–3
, 
10
, 
12
and 
14
exhibited pronounced neuroprotective effects, with the cell survival rate of 111.4, 115.5, 101.7, 90.3, 95.8 and 96.3%, respectively. The protective potent of 
1–3
displayed higher efficacy than 
10
, 
12
and 
14
, which indicated that the However, pretreatment with compounds 
1
, 
2
and 
3
(50 
μ
M) significantly reduced the percentage of apoptotic cells to 12.1%, 16.7% and 16.8%, respectively. Taken together, the result demonstrated that these three compounds could rescue H 
2
O 
2
-induced SH-SY5Y cells death by inhibiting the cell apoptosis.
</p>
         <p>
a
Compounds 
1
and 
3–5
were recorded in DMSO‑ 
d
. 
2
was recorded in 
6
methanol- 
d
4
.

</p>
         <p>
galloyl moiety might improve protective potent. For the series of common flavonoids, compound 
14
with hydroxy groups at C-7, 8 and C-3′, 4′ is associated with a high protective potency. However, when it was substituted with methoxy or galloyl, the cell viability was reduced about 20% (
6
: 69.7%, 
15
: 75.8%). A comparison of the structures and activities of compounds with galloyl substitution (compounds 
1–7
), suggested that the opening of C-ring was important for the activity. Nevertheless, when B-ring was displaced by methoxy or formyl group and C-ring was recyclized (compounds 
1–2
), the neuroprotective activities were further increased compared to their analogue 
3
. Above all, 
1–3
were the most promising compounds and they were selected for the further study.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.3. Protective effects of compounds against apoptosis

</title>
         <p>
Consequently, the further mechanism of the protective activities of compounds 

1–3
in

H 
2
O 
2
-injured SH-SY5Y cells were investigated. As illustrated in 
Fig. 6
, treatment with H 
2
O 
2
group effectively increased the cell apoptotic rate to 33.23% compared with control group.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.4. Protective effect of compounds against the oxidative stress

</title>
         <p>
As reported, excessive ROS irreversibly injuries DNA and lipids, and ultimately leads to cell apoptosis (

). H 
2
O 
2
, a common oxidant, could induce oxidative damage and increase the levels of ROS in cells (

). In next experiment, the capacity of compounds 
1–3
to rescue H 
2
O 
2
-induced oxidative stress was investigated. The flow cytometric analysis showed that H 
2
O 
2
exposure effectively increased DCF positive ratio. But compounds 
1–3
could ameliorate the situation prominently and the ROS levels were similar to control group (Fig. 7). These results suggested that compounds 
1–3
reduced H 
2
O 
2
-induced ROS accumulation in SH-SY5Y cells, which might be arising from the restoration of the antioxidant defense system.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2.5. Protective effect of compounds against the mitochondrial damage

</title>
         <p>
Mitochondrial dysfunction is proved to be one of the most emerging pathological process in neurodegenerative disorder (

). It is reported that, mitochondria is an important source of reactive oxygen species, and the increased ROS intensifies mitochondria dysfunction and cell injury (

). The decreased mitochondrial membrane potential (ΔΨm) was regarded as a significant indicator to denote mitochondrial dysfunction. As the result in 
Fig. 8
, the fluorescence intensity ratio between green and red significantly increased after treatment with H 
2
O 
2
treatment, which suggested that H 
2
O 
2
could induce mitochondrial dysfunction. This phenomenon was reversed in compound group, the percent of ΔΨm loss cells of which was reduced to 18.4%, 11.8% and 11.2%, respectively. The results suggested that compound 
1–3
could protect SH-SY5Y cells from mitochondrial dysfunction induced by H 
2
O 
2
.
</p>
         <p>
2
2
</p>
         <p>
Fig. 7.
Compounds 
1–3
attenuated H 
2
O 
2
-induced oxidative stress. In the absence or presence of 
1
, 
2
, 
3
(50 
μ
M), then SH-SY5Y cells were incubated with H 
2
O 
2
(200 
μ
M) for 4h. Cells were detected using H 
2
DCFH-DA staining by flow cytometry. 
##
P
&lt;0.01 compared with the control group, ** 
P
&lt;0.01 compared with the H 
2
O 
2
group.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions

</title>
         <p>
In conclusion, five undescribed galloylated phenolics (pithecellobiumin C-G), along with thirteen known compounds were isolated from the twigs and leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. clypearia
</tp:taxon-name>
. The substituted position of galloyl group was determined by the synergistic combination of CASE and DFT methods, when traditional spectroscopic methods could not offer enough evidence. The neuroprotective effects against H 
2
O 
2
-induced injury in SH-SY5Y cells of all isolated compounds were tested by MTT assay. The results suggested that compounds 
1–3
possessed noticeable neuroprotective effect. Subsequently, flow cytometry assays also showed that these three compounds exerted protective activity through inhibiting cell apoptosis which probably implicated in reducing ROS production and mitochondria damage. This study provided an inspiration of searching for undescribed compounds with neuroprotective activity from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. clypearia
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures

</title>
         <p>The information of the experimental procedures was described in the Supporting Information.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material

</title>
         <p>
The
twigs and leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack) I.C.Nielsen (Leguminosae)
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected from 
Huanjiang
(
Guangxi
, 
China
) with the location “ 
E108°26′
, N24°83′”. 
The
plant was genetically identified by 
Professor Jincai Lu
at 
Shenyang Pharmaceutical University. A
voucher specimen (DG-20150529) has been deposited in the herbarium of the 
Department of Natural Products Chemistry
, 
Shenyang Pharmaceutical University

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation

</title>
         <p>
The twigs and leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. clypearia
</tp:taxon-name>
(
50 kg
) were extracted three times with 70% ethanol for 2h. The solid-liquid ratio is 1:10. The extract was concentrated under reduced pressure to give 
1.8 kg
extractum. Then, the extractum was partitioned between ethyl acetate (3 L) and water (1.5 L). The EtOAc partition was initially subjected to column chromatography (silica gel 200–300 mesh) eluting with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (50:1, 30:1, 15:1, 10:1, 5:1, 1:1, 
v/v
) to obtain fractions A-D. Fraction C (
827 g
) was chromatographed on a D101 macroporous resin column eluting with water and increasing amounts of EtOH to get fractions C1 and C2. Fr. C1 (
500 g
) was fractionated on silica gel column eluted with 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (50:1–1:1, 
v/v
) to provide four fractions, among which Fr. C1-2 (
130 g
) was subjected to a HP-20 macroporous resin column (EtOH/H 
2
O; 10:90; 60:40; 90:10, 
v/v
) to yield three fractions named as C1-2-1 (
30g
), C1-2-2 (
70g
), C1-2-3 (
25g
), respectively. The three fractions above were then carried on ODS columns, using EtOH–H 
2
O (from 1:9 to 10:0) as the elution system and cross merging to obtain fractions G-J, respectively. G (
27 g
) and H (
53 g
) were further chromatographed on silica column with the mobile phase 
CH
2
Cl 
2
–MeOH (from 30:1 to 1:1) to provide fractions Fr. G1-G10 and Fr. H1–H8, respectively. G8 (
233 mg
) was applied to RP-C18 CC (MeOH–H 
2
O, 35:65, 
v/v
), then subsequently purified through preparative HPLC (MeCN–H 
2
O, 20:80, 
v/ v
) to obtain compounds 
2
(
17.5 mg
) and 
3
(
22.9 mg
). G5 (
498 mg
) was purified to afford compound 
5
(
240.8 mg
) in the same way. Compounds 
1
(
17.5 mg
) and 
4
(
97.2 mg
) was isolated from H1 (
299.5 mg
) via semipreparative HPLC (MeCN–H 
2
O, 22:78, 
v/v
).
</p>
         <p>
(1S)-pithecellobiumin C (1):
Deep yellow gum; [] 

D

20
-16.0 (
c
0.10, 
CH
3
OH); UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 210 (2.78), 280 (2.97) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3394, 2853, 1716, 1604, 1441, 1202, 
1007, 863, 758 cm
−1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
383.0739 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
18
H 
16
O 
8
Na, 383.0737).
</p>
         <p>
pithecellobiumin E (3):
Yellow gum; UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 207 (2.36), 290 (3.48) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3404, 1606, 1450, 1341, 1205, 
1036, 858, 734, 457 cm
−1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
481.0741 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
18
O 
11
Na, 481.0741).
</p>
         <p>
pithecellobiumin F (4):
Deep yellow gum; UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 240 (2.43), 280 (2.69) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3419, 2853, 2375, 1701, 1613, 1356, 1202, 
1034, 865, 623 cm
−1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
387.0674 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
17
H 
16
O 
9
Na, 387.0687).
</p>
         <p>
pithecellobiumin G (5):
Yellow gum; UV (MeOH) 
λ
max
(log 
ε
) 240 (2.63), 281 (3.46) nm; IR (KBr) 
ν
max
3405, 1721, 1614, 1440, 1350, 
1200, 999, 865, 759 cm
−1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data see 
Tables 1
and 
2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
373.0532 [M + Na] 
+
(calcd for C 
16
H 
14
O 
9
Na, 373.0530).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Computational details

</title>
         <p>The NMR, OR and ECD computational details were listed in the</p>
         <p>Supporting Information.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.5. Neuroprotective activity assay

</title>
         <p>
The protective effects of all polyphenols (
1–18
) were evaluated in H 
2
O 
2
-induced SH-SY5Y cells via MTT assay according to the previously reported procedure (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.6. Apoptosis analysis

</title>
         <p>
Compounds 
1–3
with obvious activity were further examined for apoptosis inhibition effect by annexin V-FITC/PI double staining assay using procedure previously (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.7. Reactive oxygen species (ROS) detection assay

</title>
         <p>
The ROS levels in SH-SY5Y cells treated by 
1–3
were detected using H 
2
DCF-DA fluorescent dye by flow cytometer as methods reported before (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.8. Mitochondrial membrane potential assay

</title>
         <p>
Cells treated by compounds 
1–3
were evaluated for the mitochondrial membrane potential (ΔΨm) by JC-1 assay kit. The experimental procedure carried out as the reported literature (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest

</title>
         <p>
The authors declare that no conflict of interest exists in the submission of this manuscript entitled “Phenolics from 
<tp:taxon-name>Archidendron clypearia (Jack) I.C.Nielsen.</tp:taxon-name>
protect SH-SY5Y cells against H2O2-induced oxidative stress”, and manuscript is read and approved by all authors for publication. I would like to declare on behalf of my co-authors that the work described was original research that has not been published previously, and not under consideration for publication elsewhere, in whole or in part.
</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgment
</p>
         <p>
This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(81502954) and the Career Development Support Plan for Young and Middle-aged Teachers in Shenyang Pharmaceutical University (ZQN2018006).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data

</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112414.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References

</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bao, L.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
Xu, J.
, 
Guo, X.Y.
, 
Liu, H.W.
, 
Kurihara, H.
, 
2009
. 

Effects of 
Pithecellobium clypearia
Benth extract and its main components on inflammation and allergy

. 
Fitoterapia
80
, 
349–353
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Block, G.
, 
Dietrich, M.
, 
Norkus, E.P.
, 
Morrow, J.D.
, 
Hudes, M.
, 
Caan, B.
, 
Packer, L.
, 
2002
. 
Factors associated with oxidative stress in human populations
. 
Am. J. Epidemiol.
156
, 
274–285
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bodede, O.
, 
Shaik, S.
, 
Chenia, H.
, 
Singh, P.
, 
Moodley, R.
, 
2018
. 

Quorum sensing inhibitory potential and in silico molecular docking of flavonoids and novel terpenoids from 
Senegalia nigrescens

. 
J. Ethnopharmacol.
216
, 
134–146
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Clark-Lewis, J.
, 
Porter, L.
, 
1972
. 

Phytochemical survey of the heartwood flavonoids of 
Acacia
species from arid zones of Australia

. 
Aust. J. Chem.
25
, 
1943–1955
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fan, L.
, 
Tong, Q.
, 
Dong, W.
, 
Yang, G.
, 
Hou, X.
, 
Xiong, W.
, 
Shi, C.
, 
Fang, J.
, 
Wang, W.
, 
2017
. 

Tissue distribution, excretion, and metabolic profile of dihydromyricetin, a flavonoid from Vine Tea (
Ampelopsis grossedentata
) after oral administration in rats

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
65
, 
4597–4604
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gaudreault, R.
, 
Mousseau, N.
, 
2019
. 
Mitigating Alzheimer's disease with natural polyphenols: a Review
. 
Curr. Alzheimer Res.
16
, 
529–543
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Guo, X.Y.
, 
Wang, N.L.
, 
Bo, L.
, 
Li, Y.H.
, 
Xu, Q.
, 
Yao, X.S.
, 
2007
. 

Chemical constituents from 
Pithecellobium clypearia
and their effects on T lymphocytes proliferation. J. Chin. Pharmaceut

. 
Sci.
16
, 
208–213
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Han, H.
, 
Ma, Z.
, 
Wang, W.
, 
Xu, M.
, 
Zhou, S.
, 
Li, L.
, 
Jiang, H.
, 
2016
. 

Deglycosylation and absorption of marein, flavanomarein and taxifolin-7- 
O-β
-D-glucopyranoside from capitula of 
Coreopsis tinctoria
in rats and humans

. 
J. Funct. Foods
27
, 
178–188
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Karas, D.
, 
Ulrichova, J.
, 
Valentova, K.
, 
2017
. 
Galloylation of polyphenols alters their biological activity
. 
Food Chem. Toxicol.
105
, 
223–240
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kling, B.
, 
Bucherl, D.
, 
Palatzky, P.
, 
Matysik, F.M.
, 
Decker, M.
, 
Wegener, J.
, 
Heilmann, J.
, 
2014
. 
Flavonoids, flavonoid metabolites, and phenolic acids inhibit oxidative stress in the neuronal cell line HT-22 monitored by ECIS and MTT assay: a comparative study
. 
J. Nat. Prod.
77
, 
446–454
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lee, J.
, 
2016
. 
Mitochondrial drug targets in neurodegenerative diseases
. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett
47
, 
714–720
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lee, M.W.
, 
Morimoto, S.
, 
Nonaka, G.
, 
Nishioka, I.
, 
1992
. 

Tannins and related compounds. 111. Flavan-3-ol gallates and proanthocyanidins from 
Pithecellobium lobatum

. 
Phytochemistry
31
, 
2117–2120
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lewandowska, U.
, 
Fichna, J.
, 
Gorlach, S.
, 
2016
. 
Enhancement of anticancer potential of polyphenols by covalent modifications
. 
Biochem. Pharmacol.
109
, 
1–13
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Li, Y.L.
, 
Ooi, L.S.M.
, 
Wang, H.
, 
But, P.P.H.
, 
Ooi, V.E.C.
, 
2004
. 
Antiviral activities of medicinal herbs traditionally used in southern mainland China
. 
Phytother Res.
18
, 
718–722
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mahmood, N.
, 
Pizza, C.
, 
Aquino, R.
, 
De Tommasi, N.
, 
Piacente, S.
, 
Colman, S.
, 
Burke, A.
, 
Hay, A.J.
, 
1993
. 
Inhibition of HIV infection by flavonoids
. 
Antivir. Res.
22
, 
189–199
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Marinelli, P.
, 
Pallares, I.
, 
Navarro, S.
, 
Ventura, S.
, 
2016
. 
Dissecting the contribution of Staphylococcus aureus alpha-phenol-soluble modulins to biofilm amyloid structure
. 
Sci. Rep. 6 34552
-12.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Qi, X.-L.
, 
Zhang, Y.-Y.
, 
Zhao, P.
, 
Zhou, L.
, 
Wang, X.-B.
, 
Huang, X.-X.
, 
Lin, B.
, 
Song, S.-J.
, 
2018
. 

ent-Kaurane diterpenoids with neuroprotective properties from Corn Silk (
Zea mays
)

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
81
, 
1225–1234
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Reshmitha, T.R.
, 
Thomas, S.
, 
Geethanjali, S.
, 
Arun, K.B.
, 
Nisha, P.
, 
2017
. 

DNA and mitochondrial protective effect of lycopene rich tomato (
Solanum lycopersicum
L.) peel extract prepared by enzyme assisted extraction against H 
2
O 
2
induced oxidative damage in L6 myoblasts

. 
J. Funct. Foods
28
, 
147–156
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sariki, S.K.
, 
Sahu, P.K.
, 
Golla, U.
, 
Singh, V.
, 
Azad, G.K.
, 
Tomar, R.S.
, 
2016
. 

Sen1, the homolog of human Senataxin, is critical for cell survival through regulation of redox homeostasis, mitochondrial function, and the TOR pathway in 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae

. 
FEBS J.
283
, 
4056–4083
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Shi, Y.S.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Hu, W.Z.
, 
Zhang, X.F.
, 
Fu, X.
, Lv, X., 
2017
. 

Dihydrochalcones and diterpenoids from 
Pteris ensiformis
and their bioactivities

. 
Molecules
22
, 
1413–1418
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sosa, V.
, 
Moline, T.
, 
Somoza, R.
, 
Paciucci, R.
, 
Kondoh, H.
, 
LLeonart, M.E.
, 
2013
. 
Oxidative stress and cancer: an overview. Ageing Res
. 
Rev.
12
, 
376–390
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Thao, N.P.
, 
Luyen, B.T.T.
, 
Kim, J.H.
, 
Jo, A.R.
, 
Dat, N.T.
, 
Kiem, P.V.
, 
Minh, C.V.
, 
Kim, Y.H.
, 
2016
. 

Identification, characterization, kinetics, and molecular docking of flavonoid constituents from 
Archidendron clypearia
(Jack.) Nielsen leaves and twigs

. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem.
24
, 
3125–3132
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Tian, L.-W.
, 
Feng, Y.
, 
Tran, T.D.
, 
Shimizu, Y.
, 
Pfeifer, T.
, 
Forster, P.I.
, 
Quinn, R.J.
, 
2015
. 

Tyrosyl-DNA phosphodiesterase I inhibitors from the Australian plant 
Macropteranthes leichhardtii

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
78
, 
1756–1760
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Vercauteren, J.
, 
2009
. 
Compositions of Polyphenolic Flavonoid Derivatives
, 
Their Preparation, and Their Use in the Treatment of Disease and Aging
. pp. 
53pp
Caudalie, Fr.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, W.
, 
Yao, G.-D.
, 
Shang, X.-Y.
, 
Gao, J.-C.
, 
Zhang, Y.
, 
Song, S.-J.
, 
2018
a. 
Eclalbasaponin I from Aralia elata (Miq.) Seem. reduces oxidative stress-induced neural cell death by autophagy activation. Biomed
. 
Pharmacother.
97
, 
152–161
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, Y.
, 
Ren, Q.
, 
Yan, Z.
, 
Wang, W.
, 
Zhao, L.
, 
Bai, M.
, 
Wang, X.
, 
Huang, X.
, 
Song, S.
, 
2017
. 

Flavonoids and their derivatives with 
β
-amyloid aggregation inhibitory activity from the leaves and twigs of 
Pithecellobium clypearia
Benth

. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett
27
, 
4823–4827
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wang, Y.X.
, 
Zhou, L.
, 
Wang, J.
, 
Lin, B.
, 
Wang, X.B.
, 
Huang, X.X.
, 
Song, S.J.
, 
2018
. 

Enantiomeric lignans with anti-beta-amyloid aggregation activity from the twigs and leaves of 
Pithecellobium clypearia
Benth

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
77
, 
579–585
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Williams, P.
, 
Sorribas, A.
, 
Howes, M.J.
, 
2011
. 
Natural products as a source of Alzheimer's drug leads
. 
Nat. Prod. Rep.
28
, 
48–77
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Xu, X.
, 
Fang, X.
, 
Wang, J.
, 
Zhu, H.
, 
2017
. 
Identification of novel ROS inducer by merging the fragments of piperlongumine and dicoumarol
. 
Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett
27
, 
1325–1328
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, C.F.
, 
Chen, J.
, 
Zhao, L.Q.
, 
Zhang, D.
, 
Zhang, M.
, 
Wang, Z.T.
, 
2011
a. 

Three new flavonoids from the active extract of 
Fallopia convolvulus
. J

. 
Asian Nat. Prod. Res.
13
, 
136–142
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, L.-Q.
, 
Yang, X.-W.
, 
Zhang, Y.-B.
, 
Zhai, Y.-Y.
, 
Xu, W.
, 
Zhao, B.
, 
Liu, D.-L.
, 
Yu, H.-J.
, 
2012
. 
Biotransformation of phlorizin by human intestinal flora and inhibition of biotransformation products on tyrosinase activity
. 
Food Chem.
132
, 
936–942
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, X.G.
, 
Liu, J.W.
, 
Tang, P.
, 
Liu, Z.Y.
, 
Guo, G.J.
, 
Sun, Q.Y.
, 
Yin, J.J.
, 
2018
. 

Identification of a new uncompetitive inhibitor of adenosine deaminase from endophyte 
Aspergillus niger
sp

. 
Curr. Microbiol.
75
, 
565–573
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhang, Y.H.
, 
Wu, Y.L.
, 
Tashiro, S.
, 
Onodera, S.
, 
Ikejima, T.
, 
2011
b. 
Reactive oxygen species contribute to oridonin-induced apoptosis and autophagy in human cervical carcinoma HeLa cells
. 
Acta Pharmacol. Sin.
32
, 
1266–1275
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Zhou, L.
, 
Yao, G.-D.
, 
Lu, L.-W.
, 
Song, X.-Y.
, 
Lin, B.
, 
Wang, X.-B.
, 
Huang, X.-X.
, 
Song, S.-J.
, 
2018
. 

Neolignans from red raspberry (
Rubus idaeus
L.) exhibit enantioselective neuroprotective effects against H 
2
O 
2
-induced oxidative injury in SH-SY5Y Cells

. 
J. Agric. Food Chem.
66
, 
11390–11397
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
