<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of Natural History</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00222933.2012.717644</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Patterns of species participation across multiple mixed-species flock types in a tropical forest in northeastern India</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2012</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alcippe nipalensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alcippe castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhipidura albicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Erpornis zantholeuca
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Erpornis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Abroscopus albogularis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phylloscopus reguloides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Seicercus castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Culicicapa ceylonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus remifer
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Melanochlora sultanea
(Sultan Tit)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pericrocotus flammeus
(Scarlet Minivet)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Heterophasia annectans
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Coracina melaschistos
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sitta castanea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sitta formosa
(Beautiful Nuthatch)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus remifer
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Garrulax
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cissa chinensis
(Green Magpie)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Harpactes erythrocephalus
(Redheaded Trogon)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alophoixus flaveolus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Seicercus castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xiphirhynchus superciliaris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Macronous gularis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Niltava
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ficedula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pnoepyga
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Napothera
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Niltava
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ficedula
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Abroscopus albogularis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alcippe castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alcippe nipalensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Culicicapa ceylonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus remifer
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Erpornis zantholeuca
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phylloscopus reguloides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhipidura albicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Seicercus castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Seicercus whistleri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Abroscopus superciliaris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus aeneus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Melanochlora sultanea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pericrocotus flammeus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phylloscopus cantator
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Rhipidura</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Seicercus poliogenys
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sitta castanea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alcippe rufogularis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alophoixus flaveolus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Harpactes erythrocephalus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Heterophasia annectans
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>gularis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Coracina melaschistos
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus aeneus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus remifer
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Melanochlora sultanea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pericrocotus flammeus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sitta castanea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Sitta formosa
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Abroscopus superciliaris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cissa chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Culicicapa ceylonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus hottentottus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus paradiseus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Erpornis zantholeuca
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Heterophasia annectans
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>gularis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pericrocotus brevirostris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phylloscopus reguloides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Seicercus castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alcippe castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alcippe nipalensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alophoixus flaveolus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Rhipidura albicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Patterns of species participation across multiple mixed-species flock 

types
in a tropical forest in northeastern 
India

</p>
         <p>

Umesh 
Srinivasana

,b,c*, 

Rashid Hasnain 
Razac

,d and 

Suhel 
Quaderc

,e
</p>
         <p>
aPost-graduate

Programme in Wildlife Biology and Conservation, Wildlife Conservation

</p>
         <p>

Society – 
India
Programme and National Centre for Biological Sciences, GKVK Campus, Bangalore – 560065, 
India
; 
bCentre
for Wildlife Studies, No. 1669, 31 
st
Cross, 16th Main, Banashankari 2nd Stage, Bangalore – 560070, 
India
; 
cNational
Centre for Biological Sciences, Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, GKVK Campus, Bangalore – 560065, 
India
; 
dTRAFFIC
India
, WWF 
India
, 172-B Lodhi Estate, New 
Delhi
– 110003, 
India
; 

eNature

Conservation Foundation, 3076 
/
5, IV Cross, Gokulam Park, Mysore – 570002, 
India

</p>
         <p>
(

Received 16 January 
August 2012
; final version received 
30 July 2012
; printed 
31 October 2012

)
</p>
         <p>
We
studied mixed-species bird flocks in northeastern 
India
to (a) develop a framework for quantifying species participation in mixed-species flocks, (b) characterize the ecology and behaviour of participant species, and (c) explore mechanisms influencing the coexistence of different mixed-species flock 
types
. To characterize participation in mixed-species flocks, we implement a new method incorporating species abundances, minimizing potential biases in measuring participation arising from differences in the availability of flocking species. There are at least three distinct flock 
types
in the lowland forests of northeastern 
India
; these flock 
types
differ in the body mass and vertical stratum use of participant species. The “core” of mixed-species flocks was composed of a species group that differed much more in their foraging method in comparison with “attendant” species. The exchange of benefits and minimization of interspecific competition might lead to, and maintain, heterogeneity in foraging methods among core species of mixed-species flocks

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Keywords:
core species; feeding guild; insectivore; mixed-species flock; attendant species
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction

</title>
         <p>
Mixed-species flocking is a common phenomenon in birds in tropical and temperate habitats worldwide, and has been the subject of much research (

; 

; Kotagama and 

; 

). Mixed flocks are thought to provide their participants with benefits arising from increased foraging efficiency and decreased predation risk (

). However, despite an extensive literature spanning close to a century and a half (

), several aspects of the dynamics of mixed-species flocking still remain poorly explored and unclear.
</p>
         <p>
First, variation in the propensity of different species to participate in mixed flocks and the mechanisms that might structure flocks and determine their composition remain to be satisfactorily explained. This might be partly because the quantification of flocking propensity is often simplistic, and based on metrics that do not incorporate the abundance (or “availability”) of different species, which might be expected to influence participation in flocks. Further, where multiple mixed-species flock 
types
coexist, the mechanisms underlying the formation and stability of these discrete flock 
types
has received little attention.
</p>
         <p>
This study was carried out to (a) develop a rigorous framework for quantifying species participation in mixed-species flocks by taking into account species abundances, (b) characterize the composition of mixed-species bird flocks in terms of the ecology and behaviour of participant species, and (c) identify the potential mechanisms influencing participation in, and coexistence of different mixed-species flock 
types
.
</p>
         <p>
By comparing observed participation in mixed-species flocks with expected participation based purely on the overall abundances of participant species, we characterize species as participating more than expected, as expected, or less than expected in mixed flocks. This approach takes into account the availability of species to join flocks, and is among the first attempts to do so in characterizing species participation (

). 

also use abundance data to characterize flocking propensity. However, their approach measures the probability of a species being “left behind” by a moving flock, rather than comparing expected participation (based on abundance) with empirically observed participation. We also explore how the degree of participation by different species is related to aspects of the ecology of species, specifically with factors such as body mass, diet and foraging method.
</p>
         <p>
We expected that flocking species would be predominantly insectivorous, because unlike localized resources such as nectar and fruit that might advertise themselves, arthropods are likely to be more scattered and cryptic. This property of the resource might require insectivores to keep company with other species to learn foraging locations or benefit from facilitatory behaviours of other species (e.g. 

; 

). We also expected that the “core” of a flock (composed of species that participate regularly in flocks) would be composed of species that were predominantly insectivorous, compared with attendant species, which might include arthropods in their diet in addition to other resources, and therefore might join flocks only temporarily to satisfy their dietary insect requirements. We finally hypothesized that the core of a flock would be made up of species that exchanged complementary benefits arising from specialized feeding behaviours. This might reduce interspecific competition arising from similar ecologies and also result in facilitatory foraging benefits. We therefore predicted that the core of a flock should be heterogeneous with respect to the representation of foraging methods adopted by different species (especially when compared with attendant species).
</p>
         <p>
Methods
</p>
         <p>
Study area
</p>
         <p>
Fieldwork
was carried out in the 
Namdapha National Park
(27 
◦
23 
′
30 
′′
to 

27 
◦
39 
′
40 
′′
N

and 96 
◦
15 
′
2 
′′
to 

96 
◦
58 
′
33 
′′
E

) in 
Changlang district
, eastern 
Arunachal Pradesh
, 
India
, from early 

December 2007

to mid-March 2008. 
Namdapha
is situated in the 
Eastern Himalaya
, a global 
Biodiversity Hotspot
, and an 
Important Bird Area
with about 500 bird species (

). 
Annual
rainfall varies from 
1500 to 3500 mm
, most of which falls during the southwest monsoon months of 
April
to 
October
(

). 
Sampling
was conducted in the 
Hornbill
and 
Musathi
areas in the buffer zone of the national park, at altitudes ranging from 

500 to 650 m
above sea level

. The habitat in this area is composed of dipterocarp-dominated lowland tropical evergreen forest (

)

.
</p>
         <p>
Sampling methods
</p>
         <p>
Sampling for bird species abundance
</p>
         <p>
Accurate measures of the abundance of difference bird species are essential for our method of assessing flocking propensity (see Analytical methods, below). To measure abundances, 23 line transects were established, ranging in length from 
180 to 500 m
, and oriented along random bearings. The minimum distance between adjacent transects was 
500 m
, to maximize independence between transects. Each transect was walked on four occasions, and in the case of four transects, on five occasions, thereby totalling 92 walks of 23 transects. For every species detected, the cluster size, bearing to the cluster (using a compass), and the detection distance to the centre of the cluster (using a laser rangefinder – 1000 Yardage Pro, Bushnell Corporation, Overland Park, KA, 
USA
) was recorded. A cluster was defined as a group of individuals of the same species, consisting of one or more individuals. For clusters with a detection distance below 
15 m
, detection distance was estimated visually to the nearest metre. Transects were walked between 08.30 and 12.30 hr.
</p>
         <p>
Mixed-species flock sampling
</p>
         <p>
Mixed-species flocks were defined as a group of two or more species moving in the same direction (

). Data on mixed-species flocks were recorded on the established line transects (during sampling for bird abundances), and also opportunistically along pre-existing trails from 13.00 to 15.30 hr. We avoided sampling during the early morning (when flocks would be forming), and the late evening (when they would be disbanding), to minimize any biases in the results that might arise from time of day. For mixed flocks encountered on transects, species composition of the flock was recorded, and for each species cluster in the flock, cluster size, detection bearing and detection distance were noted. These data were also used in species abundance estimation. During opportunistic sampling of mixed flocks, species composition alone was recorded. We considered flocks recorded on the same transect but on different sampling occasions independent of each other (

) because individuals join and leave flocks over very short time frames, and are “potentially interactive from minute to minute” (

).
</p>
         <p>
Analytical methods
</p>
         <p>
Abundance estimation
</p>
         <p>
In estimating the detection function and detection probability of bird species, we sought to take into account differences in detectability across species. We divided species into three “detection classes” based on their median detection distances, each class containing an equal number of species. This approach assumes intra-class homogeneity in species detection functions and models multi-species data more parsimoniously by exploiting species’ similarity in detectability (

). The detection function for each of these three classes was estimated separately using the program DISTANCE (version 5.0, 

), and these detection functions were used along with the species-specific encounter rates to estimate the cluster abundance of each species.
</p>
         <p>

Mixed-species flock 
types

</p>
         <p>
It was apparent during sampling that there were multiple flock 
types
differing in species composition. Cluster analysis (using Jaccard’s similarity index with UPGMA, or Unweighted Pair Group Method with Arithmetic mean linkage) was used to identify different flock 
types
based on the species composition of these flocks.
</p>
         <p>
Species participation in mixed-species flocks
</p>
         <p>
For each flock 
type
, a candidate pool of species potentially contributing to flock composition was identified. This pool included all species that had been observed in at least one flock of that flock 
type
. Species in this pool were then used to generate simulated flocks. The number of species drawn for each simulated flock was equal to the observed mean number of species in that flock 
type
. Simulated flocks were filled sequentially by drawing species without replacement from the candidate species pool with a probability proportional to their abundance. The measure of abundance used as the probability weight was the abundance of conspecific groups of each species rather than the number of individuals. This is because flock participants join mixed-species flocks as conspecific groups rather than as individuals. This simulation method yielded “null” flocks with a composition reflecting what would be expected in the absence of differences in the tendency of species to join mixed-species flocks (i.e. based on the availability of species alone). As many null flocks were simulated as the observed number of flocks for each flock 
type
. In this set of null flocks, the number of flocks in which a particular species occurred was counted. This proportion gives an estimate of the expected flocking propensity of a species based on abundance alone. This process was repeated 10,000 times to obtain a species-specific distribution of expected occurrence in mixedspecies flocks. The non-parametric 95% confidence limits (0.025 and 0.975 quantiles) of these distributions were obtained, and species were categorised into three classes in the following manner:
</p>
         <p>
a. 
Core species
. Species for which the observed number of occurrences in mixed-species flocks exceeded the upper 95% confidence limit of their occurrences expected by abundance alone. Our definition of core species is qualitatively similar to previous definitions (

; 

), which are also based on the degree of species participation.
</p>
         <p>
b. 
Regular attendants
. Species for which the observed number of flock occurrences fell within the 95% confidence intervals of the distribution of their expected occurrences. Although attendant species are usually defined functionally as species that are not “nuclear” (i.e. not involved in initiating or maintaining mixed-species flocks; e.g. 

), we apply this term here to describe species that do not form the “core” of a flock. 

also used degree of participation to define “attendant species” and to further classify attendants into usual, regular and accidental attendants.
</p>
         <p>
c. 
Irregular attendants
. Species for which the lower 95% confidence limit of the distribution of their expected occurrences exceeded the observed number of occurrences in mixed-species flocks.
</p>
         <p>
Our method, as opposed to previously used metrics of flocking propensity, takes into account the abundance (or availability) of species. The abundance of a species is likely to play a role in determining flock participation. For instance, a common species with relatively low tendency to flock might occur in roughly the same number of flocks as a rare species with high flocking propensity. Earlier metrics would classify both of these species as having the same flocking propensity, whereas these metrics actually measure the probability of a species being present in a flock, rather than propensity to flock 
per se
. We suggest, therefore, that measures of flocking propensity are likely to be much more realistic when the abundance of participant species has been taken into account.
</p>
         <p>
Some species occurred as irregular attendants in one flock 
type
but were either core species or regular attendants in another flock 
type
. For comparisons between flock 
types
, these species were not considered members of the flock 
type
in which they occurred as irregular attendants. This is because an irregular attendant might occur in flocks through chance alone whereas a core species or regular attendant is likely to be associated more closely with other species within a given flock 
type
.
</p>
         <p>
Species characteristics
</p>
         <p>
Species were classified as insectivores, omnivores, nectarivores, frugivores, granivores or carnivores based on the degree of predominance of a particular food component in their diet as given in secondary sources (

; 

; 

; 

). Insectivorous species were classified as foliage gleaners, bark gleaners, hoverers or salliers based on the predominant foraging method of each species as reported in secondary sources (

; 

; 

) and from observations made during the study. The definitions of gleaning, hovering and sallying are based on descriptions in 

. Gleaners are species that forage mainly by picking stationary prey items off a substrate such as foliage or tree bark; hence foliage gleaners and bark gleaners. Hoverers are species that forage predominantly by picking stationary prey items from a substrate while in flight. Salliers are species that forage mainly by pursuing flying prey and capturing these when in flight (described as “hawking” by 

). Body mass data were obtained from 

. In most cases, body mass was provided as a range from minimum to maximum, and we used the mid-point of this range in our analysis. Data on foraging heights were obtained during line-transect sampling. For each individual bird detected on a transect walk, the stratum in which the bird was detected (understorey, midstorey or canopy) was recorded.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results

</title>
         <p>

Mixed-species flocks 
types
, body mass and vertical stratification

</p>
         <p>
Species compositions of 101 mixed-species flocks were recorded from observations made along line transects, and during opportunistic sampling. Cluster analysis using Jaccard’s index with UPGMA identified three major flock 
types
(
Figure 1
). A Multiresponse Permutation Procedure, which tests for a significant difference between two or more groups, indicated clear differences between groups (chance-corrected within-group agreement, 
A
= 0.122, probability of obtaining smaller or equal 
δ &lt;
0.0001).
</p>
         <p>Canopy flocks</p>
         <p>Understorey flocks</p>
         <p>Large−bodied flocks</p>
         <p>
The mixed-species flock 
types
identified were:
</p>
         <p>
a. Understorey and midstorey flocks of predominantly small-bodied bird species (
n
= 60 flocks). Core species in these flocks (see Appendix 1 for these and other details) were 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alcippe nipalensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Nepal
Fulvetta), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alcippe castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
(Rufous-winged Fulvetta), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhipidura albicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
(White-throated Fantail), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Erpornis zantholeuca
</tp:taxon-name>
(White-bellied 
<tp:taxon-name>Erpornis</tp:taxon-name>
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Abroscopus albogularis
</tp:taxon-name>
(Rufous-faced Warbler), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phylloscopus reguloides
</tp:taxon-name>
(Blyth’s Leaf-warbler), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Seicercus castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
(Chestnut-crowned Warbler), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Culicicapa ceylonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(Grey-headed Canary Flycatcher) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus remifer
</tp:taxon-name>
(Lesser Racket-tailed Drongo). These are henceforth referred to as understorey flocks.
</p>
         <p>
b. Canopy and midstorey foraging flocks (
n
= 26 flocks), henceforth referred to as canopy flocks (Appendix 2). Core species in these flocks were 
<tp:taxon-name>
Melanochlora sultanea
(Sultan Tit)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pericrocotus flammeus
(Scarlet Minivet)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Heterophasia annectans
</tp:taxon-name>
(Rufous-backed Sibia), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Coracina melaschistos
</tp:taxon-name>
(Blackwinged Cuckoo-shrike), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sitta castanea
</tp:taxon-name>
(Chestnut-bellied Nuthatch), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sitta formosa
(Beautiful Nuthatch)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dicrurus remifer
</tp:taxon-name>
(Lesser Racket-tailed Drongo).
</p>
         <p>
c. Understorey and midstorey foraging flocks of predominantly large-bodied species (
n
= 11 flocks) composed of species such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Garrulax
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(laughing thrushes), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cissa chinensis
(Green Magpie)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Harpactes erythrocephalus
(Redheaded Trogon)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alophoixus flaveolus
</tp:taxon-name>
(White-throated Bulbul). These are henceforth referred to as large-bodied flocks. We did not analyse species and guild participation in these flocks because of the low sample size.
</p>
         <p>
The two flock 
types
that foraged in the understorey and midstorey differed in the body masses of their participant species (
Figure 2
), whereas the body masses of canopy flock participants overlapped with those of each of the two understorey–midstorey flocks (
Figure 2
).
</p>
         <p>
Patterns of species participation
</p>
         <p>
Flocking and non-flocking species
</p>
         <p>We recorded 53 species that participated to varying degrees in either understorey or canopy mixed-species flocks. Thirty-four species did not participate in mixed-species flocks (henceforth, non-flocking species). As expected, most flocking species (83.0% of 53 species) were insectivores, compared with only 47.1% of 34 non-flocking species. Omnivores and nectarivores also occurred in mixed flocks, while carnivores, frugivores and granivores were never recorded. Both the nectarivores recorded in the study area were flock participants.</p>
         <p>
Diet guilds and foraging behaviour in core and attendant species
</p>
         <p>All core species in understorey and canopy flocks, as well as regular attendants in understorey flocks, were insectivorous. Although regular attendant species in canopy flocks were dominated by insectivores (18 species), omnivores (five species) and nectarivores (one species) also participated regularly in canopy mixed-species flocks.</p>
         <p>Canopy Large−bodied Understorey flocks flocks flocks</p>
         <p>
As hypothesized, core species in both flock 
types
showed a relatively heterogeneous representation of different foraging method groups compared with regular attendant species. Only one hovering species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Seicercus castaneceps
</tp:taxon-name>
(Chestnut-crowned Warbler), occurred in canopy flocks (as a regular attendant). This species, however, was a core species in understorey flocks. Regular attendants in both flock 
types
were dominated by foliage gleaners, followed by bark-surface feeders, salliers and hoverers (
Figure 3
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
Discussion

</title>
         <p>

Mixed-species flocks 
types
, body mass and vertical stratification

</p>
         <p>

Although mixed-species flocks have been described in detail from tropical and temperate regions from 
South America
, Europe, Africa and Asia, the co-existence of three sympatric but distinct flock 
types
(
Figure 1
) has been recorded before this study only in north-central 
Myanmar
, also in dipterocarp forest (

). In our study area, “understorey” and “large-bodied” mixed flocks both foraged in the understorey and lower midstorey, and species in “understorey” flocks were smaller than those in large-bodied flocks. Canopy flocks, which did not appear to

</p>
         <p>Understorey Canopy Understorey Canopy flocks flocks flocks flocks</p>
         <p>
overlap significantly in foraging strata with understorey and large-bodied flocks, had species that did not differ in body mass from participant species of either of the two understorey–midstorey foraging flocks (
Figure 2
).
</p>
         <p>
Within vertical strata in the habitat, body mass might be a strong factor determining non-random patterns of species association. Differently sized species may exploit resources that differ to such a degree that large species might be unable to facilitate the foraging of small species and vice versa. Similarly, differently sized species might have different predators and, for a given species, joining a flock with members that are much larger or smaller than itself might not provide the same anti-predator benefits that could accrue from joining flocks of similarly sized species. However, apart from body mass, species-specific factors such as sentinel behaviour and efficiency in flushing prey, as well as structural characteristics of the habitat might also play a role in influencing species associations (

; 

).
</p>
         <p>
Patterns of species participation
</p>
         <p>
Diet as a predictor of species participation
</p>
         <p>
Flocking species were dominated by insectivores, but included omnivores and nectarivores that also feed on insects and arthropods. Granivores, frugivores and carnivores never participated in flocks, reinforcing the observation that mixed-species flocks are composed mainly of insectivorous bird species (

). Compared with resources such as fruit, which are likely to be localized, insects and arthropods are expected to be more evenly distributed in the habitat. Hence, insectivorous species might need to flock to facilitate foraging on a resource that is not localized or readily accessible. Such foraging benefits might arise from multiple independent mechanisms such as social learning about resource locations, increased foraging rates from prey flushing, and increased time available for foraging from decreased predation risk in a flock (

; review in 

). Provisioning experiments or natural outbreaks that might significantly increase local densities of arthropod or insect prey would serve as a useful test of the hypothesis that the distribution of prey affects flocking behaviour (see 

).
</p>
         <p>
Insectivorous species that we did not record participating in mixed-species flocks in the study area included species occupying bamboo or secondary forest, and some are known to occur in mixed-species flocks in those habitats (

; 

). These were species such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xiphirhynchus superciliaris
</tp:taxon-name>
(Slender-billed Scimitar-babbler) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macronous gularis
</tp:taxon-name>
(Striped Tit-babbler). Other insectivorous species that did not participate in mixed-species flocks were flycatchers (genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Niltava
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ficedula
</tp:taxon-name>
) and wren-babblers (genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pnoepyga
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Napothera
</tp:taxon-name>
). Species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Niltava
</tp:taxon-name>
are irregular participants in mixed-species flocks in other parts of Asia (

); species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ficedula
</tp:taxon-name>
are not known to flock. Flycatchers might not participate in mixed-species flocks because many are specific to certain microhabitats (

), and might depend on food sources that are localized to these areas, rather than being randomly distributed in the environment. Similarly, it is possible that wren-babblers, owing to their microhabitat specificity (such as moss-covered rocks and logs and very dense undergrowth; 

), also rely on specific 
types
of prey that are localized in the habitat. A comparison of the diets of flycatchers and wren-babblers relative to other insectivores, together with a comparison of the spatial dispersion of these prey items, might lend support to, or refute the hypothesis that the distribution of prey influences flocking behaviour.
</p>
         <p>Omnivores and nectarivores that regularly participated in mixed-species flocks may join and follow flocks only part of the time to satisfy their dietary requirement of insects, accounting for their status as regular attendants, rather than as core species. Ominvorous and nectarivorous species might require higher levels of dietary protein during certain times of the year, for instance when provisioning nestlings. A testable prediction is that given constant insect abundances, these species will increase their participation in mixed-species flocks to benefit from foraging facilitation during these periods.</p>
         <p>
Foraging method guilds and core composition
</p>
         <p>
Different foraging groups, because of their specialized behaviours, are likely to contribute qualitatively and quantitatively different benefits to heterospecifics in mixedspecies flocks. For instance, gregarious foliage gleaners are likely to flush insects or other active prey, making these accessible to salliers (

), and salliers, because they scan for insect prey, are likely to detect predators and provide early warning (

; 

). These specialized functional contributions might have the consequence of balancing foraging method representation in the “core” of a mixed-species flock. In other words, core species composition of a mixed-species flock is likely to be heterogeneous and stable as a result of the exchange of specialized, and possibly complementary benefits between individuals in the core of the flock.
</p>
         <p>

observed “substantial species-specific variation in foraging behaviour” among flock participants. They concluded that foraging facilitation was not a major benefit accruing to flock members because species with a particular foraging method would be unable to facilitate the foraging of species with a different foraging method. However, it is the 
difference
in foraging behaviour between participant species that is likely to offer foraging benefits. This might be through reduced competition, and the exchange of complementary benefits, either directly through mechanisms such as prey flushing, or indirectly through reducing the time spent on vigilance (allowing more time for foraging). Observations on the foraging success (measured in terms of foraging rate and time spent foraging) of core species in mixedspecies flocks would be required to tease out the nature and degree of benefit received by flock members. Species with different foraging methods would be expected to contribute and receive qualitatively and quantitatively different benefits. For instance, gleaners, poor at predator detection, might receive anti-predator benefits from associating with salliers (that play a sentinel role) and increase their foraging time in flocks. On the other hand, salliers might increase their foraging rate from gaining access to prey flushed by gleaners (see 

for a comprehensive review).
</p>
         <p>Our study examines some of the potential factors that might influence the composition of mixed-species flocks, and shows how diet, foraging method and body mass might be important in determining non-random patterns of species association. However, the influence of diet and foraging methods must be examined more rigorously. A finer classification of participant species in terms of diet and mode of feeding is desirable, as this will enable the examination of flocking propensity on a continuum, rather than based on categorical classifications scrounged from secondary literature. We identify questions that pertain to the mechanisms underlying species associations in mixed-species flocks, and advance testable hypotheses relating to the benefits of mixed-species flocking.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements

</title>
         <p>
We thank the Wildlife Conservation Society – 
India
Programme for financial support and the National Centre for Biological Sciences and Centre for Wildlife Studies for administrative support. We thank Pantha, Aphu and Khichaye Yobin for their enthusiasm in the field. We are grateful to the 
Arunachal Pradesh
Forest Department for providing permission to carry out this research.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References

</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ali S
. 
1977
. 
Field guide to the birds of the eastern Himalayas
. 
Delhi: Oxford University Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ali S
, 
Ripley SD
. 
1983
. 
Compact handbook of the birds of India and Pakistan, together with those of Bangladesh, Nepal, Bhutan and Sri Lanka
. 
Delhi: Oxford University Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Alldredge MW
, 
Pollock KH
, 
Simons TR
, 
Shriner SA
. 
2007
. 
Multiple-species analysis of point count data, a more parsimonious modeling framework
. 
J Appl Ecol.
44
: 
281–290
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bates HW
. 
1863
. 
The naturalist on the River Amazon
. 
London: Murray Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chen C
, 
Hsieh F
. 
2002
. 
Composition and foraging behaviour of mixed species flocks led by the Grey-cheeked Fulvetta in Fushan Experimental Forest, Taiwan
. 
Ibis
144
: 
317–330
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Datta A
. 
2007
. 
Making Conservation Work
. 
New Delhi: Permanent Black. Shahabuddin G, Rangarajan, M. Protecting with people in Namdapha: threatened forests, forgotten people
. p. 
165–207
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dunning JB
. 
2008
. 
CRC Handbook of avian body masses
. 
Boca Raton (FL): Taylor and Francis
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Farley EA
, 
Sieving KE
, 
Contreras, TA
. 
2008
. 
Characterising complex mixed-species bird flocks using an objective method for determining species participation
. 
J Ornithol.
149
: 
451–469
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Goodale E
, 
Kotagama S
. 
2005
. 
Alarm calling in Sri Lankan mixed-species bird flocks
. 
Auk
122
: 
108–120
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Graves GR
, 
Gotelli NJ
. 
1993
. 
Assembly of avian mixed-species flocks in Amazonia
. 
Proc Natl Acad Sci USA.
90
: 
1388–1391
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Grimmett R
, 
Inskipp T
, 
Inskipp C
. 
1998
. 
Birds of the Indian Subcontinent
. 
New Delhi: Oxford University Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Hobson KA
, 
van Wilgenburg S
. 
2006
. 
Composition and timing of postbreeding multispecies feeding flocks of boreal forest passerines in western Canada
. 
Wilson J Ornithol.
118
: 
164–172
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Islam MZ
, 
Rahmani AR
. 
2004
. 

Important Bird Areas in India: priority sites for conservation. BNHS - Mumbai 
/
Bird Life International 
/
IBCN

. 
New Delhi: Oxford University Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
King DI
, 
Rappole JH
. 
2001
. 
Mixed-species bird flocks in dipterocarp forest of north-central Burma (Myanmar)
. 
Ibis
143
: 
380–390
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kotagama S
, 
Goodale, E
. 
2004
. 
The composition and social organisation of mixed-species flocks in a Sri Lankan rainforest
. 
Forktail
20
: 
63–70
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Krebs JR
. 
1973
. 

Social learning and the significance of mixed-species flocks of chickadees (
Parus
spp.)

. 
Can J Zool.
51
: 
1275–1288
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
McClure HE
. 
1967
. 
The composition of mixed species flocks in lowland and submontane forests of Malaya
. 
The Wilson Bulletin
79
: 
131–154
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morse DH
. 
1977
. 
Feeding behavior and predator avoidance in heterospecific groups
. 
BioScience
27
: 
332–339
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moynihan M
. 
1962
. 
The organization and probable evolution of some mixed species flocks of neotropical birds
. 
Smithsonian Miscellaneous Collections
143
: 
7
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Munn CA
. 
1984
. 
The behavioural ecology of mixed-species bird flocks in Amazonian Peru
[PhD thesis]. [Princeton, NJ]. 
Princeton University
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Munn CA
, 
Terborgh JW
. 
1979
. 
Multi-species territoriality in neotropical foraging flocks
. 
Condor
81
: 
338–347
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Peron G
, 
Crochet, P-A
. 
2009
. 
Edge effect and structure of mixed-species bird flocks in an Afrotropical lowland forest
. 
J Ornithol.
150
: 
585–599
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rasmussen PC
, 
Anderton JC
. 
2005
. 
Birds of South Asia. The Ripley guide
. 
Washington DC: Smithsonian Institution and Barcelona: Lynx Edicions
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Robinson SK
, 
Holmes, RT
. 
1982
. 
Foraging behaviour of forest birds, the relationships among search tactics, diet and habitat structure
. 
Ecology
63
: 
1918–1931
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Sridhar H
, 
Beauchamp G
, 
Shanker K
. 
2009
. 
Why do birds participate in mixed-species foraging flocks? A large-scale synthesis
. 
Anim Behav.
78
: 
337–347
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Srinivasan U
. 
2008
. 
Structure, composition and heterospecific associations in mixed species flocks of birds in a lowland tropical forest in northeastern India [MSc. thesis]. [Manipal (Karnataka)]
. 
Manipal University
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Srinivasan U
, 
Raza RH
, 
Quader S
. 
2010
. 
The nuclear question: rethinking species importance in multi-species animal groups
. 
J Anim Ecol.
79
: 
948–954
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Swynnerton CFM
. 
1915
. 
Mixed bird parties
. 
Ibis
67
: 
346–354
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Thomas L
, 
Laake JL
, 
Strindberg S
, 
Marques FFC
, 
Buckland ST
, 
Borchers DL
, 
Anderson DR
, 
Burnham KP
, 
Hedley SL
, 
Pollard JH
, et al. 
2005
. 
Distance 5.0. Release 2
. 
Research Unit for Wildlife Population Assessment, University of St. Andrews, UK
. 
http://www.ruwpa. st-and.ac.uk/distance/
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
