<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>ZooKeys</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.328.5768</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Rotational Scanning Electron Micrographs (rSEM): A novel and accessible
               tool to visualize and communicate complex morphology</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Arthropoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Dalodesmidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Haplodesmidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Myriapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Oxysarcodexia (Xylocamptopsis) fringidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sarcophagidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ommatoiulus khroumiriensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Julidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Diplopoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Bolitogyrus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Staphylinidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Oxysarcodexia (Xylocamptopsis) fringidea</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sarcophagidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Abstract </p>
         <p>An accessible workflow is presented to create interactive, rotational scanning electron
            micrographs (rSEM). These information-rich animations facilitate the study and
            communication of complex morphological structures exemplified here by male arthropod
            genitalia. Methods are outlined for the publication of rSEMs on the web or in journal
            articles as SWF files. Image components of rSEMs were archived in MorphBank to ensure
            future data access. rSEM represents a promising new addition to the toolkit of a new
            generation of digital taxonomy.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Keywords: Scanning electron microscopy, digital taxonomy, interactive animation</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Introduction</p>
         <p> In the effort to discover, describe and organize the planet's biodiversity, taxonomists
            are faced with the challenge of providing clear and concise diagnostic characters in
            species descriptions, often involving structures with complex morphology. To address
            this challenge, a variety of imaging methods have emerged over the past ten years to
            complement more traditional line drawings, which continue to play an important role in
            species descriptions. Traditionally, diagnostic characters are illustrated in one or a
            set of standard views to facilitate the comparison of taxa within and between
            publications by taxonomists and other users. In this current paradigm, characters not or
            suboptimally visible in these conventional views are difficult for taxonomists to convey
            and for users to interpret, placing a constraint on the range of published morphological
            data. These issues are further exacerbated in the case of complex or asymmetrical male
            genitalia, which are challenging to clearly and accurately describe in words.
            Multifocal, 'stacked' images of external structures or habitus are now standard in most
            taxonomic descriptions and recent advances in micro-computed tomography ( µCT ) and
            magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) promise to yield exciting new character data from both
            external and internal morphology (i.e., , , ); even from non-sclerotized specimens
            preserved in alcohol ( ) or living specimens ( ). Both µCT and MRI scans can be
            represented as rotating ( ), even interactive ( ) animations and have dramatically
            increased the level of morphological data available to users in one 'illustration' .
            Raman-atomic force microscopy has revealed morphological differences in molecular
            surface structure between various <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name> taxa, at the
            nanometer level of resolution ( ). </p>
         <p> Since the early 1970s (for an early example, see ), scanning electron microscopy (SEM)
            has had an increasingly important role in several taxonomic fields, especially the study
            of <tp:taxon-name>Arthropoda</tp:taxon-name> , in exploring the fine surface sculpture
            and other morphological aspects impossible to assess with a standard stereo- or compound
            microscope, or poorly resolved at higher magnifications using µCT and MRI (e.g., ; , ; ,
            ; ; ; ). For some millipede families (i.e., <tp:taxon-name>Dalodesmidae</tp:taxon-name>
            Cook, 1896, <tp:taxon-name>Haplodesmidae</tp:taxon-name> Cook, 1896) characterized by
            minute genitalia, descriptions of new taxa are based primarily on SEM, supplemented with
            line drawings (e.g., , ). Additionally, the level of detail and magnification provided
            by SEMs are now commonly harnessed to facilitate the interpretation of phylogenetic
            character states (e.g. , ). </p>
         <p> Recently, we have sought for an accessible method to integrate and present diagnostic
            differences of taxa existing at non-standard and standard angles, using SEM micrographs.
            Here we describe an SEM image workflow that results in information-rich, rotatable
            animations (hereafter referred to as rSEMs - rotational scanning electron micrographs),
            which can be either web published or embedded in PDF articles for publication in
            journals accepting such media (e.g., ZooKeys). Examples of rSEM from different arthropod
            groups ( <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name> ,
               <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name>Myriapoda</tp:taxon-name> )
            are provided. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Specimen preparation and mounting">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Specimen preparation and mounting</p>
         <p> Larger, dry specimens were mounted (see below) without special cleaning or dehydration.
            Specimens preserved in 70% ethanol or glycerin were first cleaned of debris and then
            dehydrated in 96% ethanol, then acetone, and air dried before mounting. Fragile
            specimens (e.g. small flies, nymphs, larvae) should be dried using critical point drying
            to avoid shriveling or collapsing ( ). Specimens with a broad, flattened base can be
            mounted directly onto the SEM stub (Fig. 1A). The majority of specimens will have a much
            smaller contact point with the stub and should be attached via flexible secondary mounts
            consisting of electrical tape or thin, aluminum wire (Fig. 1B). Specimens should be
            mounted as close to the center of rotation and as perpendicular to the SEM stub surface
            as possible (Fig. 1), to reduce image alignment difficulties and 'swaying' rSEMs.
            Secondary mounts allow manipulation of the specimen to the optimal position, even after
            coating. </p>
         <p>Image Acquisition and processing</p>
         <p>For users unfamiliar with the elements of this workflow, a step-by-step set of
            instructions is provided in provided in Appendix 1. Specimens were sputter-coated with
            platinum/palladium and studied with a JEOL JSM-6335F scanning electron microscope. Note
            that the microscope stage MUST be able to tilt to 90° in order to produce a usable
            animation (Fig. 2). Images were taken at fixed rotational intervals and named
            sequentially.</p>
         <p> Images were then processed (adjusting the exposure, contrast, highlights, shadows,
            whites, blacks) and cropped to improve image quality and detail, and to ensure that all
            images were 'aligned' , such that they form a smooth transition when browsed in
            sequence. Images were exported as JPG. Image processing can be accomplished using
            subscription based software such as Adobe® Lightroom® or Photoshop®, or open-source
            software such as ImageJ (http://rsbweb.nih.gov/ij/). The images can now be integrated
            into an animation for submission to a scientific journal or published on a website. The
            individual images generated for this study were archived in MorphBank under object
            #830913, 830920-830935, 830953-830970 and 831016-831034; they can be found together by
            searching for collection 'rSEM' . </p>
         <p> Creation of rSEMs for submission to a journal </p>
         <p> rSEMs in the present article and in were submitted as SWF files. These files were
            embedded in the PDF version of each article by the publisher and therefore instructions
            for this procedure are not included here. Depending on the journal, SWF files may be
            embedded or included as downloadable, supplementary figures (Appendix 1 and 2). We have
            opted for the integrated nature of embedded files as plates rather than disjointed
            supplementary files. The creation of rSEMs was performed using Adobe® Flash® CS5, which
            were then exported as SWF files. Images were inserted as individual key frames and
            animated using the following Action Script in the action palette (script by 'winlwin' ,
            http://www.icodesnip.com/snippet/actionscript-3/360-degree-view): </p>
         <p>import flash.events.Event; instancename.stop(); var frameTo:Number=0;
            addEventListener(Event.ENTER_FRAME,goTo); function goTo(e:Event):void
            {frameTo=int(mouseX/stage.stageWidth*instancename.totalFrames)+1;
            instancename.gotoAndStop(frameTo);}</p>
         <p> Web publication of rSEM </p>
         <p> To publish an rSEM on the web, a program or web plug-in is needed to integrate the
            images into an animation. There is a multitude of these available online of varying
            quality and functionality (search 'object viewer' or '360 panorama' ) ranging from
            subscription-based (Magic 360 (TM) (http://www.magictoolbox.com/magic360/)) to free and
            open-source (Reel© 1.2.1 (http://jquery.vostrel.cz/reel#dict)). A set of scripts needs
            to be downloaded and a folder containing the sequentially numbered images should be
            created. We have tested the two previously mentioned options and both result in web
            animations that are compatible with all operating systems, including mobile devices. For
            full instructions, readers are directed to the tutorials provided by the publishers (see
            links above). The rSEMs included in the html version of and the present paper (Figs 3-5)
            were created using Reel 1.2.1, and an example of Magic 360 output is given in Appendix
            2. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Discussion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Discussion </p>
         <p> The workflow described herein will generate interactive, information-rich animations
            that facilitate both the study and communication of complex morphology in systematics
            (Figs 3-5). rSEMs combine sharply detailed SEM micrographs into a single, holistic
            representation of a structure that may even reveal diagnostic characters visible but yet
            unnoticed when using a light microscope. The use of SEM is not always optimal or
            appropriate as users may not have access to facilities or cannot image large, fragile or
            unique specimens. In these cases, morphological characters will still need to be
            illustrated by line drawings or stacked images, despite their potential complexity.
            Differ ences in color and degree of sclerotization are also lost in SEM. However, rSEMs
            can be created using technology and software in widespread use and provide an accessible
            alternative to other imaging methods such as µCT if the user is focused on structural
            aspects of external morphology. As HTML5 is becoming more prominent than Flash® as a
            media development standard, an update is planned to incorporate instructions for
            developing rSEM in HTML5. rSEMs are integrated into a taxonomic revision for the first
            time in a companion article ( ) to provide clear, accurate and user-accessible
            descriptions of morphological structures, which are typically difficult to interpret
            without taxonomic expertise. </p>
         <p> With the development of Web 2.0 and Open Access publishing, the demand for image
            quality and methods for visualizing taxonomic traits has increased. Recently, publishing
            3D models and embedding multimedia files in biomedical journals has become common
            practice (e.g. , ). However, the adoption of such media in taxonomy is still relatively
            scattered, and is mostly limited to MRI and Micro-computed Tomography (e.g. , , , ).
            This may be due to the perception that sophisticated imaging requires special software,
            e-infrastructure and significant funding. The rSEM workflow provided here demonstrates
            this to be incorrect. The workflow does not require special equipment beyond that of a
            scanning electron microscope and the processing and integration of images can be
            accomplished using photo editing software and Adobe Flash CS5 or a plug-in such as Reel
            1.2.1. </p>
         <p> Here, additional rSEMs of arthropod genitalia were provided as examples of complex
            morphology. However, this approach could easily be extended to structures than other
            genitalia, and could be applied to the illustration of a phylogenetically important
            character system (e.g., a rotatable insect head capsule). So far, we have only animated
            rSEM in the x-axis because our test structures varied mainly along the y-axis. However,
            illustration of structures along both x and y-axes of rotation, while requiring many
            more images, may be a powerful form of data delivery in certain situations. For example,
            if a finely controlled, electronic stage is available, full-color, rotatable habitus
            images could be produced using a dissecting microscope and stacking software. There are
            clearly far more applications of rSEM or rSEM-like animations than we have presented
            here, and we encourage readers to experiment with this technique in their own scientific
            exploration of Earth's biodiversity. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>We are grateful to Nikolaj Scharff (Copenhagen) for sharing some insights on SEM
            mounting techniques, Petr Vostrel for making his Reel plug-in freely available online.
            Daniel Mietchen, Pavel Stoev and one anonymous reviewer provided comments that greatly
            improved this manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Andersen, MS , Gaimari, SD , 2003 . Raman-atomic force microscopy of
                  the ommatidial surfaces of Dipteran compound eyes. . Journal of Structural Biology
                  142 : 364 - 368 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Akkari, N , Cheung, DK-B , Enghoff, H , Stoev, P , 2013 . Revolving
                  SEM images visualising 3D taxonomic characters: application to six species of the
                  millipede genus Ommatoiulus Latzel, 1884, with description of seven new species
                  and an interactive key to the Tunisian members of the genus (Diplopoda, Julida,
                  Julidae). . ZooKeys 328 : 5 - 45 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Akkari, N , Enghoff, H , 2011 . On some surface structures of
                  potential taxonomic importance in families of the suborders Polydesmidea and
                  Dalodesmidea (Polydesmida, Diplopoda). . Zookeys 156 : 1 - 24 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Akkari, N , Enghoff, H , 2012 . Review of the genus Ommatoiulus in
                  Andalusia, Spain (Diplopoda: Julida) with description of ten new species and notes
                  on a remarkable gonopod structure, the fovea. . Zootaxa 2528 : 1 - 53
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Beutel, R , Ge, S , Hoernschemeyer , T , 2008 . On the head
                  morphology of Tetraphalerus, the phylogeny of Archostemata and the basal branching
                  events in Coleoptera. . Cladistics 24 : 270 - 298 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Boistel, R , Swoger, J , Krzic , U , Fernandez, V , Gillet, B ,
                  Reynaud, EG , 2011 . The future of three-dimensional microscopic imaging in marine
                  biology. . Marine Ecology 32 : 438 - 452 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Chani-Posse, M , 2013 . Towards a natural classification of the
                  subtribe Philonthina (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae: Staphylinini): a phylogenetic
                  analysis of the Neotropical genera. . Systematic Entomology 38 : 390 - 406
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Edgecombe, DG , Hollington, LM , 2005 . Morphology and relationships
                  of a new species of Henicops (Chilopoda: Lithobiomorpha) from New South Wales and
                  Queensland, Australia. . Zootaxa 961 : 1 - 20 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Faulwetter, S , Vasileiadou, A , Kouratoras, M , Dailianis, T ,
                  Arvanitidis, C , 2013 . Micro-computed tomography: introducing new dimensions to
                  taxonomy. . ZooKeys 263 : 1 - 45 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Grzywacz, A , Szpila, K , Pape, T , 2012 . Egg morphology of nine
                  species of Pollenia Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830 (Diptera: Calliphoridae). . Microscopy
                  Research and Technique 75 : 955 - 967 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hart, AG , Bowtell, RW , Kockenberger, W , Wenseleers, T , Ratnieks,
                  FLW , 2003 . Magnetic resonance imaging in entomology: a critical review. .
                  Journal of Insect Science 3 : 1 - 9 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Herman, LH , 1972 . Revision of Bledius and related genera. Part I.
                  The aequatorialis, mandibularis, and semiferrugineus groups and two new genera
                  (Coleoptera, Staphylinidae, Oxytelinae). . Bulletin of the American Museum of
                  Natural History 149 : 111 - 254 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Laforsch, C , Imhof, H , Sigl, R , Settles, M , Hess , M ,
                  Wanninger, A , Alexandru, C , 2012 . InTech, Rijeka . 10.5772/31092
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lowe , T , Garwood,, RJ , Simonsen,, TJ , Bradley,, RS , Withers, PJ
                  , 2013 . Imaging inside a living chrysalis. Journal of the Royal Society Interface
                  10, 20130304. . 10.1098/rsif.2013.0304 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Mesibov, R , 2008 . The millipede genera Gephyrodesmus Jeekel, 1983
                  and Orthorhachis Jeekel, 1985 in southeastern Australia, a new Lissodesmus
                  Chamberlin, 1920 from Victoria, and observations on male leg setae, spinnerets and
                  metatergite sculpture (Diplopoda: Polydesmida: Dalodesmidae). . Zootaxa 1790 : 1 -
                  52 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Mesibov, R , 2009 . Revision of Agathodesmus Silvestri, 1910
                  (Diplopoda, Polydesmida, Haplodesmidae). . Zookeys 12 : 87 - 110 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Mietchen, D , Aberhan, M , Manz, B , Hampe, O , Mohr, B , Neumann, C
                  , Volke, F , 2008 . Three-dimensional magnetic resonance imaging of fossils across
                  taxa. . Biogeosciences 5 , 25 pp. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Miller, JA , Griswold, CE , Scharff, N , Řezac , M , Szűts , T ,
                  Marhabaie, M , 2012 . The velvet spiders: an atlas of the Eresidae (Arachnida,
                  Araneae). . ZooKeys 195 : 1 - 144 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Oster, G , Pollister, A , 1966 . Physical techniques in biological
                  research. . New York: Academic Press , 310 pp. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Rota, J , 2005 . Larval and pupal descriptions of the Neotropical
                  choreutid genera Rhobonda Walker and Zodia Heppner (Lepidoptera: Choreutidae). .
                  Annals of the Entomological Society of America 98 : 37 - 47 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Shear, W , 2012 . Snoqualmia, a new polydesmid millipede genus from
                  the northwestern United States, with a description of two new species (Diplopoda,
                  Polydesmida, Polydesmidae). . Insecta Mundi 238 : 1 - 13 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Tyzack, JK , 2008 . Dragging (and zooming and rotating) publication
                  of 3D molecular structures into the 21st century. . Trends in Biochemical Sciences
                  33 : 405 - 407 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Whitmore, D , 2009 . A review of the Sarcophaga (Heteronychia)
                  (Diptera: Sarcophagidae) of Sardinia. . Zootaxa 2318 : 566 - 588 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Whitmore, D , 2011 . New taxonomic and nomenclatural data on
                  Sarcophaga (Heteronychia) (Diptera: Sarcophagidae), with description of six new
                  species. . Zootaxa 2778 : 1 - 57 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ziegler, A , Mietchen, D , Faber, C , von Hausen, W , Schoebel , Ch
                  , Sellerer, M , Ziegler, A , 2011 . Effectively incorporating selected multimedia
                  content into medical publications. . BMC Medicine 9 , 17 pp. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Appendix 1 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>New user guide to the creation and publication of rSEM (doi:
            10.3897/zookeys.328.5768.app1) File format: Microsoft Word document (doc).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Explanation note: A step-by-step style of instructions for new users, involving the
            software used by the authors. Note: in the future, these instructions may not correspond
            exactly with the interfaces of the corresponding software.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Appendix 2</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> rSEM illustrating the distiphallus of <tp:taxon-name>Oxysarcodexia (Xylocamptopsis)
               fringidea</tp:taxon-name> (Curran &amp; Walley) (
               <tp:taxon-name>Sarcophagidae</tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>
            ); web-published using Magic 360TM script files. Click and drag to rotate the rSEM and
            point click to open and close the magnification tool. (doi:
            10.3897/zookeys.328.5768.app2) File format: Hypertext Markup Document, archived (zip).
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Explanation note: Example of rSEM published online using Magic 360TM script.</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
