<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113153</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Cytotoxic compounds from the leaf of Bersama abyssinica subspecies abyssinica</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>06</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bersama
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
(Fresen)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bersama
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
subsp. 
paulliniodes
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
subsp. 
abyssinica
(
Nyamboki et al., 2021
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
subsp. 
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
subsp. 
paullinioides
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
(Fresen) subsp. 
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Cytotoxic compounds from the leaf of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
subspecies 
<tp:taxon-name>
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Divinah Kwamboka Nyamboki
a, d
, Kibrom Gebreheiwot Bedane
a, e
, Khadija Hassan
b, c
,
</p>
         <p>
Michael Spiteller 
a
, Josphat Clement Matasyoh

a, d, 
*
</p>
         <p>
a

Institute of Environmental Research (INFU), Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, TU Dortmund, Otto-Hahn-Strasse 6, 44227, Dortmund, 
Germany

</p>
         <p>
b

Department of Microbial Drugs, Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research, 38124, Braunschweig, 
Germany

</p>
         <p>
c

German Centre for Infection Research (DZIF), Partner Site Hannover-Braunschweig, 38124, Braunschweig, 
Germany

</p>
         <p>
d

Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Sciences, Egerton University, P.O. Box 536, 20115, Egerton, 
Kenya

e

Department of Chemistry, 
Addis Ababa
University, P.O. Box 33658, 
Addis Ababa
, 
Ethiopia

</p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:

</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Cytotoxicity</p>
         <p>Bufadienolides</p>
         <p>KB3.1 cell lines</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p>
From the leaves of Kenyan medicinal plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
Subspecies 
<tp:taxon-name>
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
, four previously undescribed compounds namely, three bufadienolides, 10 
β
-formylpaulliniogenin B, 10 
β
-formylpaulliniogenin A and 1 
β
- acetoxy-3 
β
,5 
β
-dihydroxy-15-methoxy-16,19-dioxobufa-14(15),20,22-trienolide, and a phenolic compound 2,6,4 
′
-trihydroxybenzophenone-4-O-(6 
′′′
-cinnamoyl)-β- D-glucoside were isolated together with four known compounds. The structural elucidation of the compounds was based on 1D and 2D NMR spectroscopy and HRMS data analyses. The relative configurations were defined by NOESY correlations. Cytotoxic activities on L929 and KB3.1 cell lines of the isolated compounds were investigated using MTT assay. The 1 
β
-acetoxy-3 
β
,5 
β
-dihydroxy- 15-methoxy-16,19-dioxobufa-14(15),20,22-trienolide showed significant cytotoxic activity against KB3.1 cell lines with IC 
50
of 3.9 ± 0.99 μM.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction

</title>
         <p>
Plants of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bersama
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
family) are broadly dispersed in sub-Saharan Africa (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
(Fresen)
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
is widely distributed in 
Kenya
. Plants in the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
are rich sources of bufadienolides (S. Steyn and R. van Heerden, 1998), a group of compounds with a steroidal structure having a 17 
β
-2H-pyran-2-one ring system. Previous phytochemical studies on the plant led to identification of several cytotoxic bufadienolides (Kupchan et al., 1971a; Kupchan et al., 1971b; 

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
has been used as a source of traditional medicine for various ailments (

; Kupchan et al., 1971a). The leaf decoctions are used to treat stomach disorders such as diarrhea, cholera, dysentery, and intestinal worms. Earlier pharmacological studies on different extracts of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bersama
</tp:taxon-name>
plant exhibited antimicrobial (

) and antitumor activities (Kupchan et al., 1971a; Kupchan et al., 1971b).
</p>
         <p>
As a part of our ongoing research program on phytochemical investigation of medicinal plants of 
Kenya
, we recently reported bioactive bufadienolides from the stem barks of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
subsp. 
paulliniodes
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
subsp. 
abyssinica
(
Nyamboki et al., 2021
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Herein, we report the isolation, employing different chromatography techniques, and structural elucidation by NMR, mass spectrometry of four new compounds (
1–4
) and four known compounds from the leaves of this plant. To evaluate the bioactivities of the isolated compounds, cytotoxicity assay against HeLa (KB3.1) and mouse fibroblast (L929) cell lines was carried out.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. Results and discussion

</title>
         <p>
The MeOH extract of the leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
subsp. 
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
was subjected to sequential column chromatography over silica gel and Sephadex LH-20, followed by preparative HPLC to afford eight compounds 
1–8
(
Fig. 1
).
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
1
was isolated as colorless powder with a molecular formula C 
27
H 
30
O 
8
, which was determined from its HRESIMS at 
m/z
483.2016 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
27
H 
31
O 
8
, 483.2013). The NMR data assignment was done by analysis of 1D and 2D NMR spectra and by
</p>
         <p>
* Corresponding author. Institute of Environmental Research (INFU), Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, TU Dortmund, Otto-Hahn-Strasse 6, 44227, Dortmund, 
Germany
.
</p>
         <p>
E-mail address:
jmatasyoh@egerton.ac.ke (J.C. Matasyoh).
</p>
         <p>
comparison with analogues bufadienolides reported in literature data (

). These data (
Table 1
) suggested that 
1
has a bufadienolide steroidal structure with α- pyrone ring system. The presence of this characteristic α- pyrone (2H-pyran-2-one) ring was evident from the 
1
H NMR data (
Table 1
) [
δH
7.53 (H-21, s), 7.31 (H-22, d, 
J
= 9.6 Hz), and 6.34 (H-23, d, 
J
= 9.6 Hz)] and 
13
C NMR data [
δC
153.1 (C-21), 147.8 (C-22) and 116.2 (C-23)] (

). Compound 
1
also possessed an orthoacetate group in ring A, as confirmed from the presence of a characteristic orthoacetate singlet methyl proton at H 
3
-26 (
δH
1.34), which showed a strong HMBC correlation with C-25 (
δC
112.0) (

). Long-range HMBC correlations of H-1 (
δH
4.65) with C-25 (
δC
112.0) also supporting the presence of the orthoacetate structure in ring A. The COSY correlations of H 
2
-2 with H-1 and H-3, and H-3 with H 
2
-2 and H 
2
-4 identified the connectivity sequence in the A ring. Signals for 27 carbon atoms were observed in the 
13
C NMR spectrum. Comparison of its experimental and reported NMR data revealed that 
1
has similar NMR values with paulliniogenin B, which has been recently isolated from the bark 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
subsp. 
paullinioides
</tp:taxon-name>
b 
y
our group (

). The difference being the presence of a formyl group at C- 
19 in
1
. The presence of α, β- unsaturated carbonyl group in ring D was confirmed from signals at 
δC
162.4 (C-14), 
δC
151.3 (C-15), and 
δC
203.0 (C-16). It was also confirmed by the HMBC correlations of H 
3
-18 to C-14, H-17 to C-14, C-15 and C-16. Position of the methoxy group (
δH
3.81, 
δC
59.2) at C-15 was determined by strong HMBC correlations from the OMe-15 methoxy protons to C-15 (
δC
151.3). HMBC from H-17 (
δH
3.23) to C-13, C-16, C-18, C-20, C-21, and C-22 were important correlations observed in ring D and confirmed the position of the α- pyrone ring at C-17. A Singlet methyl group at 
δH
0.92 (
δC
23.2) is typical steroidal methyl group and was assigned to C-18 based on their HMBC correlations, H 
3
-18 to C-12, C-13, C-14, and C-17. The presence of a formyl group was determined from its proton at 
δH
10.25 (H-19) that showed HSQC correlation with 
δC
208.7 (C-19). HMBC correlation of formyl proton, H-19 with C-10 (
δC
54.4) confirmed the position of the formyl group at C-10.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
The relative configuration of 
1
was defined based on NOESY correlations and biosynthetic considerations, as it has the same stereogenic centers as paulliniogenin B (

). The configuration of the formyl group at C-10 assigned β- orientation based on NOESY correlations of H-19/H-8 and H-8/H 
3
-18. The NOESY correlations between H-19 and H-8 and between H-8 and H 
3
-18 suggested the β- orientation of H 
3
-18, H-8, and the formyl group at C-10. Additional NOESY correlations from H 
3
-18 to H-21 and H-22 confirmed the β- orientation of the α- pyrone ring. Thus, the structure of compound 
1
was determined as 10 
β
-formylpaulliniogenin A.
</p>
         <p>
a
Signals without multiplicity are overlapping signals deduced from the HSQC spectrum. 

b

Recorded at (
1
H: 700 MHz, 
13
C: 175 MHz). 

c

Recorded at (
1
H: 600 MHz, 
13
C: 150 MHz).

</p>
         <p>
Compound 
2
was isolated as a white powder with a molecular formula C 
26
H 
28
O 
7
, as determined from the HRESIMS at 
m/z
453.1912 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
26
H 
29
O 
7
, 453.1907). Its NMR data were very similar to those of 
1
except the absence of the methoxy signals in 
2
, and in effect, the C-15 chemical shift was more upfield (
δC
124.9) compared to 
δC
151.3 in
1
. The resulting vinylic singlet proton signal 
δH
5.96 (H-15) showed HMBC correlations with C-14, C-15, and C-17. The complete 
1
H and 
13
C NMR signal assignments and connectivity were determined from a combination of 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HSQC, and HMBC data. The relative configuration of 
2
was established from the observed identical coupling constants and NOESY correlations as in 
1
. Comparison of its NMR data with reported data indicated that 
2
has similar NMR values with paulliniogenin A except 
2
has a formyl group at C-19 (

). The presence of a formyl group was determined from its proton at 
δH
10.23 (H-19) that showed HSQC correlation with 
δC
208.5 (C-19). HMBC correlation of the formyl proton, H-19 with C-10 (
δC
54.4) confirmed the position of the formyl group at C-10. Therefore, the structure of 
2
was elucidated as 10 
β
-formylpaulliniogenin A.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
3
gave a molecular ion at 
m/z
501.2123 for [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
27
H 
33
O 
9
, 501.2119) in the HRESIMS defined a molecular formula C 
27
H 
32
O 
9
. Unlike the previous compounds, 
3
has no orthoacetate ring. It possessed an acetoxy group deduced from its carbonyl carbons at 
δC
171.9, and an acetoxy methyl group at 
δC
21.3 (
δH
1.98). The COSY correlations of H-1 to H 
2
-2, H 
2
-2 to H-3 and H-3 to H 
2
-4 identified a connectivity sequence in ring-A. The structure of ring-A and its NMR signals are identical to those reported for bersaldegenin 1-acetate (

). HMBC correlation of H-1 (
δH
5.75) with 
δC
171.9 confirmed the position of the acetoxy group at C-1. The presence of a formyl group was established from its proton at 
δH
10.14 (H-19) that showed HSQC correlation with 
δC
207.5 (C-19). HMBC correlation of the formyl proton (H-19) with C-10 (
δC
58.2) confirmed position of the formyl group at C-10. The remaining rings have identical NMR spectra as in compound 
1
. The relative configuration of 
3
was defined based on NOESY correlations and biosynthetic considerations, as it has the same stereogenic centers as 
1
. The NOESY correlations of H-19 with H-8, H-8 with H 
3
-18, and H 
3
-18 with H-22 suggested the formyl group and the pyrone ring to be 
β
-cofacially oriented. Additional NOESY correlations of H-1α (
δH
5.75) with H-11α (
δH
1.85) showed that the acetoxy group at C-2 was 
β
-oriented. Thus, the new compound (
3
) was identified as 1 
β
-acetoxy-3 
β
,5 
β
-dihydroxy-15-methoxy-16,19-dioxobufa-14(15),20,22-trienolide.
</p>
         <p>
a
Overlapping with solvent peak, deduced from HSQC.

</p>
         <p>
Compound 
4
was isolated as a yellow powder with a molecular formula C 
28
H 
26
O 
11
that was determined from its HRESIMS at 
m/z
539.1554 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
28
H 
27
O 
11
, 539.1553). A total of 28 carbons were observed on the 
13
C NMR spectrum (
Table 2
). The shielded aromatic methines at 
δC
98.2 (C-3), 
δC
96.1 (C-5), 
δC
133.5 (C-2 
′
and C- 6 
′
) and 
δC
115.7 (C-3 
′
and C-5 
′
) are typical of phenolic natural compounds. The signal at 
δC
197.5 (C-7) corresponds to carbonyl of a benzophenone (

). Four quaternary carbon signals, C-2 (
δC
162.6), C-4 (
δC
158.7), C-6 (
δC
160.0) and C-4’ (
δC
163.4), correspond to oxygenated aromatic carbons. The NMR of sub structure of 
4
, the benzophenone and the sugar moiety, are identical to those of 
5
(

). The difference being the presence of a cinnamoyl group in 
4
. The 
1
H NMR and the HSQC spectra revealed an anomeric signal (
δH
4.88, m, H1 
′′
and 
δC
101.9, C1 
′′
) together with a set of signals between 
δH
3.17–4.51 in
1
H NMR and 
δC
64.8–77.8 in
13
C NMR, firmly established the presence of a glucopyranose (

). The HMBC correlation between the anomeric proton H-1" (
δH
4.88) and C-4 (
δC
158.7) indicated 4-O-linkage between the sugar moiety and benzophenone. The cinnamoyl subunit was deduced from aromatic protons (
δH
7.42–7.63) and two olefinic 
trans
coupled protons (
δH
6.60, 
d
, 
J
= 16.0 Hz and 
δH
7.7, 
d
, 
J
= 16.0 Hz), correlated in HMBC with carbonyl carbon 
δC
168.5 (C-1 
′′′
) (

). The HMBC correlation from the methylene proton, H-6 
′′
of the sugar moiety to the carbonyl carbon, 
δC
168.5 (C-1 
′′′
) provided a link between the two subunits. The cinnamoyl fragment ion was also observed in HRMS at 
m/z
131.0493. Further analysis of the HRMS 
2
indicated fragment ion at 
m/z
293.1021 [C 
15
H 
17
O 
6
] 
+
and 
m/z
247.0602 [C 
13
H 
11
O 
5
] 
+
due to cleavage of the acetophenone and sugar moiety at 4-O linkage. A combination of 
1
H– 
1
H COSY, HSQC and HMBC data were used to determine the complete 
1
H and 
13
C NMR signal assignments. The 
type
of sugar was deduced from compound 
5
which is known (

). The main difference between compounds 
4
and 
5
is the presence of the cinnamoyl group in 
4
. The NMR data of the two compounds were also comparable. The structure of compound 
4
was therefore determined as 2,6, 4 
′
-trihydroxybenzophenone-4-O-(6 
′′′
-cinnamoyl)-β- D-glucoside.
</p>
         <p>
The known compounds were identified as 4-O- 
β
-D-glucopyranosyl- 2,6,4 
′
-trihydroxybenzophenone (
5
) (

), flacourtoside A (
6
) (

), quercetin-3-O- 
β
-D-glucoside 
7
(

), and quercetin-3-O-xyloside 
8
(

).
</p>
         <p>
Compounds 
2–3
and 
5–8
were subjected to cytotoxicity tests against HeLa (KB3.1) and mouse fibroblast (L929) mammalian cell lines (
Table 3
). Compound 
3
exhibited significant cytotoxicity against KB3.1 cell line with IC 
50
value of 3.9 ± 0.99 μM. Cytotoxic activity was also observed against KB3.1 cell line with IC 
50
value of 16.35 ± 2.45 μM for compound 
6
. However, none of the compounds tested were cytotoxic against mouse fibroblast L929 cell line. Due to limited material, compounds 
1
and 
4
were not tested.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Conclusions

</title>
         <p>
The present phytochemical study which is carried out for the first time on the leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
Subspecies 
<tp:taxon-name>
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
, allowed the isolation of four undescribed compounds (
1–4
), together with four known compounds. The isolated bufadienolides were characterized with formyl group at C-19. Whereas, those isolated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
subspecies 
paullioniodes
have a methyl group at this position (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
a
Data are expressed as mean SD; n 3 independent experiments. 
b
Positive ± = control.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Experimental

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.1. General experimental procedures

</title>
         <p>
Optical rotations were determined using a Kruss P8000-T polarimeter in methanol at 25 
◦
C. IR spectra were recorded by Bruker Tensor-27 FT-IR Spectrometer using a diffuse reflection apparatus (cricket, Harrick Scientific). UV spectra were measured using UV-1602 UV-VIS spectrometry (Shimadzu). NMR experiments were performed with a Bruker Avance III spectrometer operating at 700 MHz (
1
H) and 175 MHz (
13
C). High-resolution mass spectra (HRESIMS) were carried out using LTQ Orbitrap spectrometer (Thermo Scientific, 
USA
) equipped with a HESI-II ion source. For column chromatography, Silica gel 60 (
0.063–0.2 mm
, Macherey-Nagel) and Sephadex LH–20 (18–111 μm, GE Healthcare) were used. TLC was carried out on pre-coated silica gel 60 plates (
0.20 mm
, Macherey-Nagel). Semi-preparative HPLC was done on Shimadzu LC-20AP pump equipped with DGU-20A5R degassing unit, Shimadzu SPD-M20A detector, Shimadzu SIL-20ACHT auto-sampler using LabSolutions software.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.2. Plant material

</title>
         <p>
The
leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bersama abyssinica
(Fresen) subsp. 
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Melianthaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) was collected from 
Mt. Elgon Forest
(

1.1493 
◦
N

, 

34.5418 
◦
E

), 
Kenya
in 

March 2019

during the wet season. 
Prof. S.T Kariuki
, a taxonomist of the herbarium at 
Egerton University
, identified the plants. 
Voucher
specimen BW12 was deposited at the department of biological sciences, 
Egerton University

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3. Extraction and isolation

</title>
         <p>
The air-dried leaves of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
subp. 
<tp:taxon-name>
abyssinica
</tp:taxon-name>
(
1642.9 g
) was soaked with MeOH for 24 h, thrice at room temperature. The extract was concentrated under reduced pressure to give brown residue (
194 g
). About 
190 g
of the extract was applied to column chromatography (CC) over silica gel 60 and eluted with cyclohexane/EtOAc and then EtOAc/ MeOH mixtures of increasing polarities. Fractions were combined into nine fractions based on similar LCMS profile. Fraction 7 (EtOAc 100%) and fraction 9 (EtOAc/MeOH 80:20) were subjected to further HPLC separation. The fractions were passed through Sephadex LH-20 prior to separation by preparative HPLC.
</p>
         <p>
Compounds were separated on a Gemini C18 column (10 × 
250 mm
, 10 μm particle size, Phenomenex) using the following gradient programme: 45%–65% MeOH (B) over 25 min and thereafter isocratic conditions at 100% solvent B for 10 min, the system returned within 0.5 min to initial conditions of 55% water (A) (0.1% formic acid) and was equilibrated for 10 min; flow rate: 4 mL/min, detection: UV at λ 254, 275, and 
350 nm
. Eleven fractions (F7A-F7K) were collected from fraction 7 and fourteen fractions (F9-1-F9-14) from fraction 9. Fraction F7K was further purified by a reverse-phase preparative HPLC using VP 125/10 NUCLEODUR PolarTec column (10 × 
125 mm
, 5 μm, Macherey-Nagel) as a stationary phase with a flow rate of 4 mL/min, elution gradient: 55% isocratic conditions for 10 min, to afford compounds 
1
(
4.8 mg
) and 
3
(1.0 mg). The same column was used for the purification of the other fractions. Compound 
2
(
2.1 mg
) was obtained from fraction F7H using 50% isocratic condition for 10 min. Fraction F7J was purified using 55% isocratic condition for 12 min to afford compound 
4
(
1.3 mg
). Compound 
5
(
1.8 mg
) was obtained from fraction F7D using 40% isocratic condition for 15 min. Compound 
6
(
1.3 mg
) was purified from fraction F9-4 with isocratic elution of 40% solvent B for 10 min. Compound 
7
(
3.4 mg
) and compound 
8
(
1.6 mg
) were purified from fraction F9-13 and fraction F9-14 respectively with isocratic conditions of 50% solvent for 10 min.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.1. 10β- formylpaulliniogenin B (1)

</title>
         <p>
25
</p>
         <p>
Colorless powder; [
α
] 
D
+ 81.4 (
c
0.3, MeOH); LC-UV [acetonitrile in H 
2
O (0.1% formic acid)] 
λ
max
255, 300 nm
; IR (neat) 
ν
max
3435, 2935, 1711, 
1627 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
483.2016 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
27
H 
31
O 
8
, 483.2013).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.2. 10β- formylpaulliniogenin A (2)

</title>
         <p>
White powder; [
α
] 
D
25
+ 17.6 (
c
0.1, MeOH); LC-UV [acetonitrile in H 
2
O (0.1% formic acid)] 
λ
max
226, 303 nm
; IR (neat) 
ν
max
3410, 2934, 2358, 1719, 
1594 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
453.1912 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
26
H 
29
O 
7
, 453.1907)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.3.3. 1β- acetoxy-3β,5β- dihydroxy-15-methoxy-16,19-dioxobufa-14

</title>
         <p>
(15),20,22-trienolide (3)

</p>
         <p>
Colorless residue; [
α
] 
D
25
+ 16.4 (
c
0.1, MeOH); LC-UV [acetonitrile in H 
2
O (0.1% formic acid)] 
λ
max
223, 256, 300 nm
; IR (neat) 
ν
max
3401, 2931, 2361, 17210, 
1592 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, 
Table 1
; HRESIMS 
m/z
501.2123 for [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
27
H 
33
O 
9
, 501.2119).
</p>
         <p>
4.3.4. 2,6,4
′
-trihydroxybenzophenone-4-O-(6
′′′
-cinnamoyl)-β- D-glucoside (4)
</p>
         <p>
25
</p>
         <p>
Yellow powder; [
α
] 
D
+ 7.6 (
c
0.1, MeOH); LC-UV [acetonitrile in H 
2
O (0.1% formic acid)] 
λ
max
203, 283 nm
; IR (neat) 
ν
max
3359, 2924, 1699, 
1598 cm
1
; 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data, 
Table 2
; HRESIMS 
m/z
539.1554 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
28
H 
27
O 
11
, 539.1553)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4. Biological assays

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4.4.1. Cytotoxicity assay

</title>
         <p>
In vitro cytotoxicity (IC 
50
) of the isolated natural products was determined against two mammalian cell lines; HeLa (KB3.1) and mouse fibroblast L929. The cell lines were obtained from the Leibniz Institute DSMZ - German Collection of Microorganisms and Cell Cultures GmbH, Braunschweig, 
Germany
. The cell lines were cultured in DMEM (Gibco, ThermoFisher Scientific Hilden, 
Germany
) media, supplemented with 10% of fetal bovine serum (Gibco) under 10% CO 
2
at 37 
◦
C. The cytotoxicity assay was performed according to the MTT (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5 diphenyltetrazolium bromide) method in 96-well microplates (

). Briefly 60 μL aliquots of serial dilutions from an initial stock of 
1 mg
/mL in MeOH of the test compounds were added to 120 μL aliquots of a cell suspension in 96-well microplates. After 5 days incubation, a MTT assay was performed, and the absorbance measured at 
590 nm
using an ELISA plate reader (Victor, PerkinElmer, Überlingen, 
Germany
). The concentration at which the growth of cells was inhibited to 50% of the control (IC 
50
) was obtained from the dose response curves. The negative control was methanol. The positive control was epithilon B with IC 
50
values of 0.000056 ± 000001 μM and 0.001081 ± 0.000776 μM for KB3.1 and L929 respectively.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Declaration of competing interest

</title>
         <p>The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Michael Spiteller reports financial support was provided by German Academic Exchange Service. Michael Spiteller reports financial support was provided by Federal Ministry of Education and Research Bonn Office. Josphat Matasyoh reports financial support was provided by Alexander von Humboldt Foundation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements

</title>
         <p>
DKN., KGB and JCM are grateful to the Institute of Environmental Research (INFU), TU-Dortmund, for research visits to do this research work. DKN is also thankful to Egerton University for the doctoral studies. Prof. S.T Kariuki (Egerton University, 
Kenya
) is acknowledged for the identification and authentication of the plant. We are thankful to Mrs. Gabriele Hardes (INFU, TU-Dortmund) for the technical assistance and Dr. Wolf Hiller (Faculty of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, TU Dortmund) for NMR measurements. Wera Collisi (HZI) is gratefully acknowledged for help with bioassays. The research was supported by the German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD) and the German Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF) under the “Partnership for Sustainable Solution in Sub-Saharan Africa” grant number SSA2015-33- 074. We are also grateful to the Alexander von Humboldt Foundation for providing fellowships to DKN and JCM.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Appendix A. Supplementary data

</title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113153.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References

</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bedane, K.G.
, 
Brieger, L.
, 
Strohmann, C.
, 
Seo, E.-J.
, 
Efferth, T.
, 
Spiteller, M.
, 
2020
a. 

Cytotoxic bufadienolides from the leaves of a medicinal plant 
Melianthus comosus
collected in South Africa

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
102
, 
104102
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. bioorg.2020.104102
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bedane, K.G.
, 
Brieger, L.
, 
Strohmann, C.
, 
Seo, E.-J.
, 
Efferth, T.
, 
Spiteller, M.
, 
2020
b. 

Cytotoxic bufadienolides from the leaves of 
Melianthus major

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
83
, 
2122–2128
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.0c00060
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bourjot, M.
, 
Leyssen, P.
, 
Eydoux, C.
, 
Guillemot, J.-C.
, 
Canard, B.
, 
Rasoanaivo, P.
, Gu´eritte, F., 
Litaudon, M.
, 
2012
. 

Flacourtosides A–F, phenolic glycosides isolated from 
Flacourtia ramontchi

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
75
, 
752–758
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/ np300059n
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bowen, I.
, 
Jackson, B.
, 
Motawe, H.
, 
1985
. 

An investigation of the stem bark of 
Bersama abyssinica

. 
Planta Med.
51
, 
483–487
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-2007-969569
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dhouafli, Z.
, 
Ben Jannet, H.
, 
Mahjoub, B.
, 
Leri, M.
, 
Guillard, J.
, 
Saidani Tounsi, M.
, 
Stefani, M.
, 
Hayouni, E.A.
, 
2019
. 1,2,4- 

trihydroxynaphthalene-2- O -β- Dglucopyranoside: a new powerful antioxidant and inhibitor of Aβ42 aggregation isolated from the leaves of 
Lawsonia inermis

. 
Nat. Prod. Res.
33
, 
1406–1414
. 
https:// doi.org/10.1080/14786419.2017.1419229
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dong, X.
, 
Huang, Y.
, 
Wang, Y.
, 
He, X.
, 
2019
. 
Anti-inflammatory and antioxidant jasmonates and flavonoids from lychee seeds
. 
J. Funct.Foods
54
, 
74–80
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.jff.2018.12.04
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Gomes, N.G.M.
, 
Oliveira, A.P.
, 
Cunha, D.
, 
Pereira, D.M.
, 
Valent˜ao, P.
, 
Pinto, E.
, 
Araújo, L.
, 
Andrade, P.B.
, 
2019
. 

Flavonoid composition of 
Salacia senegalensis
(Lam.) DC. leaves, evaluation of antidermatophytic effects, and potential amelioration of the associated inflammatory response

. 
Molecules
24
, 
2530
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.3390/molecules24142530
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kubo, I.
, 
Matsumoto, T.
, 
1984
. 

Abyssinin, a potent insect antifeedant from an african medicinal plant, 
Bersama abyssinica

. 
Tetrahedron Lett.
25
, 
4601–4604
. 
https://doi. org/10.1016/S0040-4039(01)91210-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kuete, V.
, 
Mbaveng, A.T.
, 
Tsaffack, M.
, 
Beng, V.P.
, 
Etoa, F.-X.
, 
Nkengfack, A.E.
, 
Meyer, J. J.M.
, 
Lall, N.
, 
2008
. 

Antitumor, antioxidant and antimicrobial activities of 
Bersama engleriana
(Melianthaceae)

. 
J. Ethnopharmacol.
115
, 
494–501
. 
https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.jep.2007.10.027
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kupchan, S.M.
, 
Moniot, J.L.
, 
Sigel, C.W.
, 
Hemingway, R.J.
, 
1971
. 

Tumor inhibitors. LXV. Bersenogenin, berscillogenin, and 3-epiberscillogenin, three new cytotoxic bufadienolides from 
Bersama abyssinica

. 
J. Org. Chem.
36
, 
2611–2616
. 
https://doi. org/10.1021/jo00817a011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kupchan, S.M.
, 
Ognyanov, I.
, 
Moniot, J.L.
, 
1971
. 

Tumor inhibitors. LXIV. isolation and structural elucidation of novel bufadienolides, the cytotoxic principles of 
Bersama abyssinica

. 
Bioorg. Chem.
1
, 
13–31
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/0045-2068(71)90003- 4
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Moniuszko-Szajwaj, B.
, 
Pecio, L.
, 
Kowalczyk, M.
, 
Stochmal, A.
, 
2016
. 

New bufadienolides isolated from the roots of 
Kalanchoe daigremontiana
(Crassulaceae)

. 
Molecules
21
, 
243
. 
https://doi.org/10.3390/molecules21030243
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Mossmann, P.B.
, 
1983
. 
Rapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: application to proliferation and cytotoxicity assays
. 
J. Immunol. Methods
65
, 
49–53
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nishimura, E.
, 
Murakami, S.
, 
Suzuki, K.
, 
Amano, K.
, 
Tanaka, R.
, 
Shinada, T.
, 
2016
. 

Structure Determination of monomeric phloroglucinol derivatives with a cinnamoyl group isolated from propolis of the stingless Bee, 
Tetragonula carbonaria

. 
Asian J. Org. Chem.
5
, 
855–859
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ajoc.201600106
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Nyamboki, D.K.
, 
Bedane, K.G.
, 
Hassan, K.
, 
Brieger, L.
, 
Strohmann, C.
, 
Spiteller, M.
, 
Matasyoh, J.C.
, 
2021
. 

Cytotoxic compounds from the stem bark of two subsp. of 
Bersama abyssinica

. 
J. Nat. Prod.
84
, 
1453–1458
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs. jnatprod.0c01141
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rancon, S.
, 
Chaboud, A.
, 
Darbour, N.
, 
Comte, G.
, 
Bayet, C.
, 
Simon, P.-N.
, 
Raynaud, J.
, 
Di Pietro, A.
, 
Cabalion, P.
, 
Barron, D.
, 
2001
. 
Natural and synthetic benzophenones: interaction with the cytosolic binding domain of P-glycoprotein
. 
Phytochemistry
57
, 
553–557
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(01)00120-0
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Steyn, P.S.
, 
van Heerden, R.F.
, 
1998
. 
Bufadienolides of plant and animal origin
. 
Nat. Prod. Rep.
15
, 
397
. 
https://doi.org/10.1039/a815397y
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
