<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The Coleopterists Bulletin</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1649/0010-065X-68.4.656</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The Role ofCanthon humectus hidalgoensis(Bates) (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae) in Dung Removal from a Cattle Pasture</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2014</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Canthon humectus hidalgoensis (Bates)</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Scarabaeidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
CANTHON HUMECTUS HIDALGOENSIS
(BATES)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>COLEOPTERA</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>SCARABAEIDAE</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canthon humectus
(Say)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canthon humectus hidalgoensis
(Bates)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canthon humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Juniperus flaccida
Schltdl.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Juniperus deppeana
Steud.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cupressus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cupressaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canthon humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canthon acutus
Harold
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
(
Ortega-Martínez 2010
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

The Role of 
<tp:taxon-name>Canthon humectus hidalgoensis (Bates)</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>

(
<tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Scarabaeidae</tp:taxon-name>
) in Dung Removal from a

</p>
         <p>
Cattle Pasture
</p>
         <p>
Authors: 
Ortega-Martínez, Ilse J.
, 
Moreno, Claudia E.
, 
Sánchez-Rojas,
</p>
         <p>
Gerardo, and 
Barragán, Felipe
</p>
         <p>
Source: 
The Coleopterists Bulletin
, 
68
(4): 656-658
</p>
         <p>Published By: The Coleopterists Society</p>
         <p>
URL: https://doi.org/ 
10.1649/0010-065X-68.4.656
</p>
         <p>BioOne Complete (complete.BioOne.org) is a full-text database of 200 subscribed and open-access titles in the biological, ecological, and environmental sciences published by nonprofit societies, associations, museums, institutions, and presses.</p>
         <p>Your use of this PDF, the BioOne Complete website, and all posted and associated content indicates your acceptance of BioOne’s Terms of Use, available at www.bioone.org/terms-of-use.</p>
         <p>Usage of BioOne Complete content is strictly limited to personal, educational, and non - commercial use. Commercial inquiries or rights and permissions requests should be directed to the individual publisher as copyright holder.</p>
         <p>BioOne sees sustainable scholarly publishing as an inherently collaborative enterprise connecting authors, nonprofit publishers, academic institutions, research libraries, and research funders in the common goal of maximizing access to critical research.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
SCIENTIFIC NOTE

</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
THE ROLE OF
<tp:taxon-name>
CANTHON HUMECTUS HIDALGOENSIS
(BATES)
</tp:taxon-name>

(
<tp:taxon-name>COLEOPTERA</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>SCARABAEIDAE</tp:taxon-name>
) IN DUNG REMOVAL FROM A CATTLE 
PASTURE


</title>
         <p>

ILSE J. ORTEGA- MARTÍNEZ, CLAUDIA E. MORENO, GERARDO SÁNCHEZ- ROJAS, AND FELIPE BARRAGÁN 
Centro de Investigaciones Biológicas
, 
Instituto de Ciencias Básicas
e Ingeniería Universidad Autónoma del 
Estado de Hidalgo
. Carretera Pachuca-Tulancingo km 4.5 C.P. 42184, 
Mineral de la Reforma
, 
Hidalgo
, 
MEXICO
cmoreno@uaeh.edu.mx

</p>
         <p>
As rearing livestock spread in 
Mexico
, cattle dung became the main alternative food source for dung beetles in pastures (Amézquita and Favila 2010). The role of these beetles is fundamental to ecosystem functioning and recovery, given their contribution to several ecological processes including dung removal, nutrient cycling, secondary seed dispersal, and soil aeration (Nichols 
et al
. 2008). In the cattle pastures of the state of 
Hidalgo
, 
Mexico
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Canthon humectus
(Say)
</tp:taxon-name>
is one of the most common dung beetle species. In the Barranca de Meztitlán Biosphere Reserve, the subspecies 
<tp:taxon-name>
Canthon humectus hidalgoensis
(Bates)
</tp:taxon-name>
is a generalist dung feeder that represents up to 94% of the total number of dung beetles (Verdú 
et al
. 2007), so studying the behavior of this beetle will allow us to describe its possible impact on ecological processes, especially that of dung removal in pastures.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Canthon humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is a diurnal beetle that makes dung balls and rolls them from the cow pat to another site. Lone beetles do this to feed and mating pairs do it for nesting. For nesting, the ball is rolled by the male who pulls the ball with his hind legs. The female is attracted by his pheromones and takes her place atop the ball to help the male roll it. The male buries the dung ball in the nesting site, and the female transforms it into a brood ball (

). This species is common in xerophilous scrublands, in forests ranging from 
1,400 to 2,000 m
above sea level, as well as in open and isolated livestock areas (Halffter 
et al.
2011).
</p>
         <p>
The
purpose of this study was to describe some of the characteristics of the dung removal process performed by individuals and pairs (male and female) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
We
measured: 1) the linear distance (m) from the source and duration (minutes) of dung rolling; 2) the size (mm) and weight (g) of the dung ball; and 3) the abundance and density of this species in order to estimate its impact on the ecosystem. 
The
study was done in northern 
Hidalgo
, 
Mexico
, in the vicinity of 
Jacala
(
21°1′1.17″ N
99°12′2.35″ W
). 
The area
is located in the 
Sierra Madre Oriental mountain range
, at 

1,376 m

elevation. Native vegetation is temperate mixed forest dominated by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Juniperus flaccida
Schltdl.
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Juniperus deppeana
Steud.
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cupressus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(all 
<tp:taxon-name>Cupressaceae</tp:taxon-name>
). Mean annual temperature is 17.8 °C, and the rainy season occurs from June to September. The study site is a 44.37-ha ranch, of which 60% preserves temperate forest remnants. The rest of the property has been induced pasture for livestock for at least the last 38 years. During the sampling period, there were approximately 20 head of cattle and 65 sheep on the property. We studied the dung relocation behavior of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
in the cattle pasture during 10 days in 

July 2010

. At this site, the mean length of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
was 
10.11 mm
(
n
= 50, range = 
7.8–16.1 mm
) and mean weight was 
0.18 g
(
n
= 50, range = 
0.06–0.8 g
)

.
</p>
         <p>
To determine the linear displacement of dung and the total rolling time, we followed individuals from the source cow pat to the burying site. Displacement trajectories were complex, changing directions, but mean linear distance from the source to the burying site was 
2.6 m
(
n
= 24, range = 
0.28– 9.65 m
). Ball rolling lasted on average 23.6 min from departure from the cow pat until the burying process began (
n
= 25, range = 5–65 minutes; 
Fig. 1a
). This suggests that this beetle species may be removing each dung pat, which is approximately 
0.10 m
2
in

area, scattering and burying it over an area of 
21.24 m
2
(radius = 
2.6 m
, 
i.e
. the mean linear displacement), and thus contributing to important ecosystem processes such as seed secondary dispersal and organic material decomposition.
</p>
         <p>
To assess the size and weight of the dung balls, we collected from 50 individuals and 50 pairs recently formed balls that were no more than 
1 m
from the dung source. We took three measurements of the diameter with a digital caliper to calculate mean ball diameter and obtained the ball’ s weight using a digital scale. Balls were significantly larger and heavier when they were constructed by mating pairs of beetles rather than by individuals (
Fig. 1b, c
). This suggests that pairs invest more effort into making reproductive balls that will eventually be used by their offspring, while individuals roll smaller balls only for feeding.
</p>
         <p>
We compared the relative abundance of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
in two forest and two pasture sites using pitfall traps baited with horse and sheep dung over two 48-hour periods, with 30 days between sampling periods (July and August). At each site and for each sampling period, we arranged nine traps in a 3 × 3 design, leaving 
30 m
between traps. Each trap consisted of a plastic container with a 1-L capacity (
9 cm
deep and 
18.5 cm
diameter), with the container one-third filled with ethylene glycol to preserve the insects, and baited with a mixture of sheep and horse dung. Larsen and Forsyth (2005) found that 95% of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Canthon acutus
Harold
</tp:taxon-name>
beetles they captured in 
Venezuela
were attracted within a 26.2-m area surrounding each trap. Taking into account this information on trap attraction for the genus, we consider that our traps may be attracting 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
beetles in about a 30-m area around each trap. Thus, we estimate that our nine-trap design covered an area of about 1.44 ha (120 × 
120 m
).
</p>
         <p>
We recorded a mean of 1,986.3 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
beetles per 48-hour sampling period in pastures (
n
= 4, range = 
1,536
–2,804
) and 
312.5 in
forest sites (
n
= 4, range = 69–737). Based on this, we estimate there was a mean daily density of 689.7 individuals/ha in pastures and 108.5 individuals/ha in forests. If all these beetles of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
formed mating pairs and each pair buried balls weighing on average 
1.60 g
, this population would be burying 
551.74 g
of dung per day on each hectare of pasture. If beetles did not form pairs and each single individual beetle buried balls weighing 
1.19 g
(which is 6.6 times its own weight), the entire population would be burying 
820.71 g
of cattle dung daily on each hectare of pasture (about 
24 kg
per month).
</p>
         <p>
This is the first report quantifying the local impact of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus
</tp:taxon-name>
in cattle pastures. In our study site, 28% of all dung beetles are 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus hidalgoensis
(
Ortega-Martínez 2010
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, thus, the presence of other species is also quite important, and it would be very interesting to assess the economic value of the ecosystem services provided by the dung beetle community. In active livestock areas, dung production is continuous, while the activity of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. humectus
</tp:taxon-name>
may be restricted to the daytime throughout the rainy season, but we do not have data about variation in the activity of this or other dung beetle species throughout the year. Therefore, dung beetle ecology has interesting research lines to be addressed. For example, the role of dung beetles in the removal and burying of cattle dung is likely related to other functional processes such as seed dispersal, nutrient cycling, bioturbation, the control of insect pests associated with dung (Nichols 
et al
. 2008), and the emission of greenhouse gases (Penttilä 
et al
. 2013).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS

</title>
         <p>

We thank 
A. Arriaga
, 
K. Martínez
, and 
J. Calderón
for their help with the field work, and 
F. Escobar
and 
N. Pavón
for their comments and suggestions on previous versions of this mansucript. 
B. Delfosse
made valuable comments to improve the English. FOMIX CONACyT-Hidalgo project 191908 “Diversidad Biológica del 
Estado de Hidalgo
(tercera etapa)” provided funding, and manuscript writing was supported by the SEP- CONACYT Basic Science Project 222632. This manuscript was prepared using data collected for 
I. J. Ortega-Martínez’
s 
Master of Science
thesis at the Universidad Autónoma del 
Estado de Hidalgo

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>

REFERENCES 
CITED


</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Amézquita
, 
S., and M. E. Favila
. 
2010
.

Removal rates of native and exotic dung by dung beetles (Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae) in a fragmented tropical rain forest. Environmental Entomology
39
: 
328–336
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Halffter, G., V. Halffter, K. M. Martínez-Sánchez, C. E. Moreno, and G. Sánchez-Rojas. 
2011
.

Hybridization

between subspecies of 
Canthon humectus
(Say) (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae)

. 
The Coleopterists Bulletin
65
: 
425–431
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Larsen
, 
T. H., and A. Forsyth
. 
2005
.

Trap spacing and transect design for dung beetle biodiversity studies. Biotropica
37
: 
322–325
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Morón
, 
M. A
. 
2004
.

Escarabajos: 200 Millones de Años de Evolución. Instituto de Ecología, y Sociedad Entomológica Aragonesa, Zaragoza, Spain
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Nichols, E., S. Spector, J. Louzada, T. Larsen, S. Amézquita, and M. E. Favila. 
2008
.

Ecological
functions and ecosystem services provided by Scarabaeinae dung beetles
. 
Biological Conservation
141
: 
1461–1474
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Ortega-Martínez, I. J.
2010
.

Comunidades de escarabajos coprófagos en ecotonos de bosque templado y en potrero en Jacala de Ledezma, Hidalgo, México. BSc thesis
, 
Universidad Autónoma del Estado de Hidalgo, Pachuca, Mexico
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Penttilä, A., E. M. Slade, A. Simojoki, T. Riutta, K. Minkkinen, and T. Roslin. 
2013
.

Quantifying
beetle-mediated effects on gas fluxes from dung pats
. 
PLoS One
8
: e 
71454
, 
doi:10.1371/journal
. pone.0071454.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

Verdú, J. R., C. E. Moreno, G. Sánchez-Rojas, C. Numa, E. Galante, and G. Halffter. 
2007
.

Grazing
promotes dung beetle diversity in the xeric landscape of a Mexican Biosphere Reserve
. 
Biological Conservation
140
: 
308–317
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
