<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112816</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Five undescribed steroids from Talaromyces stipitatus and their cytotoxic
               activities against hepatoma cell lines</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Talaromyces stipitatus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichocomaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> T. stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form unprecedented</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus C.R. Benj. </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichocomaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Penicillium </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> T. stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> T. stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> T. stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> T stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> T stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus C.R. Benj. </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichocomaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Talaromyces stipitatus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Talaromyces stipitatus ATCC</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Talaromyces stipitatus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Five undescribed steroids from <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus </tp:taxon-name>
            and their cytotoxic activities against hepatoma cell lines </p>
         <p> Mi Zhang a, 1 , Yanfang Deng a, 1 , Fei Liu a , Meijia Zheng a , Yu Liang a , Weiguang
            Sun a , Qin Li a , </p>
         <p> Xiao-Nian Li b , Changxing Qi a , Junjun Liu a , Chunmei Chen a, ** , Hucheng Zhu a,
            *** , </p>
         <p> Yonghui Zhang a, * </p>
         <p> a Hubei Key Laboratory of Natural Medicinal Chemistry and Resource Evaluation, Tongji
            Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, Wuhan , </p>
         <p> 430030, People’ s Republic of China </p>
         <p> b State Key Laboratory of Phytochemistry and Plant Resources in West China , Kunming
            Institute of Botany, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, 650204, People’ s </p>
         <p> Republic of China </p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title> Keywords: </title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Talaromyces stipitatus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Trichocomaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Steroids</p>
         <p>Cytotoxicity</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p> Five undescribed sterol derivatives, (22 E ,24 R )-7 α -methoxy-5 α ,6 α
            -epoxyergosta-8(14),22-diene-3 β ,15 β -diol, (22 E ,24 R )-5 α ,6 α
            -epoxyergosta-8(14),22-diene-3 β ,7 β ,15 α -triol, (22 E ,24 R )-3 β ,5 α -dihydroxy-14
            β ,15 β -epoxyergosta-7,22-diene-6-one, (22 E ,24 R )-6 α -methoxy-7 α ,15 β
            -dihydroxyergosta-4,8(14),22-triene-3-one, and (25 S )- ergosta-7,24(28)-diene-3 β ,4 α
            ,6 α ,26 - tetraol were isolated from the extract of <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces
               stipitatus </tp:taxon-name> , along with eight known congeners. This is the first
            example of a class of ergosterols isolated from <tp:taxon-name> T. stipitatus
            </tp:taxon-name> . Their structures with absolute configurations were elucidated based
            on NMR spectroscopic data, ECD calculations, and X-ray crystallographic analyses. All
            these compounds were tested for their effects on three hepatoma cell lines including
            Hep3B, HepG2, and Huh-7. Moreover, (22 E ,24 R )-5 α ,6 α -epoxyergosta-8(14),22-diene-3
            β ,7 β ,15 α -triol and (22 E ,24 R )-9 α ,15 α
            -dihydroxyergosta-4,6,8(14),22-tetraen-3-one were further evaluated for their impacts on
            cell cycle progression and apoptosis due to their pronounced cytotoxicity, to uncover
            their underlying mechanisms. Our results suggested that their antiproliferative
            activities were mainly mediated by inducing cell apoptosis. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 1. Introduction </title>
         <p> Steroids are a critical source of natural products, which not only act as a pivotal
            part of membranes to maintain structures, but are also the office of precursors for the
            synthesis of important substances such as steroid hormones ( ; ; ; ). Ergosterols are a
            subclass of steroids, that possess a typical tetracyclic skeleton with an alkyl chain
            and hydroxyl groups. Apart from classical ergosterols with the mentioned carbon
            skeleton, rearranged ergosterols have also reported, and some of them have been
            synthesized, such as dankasterones A and B, resulting from 13 (14 → 8) abeo -frameworks
            as intermediaries to <tp:taxon-name>form unprecedented</tp:taxon-name> structures ( ; ).
            A large number of natural ergosterols have exhibited significant anti-inflammatory
            (Xiang et al., 2018), anti-tumor ( ), anti-bacterial ( ), and neurotrophic activities (
            ). </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus C.R. Benj. </tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichocomaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) is a potential but underexplored
            species, closely related to <tp:taxon-name> Penicillium </tp:taxon-name> , which is
            known to produce polyketides and terpenoids as principal products ( ; Zang et al.,
            2016a). An incredible examplification of remarkable structural complexity and biological
            diversity in polyketides from <tp:taxon-name> T. stipitatus </tp:taxon-name> is the
            duclauxin derivatives, which are a series of oxaphenalenone dimers that comprise the
            6/6/6/5/6/6/6 ring system ( ; ; ; Zang et al., 2016b). In our previous report, four
            fusicoccane diterpenoids with an unparalleled 5/8/6 carbon skeleton were obtained (Zhang
            et al., 2020), which stimulated us to further explore diverse bioactive compounds from
               <tp:taxon-name> T. stipitatus </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
         <p>* Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>** Corresponding author.</p>
         <p>*** Corresponding author.</p>
         <p> E-mail addresses: chenchunmei@hust.edu.cn (C. Chen), zhuhucheng@hust.edu.cn (H. Zhu),
            zhangyh@mails.tjmu.edu.cn (Y. Zhang). </p>
         <p> 1 These authors contributed equally to this work. </p>
         <p> As part of our ongoing investigation, five undescribed ergosterol derivatives ( 1–2 and
            4–6 ) along with eight known congeners were identified. To the best of our knowledge,
            this is the first example of a class of ergosterols isolated from <tp:taxon-name> T.
               stipitatus </tp:taxon-name> . All of these compounds were evaluated for their
            antiproliferative activities against Hep3B, HepG2, and Huh-7 hepatoma cell lines.
            Compounds 4 and 8 showed a remarkable cytotoxicity, cell cycle progression and apoptosis
            induced by the two compounds and therefore were detected in order to explain the
            mechanisms of their function. Meanwhile, the selectivity of both compounds on hepatoma
            suggested their potential as drug candidates against hepatoma. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 2. Results and discussion </title>
         <p> Compound 1 was obtained as a white powder. Its molecular formula was established as C
            29 H 46 O 4 based on the HRESIMS ion peak at m/z 481.3262 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 29 H
            46 O 4 Na, 481.3294), requiring a hydrogen deficiency index of seven. The 1 H NMR
            spectrum showed signals for two olefinic protons [ δ H 5.26 (1H, dd, J = 15.2, 7.3 Hz,
            H-22) and 5.24 (1H, dd, J = 15.2, 8.1 Hz, H-23)], six methyls [ δ H 1.06 (3H, s, H 3
            -18), 1.03 (3H, d, J = 6.7 Hz, H 3 -21), 0.96 (3H, d, J = 7.5 Hz, H 3 -28), 0.95 (3H, s,
            H 3 -19), 0.87 (3H, d, J = 7.5 Hz, H 3 -26), and 0.86 (3H, d, J = 7.3 Hz, H 3 -27)], and
            one methoxy group [ δ H 3.47 (3H, s, H-29)]. The 13 C NMR and DEPT spectra of 1
            displayed 29 carbons, corresponding to four olefinic carbons, three quaternary carbons
            (one oxygenated), nine methine carbons (four oxygenated), six methylenes, and seven
            methyl groups (including a methoxy). These typical signals suggested 1 to be an
            ergostane-type steroid derivative. </p>
         <p> The 1 H– 1 H COSY and HMBC experiments ( Fig. 2 ) revealed that compound 1 possesses a
            structure similar to (22 E )-5 α ,6 α -epoxyergosta-8 (14),22-diene-3 β ,7 α ,15 α
            -triol ( 3 ). The 13 C NMR and DEPT spectra of 1 displayed an additional methoxy ( δ C
            55.6, Me-29) as compared with 3 , which along with the HMBC spectrum correlation from
            Me-29 to C-7 ( δ C 72.4) confirmed the existence of a methoxy at C-7. The relative
            configuration of 1 was determined based on its NOESY spectrum ( Fig. 3 ) and key
            coupling constants. Generally, Me-18 of sterols is β -oriented and the NOESY signal of
            Me-18/H-11a revealed that they were cofacial and should adopt a dipseudoaxial
            relationship. Moreover, the NOESY correlations of Me-19/H-11a and Me-19/H-7 indicated
            the β -orientation of Me-19 and H-7, which also suggested the α -orientation of the
            epoxy ring at C-5 and C-6. In addition, the interactions of Me-19/H-1a and H-3/H- 1b
            along with the coupling constant of H-3 (tt, J = 11.1, 5.6 Hz) revealed the β
            -orientation of C-3-OH. The NOESY correlation of C-7-OCH 3 /H-15 disclosed the β
            -orientation of C-15-OH. The trans stereochemistry of the double bond was then deduced
            from the coupling constant between H-22 and H-23 ( J = 15.2 Hz). The relative
            configurations of the remaining chiral centers, including C-21 and C-28, were determined
            to be identical to these of 3 by comparison of their 1 H and 13 C NMR data ( ). Finally,
            the structure of 1 with an absolute configuration was determined via X-ray diffraction
            analysis ( Fig. 5 ). Thus, compound 1 was determined to be (22 E ,24 R )-7 α -methoxy-5
            α ,6 α -epoxyergosta-8 (14),22-diene-3 β ,15 β -diol. </p>
         <p> Compound 2 was isolated as a white powder, which shared the same molecular formula of C
            28 H 44 O 4 as that of 3 based on the HRESIMS data. The 1 H and 13 C NMR data of 2 (
            Tables 1 and 2 ) closely resembled those of 3 , except for the obviously shifted signals
            of C-5 (1.9 ppm), C-6 (+ 1.0 ppm), C-7 (1.5 ppm), C-8 (+ 2.6 ppm), and C-14 (2.6 ppm).
            After detailed analyses of the 1 H– 1 H COSY and HMBC spectra, 2 and 3 were a pair of
            stereoisomers possessing the same planar structure. The NOESY interaction of
            Me-19/C-7-OH ( Fig. 3 ), along with the abovementioned changes in the 13 C NMR data,
            suggested that 2 is the C-7 epimer of 3 . The structure and absolute configuration of
            compound 2 was further determined by X-ray diffraction analysis ( Fig. 5 ). Therefore,
            compound 2 was elucidated as (22 E ,24 R )-5 α ,6 α -epoxyergosta-8(14),22- diene-3 β ,7
            β ,15 α -triol. </p>
         <p> Compound 4 was obtained as a white powder. Its molecular formula, C 28 H 42 O 4 , was
            determined using the HRESIMS spectrum with a pseudomolecular ion peak at m/z 465.2990 [M
            + Na] + (calcd for C 28 H 42 O 4 Na, 465.2981), suggesting eight degrees of
            unsaturation. The IR spectrum indicated the presence of hydroxy ( 3386 cm 1 ) and
            conjugated carbonyl ( 1676 cm 1 ) groups. The 1 H NMR spectrum indicated signals for
            three olefinic protons [ δ H 5.83 (1H, d, J = 2.8 Hz, H-7), 5.38 (1H, dd, J = 15.3, 8.1
            Hz, H-22), and 5.20 (1H, dd, J = 15.3, 8.1 Hz, H-23)], six methyls [ δ H 1.01 (3H, s, H
            3 -18), 0.98 (3H, d, J = 6.8 Hz, H 3 -28), 0.95 (3H, d, J = 6.2 Hz, H 3 -21), 0.94 (3H,
            s, H 3 -19), 0.88 (3H, d, J = 6.8 Hz,H 3 -27), and 0.85 (3H, d, J = 6.8 Hz, H 3 -26)],
            and two oxygenated methine groups [ δ H 3.94 (1H, tt, J = 11.6, 4.6 Hz, H-3) and 3.22
            (1H, m, H-15)]. The 13 C NMR and DEPT spectra of 4 revealed 28 carbons, including one
            conjugated carbonyl, four olefinic carbons, four quaternary carbons, seven methines (two
            oxygenated), six methylenes, and six methyl groups. These data of compound 4 resembled
            those of gymnastrone B ( ), except for the presence of additional hydroxy groups at C-3
            and C-5 and the disappearance of the carbonyl at C-3. Further analyses of the 1 H– 1 H
            COSY and HMBC correlations of 4 ( Fig. 2 ) elucidated the planar structure of 4 . The
            NOESY cross-peak between Me-19 and H-4b revealed that they were cofacial (in a
            dipseudoaxial relationship), which indirectly proved the α -orientation of C-5-OH. The
            obvious NOESY correlations of H-3/H-1a and H-1b/Me-19, and the coupling constants of H-3
            (tt, J = 11.1, 4.6 Hz) revealed the β -orientation of C-3-OH. The orientation of the
            epoxy at C-14 and C-15 was assigned as β by a comparison of the NMR data of 4 with that
            of gymnastrrone B. Thus, the relative configuration of 4 was established. The absolute
            configuration of 4 was confirmed via X-ray diffraction analysis as shown ( Fig. 5 ).
            Therefore, 4 was elucidated as (22 E ,24 R )-3 β , 5 α -dihydroxy-14 β ,15 β
            -epoxyergosta-7,22-diene-6-one. </p>
         <p> Compound 5 was isolated as a colorless oil, and its molecular formula was deduced to be
            C 29 H 44 O 4 based on the HRESIMS ion peak at m/z 479.3138 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 29 H
            44 O 4 Na, 479.3137). The 1 H NMR spectrum indicated signals for three olefinic protons
            [ δ H 6.15 (1H, d, J = 1.9 Hz, H-4), 5.20 (1H, m, H-22), and 5.20 (1H, m, H-23)], six
            methyls [ δ H 1.11 (3H, s, H 3 -19), 1.04 (3H, d, J = 6.7 Hz, H 3 -21), 0.91 (3H, d, J =
            6.8 Hz, H 3 -28), 0.87 (3H, s, H 3 -18), 0.82 (3H, d, J = 6.7 Hz, H 3 -27), and 0.80
            (3H, d, J = 6.7 Hz, H 3 -26)], one methoxy group [ δ H 3.48 (1H, s, H-29)], and three
            oxygenated methine groups [ δ H 4.90 (1H, d, J = 4.1 Hz, H-7), 4.83 (1H, d, J = 4.8 Hz,
            H-15), and 3.89 (1H, dd, J = 4.1,1.9 Hz, H- 6),]. The 13 C NMR and DEPT spectra of 5
            displayed 29 carbons, established as one conjugated carbonyl, six olefinic carbons, two
            quaternary carbons, eight methines (three oxygenated), five methylenes, and seven methyl
            groups. The 1 H– 1 H COSY and HMBC data revealed that compound 5 possessed a similar
            structure as 10 did ( ), except for the presence of an additional methoxy at C-6 and
            hydroxyl at C-7. In the HMBC spectrum, correlations from H-4 to C-6 ( δ C 79.0) and from
            H-7 to C-9 ( δ C 42.8) and C-14 ( δ C 157.1), along with the 1 H– 1 H COSY correlations
            of H-6 ( δ H 3.89)/H-7 ( δ H 4.90), confirmed the existence of the methoxy at C-6 and
            hydroxyl at C-7. The relative configuration of 5 was determined by its NOESY spectrum
            and H–H coupling constants. Based on the NOESY correlations of Me-19/H-6, Me-19/H-11,
            and H-11/Me-18, Me-18, Me-19, and H-6 were assigned to be β -oriented and in the
            dipseudoaxial relationship. Therefore, the coupling constant of H-6 and H-7 ( J 6,7 =
            3.8 Hz) indicated the α -orientation of C-7-OH. In addition, the obvious NOESY
            correlation of H-20/Me-18 indicated the α -orientation of H-17, and according to the
            NOESY correlation of H-17/H-15, H-15 and H-17 were in the same orientation. Thus, the
            relative configuration of 5 was established. Since the theoretical ECD curve of 6 R ,7 S
            ,9 S , 10 R ,13 R ,15 R ,17 R ,20 R ,24 R -5 matched well with the experimental ECD
            curve of 5 ( Fig. 4 ), the absolute configuration of 5 was determined as shown.
            Therefore, 5 was elucidated as (22 E , 24 R )-6 α -methoxy-7 α ,15 β
            -dihydroxyergosta-4,8(14),22-triene-3-one. </p>
         <p> Compound 6 was isolated as colorless needles, and its molecular formula was determined
            to be C 28 H 46 O 4 based on its HRESIMS ion peak at m/z 469.3277 [M + Na] + (calcd for
            C 28 H 46 O 4 Na, 469.3294), suggesting six degrees of unsaturation. The 1 H NMR
            spectrum showed signals for four olefinic protons [ δ H 5.12 (1H, d, J = 2.1 Hz, H-7),
            4.77 (1H, brs, H 2 -28), and 4.75 (1H, brs, H-28)], four methyls [ δ H 1.06 (3H, d, J =
            7.0 Hz, H 3 -27), 0.99 (3H, d, J = 6.5 Hz, H 3 -21), 0.89 (3H, s, H 3 -19), and 0.59
            (3H, s H 3 -18)], one oxygenated methylene group [ δ H 3.58 (1H, dd, J = 10.7, 5.9 Hz, H
            2 -26), δ H 3.35 (1H, m, H 2 -26)], and three oxygenated methines [ δ H 4.28 (1H, dd, J
            = 9.3, 2.1 Hz,H-6), 3.72 (1H, dd, J = 10.2, 8.9 Hz, H-4) and 3.35 (1H, m, H-3)]. The 13
            C NMR and DEPT spectra of 6 revealed 28 carbons, corresponding to four olefinic carbons,
            two quaternary carbons, nine methine carbons (three oxygenated), nine methylene (one
            oxygenated), and four methyl groups. Careful analyses of the 1 H and 13 C NMR spectra
            revealed that compound 6 is similar to (25 S )-24-methyl-5 α -cholest-24( 241 )-ene- 3 β
            ,4 β ,6 α ,15 β, 26 - pentol (certonardosterol B) ( ) except for the absence of a
            hydroxy at C-15 and the presence of a double bond between C-7 and C-8 ( Fig. 1 ). The
            relative configuration of the nucleus is consistent with certonardosterol B and the
            absolute configuration was confirmed via X-ray diffraction analysis. Therefore, 6 was
            established as (25 S )-ergosta-7,24(28)-diene-3 β ,4 α ,6 α ,26 - tetraol. </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> a Recorded in Methanol- d . </p>
         <p> 4 b Recorded in DMSO d . </p>
         <p> ‑ 6 c Recorded in CDCl. </p>
         <p> 3 </p>
         <p> a Recorded in Methanol- d . </p>
         <p> 4 b Recorded in DMSO d . </p>
         <p> ‑ 6 c Recorded in CDCl. “o” means overlapped. </p>
         <p> 3 </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> Compounds 3 and 7–13 were identified as (22 E )-5 α ,6 α -epoxyergosta-8(14),22-diene-3
            β ,7 α ,15 α -triol ( 3 ) ( ), (22 E , 24 R )-ergosta-3 β ,5 α
            -dihydroxy-7,22-dien-6-one ( 7 ) ( ), (22 E ,24 R )-9 α ,15 α
            -dihydroxyergosta-4,6,8(14),22-tetraen-3-one ( 8 ) ( ), 15 R , 20 R, 24 R , Δ
            4,6,8(14),22 -tetraene-3-one-ergosterol ( 9 ) ( ), 15 S , 20 R , 24 R , Δ 4,6,8(14),22
            -tetraene-3-one-ergosterol ( 10 ) ( ), (22 E ,24 R )-ergosta-4,6,8(14),
            22-tetraen-3,15-dione ( 11 ) ( ), (22 E ,24 R )-ergosta-5 β , 6 β -epoxy-3 β ,7 α ,9 α
            -trihydroxy-8(14),22-dien-15-one ( 12 ) ( ), and (22 E ,24 R
            )-ergosta-7,22-dien-3,5,6-triol ( 13 ) ( ) by the comparison of their NMR data with
            those reported in the literature. </p>
         <p> Compounds 1–13 were tested for their effects on hepatoma cell lines including Hep3B,
            HepG2, and Huh-7. As a result, compounds 4 , 8 , 9 , 10 , and 11 demonstrated potent
            inhibition against the tested hepatoma cell lines (Fig. S56). Subsequently, we
            determined the IC 50 values of these compounds in the three cell lines. As observed in
            Table 3 , compounds 4 and 8 showed remarkable cytotoxic effects against the Hep3B and
            HepG2 cell lines with IC 50 values ranging from 4.75 to 8.85 μ M and 5.26–6.29 μ M,
            respectively. For the Huh-7 cells, there was a slight increase in the IC 50 values of
            both compounds, 13.78 and 16.23 μ M respectively. Compounds 9 , 10 , and 11 were
            generally less potently cytotoxic against the cell lines used compared to compounds 4
            and 8 . </p>
         <p> a Results are expressed as the mean standard error. </p>
         <p> ± b Positive control. </p>
         <p> c N.T.-not determined. </p>
         <p> Compounds 4 and 8 demonstrated pronounced cytotoxicity in the hepatoma cell lines,
            therefore, we further explored to gain insight into the mechanism of their actions. To
            examine whether compounds 4 and 8 have effects on cell cycle progression, we detected
            the DNA content using flow cytometry. As shown in Fig. 6 , compound 8 increased the
            proportion of S phase cells to 47.06 ± 2.06%, compared with 33.08 ± 1.80% of the
            corresponding controls, at 5 μ M for 24 h on Hep3B cells (p &lt; 0.001), resulting in a
            significant decrease in the G2 phase (p &lt; 0.01). Our results suggested that the
            antiproliferative effect of compound 8 was associated with its ability to induce S phase
            cell cycle arrest. Thus, no significant changes were observed in cells treated with
            compound 4 . </p>
         <p> Since compound 4 exerted a slight impact on cell cycle progression, we presumed that
            other factors might also participate in its inhibitory effect against the Hep3B cells.
            In view of this, a flow cytometric analysis was performed to determine the cell
            apoptosis death induced by compounds 4 and 8 . As observed in Fig. 7 , the proportion of
            apoptotic cells induced by compound 8 increased from 12.5 ± 0.5% at 24 h to 41.2 ± 1.1%
            at 48 h and 5 μ M. The latter value was ten times higher than that of the control group
            (3.9 ± 1.0%, p &lt; 0.0001) considering early and late apoptosis. On the other hand,
            cells treated with compound 4 at 5 μ M for 48h displayed 41.1 ± 1.3% apoptosis, a value
            much higher than that of the control (p &lt; 0.0001). Both treatment groups showed no
            significant difference (p &gt; 0.05) from the positive control sorafenib ( ) (44.6 ±
            0.9%) at 48 h ( Fig. 7 ). </p>
         <p> Given that cells undergoing apoptosis show nuclear fragmentation and chromatin
            condensation ( ), we examined the morphological changes in Hep3B cells after treatment
            with 5 μ M compounds 4 and 8 for 48 h. In keeping with sorafenib, cells treated with
            compounds 4 or 8 showed typical apoptotic features such as DNA fragmentation, condensed
            chromatin and apoptotic bodies compared with the solvent control (0.1% DMSO), as
            depicted in Fig. 8 . These results provided convincing evidence that compounds 4 and 8
            induced apoptosis and cell death. </p>
         <p> To determine the toxic effects of compounds 4 and 8 against normal cells and thus show
            their selectivity for hepatoma cells, their IC 50 values against the nontumorous human
            liver cell line LO2 were also evaluated. Compounds 4 and 8 were 49.3 and 57.1 μ M
            respectively, which were significantly higher (p &lt; 0.001 and p &lt; 0.001) than those
            on target hepatoma cell lines. These data indicate that compounds 4 and 8 can
            selectively trigger cell death in hepatoma cells, suggesting their potential for further
            consideration as lead compounds. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 3. Conclusion </title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus </tp:taxon-name> is a universal species of the
            genus <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces </tp:taxon-name> , and previous investigations have
            indicted the potential of the compounds in terms of their structural diversity and
            complexity. In our current study, a series of ergosterols were discovered, including
            five new ergosterols along with eight known compounds. Notably, compounds 4 and 8
            displayed a remarkable cytotoxicity against the hepatoma cell lines. The results of the
            cell cycle progression and apoptosis suggested that their effects were mainly mediated
            by inducing apoptosis. Our findings have enriched the chemical diversity and bioactivity
            of sterols. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4. Experimental section </title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.1. General experimental procedures </title>
         <p> Optical rotations, ECD, UV, IR spectra and high-resolution electrospray ionization mass
            spectrometry (HRESIMS) were conducted on the instruments we utilized in a previous
            report. (Zhang et al., 2020). Crystallographic experiments were performed on a Bruker
            SMART APEX-II CCD diffractometer using graphite-monochromated Cu K α radiation ( λ =
            1.54178 Å). Semipreparative high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) utilized an
            Agilent 1260 equipped with a UV detector, using a Welch Ultimate XB-C 18 column (5 μ m,
            10 × 250 mm ). Silica gel (Qingdao Marine Chemical Inc., China ), Sephadex LH-20 (GE
            Healthcare Bio-Sciences AB, Sweden ), and ODS (50 μ m,Merck, Germany ) were utilized in
            the column chromatography. Thin-layer chromatography (TLC) was performed using silica
            gel 60 F 254 (Yantai Chemical Industry Research Institute). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.2. Fungal material </title>
         <p> The fungus <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus </tp:taxon-name> was isolated from
            the soil of Beijing , China . An NCBI BLAST analysis of its partial sequence </p>
         <p> (BNCC226199) showed that it is 100% identical to <tp:taxon-name> T stipitatus
            </tp:taxon-name> strain CBS 236.60 (MH857968.1) and <tp:taxon-name> T stipitatus
            </tp:taxon-name> strain T1D1 (MN518410.1). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3. Fermentation and isolation </title>
         <p> The fermentation and extraction of the fungal <tp:taxon-name> Talaromyces stipitatus
               C.R. Benj. </tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name>Trichocomaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) were
            identical to the procedures described previously (Zhang et al., 2020). Briefly fungi
            were cultivated on a solid-substrate medium ( 35 kg ) for 32 days at 25 ◦ C. Exhaustive
            extraction with EtOAc resulted in a crude fraction (250.0 g) which was partitioned by
            silica gel CC with a gradient elution petroleum ether/- EtOAc (10:1 to EtOAc neat, v/v)
            to obtain six subfractions (Fr.1–6). Since the steroids were mainly enriched in Fr.2 (
            10.3 g ) and Fr.3 (28.0 g), Fr.2 was further chromatographed on Sephadex LH-20 (MeOH),
            ODS (50%–100%, v/v) and semipreparative HPLC to afford compounds 4 ( 3.2 mg ), 7 (5.0
            mg), 9 ( 3.5 mg ), 10 (3.0 mg), and 13 ( 7.5 mg ). Fr.3 was purified by RP-C18 gel with
            MeOH/H 2 O (60%–100%, v/v) to give seven fractions (Fr.3A Fr.3G) grounded on the TLC
            analysis. The Fr.3E was successively separated using silica gel CC with ether/EtOAc
            (15:1 to 1:1, v/v) and Sephadex LH-20, and then purified by semipreparative HPLC to
            yield compounds 1 ( 4.1 mg ), 2 ( 5.3 mg ), 3 (7.0 mg), 8 ( 3.3 mg ), and 11 ( 9.5 mg ).
            Similarly, compounds 5 ( 2.2 mg ), 6 ( 3.9 mg ), and 12 ( 6.1 mg ) were isolated from
            Fr. 3F. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.1. Compound 1 </title>
         <p> 25 </p>
         <p> White powder; [ α ] D –175.0 ( c 0.1, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max (Δ ε ) 212 (16.7); UV
            (MeOH) λ max (log ε ) 208 (4.09) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3420, 3059, 2957, 2934, 1634, 1462,
            1382, 1058, 1036, 708, 651 cm 1 ; 1 H NMR (CD 3 OD, 400 MHz) data, see Table 1 ; 13 C
            NMR (CD 3 OD, 100 MHz) data, see Table 2 ; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 481.3262 [M + Na] + (calcd
            for C 29 H 46 O 4 Na, 481.3294). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.2. Compound 2 </title>
         <p> White powder; [ α ] D 25 –14 ( c 0.1, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max (Δ ε ) 218 (6.35) nm; UV
            (MeOH) λ max (log ε ) 211 (4.34) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3374, </p>
         <p> 2955, 2868, 1738, 1723, 1452, 1383, 1124, 702 cm 1 ; 1 H NMR (DMSO ‑d 6 , 400 MHz)
            data, see Table 1 ; 13 C NMR (DMSO ‑d 6 , 100 MHz) data, see Table 2 ; (+)-HRESIMS m/z
            467.3128 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 28 H 44 O 4 Na, 467.3137). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.3. Compound 4 </title>
         <p> White powder; [ α ] D 25 –16 ( c 0.1, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max (Δ ε ) 209 (+ 5.36), 254
            (15.2) nm; UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε ) 255 (4.02) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3444, 3386, 2959,
            2874, 1712, 1676, 1461, 1384, 1278, 1163, 772 cm 1 ; 1 H NMR (CD 3 OD, 400 MHz) data,
            see Table 1 ; 13 C NMR (CD 3 OD, 100 MHz) data, see Table 2 ; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 465.2990
            [M + Na] + (calcd for C 28 H 42 O 4 Na, 465.2981). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.4. Compound 5 </title>
         <p> Colorless oil; [ α ] D 25 + 16 ( c 0.1, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max (Δ ε ) 216 (2.6), 254
            (+ 3.5) nm; UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε ) 238 (3.45) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3442, 3385, 2958,
            2871, 1711, 1664, 1462, 1383, 1221, 1009, 778 cm 1 ; 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 400 MHz) data,
            see Table 1 ; 13 C NMR (CDCl 3 , 100 MHz) data, see Table 2 ; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 479.3138
            [M + Na] + (calcd for C 29 H 44 O 4 Na, 479.3137). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.5. Compound 6 </title>
         <p> Colorless needles; [ α ] D 25 + 31 ( c 0.1, MeOH); ECD (MeOH) λ max (Δ ε ) 207 (9.1)
            nm; UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε ) 202 (3.83) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3440, 2963, 2931, 2874, 1690,
            1618, 1458, 1384, 1290, 1180, 1094, 884 cm 1 ; 1 H NMR (CD 3 OD, 400 MHz) data, see
            Table 1 ; 13 C NMR (CD 3 OD, 100 MHz) data, see Table 2 ; (+)-HRESIMS m/z 469.3277 [M +
            Na] + (calcd for C 28 H 46 O 4 Na, 469.3294). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.4. X-ray crystal structure analysis </title>
         <p> The crystallographic data of 1 , 2 , 4 , and 6 were deposited in the Cambridge
            Crystallographic Data Centre (deposition numbers 2024115, 2024114, 2024062, and 2024238,
            respectively). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.4.1. Crystal data for compound 1 </title>
         <p> 2(C 29 H 46 O 4 )• H 2 O, M = 935.33, a = 7.1096(4) Å, b = 40.217(3) Å, c = 9.9359(5)
            Å, α = 90 ◦ , β = 105.071(3) ◦ , γ = 90 ◦ , V = 2743.2(3) Å 3 , T = 100.(2) K, space
            group P 1211, Z = 2, μ (Cu Kα) = 0.584 mm 1 , 48608 reflections measured, 10648
            independent reflections ( Rint = 0.1136). The final R 1 values were 0.0742 ( I &gt; 2 σ
            ( I )). The final wR ( F 2 ) values were 0.1802 ( I &gt; 2 σ ( I )). The final R 1
            values were 0.0988 (all data). The final wR ( F 2 ) values were 0.2021 (all data). The
            goodness of fit on F 2 was 1.071. Flack parameter = 0.17(13). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.4.2. Crystal data for compound 2 </title>
         <p> C 28 H 44 O 4 • H 2 O, M = 462.65, a = 9.68210(10) Å, b = 43.6112(6) Å, c = 6.23620(10)
            Å, α = 90 ◦ , β = 90 ◦ , γ = 90 ◦ , V = 2633.22(6) Å 3 , T = 100 (2) K, space group P
            21212, Z = 4, μ (Cu Kα) = 0.618 mm 1 , 20993 reflections measured, 5175 independent
            reflections ( Rint = 0.0366). The final R 1 values were 0.0291 ( I &gt; 2 σ ( I )). The
            final wR ( F 2 ) values were 0.0700 ( I &gt; 2 σ ( I )). The final R 1 values were
            0.0311 (all data). The final wR ( F 2 ) values were 0.0718 (all data). The goodness of
            fit on F 2 was 1.029. Flack parameter = 0.08(5). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.4.3. Crystal data for compound 4 </title>
         <p> 4(C 28 H 42 O 4 )• 2( CH 4 O)• H 2 O, M = 1825.55, monoclinic, a = 24.9410 (11) Å, b =
            6.9131(4) Å, c = 32.3992(16) Å, α = 90.00 ◦ , β = 106.994 (3) ◦ , γ = 90.00 ◦ , V =
            5342.3(5) Å 3 , T = 100(2) K, space group C121, Z = 2, μ (CuKα) = 1.5418 mm 1 , 56715
            reflections measured, 10350 independent reflections ( Rint = 0.1255). The final R 1
            values were 0.0923 ( I &gt; 2 σ ( I )). The final wR ( F 2 ) values were 0.2331 ( I &gt;
            2 σ ( I )). The final R 1 values were 0.1213 (all data). The final wR ( F 2 ) values
            were 2565 (all data). The goodness of fit on F 2 was 1.056. Flack parameter = 0.04(18).
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.4.4. Crystal data for compound 6 </title>
         <p> 2(C 28 H 46 O 4 )• ( CH 4 O)• H 2 O, M = 943.35, a = 13.3602(6) Å, b = 11.5802(5) Å, c
            = 17.5830(7) Å, α = 90 ◦ , β = 102.3869(4) ◦ , γ = 90 ◦ , V = 2657.03(2) Å 3 , T =
            293(2) K, space group P 21, Z = 2, μ (Cu Kα) = 0.619 mm 1 , 63690 reflections measured,
            10566 independent reflections ( Rint = 0.0288). The final R 1 values were 0.0365 ( I
            &gt; 2 σ ( I )). The final wR ( F 2 ) values were 0.0987 ( I &gt; 2 σ ( I )). The final
            R 1 values were 0.0367 (all data). The final wR ( F 2 ) values were 0.0989 (all data).
            The goodness of fit on F 2 was 1.019. Flack parameter = -0.06(3). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.5. Theoretical ECD calculation for compound 5 </title>
         <p> The ECD calculation of 5 was implemented using Gaussian 09W. The electronic circular
            dichroism (ECD) spectra of each conformer were calculated at the B3LYP/6–311++
            G(d,p)/B3LYP/6-31G (d) level, utilizing the TDDFT method with MeOH as the solvent and
            the IEFPCM solvation model performed in the Gaussian 09 program. The ECD spectra were
            simulated using a Gaussian function with a bandwidth σ of 0.3 eV. Based on the
            population contributions of the spectra, Boltzmann weighting was combined and a UV
            correction was applied. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.6. Biological assay </title>
         <p> The human hepatocellular carcinoma cell lines, Hep3B, HepG2 and Huh-7 were purchased
            from Procell Life Technology Co. Ltd. (Wuhan, China ), and no evidence of mycoplasma
            contamination was detected by the PCR-based assay in any of these cell lines. Cells were
            cultured in Dulbecco’ s modified Eagle’ s medium (DMEM, HyClone, USA ) supplemented with
            10% FBS (Gibco, USA ), 100 μ g/ml penicillin and 100 μ g/ml streptomycin (Biosharp,
            China ) in an incubator with at 37 ◦ C and a 5% CO 2 atmosphere. For cell treatment,
            compounds 1–13 and sorafenib (MCE, USA ), the positive control, were dissolved in DMSO
            and diluted to specific concentrations with a DMEM complete medium before use. Cell
            viability and IC 50 against hepatoma cell lines were tested via a CCK-8 (TOPSCIENCE,
            China ) assay according to the manufacturer’ s instructions. Flow cytometry analysis was
            performed in a BectonDickinson (BD) FACS Canto II flow cytometer (BD Biosciences, USA )
            to determine cell cycle progression and apoptosis (Cell Cycle and Apoptosis Analysis
            Kit, Beyotime, China ). The relative distributions of cells in the G0/G1, S, and G2/M
            phases of the cell cycle were analyzed using Modfit 5.0 software and the rates of
            apoptotic cells were diagramed by FlowJo V10. For fluorescence microscopy detection of
            the apoptotic nuclear morphology, cells treated with various substrates were observed
            via fluorescence microscopy using a fluorescent microscope system (Olympus, Japan )
            after DAPI staining (Solarbio Life Science, China ). GraphPad Prism 6 was used to
            perform the statistical analyses. For most experiments, two-tailed unpaired t-tests were
            used to determine statistically significant differences between groups. All experiments
            were performed at least three times and data are presented as the means ± standard
            deviation (s.d.) unless otherwise specified. </p>
         <p> Associated content </p>
         <p> The 1D and 2D NMR, MS, IR, UV, and X-ray crystallographic data of 1 , 2 , 4 , and 6 are
            included in CIF format. This material is available free of charge via the Internet at
            http://pubs.acs.org. </p>
         <p> Notes </p>
         <p>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Declaration of competing interest </title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal
            relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title> Acknowledgments </title>
         <p>This work was financially supported by the Program for Changjiang</p>
         <p> Scholars of Ministry of Education of the People’ s Republic of China (No. T2016088);
            the National Natural Science Foundation for Distinguished Young Scholars (81725021);
            Tongji-Rongcheng Center for Biomedicine, Huazhong Universityof Science and Technology;
            the National Natural Science Foundation for Excellent Young Scholars (81922065); the
            National Science and Technology Project of China (2018ZX 09201001 -001- 003); Innovative
            Research Groups of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81721005);
            Tongji-Rongcheng Center for Biomedicine, Huazhong University of Science and Technology;
            the National Natural Science Foundation of China (82003633); the Academic Frontier Youth
            Team of HUST (2017QYTD19); and the Integrated Innovative Team for Major Human Diseases
            Program of Tongji Medical College (HUST). We thank the Analytical and Testing Center at
            Huazhong University of Science and Technology for assistance in the acquisition of the
            ECD, UV, and IR spectra. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Appendix A. Supplementary data </title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi.
            org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2021.112816.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title> References </title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Amagata, T. , Minoura, K. , Numata, A. , 1998 . Gymnasterones, novel
                  cytotoxic metabolites produced by a fungal strain from a sponge . Tetrahedron
                  Lett. 39 , 3773–3774 . https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040-4039(98)00613-3 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bryant, F.O. , Cutler, H.G. , Burla, M.C. , Newton, M.G. , 1995 .
                  Duclauxin ethyl acetate solvate, 2C29H22O11⋅C4H8O2 . Acta Crystallogr. C 51 ,
                  437–440 . https://doi.org/ 10.1107/S010827019400394X . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Chaudhary, N.K. , Crombie, A. , Vuong, D. , Lacey, E. , Piggott,
                  A.M. , Karuso, P. , 2020 . Talauxins: hybrid phenalenone dimers from Talaromyces
                  stipitatus . J. Nat. Prod. 83 , 1051–1060 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.9b01066 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Deng, C.M. , Liu, S.X. , Huang, C.H. , Pang, J.Y. , Lin, Y.C. , 2013
                  . Secondary metabolites of a mangrove endophytic fungus Aspergillus terreus (No.
                  GX7-3B) from the South China Sea. Mar . Drugs 11 , 2616–2624 .
                  https://doi.org/10.3390/md11072616 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Duecker, F.L. , Heinze, R.C. , Heretsch, P. , 2020 . Synthesis of
                  swinhoeisterol A, dankasterone A and B, and periconiastone A by radical framework
                  reconstruction . J. Am. Chem. Soc. 142 , 104–108 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1021/jacs.9b12899 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Gao, S.S. , Zhang, T. , Garcia-Borras, M. , Hung, Y.S. ,
                  Billingsley, J.M. , Houk, K.N. , Hu, Y. , Tang, Y. , 2018 . Biosynthesis of
                  heptacyclic duclauxins requires extensive redox modifications of the phenalenone
                  aromatic polyketide . J. Am. Chem. Soc. 140 , 6991–6997 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1021/jacs.8b03705 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hu, Z. , He, B. , Ma, L. , Sun, Y. , Niu, Y. , Zeng, B. , 2017 .
                  Recent advances in ergosterol biosynthesis and regulation mechanisms in
                  Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Indian J . Microbiol. 57 , 270–277 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s12088-017-0657-1 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Keating, G.M. , 2017 . Sorafenib: a review in hepatocellular
                  carcinoma . Targeted Oncol. 12 , 243–253 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s11523-017-0484-7 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kikuchi, T. , Isobe, M. , Uno, S. , In, Y . , Zhang, J. , Yamada, T
                  . , 2019 . Strophasterols E and F: rearranged ergostane-type sterols from
                  Pleurotus eryngii. Bioorg. Chem. 89 , 103011–103019 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bioorg.2019.103011 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lin, M. , Li, H. , Zhao, Y. , Cai, E. , Zhu, H. , Gao, Y. , Liu, S.
                  , Yang, H. , Zhang, L. , Tang, G. , 2017 . 2- Naphthoic acid ergosterol ester, an
                  ergosterol derivative, exhibits anti-tumor activity by promoting apoptosis and
                  inhibiting angiogenesis . Steroids 122 , 9–15 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1016/j.steroids.2017.03.007 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Luo, Q. , Yang, Z.L. , Yan, Y.M. , Cheng, Y.X. , 2017 .
                  Ganotheaecolin A, a neurotrophic conjugated ergosterol with a
                  naphtho[1,8-ef]azulene scaffold from ganoderma theaecolum . Org. Lett. 19 ,
                  718–721 . https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.orglett.7b00012 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ma, G. , Chong, L. , Li, Z. , Cheung, A.H. , Tattersall, M.H. , 2009
                  . Anticancer activities of sesquiterpene lactones from Cyathocline purpurea in
                  vitro . Canc. Chemother. Pharmacol. 64 , 143–152 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s00280-008-0863-y . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Noinart, J. , Buttachon, S. , Dethoup, T. , Gales, L. , Pereira,
                  J.A. , Urbatzka, R. , Freitas, S. , Lee, M. , Silva, A.M.S. , Pinto, M.M.M. ,
                  Vasconcelos, V. , Kijjoa, A. , 2017 . A new ergosterol analog, a new
                  bis-anthraquinone and anti-obesity activity of anthraquinones from the marine
                  sponge-associated fungus Talaromyces stipitatus KUFA 0207. Mar . Drugs 15 ,
                  139–151 . https://doi.org/10.3390/md15050139 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ohnishi, T. , Yokota, T. , Mizutani, M. , 2009 . Insights into the
                  function and evolution of P450s in plant steroid metabolism . Phytochemistry 70 ,
                  1918–1929 . https://doi.org/ 10.1016/j.phytochem.2009.09.015 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Qiao, M.-F. , Yi, Y.-W. , Deng, J. , 2017 . Steroids from an
                  endophytic Eurotium rubrum strain . Chem. Nat. Compd. 53 , 678–681 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s10600-017- 2089-x . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Qin, X.-D. , Liu, J.-K. , 2004 . Natural aromatic steroids as
                  potential molecular fossils from the fruiting bodies of the ascomycete daldinia
                  concentrica . J. Nat. Prod. 67 , 2133–2135 . https://doi.org/10.1021/np049793j .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Shi, Q. , Huang, Y. , Su, H. , Gao, Y. , Peng, X. , Zhou, L. , Li,
                  X. , Qiu, M. , 2019 . C28 steroids from the fruiting bodies of Ganoderma
                  resinaceum with potential anti-inflammatory activity . Phytochemistry 168 ,
                  112109–121117 . https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2019.112109 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sokolov, S.S. , Trushina, N.I. , Severin, F.F. , Knorre, D.A. , 2019
                  . Ergosterol turnover in yeast: an interplay between biosynthesis and transport .
                  Biochemistry (Mosc.) 84 , 346–357 . https://doi.org/10.1134/S0006297919040023 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Tanaka, R. , Kasubuchi, K. , Kita, S. , Tokuda, H. , Nishino, H. ,
                  Matsunaga, S. , 2000 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Taro, A. , Mitsunobu, D. , Makiko, T. , Katsuhiko, M. , Atsushi, N.
                  , 1999 . Dankasterone, a new class of cytotoxic steroid produced by a Gymnascella
                  species from a marine sponge . Chem. Commun . 1321–1322 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1039/A903840J . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wang, S. , Zhang, L. , Liu, L.-Y. , Dong, Z.-J. , Li, Z.-H. , Liu,
                  J.-K. , 2012 . Six novel steroids from culture of basidiomycete Polyporus ellisii
                  . Natur. Prod. &amp; Bioprosp. 2 , 240–244 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s13659-012-0058-4 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wang, W. , Li, F. , Park, Y. , Hong, J. , Lee, C.-O. , Kong, J.Y. ,
                  Shin, S. , Im, K.S. , Jung, J.H. , 2003 . Bioactive sterols from the starfish
                  certonardoa semiregularis . J. Nat. Prod. 66 , 384–391 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1021/np020507i . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Weng, Y. , Xiang, L. , Matsuura, A. , Zhang, Y. , Huang, Q. , Qi, J.
                  , 2010 . Ganodermasides A and B , two novel anti-aging ergosterols from spores of
                  a medicinal mushroom </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
