<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Zoologia</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1984-4689.v39.e21023</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Perspectives and challenges on isotopic ecology of terrestrial birds in
               Brazil</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>16</day>
            <month>05</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Aves, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Elaenia Sundevall, 1836 </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Elaenia sp. </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Turdus sp. </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Turdus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Cinclodes sp. </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cinclodes</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Elaenia cristata </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Cacatua sulphurea </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Ammodramus savannarum </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Eremophila alpestris </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Somateria mollissima </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Euphagus carolinus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Emberiza hortulana </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Fringilla montifringilla </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Turdus Linnaeus, 1758 </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Cinclodes G.R. Gray, 1840 </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Elaenia cristata Pelzeln, 1868 </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Ammodramus savannarum (J.F. Gmelin, 1789) </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Eremophila alpestris (Linnaeus, 1758) </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Somateria mollissima (Linnaeus, 1758) </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Euphagus carolinus (Statius Muller, 1776) </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> REVIEW ARTICLE </title>
         <p> Perspectives and challenges on isotopic ecology of terrestrial birds in Brazil </p>
         <p> Ana Beatriz Navarro 1 , Marcelo Magioli 2,3 , Marcelo Zacharias Moreira 4 , Luís Fábio
            Silveira 1 </p>
         <p> 1 Seção de <tp:taxon-name> Aves, Museu de Zoologia da Universidade </tp:taxon-name> de
            São Paulo . 04263-000 São Paulo , SP, Brazil . </p>
         <p> 2 Instituto Pró-Carnívoros. 12945-010 Atibaia, SP, Brazil . </p>
         <p> 3 Centro Nacional de Pesquisa e Conservação de Mamíferos Carnívoros, Instituto Chico
            Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade. 12952-011 Atibaia, SP, Brazil . </p>
         <p> 4 Laboratório de Ecologia Isotópica , Centro de Energia Nuclear na Agricultura ,
            Universidade de São Paulo . 13416-903 Piracicaba, SP, Brazil . </p>
         <p> Corresponding author: Ana Beatriz Navarro ( navarrobeatrizana@gmail.com ) </p>
         <p> http://zoobank.org/ 176323A1-9571-4986-B6D0-3C64E95EC308 </p>
         <p> ABSTRACT. Although stable isotopes have been increasingly used in ornithology since
            1980 in many places, Brazil has been slow in adopting this methodology, especially when
            it comes to terrestrial birds. The most common elements in bird ecology studies are
            carbon, nitrogen, hydrogen, and oxygen stable isotopes, which provide information on
            diet, trophic interactions, habitat use, migration, geographic patterns, and physiology.
            It is important that Brazilian ornithologists become aware of the potential of stable
            isotope analysis in ecological studies, and the shortcomings of this tool. The use of
            stable isotopes to study bird ecology has great potential in Brazil , since many
            ecological questions about Neotropical birds can be addressed by it (e.g., resource and
            habitat use, migratory routes, isotopic niches, anthropogenic impacts, individual
            specialization). Brazilian museums and other Natural History collections can provide
            samples to study long-term temporal dynamics in bird ecology. Additionally, the
            integration of avian tissue sample information into a database may increase the
            collaboration among researchers and promote sample reuse in a variety of studies. All
            biomes in Brazil have been under pressure from anthropogenic impacts (e.g., land-use
            change, habitat loss, fragmentation, intensive agriculture), affecting several taxa,
            including terrestrial birds. Considering the negative effects of human expansion over
            natural areas and that stable isotopes provide useful ecological information,
            ornithologists in Brazil should increase their use of this tool in the future. </p>
         <p> KEY WORDS. δ 13 C , δ 15 N , δ 2 H , δ 18 O , migratory birds , museum specimens ,
            ornithology , trophic ecology . </p>
         <p> The isotopic methodology generates ornithological information that used to be only
            possible with conventional approaches (e.g., regurgitates or stomach contents analyses,
            tracking with GPS and telemetry, bird ringing). Using a single sample that can be
            collected through a minimally invasive method, stable isotopes make it possible to
            gather long-term information about organisms ( ). Despite the advantages of this method,
            it has not been consistently employed in ornithological studies in Brazil . Brazilian
            studies are generally based on time-consuming and resource-demanding traditional methods
            that only offer a ‘snapshot’ of the diet of a bird. </p>
         <p> Stable isotope analysis in ornithological studies is relatively recent worldwide, since
            the first studies were published in the 1980s ( ). In Brazil , this methodology was
            first employed less than 20 years ago ( , , ). In a literature review encompassing
            2007–2009, reviewed the main studies in trophic ecology using stable isotopes. Birds
            were the fifth most studied group, particularly the ones inhabiting aquatic (ocean,
            estuaries, lake) and temperate environments (e.g., grassland, forest) ( ). The
            representation of tropical birds in the literature was less than 10%, highlighting the
            urgency to apply stable isotopes in new studies to investigate bird ecology,
            particularly in terrestrial tropical environments. </p>
         <p> Several studies have already been undertaken to compile the different facets of stable
            isotopes as a tool to understand bird ecology (e.g., , , ). None has focused on the
            Brazilian fauna, which is very distinct from the North American and European faunas. In
            this contribution, we discuss the potential of stable isotope studies in Brazil to
            better understand the ecology of terrestrial birds ( Fig. 1 ). </p>
         <p> What are stable isotopes and how to measure it (C, N, H, O) </p>
         <p> Stable isotopes are the non-radioactive forms of the same element that contain
            different numbers of neutrons. The neutron-depleted isotope is usually called “light”
            and the neutron-enriched isotope is named “heavy”. Although the amount of each stable
            isotope in each ecosystem varies naturally, the light isotopes are generally more common
            than the heavy isotopes ( ). The sentence “You are what you eat (plus a few per
            thousand)” represents the use of stable isotope analysis in ecology ( ), meaning that
            organisms express the isotopic value of the resources they consume (but see and for
            another viewpoint). Considering that the abundance of isotopes varies from one place to
            another, the proportion of each isotope in living organisms will also vary
            geographically. By analyzing different animal tissues with a mass spectrometer, it is
            possible to measure the proportion of each isotope in them, allowing the calculation of
            a ratio between heavy/light isotopes. The delta notation (δ) is used to describe the
            isotopic ratio of a sample as parts per thousand (per mille, ‰), following the equation
            ‘δX= (R sample / R standard − 1)’, where X is the measured isotope of the element, R is
            the absolute isotopic ratio (R = heavy/light isotope) and R standard is the isotopic
            ratio of the international standard for each element (e.g., V-PDB for carbon;
            atmospheric air for nitrogen; V-SMOW for hydrogen and oxygen). The use of R standard is
            to standardize the values of δX to compare among the most different samples since δX
            will always be enriched or depleted regarding the heavier element ( ). </p>
         <p> Stable carbon isotopes ( 12 C and 13 C ratio; denominated as δ 13 C) are commonly used
            to determine the habitat and resource use by an organism ( , , , ). Terrestrial
            environments are highly associated with land use and cover (e.g., forest formation,
            anthropogenic areas), and plants vary in their isotopic values according to the
            photosynthetic cycle (C 3, C 4 e CAM). Tropical forests are mainly dominated by C 3
            plants (usually trees), while C 4 plants are grasses associated with savannas and
            agricultural areas (e.g., pasture, sugarcane, maize). Neotropical C 3 plants have a wide
            range of isotopic values from -24‰ to -38‰, while C 4 plants range from -11‰ to -15‰ ( ,
            ). Thus, through the values of δ 13 C, it is possible to determine the environments used
            by birds, their food sources, and to compare the importance of forests versus
            anthropogenic areas in the ecology of a species ( , , ). Nevertheless, in addition to
            the isotopic variation according to the photosynthetic cycle, other factors (i.e., water
            stress, light intensity, soil) can also influence the δ 13 C values of plants ( , ).
            Therefore, it is crucial to consider the environmental conditions of the study site when
            collecting bird samples for isotopic analysis. </p>
         <p> Nitrogen isotopes ( 14 N and 15 N ratio; denominated as δ 15 N) are usually employed in
            studies of the dietary patterns and trophic processes. The ratio of nitrogen stable
            isotopes tends to be enriched by 3–4‰ as it moves towards the higher levels of the
            trophic chain. Consequently, top predators are expected to have higher δ 15 N values
            than primary consumers ( ), making nitrogen isotope analysis an adequate tool to
            understand bird diet, the dietary differences among species or foraging groups, and
            trophic structuring ( , , , ). Recently, new data has been published concerning the
            influence of nitrogen fertilizers on the δ 15 N values of birds inhabiting anthropogenic
            areas ( , ). Synthetic and organic nitrogen fertilizers have distinct δ 15 N values due
            to the different nitrogen sources used for their production. The synthetic fertilizers
            have isotopic values closer to zero, since they are produced with nitrogen from
            atmospheric air, while those made from organic matter (e.g., animal waste) expresses
            greater δ 15 N ( ). In view of this data, nitrogen isotopes may be useful to clarify the
            effects of increased anthropogenic pollution, agriculture expansion and urbanization, on
            the diet of birds ( ). </p>
         <p> The stable isotopes of hydrogen ( 1 H and 2 H ratio; denominated as δ 2 H) and oxygen (
            16 O and 18 O ratio; denominated as δ 18 O) can be used to uncover the geographic and
            migratory patterns of birds ( , , , ). The values of δ 2 H and δ 18 O vary according to
            latitude, precipitation patterns, temperature, elevation, and relative humidity,
            following the characteristics of the hydrological cycle in each geographic portion of
            the Earth ( ). The main sources of H and O isotopes in animal tissues are drinking water
            and water from the food they consume, but O isotopes also derive from the O 2
            respiration process ( ). The values of δ 2 H and δ 18 O are usually represented as
            isoscapes, which are the isotopic values of landscapes. However, the analysis of δ 13 C
            and δ 15 N values has increased in studies involving birds and isoscapes ( , , ).
            Investigations on the association among different isoscapes are promising to promote a
            better understanding of the migratory patterns of terrestrial birds. </p>
         <p> Factors affecting isotopic values in individuals and their environment </p>
         <p> The use of stable isotopes in terrestrial ornithological studies is increasing, and
            results are promising. Certain methodological precautions, however, need to be taken
            before the analysis of samples and discussion of results ( , , ). First, a minimal
            understanding of the natural history and ecology of the species (e.g., animal or
            plant-based diet, trophic guild, habitat preference) is fundamental to correctly
            interpret isotopic values. Animals showing similar isotopic values do not necessarily
            have the same diet, habitat use, or origin ( ). For example, it is possible to
            misinterpret data collected from nectarivore birds when the researcher does not consider
            a priori information on the influence of diet and physiology on δ 15 N: although
            hummingbirds may express high δ 15 N values because they supplement their diet with
            arthropods (mainly spiders and flies) to meet their high metabolic requirements ( ),
            resulting in isotopic values that are similar to those found in strict insectivores,
            their primary food resource is in fact nectar. </p>
         <p> Concerning the incorporation of food nutrients into animal tissues, it is important to
            remember that several biochemical reactions occur in organisms and in the ecosystems,
            leading to a process known as isotopic discrimination or more specifically, trophic
            discrimination factor (TDF). This biological process generates differences in isotopic
            values between the consumer and the resource consumed, which explains the “... (plus a
            few per mil)” in the sentence previously described ( ). Each food source along with its
            stable isotopes are incorporated into the tissues of different organisms through
            different metabolic pathways. Consequently, the TDFs vary according to the tissue and
            the diet consumed ( ). Additionally, the dynamics of isotopic incorporation vary among
            animal tissues, depending on physiological processes. Since the synthesis and
            replacement of each tissue of an animal will happen within a different period in time,
            it is possible to use multi-tissue analysis to uncover the consumption of resources at
            distinct phases of the life of an organism ( ). In the case of birds, while some tissues
            reflect the isotopic value of the resources consumed a few days ago (e.g., blood plasma,
            liver), others reflect the resources consumed months or years before (e.g., feathers,
            claws, bone collagen) ( , ). The discrimination and dynamics of isotopic incorporation
            may vary according to the species’ phylogenetic relationships or similarity in dietary
            patterns (e.g., herbivores, carnivores, omnivores), highlighting the importance of
            carefully considering the use of correction factors (e.g., TDF) in bird isotopic
            ecology. </p>
         <p> Another important consideration is to collect and create a comprehensive baseline of
            food resources ( ). The baseline can be measured through the direct isotopic analysis of
            items consumed by the species or using phylogenetically related organisms as a proxy for
            resources ( ). Creating a good baseline ensures that the isotopic comparisons among
            individuals are accurate, especially in dietary and food-web studies. In long-term
            studies, it may be difficult to sample historical resources to compose a baseline of the
            past. In this case, researchers should resort to museum collections in search of food
            items, or develop a robust proxy for the historical baseline (e.g., , ). In Brazil ,
            where biodiversity is high, a single bird species can consume many different food items
            ( , , ). Thus, collecting and analyzing the complete baseline of a species may be
            unfeasible, highlighting the importance of developing good proxies from phylogenetically
            related organisms. </p>
         <p> The diversity of environmental characteristics among biomes in Brazil (e.g.,
            precipitation, vegetation type , soil, landscape composition) is also a reason for
            caution when investigating patterns in the isotopic ecology of birds. To be able to
            understand how abiotic factors influence species’ isotopic values, it is important to
            examine refined isoscape maps for the Brazilian territory, which already incorporate
            several environmental variables in their models ( ). Vegetation from distinct regions
            can also express isotopic variation or similarity ( , ). For this reason, the isotopic
            values of the vegetation need to be considered, to correctly interpret the results of
            studies that incorporate a broad spatial area, especially because many birds have
            plant-based diets . </p>
         <p> Stable isotopes in dietary, niche and food web studies </p>
         <p> Stable isotopes can be broadly used in trophic ecology and foraging studies, for
            instance: estimating the proportion of items in the diet, assessing which environment is
            used more often to obtain food and as habitat, measuring different isotopic niche
            dimensions, and investigating foraging specializations among individuals, species, or
            groups ( Table 1 ). Most dietary studies employ the stable carbon (δ 13 C) and nitrogen
            (δ 15 N) isotopes, which give more information on habitat and resource use, and the
            trophic levels of animal species ( , ). </p>
         <p> The ingestion of many food resources by an organism can be measured with stable isotope
            mixing models, which estimate how much each food source contributes to the diet of the
            individual’s ( , ). There are several mixing models that can be used to ascertain
            foraging patterns. Currently, the Bayesian models are favored, since they fully
            incorporate sources of uncertainty (but see and for some different models and their
            particularities). used mixing models to unravel the greater contribution of C 3 plants
            (mainly forest-based) over CAM plants (cactus and agaves) in the diet of Neotropical
            birds in a semi-arid zone in Venezuela . Their results revealed the importance of forest
            patches for bird communities. evaluated the diet of two congener species of
               <tp:taxon-name> Elaenia Sundevall, 1836 </tp:taxon-name> (one resident and one
            migratory) over their annual life cycles in the Brazilian Cerrado. Using mixing models,
            the authors showed that both species employ similar foraging strategies, contrary to the
            expectation that their diets would differ. Their study brings attention to the
            importance of new research to assess differences and similarities in the diet of birds
            that co-occur in species-rich tropical biomes. Mixing models encompass a wide range of
            research possibilities, but it is crucial to have a good experimental design for sample
            collection (both from birds and their food resources), and a prior knowledge of the
            analysis to be employed and its particularities ( , ). Especially in Brazil , where
            there is a great diversity of species and food resources, it is important to sample all
            possible food items to build an adequate isotopic baseline. </p>
         <p> In addition to specifying the contribution of each food item to the diet of a species,
            stable isotopes in trophic ecology studies are also employed to assess which habitat is
            used by an animal to obtain resources (e.g., , , ). The habitat-level approach in
            foraging studies is important because it can serve as a guide for conservation,
            especially in landscapes that have been extremely modified by man. For instance, the
            isotopic results of highlight the urgency to preserve forest patches and to design
            multifunctional landscapes for the maintenance of bird communities. Another
            consideration is that generalist species of the Brazilian Atlantic Forest, which appear
            to adapt well to environmental changes, in fact consume forest resources (mainly C 3
            plants) more than they consume resources from agricultural areas (C 4 plants) ( , ).
            Nevertheless, the dependence of birds on forest habitats is not exclusive to the
            Neotropics. , in a study using carbon isotopic values, discussed the importance of
            forests as a source of food for bird communities in Central Africa. Even though
            granivores are adapted to open environments (showing δ 13 C values similar to C 4
            plants), many other trophic guilds are highly dependent on forest resources, especially
            understory insectivores ( ). In a world facing rapid human-induced changes in landscape
            composition and structure, stable isotope analysis may help to better understand the
            various ecological aspects of birds in highly modified habitats. </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> Studies in trophic ecology may estimate the isotopic niche metrics of bird species.
            Understanding a species’ niche, which includes diet, habitat use, and geographic
            patterns, is very important to understand the natural history of a species ( ). The
            isotopic niche is correlated with the ecological niche, since the δ- space is comparable
            to the n-dimensional space of the niche concept ( ). Bosenbecker and Bugoni (2020)
            investigated isotopic niche width and overlap in three sympatric species of
               <tp:taxon-name> Turdus Linnaeus, 1758 </tp:taxon-name> in southern Brazil . Even
            though the contribution of each food item is slightly different among thrushes, niche
            overlap shows that the three species share similar resources, mainly C 3 plants and
            invertebrates ( ). documented a decrease in the width of the isotopic niche of many
            trophic guilds in human-modified landscapes when compared to birds in natural areas of
            the Atlantic Forest biome. Although the niche of granivore birds tends to expand in
            human-modified landscapes, the niche of frugivore, insectivore, nectarivore, and
            omnivore birds becomes narrower in response to the anthropogenic impacts in southeastern
            Brazil ( ). Several Brazilian biomes have struggled with human expansion and,
            consequently, with their negative environmental effects, such as habitat loss,
            fragmentation, and savannization (e.g., , , , , ). Contrasting with this situation,
            little has been done in the field of isotopic niche studies to produce information that
            could guide the conservation of bird species and their habitats in the Neotropical
            region. </p>
         <p> The isotopic niche approach provides practical solutions to several questions regarding
            the ecology of birds. Nevertheless, it is worth mentioning that this method, which is
            backed up by helpful analytical software packages (e.g., SIBER – , rKIN – ), is still
            recent and has some shortfalls. To avoid them, it is important to make a detailed
            assessment of the isotopic variation of baseline resources ( ). Moreover, we do not know
            the diet of many Neotropical bird species, highlighting the need for a careful
            interpretation of the results, and expanding our knowledge about the natural history of
            those species. </p>
         <p> Stable isotope analysis has proven a valuable tool to identify foraging specializations
            in individuals or species ( , ). Species may exhibit varying degrees of intra-population
            specialization in food resource exploration and habitat use, which can be identified
            through multi-tissue isotopic analysis ( , ). Martínez del compared intrapopulation
            isotopic variation among three species of <tp:taxon-name> Cinclodes G.R. Gray, 1840
            </tp:taxon-name> in South America. Each of the species has a seasonal foraging
            singularity. Representatives of one species are generalists and consume
            terrestrial/freshwater and marine resources. Individuals of a second species have both
            generalist and specialist individuals, and a third species has specialist individuals
            strictly dependent on marine invertebrates (Martínez del ). showed that the diet of
               <tp:taxon-name> Elaenia cristata Pelzeln, 1868 </tp:taxon-name> , a terrestrial
            migratory bird in Brazil , varies depending on the time of the year (breeding, molting,
            and non-breeding), and between adults and juveniles. Some birds may have distinct
            individual dietary preferences, so it is possible to observe isotopic variations among
            individuals of different ages and sexes ( ). Nevertheless, although Brazil has a vast
            territory inhabited by several species with different degrees of specialization, stable
            isotope analysis has not been employed to its full potential to allows us to understand
            these patterns. </p>
         <p> The concept of isoscapes and the use of stable isotopes to track migratory species </p>
         <p> Detecting large-scale movement patterns in migratory species may be time consuming and
            financially costly, especially when conventional methodologies are employed (e.g.,
            telemetry, mark-recapture, leg banding) ( ). It is increasingly evident that isotopic
            analysis is a great cost-effective tool to obtain information on the geographic patterns
            of birds through the use of isoscapes and individual values of δ 2 H and δ 18 O ( , ,
            Table 1 ). There has been a growing appeal among researchers to explore Neotropical
            regions, in association with North America studies, to construct an isotopic atlas for
            migratory birds ( ). This effort aims to facilitate the understanding of migratory
            dynamics, and to develop more effective approaches to the conservation of species. Even
            though Brazil has a great diversity of migratory birds and is also in the migratory
            route of several species ( ), few studies conducted in the country have used stable
            isotopes to address this theme. </p>
         <p> Brazil stretches over a wide latitudinal and longitudinal extent, which provides
            markedly distinct isoscapes ( ). Isoscapes are the geographic patterns of isotopic
            values of landscapes, represented by maps of δ 2 H, δ 18 O, and others. The different
            Brazilian biomes have particular water regimes and, therefore, each may show different
            values of δ 2 H and δ 18 O ( ). Although seasonal variations in atmospheric circulation
            slightly influence in isoscapes annually, isotopic spatial patterns are stable on a
            large temporal scale, providing robust data to trace the geographic origin of
            individuals analyzed ( ). </p>
         <p> Migrant birds have different breeding and wintering sites. Usually, they molt during
            one of these periods, before the migration event. Thus, the values of δ 2 H and δ 18 O
            of the feathers, an inert tissue, reflect the isotopic value of the region in which the
            molting was performed ( ). Certain tropical regions are obligatory routes for several
            migratory species. If stochastic events and anthropogenic impacts reach these areas, the
            conservation of the birds passing through these routes may be impacted. observed that
            populations of some migratory birds from distinct North American sites mixed
            spatial-temporally in an area of Colombia . Populations that do not have distinct
            migratory routes may compete for resources in the same region at the same time,
            representing a possible bottleneck for the survival of these species ( ). South America
            receives many migratory birds escaping from the winter of the Northern Hemisphere.
            Forest areas in northern Brazil have been impacted by changes in land-use for
            agricultural purposes, which may pose a threat not only to resident species but also to
            migrant birds. Using isotopic analysis to track the origin of individuals may be helpful
            for the determination of priority areas for conservation of paramount sites on migratory
            routes. </p>
         <p> Altitudinal migration is another geographic pattern performed by several Neotropical
            birds and which can be measured using the isotopic analysis of hydrogen. Variations in
            precipitation rates and atmospheric dynamics along altitudinal gradients promote
            different values of δ 2 H through the environment and, consequently, in migrant
            individuals ( ). By analyzing different tissues, it is possible to track the altitudinal
            migratory route, since each has a distinct turnover rate. This means that each tissue
            will provide the δ 2 H value of the environment in which it was formed (e.g., low or
            high elevation) ( ). Nevertheless, it is fundamental to consider the seasonal variations
            in the precipitation patterns of a region to correctly interpret the isotopic values of
            birds ( ). Studies that evaluate altitudinal migration in the Brazilian territory using
            stable isotopes are recent and are few and far in-between. Adopting this methodology
            might facilitate the understanding of the elevational movement patterns of birds,
            especially considering the influence of climate change in modifying the migratory
            dynamics of species. </p>
         <p> Understanding physiological and stressful events that might affect birds through
            laboratory experiments </p>
         <p> The accuracy of isotopic analysis depends on incorporating corrections to individual
            values that consider the physiological dynamics of the species ( Table 1 ), such as
            isotopic discrimination. Correctly measuring the discrimination values between consumers
            and food resources is essential for applying mixing models and estimating the trophic
            position of individuals (Martínez del ). Nonetheless, estimating the discrimination
            factors is not trivial. Studies have proposed tools to help researchers estimate trophic
            discrimination factors (TDFs) to correct isotopic values for species, without the need
            for experimental work (e.g., , ). Still, exploring this theme in further studies is
            essential to fine-tune the isotopic analysis methodology ( ), especially concerning
            Brazil’s native birds, since their TDFs have not, for the most part, been calculated.
            Through controlled and monitored changes in the diet of individual birds in the
            laboratory, it is possible to measure the TDF of a species ( ). In this type of
            experiment, researchers must give the animals a diet with different isotopic values at
            preset intervals (e.g., starting with C 3 resources and switching to C 4 ) and,
            concomitantly, monitor the isotopic values of the tissues until the change in the diet
            can be identified. In these types of experiments, it is important to determine the
            growth rate of the target tissue for analysis. Ornithologists interested in this topic
            may rely on zoos and legal breeding programs to develop laboratory experiments, while
            keeping in mind that the physiological patterns of captive and wild individuals may
            differ ( ). </p>
         <p> The isotopic turnover of each tissue may vary greatly in time (from days to years)
            depending on the physiology of the species ( ). Several studies have already focused on
            determining the turnover rates of various tissues of birds and other taxa ( ).
            Nevertheless, the dynamics of isotopic incorporation among tissues is also a relatively
            new topic for Brazilian ornithologists. The same approach (switching diets in the
            laboratory) can be used to monitor the turnover rate of each tissue that one intends to
            use in the isotopic analysis ( ). Considering that species from diverse Brazilian biomes
            may present particular physiologies, it is desirable to understand whether they show
            distinct turnover rates for the same tissue. </p>
         <p> There is still no consensus among researchers about the influence of nutritional stress
            on the isotopic values expressed by bird tissues. Some studies have shown that δ 13 C
            and δ 15 N values can vary slightly or greatly due to stressful events, depending on the
            physiology of the species (e.g., , ). Extreme events such as starvation and natural
            disasters may have serious physiological consequences for birds, including defects in
            the feather, for instance fault bars ( , ). analyzed juvenile individuals of
               <tp:taxon-name> Ammodramus savannarum (J.F. Gmelin, 1789) </tp:taxon-name> after a
            severe storm, comparing individuals with and without pallid bands (a type of fault bar).
            Juveniles containing pallid bands showed lower values of δ 15 N than individuals with
            normal feathers, due to the environmental stressors they experienced. Other studies
            point to the lack of a relationship between the isotopic values found in bird tissues
            and stressful events, such as food restriction and disease infection (e.g., , ). None of
            these studies have been developed with birds from Brazilian biomes. Thus, ornithologists
            must make efforts to understand the relationship among physiology, stressful events, and
            isotopic values of species occurring in Brazil . </p>
         <p> Using isotopic analysis to unravel long-term temporal dynamics in bird ecology </p>
         <p> Understanding the historical patterns in the ecology of a bird is essential for the
            development of conservation practices. To that end, it is possible to obtain broad
            temporal information through the analysis of stable isotopes. All sub-themes already
            covered in this review may be subject to studies aimed to understand the history of a
            bird’s ecology, such as diet, habitat use, and geographic and physiological patterns (
            Table 1 ). To that end, natural history museums play a fundamental role in preserving
            metabolically inert tissues (e.g., feathers, bones, claws) that serve as a source for
            isotopic analysis ( ). Generally, museum specimens are useful and is the only way to
            access historical samples ( ). </p>
         <p> Although ornithological collections are a rich source of historical samples for the
            analysis of stable isotopes, museum specimens have not been broadly used in studies,
            particularly in the Neotropics. Considering the lack of extensive specific literature
            with isotopes and terrestrial birds on a temporal scale in Brazil , studies from
            temperate environments will be discussed to illuminate some prospects to be employed in
            tropical regions. Anthropogenic impacts such as land-use changes, habitat loss, and
            agriculture expansion can be directly associated with historical alterations in the
            ecology of birds, which can be observed through δ 13 C and δ 15 N values ( , ). showed
            that over 100 years of human expansion in a region of southeastern Brazil , the isotopic
            niche width of several trophic guilds (frugivores, granivores, insectivores,
            nectarivores, and omnivores) have been drastically reduced. also observed the narrowing
            of the niche of <tp:taxon-name> Eremophila alpestris (Linnaeus, 1758) </tp:taxon-name>
            since 1916, that is a widespread species in the northern hemisphere. Both studies
            suggest that the agricultural expansion in the study areas has decreased the amount and
            availability of food for these birds, consequently affecting their niche width. Given
            the severe land-use changes that can be observed in the Brazilian territory since the
            European colonization and markedly during the last hundred years, the use of isotopic
            analysis with museum specimens is important to understand the modifications in the
            ecology of tropical birds. </p>
         <p> The human impact on the isotopic values of birds has also been addressed in ecological
            studies. For instance, changes in the δ 15 N values of birds may reflect an increased
            use of fertilizers in agriculture, or even an increase in garbage disposal ( , , ).
            discussed the reduction in δ 15 N values between historical and modern birds of
            different trophic guilds and its possible relationship with the increased use of
            synthetic nitrogen fertilizers in Brazil . also showed the association among changes in
            δ 15 N values in contemporary birds, increased use of fertilizers in agriculture, and
            their negative consequences in the health of the feathers of <tp:taxon-name> Somateria
               mollissima (Linnaeus, 1758) </tp:taxon-name> in Denmark . Brazilian lands are known
            worldwide for their agricultural productivity and consequent negative influence on
            biodiversity ( ). Notwithstanding, we still lack information on the influence of
            nitrogen fertilizers applied in landscapes on the morphological characteristics of
            native bird species. </p>
         <p> Stable isotopes also allow us to ascertain changes in the migratory and geographic
            patterns of birds over time (e.g., , ). evaluated whether historical and contemporary
            individuals of <tp:taxon-name> Euphagus carolinus (Statius Muller, 1776)
            </tp:taxon-name> , a North American migratory species, have altered their geographic
            patterns since the nineteenth century. The results ofδ 2 H indicate that the small
            changes in the eastern populations may result from changes in the quality and
            availability of habitat and food resources, which generated a valuable direction in
            conservation strategies for this bird ( ). also found no geographical changes over the
            last 160 years for two declining migrant species in Europe, but argued that similar δ 2
            H patterns between historical and modern individuals may result from a homogeneous
            latitudinal decrease in the populations of these birds. In Brazil , there is a diversity
            of migratory species that may be struggling against the negative effects of climate
            change on their movement patterns. The application of isotopic analysis can be a useful
            tool to understand these spatiotemporal changes. </p>
         <p> Although long-term temporal studies are an expanding theme in bird ecology, some
            practical precautions in the use of isotopic analysis must be employed for the correct
            interpretation of the results. A representative sampling of the environmental isotopic
            baseline is essential in dietary studies, since it can represent a bias if it is not
            well addressed with adequate values that reflect the resources used in the time scale
            analyzed ( ). In this situation, natural history museum collections and herbariums are a
            significant source of food resource samples from the past, contributing to build an
            isotopic baseline. Another relevant precaution is the need to correct for isotopic
            values following temporal variations in the isotopic constitution of ecosystems and the
            atmosphere. The Suess effect represents a change in δ 13 C values in the atmosphere over
            the years, as a result of an increase in CO 2 from anthropogenic activities ( ), and it
            should be considered in studies that aim to analyze historical biological data ( ). </p>
         <p> Protocol for feather collection in field samplings </p>
         <p> The use of mist-nets in ecological studies to capture birds is common across Brazil .
            The Brazilian government agency responsible for standardizing the bird ringing process
            (CEMAVE/ ICMBio) has already counted approximately one million individuals banded since
            1977 ( ). Despite the numerous projects involving bird capture, few efforts have been
            made to consolidate a feather collection protocol for isotopic analysis ( ). The rewards
            of building a solid isotopic database are enormous, as discussed elsewhere in this text. </p>
         <p> Feathers are the most recommended tissue among ornithologists to build a comprehensive
            collection, since they are easy to collect and to store, and it is also an inert tissue
            for isotopic analysis ( , ). More than one type of feather should be collected
            (primaries, rectrices, and breast contour), since the isotopic values between them may
            vary according to their molting period ( ). Multi-feather collection is also important
            in the case of migratory species, since the molting period may be correlated with the
            environmental aspects and geographic origin of the individuals ( ). Collecting other
            tissues (e.g., blood, claw) is also relevant, since it can complement information on a
            temporal scale within the same individual. In this case, researchers must be trained
            specialists and comply with the ethics committees and animal welfare laws. </p>
         <p> Besides tissue samples, some additional information is needed to build a strong
            database for the interpretation of isotopic data ( ). Researchers should identify each
            bird to the lowest possible taxonomic level, annotate the exact collecting location
            (geographic coordinates are preferable), and the date of collection (day, month, and
            year). Whenever possible, ornithologists should accurately report the sex and age of the
            individuals sampled. The food resources (e.g., invertebrates, fruits, seeds, flowers)
            available in the environment are valuable to compose the isotopic baseline, so it is
            important to emphasize the relevance of collecting some items by opportunistic search or
            through gut contents expelled by birds during the capture (e.g., regurgitates or feces).
            Food resources should preferably be stored dry or frozen, without chemical preservation
            methods (e.g., ethanol, formaldehyde), since preserving invertebrates in ethanol may
            alter their isotopic values ( ). The recommendation for a widespread feather collection
            should not inhibit the traditional collection of museum specimens, but serve the purpose
            of increasing the availability of samples for isotopic and molecular analyses ( , ). The
            AviSample Network metadata repository is a global initiative that provides an
            opportunity for ornithologists to share all the information related to stored tissue
            samples, contributing for new collaborations among researchers and the reuse of avian
            samples ( ). </p>
         <p> The role of Brazilian museums in providing data and tissue samples </p>
         <p> Natural History Museums are rich repositories of data that have been traditionally
            employed in studies of taxonomy and systematics. More recently, collections have been
            also used in ecological studies, including studies in isotopic ecology ( , ). Up to
            twenty years ago, the worldwide use of isotopic analysis in museum bird specimens was
            not common. In Brazil , ecological studies using this approach are even more recent and
            under-explored ( ). Brazilian museums, particularly the following three examples holding
            vast Neotropical bird collections, have enormous potential for stable isotope research:
            Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo , Museu Paraense Emílio Goeldi, and Museu
            Nacional – UFRJ. Additionally, other museums and private collections throughout Brazil
            may prove valuable. </p>
         <p> Despite the recent efforts to employ the isotopic tool and the accessibility of
            ornithological collections to molecular analyzes, there is still a need for greater
            interaction between Brazilian museum curators and isotopic ornithological research. One
            concern that may worry curators is the destruction of tissues from specimens (mainly
            feathers). Nevertheless, most studies require a small amount of feather sample (e.g., 1
            mg or 0.5 cm ²) to accurately analyze stable isotopes, and this does not visually alter
            the specimen ( ). A small piece of sample is sufficient to bring relevant results to
            understand the ecology of endangered species and assist in planning the conservation of
            target birds ( ). Another point to be considered, is the creation of an integrated open
            access database of bird isotopic values, which will help to avoid the re-sampling of
            feathers and other tissues from species in museums and collections that have already
            been sampled. Besides that, this initiative would also stimulate scientific partnership
            among researchers to explore other aspects of a species’ ecology or to provide
            complementary information to other analytical methods. </p>
         <p> Improving tools to assist forensics and illegal bird trade </p>
         <p> Isotopic analysis can also be employed in forensic studies to help determine the
            geographic origin of seized birds ( , ). In Brazil , besides the impacts of
            fragmentation and habitat loss, the illegal trade of species is one of the major threats
            to bird diversity ( ). Approximately 23% of Brazilian bird species are traded illegally,
            many of which are classified into threatened categories of IUCN ( ). Associating
            isoscapes and isotopic values of seized individuals may be useful to determine
            trafficking routes in Brazil , and target more effective strategies to fight against
            illegal bird trade ( ). Additionally, the release of seized and recovered birds in
            unsuitable locations (outside their geographic range) may pose a potential risk to wild
            populations ( , ). Thus, isotopic analysis can be a relevant tool to identify the origin
            of individuals and establish appropriate places for their release. </p>
         <p> The continuous generation of isoscapes for the Brazilian territory will increase the
            robustness of isotopic analysis in forensics. Efforts are already being implemented to
            understand the isotopic differences among distinct vegetation types and precipitation
            patterns in the Brazilian biomes (e.g., , ). Expanding these efforts may help to fight
            against the illegal trade of wildlife, such as increasing coverage from the Global
            Network of Isotopes in Precipitation (GNIP), which provides data on temporal and spatial
            variations of environmental isotopes in precipitation. Another important process that
            should be better understood to improve the stable isotope tool in forensics is the
            molting periods of distinct bird taxa, promoting the correct interpretation of
            individual isotopic values and geographic origin. More recently, the use of
            compound-specific isotope analysis (CSIA) has gained interest. It consists of obtaining
            the isotopic value of amino acids rather than of bulk tissues ( ). Since essential amino
            acids do not undergo biochemical reactions, their isotopic values directly reflect the
            food ingested and isotopic data from diet sources are not necessary ( ). This recent
            advance promises more accurate and informative isotopic values, helping to improve the
            forensic tool used to fight illegal bird trade ( ). </p>
         <p> Financial and sample size shortcomings </p>
         <p> Despite the advantages of using stable isotopes as a tool to understand the ecology of
            species, there is still a financial constraint that prevents researchers from
            considering this method. The analysis can cost $10–20 US dollars per sample, depending
            on the number of isotopes of interest and whether the researcher already sends the
            samples prepared for the analysis, or not. If the samples are sent for analysis outside
            of Brazil , there are additional shipping costs and the samples must be registered with
            the SISGEN system (Sistema Nacional de Gestão do Patrimônio Genético e do Conhecimento
            Tradicional Associado). The cost of an isotopic study depends on the total number of
            samples analyzed, which may vary according to objectives of the research. Ecological
            studies usually use the rule of thumb to determine a reliable sample size (n = 30), but
            this should not be unconditional, since the experimental design must follow the
            assumptions of the analyzes employed ( ). Some isotopic niche analyzes suggest a minimum
            of 10–15 samples per group, to obtain consistent and robust results ( , ) although
            studies with other approaches may require more samples. It is relevant to point out that
            using conventional methodologies is not necessarily cheaper, as it requires greater
            field effort and the acquisition of other tools to achieve the same results obtained
            with stable isotopes. Even so, although isotopic analysis is not expensive, it is not
            yet widely available nor is it under consideration by Brazilian researchers when
            designing new project funding proposals. Additionally, it is desirable to establish
            collaboration between researchers in ornithology and isotopic ecology, increasing the
            analytical power of the study. </p>
         <p> Final remarks </p>
         <p> The Brazilian scenario for exploring the isotopic analysis of terrestrial birds is
            promising. There are many ecological topics that can be approached with this tool. Even
            the most common stable isotopes in ecology studies (carbon, nitrogen, hydrogen, and
            oxygen) are still not frequently used in studies originating in Brazil . Trophic ecology
            is one topic that may benefit from the use of isotopic analysis, since it provides
            robust information about the diet, use of habitat, and species’ niche (e.g., , , ).
            Detecting the migratory and geographic patterns of birds is another interesting topic to
            be addressed with stable isotopes (e.g., , ), especially in a territory where there is
            great diversity of migratory species. Studies on physiology and laboratory experiments
            are crucial to improve the isotopic method, adapting it to the reality of native species
            (e.g., Martínez del , ). Additionally, valuing museums and ornithological collections
            may promote desirable opportunities to increase our knowledge about the ecological
            history of birds and to compare it with the contemporary ecology, to help devise
            conservation strategies (e.g., ). </p>
         <p> Despite so many opportunities for studies in the Brazilian territory using stable
            isotopes and birds, there are still some challenges to be considered before the
            enthusiasm for the tool grows. Researchers interested in employing isotopic analysis
            must know the methodological shortcomings to correctly interpret the results ( , , ). If
            precautions are taken, however, the benefits of using isotopes to broaden our knowledge
            of bird ecology will become increasingly evident. In a country with such a vast
            territory, composed of six biomes, all under intense pressure from anthropogenic impacts
            (land-use changes, habitat loss, fragmentation), the use of isotopic analysis in new
            ornithological studies is promising. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title> ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </title>
         <p> ABN thanks the Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo (FAPESP) for the
            doctoral scholarship (process 2020/07619-0) and LFS thanks the Conselho Nacional de
            Pesquisa e Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico (CNPq) for the research grant (CNPq
            302291/2016-6 and 308337/2019-0) and to the Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de
            São Paulo to the ARCA project (Thematic project FAPESP, 2017/23548–2). We also thank the
            reviewers for their valuable comments and contributions. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title> LITERATURE CITED </title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Alves RRN , Lima JRF , Araujo HFP ( 2013 ) The live bird trade in
                  Brazil and its conservation implications: an overview . Bird Conservation
                  International 23 ( 1 ): 53–65 . https://doi. org/10.1017/S095927091200010X
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Andersson AA , Gibson L , Baker DM , Cybulski JD , Wang S , Leung B
                  , Chu LM , Dingle C ( 2021 ) Stable isotope analysis as a tool to detect illegal
                  trade in critically endangered cockatoos . Animal Conservation 24 ( 6 ): 1021–1031
                  . https://doi.org/10.1111/ acv.12705 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Araújo MS , Bolnick DI , Machado G , Giaretta AA , Reis SF ( 2007 )
                  Using δ 13 C Stable Isotopes to Quantify Individual-Level Diet Variation .
                  Oecologia 152 ( 4 ): 643–654 . https://doi. org/10.1007/s00442-007-0687-l
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Araújo MS , Bolnick DI , Layman CA ( 2011 ) The ecological causes of
                  individual specialisation . Ecology Letters 14 ( 9 ): 948– 958 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1461-0248.2011.01662.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Atkinson PW , Baker AJ , Bevan RM , Clark NA , Cole KB , Gonzalez PM
                  , Newton J , Niles LJ , Robinson RA ( 2005 ) Unravelling the migration and moult
                  strategies of a long-distance migrant using stable isotopes: Red Knot Calidris
                  canutus movements in the Americas . Ibis 147 ( 4 ): 738–749 . https://doi.
                  org/10.1111/j.1474-919x.2005.00455.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bearhop S , Waldron S , Votier SC , Furness RW ( 2002 ) Factors That
                  Influence Assimilation Rates and Fractionation of Nitrogen and Carbon Stable
                  Isotopes in Avian Blood and Feathers . Physiological and Biochemical Zoology 75 (
                  5 ): 451–458 . https://doi.org/10.1086/342800 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bearhop S , Furness RW , Hilton GM , Votier SC , Waldron S ( 2003 )
                  A forensic approach to understanding diet and habitat use from stable isotope
                  analysis of (avian) claw material . Functional Ecology 17 ( 2 ): 270–275 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1046/ j.1365-2435.2003.00725.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ben-David M , Flaherty EA ( 2012 ) Stable isotopes in mammalian
                  research: a beginner’s guide . Journal of Mammalogy 93 ( 2 ): 312–328 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1644/11-mamm-s-166.1 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Blight LK , Hobson KA , Kyser TK , Arcese P ( 2015 ) Changing gull
                  diet in a changing world: A 150-year stable isotope (δ 13 C, δ 15 N) record from
                  feathers collected in the Pacific Northwest of North America . Global Change
                  Biology 21 ( 4 ): 1497– 1507 . https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.12796 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Boecklen WJ , Yarnes CT , Cook BA , James AC ( 2011 ) On the use of
                  stable isotopes in trophic ecology . Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution and
                  Systematics 42 : 411–440 . https:// doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-102209-144726
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Boesing AL , Marques TS , Martinelli LA , Nichols E , Siqueira PR ,
                  Beier C , Camargo PB , Metzger JP ( 2021 ) Conservation implications of a limited
                  avian cross-habitat spillover in pasture lands . Biological Conservation 253 :
                  108898 . https://doi. org/10.1016/j.biocon.2020.108898 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bond AL , Hobson KA ( 2012 ) Reporting stable-isotope ratios in
                  ecology: recommended terminology, guidelines and best practices . Waterbirds 35 (
                  2 ): 324 . https://doi. org/10.1675/063.035.0213 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bond AL , Jardine TD , Hobson KA ( 2016 ) Multi-tissue
                  stable-isotope analyses can identify dietary specialization . Methods in Ecology
                  and Evolution 7 ( 12 ): 1428–1437 . https://doi. org/10.1111/2041-210X.12620
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bosenbecker C , Bugoni L ( 2020 ) Trophic niche similarities of
                  sympatric Turdus thrushes determined by fecal contents, stable isotopes, and
                  bipartite network approaches . Ecology and Evolution 10 ( 17 ): 9073–9084 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.6485 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bowen GJ , Wassenaar LI , Hobson KA ( 2005 ) Global application of
                  stable hydrogen and oxygen isotopes to wildlife forensics . Oecologia 143 ( 3 ):
                  337–348 . https://doi.org/10.1007/ s00442-004-1813-y </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Brlík V , Pipek P , Brandis K , Chernetsov N , Costa FJV , Herrera
                  LG , Kiat Y , Lanctot RB , Marra PP , Norris DR , Nwaogu CJ , Quillfeldt P ,
                  Saalfeld ST , Stricker CA , Thomson RL , Zhao T , Procházka P ( 2022 ) The reuse
                  of avian samples: opportunities, pitfalls, and a solution . Ibis 164 ( 1 ):
                  343–349 . https:// doi.org/10.1111/ibi.12997 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bugoni L , McGill RAR , Furness RW ( 2008 ) Effects of preservation
                  methods on stable isotope signatures in bird tissues . Rapid Communications in
                  Mass Spectrometry 22 ( 16 ): 2457–2462 . https://doi.org/10.1002/rcm.3633
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Cardenas-Ortiz L , Bayly NJ , Kardynal KJ , Hobson KA ( 2020 )
                  Defining catchment origins of a geographical bottleneck: Implications of
                  population mixing and phenological overlap for the conservation of Neotropical
                  migratory birds . Condor 122 ( 2 ): duaa004.
                  https://doi.org/10.1093/condor/duaa004 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Caron-Beaudoin É , Gentes ML , Patenaude-Monette M , Hélie JF ,
                  Giroux JF , Verreault J ( 2013 ) Combined usage of stable isotopes and GPS-based
                  telemetry to understand the feeding ecology of an omnivorous bird, the Ring-billed
                  Gull ( Larus delawarensis ) . Canadian Journal of Zoology 91 ( 10 ): 689–697 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Carvalho FMV , De Marco P , Ferreira LG ( 2009 ) The Cerrado
                  into-pieces: Habitat fragmentation as a function of landscape use in the savannas
                  of central Brazil . Biological Conservation 142 ( 7 ): 1392–1403 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2009.01.031 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Casey MM , Post DM ( 2011 ) The problem of isotopic baseline:
                  Reconstructing the diet and trophic position of fossil animals . Earth-Science
                  Reviews 106 (1– 2 ): 131–148 . https://doi. org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2011.02.001
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Caut S , Angulo E , Courchamp F ( 2009 ) Variation in discrimination
                  factors (Δ 15 N and Δ 13 C): The effect of diet isotopic values and applications
                  for diet reconstruction . Journal of Applied Ecology 46 ( 2 ): 443–453 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/ j.1365-2664.2009.01620.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Cheesman AW , Cernusak LA ( 2016 ) Isoscapes: A new dimension in
                  community ecology . Tree Physiology 36 ( 12 ): 1456– 1459 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1093/treephys/tpw099 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Chesson LA , Barnette JE , Bowen GJ , Brooks JR , Casale JF ,
                  Cerling TE , Cook CS , Douthitt CB , Howa JD , Hurley JM , Kreuzer HW , Lott MJ ,
                  Martinelli LA , O’Grady SP , Podlesak DW , Tipple BJ , Valenzuela LO , West JB (
                  2018 ) Applying the principles of isotope analysis in plant and animal ecology to
                  forensic science in the Americas . Oecologia 187 : 1077–1094 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-018-4188-1 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Costa FJV , Hobson KA , Wunder MB , Nardoto GB ( 2021 ) Linking
                  environmental indicators to blood, feather and claw δ 18 O in the Saffron Finch (
                  Sicalis flaveola ) in the central Brazilian savannas . Journal of Ornithology 163
                  : 223–234 . https://doi. org/10.1007/s10336-021-01939-0 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> DeNiro MJ , Epstein S ( 1976 ) You are what you eat (plus a few ‰):
                  the carbon isotope cycle in food chains . Geological Society of America 6 : 834 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Dodds WK , Collins SM , Hamilton SK , Tank JL , Johnson S , Webster
                  JR , Simon KS , Whiles MR , Rantala HM , McDowell WH , Peterson SD , Riis T ,
                  Crenshaw CL , Thomas SA , Kristensen PB , Cheever BM , Flecker AS , Griffiths NA ,
                  Crowl T , Rosi-Marshall EJ , El-Sabaawi R , Martí E ( 2014 ) You are not always
                  what we think you eat: selective assimilation across multiple whole-stream
                  isotopic tracer studies . Ecology 95 ( 10 ): 2757–2767 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1890/13-2276.1 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Dombrosky J ( 2020 ) A ~1000-year 13 C Suess correction model for
                  the study of past ecosystems . The Holocene 30 ( 3 ): 474– 478 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1177/0959683619887416 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Durães R , Marini MAÂ ( 2005 ) A quantitative assessment of bird
                  diets in the Brazilian Atlantic Forest, with recommendations for future diet
                  studies . Ornitología Neotropical 16 : 65–83 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Eckrich CA , Albeke SE , Flaherty EA , Bowyer RT , Ben-David M (
                  2020 ) rKIN: Kernel-based method for estimating isotopic niche size and overlap .
                  Journal of Animal Ecology 89 ( 3 ): 757–771 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2656.13159 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Efe MA , Martins-Ferreira C , Olmos F , Mohr LV , Silveira LF ( 2006
                  ) Diretrizes da Sociedade Brasileira de Ornitologia para a destinação de aves
                  silvestres provenientes do tráfico e cativeiro . Revista Brasileira de Ornitologia
                  14 ( 1 ): 67–72 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> English PA , Green DJ , Nocera JJ ( 2018 ) Stable isotopes from
                  museum specimens may provide evidence of long-term change in the trophic ecology
                  of a migratory aerial insectivore . Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution 6 : 14 .
                  https://doi.org/10.3389/fevo.2018.00014 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ferger SW , Bohning-Gaese K , Wilcke W , Oelmann Y , Schleuning M (
                  2013 ) Distinct carbon sources indicate strong differentiation between tropical
                  forest and farmland bird communities . Oecologia 171 : 473–486 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-012-2422-9 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Fox T , Bearhop S ( 2008 ) The use of stable-isotope ratios in
                  ornithology . British Birds 101 ( 3 ): 112–130 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Fry B ( 2008 ) Stable Isotope Ecology . Springer, New York , 316 pp.
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Gastmans D , Santos V , Galhardi JA , Gromboni JF , Batista LV ,
                  Miotlinski K , Chang HK , Govone JS ( 2017 ) Controls over spatial and seasonal
                  variations on isotopic composition of the precipitation along the central and
                  eastern portion of Brazil . Isotopes in Environmental and Health Studies 53 ( 5 ):
                  518–538 . https://doi.org/10.1080/10256016.2017.1305376 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> González-Carcacía JA , Gerardo Herrera LM , Nassar JM ( 2020 )
                  Dietary importance of C3 and CAM food pathways for birds in a Neotropical semiarid
                  zone . Biotropica 52 ( 5 ): 938–945 . https://doi.org/10.1111/btp.12798
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Graves GR , Newsome SD , Willard DE , Grosshuesch DA , Wurzel WW ,
                  Fogel ML ( 2012 ). Nutritional stress and body condition in the Great Gray Owl (
                  Strix nebulosa ) during winter irruptive migrations . Canadian Journal of Zoology
                  90 ( 7 ): 787–797 . https://doi.org/10.1139/z2012-047 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Grecian WJ , McGill RAR , Phillips RA , Ryan PG , Furness RW ( 2015
                  ) Quantifying variation in δ 13 C and δ 15 N isotopes within and between feathers
                  and individuals: Is one sample enough? Marine Biology 162 ( 4 ): 733–741 .
                  https://doi. org/10.1007/s00227-015-2618-8 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Guaraldo AC , Kelly JF , Marini MÂ ( 2016 ) Contrasting annual
                  cycles of an intratropical migrant and a tropical resident bird . Journal of
                  Ornithology 157 ( 3 ): 695–705 . https://doi. org/10.1007/s10336-016-1327-5
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Guaraldo AC , Kelly JF , Marini MÂ ( 2019 ) Independent trophic
                  behavior and breeding success of a resident flycatcher and a coexisting migratory
                  congener . Austral Ecology 44 ( 1 ): 126– 137 . https://doi.org/10.1111/aec.12660
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hardesty J ( 2009 ) Using nitrogen-15 to examine protein sources in
                  hummingbird diets . Ornitología Colombiana 8 : 19–28 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Healy K , Guillerme T , Kelly SBAA , Inger R , Bearhop S , Jackson
                  AL ( 2018 ) SIDER: An R package for predicting trophic discrimination factors of
                  consumers based on their ecology and phylogenetic relatedness . Ecography 41 ( 8
                  ): 1393–1400 . https://doi.org/10.1111/ecog.03371 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hebert CE , Wassenaar LI ( 2001 ) Stable nitrogen isotopes in
                  waterfowl feathers reflect agricultural land use in western Canada . Environmental
                  Science and Technology 35 ( 17 ): 3482–3487 . https://doi.org/10.1021/es001970p
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Herrera LG , Hobson KA , Rodríguez M , Hernandez P ( 2003 ) Trophic
                  partitioning in tropical rain forest birds: insights from stable isotope analysis
                  . Oecologia 136 ( 3 ): 439–444 . https:// doi.org/10.1007/s00442-003-1293-5
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA ( 1999 ) Tracing origins and migration of wildlife using
                  stable isotopes: a review . Oecologia 120 : 314–326 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA ( 2011 ) Isotopic ornithology: A perspective . Journal of
                  Ornithology 152 : S49–S 66 . https://doi.org/10.1007/ s10336-011-0653-x
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA , Clark RG ( 1992 ) Assessing avian diets using stable
                  isotopes I: Turnover of 13 C in tissues . Condor 94 ( 1 ): 181–188 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA , Norris DR ( 2008 ) Animal migration: a context for using
                  new techniques and approaches . In: Hobson KA , Wassenaar LI (Eds) Tracking animal
                  migration with stable isotopes . Academic Press, London , 1–19 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA , Alisauskas RT , Clark RG ( 1993 ) Stable-nitrogen
                  isotope enrichment in avian tissues due to fasting and nutritional stress:
                  implications for isotopic analyses of diet . Condor 95 ( 2 ): 388–394 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA , Wassenaar LI , Milá B , Lovette I , Dingle C , Smith TB
                  ( 2003 ) Stable isotopes as indicators of altitudinal distributions and movements
                  in an Ecuadorean hummingbird community . Oecologia 136 : 302–308 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA , Greenberg R , Van Wilgenburg SL , Mettke-Hofmann C (
                  2010 ) Migratory Connectivity in the Rusty Blackbird: Isotopic Evidence From
                  Feathers of Historical and Contemporary Specimens . Condor 112 ( 4 ): 778–788 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1525/cond.2010.100146 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA , Van Wilgenburg SL , Wassenaar LI , Powell RL , Still CJ
                  , Craine JM ( 2012 ) A multi-isotope (δ 13 C, δ 15 N, δ 2 H) feather isoscape to
                  assign Afrotropical migrant birds to origins . Ecosphere 3 ( 5 ): 1–20 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1890/ES12-00018.1 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA , Van Wilgenburg SL , Faaborg J , Toms JD , Rengifo C ,
                  Sosa AL , Aubry Y , Brito Aguilar R ( 2014 ) Connecting breeding and wintering
                  grounds of Neotropical migrant songbirds using stable hydrogen isotopes: a call
                  for an isotopic atlas of migratory connectivity . Journal of Field Ornithology 85
                  ( 3 ): 237–257 . https://doi.org/10.1111/jofo.12065 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hobson KA , Wassenaar LI , Bowen GJ , Courtiol A , Trueman CN ,
                  Voigt CC , West JB , McMahon KW , Newsome SD ( 2019 ) Outlook for Using Stable
                  Isotopes in Animal Migration Studies . In: Hobson KA , Wassenaar LI (Eds) Tracking
                  Animal Migration with Stable Isotopes . Academic Press, London , 237–244 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hopkins JB , Ferguson JM ( 2012 ) Estimating the diets of animals
                  using stable isotopes and a comprehensive Bayesian mixing model . PLoS One 7 ( 1
                  ): e 28478 . https://doi.org/10.1371/ journal.pone.0028478 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Inger R , Bearhop S ( 2008 ) Applications of stable isotope analyses
                  to avian ecology . Ibis 150 : 447–461 . https://doi.
                  org/10.1111/j.1474-919X.2008.00839.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ishikawa NF ( 2018 ) Use of compound-specific nitrogen isotope
                  analysis of amino acids in trophic ecology: assumptions, applications, and
                  implications . Ecological Research 33 ( 5 ): 825–837 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s11284-018-1616-y </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Jackson AL , Inger R , Parnell AC , Bearhop S ( 2011 ) Comparing
                  isotopic niche widths among and within communities: SIBER – Stable Isotope
                  Bayesian Ellipses in R . Journal of Animal Ecology 80 ( 3 ): 595–602 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/ j.1365-2656.2011.01806.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Jesus FM , Pereira MR , Rosa CS , Moreira MZ , Sperber CF ( 2015 )
                  Preservation methods alter carbon and nitrogen stable isotope values in crickets
                  (Orthoptera: Grylloidea) . PLoS One 10 ( 9 ): e 0137650 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0137650 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Jiguet F , Kardynal KJ , Hobson KA ( 2020 ) Feather stable isotope
                  (δ 2 H) measurements suggest no historical variation in latitudinal origin of
                  migrants in two declining songbirds . Journal of Ornithology 161 ( 4 ): 1045–1050
                  . https://doi.org/10.1007/ s10336-020-01797-2 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> John Glew KS , Wanless S , Harris MP , Daunt F , Erikstad KE , StrØm
                  H , Trueman CN ( 2018 ) Moult location and diet of auks in the north sea inferred
                  from coupled light-based and isotope-based geolocation . Marine Ecology Progress
                  Series 599 : 239–251 . https://doi.org/10.3354/meps12624 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Jovani R , Rohwer S ( 2017 ) Fault bars in bird feathers:
                  mechanisms, and ecological and evolutionary causes and consequences . Biological
                  Reviews 92 ( 2 ): 1113–1127 . https://doi. org/10.1111/brv.12273 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kelly JF ( 2000 ) Stable isotopes of carbon and nitrogen in the
                  study of avian and mammalian trophic ecology . Canadian Journal of Zoology 78 ( 1
                  ): 1–27 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kempster B , Zanette L , Longstaffe FJ , MacDougall-Shackleton SA ,
                  Wingfield JC , Clinchy M ( 2007 ) Do stable isotopes reflect nutritional stress?
                  Results from a laboratory experiment on song sparrows . Oecologia 151 ( 3 ):
                  365–371 . https:// doi.org/10.1007/s00442-006-0597-7 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Layman CA , Araújo MS , Boucek R , Hammerschlag-Peyer CM , Harrison
                  E , Jud ZR , Matich P , Rosenblatt AE , Vaudo JJ , Yeager LA , Post DM , Bearhop S
                  ( 2012 ) Applying stable isotopes to examine food-web structure: An overview of
                  analytical tools . Biological Reviews 87 ( 3 ): 545–562 . https://doi.
                  org/10.1111/j.1469-185X.2011.00208.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lopes LE , Fernandes AM , Marini MÂ ( 2005 ) Diet of some Atlantic
                  Forest birds . Ararajuba 13 ( 1 ): 95–103 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Magioli M , Moreira MZ , Fonseca RCB , Ribeiro MC , Rodrigues MG ,
                  Ferraz KMPMB ( 2019 ) Human-modified landscapes alter mammal resource and habitat
                  use and trophic structure . Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 116 (
                  37 ): 18466–18472 . https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1904384116 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Magioli M , Ferraz KMPMB , Chiarello AG , Galetti M , Setz EZF ,
                  Paglia AP , Abrego N , Ribeiro MC , Ovaskainen O ( 2021 ) Land-use changes lead to
                  functional loss of terrestrial mammals in a Neotropical rainforest . Perspectives
                  in Ecology and Conservation 19 ( 2 ): 161–170 . https://doi.org/10.1016/j.
                  pecon.2021.02.006 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Marini MÂ , Garcia FI ( 2005 ) Bird Conservation in Brazil .
                  Conservation Biology 19 ( 3 ): 665–671 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Martinelli LA , Ometto JPHB , Ferraz ES , Victoria RL , Camargo PB ,
                  Moreira MZ ( 2009 ) Desvendando questões ambientais com isótopos estáveis .
                  Oficina de textos, São Paulo , 144 pp. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Martinelli LA , Nardoto GB , Soltangheisi A , Reis CRG , Abdalla--
                  Filho AL , Camargo PB , Domingues TF , Faria D , Figueira AM , Gomes TF , Lins SRM
                  , Mardegan SF , Mariano E , Miatto RC , Moraes R , Moreira MZ , Oliveira RS ,
                  Ometto JPHB , Santos FLS , Sena-Souza J , Silva DML , Silva JCSS , Vieira SA (
                  2020 ) Determining ecosystem functioning in Brazilian biomes through foliar carbon
                  and nitrogen concentrations and stable isotope ratios . Biogeochemistry 117 ( 43
                  ): 26842–26848 . https://doi.org/10.1007/s10533-020-00714-2 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Martínez-Abraín A ( 2014 ) Is the “n = 30 rule of thumb” of
                  ecological field studies reliable? A call for greater attention to the variability
                  in our data . Animal Biodiversity and Conservation 37 ( 1 ): 95–100 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Martínez del Rio C , Sabat P , Anderson-Sprecher R , Gonzalez SP (
                  2009 a) Dietary and isotopic specialization: the isotopic niche of three Cinclodes
                  ovenbirds . Oecologia 161 : 149– 159 . https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-009-1357-2
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Martínez del Rio C , Wolf N , Carleton SA , Gannes LZ ( 2009 b)
                  Isotopic ecology ten years after a call for more laboratory experiments .
                  Biological Reviews 84 : 91–111 . https://doi. org/10.1111/j.1469-185X.2008.00064.x
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Mason NA , Unitt P , Sparks JP ( 2020 ) Agriculture induces isotopic
                  shifts and niche contraction in Horned Larks ( Eremophila alpestris ) of the
                  Colorado Desert . Journal of Ornithology 162 : 381–393 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s10336-020-01834-0 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> McGill B , Enquist B , Weiher E , Westoby M ( 2006 ) Rebuilding
                  community ecology from functional traits . Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution 21 (
                  4 ): 178–185 . https://doi.org/10.1016/j. tree.2006.02.002 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> McKinnon EA , Kurt Kyser T , Stutchbury BJM ( 2017 ) Does the
                  proportion of arthropods versus fruit in the diet influence overwintering
                  condition of an omnivorous songbird? Journal of Field Ornithology 88 ( 1 ): 65–79
                  . https://doi. org/10.1111/jofo.12187 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> MØller AP , Laursen K , Hobson KA ( 2018 ) Retrospectively analysing
                  condition in historical samples of birds . Journal of Zoology 305 ( 3 ): 188–195 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/jzo.12551 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Moraes MCP , Mello K , Toppa RH ( 2017 ) Protected areas and
                  agricultural expansion: Biodiversity conservation versus economic growth in the
                  Southeast of Brazil . Journal of Environmental Management 188 : 73–84 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2016.11.075 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Nardoto GB , Ribeiro JF , Sena-Souza JP , Guaraldo AC , Saquetti CH
                  ( 2017 ) rastreamento forense: uso dos isótopos estáveis no combate ao crime . In:
                  Costa FJV , Ferreira JM , Monteiro KRG , Mayrink RR (Eds) Ciência contra o
                  tráfico: Avanços no combate ao comércio ilegal de animais silvestres . Imprell
                  Gráfica e Editora, João Pessoa , 51–78 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Navarro AB , Magioli M , Bogoni JA , Silveira LF , Moreira MZ ,
                  Alexandrino ER , Luz DTA , Silva WR , Pizo MA , Oliveira VC , Ferraz KMPMB ( 2021
                  a) Isotopic niches of tropical birds reduced by anthropogenic impacts: a 100-year
                  perspective . Oikos 130 ( 11 ): 1892–1904 . https://doi.org/10.1111/oik.08386
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Navarro AB , Magioli M , Bogoni JA , Moreira MZ , Silveira LF ,
                  Alexandrino ER , Luz DTA , Pizo MA , Silva WR , Oliveira VC , Donatelli RJ ,
                  Christianini AV , Piratelli AJ , Ferraz KMPMB ( 2021 b) Human-modified landscapes
                  narrow the isotopic niche of neotropical birds . Oecologia 196 : 171–184 .
                  https:// doi.org/10.1007/s00442-021-04908-9 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Newsome SD , Martínez del Rio CM , Bearhop S , Phillips DL ( 2007 )
                  A niche for isotopic ecology . Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment 5 ( 8 ):
                  429–436 . https://doi.org/10.1890/060150.01 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Newsome SD , Sabat P , Wolf N , Rader JA , DelRio CM ( 2015 )
                  Multi-tissue δ 2 H analysis reveals altitudinal migration and tissue-specific
                  discrimination patterns in Cinclodes . Ecosphere 6 ( 11 ): 1–18 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Newton J ( 2016 ) Stable Isotopes as Tools in Ecological Research .
                  In: eLS Encyclopedia of Life Sciences . John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester , 1–8 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1002/9780470015902. a0021231.pub2 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Petta JC , Shipley ON , Wintner SP , Cliff G , Dicken ML , Hussey NE
                  ( 2020 ) Are you really what you eat? Stomach content analysis and stable isotope
                  ratios do not uniformly estimate dietary niche characteristics in three marine
                  predators . Oecologia 192 ( 4 ): 1111–1126 . https://doi.org/10.1007/
                  s00442-020-04628-6 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Phillips DL ( 2012 ) Converting isotope values to diet composition:
                  the use of mixing models . Journal of Mammalogy 93 ( 2 ): 342–352 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1644/11-MAMM-S-158.1 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Phillips DL , Gregg JW ( 2003 ) Source partitioning using stable
                  isotopes: coping with too many sources . Oecologia 136 : 261–269 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-003-1218-3 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Phillips DL , Inger R , Bearhop S , Jackson AL , Moore JW , Parnell
                  AC , Semmens BX , Ward EJ ( 2014 ) Best practices for use of stable isotope mixing
                  models in food-web studies . Canadian Journal of Zoology 92 ( 10 ): 823–835 .
                  https://doi. org/10.1139/cjz-2014-0127 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Post DM ( 2002 ) Using stable isotopes to estimate trophic position:
                  Models, methods, and assumptions . Ecology 83 ( 3 ): 703 .
                  https://doi.org/10.2307/3071875 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Quillfeldt P , Bugoni L , McGill RAR , Masello JF , Furness RW (
                  2008 ) Differences in stable isotopes in blood and feathers of seabirds are
                  consistent across species, age and latitude: implications for food web studies .
                  Marine Biology 155 : 593–598 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Revelle R , Suess HE ( 1957 ) Carbon dioxide exchange between
                  atmosphere and ocean and the question of an increase of atmospheric CO 2 during
                  the past decades . Tellus 9 ( 1 ): 18–27 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.2153-3490.1957.tb01849.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ribeiro MC , Metzger JP , Martensen AC , Ponzoni FJ , Hirota MM (
                  2009 ) The Brazilian Atlantic Forest: How much is left, and how is the remaining
                  forest distributed? Implications for conservation . Biological Conservation 142 (
                  6 ): 1141–1153 . https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2009.02.021 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Rocque DA , Winker K ( 2005 ) Use of Bird Collections in Contaminant
                  and Stable-Isotope Studies . Auk 122 ( 3 ): 990–994 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ross JD , Kelly JF , Bridge ES , Engel MH , Reinking DL , Boyle WA (
                  2015 ) Pallid bands in feathers and associated stable isotope signatures reveal
                  effects of severe weather stressors on fledgling sparrows . PeerJ 3 : e 814 .
                  https://doi.org/10.7717/ peerj.814 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Rubenstein DR , Hobson KA ( 2004 ) From birds to butterflies: animal
                  movement patterns and stable isotopes . Trends in Ecology and Evolution 19 ( 5 ):
                  256–63 . https://doi.org/10.1016/j. tree.2004.03.017 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Rutkowska M , Płotka-Wasylka J , Lubinska-Szczygeł M , Różańska A ,
                  Możejko-Ciesielska J , Namieśnik J ( 2018 ) Birds’ feathers – Suitable samples for
                  determination of environmental pollutants . Trends in Analytical Chemistry 109 :
                  97–115 . https://doi.org/10.1016/j.trac.2018.09.022 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sales LP , Galetti M , Pires MM ( 2020 ) Climate and land-use change
                  will lead to a faunal “savannization” on tropical rainforests . Global Change
                  Biology 26 ( 12 ): 7036–7044 . https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.15374 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sena-Souza JP , Costa FJV , Nardoto GB ( 2019 ) Background and the
                  use of isoscapes in the Brazilian context: essential tool for isotope data
                  interpretation and natural resource management . Ambiente e Agua – An
                  Interdisciplinary Journal of Applied Science 14 ( 2 ): 1 .
                  https://doi.org/10.4136/ambi-agua.2282 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Silvério DV , Brando PM , Balch JK , Putz FE , Nepstad DC ,
                  Oliveira-Santos C , Bustamante MMC ( 2013 ) Testing the Amazon savannization
                  hypothesis: fire effects on invasion of a neotropical forest by native cerrado and
                  exotic pasture grasses . Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B:
                  Biological Sciences 368 : 20120427 . https://doi.org/10.1098/ rstb.2012.0427
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Siqueira PR , Vasconcelos MF , Gonçalves RMM , Leite LO ( 2015 )
                  Assessment of stomach contents of some amazonian birds . Ornitología Neotropical
                  26 : 79–88 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Smith TB , Marra PP , Webster MS , Lovette I , Gibbs HL , Holmes RT
                  , Hobson KA , Rohwer S ( 2003 ) A call for feather sampling . Auk 120 ( 1 ):
                  218–221 . https://doi.org/10.2307/4090162 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Somenzari M , Amaral PP , Cueto VR , Guaraldo ADC , Jahn AE , Lima
                  DM , Lima PC , Lugarini C , Machado CG , Martinez J , Nascimento JLX , Pacheco JF
                  , Paludo D , Prestes NP , Serafini PP , Silveira LF , Sousa AEBA , Sousa NA ,
                  Souza MA , Telino-Júnior WR , Whitney BM ( 2018 ) An overview of migratory birds
                  in Brazil . Papéis Avulsos de Zoologia 58 : 3 .
                  https://doi.org/10.11606/1807-0205/2018.58.03 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sousa AEBA , Pereira PS ( 2020 ) Manual de anilhamento de aves
                  silvestres . ICMBio-CEMAVE, Brasília, Brazil , 113 pp. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Stock BC , Jackson AL , Ward EJ , Parnell AC , Phillips DL , Semmens
                  BX ( 2018 ) Analyzing mixing systems using a new generation of Bayesian tracer
                  mixing models . PeerJ 6 : e 5096 . https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.5096
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Symes CT ( 2012 ) Stable Isotope Research in Southern African Birds
                  . In: Ali M (Ed.) Diversity of Ecosystems . IntechOpen, London , 251–288 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Tawa K , Sagawa S ( 2021 ) Stable isotopic analysis of stuffed
                  specimens revealed the feeding habits of Oriental Storks Ciconia boyciana in Japan
                  before their extinction in the wild . Journal of Ornithology 162 : 193–206 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/ s10336-020-01806-4 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Vander Zanden MJ , Clayton MK , Moody EK , Solomon CT , Weidel BC (
                  2015 ) Stable isotope turnover and half-life in animal tissues: a literature
                  synthesis . PLoS One 10 ( 1 ): e 0116182 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0116182 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Villegas M , Newsome SD , Blake JG ( 2016 ) Seasonal patterns in δ 2
                  H values of multiple tissues from Andean birds provide insights into elevational
                  migration . Ecological Applications 26 ( 8 ): 2383–2389 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Vitória AP , Ávila-Lovera E , Oliveira Vieira T , Couto-Santos APL ,
                  Pereira TJ , Funch LS , Freitas L , Miranda LDAP , Rodrigues PJFP , Rezende CE ,
                  Santiago LS ( 2018 ) Isotopic composition of leaf carbon (δ 13 C) and nitrogen (δ
                  15 N) of deciduous and evergreen understorey trees in two tropical Brazilian
                  Atlantic forests . Journal of Tropical Ecology 34 ( 2 ): 145–156 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1017/S0266467418000093 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Whiteman J , Elliott Smith E , Besser A , Newsome S ( 2019 ) A Guide
                  to Using Compound-Specific Stable Isotope Analysis to Study the Fates of Molecules
                  in Organisms and Ecosystems . Diversity 11 ( 1 ): 8 .
                  https://doi.org/10.3390/d11010008 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wiley AE , James HF , Ostrom PH ( 2017 ) Emerging techniques for
                  isotope studies of avian ecology . In: Webster MS (Ed.) The Extended specimen:
                  emerging frontiers in collections-based ornithological research . CRC Press, Boca
                  Raton , 89–109 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Winker K ( 2005 ) Bird Collections: Development and use of a
                  scientific resource . Auk 122 ( 3 ): 966–971 . https://doi.
                  org/10.1093/auk/122.3.966 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Yohannes E , Palinauskas V , Valkiūnas G , Lee RW , Bolshakov CV ,
                  Bensch S ( 2011 ) Does avian malaria infection affect feather stable isotope
                  signatures? Oecologia 167 ( 4 ): 937–942 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s00442-011-2041-x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Author Contributions </title>
         <p>ABN and LFS conceived the ideas; ABN led the writing of the manuscript; MM, MZM and LFS
            contributed critically to the drafts and gave final approval for publication.</p>
         <p> Competing Interests </p>
         <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
         <p> How to cite this article </p>
         <p> Navarro AB, Magioli M, Moreira MZ, Silveira LF (2022) Perspectives and challenges on
            isotopic ecology of terrestrial birds in Brazil . Zoologia (Curitiba) 39: e21023.
            https://doi.org/10.1590/ S1984-4689.v39.e21023 </p>
         <p> Published by </p>
         <p>Sociedade Brasileira de Zoologia at Scientific Electronic Library</p>
         <p>Online (https://www.scielo.br/zool)</p>
         <p>Copyright</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
