<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Acta Ichthyologica et Piscatoria</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/aiep.51.74082</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Age and growth estimates from three hard parts of the spotted catfish,
               Arius maculatus (Actinopterygii: Siluriformes: Ariidae), in Songkhla Lake, Thailand’s
               largest natural lake</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>29</day>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ariidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Lutjanus coeruleolineatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Actinopterygii</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Perciformes</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Lutjanidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Carcharhinus leucas </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Doryichthys boaja </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Syngnathidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Tetrapturus albidus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Thunnus obesus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Teleostei</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Scombridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ariidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Siluriformes</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Clarias gariepinus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Siluriformes</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ariidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Clupeichthys aesarnensis </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Urogymnus polylepis </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Carcharhinus limbatus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="﻿introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Introduction </p>
         <p> The family <tp:taxon-name>Ariidae</tp:taxon-name> accommodates more than 140 species of
            catfishes, found mainly in marine and brackish waters ( ). However, some species are
            euryhaline and can live in a wide range of environments, from freshwater to marine,
            including the spotted catfish, <tp:taxon-name> Arius maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            (Thunberg, 1792), which is widely distributed across the Indo-West Pacific Region ( ).
            This species has been reported to grow as large as 80 cm TL, but the typical maximum
            size is 30 cm TL ( ). The trophic level of <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            is estimated to be 3.4 +/- 0.46, indicating carnivorous behavior. This fish feeds mainly
            on benthic invertebrates ( ), and plays an important role in the ecosystem; an imbalance
            in its abundance can trigger a trophic cascade ( ). This fish is targeted for harvest in
            many countries, where the fisheries operations are mostly in either marine or brackish
            water environments ( ; ; ; ). There is also a unique inland fishery for this species in
            Songkhla Lake, the largest natural lake in Thailand. The catch of <tp:taxon-name> A.
               maculatus </tp:taxon-name> was over 180 metric tons in 2011, following the
            restoration of the lake's fishery resources by declaring fish sanctuary zones and a
            stocking program for some indigenous species ( ). The recent catch of this species in
            2020 increased tremendously to 330 metric tons (Pattalung Inland Fisheries Research and
            Development Center, unpublished data), which was almost 1.5-fold higher than the
            previous record. This sharp rise in harvest implies that appropriate fisheries
            management of this resource is urgently required to prevent a collapse of this spotted
            catfish stock. </p>
         <p> Effective fisheries management requires an understanding of the stock status and
            population dynamics of the targeted fish species, where the growth parameters (i.e.,
            asymptotic length and curvature parameter) are among the crucial inputs ( ; ). Accurate
            estimates of growth parameters are important for monitoring the stock status as well as
            for assessing management actions that have been applied to maintain the integrity of the
            fish stock ( ). To estimate growth, precise and accurate age data are required. Age can
            be estimated by several methods but counting natural growth rings of hard body parts is
            the most common and is generally reliable ( ). Many calcified structures, both inner
            parts (e.g., otoliths, vertebrae, and urohyal bone) as well as outer parts (e.g.,
            scales, opercular bones, spines, and fin rays) have been shown to reliably reflect the
            age of fishes ( ; ; ). As many hard parts are available for age determination, a
            comparison of multiple structures to determine the most suitable ones for a particular
            species or population is always recommended ( ). mentioned that selecting the most
            suitable hard part for aging is one of the problems in age and growth studies of fishes.
            They suggested comparing different bony structures of the targeted fish to obtain the
            most suitable one that has high precision and low aging error before further growth
            analysis. Moreover, if there is no significant difference in age reading between the
            inner and outer parts, the use of outer parts is recommended, since the fish does not
            need to be sacrificed; this is particularly desirable for long-lived species ( ). </p>
         <p> Along with selecting suitable hard parts for aging, the most suitable model must be
            chosen for the length-at-age key, which can be determined by the shape of the growth
            curve and error component of the data ( ). Numerous growth curves, as well as their
            representative models, have been introduced and applied to explain fish growth. Growth
            models relate the age of fish in a population to their length or weight; the von
            Bertalanffy growth model is the most commonly adopted and widely used ( ; ; ). The von
            Bertalanffy model is commonly used because of the shape of the desired growth curve and
            from biological assumptions, one of which is that fish growth slows with age ( ). Other
            commonly used models include the Gompertz and logistic growth models ( ; ). Both models
            are well suited to fishes, which exhibit low initial growth rates, but the regions above
            and below the inflection are asymmetrical in the Gompertz model, and symmetrical in the
            logistic models ( ). The base assumption of all three of these models is that fish show
            asymptotic growth ( ). </p>
         <p> The aim of this study was to provide length-at-age data and a growth model for the
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> stock in Songkhla Lake, Thailand. We
            assess the suitability of hard parts for aging and evaluate three growth models to
            describe the relation between age and length, which can be used as a reference for other
               <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> stocks. The results are also expected
            to be further used for stock assessment and fisheries management of the stock in
            Songkhla Lake for its sustainable exploitation. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Materials and methods</p>
         <p> Study area and fish sampling. Songkhla Lake (Fig. 1 ) is a shallow coastal lagoon in
            southern Thailand ( 07°24′08″N , 100°15′42″E ), with the mean depth of 2 m. The water
            body covers 1018 km2 and is classified into three distinct zones: upper (459 km2),
            middle (377 km2), and lower (182 km2). This lake hosts a high diversity of fishes (ca.
            450 species), due in part to its range of physiological characteristics. For example,
            the upper zone is a freshwater environment, while the lower zone is brackish (maximum
            15‰) at the mouth, where it enters the Gulf of Thailand ( ). Meanwhile, the salinity in
            the middle zone fluctuates between 10‰ and 15‰ as it is a mixing zone between fresh and
            saline water ( ). Samples of <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> were
            collected from four landing sites (Fig. 1 ) in the upper and middle zones of Songkhla
            Lake (where the fishery is intensive) between January and December 2020. Individual fish
            were labeled, measured for standard length (SL), fork length (FL) total length (TL) to
            the nearest 0.1 cm, and weighed to the nearest 0.01 g in situ . Samples were then packed
            in ice and taken to the Pattalung Inland Fisheries Research and Development Center.
            Additionally, 15 <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> representing various size
            classes were collected every three months for annual ring validation. </p>
         <p> At the fisheries center, the largest pair of otoliths (i.e., lapilli) were removed,
            washed, and kept dry in a vial. Dorsal- and pectoral-fin spines were cut with
            bone-cutting forceps. Each hard part was embedded in resin and cut by a low-speed
            diamond saw (South Bay Technology Inc., model: 650). Bony parts were then polished by
            sandpaper (grit size ranging from 600 to 1500) until the core was seen. Each polished
            sample was photographed under 40 x magnification, and annual rings were counted visually
            from the monitor and using the Image-J program. An annual ring was considered as the
            boundary between the inner edge of a wide opaque zone (i.e., corresponding to high
            growth rate) and the outer edge of a narrow translucent zone (i.e., corresponding to low
            growth rate) ( ). Three (3) readers, with no background information of the size of each
            individual fish, were assigned for aging each sample. </p>
         <p> Data analysis. Length-length relations and length (TL)-weight relation (LWR) were
            examined by linear and curvilinear regressions. The estimated parameter " b " from LWR
            was tested for significant deviation from 3 by using a t -test. Annual ring formation
            was validated by marginal increment ratio (MIR) analysis ( ) as </p>
         <p>MIR = R - R n R n - R n - 1</p>
         <p> where R is the radius (distance between the center and the edge of hard part), Rn is
            the distance from center to outer edge of last complete band, and Rn - 1 is the distance
            from center to outer edge of next-to-last complete band. The difference in MIR among
            months of sampling was tested by Kruskal-Wallis test, and Dunn's post test was applied
            when a significant difference was found at α = 0.05. </p>
         <p> The percentage of agreement (PA) among the three readers was calculated as the ratio of
            the number of agreements among the three readings to the total number of readings made.
            Precision in age reading among the three readers of each hard part was tested by two
            methods ( ): mean percentage error (MPE)1 and coefficient of variation (CV). </p>
         <p>MPE = ∑ j = 1 n MPE j n</p>
         <p>where</p>
         <p> MPE j = 100 x ∑ i = 1 R x i j - x ¯ j x ¯ j R </p>
         <p> where MPE j is the mean percentage error for the j th fish, xij is the i th age
            estimate of the j th fish, x̅j is the mean age estimate for the j th fish, R is the
            number of times that each fish was aged, and n is the number of samples. </p>
         <p> CV=∑j=1nCVjn where CVj=100 x ∑i=1Rxij-x¯j2R-1x¯j </p>
         <p> where CV j is the coefficient of variation for the j th fish. The age readings of each
            fish sample and each hard part from the three readers were then averaged and rounded to
            the nearest integer. Two additional readers with extensive experience in fish aging
            reviewed each hard part and checked its designated age. The age-bias plot ( ) was
            applied to visually assess potential aging differences among hard parts. Finally, three
            common growth models ( ), i.e., von Bertalanffy model ( ), Gompertz model ( ), and
            Logistic model ( ) were fitted to the observed length-at-age data: </p>
         <p> Lt = L∞ (1 - e - k ( t - t 0)) </p>
         <p>von Bertalanffy model</p>
         <p>L t = L ∞ e - e - k t - t 0</p>
         <p>Gompertz model</p>
         <p> Lt = L∞ (1 + e - k ( t - t 0))-1 </p>
         <p>Logistic model</p>
         <p> where Lt is the predicted length-at-age t , L∞ is the asymptotic length, k is a
            relative growth rate parameter, and t 0 is the age when length is theoretically zero.
            The growth models were fitted to length-at-age data using nonlinear least-squares. The
            residual sum of squares (RSS) was used to measure the discrepancy between the data and
            an estimation model. The growth performance index ( O′ , ) of each growth model was
            estimated by </p>
         <p> O′ = log( k ) + 2log( L∞ ) </p>
         <p> The obtained L∞ [cm] and k values were further used to estimate the natural mortality
            coefficient ( M ) by using Pauly's equation ( ) </p>
         <p> log10 M = -0.0066 - 0.279log10 L∞ + 0.6543log10 k + 0.4635log10 T </p>
         <p> where T is the annual mean water temperature, which was set at 30°C (International Lake
            Environment Committee Foundation 2021). Data analysis was conducted by using
            R-statistics ( ) under Package FSA ( ) and "fishmethods" ( ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿results">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Results</p>
         <p> A size distribution of the 213 <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> samples
            used in this study is presented in Fig. 2 , with a range between 35 and 238 mm TL (mean
            +/- SD 128 +/- 43 mm TL). Body weights ranged between 0.4 and 154.1 g, with mean +/- SD
            of 26.4 +/- 23.7 g. The length-length relations showed high correlation between
            measurements ( R 2&gt; 0.95; Fig. 3A-B ); meanwhile, the log-transformed LWR revealed
            positive allometric growth, i.e., parameter " b " of WLR was significantly higher than
            3.0 ( P &lt;0.01; Fig. 3C ). </p>
         <p> The 60 <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> samples for the MIR study ranged
            between 35 and 238 mm TL, with the mean +/- SD of 128 +/- 43 mm TL. The MIR results
            showed clear increasing trends from January (MIR near 0.5) to October (MIR near 1.0) in
            all three hard parts, and a significant difference was found between January and the
            other sampling months ( P &lt;0.05; Fig. 4 ). The highest MIR was found in October for
            all hard parts and was almost double the MIR in January. The largest difference in MIR
            values between these two months was observed in otoliths. The significantly lower MIR in
            January implies that an annulus is deposited once a year. </p>
         <p> Age estimates from the three hard parts ranged from less than 1 to a maximum of 6 years
            (Fig. 5 ). The percentage of agreement among the three readers was highest for otoliths
            (58.2%), resulting in the lowest MPE (9.5%) and CV (12.6%). Meanwhile, the pectoral-fin
            spine samples showed a higher percentage of agreement (and hence lower MPE and CV) than
            dorsal-fin spine samples (Table 1 ). The designated age of each hard part (i.e., by
            three readers in the first round) was checked by two highly experienced readers with a
            perfect agreement and thus was considered the observed age of each individual fish
            (Table 2 ). Biases of age reading from otoliths and spines were obvious at ages beyond 3
            years, as the observed age from otoliths was a bit higher than the observed age from
            spines; meanwhile, less bias was found between the two spines (Fig. 6 ). </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> MPE = mean percentage error, CV = coefficient of variation. </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> Note : Numbers in each cell are the observed ages from otolith, dorsal- and
            pectoral-fin spines, respectively. </p>
         <p> Parameter estimation in all models using the observed length-at-age data from the three
            hard parts is displayed in Table 3 . It is clear that the asymptotic length ( L∞ )
            estimated from the von Bertalanffy model (around 290 mm TL) was higher than from the
            other two models, for all hard parts. The larger L∞ from the von Bertalanffy model was
            compensated by low k values, which consequently made O′ values for the three models
            relatively similar. The estimated natural mortality coefficient fluctuated between 0.573
            and 1.631 year-1, due to the estimated L∞ and k values. In each growth model, the lowest
            sum of squares was obtained from the length-at-age data from otoliths. Therefore, this
            hard part was used to explain the growth of <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus
            </tp:taxon-name> in Songkhla Lake as </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> L∞ = the asymptotic total length, k = relative growth rate parameter, t 0 = age when
            length is theoretically zero, RSS = residual sum of squares, O′ = phi prime value, M =
            natural mortality coefficient. </p>
         <p> Lt = 290.87(1 - e -0.166( t + 1.51)) </p>
         <p>von Bertalanffy model</p>
         <p>L t = 229. 82 e - e - 0. 383 (t - 0. 598)</p>
         <p>Gompertz model</p>
         <p> Lt = 209.85(1 + e -0.604( t - 1.274))-1 </p>
         <p>Logistic model</p>
         <p> By applying the growth curves of the three models (Fig. 7 ), the estimated lengths at
            age 1 to 5 years were almost identical, whereas the estimated sizes from the von
            Bertalanffy model were larger at age 6 years old and above relative to the other models.
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿discussion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Discussion</p>
         <p> The age-length key and growth estimation of fishes and shellfishes can provide valuable
            insight into their life history and be further used to prescribe optimum fishing
            regulations for sustaining their fisheries ( ). In this study, the age-length key and
            growth of <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> were assessed for the population
            in Songkhla Lake, Thailand. All the samples were from the upper or middle zones of the
            lake, implying that they can develop a stock in a low-salinity or freshwater habitat,
            contrary to the suggestion by that this fish avoids the freshwater environment in the
            Mekong Delta. </p>
         <p> The maximum length of <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> in this study was
            23.8 cm TL, which is similar to the maximum size from the Mekong Delta (25 cm TL; ).
            Tran et al. (2021) reported that, in the Lower Mekong Basin, this fish can grow as large
            as 40 cm TL. The size (around 25 cm TL) found in fresh- and brackish-water habitats is
            substantially lower than in stocks from marine environments, such as 29 cm TL off the
            coast of Malaysia ( ) and 35 cm TL in Taiwan waters ( ). Length-length relations showed
            high linearity with high correlation. The " b " coefficients (i.e., slope of the
            regression line) of SL-TL (1.15) and FL-TL (1.13) relations were similar to the values
            obtained for the stock off the coast of Taiwan for SL-TL (1.18) and FL-TL (1.06) ( ).
            Meanwhile, the coefficient " b " for SL-TL relation of the <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus
            </tp:taxon-name> stock from Peninsular Malaysia was 1.17 ( ). The similar values of " b
            " from various stocks indicate the similar body proportions of this fish, regardless of
            whether they are freshwater, brackish-water, or marine residents. The " b " coefficients
            of LWRs from this study were significantly higher than 3, indicating positive allometry
            (i.e., fish become heavier as length increases), and reflecting optimum conditions for
            growth ( ) as well as the suitability of habitat conditions ( ). Interestingly, the " b
            " coefficients of LWRs from the marine stocks were lower than 3 (between 2.6 and 2.9) (
            ; ), which could be explained either by climatic variation or resource competition ( ). </p>
         <p> Age validation through MIR analysis provides relative certainty of annulus formation
            and confirms the growth zone deposition in <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            . Low MIR was found in the early part of the year (January, winter) when the water
            temperature in the inner zone is normally less than 27°C; it is around 30°C during the
            rest of the year ( ). The maximum age (6 years) of <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus
            </tp:taxon-name> found in this study is within the applicable range for age validation.
            MIR is not suitable for long-lived species or older individuals (i.e., more than 10
            years) ( ). A higher percentage of agreement in aging from otoliths than with other hard
            parts has also been reported by other researchers ( ; ). The percentage of agreement was
            50%-60% in this study. Other studies that employed only two readers achieved rates of
            over 60% (e.g., ; ). Although the percentage of agreement was lower in this study,
            verification among the three readers through MPE and CV was still lower than the upper
            limit of 20% ( ; ). More age bias was observed between otoliths and spines (both types)
            than between dorsal- and pectoral-fin spines. In older fish (i.e., beyond 3 years), the
            higher ages estimated from otoliths could be because the spine nucleus of many fish
            species is reabsorbed and replaced by a hole (i.e., vascularization), which eliminates
            or obscures the first annulus, causing underestimation of age from spines ( ; ). For
            this reason, together with the greater consistency in aging among the three readers,
            otoliths were selected for growth estimation, similar to several other studies (e.g., ;
            ; ; ) that compare ages from various hard parts. </p>
         <p> The growth models based on the age-length key from otolith reading revealed a lower
            residual sum of squares than for spines, which confirms the suitability of this hard
            part for <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> aging. Higher L∞ and lower k
            values from the von Bertalanffy model than from other growth models have been reported
            in many studies (e.g., ; ; ; ). The obtained O′ values from all three growth models were
            within the range of values from stocks of <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name>
            elsewhere (2.08 &lt; O′ &lt;3.14), which were estimated either by otoliths or
            length-frequency data ( ). A suitable growth model should not only be selected by
            mathematical measures ( ; ), but also biological as well as management points of view (
            ; ). In a mathematical sense, the von Bertalanffy model was generally considered the
            most reliable candidate model for fish stocks (e.g., ; ; ). From a management viewpoint,
            lower L ∞ and the higher k values of <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> in
            Songkhla Lake from the Gompertz and Logistic models would result in an overestimated
            natural mortality coefficient, which would have drastic implications for fisheries
            management ( ). For example, it could lead managers to increase fishing effort due to
            the high estimated natural mortality. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="﻿conclusion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Conclusion</p>
         <p> The age-length relation and growth of <tp:taxon-name> A. maculatus </tp:taxon-name> in
            Songkhla Lake, Thailand, were examined by using hard parts. Different aging structures
            and growth models were compared for biases in the results. Results showed that otoliths
            provided more precise age estimation among three readers. The von Bertalanffy model was
            judged to be the most suitable candidate for growth estimation because of the lowest
            residual sum of squares. The obtained growth parameters (i.e., L ∞ and k ) can be used
            as inputs in other fish stock assessment models (e.g., the yield per recruit model) to
            investigate the optimum fishing level for this stock, which currently experiences high
            fishing pressure. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgment</p>
         <p> The first author is grateful for financial support towards his master's degree study
            from the Agricultural Research Development Agency (ARDA) Grant HRD6405081. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Almamari, D , Rabia, S , Park, JM , Jawad, LA , 2021 . Age, growth,
                  mortality, and exploitation rate of blueline snapper, Lutjanus coeruleolineatus (
                  Actinopterygii : Perciformes : Lutjanidae ), from Dhofar Governorate, Sultanate of
                  Oman. Acta Ichthyologica et Piscatoria 51 ( 2 ): 159 - 166 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.3897/aiep.51.63572 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Angsupanich, S , Somsak, S , Phrommoon, J , 2005 . Stomach contents
                  of the catfishes Osteogeneiosus militaris (Linnaeus, 1758) and Arius maculatus
                  (Thunberg, 1792) in the Songkhla Lake. Songklanakarin Journal of Science and
                  Technology 27(Suppl. 1): 391-402. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Anonymous , 2021 . World lake database. International Lake
                  Environment Committee Foundation. [version 01/2021] https://wldb.ilec.or.jp
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Arshad, A , Jimmy, A , Nurulamin, SM , Japarsidik, B , Harah, ZM ,
                  2008 . Length-weight and length-length relationships of five fish species
                  collected from seagrass beds of the Sungai Pulai estuary, Peninsular Malaysia.
                  Journal of Applied Ichthyology 24 ( 3 ): 328 - 329 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1439-0426.2007.01026.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Beamish, RJ , McFarlane, GA , 1983 . The forgotten requirement for
                  age validation in fisheries biology. Transactions of the American Fisheries
                  Society 112 ( 6 ): 735 - 743 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1577/1548-8659(1983)112%3C735:TFRFAV%3E2.0.CO;2
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Campana, SE , 2001 . Accuracy, precision and quality control in age
                  determination, including a review of the use and abuse of age validation methods.
                  Journal of Fish Biology 59 ( 2 ): 197 - 242 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1095-8649.2001.tb00127.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Campana, SE , Annand, MC , McMillan, JI , 1995 . Graphical and
                  statistical methods for determining the consistency of age determinations.
                  Transactions of the American Fisheries Society 124 ( 1 ): 131 - 138 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1577/1548-8659(1995)124%3C0131:GASMFD%3E2.3.CO;2
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Chu, WS , Hou, YY , Ueng, YT , Wang, JP , 2012 . Correlation between
                  the length and weight of Arius maculatus off the southwestern coast of Taiwan.
                  Brazilian Archives of Biology and Technology 55 ( 5 ): 705 - 708 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1590/S1516-89132012000500009 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Cruz-Martinez , A , Chiappa-Carrara, X , Arenus-Fuentes, V , 2004 .
                  Age and growth of the bull shark, Carcharhinus leucas , from southern Gulf of
                  Mexico. Journal of Northwest Atlantic Fishery Science 37 : 367 - 374 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.2960/J.v35.m481 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Damchoo, S , Grudpan, C , Jutagate, A , Grudpan, J , Jutagate, T ,
                  2021 . Morphological investigation and length-weight relationships of long-snouted
                  pipefish Doryichthys boaja ( Syngnathidae ) from two different environments.
                  Agriculture and Natural Resources (Bangkok) 55 : 664 - 673 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.34044/j.anres.2021.55.4.17 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Dieb-Magalhaes , L , Florentino, AC , Soares, MGM , 2015 .
                  Length-weight relationships and length at first maturity for nine fish species of
                  floodplain lakes in Central Amazon (Amazon basin, Brazil). Journal of Applied
                  Ichthyology 31 ( 6 ): 1182 - 1184 , DOI: https://doi.org/10.1111/jai.12919
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Drew, K , Die, DJ , Arocha, F , 2006 . Understanding vascularization
                  in fin spines of white marlin ( Tetrapturus albidus ). Bulletin of Marine Science
                  79 ( 3 ): 847 - 852 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Duarte-Neto, P , Higa, FM , Lessa, RP , 2012 . Age and growth
                  estimation of bigeye tuna, Thunnus obesus ( Teleostei : Scombridae ) in the
                  southwestern Atlantic. Neotropical Ichthyology 10 ( 1 ): 149 - 158 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1590/S1679-62252012000100014 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Froese, R , 2006 . Cube law, condition factor and weight-length
                  relationships: History, meta-analysis and recommendations. Journal of Ichthyology
                  22 ( 4 ): 241 - 253 , DOI: https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1439-0426.2006.00805.x
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Froese, R , Pauly, D , 2021 . FishBase. World Wide Web electronic
                  publication. www.fishbase.org </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Gebremedhin, S , Bruneel, S , Getahun, A , Anteneh, W , Goethals, P
                  , 2021 . Scientific methods to understand fish population dynamics and support
                  sustainable fisheries management. Water 13 ( 4 ) : 574 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.3390/w13040574 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Gompertz, B , 1825 . On the nature of the function expressive of the
                  law of human mortality, and on a new mode of determining the value of life
                  contingencies. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London 115 : 513
                  - 583 , DOI: https://doi.org/10.1098/rstl.1825.0026 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Haddon, M , 2011 . Modeling and quantitative methods in fisheries.
                  2nd edn. Champman and Hall/CRC, Boca Raton, FL, USA </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Isley, JJ , Grabowski, TB , 2007 . Age and growth. Pp. 187-228. In:
                  Guy CS, Brown ML (Eds) Analysis and interpretation of freshwater fisheries data.
                  American Fisheries Society, Bethesda, MD, USA. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Jones, CM , 2000 . Fitting growth curves to retrospective
                  size-at-age data. Fisheries Research 46 ( 1-3 ): 123 - 129 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1016/S0165-7836(00)00139-9 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Jumawan, CQ , Metillo, EB , Mutia, MT , 2020 . Stock assessment of
                  Arius maculatus (Thurnberg [sic], 1792) ( Ariidae , Siluriformes ) in Panguil Bay,
                  northwestern Mindanao. The Philippine Journal of Fisheries 27 ( 1 ): 40 - 53 ,
                  DOI: https://doi.org/10.31398/tpjf/27.1.2019A0013 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Katsanevakis, S , 2006 . Modelling fish growth: Model selection,
                  multi-model inference and model selection uncertainty. Fisheries Research 81 ( 2-3
                  ): 229 - 235 , DOI: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fishres.2006.07.002
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Katsanevakis, S , Maravelias, CD , 2008 . Modelling fish growth:
                  Multi-model inference as a better alternative to a priori using von Bertalanffy
                  equation. Fish and Fisheries 9 ( 2 ): 178 - 187 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-2979.2008.00279.x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Khan, S , Khan, MA , Miyan, K , 2011 . Comparison of age estimates
                  from otoliths, vertebrae, and pectoral-fin spines in African sharptooth catfish,
                  Clarias gariepinus (Burchell). Estonian Journal of Ecology 60 ( 3 ): 183 - 193 ,
                  DOI: https://doi.org/10.3176/eco.2011.3.02 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kutsyn, DN , Ablyazov, ER , Truong, BH , Cu, ND , 2021 . The
                  size-age structure, growth, and maturation of the spotted catfish Arius maculatus
                  (Thunberg, 1792) ( Siluriformes : Ariidae ) from the Mekong Delta, Vietnam.
                  Russian Journal of Marine Biology 47 ( 1 ): 56 - 63 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1134/S1063074021010053 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Morioka, S , Vongvichith, B , Marui, J , Okutsu, T , Phomikong, P ,
                  Avakul, P , Jutagate, T , 2019 . Characteristics of two populations of Thai River
                  sprat Clupeichthys aesarnensis from man-made reservoirs in Thailand and Laos, with
                  aspects of gonad development. Fisheries Science 85 ( 4 ): 667 - 675 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s12562-019-01319-x </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Nelson, GA , 2021 . fishmethods: Fishery science methods and models.
                  R package version 1.11-2. [version 07/2021]
                  https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=fishmethods </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ogle, DH , Doll, JC , Wheeler, P , Dinno, A , 2021 . FSA: Fisheries
                  stock analysis. R package version 0.9.1. [version 07/2021]
                  https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=FSA </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Pauly, D , 1980 . On the interrelationships between natural
                  mortality, growth parameters, and mean environmental temperature in 175 fish
                  stocks. ICES Journal of Marine Science 39 ( 2 ): 175 - 192 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1093/icesjms/39.2.175 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Pauly, D , Munro, JL , 1984 . Once more on the comparison of growth
                  in fish and invertebrates. ICLARM Fishbyte (2): 21. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Phomikong, P , Seehirunwong, S , Jutagate, T , 2019 . A preliminary
                  estimate of age and growth of two populations of dasyatid stingray Urogymnus
                  polylepis in Thailand. Journal of Fisheries and Environment 43 ( 3 ): 43 - 54
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Quist, MC , Pegg, MA , Devries, DR , 2012 . Age and growth. Pp.
                  677-731. In: Zale AV, Parrish DL, Sutton TM (Eds) Fisheries techniques. American
                  Fisheries Society, Bethesda, MD, USA. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> R Core Team , 2020 . R: A language and environment for statistical
                  computing. [version 01/2020] http://www.r-project.org/index.html </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Rainboth, WJ , 1996 . Fishes of the Cambodian Mekong: FAO Species
                  Identification Field Guide for Fishery Purposes. FAO, Rome </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ricker, WE , 1975 . Computation and interpretation of biological
                  statistics of fish populations. Bulletin of the Fisheries Research Board of Canada
                  191 : 1 - 382 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Tanasomwang, V , Assava-aree, A , 2013 . [Fishery status and total
                  catch in year 2011 and 2012 after restoration of fishery resources in Songkhla
                  Lake. ] Department of Fisheries, Bangkok </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Tran, DD , Shibukawa, K , Nguyen, PT , Ha, HP , Tran, LX , Mai, HV ,
                  Utsugi, K , 2013 . Mo tả đ ịnh Loại Ca . Đ ồng Bằng Song Cửu Long, Việt Nam.
                  Fishes of the Mekong Delta, Vietnam. Can Tho University Publishing House, Can Tho,
                  Vietnam </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Vitale, F , Clausen, LW , Chonchuir , GN , 2019 . Handbook of fish
                  age estimation protocols and validation methods. International Council for the
                  Exploration of the Sea, Copenhagen </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> von Bertalanffy, L , 1938 . A quantitative theory of organic growth
                  (Inquires on growth law II). Human Biology 10 ( 2 ): 181 - 213 ,
                  https://www.jstor.org/stable/41447359 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Winter, SP , Cliff, G , 1996 . Age and growth determination of the
                  blacktip shark, Carcharhinus limbatus , from the east coast of South Africa. Fish
                  Bulletin 94 : 135 - 144 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhang, K , Zhang, J , Li, J , Liao, B , 2020 . Model selection for
                  fish growth patterns based on a Bayesian approach: A case study of five freshwater
                  fish species. Aquatic Living Resources 17(33). https://doi.org/10.1051/alr/2020019
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhu, L , Li, L , Liang, Z , 2009 . Comparison of six statistical
                  approaches in the selection of appropriate fish growth models. Chinese Journal of
                  Oceanology and Limnology 27 ( 3 ): 457 - 467 , DOI:
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s00343-009-9236-6 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhu, X , Wastle, R , Leonard, D , Howland, K , Carmichael, TJ ,
                  Tallman, RF , 2017 . Comparison of scales, pectoral-fin fin rays, and otoliths for
                  estimating age, growth, and mortality of lake whitefish, Coregonus clupeaformis,
                  in Great Slave Lake. Canadian Science Advisory Secretariat, Ottawa, ON, Canada
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>It was originally (Campana 2001) "average percent error (APE)".</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
