<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Herpetozoa</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/herpetozoa.32.e35662</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Broad seasonal changes in thermoregulation of Podarcislilfordi (Squamata,
               Lacertidae) at Binicodrell islet (Menorca, Spain)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi brauni</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi brauni</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>E.</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi brauni</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Iberolacerta galani</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi brauni</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi brauni</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis melisellensis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Phrynosoma hernandesi</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trini</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Introduction </p>
         <p> As ectotherms, lizards' performance and fitness depend on their body temperatures ( ).
            Lizards often maintain their body temperatures within a relatively narrow range using
            behavioural thermoregulation, which involves various mechanisms, e.g. adjusting activity
            periods, changing body posture to maximise heat gain or loss or moving between hot and
            cool microhabitats ( ; ; ; ). The extent of behavioural thermoregulation depends on its
            costs and benefits ( ; ). Costs of thermoregulation mainly entail wasted energy and
            time, predation risk and losing opportunities for other activities. Meanwhile, benefits
            are clear: maximising physiological performance and, accordingly, individual fitness.
            The balance between these costs and benefits will determine the extent to which a lizard
            thermoregulates in a given habitat ( ; ). </p>
         <p> Energetic costs of thermoregulation increase as environmental temperatures depart from
            the thermal optima for the lizard's physiological functions ( ; ). Accordingly,
            spatio-temporal variation in biotic and abiotic environmental factors influences the
            degree of lizard thermoregulation. In temperate lizards, their microhabitat selection
            and thermoregulatory effectiveness is greatly influenced by the seasonal variation in
            environmental conditions ( ; ; ). For example, Mediterranean lacertids usually
            thermoregulate more effectively in the summer, when environmental temperatures are
            higher, than in the spring ( ). </p>
         <p> This is also the case in the Balearic lizard, <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis
               lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> . A previous study, examining the seasonal shift in thermal
            ecology of two populations, showed different seasonal effects on thermoregulation ( ).
            The magnitude of seasonal changes in thermoregulatory effort was higher in the
            population from the smaller islet. Probably its lower plant cover, smaller heterogeneity
            of microhabitats and smaller size (higher exposure to sea winds) offered fewer options
            for lizards to thermoregulate than on the larger islet. However, studying only two
            populations precluded the testing of this hypothesis. </p>
         <p> To test the hypothesis that seasonal changes in thermal ecology depend on islet size
            and traits, studies of several insular populations of the same species are needed. Here,
            we examine the thermal ecology of a third <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            population, living on Binicodrell, an islet located south of Menorca (Spain). This
            population occupies the small islet (0.5 ha), which is located less than 30 km away from
            larger islets with previously studied populations (Fig. 1). The smaller the islet, the
            more it is subjected to sea winds ( ) and the lower habitat and, consequently, climatic
            heterogeneity ( ). This would entail a negative relationship between island size and the
            seasonal variation of the climatic niche available for lizards ( ; ). Thus, other
            factors being equal, within the same lizard species, we would expect a negative
            relationship between the area of the islet and the magnitude of seasonal
            thermoregulatory variation. We predicted that (i) lizards from Binicodrell
            thermoregulate accurately and effectively and (ii) the magnitude of seasonal variation
            in the accuracy and effectiveness of thermoregulation will be higher than in lizards
            from the previously studied populations. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Materials and methods</p>
         <p>Study species and area</p>
         <p> The Balearic lizard, <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> ( Guenther ,
            1874), is endemic in the Balearic Islands (Spain), where it lives in the coastal islets
            of Mallorca and Menorca and the Cabrera Archipelago. Amongst its 23 subspecies, we study
            here <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name> , which only inhabits two
            small islets of the south of Menorca: Binicodrell Gran and Binicodrell Petit. We studied
            the population of Binicodrell Gran (Fig. 1). Lizards from this population are not
            melanic, but rather show a brownish dorsal colouration ( ). As is common in the Balearic
            lizard, this subspecies shows sexual size dimorphism, with larger males (mean snout-vent
            length [SVL] = 64.5 mm) than females (mean SVL = 57.3 mm). </p>
         <p> There are three common traits of Balearic islets that highly influence the ecology and
            evolution of <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> : food resources are scant,
            predation pressure is low and microclimatic conditions are highly variable. Hence,
            Balearic lizards tend to have high population densities, low clutch sizes and extended
            reproductive periods. In addition, they are highly opportunistic feeders with relaxed
            anti-predatory responses ( ; ; ; ). </p>
         <p> Thermal ecology of <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p> Thermal ecology has been studied for two subspecies that inhabit nearby islets:
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> from Aire and <tp:taxon-name>P.
               lilfordi brauni</tp:taxon-name> from Colom (Fig. 1). The 50% preferred temperature
            range (PTR), which approximates to the target temperatures an ectotherm aims to achieve,
            varied from 32-36 °C in spring (Aire islet; ) to 34-36 °C in summer (Aire and Colom
            islets; ; ). Lizards from Aire showed body temperatures (Tb) of ≈ 33 °C in spring and ≈
            36 °C in summer, whereas those from Colom showed less seasonal variation in Tb (≈ 34 °C
            in spring and ≈ 35 °C in summer). Although they thermoregulated accurately and
            effectively in both islets, lizards from Aire, however, showed higher seasonal
            variations relative to thermoregulation than those from Colom ( ). In spring, lizards
            from Aire began their activity before and ended it after those from Colom, at
            temperatures between 17 and 19 °C. In addition, wind speed is higher in Aire than Colom
            (≈ 0.7 vs. 0.3 m/s), while relative humidity is lower in Aire than Colom (≈ 65 vs. 73%).
            Microhabitat selection was somehow different regarding the influence of environmental
            temperatures; however, the lizards similarly selected insulated (or partially insulated)
            microhabitats, avoiding shaded areas and acting independently of wind speed and humidity
            ( ). </p>
         <p>Body temperatures</p>
         <p> We captured active lizards in May (spring) and July (summer) of 2013 by noosing during
            the daily activity period of lizards (08:00 - 17:00 h GMT). We measured their cloacal
            body temperature (Tb) within 10 s after capture, shadowing the lizard and the probe,
            with a Testo® 925 digital thermometer and a thermopar probe (precision 0.1 °C). </p>
         <p>Environmental variables</p>
         <p> In order to characterise the lizards' habitat use and thermoregulatory behaviour, we
            also measured environmental variables that are usually important for thermoregulation (
            ; ). Thus, we measured the air temperature (Ta), 1 cm above the capture point and
            substrate temperature (Ts) of the capture point and recorded the type of substrate
            (rock, soil, grass), the perch height (in cm) and the sunlight exposure (full sun,
            filtered sun, shade). Finally, we measured wind speed with a Kestrel® 3000 anemometer.
            All temperatures were measured with a Testo® 925 digital thermometer and a thermopar
            probe (precision 0.1 °C). </p>
         <p>Operative temperatures</p>
         <p> Operative temperatures (Te) provide a null hypothesis for thermoregulation, as they
            represent the Tb that lizards would achieve if they were not thermoregulating (i.e.
            behaving randomly regarding environmental temperatures; ). We registered the Te and Tb
            simultaneously to avoid possible variations in weather conditions. We used 15 hollow
            copper models as null Te models ( ), that mimicked the colour, size and shape of
            lizards, similar to adults of <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> . We placed one
            thermocouple probe into each hollow model and connected it to a data logger HOBO® H8
            (Onset Computer Corporation), programmed to take a record every five minutes. We
            haphazardly placed the copper models in different microhabitats for periods of 48 hours,
            obtaining a total record of 3714 Tes. Data loggers were placed at the same microsites in
            spring and summer to obtain comparable information about lizard's thermal environment. </p>
         <p>Quantification of behavioural thermoregulation</p>
         <p> To assess the seasonal shift in lizards' thermoregulatory effort, we calculated three
            thermoregulatory indices ( ). The first is the index of thermoregulatory accuracy (mean
            db), which is the mean absolute deviation of Tb from the PTR. As it measures the
            departure of Tb from the thermal preferences, this index is counter-intuitive: higher
            values of db indicate a lower accuracy of thermoregulation and vice versa. The second is
            the index of thermal quality of habitat (mean de), which is the mean absolute deviation
            of Te from the PTR. It is also counter-intuitive: higher values of de indicate a lower
            thermal quality of the habitat and vice versa. The third is the index of
            thermoregulation effectiveness (E), calculated as E = 1 - (mean db / mean de). Values of
            E can range from 0 to 1, with larger E meaning higher thermoregulation effectiveness
            (see ). We also provided the values of the alternative index of thermoregulation
            effectiveness proposed by as (de - db). Indices were calculated with THERMO, a Minitab
            module that has been used in previous studies (e.g. , , ). It uses three kinds of input
            data: Tb, Te and the PTR and was programmed to perform bootstraps of 500 iterations,
            building pseudo-distributions of three kinds of output values: mean db, mean de and mean
               <tp:taxon-name>E.</tp:taxon-name> We performed statistical analyses of the
            bootstrapped values of the indices. </p>
         <p>Statistical analysis</p>
         <p> Means are reported with standard deviations (SD). We studied the effect of different
            variables in lizard's Tb us ing a general linear model. As Ta and Ts were strongly
            correlated (r = 0.882), we decided to only include Ta in this analysis. We used ANCOVA
            to compare Tb between spring and summer, with Ta as the covariate. We assessed if the
            linear relationships between Tb and Ts and Tb and Ta varied seasonally, calculating the
            interaction term with the season of the respective ANCOVAs. We compared the frequencies
            of use of different sunlight exposures with the G-test of independence. Data on Te and
            indices of thermoregulation did not fulfil the assumptions of parametric tests. Hence,
            we tested the effect of season and sunlight situations on these variables using the
            Mann-Whitney's U tests ( ). We conducted the analyses on R, version 3.1.3 ( ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Results</p>
         <p>Males and females maintained similar Tb (Table 2). In addition, the sunlight situation
            and the wind speed had a significant effect on Tb, but not the substrate. The only
            studied factors affecting Tb were the season, with higher temperatures in summer and the
            Ta, with a positive relationship (Table 1, Table 2). Body temperatures varied seasonally
            when correcting by Ta variation (F1, 80 = 63.663, p &lt;0.0001). Linear regression
            slopes between Tb and environmental temperatures were similar for both seasons (Tb - Ta:
            F1, 75 = 0.010, p = 0.919; Tb - Ts: F1, 75 = 1.599, p = 0.210; Fig. 2).</p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> Operative temperatures were lower in spring than in summer for all sunlight exposures
            (Table 3). Lizards' microhabitat use varied amongst different sunlight exposures in each
            season. In spring, they used places under the full sun more frequently (G = 6.930; p =
            0.008), whereas in summer, they used shaded areas more frequently (G = 3.865; p =
            0.049). The use of microhabitats under filtered sun was similar for both seasons (G =
            0.452; p = 0.501; Fig. 3). </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> In spring, 90% of Tbs were below the PTR and only 10% fell within the PTR. In summer,
            28.3% of Tbs were within the PTR and 71.7% were above it. The index of accuracy of
            thermoregulation was significantly higher in the spring than in the summer (U = 0.00, p
            &lt;0.0001; Table 1). The index of habitat thermal quality was similar within seasons (U
            = 4427.00, p = 0.161; Table 1). <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis lilfordi
               codrellensis</tp:taxon-name> showed a poor thermoregulatory effectiveness in spring,
            significantly lower than in summer (U = 0.00, p &lt;0.0001; Table 1). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Discussion </p>
         <p> Seasonal shifts in the extent of behavioural thermoregulation of <tp:taxon-name>P.
               lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name> at Binicodrel islet were notably broad. In the
            nearby islets of Aire and Colom, body temperatures of <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi
               lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi brauni</tp:taxon-name> ,
            respectively, show a much lower degree of seasonal variation. Body temperatures found in
            Binicodrell were lower in spring than those from Aire and Colom and were similar in
            summer ( ). Linear relationships between body and air temperatures varied seasonally in
            lizards of Aire and Colom islets ( ), whereas we found similar slopes for lizards of
            Binicodrell. </p>
         <p> Microhabitat use also changed seasonally. In spring, lizards behaved similarly
            regarding the use of sun patches at Binicodrell when compared to the other two studied
            islets ( ), preferring sunny areas, that offered temperatures closer to the optimum of
            sprint speed (≈ 35 °C; ). In summer, Binicodrell lizards used shaded places (≈ 30 °C)
            significantly more than in spring, while they used sunny patches (≈ 45 °C) less. The use
            of microhabitats under filtered sun was similar in spring and summer. By using
            microhabitats differently, lizards can achieve different thermoregulation accuracy and
            effectiveness and seasonal changes are a key factor in conditioning lacertid's
            thermoregulatory effort ( ). </p>
         <p> Thermoregulatory accuracy of this population is different from those previously
            studied. In spring, it ranged from 1.9 °C in Aire to 1.1 °C in Colom ( ), whereas the
            studied lizards from Binicodrell showed a mean of 3.7 °C of deviations of body
            temperatures from the PTR. Additionally, during summer they deviated more from the PTR:
            0.4 °C in Aire, 0.6 °C in Colom ( ) and 1.2 °C in Binicodrell. Thus, assuming the PTR
            and its seasonal acclimatisation are similar in all populations ( ), the body
            temperatures of the studied lizards deviated by more than double from their thermal
            preferences vs. those of the nearby isles. </p>
         <p> There are two ways for lizards to cope with seasonal environmental variation: (1)
            behavioural thermoregulation and (2) physiological thermal acclimatisation of preferred
            body temperatures ( ) and a mix of both strategies would also be possible. Some
            lacertids change their preferred temperature range to adapt to seasonal thermal
            requirements, as is the case for <tp:taxon-name>Iberolacerta galani</tp:taxon-name> ( ).
            Nevertheless, it seems not to be the case for <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name>
            , whose preferred temperature range is similar during spring and summer. Hence,
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> seems to rely on behavioural strategies to
            adapt their thermoregulation to seasonal shifts. </p>
         <p> Our present and past results ( ) illustrate the strong intraspecific variability in the
            thermoregulatory abilities of the Balearic lizard. In addition, the interaction between
            the seasonal changes in thermoregulation effectiveness and the population ( ) is
            reinforced with the results of <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> from
            Binocodrell. Lizards are predicted to increase thermoreg ulation accuracy with habitat
            heterogeneity ( ). Heterogeneity of vegetation and substrates is greater in Colom islet
            ( <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi brauni</tp:taxon-name> ), intermediate in Aire islet (
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> ) and lower in Binicodrell (
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi codrellensis</tp:taxon-name> ; see data in niche breadth
            and biotic capacity of the three islets in ). Although thermal heterogeneity is probably
            closely related to the heterogeneity of substrates and vegetation, we do not have the
            empirical evidence that relates both variables. Nonetheless, lizards thermoregulate less
            effectively (and suffer from a greater seasonal shift in thermoregulation abilities) in
            the less heterogeneous habitat (Binicodrell). Previous studies in other Mediterranean
            lacertids found a lack of general thermoregulation patterns at small islets ( ). In any
            case, applying new thermoregulation metrics can lead us to a better understanding of the
            influence of habitat thermal quality in thermoregulation effort of this and other lizard
            species and its flexibility between seasons and islets ( ). </p>
         <p> Furthermore, thermoregulation differences found on the different populations of
               <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> might be connected with biological
            differences amongst the three subspecies. They differ in many biological traits (e.g.
            size, colour, diets and foraging behaviour) which could influence their thermal biology.
            Lizards from Aire ( <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi lilfordi</tp:taxon-name> ) are melanic
            and larger than the others, lizards from Colom ( <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi
               brauni</tp:taxon-name> ) are non-melanic (brownish-greenish colouration) and of
            intermediate size and lizards from Binicodrell ( <tp:taxon-name>P. lilfordi
               codrellensis</tp:taxon-name> ) are also non-melanic (brownish) and smaller than the
            others ( ; ). Their foraging behaviour and predation pressure are also highly variable (
            ; ; ). Small behavioural differences, even in morphotypes of the same species sharing
            the same habitat, can lead to different body temperatures, as found in
               <tp:taxon-name>Podarcis melisellensis</tp:taxon-name> ( ). </p>
         <p> A reciprocal transplant experiment showed that <tp:taxon-name>Phrynosoma
               hernandesi</tp:taxon-name> lizards living at different elevations immediately
            adjusted to the use of light environment by means of phenotypic plasticity ( ).
            Phenotypical plasticity can have an important role in the thermoregulation variability
            found in the Balearic lizard. This would provide lizards with the potential to
            behaviourally buffer the impacts of climate change, whenever cool microsites are
            available within their habitats ( ). The fact that lizards adapt to seasonal changes in
            thermal conditions suggests, at least, some degree of phenotypic plasticity. We still do
            not know whether the high thermoregulation flexibility found in the Balearic lizard is
            due to habitat differences, local adaptation or phenotypic plasticity. It is probable
            that all three causes contribute to the observed flexibility in behavioural
            thermoregulation and disentangling their relative contributions will be necessary to
            understand how insular populations of lizards modulate their thermoregulation responses
            to environmental changes. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p> Lizards were captured under permit CEP 35/2013 of the Balearic Islands' Government. We
            thank M. Garrido and A. Perez-Cembranos for support during fieldwork. We thank Mary
               <tp:taxon-name>Trini</tp:taxon-name> Mencia and Joe McIntyre for linguistic revision.
            During fieldwork, funding was provided to Z. O. and A. M. by predoctoral grants from the
            University of Salamanca (FPI program) and partially supported by the research project
            CGL2012-39850-CO2-02 (Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation). We also thank the
            financial support of Coordenacao de Aperfeicoamento de Pessoal de Nivel Superior (CAPES,
            Brazil) and the Programa de Pos-graduacao em Ecologia e Conservacao (PPGEC) and Programa
            de Pos-graduacao em Biologia Animal (PPGBA) of the UFMS. During analysis and writing, A.
            G. was funded by a CNPq Master's Scholarship and Z. O. and A. M. were funded by
            PNDP/CAPES post-doctoral fellowships. All research was conducted in compliance with
            ethical standards and procedures of the University of Salamanca. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Adolph, SC , Porter, WP , 1993 . Temperature, activity, and lizard
                  life histories. . The American Naturalist 142 : 273 - 295 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Algar, AC , Mahler, DL , 2016 . Area, climate heterogeneity, and the
                  response of climate niches to ecological opportunity in island radiations of
                  Anolis lizards. . Global Ecology and Biogeography 25 : 781 - 791 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bakken, GS , Angilletta, MJ , 2014 . How to avoid errors when
                  quantifying thermal environments. . Functional Ecology 28 : 96 - 107
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Basson, CH , Levy, O , Angilletta, MJ , Clusella‐Trullas, S , 2016 .
                  Lizards paid a greater opportunity cost to thermoregulate in a less heterogeneous
                  environment. . Functional Ecology 31 : 856 - 865 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Blouin-Demers, G , Weatherhead, PJ , 2001 ..
                  https://doi.org/10.1890/0012-9658(2001)082[3025:TEOBRS]2.0.CO;2 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bauwens, D , Garland, JrT , Castilla, AM , Van Damme, R , 1995 .
                  Evolution of sprint speed in lacertid lizards: morphological, physiological, and
                  behavioral covariation. . Evolution 49 : 848 - 863 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bauwens, D , Hertz, PE , Castilla, AM , 1996 . Thermoregulation in a
                  lacertid lizard: the relative contributions of distinct behavioral mechanisms. .
                  Ecology 77 : 1818 - 1830 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Carrascal, LM , Lopez , P , Martin , J , Salvador, A , 1992 .
                  Basking and antipredator behaviour in a high altitude lizard: implications of
                  heat‐exchange rate. . Ethology 92 : 143 - 154 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Crawley, MJ , 2012 .. https://doi.org/10.1002/9781118448908
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Diaz , JA , Iraeta, P , Monasterio, C , 2006 . Seasonality provokes
                  a shift of thermal preferences in a temperate lizard, but altitude does not. .
                  Journal of Thermal Biology 31 : 237 - 242 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Dzialowski, EM , 2005 . Use of operative temperature and standard
                  operative temperature models in thermal biology. . Journal of Thermal Biology 30 :
                  317 - 334 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Garrido, M , Perez-Mellado , V , 2014 . Assessing factors involved
                  in determining fluctuating asymmetry in four insular populations of the Balearic
                  lizard Podarcislilfordi. . Salamandra 50 : 147 - 154 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Gvozdik , L , 2012 .. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2011.0960
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hertz, PE , Huey, RB , Stevenson, RD , 1993 . Evaluating temperature
                  regulation by field-active ectotherms: the fallacy of the inappropriate question.
                  . The American Naturalist 142 : 796 - 818 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Huey, RB , Slatkin, M , 1976 . Cost and benefits of lizard
                  thermoregulation. . The Quarterly Review of Biology 51 : 363 - 384
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Huyghe, K , Vanhooydonck, B , Herrel, A , Tadic , Z , Van Damme, R ,
                  2007 . Morphology, performance, behavior and ecology of three color morphs in
                  males of the lizard Podarcismelisellensis. . Integrative and Comparative Biology
                  47 : 211 - 220 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Little, AG , Seebacher, F , Vieira de Andrade, D , Bevier, CR ,
                  Carvalho, JE , 2016 . Taylor and Francis Group, Florida .
                  https://doi.org/10.1201/b20420-3 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Mencia , A , Ortega, Z , Perez-Mellado , V , 2017 ..
                  https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.2828 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Nitis, T , Kitsiou, D , Klaic , ZB , Prtenjak, MT , Moussiopoulos, N
                  , 2005 . The effects of basic flow and topography on the development of the sea
                  breeze over a complex coastal environment. . Quarterly Journal of the Royal
                  Meteorological Society 131 : 305 - 327 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ortega, Z , Martin‐Vallejo , FJ , 2018 ..
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/1749-4877.12363 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ortega, Z , Perez-Mellado , V , 2016 . Seasonal patterns of body
                  temperature and microhabitat selection in a lacertid lizard. . Acta Oecologica 77
                  : 201 - 206 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ortega, Z , Perez-Mellado , V , 2017 . The effect of thermal
                  requirements on microhabitat selection and activity of Podarcislilfordi (Squamata:
                  Lacertidae). . Salamandra 53 : 351 - 358 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ortega, Z , Mencia , A , Perez-Mellado , V , 2016a . : Sexual
                  differences in behavioral thermoregulation of the lizard Scelarcisperspicillata. .
                  Journal of Thermal Biology 61 : 44 - 49 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ortega, Z , Mencia , A , Perez-Mellado , V , 2016b . The peak of
                  thermoregulation effectiveness: thermal biology of the Pyrenean rock lizard,
                  Iberolacertabonnali (Squamata, Lacertidae). . Journal of Thermal Biology 56 : 77 -
                  83 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ortega, Z , Mencia , A , Perez-Mellado , V , 2016c . Adaptive
                  seasonal shifts in the thermal preferences of the lizard Iberolacertagalani
                  (Squamata, Lacertidae). . Journal of Thermal Biology 62 : 1 - 6 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ortega, Z , Perez-Mellado , V , Garrido, M , Guerra, C ,
                  Villa-Garcia , A , Alonso-Fernandez , T , 2014 . Seasonal changes in thermal
                  biology of Podarcislilfordi (Squamata, Lacertidae) consistently depend on habitat
                  traits. . Journal of Thermal Biology 39 : 32 - 39 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Pafilis, P , Lymberakis, P , Sagonas, K , Valakos, E , 2016 . The
                  particularities of a remote islet shape the thermoregulatory profile of an endemic
                  Mediterranean lizard. . Journal of Thermal Biology 61 : 55 - 60 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Perera, A , Perez-Mellado , V , 2002 . Ausencia de plasticidad
                  fenotipica en las estrategias reproductoras de la lagartija balear,
                  Podarcislilfordi (Squamata, lacertidae). . Revista de Menorca 86 : 159 - 171
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Perez-Cembranos , A , Leon , A , Perez-Mellado , V , 2016 ..
                  https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0148947 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Perez-Mellado , V , Corti, C , 1993 . Dietary adaptations and
                  herbivory in lacertid lizards of the genus Podarcis from western Mediterranean
                  islands (Reptilia. Sauria). . Bonner Zoologische Beitraege 44 : 193 - 220
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Perez-Mellado , V , Martin-Vallejo , J , Brown, R , Picornell, A ,
                  Castro, J , Ramon , MM , Terrassa, B , Garcia-Diez , T , Hernandez-Estevez , JA ,
                  2008 . Population density in Podarcislilfordi (Squamata, Lacertidae), a lizard
                  species endemic to small islets in the Balearic Islands (Spain). .
                  Amphibia-Reptilia 29 : 49 - 60 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Refsnider, JM , Qian, SS , Streby, HM , Carter, SE , Clifton, IT ,
                  Siefker, AD , Vazquez, TK , 2018 . Reciprocally transplanted lizards along an
                  elevational gradient match light environment use of local lizards via phenotypic
                  plasticity. . Functional Ecology 32 : 1227 - 1236 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sears, MW , Angilletta, MJ , 2015 .. https://doi.org/10.1086/680008
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sears, MW , Jr. Angilletta, MJ , Schuler, MS , Borchert, J ,
                  Dilliplane, KF , Stegman, M , Rusch, TW , Mitchell, WA , 2016 . Configuration of
                  the thermal landscape determines thermoregulatory performance of ectotherms. .
                  Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 113 : 10595 - 10600
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Van Damme, R , Bauwens, D , Verheyen, RF , 1987 . Thermoregulatory
                  responses to environmental seasonality by the lizard Lacertavivipara. .
                  Herpetologica 43 : 405 - 415 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Vickers, M , Schwarzkopf, L , 2016 . A random walk in the park: an
                  individual-based null model for behavioral thermoregulation. . The American
                  Naturalist 187 : 481 - 490 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
