<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>PhytoKeys</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/phytokeys.20.4033</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Zyzyura, a new genus of Eupatorieae (Asteraceae) from
               Belize</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia mayana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia mayana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sartorina</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Isocarpha</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Praxelis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eupatoriopsis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Praxelinae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ageratina</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gymnocondylus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Zyzyura</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Zyzyura H. Rob. &amp; Pruski</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia mayana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Zyzyura mayana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Zyzyura mayana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Zyzyura mayana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia mayana</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Introduction </p>
         <p> The recent description of <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia mayana</tp:taxon-name> Pruski (
            ) (Figs 1, 2) was based on material of a procumbent epilithic herb from the western
            slope of Victoria Peak in the Cockscomb Range of the Maya Mountains in Belize. The type
            specimen includes four segments of prostrate stems with ascending flowering branches and
            accompanying photos of the plants in the field. Details of the plants that are visible
            are essentially consistent throughout. In the initial study by , using a manuscript key
            to the Eupatorieae of Mesoamerica ( ), the species was identified as a member of the
            genus <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> , and it was described in that genus.
            Now the type specimen has been subjected to a more intense study by the present authors,
            and a number of characteristics have been seen that preclude a position in
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> ( , ). </p>
         <p> The concept of <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> Sch.Bip. has been well
            established since the redefinition of the limits of the genus ( , ) and in subsequent
            studies ( , , , , , , ). The concept is now based on more than 90 species showing great
            uniformity in floral characteristics. </p>
         <p> Four characteristics of <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia mayana</tp:taxon-name> are
            inconsistent with the characters that define
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> or even its only recognized close
            relative, <tp:taxon-name>Sartorina</tp:taxon-name> R.M.King &amp; H.Rob. (1987). </p>
         <p> The involucre of the Belize species is eximbricate with mostly 2 series of equal,
            obovate bracts with broadly rounded tips (Fig. 2C). While
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> often has the superficial appearance of
            being eximbricate, an appearance allowed for in many keys ( ), it is always actually
            subimbricate with the involucral bracts in more than two series. </p>
         <p> The receptacle of the Belize species is highly conical as seen in two heads in which
            the receptacle shows without dissection (Fig. 1C), while that of
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> is plane to scarcely convex. </p>
         <p> The corolla has a basal tube closely investing the style and an abruptly expanded
            campanulate limb, differing from consistently funnelform shape in
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> . </p>
         <p> The carpopodium of the Belize plant has enlarged and elongate cells (Fig. 1F), a
            feature different from the smaller subquadrate cells in
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> . </p>
         <p> There are a few more subtle distinctions from
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> : </p>
         <p>The anther thecae are very short, and the apical anther appendages are slightly broader
            than long (Fig. 1E).</p>
         <p> The cells of the corolla lobes are shorter and broader than those of
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> (Fig. 1D) </p>
         <p> The pappus bristles are ca. ten in number and separated at the base (Fig. 2), a feature
            true of some <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> , but the bristles of the
            pappus are broad at the base unlike those in the
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> species which have five or ten
            non-contiguous bristles. </p>
         <p> A few features are similar to those of <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> :
            the cells of the corolla lobes project at their distal ends on both surfaces of the
            lobes (Fig. 1D), the anther collars are very narrow and strongly transversely annulated,
            though the annulations do not completely obscure the crosswalls of the cells in the
            collars, the cells of the carpopodium have reasonably thick walls, and the style bases
            are neither enlarged nor papillose. </p>
         <p>The most striking feature of the new genus is the high-conical and fistulose receptacle
            (Fig. 1C). How this structure functions is hard to determine, since there is no evidence
            of raised central florets in the flowering heads on the holotype. Careful examination of
            the photographs, however, shows a central cluster of corolla-like material and a
            possible exposed tip of receptacle in the center of the cluster (Fig. 1B). It seems
            possible that florets never fully develop on the distal part of the receptacle.</p>
         <p> The position of the Belize species in the Eupatorieae is not resolved. Although a
            number of features are shared with <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> , and
            the two may have some phylo genetic relationship, the distinction of the species from
            anything in <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> is now certain. Furthermore,
            the new genus, cannot be placed in any of the other genera presently recognized in the
            tribe. It is particularly notable that few members of the Eupatorieae have a highly
            conical receptacle: <tp:taxon-name>Isocarpha</tp:taxon-name> R. Br. in which the
            receptacle is paleate, and <tp:taxon-name>Praxelis</tp:taxon-name> Cass, and
               <tp:taxon-name>Eupatoriopsis</tp:taxon-name> Hieron., both members of the subtribe
               <tp:taxon-name>Praxelinae</tp:taxon-name> , that have completely deciduous involucral
            bracts. The latter two also have 3-costate or obcompressed achenes. </p>
         <p> In the general key to all the Eupatorieae genera in the new genus runs to couplet 137
            on the basis of the articulated bases of the involucral bracts, the more than five
            florets in the capitula, the symmetrical corollas of the capitula, the well-developed
            apical anther appendage, the three to five-ribbed prismatic cypsela, the pappus of ten,
            subequal capillary, non-plumose, persistent bristles, the persistent involucre, the
            pedunculate capitula, the epaleate receptacles and the leaves subtending the peduncles
            not in pseudowhorls. Of the three genera in couplet 137,
               <tp:taxon-name>Ageratina</tp:taxon-name> Spach,
               <tp:taxon-name>Gymnocondylus</tp:taxon-name> R.M.King &amp; H.Rob. &amp;
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> , all differ from the new genus by their
            plane or slightly convex receptacles. The first two differ by their expanded style
            bases, and <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> differs as indicated above.
            Because of these characteristics and because of the generally distinctive aspect of the
            specimen, the species is placed here in another new genus of the Eupatorieae which we
            name <tp:taxon-name>Zyzyura</tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="Taxonomic treatments">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Taxonomic treatments</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Zyzyura H. Rob. &amp; Pruski</tp:taxon-name> gen nov. </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Latin">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> Differs from <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia</tp:taxon-name> by the conical and
               fistulose receptacle, the eximbricate rather 'Piquerian' involucre, the slender-based
               corolla with broadly campanulate limb, and elongate cells of the carpopodium. </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Type">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Type.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia mayana</tp:taxon-name> Pruski. </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Description.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> Decumbent epilithic herbs rooting at proximal nodes, prostrate portions 5-20 cm
               long, with short internodes, mostly glabrous, ascending portions 15-30 cm tall, with
               few small hairs, with long basal internodes; stems narrowly fistulose. Leaves (Fig.
               1A) opposite, petioles mostly 3-5 mm; blades deltate in outline, mostly 4-7 mm long
               and wide, 3-7-lobed with sinuses 1/3-1/2 to midvein, basal margin truncate or
               subtruncate, triplinervate at base, margins of lobes often slightly notched, sparsely
               pilose adaxially, paler and hairless with crowded glandular dots abaxially.
               Inflorescence (Fig. 1B) terminal on ascending portions, ascending parts not branched
               below, distally loosely branching with 3-10 capitula, with few minute opposite to
               subopposite bracteoles; peduncles mostly 0.5-1.8 cm long. Capitula discoid, broadly
               hemispherical, to 7 mm high and wide; involucres (Fig. 1C) eximbricate; bracts c. 16
               in mostly 2 series, subequal, obovate, with obtuse to rounded tips,
               chartaceous-becoming more scarious distally, bicostate proximally, few shorter outer
               bracts, scarcely spreading at maturity, essentially glabrous; receptacle (Fig. 1C)
               high-conical, fistulose, epaleate, without evidence of fully developed florets born
               on distal part. Florets 20-23; corollas white, 2.2-2.3 mm long, mostly glabrous,
               sparse glandular dots on lobes, immediate base dilated, thickly ribbed, narrowed to a
               slender tube closely investing the style, limb abruptly ampliate, campanulate, lobes
               (Fig. 1D) deltate, with intermarginal ribs, cells projecting at distal ends on inner
               and outer surface; anther collars slender, with numerous annular thickenings that do
               not completely obscure transverse cell walls; anther thecae (Fig. 1E) c. 0.5 mm long;
               apical appendage slightly broader than long. Style base without expanded node,
               papillae or hairs, style appendages thickened, densely papillose. Cypsela (Fig. 2)
               1.2-1.3 mm long, somewhat fusiform, 3-5 costate, with few scabrae on ribs;
               carpopodium (Fig. 1F) broadened, with distinct projecting upper rim, cells enlarged
               and elongate with moderately thickened walls; pappus iniser ate (Fig. 2) with c. 10
               persistent capillary bristles, reaching to approximately the base of corolla lobes,
               broadened but not contiguous at base, scabridulous, narrowed to apex. Pollen c. 18
               [my]m in diam. in fluid. </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Distribution.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>The genus contains only the single species that may be endemic to the type locality
               in the Maya Mountains of the Cockscomb range in Belize.</p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Ecology">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Ecology.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Cited as epilithic.</p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Etymology.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Contrived name (no meaning).</p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="Specimens examined">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Specimens examined.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Zyzyura mayana</tp:taxon-name> (Pruski) H. Rob. &amp; Pruski, comb.
               nov. (IPNI ID: urn:lsid:ipni.org:names:77124264-1), basionym:
                  <tp:taxon-name>Fleischmannia mayana</tp:taxon-name> Pruski in Pruski and Clase,
               Phytoneuron 2012-32 : 6. 2012. Presently known only from Victoria Peak in the
               Cockscomb range of the Maya Mountains in Belize (Brewer &amp; Pau 3349, holotype MO).
            </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>Steven W. Brewer is thanked for providing the material of the new genus and his field
            photographs of the living plants. Carol Kelloff of the Department of Botany, NMNH, is
            thanked for operating the SEM. James Di Loreto, Smithsonian, National Museum of Natural
            History Imaging is thanked for the close-up photographs of the capitula, Alice Tangerini
            of the Department of Botany, NMNH, is thanked preparation of the plates. The Missouri
            Botanical Garden is thanked for the loan of the holotype specimen to the Department of
            Botany, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution. We also thank two
            anonymous reviewers and the Editor for their useful suggestions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> King, RM , Robinson, H , 1966 . Generic limitations in the
                  Hofmeisteria complex (Compositae-Eupatorieae). Phytologia 12 : 465 - 476
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> King, RM , Robinson, H , 1970 . Studies in the Eupatorieae
                  (Compositae). XVIII. New combinations in Fleischmannia. Phytologia 19 : 201 - 207
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> King, RM , Robinson, H , 1972 . Phytologia 24 : 281 - 284
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> King, RM , Robinson, H , 1974 . Studies in the Eupatorieae
                  (Asteraceae). CXXI. Additions to the genus Fleischmannia. Phytologia 28 : 73 - 96
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> King, RM , Robinson, H , 1975 . Studies in the Eupatorieae
                  (Asteraceae). CXLVI. Two new species of Fleischmannia from Central America.
                  Phytologia 31 : 305 - 310 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> King, RM , Robinson, H , 1978 . Studies in the Eupatorieae
                  (Asteraceae) CLXIX. Two new species of Fleischmannia from Guatemala. Phytologia 38
                  : 417 - 423 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> King , RM , Robinson, H , 1991 . Two new species of Fleischmannia
                  from Mesoamerica (Eupatorieae: Asteraceae). Phytologia 71 : 181 - 183
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Robinson, H , 2001 . New species of Fleischmannia from Panama and
                  Andean South America (Asteraceae: Eupatorieae). Proceedings of the Biological
                  Society of Washington 114 : 229 - 556 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Robinson, H , 2008 . 190(3) Compositae-Eupatorieae. Flora of Ecuador
                  83 : 1 - 347 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Robinson, H , 2011 . A New Species of Fleischmannia (Asteraceae:
                  Eupatorieae) from El Salvador. Phytokeys: 7 : 37 - 40 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
