<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of Natural History</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4232/1.3262</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Politbarometer Ost 1999 (Kumulierter Datensatz)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2000</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Marchantiopsida</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Marchantiopsida</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Lophoziaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Jungermanniaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Leiocolea </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Lejeunea </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Investigator , la Voyage </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Pseudothyracella </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Parapagurus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Dynomenidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Dynomene </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Book reviews </p>
         <p> Parasites in Social Insects . Monographs in Behavior and Ecology. By P. SCHMID-HEMPEL,
            1998 (Princeton University Press) [Pp. 409]. Price US$ 35.00. ISBN 0 -691-05923-3. </p>
         <p>Wherever organisms live together in societies, other organisms have found means to
            exploit the bene®ts of the society. Many monographs on social insects also contain short
            chapters concerned with their parasites. In this book, Schmid-Hempel has compiled all
            available information and attempted to synthesize the present knowledge on parasites of
            social insects. The results are presented in eight chapters each with a short summary at
            the end. In the ®rst chapter, the biology of social insects is recapitulated in order to
            lay the foundation necessary for those of us who are not on every-day terms with this
            group of organisms. All major groups of parasites and their respective biology are
            introduced in the second chapter followed by a chapter entitled`Breaking into the
            fortress’. In this latter chapter it becomes clear that infestation of the social group
            is achieved by various pathways usually via the brood but also via adult workers. The
            following two chapters explore how the organization of the colony aOEects the parasite’s
            population dynamics (Chapter 4) and how genetic variability of social insects inūences
            their susceptibility to parasites (Chapter 5). While the author identi®es some traits,
            he emphasizes that these topics are complex and much more future research is necessary.
            Similarly, in the next two chapters on`Host±parasite dynamics’ and`Virulence and
            resistance’, many questions need to be answered in the future. How are the dynamics of
            host and parasite populations linked, and how do parasites achieve virulence and hosts
            resistance? In Chapter 7 it becomes evident that many hosts and their respective
            parasites co-evolve and that a continuous arms-race is proceeding between them. In the
            ®nal chapter, which is more like a discussion in character than the previous chapters,
            Schmid-Hempel brilliantly examines the evolution of sociality from the perspective of a
            parasitologist. The continuing conīct for social cohabitants of recognizing members and
            discriminating against non-members (yet conspeci®cs) has provided many opportunities for
            parasites to`get a foot in the door’. To point out the importance of understanding and
            acknowledging the role of parasites in the continuing evolution of social insects is one
            of the most important achievements of Schmid- Hempel’s book. Beyond this, the author
            introduces new concepts and ideas, many of which will have to be put to a thorough test
            in future studies. Anybody interested in the topic will appreciate the extensive
            reference section spanning more than 50 pages. Additionally, the book includes an
            extensive appendix presenting tables with long lists of parasites of social insects, a
            resource that will be most useful to all scholars of social insects. The glossary is
            unfortunately short, and I found myself several times consulting it without success.
            Since the author provides a relatively basic introduction, he must have had in mind that
            his book will be read by non-specialists who do not immediately know what dysentry,
            dulosis or inquilinism mean, just to name a few. Furthermore, the book contains a few
            typographical errors, for which exclusively the publishers would be to blame. Most of
            these typos are of the following kind:`or’ instead of`of ’,`...of of ...’,`adults’
            instead of`adult’, and I only emphasize them to demonstrate that computer programs are
            still not smart enough to replace a thorough proof-reader. Without any further
            nit-picking, I like to conclude by congratulating the author who has provided the ®rst
            complete synthesis on Parasites in Social Insects. The role of parasites in ecological
            interactions becomes increasingly acknowledged, and this book will do its share to
            foster this knowledge. Its modest price should allow a high prevalence of this book in
            institutional and personal libraries.</p>
         <p>MARTIN THIEL</p>
         <p> The Liverwort Flora of the British Isles . By JEAN A. PATON, 1999 (Colchester: Harley
            Books) [Pp. 626]. Price £52.50 (hbk). ISBN 0 946589 60 7. </p>
         <p> The British Isles contain a very signi®cant proportion of the bryophyte ¯ora of Europe,
            and the importance of this group of organisms in the biodiversity and biogeography of
            Britain and Ireland is being recognized increasingly by ecologists. Fortunately, since
            the inception of the Moss Exchange Club in 1896 (latterly the British Bryological
            Society), there has been a dedicated (if albeit small) army of British bryologists whose
            members have collected, identi®ed and catalogued these small plants. Consequently, the
            content and distribution of the bryophyte ¯ora of the British Isles is probably better
            known than any area of comparable size in the world. This has been possible only as a
            result of the availability of a small number of excellent descriptive ¯oras (and
            distribution atlases), which have been published in succession during this century, each
            building on the accumulation of knowledge and experience gained from their predecessors. </p>
         <p> Jean Paton’s impressive book builds on S. M. Macvicar’s Student’s Handbook of British
            Hepatics (1912) and A. J. E. Smith’s The Liverworts of Britain and Ireland (1990) and is
            the result of 30 years dedicated to the study of liverworts in Britain and Ireland .
            Remarkably, she has observed all but ®ve of the 296 species in their natural habitats in
            the ®eld and is widely recognized as an authority on this rather di cult group. The book
            includes 20 introductory pages that deal with the collection and examination of
            specimens, together with helpful notes on important identi®cation features. Under the
            heading of`Habitats and Distribution’ there are lists indicating the preferences that
            certain species show for particular habitats. I always liked this feature in E. V.
            Watson’s British Mosses and Liverworts (1968) since it is so useful for non-experts to
            have some idea of what they may expect to ®nd. In the`Conspectus of Classi®cation’, the
               <tp:taxon-name>Marchantiopsida</tp:taxon-name> and the Anthocerotopsida have been
            treated as classes within the division Bryophyta. Within the
               <tp:taxon-name>Marchantiopsida</tp:taxon-name> , the
               <tp:taxon-name>Lophoziaceae</tp:taxon-name> is given family status separate from the
               <tp:taxon-name>Jungermanniaceae</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Leiocolea
            </tp:taxon-name> is separated as a genus from <tp:taxon-name> Lejeunea </tp:taxon-name>
            . </p>
         <p>The main part of the ¯ora, of course, deals with description and identi®cation. There
            are detailed dichotomous keys that will traumatize novices such as undergraduate
            students in the age-old fashion, but as far as I could tell, all of the technical terms
            are adequately de®ned in a glossary which is cross-referenced with a series of ®gures
            illustrating features such as leaf insertion, shape and surface characters. All the
            species of liverworts known in the British Isles are described with invaluable
            information (where available) on chromosome numbers, largely thanks to studies by Dr
            Martha Newton. In addition, there are useful notes on ecology and distribution. Each
            species is illustrated by excellent line drawings and given a separate ®gure showing
            habit and details of key features. For many, myself included, this will be one of the
            most important features of this book. At the back, there is a map and list of Vice
            Counties in the British Isles followed by a comprehensive bibliography.</p>
         <p>I write this review as someone who needs to identify liverworts occasionally, sometimes
            in the course of vegetation surveys, but also during the supervision of undergraduate
            ®eld and project work. I am not a bryologist; however, the identi®cation of lower plants
            is now regarded as essential in ecological surveys, whether the agenda centres on
            biodiversity, vegetation classi®cation or environmental impact assessment. This book
            will be particularly helpful to the growing numbers of us who have to deal with those
            things and will allow us to move up a notch in our bryophyte identi®cation skills. It
            will become one of the most important descriptive ¯oras of the British Isles and is an
            essential acquisition for anyone interested in bryophytes.</p>
         <p>CHARLES HIPKIN</p>
         <p> ReÂsultats des Campagne s MUSORSTOM , Volume 20 . Coordinated by ALAIN CROSNIER, 1999.
            MeÂmoires du MuseÂum national d’Histoire naturelle 180 : 588, 192 ®gures (Paris: MuseÂum
            national d’Histoire naturelle and ORSTOM). Price 600 FF (hbk). ISBN 2 85653 520 8, ISNN
            1243 4442. </p>
         <p> Potentially, reviewing Volume 20 of the ReÂsultats des Campagnes MUSORSTOM appeared to
            be a straightforward task that would at most take a couple of hours after which I could
            place the tome into my book case. The only challenging part to writing a short snappy
            review would be the inclusion of a topical humorous reference to the purchase of a
            certain British agricultural product. But such a cheap book review would most certainly
            go down in the annals of oceanography as one of the greatest misjudgements of the 20th
            century because I would have completely devalued the outstanding scienti®c contribution
            made by MUSORSTOM. This remarkable deep-sea exploration programme must now rank
            alongside the truly great marine expeditions such as Challenger , <tp:taxon-name>
               Investigator , la Voyage </tp:taxon-name> au poÃle sud et dans l’ OceÂanie sur les
            corvettes l’ Astrolabe et la ZeÂleÂe , and United States Exploring Expedition under the
            Command of Charles Wilkes, to name but a few. And yet the marine biological achievements
            of this French project appear to have sailed past the scienti®c community virtually
            unnoticed. </p>
         <p> In 1976, two French Institutions with a world-renowned reputation for scienti®c
            excellence, the MuseÂum national d’Histoire naturelle (MNHN) and l’Institut FrancËais de
            Recherche Scienti ®que pour le DeÂveloppement CoopeÂration (ORSTOM), now renamed
            Institut de Recherche pour le DeÂveloppement (IRD), organized a 10-day cruise to the
            Philippines . The aim of this expedition was to collect samples of a glypheid
            crustacean. This`living fossil’ is known only from a single specimen that is in poor
            condition and was originally captured in the Philippines area at a depth of about 200 m
            during 1908 by the US research vessel Albatross . The French deep-sea cruise was
            successful because ORSTOM research vessel Vauban collected eight specimens of the wanted
            glypheid. Two further cruises in the same area were carried out in 1980 and 1985 with
            the aim of collecting more specimens of the`living fossil’ . </p>
         <p> Following these three cruises in the Philippines , a new ambitious programme known as
            MUSORSTOM extended the research to other archipelagos in the Indo-West Paci®c with a
            view to sampling the bathyal depths for a better knowledge of the tropical deep-water
            fauna. These expeditions became known as les campagnes MUSORSTOM. </p>
         <p> To date, 11 cruises have been undertaken, including cruise 1 (1976), 2 (1980) 3 (1985)
            to the Philippines Islands; 4 (1985), 5 (1986), 6 (1989) to New Caledonia ; 7 (1992) to
            the Wallis and Futuna Islands; 8 (1994) to Vanuatu ; 9 (1997) to the Marquesas Islands
            and 10 (1998), 11 (1998) to Fiji . Other deep-sea cruises, engaged in bio-prospecting,
            also contributed additional samples and information about the deep sea. During all these
            investigations, a total of 764 days were spent at sea with over 2800 trawls and dredges
            collecting marine life from depths of 100 m down to 3700 m . Each station is accompanied
            by a meticulously documented set of ®eld data. To put this programme into perspective,
            the MUSORSTOM cruises to New Caledonia alone collected more samples than all the great
            international expeditions since the 19th century. Of the 1600 invertebrate species
            currently recorded from the economic zone of New Caledonia , 60% were described as new.
            However, the MUSORSTOM cruises have not ®nished; in 2000 an expedition to the Tonga
            Islands is scheduled. </p>
         <p> The material from the expeditions was sent to the MNHN for sorting and is still only
            partly studied. At the Museum the MUSORSTOM project has been a truly international
            eOEort because since 1976, 181 scientists from 92 research institutes and representing
            24 countries have taken part in the taxonomic studies of MUSORTOM specimens. Many
            scientists have visited the collections in Paris with the assistance of generous
            ®nancial support from ORSTOM, MNHM and the French Foreign AOEairs Ministry. </p>
         <p> Most of the results are published in a series ReÂsultats des Campagnes MUSORSTOM in the
            MeÂmoires of the MuseÂum national d’Histoire naturelle . Initially only 12 volumes were
            envisaged but today I am reviewing Volume 20 and I know that two more volumes are in
            preparation for publication in 2000. This series of volumes comprises some 200
            contributions (approximately 50% of papers are in English, the other half are in
            French), about 9100 pages of taxonomic revisions and biogeography, and contains
            descriptions of 4587 species of which 1324 are new to science, as well as several new
            families and 126 new genera. Detailed cruise narratives are reported in French and
            English. Apart from the 20 MUSORSTOM volumes, about 500 notes and short papers have been
            accepted for publication. To underline the international concord of this project
            further, a proportion of the identi®ed biological specimens have been donated and
            deposited in various museums around the globe. </p>
         <p>To save publishing costs, these MUSORTOM volumes have been prepared as cameraready copy
            for the printers using desktop publishing and this has not compromised the quality of
            the series. Further, the series has received sponsorship from a number of sources for
            the production costs of these tomes. Since Volume 15 and at very little extra expense,
            the series has been produced with hard covers.</p>
         <p> The editor of Volume 20 is Alain Crosnier and he has been the scienti®c editor for 11
            other MUSORSTOM volumes including 6, 8±16 and 18. Volume 20 is typical of the
            international collaboration described in this review with 11 authors representing Japan
            , New Zealand , USA and Europe, covering the following zoological groups of deep-sea
            corals, Bryozoa, Crustacea and snake eels. One subfamily, ®ve genera and 60 species are
            described as new to science, and new data are presented on an additional 250 species.
            One paper in this volume records a living example of the bryozoan genus <tp:taxon-name>
               Pseudothyracella </tp:taxon-name> , which was only previously known as a Palaeogene
            fossil from Europe and North America; this highlights just how inadequately the tropical
            deep sea has been sampled. However, there are three lengthy taxonomic studies that
            represent a considerable amount of investment by the authors concerned. The deep-water
            Scleractinia paper by Stephen Cairns reports on 134 species from Vanuatu , Wallis and
            Futuna Islands. All but one species is a new record for the region, 16 are described as
            new to science, examples of commensal/parasite relationships are reported and 22 ®gures
            of black and white photographs accompany the text. This is a substantial contribution to
            anthozoan taxonomy. The review of the pagurid crustacean genus <tp:taxon-name>
               Parapagurus </tp:taxon-name> by Rafael Lemaitre comprises 75 pages of text supported
            by well-illustrated ®gures and a comprehensive key to the Paci®c and Indian Ocean
            species. With the description of seven new parapagurids, the genus now contains 17
            species of which only three are known from the Atlantic Ocean. The author also
            summarizes bathymetric distribution data for all species assigned to the genus. Paper
            nine in Volume 20 is a revision of the <tp:taxon-name>Decapoda</tp:taxon-name> family
               <tp:taxon-name>Dynomenidae</tp:taxon-name> , a group of small primitive crabs often
            associated with corals. All the genera and species of the family are revised and
            redescribed with the genus <tp:taxon-name> Dynomene </tp:taxon-name> divided into two
            genera. Forty-one ®gures illustrate the text and these include photographs of specimens,
            pictures taken with a scanning electron microscope, excellent line drawings, several
            cladograms and maps displaying geographical distributions. The author, Colin McLay, also
            provides a key to the species of the family. Volume 20 comprises 588 pages, 192 ®gures,
            two colour photographs which are all printed on acid-free paper at a cost of only 600
            French francs plus postage. However, if your Institution is not subscribing to this
            major on-going zoological series on tropical deep-sea benthos make contact with email
            address dhenry@mnhn.fr for details. </p>
         <p> The MUSORSTOM marine biological project with its vision of unsel®sh international
            scienti®c collaboration is probably unrivalled in our modern era. May its tropical
            deep-sea programme continued to be funded by the French Government. Vive la France . </p>
         <p>PAUL F. CLARK</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
