<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of Systematics and Evolution</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jse.12181</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Collections-based systematics: Opportunities and outlook for
               2050</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>29</day>
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>form via</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Avena fatua </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Review </title>
         <p> Collections-based systematics: Opportunities and outlook for 2050 </p>
         <p> Jun Wen 1 *, Stefanie M. Ickert-Bond 2 , Marc S. Appelhans 1,3 , Laurence J. Dorr 1 ,
            and Vicki A. Funk 1 </p>
         <p> 1 Department of Botany, MRC-166, Smithsonian Institution, PO Box 37012, Washington , DC
            20013-7012, USA </p>
         <p> 2 UA Museum of the North and Department of Biology and Wildlife, University of Alaska
            Fairbanks, 907 Yukon Dr., PO Box 756960, Fairbanks, Alaska 99775-6960, USA </p>
         <p> 3 Department of Systematics, Biodiversity and Evolution of Plants, Albrecht-von-Haller
            Institute of Plant Sciences,University of Gottingen €,Untere Karsp€ ule 2, 37073 G
            ottingen €, Germany </p>
         <p> *Author for correspondence. E-mail: wenj@si.edu . Tel.: 1-202-6334881. Fax:
            1-202-7862563. </p>
         <p> Received 11 May 2015 ; Accepted 25 August 2015 ; Article first published online 29
            September 2015 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Abstract Systematic biology is a discipline rooted in collections. These collections
            play important roles in research and conservation and are integral to our efforts to
            educate society about biodiversity and conservation. Collections provide an invaluable
            record of the distribution of organisms throughout the world and through recent and
            geological time, and they are the only direct documentation of the biological, physical,
            and cultural diversity of the planet: past, present, and future. Recent developments in
            bioinformatics and cyberinfrastructure are transforming systematics by opening up new
            opportunities and as a result major digitization efforts have increasingly made
            available large amounts of biodiversity data. The collections-based systematics
            community needs to train the nextgeneration of systematists with integrative skills,
            address grand questions about biodiversity at different scales, develop a community-wide
            cyberinfrastructure, effectively disseminate systematic data to biologists and the
            public, and proactively educate the public and policy makers on the importance of
            systematics and collections in the biodiversity crisis of the Anthropocene.
            Specifically, we call for a new global Biodiversity CyberBank, comparable to GenBank for
            genetic data, to be the repository of all biodiversity data, as well as a World
            Organization of Systematic Biology to lead major initiatives of the field. We also
            outline a new workflow for taxonomic monographs, which utilizes both the traditional
            strengths of synthesizing diverse collections-based taxonomic data and the capacity of
            online resources and bioinformatics tools. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Key words: Biodiversity CyberBank, collections-based systematics, e-monograph,
            Systematics Agenda 2050, World Organization of Systematic Biology. </p>
         <p> Systematics is a discipline firmly based in and dependent on biological collections.
            Although influenced by early workers such as Tournefort and de Jussieu, the field was
            founded as a scientific discipline in the 1700s by Carl Linnaeus. It has experienced
            several major periods of revolution including the production of the first comprehensive
            world flora ( – 1873), incorporation of Charles Darwin ’ s theory of evolution, J. D.
            Hooker ’ s biogeographic discoveries, cladistics and the proposition of phylogenetic
            hypotheses, and DNA-based molecular systematics ( ; ; ). Recent bioinformatic
            developments related to systematic collections are also transforming systematics by
            opening up new opportunities for the discipline ( ; ). As we enter the era of genomics
            there is a need for collections to grow even stronger in order for us to interpret the
            large amounts of molecular data that are being generated. At the present time with
            genomics and bioinformatics transforming the field of systematics, collections in
            general face major challenges and a proactive strategy is needed to ensure a robust
            future. </p>
         <p> Systematic collections play important roles in research in biological sciences as well
            as in educating society on biodiversity and conservation ( Fig. 1 ). They provide an
            invaluable record of the distribution of plants and animals throughout the world and
            through recent and geological time, and they are being used in many types of studies
            including those focused on climate change, movement of invasive species, and niche
            modeling (O ’ ; ; ). Collections are the only direct documentation of the biological,
            physical, and cultural diversity of the planet: past, present, and future ( ). Herbaria
            and museums that house collections are not static repositories, instead they are
            essential tools for research and education in biological sciences ( Fig. 2 ; ; ). </p>
         <p> Collections-based systematics encompasses the naming, describing, and classifying of
            biodiversity, the synthesis of this information into a wide array of checklists,
            floras/faunas and monographs, and the interpretation of these data in light of
            phylogenetic and biogeographic hypotheses ( , 1994; ). The discipline and its
            collections should continue to play a central role in today ’ s biology and society,
            because we are still in the infancy of understanding the diversity and assembly of our
            planet ’ s floras and faunas, especially in the tropics, under the sea, and in the soil
            ( ). Natural history collections now play an unprecedented role in documenting climatic
            and biodiversity changes and shifts in the critical age of our time, a period known as
            the Anthropocene, which denotes the current interval of anthropogenic global
            environmental change ( ; ). </p>
         <p> Bioinformatic developments in the last decade have helped us explore ways to enhance
            the efficiency in organizing, publishing, and utilizing systematic information. Online
            resources coupled with the advent of new molecular and genomic technologies that are
            helping make use of older specimens, coupled with an ability to publish results quickly
            via online outlets ( ) will no doubt result in dramatic changes in the next decade. More
            than ever collections and those who study them are central to understanding the results
            from modern studies. </p>
         <p> In this paper, we highlight the opportunities available for today ’ s collections-based
            systematics and outline directions for the coming decades, emphasizing the role of
            collections in charting the biosphere in the era of bioinformatics and genomics. We
            wrote this paper targeting the systematics community, including professionals and
            students, as our principal audience. Even though some of the points have been made
            elsewhere, we hope this broad synthesis will prove to be useful to readers to help them
            understand the current state and the possible future of collections-based systematics.
            We especially encourage next-generation systematists to fully incorporate
            collections-based components in developing their integrative research programs in
            systematics. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Opportunities </title>
         <p> An organized, informed systematics community </p>
         <p> In general major professional societies/associations in systematics and botany are well
            organized. The goals of these organizations usually go far beyond promoting the science,
            as they often value and promote efforts for the long-term sustainability of
            collections-based systematics. One successful example is the Systematics Agenda 2000
            initiative ( , 1994). It was an important effort organized by the systematics community
            in the United States under the auspices of the Society of Systematic Biologists (SSB),
            the American Society of Plant Taxonomists (ASPT), the Willi Hennig Society, and the
            Association of Systematics Collections (ASC). The initiative set an agenda for a 25-year
            period for systematics, and the agenda was also widely circulated in Europe ( ). This
            initiative developed into Diversitas (http://www.diversitasinternational.org/), a global
            effort, the organizers of which met regularly for a number of years. There were more
            recent discussions on Systematics Agenda 2020 ( ), but these were at a much smaller
            scale.The systematics community needs to reassess the status and missions of the major
            areas of systematics, and to take actions to strategically move the important
            systematics agenda forward in this century. </p>
         <p> The systematics community has taken positive steps towards assessing the world ’ s
            biota, making use of online resources in the informatics age of biology. Species 2000
            (www.species2000.org/), a “ federation ” of database organizations working closely with
            users, taxonomists, and sponsoring agencies, has the goal of creating a validated
            checklist of all the world ’ s species (plants, animals, fungi, and microbes). This
            program brings together an array of global species databases covering each of the major
            groups of organisms. The program in partnership with the Integrated Taxonomic
            Information System (ITIS) of North America currently produces the Catalogue of Life ,
            which is used by the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) and the
            Encyclopedia of Life (EoL) as the taxonomic backbone of their web portals. </p>
         <p> Rapid advances in digitization of systematics collections The systematics community has
            advanced rapidly in digitizing specimens and establishing various data portals for
            natural history collections and biodiversity assessments ( ; ; Fig. 3 ). Some examples
            of major initiatives are discussed as follows. </p>
         <p> The Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF, http:// www.gbif.org/) is an
            international open data infrastructure funded by governments. It facilitates the global
            digitization and dissemination of primary biodiversity data. Since 2004 GBIF has been
            the largest single gateway to specimen data from herbaria and museums despite
            deficiencies concerning data quality and lack of a direct feedback mechanism ( ). </p>
         <p> The JSTOR Global Plants (GP, http://about.jstor.org/content/ global-plants) database
            includes more than 2.2 million digitized herbarium type specimens from more than 300
            herbaria and museums worldwide as partners. Although GP began with type specimens, it
            increasingly includes other historical and geographically defined specimens. The JSTOR
            database grew tremendously for ten years until the main funding by the Andrew W. Mellon
            foundation ended in 2014. Now a membership fee is in place for those wishing to access
            the high-resolution images, while the low-resolution images remain available free of
            charge. </p>
         <p> Integrated Digitized Biocollections (iDigBio, https://www. idigbio.org/) is the
            national resource in the United States for digitized information about natural history
            collections. Among many diverse functions, iDigBio serves as the coordinating center for
            a national digitization effort, fosters partnerships and innovations, and promotes the
            use of collections data in science, education, and other sectors of society.
            Digitization efforts have also gone beyond the traditional imaging and metadata capture.
            More recently, digitization has used the principles of automation and crowd sourcing,
            with minimal initial metadata collection ( ). </p>
         <p> The Catalogue of Life (CoL, http://www.catalogueoflife.org/) is a currently available
            global index of species, with a single integrated species checklist and taxonomic
            hierarchy. The Catalogue holds taxonomic information on the names, relationships, and
            distributions of over 1.5 million species. The information is updated regularly from
            diverse sources around the world. </p>
         <p> The Integrated Taxonomic Information System (ITIS, http:// www.itis.gov) represents a
            partnership of agencies in the United States , Canada , and Mexico (ITIS-North America),
            other organizations, and taxonomic specialists. ITIS provides authoritative taxonomic
            information on plants, animals, fungi, and microbes of North America and the world. It
            is also a partner of Species 2000 and GBIF. </p>
         <p> Some countries have either established virtual herbaria or are in the process of doing
            so. Perhaps the first one was the Australian Virtual herbarium
            (http://avh.chah.org.au/). More recent ones are from France , the Netherlands , the
            United States , and China where progress has been made in digitizing herbarium
            collections and in disseminating the information. The world ’ s largest herbarium in
            Paris was digitized during its recent physical renovation (https://science.mnhn.fr/). In
            the Netherlands , the National Herbarium in Leiden was completely digitized in a short
            timeframe using the digitization pipeline Herbarium digistreet ( Fig. 3 ;
            https://science. naturalis.nl/en/collection/naturalis-collections/botany/). The US
            Virtual Herbarium project (USVH, http://usvhproject.org/) ( ) has its goal digitize all
            specimens in all United States herbaria, making these data accessible via a single
            portal iDigBio. Likewise, the Chinese Virtual Herbarium (CVH, http://www.cvh.org.cn/) is
            an online portal allowing access to herbarium specimen information and other botanical
            knowledge in China . CVH is a collaboration among more than 20 major herbaria in China
            to create global, comprehensive, and sustainable access to China ’ s plant biodiversity.
            The project has been much better funded via the main funding agencies in China than the
            USVH has been in the United States . The Council of Heads of Australasian Herbaria
            (CHAH) (Council , ) is an organization comprised of the major herbaria in Australia and
            New Zealand with the objective of promoting all matters of interest to herbaria in
            Australasia and increasing cooperation and understanding between herbaria. </p>
         <p> BRAHMS (Botanical Research and Herbarium Management System,
            http://www.brahmsonline.com) is a database management system developed at the Department
            of Plant Sciences, University of Oxford for botanical research and for managing
            collections in herbaria, botanical gardens, and seed banks. It provides a platform to
            gather, edit, analyze, and publish systematic data, optimizing these data for curation
            services and research outputs. The largest database employing BRAHMS to date is in the
            Netherlands with the herbarium specimen data of the National Herbarium of the
            Netherlands folded into this system. </p>
         <p> Recent major changes to the International Code of Nomenclature (ICN) </p>
         <p> Recent major changes to the International Code of Nomenclature for algae, fungi, and
            plants (Melbourne Code) (ICN; ) have had a positive impact on revisionary/ monographic
            systematic studies ( ). The relevant major changes to botanical systematics include: (i)
            Starting on January 1, 2012 , electronic publication is permitted for new scientific
            names in Portable Document Format (PDF) in online publications with an International
            Standard Serial Number (ISSN) or International Standard Book Number (ISBN) (ICN Articles
            29 – 31); and (ii) Starting on January 1, 2012 , English may be used as an alternative
            to Latin for the descriptions or diagnoses of new taxa (Article 39). </p>
         <p> Systematists have adopted nomenclatural rules varying by organism that were at first
            unwritten but later came to be codified in the early 19th century for zoologists ( ) and
            the late 19th century for botanists, including those who study fungi and algae ( ; ).
            Nomenclature for bacteria and viruses, which was in part regulated by earlier botanical
            codes, is now regulated by a separate code ( ). A BioCode was proposed by , ) to provide
            a unified context for all codes across all organisms, but it was not accepted by the
            taxonomic community ( ).The 2011 IBC in Melbourne declined to consider the BioCode
            proposal. </p>
         <p> In 2013 a user ’ s guide for botanical nomenclature was published ( ) and this has
            greatly expanded the accessibility of the Melbourne Code. In addition IAPT has conducted
            workshops around the world (e.g., in Argentina , Brazil , and China ) teaching the
            basics of the ICN to hundreds of young scientists. There is little doubt that dealing
            with botanical nomenclature is complicated and that few people in the community truly
            grasp the complexities of the ICN, but it is also true that the basic principles are
            straightforward and can be simply explained. We recommend further actions on the
            simplification of the ICN along with additional training workshops to ensure the
            sustainability of nomenclature. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Wealth of online botanical literature </title>
         <p> Unlike many other biological disciplines, systematists need to have knowledge and
            access to historic literature to determine where and when a name was published.
            Databases of names have become very helpful in the process of determining which name has
            nomenclatural priority and which should be considered a synonym. Similarly, biographical
            information with respect to authors of names and collectors of specimens is important
            because such information is often the key to locate literature and find collections that
            serve as type specimens. Organization and management of these sorts of collections-based
            data have improved dramatically in the last few decades. </p>
         <p> One of the most useful databases for plant systematists is the International Plant
            Names Index (IPNI, http://www.ipni. org), which came about through a collaboration
            between the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, the Harvard University Herbaria, and the
            Australian National Herbarium ( ; ). IPNI has been continuously updated since its launch
            in 1999. The Harvard University Herbaria maintain authority files
            (http://kiki.huh.harvard.edu/databases/botanist index.html) that are used for editing
            IPNI. However, with a plant name, its author, and its place of publication in hand it
            can still be difficult to locate the original publication and protologue. Several
            printed resources have recently become available electronically. One of the most
            valuable guides to botanical and fungal literature, which is also of value to
            zoologists, is Taxonomic Literature , ed. 2 (TL-2; 1976 – 2009; see ). After the final
            volume of Taxonomic Literature , ed. 2 was published, the entire work was made available
            on-line as a searchable document (http://www.sil.si. edu/digitalcollections/tl-2/) and
            in a more static <tp:taxon-name>form via</tp:taxon-name> the Biodiversity Heritage
            Library (BHL) (http://www.biodiversity library.org/bibliography/48631-/summary). </p>
         <p>With the digitization of serials and books, collections-based systematics literature is
            available to anyone with a computer and internet access. For a systematist engaged in
            writing revisions or monographs, what once was a long, tedious process of locating which
            library held which volume is now something that can be resolved almost immediately.</p>
         <p> Botanicus (http://www.botanicus.org/) introduced about 1995 was an effort by the Peter
            H. Raven Library of the Missouri Botanical Garden to make digitized copies of botanical
            literature freely available. Although still available, this Garden effort was subsumed
            by the efforts of a dozen natural history libraries that launched the Biodiversity
            Heritage Library (BHL, http://biodiversitylibrary.org) in 2005. BHL is now a large,
            worldwide consortium of natural history and botanical libraries that have digitized over
            100 000 titles. Other important and large-scale literature digitization projects that
            include material of interest to collections-based systematists are Gallica (http://
            gallica.bnf.fr/) and the HathiTrust Digital Library (https://www. hathitrust.org/). The
            latter is a consortium of universities in the United States , Canada , and Europe and
            their website offers content digitized via the Google Books project as well as content
            digitized locally by libraries. Another invaluable resource for locating specimens via a
            search based on a collector ’ s name is the Index Herbariorum (http://sciweb.nybg.
            org/science2/IndexHerbariorum.asp). </p>
         <p> We anticipate that institutions and/or societies will experiment with new interlinked
            electronic resources in a way that will make monographs more dynamic in the future.
            Perhaps this represents the area of greatest need for most comprehensive monographic
            series (e.g., Systematic Botany Monographs published by the American Society of Plant
            Taxonomists), which otherwise have remained relatively classical in their approach. </p>
         <p> Innovative rapid publications in systematics </p>
         <p> Innovative rapid electronic open access publications in systematics have become
            established and are gaining popularity in the community. These advances include rapid
            electronic publications, Open Access, the linkage of electronic registers, indices and
            aggregators to important taxonomic databases, and the development of Web 2.0
            technologies (see ). In the future, journal articles need to be fully integrated with
            all of the resources systematists use to formulate their hypotheses such as GenBank
            (http:// www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/) and DRYAD (http://datadryad. org/). We fully
            expect that these innovative interlinked ways of publication will revolutionize the way
            we disseminate our research. </p>
         <p> A few journals have been designed to rapidly document, analyze, and publish the world ’
            s taxonomic diversity. This more innovative model of publication has been pioneered by
            Pensoft (http://www.pensoft.net/), a leading publisher of open access cybertaxonomy.
            Pensoft publishes ZooKeys , PhytoKeys , and MycoKeys ( , ; ; , ; ). These journals
            disseminate biodiversity data in both traditional and innovative ways, and register all
            new nomenclature with databases such as ZooBank (http://www.zoobank.org/) and IPNI
            (http://www.ipni.org/). These journals also provide species descriptions to the more
            public oriented Encyclopedia of Life (EOL) as part of their routine workflow. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Outlook for 2050 </title>
         <p> Building the Biodiversity CyberBank — an ambitious global community-wide
            cyberinfrastructure </p>
         <p> An ambitious global community-wide cyberinfrastructure needs to be established and
            funded long-term by governments, the biodiversity community, the public, and the private
            sector (also see ; ; ). We envision the cyberinfrastructure or CyberBank ( Fig. 4 ) to
            be similar to GenBank for genetic data, but with enhanced multifunctionality and
            biodiversity collections data as the core, along with links to genetic, ecological,
            paleontological, morphological, and conservation databases. Such a biodiversity
            cyberbank will be critical for safeguarding the community-wide data on collections and
            biodiversity, and for serving as the biodiversity data repository for the scientific
            community, applied agencies, and the public. Existing efforts especially GBIF and
            iDigBio have highly compatible goals, and can function as the foundation for a broader
            biodiversity cyberbank, with more emphasis on serving the broader scientific community
            with sustainable development of the necessary informatics tools for biodiversity,
            especially collections-based and integrative systematics. </p>
         <p> Establishing a World Organization of Systematic Biology </p>
         <p> In the next decades, we believe the global systematics community must reorganize and
            become a bolder and more forceful entity. This community should seek every opportunity
            to advance the goals of the discipline. Specifically we should convene an open
            discussion on the development of a Systematics Agenda 2050 that includes the future of
            natural history collections. An earlier effort in the late 1990 ’ s and early 2000 ’ s
            was launched and called the “ International Federation of Systematic Societies ” , which
            had societies as members, but this effort failed because of a lack of strong leadership.
            To ensure that such an organization survives and accomplishes its goals it should be led
            by international organizations such as the International Association for Plant Taxonomy
            (IAPT) and the Society for Systematic Biologists (SSB). In fact, an opportunity to push
            for a Systematics Agenda 2050 and the World Organization of Systematic Biology is
            approaching because the global botanical community meets every 6 years at the
            International Botanical Congress (IBC; next meeting in 2017 in Shenzhen, China ). The
            IBC is an excellent platform for botanists to have an open dialogue and create a
            strategic plan for the healthy development of systematics and collections. If an
            organization can be discussed and agreed upon at the IBC then it may be easier to
            involve the SSB. </p>
         <p> Preparing next-generation systematists with a solid foundation in systematic
            collections </p>
         <p>Next-generation collections-based systematics research should be designed to be highly
            integrative, interactive, and stimulating. A revisionary or monographic project should
            also employ cutting-edge tools available in bioinformatics, morphology, and
            molecules/genomics and be able to answer important questions concerning delimiting
            species and higher taxa, biogeographic reconstructions, and hypotheses such as modes of
            speciation, and morphological character evolution. Although the scientific products from
            these integrative studies will be highly multifaceted, they will continue to have
            collections as their foundation. Such creative collectionsbased programs led by our
            students will expand the reputation of taxonomy as an important, rigorous, and
            stimulating scientific discipline.</p>
         <p>Next-generation systematists should include systematic collections as an important
            component in the research program, as well as field work. Field work facilitates the
            development of evolutionary hypotheses on the plant groups under study. It has been
            rewarding for us to observe how much our students and interns have enjoyed field classes
            and field trips with us over the years. The field serves as an open laboratory of
            systematic biology and is eye-opening for young students who discover the diversity of
            plants and their interactions with other organisms and the environment. Collections that
            students and researchers make during their studies also contribute to the overall
            sustainability of natural history collections.</p>
         <p>The systematics community needs to work to facilitate the permitting process for
            scientific research in systematic biology. One unintended outcome of the Convention on
            Biological Diversity (CBD) is that it has become more difficult and sometimes impossible
            to obtain collecting permits in parts of the world with rich biodiversity. Major
            systematics organizations (societies and associations) should initiate a dialogue with
            their respective memberships and funding agencies about the importance of fieldwork,
            training of the next-generation with more field opportunities as well as nomenclature
            (ICN), and incorporating collections and collections-based questions in broad
            integrative systematics projects.</p>
         <p> Bridging collections-based systematics with other fields of biology without losing the
            identity of systematics Collections-based systematics is relevant to many fields of
            biology. In the past, systematic research on collections has allowed us to document the
            Cambrian explosion of animals ( ), the ‘ Big-Five ’ mass extinctions responsible for a
            loss of over 75% of species in the last 540 million years ( ; ), and the last
            glacialinterglacial transition from rapid warm-cold-warm fluctuation under climate
            change ( ; ; ).These critical planetary-scale transitions and state shifts would not
            have been possible to detect without contributions from systematic collections-based
            research. </p>
         <p> At finer scales, the systematic study of herbarium specimens allowed to document a
            decline in stomatal density as a result of increased CO 2 emissions in the industrial
            era and this has major implications for future aridification scenarios and the spread of
            C 4 grasses ( ). The inverse relationship of stomatal density and CO 2 emission has also
            been used to look at the fossil record to infer CO 2 concentrations in past epochs ( ).
            Several studies have used herbarium specimens to demonstrate earlier flowering in
            response to a warming climate ( ; ) and species distributional dynamics ( ). The
            hypothesis that climate change is threatening a large portion of the endemic flora of
            California has been extrapolated from occurrence data on herbarium specimens and niche
            modeling ( ). </p>
         <p> Microbial ecology, biogeography, and phylogenetic relationships of microbes such as
            grass-infecting viruses have been studied based on the preservation of these viruses in
            herbarium specimens and their human-mediated spread ( ; ). The link between human
            settlements in the 18th and the 19th centuries and the displacement of native perennial
            and bunchgrasses in California has been linked to the importation of invasive
            Mediterranean grasses such as <tp:taxon-name> Avena fatua </tp:taxon-name> L. that carry
            cereal yellow dwarf viruses and their ability to increase vector populations of yellow
            dwarf viruses and promote incidences in native grasses thus causing shifts in grassland
            ecosystem composition in California and other countries ( ). </p>
         <p> Our knowledge of the origin of polyploid crops and their domestication is closely tied
            to collections-based systematics because the identification of wild relatives involves
            comparative systematic research based on sampling of wild populations and species to
            recover putative progenitors ( ; ). Additionally, ethnobotanical, ethnographic, and
            archaeological studies often rely on systematics collections in order to better
            understand which taxa are used by certain ethnic groups, or which materials were used.
            Several major herbaria have ethnobotanical holdings of vouchered specimens (e.g., BM, F,
            K, MO, NY, P, and US ). </p>
         <p> The value of collections-based systematics for society as a whole is also reflected in
            the use of collections for combatting infectious diseases (e.g., influenza, West Nile
            virus, hantavirus), agricultural pests, detecting environmental contaminant levels, and
            studying the many effects of global climate change (e.g., habitat loss and biological
            invasions; ) ( Fig. 1 ). </p>
         <p> Developing floras as major platforms for documenting plant diversity as well as
            educating the public </p>
         <p> Many floras have been published (see ). An example of a significant new flora is the
            Flora of China (FOC). FOC represents a major achievement of international collaboration,
            yet it is still a static flora in the traditional sense. Similarly, the ongoing Flora of
            North America (FNA) series is progressing as paper-published volumes covering all
            vascular plant species found in North America north of Mexico . The format of FNA is
            similar to that of FOC. The funding for such major floras has been limited and hence the
            production of FNA has been slow. </p>
         <p> In the future, floras should be electronic. They should be online, searchable, with
            interactive keys, images of diagnostic characters,morphological descriptions, ecology,
            conservation status, distribution, collections-data to model future distributions, and
            have links to species biology. Several e-flora projects have done a good job and
            examples include the Jepson e-flora (http://ucjeps.berkeley.edu/IJM.html), the Flora da
            Reserva Ducke (http://peld.inpa.gov.br/publicacoes/guias), and Flora of Nepal On-line
            Accounts (http://padme.rbge.org. uk/floraofnepal/?page=onlineflora). </p>
         <p> In addition to floras, we also value electronic field guides in engaging the public on
            biodiversity. As an example, the Leafsnap project (http://leafsnap.com/) utilizes visual
            recognition software to help identify species from photographs. Leafsnap is a series of
            electronic field guides being developed to help identify tree species from photographs
            of their leaves and also contains high-resolution images of their flowers, fruits,
            petioles, seeds, and bark. It was originally developed in the United States but has
            become an international effort with pilot projects in the United Kingdom , and
            elsewhere. This type of project reaches broad audiences using personal electronic
            devises of individuals who are interested in the woody flora of their respective
            country. </p>
         <p> Charting next-generation monography and taxonomic revisions in the bioinformatics era </p>
         <p> A monograph of a natural group of plants (i.e., a subgenus, a genus, or a family) is a
            comprehensive account of all the taxonomic data relating to that group, involving the
            integration of previously known information with results of the monographer ’ s own
            research ( ). A monograph usually covers the entire geographic range of the taxonomic
            group and includes a complete synonymy, descriptions, and a detailed listing of
            ecological, geographical, cytological, chemical, and anatomical information (e.g., ),
            while a revision is restricted to a certain geographic region (e.g., ). Monographs and
            revisions differ primarily in their scope and completeness (see ; ). </p>
         <p> A more efficient taxonomic synthesis needs to be produced, not only for taxonomists,
            but also for other colleagues in biology and conservation. Monographic and revisionary
            studies should include ample experimental data to test species delimitations and to take
            full advantage of online resources (e.g., images of specimens including types , original
            species descriptions and subsequent early publications, and online and georeferenced
            collection data) and bioinformatics and analytical tools. So far few studies have been
            published utilizing all of the available resources. </p>
         <p> The systematics community needs to develop methods for more efficient taxonomic
            syntheses so that taxonomists can produce their work more quickly, making the monographs
            available to colleagues in other disciplines of biology such as conservation. published
            such an example of an e-monograph of the economically important papaya family,
            Caricaceae, in order to showcase the use of biodiversity informatics tools
            (http://herbaria.plants.ox.ac. uk/bol/caricaceae). The authors brought together all
            information on this family, including keys, species descriptions, specimen data, and
            morphological characters, and assigned the 230 published names to 34 recognized species
            and one hybrid. The treatment can be continuously updated electronically to improve the
            monograph ’ s quality and utility. Such studies should be undertaken regularly by the
            collectionsbased systematists. </p>
         <p> We herein outline a new workflow for taxonomic monographs ( Fig. 5 ), which utilizes
            the traditional strengths of synthesizing diverse collections-based taxonomic data and
            the capacity of online resources and bioinformatics tools. We also advocate that species
            distributions incorporate collections data and niche modeling, with the capacity to
            predict future range dynamics, broadening the utility of systematic treatments, keeping
            in mind, of course, that collections data from online sources may contain misidentified
            specimens ( ; ). With decreasing costs of DNA sequencing and genomic approaches, it is
            anticipated that 21st century monographs will have explicit tests of species concepts
            and criteria of species delimitations. Detailed distribution data coupled with niche
            modeling should enhance the conservation value of taxonomic monographs. We especially
            promote e-monographs for the next decades, for efficient and broader dissemination of
            scientific results. The format may allow some form of hard copy to be produced from
            online resources. For example, one may only need the taxa in a country for fieldwork,
            such an e-monograph should be able to generate such data, including a key for the region
            of interest. In short, the format should be versatile enough that users could set up
            what they desire to use. </p>
         <p> Revitalizing herbaria and natural history museums to engage the public more readily </p>
         <p> Museums and herbaria house natural history/systematics collections and are the window
            into biodiversity: past, present, and future ( , ; ; ). Natural history museums serve a
            critical role in preserving our Earth ’ s past and educating the public about the planet
            ( ; ). New challenges and evolving expectations are transforming museums and herbaria
            around the world. A critical issue concerns the role of science in a major museum. Wide
            applications of personal electronic devices (e.g., iPhone, iPad) and the availability of
            digital information provide us with new ways to engage the public and share with them
            information about our collections and science.In addition, natural history museums and
            herbaria have the potential to expand their roles in explaining scientific discoveries
            through public education. Citizen- and crowdsource science is another excellent way to
            engage the public. This area has been utilized by the community and clearly has
            tremendous potential to develop further. Perhaps this engagement with the public can be
            used to strengthen support for our institutions and combat what seems to be a rise in
            indifference by local and national governments as to the importance of museum and
            university collections. </p>
         <p> A successful example of advancing an herbarium with coordinated development in the
            strengths of both science and public programs is the University and Jepson Herbaria of
            the University of California , Berkeley. Their active research is complemented by the
            major role they play in the Consortium of California Herbaria
            (http://ucjeps.berkeley.edu/consortium/). They have helped pioneer data portal
            development and eFlora projects, and have an active public education program. In
            addition the molecular lab and the herbarium are well integrated and are incorporated in
            the plans for the future. Such examples should be sought out and highlighted by the
            systematics community. </p>
         <p>To appropriately appreciate and properly steward biodiversity, ecosystems, and cultural
            heritage on which our society depends, society needs an extensive and constantly
            expanding environmental knowledge base. It is imperative that this knowledge base be
            founded on vouchered observations of nature, and that this knowledge be accessible to
            all of society, not just one segment of it, so that we can learn to live sustainably on
            our planet. The systematics community needs to share their systematic knowledge with the
            general public more readily and engage intensely in public outreach and put more effort
            into fund-raising in the next decades. Furthermore, collection-based science is the soul
            of museums and herbaria and it should retain its central role in the multifaceted
            museums and herbaria of the 21st century.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Conclusions </title>
         <p> Natural history collections are important for inventorying the world ’ s biota,
            undertaking comparative evolutionary analyses, and understanding patterns and processes
            of biodiversity evolution and assembly of life on Earth ( ).Collections and collections
            data continue to play a significant role in transforming biology in the 21st century.The
            primary mission of natural history collections has been to serve the communities of
            systematic biology and biodiversity sciences, and the roles of collections in education
            and outreach have become more and more prominent in the 21st century (see also Fig. 4 ). </p>
         <p> Digitization of specimen collections and their availability online have progressed
            dramatically in the last decade ( ; ; ; ) with many new projects posting data. Yet the
            community still awaits major progress toward a userfriendly community-wide system to
            collect, edit, and publish collections-based research such as monographs, revisions,
            checklists, and floras, and to provide a means for the public to use and contribute to
            such efforts. More broadly used systems or tools such as BRAHMS have appeared attractive
            with the potential capacity to link collections, research, and outreach. Nevertheless,
            such a system needs the infusion of major funding to enhance its efficiency and its
            utility for the broader botanical community. </p>
         <p>With advances in bioinformatics, DNA systematics, and phylogenomics, collections-based
            systematics needs to be part of an important enterprise of a new era of taxonomy
            tackling important questions in evolution and gaining insights into biodiversity
            assembly. Isolated efforts on pure morphological and type-based taxonomy are still vital
            to our overall understanding but they need to be linked to larger efforts to be
            maximally useful. Collections-based systematics in the 21st century should be highly
            integrative, and represent part of an exciting and rigorous program of exploring the
            evolution of biodiversity in the field, in herbaria or museums, and in the laboratory
            using cutting-edge tools, methods and theories, and defining and classifying species and
            taxa objectively.</p>
         <p> Changes in the ICN, the availability of e-resources, and more rapid means of
            publications will facilitate information dissemination of future monographs (see also ).
            It is essential that authoritative information on nomenclature and species
            distributions, and high-quality data by taxonomists in revisions and monographs are made
            widely accessible to the biological community and the public, especially concerning
            numerous economically important plant groups ( ; ; ). Training in collections
            informatics needs to be emphasized and executed for future revisionary, monographic, and
            floristic projects. Botanical nomenclature is not easy for a newcomer to taxonomy and
            the systematics community should increase training in this area. </p>
         <p>The journey for charting the biosphere continues in the 21st century, for collecting and
            curating specimens, for scientific studies on biodiversity today, and for future
            generations. Collections today play an unprecedented role in documenting climatic and
            biodiversity changes, and shifts in the critical age of our time of the
            Anthropocene.</p>
         <p> Biological sciences have become highly collaborative and multidimensional in the last
            decades ( ). Collections-based systematists should recognize the interactive and dynamic
            roles of natural history collections in today ’ s biology. Nevertheless,
            collections-based systematics should not be eroded and side-tracked and should maintain
            its identity as an essential component of today ’ s biological sciences. We are aware
            that many natural history museums and herbaria face major challenges in funding and that
            there is an uphill battle in defending the need for such collections, but we think that
            taking a proactive role in promoting collectionsbased science is the best path to a
            stable future. </p>
         <p> Perhaps, the most critical need at present is a strong effort by the entire systematics
            community to strategically plan a Systematics Agenda 2050 and to move forward with
            collections-based approaches as its core to chart the biosphere, unravel the
            evolutionary assembly of the floras and faunas and their interactions in the era of
            genomics and bioinformatics, and conserve the biodiversity of our planet in the
            challenging times of the Anthropocene. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title> Acknowledgements </title>
         <p> We thank Robin Everly for library assistance, Vera Weterings (Picturae, the Netherlands
            ), and Suzanne de Jong-Kole and Gerard Thijsse (both L) for providing photos of the
            pipeline “ Herbarium digistreet ” and their permission to use these photos in this
            paper, Gary Krupnick for providing a photo of the United States National Herbarium, and
            Lucinda McDade and an anonymous reviewer for their constructive suggestions. Lucinda ’ s
            comments have reshaped the organization of this paper. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title> References </title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Anderson RP . 2012 . Harnessing the world ’ s biodiversity data:
                  Promise and peril in ecological niche modeling of species distributions . Annals
                  of the New York Academy of Sciences 1260 : 66 – 80 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Barkworth ME , Murrell ZE . 2012 . The US Virtual Herbarium: Working
                  with individual herbaria to build a national resource . ZooKeys 209 : 55 – 73 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Barnosky AD , Hadly EA , Bascompte J , Berlow EL , Brown JH ,
                  Fortelius M , Getz WM , Harte J , Hastings A , Marquet PA , Martinez ND , Mooers A
                  , Roopnarine P , Vermeij G , Williams JW , Gillespie R , Kitzes J , Marshall C ,
                  Matzke N , Mindell DP , Revilla E , Smith AB . 2012 . Approaching a state shift in
                  Earth ’ s biosphere . Nature 486 : 52 – 58 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Barnosky AD , Matzke N , Tomiya S , Wogan GOU , Swartz B , Quental
                  TB , Marshall C , McGuire JL , Lindsey EL , Maguire KC , Mersey B , Ferrer EA .
                  2011 . Has the Earth ’ s sixth mass extinction already arrived? Nature 471 : 51 –
                  57 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Beaman RS , Cellinese N. 2012 . Mass digitization of scientific
                  collections: New opportunities to transform the use of biological specimens and
                  underwrite biodiversity science . ZooKeys 209 : 7 – 17 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Blagoderov V , Kitching IJ , Livermore L , Simonsen TJ , Smith VS .
                  2012 . No specimen left behind: Industrial scale digitization of natural history
                  collections . ZooKeys 209 : 133 – 146 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Borer ET , Hosseini PR , Seabloom EW , Dobson AP . 2007 .
                  Pathogeninduced reversal of native dominance in a grassland community .
                  Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA 104 : 5473 – 5478 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Carvalho AF , Filer D , Renner SS . 2015 . Taxonomy in the
                  electronic age and an e-monograph of the papaya family (Caricaceae) as an example
                  . Cladistics 31 : 321 – 329 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Christenhusz MJM , Chase MW , Fay MF , Lumbsch T , Monro A ,
                  Vorontsova M , Zhang Z-Q. 2009 . A new international journal for rapid publication
                  of botanical taxonomy . Phytotaxa 1 : 1 – 2 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Claridge MF . 1995 . Introducing Systematics Agenda 2000 .
                  Biodiversity and Conservation 4 : 451 – 454 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Council of Heads of Australasian Herbaria . 2010 . Australian plant
                  census . Available at http://www.anbg.gov.au/chah/apc/index. html .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Council of Heads of Australasian Herbaria . 2013 . Australia ’ s
                  Virtual Herbarium . Available at http://avh.chah.org.au/ . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Croft J , Cross N , Hinchcliffe S , Lughadha EN , Stevens PF , West
                  JG , Whitbread G. 1999 . Plant names for the 21st century: The International Plant
                  Names Index, a distributed data source of general accessibility . Taxon 48 : 317 –
                  324 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Daly M , Herendeen PS , Guralnick RP , Westneat MW , McDade L. 2012
                  . Systematics Agenda 2020: The mission evolves . Systematic Biology 61 : 549 – 552
                  . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> de Candolle AP . 1867 . Lois de la nomenclature botanique adoptees
                  par le congres international de botanique tenu a Paris en ao ^ ut 1867 . Paris:
                  J.-B . Bailliere . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> de Candolle AP , de Candolle ALPP . 1824 – 1873. Prodromus
                  Systematis Naturalis Regni Vegetabilis, 17 vols . Paris: Sumptibus Sociorum
                  Treuttel et W urtz €. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Edwards EJ , Smith SA . 2010 . Phylogenetic analyses reveal the
                  shady history of C 4 grasses . Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA
                  107 : 2532 – 2537 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ellis EC , Antill EC , Kreft H. 2012 . All is not loss: Plant
                  biodiversity in the Anthropocene . PLoS ONE 7 ( 1 ): e 30535 . doi:
                  10.1371/journal.pone.0030535 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Emshwiller E , Theim T , Grau A , Nina V , Terrazas F. 2009 .
                  Origins of domestication and polyploidy in oca ( Oxalis tuberosa ; Oxalidaceae).
                  3. AFLP data of oca and four wild, tuber-bearing taxa . American Journal of Botany
                  96 : 1839 – 1848 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Feeley KJ . 2012 . Distributional migrations, expansions, and
                  contractions of tropical plant species as revealed in dated herbarium records .
                  Global Change Biology 18 : 1335 – 1341 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Flann C. 2011 . BioCode: Third time lucky? Zootaxa 2874 : 38 – 40 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Frodin DG . 2001 . Guide to standard floras of the world . 2nd ed .
                  Cambridge: Cambridge University Press . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Funk VA . 2003 a. The importance of herbaria . Plant Science
                  Bulletin 49 : 94 – 95 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Funk VA . 2003 b. 100 uses for an herbarium (well at least 72) .
                  ASPT Newsletter 17 : 17 – 19 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Funk VA . 2006 . Floras: A model for biodiversity studies or a thing
                  of the past? Taxon 55 : 581 – 588 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Garcia-Milagros E , Funk VA . 2010 . Improving the use of
                  information from museum specimens: Using Google Earth to georeference Guiana
                  Shield specimens in the US National Herbarium . Frontiers of Biogeography 2.3 : 71
                  – 77 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Greuter W , Garrity G , Hawksworth DL , Jahn R , Kirk PM , Knapp S ,
                  McNeill J , Michel E , Patterson DJ , Pyle R , Tindall BJ . 2011 . Draft BioCode
                  (2011): Principles and rules regulating the naming of organisms . Taxon 60 : 201 –
                  212 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Greuter W , Hawksworth DL , McNeill J , Mayo MA , Minelli A , Sneath
                  PHA , Tindall BJ , Trehane P , Tubbs P , IUBS/IUMS International Committee for
                  Bionomenclature. 1996 . Draft BioCode: The prospective international rules for the
                  scientific names of organisms . Taxon 45 : 349 – 372 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Haston El , Cubey R , Pullan M , Atkins H , Harris DJ . 2012 .
                  Developing integrated workflows for the digitisation of herbarium specimens using
                  a modular and scalable approach . ZooKeys 209 : 93 – 102 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hoek WZ . 2008 . The last glacial-interglacial transition . Episodes
                  31 : 226 – 229 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> ICZN . 1999 . International code of zoological nomenclature . 4 th
                  ed . London: The International Trust for Zoological Nomenclature .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Jablonski D. 1994 . Extinctions in the fossil record . Philosophical
                  Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences 34 : 11 – 17 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Johnson KG , Brooks SJ , Fenberg PB , Glover AG , James KE , Lister
                  AM , Michel E , Spencer M , Todd JA , Valsami-Jones E , Young JR , Stewart JR .
                  2011 . Climate change and biosphere response: Unlocking the collections vault .
                  BioScience 61 : 147 – 153 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Johnson KR . 2015 . Surrounded by science: Tracing the evolution of
                  modern museums of science and natural history . Science 347 : 618 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kress WJ . 2004 . Paper floras: How long will they last? A review of
                  flowering plants of the neotropics . American Journal of Botany 91 : 2124 – 2127 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kress WJ , Penev L. 2011 . Innovative electronic publication in
                  plant systematics: PhytoKeys and the changes to the “ Botanical Code ” accepted at
                  the XVIII International Botanical Congress in Melbourne . PhytoKeys 6 : 1 – 4 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lane MA . 1996 . Roles of natural history collections . Annals of
                  the Missouri Botanical Garden 83 : 536 – 545 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lapage SP , Sneath PHA , Lessel EF eds. 1992 . International code of
                  nomenclature of bacteria: Bacteriological code . 1990 Revision . Washington, D.C.:
                  ASM Press . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lavoie C. 2013 . Biological collections in an ever changing world:
                  Herbaria as tools for biogeographical and environmental studies . Perspectives in
                  Plant Ecology, Evolution and Systematics 15 : 68 – 76 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lenton TM . 2011 . Early warning of climate tipping points . Nature
                  Climate Change 1 : 201 – 209 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Loarie SR , Carter BE , Hayhoe K , McMahon S , Moe R , Knight CA ,
                  Ackerly DD . 2008 . Climate change and the future of California ’ s endemic flora
                  . PLoS ONE 3 : e 2502 . doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0002502 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lughadha E. 2004 . Towards a working list of all known plant species
                  . Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences 359 : 681
                  – 687 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lujan NK , Page LM . 2015 . Libraries of life. New York Times 27
                  February page A25. [online] . Available from http://www.nytimes.com/ 2015/ 02/27
                  /opinion/libraries-of-life.html?_r=0 [accessed 1 May 2015 ]. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Lumbsch T , Miller AN , Begerow D , Penev L. 2011 . MycoKeys,or why
                  we need a new journal in mycology? MycoKeys 1 : 1 – 6 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Malmstrom CM , Shu R , Linton EW , Newton LA , Cook MA . 2007 .
                  Barley yellow dwarf viruses (BYDVs) preserved in herbarium specimens illuminate
                  historical disease ecology of invasive and native grasses . Journal of Ecology 95
                  : 1153 – 1166 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Marhold K , Stuessy T , Agababian M , Agosti D , Alford MH , Crespo
                  A , Crisci JV , Dorr LJ , Ferencova Z , Frodin D , Geltman DV , Kilian N , Linder
                  HP , Lohmann LG , Oberprieler C , Penev L , Smith GF , Thomas W , Tulig M ,
                  Turland N , Zhang XC . 2013 . The future of botanical monography: Report from an
                  international workshop , 12 – 16 March 2012 , Smolenice, Slovak Republic. Taxon 62
                  : 4 – 20 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Marshall CR . 2006 . Explaining the Cambrian “ explosion ” of
                  animals . Annual Review of Earth and Planetary Sciences 34 : 355 – 384 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> McElwain JC , Chaloner WG . 1995 . Stomatal density and index of
                  fossil plants track atmospheric carbon dioxide in the Paleozoic . Annals of Botany
                  76 : 389 – 395 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> McNeill J , Barrie FR , Buck WR , Demoulin V , Greuter W ,
                  Hawksworth DL , Herendeen PS , Knapp S , Marhold K , Prado J , Prud ’ homme Van
                  Reine WF , Smith GF , Wiersema JH , Turland NJ . 2012 . International code of
                  nomenclature for algae, fungi, and plants (Melbourne code) adopted by the 18th
                  International Botanical Congress, Melbourne, Australia, July 2011 . Regnum
                  Vegetabile 154 . Ruggell: ARG Gantner Verlag KG. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Meier R , Dikow T. 2004 . Significance of specimen databases from
                  taxonomic revisions for estimating and mapping the global species diversity of
                  invertebrates and repatriating reliable specimen data . Conservation Biology 18 :
                  478 – 488 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Miller J , Dikow T , Agosti D , Sautter G , Catapano T , Penev L ,
                  Zhang ZQ , Pentcheff D , Pyle R , Blum S , Parr C , Freeland C , Garnett T , Ford
                  LS , Muller B , Smith L , Strader G , Georgiev T , Benichou L. 2012 . From
                  taxonomic literature to cybertaxonomic content . BMC Biology 10 : 87 . doi:
                  10.1186/1741-7007-10-87 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Miller JS , Funk VA , Wagner WL , Barrie F , Hoch PC , Herendeen P.
                  2011 . Outcomes of the 2011 Botanical Nomenclature Section at the XVIII
                  International Botanical Congress . PhytoKeys 5 : 1 – 3 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> O ’ Connell AF , Gilbert AT , Hatfield JS . 2004 . Contribution of
                  natural history collection data to biodiversity assessment in national parks .
                  Conservation Biology 18 : 1254 – 1261 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Panchen ZA , Primack RB , Anisko T , Lyons RE . 2012 . Herbarium
                  specimens, photographs, and field observations show Philadelphia area plants are
                  responding to climate change . American Journal of Botany 99 : 751 – 756 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Penev L , Agosti D , Georgiev T , Catapano T , Miller J , Blagoderov
                  V , Roberts D , Smith VS , Brake I , Ryrcroft S , Scott B , Johnson NF , Morris RA
                  , Sautter G , Chavan V , Robertson T , Remsen D , Stoev P , Parr C , Knapp S ,
                  Kress WJ , Thompson CF , Erwin T. 2010 a. Semantic tagging of and semantic
                  enhancements to systematics papers: ZooKeys working examples . ZooKeys 50 : 1 – 16
                  . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Penev L , Kress W , Knapp S , Li DZ , Renner S. 2010 b. Fast,
                  linked, and open – the future of taxonomic publishing for plants: Launching the
                  journal PhytoKeys . PhytoKeys 1 : 1 – 14 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Powers KE , Prather AL , Cook JA , Wooley J , Bart HL Jr , Monfils
                  AK , Sierwald P. 2014 . Revolutionizing the use of natural history collections in
                  education . Science Education Reviews 13 : 24 – 33 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Primack D , Imbres C , Primack RB , Miller-Rushing AJ , Del Tredici
                  P. 2004 . Herbarium specimens demonstrate earlier flowering times in response to
                  warming in Boston . American Journal of Botany 91 : 1260 – 1264 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Robbirt KM , Davy AJ , Hutchings MJ , Roberts DL . 2011 . Validation
                  of biological collections as a source of phenological data for use in climate
                  change studies: A case study with the Orchid Ophrys sphegodes . Journal of Ecology
                  99 : 235 – 241 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> SA 2000 (Systematics Agenda 2000). 1994. Charting the biosphere: A
                  global initiative to discover, describe and classify the world ’ s species.
                  Technical report . New York: American Society of Plant Taxonomists, Society of
                  Systematic Biologists, and the Willi Hennig Society . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Schilthuizen M , Vairappan CS , Slade EM , Mann DJ , Miller JA .
                  2015 . Specimens as primary data: Museums and ‘ open science ’ . Trends in Ecology
                  and Evolution 30 : 237 – 238 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Schmid R , Dorr LJ . 2009 . TL2/TL2S done!:15 volumes 1976 –
                  2009,11,227 pages, about 37,600 entries. Taxon 58 : 689 – 691 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Scotland RW , Wood JRI . 2012 . Accelerating the pace of taxonomy .
                  Trends in Ecology and Evolution 27 : 415 – 416 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Spooner DM , Rodriguez F , Polgar Z , Ballard HE , Jansky SH . 2008
                  . Genomic origins of potato polyploids: GBSSI gene sequencing data . Crop Science
                  48 (S 1 ): S27 – S36 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Stuessy TF . 1993 . The role of creative monography in the
                  biodiversity crisis . Taxon 42 : 313 – 321 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Stuessy TF , Lack HW eds. 2011 . Monographic plant systematics:
                  Fundamental assessment of plant biodiversity. Regnum Vegetabile 153 . Ruggell: ARG
                  Gantner Verlag KG . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Suarez AV , Tsutsui ND . 2004 . The value of museum collections for
                  research and society . BioScience 54 : 66 – 74 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Thomson KS . 2005 . Natural history museum collections in the 21st
                  Century. actionbioscience [online] . Available from http://www.
                  actionbioscience.org/evolution/thomson.html [accessed March 15, 2015 ].
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Tripp EA , Hoagland KE . 2013 . Typifying an era in biology through
                  synthesis of biodiversity information: Achievements and impediments . Taxon 62 :
                  899 – 911 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Tulig M , Tarnowsky N , Bevans M , Anthony Kirchgessner , Thiers BM
                  . 2012 . Increasing the efficiency of digitization workflows for herbarium
                  specimens . Zookeys 209 : 103 – 113 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Turland N. 2013 . The code decoded. A user ’ s guide to the
                  International Code of Nomenclature for algae, fungi, and plants. Regnum Vegetabile
                  155 . K€ onigstein, Germany: Koeltz Scientific Books . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Vollmar A , Macklin JA , Ford LS . 2010 . Natural history specimen
                  digitization: Challenges and concerns . Biodiversity Informatics 7 : 93 – 112 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wen J. 2011 . Systematics and biogeography of Aralia L.
                  (Araliaceae): Revision of Aralia sects. Aralia , Humiles , Nanae , and
                  Sciadodendron . Contributions from the United States National Herbarium 57 : 1 –
                  172 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wen J , Ree RH , Ickert-Bond S , Nie Z-L , Funk VA . 2013 .
                  Biogeography: Where do we go from here? Taxon 62 : 912 – 927 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wen J , Shi W. 2012 . Revision of the Maddenia clade of Prunus
                  (Rosaceae) . PhytoKeys 11 : 39 – 59 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wheeler QD ed. 2008 . The new taxonomy. (The systematics association
                  special volumes series; 76) . Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wheeler QD . 2010 . What would NASA do? Mission-critical
                  infrastructure for species exploration . Systematics and Biodiversity 8 : 11 – 15
                  . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wheeler QD , Knapp S , Stevenson DW , Stevenson J , Blum SD , Boom
                  BM , Borisy GG , Buizer JL , De Carvalho MR , Cibrian A , Donoghue MJ , Doyle V ,
                  Gerson EM , Graham CH , Graves P , Graves SJ , Guralnick RP , Hamilton AL , Hanken
                  J , Law W , Lipscomb DL , Lovejoy TE , Miller H , Miller JS , Naeem S , Novacek MJ
                  , Page LM , Platnick NI , Porter-Morgan H , Raven PH , Solis MA , Valdecasas AG ,
                  Van Der Leeuw S , Vasco A , Vermeulen N , Vogel J , Walls RL , Wilson EO , Woolley
                  JB . 2012 . Mapping the biosphere: Exploring species to understand the origin,
                  organization and sustainability of biodiversity . Systematics and Biodiversity 10
                  : 1 – 20 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wilson EO . 1992 . The diversity of life . Cambridge: Harvard
                  University Press . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Woodward FI . 1987 . Stomatal numbers are sensitive to increases in
                  CO 2 from pre-industrial levels . Nature 327 : 617 – 618 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Yesson C , Brewer PW , Sutton T , Caithness N , Pahwa JS , Burgess M
                  , Gray WA , White RJ , Jones AC , Bisby FA , Culham A. 2007 . How global is the
                  Global Biodiversity Information Facility? PLoS ONE 2 ( 11 ): e 1124 . doi:
                  10.1371/journal.pone.0001124 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zalasiewicz J , Williams M , Haywood A , Ellis M. 2011 . The
                  Anthropocene: A new epoch of geological time? Philosophical Transactions of the
                  Royal Society A 369 : 835 – 841 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhang Z-Q. 2006 . The first five years of Zootaxa . Zootaxa 1111 :
                  68 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhang Z-Q. 2008 . Contributing to the progress of descriptive
                  taxonomy . Zootaxa 1968 : 65 – 68 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
