<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Journal of Hymenoptera Research</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/jhr.53.9902</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Two unusual new species of Aulacus Jurine (Hymenoptera, Aulacidae) from
               South America</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2016</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Pristaulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Xiphydriidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus costulatus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus costulatus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> flavus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> subflavus </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus flavus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus subflavus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus flavus Smith</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus subflavus Smith</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus flavus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Introduction </p>
         <p> Both genera of <tp:taxon-name>Aulacidae</tp:taxon-name> ,
               <tp:taxon-name>Pristaulacus</tp:taxon-name> Kieffer and
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name> Jurine, are widespread in the Neotropics.
            Twelve Neotropical species of <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name> were listed by .
            Subsequently, 13 species have been added ( , , ; ). Here, I describe two species very
            different from other <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name> species. </p>
         <p> Hosts are not known, but elsewhere aulacids are parasitoids of wood-boring
               <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Xiphydriidae</tp:taxon-name> ) and
               <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name> (mainly Buprestidae and
               <tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae</tp:taxon-name> ) ( , ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Materials and methods </p>
         <p>Abbreviations: AEI, American Entomological Institute, Gainesville, FL; RBINS, Royal
            Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences, Bruxelles; CNC, Canadian National Collection of
            Insects, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada; MCZ, Museum of Comparative Zoology, Cambridge, MA;
            USNM, National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington DC.</p>
         <p>Images were acquired through an EntoVision micro-imaging system. This system included a
            Leica M16 or Leica DRMB compound microscope with a JVC KY-75U 3-CCD digital video camera
            or a GT-Vision Lw11057C-SCI digital camera attached that fed image data to a notebook or
            desktop computer. The program Cartograph 6.6.0 was then used to merge an image series
            into a single in-focus image.</p>
         <p> Terminology follows and . Descriptions are based on the female holotypes. The species
            used for comparison (Figs 1-3) is <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus costulatus</tp:taxon-name>
            (Kieffer), which occurs in Brazil. The specimen illustrated is from Santa Catarina, Nova
            Teutonia, 27°11'S , 52°23'W , 300-500 m, Nov. 1966, Fritz Plaumann. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Results</p>
         <p> The two species described below belong to <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name> as
            currently defined (e.g., , ; ). They are distinguished from other
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name> species in the first couplet in the key below.
            No other species of <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name> share the flat mesoscutum,
            tubercles on the mesonotum, axillae, and scutellum, enlarged pronotum, and enlarged
            genae. The exact relationship with other species of
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name> is unknown. considered the genus paraphyletic,
            and the phylogenetic classification remains unresolved. A study of world
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus</tp:taxon-name> on a much more comprehensive basis is needed
            to determine relationships of the two species described here. </p>
         <p>Key to species</p>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus flavus Smith</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Figs 4-9 </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Description.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> Female (holotype). Length, 9.5 mm; forewing 7.0 mm; ovipositor 4.5 mm. Antenna
               black; scape yellow. Head yellow with frons and ocellar area and vertex black; lower
               inner orbits, area below antennae, genae and upper inner orbits with spot extending
               behind each lateral ocellus yellow. Mesosoma with propleuron black; pronotum yellow,
               pleurae black with orange spot on lower part of mesepisternum, and mesoscutum,
               metanotum, and propodeum black. Fore and midlegs orange; apical 1 or 2 tarsomeres
               dark; hind leg black with extreme apex of coxae, both trochanteral segments, extreme
               apex of femur and extreme base of tibia and tarsus except for apical tarsomere black.
               Metasoma orange with tergum 1 black dorsally interrupted by transverse orange band at
               center, terga 2 to apex each with central black spot, appearing as a longitudinal
               black stripe; sheath black. Wings hyaline with apex black; veins and stigma black.
               Head (Figs 5-7): Shiny; clypeus and supraclypeal area rugose, with scattered pits
               separated by flat shiny interspaces several times diameter of an ocellus; pits
               densest on frons. Antennal length about 3.0 x head width; first antennomere longer
               than broad, second antennomere about as long as broad, third and fourth antennomeres
               subequal in length. Lower interocular distance subequal to eye height. Malar space
               about 0.25 x eye length. Head behind eyes from above slightly convex behind eyes; in
               lateral view, lower gena markedly produced with greatest width of gena more than half
               width of eye. Mesosoma (Figs 4, 8, 9): Shiny with fine white hairs; longs hairs
               laterally and ventrally on propleuron. Propleuron with dorsolateral longitudinal
               carina; area above carina slightly dulled, microsculptured; area below carina
               punctured with flat interspaces equal to or slightly more than puncture diameters.
               Pronotum shiny with widely scattered punctures; vertical scrobiculate line near
               posterior margin; front and lower margins flangelike. Mesoscutum shiny, with pair of
               tubercles on anterior margin, area anterior to tubercles punctate, posterior to
               tubercles with about 10 strong widely spaced transverse carinae; notauli meeting
               transscutal articulation at separate points; axilla with one or two transverse
               carinae, each with small tubercle; mesoscutellm with 3 or 4 transverse carinae, with
               small tubercle near posterior margin, area lateral to mesoscutellum rugulose. Meso-
               and metapleurae finely punctate, with small shiny impunctate area on upper halves.
               Propodeum coarsely rugulose. Tarsal claws simple. Hind coxa about 2.2 x longer than
               broad, shiny, punctate, punctures denser and somewhat more rugulose on sides and
               venter; without projecting ventral lobe; ovipositor guide a very shallow, almost
               indiscernible oblique groove near apex on inner surface. Hind tarsus about 1.2 x
               length of hind tibia; hind basitarsus subequal in length to remaining tarsomeres
               combined. Forewing with 2-Rs+M long, longer than first discal cell. Hind wing with 3
               hamuli. Metasoma: Shiny with short, fine white hairs, densest on apical 3 segments.
               Ovipositor about 0.7 length of forewing </p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Male. Length, 8.5 mm. Color and structure similar to female.</p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type material">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Type material.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> Holotype female, "Brasilien, Rondon [ Parana ], 24°38'B, 54°07'L, 500 m, May 1953,
               Fritz Plaumann" with red holotype label (AEI). Paratypes: BRAZIL: Same data as for
               holotype (3 ♀, 2 ♂), same data except for dates, X.4.1952 (1 ♂), X.12.1952 (1 ♀),
               X.16.1952 (1 ♂), X.22.1952 (1 ♂), X.23.1952 (1 ♂), X.26.1952 (1 ♀), X.30.1952 (1 ♀),
               X.31.1952 (1 ♀), XI.6.1952 (1 ♂), XI.8. 1952 (1 ♀), XI.12.1952 (1 ♂), XI.14.1952 (1
               ♂), XI.15.1962 (1 ♂), XI.16.1952 (1 ♂), XI.20.1952 (2 ♂), XI.23.1952 (1 ♂),
               XI.25.1952 (2 ♂, 1 USNM), XI.28.1952 (1 ♂), XI .29.1952 (1 ♂), XII.1.1952 (1 ♂),
               XII.4.1952 (1 ♂), XII.6.1952 (1 ♂), XII.7.1952 (1 ♂), XII.10.1952 (1 ♂), I.2.1953 (1
               ♂), III.1953 (1 ♀), III.29.1953 (1 ♀), IV.1953 (3 ♀, 1 USNM), IV.13.1953 (1 ♀),
               IV.14.1953 (1 ♀), V.1953, XI.13.1953 (1 ♀), X .12.1962 (♀ CNC), X.16.1062 (1 ♀ CNC),
               X.26.1962 (1 ♀ CNC); Rio Caraguata [Mato Grosso do Sul], 1°48'B, 52°27'L, 400 m,
               XI.4.1953, Fritz Plaumann (1 ♀), same except dates, III.1953 (1 ♀); III.30.1953 (1♀,
               1♂), IV.1953 (1 ♀), XI.21.1953 (1 ♀), XI.22.1953 (1 ♂), XI.24.1953 (1 ♂), XI.25.1953
               (1 ♀), XI.30.1953 (1 ♂); Nova Teutonia, Santa Catarina, II.9.1940, Fritz Plaumann,
               same except dates, I.#.1941 (2 ♀), I.17.1941 (1 ♀), XII.9.1942 (1 ♀ MCZ), X.27.1952
               (1 ♀), XI.1.1952 (1 ♀), VI.1953 (1 ♀); Encruzilhada, Bahia, XI.'74, 980 m, M.
               Alvarenga (1 ♀); Itapetinca, Bahia, 800 m, XI.'69, F. M. Oliveira (1 ♀). Deposited at
               AEI, except where noted. </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Distribution.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> Brazil: Bahia, Mato Grosso do Sul, Parana , Santa Catarina. Apparently most common
               in southern Brazil. </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Etymology.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>From Latin meaning yellow, with reference to the entirely yellow pronotum.</p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="remarks">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Remarks.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> There are slight variations in color, especially the amount of orange on the
               mesonotum and size of black marks on the metasoma. The entirely yellow pronotum seems
               to be constant in the specimens examined. Size is relatively stable, the length
               varying only by +/- 1.0 mm; proportions of the ovipositor and forewing remain the
               same regardless of length. </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus subflavus Smith</tp:taxon-name> sp. n. Figs 10-15 </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> Description . </p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> Female (holotype). Length, 8.0 mm; forewing 6.0 mm; ovipositor 4.2 mm. Similar to
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aulacus flavus</tp:taxon-name> except for the following
               differences: Pronotum white on dorsal half, black on ventral half (Figs 10, 15). Head
               (Figs 11-13) with eyes larger; lower interocular distance 0.8 x eye height; in dorsal
               view straight behind eyes; in lateral view lower gena less produced with greatest
               width of gena half or less width of eye. </p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Male. Length, 7.5 mm. Color and structure similar to female.</p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type material">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Type material.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Holotype female, "Coll. I.R.Sc.N.B., French Guyana, Kourou, Malaise trap (Piste
               Soumourou), 15-23.VIII.2001, Leg. D. Faure" with red holotype label (RBINS).
               Paratypes: FRENCH GUIANA: Same data as for holotype (14 ♀, RBINS, USNM); Coll.
               I.R.Sc.N.B., Kourou, Piste Skoumourou, Malaise trap, XI.2002, Leg. D. Faure (9 ♀, 5
               ♂, RBINS, USNM); Coll. I.R.Sc.N.B., Kourou, Piste Soumourou, Malaise trap,
               1-8.IX.2001, Leg. D. Faure (1 ♀, RBINS). GUYANA: Kamakusa, British Guiana, IX.1922,
               H. Lang, J. Bequaert Collections (1 ♀, MCZ).</p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="other specimens">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Other specimens.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> BRAZIL: Sinop, M. Grosso, 12°31'S , 55°37'W , X.1974, M. Alvarenga (2 ♀, AEI); Vila
               Vera, 12°30'S , 50°30'W , October 1973, M. Alvarenga (2 ♀, AEI). </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Distribution.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Brazil: Mato Grosso; French Guiana; Guyana.</p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Etymology.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>From the Latin partly yellow, referring to the usual half yellow and half black
               pronotum.</p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="remarks">
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p>Remarks.</p>
         </sec>
         <sec sec-type="inferred">
            <title>Orphanage</title>
            <p> The "other specimens" are structurally like this species but the mesosoma is
               entirely yellow orange and I prefer not to include them in the type series. The
               bicolored pronotum seems to be a helpful character, though several specimens have an
               entirely yellow pronotum. The side lobes of the mesonotum may be entirely black or
               partly orange. The length varies only by about +/- 0.7 mm; the proportions of the
               ovipositor and forewing remain the same regardless of size. </p>
         </sec>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Acknowledgments </p>
         <p>I thank J. Constant (RBINS), John Huber (CNC), David Wahl (AEI), and Philip D. Perkins
            (MCZ) for loan of specimens. Mention of trade names of commercial products in this
            publication is solely for the purpose of providing specific information and does not
            imply recommendation or endorsement by the USDA. USDA is an equal opportunity provider
            and employer.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Huber, JT , Sharkey, MJ , Goulet, H , Huber, JT , 1993 . Hymenoptera
                  of the world: An identification guide to families . Research Branch, Agriculture
                  Canada : 13 - 59 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Jennings, JT , Austin, AD ,, 2004 . Biology and host relationships
                  of aulacid and gasteruptiid wasps (Hymenoptera: Evanioidea). . In: Austin, AD ,
                  Dowton, M , Eds., Hymenoptera, Evolution, Biodiversity and Biological Control .
                  CSIRO Publishing, Collingwood : 154 - 164 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Smith, DR , 2001 . World catalog of the family Aulacidae
                  (Hymenoptera). . Contributions on Entomology, Inernational 4 : 263 - 319
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Smith, DR , 2005a . Aulacidae (Hymenoptera) of northern South
                  America, emphasizing Colombia. . Transactions of the American Entomological
                  Society 131 : 217 - 253 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Smith, DR , 2005b . Review of the Aulacidae (Hymenoptera) of Chile
                  and adjacent Argentina. . Proceedings of the Entomological Society of Washington
                  107 : 820 - 834 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Smith, DR , 2008 . Aulacidae of the southwestern United States,
                  Mexico, and Central America (Hymenoptera). . Beitraege zur Entomologie 58 : 267 -
                  355 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Smith, DR , Carvalho, DV de , 2010 . Three new species of Aulacidae
                  (Hymenoptera) from Brazil. . Proceedings of the Entomological Society of
                  Washington 112 : 140 - 148 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Turrisi, GF , Jennings, JT , Vilhelmsen, L , 2009 . Phylogeny and
                  generic concepts of the parasitoid wasp family Aulacidae (Hymenoptera:
                  Evanioidea). . Invertebrate Systematics 23 : 27 - 29 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
