<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>One Ecosystem</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/oneeco.6.e67320</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A protocol for modelling generalised biological responses using latent
               variables in structural equation models</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>08</day>
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group/>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Introduction </p>
         <p> The quest for generalisation in the ecological sciences is a fundamental challenge. One
            way that a general reaction by a system or organism can be detected is if there is a
            multivariate response where numerous individual properties change in concerted fashion.
            While such concerted reactions are often described using standard multivariate
            statistical analyses, causal investigations of the nature of integrated multivariate
            responses fall primarily into the purview of latent variable structural equation
            modelling (LVSEM, , ). LVSEM represents a foundational method in quantitative training
            in the fields of psychology and sociology, while other fields, including ecology, have
            historically focused on observed variable models (e.g. OVSEM, aka path analysis). While
            there has been an increased use of LVs in ecological models in the past 20 years (e.g. ,
            , , , ), only a few descriptions of the methods have emerged ( , , ). More importantly,
            the depth of coverage of the subject in ecological treatments is much less than in
            social science treatments, leaving untapped the full potential for LVSEM to advance
            ecological understanding. In this paper, we present a protocol designed to guide
            ecological researchers through the evaluation of hypotheses about generalised responses
            using LVSEM. </p>
         <p> Fig. 1 provides a high-level perspective of the problem of interest in this paper. The
            particular form of representation here is referred to as a Structural Equation
            Meta-Model (SEMM), which represents the conceptual entities of interest in the study and
            the hypothesised causal connections amongst them ( ). SEMMs are meant to solve a
            ubiquitous problem in statistical modelling, which is that our theories exist at a
            general level, while our fully-specified statistical models are highly specific. SEMMs
            are meant to facilitate an explicit linkage between our theoretical ideas and our
            specific findings. Typically, this step in the science process is implicit and, thus,
            the question of how our results generalise goes undescribed (and presumably only lightly
            considered). </p>
         <p> The hypothesis represented in Fig. 1 is very general. It simply posits that the
            response of a system to perturbation can be understood through an evaluation of the
            mediating mechanisms. In this paper, a primary emphasis is on the nature of the
            response. We are especially interested in the degree to which the subjects of study
            exhibit a tightly integrated suite of changes. Several theoretical possibilities exist.
            In highly integrated responses, multivariate reactions will manifest strong and
            consistent correlations amongst measured indicator variables. At the other extreme,
            non-integrated responses will manifest reactions, such that each measured property acts
            independently from the others. Between those extremes are cases where there are mixtures
            of general and individual responses. All of these details are of interest if we are to
            develop an understanding of the study system and if we wish to properly represent
            hypotheses that can explain the observed data. That said, a substantial degree of
            intercorrelation amongst measured indicator variables is required if general responses
            are expected to conform to the requirements for latent variables. LVSEM allows us to
            empirically test hypotheses about the latent responses so as to arrive at a model with
            both theoretical and empirical support. </p>
         <p> Fig. 2 illustrates the LVSEM approach to representing a general multivariate response.
            Conceptually, Fig. 2 describes the case where there is some underlying cause for the
            various specific, yet correlated, responses. It is characteristic that the underlying
            cause is not directly observed. Instead, we learn about the latent properties of the
            underlying cause through the patterns of correlations amongst specific manifestations.
            Statistically, Fig. 2 represents a very particular hypothesis. For those not accustomed
            to causal modelling, an important shift in thinking is required to differentiate one's
            logic from that associated with descriptive statistical models. For example, we might
            employ principal components analysis to estimate a set of parameters consistent with
            Fig. 2 . Such parameters would be purely descriptive, a summary of the data and fail to
            correspond to any particular causal explanation. In LVSEM, the model evaluated is
            treated as a causal hypothesis, which, in this case, is that the intercorrelations
            amongst indicator variables can be adequately explained by a single common causal
            process. All other sources of variation for the indicators are assumed to be
            independent. There are many ways in which data may fail to confirm this hypothesis,
            leading us to construct alternative causal hypotheses in order to explain what is going
            on. </p>
         <p> Numerous complexities can be encountered when analysing models containing latent
            variables with multiple indicators. It is probably safe to say that the available
            literature may be inadequate for the beginning user of SEM to navigate the various
            diagnostics and decisions required for such models. Our primary objective in this paper
            is to provide a series of questions that can guide the investigator through the process.
            Our advice is targeted for the general objective outlined in Fig. 1 and may have to be
            supplemented for models with more complex purposes. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="the basic analytic machinery for lvsem">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>The Basic Analytic Machinery for LVSEM</p>
         <p> There exist many technical descriptions of the analytical machinery used to implement
            LVSEM. Here, we provide a non-technical summary and refer the reader to for a detailed
            treatment. A concise presentation of the equations and notation corresponding to our
            presentation can be found in Suppl. material 1. </p>
         <p> Fig. 3 provides a more complete representation of the kind of model we seek to evaluate
            in this paper. Here, we see that, in addition to a latent variable for the general
            response and its four indicator variables, our hypothesis includes latent variables for
            a specific perturbation and a hypothesised mediator variable that explains the effect of
            perturbation on the general response. The model also proposes that the Perturbation can
            affect the General Response independently from the Mediator and the Mediator can affect
            particular responses (e.g. response4) to some degree differently from the other
            responses. </p>
         <p>The classical approach to implementing SEM involves the analysis of covariances. For
            this, the rows of raw data are converted into a variance-covariance square matrix.
            Hypothesised models represent a set of expectations about the patterns of covariances
            that should be found in data. Typically, covariance modelling estimates the parameters
            of the causal diagram via maximum likelihood while respecting the assumed causal
            relationships specified in the causal graph. Covariance SEM also produces a statistic
            that summarises the differences between the observed covariances and those predicted
            while agreeing with the model structure and tests the null hypothesis that the observed
            and predicted covariances are equal, except for random sampling variation. Failure to
            reject this null hypothesis is evidence that the assumed causal structure is
            correct.</p>
         <p> For LVSEM, model structure is described using equations representing the relationships
            between latent variables and their indicators and equations describing relationships
            amongst latent variables (Suppl. material 1). For the model in Fig. 3 , software would
            implement the variables Specific Perturbation and Specific Mediator as latent variables
            with single indicators in order to be consistent in the use of separate matrices for
            relationships amongst latent variables and relationships between latent and observed
            variables (Suppl. material 1, Table S1.1). Variables are described as exogenous if they
            serve only as predictors of other variables (no arrows pointing to them) and endogenous
            if predicted by other variables (possess incoming arrows). In Fig. 3 , Perturbation is
            the only exogenous variable, all others are endogenous. The Greek symbols used to denote
            various parameters correspond to the matrices used to implement the models. The lambda
            matrix contains the model-implied weights between latent variables and their indicators,
            the beta matrix contains the effects of endogenous variables on other endogenous
            variables and the gamma matrix contains the effects of exogenous variables on endogenous
            variables. Two additional matrices are the psi matrix, which contains the latent error
            terms (zeta 1 and 2), as well as their intercorrelations, if such are specified and the
            theta-epsilon matrix, which includes the errors for indicators (epsilon 1-4) and their
            intercorrelations, if any. The practical value of these matrices is that they permit a
            great flexibility in model specification, allowing for error correlations, reciprocal
            effects and a great many customised specifications. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec
         sec-type="an ecological example: the responses of grape nutritive qualities to intensity of agricultural management">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>An Ecological Example: The Responses of Grape Nutritive Qualities to Intensity of
            Agricultural Management</p>
         <p> conducted a study of Swiss vineyards managed under different intensities of weed
            management, which resulted in different levels of non-crop plant biodiversity. Grape
            qualities of known importance to wine-making (nitrogen, sugars, tartric acid and malic
            acid) were measured and served as indicators of the general property "Grape Qualities".
            Features of the spontaneous vegetation that were measured included total cover, total
            species richness and abundance of nitrogen fixing plants. The empirical measurements
            corresponding with the concepts of theoretical interest are summarised in Table 1 . </p>
         <p> The overall study objectives are summarised in Fig. 4 . Here, it can be seen that the
            overall problem was to determine whether management intensity has an influence on grape
            qualities and whether such an effect can be explained by hypothesised mediators. One
            question of interest in this study was whether the measured properties of grapes show an
            integrated pattern of response. This question was evaluated first before examining
            effects of management intensity, spontaneous non-crop vegetation and soil nitrogen on
            grape qualities. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="illustration of a protocol for evaluating hypotheses about general responses">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Illustration of a Protocol for Evaluating Hypotheses about General Responses</p>
         <p> Question #1: What are the Anticipated Characteristics of the Theoretical Construct(s)
            of Interest ? </p>
         <p> We learn about latent variables indirectly. More specifically, we learn about them
            through theorising and empirical investigations, rather than direct measurement. It is
            important, therefore, that we consider the theoretical meaning of constructs carefully
            and explicitly. Most ecologists are accustomed to using descriptive procedures, such as
            principal components analysis (PCA), when faced with a set of related measurements. PCA
            seeks to reduce a set of variables to some smaller number of composite variables (aka
            components) that contain most of the information in the set. PCA is purely a
            data-reduction method and there is no basis for drawing causal interpretations of the
            resulting components ( , Chapter 30). </p>
         <p> With LVSEM, we might pose a hypothesis, such as the one shown in Fig. 5 A for the grape
            study. Here, we are hypothesising that the chemical composition of grapes is tightly
            regulated within plants and, thus, there should be strong integration and tight
            correlations (positive or negative) amongst indicator variables. However, the simple
            structure shown in Fig. 5 A is not necessarily the only model to initially consider. For
            example, we might wish to also consider a model like the one in Fig. 5 B, which
            anticipates that certain chemical properties will be inherently more tightly
            constrained. In that case, we might expect an additional effect, which can be
            represented by including an error correlation. The error correlation is actually an
            implied latent variable. We might want to represent this effect using a double-headed
            arrow rather than by including an explicit latent variable for several reasons. First,
            it allows us to retain focus on our primary hypothesis. Second, it only involves a
            single parameter, thereby saving model degrees of freedom and maintaining statistical
            power. </p>
         <p> In thinking about our theoretical constructs, of fundamental importance is whether we
            think the concept is unidimensional (behaves like it is one thing) or multidimensional
            (behaves like a collection of different things). Taken literally (which software
            estimation will do), the hypothesis being evaluated in Fig. 5 A is that there is a
            single common cause influencing all the response indicators. The effects (lambdas) do
            not have to be equal, but their relative strengths have to be consistent if we are to
            believe they are correlated due to a single common cause. All other causes contributing
            variations to response indicators are independent (the epsilons). If we think there are
            latent factors causing some response indicators to be more strongly correlated than
            could be explained by the single cause of theoretical interest, we might expect the need
            to include correlations amongst errors. </p>
         <p> There are many other possibilities that might be supported by theory. The most common
            alternative is that a theoretical "construct" or concept may be a collection of
            independent or semi-independent causes. The details that accompany this situation are
            beyond our purpose in this paper and the reader is referred to for a discussion of this
            larger topic. </p>
         <p> Question #2: Are there Appropriate Measured Variables that can Serve as Indicators of
            the General Theoretical Constructs ? </p>
         <p> When interested in a general property of a study system, it is recommended that one
            gives careful consideration to the previous question about expected attributes when
            designing the sampling scheme. This is one of those interesting differences between
            science practice in the social sciences versus the ecological sciences. In the social
            sciences, particularly when studies involve human behaviour, the default assumption is
            that the latent properties are of primary interest. Studies may involve human attitudes
            and motivations, which are assumed from the outset to be "deeply latent" and only
            discernible indirectly. This has led to the development of a process for careful
            consideration of the development of proper measures for the constructs of interest. For
            example, the American Association of Psychology Dictionary ( ) provides the following
            description for scale development : </p>
         <p>"The process of creating a new instrument [a set of specific measurements] for measuring
            an unobserved or latent construct, such as depression, sociability, or fourth-grade
            mathematics ability. The process includes defining the construct and test
            specifications, generating items and response scales, piloting the items in a large
            sample, conducting analyses to fine-tune the measure, and then readministering the
            refined measure to develop norms (if applicable) and to assess aspects of reliability
            and validity."</p>
         <p> Our purpose here is to raise awareness of the fact that there has been substantial
            development of methodologies in other scientific disciplines that could be of interest
            to natural scientists, but that has been systematically ignored to the detriment of our
            scientific studies. It is beyond the scope of the present paper to consider this body of
            knowledge in detail, though the expected requirements for a set of indicators to
            represent a theoretical construct will be illustrated via our presentation. For a more
            general introduction to scale development, one can refer to . </p>
         <p>When one wishes to develop a latent variable SE model, it is possible to proceed by
            having one or more indicator measurements. Having only a single measure provides limited
            opportunities. The most commonly adopted approach is to simply assume that the measured
            variable is a perfect representation of the latent property. The main accomplishment
            achieved in such a model is to make a conceptual distinction between the concept of
            interest and the observed measure. When we have some estimate for the reliability
            (repeatability) of a measurement process, we can insert that information into our model
            and remove bias due to measurement error. Once we have two or more indicators, it is
            possible to confirm or not the presence of a latent cause. This is the example situation
            we address in the current paper.</p>
         <p> Indicator validity refers to the requirement that measured variables are interpretable
            as measures of the concept of interest. This is a theoretical requirement, but one to
            not forget to address in a paper. We recommend the construction of a table such as Table
            1 as a formal means of defining explicitly the basis for explaining the logic connecting
            indicators to latent variables. </p>
         <p> Question #3: What do the Patterns of Intercorrelations Amongst Indicator Variables
            Suggest ? </p>
         <p> It is one thing to conceptualise a set of observed variables as reflections of a
            concept of interest, but it is another thing for the data to agree with one's
            conceptualisation. A simple first approach to this problem is to construct a correlation
            matrix to see if the patterns of correlations amongst indicator variables are roughly
            consistent with theoretical expectations. For this exercise, we focus on the sub-model
            shown in Fig. 5 A rather than the entire model for simplicity. Data for this paper were
            simulated from the results found by , as our goal is not to revisit the analyses
            performed by , but instead to use that study as a tangible example of the methods
            demonstration in this paper. </p>
         <p> Fig. 5 A implies two main things about our expectations of the data. The first
            expectation is very general; we expect the indicators to be correlated with one another.
            If we fail to find significant correlations (based on standard tests and null hypothesis
            testing, p &lt;0.05, then the indicators are not varying in concert and the data will
            not support the claim of a latent cause. Beyond that primary expectation, we might
            expect the standardised lambdas to be similar to each other in magnitude if they are
            simply controlled by a single common cause. There are many reasons this expectation
            might not be met. For example, if the true model is as shown in Fig. 5 B, we would
            expect a somewhat different pattern of correlations. If that model were the true model,
            we would expect sugars and malic acids to be more strongly correlated with each other
            than with the other measures. Going one step further, the pattern of correlations may
            tell us which of several a priori theoretical alternatives are likely to be supported. </p>
         <p> When one starts working with LVSEM, it is found that there are many ways that data may
            deviate from showing equal correlation strengths amongst indicators, aside from error
            correlations, some of which are suggested in Fig. 3 . In the case of the data presented
            in Table 2 , the correlations amongst indicators vary in strength, ranging from 0.61 to
            0.27. The first thing to note is that sugars are negatively correlated with the other
            properties, suggesting some metabolic trade-off. A second observation is that tartric
            and malic acids are only weakly correlated, which argues against the idea that acid
            production is a general property. </p>
         <p> Question #4: Do Analyses Support There Being a Generalised Response ? </p>
         <p> It is customary in SEM practice to analyse latent variable models in two stages, first
            evaluating the fit between latent variables and indicators (Fig. 5 A) and then second,
            evaluating the full model (e.g. Fig. 6 ). Results obtained from the analysis of
            sub-models are only provisional, but this provides an opportunity to isolate certain
            kinds of misspecifications without working through models containing multiple
            misspecifications. SE models that include only latent variables and their indicators are
            often referred to as confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) models. describes an integrated
            approach to comparing SE models that is consistent with current views from the field of
            statistics. The approach described involves an assessment of the weight of evidence
            supporting each model in the theoretically-defensible set of models being compared and
            considers the use of p -values along with information criteria, such as Akaike
            Information Criteria. Some readers may find that treatment a useful complement to the
            presentation in this paper. </p>
         <p> Table 3 presents the code used to conduct a CFA examination of the model shown in Fig.
            5 A. As can be seen in Table 3 , lavaan allows for the use of covariance matrices as
            input data, which is very helpful in methods illustrations. The CFA command "GrapeQual
            =~ N +Sugars +Tart +Malic" is read as, "The latent property Grape quality is measured by
            four indicators, nitrogen, sugars, tartric acid and malic acid." </p>
         <p>Tables of results for all models run in the paper are provided in Suppl. material 2. The
            reader may find it useful to download that file to follow along if they wish to see more
            of the raw results. References to specific tables of results (e.g. Table S2.1) are
            provided in the text that follows. Suppl. material 3 contains the R script as a separate
            document.</p>
         <p>Examination of results focuses initially on overall model fit (Suppl. material 2, Table
            S2.1). We do not want to interpret results related to parameter estimates until we are
            confident there are no major model-data discrepancies; therefore, initial focus is
            placed on model fit evaluation.</p>
         <p> Results show strong support for our initial model (Table S2.1). A test statistic (Model
            Chi-square) value of 0.808 with an associated p -value of 0.668 was found. This p -value
            is well above the 0.05 criterion, providing strong support for there not being major
            model-data discrepancies. A Comparative Fit Index value of 1.000 further indicates a
            near-perfect explanation of the observed covariances by the model. Thus, it is extremely
            unlikely that additions to our model, such as shown in Fig. 5 B, would be justified.
            That said, we do not use a 0.05 criterion as an absolute cutoff for adequate fit, since
            p -values above 0.05 can hide important discrepancies. </p>
         <p> Having assessed the global model fit, we turn attention to the parameter estimates
            (Table S2.1). Again, we do not treat p -values as absolute cutoffs, but instead as
            continuous measures of evidence that a parameter or model deviates from the default
            expectation ( ). For our assessment of global model fit (Table S2.1), the default
            expectation is our hypothesised model (Fig. 5 A). For parameter estimates (Table S2.1),
            however, the default expectation is a value of zero. The p -values for parameters, which
            range from &lt;0.001 to 0.003, provide further support for the model in Fig. 5 A. Note
            that the estimate for N (lambda1) is fixed to a defined value of 1.0 as a lavaan
            default. This is done to set the scale for the latent variable, which would otherwise be
            unidentified. Finally, R-square values are provided in Table S2.1 and indicate the
            degree to which our hypothesised latent cause explains the total observed variation in
            the indicator variables. Values returned were 0.78 for N, 0.38 for Sugars, 0.21 for Tart
            and 0.46 for Malic. Thus, in this case, variation in N appears to be less influenced by
            factors outside the model compared to the other indicators. </p>
         <p> Question #5: Does the Generalised Response Exhibit a Concerted Reaction to
            Perturbation? and </p>
         <p> Question #6: Are there Unique Reactions by Specific Indicators ? </p>
         <p> The complexity of SE models and the variety of inferences we typically wish to make
            lead us to move through the evaluation of our overall hypothesis in stages. It is
            important to keep in mind that conclusions one might draw, based on the analysis of
            sub-models, may need to be reconsidered once the full model is examined. Having examined
            the latent response sub-model, we now move to a pair of competing models shown in Fig. 6
            . Here, we use single measures for management intensity and non-crop vegetation. </p>
         <p> In Fig. 6 , we address a pair of questions; "Do grape qualities vary as a function of
            management intensity?" and "Does the cover of non-crop N-fixing plant species explain
            some or all of the effects of management intensity." The first of these questions is
            represented in Fig. 6 A and the lavaan code is provided in Table 4 . Lavaan code is used
            to specify two latent variables using the =~ operator, then to represent the hypothesis
            that Grape Qualities depend on Management Intensity. We first request overall fit
            measures using the "show" command, then modification indices to see if there are
            meaningful suggestions for model improvement. </p>
         <p> Results for the initial model (Fig. 6 A) revealed substantial model-data discrepancy
            (Table S2.3). Not only is the p -value for the test statistic &lt;0.001, the CFI value
            of 0.789 is well below typical recommendations for a value of 0.95 or greater ( , ).
            Modification indices suggest some sort of a unmodeled relationship between management
            intensity and tartric acid. Since modification indices are best thought of as uninformed
            suggestions, we must use theoretical knowledge to decide what alternative model would be
            appropriate to consider. </p>
         <p> As illustrated in Fig. 3 , one of the theoretical possibilities we might anticipate for
            this model is specific effects of management on particular grape qualities. Here, we
            considered a reasonable alternative to be the addition of a direct effect of management
            intensity on tartric acid (Table 4 , Revised Net Effect Model). Results showed this
            revised model to have near-perfect correspondence with the data (Table S2.2). </p>
         <p> Our second question, represented in Fig. 6 B, involves a mediator that might explain
            why management intensity has an observed effect on grape qualities. considered a number
            of possibilities. We do not revisit the full variety of possible mediator models
            considered in the original study, but focus on the possibility that the cover of
            nitrogen-fixing non-crop plants might explain all or part of the effects of management
            intensity on grape qualities. While we might expect to again find a specific effect of
            management on tartric acid, we nonetheless begin with the most general version of the
            mediator model shown in Fig. 6 B (which we refer to as LVMed1 in Table 5 .) Results
            again indicate that management intensity has a specific effect on tartric acid separate
            from its general effect. Once that link is included in the Revised Mediated Effect Model
            (LVMed2, Table 5), fit was found to be very close (CFI = 1.0, Table S2.3). </p>
         <p> Question #7: Can we Simplify the Model, Thereby Increasing Generality ? </p>
         <p> Since SE models are used for explanatory representations of scientist's understanding
            of systems ( ), there are many cases where that purpose may lead investigators to use a
            light hand in pruning weak effects from their models. However, when the goal is to make
            general inferences, model simplicity is preferred. In the context of the current paper,
            simplicity can be approached by fixing parameters to set values (such as zero) so that
            model structure is maintained while the number of estimated parameters is reduced. Fixed
            values of parameters represent general statements. In addition, the fewer the number of
            estimated parameters, the greater the statistical power per parameter (number of
            observations/number of estimated parameters). </p>
         <p> Regarding our example, we next turn to an examination of individual parameter estimates
            to determine whether model simplification of model LVmed2 is possible (Table S2.4). P
            -values provide strong support for all estimated lambdas (all &lt;0.001), as well as all
            other estimated parameters, except beta1 ( p = 0.713), which is the effect of the
            mediator Non-Crop Vegetation on Grape Qualities. We estimated a simplified model (not
            shown) with beta1 set to zero (beta1 == 0) and determined that model fit was improved,
            as discrepancy increased very slightly while the number of estimated parameters was
            reduced by one (and fit is a measure of the amount of discrepancy prorata to the number
            of estimated parameters). We continue discussing ways to minimise the number of
            estimated parameters in the next section where we address the complexity that arises
            when there is more than one variety of grape being modelled. </p>
         <p> Question #8: What About Generality Across Groups ? </p>
         <p> LVSEM has the capacity to formally evaluate parameter equality across groups. Referred
            to as multi-group analysis , the investigator can test hypotheses by asking whether
            models of the same general form apply beyond single groups. With regard to the Swiss
            grape study, the investigators sampled vineyards that cultivated two different varieties
            of grapes, Chasselas and Pinot noir . Suppl. material 3 includes simulated data for the
            two varieties of grape, as well as code for multi-group analysis. </p>
         <p> If multigroup models are specified without constraints, all parameters will be
            independently estimated for each group by default. One way to set equality constraints
            across groups is to add labels to the code. In this case, one first uses the format c(
            "label1" , "label2" ) to create names for the parameters where there are two groups.
            This example will generate two independent parameter estimates, one for each group,
            since the labels are unique. If we specify c( "lambda1" , "lambda1" ), the repeated use
            of a common label means a single value will be estimated for both groups (Table 6 ). The
            effects of this constraint will be reflected in the model discrepancy and we can judge
            whether this equality constraint has a small or large effect (Table S2.5). Adding the
            three constraints caused Model Degrees of Freedom to increase by 3 (going from 4 to 7)
            in the constrained model. This reduction in the number of estimated parameters is very
            helpful for small sample studies because multigroup models can contain twice as many
            parameters. </p>
         <p> Using the approach in Table 6 , the results obtained show that even with all lambdas
            constrained to be equal across groups, global model fit is very close (CFI = 1.0, Table
            S2.6). Based on this finding, we proceeded to estimate the full model, first allowing
            all gamma and beta parameters to be independent, then adding equality constraints and
            revisiting model fit. Proceeding in this fashion, we arrive at the model in Table 7 and
            the results are shown in Fig. 7 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Discussion</p>
         <p>It is important to be able to judge whether a system exhibits a generalised multivariate
            response to environmental change rather than an independent collection of uncoordinated
            responses. This paper presents an approach to addressing that question. A particular
            aspect of the approach demonstrated is that it invokes causal reasoning. We ask if
            suites of observed properties behave as if they are jointly influenced by a "hidden
            hand" or integrative cause.</p>
         <p>Studying generalised responses is inherently challenging. Our objective is to focus our
            attention on the general, while moving the specifics to the background - at least
            initially. The sequence of operations described support a "general first, specifics
            second" perspective. Ultimately, SEM forces us to address both. Along the way, we must
            confront the large number of possible explanations that can exist for the actual
            functioning of the system being studied. This complexity means one cannot take a rigid
            approach, but must follow clues along a path to selecting a final model to use for
            interpretation. We suggest a series of questions that can guide investigators through
            several critical steps in model evaluation. In addition, we recognise that the research
            context matters, so the list may need to be modified for particular applications.</p>
         <p> Success in applying a flexible, adaptive approach requires a solid understanding of how
            the analytical system 'thinks' about things. Within LVSEM, latent variables represent
            the common variance or overlapping information for a set of measures. They represent, in
            essence, the consensus opinion about the latent factor that functions as their common
            causal connection. There will, of course, be unique information associated with the
            individual measures, particularly if they are selected to represent multiple facets of a
            theoretical construct. Our core challenge is to capture the general opinions of the data
            without becoming overly distracted by the unique responses. </p>
         <p> Fig. 7 provides us with a vehicle for making some main points about the evaluation of
            general responses. By including latent variables and their indicators, an explicit
            distinction between concepts of interest and the measures used to quantify those
            concepts is made. This approach means that in future studies, one may retain their
            general hypothesis while adapting the details of model to the particulars of the
            measured indicators. It also means that we have a model that can adjust for measurement
            error if we choose to incorporate that information (e.g. ). While Fig. 7 presents
            standardised results, Table S2.7 shows that the unstandardised lambdas for Grape
            Qualities are equal for the different grape varieties. This suggests the observed
            indicators have physiological meaning at a fundamental level. Future studies may wish to
            further examine the physiological properties of grapes to develop a deeper understanding
            of the role of external conditions on their expression. </p>
         <p> A number of mysteries are exposed in our multigroup model (Fig. 7 ). For some reason,
            the Chasselas variety does not respond to the abundance of nitrogen-fixing plants, while
            Pinot noir is quite responsive. Beyond that, the total effect of management intensity on
            grape qualities for Pinot noir is partly dependent on management through its influence
            on non-crop vegetation (indirect effect: -0.47*0.59 = -0.28), but is also largely
            impacted through other mechanisms (direct effect: 0.63). We might speculate that these
            other mechanisms have to do with a reduction in the competitive effects of non-crop
            vegetation on grape qualities, but further studies could explore that relationship in
            greater detail. Finally, the Chasselas variety exhibits a differential response of
            tartric acid to management compared to the other grape properties, which suggests the
            need for further examination. </p>
         <p>It is our hope that this paper demonstrates both how to approach using LVSEM to
            investigate multivariate responses and also to hint at the variety of scientific
            insights that can be gleaned from the effort. We believe there is an important
            opportunity for LVSEM to play a greater role in our quantitative understanding of
            ecological responses to environmental change.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>We thank two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments and suggestions. This work was
            supported by the USGS Ecosystems and Land Change Science Climate Research and
            Development Programs. Any use of trade, firm or product names is for descriptive
            purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Arhonditsis, G. B. , Stow, C. A. , Steinberg, L. J. , Kenney, M. A.
                  , Lathrop, R. C. , McBride, S. J. , Reckhow, K. H. , 2006 . Exploring ecological
                  patterns with structural equation modeling and Bayesian analysis . Ecological
                  Modelling 192 : 385 - 409 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bollen, K. A. , 1989 . Structural equations with latent variables .
                  John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Cubaynes, S. , Doutrelant, C. , Grgoire, A. , Perret, P. , Faivre,
                  B. , Gimenez, O. , 2012 . Testing hypotheses in evolutionary ecology with
                  imperfect detection: capture-recapture structural equation modeling . Ecology 93 :
                  248 - 255 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> DeVellis, R. F. , 2016 .. Scale development: Theory and applications
                  26 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Grace, J. B. , 2006 . Structural equation modeling and natural
                  systems . Cambridge University Press </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Grace, J. B. , Keeley, J. E. , 2006 . A structural equation model
                  analysis of postfire plant diversity in California shrublands . Ecological
                  Applications 16 : 503 - 514 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Grace, J. B. , Anderson, T. M. , Olff, H. , Scheiner, S. M. , 2010 .
                  On the specification of structural equation models for ecological systems .
                  Ecological Monographs 80 : 67 - 87 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Grace, J. B. , 2020 . A 'Weight of Evidence' approach to evaluating
                  structural equation models . One Ecosystem 5 ( e50452 ) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Grace, J. B. , Irvine, K. M. , 2020 . Scientists guide to developing
                  explanatory statistical models using causal analysis principles . Ecology 101 (
                  e02962 ) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hu, L. T. , Bentler, P. M. , 1999 . Cutoff criteria for fit indexes
                  in covariance structure analysis: Conventional criteria versus new alternatives .
                  Structural equation modeling: a multidisciplinary journal 6 : 1 - 55
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Joreskog, K. G. , 1970 . A general method for analysis of covariance
                  structures . Biometrika 57 : 239 - 251 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Liu, X. , Swenson, N. G. , Lin, D. , Mi, X. , Umana, M. N. , Schmid,
                  B. , Ma, K. , 2016 . Linking individual level functional traits to tree growth in
                  a subtropical forest . Ecology 97 : 2396 - 2405 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> McCune, B. , Grace, J. B. , Urban, D. , 2002 . Analysis of
                  ecological communities: Chapter 30 . In: MjM Software, Gleneden Beach, OR, USA.
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Pugesek, B. H , Tomer, A. , von Eye, A. , 2003 . Structural Equation
                  Modeling: Applications in Ecological and Evolutionary Biology . Cambridge
                  University Press </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Team, R Core , 2019 . R: A language and environment for statistical
                  computing . R Foundation for Statistical Computing </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Rosseel, Y. , 2012 . lavaan: An R Package for Structural Equation
                  Modeling . Journal of Statistical Software 48 : 1 - 36 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Shipley, B. , Lechowicz, M. J. , Wright, I. , Reich, P. B. , 2006 .
                  Fundamental tradeoffs generating the worldwide leaf economics spectrum . Ecology
                  87 : 535 - 541 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Shipley, B. , 2016 . Cause and correlation in biology . Cambridge
                  University Press </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Souchay, G. , Wijk, R. E. , Schaub, M. , Bauer, S. , 2018 .
                  Identifying drivers of breeding success in a long distance migrant using
                  structural equation modelling . Oikos 127 : 125 - 133 </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Steiner, M. , Grace, J. B. , Bacher, S. , 2021 . Biodiversity
                  effects on grape Quality depend on variety and management intensity . Journal of
                  Applied Ecology In Press </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> VandenBos, G. R. , 2007 . APA dictionary of psychology . American
                  Psychological Association </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>Supplementary material 1 A protocol for modelling generalised biological responses using
            latent variables in structural equation models Data type</p>
         <p>Mathematical equations and notation for latent variable structural equation
            modelling.</p>
         <p>Brief description</p>
         <p>This text file contains the equations and notation mentioned in Grace JB, Steiner M
            (2021) A protocol for modelling generalised biological responses using latent variables
            in structural equation models. One Ecosystem</p>
         <p>File: oo_559472.pdf</p>
         <p>Grace JB, Steiner M</p>
         <p>Supplementary material 2 A protocol for modelling generalised biological responses using
            latent variables in structural equation models Data type</p>
         <p>Results Tables</p>
         <p>Brief description</p>
         <p>This file contains the results tables for the demonstrations included in Grace JB,
            Steiner M (2021) A protocol for modelling generalised biological responses using latent
            variables in structural equation models. One Ecosystem.</p>
         <p>File: oo_562638.pdf</p>
         <p>Grace JB, Steiner M</p>
         <p>Supplementary material 3 A protocol for modelling generalised biological responses using
            latent variables in structural equation models Data type</p>
         <p>R code</p>
         <p>Brief description</p>
         <p>: This text file contains the R code used to develop the demonstrations included in
            Grace JB, Steiner M (2021) A protocol for modelling generalised biological responses
            using latent variables in structural equation models. One Ecosystem.</p>
         <p>File: oo_559445.R</p>
         <p>Grace JB, Steiner, M</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
