<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Biodiversity Data Journal</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.8.e58033</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Reptile occurrences data in the Volga River basin (Russia)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Testudo caspica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mauremys caspica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Tenuidactylus caspius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Natrix tessellata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Natrix tessellata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eremias arguta
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Elaphe dione
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alsophylax pipiens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Chordata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Reptilia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Squamata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Testudines</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Agamidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Anguidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Boidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Colubridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Emydidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gekkonidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Lacertidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Lamprophiidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Viperidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Emys orbicularis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Alsophylax pipiens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynocephalus guttatus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynocephalus helioscopus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynocephalus mystaceus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Anguis colchica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eremias arguta
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eremias velox
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lacerta agilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Zootoca vivipara
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eryx miliaris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Coronella austriaca
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Elaphe dione
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Elaphe sauromates
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hierophis caspius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Natrix natrix
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Natrix tessellata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Malpolon monspessulanus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Vipera berus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Vipera renardi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Tenuidactylus (Cyrtopodion) caspius</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Reptilia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sauria</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gekkonidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Coronella austriaca
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Serpentes</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Colubridae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lacerta agilis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Reptilia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Lacertidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Vipera berus</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Vipera nikolskii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Reptilia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Viperidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Vipera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Eremias arguta</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Zootoca vivipara
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Reptilia</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Lacertidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cyrtopodion caspius</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Gekkonidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sauria</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Natrix tessellata</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Introduction
</p>
         <p>
The Volga is the longest river in Europe and the 16th largest in the world with 3690 km in length (

). The area of the Volga basin is about 1.4 million km2, which is 33% of European Russia and almost 13% of the territory of Europe. There are different types of biomes in the region, such as taiga in the north and semi-desert in the south (

). The Volga basin includes all or part of the territory of 29 oblasts, eight republics and one krai of Russia, as well as two oblasts of Kazakhstan (

). Previous herpetological studies suggested that more than 20 species of reptiles lived in the Volga basin. Some of the previously-noted species may have been identified incorrectly or have disappeared by now in the Volga basin. For example, I.G. Georgi (1801) mentions " 
<tp:taxon-name>
Testudo caspica
</tp:taxon-name>
" - 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mauremys caspica
</tp:taxon-name>
(Gmelin, 1774) - on the Lower Volga. One species - 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tenuidactylus caspius
</tp:taxon-name>
(Eichwald, 1831) - is considered to have been introduced presumably at the end of the 20th century (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
The first data about the reptiles of the Volga basin appeared in the 10th century (

). However, reliable species identification of the snakes mentioned by Ibn-Fadlan is not possible.
</p>
         <p>
Adam Olshlegel (

, S. 358-359) in 1636 encountered the "Rotbunte" snake - 
<tp:taxon-name>
Natrix tessellata
</tp:taxon-name>
. The record referred to the left Bank of the Volga in the vicinity of Samara.
</p>
         <p>
The main composition of the herpetofauna of the Volga basin was established by the participants of the 1768-1774 academic expedition: P.S. Pallas (

, 

, 

, 

), I. I. Lepekhin (

, 

), J. P. Falk (

, 

) and J. G. Georgi (

, 

, 

). P.S. Pallas described two new species of reptiles from the territory of the Volga basin and I. I. Lepekhin described four species.
</p>
         <p>
Specialists from the Institute of Ecology of the Volga River basin of Russian Academy of Sciences began the study of the herpetofauna of the region in 1984, when the Institute was founded (

, 

, 

, 

, 

, 

). In addition, many studies have been conducted in different regions of the Volga basin over the past 20 years. These studies investigated both the ecological and genetic features of species and post-fire changes in herpetofauna (

, 

, 

, 

, 

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
The purpose of this paper is to describe a dataset on occurrences of reptiles in the Volga River basin (European Russia) recently published by us in GBIF as a Darwin Core Archive (

). This paper was prepared according to the concept of "data paper" (

, 

).The main idea of the data paper is to publish the usually not easily accessible or discoverable primary biodiversity data as a scientific publication, thus providing free and open access to that information. This is essential for making informed decisions in biodiversity conservation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="project description">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Project description</p>
         <p>Title</p>
         <p>Reptile occurrences data in the Volga River basin (Russia).</p>
         <p>Personnel</p>
         <p>Alexander Kirillov, Nadezhda Kirillova, Andrey Bakiev, Alexander Ruchin, Anastasiya Klenina, Roman Gorelov, Natalya Kostina.</p>
         <p>Study area description</p>
         <p>
The Volga River basin is situated in the Russian Plain - centre of European Russia. Water resources of the Volga basin account for only about 5% of the water resources of all Russia. The Volga riverbed and its tributaries are located along the lowlands and only in some places the river passes through the hills (Zhiguli Hills on the Samarskaya Luka). A network of reservoirs has been created on the Volga and its tributaries. There are eight very large reservoirs only on the Volga itself. This determines the configuration of the Volga basin as a whole: below the confluence of the Volga with the Kama, the formation of the lateral inflow practically ends (

).
</p>
         <p>
The Volga basin is divided into three regions named as the Upper, Middle and Lower Volga. Gorky and Zhigulevskaya dams are considered the borders of the Upper and Middle Volga and the Middle and Lower Volga, respectively. The Volga basin covers various latitudinal climatic zones. The large extent of the Volga basin from north to south is characterised by a change in biomes from taiga to semi-desert. There is a forest belt on the north of the Volga basin formed by southern taiga and mixed coniferous-deciduous forest. To the south of the forest belt, there is a forest-steppe biome. Biomes of steppes, semi-deserts and deserts are located in the extreme south of the Volga basin. The desert biome is adjacent to the southern part of the Akhtuba River floodplain near the Caspian lowlands (

).
</p>
         <p>
The climate of the Upper Volga basin is moderate continental, characterised by cold winters and relatively warm summers. The climate of the Middle Volga region is similar to the climate of the Upper Volga region in winter, but the summer climate is less variable. The climate of the Lower Volga region is predominantly continental, characterised by hot summers and relatively short, but cold winters (

).
</p>
         <p>Design description</p>
         <p>
The study of the distribution of reptiles in the Volga basin was carried out during field scientific expeditions by manual capture and species identification of the encountered individuals. Since 2002, the number of original studies of reptiles in the region has increased (Fig. 
1
). While studying the Volga basin, it was possible to collect data as of common reptile species as rare species, which are listed in the various regional Red Lists.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="sampling methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Sampling methods</p>
         <p>Sampling description</p>
         <p>
The dataset is based on personal records from field diaries, some of them having been published earlier, but schematically and without a geographical coordinate reference (

, 

, 

). The coordinate reference to each reptile sampling point is given for the first time in this dataset.
</p>
         <p>Quality control</p>
         <p>Most of the data was collected by herpetologists. The rest of the data was identified by herpetologists from the Institute of Ecology of the Volga River Basin of RAS from photographs we received from amateur naturalists.</p>
         <p>Step description</p>
         <p>
The 
fields'
names of the dataset were chosen according to Darwin Core (

) and include the following: 
"occurrenceID"
, 
"basisOfRecord"
, scientificName", 
"kingdom"
, "phylum, 
"class"
, 
"order"
, 
"family"
, 
"geodeticDatum"
, 
"coordinateUncertaintyInMetres"
, 
"coordinatePrecision"
"decimalLatitude"
, 
"decimalLongitude"
, 
"country"
, 
"countryCode"
, 
"individualCount"
, 
"eventDate"
, 
"recordedBy"
, 
"identifiedBy"
.
</p>
         <p>The geographical reference, in most cases, was carried out by determining the coordinates of the finding place of reptiles using a GPS navigator. In other cases, where the geographical coordinates were not obtained using a GPS navigator, but there were original data about the reptile finding places, we determined the coordinates using Google maps (https://www.google.ru/maps/). The margin of error in the measurement of coordinates is 10 m. The accuracy of determining coordinates is up to the fourth digit. In all cases, the WGS-84 coordinate system is used.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="geographic coverage">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Geographic coverage</p>
         <p>Description</p>
         <p>
The Volga River basin is located in the Russian Plain (Fig. 
2
). There are the 
world's
northernmost populations of dice snake 
<tp:taxon-name>
Natrix tessellata
</tp:taxon-name>
in the Volga basin (Bashkortostan and Samara oblast) (

, 

). Samara oblast also contains Europe's northernmost populations of steppe-runner 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eremias arguta
</tp:taxon-name>
and the 
Pallas'
coluber 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elaphe dione
</tp:taxon-name>
(

, 

). The Volga basin (Astrakhan oblast) contains the only European population of the even-fingered gecko 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alsophylax pipiens
</tp:taxon-name>
(

).
</p>
         <p>Coordinates</p>
         <p>45°40'48'' and 60°26'49.2'' Latitude; 57°24'21.6'' and 34°8'16.8'' Longitude.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="taxonomic coverage">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Taxonomic coverage</p>
         <p>Description</p>
         <p>
All reptile individuals were identified to the species level. The database contains 20 species, belonging to nine reptile families (Fig. 
3
). Taxonomic affiliation is determined according to the Determinant Atlas of Amphibians and Reptiles of Russia (

), in accordance with the recommendations of the "International Code of Zoological Nomenclature" 

and is accepted in this database according to the GBIF.
</p>
         <p>Taxa included</p>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="traits coverage">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Traits coverage</p>
         <p>Enter subsection title</p>
         <p>Enter subsection text</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="usage licence">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Usage licence</p>
         <p>Usage licence</p>
         <p>Other</p>
         <p>IP rights notes</p>
         <p>Creative Commons Attribution (CC-BY) 4.0 License</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="data resources">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Data resources</p>
         <p>Data package title</p>
         <p>Occurrence of the reptiles in the Volga River basin (Russia).</p>
         <p>Resource link</p>
         <p>https://www.gbif.org/dataset/2fdc8f80-3f12-482e-ac28-8683d448e881</p>
         <p>Alternative identifiers</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.15468/n4tztr</p>
         <p>Number of data sets</p>
         <p>1</p>
         <p>Data set 1.</p>
         <p>Data set name</p>
         <p>Occurrence of the reptiles in the Volga River basin (Russia).</p>
         <p>Data format</p>
         <p>Darwin Core Archive format</p>
         <p>Number of columns</p>
         <p>19</p>
         <p>Character set</p>
         <p>UTF-8</p>
         <p>Download URL</p>
         <p>https://www.gbif.org/dataset/2fdc8f80-3f12-482e-ac28-8683d448e881</p>
         <p>Description</p>
         <p>
Our dataset contains information on reptile occurrences in the Volga River basin, located in the Russian Plain, European Russia. The dataset is based on our own research by the staff of the Laboratory of Herpetology and Toxinology and Laboratory of Population Ecology of the Institute of Ecology of the Volga River basin of the Russian Academy of Sciences and Joint Directorate of the Mordovia State Nature Reserve and National Park 
"Smolny"
. The dataset summarises reptile occurrences noted by field studies in various areas of the Volga River basin from 1988 to 2020. The dataset consists of 5,086 occurrence records, all of them being georeferenced. A total of 20 reptile species belonging to 14 genera and nine families are reported in the Volga River basin, although the distribution of reptile species in this region of Russia has not yet been fully studied.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgements">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>The research was carried out within the framework of the research topic "Ecological patterns of sustainable functioning of ecosystems and the potential resources of the Volga basin" AAAA-A17-117112040039-7 of the Institute of Ecology of the Volga River basin, a branch of the Samara Federal Research Center of the Russian Academy of Sciences.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="author contributions">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Author contributions</p>
         <p>A. Bakiev - reptile sample collection, species identification, georeferencing, manuscript editing</p>
         <p>A. Kirillov - reptile sample collection, species identification, georeferencing, data preparation, manuscript editing</p>
         <p>N. Kirillova - reptile sample collection, species identification, data preparation, manuscript editing</p>
         <p>A. Ruchin - reptile sample collection, species identification, georeferencing, data preparation</p>
         <p>A. Klenina - reptile sample collection, species identification, data preparation, manuscript editing</p>
         <p>R. Gorelov - reptile sample collection, species identification, data preparation, georeferencing</p>
         <p>N. Kostina - manuscript editing</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Andreev, V Y
, 
Andreev, A V
, 
Pestov, M V
, 
2019
. 

The current state of the synanthropic population of the gecko 
Tenuidactylus (Cyrtopodion) caspius
(
Reptilia
, 
Sauria
, 
Gekkonidae
) in the city of Astrakhan (Russia)

. In: 
Selevinia.
: 
105 - 109
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bakiev, A. G.
, 
Fayzulin, A. I.
, 
2002
. 
Materials for the inventory of amphibians and reptiles in the Middle Volga basin
. 
Nizhny Novgorod
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bakiev, A. G.
, 
Garanin, V. I.
, 
Litvinov, N. A.
, 
Pavlov, A. V.
, 
Ratnikov, V. Y.
, 
2004
. 
Snakes of Volzhsko-Kamskij Region
. 
Publishing house of Samara Scientific Center Russian Academy of Sciences, Samara
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bakiev, A G
, 
Malenev, A L
, 
Zaitseva, O V
, 
Shurshina, I V
, 
2009
. 
Snakes of the Samara region
. 
Kassandra, Togliatti
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bakiev, A. G.
, 
Shurshina, I. V.
, 
Zaytseva, O. V.
, 
Poklontseva, A. A.
, 
2009
. 
Snakes in Collection of Institute of Ecology of the Volga River basin of the Russian Academy of Sciences
. 
Samarskaya Luka
18
(
1
): 
31 - 41
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bakiev, A. G.
, 
Garanin, V. I.
, 
Gelashvili, D. B.
, 
Gorelov, R. A.
, 
Doronin, I. V.
, 
Zaytseva, O. V.
, 
Zinenko, A. I.
, 
Klenina, A. A
, 
Makarova, T. N.
, 
Malenev, A. L.
, 
Pavlov, A. V.
, 
Petrova, I. V.
, 
Ratnikov, V. Yu.
, 
Starkov, V. G.
, 
Shiryaeva, I. V.
, 
Yusupov, R. H.
, 
Yakovleva, T. I.
, 
2015
. 
Vipers (Reptilia: Serpentes: Viperidae: Vipera) in Volga River basin. Part. 1.
Cassandra, Togliatti
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bakiev, A. G.
, 
Kalmykova, O. G.
, 
Gorelov, R. A.
, 
2018
. 

Smooth snake 

Coronella austriaca

(
Serpentes
: 
Colubridae
), a new species for the ophidiofauna in the Orenburg State Nature Reserve (Russia)

. 
Nature Conservation Research
3
(
Suppl.1
): 
140 - 143
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Bakiev, A. G.
, 
Gorelov, R. A.
, 
Klenina, A. A.
, 
2019
. 

Post-fire abundance and age composition dynamics of 

Lacerta agilis

(
Reptilia
, 
Lacertidae
) in the Orenburg State Nature Reserve (Russia)

. 
Nature Conservation Research
4
(
Suppl.1
): 
105 - 109
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Chavan, Vishwas
, 
Penev, Lyubomir
, 
2011
. 
The data paper: a mechanism to incentivize data publishing in biodiversity science.
BMC Bioinformatics
12 Suppl 15
: S2
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dunaev, E A
, 
Orlova, V F
, 
2017
. 
Amphibians and reptiles of Russia: Determinant Atlas
. 
Publishing house "Fiton +", Moscow
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Efimov, R. V.
, 

Zav'yalov
, E. V.

, 
Velikov, V. A.
, 
Tabachishin, V. G.
, 
2011
. 

Genetic divergence of 
Vipera berus
and 

Vipera nikolskii

(
Reptilia
: 
Viperidae
, 
Vipera
) populations in lower Volga and adjacent territories assessed according to the sequences of cytochrome oxidase III and 12S ribosome RNA genes

. 
Russian Journal of Genetics
44
(
2
): 
240 - 243
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eplanova, G V
, 
Bakiev, A G
, 
Lysenko, T M
, 
2001
. 

On the distribution and distribution of multicolored foot-and-mouth disease 
Eremias arguta
(Pallas, 1773) in the Middle Volga region, especially in the Samara region

. 
Actual problems of herpetology and toxinology
5
: 
50 - 56
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eplanova, G. V.
, 
Gorelov, R. A.
, 
2009
. 
Lizards in Collection of Institute of Ecology of the Volga River basin of the Russian Academy of Sciences
. 
Samarskaya Luka
18
(
1
): 
24 - 30
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Eplanova, G. V.
, 
Kalmykova, O. G.
, 
Bakiev, A. G.
, 
Klenina, A. A.
, 
2018
. 

Ecology and some morphological characteristics of the 

Zootoca vivipara

(
Reptilia
: 
Lacertidae
) on the southern periphery of its range in the steppe zone (Orenburg State Nature Reserve, Russia)

. 
Nature Conservation Research
3
: 
98 - 109
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Falk, J. P.
, 
1786
.. 

Beitraege
zur topographischen 
Kenntniβ
des 
Ruβischen
Reichs

3
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Falk, J. P.
, 
1824
. 
Travel notes of academician Falk
. 
Imperial Academy of Sciences, St. Peterburg
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Fayzulin, A. I.
, 
Bakiev, A. G.
, 
Eplanova, G. V.
, 
2009
. 
Collection of amphibians and reptiles in Institute of Ecology of the Volga River basin of the Russian Academy of Sciences
. 
Proceedings of Ukrainian Herpetological Community
2
: 
90 - 93
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Georgi, J. G.
, 
1775
. 

Bemerkungen einer Reise im 
Ruβischen
Reich in den Jahren 1773. und 1774. Zweyter Band.

Kayserliche Academie der Wissenschaften, St. Petersburg
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Georgi, J. G.
, 
1801
.. 
Geographisch-physikalische und Naturhistorische Beschreibung des Russischen Reichs
Th. 3, Bd. 7
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Georgi, J. G.
, 
1802
. 

Nachtraege
fuer
dessen Geographisch-phisikalische und Naturhistorische Beschreibung des Russischen Reichs

. 

Friedrich Nicolovius, 
Koenigsberg

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ibn-Fadlan,
, 
1939
. 
Ibn-Fadlan's journey to the Volga
. 
Publishing house of the Academy of Sciences of the USSR, Moscow, Leningrad
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kirillov, A
, 
Kirillova, N
, 
Bakiev, A
, 
Ruchin, A
, 
Klenina, A
, 
Gorelov, R
, 
2020
.
. Version 1.9. Institute of Ecology of the Volga river basin of Russian Academy of Sciences. Occurrence dataset2020-10-11T00:00:00+03:00https://www.gbif.org/dataset/2fdc8f80-3f12-482e-ac28-8683d448e8811.9
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Klenina, A.
, 
Atyasheva, T.
, 
Gorelov, R.
, 
Bakiev, A.
, 
2019
. 
Current state of collection of viperids in Institute of Ecology of the Volga River basin of the Russian Academy of Sciences
. 
Proceedings of Mordovia State Nature Reserve
23
: 
86 - 100
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Klenina, A.
, 
2020
. 
Results, plans and prospects of the Laboratory of Herpetology and Toxinology of Institute of Ecology of the Volga River basin of the Russian Academy of Sciences
. 
Samarskaya Luka
29
(
1
): 
125 - 131
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Klenina, A.
, 
Atyasheva, T.
, 
2020
. 
Current state of lizard collection in Institute of Ecology of the Volga River basin of the Russian Academy of Sciences
. 
Samarskaya Luka
29
(
2
): 
111 - 117
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Kuzmin, S L
, 
Semenov, D V
, 
2006
. 
Synopsis of the fauna of amphibians and reptiles of Russia
. 
Partnership of scientific publications KMK, Moscow
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lebedinskii, Andrei A.
, 
Noskova, Olga S.
, 
Dmitriev, Alexander I.
, 
2019
. 
Post-fire recovery of terrestrial vertebrates in the Kerzhensky State Nature Biosphere Reserve (Central Volga Region, Russia)
. 
Nature Conservation Research
4
: 
45 - 56
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lepekhin, I. I.
, 
1771
.. 
Daily notes of the travels of the doctor and the adjunct of the Academy of Sciences Ivan Lepekhin to different provinces of the Russian state in 1768 and 1769
1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lepekhin, I. I.
, 
1772
.. 
Continuation of the daily notes of the journey of academician and medicine doctor Ivan Lepekhin to different provinces of the Russian state in 1770
2
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Litvinov, Alexander S.
, 
Korneva, Ludmila G.
, 
Gerasimov, Yuri V.
, 
Kitaev, Alexander B.
, 
Seletkova, Elena B.
, 
Okhapkin, Alexander G.
, 
Mineeva, Natalya M.
, 
Lazareva, Valentina I.
, 
Dvinskikh, Svetlana A.
, 
Alexevnina, Margarita S.
, 
Zinov'ev, Euvgeny A.
, 
Shurganova, Galina V.
, 
Papchenkov, Vladimir G.
, 
Shcherbina, Grigory Kh.
, 
Noskov, Victor M.
, 
Presnova, Elena V.
, 
Baklanov, Mikhail A.
, 
2009
. 
Volga River Basin
. In: 
Rivers of Europe.
: 
23 - 57
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Litvinov, N. A.
, 
Ganshchuk, S. V.
, 
Chetanov, N. A.
, 
2013
. 
Body temperature of reptiles inhabiting the Volga River basin and its relation to the ambient temperature
. 
Zoologicheskii Zhurnal
92
(
5
): 
568 - 576
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Olearius, A.
, 
1663
. 

Adam Olearii 
Aussfuehrliche
Beschreibung Der Kundbaren Reyse Nach Muscow und Persien

. 

Gedruckt in der 
Fuerstl
. Druckerey durch Johan Holwein, 
Schlesswig

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pallas, P. S.
, 
1771
.. 

P.S. Pallas D.A.D. Professors der Natur-Geschichte und ordentlichen Mitgliedes der Russisch-Kayserlichen Academie d. W. der freyen oeconomischen Gesellschaft in St. Petersburg, wie auch der 
Roemisch-Kayserlichen
Academie der Naturforscher und 
Koenigl
. Engl. 
Societaet
; Reise durch verschiedene Provinzen des Russischen Reichs

1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pallas, P. S.
, 
1776
.. 

P.S. Pallas D.A.D. Professors der Natur-Geschichte und ordentlichen Mitgliedes der Russisch-Kayserlichen Academie d. W. der freyen oeconomischen Gesellschaft in St. Petersburg, wie auch der 
Roemisch-Kayserlichen
Academie der Naturforscher und 
Koenigl
. Engl. 
Societaet
; Reise durch verschiedene Provinzen des Russischen Reichs

3
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pallas, P. S.
, 
1799
.. 

Bemerkungen auf einer Reise in die 
suedlichen
Statthalterschaften des Russischen Reichs in den Jahren 1793 und 1794

1
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pallas, P. S.
, 
1814
.. 
Zoographia Rosso-Asiatica, sistens omnium animalium in extenso Imperio Rossico et adjacentibus maribus observatorum recensionem, domicilia, mores et descriptiones, anatomen atque icones plurimorum; auctore Petro Pallas, eq. aur. Academico Petropoliano.
3
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Penev, Lyubomir
, 
Mietchen, Daniel
, 
Chavan, Vishwas
, 
Hagedorn, Gregor
, 
Smith, Vincent
, 
Shotton, David
, 

O
Tuama, 
Eamonn

, 
Senderov, Viktor
, 
Georgiev, Teodor
, 
Stoev, Pavel
, 
Groom, Quentin
, 
Remsen, David
, 
Edmunds, Scott
, 
2017
. 
Strategies and guidelines for scholarly publishing of biodiversity data
. 
Research Ideas and Outcomes
3
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Pestov, M V
, 
Kalinina, O N
, 
Grankina, L I
, 
2009
. 

Caspian gecko - 
Cyrtopodion caspius
(
Gekkonidae
, 
Sauria
) - a new species for the Astrakhan region and the Volga region

. 
Samarskaya Luka
18
(
1
): 
108 - 110
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ride, W. D.L.
, 
1999
. 
International Code of Zoological Nomenclature
. 
The International Trust for Zoological Nomenclature, London
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Roitberg, Evgeny S.
, 
Kuranova, Valentina N.
, 
Bulakhova, Nina A.
, 
Orlova, Valentina F.
, 
Eplanova, Galina V.
, 
Zinenko, Oleksandr I.
, 
Shamgunova, Regina R.
, 
Hofmann, Sylvia
, 
Yakovlev, Vladimir A.
, 
2013
. 
Variation of reproductive traits and female body size in the most widely-ranging terrestrial reptile: Testing the effects of reproductive mode, lineage, and climate
. 
Evolutionary Biology
40
(
3
): 
420 - 438
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Rosenberg, G S
, 
2009
. 
The Volga basin: on a way towards sustainable development
. 
Kassandra, Togliatti
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>TennekesM.Treemap Visualization. R package version 2.4-2https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=treemap2020-08-13T00:00:00+03:00</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wieczorek, John
, 
Bloom, David
, 
Guralnick, Robert
, 
Blum, Stan
, 

Doering
, Markus

, 
Giovanni, Renato
, 
Robertson, Tim
, 
Vieglais, David
, 
2012
. 
Darwin Core: An evolving community-developed biodiversity data standard
. 
PLOS One
7
(
1
)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Yakovlev, A G
, 
Sabirzyanov, I R
, 
Yakovleva, T I
, 
Bakiev, A G
, 
2016
. 

Dice snake 
Natrix tessellata
in Bashkortostan: the first reliable habitat. Samarskaya Luka

. 
Samarskaya Luka
25
(
4
): 
90 - 93
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
