<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Zootaxa</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.273606</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Description of the larva and pupa of Potamyia phaidra Malicky and Chantaramongkol (Trichoptera: Hydropsychidae) from southern Thailand</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2006</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
Malicky and Chantaramongkol
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
Malicky and Chantaramongkol
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichomacronema paniae

Malicky (
1991
)

</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
Malicky and Chantaramongkol
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. czekanowskii
(Martynov)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. czekanowskii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidr
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. czekanowskii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. flavata
Banks
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. flavata
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P. flava</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
P. czekanowskii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoptera (

Morse 
2003

)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Description of the larva and pupa of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
Malicky and Chantaramongkol
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
) from southern 
Thailand
</p>
         <p>
TAENG ON PROMMI 
1
, SURAKRAI PERMKAM 
2
&amp; ROBERT W. SITES 
3
*
</p>
         <p>
1


Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, Prince of Songkla University, Hat Yai, 
Thailand
. E-mail: tprommi@yahoo.com

</p>
         <p>
2


Department of Pest Management, Faculty of Natural Resources, Prince of Songkla University, Hat Yai, 
Thailand
. E-mail: surakrai.p@psu.ac.th

</p>
         <p>
3


Enns Entomology Museum, University of Missouri, 
Columbia
, MO 
65211
, 
U.S.A.
E-mail: sitesr@missouri.edu

</p>
         <p>
*Corresponding author
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Abstract

</title>
         <p>
Larvae and pupae of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
Malicky and Chantaramongkol
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
) were collected from montane streams in southern 
Thailand
. Pupal identifications were based on genitalic features in common with described adults, and larvae were associated with the pupae. Herein, the final larval instar and pupa are described, diagnosed, and figured.
</p>
         <p>
Key words
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
, larva, pupa, description, 
Thailand
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
Introduction

</title>
         <p>
Southern 
Thailand
is topographically diverse with flat agricultural regions punctuated by disjunct mountain ranges and associated waterfalls and streams. These numerous lotic systems harbor a diverse aquatic insect fauna. Our taxonomic understanding of these insects is very poor, especially of the immature stages. In one of very few papers addressing this fauna, Sites 
et al.
(
2001
) provided keys and notes on the immatures of the families and genera of mayflies (Ephemeroptera) of the southernmost 
10
provinces of 
Thailand
. No documentation of the immature stages of 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
exists for this region, nor for any other region of 
Thailand
.
</p>
         <p>
Research on 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Thailand
has been restricted mainly to descriptions of the adult stage, of which more than 
700
species have now been identified (

; 

). However, very few larvae are known at the species level, and most reports concerning these insects are recent. For example, the larvae of four species in different families were described from Doi Inthanon in northern 
Thailand
(

). The only species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Thailand
known in the larval stage is 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichomacronema paniae

Malicky (
1991
)

</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
A total of 
122
species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Hydropsychidae</tp:taxon-name>
has been recorded from 
Thailand
(Malicky &amp; Chantaramongkol 
1997
, 

), including 
13
species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
. Specifically, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
Malicky and Chantaramongkol
</tp:taxon-name>
is widespread throughout much of 
Thailand
(Malicky &amp; Chantaramongkol 
1997
). This species was previously known only in the adult stage, thus larvae and pupae were unknown. Presented herein are descriptions, diagnoses, and figures of the final larval instar and pupa of this species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Material and methods

</title>
         <p>
Hydropsychid larvae and pupae were collected from streams in southern 
Thailand
(Chumphon, Nakhon Si Thammarat, 
Surat
Thani, and Trang provinces). At each collection site, adults were collected using black light traps on timers to operate simultaneously from one hour before sunset to 1.5 hours after sunset near the stream margin. Insects attracted to the black light were collected in trays filled with water and a few drops of detergent and transferred into 
80
% ethyl alcohol the next morning.
</p>
         <p>
Larvae and pupae were collected by handpicking from the surfaces of stones, stone crevices, gravel, woody debris, and other stable substrates. The specimens were preserved in 
95
% ethyl alcohol and brought to the laboratory where they were sorted to morphospecies. Adult genitalia were cleared by heating in 
10
% NaOH at 
70
o C for 
30
minutes. The association between the adult and the fully developed pupa was established with genitalic characteristics. Further, the identified pupa was then associated with the final larval instar. Morphological terminology is based on 

. Voucher specimens were deposited in the Department of Pest Management, Faculty of Natural Resources, Prince of Songkla University; and Enns Entomology Museum, University of Missouri-Columbia, 
U.S.A.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Description

</title>
         <p>
Larva
: Total length 10.86–13.03 mm (n= 
10
). Overall body shape campodeiform (Fig. 
1
). Head yellowish to brown, with muscle scars on posterior half. Notal sclerites yellowish to brown, with muscle scars on posterior half of pronotum.
</p>
         <p>
Head
: Head capsule width 1.00–1.16 mm (n= 
10
). Dorsum of head dark brown anteriorly, becoming lighter posteriorly, with yellowish ring around each eye (Fig. 
2
). Posterior half of dorsum and area near eyes with numerous muscle scars. Frontoclypeus with anterior margin concave, slightly crenulate; posteromedian portion with 
1
pair each of large and small muscle scars (Fig. 
3
). Head with numerous short and long setae on dorsal and lateral regions in anterior 
3
/ 
4
(Figs. 
2, 4
). Head ventrally with stridulatory lines in anterior half (Fig. 
4
). Labrum elliptical in dorsal view, bearing well-developed, lateral, reddish-brown brushes and thick and thin short setae on dorsal surface, posterior margin slightly convex medially (Fig. 
5
). Mandibles with prominent lateral flanges, each with a row of setae along lateral groove. Each mandible with 
3–5
apical and subapical teeth (Fig. 
6
). Submentum with posterolateral corner broadly rounded; anterior margin broadly Vshaped with median cleft; cleft with sides parallel (Fig. 
7
). Anterior ventral apotome with prominent anteromedian tubercle, lateral arms long, narrow, slightly enlarged at apex; each apex usually cleft (Fig. 
7
).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Thorax
: Nota yellow to brown with a dense covering of dark brown setae. Pronotum with numerous long setae on anterior margin; muscle scars midway between midline and lateral margin in posterior half (Fig. 
8
). Mesonotum and metanotum each with setae projecting beyond anterior margin (Figs. 
9, 10
). Prosternite transverse, narrow, with broad dark band along posterior margin, with pair of small sclerites posterolaterally (Fig. 
11
). Propleuron with numerous setae in ventral portion; trochantin acuminate with stout setae (Fig. 
12
). Foreleg with long setae on anterior surface of coxa; femur with long setae on ventral surface (

Fig. 
13

). Mid- and hind legs similar in size, shape, and structure; with branched setae only on posterior surface of femur; no branched setae on tibia or tarsus (

Figs. 
14, 15

). Mesosternum with 
1
pair of gills; metasternum with 
2
pairs of gills; gills consisting of central stem bearing many lateral filaments.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Abdomen
: Abdominal segments with dark, recumbent setae, more dense ventrally. First segment with 
2
pairs of gills on sternum; gills with adjacent bases. Segments II–V each with 
1
pair of median gills. Segments II–VI each with 
1
pair of lateral gills; each gill arising from a common base. Segment VIII with 
1
pair of lateral gills. Sterna of segments VIII and IX each with a pair of spine-bearing plates, only sterna of segment IX with spines emanating from prominent sockets. Each sclerite of abdominal sternum IX distinct, not fused (

Fig. 
16

). Tergum IX with small lateral sclerite and pair of large dorsal sclerites. Anal prolegs with a bent claw and cluster of long bristles, without spine-like setae on ventral surface (

Fig. 
17

).
</p>
         <p>
Pupa
: Total length 7.01–7.68 mm (n= 
4
). Mandibles tapering regularly to pointed apex; inner margin with 
2
large teeth; widened basally, with 
2
groups of elongate setae on lateral and ventral surfaces (

Fig. 
18

). Dorsally, with 
1
pair of anterior hook plates on abdominal segments III–VIII (

Figs. 
19, 20

); 
1
pair of posterior hook plates on segments III–IV (

Figs. 
21–26

), posterior hook plate of segment IV covered with row of long setae (

Fig. 
22

). Apical processes with wide base narrowing to apex; ventral surface and lateral margins bearing elongate setae (

Fig. 
27

).
</p>
         <p>
Diagnosis
: Although diagnostic features to distinguish larval 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
from Southeast Asian congeners cannot be determined until the larvae of other species are described, several features distinguish the larva of this species from those of 
P. f l a v a
(Hagen) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. czekanowskii
(Martynov)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Specifically, the anterior ventral apotome of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
has a prominent anteromedian tubercle and cleft apices, whereas 
P. f l a v a
has a prominent anteromedian tubercle, but the apices are not cleft. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
has the ventral sclerites of abdominal sternum IX separate, fully covered with spines, and with the inner margins concave, whereas for 
P. f l a v a
, the ventral sclerites are less spinose near the lateral margins, and the inner margins are straight. The lateral margin of the mandible is narrowly flanged for its entire length in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
, whereas for 
P. f l a v a
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. czekanowskii
</tp:taxon-name>
, the flange is well-developed, although apparently only in the basal half of the mandible in the latter species. The fore trochantin of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
is not forked, whereas it is forked in 
P. f l a v a
. The anterior margin of the frontoclypeus in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidr
</tp:taxon-name>
a and 
P. f l a v a
is concave and weakly crenulate, whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. czekanowskii
</tp:taxon-name>
the anterior margin appears to be relatively straight. Other noteworthy features that might be useful in distinguishing among the larvae of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
include the size and shape of the black maculation on the midline of the posterior margin of the metanotum, color pattern on the head, and overall size.
</p>
         <p>
Material examined
: 

THAILAND

: Chumphom Prov.: Khuan Mae Yay Mhom Wildlife Sanctuary, stream from Hawe Lome Waterfall, 

2
.iv. 
2005

, Prommi, 

17
larvae

, 

2
pupae

, 

8
adults

; Nakhon Si Thammarat Prov.: Yong Waterfall National Park, stream from Yong Waterfall, 

10
.viii. 
2004

, Prommi, 

28
larvae

, 

5
pupae

, 

6
adults

; same locality, 

11
.X. 
2004

, 
15 larvae
, 

4
pupae

, 

10
adults

; Khao Luang National Park, stream from Ai Khaew Waterfall, 

3
.xii. 
2004

, Prommi, 

13
larvae

, 

14
adults

; stream from Yord Luang Waterfall, 

7
.iv. 
2005

, Prommi, 

35
larvae

, 

2
pupae

; same locality, 

26
.v. 
2005

, 
57 larvae
, 

4
pupae

; 
Surat
Thani Prov.: 
Tai
Rom Yen National Park, stream from Dad Fah Waterfall, 

9
.viii. 
2004

, Prommi, 

53
larvae

, 

4
pupae

, 

6
adults

; Khao Sok National Park, stream from Sib-Et-Chan Waterfall, 

7
.x. 
2004

, Prommi, 

10
larvae

, 

2
pupae

, 

30
adults

; Trang Prov.: Khao Chong Wildlife Management Station, 

5
.viii. 
2004

, Prommi, 

4
larvae

, 

1
adult

; same locality, 

5
.x. 
2004

, 
2 larvae
.
</p>
         <p>
Discussion
: Of the 
13
species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
known from 
Thailand
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. phaidra
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. flavata
Banks
</tp:taxon-name>
have the most widespread distribution (Malicky &amp; Chantaramongkol 
1997
; 

). The other 
11
species known to occur in 
Thailand
appear to have more restricted distributions. However, the known distribution of a species does not necessarily represent its actual distribution, in part because of regionally disparate sampling efforts. For example, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. flavata
</tp:taxon-name>
was not found in southern 
Thailand
, but is widespread and common in northern 
Thailand
and further south in Sumatra, Java, and Bali. Other congeners might be endemic to particular areas further north (

). In other geographic regions, adults of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Potamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
are known from 
China
, however the larval stage has not been recorded (

). More attention has been given to the immature stages of insects in North 
America
and Europe. 
As
a consequence, the larval and adult stages have been described for 

<tp:taxon-name>P. flava</tp:taxon-name>

in North 
America
(

) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. czekanowskii
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Russia
(

). The Oriental biogeographical region has the highest known species diversity and species density of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichoptera (

Morse 
2003

)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Because the taxonomy of 
<tp:taxon-name>Trichoptera</tp:taxon-name>
is largely based on male genitalia, most taxonomic research has focused on adults. 
As
a consequence, very few taxonomic studies have addressed the immature stages, which ironically, are more important from a water quality perspective. Clearly, many more descriptions of larvae are needed to enable a refined understanding of the benthic fauna in Southeast Asian streams.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements

</title>
         <p>
We thank the 
Thailand
Royal Forest Department for providing facilities for field work and permission to collect in the national parks, wildlife sanctuaries, and wildlife management stations. We also thank H. Malicky for a critical review of this manuscript. This study has been supported by the Royal Golden Jubilee program (Grant no. PHD/0280/ 
2545
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References

</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Dudgeon, D.
(

1999

) 

Tropical Asian streams: zoobenthos, ecology and conservation

. 

Hong Kong
University Press

, 

830
pp.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Lepneva, S.G.
(

1948

) 

Trichoptera larvae in Jenisci Basin. 
Izv. Biologo-peopr. Manchmo-Issled

. 
Irkutsk
, 

10
, 
60–99

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Malicky, H.
&amp; 
Chantaramongkol, P.
(

1991

) 

Beschreibung von 
Trichomacronema paniae
n.sp. (Trichoptera, Hydropsychidae) aus Nord-Thailand und Beobachtungen über ihre Lebensweise (Arbeit über thailändische Köcherfliegen Nr. 
9
)

. 

Entomologische Berichte Luzern

, 

25
, 
113–122

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Malicky, H.
&amp; 
Chantaramongkol, P.
(

1999

) 


A preliminary survey of the caddisflies (Trichoptera) of 
Thailand

.

Proceedings of the International Symposium on Trichoptera
, 

9
, 
205–216

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Morse, J.C.
(

2003

) 
Trichoptera (caddisflies)
. 
In
: 
Resh, V. H.
&amp; 
Cardé, R.T.
(Eds.), 

Encyclopedia of Insects

. 
Academic Press, New York
, pp. 


1145–1151


.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Ross, H.H.
(

1944

) 

The caddis flies, or Trichoptera, of Illinois

. 

Illinois Natural History Survey Bulletin, 
23

, 
326 pp.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Thamsenanupap, P.
, 
Chantaramongkol, P.
, &amp; 
Malicky, H.
(

2005

) 

Description of caddis larvae (Trichoptera) from northern 
Thailand
of the genera 
Himalopsyche
(Rhyacophilidae), 
Arctopsyche
(Arctopsychidae), cf. 
Eoneureclipsis
(Psychomyiidae) and 
Inthanopsyche
(Odontoceridae)

. 


Braueria (Lunz am See, 
Austria
)


, 

32
, 
7

– 
11
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Thapanya, D.
, 
Chantaramongkol, P.
, &amp; 
Malicky, H.
(

2004

) 

An updated survey of caddisflies (Trichoptera, Insecta) from Doi Suthep-Pui and Doi Inthanon national parks, Chiangmai Province, 
Thailand

. 

Journal of Natural History Chulalongkorn University

, 

4
, 
21–40

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
Wiggins, G.B.
(

1996

) 

Larvae of North American caddisfly genera (Trichoptera)
. Second Edition

. 
University of Toronto Press. Toronto and Buffalo
, 

457
pp.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
