<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Anthropozoologica</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5252/az2014n2a02</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Camels, donkeys and caravan trade: an emerging context from Baraqish- , ancient Yathill (Wadi- - al-Jawf, Yemen)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2014</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus dromedarius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Equus asinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
dromedarius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Equus asinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus dromedarius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ovis aries
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Capra hircus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bos taurus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus dromedarius
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Equus asinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis familiaris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Gazella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Capra ibex
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Hystrix
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Struthio camelus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arca
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Equus asinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Equus asinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Francesco G. FEDELE

Laboratorio di Antropologia, Università di Napoli ‘Federico II’, Naples, 
Italy
(retired), current address: via Foligno 78/10, 10149 Torino (
Italy
) fedele0@yahoo.it 
KEY WORDS
Dromedary (
<tp:taxon-name>
Camelus dromedarius
</tp:taxon-name>
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
wild, donkey (
<tp:taxon-name>
Equus asinus
</tp:taxon-name>
), caravan trade, archaeological indicators of ‘caravan’ activity, ‘frankincense route’ in 
Yemen
, Barāqish, Yathill.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

Fedele F. G. 2014. — Camels, donkeys and caravan trade: an emerging context from Bara¯qish, ancient Yathill (Wa -di 
al-Jawf
, 
Yemen
). 

Anthropozoologica

49 (2): 
177-194
. 

http:// dx.doi.org/ 
10.5252/az2014n2a02

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
ABSTRACT

</title>
         <p>
Work at Barāqish/Yathill in 2005-06 has produced sequences encompassing the Sabaean (13th-6th centuries BC) and Minaean/Arab (
c.
550 BC-AD 1) occupations. Abundant animal remains were retrieved and contexts of use and discard were obtained. Camels and donkeys are studied together as pack animals, the camel being the domestic dromedary. Their zooarchaeological and contextual study at Yathill is justified from this city’s location on the famous frankincense caravan route of the 1st millennium BC. An extramural stratigraphic sequence documenting the relationships between the city and the adjoining plain from 
c.
820 BC to the Islamic era was investigated to the northwest of the Minaean wall. Domestic camels were present by 800 BC, the earliest well-documented occurrence in 
Yemen
; wild dromedary herds were still in the area during the 7th century and perhaps later. The study of the archaeological context links these Sabaean-age camels to campsites possibly formed by non-residents. This pattern greatly developed during the Minaean period, with trade-jar handling posts outside the walled city and frequent stationing of camels and donkeys on the upper talus. Such data directly support the role of Yathill in the overland caravan trade and suggest that the extramural area was functionally important in this respect.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
RÉSUMÉ

Chameaux, ânes et commerce caravanier: leur contexte archéologique à Barāqish, ancient Yathill (WādĪ 
al-Jawf
, 
Yémen
).

Les travaux archéologiques à Barāqish/Yathill en 2005-2006 ont produit une séquence chronologique qui englobe des occupations de la période Sabéenne (13 
e-
6 
e
siècles BC) à la période Minéenne/Arabe (c. 550 BC-AD 1). De nombreux restes animaux ont été collectés et les contextes d’utilisations et de rejets ont pu être documentés. Les chameaux et les ânes sont étudiés ensemble comme bêtes de somme, le camélidé étant le dromadaire domestique. Leur étude archéozoologique et l’analyse contextuelle de ces restes à Yathill sont justifiées de par la localisation du site sur la route de l’encens au 1 
er
millénaire avant notre ère. Au nord-ouest du mur minéen, une séquence stratigraphique extramurale documente les relations entre la cité et la plaine environnante entre 820 BC jusqu’a l’époque 

MOTS CLÉS

islamique. Les chameaux domestiques étaient présents à 800 BC, l’occurrence la dromadaire (
<tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
</tp:taxon-name>
plus ancienne et la mieux documenté pour le 
Yémen
. Des dromadaires sauvages 

<tp:taxon-name>
dromedarius
</tp:taxon-name>
),

étaient encore dans la zone durant le 7e siècle et peut être même après. L’étude du 
<tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
sauvage, 

âne (
<tp:taxon-name>
Equus asinus
</tp:taxon-name>
),

contexte archéologique relie ces chameaux de la période sabéenne aux campements commerce caravanier, apparemment formés par des non-résidants. Ce schéma se développe largement 
indicateurs
à la période minéenne, lorsqu'on observe des cabanes pour le maniement des
</p>
         <p>
archéologiques d’activités “caravanières”, jarres commerciaux en dehors du mur de la cité et le stationnement fréquent des “route de l’encens” chameaux et des ânes sur le talus. Ce genre d’information confirme directement au 
Yémen
, Barāqish, le rôle de Yathill sur la route du commerce caravanier et suggère que cette zone Yathill. extramurale de la cité avait une fonction importante dans ce contexte.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>
INTRODUCTION AND EXCAVATIONS
</title>
         <p>
The purpose of this paper is an archaeological investigation of camels and donkeys as beasts of burden in the context of a first-millennium BC caravan station on the Arabian frankincense route, Barāqish (
Yemen
). Unless specified otherwise, the camel species referred to in this paper is the domestic dromedary, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Camelus dromedarius
</tp:taxon-name>
, while geographically the focus is Southwest Arabia. In this region and during the period under study camels and donkeys were the only pack animals commonly employed, although their usefulness extended to other tasks and economic sectors, at least occasionally (e.g. 

). In addition, following historical analogy, one can surmise that the two species might have fulfilled broadly complementary roles in parcel transport, the camel as a long-range specialist while the donkey was particularly efficient on a local to regional scale. However, these latter aspects would need to be tested archaeologically in order to define their temporal or regional oscillations.
</p>
         <p>A joint examination of camels and donkeys is thus justified in the perspective of a functional study of their combined role as beasts of burden.This role was at the same time economic and technological.If considered in isolation, each single species is insufficient for the purpose of a functional, ‘behavioural’ investigation of this particular role and the techno-economic system it determined. A further reason of interest lies with the unique importance of such a component in an Arabian context, and, more specifically, within an evolving community preeminently associated with first-millennium trade. For this period and subject Barāqish not only represents a most favourable locale, but is the only southwest Arabian site with a suitable – albeit incipient – archaeological and archaeofaunal record.An outline of archaeology and chronology and a summary of the site’s animal evidence comprise the first part of this paper. However, a functional study</p>
         <p>Area C excavations</p>
         <p>2005-2006</p>
         <p>of camels and donkeys will require an examination of archaeological context.This subject,and associated issues of archaeological theory concerning ‘caravan’ sites, will be approached in the second part of the paper.</p>
         <p>
Known in Arabic as Barāqish, ancient Yathill (or perhaps Yathull, based on Greek 
Athroula
) (
Fig. 1
) is a walled city located on the margin of Wādī 
al-Jawf
, the vast depression of northeastern 
Yemen
.Its remarkably well-preserved walls were built by the Minaeans between the 6th and 3rd centuries BC, as revealed by the Italian excavations summarized below. They enclose an area of four hectares, this figure representing a medium-sized city for the region and period (

). It has long been known from classical sources, notably Pliny (
Naturalis historia
, xii, 63), that Yathill was a stop on the main overland route for frankincense and other Arabian resins, a commerce that had probably already begun by 1000 BC (e.g. 

, 2003b; 2009, 23-29; 

; 

; 

; Potts 1998; 

; on the origins and dating see 

). Other luxury goods including spices, textiles and alabaster were traded as well (cf. 

).
</p>
         <p>Considering this role of Yathill, two main questions need be addressed: (i) what evidence is available for pack animals and, if any, how is it patterned in its</p>
         <p>m</p>
         <p>
temporal and spatial distributions? and (ii) is there any ‘hard’ evidence for caravan trade? Concerning camels, in particular, one further question emerging from the city’s location at the desert margin has been discussed elsewhere (Fedele, in press): is this setting of any specific interest in connection with the open problems of dromedary domestication? (Qualified discussions on these problems can be seen, e.g., in Al-Saud 1996; 

; 

; 

; 

.)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
BARĀQISH: STRATIGRAPHY AND CHRONOLOGY
</title>
         <p>
Archaeological excavations by the Italian Mission in 
Yemen
, led by Alessandro de Maigret, were begun in 1986- 
92 in
the temple area within the city, and resumed after a long interruption in 2004 (

; 

). During two subsequent seasons, in 2005-06, a comprehensive exploration of stratigraphy was carried out outside the Minaean wall (
Fig. 1
). This over-wall operation or Area C will be called the ‘extramural area’ in this paper. The excavation was designed to shed light on the nature of human occupation in general terms, at the presumed interface between the city and the surrounding plain and well away from the cultic precinct. Environmental information and activity indicators were also sought, and one particular purpose of this work was to retrieve animal and plant remains, for the first time in the Jawf. These goals were met with considerable success (

).
</p>
         <p>
A stepped trench was laid out on the northwestern slope of the mound, where it rises about 
15 m
above the surrounding surfaces. The mound’s margin was dug radially down and away from the wall and dissected from top to base. This trench cut into the talus and expanded beyond the foot of the slope into the adjacent plain (sectors 
D
and 
E
; the topographic sectors of the excavation will be marked in italics). Further away in the plain an isolated test pit, Sounding 
F
, was sunk 
78 m
from the nearest point of the wall. Finally, at the upper end of the operation, Sounding 
A
reached a depth of 
8 m
and brought to light the foundations of the Minaean wall (
Fig. 1
). By linking all these sectors, a comprehensive stratigraphic profile was obtained, in which sectors 
A
to 
E
in particular provide an essentially continuous cutting 
52 m
long and 
14 m
high through the outer tell and talus (‘C/S1 Reference section’; 

, 

). Only the two end portions of this profile are of interest for this article (
Fig. 2
). ‘Tell’, ‘talus’ and ‘plain’ refer to the three depositional domains represented in the extramural area, with the talus profile shifting and evolving over time as a result of the accumulationerosion balance and human activity. Neither sterile soil nor bedrock were found.
</p>
         <p>
Overall, three historical periods were recognized at Barāqish/Yathill (
Table 1
): Sabaean, Minaean (including an Arab subphase), and Islamic.The interface between the Sabaean and Minaean phases corresponds to a problematic sediment suite, Stratum K (equated with a so-called ‘Intermediate’ phase; 
Fig. 2
), possi- bly reflecting warfare and reduced occupation, after which a different material culture became common and the Minaean polity was demonstrably in control of the city (see 

for details).The Minaean phase lasted from the 6th century BC to about AD 1, with the Minaean rule proper on the wane by 200 BC; the last two centuries were characterized by the increasing presence and probable dominance of Arab tribes (

).After about AD 1 Yathill was abandoned and a similar fate involved the other cities of the Jawf, possibly as a result of shifting caravan-trade arrangements and environmental deterioration (

, 115-116; 

).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Significantly, the extramural excavations confirmed the existence of a substantial Sabaean settlement underneath the Minaean layers, reaching back to the end of the 9th century BC, but continuing further down. They also revealed that the settlement extended well beyond the surface of the Minaean city. The thickness of the Sabaean occupation was similarly documented in a temple area sounding made by de Maigret in 2006, where levels of the 13th century were reached. Detailed reports on the extramural excavations and the city sounding have been published (

; 

, 

; see also 

). For the purpose of this paper, however, only the extramural excavations are relevant, because only the bone assemblages from this area could be examined. Furthermore, as the Barāqish mission came to an unfortunate halt in 2007, only the material from Sounding 
A
could be studied in reasonable detail.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
THE ARCHAEOFAUNAL EVIDENCE
</title>
         <p>As mentioned,abundant and generally well preserved animal remains were recovered, the extramural collec-</p>
         <p>
tion numbering several thousand pieces.An overview of the faunal data for the Sabaean and the Minaean phases (
Table 2
) shows that in terms of species composition domestic animals are overwhelming.Both the Sabaeans and the Minaeans relied heavily on sheep and goat, with cattle very subordinate. Wild species are virtually nonexistent among the remains.Against this background, however, a few individual finds do stand out: several ostrich bones in the Minaean levels (

, 111-112: fig. 10f), and isolated finds of wild dromedary (
<tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
) in the Later Sabaean and possibly the Minaean phases (Fedele in press). 
Figure 3
presents a preliminary attempt at quantification on the basis of the collection from Sounding 
A
; the zooarchaeological details will be presented elsewhere. A ceramic figurine of a camel was found on the Minaean 2/3 surface in Sounding 
A
(

: fig. 10 h1).
</p>
         <p>
The temporal distribution of the camel and the donkey – or the equids in general – is significant. One can observe an increase of both with the Later Sabaean phase, and perhaps a relatively sharper increase with the advent of the Minaean presence. In fact, no donkey remains were retrieved from the Earlier Sabaean levels, although there might be traces of equid coprolites in a layer of that age. When the donkey becomes apparent, starting with the Later Sabaean, all its bones derive from mature or old animals. The fact that donkeys were killed at the end of their working life provides indirect confirmation of their chief use for transport. Given this origin of the bone residue it is usual that non-meat animals such as the donkey, the dog, and to some extent the camel, are underrepresented considerably in terms of bones. As indicated in the upper part of 
Table 2
, all bone residue in the extramural area is from cooking or meals, although the particular contexts of deposition varied over time.
</p>
         <p>
The recognition of wild dromedaries and presumed equid hybrids in the collection was based on a combination of morphological and metrical observations as well as – for the former – on considerations of context. The camel remains having been presented in detail elsewhere, in the context of a discussion of camel domestication (Fedele, in press), only the essentials are repeated here.Skeletal morphology and size indices show that domestic camels were already present by about 800 BC, one of the earliest occurrences in 
Yemen
. The available logarithmic size indices for the Barāqish finds were interpreted in light of the diagram generated by 

: fig. 3; 

: fig. 9), adopted as a reference. Most of the camel bones appear to be osteologically domestic throughout the Barāqish sequence.
</p>
         <p>
On the other hand, the case for a wild dromedary can be argued on the basis of a distal humerus from the outskirts of the Later Sabaean settlement, bordering the plain (find 151.1 from Locus 
151 in
sector 
E
, see below; cf. 
Fig.2
,below; 
Fig.5
), and less confidently for a phalanx from a Minaean 1 level.There is little doubt that the large humerus belongs to a wild animal of dromedary morphology (LSI= 0.045).The bone was chopped by heavy percussion and partially roasted;in surface appearance and size it is very different from all other camel material from the extramural area. Locus 151, which as part of Stratum M can be dated within the 7th century BC, contained two more fragments of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Camelus
</tp:taxon-name>
long bones, also slightly burnt.
</p>
         <p>
Althrough obviously limited,these finds are interesting because they indicate that wild dromedary herds still existed in 
Yemen
during the 7th and perhaps as late as the mid-first millennium BC (cf. 

, 257; 
U.A.E.
data), when the domestication of the species had been under way for a long time and was being perfected (Fedele, in press, with references). The wild population inferred from humerus 151.1 may be located in the wider area of Yathill, but this is unsure. Although the bone may be a result of episodical hunting by residents of Yathill, it might, alternatively, derive from a chance encounter with a wild herd in the course of travel or caravan traffic, and thus have been brought in from greater distance for meat.
</p>
         <p>
Both the Sabaean and Minaean donkeys were small. However, there is a possibility of equid hybrids in the Minaean. A metrical analysis of the measured bones would suggest that at least an astragalus is from a mule, while a first ‘asinine’ phalanx appears to fall within the hemione distribution, as does a second phalanx (
Fig.4
). Since no caballine trait is detectable, all these presumed hybrids would derive –surprisingly – from crosses with hemiones (onagers).Incidentally, an upper premolar or molar shows a mix of ass and ‘hemione’ traits as well. Onagers might have been present on the borders of the Ramlat as-Sab‘atayn desert of 
Yemen
, albeit at an earlier date (revised data from site HAR2, cf. Fedele in 

, 141-145; mentioned in 

, 69), but of course this contention is problematic and needs further research.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ARCHAEOLOGICAL CONTEXT AND THEORY
</title>
         <p>
In this section the archaeological contexts in which camels and donkeys occur at Barāqish will be reviewed. As mentioned, an examination of archaeological context is essential for approaching a functional study of animals’ roles through time and in connection with people. From this perspec- tive, and starting with the Sabaean evidence, it is of interest that the sampled contexts at the base of the Sabaean talus and in the adjacent plain appear to suggest the occurrence of campsites or tentsites, possibly partly formed by non-residents. In particular, the context associated with camel humerus 151.1 (cited above) suggests a clustered tentsite-like feature outside the settlement, one in a series of such traces stratified on the former plain along the footslope of the talus (
Fig. 5
).
</p>
         <p>
The composition and condition of materials in Locus 151 do not suggest ‘normal’ kitchen refuse. Rather than intensive occupation they indicate repeated episodes of activity in the open, possibly associated with light-shelter constructions. The archaeological association – cooking pots, tripods, pans, ‘torpedo’ jars and evidence of burning – combined with what looks like a patchy distribution of activity clusters, suggests a scenario of bivouacs or tents on the plain. Some unusual or exotic items (cf. 
Table 4
) may further suggest that foreign parties – occasional ‘migrants’? merchant caravans? – were possibly involved. Although ‘torpedo’ jars have recently been demoted from their presumed role of specialized trade containers (this latter reiterated by de Maigret, e.g. 2003a), a general association with sealed beverage transport (

) appears to fit a ‘migrant’ campsite scenario.
</p>
         <p>This kind of inference sounds rather daring at the present stage of the excavations, given the very limited evidence that it was possible to obtain from one restricted sampling round the city perimeter. Unfortunately at the moment one can only glimpse a pattern, to which the direct, walking experience of the Barāqish setting, and surface observations at some distance west of the tell, seem to add credibility. With this caveat in mind, how can we enhance our possibility of detecting patterns and contexts capable of shedding light on any remnant of transient campsites? It is widely known that the available literature on the material correlates of nomadism, or ‘transience’ more generally, is fairly scanty. Caravan activity should be understood archaeologically as a kind of nomadism.</p>
         <p>
With 

; my emphasis) one can state that ‘archaeologists are 
just beginning
to develop techniques for identifying sites representing early forms of pastoral activities, especially those with higher mobility. [...] Ephemeral occupations, shallow deposits, and poor surface evidence cannot be dismissed as reasons why mobile pastoralist sites have been neglected in regional surveys.’ But whereas mobile pastoralist sites have now been examined with a relatively focused approach, sites generated by other kinds of ‘migrants’ – including pack-transport sites and even ‘caravan’ sites – have generally eluded specific consideration. This touches particularly upon the material, non-textual evidence for caravan trade, which is a research subject still neglected in mainstream South Arabian archaeology. Artefactual correlates and offsite traces await investigation in 
Yemen
and over most of Arabia (cf. 

).
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
In 
Table 3
, the elements of a theory of archaeological evidence for caravan activity are tentatively outlined, as an attempt towards a more general theory of the material correlates of ‘transience’. The table lists five separate ‘activity modes’ and a number of archaeological and zooarchaeological ‘indicators’, admittedly inspired from the case of archaeological Barāqish and ancient Yathill. The information in the table was compiled from a critical reading of literature, while informal observations personally made in 
Iraq
(1980-81) and 
Yemen
(1984-2007) were also useful. For such data and the relevant interpretive framework particular reference should be made to 

, 181, 256-265), 

, 

, 

), David &amp; Kramer (2001, 239-242, 255-270), 

, 

, 

, 

, 

), 

, 

, 126), 

, 

, 

, 

), 

, 

, 

, 

, 135- 144), and to contributions in seminal edited volumes such as 

, Bar-Yosef &amp; Khazanov (1992) and 

. Limits of space prevent from a detailed discussion, and this complex subject is being developed for publication elsewhere.
</p>
         <p>Fedele F. G.</p>
         <p>INDICATORS OF CARAVAN TRADE IN THE SABAEAN AND MINAEAN CONTEXTS</p>
         <p>
With the above framework in mind, two separate lists of activity indicators potentially bearing on caravan trade are here presented for the Sabaean and the Minaean levels. 
Table 4
is a summary of the indicators for ‘tent-camping’ and/or ‘foreigners/migrants’ from the Sabaean sequence, mostly dating from the Later Sabaean (7th and possibly early 6th century BC). Following the entries in the figure, one can recognize (i) indications of regular stays of camels and perhaps donkeys; (ii) the occurrence of cultural residue both clustered and suggestive of ‘light’ cooking and meals in the open (already mentioned above); and (iii) a possibility that ‘foreigners’ were often involved, to judge from some rather exotic items, such as the wild dromedary humerus and its cluster. Were these non-residents not just ‘foreigners’ or ‘travellers’, but traders? The peculiar clustering of cultural debris and burnt patches can be particularly observed in the Later Sabaean occupation levels (
Fig. 5
), by which time camels and donkeys had clearly become more significant (
Table 2
; 
Fig. 3
).
</p>
         <p>The extramural excavations may thus provide first-hand evidence for trade as early as the Sabaean period: camels as probable pack animals, jar handling, exotic items, and camping in tents (Fedele, in press). With further data trade may emerge – unsurprisingly – as a pivotal factor in Yathill’s existence from the beginning. Of course, the Sabaean occupation of Yathill should be much more widely investigated before sound judgments can be made on the subject.</p>
         <p>
However, during the Minaean occupation this kind of archaeological pattern developed further, with our data pointing to a broad specialization in the material repertoire. There are already hints of this development in the Intermediate phase, during the deposition of Stratum K. In 
Table 5 a
list of the activity indicators for ‘tent-camping’ and/ or ‘foreigners’ and/or trade is presented for the Mi- spatial patterning itself adds to the evidence for naean; trade can now be written without quotation extramural specialization during the Minaean pemarks because there is positive evidence for it. The riod (

). These three locations and the finds from the Minaean sequence in the extramural information they provide will be briefly reviewed. area can indeed be reduced to a narrow range of A significant piece of evidence is represented by categories, a vast proportion being represented by the recognition of trade-jar handling posts outside the indicators on this list. Several indications from the walled city, along and near the wall itself, on the bone evidence (
Table 5
, bottom) have already a recurrent basis during the Later Minaean. The been mentioned. It must be reported in this context existence of an imposing wall created new opporthat the presence of foreigners at Minaean Yathill tunities in this respect. Direct evidence for trade has now been directly shown by the excavation of has come to light, particularly including jar sealing, a presumed cenotaph cemetery on Hill D to the as demonstrated by stamped plaster (
cretulae
) and west of the city (cf. 
Fig. 1
, inset); from the ‘rather lithic evidence for jar stopper manufacture (flaked lowly social status’ inferred through the burials it discs made from cryptocrystalline limestone; Fewas thought that the cemetery is ‘possibly to be as- dele 2011: fig. 10 b; on jar sealings in general see sociated with the caravaneers themselves’ (Antonini 

). Such material is associated in the and Agostini 2010, 45). levels of Minaean 4 with a decayed stone and
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
Furthermore, the available evidence is spatially mudbrick structure, interpreted as a jar-sealing concentrated. Three locations are involved: the workshop, in which people both worked and great wall, the upper talus, and the plain. Taking lived (structure F8; 

, 114-115: fig. 8 into due account the geomorphic and culturally- b). It was perhaps only one of several such sheds induced evolution of the talus (

), this located against the wall.
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>Concerning the animals of burden, during the Minaean one can observe:</p>
         <p>
•
an unprecedented frequency of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Equus asinus
</tp:taxon-name>
, almost exclusively represented by adult or aged individuals;
</p>
         <p>
•
and (almost certainly) the appearance of mules;
</p>
         <p>all indicators of systematic use of donkeys in work and/or pack transport;</p>
         <p>and plausible indicators of at least local transport (hence probably short-distance trade?).</p>
         <p>
A concurrent and complementary piece of evidence is relevant to our subject: the dark brown ‘manure’ layers in the upper part of the extramural deposits, precisely corresponding to a part of Stratum K and the whole series of the Minaean strata.Their location is the former upper talus (
Fig. 2
, above; 
Fig. 6
). In these layers both ‘manure’ – i.e. dung – and ‘plantorganic’ units can be distinguished, on the basis of the composition and ratio of actual excreta to plant fraction, as well as sedimentary texture cum structure. The reader is referred for details to previous work (

, 

); chemical analyses and a search for spherulites, unfortunately, could not be arranged, but the nature and origin of such lenses and layers cannot be doubted. Where preservation is good, camel and donkey coprolites constitute the large majority of the recognizable components.
</p>
         <p>
The pattern exhibited by such a rich sequence of dung and dung-enriched layers is unprecedented in the sedimentary history of the extramural area. The interpretation is inescapable:throughout the Minaean period there must have been frequent stationing of camels and donkeys on the upper talus. From excavation sectors 
B
and 
C
we have reconstructed that the stationing would particularly occur on level strips below the wall, in a belt 
7-20 m
from the curtain (cf. 
Fig. 2
), and the area concerned can vaguely be perceived behind the present morphology (
Fig. 6
). At times, constructed stalls or enclosures for camels and/or donkeys may have existed,as dung concentrations often are indicators of enclosed animals, and a pointed vertical stake was indeed found in sector 
B
.
</p>
         <p>
The other area in which the Minaeans dealt with trade jars, or trading in general, in addition to the strip between the upper talus and wall, was the plain. Although extremely restricted,the sampling provided by Sounding 
F
was revealing. There is evidence of Minaean levels replete with both trading-jar remains and flakes from lithic jar stoppers.Whole stoppers are also frequent. Fragments of cuboid burners made of limestone, probably to be explained as broken lamps left by camping parties, are only common in this area (
F
) and at the base of the talus (lower sector 
E
; on the function of these ‘incense’ burners cf. 

, 115, with references). Additional clues to the role of the extramural areas to the west of the city come from the already mentioned excavation carried out by S. Antonini on Hill D (cf. 
Fig. 1
, inset). The presence of plaster jar sealings, clay stoppers for trade jars, and even a bronze seal fragment, although coming from reworked aggregates (

), might provide further evidence for caravan trade activity on Hill D or nearby, at a distance of a mere 
100-120 m
from the Minaean activity locations discussed above.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
CONCLUDING REMARKS
</title>
         <p>
Within the obvious excavation limits, two areas present indisputable evidence pertaining to trade during the Minaean period. One is the area flanking the north-western wall, a short distance from the city’s gate, which appears to have been particularly and repeatedly used for the handling of trade jars, while pack animals were often kept on the talus a little below. One could surmise that several operations connected with trade goods took place in installations outside the walls, plausibly including the packing and dispatching of caravans. Concurrently, the adjoining flats to the northwest of the tell appear to have been used within the same functional framework. Also a low outlying mound, Hill C (
Fig. 1
), might have played a role in connection with both caravan tent camps and the daily unloading and loading of animals.An archaeological package suggesting caravan commerce thus emerges as a functional signature for the plain and talus, to the exclusion of any other systematic activity.
</p>
         <p>
The areas to the west and northwest of the city might indeed emerge as the preferred location for this vital activity of Yathill, and especially for the stands or sojourns of people and animals. The relative proximity to the city’s gate might have been important. At traffic peaks caravan space had to be found extramurally,Yathill being too small to provide rest for hundreds or thousands of dromedaries – the average caravan.In such a case separation of caravan space from city space was probably standard. Analogies from pre-modern historical sources may help flesh out the composition of ancient trans-Arabian caravans and their behaviour in relation to stagingpost cities (e.g. Jāzim and Leclercq-Neveu 2001). Admittedly, apart from our scrutiny along radius 
A–F
, little is known of the remainder of the areas encircling Yathill.
</p>
         <p>Although Yathill’s association with overland caravan trade has long been deduced from geographic position and textual sources, mainly classical,the data reviewed in this article begin to support this pivotal role of the city with direct and explicit archaeological evidence. The emphasis is on material culture, the extramural excavations providing modest but tangible evidence for this defining aspect of Minaean society. Equally important is a preliminary indication that at least part of the functional patterns detected for the Minaean period were already effective during the preceding occupation by the Sabaeans. It seems reasonable to infer that throughout the first-millennium history of Yathill the plain and eventually the talus were not inert appendages of the tell, but in fact specialized, fully functional parts of the settlement.</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgments
</p>
         <p>
I wish to thank Clive Gamble (University of London) for a much-appreciated copy of his monograph, 

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES
</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
AKKERMANS P. M. M. G.
1993
. — 

Villages in the Steppe. Late Neolithic Settlement and Subsistence in the Balikh Valley, Northern Syria
. Archaeological

Series 5. 
International Monographs in Prehistory. Ann Arbor
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
AL- 
SAUD A. S.
1996
. — 
The domestication of camels and inland trading routes in Arabia
. 

Atlal

14
: 
129-136
(English section), 99-104 (Arabic section).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ANTONINI S.
&amp; 
AGOSTINI A.
2010
. — 

A Minaean Necropolis at Barāqish (Jawf, Republic of Yemen). Preliminary Report of the 2005-2006 Archaeological Campaigns
. Istituto Italiano per l’Africa e l’Oriente

. 
Rome
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
BARNARD H.
&amp; 
WENDRICH W.
(eds) 
2008
. — 

The Archaeology of Mobility. Old World and New World Nomadism
. Cotsen Advanced Seminars 4

. 
Cotsen Institute of Archaeology, University of California. Los Angeles
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
BAR- 
YOSEF O.
&amp; 
KHAZANOV A.
(
EDS
) 
1992
. — 

Pastoralism in the Levant. Archaeological Materials in Anthropological Perspectives

. 
Prehistory Press. Madison
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
BEECH M.
, 
MASHKOUR M.
, 
HUELS M.
&amp; 
ZAZZO A.
2009
. — 
Prehistoric camels in south-eastern Arabia: the discovery of a new site in Abu Dhabi’s Western Region, United Arab Emirates
. 

Proceedings of the Seminar for Arabian Studies

39
: 
17-30
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
BRUNNER U.
1997
. — 
Geography and human settlements in ancient Southern Arabia
. 

Arabian Archaeology and Epigraphy

8
: 
190-202
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
CHANG C.
&amp; 
KOSTER H. A.
1986
. — 
Beyond bones: toward an archaeology of pastoralism
. 
in
SCHIFFER M. B.
(ed.), 

Advances in Archaeological Method and Theory

, 
vol
. 
9
: 
97-148
. Academic Press (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, Publishers). Orlando.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
COSTA P. M.
1991
. — 
South Arabian jar sealings
. 

Proceedings of the Seminar for Arabian Studies

21
: 
41-48
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
CRIBB R. L. D.
1991
. — 
Mobile villagers: the structure and organisation of nomadic pastoral campsites in the Near East
. 
in
GAMBLE C. S.
&amp; 
BOISMIER W. A.
(eds), 

Ethnoarchaeological Approaches to Mobile Campsites. Hunter-gatherer and Pastoralist Case Studies
, International Monographs in Prehistory

. 
Ann Arbor
: 
371-393
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
CRIBB R.
2004

[originally published 1991]. — 
Nomads in Archaeology

. 
Cambridge, Cambridge University Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
D 
AVID N.
&amp; 
KRAMER C.
2001
. — 

Ethnoarchaeology in Action

. 
Cambridge, Cambridge University Press
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DE MAIGRET A.
1997
. — 
The frankincense road from Najrān to Ma‘ān: a hypothetical itinerary
. 
in
AVAN-
ZINI A.
(ed.), 
Profumi d’Arabia. Atti del Convegno
, 
315-331
. ‘ 
L’Erma’ di Bretschneider. Rome
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DE MAIGRET A.
2004
. — 

Barāqish, Minaean Yathill. Excavation and Restoration of the Temple of Nakrah

. 

YICAR Papers 1. San‘ā [
sic
] Italian Archaeological Mission in the Republic of Yemen

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DE MAIGRET A.
2003
A. — La ceramica sabea
. 
Specifi-
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DE MAIGRET A.
2003

B. — L’ancienne route caravanière de l’encens dans l’Arabie préislamique. Éléments d’information sur son itinéraire et sa chronologie. 
Chroniques Yéménites
11: Online

http://cy.revues. org/160#ftn0
, accessed 
31 October 2011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

DE
MAIGRET A.

2009
. — 

Arabia Felix. An Exploration of the Archaeological History of Yemen.
2nd ed. with a foreword by Professor T

. 
J. Wilkinson. London, Stacey International
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DE MAIGRET A.
2010
. — 
A ‘Sabaean’ stratigraphy from Barāqish
. 

Arabia
4 (2007-10): 67

- 
95
, 
205-240
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DE MAIGRET A.
&amp; 
ROBIN C.
1993
. — 
Le temple de Nakrah à Yathill (aujourd’hui Barāqish), Yémen, résultats des deux premières campagnes de fouilles de la Mission italienne
. 

Académie des Inscriptions &amp; Belles-Lettres, Comptes rendus des séances de l’année 1993

137
(
2
): 
427-496
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
DI MARIO F.
, 
COSTANTINI L.
, 
FEDELE F. G.
, 
GRAVINA F.
&amp; 
SMRIGLIO C.
1989
. — 
The western ar-Rub‘ al- Khālī ‘Neolithic’: new data from the Ramlat Sab‘atayn (Yemen Arab Republic)
. 

Annali, Istituto Universitario Orientale

49
: 
109-148
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
EDENS C.
&amp; 
WILKINSON T. J.
1998
. — 
Southwest Arabia during the Holocene: recent archaeological developments
. 

Journal of World Prehistory

12
(
1
): 
55-119
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
FEDELE F. G.
2009
. — 
Sabaean animal economy and household consumption at Yalā, eastern Khawlān al- Tiyāl, Yemen
. 

Proceedings of the Seminar for Arabian Studies

39
: 
135-154
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
FEDELE F. G.
2010
. — 
Barāqish, over-wall excavations 2005-2006: stratigraphy, environment and economy of the Sabaean-Islamic sequence
. 

Arabia
4 (2007-10): 97

- 
161
, 
241-257
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
FEDELE F. G.
2011
. — 
The wall and talus at Barāqish, ancient Yathill (al-Jawf, Yemen): a Minaean stratigraphy
. 

Proceedings of the Seminar for Arabian Studies

41
: 
101-120
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
FEDELE F. G.
IN PRESS
. — 

New data on domestic and wild camels (
Camelus dromedarius
and 
Camelus
sp.) in Sabaean and Minaean Yemen. 
in


MASHKOUR M.

&amp; 

BEECH M.

(eds), 

Archaeozoology of the Near East IX. Proceedings of the Ninth International Symposium on the Archaeozoology of Southwestern Asia and Adjacent Areas, Al Ain, Abu Dhabi (UAE), November 
2008
.

Oxford, Oxbow Books
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
GAMBLE C. S.
&amp; 
BOISMIER W. A.
(eds) 
1991
. — 

Ethnoarchaeological Approaches to Mobile Campsites. Huntergatherer and Pastoralist Case Studies
. International Monographs in Prehistory, Ethnoarchaeological

Series 1. 
Ann Arbor, International Monographs in Prehistory
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
GILBERT A. S.
1975
. — 
Modern nomads and prehistoric pastoralists: the limits of analogy
. 

The Journal of the Ancient Near Eastern Society of Columbia University

7
: 
53-71
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
GLANZMAN W. D.
2004
. — 
Ancient South Arabia’s camel caravans: a reassessment of the evidence, and the road ahead. Abstract
presented at 
the Seminar for Arabian Studies, London, 22 July.Online
http://www. arabianseminar.org.uk/abstracts2004.html
, accessed 
31 October 2011
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
GROOM N.
STJ
. 
1981
. — 

Frankincense and Myrrh: A Study of the Arabian Incense Trade
.

Longman. London, New York
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
GYSELEN R.
(
ED
.) 
1998
. — 

Parfums d’Orient

. 
Res Orientales 11. Bures-sur-Yvette, Groupe pour L’Étude de la Civilisation du Moyen-Orient; Peeters. Leuven
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
HARRINGTON R.
1978
. — 
On the frankincense road in Yemen
. 

Canadian Geographical Journal

95
(
3
): 
14-21
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
HOLE F.
1978
. — 
Pastoral nomadism in western Iran
. In 
GOULD R. A.
(ed.), 

Explorations in Ethnoarchaeology
, School of American Research Advanced Seminar Series

. 
University of New Mexico Press. Albuquerque
: 
127-167
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
HOLE F.
1979
. — 
Re-discovering the past in the present: ethnoarchaeology in Luristan, Iran
. In 
KRAMER C.
(ed.), 

Ethnoarchaeology: Implications of Ethnography for Archaeology

. 
Columbia University Press. New York
: 
192-218
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
HOLE F.
1980
. — 
The prehistory of herding: some suggestions from ethnography
. 
in
BARRELET M. T.
(ed.), 

L’Archéologie de l’Iraq du Début de l’Époque Néolithique à 333 Avant Notre Ère

, 
Paris, Éditions du Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique
: 
119-130
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
HOLE F.
2009
. — 
Pastoral mobility as an adaptation
. In 
SZUCHMAN J.
(ed.), 

Nomads, Tribes, and the State in the Ancient Near East. Cross-disciplinary Perspectives

, 
The Oriental Institute of the University of Chicago
: 
261-283
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
JASMIN M.
2005
. — 

Les conditions d’émergence de la route de l’encens à la fin du 
IIe
millénaire avant notre ère

. 

Syria

82
: 
49-62
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
JĀ ZIM M. K. A.
&amp; LECLERCQ- 
NEVEU B.
2001
. — 

L’organisation des caravanes au Yémen selon al-Hamdânî (
Xe
siècle)

. 

Chroniques Yéménites

9
: 
2-9
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
KITCHEN K. A.
1997
. — 
Sheba and Arabia
. In 
HANDY L. K.
(ed.), 

The Age of Solomon. Scholarship at the Turn of the Millennium

, 
126-153
. 
Leiden, New York, Köln, Brill
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
LIVERANI M.
1992
. — 
Early caravan trade between South- Arabia and Mesopotamia
. 

Yemen. Studi Archeologici, Storici e Filologici sull’Arabia Meridionale

1
: 
111-115
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
MASHKOUR M.
&amp; 
ABDI K.
2002
. — 
The question of mobile pastoralist campsites in archaeology: the case of Tuwah Khoshkeh
. 
in
BUITENHUIS H.
, 
CHOYKE A. M.
, 
MASHKOUR M.
&amp; AL- 
SHIYAB A. H.
(eds), 

Archaeozoology of the Near East V. Proceedings of the Fifth International Symposium on the Archaeozoology of Southwestern Asia and Adjacent Regions

, 
ARC- Publicaties
62
. Groningen: 
211-227
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
MCDONALD M.
1998
. — 
Early African pastoralism: view from Dakhleh Oasis (South Central Egypt)
. 

Journal of Anthropological Archaeology

17
: 
124-142
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
MORTENSEN P.
1972
. — 
Seasonal camps and early villages in the Zagros
. 
in
UCKO P. J.
, 
TRINGHAM R.
&amp; 
DIMBLEBY W.
(eds), 

Man, Settlement and Urbanism

, 
293-298
. 
London, Gerald Duckworth &amp; Co
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
PACHUR H. J.
1991
. — 
Tethering stones as palaeoenvironmental indicators
. 

Sahara

4
: 
13-32
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
PETERS J.
2001
. — 

Aspekte der Domestikations- und Kulturgeschichte des Dromedars (
Camelus dromedarius
)

. 
in
BUITENHUIS H.
&amp; 
PRUMMEL W.
(eds), 

Animals and Man in the Past. Essays in Honour of Dr. A. T. Clason Emeritus Professor of Archaeozoology Rijksuniversiteit Groningen, The Netherlands

. 
ARC- Publicaties
41
. Groningen: 
330-341
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
PORTER A.
, 
STACEY R.
&amp; 
DERHAM B.
2009
. — 
The function of ceramic jar Type 4100: a preliminary organic residue analysis
. 

Proceedings of the Seminar for Arabian Studies

39
: 
337-350
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
POTTS D. T.
1988
. — 
Trans-Arabian routes of the Pre- Islamic period
. 
in
SALLES J. F.
(ed.), 

L’Arabie et Ses Mers Bordiers
. Travaux de la Maison de l’Orient. Maison de l’Orient et de la Méditerranée

. 
Lyon
: 
127-162
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
RETSÖ J.
1991
. — 
The domestication of the camel and the establishment of the Frankincense Road from south Arabia
. 

Orientalia Suecana

40
: 
187-219
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ROBIN C.
&amp; 
DE MAIGRET A.
2009
. — 
Le royaume sudarabique de Ma‘īn: nouvelles données grâce aux fouilles italiennes de Barāqish (l’antique Yathill)
. 

Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres, Comptes rendus des séances de l’année 2009

153
(
1
): 
57-96
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ROSEN S. A.
1993
. — 
A Roman period pastoral tent camp in the Negev, Israel
. 

Journal of Field Archaeology

20
: 
441-451
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ROSEN S. A.
2003
. — 
Early multi-resource nomadism: excavations at the Camel site in the central Negev
. 

Antiquity

77
(
298
): 
750-761
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
SAIDEL B. A.
2009
. — 
Pitching camp: ethnoarchaeological investigations of inhabited tent camps in the Wadi Hisma, Jordan
. 
in
SZUCHMAN J.
(ed.), 

Nomads,Tribes, and the State in the Ancient Near East. Cross-disciplinary Perspectives

: 
87-104
. 
Chicago, The Oriental Institute of the University of Chicago
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
SCHIETTECATTE J.
2010
. — 
Why did the cities of the Jawf valley collapse? An archaeogeographical approach
. 
in
ALARASHI H.
, 
CHAMBRADE M.-L.
, 
GONDET S.
, 
JOUVENEL A.
, 
SAUVAGE C.
&amp; 
TRONCHÈRE H.
(eds), 

Regards Croisés sur l’Étude Archéologique des Paysages Anciens. Nouvelles Recherches dans le Bassin Méditerranéen, en Asie Centrale et au Proche et au Moyen-Orient
. Travaux de la Maison de l’Orient. Maison de l’Orient et de la Méditerranée

. 
Lyon
: 
149-161
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
SWEET L. E.
1965
. — 
Camel pastoralism in north Arabia and the minimal camping unit
. 
in
LEEDS A.
&amp; 
VAYDA A. P.
(eds), 

Man, Culture, and Animals. The Role of Animals in Human Ecological Adjust- ments
, AAAS Publication 78

. 
American Association for the Advancement of Science. Washington, DC
: 
129-152
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
UERPMANN H.-P.
1991
. — 

Equus africanus
in Arabia

. In 
MEADOW R. H.
&amp; 
UERPMANN H-P.
(eds), 

Equids in the Ancient World. II
, Beihefte zum Tübinger Atlas des Vorderen Orients, Reihe A

19/2, 
Dr. Ludwig Reichert Verlag, Wiesbaden
: 
12-33
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
UERPMANN H.-P.
&amp; 
UERPMANN M.
2002
. — 
The ap- pearance of the domestic camel in south-east Arabia
. 

The Journal of Oman Studies

12
: 
235-260
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
YEKUTIELI Y.
2009
. — 
The Har Hemar site: a northern outpost on the desert margin?

Tel Aviv

36
(
2
): 
218-240
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
ZARINS J.
1989
. — 
Pastoralism in southwest Asia: the second millennium BC
. 
in
CLUTTON-
BROCK J.
(ed.), 

The Walking Larder. Patterns of Domestication, Pastoralism, and Predation
, One World Archaeology 2. Unwin Hyman. London

: 
127-155
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
