<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.112234</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Grayanane diterpenoid glucosides as potent analgesics from Pieris
               japonica</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Pieris japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Pieris japonica (Thunb.) D. Don ex G. Don </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Pieris japonica (Thunb.) D. Don ex G. Don </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Rhododendron molle </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> R. decorum ( Zhu et al., 2018 ) </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> R. micranthum </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> R. auriculatum </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Pieris formosa </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> R. molle </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> Pieris japonica (Thunb.) D. Don ex G. Don </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> R. micranthum </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. formosa </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P . japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica (Thunb.) D. Don ex G. Don </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Grayanane diterpenoid glucosides as potent analgesics from <tp:taxon-name> Pieris
               japonica </tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p> Guijuan Zheng a , Pengfei Jin a , Lang Huang a , Na Sun a , Hanqi Zhang a , Hao Zhang b
            , Mingbo Yue b , </p>
         <p> Lingkui Meng a , Guangmin Yao a, ∗ </p>
         <p> a Hubei Key Laboratory of Natural Medicinal Chemistry and Resource Evaluation, School
            of Pharmacy , Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University of Science and </p>
         <p> Technology, Wuhan, 430030, PR China </p>
         <p> b School of Chemistry and Chemical Engineering, Qufu Normal University, Qufu, 273165,
            PR China </p>
         <p>A R T I C L E I N F O</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title> Keywords: </title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name> Pieris japonica (Thunb.) D. Don ex G. Don </tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) </p>
         <p>Grayanane diterpenoid glucosides Single-crystal X-ray diffraction</p>
         <p>Analgesic activity</p>
         <p>Structure-activity relationships</p>
         <p>A B S T R A C T</p>
         <p> A total of fifteen grayanane diterpenoid glucosides including eight undescribed ones,
            pierisjaponosides A−H, were isolated from the leaves of <tp:taxon-name> Pieris japonica
               (Thunb.) D. Don ex G. Don </tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            ). Their structures were established by extensive spectros copic techniques including
            HRESIMS and NMR, as well as chemical methods. The absolute configurations of
            pierisjaponosides A, B, and D were finally established by single-crystal X-ray
            diffraction with Cu K α radiation. This is the first time to report the crystal
            structure of a 5,9-epoxygrayanane diterpenoid glucoside. Pierisjaponoside E represents
            the first example of a 9 β -hydroxygrayan-1(10)-ene diterpenoid. All the isolated
            grayanane diterpenoid glucosides were evaluated for their analgesic activities in the
            acetic acid-induced writhing models in mice, and showed significant analgesic effects.
            Pierisjaponosides A and C–H, micranthanoside A, pieroside A, and craiobiosides A and B
            displayed significant analgesic effects with the writhe inhibition rates over 50% at a
            dose of 5.0 mg/kg. Pierisjaponoside E exhibited significant analgesic activities with
            the percentage inhibitions of 81.7%, 70.4%, and 52.1% at the doses of 5.0, 1.0, and 0.2
            mg /kg, respectively. The preliminary structure-activity relationships of grayanane
            diterpenoid glucosides as potent analgesics were discussed, giving some clues to design
            novel analgesics. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 1. Introduction </title>
         <p> The International Association for the Study of Pain (IASP) defines pain as “an
            unpleasant sensory and emotional experience associated with actual or potential tissue
            damage or described in terms of such damages” ( ). The duration of the painful stimulus
            can be classified as acute pain and chronic pain. Acute pain has protective value for
            human bodies. Chronic pain is an international health issue of immense importance that
            is influenced by negatively physical and psychological factors, such as sleep, work,
            daily activities, and overall quality of life ( ). At present, μ - opioid receptor
            agonists and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) are generally used to relieve
            pains in clinic. Opioids are the most potent and prevalently used analgesic agents for
            the treatment of severe acute, surgical, and cancer pain ( ). However, opioid analgesics
            are fought with problematic adverse effects, such as dependence, tolerance, somnolence,
            vomiting, and respiratory depression ( ). NSAIDs are proved to cause gastrointestinal
            reactions, such as gastric ulcers, gastric bleeding, as well as allergic reactions ( ).
            Thus, it is urgent to </p>
         <p> ∗ Corresponding author. find novel analgesics with high efficiency and low toxicity. </p>
         <p> Natural products from medicinal plants are tremendous sources of new drug candidates (
            ), and morphine, a μ - opioid receptor agonist, is the first naturally occurring
            analgesic. The <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name> plants are famous not only for
            their beautiful flowers but also for the structurally novel diterpenoids with
            significant biological activities ( , , , ; , , ; ). Recently, grayanane and related
            diterpenoids with significant analgesic activities have been reported from the
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name> plants such as <tp:taxon-name> Rhododendron
               molle </tp:taxon-name> ( , 2018), <tp:taxon-name> R. decorum ( Zhu et al., 2018 )
            </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> R. micranthum </tp:taxon-name> ( , ; ),
               <tp:taxon-name> R. auriculatum </tp:taxon-name> ( , ), and <tp:taxon-name> Pieris
               formosa </tp:taxon-name> ( , ). Among them, rhodojaponins III and VI from the roots
            of <tp:taxon-name> R. molle </tp:taxon-name> showed significant analgesic effects than
            the positive control morphine and ibuprofen in the acute and inflammatory pain models (
            ). In the streptozotocin-induced diabetic mouse models, rhodojaponins III and VI also
            showed comparable potency at a lower dose ( 0.4 mg /kg) than gabapentin ( 50 mg /kg), a
            firstline agent for neuropathic pain treatment ( ). Therefore, grayanane diterpenoids
            may represent a new class of naturally occurring non-opioid analgesics, which stimulates
            us to search for novel diterpenoids with analgesic activities from
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name> plants. </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name> Pieris japonica (Thunb.) D. Don ex G. Don </tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) is a deciduous shrub or small tree and
            distributes in Anhui , Zhejiang , and Fujian provinces of the Mainland China , as well
            as Japan . The leaves of <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name> have been used as
            a traditional medicine to treat tinea and scabies ( ). Literature survey revealed that
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name> is a potent source of grayanane
            diterpenoids ( ), and total 42 diterpenoids have been reported so far ( ). However, only
            two grayanane diterpenoid glucosides, pierosides A ( ) and C ( ), were reported from the
            leaves of <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name> which were collected in Japan .
            To date, there is no report of grayanane diterpenoid glucosides from <tp:taxon-name> P.
               japonica </tp:taxon-name> collected in China . </p>
         <p> To search for novel naturally occurring analgesics from
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name> plants in China ( , , , ), the leaves of
               <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name> collected at Baishanzu scenery, Zhejiang
            province , China , were investigated, leading to the isolation of fifteen grayanane
            diterpenoids ( 1–15 ) ( Fig. 1 ). Among them, eight diterpenoid glucosides are
            previously undescribed and named pierisjaponosides A−H ( 1–8 ). The absolute
            configurations of pierisjaponosides A ( 1 ), B ( 2 ), and D ( 4 ) were unambiguously
            established by single-crystal X-ray diffraction. This is the first time to report the
            crystal structure of a 5,9-epoxygrayanane diterpenoid glucoside. Pierisjaponoside E ( 5
            ) represents the first example of a 9 β -hydroxygrayan-1(10)-ene diterpenoid. More
            importantly, all the isolated grayanane diterpenoid glucosides 1–15 showed significant
            analgesic activities. In this paper, the isolation, structure elucidation, analgesic
            activities, and structure-activity relationships of 1−15 as analgesics would be
            discussed. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 2. Results and discussions </title>
         <p> The leaves of <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name> were powdered and extracted
            with 95% EtOH at room temperature, and the crude extract was suspended in H 2 O and
            partitioned with petroleum ether, EtOAc, and n -BuOH. The polar EtOAc and n -BuOH
            fractions were subjected to repeated column chromatography over silica gel, Sephadex
            LH-20, reverse phase (RP) C 18 , and semipreparative RP C 18 or phenyl HPLC to obtain
            eight unreported grayanane diterpenoid glucosides, named pierisjaponosides A−H ( 1–8 ),
            and seven known analogues ( 9–15 ), which were identified to be grayanosides B ( 10 ) (
            ), C ( 14 ) ( ), and D ( 9 ) (Sakakibara and Shirai, 1980), micranthanoside A ( 11 ) (
            ), pieroside A ( 12 ) ( ), and craiobiosides A ( 13 ) and B ( 15 ) ( ), respectively, by
            comparison of the spectroscopic data and optical rotations data with those reported in
            the literature. Six known grayanane diterpenoid glucosides 9–11 and 13–15 were isolated
            from <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name> for the first time. </p>
         <p> Pierisjaponoside A ( 1 ) was isolated as colorless block crystals with mp 168–169 °C
            (MeOH), and has a molecular formula of C 26 H 42 O 10 as established by the HRESIMS ion
            at m/z 537.2668 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 42 O 10 Na, 537.2676) and the 13 C NMR
            data. The 1 H NMR spectrum of 1 ( Table 1 ) exhibited resonances for four methyls ( δ H
            1.34, s, H 3 -17; 1.12, s, H 3 -18; 0.97, s, H 3 -19; 1.33, s, H 3 -20), two oxymethines
            ( δ H 3.53, dd, J = 5.0, 2.0 Hz, H-3 α ; 3.77, dd, J = 3.6, 1.6 Hz, H-6 α ), and a
            typical glucopyranosyl unit ( δ H 4.18, d, J = 7.7 Hz, H-1′; 3.11, dd, J = 9.2, 7.7 Hz,
            H-2′; 3.30, overlap, H-3′; 3.19, overlap, H-4′; 3.19, overlap, H-5′; 3.83, dd, J = 11.8,
            2.1 Hz, H-6′a; 3.61, dd, J = 11.8, 5.4 Hz, H-6′b) ( , ; ). The 13 C NMR data ( Table 1 )
            showed 26 carbon signals, which were assignable by the DEPT data to four methyls ( δ C
            24.1, C-17; 19.1, C-18; 25.3, C-19; 27.4, C-20), six methylenes ( δ C 32.8, C-2; 41.8,
            C-7; 27.6, C-11; 25.9, C-12; 39.1, C-14; 54.7, C-15), four methines ( δ C 59.8, C-1;
            93.7, C-3; 71.4, C- 6; 47.4, C-13), two quaternary carbons ( δ C 49.5, C-4; δ C 48.1,
            C-8), four oxygenated tertiary carbons ( δ C 94.2, C-5; 89.4, C-9; 84.5, C-10; 81.3,
            C-16), and a glucopyranosyl group ( δ C 106.4, C-1′; 75.7, C-2′; 78.0, C- 3′; 72.2,
            C-4′; 77.7, C-5′; 63.2, C-6′) ( , ; ). The NMR data of 1 were closely similar to those
            of grayanoside D ( 9 ) (Sakakibara and Shirai, 1980), and the major difference was the
            presence of an oxygenated tertiary carbon ( δ C 84.5, C-10) in 1 , instead of a methine
            ( δ H 37.7, C-10) in grayanoside D ( 9 ). In addition, the methyl singlet ( δ H 1.33, s,
            H 3 -20) in 1 replaced the methyl doublet ( δ H 0.98, d, J = 7.0 Hz, H 3 -20) in 9 .
            Therefore, pierisjaponoside A ( 1 ) is the 10-hydroxy derivative of 9 . HMBC
            correlations from H 3 -20 ( δ H 1.33, s) to C-1 ( δ C 59.8), C-9 ( δ C 89.4), and C-10 (
            δ C 84.5) further supported this deduction ( Fig. 2 ). </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> Similar to 9 , H-1 was assigned as α -orientation. The NOESY correlations ( Fig. 2 )
            between H-1 α and H-6 and between H-6 and H 3 -19 indicated that H-6 and H 3 -19 were α
            -oriented. The strong NOESY correlation between H 3 -19 α and H-3 established the α
            -orientation of H-3. The NOESY correlation between H-2 β and H 3 -20 suggested the β
            -orientation of H 3 -20. The β -orientation of H 3 -17 and the cis -junction of rings C
            and D were established by the NOESY correlation between H 3 - 17 and H-12 β . </p>
         <p> To determine the absolute configuration of the glucose moiety, pierisjaponoside A ( 1 )
            was hydrolyzed and the trimethylsilylthiazolidine derivative of the hydrolysate was
            prepared ( ; ; ). The absolute configuration of the glucose unit in 1 was determined to
            be D by comparison of the GC retention time of the trimethylsilylthiazolidine derivative
            of the hydrolysate of 1 with those of the standards, D and L-glucoses. The large
            coupling constant ( J = 7.7 Hz) of H-1′ revealed the β -glucopyranosyl linkage in 1 ( ).
            Thus, the structure of pierisjaponoside A ( 1 ) was established as 3 β -( β
            -D-glucopyranosyloxy)-6 β ,10 α ,16 α -trihydroxy-5 β ,9 β -epoxygrayanane. The absolute
            configuration of 1 was eventually confirmed as 1 S ,3 S ,5 R ,6 R ,8 R ,9 S ,10 S ,13 R
            ,16 R ,1′ R , 2′ R ,3′ S ,4′ S ,5′ R by a single-crystal X-ray ( Fig. 3 ) diffraction
            with the obtained Flack parameter of −0.01(2) ( ). This is the first report of the
            crystal structure of a 5,9-epoxygrayanane diterpenoid glucoside. </p>
         <p> Pierisjaponoside B ( 2 ), colorless prisms with mp 158–159 °C, has a molecular formula
            of C 26 H 42 O 10 based on the HRESIMS ion at m/z 537.2672 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H
            42 O 10 Na, 537.2676) and the 13 C NMR data. The NMR data of 2 ( Table 1 ) were similar
            to those of grayanoside B ( 10 ) ( ) except for an oxymethine ( δ H 4.27, dd, J = 4.1,
            2.7 Hz, H-2 α ; δ C 79.7, C-2) in 2 , replacing the methylene ( δ C 37.5, C-2) in 10 .
            Thus, pierisjaponoside B ( 2 ) is the 2- hydroxy derivative of 10 . The 1 H– 1 H COSY
            correlations from H-1 ( δ H 2.44, d, J = 2.7 Hz) and H-3 ( δ H 3.61, d, J = 4.1 Hz) to
            H-2 ( δ H 4.27, dd, J = 4.1, 2.7 Hz) confirmed the presence of the spin system of “– CH
            (1)– CH (2)– CH (3)–” in 2 , which was further supported by the HMBC correlations from
            H-1 and H-3 to C-2 (Supplementary Information, Fig. S1 ). Ignoring C-2, the relative
            configuration of pierisjaponoside B ( 2 ) was the same as 10 . The α -orientation of H-1
            was defined by the chemical shift of C-1 ( δ C 45.6) ( ). The small coupling constant (
            J = 2.7 Hz) between H-2 and H-1 α established the α -orientation of H-2 ( ). Similar to
            1 , comparison of the GC retention time of the derivative of the hydrolysate of 2 with
            those of the standards determined the D-absolute configuration of the glucose moiety in
            2 . The large coupling constant ( J = 7.6 Hz) of the anomeric proton at δ H 4.38 (H-1′)
            revealed the β -glucopyranosyl linkage in 2 . Finally, the structure of 2 was
            established as 3 β -( β -D-glucopyranosyloxy)-2 β ,5 β ,6 β ,16 α
            -tetrahydroxygrayan-10(20)-ene by single-crystal X-ray diffraction ( Fig. 4 ), and the
            resulting Flack parameter of 0.14(6) ( ) defined the absolute configuration of 2 as 1 R
            ,2 S ,3 R ,5 R ,6 R ,8 R ,9 R ,13 R ,16 R ,1′ R ,2′ R ,3′ S ,4′ S ,5′ R . </p>
         <p> The molecular formula of pierisjaponoside C ( 3 ) was assigned as C 27 H 44 O 9 by the
            HRESIMS ion at m/z 535.2871 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 27 H 44 O 9 Na, 535.2883) and the 13
            C NMR data. The NMR data of 3 ( Table 1 ) closely resembled those of grayanoside B ( 10
            ) ( ), and the major differences were the presence of an oxymethyl group ( δ H 3.13, s;
            δ C 49.7) and the deshielding of C-16 ( δ C 87.3) in 3 by 8.0 ppm compared to 10 ( δ C
            79.3). Thus, pierisjaponoside C ( 3 ) is the 16-oxymethyl derivative of 10 , which was
            proved by the HMBC correlation from the O CH 3 group ( δ H 3.13) to C-16. H-1 was
            assigned to be α -orientation by the chemical shift of C-1 ( δ C 44.1) ( ). The relative
            configuration of 3 was the same as 10 as established by the NOESY correlations of
            H-1/H-6, H-6/H 3 -19, H-3/H 3 -19, H-9 β /H-15 β , and H-12 β /H-17. Therefore, the
            structure of pierisjaponoside C ( 3 ) was defined as 3 β -( β -D-glucopyranosyloxy)-5 β
            ,6 β -dihydroxy-16 α - methoxygrayan-10(20)-ene by the detailed 2D NMR data analysis
            (Supplementary Information, Fig. S2 ) and chemical methods. </p>
         <p> Pierisjaponoside D ( 4 ) was obtained as colorless prisms, and its molecular formula
            was assigned to be C 26 H 42 O 10 on the basis of the HRESIMS ion at m/z 537.2666 [M +
            Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 42 O 10 Na, 537.2676) and the 13 C NMR data. The NMR data (
            Table 2 ) of 4 were similar to those of micranthanoside A ( 11 ) ( ), which was recently
            isolated from the leaves of <tp:taxon-name> R. micranthum </tp:taxon-name> and its
            structure was confirmed by single crystal X-ray diffraction, and the major differences
            between them were the presence of two additional oxygenated methines ( δ H 4.22, t, J =
            8.1 Hz, H-2; δ C 74.2, C-2; δ H 3.71, dd, J = 11.5, 1.5 Hz, H-6; 79.8, C-6) in 4 ,
            replacing two methylenes ( δ H 2.21, H-2 α ; 1.82, H-2 β ; δ C 35.4, C-2; δ H 1.29, H-6
            α ; 1.94, H-6 β ; δ C 33.2, C-6) in 11 . Thus, 4 is a 2,6-dihydroxy derivative of 11 .
            Two partial structures “– CH (1)– CH (2)– CH (3)–” and “– CH (6)– CH 2 (7)–” were
            constructed by the 1 H– 1 H COSY data analysis (Supplementary Information, Fig. S3 ).
            The chemical shift of C-1 ( δ C 60.1) suggested the β -orientation of H- 1 in 4 ( ). The
            NOESY correlations from H-1 β ( δ H 2.87, d, J = 8.1 Hz) to H-9 ( δ H 2.19, d, J = 5.4
            Hz) and H 3 -18 ( δ H 1.22, s) indicated the β -orientations of H-9 and H 3 -18
            (Supplementary Information, Fig. S3 ). The strong NOESY correlations from H 3 -19 α ( δ
            H 1.26, s) to H-3 ( δ H 3.88, d, J = 8.1 Hz) and H-6 ( δ H 3.71, dd, J = 11.5, 1.5 Hz)
            revealed that H-3 and H-6 were α -oriented. NOESY correlations from H-9 β to H-15 β and
            from H 3 -17 to H-12 β established the cis -fused of rings C and D and the β
            -orientation of H 3 -17. The D-absolute configuration of the glucose moiety in 4 was
            determined by comparison of the GC retention time of the trimethylsilylthiazolidine
            derivative of the hydrolysate with those of the standards. The large coupling constant
            of H-1′ ( J = 7.8 Hz) revealed the β -glucopyranosyl linkage in 4 . Thus, the structure
            of pierisjaponoside D ( 4 ) was confirmed as 3 β -( β -D-glucopyranosyloxy)-2 β ,5 α ,6
            β ,16 α -tetrahydroxy-1- β H-grayan-10(20)-ene. </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> The absolute configuration of pierisjaponoside D ( 4 ) was unambiguously assigned as 1
            S ,2 S ,3 R ,5 S ,6 R ,8 R ,9 R ,13 R ,16 R ,1′ R , 2′ R ,3′ S ,4′ S ,5′ R by
            single-crystal X-ray diffraction analysis ( Fig. 5 ) with the Flack parameter of 0.04(5)
            ( ). To date, only seven 5 α -hydroxy-1- β H-grayanane diterpenoids, micranthanosides
            A−D ( ), auriculatol B ( ), 3- epi -auriculatol B ( ), and 19-hydroxy-auriculatol B ( )
            have been isolated, and all of them are 2,6-dideoxygrayanane diterpenoids.
            Pierisjaponoside D ( 4 ) is the first example of a 2 β ,5 α ,6 β - trihydroxy-1- β
            H-grayanane diterpenoid. </p>
         <p> In the reported grayanane diterpenoids, 5-OH is usually β -oriented, whereas 5 α -OH is
            rare ( , 2019). To date, only seven 5 α - OH-1- β H-grayanane ( , ) and three 5 α -OH-1-
            α Hgrayanane diterpenoids ( ; ) have been reported. NMR data analysis revealed that the
            orientations of H-1 and 5-OH will determine the chemical shift of C- 5 in the grayanane
            diterpenoids. The chemical shift of C-5 is about 83.3–84.0 ppm in the A/B trans -fused
            grayanane diterpenoids (5 β -OH-1- α H or 5 α -OH-1- β H), while, the chemical shift of
            C-5 is about 85.9–91.0 ppm in the A/B cis - fused grayanane diterpenoids (5 β -OH-1- β H
            or 5 α -OH-1- α H) ( , , ; ; , 2019; ). Thus, chemical shift of C-5 could be used to
            assign the orientation of 5-OH in grayanane diterpenoids, as the orientation of H-1
            could be assigned by the chemical shift of C-1 ( ). </p>
         <p> The molecular formula of pierisjaponoside E ( 5 ) was established as C 26 H 42 O 10 by
            the HRESIMS ion at m/z 537.2679 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 42 O 10 Na, 537.2676) and
            the 13 C NMR data. The NMR data of 5 ( Table 2 ) showed some similarities to grayanoside
            B ( 10 ) except that there were a tetra-substituted endocyclic double bond ( δ C 143.1,
            C-1; 141.7, C-10), a methyl group ( δ H 1.88, s, H 3 -20; δ C 19.8, C-20), and an
            oxygenated tertiary carbon ( δ C 79.8, C-9) in 5 , instead of the di-substituted
            exocyclic double bond ( δ H 5.00, 4.96, each s, H 2 -20; δ C 113.8, C-20; 152.4, C-10)
            and two methines ( δ H 2.85, t, J = 9.6 Hz, H-1; 2.42, t, J = 7.1 Hz, H-9; δ C 44.2,
            C-1; 55.6, C-9) in 10 . Thus, pierisjaponoside E ( 5 ) should be a 9-hydroxy derivative
            of grayanoside B ( 10 ). HMBC correlations from H 3 -20 ( δ H 1.88, s) to C-1 ( δ C
            143.1), C-10 ( δ C 141.7), and C-9 ( δ C 79.8), from H-3 ( δ H 3.74, d, J = 3.4 Hz) to
            C-1 ( δ C 143.1), and from H 2 -11 to C-10 established the location of the Δ 1(10)
            tetra-substituted double bond and the oxygenated tertiary carbon C-9. The relative
            configuration of pierisjaponoside E ( 5 ) was defined on the basis of the NOESY
            correlations (Supplementary Information, Fig. S4 ). H-3 was assigned as α -orientation
            randomly. NOESY interactions from H-3 α to H 3 -19 and from H 3 -19 to H-6 indicated the
            α -orientations of H-6 and H 3 -19. The β -orientation of H 3 -17 and the cis -fused of
            rings C and D were the same to the typical grayanane diterpenoids ( ). To date, only
            five grayanane diterpenoids with 9 β -OH, asebotoxin VII ( ), pieristoxins G ( ) and J−K
            ( ) from <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name> collected in Japan and
            pierisformoside H ( ) from <tp:taxon-name> P. formosa </tp:taxon-name> , have been
            reported, and the structure of pieristoxin G was defined by the single-crystal X-ray
            diffraction ( ). In consideration of the biogenetic origin, the orientation of 9-OH in
            pierisjaponoside E ( 5 ) was suggested to be β . The D-absolute configuration of the
            glucose moiety in 5 was determined by chemical methods. The large coupling constant of
            H-1′ ( J = 7.8 Hz) established the β -glucopyranosyl linkage in 5 . Thus, the structure
            of 5 was defined as 3 β -( β -D-glucopyranosyloxy)-5 β ,6 β ,9 β ,16 α -
            tetrahydroxygrayan-1(10)-ene. Pierisjaponoside E ( 5 ) represents the first example of a
            9 β -hydroxygrayan-1(10)-ene diterpenoid. </p>
         <p> Pierisjaponoside F ( 6 ) possessed a molecular formula of C 26 H 40 O 9 as indicated by
            the HRESIMS ion at m/z 519.2561 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 40 O 9 Na, 519.2570) and
            the 13 C NMR data. Detailed analysis of the NMR data ( Table 2 ) indicated that 6 is a
            grayanane diterpenoid glucoside structurally close to pierisjaponoside B ( 2 ). The
            major difference was the presence of a tetra-substituted endocyclic double bond ( δ C
            142.8, C-1; 150.5, C-5) in 6 , replacing the methine ( δ H 2.44, d, J = 2.7 Hz, H-1; δ C
            45.6, C-1) and the oxygenated tertiary carbon ( δ C 84.3, C-5) in 2 . Thus,
            pierisjaponoside F ( 6 ) was a 1,5-dehydration derivative of 2 . The location of the
            tetra-substituted Δ 1(5) double bond in 6 was determined by the HMBC correlations from
            H-2/H-3/H-6/H-9/ H 2 -20 to C-1 and H-2/H-3/H-7/H 3 -18/H 3 -19 to C-5 (Supplementary
            Information, Fig. S5 ). H-3 was assigned randomly as α -orientation. The strong NOESY
            correlations from H 3 -19 to H-3 α , H-2, and H-6 established the α -orientations of
            H-2, H-6, and H 3 -19. In the NOESY spectrum, cross-peaks between H-9 and H-15 β and
            between H-12 β and H 3 - 17 indicated the β -orientations of H-9 and H 3 -17. Similar to
            2 , comparison of the GC retention time of the derivative of the hydrolysate with those
            of the standards established the D-absolute configuration of the glucose moiety in 6 .
            The large coupling constant of H-1′ ( J = 7.4 Hz) revealed the β -glucopyranosyl linkage
            in 6 . Thus, the structure of pierisjaponoside F ( 6 ) was defined as 3 β -( β
            -D-glucopyranosyloxy)-2 β ,6 β ,16 α -trihydroxygrayan-1(5),10(20)-diene. </p>
         <p> The HRESIMS data at m/z 519.2567 [M + Na] + and the 13 C NMR data assigned a molecular
            formula of C 26 H 40 O 9 to pierisjaponoside G ( 7 ). The NMR data ( Table 3 ) of 7
            closely resembled those of pieroside A ( 12 ) ( ), except for an oxymethine ( δ H 4.21,
            t, J = 3.4 Hz, H-2 α ; δ C 80.1, C-2) in 7 , replacing the methylene ( δ H 2.33, ddd, J
            = 14.7, 9.8, 4.8 Hz, H-2 α ; 1.80, ddd, J = 14.7, 9.8, 2.1 Hz, H-2 β ; δ C 39.6, C-2) in
            12 . Therefore, 7 is the 2-hydroxy derivative of pieroside A ( 12 ). The partial
            structure “− CH (1)− CH (2)− CH (3)−” was established by the 1 H– 1 H COSY data, and the
            coupling constants of H-1 ( δ H 2.36, d, J = 3.4 Hz), H-2 ( δ H 4.21, t, J = 3.4 Hz),
            and H-3 ( δ H 3.62, d, J = 3.4 Hz) supported that these three protons were in a spin
            system. The chemical shift of C-1 ( δ C 50.6) suggested the α -orientation of H-1 ( ).
            The α -orientation of H-2 was determined by the small coupling constant between H-1 and
            H-2 ( J = 3.4 Hz) and the NOESY correlations from H-2 to H-1 and H-3. Detailed 2D NMR
            data analyses (Supplementary Information, Fig. S6 ) and chemical methods defined the
            structure of 7 to be 3 β -( β -D-glucopyranosyloxy)-2 β ,5 β ,6 αβ -
            trihydroxygrayan-10(20),15(16)-diene. </p>
         <p> Pierisjaponoside H ( 8 ) had a molecular formula of C 26 H 44 O 10 as determined by the
            HRESIMS ion at m/z 539.2803 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 44 O 10 Na, 539.2832) and the
            13 C NMR data. The NMR data ( Table 3 ) of 8 were similar to those of craiobioside A (
            13 ) ( ), except for the presence of a methylene C-2 ( δ H 2.29, dd, J = 14.9, 9.6 Hz,
            H-2 α ; 2.02, ddd, J = 14.9, 9.6, 4.7 Hz, H-2 β ; δ C 34.6) in 8 , replacing the
            oxymethine ( δ H 4.41, dd, J = 8.1, 4.7 Hz, H-2 α ; δ C 74.2) in 13 . Thus, 8 is the
            2-deoxy derivative of 13 . The partial structure “− CH (1)− CH (2)− CH (3)−” was
            established by the 1 H– 1 H COSY data and the HMBC correlations from H-1 ( δ H 2.44, t,
            J = 9.6 Hz) and H-3 ( δ H 3.72, t, J = 4.7 Hz) to C-2 ( δ C 34.6). The β -orientation of
            H-1 was defined by the large chemical shift of C-1 ( δ C 65.5) ( ). NOESY correlations
            between H-1 β and H-9, between H-9 and H-15 β , and between H-15 β and H 3 -17
            established the β -orientations of H- 9 and H 3 -17. Strong correlations from H-3 α to H
            3 -19 and from H-6 to H 3 -19 established that H-3 and H-6 were α -oriented. Detailed 2D
            NMR data analyses (Supplementary Information, Fig. S7) and chemical methods defined the
            structure of pierisjaponoside H ( 8 ) as 3 β -( β -Dglucopyranosyloxy)-5 β ,6 β ,10 β
            ,16 α -tetrahydroxy-1- β H-grayanane. </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> Since the grayanane diterpenoids have been reported to possess significant analgesic
            activities ( , ; ), all the isolated grayanane diterpenoid glucosides 1–15 were
            evaluated for their analgesic activities in the acetic acid-induced writhing test in
            mice, and morphine was used as a positive control. Results ( Fig. 6 ) revealed that all
            the isolated grayanane diterpenoid glucosides 1–15 showed significant analgesic effects,
            compared to the vehicle tests (*** p &lt;0.001). Among them, pierisjaponosides A ( 1 )
            and C–H ( 3–8 ), micranthanoside A ( 11 ), pieroside A ( 12 ), and craiobiosides A ( 13
            ) and B ( 15 ) displayed significant analgesic effects with the writhe inhibition rates
            over 50% at the dose of 5.0 mg/kg. In particular, pierisjaponoside E ( 5 ) showed
            significant analgesic activities with the writhe inhibition rates of 81.7%, 70.4%, and
            52.1% at the doses of 5.0, 1.0, and 0.02 mg / kg, respectively. </p>
         <p> Some conclusions could be drawn from the analysis of the structures and their analgesic
            activities. Among all the isolated grayanane diterpenoid glucosides 1–15 ,
            pierisjaponoside E ( 5 ) exhibited the most potent analgesic effects even at the lower
            concentration of 0.2 mg /kg. Thus, 5 β ,6 β ,9 β -trihydroxy-grayan-1(10)-ene is the
            favorable grayanane diterpene 3- O -β -D-glucoside skeleton type for the potent
            analgesics, and the Δ 1(10) double bond and the 9 β -hydroxy group might contribute more
            to the analgesic activity. In addition, micranthanoside A ( 11 ) also showed potent
            analgesic activity, which was consistent with literature report ( ), supporting the
            importance of the 5 α -hydroxy- 1- β H-grayan-10(20)-ene skeleton to the analgesic
            activities. While, 2 β ,6 β -dihydroxy groups may be the deactivating groups to the
            analgesic activities of the 5 α -hydroxy-1- β H-grayan-10(20)-ene diterpene 3- O -β
            -Dglucosides, due to the weaker analgesic activity of pierisjaponoside D ( 4 ) with 2 β
            ,6 β -dihydroxy groups than micranthanoside A ( 11 ) without 2 β ,6 β -dihydroxy groups.
            Pierisjaponoside B ( 2 ) bearing 2 β -OH exhibited weaker analgesic effects than
            grayanoside B ( 10 ) without 2 β - OH, suggesting the deactivation of 2 β -OH group in
            the 5 β ,6 β ,16 α -trihydroxy-1- α H-grayan-10(20)-ene diterpenoid 3- O -β
            -D-glucosides. This same conclusion could also be drawn for 5 β ,6 β -dihydroxy-1- α
            H-grayan- 10(20),15(16)-diene and 5 β ,6 β ,10 β ,16 α -tetrahydroxy-1- β H-grayanane
            diterpenoid 3- O -β -D-glucosides, based on the fact that pierisjaponoside G ( 7 ) with
            2 β -OH had weaker analgesic effects than pieroside A ( 12 ) without 2 β -OH, and
            craiobioside A ( 13 ) with 2 β -OH also showed weaker analgesic effects than
            pierisjaponoside H ( 8 ) without 2 β -OH. While, the 2 β -hydroxy group may be an
            activating group in the 5 β ,6 β ,16 α -trihydroxy-1- β H-grayan-10(20)-ene diterpene
            glucosides, because craiobioside B ( 15 ) with 2 β -OH had more significant analgesic
            effects than grayanoside C ( 14 ) without 2 β -OH. 5 α -Hydroxy-1- β Hgrayanane
            glucoside 4 exhibited approximately comparable analgesic effect to 5 β -hydroxy-1- β
            H-grayanane glucoside 15 , suggesting that the orientation of 5-OH had no effects on the
            analgesic effects of the 2 β ,6 β ,16 α -trihydroxy-1- β H-grayan-10(20)-ene diterpene
            3- O -β -D-glucosides. Pierisjaponoside A ( 1 ) with 10 α -OH showed more significant
            analgesic effects than pieroside A ( 9 ) without 10 α -OH, indicating that 10 α -OH may
            be an activating group to the analgesic activity in the 5 β ,9 β -epoxygrayanane
            diterpenoid 3- O -β -D-glucosides. Similarly, 10 β - OH may be also an activating group
            to the analgesic activity in the 5 β ,6 β ,16 α -trihydroxy-1- β H-grayanane diterpenoid
            3- O -β -D-glucosides, because of the fact that pierisjaponoside H ( 8 ) with 10 β -OH
            possessed more significant analgesic effect than 14 without 10 β -OH. However, the 16 α
            -hydroxy group may be a deactivation group, based on the result that pierisjaponoside G
            ( 7 ) without a 16 α -OH showed more significant analgesic activity than
            pierisjaponoside B ( 2 ) with a 16 α -OH. This same conclusion could be drawn from the
            result that pieroside A ( 12 ) without 16 α -OH showed more significant analgesic
            activity than grayanoside B ( 10 ) with 16 α -OH. In other words, the exocyclic Δ 10(20)
            double bond may be an deactivation group in the 5 β ,6 β ,16 α -trihydroxy-1- β
            Hgrayanane diterpenoid 3- O -β -D-glucosides, while, the endocyclic Δ 15(16) double bond
            may be an activating group. Furthermore, pierisjaponoside C ( 3 ) with a 16 α -O CH 3
            also had more significant analgesic activity than grayanoside B ( 10 ) with a 16 α -OH,
            further supporting the conclusion that the 16 α -hydroxy group may be a deactivation
            group. Therefore, the hydroxy groups not only play important roles in the solubility in
            water, but also affect the analgesic activities of the grayanane diterpenoids. These
            preliminary structure-activity relationships may give some clues to design novel
            analgesics on the basis of grayanane diterpenoid glucosides. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 3. Conclusions </title>
         <p> In summary, eight undescribed grayanane diterpenoid glucosides, pierisjaponosides A−H (
            1–8 ) and seven known analogues ( 9–15 ) were isolated from the leaves of
               <tp:taxon-name> P . japonica </tp:taxon-name> . The absolute configurations of
            pierisjaponosides A ( 1 ), B ( 2 ), and D ( 4 ) were unambiguously defined by
            single-crystal X-ray diffraction using Cu K α radiation. This is the first report of the
            crystal structure of a 5,9-epoxy-grayanane diterpenoid glucoside. Pierisjaponoside E ( 5
            ) represents the first example of a 9 β - hydroxygrayan-1(10)-ene diterpenoid. Six known
            grayanane diterpenoid glucosides 9–11 and 13–15 were isolated from <tp:taxon-name> P.
               japonica </tp:taxon-name> for the first time. All grayanane diterpenoid glucosides (
            1–15 ) showed significant analgesic activities in the acetic acid-induced writhing
            models in mice. Pierisjaponosides A ( 1 ) and C–H ( 3–8 ), micranthanoside A ( 11 ),
            pieroside A ( 12 ), and craiobiosides A ( 13 ) and B ( 15 ) displayed significant
            analgesic effects with the writhe inhibition rates over 50% at the dose of 5.0 mg/kg.
            Pierisjaponoside E ( 5 ) and micranthanoside A ( 11 ) also exhibited significant
            analgesic effects even at the lower dose of 0.2 mg /kg. The structure-activity
            relationship studies revealed that the Δ 1(10) double bond, 9 β -OH, and 10-OH groups
            may be the activating groups, and 2 β -OH and 16 α -OH groups may be the deactivation
            groups in the grayanane diterpenoid glucosides. Grayanane diterpenoid glucosides have
            good solubility in water, and could be developed as potent analgesic injections. This
            study provides a new source to develop novel analgesics. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4. Experimental </title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.1. General experimental procedures </title>
         <p> Optical rotations were acquired using a Perkin-Elmer 341 polarimeter in methanol.
            Melting points of the crystals were recorded on a Beijing TechX-5 microscopic melting
            point apparatus. UV data were measured on a Varian Cary 50 spectrophotometer. FT-IR
            spectra were recorded using a Bruker Vertex 70 instrument. HRESIMS data were measured on
            a Bruker micro TOF II spectrometer in a positive ion mode. The NMR spectra were acquired
            on a Bruker AM-400 spectrometer, and the 1 H and 13 C NMR chemical shifts were
            referenced to the solvent residual peaks for methanol- d 4 at δ H 3.31 and δ C 49.15.
            The crystallographic data were obtained on a XtaLAB PRO MM007HF SC-XRD diffractometer
            equipped with graphite-monochromatized Cu K α radiation ( λ = 1.54178 Å). Sephadex LH-20
            (GE Chemical Corporation), silica gel (100–200, 200–300 mesh, Qingdao Marine Chemical
            Factory, People's Republic of China ), silica gel H (Qingdao Marine Chemical Factory,
            People's Republic of China ), and ODS (50 μ m, YMC, Japan ) were used for column
            chromatography (CC). TLC was carried out with precoated glass silica gel GF254 plates
            (Qingdao Marine Chemical Factory). Spots were visualized under UV light or by spraying
            with 10% H 2 SO 4 –EtOH followed by heating. Samples were purified by semipreparative
            HPLC using a Dionex P680 quaternary system with a UV detector and a semipreparative
            column (5 μ m, 10 × 250 mm , Welch Ultimate XB-C 18 or XB-phenyl) at a flow rate of 1.5
            mL/min. GC was analyzed on an Agilent 7820A GC ( 30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.5 μ m, Welch WM-1).
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.2. Plant material </title>
         <p> The leaves of <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica (Thunb.) D. Don ex G. Don </tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Ericaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) were collected at Baishanzu scenery
            (longitude 119°19′East , latitude 27°74′North, and altitude 1857 m ), Lishui city,
            Zhejiang province , China , in July 2014 , and identified by Professor Bing-Yang Ding at
            Wenzhou University. A voucher specimen (NO.20140722) has been deposited at Hubei Key
            Laboratory of Natural Medicinal Chemistry and Resource Evaluation , School of Pharmacy ,
            Tongji Medical College , Huazhong University of Science and Technology . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3. Extraction and isolation </title>
         <p> The dried leaves of <tp:taxon-name> P. japonica </tp:taxon-name> (37.0 kg) were
            powdered and extracted four times using 95% EtOH at room temperature (7 days each). A
            dark green crude extract ( 6.7 kg ) was obtained by the concentration of the combined
            filtrate under the reduced pressure. The residue ( 6.7 kg ) was suspended in 80 L H 2 O
            and extracted with petroleum ether, EtOAc, and n -BuOH, respectively. The EtOAc fraction
            ( 426.5 g ) was subjected to a silica gel ( 3.5 kg , 100–200 mesh) column eluted with CH
            2 Cl 2 –MeOH (50:1 to 2:1, v/v) to afford ten fractions A−J based on the TLC analysis.
            Fraction I was chromatographed on an RP C 18 column with MeOH–H 2 O (from 0:100 to
            70:30) to produce nine subfractions (I1–I9). Fraction I7 was separated on a Sephadex
            LH-20 column with MeOH to yield four subfractions I7a−I7d. Fraction I7d was further
            separated by chromatograph column over ODS eluted with MeOH–H 2 O (5:95 to 20:80) to
            obtain seven subfractions (I7d1−I7d7). Fractions I7d5 and I7d6 were purified by a
            semipreparative RP C 18 HPLC (MeOH–H 2 O, 49:51) to yield compounds 11 ( 4.8 mg , t R
            49.3 min) and 9 ( 36.8 mg , t R 45.5 min), respectively. Fraction I8 was separated by a
            Sephadex LH-20 (MeOH) column to give subfractions (I8a−I8c). Fraction I8b was applied to
            a silica gel CC with CH 2 Cl 2 –MeOH (40:1 to 30:1) to obtain the eight subfractions
            I8b1−I8b8. Compounds 3 (9.0 mg, t R 45.2 min) and 7 ( 5.4 mg , t R 84.4 min) were
            obtained by the purification of fraction I8b8 with a semipreparative RP C 18 HPLC
            (MeOH–H 2 O, 60:40). Fraction I9 was subjected to a silica gel H eluted with CH 2 Cl 2
            –MeOH (50:1) to produce five subfractions, I9a−I9d and compound 12 ( 17.8 mg ). </p>
         <p> The n -BuOH fraction ( 1109.1 g ) was loaded on an AB-8 macroporous adsorption resin
            column eluted excessively with 0%, 10%, 30%, 50%, and 95% EtOH. The combined 0% and 10%
            EtOH fractions ( 441.7 g ) was separated using a silica gel column (100–200 mesh) eluted
            with CH 2 Cl 2 –MeOH (20:1 to 3:1, v/v) to give eleven fractions 1–11, on the basis of
            the TLC analysis. Fraction 8 was applied to a MPLC ODS column eluting with MeOH–H 2 O
            (0:100 to 50:50) to get eight subfractions 8A−8 H. Fraction 8G was further separated by
            a Sephadex LH-20 column (MeOH) and a silica gel H column ( CH 2 Cl 2 –MeOH 35:1) to
            obtain the main subfraction 8G3e, which was further purified using a semipreparative RP
            phenyl HPLC (MeOH–H 2 O, 45:55) to yield compound 2 ( 25.4 mg , t R 41.6 min). Fraction
            9 was subjected to a MPLC ODS column eluting with a gradient of MeOH–H 2 O (0:100 to
            50:50) to get eight subfractions 9A−9 H. Fraction 9A was separated by a Sephadex LH-20
            column (9A1−9A4), a silica gel column eluting with CH 2 Cl 2 –MeOH (15:1 to 8:1,
            9A2a−9A2d), and a repeat Sephadex LH-20 column to obtain three subfractions 9A2b1−9A2b3.
            Compound 1 (26.0 mg, t R 47.5 min) was isolated from fraction 9A2b1 by a semipreparative
            RP C 18 HPLC (MeOH–H 2 O, 23:77). Fraction 9B was chromatographed by a Sephadex LH-20
            column to get five subfractions 9B1–9B5. Fraction 9B1 was separated using a silica
            column to yield five subfractions 9B1a−9B1e. Fraction 9B1b was purified by a
            semipreparative RP C 18 HPLC (MeOH–H 2 O, 43:57) to obtain compound 4 ( 67.4 mg , t R
            19.2 min). Fraction 9B1c was purified by a semipreparative RP phenyl HPLC (MeCN–H 2 O,
            18:82) to get compound 5 (9.0 mg, t R 34.9 min). Fraction 9C was subjected to a silica
            gel column ( CH 2 Cl 2 –MeOH, 20:1 to 5:1) to obtain nine subfractions, 9C1–9C8 and
            compound 13 ( 164.6 mg ). Fraction 9E was separated using a Sephadex LH-20 column to
            yield four subfractions 9E1−9E4. Compound 15 ( 9.6 mg , t R 39.2 min) was obtained by
            the purification of fraction 9E2 by a semipreparative RP C 18 HPLC (MeOH–H 2 O, 45:55).
            Compound 6 ( 25.8 mg , t R 49.5 min) was yielded by the purification of fraction 9E3 by
            a semipreparative RP C 18 HPLC (MeOH–H 2 O, 40:60). Fraction 10 was applied to a MPLC
            ODS column eluting with a gradient MeOH–H 2 O (0:100 to 45:55) to get fourteen
            subfractions 10A− 10N. Fraction 10L was separated by a Sephadex LH-20 column to get four
            subfractions 10L1−10L4. Fraction 10L4 was further purified by a semipreparative RP
            phenyl HPLC (MeOH–H 2 O, 35:65) to produce compounds 8 (14.0 mg, t R 32.4 min) and 14 (
            2.4 mg , t R 50.6 min). Fraction 10M was applied to a Sephadex LH-20 column to get two
            subfractions 10M1 and 10M2. Fraction 10M1 was subjected to a silica gel H column ( CH 2
            Cl 2 –MeOH, 15:1) to yield compound 10 ( 10.4 mg ) . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.1. Pierisjaponoside A (1) </title>
         <p> Colorless blocks (MeOH); mp 168–169 °C; [] 27 D −7 ( c 0.3, MeOH); 1 H NMR and 13 C NMR
            data, see Table 1 ; HRESIMS m/z 537.2668 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 42 O 10 Na,
            537.2676). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.2. Pierisjaponoside B (2) </title>
         <p> Colorless prisms (MeOH:H 2 O = 10:1); mp 158–159 °C; [] 27 D −28 ( c 0.8, MeOH); 1 H
            NMR and 13 C NMR data, see Table 1 ; HRESIMS m/z 537.2672 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H
            42 O 10 Na, 537.2676). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.3. Pierisjaponoside C (3) </title>
         <p> Colorless oil; [] D 27 −15 ( c 0.3, MeOH); 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Table 1 ; HRESIMS
            m/z 535.2871 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 27 H 44 O 9 Na, 535.2883). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.4. Pierisjaponoside D (4) </title>
         <p> Colorless prisms (MeOH: THF = 20: 1); mp 278–280 °C; [] 27 D −21 ( c 0.4, MeOH); 1 H
            and 13 C NMR data, see Table 2 ; HRESIMS m/z 537.2666 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 42 O
            10 Na, 537.2676). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.5. Pierisjaponoside E (5) </title>
         <p> Colorless oil; [] 27 D −17 ( c 0.3, MeOH); 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Table 2 ; HRESIMS
            m/z 537.2679 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 42 O 10 Na, 537.2676). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.6. Pierisjaponoside F (6) </title>
         <p> White amorphous powders; [] 27 D +74 ( c 0.3, MeOH); UV (MeOH) λ max (log ε ): 240
            (3.42) nm; IR (KBr) ν max 3385, 2936, 2871, 1640, 1449, 1376, 1170, 1079, 1030, 805 cm
            −1 . 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Table 2 ; HRESIMS m/z 519.2561 [M + Na] + (calcd for C
            26 H 40 O 9 Na, 519.2570). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.7. Pierisjaponoside G (7) </title>
         <p> Colorless oils; [] 27 D −33 ( c 0.1, MeOH); 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Table 3 ;
            HRESIMS m/z 519.2567 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 40 O 9 Na, 519.2570). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.3.8. Pierisjaponoside H (8) </title>
         <p> Colorless oils; [] 27 D −14 ( c 0.5, MeOH); 1 H and 13 C NMR data, see Table 3 ;
            HRESIMS m/z 539.2803 [M + Na] + (calcd for C 26 H 44 O 10 Na, 539.2832). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.4. Single-crystal X-ray diffraction analysis and crystallographic data of
            pierisjaponosides A (1), B (2), and D (4) </title>
         <p> The crystallographic data were obtained on a XtaLAB PRO MM007HF SC-XRD diffractometer
            equipped with graphite-monochromatized Cu K α radiation ( λ = 1.54178 Å) for
            pierisjapanosides A ( 1 ), B ( 2 ), and D ( 4 ). The intensity data collection,
            structures solution, reduction, and hydrogen atoms treatment for 1 , 2 , and 4 were
            performed as described in a previous paper ( ). The ORTEP drawing crystal structures are
            shown in Fig. 3−5 , respectively. The crystallographic data for the structures of
            pierisjaponosides A ( 1 ) (CCDC 1944895), B ( 2 ) (CCDC 1944896), and D ( 4 )
            (CCDC1944897) have been deposited in the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Center. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.4.1. Crystallographic data of pierisjaponoside A (1) </title>
         <p> C 26 H 42 O 10 •2(H 2 O), M = 550.63, crystal size 0.12 × 0.10 × 0.10 mm 3 , a =
            10.1882(10) Å, b = 13.9145(13) Å, c = 19.0825(18) Å, α = 90°, β = 90°, γ = 90°, V =
            2705.2(4) Å 3 , T = 297(2) K, wavelength: 1.54178 Å, orthorhombic, space group P 212121
            , Z = 4, absorption coefficient 0.889 mm −1 , F (000) = 1192, theta range for data
            collection 3.932 –70.707 °, index ranges −11 ≤ h ≤ 10, −16 ≤ k ≤ 16, −21 ≤ l ≤ 23, 19739
            reflections measured, 4779 independent reflections [ R (int) = 0.034], completeness to
            theta (67.679°) 96.7%, data/restraints/parameters 4779/6/377, largest diff. peak and
            hole 0.408 and − 0.171 e .Å −3 . The final R 1 value was 0.0346 [ I &gt; 2 σ ( I )],
            final w R 2 value was 0.0988 [ I &gt; 2 σ ( I )]. The final R 1 value (all data) was
            0.0347, final wR 2 value (all data) was 0.0989. The goodness of fit on F 2 was 1.057,
            Flack parameter −0.01(2). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.4.2. Crystallographic data of pierisjaponoside B (2) </title>
         <p> C 26 H 42 O 10 , M = 514.60, crystal size 0.05 × 0.04 × 0.03 mm 3 , a = 11.3944(10) Å,
            b = 6.0800(5) Å, c = 20.7913(19) Å, α = 90°, β = 103.925(3)°, γ = 90°, V = 1398.0(2) Å 3
            , T = 173(2) K, wavelength: 1.54178 Å, monpclinic, space group P 21 , Z = 4, absorption
            coefficient 0.773 mm −1 , F (000) = 616, theta range for data collection 3.997 –66.553
            °, index ranges −13 ≤ h ≤ 12, −7 ≤ k ≤ 7, −24 ≤ l ≤ 23, 11281 reflections measured, 4788
            independent reflections [ R (int) = 0.0342], completeness to theta (66.553°) 98.7%,
            data/restraints/parameters 4788/3/340, largest diff. peak and hole 0.549 and − 0.24 e .Å
            −3 . The final R 1 value was 0.0604 [ I &gt; 2 σ ( I )], final wR 2 value was 0.1765 [ I
            &gt; 2 σ ( I )]. The final R 1 value (all data) was 0.0614, final wR 2 value (all data)
            was 0.1775. The goodness of fit on F 2 was 1.533, Flack parameter 0.14(6). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.4.3. Crystallographic data of pierisjaponoside D (4) </title>
         <p> C 26 H 42 O 10 •2(H 2 O), M = 550.63, crystal size 0.30 × 0.20 × 0.10 mm 3 , a =
            39.6645(3) Å, b = 6.79980(10) Å, c = 10.1970(2) Å, α = 90°, β = 96.3520(10)°, γ = 90°, V
            = 2733.36(7) Å 3 , T = 173(2) K, wavelength: 1.54178 Å, monoclinic, space group C2, Z =
            4, absorption coefficient 0.880 mm −1 , F (000) = 1192, theta range for data collection
            2.241 –67.495 °, index ranges −47 ≤ h ≤ 47, −7 ≤ k ≤ 8, −12 ≤ l ≤ 12, 28448 reflections
            measured, 4736 independent reflections [ R (int) = 0.0306], completeness to theta
            (67.495°) 100.0%, data/restraints/parameters 4736/1/ 355, largest diff. peak and hole
            0.414 and − 0.279 e .Å −3 . The final R 1 value was 0.0270 [ I &gt; 2 σ ( I )], final wR
            2 value was 0.0714 [ I &gt; 2 σ ( I )]. The final R 1 value (all data) was 0.0273, final
            wR 2 value (all data) was 0.0717. The goodness of fit on F 2 was 1.042, Flack parameter
            0.04(5). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.5. Acid hydrolysis and determination of the absolute configuration of glucose in
            pierisjaponosides A−H (1–8) </title>
         <p> Pierisjapanoside A ( 1 ) was added to 1.5 mL 2 mM HCl and stirred for 6 h at 80 °C.
            After cooling to room temperature, the reaction mixture was extracted with EtOAc (3 ×
            2.0 mL). The aqueous layer was evaporated under the reduced pressure. The dried sugar
            residue was dissolved in 0.2 mL anhydrous pyridine, then added 0.2 mg L-cysteine methyl
            ester hydrochloride and stirred at 60 °C for 1.5 h. Subsequently, 0.1 mL of N
            -trimethylsilylimidazole was added to the above reaction mixture and stirred at 60 °C
            for 1.5 h. The reactant was dissolved in 1.0 mL H 2 O and extracted with n -hexane (3 ×
            1.0 mL). The n -hexane layer was analyzed by an Agilent 7820A gas chromatography with a
            Welch WM-1 capillary column ( ; ). Nitrogen was used as a carrier gas at a flow rate of
            1.0 mL/min and the split ratio was 10:1. Flame ionization detector (FID) and injection
            were set at 250 °C. The oven temperature was programmed as follows: initial temperature
            at 220 °C for 5 min, increased to 270 °C at 10 °C/min, and held 10.0 min at the final
            temperature. The GC retention times of the trimethylsilylthiazolidine derivatives of the
            hydrate of 1 and the standers D- and L-glucoses were found to be 14.801 , 14.840 , and
            15.062 min, respectively (Supplementary Information, Fig. S8−S10). Therefore, the
            absolute configuration of glucose unit in pierisjapanoside A ( 1 ) was determined to be
            D-configuration. </p>
         <p> In the same way, pierisjapanosides B–H ( 2–8 ) were hydrolyzed by 2 mM HCl,
            respectively, and the trimethylsilylthiazolidine derivatives of the hydrates of
            compounds 2–8 were prepared. The trimethylsilylthiazolidine derivatives of the hydrates
            of 2−8 gave GC retention times at 14.767, 14.793, 14.818, 14.844, 14.889, 14.807 and
            14.819 min, respectively, indicating the presence of D-glucoses in 2−8 (Supplementary
            Information, Fig. S11−S17). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4.6. Analgesic activities assay </title>
         <p> According to the procedures described in the literature, the analgesic assay of
            grayanane diterpenoid glucosides 1–15 were carried out on the acetic acid-induced
            writhing model in mice ( , ; ). Morphine (morph) and 0.9% NaCl (5.0 mL/kg) were used as
            a positive control drug and the vehicle control, respectively. Group of 10 Kunming mice
            were used for the control and the test groups. The male and female mice ( 18–22 g ) were
            purchased from the Laboratory Animal Center, Tongji Medical College, Huazhong University
            of Science and Technology. Thirty minutes after the administration of the test groups in
            different doses (5.0, 1.0, and 0.2 mg /kg), the mice were given an intraperitoneal
            injection of 0.8% v/v acetic acid solution (0.1 mL/ 10 g ). The mice were placed into
            iron net cages individually. The writhing events produced in these mice were counted for
            30 min. A writhe is defined as abdominal stretching with a simultaneous stretching of at
            least one hind limb ( ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Declaration of competing Interest </title>
         <p>All the authors declare no competing financial interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title> Acknowledgements </title>
         <p> This work was supported financially by National Natural Science Foundation of China
            (U1703109) and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (HUST:
            2016YXMS148). We are grateful to the Drs. Yuncheng Cai and Tiantian Zeng at Huazhong
            University of Science and Technology Analytical and Testing Center for IR, UV, and X-ray
            crystallographic data collection, and Prof. Li-Jun Han at Huai-Hai Institute of
            Technology for X-ray crystallographic data analysis </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Appendix A. Supplementary data </title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://
            doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.112234.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title> References </title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Al-Lawati, H. , Binkhathlan, Z. , Lavasanifar, A. , 2019 .
                  Nanomedicine for the effective and safe delivery of non-steroidal
                  anti-inflammatory drugs: a review of preclinical research . Eur. J. Pharm.
                  Biopharm. 142 , 179–194 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bao, G. , Wang, L. , Cheng, K. , Feng, Y. , Li, X. , Qin, G. , 2003
                  . Diterpenoid and phenolic glycosides from the roots of Rhododendron molle .
                  Planta Med. 69 , 434–439 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Cunningham, C.W. , Elballa, W.M. , Vold, S.U. , 2019 . Bifunctional
                  opioid receptor ligands as novel analgesics . Neuropharmacology 151 , 195–207 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Dang, T. , Zheng, G. , Zhang, Q. , Jin, P. , Zhang, H. , Su, L. ,
                  Qin, D. , Yao, G. , 2019 . Sesquiterpenoids with diverse carbon skeletons from the
                  roots of Cichorium glandulosum and their anti-inflammatory activities .
                  Fitoterapia 136 , 104170–104177 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Fukuyama, K. , Tsukihara, T. , Katsube, Y. , Katai, M. , Meguri, H.
                  , 1976 . A structure analysis of pieristoxin G by the X-ray diffraction method .
                  Chem. Pharm. Bull. 24 , 2775–2780 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hikino, H. , Ogura, M. , Takemoto, T. , 1971 . Stereostructure of
                  asebotoxin VII, toxin of Pieris japonica . Chem. Pharm. Bull. 19 , 1980–1981 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Jamison, R.N. , Mao, J. , 2015 . Opioid analgesics. Mayo Clin .
                  Proc. 90 , 957–968 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Joksimovic, S.L. , Covey, D.F. , Jevtovic, T.V. , Todorovic, S.M. ,
                  2018 . Neurosteroids in pain management: a new perspective on an old player .
                  Front. Pharmacol. 9 , 1127–1136 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kaiya, T. , Sakakibara, J. , 1985 . Occurrence of pieroside C,
                  grayanotox-9-ene derivative , in Pieris japonica . Chem. Pharm. Bull. 33 ,
                  4637–4639 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Katai, M. , Matsushima, T. , Terai, T. , Meguri, H. , 1975 . Studies
                  on the constituents of the leaves of Pieris japonica D. don. IV. The isolation and
                  the structure of pieristoxin F, pieristoxin G and several toxic components .
                  Yakugaku Zasshi 95 , 778–783 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Katai, M. , Fujiwara, M. , Terai, T. , Meguri, H. , 1980 . Studies
                  on the constituents of the leaves of Pieris japonica D . Don. Chem. Pharm. Bull.
                  28 , 3124–3126 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Li, Y. , Liu, Y. , Yu, S. , 2013 . Grayanoids from the Ericaceae
                  family: structures, biological activities and mechanism of action . Phytochem.
                  Rev. 12 , 305–325 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Li, Y. , Liu, Y. , Zhang, J. , Liu, Y. , Ma, S. , Qu, J. , Lv, H.,
                  Yu, S. , 2015 . Antinociceptive grayanoids from the roots of Rhododendron molle .
                  J. Nat. Prod. 78 , 2887–2895 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Li, C. , Yan, X. , Zhang, A. , Gao, J. , 2017 . Structural diversity
                  and biological activity of the genus Pieris terpenoids . J. Agric. Food Chem. 65 ,
                  9934–9949 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Li, Y. , Zhu, Y. , Zhang, Z. , Liu, Y. , Liu, Y. , Qu, J. , Ma, S. ,
                  Wang, X. , Yu, S. , 2018 . Diterpenoids from the fruits of Rhododendron molle ,
                  potent analgesics for acute pain . Tetrahedron 74 , 693–699 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Li, C. , Zhang, J. , Zhang, X. , Li, S. , Gao, J. , 2019 . An
                  overview of grayanane diterpenoids and their biological activities from the
                  Ericaceae family in the last seven years . Eur. J. Med. Chem. 166 , 400–416 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Liu, C. , Lei, C. , Zhong, Y. , Gao, L. , Li, J. , Yu, M. , Li, J. ,
                  Hou, A. , 2014 . Novel grayanane diterpenoids from Rhododendron principis .
                  Tetrahedron 70 , 4317–4322 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Mercadante, S. , Porzio, G. , Gebbia, V. , 2014 . New opioids . J.
                  Clin. Oncol. 32 , 1671–1676 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Newman, D.J. , Cragg, G.M. , 2016 . Natural products as sources of
                  new drugs from 1981 to 2014 . J. Nat. Prod. 79 , 629–661 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Niu, C. , Li, Y. , Liu, Y. , Ma, S. , Li, L. , Qu, J. , Yu, S. ,
                  2016 . Analgesic diterpenoids from the twigs of Pieris formosa . Tetrahedron 72 ,
                  44–49 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Niu, C. , Li, Y. , Liu, Y. , Ma, S. , Wang, X. , Liu, F. , Liu, S. ,
                  Qu, J. , Yu, S. , 2019 . Diverse epoxy grayanane diterpenoids with analgesic
                  activity from the roots of Pieris formosa . Fitoterapia 133 , 29–34 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Parsons, S. , Flack, H.D. , Wagner, T. , 2013 . Use of intensity
                  quotients and differences in absolute structure refinement . Acta Crystallogr. B
                  69 , 249–259 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sakakibara, J. , Shirai, N. , 1980 . Grayanoside D, a diterpene
                  glucoside from Leucothoe grayana . Phytochemistry 19 , 2159–2162 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sakakibara, J. , Shirai, N. , Kaiya, T. , Nakata, H. , 1979 .
                  Grayanotoxin XVIII and grayanoside B, a new A- nor -B- homo-ent -kaurene and its
                  glucoside from Leucothoe grayana . Phytochemistry 18 , 135–137 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sakakibara, J. , Kaiya, T. , Shirai, N. , 1980 a. Studies on the
                  constituents of Pieris japonica . Isolation and structural elucidation of a new
                  diterpene, asebotoxin X and a new diterpene glucoside, pieroside A . Yakugaku
                  Zasshi 100 , 540–545 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sakakibara, J. , Shirai, N. , Kaiya, T. , Iitaka, Y. , 1980 b.
                  Grayanoside C, a diterpene glucoside from Leucothoe grayana . Phytochemistry 19 ,
                  1495–1497 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sun, N. , Zhu, Y. , Zhou, H. , Zhou, J. , Zhang, H. , Zhang, M. ,
                  Zeng, H. , Yao, G. , 2018 . Grayanane diterpenoid glucosides from the leaves of
                  Rhododendron micranthum and their bioactivities evaluation . J. Nat. Prod. 81 ,
                  2673–2681 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sun, N. , Qiu, Y. , Zhu, Y. , Liu, J. , Zhang, H. , Zhang, Q. ,
                  Zhang, M. , Zheng, G. , Zhang, C. , Yao, G. , 2019 a. Rhodomicranosides A−I,
                  analgesic diterpene glucosides with diverse carbon skeletons from Rhododendron
                  micranthum . Phytochemistry 158 , 1–12 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sun, N. , Zheng, G. , He, M. , Feng, Y. , Liu, J. , Wang, M. ,
                  Zhang, H. , Zhou, J. , Yao, G. , 2019 b. Grayanane diterpenoids from the leaves of
                  Rhododendron auriculatum and their analgesic activities . J. Nat. Prod. 82 ,
                  1849–1860 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sun, N. , Feng, Y. , Zhang, Q. , Liu, J. , Zhou, H. , Zhang, H. ,
                  Zheng, G. , Zhou, J. , Yao, G. , 2019 c. Analgesic diterpenoids with diverse
                  carbon skeletons from the leaves of Rhododendron auriculatum . Phytochemistry 168
                  , 112113–112123 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Teng, Y. , Zhang, H. , Zhou, J. , Zhan, G. , Yao, G. , 2018 .
                  Hebecarposides A−K, antiproliferative lanostane-type triterpene glycosides from
                  the leaves of Lyonia ovalifolia var. hebecarpa . Phytochemistry 151 , 32–41 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wang, L. , Qin, G. , Chen, S. , Li, C. , 2001 . Three diterpene
                  glucosides and a diphenylamine derivative from Pieris formosa . Fitoterapia 72 ,
                  779–787 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Yao, G. , Ding, Y. , Zuo, J. , Wang, H. , Wang, Y. , Ding, B. ,
                  Chiu, P. , Qin, G. , 2005 . Dihydrochalcones from the leaves of Pieris japonica .
                  J. Nat. Prod. 68 , 392–396 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhang, H. , Wang, L. , Qin, G. , 2005 . Grayanane diterpenoids from
                  the leaves of Craiobiodendron yunnanense . Bioorg. Med. Chem. 13 , 5289–5298 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhang, M. , Xie, Y. , Zhan, G. , Lei, L. , Shu, P. , Chen, Y. , Xue,
                  Y. , Luo, Z. , Wan, Q. , Yao, G. , Zhang, Y. , 2015 . Grayanane and leucothane
                  diterpenoids from the leaves of Rhododendron micranthum . Phytochemistry 117 ,
                  107–115 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhou, J. , Sun, N. , Zhang, H. , Zheng, G. , Liu, J. , Yao, G. ,
                  2017 a. Rhodomollacetals A–C, PTP1B inhibitory diterpenoids with a 2,3:5,6-di-
                  seco -grayanane skeleton from the leaves of Rhododendron molle . Org. Lett. 19 ,
                  5352–5355 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhou, J. , Zhan, G. , Zhang, H. , Zhang, Q. , Li, Y. , Xue, Y. ,
                  Yao, G. , 2017 b. Rhodomollanol A, a highly oxygenated diterpenoid with a 5/7/5/5
                  tetracyclic carbon skeleton from the leaves of Rhododendron molle . Org. Lett. 19
                  , 3935–3938 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhou, J. , Liu, J. , Dang, T. , Zhou, H. , Zhang, H. , Yao, G. ,
                  2018 a. Mollebenzylanols A and B, highly modified and functionalized diterpenoids
                  with a 9-benzyl-8,10-dioxatricyclo [5.2.1.0 1,5 ]decane core from Rhododendron
                  molle . Org. Lett. 20 , 2063–2066 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhou, J. , Liu, T. , Zhang, H. , Zheng, G. , Qiu, Y. , Deng, M. ,
                  Zhang, C. , Yao, G. , 2018 b. Anti-inflammatory grayanane diterpenoids from the
                  leaves of Rhododendron molle . J. Nat. Prod. 81 , 151–161 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhu, Y. , Zhang, Z. , Yan, H. , Lu, D. , Zhang, H. , Li, L. , Liu,
                  Y. , Li, Y. , 2018 . Antinociceptive diterpenoids from the leaves and twigs of
                  Rhododendron decorum . J. Nat. Prod. 81 , 1183–1192 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhu, Y. , Yan, H. , Wang, X. , Zhang, Z. , Zhang, H. , Chai, L. ,
                  Li, L. , Qu, J. , Li, Y. , 2019 . Micranthanosides I and II, two novel
                  1,10-secograyanane diterpenoids and their antinociceptive analogues from the
                  leaves and twigs of Rhododendron micranthum . RSC Adv. 9 , 18439–18450 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
