<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-58551-0</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>‘Mainland-island’ population structure of a terrestrial salamander in a forest-bocage landscape with little evidence for in situ ecological speciation</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>03</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Salamandra salamandra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Salamandra salamandra
Linnaeus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. salamandra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. salamandra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
S. salamandra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Fagus sylvatica
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>s. salamandra</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

‘Mainland-island’ population structure of a terrestrial salamander in a forest-bocage landscape with little evidence for 
in situ
ecological

speciation

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Jan W. Arntzen
*
&amp; 
Joep van Belkom
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Adaptation to different ecological environments can, through divergent selection, generate phenotypic and genetic differences between populations, and eventually give rise to new species.The fire salamander (
<tp:taxon-name>
Salamandra salamandra
</tp:taxon-name>
) has been proposed to represent an early stage of ecological speciation, driven by differential habitat adaptation through the deposition and development of larvae in streams versus ponds in the Kottenforst near Bonn (Germany). We set out to test this hypothesis of ecological speciation in an area different from the one where it was raised and we took the opportunity to explore for drivers of genetic differentiation at a landscape scale. Asurvey over 640 localities demonstrated the species’ presence in ponds and streams across forests, hilly terrain and areas with hedgerows (‘bocage’). Genetic variation at 14 microsatellite loci across 41 localities in and around two small deciduous forests showed that salamander effective population sizes were higher in forests than in the bocage, with panmixia inthe forests (
F
st

&lt;

0.010) versus geneticdriftorfoundereffectsin several of thesmalland more orlessisolatedbocage populations (
F
st

&gt; 

0.025).The systemfits the ‘mainlandisland’ metapopulation model rather than indicating adaptive genetic divergence in pond versus stream larval habitats. Areanalysis of the Kottenforst data indicated that microsatellite genetic variation fitted a geographical rather than an environmental axis, with a sharp transition from a western pondbreeding to an eastern, more frequently stream-breeding group of populations. Aparallel changeover in mitochondrial DNA exists but remains to be well documented.The data support the existence of a hybrid zone following secondary contact of differentiated lineages, more so than speciation 
in situ
.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Adaptation to different ecological environments can, through divergent selection, generate phenotypic and genetic differences between populations. These changes may eventually give rise to new species. The speciation process is often quantitative in nature, as illustrated by numerous studies showing that divergence during speciation varies continuously, and the sequence of genetically-based changes that occur as two lineages on the pathway to reproductive isolation diverge fromone anotherhas been coinedthe ‘speciation continuum’ 


, 


. Divergent evolution and reproductive isolation are the primary elements of the speciation continuum, but many have recognized that reproductive isolation is usually a signature effect rather than a primary cause of speciation. Whereas the mechanisms underlying reproductive isolation are by now mostly well understood (such as natural and sexual selection and genetic drift due to founder events, etc.), biologists continue to struggle with understanding how and why these evolutionary processes cause the disjoined genetic connections that are integral to the emergence of newspecies, in particularin conditions of sympatry 


– 


. Organismsthat areorganized indeme-structured metapopulations, with good population sizes and small to moderate dispersal capabilities, such as many amphibian species, are good models for population genetic research and convincing examples involving the early stages of ecological speciation in this group would be particularly welcome. Unfortunately, amphibians also appear particularly proneto severelossesin recenttimes e.g. 


, 


andthis includesthe fire salamander 
<tp:taxon-name>
Salamandra salamandra
Linnaeus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 

17589, 


.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Naturalis Biodiversity Center,Leiden,The Netherlands
. *email: 
pim.arntzen@naturalis.nl
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The fire salamander represents a remarkable study system because from studies in the Kottenforst, near Bonn in Germany, it figures as an example of local ecological and genetic differentiation and adaptation, with pond- and stream-breedingpopulations possiblyrepresenting thefirst stepinthe speciation process 


– 


. It wouldbeimportant to determine whether similar processes can be uncovered in other regions where the species is distributed today. Other regions may serve as replicates despite the fact that each region may have had its own contingent evolutionary specificities. To perform a replicate study, we choose the ‘département’ (department) Mayenne in the west of France where we found the fire salamanders to deposit their larvae in streams as well as in ponds.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The standing genetic variability of populations represents the adaptive potential to changing environmental conditions and acts as a buffer against stochastic and catastrophic events 


, 


. The protection of genetic diversity, along with that of habitats and species 
per se
is thus a pillar to nature conservation 


, 


. The landscapes of the French coastal zone represent the archetypal dense hedgerow configuration known as ‘bocage’. From the perspective of biodiversity conservation prime assets of hedgerows are that they act as shelter areas for species unable to exist elsewhere in farmland and that they are usually interconnected into networks which facilitates dispersal across the landscape 

. The network of hedgerows possibly supports the presence and dispersal of the fire salamander and that of other primarily forest-dwelling species. The Mayenne study area therewith affords the opportunity to explore other landscape processes in this system, such as supported by continuous forest versus a mosaic of hedgerows. It is important to document if species are reliant on the bocage because a decline through the thinning of the hedgerow network could fragment otherwise continuous species distributions. Accordingly, in the present study we aimed to determine whether adaptive divergence in pond- and stream-breeding populations of the fire salamander could be identified in the west of France. We expect genetic differentiation to be more strongly associated with a pond- versus stream-breeding habitat than with the wider geography. Asecond aim was to quantify the importance of the bocage as a constituent to the fire salamander habitat and to evaluate what role it plays in the population dynamics of the species. Finally, informed by our new findings, we reanalyzed the Kottenforst data in an explicit geographical context.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Results

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
ForestandbocagepopulationsinthewestofFrance.
Larvaeof 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. salamandra
</tp:taxon-name>
werepresentin 251 localities (39%) and absent in 389 localities (61%). Localities are listed in a.kml file for use with e.g. Google Earth (Supplementary Information I). In logistic regression analysis the presence of the fire salamander is positively associated with forestation (P &lt;0.001), altitude (P &lt;0.001) and hedgerows (P &lt;0.05). At any amphibian breeding site, the probability for the occurrence of the fire salamander (
P
s
) is estimated by the equation (1/ (1 +exp(−0.0303 
*
percent_forest_cover-0.00562 
*
altitude-0.0299 
*
percent_hedgerow_cover +1.769))). The fitof the model is expressed by the ‘area under the curve’ statistic AUC = 0.721 ±0.020, indicating that we achieved a good description of favourable versus unfavourable fire salamander terrestrial habitats. When habitat parameter values are standardized the formulais (1/(1+ exp(a 
*
forest_cover +b 
*
altitude + c 
*
hedgerow_cover + 0.0210))), indicating the relative contributions to the model in the order forest (a = −0.910), altitude (b = −0.288) and hedgerows (c = −0.275). Extrapolating the model over the entire department suggests that habitats for the fire salamander outside forests are widespread in the hilly bocage landscape in the northeastern and northwestern corners of the department Mayenne. Low habitat suitability is found in the flat and deforested southern part of Mayenne, in particular the southwest (
Fig. 1
). The area studied for population genetic characteristics shows low habitat suitability in between and south of the forests Forêt de Bourgon and Bois de Hermet, intermediate habitat suitability surrounding the forests in the other cardinal directions and high habitat suitability further east of Bois de Hermet.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Localities studied for population genetic differentiation included 25 ponds and 16 streams and were 23 times from inside and 18 times from outside the forest. For the subdivision pond inside – outside and streams inside – outside the forests see 
Table 1. Ahigh
frequency of inferred null alleles (11.7%) and a substantial amount of missing data (5.0%) were observed for the microsatellite locus C2. After exclusion of this marker and the subsequent removal of seven individuals that had data missing for more than one locus (N = 734 remaining) the frequency of null alleles was estimated at 1.6% and 0.11% of data was missing. The genotypic data are presented in Supplementary Information II. The analyses with Colony software suggested that among individuals sampled from the same locality many were full siblings. With just one representative per family group population sample sizes went down by 357 under monogamy (48.6%) and by 85 under polygamy (11.6%). This approach also revealed a high potential for false positives since inferred siblings were frequent among larvae from different localities (N= 315 under monogamy, 42.9% and N =108 under polygamy, 14.7%). Analytical resultsforthe three data sets are summarized in 
Table 2
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The number of alleles observed per locus ranged from four in locus SalE5 to 15 in locus Sal3. Asingle locus significantly deviated from Hardy-Weinberg expectations and there were four instances of pairs of loci showing linkage disequilibrium. The overall 
F
st
was 0.0244. The statistical power to be able to detect the mixture of genetically differentiated populations with genetic clustering methods is dependent on sample size, the number of loci studied (14), the number of alleles per locus (average 9.4) and the proportioning of the samples over habitats, in our casesamplesize in streamsandponds (285/449 =0.63) orforestversusoutside forest (294/440 =0.67). Under equation 1 of Jorde 
et al
. (2018: 4021; see Materials and methods) the threshold for apower of 10% is 
F
st
~0.004, which is wellbelow the observed 
F
st-
value of 0.024.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
No association was observed between the pairwise distance matrices for genetic differentiation (
F
st
/(1- 
F
st
)) andthe logarithm of geographical distance (non-parametric matrix correlation, 
ρ
= −0.033, 
P
&gt;0.05), indicating the absence of isolation by distance over the study area. The observed amount of genetic differentiation is substantial but does not have a bimodal distribution as is illustrated by the UPGMA-dendrogram on 
F
st
(
Fig. 2A
). Atight cluster at 
F
st
&lt;0.010 is mostly composed of forest populations. Populations that join the dendrogram at higher 
F
st-
values are mostly from outside the forests, which reflects a non-random distribution (
G
-test for independence, 
G
= 11.34, df =1, P&lt;0.001). At 
F
st
&gt;0.025 just non-forest populations are added. No significant genetic differentiation was found for pond- versus stream inhabiting population (
G
= 1.35, P&gt; 0.05). Analyses with principal components revealed a wide overlap for the forest and non-forest groups. However, the forest populations form a tight group whereas the non-forest populations are more widely scattered over the bivariate plot (
Fig. 2B
). Accordingly, average distance to their nadir in the PC-plots is smaller for forest than for non-forest populations (Student’s 
t
-test, 
t
= 3.18, df =21.1, P &lt;0.01). No significant difference was found for the pond- versus stream-breeding classification (
t
= 0.58, df = 39, P&gt;0.05). The analysis with Structure yielded flat distributions with undifferentiated Q-values (
Table 2
). It is now realized thatthe methods employed frequently identify K =2 as the top level ofhierarchical structure, even whenmore subpopulations are actually present 

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Estimates for effective population size 
Ne
(
Ňe
) were significantly higher forforest than fornon-forest populations (
Ňe/forested
= 32.0, 
Ňe/non-forested
= 22.4; Mann-Whitney 
U
-test, 
U
= 301, P &lt;0.05) whereas they were not significantly different for pond and stream populations (
Ňe/pond
=27.0, 
Ňe/stream
= 29.0; 
U
= 240.5, P&gt; 0.05). Among just pond populations, those from theforest were larger than those from outside the forest (
Ňe/forested
= 32.7, 
Ňe/ non-forested
= 20.8; Kruskal-Wallis test statistic 5.25, P&lt;0.05) (
Table 1
; see also Supplementary Information III). No significant indications for population genetic bottleneck effects were observed.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Mitochondrial DNA sequences were 755–756 bp. The shorter sequence (Genbank accession number MK395359, N = 40) conforms to ‘type 1b’ and the longer one (Genbank accession number MK395358, N =89) to ‘type 1a’ 

. Sequences are equivalent to Genbank accession number KU 
24998920
with an indel at position 599. The distribution of the two mtDNA types bears no correspondence to the forest/non-forest inhabiting or to the stream- versus pond-breeding habitat classification (see Supplementary Information IV). For a compilation of mtDNA data from across northern Europe see Supplementary Information V.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
ForestpopulationsintheKottenforst, Germany.
MicrosatellitegeneticdatafortheKottenforstwere taken from Hendrix 
etal
. 

. Allthe investigated populationsare situated inside the forest. Firesalamander larvae were observed in a variety of aquatic habitats (
Table 3
), with streams less frequent in the western section of the forest (one stream locality out of 27, 4%) than in the eastern section of the forest (six stream localities out of 20, 30%).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Analyses with Colony software suggested that many of the sampled individuals were full siblings. With only one representative per family group population sample sizes went down by 1628 under monogamy (63.5%) and by 1194 under polygamy (46.6%). Colony also revealed ahigh potential for false positives since inferred siblings werefrequentamonglarvae from differentlocalities (N = 624 under monogamy, 24.3% and N = 210 under polygamy, 8.2%). Results for genetic (dis)equilibria, genetic bottleneck effects and isolation by distance were markedly different for full and the sibling-excluded data sets. In the former we found 72 cases of significant deviation from Hardy-Weinberg expectations and 941 pairwise locus combinations with significant linkage disequilibrium (
Table 2
). Numbers were by two orders of magnitude lower in the reduced data sets, suggesting that the significant signals for genetic equilibria are largely to be attributed to the sampling of family groups. In the sibling reduced data set we identified no significant signal for population genetic bottlenecks whereas there were seven in the full data set. Finally, the signal for isolation by distance was not significant in the full data set (non-parametric matrix correlation, 
ρ
= 0.070, P&gt;0.05) and significant in the reduced data sets (
ρ
=0.191, P &lt;0.001 under monogamy and 
ρ
= 0.119, P&lt;0.05 under polygamy).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Estimates for effective population size varied widely and were not significantly different for forest sections (
Ňe/west
= 31.2, range 4–104; 
Ňe/east
= 55.6, range 2–272; Mann-Whitney 
U
-test, 
U
=249, P&gt;0.05). Average effective population sizes for the Kottenforst were not significantly different from those in Mayenne (Mann-Whitney 
U
-test, 
U
= 1037, P&gt; 0.05), but showed a wider range in the Kottenforst than in Mayenne (5 &lt;
Ňe
&lt;56, see also Supplementary Information III).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The overall 
F
st
for the studied fire salamander populations was 0.0360, which value widely surpassed the threshold for 10% analytical power of 0.0016. The UPGMA-dendrogram of pairwise 
F
st-
values reveals two clusters that are differentiated at 
F
st
=0.04 (
Fig. 3A
). One cluster is made up of one eastern plus 14 western populations and the other cluster is made up of two western and 14 eastern populations, which reflects a non-random distribution (
G
-test for independence, 
G
= 23.54, df = 1, P &lt;0.001). This signal is stronger than the parallel separation in pond- and stream-breeding populations (
G
=4.60, P&lt;0.05). Populations joining the dendrogram at higher 
F
st
levelsare fromeither forest section. This setof populationsis characterizedbyparticularly low 
Ňe
(average 
Ňe
= 7.6 versus 
Ňe
= 60.1 for the remainder; Mann-Whitney 
U
-test, 
U
= 439.5, P&lt;0.001), suggesting that a founder effect or genetic drift underlies the genetic differentiation of small populations. Analyses with principal components supports the population allocation of two spatial groups, in which the western and eastern group show no overlap along the first PC-axis if indeed small populations are excluded (
Fig. 3B
). The support for separation of a western versus an eastern group is several orders of magnitude stronger than that for the (more or less parallel) separation of pond- and stream-breeding salamander populations (Student’s 
t
-test, 
t
= 8.58, df = 29.0, P &lt;0.000001 versus 
t
= 2.81, df = 45, P = 0.007401). In line with these results, the plot of the PC1-scores over a west to east axis describes a genetic transition in a sigmoid curve of the type reminiscent to those analyzed in the classical hybrid zone literature e.g. 

. The cline that best fitted the data has a central position at km 365.3 of the longitudinal axis of the Universal Transverse Mercator coordinate system grid (UTM) and a width of 3.95 km (
Fig. 4A
). Because the PC-analysis extracted only a small proportion of the total variance in the data (2.1% along the first axis) we repeated the cline fitting procedure with the ‘proportion of pond- versus stream-breeding genotypes’ or ‘assignment probabilities’ of Hendrix 
et al
. 

under an inferred optimal number of two genetic clusters (K = 2), derived with Structure software 


, 


. The cline description that best accommodates these values has a central position at km 365.1 and a width of 1.11 km (
Fig. 4B
). The full model descriptions are presented in Supplementary Information VI.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Discussion

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Adult fire salamanders are terrestrial amphibians that deposit larvae in ponds or streams, in where these develop until metamorphosis. The species figures as an example of local ecological and genetic differentiation and adaptation, possibly representing the firststep in the speciation process 


, 


. We set out to replicate the observation of genetic differentiation of stream- and pond-breeding populations and we sought the opportunity to explore for additional drivers of genetic differentiation at a landscape scale. However, the microsatellite data we obtained for the fire salamander in Mayenne did not yield a signal for genetic differentiation of pond- and stream-breeding populations. Instead we found genetic differences for populations from inside and outside forests.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
FiresalamanderpopulationstructureinMayenne, France.
Theresultsofourhabitatsuitabilitymodelling are in line with the general habitat preference of the fire salamander in Central Europe, namely mixed deciduous forest at 200–400 m a.s.l. 


, 


. In addition, wedocument the regular presence of fire salamanders outside forests, in particular in hilly areas where the network of hedges is dense. Such a pastural landscape is known as ‘bocage’. Our data suggest that forests are the primary fire salamander habitat. Firstly, forestation represents the most prominent contribution to the habitat model. Secondly, the estimates for effective population sizes are larger for forest than for bocage populations. Thirdly, forest populations are genetically most similar suggesting ongoing gene flow, presumably covering historical times. In contrast, the bocage populations are frequently genetically differentiated fromone another (
F
st
&gt; 0.025) indicatingthat they are more or lessisolated and thatgenetic drift and founder effect operate more effectively in these small populations. In metapopulation terminology, the fire salamander system in Mayenne fits the ‘mainland-island’ model 

in which forests are the mainland and the bocage represents an archipelago of islands. In Spain, genetic differentiation was observed to increase from 
F
st
&lt;0.05 among most continental 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. salamandra
</tp:taxon-name>
populations to 
F
st
~0.10 for peninsular populations separated for at least 2000 years, to 
F
st
~0.19 forinsular populationsseparated for 6–13 Kybp (thousands of years before present) (geological data 


, 


, genetic data 


, 


). Thissystem, literally fitting themainland-island model andat acomparablespatial scale to Mayenne, confirms the propensity for genetic drift in small and isolated fire salamander populations.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The two forests in Mayenne may be interconnected by dispersal through the dense but patchy and declining bocage. While population connectivity operating through the network of hedgerows is likely, the study area does not offer a good setting for testing this hypothesis. First, we noted no consistent spatial genetic signal and it will be difficult to assess if this can be attributed to the counteracting forces of isolation by distance and connectivity by habitat. Second, to be able to disentangle these effects requires an explicit spatial configuration. For example, to test for fire salamander dispersal along hedgerows, the hypothesized corridor is to deviate from a straight line. If not, genetic differentiation will, by default, be associated to geographical, not ecological distance.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
We found no strong evidence for population genetic bottlenecking, suggesting that fire salamander populations may be stable over time. Another line of evidence for the long-term persistence of fire salamander populations areseveraloccurrencesin the northwestof Mayenne (Supplementary Information I) 

. Thisareais currently devoid of forests (
Fig. 2B
) and also 18 
th
century maps bythe Cassinifamily (accessible at https://www.geoportail. gouv.fr/donnees/carte-de-cassini) show no forest at the localities where fire salamanders were actually observed, suggesting that extant populations persisted in the bocage over the centuries and providing ample opportunity for genetic drift to operate. While we could not detect significant departures from panmixia in forests, the bocage populations are more or less isolated. Yet the bocage localities may serve as ‘islands’ or ‘stepping stones’. Even a loose network may help to preserve population connectivity at a wider spatial scale and eventually promote the genetic exchange between forest populations, such as those of Forêt de Bourgon and Bois de Hermet (
Fig. 2B
). However, the pastural landscape in western France rapidly deteriorates from the perspective of wildlife, mostly through field size enlargements and agricultural reform, with the concomitant loss of small landscape elements such as hedgerows, spinneys and ponds 


, 

– 


. Afurther deterioration of the bocage is likely to isolate the forest populations from one another. To illustrate this point, in the flat, southern part of Mayenne the bocage has largely disappeared since the Second World War 

and the fire salamander is locally rare with some scattered occurrences 

(Supplementary Information I).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
FiresalamanderpopulationstructureintheKottenforst.

TheGermanKottenforstsupportstwofire salamander population groupsthat are differentiated at 
F
st
= 0.030 and thatare proposed to represent pond- versus stream-breeders. However, the ecological data in support of this interpretation are meagre, simply because stream-breeding populations are a minority in the Kottenforst system. Moreover, focusing on large and presumably healthy populations that are locally more frequently found in streams than in ponds (
Table 3
) strengthens the eco-geographical distinction more so than it sharpens the genetic differentiation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The west to east distinction is to some degree obscured by a suite of 16 populations that are more deeply genetically differentiated (0.030 &lt;
F
st
&lt;0.153; 
Fig. 3
). These latter populations are characterized by significantly smaller effective population sizes than average and 11 of them have 
Ňe
≤ 10. The small population sizes suggest that genetic drift might be prominent, but given the more or less unhampered dispersal of adult fire salamanders across the forest, populations are unlikely to be isolated and a genetic founder effect is a more plausible explanation.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
With an average minimum distance of neighbouring populations of ca. 400 m the grid of localities studied in the Kottenforst is tighter than in Mayenne. Yet, unlike Mayenne, the pond- and stream-breeding populations appear to be spatially, behaviourally and genetically separated. This separation takes effect along a roughly longitudinal axis. The by approximation sigmoid shaped transition is 1.11–3.95 km wide, with inflection points that are 730–1440 m apart (
Fig. 4
). A cline this narrow cannot result from neutral processes exclusively. In the absence of selection, the width (
w
) of the cline can be predicted from a diffusion model as a function of dispersal distance (
d
) and the lengthof timesince contact (
t
), as 
w
=2.51 
d
√(
t
) 

. Generation time is reported as six years forboth sexes 

and alsoas three years formales andfour years for females 

. At an averagedispersal of 200 mper generation, which is at the lower limit because it just covers the regular home range, cline widths would exceed the measured width in a couple of generations and at higher dispersal, such as distances of up to 2000 m 

, the collapse of the cline would be near-instantaneous. However, the Kottenforst genetic transition is sharp, suggesting that intrinsic selection operates against the two lineages’ mixed offspring. The center of the transition is further characterized by a paucity of material studied, presumably caused by lack of aquatic habitat suitable for the deposition of larvae. This observation fits classical theory where a hybrid zone may be ‘captured’ where an area of low population densityacts as abarrierto further movement 


, 


. If dispersalis high, selectionagainst hybridsis to be strong. Evidence for genetic incompatibility of thelineages may have been overlooked by Caspers 
et al
. 

. These authors were surprised to find that offspring numbers in the Kottenforst 
increased
with the degree of genetic relatedness between females and their sires. Puzzling as this observation might be for within-lineage data, in the context of selection against hybrids it makes direct sense.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The postglacial range expansion of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. salamandra
</tp:taxon-name>
has been linked to the spread of the beech, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fagus sylvatica
</tp:taxon-name>
L 


, 

, 


. Thecontact zone, cq. intra-specific hybrid zoneinthe Kottenforst may haveoriginated ca. 8 Kybp, by colonization from southern European glacial refuge areas, possibly involving the south of France and the northern Balkans, butmore northerlylocations cannotbe excluded 


, 


. Regardlessof the location of the glacial refugia, the hybrid zone in the Kottenforst appears to have been kept in check over hundreds or thousands of years, in which selection against hybrids counteracted dispersal into the zone. As an alternative explanation to 
in situ
ecological speciation, we suggest that the Kottenforst is an area of secondary contact of a pond-breeding western lineage and astream-breedingeastern lineage. Pond-breeding inthe Kottenforstis consideredarecent adaptation 


, 


, but we consider this unlikely becausethe conditionis widespreadin western Europe 


, 

, 

, 

, 


.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
An argument against the secondary contact scenario may be that the Kottenforst fire salamander populations are more similarto one anotherthanto other, nearby populations for mitochondrial 

and nuclear genetic markers 

. The fire salamander in northern Europe is characterized by two mitochondrial DNA lineages with ‘type 1’ in the west and ‘type 2’ in the east. According to Weitere 
et al
. 

the pond- and stream-breeding populations in the Kottenforst are all descendants of the western mitochondrial DNA lineage. However, a sharp and complete transition from type 1 to type 2 is found not far away (at 70–80km north, in between the localities Felderbachtal and Bochum; Supplementary Information V). We propose that the mtDNA cline is displaced relative to the cline from the nuclear genetic markers, a phenomenon regularly observed, especially for uniparentally transmitted markers 


– 


. Unfortunately, a wide sampling gap (&gt;350 km) precludes measuring position, width and shape of the mtDNA transition east of the Kottenforst. With microsatellite data Steinfartz 
et al
. 

also found that the Kottenforst populations are the most closely related in the wider area. This conclusion, however, depends on the position of the ‘root’ of the graph (which is not provided) and the supporting evidence is not unambiguous given the graph’s short internal branches. Future research might reveal a continuation of the fire salamander contact zone outside the Kottenforst and possibly show that the western and eastern lineages represent the currently described subspecies 
S. s. terrestris
Lacépède, 1788 and 

S. 
<tp:taxon-name>s. salamandra</tp:taxon-name>

. A wider phylogeographic survey is required to solve these issues.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Concludingremarks.
Thefiresalamanderisaspeciespronetopopulationgeneticdifferentiation. Substantial genetic drift has beenreported for small and isolatedpopulations across its range 


, 

– 


. We analyzed microsatellite genetic data in two metapopulations of the fire salamander in the northwest of Europe, with contrasting results. In France we documented small, isolated, persisting and genetically differentiated populations in the bocage versus panmixia in two small deciduous forests. This population structure fits the classical mainland-island model. Amainland-island population structure may have been paramount to the fire salamander prior to the recent intensification of agriculture, the field size enlargements that came with it and the widespread conversion from pasture for cattle-breeding to arable for growing crops. We did not find a bimodal distributioncoinciding withstream- andpond-reproductionas detectedin the Kottenforst 


, 

, 


. Accordingly, the fire salamander system in France offers no support for habitat driven genetic differentiation other than through drift and founder effects operating in more or less isolated bocage populations. In Germany we found small and genetically differentiated populations scattered over the Kottenforst, in addition to larger populations occupying ponds in the western section and ponds and streams in the eastern section of the forest. The finding is somewhat puzzling, given the unrestricted gene flow that we documented for the French forest populations and the rampant migration documented for the Kottenforst 
per se
, with large home ranges and frequent long-distance dispersal 

. An 
ad hoc
explanation, supported by the high frequencies of full-siblings and low effective population sizes, is that these localities represent a particularly intensive sampling scheme, with larvae included from unusual aquatic habitats such as puddles and wheel ruts (
Table 3
). These small and frequently impermanent water bodies may represent sub-optimal conditions for larval growth, survival and metamorphosis and be transient satellites to the core fire salamander populations. Finally, to explain the significant spatial component in the remaining genetic variation, we propose that secondary contact between a western and an eastern fire salamander lineage better explains the available data than an ecological sympatric speciation scenario.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Materials and Methods

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
We recorded the presence or absence of fire salamander larvae in 640 amphibian pond and stream breeding sites across the department Mayenne. Ponds represent focal points of amphibian presence and harbour more or less isolated populations (or ‘demes’) that together constitute a metapopulation. The deme structure in streams is less obvious, but clearly not all sections of a stream are equally suitable for reproduction, for example in sections with and without predatory fish, or sections falling dry. Yet, for consistency, we consider the amphibian sites that we study to represent local populations. Locality data on altitude (m above sea level, a.s.l.), forestation and hedgerows (percent cover) were extracted from digital IGN maps (Institute Géographique Nationale) with a 25 m spatial resolution, provided by department officials. The area considered around each pond or stream sampling locality had a radius of 200 m. This scale should represent a typical fire salamander home range because 200m is the median distance travelled by adults in a capture-recapture study in the Kottenforst 

. The biological and environmental data were analyzed by logistic regression with a weight parameter, so that in analysis the number of fire salamander presences equaled the number of absences. Habitat models were visualized with ILWIS 
3.658
. We did not observe a disease-born population declinethat wasreported ca. 500 kmto the northwest, in The Netherlands 

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
The area selected for population genetic research is situated around two small, largely deciduous forests and positioned at the transition from flat and deforested in the south of Mayenne, to hilly with a bocage landscape in the north (
Fig. 1
). Larvae were captured with dip nets in 41 ponds and streams which were located inside as well as outside the forests. The larvae were released on the spot directly after tail tip tissue sampling. Altogether 741 salamander larvae were genotyped for 15 polymorphic microsatellite loci. The loci Sal3, Sal29, SalE11, SalE5, SalE6, SalE7 and SalE8 were studied following Steinfartz 
et al
. 

and the loci B11, C2, C3, E11, G6, G9, IA6, IIA6 were studied following Hendrix 
et al
. 

. Locus SalE5 is adinucleotide microsatellitelocus and the othersare composed of tetramer motifs. After a quality check (see Results) data for the locus C2 were excluded so that 14 markers remained. Atotal of 129 individuals from 14 localities was sequenced for the mitochondrial D-loop (control region, 756 bp) as describedin Steinfartz 
et al
. 

. Nucleargeneticdatafrom the German Kottenforstinvolved 2563 larvalfiresalamanders studied at 17 polymorphicmicrosatellite loci andwere retrievedfrom Hendrix 
et al
. 

. The 47 Kottenforst sampling localities were classified in two spatial groups (‘west’ with localities K01-K27 and ‘east’ with localities K28-K47) that represent opposite sections of a sharp genetic transition (see Results).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Computer programs employed for the genetic data were as follows. FreeNA 

to analyze for the presence of null-alleles. FreeNA was run with 1000 replicates using the EM algorithm. GenePop version 
4.263
to estimate 
F
st-
values and analyze for Hardy-Weinberg and linkage (dis)equilibria. GenePop was run with dememorization number 1000, 100 batches and 1000 iterations per batch. Linkage disequilibrium was determined using the log likelihood ratio statistic. Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium and linkage disequilibrium results were interpreted under the Benjamini-Hochberg correction for multiple comparisons. Statistical power for the detection of genetically differentiated yet sympatric populations was estimated following Jorde 
et al
. 

. The genetic diversity among populations was summarized by clustering with the unweighted pair group method with arithmetic mean with Primer-e software (UPGMA 
65
) and by principalcomponent analysis (PC) with Adegenetversion 2.0.0 following the manuals 


, 


. We also carried out a Bayesian assignment analysis with Structure 

, to which we adopted the program settings for the similar analyses by Hendrix 
et al
. 

. The parameter K (the number of genetic groups suggested by the data) was evaluated under the ‘Evanno-criterion’ that is implemented in StructureHarvester 

. We used Colony version 2.0. 
6.270
to analyze family groupsand to estimateeffective population size (
Ňe
) from the frequency of siblings. Settings for Colony were both sexes either monogamous or polygamous (see below), no allelic dropout or typing errors, diploid, codominant markers, no inbreeding, scaled full sibship, unknown population allele frequency, ten ‘medium long’ or ‘very long’ runs under full-likelihood with ‘medium’ precision and a ‘strong/optimal’ sibship priorfor effectivepopulation size. Results for 
Ňe
reportedareunder α is zero, assuming that deviations from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium are negligible. We used Bottleneck 

to test for reductions in effective population size by considering that alleles are generally lost faster than heterozygosity and thus, populations that have experienced a reduction in effective population size are expected to have excess heterozygosity relative to that expected under mutation-drift equilibrium. Samples smaller than for ten individuals were ignored. Statistical relevance of the results were determined with the Wilcoxon signed-rank test. We applied the two phase model with 93.6% single step mutations, variance 30 and 10,000 replications. The proportion of single-step mutations was determined with Misat version 
1.072
with dimer code 2, tetramer code 4, gridsize 40, moments estimated under the one-step model, 100,000 runs through the Markov chain, with continuously updating the value of 
θ
0
. We used HZAR 

to formalize the geographical clinesuggested by the first PC-axis for the Kottenforst. The chain length was 100,000 with a burn-in of 10%, randomized seeds and model selection based on AICc scores. For details on the cline fitting procedure and model selection see e.g. 

. Mitochondrial DNA sequences were aligned with ClustalW version 
275
under default settings. Matrix correlations were done with Primer-e 

under 10,000 permutations. Other statistical analyses were with SPSS v. 
2076
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Reproduction in the fire salamander may be monogamous or polygamous. The available data indicate that both systems occur in nature about equally frequent 

and we explored both possibilities. Including siblings in analyses of population diversity and structurecanintroduce avarietyof biases (

and references therein). Clutch sizes in the fire salamander are ca. 
3027
and the more or less frequent sampling of full- and half-siblings in our study cannot be excluded. However, excluding all but one members of a family group is not exempt from problemsneitherand will cause other biases 


, 


. Consideringthe moderate number of markersand alleles ineitherof the two data sets we tested for the presence of full-siblings in the material at two levels. Firstly, we reconstructed family groups per population. The numbers of inferred full-siblings were substantial. Secondly, we compared all individuals across localities. Although female fire salamanders may deposit larvae in more than one water body 

this phenomenon will be rare in our sampling of disparate localities with average minimum distances of ca. 1.1 km in Mayenne and 400 m in the Kottenforst. Consequently, inferred full-siblings from different localities possibly qualify as false positives. It is altogether not straightforward to determine the balance between redundant information from siblings included versus independent information from false positives excluded. We here present resultsfrom the fulldata set not to hampercomparability with published results 

, withthe parallelresults for the siblings excludeddata setin 
Table 2
. The mitochondrial DNAdata considered include 

.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Ethicsstatement.
Methodswerecarriedoutinaccordancewiththerelevantguidelinesandregulations. The tissue sampling protocol was approved by the Research Coordination Office of Naturalis Biodiversity Center. Fieldwork was carried under out under license from the ‘Service Aménagement Environnement-Chasse, Direction départementale de l’Agriculture et de la Forêt, Mayenne arrêt no. 2003-A-207.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Data availability

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The genotypic data for fire salamanders from Mayenne, France are presented in Supplementary Information II. The data for the Kottenforst, Germany are accessible at https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.h0r6q.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Received: 21 August 2019; Accepted: 9 January 2020; Published: xx xx xxxx</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
References

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

1. 
Hendry, A. P.
, 
Bolnick, D. I.
, 
Berner, D.
&amp; 
Peichel, C. L.
Along the speciation continuum in sticklebacks
. 

Journal of Fish Biology

75

, 
2000–2036
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1095-8649.2009.02419.x
(
2009
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

2. 
Nosil, P.
Ecological Speciation

. 
Oxford University Press: Oxford, United Kingdom
, 
https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:osobl/ 9780199587100.001.0001
(
2012
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

3. 
Harrison, R. G.
Molecular changes at speciation
. 

Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics

22

, 
281–308
, 
https://doi.org/10.1146/ annurev.ecolsys.22.1.281
(
1991
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

4. 
Coyne, J. A.
&amp; 
Price, T. D.
Little evidence for sympatric speciation in island birds
. 

Evolution

54

, 
2166–2171
, 
https://doi. org/10.1554/0014-3820(2000)054[2166:LEFSSI]2.0.CO;2
(
2000
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

5. 
Shaw, K. L.
&amp; 
Mullen, S. P.
Genes versus phenotypes in the study of speciation
. 

Genetica

139

, 
649–661
, 
https://doi.org/10.1007/ s10709-011-9562-4
(
2011
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

6. 
Shaw, K.L.
, 
Mullen, S.P.
Speciation continuum
. 

Journal of Heredity

105

, (Special Issue), 
741–742
, 
https://doi.org/10.1093/jhered/ esu060
(
2014
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

7. 
Allentoft, M. E.
&amp; 
O’Brien,J.
Global amphibian declines,loss of genetic diversity andfitness:a review
. 

Diversity

2

, 
47–71
, 
https://doi. org/10.3390/d2010047
(
2010
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

8. 
McCartney‐Melstad, E.
&amp; 
Shaffer, H.B.
Amphibianmolecular ecology and how it hasinformed conservation
. 

Molecular Ecology

24

, 
5084–5109
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.13391
(
2015
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

9. 
Martel, A.
et al
. 
Recent introduction of a chytrid fungus endangers Western Palearctic salamanders
. 

Science

346

, 
630–631
, 
https:// doi.org/10.1126/science.1258268
(
2014
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

10. 
Spitzen-van der Sluijs, A.
et al
. 

Rapid enigmatic decline drives the fire salamander (
Salamandra salamandra
) to the edge of extinction in the Netherlands

. 

Amphibia-Reptilia

34

, 
233–239
, 
https://doi.org/10.1163/15685381-00002891
(
2013
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

11. 
Weitere, M.
, 
Tautz, D.
, 
Neumann, D.
&amp; 
Steinfartz, S.
Adaptive divergence vs. environmental plasticity: tracing local genetic adaptation of metamorphosis traits in salamanders
. 

Molecular Ecology

13

, 
1665– 1677
, https://doi. org/ 
10.1111/j.1365-294X.2004.02155.x
(
2004
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

12. 
Steinfartz, S.
, 
Weitere, M.
&amp; 
Tautz, D.
Tracing the first step to speciation: ecological and genetic differentiation of a salamander population in a small forest
. 

Molecular Ecology

16

, 
4550–4561
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2007.03490.x
(
2007
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

13. 
Caspers, B. A.
et al
. 

The more the better – polyandry and genetic similarity are positively linked to reproductive success in a natural population of terrestrial salamanders (
Salamandra salamandra
)

. 

Molecular Ecology

23

, 
239–250
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.12577
(
2014
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

14. 
Frankham, R.
; 
Ballou, J. D.
, 
Briscoe, D.A.
Introduction to Conservation Genetics

. 
Cambridge University Press: Cambridge, United Kingdom
, 
https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511808999
(
2002
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

15. 
Willi, Y.
, 
van Buskirk, J.
&amp; 
Hoffmann, A. A.
Limits to the adaptive potential of small populations
. 

Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics

37

, 
433–458
, 
https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.37.091305.110145
(
2006
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

16. 
Balkenhol, N.
et al
. 
Identifying future research needs in landscape genetics: where to from here?
Landscape Ecology

24

, 
455–463
, 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10980-009-9334-z
(
2009
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

17. 
Hoban, S. M.
et al
. 
Bringing genetic diversity to the forefront of conservation policy and management
. 

Conservation Genetics Resources

5

, 
593–598
, 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s12686-013-9859-y
(
2013
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

18. 
Baudry, J.
, 
Bunce, R. G.
&amp; 
Burel, F.
Hedgerows: an international perspective on their origin, function and management
. 

Journal of Environmental Management

60

, 
7–22
, 
https://doi.org/10.1006/jema.2000.0358
(
2000
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

19. 
Janes, J.K.
etal
. 

The 
K
=2 conundrum

. 

Molecular Ecology

26

, 
3594–3602
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.14187
(
2017
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

20. 
Pereira,R.J.
, 
Martínez‐Solano, I.
&amp; 
Buckley, D.
Hybridization duringaltitudinal range shifts:nuclear introgression leadsto extensive cyto‐nuclear discordance in the fire salamander
. 

Molecular Ecology

25

, 
1551–1565
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.13575
(
2016
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

21. 
Hendrix, R.
, 
Schmidt, B. R.
, 
Schaub, M.
, 
Krause, E. T.
, 
Steinfartz, S.
Data from: Differentiation of movement behavior in an adaptively divergng salamander population
. 

Dryad Digital Repository

., 
https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.h0r6q
(
2017
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

22. 
Pannekoek, A. J.
The Ria problem. The role of antecedence, deep weathering, and Pleistocene slope-wash in the formation of the west-Galician Rias
. 

Tijdschrift Koninklijk Nederlands Aardrijkskundig Genootschap

83

, 
289–297
(
1966
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

23. 
Szymura,J. M.
&amp; 
Barton,N. H.

Genetic analysis of ahybrid zone betweenthe fire‐belliedtoads, 
Bombina bombina
and 
B.variegata
, near Cracowin southern Poland

. 

Evolution

40

, 
1141–1159
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1558-5646.1986.tb05740.x
(
1986
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

24. 
Pritchard,J.K.
, 
Stephens, M.
&amp; 
Donnelly, P.
Inference of populationstructure usingmultilocus genotype data
. 

Genetics

155

, 
945–959
(
2000
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

25. 
Hendrix, R.
, 
Schmidt, B. R.
, 
Schaub, M.
, 
Krause, E. T.
&amp; 
Steinfartz, S.
Differentiation of movement behaviour in an adaptively diverging salamander population
. 

Molecular Ecology

26

, 
6400–6413
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.14345
(
2017
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

26. 
Caspers, B. A.
, 
Steinfartz, S.
&amp; 
Krause, E. T.
Larval deposition behaviour and maternal investment of females reflect differential habitat adaptation in a genetically diverging salamander population
. 

Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology

69

, 
407–413
, 
https://doi. org/10.1007/s00265-014-1853-1
(
2015
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

27. 
Thiesmeier, B.
Ökologie des Feuersalamanders

. 
Westarp Wissenschaften:Essen, Germany
(
1992
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

28. 
Thiesmeier,B.
&amp; 
Grossenbacher,K.
Salamandrasalamandra
(Linnaeus, 1758) —Feuersalamander.Pp

. 
1059-1132
in: 
Handbuchder Reptilien und Amphibien Europas: Schwanzlurche IIB
. Eds. 
Thiesmeier, B. and K. Grossenbacher. Aula Verlag: Wiebelsheim, Germany
(
2004
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

29. 
Hanski, I.
&amp; 
Gilpin, M.
Metapopulationdynamics:brief history and conceptualdomain
. 

Biological Journalof the Linnean Society

42

, 
3–16
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1095-8312.1991.tb00548.x
(
1991
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

30. 
Dias, J.M.A.
, 
Boski,T.
, 
Rodrigues, A.
&amp; 
Magalhaes,F.
Coastlineevolution in Portugal since the Last Glacial Maximumuntilpresent – a synthesis
. 

Marine Geology

170

, 
177–186
, 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0025-3227(00)00073-6
(
2000
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

31. 
Velo-Antón, G.
, 
Zamudio, K. R.
&amp; 
Cordero-Rivera, A.

Genetic drift and rapid evolution of viviparity in insular fire salamanders (
Salamandrasalamandra
)

. 

Heredity

108

, 
410–418
, 
https://doi.org/10.1038/hdy.2011.91
(
2012
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

32. 
Lourenço, A.
, 
Sequeira, F.
, 
Buckley, D.
&amp; 
Velo‐Antón, G.
Role of colonization history and species‐specific traits on contemporary genetic variation of two salamander species in a Holoceneisland‐mainland system
. 

Journal of Biogeography

45

, 
1054–1066
, 
https:// doi.org/10.1111/jbi.13192
(
2018
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

33. 
Baudin, B.
Amphibiens et Reptiles de la Mayenne

. 
Mayenne Nature Environnement:Laval,France
(
2010
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

34. 
Schoorl, J.
&amp; 
Zuiderwijk, A.

Ecological isolation in 
Triturus cristatus
and 
Triturus marmoratus
(Amphibia: Salamandridae)

. 

Amphibia-Reptilia

1

, 
235–252
, 
https://doi.org/10.1163/156853881X00357
(
1980
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

35. 
Arntzen, J. W.
, 
Abrahams, C.
, 
Meilink, W. R. M.
, 
Iosif, R.
&amp; 
Zuiderwijk, A.
Amphibian decline, pond loss and reduced population connectivity under agricultural intensification over a 38 year period
. 

Biodiversity and Conservation

26

, 
1411–1430
, 
https://doi. org/10.1007/s10531-017-1307-y
(
2017
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

36. 
Boissinot, A.
, 
Besnard, A.
&amp; 
Lourdais, O.
Amphibian diversity in farmlands: combined influences of breeding-site and landscape attributes in western France
. 

Agriculture Ecosystems and Environment

269

, 
51–61
, 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agee.2018.09.016
(
2019
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

37. 
Visser, M.
, 
de Leeuw, M.
, 
Zuiderwijk, A.
&amp; 
Arntzen, J. W.
Stabilization of a salamander moving hybrid zone
. 

Ecology and Evolution

7

, 
689–696
, 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.2676
(
2017
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

38. 
Barton, N. H.
, 
Gale, K. S.
Genetic analysis of hybrid zones. Pp. 13-45
in 
Harrison RG.
Hybrid Zones andthe Evolutionary Process

. 
Oxford University Press, Oxford, United Kingdom
(
1993
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

39. 
Seifert,D.
Untersuchungen an einer ostthüringischen Population des Feuersalamanders
. 

Salamandra salamandra
. 
Artenschutzreport

1

, 
1–6
(
1991
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

40. 
Trochet, A.
et al
. 
Adatabase of life-history traits of European amphibians
. 

Biodiversity Data Journal

2

, 
https://doi.org/10.3897/ BDJ.2.e4123
(
2014
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

41. 
Barton, N. H.
The dynamics of hybrid zones
. 

Heredity

43

, 
341–359
, 
https://doi.org/10.1038/hdy.1979.87
(
1979
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

42. 
Barton, N. H.
&amp; 
Hewitt, G. M.
Analysis of hybrid zones
. 

Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics

16

, 
113–148
, 
https://doi. org/10.1146/annurev.es.16.110185.000553
(
1985
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

43. 
Eiselt, J.Der

Feuersalamander 
Salamandrasalamandra
(L.).Beiträgezueinertaxonomischen Synthese

. 

Abhandlungenund Berichte für Naturkunde und Vorgeschichte Magdeburg

10

, 
77–154
(
1959
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

44. 
Bhagwat,S.A.
&amp; 
Willis, K.J.
Species persistence in northerly glacial refugia of Europe:a matter of chance or biogeographicaltraits?
Journal of Biogeography

35

, 
464–482
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2699.2007.01861.x
(
2008
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

45. 
Magri, D.
et al
. 
Anew scenario for the Quaternary history of European beech populations: palaeobotanical evidence and genetic consequences
. 

New Phytologist

171

, 
199–221
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2006.01740.x
(
2006
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

46. 
Reinhardt, T.S.
, 
Steinfartz, S.
, 
Paetzold, A.
&amp; 
Weitere, M.
Linking the evolution of habitat choice to ecosystem functioning:direct and indirect effects of pond-reproducing fire salamanders on aquatic-terrestrial subsidies
. 

Oecologia

173

, 
281–291
, 
https://doi. org/10.1007/s00442-013-2592-0
(
2013
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

47. 
Thiesmeier, B.
&amp; 
Mutz, T.

Zur Laichzeit und Larvalentwicklung des Feuersalamanders (
Salamandra salamandra terrestris
) im nordwestdeutschen Tiefland

. 

Zeitschrift für Feldherpetologie

4

, 
115–125
(
1997
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

48. 
Duguet, R.
, 
Melki, F.
(eds) 

Les Amphibiens de France, Belgique et Luxembourg

. 
Biotope:Mèze, France
(
2003
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

49. 
Steinfartz, S.
, 
Stemshorn, K.
, 
Kuesters, D.
&amp; 
Tautz, D.

Patterns of multiple paternity within and between annual reproduction cycles of the fire salamander (
Salamandra salamandra
) under natural conditions

. 

Journal of Zoology

268

, 
1–8
, 
https://doi. org/10.1111/j.1469-7998.2005.00001.x
(
2006
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

50. 
Toews, D. P. L.
&amp; 
Brelsford, A.
The biogeography of mitochondrial and nuclear discordance in animals
. 

Molecular Ecology

21

, 
3907–3930
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05664.x
(
2012
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

51. 
Sloan, D. B.
, 
Havird, J. C.
&amp; 
Sharbrough, J.
The on‐again‐off‐again relationship between mitochondrial genomes and species boundaries
. 

Molecular Ecology

26

, 
2212–2236
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.13959
(
2016
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

52. 
Bonnet, T.
, 
Leblois, R.
, 
Rousset, F.
&amp; 
Crochet, P.‐A.
Areassessment of explanations for discordant introgressions of mitochondrial and nuclear genomes
. 

Evolution

71

, 
2140–2158
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/evo.13296
(
2017
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

53. 
Álvarez, D.
, 
Lourenço,A.
, 
Oro, D.
&amp; 
Velo-Antón, G.
Assessment of census (N) and effective population size (Ne) reveals consistency of Ne single-sample estimatorsand ahigh Ne/N ratio in an urban andisolated population offire salamanders
. 

Conservation Genetics Resources

7

, 
705–712
, 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s12686-015-0480-0
(
2015
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

54. 
Lourenço, A.
, 
Alvarez, D.
, 
Wang, I. J.
&amp; 
Velo-Antón, G.
Trapped within the city: integrating demography, time since isolation and population-specific traits to assess the genetic effects of urbanization
. 

Molecular Ecology

26

, 
1498–1514
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/ mec.14019
(
2017
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

55. 
Lourenço, A.
, 
Antunes, B.
, 
Wang, I. J.
&amp; 
Velo-Antón, G.
Fine-scale genetic structure in a salamander with two reproductive modes: Does reproductive mode affect dispersal?
Evolutionary Ecology

32

, 
699–732
, 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10682-018-9957-0
(
2018
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

56. 
Konowalik, A.
, 
Najbar, A.
, 
Babik, W.
, 
Steinfartz, S.
&amp; 
Ogielska, M.

Genetic structure of the fire salamander 
Salamandra salamandra
in the Polish Sudetes

. 

Amphibia-Reptilia

37

, 
405–415
, 
https://doi.org/10.1163/15685381-00003071
(
2016
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

57. 
Krause, E. T.
&amp; 
Caspers, B. A.

The influence of a water current on the larval deposition pattern of females of a diverging fire salamander population (
Salamandra salamandra
)

. 

Salamandra

51

, 
156–60
(
2015
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

58. 
ILWIS
. 

Integrated Landand Water Information System (ILWIS)

. Open softwareversion 3.6. 
ITC:Enschede, The Netherlands
(
2009
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

59. 
Steinfartz, S.
, 
Kuesters, D.
&amp; 
Tautz, D.

Isolation and characterization of polymorphic tetranucleotide microsatellite loci in the Fire salamander 
Salamandrasalamandra
(Amphibia: Caudata)

. 

Molecular Ecology Notes

4

, 
626–628
, 
https://doi. org/10.1111/j.1471-8286.2004.00716.x
(
2004
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

60. 
Hendrix, R.
, 
Hauswaldt, S.
, 
Veith, M.
&amp; 
Steinfartz, S.

Strong correlation between cross‐amplification success and genetic distance across all members of ‘True Salamanders’(Amphibia: Salamandridae) revealed by 
Salamandra salamandra
‐specific microsatellite loci

. 

Molecular Ecology Resources

10

, 
1038–1047
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2010.02861.x
(
2010
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

61. 
Steinfartz, S.
, 
Veith, M.
&amp; 
Tautz, D.

Mitochondrial sequence analysis of 
Salamandra
taxa suggests old splits of major lineages and postglacial recolonizations of Central Europe from distinct source populations of 
Salamandra salamandra

. 

Molecular Ecology

9

, 
397–410
, 
https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-294x.2000.00870.x
(
2000
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

62. 
Chapuis, M.-P.
&amp; 
Estoup, A.
Microsatellitenull alleles and estimation of population differentiation
. 

Molecular Biologyand Evolution

24

, 
621–631
, 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msl191
(
2007
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

63. 
Rousset, F.
GenePop’007: a complete re‐implementation of the GenePop software for Windows and Linux
. 

Molecular Ecology Resources

8

, 
103–106
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-8286.2007.01931.x
(
2008
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

64. 
Jorde, P. E.
, 
Andersson, A.
, 
Ryman, N.
&amp; 
Laikre, L.
Are we underestimating the occurrence of sympatric populations?
Molecular Ecology

27

, 
4011–4025
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.14846
(
2018
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

65. 
Clarke, K.R.
, 
Gorley, R. N.
Primer v6: User Manual/Tutorial

. 
Primer-e:Plymouth, United Kingdom
(
2006
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

66. 
Jombart, T.
Adegenet: a Rpackage for the multivariate analysis of genetic markers
. 

Bioinformatics

24

, 
1403–1405
, 
https://doi. org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btn129
(
2008
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

67. 
Jombart, T.
, 
Pontier, D.
&amp; 
Dufour, A. B.
Genetic markers in the playground of multivariate analysis
. 

Heredity

102

, 
330
, 
https://doi. org/10.1038/hdy.2008.130
(
2009
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

68. 
Pritchard,J.K.
, 
Stephens, M.
&amp; 
Donnelly, P.
Inference of populationstructure usingmultilocus genotype data
. 

Genetics

155

, 
945–959
(
2000
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

69. 
Earl, D. A.
&amp; 
vonHoldt, B. M.
Structure Harvester: a website and program for visualizing STRUCTURE output and implementing the Evanno method
. 

Conservation Genetics Resources

4

, 
359–361
, 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s12686-011-9548-7
(
2012
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

70. 
Jones, O. R.
&amp; 
Wang, J.
COLONY:a program for parentage and sibship inference from multilocus genotype data
. 

Molecular Ecology Resources

10

, 
551–555
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2009.02787.x
(
2010
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

71. 
Piry,S.
, 
Luikart, G.
&amp; 
Cornuet, J. M.
BOTTLENECK:a computer programfor detecting recent reductions in theeffective population size using allele frequency data
. 

Journal of Heredity

90

, 
502–503
, 
https://doi.org/10.1093/jhered/90.4.502
(
1999
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

72. 
Nielsen, R.
Amaximum likelihood approach to population samples of microsatellite alleles
. 

Genetics

146

, 
711–716
(
1997
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

73. 
Derryberry, E. P.
, 
Derryberry, G. E.
, 
Maley, J. M.
&amp; 
Brumfield, R. T.
HZAR: hybrid zone analysis using an Rsoftware package
. 

Molecular Ecology Resources

14

, 
652–663
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/1755-0998.12209
(
2014
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

74. 
Prada, C.
&amp; 
Hellberg, M. E.
Strong natural selection on juveniles maintains a narrow adult hybrid zone in a broadcast spawner
. 

American Naturalist

184

, 
702–713
, 
https://doi.org/10.1086/678403
(
2014
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

75. 
Larkin, M. A.
et al
. 
ClustalW and ClustalX version 2
. 

Bioinformatics

23

, 
2947–2948
, 
https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btm404
(
2007
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

76. 
IBM SPSS
. 

Statistical Package for the Social Sciences

. 
SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA
(
2016
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

77. 
Goldberg, C. S.
&amp; 
Waits, L. P.
Quantification and reduction of bias from sampling larvae to infer population and landscape genetic structure
. 

Molecular Ecology Resources

10

, 
304–313
, 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1755-0998.2009.02755.x
(
2010
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

78. 
Sánchez-Montes, G.
, 
Ariño, A. H.
, 
Vizmanos, J. L.
, 
Wang, J.
&amp; 
Martínez-Solano, I.
Effects of sample size and full sibs on genetic diversity characterization: a case study of three syntopic Iberian pond-breeding amphibians
. 

Journal of Heredity

108

, 
535–543
, 
https://doi.org/10.1093/jhered/esx038
(
2017
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

79. 
O’Connell, K. A.
, 
Mulder, K. P.
, 
Maldonado, J.
, 
Currie, K. L.
&amp; 
Ferraro, D. M.
Sampling related individuals within ponds biases estimates of population structure in a pond‐breeding amphibian
. 

Ecology and Evolution

9

, 
3620–3636
, 
https://doi.org/10.1002/ ece3.4994
(
2019
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

80. 
Najbar, A.
, 
Babik, W.
, 
Najbar, B.
&amp; 
Ogielska, M.

Genetic structure and differentiationof the fire salamander 
Salamandrasalamandra
at the northern margin of its range in the Carpathians

. 

Amphibia-Reptilia

36

, 
301–331
, 
https://doi.org/10.1163/15685381-00003005
(
2015
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Acknowledgements

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>We thank Maarten de Leeuw, Jaap Schoorl, Machiel Visser, Pieter de Wijer and Annie Zuiderwijk for field observations and Mrs. I. Brugioni of the ‘Conseil départemental de la Mayenne’, Laval, for environmental data in digital format. J.v.B. thanks Ralf Hendrix, Gabrielle Keunecke and Sebastian Steinfartz for hospitality and advice in the laboratory and the Jan-Joost ter Pelkwijk fund for a travel grant.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Author contributions

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>J.W.A. conceived and designed the study, and organized the species inventory. The files SI I and SI V are also available at https://www.repository.naturalis.nl/record/707616. J.v.B. collected the tissue samples and performed the laboratory work in the laboratory of S. Steinfartz, Braunschweig. J.W.A. analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript with the help of J.v.B.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Competing interests

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Additional information

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Supplementary information
is available for this paper at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-58551-0.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Correspondence
and requests for materials should be addressed to J.W.A.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Reprintsand permissions information
is available at www.nature.com/reprints.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Publisher’s note
Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Open Access
This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
