<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-63799-7</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Bat coronavirus phylogeography in the Western Indian Ocean</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>23</day>
            <month>04</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Bat coronavirus phylogeography in the Western Indian Ocean
</title>
         <p>
Léa Joffrin
1


✉, 

Steven M. Goodman
2
, 
3


, 
David A. Wilkinson
1

, 
Beza Ramasindrazana
1
, 
2
, 
9

,

Erwan Lagadec
1
,Yann Gomard

1

, 
Gildas Le Minter
1

, 
Andréa Dos Santos
4

, 
M. Corrie Schoeman
5

, 
Rajendraprasad Sookhareea
6

, 
Pablo Tortosa
1

, 
Simon Julienne
7

, 
Eduardo S. Gudo
8
,

Patrick Mavingui
1

&amp; 
Camille Lebarbenchon
1


✉

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>
Bats provide key ecosystem services such as crop pest regulation, pollination, seed dispersal, and
soil fertilization. Bats are also major hosts for biological agents responsible for zoonoses, such as coronaviruses (CoVs).The islands of the Western Indian Ocean are identified as a major biodiversity hotspot, with more than 50 bat species. In this study, we tested 1,013 bats belonging to 36 species from Mozambique, Madagascar, Mauritius, Mayotte, Reunion Island and Seychelles, based on molecular screening and partial sequencing of the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase gene. In total, 88 bats

(8.7%) tested positive for coronaviruses, with higher prevalence in Mozambican bats (20.5% ± 4.9%)
as compared to those sampled on islands (4.5% ± 1.5%). Phylogenetic analyses revealed a large diversity of
α 
- and
β 
-CoVs and a strong signal of co-evolution between CoVs and their bat host species, with limited evidence for host-switching, except for bat species sharing day roost sites.These results highlight that strong variation between islands does exist and is associated with the composition of
the bat species community on each island. Future studies should investigate whether CoVs detected in these bats have a potential for spillover in other hosts.
</title>
         <p>
The burden of emerging infectious diseases has significantly increased over the last decades and is recognized as a major global health concern. In 2018, the World Health Organization (WHO) established the “Blueprint priority disease list”, identifying viruses such as Ebola, Lassa fever, Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS), and Nipah fever as significant threats to international biosecurity 

1

. This list also highlights the potential pandemic risk from the emergence of currently unknown zoonotic pathogens, collectively referring to these unknown threats as “disease X″ 

1

. Investigation of the potential zoonotic pathogens in wild animals, particularly vertebrates, is thus critical for emerging infectious disease preparedness and responses.
</p>
         <p>
Bats represent nearly 1,400 species and live on all continents except Antarctica 

2

. They provide key ecosystem services such as crop pest regulation, pollination, seed dispersal, and soil fertilization 

3
– 
10

. Bats are also recognized as reservoirs of many zoonotic pathogens, including coronaviruses (CoVs) 

11
– 
13

. Indeed, several CoVs originating from bats have emerged in humans and livestock with sometimes major impacts to public health. For instance, in 2003, the Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) CoV emerged in humans, after spillover from bats to civets 

14
– 
18

, and led to the infection of 8,096 people and 774 deaths in less than a year 

19

.
</p>
         <p>
Our study area spans geographic locations across the islands of the Western Indian Ocean and southeastern continental Africa (SECA) (

). These islands have diverse geological origins that have influenced the process of bat colonization and species distributions 

20

. The ecological settings and species diversity on these islands for bats are notably different. On Madagascar, more than 45 bat species are known to occur, of which more than 80% are endemic to the island 

21
– 
23

. The smaller studied islands of the Western Indian Ocean, Mauritius, Mayotte, Reunion Island, and Mahé (Seychelles), host reduced bat species diversity (e.g. three species on Reunion Island), whereas SECA supports a wide range of bat species. To date, several studies have identified bat-infecting CoVs in countries of continental Africa, including Zimbabwe 

24

, South Africa 

25
, 
26

, Namibia 

27

, and Kenya 

28
, 
29

. CoVs
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
1
Université de La Réunion,UMR Processus Infectieux en Milieu InsulaireTropical (PIMIT), INSERM 1187,CNRS 9192, IRD 249, Sainte-Clotilde, La Réunion, France. 

2

Association Vahatra,Antananarivo, Madagascar. 

3

Field Museum of Natural History,Chicago,USA. 

4

Veterinary Faculty,Eduardo Mondlane University, Maputo, Mozambique. 

5

School of Life Sciences,University of Kwa-Zulu Natal, Kwa-Zulu Natal,South Africa. 

6

National Parks and Conservation Service, Réduit,Mauritius. 

7

Seychelles Ministry of Health,Victoria, Mahe,Seychelles. 

8

Instituto Nacional de Saúde, Maputo, Mozambique. 

9

Present address: Beza Ramasindrazana,Institut Pasteur de Madagascar, BP 1274,Ambatofotsikely, Antananarivo, 101, Madagascar. ✉e-mail: lea.joffrin@gmail.com; camille.lebarbenchon@univ-reunion.fr
</p>
         <p>
have also been reported in fruit bats (
<tp:taxon-name>Pteropodidae</tp:taxon-name>
) in Madagascar, where β- coronaviruses belonging to the D-subgroup were identified in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eidolon dupreanum
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pteropus rufus
</tp:taxon-name>
30

.
</p>
         <p>In this study, we investigated the presence of CoVs in over 1,000 individual bats belonging to 36 species, sampled on five islands (Madagascar, Mauritius, Mayotte, Reunion Island, and Mahé) and one continental area (Mozambique). Based on molecular screening and partial sequencing of the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase gene, we (i) estimated CoV prevalence in the regional bat populations, (ii) assessed CoV genetic diversity, and (iii) identified associations between bat families and CoVs, as well as potential evolutionary drivers leading to these associations.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>
Results

</title>
         <p>
Prevalence of CoV.
A total of 1,013 bats were tested from Mozambique, Mayotte, Reunion Island, Seychelles, Mauritius and Madagascar (

). In total, 88 of the 1,013 bat samples tested positive for CoV by Real-Time PCR (mean detection rate: 8.7%). The prevalence of positive bats was different according to the sampling locations (Χ² = 77.0, df = 5; p &lt;0.001), with a higher prevalence in Mozambique (±95% confidence interval: 20.5% ± 4.9%) than on all Western Indian Ocean islands (4.5% ± 1.5%) (

). A significant difference in the prevalence of positive bats was also detected between families (Χ² = 44.8, df = 8; p &lt;0.001; Supplementary 

). The highest prevalence was observed in the families 
<tp:taxon-name>Nycteridae</tp:taxon-name>
(28.6% ± 23.6%) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophidae</tp:taxon-name>
(26.2% ± 11.0%). Bat species had a significant effect on the probability of CoVs detection (Χ² = 147.9, df = 39; p &lt;0.001; Supplementary 

). Finally, the prevalence of CoV positive bats in Mozambique was significantly different (N = 264, Χ²= 22.8, df = 1; p &lt;0.001; Supplementary 

) between February (37.4% ± 9.9%) and May (11.6% ± 4.8).
</p>
         <p>
RdRp sequence diversity.
Of the 88 positive samples, we obtained 77 partial RdRp sequences using the Real-Time PCR detection system (179 bp) and 51 longer partial RdRp sequences using a second PCR system (440 bp). Sequences generated with the second system were subsequently used for phylogenetic analyses. Details of the sequenced CoV-positive samples are provided in Supplementary Table S1. Pairwise comparison of these 51 sequences revealed 28 unique sequences, and sequences similarities ranging from 60.2% to 99.8%. The lowest sequence similarity was found in Mozambique (60.2% to 99.8%), then in Madagascar (64.0% to 99.8%). No genetic variation was observed for samples from Mayotte and Reunion Island.
</p>
         <p>
Phylogenetic structure of CoVs.
Sequence comparison indicated that Western Indian Ocean bats harbor a high diversity of both α and β- CoVs, with conserved groups clustering mostly by bat family (

). Specifically, 25 sequences were identified as α- CoVs, and three sequences were genetically related to the β- CoVs. For α- CoVs, all sequences detected in our tested 
<tp:taxon-name>Molossidae</tp:taxon-name>
formed a highly supported monophyletic group, including CoV sequences from 
<tp:taxon-name>Molossidae</tp:taxon-name>
bats previously detected in continental Africa (

). CoVs detected in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mops condylurus
</tp:taxon-name>
(Mozambique), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mormopterus francoismoutoui
</tp:taxon-name>
(Reunion Island), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chaerephon pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chaerephon
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. (Mayotte), and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mormopterus jugularis
</tp:taxon-name>
(Madagascar) shared 90%–98% nucleotide similarity with a CoV detected in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chaerephon
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. in Kenya (Supplementary Table S2). All CoVs found in 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopteridae</tp:taxon-name>
clustered in a monophyletic group, including 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopteridae CoVs</tp:taxon-name>
sequences from Africa, Asia, and Oceania (Supplementary Table S2). The great majority of α- CoVs detected in 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophidae</tp:taxon-name>
bats clustered in two monophyletic groups (

); one with African 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophidae CoVs</tp:taxon-name>
and one with Asian 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophidae CoVs. We</tp:taxon-name>
also detected one CoV from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus rhodesiae
</tp:taxon-name>
, which was 100% similar to a 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopteridae</tp:taxon-name>
CoV from this study. 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinonycteridae CoVs</tp:taxon-name>
formed a single monophyletic group with NL63 Human CoVs. The 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinonycteridae CoVs</tp:taxon-name>
detected clustered with NL63-related bat sequences found in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Triaenops afer
</tp:taxon-name>
in Kenya (

) and showed 85% similarity to NL63 Human CoVs (Supplementary Table S2). 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideridae</tp:taxon-name>
α- CoVs mainly clustered into a single monophyletic group, including 229E Human CoV-related bat sequence found in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hipposideros vittatus
</tp:taxon-name>
from Kenya (

; Supplementary Table S2).
</p>
         <p>
For β- CoVs, two sequences obtained from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nycteris thebaica
</tp:taxon-name>
clustered in the C-subgroup together with other CoVs previously reported in African 

<tp:taxon-name>Nycteris</tp:taxon-name>
sp

. bats (

). The sequences showed 88% nucleotide identity to a β- C CoV found in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nycteris gambiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
in Ghana (Supplementary Table S2). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rousettus madagascariensis
CoVs
</tp:taxon-name>
clustered with 
<tp:taxon-name>Pteropodidae CoVs</tp:taxon-name>
belonging to the D-subgroup of β- CoVs (

). BLAST queries against the NCBI database showed 98% nucleotide identity between CoV sequences from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rousettus madagascariensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and a β- D CoV sequence detected in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eidolon helvum
</tp:taxon-name>
from Kenya (Supplementary Table S2).
</p>
         <p>
Co-phylogeny between bats and CoVs.
Co-phylogeny tests were conducted using 11 Cyt 
b
sequences obtained from the 11 CoVs positive bat species and 27 partial CoV RdRp sequences (440 bp). Results supported co-evolution between the Western Indian Ocean bats and their CoVs (ParaFitGlobal =0.04; p = 0.001) and a high level of phylogenetic congruence (

).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
Discussion

</title>
         <p>
We provide evidence for a high diversity of CoVs in bats on Western Indian Ocean islands. The overall prevalence of CoV positive bats was consistent with studies from continental Africa 

25

and from islands in the Australasian region 

31

, although we detected significant variation in the prevalence of infected bats, according to their family, species, sampling location and season. Our study is nevertheless affected by the strong heterogeneity of bat communities in the island of the Western Indian Ocean, in particular in term of species richness. The high CoV genetic diversity detected in bats from Mozambique and Madagascar is likely to be associated with the higher bat species diversity in the African mainland and in Madagascar, has compared to small oceanic islands 

20

. In addition, CoV prevalence in bat populations may significantly vary across seasons, as found in Mozambique with higher prevalence during the wet season than in the dry season. Several studies on bat CoV have indeed shown significant variations in the temporal infection dynamic of CoV in bats, potentially associated with bat parturition 

32
– 
34

.
</p>
         <p>
Host specificity is well known for some bat CoVs subgenera 

35
– 
37

. For example, β- C CoVs are largely associated with 
<tp:taxon-name>Vespertilionidae</tp:taxon-name>
, whereas β- D CoVs are found mostly in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pteropodidae</tp:taxon-name>
36
, 
38

. In our study, we showed that Western Indian Ocean bats harbor phylogenetically structured CoVs, of both α- CoV and β- CoV subclades, clustering mostly by bat family. In the new CoV taxonomy based on full genomes proposed by the International Committee of Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV), α- CoVs and β- CoVs are split in subgenera mostly based on host families 

39

, reflected in the subgenera names (e.g. Rhinacovirus for a 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophidae</tp:taxon-name>
α- CoV cluster, Minuacovirus for a 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopteridae</tp:taxon-name>
α- CoV cluster, Hibecovirus for an 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideridae</tp:taxon-name>
β- CoV cluster). Although our classification was based on a partial sequence of the RdRp region, we identified sequences from samples belonging to four of these subgenera (Minuacovirus, Duvinacovirus, Rhinacovirus, and Nobecovirus) and three that could not be classified according to this taxonomic scheme hence representing unclassified subgenera (we propose “Molacovirus”, “Nycbecovirus”, and “Rhinacovirus2”).
</p>
         <p>
A strong geographical influence on CoVs diversity, with independent evolution of CoVs on each island, was expected in our study, because of spatial isolation and endemism of the tested bat species. Anthony 
et al
. 

38

found that the dominant evolutionary mechanism for African CoVs was host switching. Congruence between host and viral phylogenies however suggests a strong signal for co-evolution between Western Indian Ocean bats and their associated CoVs. Geographical influence seems to occur within bat families, as for 
<tp:taxon-name>Molossidae</tp:taxon-name>
. Endemism resulting from geographic isolation may thus have played a role in viral diversification within bat families.
</p>
         <p>

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_229303_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mo.condylurus
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183182

</p>
         <p>

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_229296_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mo.condylurus
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183179

</p>
         <p>

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_229266_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mo.condylurus
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183180

</p>
         <p>
Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_229293_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mo.condylurus
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183181 ● 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideridae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Chaerephon</tp:taxon-name>
_bat_coronavirus_KY22 _ 
Ch.sp
_Kenya_2006_HQ728486 BtCoV _NCL _MCO1_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mo.condylurus
</tp:taxon-name>
_South_Africa_2012_KF843853 ● 
<tp:taxon-name>Megadermatidae</tp:taxon-name>
PREDICT_GVF_CM_ECO70102_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mo.condylurus
</tp:taxon-name>
_Cameroon_2013_KX284982 

Bat_ CoV_ MAY027_ Mayotte_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ch.pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
_2014_MN183176

● 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miniopteridae 

Bat Bat_ _CoV CoV_ _MAY MAY025 051_ _Mayotte Mayotte_ _ 

Ch 
Ch.pusillus
.sp

_2014_2014_MN_MN183174 183175

</tp:taxon-name>
● 
<tp:taxon-name>
Molossidae 

Bat Bat_ _ CoV CoV _ _ MAY MAY 015 033 _ _Mayotte Mayotte _ _ 

Ch Ch.. 
pusillus
pusillus

_ _ 2014 2014 _ _ MN MN183173 183178

</tp:taxon-name>
● 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mormoopidae 

Bat Bat_ _ CoV CoV_ _ MAY UADBA004_ _33728Mayotte_Madagascar_ 

Ch.pusillus
_ 
Mo

_2014. 

jugularis

_MN183177_2013_MN183183

</tp:taxon-name>
● 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nycteridae 

Bat_ CoV_ UADBA_33735_Madagascar_ 

Mo.jugularis

_2013_MN183186

</tp:taxon-name>
● 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phyllostomidae 

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_222698 _Madagascar_ 

Mo.jugularis

_2013_MN183185 Bat Bat_ _ CoV CoV_ _FMNH UADBA_ _222691 33733_ _Madagascar Madagascar_ _ 

Mo Mo.. 
jugularis
jugularis

_ _2013 2013_ _MN MN183187 183184

</tp:taxon-name>
● 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pteropodidae Bat 
Bat
</tp:taxon-name>
_ 
_
coronavirus 
CoV _RB 369
_POA 
_Reunion
_ Uknown_ 
Mo
_. 
<tp:taxon-name>
francoismoutoui
</tp:taxon-name>
Brazil_2012_144_ 
_
KC 
2015
110778 
_MN183188
● 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophidae Bat</tp:taxon-name>
_coronavirus_2173_ 
Cy.planirostris
_Brazil_2014_KU552078 ● 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinonycteridae 

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228953_ Mozambique_ 

Rh.rhodesiae

_2015_MN183148

</tp:taxon-name>
● 
<tp:taxon-name>
Vespertillionidae 

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228945_ Mozambique_ 

Rh.rhodesiae

_2015_MN183146 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228957_ Mozambique_ 

Rh.rhodesiae

_2015_MN183150 Bat Bat_ _ CoV CoV_ _ FMNH FMNH_ _228955 228962_ _ Mozambique Mozambique_ _ 

Rh Rh.. 
rhodesiae
rhodesiae

_ _2015 2015_ _MN MN183147 183151

</tp:taxon-name>
Human CoV 

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228956_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.rhodesiae
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183149 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228951 _Mozambique _ 
Rh.sp
_2015 _MN183152 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228939_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.lobatus
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183154 Bat Bat_ _ CoV CoV_ _ FMNH FMNH_ _228940 228952_ _ Mozambique Mozambique_ _ 

Rh Rh.. 
<tp:taxon-name>lobatus</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>rhodesiae</tp:taxon-name>

_2015_2015_MN_MN183155 183153 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_ 228941_Mozambique _ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.lobatus
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183156

Kenya bat_coronavirus_BtKY83_ 
Rh.sp
_Kenya_2007_GU065427 Bat_coronavirus_KY43_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ca.cor
</tp:taxon-name>
_Kenya_2006_HQ728480 Bat Bat_ _COV coronavirus_HKU10_ _BB TLC98 −1347 15_ A 
Rh
_. 

<tp:taxon-name>Hi blasii</tp:taxon-name>
.pomona

_Bulgaria_China_2008_2010_GU_JQ190232 989273 Bat_COV_HKU 10_175A_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ro.leschenaultii
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_2005_JQ989271 Bat_coronavirus_2231_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hi.diadema
</tp:taxon-name>
_Philippines _2010_AB683971 BtRf _AlphaCoV _HuB2013_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.ferrumequinum
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_2013_KJ473807 BtMs_AlphaCoV_GS2013_ 
My.sp
_China_2013_KJ473810 BtCoV_4307_1_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.affinis
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_2013_KP 876527 Bat_coronavirus_Aju21_ 
Ar.jamaicensis
_Costa _Rica_2012_KC779226 BtCoV_KP565_ 
Ar.jamaicensis
_Panama_2010_JQ731786 BtCoV_KP256_ 
Ar.jamaicensis
_Panama_2010_JQ731784 

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228980_ Mozambique_ 
Mi.mossambicus
_2015_MN183160 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228949_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.rhodesiae
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183159 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228978_ Mozambique_ 
Mi.mossambicus
_2015_MN183157 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228969_ Mozambique_ 
Mi.mossambicus
_2015_MN183158

Miniopterus bat_coronavirus_KY27_ 
Mi.natalensis
_Kenya _2006_HQ728484 
Bat
BtMf 
_
_ 
CoV
AlphaCoV 
_ FMNH
_ 
_
AH 
228971
2011 
_
_ 
Mozambique
Mi.fuliginosus
_
_ 
Mi
China. 
mossambicus
_2011_KJ473795 
_2015 _MN183161
Bat BtMf _ _ coronavirus AlphaCoV_ _ HuB 1A _ 2013 

Mi. 
<tp:taxon-name>magnater</tp:taxon-name>

_ 
Mi.fuliginosus
_China _ _ 2005 China _ _ DQ 2013 666337 _KJ473803 Miniopterus bat_coronavirus_1A_ 
Mi.sp
_HongKong_2008_EU 420138 Bat Bat_ _coronavirus coronavirus_ _Anlong1B _ 
Mi.
_ 
sp
171_HongKong_ 
Mi.schreibersii
_2008_ _EU China420137_2012_KF294275 Bat Bat_ _coronavirus coronavirus_ _CoV HKU100 7_ 
Mi
_ 

<tp:taxon-name>Rh.magnater</tp:taxon-name>
.megaphyllus

_DQ249226_Australia_2007_EU834953 Bat_coronavirus_CoV 132_ 
Mi.australis
_Australia_2007_EU834954 Bat_coronavirus_HKU 8_ 

Mi. 
<tp:taxon-name>pusillus</tp:taxon-name>

_China_2004_DQ249228 BNM Alphacoronavirus98_30_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ny.leisleri
</tp:taxon-name>
_BtCoV_Bulgaria_MSTM_2_2008 
Mi.natalensis
_GU190239_South_Africa_2010 _KF843851 Alphacoronavirus_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ny.lasiopterus
</tp:taxon-name>
_Spain_2007_HQ184055 Pip1_Cr_ 

Pi. 
<tp:taxon-name>pipistrellus</tp:taxon-name>

_France_2014_KT345294 BtNv BtCoV_AlphaCoV_VH_NC2_ _SC 
Ne
2013. 
<tp:taxon-name>
capensis
</tp:taxon-name>
_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ny.velutinus
</tp:taxon-name>
_South_Africa_China_2012_2013_KF_KJ843854 473809 alpha Alphacoronavirus_Iprima _ 
Pi.kuhlii
_Spain_2007_HQ184058 Bat_coronavirus_VM105_ 
My.dasycneme
_Netherlands_2006_GQ259968 Bat Bat_ _coronavirus coronavirus_ _D Moxy5.70 4235_ 
Pi.pygmaeus
_IT_16_ 
My
_. 
oxygnathus
Germany_2007_Italy_EU_2016 375867_KY780395 Bat_coronavirus_HKU 6_ 
My.pilosus
_China_2004_DQ249224 Bat CoV_ _coronavirus75_55_L01_ _R 
My
1_. 
lucifugus
CoV_BAT_ _Canada VN_ 
Sc
_. 
kuhlii
2010_ _KY Vietnam799179_KX092163 Rocky_Mountain_Bat_Coronavirus_11_ 
My.lucifugus
_USA_2011_EF544563 Bat _coronavirus _P1ab_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mu.leucogaster
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_2013_KU182966 Lushi _Ml _bat _CoV _Neixiang_23_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mu.leucogaster
</tp:taxon-name>
_China _2012_KF294375 PEDV_Porcine_Epidemic _COV _ 
Su.domesticus
_1993_NC 003436 BtCoV BtCoV _ _ LUX LUX 15 15 _ _ A A_ _ 59 46 _ _ 
My My.. emarginatus emarginatus
_ _Luxembourg Luxembourg_ _ 2015 2015 _ _ KY KY 502386 502383 Alphacoronavirus_13rs384_31_ 
My.blythii
_Italy_2012_KF 312400 Bat_coronavirus_Anlong_46 _ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
_China _2013_KY770855 Bat_coronavirus_Anlong_60__ 
Ia.io
_China_2013_KY770857 BtCoV_BRA182_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mo.rufus
</tp:taxon-name>
_Brazil_2009_JQ731799 BtCoV_BRAP103_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mo.currentium
</tp:taxon-name>
_Brazil_2009_JQ731800 

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228887_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tr.afer
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183162

NL 63_related_bat_coronavirus_BtKYNL63_15_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tr.afer
</tp:taxon-name>
_Kenya_2008_KY073746 

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_ 228891_Mozambique _ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tr.afer
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015 _MN183163 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_229232_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tr.afer
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183165 Bat Bat _ _ CoV CoV _ _ FMNH FMNH _ _ 229212 229241 _ _Mozambique Mozambique _ _ 

Tr Tr.. 
<tp:taxon-name>afer</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>afer</tp:taxon-name>

_ _ 2015 2015_ _MN MN183166 183164 Bat Bat

Human 
_ _ CoV CoV
_coronavirus 
_ _ FMNH FMNH_ _228892 228888
_NL 63 
_ _ Mozambique Mozambique
_isolate_HCOV 

_ _ 
Tr Tr

_..005 

<tp:taxon-name>afer</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>afer</tp:taxon-name>

_ 
_ _
Ho
2015 2015
. 
sapiens
_ _MN MN183167 183168
sapiens
_ Kenya_2 0 0 9 _KP1 1 2 1 5 4 Human_Cov_NL63_ 
Ho.sapiens sapiens
_Netherlands_2004_NC005831 NL 63_related_bat_coronavirus_BtKYNL63_9a_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tr.afer
</tp:taxon-name>
_Kenya_2010_KY073744 

Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_229243_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tr.afer
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183169 Bat Bat_ _ CoV CoV_ _ FMNH FMNH_ _228926 228933_ _ Mozambique Mozambique_ _ 

Hi Hi.. 
<tp:taxon-name>caffer</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>caffer</tp:taxon-name>

_ _2015 2015_ _MN MN183172 183171 Bat

Alpaca 
_ CoV
_respiratory 
_ FMNH_ 228981
_coronavirus 
_Mozambique
_isolate 
_
_CA 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hi.caffer
</tp:taxon-name>
08_1_ 
_
Vi
2015
. 
pacos
_MN
_USA 
183170
_2008_JQ410000 Camel229E_CoV_AC04 _ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ca.dromedarius
_SouthKorea
</tp:taxon-name>
_2014_KT253327 229E_related_bat_CoV _BtCov_KY229E_8_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hi.vittatus
</tp:taxon-name>
_Kenya_2010_KY073748 229 E_related_bat_CoV_BtCoV_ AT1A_F 45_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hi.abae
</tp:taxon-name>
_Ghana_2010_KT253259 Human_coronavirus_229E_ 
Ho.sapiens sapiens
_NC002645 229E_related _bat_CoV_BtCoV_KW 1C_F161_ 
Hi.ruber
_Ghana_2010_KT253264 Bat BtCoV _coronavirus _KP816_ _ 
Ph
4292. 
discolor
_ 
De.rotundus
_Panama _ _ Brazil 2011_ _ JQ 2013 731782 _KU552072 Bat_coronavirus_strain _328_11_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mo.molossus
</tp:taxon-name>
_Brazil _2011_KX094982 Bat _coronavirus_1CO7BA_ 
Gl.soricina
_Trinidad_2007_EU769558 BtCoV_KP534_ 
Ar.jamaicensis
_Panama_2010_JQ731787 BtCoV_KCR253_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ca.perspicillata
</tp:taxon-name>
_Costa_Rica_2010_JQ731789 Bat_cov_309_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ca.castanea
</tp:taxon-name>
_Costa_Rica_2014_KM215147 Bat_coronavirus_1599_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ca.perspicillata
</tp:taxon-name>
_Brazil_2012_KT717385 BtCoV Porcine_ _BRA enteric118_ _alphacoronavirus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ca.perspicillata
</tp:taxon-name>
_ _Brazil strain_ _GDS2009 04_JQ_ 
Su
731796. 
domesticus
_China_2017_MF 167434 Bat SADS_coronavirus_related _coronavirus_HKU2−1_ _ 
Rh Rh.sp.sp
_ _China China_ _2004MF 094687_DQ Bat_coronavirus_HKU 2_GD− 430_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.sinicus
</tp:taxon-name>
_China 249235 _2004_NC 009988 BtCoV_4307−2_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.affinis
</tp:taxon-name>
_China _2013_KP876528 Bat_coronavirus_MLHJC 4_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.sinicus
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_2012_KU182954 
Bat
BtRf 
_
_ 
CoV
AlphaCoV 
_ FMNH
_ 
_
YN 
228963
2012 
_
_ 
Mozambique
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.ferrumequinum
</tp:taxon-name>

_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.rhodesiae
</tp:taxon-name>

_China _2012 
_2015
_KJ 
_MN
473808 

183190 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_228954_ Mozambique_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.lobatus
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183189

Porcine_respiratory_coronavirus _ 
Su.domesticus
_USA_2014_KR270796 Canine Transmissible_coronavirus_gastroenteritis_strain_171_virus_ 
Ca
_. 
Su lupus.scrofa familiaris
_China_ _Germany2015_KX_083668 1971_KC175339 Feline_coronavirus_UU 15_ 
Fe.catus
_Netherlands _2007_FJ938057 Mink_coronavirus_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mu.vison
</tp:taxon-name>
_USA_1998_HM245925 Bat_coronavirus_1573_ 
St.lilium
_Brazil _2012_KT717392 MERS_COV_Korea_Seoul_SNU1_035_Human_ 
Ho.sapiens sapiens
_South_Korea_2015_KU308549 MERS_COV_Hu_Riyadh_KSA_12160_Human_ 
Ho.sapiens sapiens
_South_Korea_2016_KX154688 MERS_COV_KFU_HKU_19Dam_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ca.dromedarius
_Saudi
</tp:taxon-name>
_Arabia_2013_KJ650296 MERS_COV_2c_EMC _Human_ 
Ho.sapiens sapiens
_2012_JX869059 MERS_COV_D2731.3_14_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ca.dromedarius
</tp:taxon-name>
_United_Arab_Emirates _KT 751244 MERS MERS_ _COV COV_ _related 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ca.dromedarius
</tp:taxon-name>
_5038_ 
Ne
_. 
<tp:taxon-name>
capensis
</tp:taxon-name>
Egypt_2013_South_KJ477102_Africa BtCoV_UKR_G 17_ 
Pi.nathusii
_Ukraine_2011_KC243392 _2015_MF593268 BtCoV_8_724 _ 
Pi.pygmaeus
_Romania_2009_KC243390 Bat_coronavirus_16BF104_ 
Ep.serotinus
_South_Korea_2016_KY432468 Bat_Coronavirus_HKU5_ 
Pi.abramus
_China_2007_NC009020 beta C CoV _2012_174_ 
Er.europaeus
_Germany_2012_NC039207 Bat_Coronavirus_HKU4_ 
Ty.pachypus
_NC009019 

Bat Bat Bat_ _ _ CoV CoV CoV_ _ _ FMNH FMNH FMNH_ _ _228903 228899 228900_ _ _ Mozambique Mozambique Mozambique _ _ _ 

Ny Ny Ny... 
<tp:taxon-name>thebaica</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>thebaica</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>thebaica</tp:taxon-name>

_ _ _2015 2015 2015_ _ _MN MN MN183195 183194 183193 Bat_ CoV_ FMNH_ 228901_Mozambique _ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ny.thebaica
</tp:taxon-name>
_2015_MN183196

BtCoV BtCoV_ _KW KW2 2E E_ _F F93 82 _ _ 

Ny Ny.. 
<tp:taxon-name>gambiensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>gambiensis</tp:taxon-name>

_ _Ghana Ghana_ _2010 2011_ _JX JX899383 899382 BtCoV_KW2E_F53 _ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ny.gambiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
_Ghana_2011_JX899384 BtCoV_KCR230_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pt.parnellii
_CostaRica
</tp:taxon-name>
_2010_JQ731779 BtCoV BtCoV_ _KCR KCR15 180_ _ 

Pt 
<tp:taxon-name>Pt.parnellii</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>parnellii</tp:taxon-name>

_ _Costa CostaRica_Rica_ _2012 2012_ _KC KC633195 633193 BtCoV_KCR155_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pt.parnellii
_CostaRica
</tp:taxon-name>
_2012_KC633194 Bat_coronavirus_49_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pt.davyi
</tp:taxon-name>
_Mexico _2012_KC886322 SARS _COV _HKU39849 _Human_ 
Ho.sapiens sapiens
_United_Kingdom_2003_JN854286 SARS _coronavirus_SZ3_Civet_ 
Pa.larvata
HongKong_2003_AY 304486 SARS_coronavirus_Tor2_Human_ 
Ho.sapiens sapiens
_Canada_2003_NC004718 Bat_SARS _CoV_Rf 1_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.ferrumequium
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_2004_DQ412042 Bat_SARS_COV _HKU3_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.sinicus
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_2006_DQ022305 SARS_like_CoV _SL _CoVZXC21_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.sinicus
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_2015_MG 772934 Bat_SARS_coronavirus_Rm1_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.macrotis
</tp:taxon-name>
_China _2004_DQ412043 SARS SARS _ _bat related_coronavirus_BtCoV _ _ 
Rh
Is39. 
<tp:taxon-name>
ferrumequinum
</tp:taxon-name>
_ 
Rh.sp
_Japan_ _Luxembourg2013_AB889995_2016_KY502395 beta B Bat_coronavirus_BB98 −16_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.blasii
</tp:taxon-name>
_Bulgaria_2008_GU190217 Bat Betacoronavirus_coronavirus_ _292 187632_ 
Hi.
_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
caffer
</tp:taxon-name>
2_ 
Rh
_. 
hipposideros
Gabon_2009_ _Italy JX174638_2012_KF500952 Zaria_bat_coronavirus_ 
Hi.commersoni
_Nigeria_2008_HQ166910 Bat_Hp_betacoronavirus_Zhejiang2013_ 
Hi.pratti
_2013_China_KF636752 Sable Bovine_ _Antelope COV_ 
Bo
_Cov. 
sp
_ _NC 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hi.niger
</tp:taxon-name>
_003045_USA_2003_EF424621 Human_coronavirus_OC43 _ 
Ho.
Rabbit_COV_HKU14_ 
Or.cuniculus sapiens
_China 
sapiens
_2006_ _AY NC391777_017083 MHV _COV_StrainA59_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mu.musculus
</tp:taxon-name>
_USA_2014_MF 618253 beta A Human _coronavirus_HKU1_N11 _genotype_A _ 
Ho.sapiens
_DQ415908 Bat Bat_ _coronavirus coronavirus_ _GLCC Diliman1_1525 
Cy.sphinx
G 2_ 
Cy
_. 
brachyotis
China_2005_Philippines_KU182962_2008_AB539082 Bat_coronavirus_2265_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pt.jagori
</tp:taxon-name>
_Philippines_2010_AB683971 Bat_coronavirus_KY06_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ro.aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>
_Kenya_2006_HQ728484 Bat_coronavirus _HKU 9_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ro.leschenaultii
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_NC009022 Bat_coronavirus_HKU9_PREDICT_LAP11 _K0006_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eo.spelaea
</tp:taxon-name>
_Laos_2011_KX284911 Bat PREDICT_coronavirus_CoV_ _22NWDC_LAP188 11_ _D 
Me
0063. 
kusnotoi
_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eo.spelaea
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_ _Laos2013_ _2011KU182986_KX284906 Bat BtKY_coronavirus89 _ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ei.helvum
</tp:taxon-name>
_RK_074Kenya_ 
Eo
_2007. 
spelea
_GU_China065433_2010_KX520659 beta D Bat_coronavirus_KY24_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ei.helvum
</tp:taxon-name>
_Kenya_2006_HQ728482 

Bat_ CoV_ UADBA_50636_Madagascar_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ro.madagascariensis
</tp:taxon-name>
_2014_MN183192 Bat_ CoV_ UADBA_50625_Madagascar_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ro.madagascariensis
</tp:taxon-name>
_2014_MN183191

PREDICT_CD 116088_ 
Ep.franqueto
_Congo_2014_KX285095 PREDICT PREDICT_ _ CD GVF 116004 _CM_ _ ECO 
Mi.
70527 
<tp:taxon-name>
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
_ _ 
Ep
Congo. 
gambianus
_2014_ _ KX Cameroon 285087 _2013_KX285008 PREDICT_AATHA_ 
Ep.sp
_Tanzania_2013 _KX 285299 White_eye_COV_HKU16_ 
Zo.sp
_China_2007_NC 016991 Bulbul Coronavirus_coronavirus_HKU15_ _HKU 
Su.
11 
domesticus
_934_ 
Py.jocosus
_China _ _2014China_LC_2007 216914_FJ Munia_COV_HKU13 _3514_ 
Lo.striata
_China_2007_NC011550 376619 Wigeon _COV _HKU20_ 
Ma.penelope
_China_2008_NC016995 delta Night _Heron_COV _HKU 19_ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ny.nycticorax
</tp:taxon-name>
_China_2007_NC_016994 Infectious_bronchitis_virus_isolate_YN_ 
Ga.gallusdomesticus
_China_2005_JF893452 Duck_coronavirus_isolate_DK_CH_HN_ZZ2004_ 
An.platyrhynchos
_China_2004_JF 705860 Turkey Beluga _ _ coronavirus Whale_coronavirus _strain_ _ TCoV SW1 _ _ VA 
De
_. 
leucas
74_03_ _ 
Me
NC. 010646 
gallopavo
_GQ 427173 gamma Bottlenose_dolphin_coronavirus_HKU22_isolate_CF090331 _ 
Tu.sp
_KF 793826 0.1
</p>
         <p>
Although co-evolution could be the dominant mechanism in the Western Indian Ocean, host-switching may take place in certain situations. For example, in Mozambique, we found a potential 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopteridae</tp:taxon-name>
α- CoV in a 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophidae bat</tp:taxon-name>
co-roosting with 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopteridae</tp:taxon-name>
in the same cave. These host-switching events could be favored when several bat species roost in syntopy 

40

. A similar scenario was described in Australia where
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Miniopteridae</tp:taxon-name>
α- CoV was detected in 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophidae</tp:taxon-name>
bats 

31

. These infrequent host-switching events show that spillovers can happen but suggest that viral transmission is not maintained in the receiver host species. The host-virus co-evolution might thus have resulted in strong adaptation of CoVs to each bat host species. In addition, viral factors (mutation rate, recombination propensity, replication ability in the cytoplasm, changes in the ability to bind host cells), environmental factors (climate variation, habitat degradation, decrease of bat preys), and phylogenetic relatedness of host species are also critical for the viral establishment in a novel host 

41
– 
44

. Nevertheless, apparent evidence of host switching as a dominant mechanism of CoV evolution could be an artifact of a lack of data for some potential bat hosts, leading to incomplete phylogenetic reconstructions 

38

.
</p>
         <p>
Several bat CoVs we identified in 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinonycteridae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideridae</tp:taxon-name>
from Mozambique had between 85% and 93% nucleotide sequence similarity with NL63 Human CoVs and 229E Human CoVs, respectively. These two human viruses are widely distributed in the world and associated with mild to moderate respiratory infection in humans 

45

. Tao 
et al
. established that the NL63 Human CoVs and 229E Human CoVs have a zoonotic recombinant origin from their most recent common ancestor, estimated to be about 1,000 years ago 

46

. During the past decade, they were both detected in bats in Kenya, and in Ghana, Gabon, Kenya, and Zimbabwe, respectively 

24
, 
28
, 
47
, 
48

. Intermediate hosts are important in the spillover of CoVs, despite major knowledge gaps on the transmission routes of bat infectious agents to secondary hosts 

49

. This hypothesis has been formulated for the 229E Human CoV, with an evolutionary origin in 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideridae</tp:taxon-name>
bats and with camelids as intermediate hosts 

48

. The ancient spillover of NL63 from 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinonycteridae</tp:taxon-name>
bats to humans might have occurred through a currently
</p>
         <p>
unidentified intermediate host 

28
, 
50
, 
51

. Because receptor recognition by viruses is the first essential cellular step to infect host cells, CoVs may have spilt over into humans from bats through an intermediate host possibly due to mutations on spike genes 

13
, 
28

. Further investigations of CoVs in Kenyan and Mozambican livestock and hunted animals could potentially provide information on the complete evolutionary and emergence history of these two viruses before their establishment in humans.
</p>
         <p>
MERS-like CoV, with high sequence similarity (&gt;85%) to human and camel strains of MERS-CoV, have been detected in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neoromicia capensis
</tp:taxon-name>
in South Africa and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pipistrellus
</tp:taxon-name>
cf. 
hesperidus
in Uganda, suggesting a possible origin of camel MERS-CoV in vespertilionid bats 

25
, 
38
, 
52

. This family has been widely studied, with 30% of all reported bat CoVs sequences from the past 20 years coming from vespertilionids 

53

. No members of this family were positive for CoV in our study, which may be associated with the low number of individuals tested; additional material is needed to explore potential MERS-like CoV in the Western Indian Ocean, in particular on Madagascar.
</p>
         <p>
Knowledge on bat CoV ecology and epidemiology has significantly increased during the past decade. Anthony 
et al
. estimated that there might be at least 3,204 bat CoVs worldwide 

38

; however, direct bat-to-human transmission has not been demonstrated so far. As for most emerging zoonoses, CoV spillover and emergence may be associated to human activities and ecosystem changes such as habitat fragmentation, agricultural intensification and bushmeat consumption. The role of bats as epidemiological reservoir of infectious agents needs to be balanced with such human driven modifications on ecosystem functioning, in order to properly assess bat-borne CoV emergence risks.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Materials and Methods

</title>
         <p>
Origin of the tested samples.
Samples obtained from vouchered bat specimens during previous studies in Mozambique (February and May 2015), Mayotte (November to December 2014), Reunion Island (February 2015), Seychelles (February to March 2014), Mauritius (November 2012) and Madagascar (October to November 2014) were tested 

54
– 
57

(Supplementary Information). We also collected additional swab samples from several
</p>
         <p>synanthropic bat species on Madagascar, in January 2018 (Supplementary Information). Details on sample types, bat families, species, and locations are provided in Supplementary Table S3.</p>
         <p>
Ethical statement.
The ethical terms of these research protocols were approved by the CYROI Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (Comité d’Ethique du CYROI no.114, IACUC certified by the French Ministry of Higher Education, of Research and Innovation). All protocols strictly followed the terms of research permits and regulations for the handling of wild mammals and were approved by licencing authorities (Supplementary Information).
</p>
         <p>
Molecular detection.
RNA was extracted from 140 µL of each sample using the QIAamp Viral RNA mini kit (QIAGEN, Valencia, California, USA), and eluted in 60 µL of Qiagen AVE elution buffer. For bat organs, approximately 1 mm 

3

of tissue (either lungs or intestines) was placed in 750 µL of DMEM medium and homogenized in a TissueLyser II (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) for 2 min at 25 Hz using 3 mm tungsten beads, prior to the RNA extraction. Reverse transcription was performed on 10 µL of RNA using the ProtoScript II Reverse Transcriptase and Random Primer 6 (New England BioLabs, Ipswich, MA, USA) under the following thermal conditions: 70 °C for 5 min, 25 °C for 10 min, 42 °C for 50 min, and 65 °C for 20 min 

58

. cDNAs were tested for the presence of the RNA-dependent RNA-polymerase (RdRp) gene using a multi-probe Real-Time PCR 
59
. The primer set with Locked Nucleic Acids (LNA; underlined position in probe sequences) was purchased from Eurogentec (Seraing, Belgium): 11-FW: 5′-TGA-TGA-TGS-NGT-TGT-NTG-YTA-YAA -3′ a n d 1 3-RV: 5′-G C A- T WG -T RT- G Y T- G N G -A R C -A R A- AT T- C -3′. T h r e e p r o b e s w e r e u s e d: p r o b e I (R O X): 5′ -T T G - TAT-TAT-C A G - A AT- GG Y- G T S - T T Y- AT- 3 ′, p r o b e I I (FA M): 5 ′ - T G T- G T T- C AT- G T C -W G A- R G C -WA A- AT G - T T- 3 ′, a n d p r o b e I I I (H E X): 5′-TCT-AAR-TGT-TGG-GTD-GA-3′. Real-Time PCR was performed with ABsolute Blue QPCR Mix low ROX 1X(Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) and 2.5 µL of cDNA under the following thermal conditions: 95 °C for 15 min, 95 °C for 30 s, touchdowns from 56 °C to 50 °C for 1 min and 50 cycles with 95 °C for 30 s and 50 °C for 1min in a CFX96 Touch Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA).
</p>
         <p>
Because of the limited size of sequences generated from the Real-Time PCR, a second PCR targeting 440 bp of the RdRp gene was performed with 5 µL of cDNA of each positive sample, with the following primer set: IN-6: 5′-GGT-TGG-GAC-TAT-CCT-AAG-TGT-GA-3′ and IN-7: 5′-CCA-TCA-TCA-GAT-AGA-ATC-ATC-ATA-3′ 

60

. PCRs were performed with the GoTaq G2 Hot Start Green Master Mix (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) in an Applied Biosystems 2720 Thermal Cycler (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), under the following thermal conditions: 95°C for 2 min, 45 cycles with 95°C for 1 min, 54°C for 1 min, 72°C for 1 min, and a final elongation step at 72°C for 10min. After electrophoresis in a 1.5% agarose gel stained with 2% GelRed (Biotium, Hayward, CA, USA), amplicons of the expected size were sequenced on both strands by Genoscreen (Lille, France).
</p>
         <p>
Statistical analysis.
We have performed Pearson Χ² tests on all samples (1,013 bats) to explore the effect of (i) location, (ii) bat family, and (iii) bat species on the detection of coronavirus RNA. Two sampling campaigns, at two different season, in the same location, were available for Mozambique. We thus investigated the effect of the sampling season, between the wet (February) and dry (May) season, on CoV detection in Mozambique in 2015 (264 bats). Analyses were conducted with R v3.5.1 software 

61

.
</p>
         <p>
Phylogenetic analyses.
Sequences obtained with the second PCR system 

60

were edited with the Chromas Lite Software package version 2.6. 
462
. We explored CoV diversity of the sequences with pairwise identity values obtained from 
seqidentity
function in R 
bio3d
package v2.3- 
463
and identified the most similar CoV RdRp sequences referenced in GenBank using BLASTN 2.2.29+. An alignment was then generated using the 51 nucleotide sequences obtained in this study and 151 reference CoV sequences representing a large diversity of hosts and geographic origins (Europe, Asia, Oceania, America and Africa), with CLC Sequence viewer 8.0 Software (CLC Bio, Aarhus, Denmark). A phylogenetic tree was obtained by maximum likelihood using MEGA Software v 
10.0.464
, with 1,000 bootstrap iterations, and with the best evolutionary model for our dataset as selected by modelgenerator v 
0.8565
.
</p>
         <p>
Host-virus associations were investigated using the phylogeny of Western Indian Ocean bats and their associated CoVs. Bat phylogeny was generated from an alignment of 1,030 bp of mitochondrial Cytochrome 
b
(Cyt 
b
) gene sequences (Supplementary Table S4), for each CoV positive bat species. Finally, bat and pruned CoV phylogenies based on each 393 bp RdRp unique sequence fragment were generated by Neighbor-Joining with 1,000 bootstrap iterations, using CLC Sequence viewer 8.0 Software (CLC Bio, Aarhus, Denmark) 

66

. Phylogenetic congruence was tested to assess the significance of the coevolutionary signal between bat host species and CoVs sequences, using 
ParaFit
with 999 permutations in the 
ape
package v5.0 in R 3.5. 

167, 
68

. Tanglegram representations of the co-phylogeny were visualized using the Jane software v 
4.0169
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Data availability

</title>
         <p>
DNA sequences: Genbank accessions MN183146 to MN183273.
</p>
         <p>
Received: 22 November 2019; Accepted: 31 March 2020;
</p>
         <p>
Published: xx xx xxxx
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References

</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1. 
Reusken, C.
et al
. 
WHO Research and Development Blueprint 2018 Annual review of diseases prioritized under the Research and Development Blueprint Informal consultation
. 
http://www.who.int/csr/research-and-development/documents/prioritizing_ diseases_progress/en/
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
2. 
American Society of Mammalogist
. 
Chiroptera (ASM Mammal Diversity Database)
. 
https://mammaldiversity. org/#Y2hpcm9wdGVyYSZnbG9iYWxfc2VhcmNoPXRydWUmbG9vc2U9dHJ1ZQ
(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
3. 
Muscarella, R.
&amp; 
Fleming, T.H.
The role of frugivorous bats in tropical forest succession
. 

Biol.Rev.


82

, 
573–590
(
2007
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
4. 
Kunz, T. H.
, 
Braun de Torrez, E.
, 
Bauer, D.
, 
Lobova, T.
&amp; 
Fleming, T. H.
Ecosystem services provided by bats
. 

Ann. N.Y. Acad. Sci.


1223

, 
1–38
(
2011
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
5. 
Kasso, M.
&amp; 
Balakrishnan, M.
Ecological and economic importance of bats (Order Chiroptera)
. 
ISRN Biodivers.
2013
, Article ID 
187415
(
2013
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
6. 
Boyles, J.G.
, 
Cryan, P. M.
, 
McCracken, G. F.
&amp; 
Kunz, T.K.
Economic importance of bats in agriculture
. 

Science


332

, 
41–42
(
2011
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
7. 
Kemp,J.
et al
. 
Bats as potential suppressors of multiple agricultural pests:A case study from Madagascar
. 

Agric.Ecosyst.Environ.


269

, 
88–96
(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
8. 
Jones, G.
, 
Jacobs, D. S.
, 
Kunz, T.H.
, 
Wilig, M. R.
&amp; 
Racey, P.A.
Carpe noctem:The importance of bats as bioindicators
. 

Endangered Species Research


8

, 
93–115
(
2009
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
9. 
Russo, D.
, 
Bosso, L.
&amp; 
Ancillotto, L.
Novel perspectives on bat insectivory highlight the value of this ecosystem service in farmland: Research frontiers and management implications
. 

Agric.Ecosyst.Environ.


266

, 
31–38
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
10. 
Taylor, P. J.
, 
Grass, I.
, 
Alberts, A. J.
, 
Joubert, E.
&amp; 
Tscharntke, T.
Economic value of bat predation services – A review and new estimates from macadamia orchards
. 

Ecosyst.Serv.


30

, 
372–381
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
11. 
Sulkin, S. E.
&amp; 
Allen, R.
Virus Infections in Bats
.in 
Monographs in Virology
(ed. 
Karger, S.
) 
3–7
(
Basel
, 
1974
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
12. 
Calisher, C. H.
, 
Childs, J. E.
, 
Field, H. E.
, 
Holmes, K. V.
&amp; 
Schountz, T.
Bats: Important reservoir hosts of emerging viruses
. 

Clin. Microbiol.Rev.


19

, 
531–545
(
2006
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
13. 
Cui, J.
, 
Li, F.
&amp; 
Shi, Z.-L.
Origin and evolution of pathogenic coronaviruses
. 

Nat. Rev.Microbiol.


17

, 
181–192
(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
14. 
Guan, Y.
et al
. 
Isolation and characterization of viruses related to the SARS coronavirus from animals in Southern China
. 

Science


302

, 
276–279
(
2003
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
15. 
Kan, B.
et al
. 
Molecular evolution analysis and geographic investigation of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus-like virus in palm civets at an animal market and on farms
. 

J.Virol.


79

, 
11892–11900
(
2005
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
16. 
Tu, C.
et al
. 
Antibodies to SARS coronavirus in civets
. 

Emerg.Infect.Dis.


10

, 
2244–2248
(
2004
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
17. 
Lau, S. K. P.
et al
. 
Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-like virus
in Chinese horseshoe bats. 

Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.


102

, 
14040–14045
(
2005
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
18. 
Li, W.
et al
. 
Bats are natural reservoirs of SARS-like coronaviruses
. 

Science


310

, 
676–679
(
2005
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
19. 
World Health Organization
. 
Summary of probable SARS cases with onset of illness from
1 November 2002 to 31 July 2003 

Based on data as of the 31 December 2003. 
World Health Organization

https://www.who.int/csr/sars/country/table2004_04_21/en/
(
2003
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
20. 
O’Brien, J.
Bats of the Western Indian Ocean islands
. 

Animals


1

, 
259–290
(
2011
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
21. 
Goodman, S.M.
Les chauves-souris de Madagascar
.(
Association Vahatra
, 
2011
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
22. 
Goodman, S. M.
&amp; 
Ramasindrazana, B.
Description of a new species of the Miniopterus aelleni group (Chiroptera:Miniopteridae) from upland areas of central and northern Madagascar
. 

Zootaxa


3936

, 
538–558
(
2015
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
23. 
Goodman, S. M.
et al
. 
An integrative approach to characterize Malagasy bats of the subfamily Vespertilioninae Gray, 1821, with the description of a new species of Hypsugo
. 

Zool. J.Linn.Soc.


173

, 
988–1018
(
2015
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
24. 
Bourgarel, M.
et al
. 
Circulation of alphacoronavirus,betacoronavirus and paramyxovirus in Hipposideros bat species in Zimbabwe
. 

Infect.Genet. Evol.


58

, 
253–257
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
25. 
Ithete, N.L.
et al
. 
Close relative of human Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus in bat, South Africa
. 

Emerg. Infect.Dis.


19

, 
1697–1699
(
2013
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
26. 
Geldenhuys, M.
, 
Weyer, J.
, 
Nel, L. H.
&amp; 
Markotter, W.
Coronaviruses in south african bats
. 

Vector-Borne Zoonotic Dis.


13

, 
516–519
(
2013
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
27. 
Müller, M. A.
et al
. 
Coronavirus antibodies in African bat species
. 

Emerg. Infect. Dis.


13

, 
1367–1370
(
2007
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
28. 
Tao, Y.
et al
. 
Surveillance of bat coronaviruses in Kenya identifies relatives of human coronaviruses NL63 and 229E and their recombination history
. 

J.Virol.
91
, e01953

–16 (
2017
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
29. 
Waruhiu, C.
et al
. 
Molecular detection of viruses in Kenyan bats and discovery of novel astroviruses, caliciviruses and rotaviruses
. 

Virol. Sin.


32

, 
101–114
(
2017
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
30. 
Razanajatovo, N. H.
et al
. 
Detection of new genetic variants of betacoronaviruses in endemic frugivorous bats of Madagascar
. 

Virol. J.


12

, 
42
(
2015
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
31. 
Smith, C. S.
et al
. 
Coronavirus infection and diversity in bats in the Australasian region
. 

Ecohealth


13

, 
72–82
(
2016
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
32. 
Annan, A.
et al
. 
Human betacoronavirus 2c EMC/2012-related viruses in bats, Ghana and Europe
. 

Emerg. Infect. Dis.


19

, 
456–459
(
2013
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
33. 
Drexler, J. F.
et al
. 
Amplification of emerging viruses in a bat colony
. 

Emerg. Infect. Dis.


17

, 
449–456
(
2011
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
34. 
Wacharapluesadee, S.
et al
. 

Longitudinal study of age-specific pattern of coronavirus infection in Lyle’s flying fox (

Pteropus
lylei

) in Thailand

. 

Virol. J.


15

, 
38
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
35. 

Leopardi, S.
et al
. 
Interplay between co-divergence and cross-species transmission in the evolutionary history of bat coronaviruses
. 

Infect.Genet. Evol.


58

, 
279–289
(
2018
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
36. 
Cui, J.
et al
. 
Evolutionary relationships between bat coronaviruses and their hosts
. 

Emerg. Infect.Dis.


13

, 
1526–1532
(
2007
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
37. 

Drexler, J. F.
, 
Corman, V. M.
&amp; 
Drosten, C.
Ecology, evolution and classification of bat coronaviruses in the aftermath of SARS
. 

Antiviral Res.


101

, 
45–56
(
2014
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
38. 

Anthony, S. J.
et al
. 
Global patterns in coronavirus diversity
. 

Virus Evol.


3

, vex012 (
2017
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
39. 

Ziebuhr, J.
et al
. 
ICTV Report 2017.013S
. 
https://talk.ictvonline.org//taxonomy/p/taxonomy-history?taxnode_id=201851846
(
2017
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
40. 

Luis, A. D.
et al
. 
A comparison of bats and rodents as reservoirs of zoonotic viruses: are bats special?

Proc.R. Soc. B Biol.Sci.


280

, 
20122753
(
2013
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
41. 

Willoughby, A. R.
, 
Phelps, K. L.
&amp; 
Olival, K. J.
A comparative analysis of viral richness and viral sharing in cave-roosting bats
. 

Diversity


9

, 
35
(
2017
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
42. 

Olival, K. J.
et al
. 
Host and viral traits predict zoonotic spillover from mammals
. 

Nature


546

, 
646–650
(
2017
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
43. 

Streicker, D. G.
et al
. 
Host phylogeny constrains cross-species emergence and establishment of rabies virus in bats
. 

Science


329

, 
676–9
(
2010
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
44. 

Parrish, C. R.
et al
. 
Cross-species virus transmission and the emergence of new epidemic diseases
. 

Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev.


72

, 
457–70
(
2008
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
45. 

Dijkman, R.
&amp; 
van der Hoek, L.
Human coronaviruses 229E and NL63: close yet still so far
. 

J.Formos. Med. Assoc.


108

, 
270–279
(
2009
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
46. 

Pyrc, K.
et al
. 
Mosaic structure of human coronavirus NL63, one thousand years of evolution
. 

J.Mol. Biol.


364

, 
964–973
(
2006
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
47. 

Pfefferle, S.
et al
. 
Distant relatives of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus and close relatives of human coronavirus 229E in bats
, 

Ghana. 
Emerg. Infect. Dis.


15

, 
1377–1384
(
2009
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
48. 

Corman, V.M.
et al
. 
Evidence for an ancestral association of human coronavirus 229E with bats
. 

J.Virol.


89

, 
11858–11870
(
2015
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
49. 

Joffrin, L.
, 
Dietrich, M.
, 
Mavingui, P.
&amp; 
Lebarbenchon, C.
Bat pathogens hit the road: But which one?

PLoS Pathog.


14

, e 
1007134
(
2018
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
50. 

El-Duah, P.
et al
. 
Development of a whole-virus ELISA for serological evaluation of domestic livestock as possible hosts of human coronavirus NL63
. 

Viruses

11
, 
v
11010043
(
2019
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
51. 

Huynh, J.
et al
. 
Evidence supporting a zoonotic origin of human coronavirus strain NL63
. 

J.Virol.


86

, 
12816–25
(
2012
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
52. 

Geldenhuys, M.
et al
. 
A metagenomic viral discovery approach identifies potential zoonotic and novel mammalian viruses in Neoromicia bats within South Africa
. 

PLoS One


13

, e 
0194527
(
2018
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
53. 

Chen, L.
, 
Liu, B.
, 
Yang, J.
&amp; 
Jin, Q.
DBatVir:The database of bat-associated viruses
. 

Database


2014

, bau021 (
2014
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
54. 

Wilkinson,D. A.
et al
. 
Identification of novel paramyxoviruses in insectivorous bats of the Southwest Indian Ocean
. 

Virus Res.


170

, 
159–163
(
2012
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
55. 

Wilkinson, D. A.
et al
. 
Highly diverse morbillivirus-related paramyxoviruses in wild fauna of the Southwestern Indian Ocean islands: evidence of exchange between introduced and endemic small mammals
. 

J. Virol.


88

, 
8268–77
(
2014
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
56. 

Gomard, Y.
et al
. 
Malagasy bats shelter a considerable genetic diversity of pathogenic Leptospira suggesting notable host-specificity patterns
. 

FEMS Microbiol.Ecol.


92

, fiw037 (
2016
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
57. 

Mélade,J.
et al. 
An eco-epidemiological study of Morbilli-related paramyxovirus infection in Madagascar bats reveals host-switching as the dominant macro-evolutionary mechanism
. 
Sci. Rep.
6
, (
2016
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
58. 

Lebarbenchon, C.
et al
. 
Astroviruses in bats, Madagascar
. 

Emerg.Microbes Infect.


6

, e 
58
(
2017
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
59. 

Muradrasoli, S.
et al
. 
Broadly targeted multiprobe QPCR for detection of coronaviruses: coronavirus is common among mallard ducks (Anas platyrhynchos)
. 

J.Virol. Methods


159

, 
277–287
(
2009
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
60. 

Poon, L. L.M.
et al
. 
Identification of a novel coronavirus in bats
. 

J.Virol.


79

, 
2001–9
(
2005
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
61. 

R 
Core Team
. 
R: A language and environment for statistical computing
. 
R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria
. 
https://www.r-project.org/
(
2018
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
62. 

Technelysium Pty
. 
Ltd
. 
Chromas Lite Software
. 
http://technelysium.com.au/wp/chromas/
(
2018
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
63. 

Grant, B.J.
, 
Rodrigues, A.P.C.
, 
ElSawy, K. M.
, 
McCammon,J. A.
&amp; 
Caves,L. S. D.
Bio3d: an R package for the comparative analysis of protein structures
. 

Bioinformatics


22

, 
2695–2696
(
2006
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
64. 

Kumar, S.
, 
Stecher, G.
, 
Li, M.
, 
Knyaz, C.
&amp; 
Tamura, K.
MEGA X: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis across Computing Platforms
. 

Mol.Biol. Evol.


35

, 
1547–1549
(
2018
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
65. 

Keane, T. M.
, 
Creevey, C. J.
, 
Pentony, M. M.
, 
Naughton, T. J.
&amp; 
Mclnerney, J. O.
Assessment of methods for amino acid matrix selection and their use on empirical data shows that ad hoc assumptions for choice of matrix are not justified
. 

BMC Evol.Biol.


6

, 
29
(
2006
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
66. 


QIAGEN

. 
CLC Sequence Viewer
8. 
https://clc-sequence-viewer.software.informer.com/8.0/
(
2018
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
67. 

Paradis, E.
&amp; 
Schliep, K.
ape 5.0: an environment for modern phylogenetics and evolutionary analyses in R
. 

Bioinformatics


35

, 
526–528
(
2018
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
68. 

Legendre, P.
, 
Desdevises, Y.
&amp; 
Bazin, E.
A Statistical test for host-parasite coevolution
. 

Syst. Biol


51

, 
217–234
(
2002
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
69. 

Conow, C.
, 
Fielder, D.
, 
Ovadia, Y.
&amp; 
Libeskind-Hadas, R.
Jane: a new tool for the cophylogeny reconstruction problem
. 

Algorithms Mol. Biol.


5

, 
16
(
2010
).

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
Acknowledgements

</title>
         <p>
We are very grateful to S. Muradrasoli for recommendations on the optimization of the multiprobe PCR protocol as well as for providing PCR controls and to C. Cordonin for providing bat Cyt 
b
sequences. L. Biscornet, C. Dionisio, L. Domergue, M. Dietrich, T. Mbohoahy, T. Nekena, J. Rakotoarivelo, M. Rakotomanga, C. F. Rakotondramanana, and A. Randrenjarison are thanked for their assistance in the field. We also thank S. Bos and A. Hoarau for their help in the laboratory, and K. Dellagi and H. Pascalis for the development and the management of the ‘partenariat Mozambique-Réunion dans la recherche en santé: pour une approche intégrée d’étude des maladies infectieuses à risque épidémique (MoZaR)’ research program. Field research was funded by the ‘Pathogènes associés à la Faune Sauvage Océan Indien (FS-OI)’, the ‘Leptospirose Ocean Indien (LeptOI)’, the ‘Paramyxovirus Océan Indien (ParamyxOI)’, and the ‘Partenariat Mozambique-Réunion dans la recherche en santé: pour une approche intégrée d’étude des maladies infectieuses à risque épidémique (MoZaR)’ programs (Fond Européen de Développement Régional, Programme Opérationnel de Coopération Territoriale). Fieldwork on Mayotte was funded by the ‘Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique’ (Projets Exploratoires Premier Soutien BATMAN). Molecular analyses were financially supported by tutorship institutions of the UMR PIMIT. L.J. is a recipient of a ‘Région Réunion, European Regional Development Fund (FEDER 2014–2020)’ PhD fellowship. B.R.’s post-doctoral fellowship was supported by the ‘Run Emerge’ European Union’s Seventh Framework Program (FP7/2007–2013; Grant agreement NO 263958), the ‘Fonds de Coopération Régionale, Prefecture de La Réunion’, and The Field Museum of Natural History, Chicago, through the Ralph and Marian Falk Medical Research Trust. C.L. is supported by a ‘Chaire mixte: Université de La Réunion – INSERM’. The funding agencies were not involved in the study design, implementation or publishing of this study, and the research presented herein represents the opinions of the authors but not necessarily the opinions of the funding agencies.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Author contributions

</title>
         <p>C.L. and L.J. conceived and designed the study. B.R., C.L., D.A.W., E.L., L.J., P.T., S.M.G. and Y.G. collected biological material on Madagascar. S.M.G., R.S. and Y.G. collected biological material on Mauritius. B.R., E.L. and G.L.M., collected biological material on Mayotte. S.M.G., G.L.M., A.D.S. and M.C.S., collected biological material in Mozambique. B.R., D.A.W., E.L. and G.L.M. collected biological material on Reunion Island. E.L., G.L.M., S.J. and Y.G. collected biological material in the Seychelles. L.J. performed the molecular analyses. C.L., D.A.W., and L.J. analyzed the data. C.L. and L.J. wrote the paper. S.M.G., E.S.G., P.M. and S.J. contributed to the project management in Malagasy, Mauritian, Seychelles, Mozambican, and French institutions. All authors edited, read, and approved the final manuscript.</p>
         <p>
Competing interests

</p>
         <p>
The authors declare no competing interests.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Additional information

</title>
         <p>
Supplementary information
is available for this paper at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-63799-7.
</p>
         <p>
Correspondence
and requests for materials should be addressed to L.J. or C.L.
</p>
         <p>
Reprints and permissions information
is available at www.nature.com/reprints.
</p>
         <p>
Publisher’s note
Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.
</p>
         <p>
Open Access
This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
</p>
         <p>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.</p>
      </sec>
      <p>© The Author(s) 2020</p>
   </body>
</article>
