<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Science</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abc1490</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Manta-like planktivorous sharks in Late Cretaceous oceans</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>19</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
PALEONTOLOGY

</title>
         <p>
Manta-like planktivorous sharks in Late Cretaceous oceans
</p>
         <p>
Romain Vullo
1

*
, 

Eberhard Frey
2
, 
Christina Ifrim
3
, 
Margarito A. González González
4
, 
Eva S. Stinnesbeck
5
, 
Wolfgang Stinnesbeck
6

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

The ecomorphological diversity of extinct elasmobranchs is incompletely known. Here, we describe 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna milarcae
</tp:taxon-name>
, a bizarre probable planktivorous shark from early Late Cretaceous open marine deposits in Mexico. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
, tentatively assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>Lamniformes</tp:taxon-name>
, is characterized by hypertrophied, slender pectoral fins. This previously unknown body plan represents an unexpected evolutionary experimentation with underwater flight among sharks, more than 30 million years before the rise of manta and devil rays (
<tp:taxon-name>Mobulidae</tp:taxon-name>
), and shows that winglike pectoral fins have evolved independently in two distantly related clades of filter-feeding elasmobranchs. This newly described group of highly specialized long-winged sharks (Aquilolamnidae) displays an aquilopelagic-like ecomorphotype and may have occupied, in late Mesozoic seas, the ecological niche filled by mobulids and other batoids after the Cretaceous–Paleogene boundary.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
E
lasmobranchs—the groupof cartilaginous fishesincludingsharks, skates, andrays— areasuccessfulgroup ofecomorphologicallydiversecartilaginousfishesthat firstappearedaround380 millionyearsago, duringtheLateDevonian period(

).
</p>
         <p>
Modern plankton-feeding elasmobranchs are represented by two main ecomorphotypes corresponding, on one hand, to the whale shark (
<tp:taxon-name>Rhincodontidae</tp:taxon-name>
), the basking shark (
<tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
) and the megamouth shark (
<tp:taxon-name>Megachasmidae</tp:taxon-name>
) (i.e., a macroceanic– tachypelagic morphotype characterized by a large fusiform body) and, on the other hand, to manta and devil rays (
<tp:taxon-name>Mobulidae</tp:taxon-name>
) (i.e., an aquilopelagic morphotype characterized by a dorsoventrally flattened body and winglike pectoral fins with a narrowly angular shape) (


– 


). Whereas the former ecomorphotype convergently evolved during the Mesozoic in giant pachycormid bony fishes (

), the latter ecomorphotype has not been identified so far in the pre-Cenozoic fossil record (

, 

, 

). We report here a new, bizarre fossil sharkshowing a previously unknown bauplan and morphological features indicative of filter-feeding habits. This complete specimen from the early Late Cretaceous (Turonian) of Mexico offers important insights into the Mesozoic evolution of medium- to large-sized planktivorous fishes and the riseof “winged” pelagicelasmobranchs, long before the Paleogene origin and opportunistic radiation of mobulid rays (


– 


).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna milarcae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen.et sp. nov.
(formal taxonomic description is provided in the supplementary materials; 
Figs. 1
and 
2
and figs. S3 to S6) stands out among both living and fossil elasmobranchs, with a body plan characterized by the acquisition of unusually hypertrophied pectoral fins combined with the persistence of a powerful tail showing a welldeveloped caudal fin (mosaic evolution).Among selachimorphs (modern sharks), narrow, distally expanded bladelike pectoral fins are known in various macroceanic sharks (

, 

), but these predatory (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Isurus paucus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Carcharhinus longimanus
</tp:taxon-name>
) or planktivorous (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Megachasma pelagios
</tp:taxon-name>
) forms are less specialized than 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
. Another notable feature of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
is its apparent lack of dorsal and pelvic fins, although a taphonomic cause cannotberuled out. Amongneoselachians (modern elasmobranchs), dorsal fins are absent in the enigmatic Early Jurassic eel-shaped shark 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ostenoselache
</tp:taxon-name>
(

) as well as in various rajiform and myliobatiform rays (

, 

). The assumed dorsal fin secondary loss (or reduction) in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
could be interpreted as a direct consequence of the acquisitionof hypertrophied pectoral fins. In contrast, pelvic fins were lost only in a few extinct chondrichthyan taxa, including eugeneodontiforms (

) and possibly 
<tp:taxon-name>
Squatinactis
</tp:taxon-name>
, a small-sized Paleozoic cladodont shark with enlarged pectoral fins (

).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
is tentatively assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>Lamniformes</tp:taxon-name>
(mackerel sharks) on the basis of features such as the radial asterospondylictype vertebrae (

) and the caudal fin skeleton showing a high hypochordal ray angle (i.e., ventrally directed hypochordal rays) (

). The discovery of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
provides further insight into the Late Cretaceous diversification of neoselachians (

, 

) and likely represents another example of the ecomorphological plasticity and disparity of lamniform sharks, a group that appeared during the Early Cretaceous and today comprises mainly highly autapomorphic taxa that share relatively few synapomorphies (


– 


). Living lamniforms show an impressive variety of morphologies, habitats, behaviors, and diets, with forms ranging from filter-feeders (
<tp:taxon-name>Cetorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Megachasmidae</tp:taxon-name>
) to top predators (
<tp:taxon-name>Lamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
) (

, 

, 

). Aquilolamnids would reinforce the view that lamniforms achieved high levels of ecomorphological disparity precociously in their evolutionary history, as early as the mid-Cretaceous (

, 

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
The overall morphology and peculiar features of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
(i.e., broad head with wide and near-terminal mouth, dentitionmost likely consisting of minute teeth, wing-shaped pectoral fins; see supplementary materials) strongly suggest that this shark was a suspension feeder, more closely related to the aquilopelagic than to the macroceanic– tachypelagic ecomorphotype category (
Fig. 3
and figs. S10 and S11). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
was probably a relatively slow swimmer, comparable to other suspension-feeding elasmobranchs (

). The long and slender pectoral fins of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
most likely acted as stabilizers, but they may also have been used for propulsion by slow flapping movements. In addition, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
had a typical, well-developed heterocercal caudal fin, similar to that of most macroceanic sharks (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Megachasma
</tp:taxon-name>
) (

). Therefore, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
probably used a combination of axial-based undulation and pectoralfin-based oscillation for its locomotion, with main thrust generated by the caudal fin and pectoral fins activated for increasing speed and for maneuvering. This contrasts with the strict pectoral fin-based locomotion of modern suspension-feeding aquilopelagic forms (i.e., mobulids), which are characterized bypowerful enlarged pectoral fins (broad-based “wings” used for propulsion by oscillation) and a whiplike tail (

, 

). Among neoselachians, the combination of axial and pectoral locomotionis known onlyin guitarfishes (Rhinopristiformes) and some electric rays (Torpediniformes) (

, 

); however, these batoids are undulatory appendage propulsors (

, 

), unlike 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The skeleton-based genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
may correspond to the enigmatic tooth-based genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
(fig. S9), known from the Late Cretaceous (Cenomanian–Maastrichtian) of North America and North Africa (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
is especially common in the Eagle Ford Group of Texas (

), a lateral equivalent of the Agua Nueva Formation that yielded the holotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. milarcae
</tp:taxon-name>
(figs. S1 and S9). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
is characterized by simple, minute hooked teeth (less than 2 mm high) that are indicative of planktivory, like teeth of manta rays and whale and basking sharks. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
was originally described as an early member of 
<tp:taxon-name>Mobulidae</tp:taxon-name>
(

) and subsequently regarded as a possible planktivorous lamniform shark (

, 

). The microstructure of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
teeth, characterized by the presence of parallelbundled and tangled-bundled enameloid layers typical of selachimorphs, strongly favorsthelatter hypothesis (

). Theinterpretation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
as a suspension-feeding lamniform is consistent with the taxonomic and trophic positions proposed here for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
. Therefore, we tentatively assign the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>Aquilolamnidae</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platylithophycus
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Niobrara Chalk (

) is another mysterious Late Cretaceous (Coniacian–Campanian) genus that might also belong to Aquilolamnidae. On the basis of a single incomplete specimen consisting of gill arches and associated cartilage fragments, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platylithophycus
</tp:taxon-name>
was recently recognized as a large, possible filter-feeding elasmobranch of uncertain affinities, characterized by the presence of gill rakers of unusual morphology (

). Athird putative Late Cretaceous plankton-feeding sharkis thetoothbased genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudomegachasma
</tp:taxon-name>
, a lamniform restricted to the Cenomanian andinterpreted as a specialized sand tiger shark (
<tp:taxon-name>Odontaspididae</tp:taxon-name>
) (

). Givenits tooth morphologyand systematic placement, it can be reasonably assumed that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudomegachasma
</tp:taxon-name>
had an 
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontaspis
</tp:taxon-name>
-like or 
<tp:taxon-name>
Megachasma
</tp:taxon-name>
-like general appearance, clearly distinct from that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
1
Univ Rennes,CNRS,Géosciences Rennes,UMR 6118,Rennes, France. 
2
Staatliches Museum für Naturkunde Karlsruhe, Karlsruhe,Germany. 
3
SNSB 
–
Jura-Museum,Willibaldsburg, Eichstätt, Germany. 
4
Indepedent Researcher, Sabinas Hidalgo, Nuevo LeÓn,Mexico. 
5
Steinmann-Institut für Geologie, Mineralogie und Paläontologie, Rheinische Friedrich-Wilhelms- Universität,Bonn, Germany. 
6
Institute für Geowissenschaften, Ruprecht-Karls-Universität,Heidelberg,Germany.
</p>
         <p>
Late Cretaceous aquilolamnid sharks (
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna
</tp:taxon-name>
and possibly 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platylithophycus
</tp:taxon-name>
) andgiant suspension-feeding pachycormid bony fishes (
<tp:taxon-name>
Bonnerichthys
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinconichthys
</tp:taxon-name>
) (

) may have been directly affected by the severe end-Cretaceous extinction of calcifying planktonic organisms resulting from an extreme acidification of surface oceans (


– 


). Aquilolamnids and giant pachycormids all became extinct at the Cretaceous–Paleogene (K–Pg) event and were ecologically replacedduring the early Paleogene (Paleocene) by pelagic planktivorous batoids (
<tp:taxon-name>
Archaeomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sulcidens
</tp:taxon-name>
, and the stem mobulid 
<tp:taxon-name>
Burnhamia
</tp:taxon-name>
) (


– 


) and rhincodontid sharks (
<tp:taxon-name>
Palaeorhincodon
</tp:taxon-name>
) (

), respectively (
Fig. 4
). The discovery of aquilolamnids suggests that the guild of large filter-feeding fishes changed in composition but not in structure after the end-Cretaceous mass extinction event, with both aquilopelagic and macroceanic–tachypelagic convergent forms being represented in pre- and post-K–Pg open marine ecosystems.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
REFERENCES AND NOTES

</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 

Environ. Biol. Fishes


28

, 

33 
–
75

(
1990
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
2. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, in 

Sharks of the Open Ocean: Biology, Fisheries and Conservation

, 
M. D. Camhi, E. K. Pikitch, E. A. Babcock
, Eds. (
Blackwell
, 
2008
), pp. 

14 
–
23

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
3. 
C. Pimiento
, 
J. L. Cantalapiedra
, 
K. Shimada
, 
D. J. Field
, 
J. B. Smaers
, 

Evolution


73

, 

588 
–
599

(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
4. 
M. Friedman
et al
., 

Science


327

, 

990 
–
993

(
2010
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
5. 
C. J. Underwood
, 
M. A. Kolmann
, 
D. J. Ward
, 

J. Vertebr
. 
Paleontol
.


37

, e 
1293068
(
2017
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
6. 
S. Adnet
, 
H. Cappetta
, 
G. Guinot
, 
G. Notarbartolo di Sciara
, 

Zool. J. Linn. Soc.


166

, 

132 
–
159

(
2012
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
7. 
T. Tomita
, 
S. Tanaka
, 
K. Sato
, 
K. Nakaya
, 

PLOS ONE


9

, e 
86205
(
2014
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
8. 
C. J. Duffin
, 

Paleontologia Lombarda


9

, 

3 
–
27

(
1998
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
9. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 

Am. Zool
.


17

, 

303 
–
322

(
1977
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
10. 
O. Larouche
, 
M. L. Zelditch
, 
R. Cloutier
, 

BMC Biol.


15

, 
32
(
2017
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
11. 
R
. 
Lund, R. Zangerl
, 

Ann. Carnegie Mus.


45

, 

43 
–
55

(
1974
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
12. 
E. G. White
, 

Bull. Am. Mus. Nat. Hist.


74

, 

25 
–
138

(
1937
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
13. 
S. H. Kim
, 
K. Shimada
, 
C. K. Rigsby
, 

Anat. Rec
.


296

, 

433 
–
442

(
2013
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
14. 
C. J. Underwood
, 

Paleobiology


32

, 

215 
–
235

(
2006
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
15. 
G. Guinot
, 
L. Cavin
, 

Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc
.


91

, 

950 
–
981

(
2016
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
16. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 

NOAA Tech. Rep. NMFS


90

, 

357 
–
379

(
1990
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
17. 
L. J. V. Compagno
, 

FAO Species Cat. Fish. Purp.


1

, 

1 
–
269

(
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
18. 
R. Vullo
, 
G. Guinot
, 
G. Barbe
, 

J. Syst
. 
Palaeontol
.


14

, 

1003 
–
1024

(
2016
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
19. 
F. L. Condamine
, 
J. Romieu
, 
G. Guinot
, 

Proc.Natl. Acad.Sci. U.S.A
.


116

, 

20584 
–
20590

(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
20. 
D. W. Sims
, 

J. Exp. Mar. Biol. Ecol.


249

, 

65 
–
76

(
2000
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
21. 
L. J. Rosenberger
, 

J. Exp. Biol
.


204

, 

379 
–
394

(
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
22. 
C. A. D. Wilga
, 
G. V. Lauder
, in 

Biology of Sharks and Their Relatives

, 
J. C. Carrier, J. A. Musick, M. R. Heithaus
, Eds. (
CRC Press
, 
2004
), pp. 

139 
–
164

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
23. 
B. J. Welton
, 
R. F. Farish
, 

The Collector’ s Guide to Fossil Sharks and Rays from the Cretaceous of Texas

(
Before Time
, 
1993
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
24. 
G. R. Case
, 
T. T. Tokaryk
, 
D. Baird
, 

Can. J. Earth Sci
.


27

, 

1084 
–
1094

(
1990
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
25. 
A. Noubhani
, 
H. Cappetta
, 

Palaeo Ichthyologica


8

, 

1 
–
327

(
1997
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
26. 
S. Enault
, 
H. Cappetta
, 
S. Adnet
, 

Zool. J. Linn. Soc.


169

, 

144 
–
155

(
2013
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
27. 
A. W. Bronson
, 
J. G. Maisey
, 

J. Paleontol
.


92

, 

743 
–
750

(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
28. 
K. Shimada
, 
E. V. Popov
, 
M. Siversson
, 
B. J. Welton
, 
D. J. Long
, 

J. Vertebr
. 
Paleontol.


35

, e 
981335
(
2015
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
29. 
L. Alegret
, 
E. Thomas
, 
K.C. Lohmann
, 

Proc. Natl. Acad.Sci. U.S.A.


109

, 

728 
–
732

(
2012
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
30. 
A. Tajika
, 
A. Nützel
, 
C. Klug
, 

PeerJ


6

, e 
4219
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
31. 
M. J. Henehan
et al
., 

Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A
.


116

, 

22500 
–
22504

(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS

</title>
         <p>
We are grateful to M. Fernández Garza, who made the specimen accessible for scientific research and supports our paleontological work at Vallecillo. We thank A. H. González González and J. M. Padilla Gutiérrez for logistic support and access to the Museo del Desierto collection in Saltillo; O. Sanisidro for the lifelike reconstruction of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. milarcae
</tp:taxon-name>
; T. Tomita for information on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Megachasma
</tp:taxon-name>
; B. J. Welton for providing 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
teeth; L. Joanny for SEM imaging; and three anonymous reviewers for their insightful comments on the manuscript. 
Funding:
Financial support was provided by a scholarship of the DAAD (57381316 to E.S.S.) and by Géosciences Rennes, UMR CNRS 6118 (to R.V.).
</p>
         <p>
Author contributions:
W.S. designed the Vallecillo research project. R.V. and W.S. designed the study. M.A.G.G. secured, collected, and prepared the specimen. R.V., E.F., E.S.S., and W.S. collected the data and participated in the observation and interpretation of the specimen. C.I. and W.S. provided information on the stratigraphic context, associated invertebrates, and age of the specimen. R.V., E.F., E.S.S., and W.S. photographed the specimen. R.V. prepared the figures and wrote the manuscript, with input from all authors. 
Competing interests:
The authors declare no competing interests. 
Data and materials availability:
All data are available in the main text and the supplementary materials; the holotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna milarcae
</tp:taxon-name>
is housed and displayed in the Museo La Milarca in San Pedro Garza García (MMSP), Nuevo LeÓn State, Mexico, under Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia (INAH) registration number 2544 P.F.17. The teeth of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cretomanta
</tp:taxon-name>
are stored in the paleontological collection of the Geological Institute of the University of Rennes 1 (IGR), Rennes, France.
</p>
         <p>
SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS

science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6535/1253/suppl/DC1
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Materials and Methods</p>
         <p>Supplementary Text</p>
         <p>
Figs. S1
to S11
</p>
         <p>Tables S1 to S6</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
References (
32–58
)
</p>
         <p>MDAR Reproducibility Checklist</p>
         <p>8 April 2020; accepted 9 February 2021</p>
         <p>10.1126/science.abc1490</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Manta-like planktivorous sharks in Late Cretaceous oceans

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Romain Vullo, Eberhard Frey, Christina Ifrim, Margarito A. González González, Eva S. Stinnesbeck and Wolfgang Stinnesbeck</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Science
371
(6535), 1253-1256. DOI: 10.1126/science.abc1490
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
A soaring shark

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Modern sharks occupy marine ecosystems across the world but display little morphological diversity, being mostly streamlined predators. Vullo 
et al.
describe a new species of shark from the late Cretaceous that shows that the lack of current variation is not due to limited morphological ''exploration'' in the past. Specifically, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aquilolamna milarcae
</tp:taxon-name>
displays many features similar to modern manta rays, notably long, slender fins and a mouth seemingly adapted to filter feeding, suggesting that it was planktivorous. This finding indicates both that elasmobranchs evolutionarily experimented with other forms and that the planktivorous ''soarers'' emerged in this group at least 30 million years earlier than previously recognized.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Science
, this issue p. 1253
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
ARTICLE TOOLS

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>http://science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6535/1253</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
SUPPLEMENTARY

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
MATERIALS

</title>
         <p>http://science.sciencemag.org/content/suppl/2021/03/17/371.6535.1253.DC1</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
REFERENCES

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>This article cites 43 articles, 8 of which you can access for free http://science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6535/1253#BIBL</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
PERMISSIONS

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>http://www.sciencemag.org/help/reprints-and-permissions</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Use of this article is subject to the Terms of Service</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Science
(print ISSN 0036-8075; online ISSN 1095-9203) is published by the American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1200 New York Avenue NW, Washington, DC 20005. The title 
Science
is a registered trademark of AAAS.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Copyright © 2021 The Authors, some rights reserved; exclusive licensee American Association for the Advancement of Science. No claim to original U.S. Government Works</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
