<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nature</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-03082-x</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Dire wolves were the last of an ancient New World canid lineage</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>13</day>
            <month>01</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>

Alice Mouton

</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Selina Brace
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Canidae</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis dirus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis lupus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis latrans
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cuon alpinus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aenocyon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis lupaster
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis familiaris
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis simensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lycaon pictus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lycalopex culpaeus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Urocyon cinereoargenteus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis mesomelas
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis adustus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lycaon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cuon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lycaon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Cuon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Lupulella
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aenocyon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis dirus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis armbrusteri
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis edwardii
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Canis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Eucyon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Xenocyon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Panthera
atrox
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Arctodus simus
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Alice Mouton, Sandra Álvarez-Carretero.</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>r.perri</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>P values</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>values</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Article
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Dire wolves were the last of an ancient New World canid lineage

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.1038/s41586-020-03082-x
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Accepted: 
12 November 2020
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Published online: xx xx xxxx</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Check for updates</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Angela R. Perri
1,44
✉, 

Kieren J. Mitchell

2,44
✉, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alice Mouton

</tp:taxon-name>
3,44

, 
Sandra Álvarez-Carretero

4,44

, 
Ardern Hulme-Beaman

5,6

, 
James Haile

, 
Alexandra Jamieson

, 
Julie Meachen

, 

Audrey T. Lin

7,9, 

, 
Blaine W. Schubert

, 
Carly Ameen

, 
Ekaterina E. Antipina

, 
Pere Bover


, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Selina Brace
</tp:taxon-name>

, 
Alberto Carmagnini

, 
Christian Carøe

, 
Jose A. Samaniego Castruita

, 
James C. Chatters

17

, 
Keith Dobney

5,18,19,20

, 
Mario dos Reis

, 
Allowen Evin

, 
Philippe Gaubert


, 

Shyam Gopalakrishnan

, 
Graham Gower

, 
Holly Heiniger

, 
Kristofer M. Helgen


, 
Josh Kapp

, 
Pavel A. Kosintsev

25,26

, 
Anna Linderholm

7,27

, 
Andrew T. Ozga


28,29, 



, 
Samantha Presslee

, 
Alexander T. Salis

, 
Nedda F. Saremi

, 
Colin Shew

, 
Katherine Skerry

, 
Dmitry E. Taranenko

, 
Mary Thompson

, 
Mikhail V. Sablin

, 
Yaroslav V. Kuzmin

35,36

, 
Matthew J. Collins

16,37

, 
Mikkel-Holger S. Sinding

16,38

, 
M. Thomas P. Gilbert

16,39

, 
Anne C. Stone

28,29,40

, 
Beth Shapiro

24,41

, 
Blaire Van Valkenburgh

, 
Robert K. Wayne

, 
Greger Larson

, 
Alan Cooper

42

&amp; 
Laurent A. F. Frantz

4,43
✉ 

Received: 
14 April 2020

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Dire wolves are considered to be one of the most common and widespread large carnivores in Pleistocene America 

, yet relatively little is known about their evolution or extinction.Here,to reconstruct the evolutionary history of dire wolves,we sequenced five genomes from sub-fossil remains dating from 13,000 to more
</p>
         <p>
than 50,000 years ago. Our results indicate that although they were similar morphologically to the extant grey wolf,dire wolves were a highly divergent lineage that split from living canids around 5.7 million years ago.In contrast to numerous examples of hybridization across 
<tp:taxon-name>Canidae</tp:taxon-name>

, 

, there is no evidence for gene flow between dire wolves and either North American grey wolves or coyotes.This suggests that dire wolves evolved in isolation from the Pleistocene ancestors of these species. Our results also support an early New World origin of dire wolves,while the ancestors of grey wolves,coyotes and dholes evolved in Eurasia and colonized North America only relatively recently.
</p>
         <p>
Dire wolves (
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis dirus
</tp:taxon-name>
) were large (around 
68 kg
)wolf-like canids and among the most common extinct large carnivores of the American Late Pleistocene megafauna 

. Dire wolf remains are present in the North American palaeontological record from at least around 250,000 to about13,000years ago,at the end of the Pleistocene epoch,particularly in the lower latitudes 

(
Fig.1a
). Other canid species that were present in Late Pleistocene North America include the slightly smaller grey wolf (
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis lupus
</tp:taxon-name>
), the much smaller coyote (
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis latrans
</tp:taxon-name>
) and the dhole (or Asiatic wild dog; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cuon alpinus
</tp:taxon-name>
), although dire wolves appear to have been more common overall 

. For example,more than 4,000 individuals have been excavated from California’s fossil-rich Rancho La Brea tar seeps alone,where they outnumber grey wolves more than100-fold 

, 

. Despite the abundance of dire wolf fossils,their origins,taxonomic relationships and ultimate driver of their extinction remain unclear. Dire wolves are generally described as a sister species to 

– 

, or even conspecific with, the grey wolf 

. The leading hypothesis to explain their extinction is that, owing to their larger body size compared with grey wolves and coyotes,dire wolves were more specialized for hunting large prey and were unable to survive the extinction of their megafaunal prey 

– 

. To test this hypothesis, we performed geomet- ric morphometric analyses of more than 
700 specimens
.Our results indicate that although specimens of dire wolves and grey wolves can be differentiated,their morphology is highly similar (
Fig.1b
, Supple- mentary Information, Supplementary 
Figs. 1
–6 and Supplementary Data 3–12).Although this morphometric similarity may be driven in part by allometry (
Fig.1b
, Supplementary Information),the lack of dis- tinctiveness between grey wolves and dire wolves has been interpreted to be a result of a close evolutionary relationship 

, 

. Alternatively, a competing hypothesis maintains that these morphological similari- ties are the result of convergence,and that dire wolves instead are a species that belongs to a separate taxonomic lineage (classified in the monotypic genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aenocyon
</tp:taxon-name>
, ‘terrible’ or ‘dreadful’ wolf 

).
</p>
         <p>
To resolve the evolutionary history of dire wolves, we screened 46 sub-fossil specimens for the presence of preserved genomic DNA (Supplementary Data 1). We identified five samples from 
Idaho
(Dire- AFR &amp; DireGB), 
Ohio
(DireSP), 
Tennessee
(DireGWC) and 
Wyoming
(DireNTC),dating to between 12,900 and more than 50,000years ago, that possessed sufficient endogenous DNA to obtain both mitochon- drial genomes(between around 1× and 31× coverage) and low-coverage nuclear genome sequences (approximately 0.01× to 0.23× coverage) using hybridization capture or shotgun sequencing methods (Supple- mentary Information).All of these samples displayed molecular dam- age profiles that are typical of ancient DNA (Supplementary Figs.8,9). Although we did not successfully sequence DNA from dire wolf specimens from the La Brea tar seeps, one specimen did contain type-I collagen (
COL1
) that was suitable for sequencing using pal- aeoproteomic methods (Supplementary Data 1 and Supplementary Information). Analyses of the dire wolf 
COL1
sequence suggested that they were not closely related to grey wolves,coyotes,African wolves(
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis lupaster
</tp:taxon-name>
) or dogs(
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis familiaris
</tp:taxon-name>
) (Supplementary Fig.7).These data,however, could not confidently resolve the relationships between more distantly related canids owing to a lack of lineage-specific amino acid changes among these species 

. Phylogenetic analyses of the mitochondrial genomes indicated that dire wolves form a well-supported monophyl- etic group that is highly divergent from grey wolves and coyotes (Sup- plementary Fig. 10; see Supplementary Data 13 and Supplementary Tables 2–4 for a list of the 13 species and their coverage used in this analysis),contradicting recent palaeontological analyses 


– 


(
Fig. 1b
). Canid mitochondrial phylogenies, however, may not represent the true evolutionary relationships of the species as both admixture and incomplete lineage sorting have been shown to affect canid phyloge- netic topologies 


,17

. To resolve the phylogenetic relationships of dire wolves,we analysed the nuclear genomic data of the dire wolves together with previously published genomic data from eight extant canids:grey wolf, coyote, African wolf, dhole, Ethiopian wolf (
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis simensis
</tp:taxon-name>
), African wild dog (
<tp:taxon-name>
Lycaon pictus
</tp:taxon-name>
), Andean fox (
<tp:taxon-name>
Lycalopex culpaeus
</tp:taxon-name>
) and grey fox (
<tp:taxon-name>
Urocyon cinereoargenteus
</tp:taxon-name>
—an outgroup).Of these species,the geographical ranges of grey wolves,coyotes,dholes and grey foxes overlapped with that of dire wolves during the Pleistocene epoch (
Fig.1a
). We also gener- ated new nuclear genome sequences for a grey wolf from 
Montana
and the two endemic African jackals—the black-backed and side-striped jackal (
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis mesomelas
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis adustus
</tp:taxon-name>
, respectively)—to ensure representation of all extant members of the ‘wolf-like canid’ clade (com- prising 
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lycaon
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cuon
</tp:taxon-name>
and their extinct relatives) (Supplementary Data 13).Supermatrix analyses,based on nuclear sequence alignments of 70 kb to 28 Mb (depending on overall coverage for each dire wolf genome;Supplementary Tables 5,7) confirmed a distant evolutionary relationship between dire wolves and the other wolf-like canids(
Fig. 2a
, Supplementary Fig. 11 and Supplementary Figs.15,16).This analysis, however, could not definitively resolve whether dire wolves were the basal members of the wolf-like canid clade or the second lineage to diverge after the common ancestor of the two African jackals. We investigated canid phylogenetic relationships in greater detail using a range of species tree analyses 

, 

and 
D
-statistics(Supplemen- tary Information).These approaches produced concordant trees that support the monophyly of three primary lineages:dire wolves,African jackals and a clade comprising all other extant wolf-like canids(
Fig.2a
, Supplementary Tables 6–8 and Supplementary Figs.11–16).Although our species tree analyses provided equivocal results regarding the relationships among these lineages,grey wolves (genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis
</tp:taxon-name>
)are more closely related to African wild dogs (genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lycaon
</tp:taxon-name>
) (Supplementary Fig. 19), dholes (genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cuon
</tp:taxon-name>
) (Supplementary Fig. 21) and Ethiopian wolves (Supplementary Fig. 22) than to either dire wolves or African jackals (both genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis
</tp:taxon-name>
). This finding is consistent with previously proposed designations of the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lupulella
</tp:taxon-name>

for the African jackals and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aenocyon
</tp:taxon-name>

for dire wolves. To assess the timing of divergence among the major wolf-like canid lineages,we performed a Bayesian clock-dating analysis using MCMC- tree 

. Although the dire wolf sequences are low coverage and include post-mortem damage, extensive simulations indicated that this is unlikely to affect the time of divergence estimates inferred by MCMC- tree (Supplementary Information,Supplementary Tables 9–11 and Sup- plementary Fig.17).This analysis confirmed that the initial divergences of the three primary wolf-like canid lineages occurred rapidly,which contributes to the poor resolution of the tree as a result of incomplete lineage sorting (Fig. 2a). The dire wolf lineage last shared a common ancestor with extant wolf-like canids around 5.7 million years ago(95% highest posterior density (HPD), 4.0–8.5 million years ago) (Fig. 2a), followed by the divergence of African jackals around 5.1 million years ago (95% HPD,3.5–7.6 million years ago) (Fig.2b).
</p>
         <p>A list of affiliations appears at the end of the paper.</p>
         <p>
Given the tendency for sympatric canid species to interbreed 

, 

, 

, we tested for genomic signals of admixture between extant North American canids and dire wolves using 
D
-statistics 

(Supplementary Information) on a dataset that included 22 modern North American grey wolves and coyotes,three ancient dogs 

– 

and a Pleistocene wolf 

(Supplementary Data 13). Specifically, we computed statistics of the form 
D
(outgroup (grey fox); dire wolf; North American canid (grey wolf or coyote); African wolf/Eurasian wolf) and found no significant excess of shared derived alleles between dire wolves and any extant North American canid (Fig. 2b, Supplementary Fig. 18 and Supple- mentary Data 14).This result indicates that the dire wolves sequenced in this study did not possess ancestry from grey wolves,coyotes or their recent North American ancestors.Although we cannot exclude the possibility that some unsampled canid population has some dire wolf hybrid ancestry,the lack of a hybridization signal in our broad set of genomes suggests that admixture is unlikely to have occurred. Although we did not find evidence of recent admixture,we did find that African wild dogs share fewer derived alleles with dire wolves than with grey wolves,coyotes,African wolves,dholes or Ethiopian wolves (Fig. 2c, Supplementary Fig.20 and Supplementary Data 15, 16). This indicates that an episode of ancient admixture between the ancestor of dire wolves and the ancestor of wolves,coyotes and dholes occurred at least around 3 million years ago (based on the lower bound of the 95% HPD on the age of their common ancestor) (Fig. 2a), which may have contributed to the challenge of resolving the branching order of the basal wolf-like canid lineages (Fig.2a).
</p>
         <p>
Hybridization is common among wolf-like canid lineages when their ranges overlap.For example,modern grey wolves and coyotes hybridize readily in North America 

. Genomic data also suggest that gene flow occurred between dholes and African wild dogs during the Pleistocene epoch 

, millions of years after their divergence. Consequently, our finding of no evidence for gene flow between dire wolves and grey wolves,coyotes or their common ancestor—despite substantial range overlap with dire wolves during the Late Pleistocene—suggests that the common ancestor of grey wolves and coyotes probably evolved in geographical isolation from members of the dire wolf lineage.This result is consistent with the hypothesis that dire wolves originated in the Americas 

, 

, 

, 

, and probably belonged to the same lineage as the extinct Armbruster’s wolf (
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis armbrusteri
</tp:taxon-name>
) 

.
</p>
         <p>
Long-term isolation of the dire wolf lineage in the Americas implies that other American fossil taxa, such as the Pliocene 
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis edwardii
</tp:taxon-name>
, a proposed relative of the coyote 

, may instead belong to the dire wolf lineage. Thus, the diversification of the extant wolf-like canids probably occurred in parallel outside of the Americas, and perhaps began earlier than hypothesized. The living 
<tp:taxon-name>
Canis
</tp:taxon-name>
species may have descended from Old World members of the extinct genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eucyon
</tp:taxon-name>
, which first appeared in the fossil record of Africa and Eurasia at the end of the Miocene epoch 

. Geographical isolation since the late Miocene is consistent with our molecular estimates for the age of the dire wolf lineage, and may have allowed dire wolves to evolve some degree of reproductive isolation before the arrival of grey wolves,
</p>
         <p>
coyotes, dholes and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenocyon
</tp:taxon-name>
(another extinct wolf-like canid) in North America during the Late Pleistocene.
</p>
         <p>
Despite their overall phenotypic similarities,grey wolves and coy- otes survived the Late Pleistocene megafaunal extinctions whereas dire wolves did not.One possible reason may be that both grey wolves and coyotes possessed greater morphological plasticity and dietary flexibility, thus allowing them to avoid extinction and become the dominant terrestrial predators in North America 

, 

. This scenario is supported by the date that we obtained from the DireGWC specimen (
12,820
–12,720
calibrated years before present), which suggests that dire wolves survived until at least the Younger Dryas cold reversal, a period that also witnessed the latest known dates for other specialized North American mega-carnivores such as the American lion(
<tp:taxon-name>
Panthera
atrox
</tp:taxon-name>
) and giant short-faced bear (
<tp:taxon-name>
Arctodus simus
</tp:taxon-name>
) 

, 

. Alternatively, grey wolves and coyotes may have survived as a result of their ability to hybridize with other canids.Through adaptive introgression with dogs,North American grey wolves are known to have acquired traits related to coat colour,hypoxia and immune response 

, 

.Specifically, enhanced immunity may have allowed grey wolves to resist diseases carried by newly arriving Old World taxa.Because our results demon- strate that dire wolves did not derive any ancestry from other wolf-like canid species,it is plausible that reproductive isolation prevented dire wolves from acquiring traits that may have allowed them to survive into the Holocene epoch.
</p>
         <p>
Online content
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Any methods,additional references,Nature Research reporting sum- maries, source data, extended data, supplementary information, acknowledgements,peer review information;details of author contri- butions and competing interests;and statements of data and code avail- ability are available at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-03082-x.</p>
         <p>

1. 
Dundas,R.G.

Quaternary records of the dire wolf, 
Canis dirus

, in 
North and South America
. 

Boreas

28

, 
375–385
(
1999
).

</p>
         <p>

2. 
vonHoldt,B.M.
et al. 
Whole-genome sequence analysis shows that two endemic species of North American wolf are admixtures of the coyote and gray wolf
. 

Sci.Adv
.

2

, e 
1501714
(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

3. 
Gopalakrishnan,S.
et al. 

Interspecific gene flow shaped the evolution of the genus 
Canis

. 

Curr.Biol
.

28

, 
3441–3449
(
2018
).

</p>
         <p>

4. 
Meachen,J. A.
, 
Brannick,A.L.
&amp; 
Fry,T.J.
Extinct Beringian wolf morphotype found in the continental U.S.has implications for wolf migration and evolution
. 

Ecol.Evol
.

6

, 
3430–3438
(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

5. 
Leonard,J.A.
et al. 
Megafaunal extinctions and the disappearance of a specialized wolf ecomorph
. 

Curr.Biol
.

17

, 
1146–1150
(
2007
).

</p>
         <p>

6. 
Kurtén,B.
&amp; 
Anderson,E.
Pleistocene Mammals of North America
(Columbia Univ

. 
Press
, 
1980
).

</p>
         <p>

7. 
Tedford, R. H.
, 
Wang, X.
&amp; 
Taylor, B. E.
Phylogenetic systematics of the North American fossil Caninae (Carnivora: Canidae)
. 

Bull. Am. Nat. Hist
.

325

, 
1–218
(
2009
).

</p>
         <p>

8. 
Prevosti, F. J.
Phylogeny of the large extinct South American Canids (Mammalia, Carnivora, Canidae) using a ‘total evidence’ approach
. 

Cladistics

26

, 
456–481
(
2010
).

</p>
         <p>

9. 
Zrzavý,J.
, 
Duda,P.
, 
Robovský,J.
, 
Okřinová,I.
&amp; 
Pavelková Řičánková,V.
Phylogeny of the Caninae (Carnivora):combining morphology,behaviour,genes and fossils
. 

Zool.Scr
.

47

, 
373–389
(
2018
).

</p>
         <p>

10. 
Álvarez-Carretero, S.
, 
Goswami,A.
, 
Yang,Z.
&amp; 
Dos Reis,M.
Bayesian estimation of species divergence times using correlated quantitative characters
. 

Syst.Biol
.

68

, 
967–986
(
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

11. 
Goulet,G.D.
Comparison of temporal and geographical skull variation among Nearctic modern
, 

Holocene and Late Pleistocene gray wolves (
Canis lupus
) (and selected 
Canis
)

. (
1993
).

</p>
         <p>

12. 
Graham,R.W.
&amp; 
Mead,J.I.
in 

North America and Adjacent Oceans During the Last
Deglaciation

(eds 
Ruddiman,Q. F.
&amp; 
Wright, H. E.Jr.
) 
371–402
(
Geological Society of America
, 
1987
).

</p>
         <p>

13. 
Barnosky,A.D.
in 

Mass Extinctions: Processes and Evidence

(ed. 
Donovan,S. K.
) 
235–254
(
Belhaven
, 
1989
).

</p>
         <p>

14. 
DeSantis,L. R. G.
et al. 
Causes and consequences of pleistocene megafaunal extinctions as revealed from Rancho La Brea mammals
. 

Curr. Biol
.

29

, 
2488–2495
(
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

15. 
Merriam,J.C.

Note on the systematic position of the wolves of the 
Canis dirus
group

. 

Bull.
Dept.Geol.Univ.California

10

, 
531–533
(
1918
).

</p>
         <p>

16. 
Buckley, M.
, 
Harvey, V. L.
&amp; 
Chamberlain, A. T.

Species identification and decay assessment of Late Pleistocene fragmentary vertebrate remains from Pin Hole Cave (Creswell Crags, UK) using collagen fingerprinting. 
Boreas
46
, 402–411 (2017). 17. Koepfli,K.-P.et al. Genome-wide evidence reveals that African and Eurasian golden jackals are distinct species

. 

Curr.Biol
.

25

, 
2158–2165
(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

18. 
Bryant,D.
, 
Bouckaert,R.
, 
Felsenstein,J.
, 
Rosenberg,N.A.
&amp; 
RoyChoudhury,A.
Inferring species trees directly from biallelic genetic markers:bypassing gene trees in a full coalescent analysis
. 

Mol.Biol. Evol
.

29

, 
1917–1932
(
2012
).

</p>
         <p>

19. 
Yang,Z.The
BPP program for species tree estimation and species delimitation
. 

Curr.Zool
.

61

, 
854–865
(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

20. 
Geraads,D.
A revision of the fossil Canidae (Mammalia) of north-western Africa
. 

Palaeontology

54

, 
429–446
(
2011
).

</p>
         <p>

21. 
Yang,Z.
PAML 4:phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood
. 

Mol.Biol.Evol
.

24

, 
1586–1591
(
2007
).

</p>
         <p>

22. 
vonHoldt,B.M.
et al. 
A genome-wide perspective on the evolutionary history of enigmatic wolf-like canids
. 

Genome Res
.

21

, 
1294–1305
(
2011
).

</p>
         <p>

23. 
Patterson, N.
et al. 
Ancient admixture in human history
. 

Genetics

192

, 
1065–1093
(
2012
).

</p>
         <p>

24. 
Sinding,M.S.
et al. 
Arctic-adapted dogs emerged at the Pleistocene–Holocene transition
. 

Science

368

, 
1495–1499
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

25. 
Ní Leathlobhair,M.
et al. 
The evolutionary history of dogs in the Americas
. 

Science

361

, 
81–85
(
2018
).

</p>
         <p>

26. 
Frantz,L.A. F.
et al. 
Genomic and archaeological evidence suggest a dual origin of domestic dogs
. 

Science

352

, 
1228–1231
(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

27. 
Skoglund,P.
, 
Ersmark,E.
, 
Palkopoulou,E.
&amp; 
Dalén,L.
Ancient wolf genome reveals an early divergence of domestic dog ancestors and admixture into high-latitude breeds
. 

Curr.Biol
.

25

, 
1515–1519
(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

28. 
Nowak,R.M.

North American quaternary 
Canis.Monograph of the Museum of Natural
History
(Univ

. 
Kansas
, 
1979
).

</p>
         <p>

29. 
Nowak,R.M.
in 

Wolves: Behavior,Ecology, and Conservation

(eds. 
Mech,L. D.
&amp; 
Boitani, L.
) 
239–258
(
Univ.Chicago Press
, 
2003
).

</p>
         <p>

30. 
Sotnikova, M.
&amp; 
Rook, L.
Dispersal of the Canini (Mammalia, Canidae: Caninae) across Eurasia during the Late Miocene to Early Pleistocene
. 

Quat. Int
.

212

, 
86–97
(
2010
).

</p>
         <p>

31. 
Saunders,J.J.
, 
Styles,B. W.
&amp; 
Baryshnikov,G.F.
Quaternary Paleozoology in the Northern
Hemisphere

(
Illinois State Museum
, 
1998
).

</p>
         <p>

32. 
Cooper,A.
et al. 
Abrupt warming events drove Late Pleistocene Holarctic megafaunal turnover
. 

Science

349

, 
602–606
(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

33. 
Schubert,B. W.

Late Quaternary chronology and extinction of North American giant short-faced bears (
Arctodus simus
)

. 

Quat.Int
.

217

, 
188–194
(
2010
).

</p>
         <p>

34. 
Schweizer,R.M.
et al. 
Natural selection and origin of a melanistic allele in North American gray wolves
. 

Mol. Biol. Evol
.

35

, 
1190–1209
(
2018
).

</p>
         <p>

35. 
Anderson,T.M.
et al. 
Molecular and evolutionary history of melanism in North American gray wolves
. 

Science

323

, 
1339–1343
(
2009
).

</p>
         <p>

36. 
IUCN
. 

The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species

version 2019
-2 
https://www.iucnredlist. org
(
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

37. 
R Core Team
. 

R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing

http://www. R-project.org/
(
R Foundation for Statistical Computing
, 
2013
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Corresponding author(s):
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Laurent Frantz, Angela Perri, Kieren Mitchell</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Last updated by author(s): 
Oct 26, 2020
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Reporting Summary
</title>
         <p>
Nature Research wishes to improve the reproducibility of the work that we publish. This form provides structure for consistency and transparency
</p>
         <p>
in reporting. For further information on Nature Research policies, see Authors &amp; Referees and the Editorial Policy Checklist.
</p>
         <p>
Statistics
</p>
         <p>
For all statistical analyses, confirm that the following items are present in the figure legend, table legend, main text, or Methods section.
</p>
         <p>n Confirmed</p>
         <p>

The exact sample size (
n
) for each experimental group/condition, given as a discrete number and unit of measurement

</p>
         <p>A statement on whether measurements were taken from distinct samples or whether the same sample was measured repeatedly</p>
         <p>The statistical test(s) used AND whether they are one- or two-sided</p>
         <p>
Only common tests should be described solely by name; describe more complex techniques in the Methods section.
</p>
         <p>A description of all covariates tested</p>
         <p>A description of any assumptions or corrections, such as tests of normality and adjustment for multiple comparisons</p>
         <p>A full description of the statistical parameters including central tendency (e.g. means) or other basic estimates (e.g. regression coefficient)</p>
         <p>AND variation (e.g. standard deviation) or associated estimates of uncertainty (e.g. confidence intervals)</p>
         <p>
For null hypothesis testing, the test statistic (e.g. 
F
, 
t
, 
r
) with confidence intervals, effect sizes, degrees of freedom and 
P
value noted
</p>
         <p>

Give 
<tp:taxon-name>P values</tp:taxon-name>
as exact 
<tp:taxon-name>values</tp:taxon-name>
whenever suitable.

</p>
         <p>For Bayesian analysis, information on the choice of priors and Markov chain Monte Carlo settings</p>
         <p>For hierarchical and complex designs, identification of the appropriate level for tests and full reporting of outcomes</p>
         <p>
nature research | reporting summary 

October 2018

1 Estimates of effect sizes (e.g. Cohen's 
d
, Pearson's 
r
), indicating how they were calculated
</p>
         <p>
Our web collection on statistics for biologists contains articles on many of the points above.
</p>
         <p>
Software and code
</p>
         <p>
Policy information about availability of computer code
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Data collection
</title>
         <p>TpsDig 2.3 software was used for digitising landmarks in morphometric analysis</p>
         <p>
Data analysis
</p>
         <p>Morphometric analyses: Morpho R package (v2.8); Shapes R package (v1.2.5); Geomorph R package (v3.2.0); Geiger R package (v2.0.6.4); Phytools R package (v0.6-99).</p>
         <p>Proteomics analyses: PEAKS (v7.5); MAFFT (v7.123b); MrBayes (v3.2.6).</p>
         <p>Genomic analyses: BWA (mem and aln mode; v0.7.17); Picard (v1.137); MapDamage (v2.0); GATK (v4.0.11.0); ANGSD (v0.931-2-</p>
         <p>gfd2a527); RAxML (v8.2.9); htsbox (v-r327); AMAS (v0.94); PartitionFinder (v2); MrBayes (v3.2.1); BedTools (v2.17.0); BPP (v4.0.4);</p>
         <p>DISCOVISTA(https://github.com/esayyari/DiscoVista); mcmc3r; BEAST (v2.5.1); BCFtools (v0.1.17); eig-utils (https://github.com/</p>
         <p>grahamgower/eig-utils); PAML (v4.9); Phyclust R package (v0.1-28); mcmc3r (https://github.com/dosreislab/mcmc3r); ADMIXTOOLS (v3);</p>
         <p>For manuscripts utilizing custom algorithms or software that are central to the research but not yet described in published literature, software must be made available to editors/reviewers.</p>
         <p>We strongly encourage code deposition in a community repository (e.g. GitHub). See the Nature Research guidelines for submitting code &amp; software for further information.</p>
         <p>
Data
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>Geomorphometric data (2D) was deposited on Dryad with DOI: https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.63xsj3v16</p>
         <p>The mass spectrometry proteomics data are available via ProteomeXchange with identifier PXD021930 - and consensus sequence of the dire wolf can be found in Supplementary Data 17.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Field-specific reporting
</title>
         <p>Please select the one below that is the best fit for your research. If you are not sure, read the appropriate sections before making your selection. Life sciences Behavioural &amp; social sciences Ecological, evolutionary &amp; environmental sciences</p>
         <p>For a reference copy of the document with all sections, see nature.com/documents/nr-reporting-summary-flat.pdf</p>
         <p>Ecological, evolutionary &amp; environmental sciences study design</p>
         <p>All studies must disclose on these points even when the disclosure is negative.</p>
         <p>
Study description
</p>
         <p>
Research sample
</p>
         <p>
Sampling strategy
</p>
         <p>
Data collection
</p>
         <p>
Timing and spatial scale
</p>
         <p>
Data exclusions
</p>
         <p>No data was excluded from the analysis</p>
         <p>
nature research | reporting summary 

October 2018

2
</p>
         <p>
Reproducibility
</p>
         <p>Detailed description of all experimental work is available in the supplementary information. All museum codes from which samples were taken are also detailed.</p>
         <p>No-template (“blank”) controls were processed alongside all samples. These samples failed to amplify efficiently and no reads sequenced from no-template libraries could be unambiguously mapped, indicating that background and cross-contamination were minimal.</p>
         <p>
Randomization
</p>
         <p>No experiment requiring randomization was conducted in this study</p>
         <p>Blinding No experiment requiring randomization was conducted in this study</p>
         <p>
Did the study involve field work?
</p>
         <p>Yes No</p>
         <p>Reporting for specific materials, systems and methods</p>
         <p>
We require information from authors about some 
types
of materials, experimental systems and methods used in many studies. Here, indicate whether each material, system or method listed is relevant to your study. If you are not sure if a list item applies to your research, read the appropriate section before selecting a response.
</p>
         <p>
Palaeontology
</p>
         <p>
Specimen provenance DireAFR:American Falls Reservoir, 
Idaho
, 
USA
.
</p>
         <p>
DireNTC: Natural Trap Cave, 
Wyoming
, 
USA
.
</p>
         <p>
DireGB: Gigantobison Bay (48001), American Falls Reservoir, 
Idaho
, 
USA
.
</p>
         <p>
DireSP: Sheriden Pit, 
Ohio
, 
USA
.
</p>
         <p>
DireGWC: Guy Wilson Cave, 
Tennessee
, 
USA
.
</p>
         <p>No permits were necessary as all specimens were already collected and accessioned in museum collections. Samples were taken</p>
         <p>with permission from the organisations holding the collections.</p>
         <p>
Specimen deposition DireAFR:Specimen accessioned as IMNH 255/8007 at the 
Idaho
Museum of Natural History. DNA accessioned as AJ66 at the
</p>
         <p>PalaeoBarn (University of Oxford)</p>
         <p>
DireNTC: Specimen accessioned as KU48130 at the University of 
Kansas
Museum. DNA accessioned as ACAD5529 at Australian
</p>
         <p>Centre for Ancient DNA (University of Adelaide)</p>
         <p>
DireGB: Specimen accessioned as IMNH 48001/52 at the 
Idaho
Museum of Natural History. DNA accessioned as ACAD18742 at
</p>
         <p>Australian Centre for Ancient DNA (University of Adelaide)</p>
         <p>DireSP: Specimen accessioned as VP1737 at the Cincinnati Museum Centre. DNA accessioned as ACAD1735 at Australian Centre</p>
         <p>for Ancient DNA (University of Adelaide)</p>
         <p>
DireGWC: Specimen accessioned as MMNHC 0013 at the McClung Museum, University of 
Tennessee
. DNA accessioned as
</p>
         <p>RW001 at UCLA.</p>
         <p>Dating methods DireAFR:N/A</p>
         <p>DireNTC: Pretreated with HCl-NaOH-HCl rinses and ultrafiltration (&gt;30kDa) then radiocarbon dated at the Oxford Radiocarbon</p>
         <p>Accelerator Unit (OxA-37752; 19970 ± 110 BP)</p>
         <p>DireGB: N/A</p>
         <p>DireSP: N/A</p>
         <p>DireGWC: Submitted to DirectAMS for radiocarbon dating and underwent standard gelatin extraction procedures (D-AMS 26659;</p>
         <p>10944 ± 22 years BP)</p>
         <p>Tick this box to confirm that the raw and calibrated dates are available in the paper or in Supplementary Information.</p>
         <p>
nature research | reporting summary 

October 2018

3
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
