<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Royal Society Open Science</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.190638</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Early animal Two hypotheses for the early radiation of the metazoans are evolution: a morphologist ’s view.</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Amphimedon
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Haeckelia
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mnemiopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Trichoplax</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Polypodium
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Sabrina Pankey Mı Ohdera</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Medina Mı Plachetzki</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Pleurobrachia pileus
(Müllerı 1776)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Aegina citrea
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Haeckelia rubra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Euchlora rubra
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mnemiopsis leidyi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Mnemiopsis leidyi
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Bilateria
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
(Placozoa)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax adhaerens
(Placozoa)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax adhaerens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax adhaerens
(Placozoa)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax adhaerens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax adhaerens
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>
Polypodium hydriforme
</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
royalsoƖietypublishing.org/journal/rsos

</title>
         <p>
Review

</p>
         <p>

cite this artiƖle: Nielsen C. 

2019

Early animal evolution: a morphologist

’

s view. 
R. Soc. open sci.


6
: 

190638

. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 

10.1098/rsos. 
190638

</p>
         <p>

Received: 
5 April 2019
</p>
         <p>

Accepted: 
4 July 2019
</p>
         <p>
SubjeƖt category:

</p>
         <p>
Biology (whole organism)

</p>
         <p>
SubjeƖt Areas:

</p>
         <p>
evolution

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>
Keywords:

</title>
         <p>
animaliaı morphologyı ultrastructureı

</p>
         <p>
large molecules

</p>
         <p>
Author for ƖorrespondenƖe:

</p>
         <p>
Claus Nielsen

</p>
         <p>
e-mail: cnielsen@snm.ku.dk

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="document_head">
         <title>
Early

animal

evolution:

a

morphologist
’
s

view

</title>
         <p>
Claus Nielsen

</p>
         <p>

The Natural History Museum of Denmarkı University of Copenhagenı Zoological Museumı Universitetsparken 
15ı
DK- 
2100
Copenhagenı 
Denmark
CNı 0000-0001-6898-7655


</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Two hypotheses for the early radiation of the metazoans are vividly discussed in recent phylogenomic studies̗ the 
‘
Porifera- first 
’
hypothesis̗ which places the poriferans as the sister group of all other metazoans̗ and the 
‘
Ctenophora-first 
’
hypothesis̗ which places the ctenophores as the sister group to all other metazoans. It has been suggested that an analysis of morphological characters (including specific molecules) could throw additional light on the controversy̗ and this is the aim of this paper. Both hypotheses imply independent evolution of nervous systems in Planulozoa and Ctenophora. The Porifera- first hypothesis implies no homoplasies or losses of major characters. The Ctenophora-first hypothesis shows no important synapomorphies of Porifera̗ Planulozoa and Placozoa. It implies either independent evolution̗ in Planulozoa and Ctenophora̗ of a new digestive system with a gut with extracellular digestion̗ which enables feeding on larger organisms̗ or the subsequent loss of this new gut in the Poriferans (and the re-evolution of the collar complex). The major losses implied in the Ctenophora-first theory show absolutely no adaptational advantages. Thus̗ morphology gives very strong support for the Porifera-first hypothesis.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
1. Introduction

</title>
         <p>
Until recently̗ the poriferans have almost unanimously been regarded as the sister group of all other animals. Haeckel [

] even placed them with the 
‘
protists 
’
̗ outside the animals. However̗ the position of the poriferans as the sister group of the eumetazoans became challenged when large phylogenomic studies including two ctenophore genomes showed the Ctenophora as the sister group to all the other metazoans [2̗3]. Several later phylogenomic studies have found support for this 
‘
Ctenophora-first 
’
theory [4̗5]. However̗ another set of large phylogenomic studies favour the alternative 
‘
Porifera-first 
’
theory [

–

].
</p>
         <p>Some recent phylogenomic studies simply conclude that the position of deep-diverging lineages̗ such as the ctenophores̗ may exceed the limit of resolution afforded by the traditional phylogenomic analyses [4̗10̗11]. It therefore appears timely to see if a phylogenetic hypothesis can be constructed based exclusively on morphology in the widest sense̗ i.e. including molecules̗ for comparison with the phylogenomic hypotheses.</p>
         <p>
The review is almost exclusively based on papers which contain information about the Choanoflagellata and the four major metazoan groups̗ Porifera̗ Cnidaria (as a representative of the Planulozoa̗ i.e. Cnidaria + 
<tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
)̗ Placozoa and Ctenophora.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
2. The sister group of the Metazoa: Choanoflagellata

</title>
         <p>
Almost all recent authors regard the choanoflagellates as the sister group of the metazoans [

]. The closest outgroups̗ ichthyosporeans and filastraeans are parasites or commensals̗ with life cycles comprising uninucleate̗ opisthokont swarmers and colonial or plasmodial adults [

]. They may all be haploid [

]. The ichthyosporean 
Sphaeroforma arctica
has a multinucleate stage̗ and cellularization leads to the formation of a polarized layer of individual cells resembling an epithelium without a basement membrane [

].
</p>
         <p>
The choanoflagellates are solitary or colonial organisms with a 
‘
collar complex 
’
consisting of an undulating cilium (usually called flagellum)̗ with a vane̗ surrounded by a conical collar of microvilli [12̗16] (
table 1
). Unicellularity precludes differentiation into non-feeding cell types̗ because there is no exchange of nutrients between the cells. The cilium propels water away from the cell body (opisthokont)̗ and microscopic particles̗ mostly bacteria̗ are caught at the outside of the collar and ingested by pseudopodia. Digestion is poorly known̗ but it is believed that the particles disintegrate inside a vacuole and the molecules become absorbed. Sexual reproduction seems to be rare̗ but isogamy (or slightly different sizes of otherwise similar gametes) has been observed in cultures of 
Salpingoeca rosetta
[30̗31]. The cells are haploid̗ but a short diploid phase after fertilization may occur [

].
</p>
         <p>Large numbers of genes involved in organizing structures in metazoans̗ such as epithelia and nervous systems̗ are present already in choanoflagellates̗ where their functions are unknown [13̗28̗35]. Obviously̗ the presence of such genes̗ as̗ for example̗ genes of the postsynaptic scaffold found in choanoflagellates and poriferans [11̗36]̗ does not indicate that these organisms are descendants of organisms with a nervous system!</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
3. Origin of the Metazoa (Animalia): the latest common ancestorı choanoblastaea

</title>
         <p>
It is generally hypothesized that the sponges evolved from clonal colonies of choanoflagellate-like ancestors [

]̗ perhaps via a 
‘
rosetta 
’
stage [

].
</p>
         <p>Choanoflagellates and choanocytes are generally very similar̗ most differences probably being related to their different positions̗ choanoflagellates being single cells or cells in small colonies̗ whereas the sponge choanocytes are arranged in choanocyte chambers situated in interior water canals [16̗34].</p>
         <p>
Evolution of the ancestral metazoan̗ choanoblastaea̗ probably passed from a sphere of clonal̗ feeding choanoflagellates to the multicellular ancestor [37̗38]. The establishment of an epithelium with tight cell contacts [

] enabled the exchange of nutrients between the cells̗ and this made the evolution of non-feeding cells possible̗ both cells at the surface of the sphere and internal cells. Many types of ciliated eumetazoan cells show their evolution from choanoblastaea cells̗ having a ring of shorter or longer stiff microvilli around a non-contractile cilium̗ for example̗ many types of sensory cells and the weir cells in protonephridia̗ but their function is never particle collecting [

]; these cells have been called choanocytes but are better-called collar cells. The sharing of nutrients paved the way to other metazoan specializations̗ such as oogamy and diploidy [

]. A stabilizing basement membrane probably evolved at an early point. The associated collagen IV is present in all the metazoan groups but absent in the demosponge 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amphimedon
</tp:taxon-name>
[

]. The occurrence of the basement membrane is scattered in the non-bilaterian animals̗ with presence or absence in sponges and ctenophores̗ absence in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
and presence in cnidarians and in almost all bilaterians (
table 1
).
</p>
         <p>
There is an impressive addition of novel genes and gene families at the base of the Metazoa [

]̗ for example̗ cell 
–
cell adhesion by β- catenin regulated cadherins and developmental signalling pathways̗ such as WNT and transforming growth factor-β [13̗25̗40 
–
42].
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
4. Origin and evolution of the Porifera

</title>
         <p>
There are different theories for the origin of the sponges [

] but only the theory of Nielsen [

] presents a continuous series of evolutionary stages based on changes in structure and function. This theory explains how an advanced choanoblastaea settled by an area of unciliated cells and organized the choanocytes in a groove̗ and how this groove became transformed into a choanocyte chamber. This was the ancestral sponge̗ which with increasing body size developed more choanocyte chambers organized in an aquiferous system.
</p>
         <p>
Digestion is intracellular [32̗33]̗ as that of the choanoflagellates̗ with particles in vacuoles disintegrating̗ apparently without being digested by enzymes [

]. One clade of demosponges [

] has lost the collar chambers and specialized in feeding on small captured animals̗ such as crustaceans; the digestion is again intracellular without secreted enzymes [

].
</p>
         <p>Sponges have epithelia with various types of cell junctions [23̗29].</p>
         <p>
Muscle cells do not occur in the sponges̗ but the whole body and̗ for example̗ the ostia of demosponges can change the shape by contraction of the pinacoderm̗ and small specimens can even crawl on the substratum [46̗47]. The 
‘
myocytes 
’
(actinocytes) of the mesohyle have been reported to be contractile̗ but this is uncertain [

].
</p>
         <p>
The sponges lack a nervous system̗ but demosponge behaviour indicates communication between cells [49̗50]. Cells at the oscula with a short̗ stiff cilium are supposed to be sensory [

]. In the hexactinellids̗ ciliary activity is controlled by electrical impulses in the whole syncytium [

]. The lack of a nervous system has been interpreted as a loss [

]̗ but the explanation is highly imaginative!
</p>
         <p>
Some early steroid sponge-markers are from the Ediacaran̗ 
ca
660 
–
635 Ma [

]̗ but this has been questioned [

]. The earliest reasonably certain sponge spicules are from the earliest Cambrian̗ about 540 Ma [

]. This has been characterized as a 
‘
fossil gap 
’
[

]̗ but it should be remembered that the defining character of a sponge is the presence of an aquiferous system with choanocyte chambers̗ not the presence of a skeleton̗ so the poriferan ancestor must have preceded an ancestral 
‘
thin-walled̗ hexactine-based sponge 
’
[

]. It is much more probable that the earliest sponges were small and without a skeleton̗ and that they therefore have left no body fossils.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
5. Origin of the Eumetazoa: the latest common ancestor: gastraea

</title>
         <p>
The eumetazoans comprise three main groups̗ Planulozoa (Cnidaria + 
<tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
̗ in the following discussion represented by the Cnidaria)̗ Placozoa and Ctenophora. The most obvious character̗ which distinguishes the eumetazoans from the sponges is the division of the epithelium into an inner or 
‘
ventral 
’
layer of digestive cells̗ endoderm̗ and an outer or 
‘
dorsal 
’
protective ectoderm. This was probably followed by a loss of digestive functions in the ectodermal cells [

]. The digestive epithelium is invaginated as an archenteron in planulozoans and ctenophores but forms a creeping sole in the placozoans. Digestion is extracellular with digestive enzymes secreted into the archenteron (or in placozoans into a temporarily sealed space between the endoderm and the substratum)̗ and digested materials become absorbed by the endodermal cells. Unfortunately̗ there seems to be no study of the digestive enzymes of placozoans and ctenophores̗ which could provide important phylogenetic information. The new organization of feeding and digestion opens up a wealth of new lifestyles̗ and the morphological diversity of the eumetazoans is enormous compared to that of the sessile poriferans̗ which are limited to feeding on bacteria and small particles. The Ctenophora-first theory implies either that the poriferans lost the gut and reverted to intracellular digestion or that gut and extracellular digestion evolved convergently in ctenophores and parahoxozoans; both possibilities appear highly improbable.
</p>
         <p>
Movements were mainly by cilia on monociliate cells̗ but changes in shape may have been possible through contractions of actin filaments̗ as seen in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
(see below). A nervous system and muscles were not present̗ but the cells could have had peptidergic communication̗ as seen in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
[

].
</p>
         <p>
A large number of genes found in the eumetazoans are absent from the poriferans [

]̗ and a number is absent from the ctenophores too [

].
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
6. Evolution of the Eumetazoa: the relationship between Cnidaria and Ctenophora

</title>
         <p>
The classical Coelenterata hypothesis was based mainly on general morphological similarities between the pelagic medusa and the (usually) pelagic ctenophores̗ but the ancestral cnidarian was most likely a polyp [

]. The two groups share a general body organization with ectoderm and invaginated digestive endoderm (characteristic of the gastraea)̗ but when studied more closely̗ the differences between the two groups become very apparent̗ indicating separate evolution from the gastraea [

].
</p>
         <p>
The cnidarian larvae have an apical organ with a tuft of cilia̗ like that of many ciliated bilaterian larvae; this organ is probably a chemoreceptor related to larval metamorphosis [

]. The ctenophores lack a primary larva and hatch as small juveniles̗ which have an obviously non-homologous aboral organ (retained in the adults) with a dome of cilia covering four compound balancer cilia supporting a ball of statoliths̗ i.e. a gravity-sensing organ [19̗61̗62].
</p>
         <p>
The cnidarians have cnidae̗ cells containing a collagen-like sphere with an invaginated tube̗ which can be everted and inject various toxins into prey or predator [

]̗ and the ctenophores have colloblasts̗ mushroom-shaped cells with numerous vesicles with adhesive substances [

]. The cnidae found in the ctenophore 
<tp:taxon-name>
Haeckelia
</tp:taxon-name>
originate from ingested medusae [

].
</p>
         <p>The cnidarian gut is a sac with only one opening̗ functioning as both mouth and anus̗ whereas the ctenophores have a gut with a mouth̗ a stomach and a pair of anal canals leading to temporal anal openings (pores) [19̗64̗65].</p>
         <p>
Cnidarians have myoepithelial cells (and the bilaterians additionally have mesodermal muscles)̗ whereas the ctenophores have both an epithelial net of muscles and mesogloeal myocytes [19̗22̗61]. The majority of signalling molecules and transcription factors involved in specifying and differentiating the mesoderm of bilaterian animals are absent in the ctenophore 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mnemiopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
[

]. Striated muscle cells are found in most bilaterians̗ but the scattered occurrence in the tentillae of the ctenophore 
Euplokamis
and in the hypocodon of hydrozoan medusae [

] must be regarded as homoplasies [

].
</p>
         <p>
The ability to communicate fast and precisely between cells/organs in the more active eumetazoans is necessary for their more active̗ often vagile lifestyles. This is made possible through the evolution of nervous systems. These systems consist of neurons̗ i.e. cells dedicated to transmitting information from one cell to another̗ usually through electric impulses. A neuron consists of a cell body with the nucleus (perikaryon) usually with a long̗ thin neurite; bundles of neurites are called nerves [67̗68]. Connections between the cells are of two types̗ chemical (synapses) and electrical (gap junctions). Cnidarians and ctenophores have nervous systems without a brain̗ whereas the bilaterians have a ventral nervous system and an anterior̗ dorsal brain [

]. The prevailing theory for the evolution of the nervous system appears to be that of Mackie [

]̗ which proposes that neurons and myocytes differentiated from myoepithelial cells. This could well have taken place more than once̗ as suggested by a number of studies [3̗71]. However̗ other theories have been proposed [

].
</p>
         <p>
The synapses of cnidarians (and bilaterians) generally have the 
‘
usual 
’
ultrastructure with a simple arrangement of synaptic vesicles along the contact with the effector cell [

]̗ whereas the ctenophore synapses show a specialized 
‘
triad 
’
structure with a series of vesicles and a thin extension of the endoplasmatic reticulum along the cell contacts [74̗75]. The isolated occurrence of bidirectional̗ triad-like synapses in the medusa of the scyphozoan 
Cyanea
[76̗77] is most likely a homoplasy.
</p>
         <p>
There are major differences between the neurotransmitters in the cnidarian-bilaterian synapses̗ which use̗ e.g. acetylcholine̗ glutamate and GABA (here called neurotransmitters A)̗ and the ctenophores̗ with mainly peptidergic synapses (here called neurotransmitters B) [

]; the two groups do not share any of the specific neurotransmitters [

]. This is a strong indication of a separate evolution of synapses in cnidarians and ctenophores. Also̗ the neuronal-specific genes of the two groups are completely different̗ with the ctenophores lacking̗ for example̗ neurogenins̗ NeuroD̗ Achaete-scute̗ REST̗ HOX and Otx [3̗71].
</p>
         <p>
Invertebrate gap junctions consist of a ring of eight innexin units̗ surrounding a pore which can be opened and closed [

]. These pores permit the exchange of small molecules between the cells and transmission of electrical impulses [

]. This type of cell junctions is present in cnidarians (and bilaterians) and ctenophores̗ but although there is a considerable variation in the innexins of planulozoans and ctenophores̗ the high number of special innexis in the ctenophores could indicate independent evolution [

].
</p>
         <p>
Important components of the HIF respiratory pathway are only found in placozoans̗ cnidarians and bilaterians [

].
</p>
         <p>Based on these characters̗ it appears probable that Cnidaria (+ Placozoa̗ see below) and Ctenophora are sister groups̗ which evolved independently from the advanced gastraea. This implies that both nervous system and mesoderm evolved convergently in the two groups.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

7. Origin of the Parahoxozoaı i.e. Placozoa + Cnidaria (+ 
<tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
)


</title>
         <p>
It is difficult to identify distinguishing characters of this group̗ which̗ however̗ seems to be found in the majority of the phylogenomic analyses [6̗8̗80 
–
82]. Most of these analyses resolve the interrelationships of the three groups as Placozoa + (Cnidaria + 
<tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
)̗ but the topology (Placozoa + Cnidaria) + 
<tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
has been found in some recent studies [

]. The group has been named after the Parahox genes̗ which are found in all planulozoans (Cnidaria + 
<tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
). A Parahox-like gene̗ 
Trox-2
̗ is found in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
̗ although the authors note that this could be either a true ParaHox gene (
Gsx
) or a 
‘
ProtoHox 
’
gene diverging before distinct Hox and ParaHox genes arose [

]. Either possibility is consistent with a clade comprising Placozoa̗ Cnidaria and 
<tp:taxon-name>Bilateria</tp:taxon-name>
. The interpretation of this as a synapomorphy uniting these three groups was challenged by the discovery of a putative Parahox gene (
Cdx
) in calcareous sponges [

]; however̗ this is still being discussed [

].
</p>
         <p>
The basement membrane contains nidogen and perlecan̗ which are restricted to the Parahoxozoa [

]. Also̗ the Zic genes seem to be restricted to placozoans and planulozoans; they are expressed at the lateral edges of the neural plate in nematodes̗ annelids and chordates [

]. Only the parahoxozoans have the complete HIF respiratory pathway [

].
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
8. Morphology and position of the Placozoa

</title>
         <p>
The flattened̗ amoeboid placozoans consist of a pseudostratified 
‘
ventral 
’
epithelium̗ which serves as a digestive creeping sole̗ consisting mainly of monociliate cells with long microvilli̗ and a 
‘
dorsal 
’
ectoderm consisting of thin monociliate cells. The 
‘
dorsal 
–
ventral 
’
orientation is supported by studies of gene expression [

]. Between these layers are found a number of fibre cells with long̗ branching processes̗ which contact all epithelial cells without forming organized junctions [26̗88]. The 
‘
amoeboid 
’
movements of the organism appear to be caused by the contraction of actin filaments in the fibre cells [89̗90]. There is no nervous system̗ but peptidergic signalling between the various cells induces various types of behaviour [

]̗ and a ring of gland cells at the periphery are FRMFamide immunoreactive [

]. The epithelial cells are united by adherens junctions with apical actin networks [

]̗ and contractions of this network may contribute to changes in the shape of the body [

]. Cells in the lower epithelium secrete digestive enzymes into the sealed space between the epithelium and the substratum̗ and digested material becomes absorbed [

].
</p>
         <p>
For many years̗ only one placozoan species̗ 

<tp:taxon-name>Trichoplax</tp:taxon-name>
adherens

̗ was recognized̗ but molecular studies have revealed a considerable diversity of species [

]̗ and new genera are now being described [

].
</p>
         <p>
The Ediacaran fossil 
Dickinsonia
(571 
–
541 Ma) could perhaps best be interpreted as an upper̗ protective sheet of a placozoan (see also [

]).
</p>
         <p>
The interpretation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichoplax
</tp:taxon-name>
as a descendant of the gastraea implies that the gastraean ancestor expanded the periphery of the body with the ciliated digestive endoderm becoming the creeping digestive sole. At first̗ this appears less plausible̗ but a similar lifestyle is actually seen in the polyp stage of the hydrozoan 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polypodium
</tp:taxon-name>
̗ which lives parasitic in eggs of sturgeons. Inside the sturgeon egg̗ the zygote develops into a planula-like larva̗ but with an outer layer of monociliated digestive cells̗ which later becomes the endoderm̗ surrounding an inner layer̗ which becomes the ectoderm. An inverted stolon with polypide buds develops inside the endoderm̗ and when released̗ the 
‘
larva 
’
evaginates the stolon with the polyps̗ which begin to feed and produce small medusae [

].
</p>
         <p>
The 
‘
opposite 
’
theory̗ the plakula theory̗ proposes that the placozoans represent the ancestral eumetazoan type [

]. This is purely speculative̗ and a flat plakula stage has never been observed in the ontogeny of any eumetazoan̗ whereas a gastrula stage has been observed in the ontogeny of almost all eumetazoan phyla [

].
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
9. Discussion

</title>
         <p>When the major characters discussed above are plotted onto the phylogenetic branching patterns of the Porifera-first and Ctenophora-first hypotheses̗ a clear picture emerges. Both hypotheses imply that the nervous systems have evolved independently in planulozoans and ctenophorans̗ so this character has been omitted in the trees.</p>
         <p>
The Porifera-first hypothesis (
figure 1
) shows a number of apomorphies in each lineage and no symplesiomorphies or losses (except the loss of the choanocyte collar in connection with the transition to the new mode of feeding/digestion). It resembles 
‘
traditional 
’
morphology-based phylogenies but places the Ctenophora as the sister group of the Parahoxozoa (Placozoa + Planulozoa). At first̗ this position appears counterintuitive̗ but it is strongly supported both by most of the phylogenomic studies and by characters from morphology̗ as shown above.
</p>
         <p>
The branching pattern of the Ctenophora-first hypothesis implies either a tree based on homoplasies (
figure 2
) or a tree based on losses (
figure 3
). Both trees show a lineage of Porifera + Cnidaria + Placozoa without any synapomorphies. The first tree (
figure 2
) shows that the new digestive system (gut) consisting of a digestive endoderm and extracellular digestion should have evolved independently in Ctenophora + Placozoa and Ctenophora from an advanced choanoblastaea without differentiation of ectoderm and endoderm and with intracellular digestion. This appears quite unlikely̗ but studies on the almost unknown digestion of placozoans and ctenophores could throw light on the homology question. The second tree (
figure 3
) shows that the Porifera should have evolved from a gastraea through the loss of the gut (as described above) and the re-evolution of the collar complex. It implies the loss of the ability to ingest and digest larger organisms̗ and it is very difficult to see any evolutionary advantage of such a loss. Furthermore̗ a number of characteristic eumetazoan genes should have been lost.
</p>
         <p>It must be concluded that the Porifera-first hypothesis finds full support from morphology̗ whereas the Ctenophora hypothesis implies groups with no synapomorphies and various evolutionary changes which appears most unlikely.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Data accessibility.
This article has no additional data.
</p>
         <p>
Competing interests.
The author declares that he has no competing interests.
</p>
         <p>
Funding.
I received no funding for this study.
</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgements.
The author is much indebted to Dr Peter 
Holland
(University of Oxford) for constructive comments to an earlier version of the manuscript. The input from two anonymous reviewers is greatly appreciated.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References

</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1.
Haeckel E.
1866

Generelle Morphologie der Organismen

. 

2 Vols. Berlinı 
Germany
: Georg Reimer

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

2. 
Ryan JF
et al.
2013

The genome of the ctenophore 
Mnemiopsis leidyi
and its implications for cell type evolution

. 

Science

342
ı 
1242592
. (
doi:10.1126/science.1242592)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

3. 
Moroz LL
et al.
2014
The ctenophore genome and the evolutionary origins of neural systems
. 

Nature

510
ı 

109 
–
114

. (doi:10.1038/ nature13400)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


4. 
Shen X-Xı
Hittinger CTı Rokas A.
2017
Contentious relationships in phylogenomic studies can be driven by a handful of genes

. 

Nat. Ecol. Evol.

1
ı 0126. (
doi:10.1038/s41559-
017-0126)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


5. 
Whelan NVı Kocot KMı Moroz TPı Mukherjee Kı Williams Pı Paulay Gı Moroz LLı Halanych KM
. 
2017
Ctenophore relationships and their placement as the sister group to all other animals

. 

Nat. Ecol. Evol.
1ı


1737 
–
1746

. (doi:10. 1038/s41559-017-0331-3)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


6. 
Pisani Dı Pett Wı Dohrmann Mı Feuda Rı
Rota- Stabelli Oı Philippe Hı Lartillot Nı Wörheide G. 
2015
Genomic data do not support comb jellies as the sister group to all other animals

. 


Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. 
USA


112ı 
15

402 
–
15

407. (
doi:10.1073/pnas.1518127112)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


7. 
Feuda Rı Dohrmann Mı Pett Wı Philippe Hı Rota-Stabelli Oı Lartillot Nı Wörheide Gı Pisani D.
2017
Improved modeling of compositional heterogeneity supports sponges as sister to all other animals

. 

Curr. Biol.

27
ı 

3864 
–
3870

. (
doi:10.1016/j.cub.2017.11.008)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

8. 
Simion P
et al.
2017
A large and consistent phylogenomic dataset supports sponges as the sister group to all other animals
. 

Curr. Biol.

27
ı 

958 
–
967

. (
doi:10.1016/j.cub.2017.02.031)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


9.
Laumer CEı Gruber-Vodicka Hı Hadfield MGı Pearse VBı Riesgo Aı Marioni JCı Giribet G.
2018
Support for a clade of Placozoa and Cnidaria in genes with minimal compositional bias

. 

eLife

7
ı e 
36278
. (
doi:10.7554/eLife.36278)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
10
. 

Pett Wı Adamski Mı Adamska Mı Francis WRı Eitel Mı Pisani Dı Wörheide G.
2019

The role of homology and orthology in the phylogenomic 


analysis of metazoan gene content. 

Mol. Biol. Evol.


36
ı


643 
–
649

. (
doi:10.1093/molbev/
msz013)




</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


11. 
Burkhardt Pı Sprecher SG
. 
2017
Evolutionary origin of synapses and neurons 
–
bridging the gap

. 

Bioessays

39
ı 
1700024
. (
doi:10.1002/bies
. 201700024)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


12. 
Brunet Tı King N.
2017
The origin of animal multicellularity and cell differentiation

. 

Dev. Cell.

43
ı 

124 
–
140

. (
doi:10.1016/j.devcel.2017.09.016)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


13. 
Sebé-Pedrós Aı Degnan BMı Ruiz-Trillo I
. 
2017
The origin of Metazoa: a unicellular perspective

. 

Nat. Rev. Genet.

18
ı 
498
. (doi:10. 1038/nrg.2017.21)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

14. 
Marshall WLı Berbee ML
. 
2010

Population-level analyses indirectly reveal cryptic sex and life history traits of 
Pseudoperkinsus tapetis
(Ichthyosporeaı Opisthokonta): a unicellular relative of the animals

. 

Mol. Biol. Evol
.

27ı 

2014 
–
2026

. (
doi:10.1093/molbev/msq078)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


15.
Dudin Oı Ondracka Aı Grau-Bové Xı Haraldsen AAı Toyoda Aı Suga Hı Brate Jı Ruiz-Trillo I
. 
2019
A unicellular relative of animals generates an epithelium-like cell layer by actomyosindependent cellularization

. 

bioRxiv

563726
. (
doi:10.1101/563726)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


16. 

Laundon Dı Larson BTı 
McDonald
Kı King Nı Burkhardt P.

2019
The architecture of cell differentiation in choanoflagellates and sponge choanocytes

. 

PLoS Biol.

17
ı e 
3000226
. (doi:10. 1371/journal.pbio.3000226)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


17. 
Franc JM
. 
1978
Organization and function of ctenophore colloblasts: an ultrastructural study

. 

Biol. Bull. Woods Hole

155
ı 

527 
–
541

. (doi:10. 2307/1540788)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


18. 
Moroz LLı Kohn AB
. 
2015
Unbiased view of synaptic and neuronal gene complement in ctenophores: are there pan-neuronal and pansynaptic genes across Metazoa?


Integr. Comp. Biol.

55
ı 

1028 
–
1049

. (
doi:10.1093/icb/icv104)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

19.
Norekian TPı Moroz LL
. 
2019

Neuromuscular organization of the ctenophore 
Pleurobrachia bachei

. 

J. Comp. Neurol.

527
ı 

406 
–
436

. (doi:10. 1002/cne.24546)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


20. 
Marlow Hı Tosches Mı Tomer Rı Steinmetz Pı Lauri Aı Larsson Tı Arendt D.
2014
Larval body


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

patterning and apical organs are conserved in animal evolution
. 

BMC Biol
.


12ı 7. (doi:10.1186/ 
1741
-7007

- 
12-7
)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


21. 
David CNı Özbek Sı Adamczyk Pı Meier Sı Pauly Bı Chapman Jı Hwang JSı Gojobori Tı Holstein TW
. 
2008
Evolution of complex structures: minicollagens shape the cnidarian nematocyst

. 

Trends Genet.

24
ı 

431 
–
438

. (
doi:10.1016/j.tig
. 2008.07.001)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


22. 
Dayraud Cı Alié Aı Jager Mı Chang Pı Le Guyader Hı Manuel Mı Quéinnec E.
2012
Independent specialisation of myosin II paralogues in muscle vs. non-muscle functions during early animal evolution: a ctenophore perspective

. 

BMC Evol. Biol.
12ı 107.

(doi:10. 
1186
/ 
1471-2148
-12-107)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

23. 
Fidler AL
et al.
2017
Collagen IV and basement membrane at the evolutionary dawn of metazoan tissues
. 

eLife

6
ı e 
24176
. (doi:10.7554/ eLife.24176)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


24. 
Mills DBı Francis WRı Vargas Sı Larsen Mı Elemans CPHı Canfield DEı Wörheide G.
2018
The last common ancestor of animals lacked the HIF pathway and respired in low-oxygen environments

. 

eLife

7
ı e 
31176
. (doi:10.7554/ eLife.31176)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


25. 
Srivastava M.
2015
A comparative genomics perspective on the origin of multicellularity and early animal evolution

. In 

Evolutionary transitions to multicellular life: principles and mechanisms

(eds 
I Ruiz-Trilloı AM Nedelcu
) 
ı pp.

269 
–
299

. 

Dordrechtı 
The Netherlands
: Springer

.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

26. 
Smith CLı Pivovarova Nı Reese TS
. 
2015

Coordinated feeding behavior in 
Trichoplax
ı an animal without synapses

. 

PLoS ONE

10
ı e 
0136098
. (
doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0136098)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


27.
Hashimshony Tı Feder Mı Levin Mı Hall BKı Yanai I
. 
2015
Spatiotemporal transcriptomics reveals the evolutionary history of the endoderm germ layer

. 

Nature

519
ı 

219 
–
222

. (
doi:10.1038/nature13996)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
28.

Srivastava M
et al
. 
2010

The 
Amphimedon queenslandica
genome and the evolution of animal complexity

. 

Nature

466
ı 

720 
–
726

. (
doi:10.1038/nature09201)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
29.
Leys SPı Nichols SAı Adams EDM
. 
2009
Epithelia and integration in sponges
. 

Integr. Comp. Biol.

49
ı 

167 
–
177

. (

doi:10.1093/icb/icp038
)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


30. 

Levin 
TCı
King N.

2013
Evidence for sex and recombination in the choanoflagellate Salpingoeca rosetta

. 

Curr. Biol

. 23ı 

2176 
–
2180

. (
doi:10.1016/j.cub.2013.08.061)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


31. 
Woznica Aı Gerdt JPı Hulett REı Clardy Jı King N.
2017
Mating in the closest living relatives of animals is induced by a bacterial chondroitinase

. 

Cell

170
ı 

1175 
–
1183

.e1111. (
doi:10.1016/j.cell
. 2017.08.005)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

32. 
Simpson TL
. 
1984

The cell biology of sponges

. 
New Yorkı NY: Springer
.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

33. 
Vacelet Jı Duport E.
2004

Prey capture and digestion in the carnivorous sponge 
Asbestopluma hypogea
(Porifera: Demospongiae)

. 

Zoomorphology

123
ı 

179 
–
190

. (doi:10.1007/ s00435-004-0100-0)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


34. 
Mah JLı Christensen-Dalsgaard KKı Leys SP
. 
2014
Choanoflagellate and choanocyte collarflagellar systems and the assumption of homology

. 

Evol. Dev.

16
ı

25 
–
37

. (doi:10.1111/ ede.12060)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


35. 
Liebeskind BJı Hofmann HAı Hillis DMı Zakon HH
. 
2017
Evolution of animal neural systems

. 

Annu. Rev. Ecol. Evol. Syst.

48
ı 

377 
–
398

. (
doi:10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-110316-
023048)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

36. 
Burkhardt Pı Stegmann CMı Cooper Bı Kloepper THı Imig Cı Varoqueaux Fı Wahl MCı Fasshauer D.
2011

Primordial neurosecretory apparatus identified in the choanoflagellate 
Monosiga brevicollis

. 


Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. 
USA


108ı 
15
264 
–
15 
269
. (
doi:10.1073/pnas.1106189108)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


37. 
Nielsen C.
2008
Six major steps in animal evolution: are we derived sponge larvae?


Evol. Dev.

10
ı 

241 
–
257

. (
doi:10.1111/j.1525-142X
. 2008.00231.x)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


38. 
Arendt Dı Benito-Gutierrez Eı Brunet Tı Marlow H.
2015
Gastric pouches and the mucociliary sole: setting the stage for nervous system evolution

. 

Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B

370
ı 
20150286
. (
doi:10.1098/rstb.2015.0286)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


39. 
Richter DJı King N.
2013
The genomic and cellular foundations of animal origins

. 

Annu. Rev. Genet.

47
ı 

509 
–
537

. (
doi:10.1146/annurevgenet-111212-133456)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


40. 

Paps Jı 
Holland
PWH

. 
2018
Reconstruction of the ancestral metazoan genome reveals an increase in genomic novelty

. 

Nat. Commun.
9ı 1730

. (
doi:10.1038/s41467-018-04136-5)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


41. de Mendoza Aı Sebé-Pedrós Aı
Š 
estak MSı Matej
č 
i
ć 
Mı Torruella Gı Domazet-Lo
š 

o Tı Ruiz- 
Trillo I.
2013
Transcription factor evolution in eukaryotes and the assembly of the regulatory toolkit in multicellular lineages. 


Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. 
USA


110
ı E 

4858 
–
E4866

. (
doi:10.1073/pnas
. 1311818110)



</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

42.

Paps J.
2018
What makes an animal? The molecular quest for the origin of the animal kingdom. Integr. Comp. Biol. 58ı
654–665
.


(
doi:10.1093/icb/icy036)


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
43
. 

Cavalier-Smith T.
2017

Origin of animal multicellularity: precursorsı causesı consequences 
—
the choanoflagellate/sponge transitionı neurogenesis and the Cambrian explosion

. 

Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B

372
ı 
20150476
. (
doi:10.1098/rstb.2015.0476)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

44. 
Imsiecke G.
1993

Ingestionı digestionı and egestion in 
Spongilla lacustris
(Poriferaı Spongillidae) after pulse feeding with 
Chlamydomonas reinhardtii
(Volvocales)

. 

Zoomorphology

113
ı 

233 
–
244

. (doi:10.1007/ bf00403314)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


45. 
Hestetun JTı Vacelet Jı Boury-Esnault Nı Borchiellini Cı Kelly Mı Ríos Pı Cristobo Jı Rapp HT
. 
2016
The systematics of carnivorous sponges

. 

Mol. Phylogenet. Evol.

94
ı 

327 
–
345

. (
doi:10.1016/j.ympev.2015.08.022)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

46. 
Nickel Mı Scheer Cı Hammel JUı Herzen Jı Beckmann F.
2011

The contractile sponge epithelium 
sensu lato –
body contraction of the demosponge 
Tethya wilhelma
is mediated by the pinacoderm

. 

J. Exp. Biol.

214
ı 
1692
. (doi:10. 1242/jeb.049148)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


47. 
Elliott GRDı Leys SP
. 
2007
Coordinated contractions effectively expel water from the aquiferous system of a freshwater sponge

. 

J. Exp. Biol.

210
ı 
3736
. (
doi:10.1242/jeb
. 003392)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


48. 
Nickel M.
2010
Evolutionary emergence of synaptic nervous systems: what can we learn from the non-synapticı nerveless Porifera?


Invertebr. Biol.

129
ı 

1 
–
16

. (
doi:10.1111/j.1744-
7410.2010.00193.x)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


49. 
Leys SP
. 
2015
Elements of a

‘
nervous system
’

in sponges. 

J. Exp. Biol.

218
ı 

581 
–
591

. (doi:10. 1242/jeb.110817)


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


50. 
Leys SPı Farrar N.
2016
Porifera

. In 

Structure and evolution of invertebrate nervous systems
(eds A Schmidt-Rhaesaı S Harzschı

G Purschke
) 
ı pp.

9 
–
17

. 

Oxfordı 
UK
: Oxford University Press

.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


51.
Ludeman Dı Farrar Nı Riesgo Aı Paps Jı Leys S.
2014
Evolutionary origins of sensation in metazoans: functional evidence for a new sensory organ in sponges

. 

BMC Evol. Biol.

14
ı 
3
. (
doi:10.1186/1471-2148-14-3)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


52. 
Leys SPı Mackie GO
. 
1997
Electrical recording from a glass sponge

. 

Nature

387
ı 

29 
–
30

. (
doi:10.1038/387029b0)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


53. 
Ryan JFı Chiodin M.
2015
Where is my mind? How sponges and placozoans may have lost neural cell types

. 

Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B

370
ı 
20150059
. (
doi:10.1098/rstb.2015.0059)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


54.
Zumberge JAı Love GDı Cárdenas Pı Sperling EAı Gunasekera Sı Rohrssen Mı Grosjean Eı Grotzinger JPı Summons RE
. 
2018
Demosponge steroid biomarker 26-methylstigmastane provides evidence for Neoproterozoic animals

. 

Nat. Ecol. Evol.
2ı


1709 
–
1714

. (doi:10.1038/ s41559-018-0676-2)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

55. 
Nettersheim BJ
et al.
2019

Putative sponge biomarkers in unicellular 
Rhizaria
question an early rise of animals

. 

Nat. Ecol. Evol.

3
ı 

577 
–
581

. (
doi:10.1038/s41559-019-0806-5)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


56.
Botting Pı Muir LA
. 
2018
Early sponge evolution: a review and phylogenetic framework

. 

Palaeoworld

27
ı 

1 
–
29

. (doi:10. 1016/j.palwor.2017.07.001)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


57. 
Botting JPı Nettersheim BJ
. 
2018
Searching for sponge origins

. 

Nat. Ecol. Evol.
2ı


1685 
–
1686

. (
doi:10.1038/s41559-018-0702-4)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


58. 
Varoqueaux Fı Williams EAı Grandemange Sı Truscello Lı Kamm Kı Schierwater Bı Jékely Gı Fasshauer D.
2018
High cell diversity and complex peptidergic signaling underlie placozoan behavior

. 

Curr. Biol.

28
ı


3495 
–
3501

.e3492. (

doi:10.1016/j.cub. 
2018

.
08.067)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


59. 

Kayal Eı Bentlage Bı 
Sabrina Pankey Mı Ohdera
AHı 
Medina Mı Plachetzki
DCı Collins AGı Ryan JF

. 

2018

Phylogenomics provides a robust topology of the major cnidarian lineages and insights on the origins of key organismal traits

. 

BMC Evol. Biol.


18
ı 
68

. (

doi:10.1186/s12862-018- 
1142
-0)


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


60.
Harbison GR
. 

1985

On the classification and evolution of the Ctenophora

. In 

The origins and relationships of lower invertebrates

(ed 
S Conway Morris
) 
ı pp.

78 
–
100

. 

Oxfordı 
UK
: Oxford University Press

.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


61. 
Jager Mı Chiori Rı Alié Aı Dayraud Cı Quéinnec Eı Manuel M.

2011

New insights on ctenophore neural anatomy: immunofluorescence study in 

Pleurobrachia pileus
(Müllerı 1776)


. 

J. Exp. Zool. (Mol. Dev. Evol.)

316
Bı 

171 
–
187

. (doi:10.1002/ jez.b.21386)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>



62. 
Tamm SL
. 

1982

Ctenophora

. In 

Electrical conduction and behaviour in


‘ 
simple
’ 

invertebrates (ed. 
GAB Shelton
) 
ı pp.

266 
–
358

. 

Oxfordı 
UK
: Oxford University Press

.


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


63. 
Mills CEı Miller RL
. 

1984

Ingestion of a medusa (

Aegina citrea

) by the nematocyst-containing ctenophore 

Haeckelia rubra

(formerly 

Euchlora rubra

): phylogenetic implications

. 

Mar. Biol.


78
ı


215 
–
221

. (
doi:10.1007/BF00394704)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


64. 
Presnell JSı Vandepas LEı Warren KJı Swalla BJı Amemiya CTı Browne WE
. 

2016

The presence of a functionally tripartite through-gut in Ctenophora has implications for metazoan character trait evolution

. 

Curr. Biol
.

26 

ı 

2814
–
2820


. (
doi:10.1016/j.cub.2016.08.019)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

65. 
Tamm SL

2019


Defecation by the ctenophore 

Mnemiopsis leidyi

occurs with an ultradian rhythm through a single transient anal pore

. 

Invertebr. Biol.

138

ı 

3 
–
16

.

(
doi:10.1111/ivb
. 12236)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

66. 
Steinmetz PRH
et al.

2012

Independent evolution of striated muscles in cnidarians and bilaterians
. 

Nature

487
ı 

231 
–
234

. (doi:10.1038/ nature11180)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

67. 
Schmidt-Rhaesa A.

2007


The evolution of organ systems

. 

Oxfordı 
UK
: Oxford University Press

.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

68. 
Richter S
et al.

2010

Invertebrate neurophylogeny: suggested terms and definitions for a neuroanatomical glossary
. 

Front. Zool.


7
ı 
29

. (

doi:10.1186/ 
1742
-9994-7-29)


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

69. 
Nielsen C.

2012


Animal evolution: interrelationships of the living phyla
ı 3rd
edn

. 

Oxfordı 
UK
: Oxford University Press

.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


70. 
Mackie GO
. 

1970

Neuroid conduction and the evolution of conducting tissues

. 

Q. Rev. Biol.


45
ı


319 
–
332

. (
doi:10.1086/406645)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


71. 
Moroz LLı Kohn AB
. 

2016

Independent origins of neurons and synapses: insights from ctenophores

. 

Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B

371
ı 
20150041
. (
doi:10.1098/rstb.2015.0041)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


72. 
Jékely Gı Keijzer Fı Godfrey-Smith P

2015

An option space for early neural evolution

. 

Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B

370
ı 
20150181
. (doi:10.1098/ rstb.2015.0181)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


73. 
Westfall JA
. 

1996

Ultrastructure of synapses in the first-evolved nervous systems

. 

J. Neurocytol.


25
ı


735 
–
746

. (
doi:10.1007/bf02284838)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
74
. 

Moroz LL
. 

2015

Convergent evolution of neural systems in ctenophores
. 

J. Exp. Biol.

218
ı 

598 
–
611

. (

doi:10.1242/jeb. 
110692
)


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
75. 
Hernandez-Nicaise M-L.

1973

The nervous system of ctenophores III. Ultrastructure of synapses
. 

J. Neurocytol.


2
ı


249 
–
263

. (doi:10

. 

1007
/bf01104029)


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


76. 
Anderson AV
. 

1985

Physiology of a bidirectionalı excitatoryı chemical synapse

. 

J. Neurophysiol.


53
ı


821 
–
835

. (
doi:10.1152/jn.1985.53.3.821)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


77. 
Horridge GAı Mackay B.

1962

Naked axons and symmetrical synapses in coelenterates

. 

Q. J. Microsc. Sci.

103
ı 

531 
–
541

.

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


78. 
Skerrett IMı Williams JB

2017

A structural and functional comparison of gap junction channels composed of connexins and innexins

. 

Dev. Neurobiol.


77
ı


522 
–
547

. (
doi:10.1002/dneu
. 22447)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


79. 
Abascal Fı Zardoya R.

2013

Evolutionary analyses of gap junction protein families

. 

Biochim. Biophys. Acta Biomembr.



1828
ı


4 
–
14

.

(
doi:10.1016/j.bbamem.2012.02.007)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

80. 
Ryan Jı Pang Kı Mullikin Jı Martindale Mı Baxevanis A.

2010


The homeodomain complement of the ctenophore 

Mnemiopsis leidyi

suggests that Ctenophora and Porifera diverged prior to the ParaHoxozoa

. 

EvoDevo


1
ı

9
. (

doi:10.1186/ 
2041
-9139-1-9)


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

81. 
Collins AG
. 

1998


Evaluating multiple alternative hypotheses for the origin of 

Bilateria

: an analysis of 18S rRNA molecular evidence

. 


Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. 
USA



95
ı

15458
. (doi:10.1073/ pnas.95.26.15458)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

82. 
Eitel M
et al.

2018

Comparative genomics and the nature of placozoan species
. 

PLoS Biol.


16
ı

e 
2005359
. (
doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.2005359)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


83
. 

Jakob Wı Sagasser Sı Dellaporta Sı 
Holland
Pı Kuhn Kı Schierwater B.


2004

The Trox-2 Hox/ ParaHox gene of 

Trichoplax
(Placozoa)

marks an


epithelial boundary. 

Dev. Genes Evol.

214
ı 

170 
–
175

. (
doi:10.1007/s00427-004-0390-8)


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


84. 
Fortunato SAVı Adamski Mı Ramos OMı Leininger Sı Liu Jı Ferrier DEKı Adamska M.

2014

Calcisponges have a ParaHox gene and dynamic expression of dispersed NK homeobox genes

. 

Nature

514
ı 

620 
–
623

. (doi:10.1038/ nature13881)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


85. 
Pastrana CCı DeBiasse MBı Ryan JF
. 

2019

Sponges lack ParaHox genes

. 

Genome Biol. Evol.

11
ı 


1250 
–
1257


. (
doi:10.1093/gbe/evz052)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


86.
Aruga Jı Hatayama M.

2018

Comparative genomics of the Zic family genes

. 

Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.


1046


ı 

3 
–
26


.


(
doi:10.1007/978-981-
10-7311-3_1)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

87. 
Ryan Jı Martindale MQı DuBuc TQ
. 

2019


‘

Dorsalventral
’

genes are part of an ancient axial patterning system: evidence from 

Trichoplax adhaerens
(Placozoa)

. 

Mol. Biol. Evol.


36
ı


966 
–
973

. (
doi:10.1093/molbev/msz025)


</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

88. 
Smith CLı Varoqueaux Fı Kittelmann Mı Azzam RNı Cooper Bı Winters CAı Eitel Mı Fasshauer Dı Reese TS
. 

2014


Novel cell typesı neurosecretory cellsı and body plan of the early-diverging metazoan 

Trichoplax adhaerens


. 

Curr. Biol.
24ı



1565
–
1572


. (
doi:10.1016/j.cub.2014.05.046)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


89.
Syed Tı Schierwater B.

2002

The evolution of the Placozoa: a new morphological model

. 

Senckenb. Lethaea


82
ı


315 
–
324

. (doi:10.1007/ BF03043791)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

90. 
Thiemann Mı Ruthmann A.

1989


Microfilaments and microtubules in isolated fiber cells of 

Trichoplax adhaerens
(Placozoa)


. 

Zoomorphology

109

ı 

89 
–
96


. (
doi:10.1007/BF00312314)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

91.
Schuchert P.

1993



Trichoplax adhaerens

(phylum Placozoa) has cells that react with 

antibodies against the neuropeptide RFamide. 

Acta Zool. (Stockh.)


74
ı


115 
–
117

. (doi:10.1111/ j. 
1463
-6395.1993.tb01227.x)



</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

92. 
Smith CLı Reese TS
. 

2016


Adherens junctions modulate diffusion between epithelial cells in 

Trichoplax adhaerens


. 

Biol. Bull. (Woods Hole)

231
ı 

216 
–
224

. (
doi:10.1086/691069)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


93. 
Armon Sı Bull MSı Aranda-Diaz Aı Prakash M.

2018

Ultrafast epithelial contractions provide insights into contraction speed limits and tissue integrity

. 


Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. 
USA


115
ı E 
10333
. (
doi:10.1073/pnas.1802934115)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>


94. 
Voigt Oı Collins AGı Pearse VBı Pearse JSı Ender Aı Hadrys Hı Schierwater B.

2004

Placozoa 
–
no longer a phylum of one

. 

Curr. Biol.


14
ı

R 

944 
–
R945

. (

doi:10.1016/j.cub. 
2004

. 10.036)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

95. 
Osigus HJı Rolfes Sı Herzog Rı Kamm Kı Schierwater B.

2019


Polyplacotoma mediterranea
is a new ramified placozoan species

. 

Curr. Biol.


29
ı

R 

148 
–
R149

. (

doi:10.1016/j.cub. 
2019

. 01.068)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

96. 
Sperling EAı Vinther J.

2010


A placozoan affinity for 
Dickinsonia
and the evolution of late Proterozoic metazoan feeding modes

. 

Evol. Dev.


12
ı


201 
–
209

. (

doi:10.1111/j. 
1525
-142 
X.2010

. 00404.x)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>

97. 
Raikova EV
. 

1994


Life cycleı cytologyı and morphology of 

Polypodium hydriforme

ı a coelenterate parasite of the eggs of acipenseriform fishes

. 

J. Parasitol.


80
ı 

1 
–
22

.

(
doi:10.2307/3283338)

</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
98.
Osigus H-Jı
Eitel Mı Schierwater B.

2013

Chasing the urmetazoon: striking a blow for quality data?

Mol. Phylogenet. Evol.


66
ı


551 
–
557

. (
doi:10.1016/j.ympev.2012.05.028)
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
