<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1038/s41598-020-64159-1</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Genetic diversity and ecology of coronaviruses hosted by cave-dwelling bats in Gabon</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Genetic diversity and ecology of

coronaviruses hosted by 

cavedwelling bats in 
Gabon</title>
         <p>Gael Darren Maganga1
, 
2

✉, 
<tp:taxon-name>Anaïs Pinto</tp:taxon-name>1
, 
Illich Manfred Mombo1
, 
Mankomra Madjitobaye1
, 
Antoine Mitte Mbeang Beyeme2
, 
Larson Boundenga1
, 
Meriadeg Ar Gouilh3
, 
Nadine N’Dilimabaka1
, 
Jan Felix Drexler4
, 
5
, 
Christian Drosten4
, 
5
&amp; 

Eric 
Maurice
Leroy
1
, 
6</p>
         <p>Little research on coronaviruses has been conducted on wild animals in Africa. Here, we screened a
</p>
         <p>
wide range of wild animals collected in six provinces and five caves of 
Gabon
between 2009 and 2015. We collected a total of 1867 animal samples (cave-dwelling bats, rodents, non-human primates and other wild animals). We explored the diversity of CoVs and determined the factors driving the infection of CoVs in wild animals. Based on a nested reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction, only bats, belonging to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
(4/156), 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
(13/262) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopterus inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>
(1/249) species, were found infected with CoVs. We identified alphacoronaviruses in 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. 

cf. 
ruber
and betacoronaviruses in 
H. gigas

. All 
Alphacoronavirus
sequences grouped with 
Human coronavirus 229E
(HCoV-229E). Ecological analyses revealed that CoV infection was significantly found in July and October in 
H. gigas

and in October and November in 
H
. cf 
ruber

. The prevalence in the Faucon cave was significantly higher. Our findings suggest that insectivorous bats harbor potentially zoonotic CoVs; highlight a probable seasonality of the infection in cave-dwelling bats from the North-East of 
Gabon
and pointed to an association between the disturbance of the bats’ habitat by human activities and CoV infection.

</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Coronaviruses (CoVs) belonging to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Coronaviridae
</tp:taxon-name>
family are viruses known to infect a wide range of animals and humans. In humans, CoVs are responsible for mild to severe respiratory illnesses such as the Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) and the Middle-East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS). The epidemic of SARS which started in 
2002 inChina
, and spread on various other continents such as North America and Europe, reached a mortality rate of 9% 
1
. The other severe epidemic illness (MERS) appeared more recently in the Middle East, and like the SARS, it also spread in other countries in Africa, America and Europe with case fatality rates of 35% (reviewed by de Wit 
et al
. 
2
). Currently the world is facing an ongoing pandemic caused by a new coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) that emerged in 
China
in 
December 2019
and caused disease (COVID-19) resulting in 118 326 confirmed cases and 4292 deaths as of March 11, 
20203
. Since the emergence of these respiratory diseases, CoVs have been considered a real public health problem because of their ability to become epidemic and pandemic 
4
. Even though human to human transmission of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV occurs mainly through nosocomial transmission, some human cases recorded were occasionally the results of a zoonotic transmission 
5
. This raised an interest in the identification of animal reservoirs. Indeed, it appears that almost each human CoV have zoonotic origins or otherwise have a close relative that circulate in wild animals (bats) 
6
– 
8
and domestic animals (camels and cattle) 
9
, 
10
. Besides SARS-CoVs and MERS-CoVs, numerous other CoVs have been detected in bats in Africa, Asia, Europe and America and are classified into the genera 
Alphacoronavirus
and 
Betacoronavirus
11
, 
12
. For SARS-CoV-2, a recent study revealed that the whole genome sequence of SARS-CoV-2 was most closely related with a bat coronavirus detected in bats from 
Yunnan Province
in 
China13
. Consequently, bats were defined as reservoirs of ancestral coronaviruses which were transmitted to humans 
14
, 
15
. Other wildlife species appear to
</p>
         <p>1
Centre International de Recherches Médicales de Franceville (CIRMF), BP, 769, Franceville, 
Gabon
. 
2
Université des Sciences etTechniques de Masuku (USTM),Institut National Supérieur d’Agronomie et de Biotechnologies (INSAB), BP, 913, Franceville, 
Gabon
. 
3Normandie
Université, EA2656,Groupe de Recherche sur l’Adaptation Microbienne, 14000,Caen, 
France
. 
4
Charité-Universitätsmedizin 
Berlin
,corporate member of Freie Universität 
Berlin
, Humboldt- Universität zu, 
Berlin
, 
Germany
. 
5
German Centre for Infection Research (DZIF), Heidelberg, 
Germany
. 
6
UMR (IRD 224/CNRS 5290/UM1-UM2), Institut de Recherche pour le Développement, Montpellier, 
France
. ✉e-mail: gael_ maganga@yahoo.fr
</p>
         <p>
play an important role in the chain of transmission and the emergence of these viruses in humans, namely palm civets 
5
and wild rodents, in which infections by an alphacoronavirus and a betacoronavirus have been recently identified 
16
.
</p>
         <p>Gabon
, a country located in Central Africa, displays a large diversity of wildlife species. Aside from bats in which CoVs have been detected in the cave-dwelling species 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>17
, to our knowledge, there is no information on the carriage of other mammalian species. CoVs are prone to host switching 
18
and could be a current and future threat to public health.
</p>
         <p>
The aim of this study was to explore the genetic diversity and the ecology of CoVs circulating among several wild mammals in 
Gabon
in order to determine the potential reservoir species of these viruses and the risk for zoonotic emergence, and identify the factors driving CoVs infection in bats.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>Results
</title>
         <p>Molecular identification of coronaviruses.
A total of 1867 animal samples, including 1066 from bats of 5 different species, 494 from rodents of 16 different species, 33 from 4 species of primates, and 274 from 14 species of other wild animals, were screened for CoVs (
Tables 1
and 
2
).
</p>
         <p>
Using nested RT-PCR, coronaviruses were detected in 18 intestine samples, giving an overall detection rate of 0.96% (18/1867). Positive samples originate from bats only, and the infection rate was 1.69% (18/1066). No CoVs were found in rodents, primates, or other terrestrial wild mammals. The 18 bat samples identified as CoV positive included 13 among the 262 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
(4.96%), 4 among the 156 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
(2.56%), and 1 among the 249 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopterus inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>
(0.4%). All the positive bats came from the 
Ogooue-Ivindo province
, in northeastern 
Gabon
(

), including 15 from the Faucon cave and 3 from the Batouala cave (
Table 3
). Besides CoVs detected in the 
Ogooué-Ivindo province
and in the Faucon and Batouala caves, no other CoVs were detected in another province or in another cave. Bats positive for CoVs were captured in 
November and December 2009
, 
October 2010
and 
July 2013
. No individuals captured in 2011 and 2014 were found infected with CoVs. Both females and males were infected regardless of age.
</p>
         <p>Molecular characterization of identified CoVs.
Fifteen bat nucleotide sequences were obtained and compared to those available in the public database using the algorithm “Blastn” of NCBI BLAST. The results indicated that all the nucleotide sequences from this study matched the deposited CoVs sequences. In order to determine the genetic relationships between the 18 bat CoVs from this study and previously described CoVs, phylogenetic analysis was performed based on 327-bp RdRp truncated sequences (

). The results showed that 12 out of 15 sequences belonged to the 
Alphacoronavirus
(α- CoV) genus (

), whereas the remaining three belonged to the 
Betacoronavirus
(β- CoV) genus (

). Among the 12 sequences of α- CoVs, 7 were obtained from individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>H. cf. ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
caught in 
2009 in
the Faucon cave, 2 from other individuals of the same species but caught the same year in the Batouala cave; the other 3 sequences were obtained from 2 
<tp:taxon-name>H. cf. ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
and 1 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
, all caught in 
2010 in
the Faucon cave. The 3 sequences of β- CoVs were detected only in 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The sequences of 
Alphacoronavirus
were 91.9–100% identical with each other. The 7 sequences from 2009 from 
<tp:taxon-name>H. cf. ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
individuals of the Faucon cave showed 100% identity with each other. Regarding the 2 sequences of 
Alphacoronavirus
from 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
of the Batouala cave, the 09GB0761 (
MG963198
) sequence displayed either 96.5% or 96.8% with the 7 other sequences, while the 09GB0809 (
MG963189
) sequence showed 100% identity with the sequences from 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
of the Faucon cave. Phylogenetic analysis supported this finding (

) and also showed that these 7 sequences clustered with 2 bat α- CoVs sequences (
JX174639
and 
JX174640
) from 2 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Faucon cave caught in 2009. These two bat sequences showed 100% identity at nucleotide level with the 7 others. The 3 sequences of α- CoV (10GB0354, 10GB0309 and 10GB0318) from 2010 were 93.2– 99.7% identical with each other. The 10GB0309 (
MG963199
) and 10GB0318 (
MG963201
) sequences, identical at 99.7%, from individuals of the same species (
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
) caught in the Faucon cave, diverged respectively by 6.4% and 6.8% from the 10GB0354 (
MG963200
) sequence from an 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
captured in the same cave.
</p>
         <p>
Furthermore, all α- CoV sequences grouped with the human coronavirus 229E (HCoV-229E) strain (
AF304460
). The nucleotide identity with HCoV-229E was 90.5–93.6%. Finally, the 10GB0354 sequence, from 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
caught in the Faucon cave, showed 93.8% nucleotide identity with a CoV strain named Alpaca CoV (
JQ410000
), detected in 
<tp:taxon-name>Vicugna pacos
</tp:taxon-name>
commonly known as alpaca (family 
<tp:taxon-name>Camelidae</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
         <p>
The 3 sequences of β- CoV, 13GB0214 (
MG963186
), 13GB0215 (
MG963187
) and 13GB0273 (
MG963188
) were obtained from 3 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
caught in 
2013 in
the Faucon cave. The 13GB0214 and 13GB0215 sequences displayed 99.7% identity at nucleotide level. These two sequences shared a nucleotide identity of 96.5% and 96.9% respectively with the 13GB0273 strain. In addition, these 3 sequences formed a distinct cluster with a bat β- CoV named the Zaria bat coronavirus (ZCoV) (accession number 
HQ166910
), detected in 
Nigeria
in 
2008 in
a species of bat genetically close to 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros commersoni
</tp:taxon-name>
. The nucleotide identities between ZCoV and 13GB0214, 13GB0215 and 13GB0273 were 96.8%, 96.5% and 97.8%, respectively.
</p>
         <p>
Bats of the species 
<tp:taxon-name>H. cf. ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
positive for alphacoronaviruses shared the same caves with the species 
<tp:taxon-name>Coleura afra
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Rousettus aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>
, which were negative for alphacoronaviruses. Moreover, the three 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
bats from the Faucon cave caught in 2013 (
Table 3
), shared the same cave with bats of the species 
<tp:taxon-name>C. afra
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>M. inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>
in which no 
Betacoronavirus
was detected. Only the 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
species was infected with a 
Betacoronavirus
.
</p>
         <p>
High throughput sequencing yielded about 9.9 million reads (

). Quality filtering discarded 86 955 (0.87%) sequences. No reads related to coronavirus could be detected with EDGE’s taxonomy classification module, but BLAST alignments (98–100% and 90–95%, for respectively query coverage and identity percentage) revealed 2 small coronavirus contigs (210 bp and 271 bp) from one sample. Those contigs have been determined as being parts of replicase polyprotein 1ab.
</p>
         <p>Group
Province
City
Species
Year of sampling 2012 2013 2015
Rodents
EstuaireLibreville<tp:taxon-name>Mus musculus
</tp:taxon-name>—23—<tp:taxon-name>Mus nannomys
</tp:taxon-name>—3—Owendo<tp:taxon-name>Mus musculus
</tp:taxon-name>—54—<tp:taxon-name>Rattus rattus
</tp:taxon-name>—15—undetermined—1—Haut-OgooueFrancevilleDoemys ferrugiens
6——<tp:taxon-name>Lemniscomys striatus
</tp:taxon-name>9——<tp:taxon-name>Lophuromys ssp
</tp:taxon-name>3——<tp:taxon-name>Mus nannomys
</tp:taxon-name>4——<tp:taxon-name>Praomys</tp:taxon-name>
sp

12——<tp:taxon-name>Rattus rattus
</tp:taxon-name>68——<tp:taxon-name>Stochomys longicaudatus
</tp:taxon-name>3——Leconi<tp:taxon-name>Cricetomys emini
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Lemniscomys striatus
</tp:taxon-name>—3—<tp:taxon-name>Lophuromys ssp
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Mus musculus
</tp:taxon-name>—8—<tp:taxon-name>Mus nannomys
</tp:taxon-name>—16—<tp:taxon-name>Praomys</tp:taxon-name>
sp

—1—<tp:taxon-name>Rattus rattus
</tp:taxon-name>—38—Ogooue-IvindoMakokou<tp:taxon-name>Cricetomys emini
</tp:taxon-name>—7—<tp:taxon-name>Grammomys poensis
</tp:taxon-name>1——<tp:taxon-name>Hybomys univittatus
</tp:taxon-name>4——<tp:taxon-name>Hylomyscus</tp:taxon-name>
sp

204—<tp:taxon-name>Lophuromys nudicaudus
</tp:taxon-name>12—<tp:taxon-name>Malacomys longipes
</tp:taxon-name>31—<tp:taxon-name>Mus musculus
</tp:taxon-name>2315—<tp:taxon-name>Mus nannomys setulosus
</tp:taxon-name>7——<tp:taxon-name>Mus monticola
</tp:taxon-name>1——<tp:taxon-name>Oenomys hypoxantus
</tp:taxon-name>—2—<tp:taxon-name>Praomys</tp:taxon-name>
sp

.
4015—<tp:taxon-name>Rattus rattus
</tp:taxon-name>1948—<tp:taxon-name>Stochomys longipes
</tp:taxon-name>—1—undetermined7——Non-human primates
Haut-Ogooue<tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus pogonias
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus cephus
</tp:taxon-name>—4—<tp:taxon-name>Cercocebus torquatus
</tp:taxon-name>—2—Ogooue-Ivindo<tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus cephus
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus nictitans
</tp:taxon-name>——15<tp:taxon-name>Colobus satanus
</tp:taxon-name>——24Ngounie<tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus cephus
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Cercopithecus nictitans
</tp:taxon-name>—2—<tp:taxon-name>Cercocebus torquatus
</tp:taxon-name>—9—Other wild animals
Haut-Ogooue<tp:taxon-name>Eudorcas rififons
</tp:taxon-name>—5—<tp:taxon-name>Hystrix cristata
</tp:taxon-name>—4—<tp:taxon-name>Loxodont africana
</tp:taxon-name>——15<tp:taxon-name>Manis javanica
</tp:taxon-name>—3—<tp:taxon-name>Strix aluco
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Syncerius caffer</tp:taxon-name>
nanus

——49Ogooue-Ivindo<tp:taxon-name>Sylvicapra grimmia
</tp:taxon-name>——1<tp:taxon-name>Cepahlophus monticola
</tp:taxon-name>——8<tp:taxon-name>Cephalophus silvicultor
</tp:taxon-name>——3<tp:taxon-name>Cephalophus dorsalis
</tp:taxon-name>——20<tp:taxon-name>Civettictis civetta
</tp:taxon-name>——7Continued</p>
         <p>GroupProvinceCitySpeciesYear of sampling 2012 2013 2015<tp:taxon-name>Eudorcas rififrons
</tp:taxon-name>—6—<tp:taxon-name>Genetta genetta
</tp:taxon-name>——1Hypotragus equinus
—4—<tp:taxon-name>Hystrix cristata
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Loxodonta africana
</tp:taxon-name>——20<tp:taxon-name>Manis javanica
</tp:taxon-name>—4—<tp:taxon-name>Potamochoerus porcus
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Syncerius caffer</tp:taxon-name>
nanus

——15<tp:taxon-name>Tragulus javanicus
</tp:taxon-name>——1Ogooue-Lolo<tp:taxon-name>Eudorcas rififons
</tp:taxon-name>—2—Hypotragus equinus
—2—Ngounie<tp:taxon-name>Hystrix cristata
</tp:taxon-name>—2—<tp:taxon-name>Manis javanica
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Eudorcas rififrons
</tp:taxon-name>—6—<tp:taxon-name>Osteolaemus tetraspis
</tp:taxon-name>—1—Hypotragus equinus
—2—Woleu-Ntem<tp:taxon-name>Manis javanica
</tp:taxon-name>—1—<tp:taxon-name>Eudorcas rififrons
</tp:taxon-name>—2—Hypotragus equinus
—1—</p>
         <p>Table 1.
Wild animal species analyzed by year and by locality.
</p>
         <p>ProvinceCaveSpeciesNumber of samples collected per year 2009 2010 2011 2013 2014TotalNumber of bats infected with CoVsHaut-OgooueDjibilong<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>———5—50<tp:taxon-name>Miniopterus inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>———69—690<tp:taxon-name>Rousettus aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>———8—80Ogooue-IvindoBatouala<tp:taxon-name>Coleura afra
</tp:taxon-name>10————100<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>58————582<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros gigas
</tp:taxon-name>17————170<tp:taxon-name>Miniopterus inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>102——6—1081<tp:taxon-name>Rousettus aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>4——6—100Zadie<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>4616251—880<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros gigas
</tp:taxon-name>75253—400<tp:taxon-name>Rousettus aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>37285035—1500Faucon<tp:taxon-name>Coleura afra
</tp:taxon-name>—345018—1020<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>57132516—11111<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros gigas
</tp:taxon-name>24302516—954<tp:taxon-name>Miniopterus inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>—75011—680Ogooue-LoloKessipoughou<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros gigas
</tp:taxon-name>————440<tp:taxon-name>Miniopterus inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>————440<tp:taxon-name>Rousettus aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>————1191190362133250194127106618</p>
         <p>Table 2.
Species of bats analyzed by year and by locality.
</p>
         <p>Factors driving CoV positivity in bats.
The comparison of the proportions of infected bats by category for each variable showed that the differences observed between bat genera (

) were statistically significant (
p
-value = 0.00002804), as well as the variations within species (
p
-value = 0.00003354) (

), ages (
p
-value = 0.0000355) (

), months of capture (
p
-value = 0.00003423) (

) and sites (
p
-value = 0.0004276) (

). There was no significant difference between the 2 sexes (

). Furthermore, the MCA on all the bats revealed that the most important variables were the month of capture and the site followed by the species. In infected bats, the most important variables were also the month of capture, followed by the site and species (

). 

and 
Table 4
show the association between the categories of the variables and the characteristics of the different groups, respectively. According to these results, it appears that CoV infection in 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
is correlated with the months of July and October. In addition, infection with CoVs in the 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
species can be associated with the months of November but also October. It appears that CoV infection is particularly associated with the Faucon cave.
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Bat ID
Genus
Species
Sex
Age
Location
Date of capture
Detected CoVs
Genbank accession number
09GB0274<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>FSAFaucon caveNovember 2009Alphacoronavirus
MG96319409GB0296<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>FSAFaucon caveNovember 2009Alphacoronavirus
MG96319509GB0323<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>MSAFaucon caveNovember 2009Alphacoronavirus
MG96319209GB0328<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>FSAFaucon caveNovember 2009Undetermined
NA09GB0329<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>MSAFaucon caveNovember 2009Alphacoronavirus
MG96319309GB0376<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>MSAFaucon caveNovember 2009Alphacoronavirus
MG96319609GB0379<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>MSAFaucon caveNovember 2009Alphacoronavirus
MG96319709GB0380<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>FSAFaucon caveNovember 2009Undetermined
NA09GB0383<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>FSAFaucon caveNovember 2009Alphacoronavirus
MG96319109GB0761<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>MABatouala caveDecember 2009Alphacoronavirus
MG96319809GB0809<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>MABatouala caveDecember 2009Alphacoronavirus
MG96318909GB0812<tp:taxon-name>Miniopterus
inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>MABatouala caveDecember 2009Undetermined
NA10GB0309<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>MJuvFaucon caveOctober 2010Alphacoronavirus
MG96319910GB0318<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>FJuvFaucon caveOctober 2010Alphacoronavirus
MG96320110GB0354<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
gigas
</tp:taxon-name>MAFaucon caveOctober 2010Alphacoronavirus
MG96320013GB0214<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
gigas
</tp:taxon-name>MAFaucon caveJully 2013Betacoronavirus
MG96318613GB0215<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
gigas
</tp:taxon-name>MSAFaucon caveJully 2013Betacoronavirus
MG96318713GB0273<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
gigas
</tp:taxon-name>MAFaucon caveJully 2013Betacoronavirus
MG963188</p>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>Discussion
</title>
         <p>
We studied 1867 animals from 39 species including rodents, bats, primates and other wildlife species, from 6 provinces (
Estuaire
, 
Haut-Ogooué
, 
Ogooué-Ivindo
, 
Ogooué-Lolo
, 
Ngounié
and 
Woleu-Ntem
) in 
Gabon
. This study identified coronaviruses (CoVs) in 18 bats belonging to the species 
<tp:taxon-name>H. cf. ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>M. inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>
from two caves located in the 
Ogooue-Ivindo province
located northeast of 
Gabon
. The nucleotides sequences obtained showed that these CoVs belonged to the 
Alphacoronavirus
and 
Betacoronavirus
genera. In a previous study, the identification of CoVs was already reported in 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Gabon17
. Taken together, these results indicated that genetically distinct coronaviruses co-circulate among bats in the 
Ogooue-Ivindo province
. These findings supported that bats carry a great genetic diversity of CoVs and Woo 
et al
. 
19
suggested that bats were ideal hosts for both alphacoronaviruses and betacoronaviruses and could play an important role in the ecology and evolution of coronaviruses. Although no coronavirus was identified in other animal species, alpha- and betacoronaviruses were already found naturally in various wild mammals such as civets 
5
, buffalos 
20
and rodents 
21
– 
23
. In their studies in rodents from 
China
, Lau 
et al
. 
21
and Wang 
et al
. 
22
analyzed 725 and 1465 rodents, respectively, whereas we analyzed only 494 rodents. The lack of detection of CoVs in our study could be linked to the small sample size, unlike the aforementioned studies. However, in their study, Ge 
et al
. 
23
found 23 infected rodents out of the 177 studied. Unfortunately the rodents in our study come mainly from urban localities, rodent captures should also be considered in rural forest areas around caves inhabited by bats. Moreover, experimental infections have been described in non-human primates 
24
, 
25
but no natural infection of CoV in NHP have yet been reported. For other wild animals, the small size of samples investigated by species could explain the lack of CoVs found in this study.
</p>
         <p>Figure 2.
Phylogenetic relationship of coronaviruses based on a fragment of 495-bp of RdRP gene (
a
). Phylogenetic relationship between Alphacoronavirus (
b
), Betacoronavirus (
c
) and bat coronaviruses from this study are highlighted.
</p>
         <p>
Alphacoronaviruses and betacoronaviruses were detected only in 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
, 2 among the 5 species tested. These results from the Ogooue-Ivindo province suggest that these 2 species could be both natural reservoirs of and specific for the alpha- and the betacoronavirus, respectively. A close co-evolutionary association could be suspected between CoVs, particularly betacoronaviruses, and bats of this family 
26
. Interestingly, in our study, we detected a specific 
<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideridae Betacoronavirus
</tp:taxon-name>
clustering with a 
Betacoronavirus
previously detected in 
Thaïland
in 
200726
. It was suggested that phylogenetic relationships between betacoronaviruses are mainly driven by the host phylogeny 
26
. However, in a study conducted in Africa, Quan 
et al
. 
27
suggested that there was no strict association between bat species and betacoronaviruses. Besides this study, previous studies on CoV host species in Asia have suggested that there was no strict association between bat species and alphacoronaviruses 
28
, 
29
. Indeed, many studies have described coronaviruses in a wide range of bat species 
30
, 
31
. Nevertheless, despite the report of alphacoronaviruses in numerous species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopteridae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Vespertillionidae, Ar Gouilh 
et al
.
</tp:taxon-name>32
suggested a strict association between 
Alphacoronavirus
EPI6 and 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophidae</tp:taxon-name>
, a familly usually associated with betacoronaviruses.
</p>
         <p>Figure 3.
Identification of viral sequences from raw data generated by high-throughput sequencing. From the raw data, BLAST was performed against viral sequences from RefSeq to identify potential viruses. Then to discard false positive calls, reads having aligned with viral references were again aligned with NCBI Nucleotide database (nr).
</p>
         <p>
No CoVs were detected in chiropteran species sharing the same caves with the positive species (
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
), suggesting a specificity of CoVs for these species or an absence of contact or interaction between some species. It was observed, for example, in the Faucon cave, that colonies of 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
were found separately, in specific areas of the cave, the same with the other species (
<tp:taxon-name>M. inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>C. afra
</tp:taxon-name>
), except for 
<tp:taxon-name>R. aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>
which was not present in this cave. This spatial segregation could limit direct contact between species and represent a behavioral barrier to interspecific transmission, as previously described for lentiviruses and felids 
33
, 
34
and more recently for bats and coronaviruses 
32
.
</p>
         <p>
A strain of 
Alphacoronavirus
was identified in 7 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
nesting in the same cave (Faucon cave) and caught the same year (2009). Likewise, 2 other 
<tp:taxon-name>H. cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Batouala cave but caught in 2010 were infected by the same alphacoronavirus infecting the 7 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Faucon cave. Corman 
et al
. 
14
had already identified a closely related strain of 
Alphacoronavirus
in 2 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Faucon cave in 2009. Altogether, these findings first suggest the transmission of CoVs between individuals of the same species through close contacts probably increased by social and roosting behavior, large colony size and reduced space in these caves 
26
; this strain of 
Alphacoronavirus
could be enzootic in 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
in this area of 
Gabon
and roosts harboring a large number of bats nesting together promotes viral diffusion in the colony 
29
, 
35
, and second, local movements of bats individuals in the region imputable to seasonal/reproductive or opportunistic roosting behaviors, as the two caves being only 
67 km
apart. The migratory behavior of some bats provides an opportunity for pathogens to spread over long distances, as reported for flying foxes of the species 
<tp:taxon-name>Eidolon helvum
</tp:taxon-name>
able to migrate more than 
1000 km36
.
</p>
         <p>
No individuals caught in 2011 and 2014 were found infected with CoVs. In 2011, only the guano of 
<tp:taxon-name>C. afra
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>M. inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>R. aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>
species was collected, unlike other years where organs were taken from bats. In this cave, the 
<tp:taxon-name>R. aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>
colony lives in areas separated from other species including 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
. The lack of detection in 
2011 may
be due to the poor quality of the samples having undergone several thawing. In 2014, only the 
<tp:taxon-name>R. aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>
species was sampled in the Kessipoughou cave. In this cave, the 
<tp:taxon-name>R. aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>
populations live in areas separated from other species including 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
. However, Tong 
et al
. 
37
and Lau 
et al
. 
30
detected alphacoronaviruses in 
<tp:taxon-name>Rousettus
</tp:taxon-name>
bats in 
Kenya
and 
China
.
</p>
         <p>Alphacoronavirus
strains detected in 
<tp:taxon-name>H. cf. ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Faucon cave displayed a variable nucleotide identity of 91 to 93% with human coronavirus 229E. This virus causes a respiratory disease and is the cause of seasonal epidemics in humans 
38
. In 
Ghana
, Pfefferle 
et al
. 
6
identified a strain of 
Alphacoronavirus
in 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
closely related to the human coronavirus 229E. Our finding argues that close relatives of the human coronavirus 229E exist in African bats 
14
. The phylogenetic proximity of the CoV strains identified in this study with the human CoV-229E strain suggests a risk of emergence of this virus in humans in Africa. Furthermore, the 10GB0354 alphacoronavirus strain (
MG963188
), from 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
bats caught in 
2010 in
the Faucon cave, was phylogenetically close (93.8% nucleotide identity) to the Alpaca CoV strain detected in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Vicugna pacos
</tp:taxon-name>
species, commonly known as alpaca (
JQ410000
). Maganga 
et al
. 
17
and Corman 
et al
. 
14
already described two Gabonese CoV strains from hipposiderid bats caught in 
2009 in
the Faucon cave closely related to Alpaca CoV. Indeed, this coronavirus was described in 2007 during the epidemic of severe respiratory disorders associated with abortions in alpacas. It could be the direct progeny of its common ancestor with HCoV-229E, sharing with the latter a nucleotide identity of 92.2% 
39
, 
40
, on 440 bases of the nsp12 (polymerase). The phylogenetic link between these 2 CoVs could originate from an inter-species transmission, as a result of the opportunistic evolution of their common ancestor. As a result of genetic mutations and recombinations, the Alpaca CoV would have passed from bats to alpaca and 
vice versa
. Phylogenetic analysis also revealed that two betacoronaviruses from 2 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
, caught in 
2013 in
the Faucon cave, were phylogenetically close to a bat betacoronavirus named the Zaria bat coronavirus (ZCoV), detected in 
Nigeria
in 
2008 in
a species of chiroptera genetically close to 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>H. commersoni
</tp:taxon-name>27
, suggesting that phylogenetic proximity between host species may promote inter-species transmission 
41
.
</p>
         <p>Figure 4.
Comparison of the proportions of infected bats by genus (a), species (
b
), age (
c)
, sex (
d
), month (
e
) and site (
f
). The error bars represent the confidence interval.
</p>
         <p>Figure 5.
Multiple correspondence analysis on infected bats. Projection of the variables (
a
); projection of individuals (
b
).
</p>
         <p>Groups
Categories Genus
Species
Sex
Age
Site
Month
Group 1<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>caffer
</tp:taxon-name>FSAFaucon caveNovemberGroup 2<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>caffer
</tp:taxon-name>F/MJFaucon caveOctoberGroup 3<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros
gigas
</tp:taxon-name>MA/SAFaucon caveJuly/OctoberGroup 4<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
<tp:taxon-name>Miniopterus</tp:taxon-name>
caffe/ 
<tp:taxon-name>inflatus</tp:taxon-name>MABatouala caveDecember</p>
         <p>Table 4.
Characteristics of individuals in groups.
</p>
         <p>BLAST succeded in finding 2 contigs linked to coronavirus while no reads from this species could be detected by all EDGE’s taxonomy tools. To identify coronavirus reads having being assembled into those 2 contigs, further analyses using BLAST against NCBI RefSeq virus database were carried, allowing for the identification of 7 coronavirus reads. Since BLAST proved to be more sensitive, the same was done for the 2 other samples in order to verify that no coronavirus reads could have been missed. No more reads related to coronavirus were found. Moreover, this analysis overall showed that viral reads were extremely under-represented. One could argue that not finding the targeted virus might be caused by low DNA concentration in sequencing libraries. However, even in the sample where the highest concentration has been recorded, no coronavirus reads were found. Furthermore despite having achieved a satisfying quality sequencing, the biased amplification (majority species will be over-represented) and the low viral load explain why coronavirus was identified with such weak coverage.</p>
         <p>
Knowledge on the diversity of coronaviruses in bats and the factors promoting this diversity is important to prevent the risks of emergence in humans. Based on the analysis of data on life history traits of bats collected in the field, our findings suggest that the diversity of bat coronaviruses was associated with the seasonality and the site of capture, as well as the species of bats. It appeared that CoV infection in 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
correlated with the months of July and October, while CoV infection in 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
was associated with the months of October and November.
</p>
         <p>
In tropical ecosystems, some bat species seem to breed year-round, whereas others have annual or biannual birth peaks 
42
. In 
Gabon
, the parturitions in 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
occur synchronously but some colonies give birth in March and others in October. In 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
from the 
Republic of Congo
, a neighboring country, the young are born at the beginning of the rainy season. In 
Gabon
, the months of October and November correspond to the beginning of the rainy season. A study demonstrated a high prevalence of CoVs in Chinese bats during the beginning of the rainy season 
43
. The same finding was reported for the shedding of astroviruses in insectivorous bats in Asia (Borneo) 
42
. Moreover, these months also correspond to the parturition season for 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
. Indeed, lactating females of 
<tp:taxon-name>H. cf. ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
and juveniles of the same species were observed in October in northeastern 
Gabon
. Regarding 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
, these observations are more difficult, Brosset and Saint Girons 
44
reported that the seasonal events of mating and parturition in 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
were confined in large caves where these large bats are entirely dependent to raise their young. According to Plowright 
et al
. 
45
, reproductive stress was an important driver of Hendra virus antibody prevalence. The prevalence of antibodies against the Hendra virus was higher in pregnant and lactating female of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pteropus scapulatus
</tp:taxon-name>
contrary to non-reproductive females. Different studies showed that parturition and lactation were important risk factors for CoVs shedding in insectivorous bats 
46
, 
47
. These two physiological states are energetically costly and thus lead to a depression of the immune system.
</p>
         <p>
Moreover, our findings suggested that CoV infection was particularly associated with the Faucon cave. Of all the caves studied, the Faucon cave was the largest, with many cavities sheltering a diversity of bat species living in sympatry. This cave is regularly visited by villagers to hunt bats for human consumption. This hunting pressure could cause habitat disturbance and stress to these animals. Although Seltmann 
et al
. 
42
found no association between habitat disturbance and the detection rate of CoVs in insectivorous bats, numerous studies in bats reported that pathogen prevalence was associated with habitat disturbance 
48
. Many authors argued that habitat disturbance in some bats species may cause chronic stress and consequently immunosuppression 
42
, 
49
– 
51
, increasing the susceptibility of animals to acquire and shed viruses.
</p>
         <p>
In summary, the results of our study highlight a genetic diversity of CoVs in insectivorous bats in northeastern 
Gabon
and show that the beginning of the rainy season and mainly the parturition season constitute a period of risk for CoV infection of insectivorous bats 
<tp:taxon-name>H
. cf. 
ruber
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
. These results also suggest an association between the disturbance of the bats’ habitat by human activities and the infection of these animals with these viruses. This study highlights a probable seasonality of the infection of insectivorous cave bats of the north-east of 
Gabon
by CoVs. To conclude, a longitudinal monitoring should be carried out at different months of the year in order to determine the reproduction periods of the different bat species and therefore the periods favorable to viral shedding. The effect of the habitat disturbance on viral shedding should also be studied further. Bats harbor a large number of potentially zoonotic CoVs and pose a threat to public health for populations that are in contact with reservoir species of these viruses. The knowledge of CoVs ecology in bats is essential to prevent emergence in human populations.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Methods
</title>
         <p>Ethical approval.
All experiments were performed in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations. Experimental protocol was approved by the National 
Center
of Scientific and Technologic Research (CENAREST) (permission number AR0031/09) for the use of non-human primate fecal samples. Fecal sample collection from non-human primates (NHPs) in protected areas was approved by the National Parcs Agency (ANPN). Bat and rodent captures and sampling were conducted with the permission of the Wildlife and Hunting Department of the Gabonese Ministry of Water and Forestry (N°003/MEFE-PA/SG/DGEF/DCF, N°0021/MEFE-PA/SG/DGEF/ DCF and N°0031/MEFDD/SG/DGEF/DFC). All the capture events, animal handling, euthanasia and transfer of samples across the country were performed in accordance with the guidelines of the American Society of Mammalogists (http://www.mammalsociety.org/committees/animal-care-and-use). Safe and humane euthanasia was achieved through the use of halothane prior to autopsy. We performed the autopsies under a microbiological safety station equipped with personal protective equipment, mask and visor.
</p>
         <p>Study area and sample collection.
We screened several samples from bushmeat, bats, rodents and NHPs collected from 2009 to 2011 and from 
2013 to 2015 in
six provinces of 
Gabon
(

).
</p>
         <p>Bushmeat sampling.
Bushmeat was collected from officers of the provincial direction of the 
Gabon
Ministry of Water Affairs and Forestry after seizures of illegal hunting, as well as from salesmen during the hunting season. The sampling was performed in 
2013 in
four provinces of 
Gabon
(
Haut-Ogooué
, 
Ngounié
, 
Ogooué-Ivindo
and 
Woleu-Ntem
). Species identification was performed as previously described 
52
. Samples, including whole blood,
</p>
         <p>
liver, spleen and gut, were then kept in liquid nitrogen until their delivery at the CIRMF (
Centre
International de Recherches Médicales de Franceville

) and stored at −80 °C for further laboratory investigations.
</p>
         <p>Bat and rodent sampling.
Bat capture took place in three provinces of 
Gabon
, namely 
Ogooué-Ivindo
, 
Ogooué-Lolo
and 
Haut-Ogooué
in 2009, 2010, 2011, 2013 and 2014. In 
Ogooué-Ivindo
, capture was performed in three caves, the Faucon (
1°07 N13°20 E
), Zadie (0°98 N 
13°19 E
) and Batouala (0°82N 
13°45 E
) caves, located in the heart of the Belinga mountains. The distances between the three different caves located in Belinga were as follows: 33.7 km between the Batouala and Zadie caves, 11.7 km between the Zadie and Faucon caves and 37.7km between the Batouala and Faucon caves 
53
.
</p>
         <p>
In the 
Ogooué-Lolo province
, bats were caught in the Kessipoughou cave (0°86 S 12°77 E); and in the 
Haut-Ogooué province
, bats were captured in the Djibilong cave (
1°36 S13°46 E
), located north of Franceville. For bats, sex, stage of maturity or age (adult, subadult, juvenile) and capture season were recorded. Rodents were sampled in 2012 and 2013, using Tomahawk and Sherman traps as previously described 
54
. The traps were set in houses and their vicinities in three provinces of 
Gabon
: 
Estuaire
(Libreville and Owendo), 
Ogooué-Ivindo
(Makokou) and 
Haut-Ogooué
(Franceville and Leconi). After autopsy, organs were collected in bats and rodents, frozen and then stored at −80 °C until analysis. Bat and rodent species were identified by trained field biologists.
</p>
         <p>Feces collection.
Fecal samples were collected from NHPs, bats and wild animals. Fresh bat droppings were collected on plastic film arranged below roost sites in the caves 
55
. Additionally, fecal pellets were directly collected in bags in which the bats were put individually after capture. Fecal samples from NHPs were collected in the field in the 
Ogooué-Ivindo province
(Lope National Park) in 2015. Feces from other wild animals were sampled in 
2015 in
the 
Haut-Ogooué
(Lekedi Park in Bakoumba) and 
Ogooué-Ivindo
(Lope National Park and Mopia) provinces. Fresh fecal samples were preserved in approximately 10ml of RNA 
later
(Ambion) or frozen and transferred to the CIRMF laboratory, where they were stored at −80 °C until analysis.
</p>
         <p>Specimen preparation and RNA extraction.
Total RNAs were extracted from the intestines of bats and rodents coming from bushmeat, and from the feces of bats, PNHs and other wild animals. Around 
100 mg
of intestine was pooled according to the species and crushed in 600 µl of cold phosphate buffer saline (PBS) (Biological Diagnostic Supplies Ltd) in a ball-mill tissue grinder (Geno/Grinder 2000, Spex Centripep). Total RNA was extracted from 100 µl of homogenate supernatant using a Biorobot EZ1 and the EZ1 RNA tissue mini kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer’s guidelines in a BSL3. For feces preserved in RNA 
later
solution, RNA 
later
was taken out before feces was suspended in PBS and centrifuged at 1500 rpm for 5 min. RNAs were then extracted from 400 µl of supernatant, using the EZ1 RNA Viral Mini kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer’s recommendations.
</p>
         <p>
The RNA was then tested for the detection of CoVs using a nested reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (nRT-PCR) 
56
using generic primers targeting a 494 bp fragment of a conserved region of the RNA-dependant RNA polymerase (RdRp) gene. The first-round PCR was carried out using the Qiagen One-step RT PCR kit (Qiagen). Amplification involved 30 min at 50 °C; 15 sec at 95 °C, followed by a touchdown element of 10 cycles of 20 sec at 94 °C, 30 sec starting at 60 °C with a decrease of 0.5 °C per cycle, and 40 sec at 72 °C; and 40 cycles of 20 sec at 95 °C, 30 sec at 54 °C, 40 sec at 72 °C, with a final elongation step of 5 min at 72 °C. The second-round PCR was performed using the 
Platinum Taq
DNA polymerase kit (Life Technologies). Amplification involved 3 min at 94 °C followed by 40 cycles of 20 sec at 94°, 30 sec at 60 °C, 40 sec at 72 °C, with a final elongation step of 1 min at 72 °C. Individual samples from pools which gave positive results were tested separately by the same nRT-PCR.
</p>
         <p>Hight-throughput sequencing.
The hight-throughput sequencing was performed using a MiSeq machine. The DNA library was prepared from 3 samples (13GB0214, 13GB0215 and 09GB0323) using the NEBNext Ultra RNA Library Prep kit for Illumina (New 
England
BioLabs, 
UK
) following the manufacturer’s recommandations. Briefly, after RNA quantification and fragmentation, cDNAs were generated with SuperScript III reverse transciptase. Agencourt AMpure XP beads (Beckmann Coulter, 
The Netherlands
) was used for size selection purification and resulted in a total library size 300–500 bp. Library quality was evaluated on an Agilent BioAnalyser 2100 (Agilent Technologies, 
USA
). Sequencing was performed on Illumina’s MiSeq (V2 reagents) to obtain 2 ×150bp paired-end reads. Bioinformatic analyses were conducted with EDGE v2.3.1 pipeline 
57
. EDGE’s quality module (FastQC v2.08 tool) filtered sequencing reads based on a 25 PHRED score threshold, no ambiguous bases and a 50 bp minimum size. Then taxonomy classification was conducted on both trimmed reads and contigs after assembly (SPAdes v3.13.0). The EDGE’s taxonomy module allows for a broad exploration using minimap2 v2.16, Kraken2 v2.0.7, Metaphlan v2.7.7, BWA v0.7.12 and GOTTCHA2 v2.1.5. Unclassified contigs were aligned with BLAST 
58
and NCBI RefSeq virus database (
September 16, 2019
release).
</p>
         <p>Phylogenetic analyses.
The partial RdRp sequences obtained were cleaned and the contigs assembled using ChromasPro 1.5. The nucleotide sequences were compared to those available in GenBank using the “Blastn” algorithm of NCBI BLAST. Multiple sequence alignments were performed using the ClustalW algorithm implemented in the MEGA 7 software 
59
. Phylogenetic analyses were performed by maximum likelihood algorithm using 1,000 bootstraps replications with PhyML 
60
and also under a Bayesian statistical framework implemented in BEAST (version 1.8.3) 
61
using the general time reversible model of substitution, with a gamma distribution and a proportion of invariant sites (GTR+ I + G).
</p>
         <p>Nucleotide sequence accession numbers.
All the sequences obtained in this study have been deposited in Genbank under the accession numbers 
MG963186
- 
MG963189
and 
MG963191
- 
MG963201
.
</p>
         <p>Variables
Description
No. of animals
Species
<tp:taxon-name>Coleura afra
</tp:taxon-name>112<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros cf.ruber
</tp:taxon-name>262<tp:taxon-name>Hipposideros gigas
</tp:taxon-name>156<tp:taxon-name>Miniopterus inflatus
</tp:taxon-name>249<tp:taxon-name>Rousettus aegyptiacus
</tp:taxon-name>287Sex
Male620Female443NA3Sites/Caves
Batouala203Djibilong82Faucon376Kessipoughou127Zadie278Months
January65February127March93April129June101July112October77November74December288Age
Adult823Subadult205Juvenile35NA3</p>
         <p>Table 5.
Description of risk factors for infection of cave-dwelling bats with CoVs.
</p>
         <p>Statistical analysis.
Bat data were analyzed for factors associated with CoV positivity. The methodology is based on the combined use of multiple correspondence analysis and hierarchical clustering. First, multiple correspondence analysis (MCA) was done on all the individuals, and then only on the positive bats to better identify these factors. For each variable included in the analyses (age, sex, bat genus and species, month of capture, site) (
Table 5
), the proportions of the infected animals were compared using the Chi square test. A 
p
value of &lt;0.05 was considered for significant results. A characterization of the infected bats was made through a hierarchical clustering by the k-means method. The data were analyzed using R version 3.4.3.
</p>
         <p>
Received: 
17 September 2018
; Accepted: 
6 April 2020
;
</p>
         <p>Published: xx xx xxxx</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References
</title>
         <p>
1. 
Peiris, J.S.
, 
Yuen, K.Y.
, 
Osterhaus, A. D.
&amp; 
Stöhr, K.The severe acute respiratory syndrome
. 
New England Journal of Medicine
349

, 
2431–2441
(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
2. 
de Wit,E.
, 
van Doremalen, N.
, 
Falzarano, D.
&amp; 
Munster, V.J.SARS and MERS: recent insights into emerging coronaviruses
. 
Nature Reviews Microbiology
14

, 
523
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
3. 
WHO
. 
Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19
). 
Situation Report-51. Available at
, 
https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/ coronaviruse/situation-reports/20200311-sitrep-51-covid-19.pdf. Accessed March 13.9
(
2020
).
</p>
         <p>
4. 
Assiri, A.Hospital Outbreak of Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (vol 369, pg 407, 2013)
. 
New England Journal of Medicine
369

, 
886–886
(
2013
).
</p>
         <p>
5. 
Wang, M.et al
. 
SARS-CoV infection in a restaurant from palm civet
. 
Emerging infectious diseases
11

, 
1860
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
6. 
Pfefferle, S.et al
. 
Distant relatives of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus and close relatives of human coronavirus 229E in bats, Ghana
. 
Emerging infectious diseases
15

, 
1377
(
2009
).
</p>
         <p>
7. 
Donaldson, E. F.et al
. 
Metagenomic analysis of the viromes of three North American bat species: viral diversity among different bat species that share a common habitat
. 
Journal of virology
84

, 
13004–13018
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>
8. 
Huynh, J.et al
. 
Evidence supporting a zoonotic origin of human coronavirus strain NL63
. 
Journal of virology
86

, 
12816–12825
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
9. 
Sabir, J. S.et al
. 
Co-circulation of three camel coronavirus species and recombination of MERS-CoVs in Saudi Arabia
. 
Science
351

, 
81–84
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
10. 
Vijgen, L.et al
. 
Complete genomic sequence of human coronavirus OC43: molecular clock analysis suggests a relatively recent zoonotic coronavirus transmission event
. 
Journal of virology
79

, 
1595–1604
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
11. 
Drexler, J. F.
, 
Corman, V. M.
&amp; 
Drosten, C.Ecology, evolution and classification of bat coronaviruses in the aftermath of SARS
. 
Antiviral research
101

, 
45–56
(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
12. 
King, A. M.
, 
Lefkowitz, E.
, 
Adams, M. J.
&amp; 
Carstens, E. B.Virus taxonomy: ninth report of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses.Vol.9
(
Elsevier
, 
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
13. 
Zhou, P.et al
. 
Discovery of a novel coronavirus associated with the recent pneumonia outbreak in humans and its potential bat origin
. 
Nature Reviews Microbiology
579

(
2020
).
</p>
         <p>
14. 
Corman, V. M.et al
. 
Evidence for an Ancestral Association of Human Coronavirus 229E with Bats
. 
Journal of Virology
89

, 
11858–11870
, 
https://doi.org/10.1128/jvi.01755-15
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
15. 
Hu, B.
, 
Ge, X.
, 
Wang, L.-F.
&amp; 
Shi, Z.Bat origin of human coronaviruses
. 
Virology journal
12

, 
221
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
16. 
Monchatre-Leroy, E.et al
. 
Identification of alpha and beta coronavirus in wildlife species in France: bats, rodents, rabbits, and hedgehogs
. 
Viruses
9

, 
364
(
2017
).
</p>
         <p>
17. 
Maganga, G. D.et al
. 
Bat distribution size or shape as determinant of viral richness in african bats
. 
PLoS One
9

(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
18. 
Woo, P.C.
, 
Lau, S.K.
, 
Huang, Y.
&amp; 
Yuen,K.-Y.Coronavirus diversity, phylogeny and interspecies jumping
. 
Experimental Biology and Medicine
234

, 
1117–1127
(
2009
).
</p>
         <p>
19. 
Woo, P. C.et al
. 
Discovery of seven novel Mammalian and avian coronaviruses in the genus deltacoronavirus supports bat coronaviruses as the gene source of alphacoronavirus and betacoronavirus and avian coronaviruses as the gene source of gammacoronavirus and deltacoronavirus
. 
Journal of virology
86

, 
3995–4008
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
20. 
Lau,S.et al
. 
First genome sequences of buffalo coronavirus from water buffaloes in Bangladesh
. 
New microbes and new infections
11

, 
54–56
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
21. 
Lau, S. K.et al
. 
Discovery of a novel coronavirus, China Rattus coronavirus HKU24, from Norway rats supports the murine origin of Betacoronavirus 1 and has implications for the ancestor of Betacoronavirus lineage A
. 
Journal of virology
89

, 
3076–3092
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
22. 
Wang, W.et al
. 
Discovery, diversity and evolution of novel coronaviruses sampled from rodents in China
. 
Virology
474

, 
19–27
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
23. 
Ge, X.-Y.et al
. 
Detection of alpha-and betacoronaviruses in rodents from Yunnan, China
. 
Virology journal
14

, 
98
(
2017
).
</p>
         <p>
24. 
Munster, V.J.
, 
de Wit, E.
&amp; 
Feldmann, H.Pneumonia from human coronavirus in a macaque model
. 
The New England journal of medicine368

(
2013
).
</p>
         <p>
25. 
Johnson, R. F.et al
. 
3B11-N, a monoclonal antibody against MERS-CoV, reduces lung pathology in rhesus monkeys following intratracheal inoculation of MERS-CoV Jordan-n3/2012
. 
Virology
490

, 
49–58
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
26. 
Gouilh, M. A.et al
. 
SARS-Coronavirus ancestor’s foot-prints in South-East Asian bat colonies and the refuge theory
. 
Infection, Genetics and Evolution
11

, 
1690–1702
(
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
27. 
Quan, P.-L.et al
. 
Identification of a severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-like virus in a leaf-nosed bat in Nigeria
. 
MBio
1

, e00208–00210 (
2010
).
</p>
         <p>
28. 
Chu, D.et al
. 
Coronaviruses in bent-winged bats (Miniopterus spp.)
. 
Journal of General Virology
87

, 
2461–2466
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
29. 
Tang, X.et al
. 
Prevalence and genetic diversity of coronaviruses in bats from China
. 
Journal of virology
80

, 
7481–7490
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
30. 
Lau, S. K.et al
. 
Recent transmission of a novel alphacoronavirus, bat coronavirus HKU10, from Leschenault’s rousettes to pomona leaf-nosed bats:first evidence of interspecies transmission of coronavirus between bats of different suborders
. 
Journal of virology
86

, 
11906–11918
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
31. 
Goffard, A.et al
. 
Alphacoronaviruses detected in french bats are phylogeographically linked to coronaviruses of european bats
. 
Viruses
7

, 
6279–6290
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
32. 
Gouilh, M. A.et al
. 
SARS-CoV related Betacoronavirus and diverse Alphacoronavirus members found in western old-world
. 
Virology
517

, 
88–97
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
33. 
Troyer, J.L.et al
. 
FIV cross-species transmission: an evolutionary prospective
. 
Veterinary immunology and immunopathology
123

, 
159–166
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
34. 
VandeWoude, S.
, 
Troyer, J.
&amp; 
Poss, M.Restrictions to cross-species transmission of lentiviral infection gleaned from studies of FIV
. 
Veterinary immunology and immunopathology
134

, 
25–32
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>
35. 
Woo, P.C.et al
. 
Molecular diversity of coronaviruses in bats
. 
Virology
351

, 
180–187
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
36. 
Epstein, J. H.et al
. 
Pteropus vampyrus, a hunted migratory species with a multinational home-range and a need for regional management
. 
Journal of Applied Ecology
46

, 
991–1002
(
2009
).
</p>
         <p>
37. 
Tong, S.et al
. 
Detection of novel SARS-like and other coronaviruses in bats from Kenya
. 
Emerging infectious diseases
15

, 
482
(
2009
).
</p>
         <p>
38. 
Su, S.et al
. 
Epidemiology, genetic recombination, and pathogenesis of coronaviruses
. 
Trends in microbiology
24

, 
490–502
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
39. 
Crossley, B. M.et al
. 
Identification of a novel coronavirus possibly associated with acute respiratory syndrome in alpacas (Vicugna pacos) in California
, 2007. 
Journal of veterinary diagnostic investigation
22

, 
94–97
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>
40. 
Crossley, B. M.
, 
Mock, R. E.
, 
Callison, S. A.
&amp; 
Hietala, S. K.Identification and characterization of a novel alpaca respiratory coronavirus most closely related to the human coronavirus 229E
. 
Viruses
4

, 
3689–3700
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
41. 
Baric, R. S.
, 
Sullivan, E.
, 
Hensley, L.
, 
Yount, B.
&amp; 
Chen, W.Persistent infection promotes cross-species transmissibility of mouse hepatitis virus
. 
Journal of virology
73

, 
638–649
(
1999
).
</p>
         <p>
42. 
Seltmann, A.et al
. 
Seasonal fluctuations of astrovirus, but not coronavirus shedding in bats inhabiting human-modified tropical forests
. 
EcoHealth
14

, 
272–284
(
2017
).
</p>
         <p>
43. 
Lau, S. K.et al
. 
Ecoepidemiology and complete genome comparison of different strains of severe acute respiratory syndrome-related Rhinolophus bat coronavirus in China reveal bats as a reservoir for acute, self-limiting infection that allows recombination events
. 
Journal of virology
84

, 
2808–2819
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>
44. 
Brosset, A.
&amp; 
Saint Girons, H.Cycles de reproduction des microchiroptères troglophiles du nord-est du Gabon
. 
Mammalia
44

, 
225–232
(
1980
).
</p>
         <p>
45. 
Plowright, R. K.et al
. 
Reproduction and nutritional stress are risk factors for Hendra virus infection in little red flying foxes (Pteropus scapulatus)
. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences
275

, 
861–869
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
46. 
Gloza-Rausch, F.et al
. 
Detection and prevalence patterns of group I coronaviruses in bats, northern Germany
. 
Emerging infectious diseases
14

, 
626
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
47. 
Drexler, J. F.et al
. 
Amplification of emerging viruses in a bat colony
. 
Emerging infectious diseases
17

, 
449
(
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
48. 
Turmelle, A. S.et al
. 
Ecology of rabies virus exposure in colonies of Brazilian free-tailed bats (Tadarida brasiliensis) at natural and man-made roosts in Texas
. 
Vector-Borne and Zoonotic Diseases
10

, 
165–175
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>
49. 
Sapolsky, R. M.
, 
Romero, L. M.
&amp; 
Munck, A. U.How do glucocorticoids influence stress responses? Integrating permissive, suppressive, stimulatory, and preparative actions
. 
Endocrine reviews
21

, 
55–89
(
2000
).
</p>
         <p>
50. 
Suorsa, P.et al
. 
Effects of forest patch size on physiological stress and immunocompetence in an area-sensitive passerine, the Eurasian treecreeper (Certhia familiaris):an experiment
. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society of London.Series B: Biological Sciences
271

, 
435–440
(
2004
).
</p>
         <p>
51. 
Wikelski, M.
&amp; 
Cooke, S. J.Physiological assessment of environmental stressors.Trends in Ecology
&amp;. 
Evolution
1

, 
38–46
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
52. 
Boundenga, L.et al
. 
Haemosporidian parasites of antelopes and other vertebrates from Gabon, Central Africa
. 
Plos One
11

(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
53. 
Rougeron,V.et al
. 
Characterization and phylogenetic analysis of new bat astroviruses detected in Gabon, Central Africa
. 
Acta Virol
60

, 
386–392
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
54. 
Duplantier, J.-M.Les rongeurs myomorphes forestiers du nord-est du Gabon: structure du peuplement, démographie, domaines vitaux
. 
Revue d'écologie

(
1989
).
</p>
         <p>
55. 
Drexler, J. F.et al
. 
Henipavirus RNAin African bats
. 
PloS one
4

(
2009
).
</p>
         <p>
56. 
de Souza Luna, L. K.et al
. 
Generic detection of coronaviruses and differentiation at the prototype strain level by reverse transcription-PCR and nonfluorescent low-density microarray
. 
Journal of clinical microbiology
45

, 
1049–1052
(
2007
).
</p>
         <p>
57. 
Li, P.-E.et al
. 
Enabling the democratization of the genomics revolution with a fully integrated web-based bioinformatics platform
. 
Nucleic acids research
45

, 
67–80
(
2017
).
</p>
         <p>
58. 
Altschul, S.F.
, 
Gish, W.
, 
Miller, W.
, 
Myers, E.W.
&amp; 
Lipman, D. J.Basic local alignment search tool
. 
Journal of molecular biology
215

, 
403–410
(
1990
).
</p>
         <p>
59. 
Kumar, S.
, 
Stecher, G.
&amp; 
Tamura, K.MEGA7: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 7.0 for bigger datasets
. 
Molecular biology and evolution
33

, 
1870–1874
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
60. 
Dereeper, A.et al
. 
Phylogeny.fr: robust phylogenetic analysis for the non-specialist
. 
Nucleic Acids Res
36

, W 
465–469
, 
https://doi. org/10.1093/nar/gkn180
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
61. 
Drummond, A. J.
&amp; 
Rambaut, A.BEAST: Bayesian evolutionary analysis by sampling trees
. 
BMC Evol Biol
7

, 
214
, 
https://doi. org/10.1186/1471-2148-7-214
(
2007
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements
</title>
         <p>
We acknowledge Heïdi Lançon for the English revision, and Andy Nkili Meyong and Ingrid Labouba for highthroughput sequencing and bioinformatics analysis. We thank all the persons involved in sample collection. The CIRMF is supported by the Government of 
Gabon
, Total-Fina-Elf 
Gabon
, and the Ministère de la Coopération Française.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Author contributions
</title>
         <p>G.D.M. and E.M.L. designed and conceived the work. G.D.M., A.P. and M.M. carried out the experiments, G.D.M., I.M.M., A.M.M.B., L.B., M.A.G. and N.N. analyzed the data, J.F.D., C.D. and E.M.L provided essential material. G.D.M. and I.M.M. wrote the main manuscript text. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Competing interests
</title>
         <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Additional information
</title>
         <p>Correspondence
and requests for materials should be addressed to G.D.M.
</p>
         <p>Reprints and permissions information
is available at www.nature.com/reprints.
</p>
         <p>Publisher’s note
Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.
</p>
         <p>Open Access
This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
</p>
         <p>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.</p>
      </sec>
      <p>© The Author(s) 2020</p>
   </body>
</article>
