<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112516</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Variation in the amino acids, volatile organic compounds and terpenes profiles in induced polyploids and in Solanum tuberosum varieties</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>
Variation in the amino acids, volatile organic compounds and terpenes profiles in induced polyploids and in 
Solanum tuberosum
varieties
</p>
      <p>
Nicol´as Cara 
a
, 
Patricia N. Piccolia, b
, 
Leonardo Bolcatob
, 
Carlos F. Marfila, b
,
</p>
      <p>Ricardo W. Masuellia, b, *</p>
      <p>aFacultad de Ciencias Agrarias, UNCuyo, Almirante Brown 500, M5528AHB, Mendoza, Argentina
</p>
      <p>bInstituto de Biología Agrícola de Mendoza (IBAM), CONICET-UNCuyo, Almirante Brown 500, M5528AHB, Mendoza, Argentina
</p>
      <p>A R T I C L E I N F O A B S T R A C T</p>
      <p>Keywords:
Polyploids often display a variety of phenotypic novelties when compared to their diploid progenitors, some of
</p>
      <p>Solanum tuberosum
which may represent ecological advantages, especially regarding tolerance to biotic and abiotic factors. Plants
</p>
      <p>Solanum kurtzianum
cope with environmental factors by producing chemicals such as volatile organic compounds (VOCs) and specific
</p>
      <p>Solanaceae amino acids (AAs). In potato, the third most important food crop in the world, gene introgression from diploid</p>
      <p>Allopolyploid wild relative species into the genetic pool of the cultivated species (tetraploid) would be of great agronomical</p>
      <p>Autopolyploid</p>
      <p>
Secondary metabolites interest. The consequences of allopolyploidization on the potato VOCs and AAs profiles have not been yet analyzed. In this work, the effects of whole genome duplication on VOCs and AAs contents in leaves of potato allo- and autotetraploids and cultivated varieties were studied. The polyploids were obtained by chromosomal duplication of a genotype of the wild diploid species 
S. kurtzianum
(autopolyploid model), and a diploid interspecific hybrid between the cultivated species 
S. tuberosum
and 
S. kurtzianum
(allopolyploid model). Almost all compounds levels varied greatly among these tetraploid lines; while all tetraploids showed higher contents of non-isoprenoids compounds than diploids, we found either increments or reductions in terpenes and AAs content. The results support the idea that genome duplication is a stochastic source of variability, which might be directly used for introgression in the 4x gene pool of the cultivated potato by sexual hybridization.
</p>
      <p>1. Introduction
</p>
      <p>It has been largely demonstrated that polyploidy has played an important role in the speciation, diversification, and adaptability of plant species (Flagel and Wendel, 2009; Otto, 2007; Soltis et al., 2009). Most angiosperms have undergone at least one round of whole-genome doubling throughout their evolution (Masterson, 1994), including many important crops such as wheat, cotton, alfalfa, coffee and potato. Polyploids may arise from sexual reproduction through unreduced gametes 2n or by means of somatic chromosome duplication (Ramsey and Schemske, 1998).</p>
      <p>In addition, there are two forms of polyploidy that can be distinguished: allopolyploids, which combine two or more genomes from different species and exhibit bivalent pairing and disomic inheritance, and autopolyploids that have multiple genomes of the same species and show multivalent pairing and polysomic inheritance (Zielinski and Mittelsten Scheid, 2012).</p>
      <p>Polyploidy often results in a variety of phenotypic novelties when compared to their diploid progenitors, comprising morphological traits like larger leaves, flowers, fruits and seeds (Chen et al., 2016; Gao et al., 2016; Stanys et al., 2006; Sugiyama, 2005), and physiological features such as higher growth rate and shorter or longer flowering time (Kondorosi et al., 2000; Pires et al., 2004). Moreover, it has been shown that polyploidy may increase tolerance to abiotic factors, like salinity (Chao et al., 2013; Saleh et al., 2008), drought (Del Pozo and Ramirez-Parra, 2014), and extreme temperatures (Zhang et al., 2010), or affect interactions with biotic agents such as pollinators and herbivores (K¨onig et al., 2014; Nuismer and Cunningham, 2005; Segraves and Anneberg, 2016).</p>
      <p>One strategy by which plants can cope with environmental factors is by producing and releasing chemicals such as volatile organic compounds (VOCs) (Pichersky and Gang, 2000), which are low molecular weight species including terpenoid [isoprene (5C), monoterpenes (C10), sesquiterpenes (C15)] and non-isoprenoid compounds as oxygenated</p>
      <p>* Corresponding author. Almirante Brown 500, M5528AHB, Mendoza, Argentina.</p>
      <p>E-mail addresses:
ncara@fca.uncu.edu.ar (N. Cara), ppiccoli@fca.uncu.edu.ar (P.N. Piccoli), lbolcato@fca.uncu.edu.ar (L. Bolcato), cmarfil@fca.uncu.edu.ar (C.F. Marfil), rmasuelli@fca.uncu.edu.ar (R.W. Masuelli).
</p>
      <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112516</p>
      <p>Received 30 June 2019; Received in revised form 25 July 2020; Accepted 7 September 2020</p>
      <p>Available online 17 September 2020</p>
      <p>0031-9422/© 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</p>
      <p>hydrocarbons (alcohols, aldehydes and ketones) (Kesselmeier and Staudt, 1999). These compounds may, for instance, protect plants against biotic and abiotic stresses (Loreto and Schnitzler, 2010; Pe˜nuelas et al., 2014; Pichersky and Gershenzon, 2002). VOCs can also include defense mechanisms to control growth of neighboring plants (Karban et al., 2014; Kegge et al., 2015; Ninkovic et al., 2016; Pierik et al., 2003).</p>
      <p>
Polyploidy has been artificially induced 
in vitro
using antimitotic agents like colchicine, oryzalin and trifluralin (Dhooghe et al., 2011). Higher amounts of bioactive secondary metabolites have been obtained in synthetic polyploids of 
Tanacetum parthenium
(Majdi et al., 2010), 
Hyoscyamus muticus
(Dehghan et al., 2012), 
Datura stramonium
(Berkov and Philipov, 2002) and 
Echinacea purpurea
(Xu et al., 2014). However, not always increased ploidy levels correspond to higher amounts of secondary metabolites (Lavania, 2005). In tetraploids of 
Mentha spiculata
, 
Digitalis purpurea
, 
Digitalis lanata
and 
Trigonella foenum-graecum
have been reported mild to severe reductions in different metabolites content respect to their diploid counterparts (Evans and Evans, 2009). The unpredictable effect of genome duplication on secondary metabolites pathways demonstrates a lack of knowledge about gene dosage regulation and the necessity to further study this phenomenon.
</p>
      <p>
In tuber bearing 
Solanum
species few works have addressed this matter. Working with 
S. bulbocastanum
autotetraploids Caruso et al. (2013) did not observed clear differences when several compounds were measured in the tetraploids and their original diploids. Otto (1990), Seabra et al. (2013) found mostly stochastic changes in the transcriptome and metabolome of synthetic autotetraploids, suggesting a strong genotypic response to genome duplication in potato. As far as we know, the effect of ploidy on the production of secondary metabolites in an allopolyploid model has not yet been studied in potato. In a recent study, Marfil et al. (2018) demonstrated that the hybridization event is an additional genomic shock that the allopolyploids experience compared with autopolyploids. Also, since ploidy manipulations are frequently used in plant breeding to overcome zygotic and post-zygotic barriers and for introgression of resistance genes from related germplasm (diploid) into the genetic pool of the cultivated species (tetraploid); the agronomic, molecular and metabolomic characterization of the newly synthesized polyploids would be important for efficient genotypes selection. Our hypothesis is that allopolyploids would have greater metabolic changes compared with autopolyploids, due to the absence of hybridization in the latter. In this work, we analyze the profiles and content of VOCs and amino acids in leaves of 
Solanum
auto- and allotetraploids, their respective diploid lines and three cultivated varieties.
</p>
      <p>2. Experimental
</p>
      <p>2.1. Plant material
</p>
      <p>
Synthetic potato allotetraploids and autotetraploids previously obtained by Marfil et al. (2018) were assayed. Briefly, in the allopolyploid model, a diploid parental interspecific hybrid (2xPIH) between a 
S. tuberosum
dihaploid (2n = 2x = 24) and a genotype of 
S. kurtzianum
Bitter &amp; Wittm. (2n =2x =24) (Marfil et al., 2006) was 
in vitro
treated with colchicine and two allotetraploid derived lines were selected and analyzed: 4xAL2 and 4xAL4. The autotetraploid lines were generated from a diploid genotype of 
S. kurtzianum
(diploid parental line; 2xPL), which was 
in vitro
treated with oryzalin and three autotetraploid (4xAuL1, 4xAuL2 and 4xAuL3) lines were selected for further studies. Also, three 
S. tuberosum
cultivated varieties were included: cv. Calen-INTA (4xCalen), cv. Innovator (4xInnovator) and cv. Pampeana-INTA (4xPampeana).
</p>
      <p>2.2. Experimental design
</p>
      <p>
Allo- and autotetraploid lines and 
S. tuberosum
cultivated varieties were grown in pots with a mixture of clay soil, sand and peat moss (1:1:1 v/v). The soil mixture was combined with commercial fertilizer (containing 15% N, 15% P and 15% K) and autoclaved. Plants were cultivated during 5 months in an insect-proof greenhouse from October to February until tubers were collected and stored for 7 months at 4 
◦
C. This cultivation cycle was repeated 4 times for stabilization of the lines, before being used in this study. Five biological replicates from 
S. tuberosum
cultivated varieties, the allotetraploid lines 4xAL2 and 4xAL4, the autotetraploids 4xAuL1, 4xAuL2 and 4xAuL3, and their respective parental lines, 2xPIH and 2xPL, were set in a random design for the assay. Plants were grown in 2,5 L pots filled with soil mixture in a growth chamber under 16 h light: 8 h dark photoperiod at 325 μmol m 
2
s 
1
irradiance and 25 ± 2 
◦
C. After 30 days, fully expanded leaves (young and photosynthetically active, located 10 cm from the apex) were dissected and immediately processed or frozen at 80 
◦
C for further analysis. All further analyses were performed on three independent samplings of the 5 plants (biological replicates) for each of the 10 evaluated lines (2 diploid and 8 tetraploids).
</p>
      <p>2.3. Determination of secondary metabolites in potato leaves by SPME- GC-MS (solid-phase microextraction-gas chromatography-mass spectrometry)
</p>
      <p>
Samples of fully expanded leaves (1 g Fresh Weight, fr. wt) from 5 plants of each line were ground to a fine powder using mortar and pestle, and then transferred to amber vials with 5 ml of saturated saline solution (25% NaCl). An aliquot of 10 μl 4-methyl-2-pentanone (Sigma Aldrich Chromasolv for HPLC, St Louis, USA) was added as internal standard to the mixture, and immediately the vials were hermetically sealed with a polypropylene hole cap and PTFE/silicone septa (Supelco, Bellefonte, PA, USA). The vials were sonicated 10 min at 4 
◦
C and left to equilibrate 10 min in a temperature-controlled vial agitator tray (40 
◦
C, ~700 rpm). Then, a SPME fiber (PDMS/DVB 65 μm; Supelco, Bellefonte, PA, USA) was inserted into the sealed vial by manually penetrating the septum, and was exposed to the aqueous samples during the extraction time of 30 min at 40 
◦
C. Following the sampling procedure, the SPME device was immediately inserted into the GC-MS system for split-less injection port and thermally desorbed for 4 min at 250 
◦
C. The splitter, at 10 ml min 
1
, was opened during other 4 min. Fibers were thermally conditioned in accordance with the manufacturer’ s recommendations before first use. Also, before each sampling procedure, fibers were reconditioned for 10 min in the injection port of GC at 250 
◦
C. This reconditioning procedure was enough to guarantee no peaks in blank runs, and it was a good compromise between the chromatography runs and the extraction procedures. The Column used was a 30 m x 0,32 mm (ID) x 0,25 μm Agilent DB-WAX column, temperature-programmed after 5 min from 35 
◦
C to 70 
◦
C at 3 
◦
C min 
1
, hold for 2 min, and then to 165 
◦
C at 2 
◦
C min 
1
with a final hold of 1 min. The He carrier gas flow was constant at 1 ml min 
1
; injector and interface temperatures were 240 
◦
C and 200 
◦
C, respectively. The GC-MS analysis was carried out with a PerkinElmer model Clarus 500 (Shelton, CA, United States). The total time of an analytical cycle was optimized to 67 min. Compounds were identified by comparison of GC retention times and full mass spectra of the corresponding standard and by using their fragmentation pattern and comparison with data of the NIST library. Peak areas were referred to the standard 4 methyl 2 pentanone for quantification. Each experiment was repeated three times.
</p>
      <p>2.4. Determination of secondary metabolites compounds in potato leaves by MTBE-GC-MS (methyl tert-butyl ether)
</p>
      <p>
According to the experimental design, potato leaves (500 mg fr. wt) from 5 plants were cut and immediately ground with liquid nitrogen and put into amber glass tubes with 1 ml of MTBE (anhydrous 99,8%, Sigma- Aldrich). The mix was vigorously shaken for 30 s and transferred to 1.5 ml microtubes. After centrifuged for 10 min at 13,200 rpm (Eppendorf model 5415 D) 100 μl of supernatant were put into a vial. Then, an aliquot (1 μl) was injected and analyzed by GC-MS (same equipment mentioned above) in split-less mode (purge after 1.5 min) onto a 30 m x 0,25 mm (ID) x 0,25 μm Agilent HP-5MS column. The temperature program was: 3.5 min from 44 
◦
C to 200 
◦
C at 5 
◦
C min 
1
, then to 310 
◦
C at 40 
◦
C min 
1
with a final hold of 13 min. The He carrier gas flow was constant at 1.30 ml min 
1
; injector and interface temperatures were 240 
◦
C and 200 
◦
C, respectively. N-hexadecane was used as an internal standard. The ionization potential was 70 eV and a range of 40–500 atomic mass units (amu) was scanned. Each experiment was repeated three times.
</p>
      <p>2.5. Analysis of amino acids (AAs) compounds in potato leaves by SPE- GC-MS (solid phase extraction)
</p>
      <p>
For the determination and quantification of free amino acids, 50–60 mg of fully expanded leaves stored in a freezer of 80 
◦
C were ground to a fine powder using a mortar and pestle in liquid nitrogen. Then, they were macerated with 1 ml of 0.1 M HCl. The suspension was transferred to an Eppendorf microtube, and 10 μl of methionine sulfone (1000 ppm) were added as internal standard. The tubes were shaken for 10 min and centrifuged for 5 min at 13,200 rpm. After that, the supernatant was purified by SPE, using a column of Isolute SCX 100 mg ml 
1
(Biotage brand, USA) preconditioned with 1 ml of 0.1 M HCl and 3 ml of water milliQ. The amino acids were eluted with 250 μl of 8 M NH 
4
OH: MeOH (1:1) and the fraction was collected in a 1.5 ml glass vial. Once the free amino acids had been obtained and purified, they were derivatized with 10 μl of pyridine (Fluka, Germany) and 20 μl of ethyl chloroformate (Alfa Aesar, Shore Roads, United Kingdom). Then, 90 μl of chloroform and 90 μl of 50 mM NaHCO 
3
were added by vortexing for 1 min and placed in a freezer for 15 min. At that point, 70 μl of the lower phase were taken and transferred to another glass vial. Finally, 2 μl were injected by autosampler into a GC-MS system (as mentioned above). The column used was Phenomenex ZB 5 MS Plus, capillary column 30 m long, 0.25 mm thick and 0.25 μm film. The injector temperature was set at 240 
◦
C and the injections were carried out in the splitless mode. He (purity 99.9%) was used as a carrier gas at a flow rate of 1.0 ml min- 
1
. The oven temperature program was set as follows: initial temperature at 70 
◦
C for 1 min, followed by an increase of 10 
◦
C min 
1
to 280 
◦
C, and held for 10 min. The ionization potential was 70 eV and a range of 50–360 amu was scanned. Compounds were identified by comparison of retention times and mass spectra with a set of authentic standards to obtain unambiguous identification (Ala) L-alanine, (Asn) L-asparagine, (Asp) L-aspartic acid, (Cys) L-cysteine, (GABA) γ- aminobutyric acid, (Glu) L-glutamic acid, (Gln) L-glutamine, (Gly) glycine, (His) L-histidine, (Iso) L-isoleucine, (Leu) L-leucine, (Lys) L-lysine, (Met) L-methionine, (Phe) L-phenylalanine, (Pro) L-proline, (Thr) L-threonine, (Trp) Ltryptophan, (Tyr) L-tyrosine, (Val) L-valine, obtained from Fluka (Sigma-Aldrich, Steinheim, Switzerland), and peak areas were referred to the standard methionine sulfone for quantification.
</p>
      <p>2.6. Data analysis
</p>
      <p>
For each compound, analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to determine statistical differences between the content in allo- and autotetraploids and their respective diploid lines, as well as among 
S. tuberosum
cultivated varieties. A Duncan’ s multiple range test (DMRT) was used as a post hoc test to measure specific differences between pairs of means. For each compound, the logarithm of the fold change (logFC) in tetraploids respect to the diploid was calculated as log10(Tetraploid/ Diploid). Also, the average of the absolute logFC for each tetraploid line was obtained and ANOVA and DMRT were carried out as statistical tests. ANOVA and DMRT were performed using agricolae package of R (de Mendiburu, 2019). From SPME determination and amino acids results, principal component analyses (PCAs) were obtained using the Euclidean distance to calculate the distance matrix of all samples, based on centered and standardized data. Data was analyzed separately for the
</p>
      <p>
three groups: allotetraploids, autotetraploids and 
S. tuberosum
varieties. PCAs were done using FactoMineR and factoextra packages of R (Kassambara and Mundt, 2017; Leˆet al., 2008). A hierarchical clustering analysis (HCA) was carried out to compare allotetraploids, autotetraploids and cultivated varieties based on the amino acids data, since the same compounds were found in both groups. Matrices were normalized by compound and clustering was done by genotype and by compound using UPGMA (Unweight Pair Group Method with Arithmetic Mean) clustering method. Genesis Software (Sturn et al., 2002) was used for HCA analysis.
</p>
      <p>3. Results
</p>
      <p>3.1. Analysis of potato leaf extracts by SPME-GC-MS and MTBE-GC-MS
</p>
      <p>The profiles of VOC, non-isoprenoid and terpenoid compounds, for tetraploid lines, diploid parents and cultivated varieties were evaluated by SPME analysis and, to expand the identification of more possible compounds, an MTBE trial was included. The metabolic profiling of leaf extracts by SPME-GC-MS identified 39 compounds for allotetraploids and 28 for autotetraploids, including their respective diploid parents, and 41 compounds for cultivated varieties (Supplementary Tables S1, S2 and S3). Between diploid lines, the 2xPL leaf extract presented 75% more total content than the 2xPIH extract (Supplementary Tables S1 and S2). In allotetraploids 21 sesquiterpenes (2 derivatives), 5 monoterpenes and 13 non-isoprenoid compounds were detected; whereas in autotetraploids, sesquiterpenes showed less diversity with 9 compounds and 2 derivatives. Monoterpenes (4) and non-isoprenoid (13) compounds maintained similar diversity with respect to allotetraploid lines (Supplementary Table S2). In the cultivated varieties 21 sesquiterpenes (1 derivative), 4 monoterpenes (1 derivative) and 15 non-isoprenoids were found.</p>
      <p>
Line 4xAL2 showed the highest content of sesquiterpenes (≈140 μg g 
1
fr. wt) exceeding in more than 22 times the value found in its parental line 2xPIH (≈6.3 μg g 
1
fr. wt) and 93 times the total identified in 4xAL4 (≈1.5 μg g 
1
fr. wt). Among them, (T14) α- himachalene, (T15) β- himachalene, and (T17) longifolene exhibited the highest concentrations in 4xAL2. Moreover, the content of (T15) β- himachalene identified in 4xAL2 (over 48 μg g 
1
fr. wt) was significantly higher than in 2xPIH (≈0.42 μg g 
1
fr. wt) and in 4xAL4 lines (≈0.09 μg g 
1
fr. wt). Also, 4xAL2 exceeded by far the content of (T14) α- himachalene, (T16) γ -himachalene, (T04) epi-bicyclosesquiphellandrene, (T12) β- farnesene and (T19) valencene found in 2xPIH and 4xAL4 (Supplementary Table S1).
</p>
      <p>
On the other hand, sesquiterpenes detected in autotetraploids were fewer in diversity (Supplementary Table S2). 4xAuL1 and 4xAuL3 presented the highest contents (≈70 μg g 
1
fr. wt and ≈64 μg g 
1
fr. wt), 6 times the values found in 2xPL and AuL2. Among them, (T17) Longifolene was one of the most abundant either in 4xAuL1 (≈32.50 μg g 
1
fr. wt) and in 4xAuL3 (≈27.65 μg g 
1
fr. wt). Also, (T04) epibicyclosesquiphellandrene was similarly high in both 4xAuL1 and 4xAuL3 (≈28.90 μg g 
1
fr. wt and ≈28.30 μg g 
1
fr. wt, respectively), and less abundant in 4xAUL2 and 2xPL (≈3.80 μg g 
1
fr. wt and ≈4.80 μg g 
1
fr. wt). Among the three cultivated varieties, extracts from 4xPampeana (≈11 μg g 
1
fr. wt) and 4xCalen (≈10 μg g 
1
fr. wt) contained more than two times higher amounts of sesquiterpenes than 4xInnovator. On average, allotetraploids (≈56 μg g 
1
fr. wt) as well as autotetraploids (≈39 μg g 
1
fr. wt) presented more sesquiterpenes than cultivated varieties (≈8.77 μg g 
1
fr. wt).
</p>
      <p>
By contrast, monoterpenes were sparser compared to sesquiterpenes, representing a minor fraction of the total terpene content (Supplementary Tables S1, S2 and S3). D-limonene (T54) showed the highest abundance among autotetraploids (≈568 ng g 
1
fr. wt) in 4xAuL1 line, meanwhile (T55) β- pinene (≈103 ng g 
1
fr. wt) and (T53) camphene (≈91 ng g 
1
fr. wt) were the highest in the allotetraploids (4xAL2). Among the three cultivated varieties tested, dihydrocarveol was always the most abundant compound (Supplementary Table S3).
</p>
      <p>Through MTBE analysis 16 terpenes additional to the ones detected by SPME were identified. Although the concentration of sesquiterpenes diminished significantly respect to the SPME analysis, the major values were, again, identified in 4xAL2 line for the allotetraploid group (Supplementary Tables S4) and 4xAuL1 and 4xAuL3 for the autotetraploid group (Supplementary Table S5). In the cultivated varieties group, 4xPampeana showed the highest amount of sesquiterpenes followed by 4xInnovator (Supplementary Table S6).</p>
      <p>As it can be observed, the secondary metabolite profiles of artificially induced tetraploids did not differ in diversity respect to their parental lines, but they did vary drastically in their concentration (Supplementary Tables S1 and S2). Also, both allo- and autotetraploid lines presented significantly higher amounts of sesquiterpenes with respect to cultivated varieties.</p>
      <p>3.2. Amino acids analysis
</p>
      <p>
Eighteen amino acids were detected in leaves of allotetraploids and cultivated varieties, while 17 amino acids were determined in autotetraploids (Supplementary Tables S7, S8 and S9). Within allotetraploids, 4xAL4 by far presented the major content of amino acids, except for Ltryptophan, for which the parental line 2xPIH doubled the values of both 4xAL2 and 4xAL4 (Supplementary Table S7). In autotetraploids, though the concentration of amino acids was superior in 4xAuL1 leaves (Supplementary Table S8), the content of glycine (6.971 μg g 
1
fr. wt) in 4xAuL3 surpassed the concentration found in 2xPL and the other two autotetraploid lines. Among cultivated varieties, 4xPampeana showed around 80% more amino acids than the other two varieties (Supplementary Table S9). The level of L-proline was particularly high (15.073 μg g 
1
fr. wt), accounting for 27% of the total amino acid content. Glutamine and serine were not detected in either group.
</p>
      <p>Within allotetraploids, 4xAL4 leaves concentrated the highest abundance of amino acids (Supplementary Table S7), contrasting with the content of terpenes and non-isoprenoid compounds, in which 4xAL2 registered the greatest concentrations.</p>
      <p>For the three groups the non-polar amino acids were the same and they differed only in one polar amino acid, although, in terms of concentration, the cultivated varieties presented greater amounts than allo- and autotetraploids (Supplementary Tables S7, S8 and S9).</p>
      <p>3.3. Volatile organic compounds (VOCs)
</p>
      <p>VOCs are compounds of low molecular weight which are in a gaseous form under standard atmospheric and temperature conditions. They include isoprenoids and non-isoprenoids compounds as hydrocarbons, alcohols, aldehydes, and ketones. From the 39 compounds analyzed for allotetraploids (Supplementary Tables S1) and 13 non isoprenoids VOCs were identified. Among them: 1 aliphatic alkane, 1 aromatic alkene, 5 aliphatic alcohols, 3 aliphatic aldehydes, 1 aliphatic acid, 1 aliphatic ketone, and 1 furan derivative. Regarding autotetraploids, 1 aliphatic and 1 aromatic alkane, 1 aliphatic alkene, 1 aromatic and 4 aliphatic alcohols, 1 aliphatic ketone, 2 aliphatic aldehydes and 2 esters (1 aromatic) were detected (Supplementary Table S2). In the three cultivated varieties 15 non isoprenoids were found, which comprised 1 aliphatic alkane, 1 aromatic alkene, 1 aromatic and 4 aliphatic alcohols, 5 aliphatic aldehydes, 1 aliphatic ketone, 1 furan derivative and 1 salicylic acid derivative (Supplementary Table S3).</p>
      <p>In general, for both allo- and autotetraploid groups, the metabolic profiles of the tetraploids were by far superior to their parental diploid lines (Supplementary Tables S1 and S2). By comparing within allotetraploids and autotetraploids, 4xAL2 and 4xAuL1 exhibit the highest concentrations of each group.</p>
      <p>Only in a few cases the parental lines outgrew their tetraploid derivatives, such as (NI04) Spiro 2,4 hepta-4,6-diene in 2xPIH and, (NI05) undecane and (NI16) 4-undecene-7-methyl in 2xPL.</p>
      <p>3.4. LogFC of compounds content in tetraploids respect to diploids
</p>
      <p>
In order to compare both models, the allotetraploid and the autotetraploid, an analysis of the compounds content logFC respect to the diploid lines was performed. In the allotetraploid model, 4xAL2 showed increases for terpenes and non-isoprenoid compounds and decreases in amino acids, respect to the diploid 2xPIH. On the other hand, 4xAL4 behaved exactly in the opposite way (

). In the autotetraploid model the three lines showed smaller changes than the allotetraploids, except for line 4xAuL1 regarding amino acid content (

).
</p>
      <p>
Considering the three metabolite classes together (non-isoprenoids, terpenoids and amino acids), the change in compounds content was larger on average for the allotetraploids (0.82) than for autotetraploids (0.45) (p 
&lt;
0.01).
</p>
      <p>3.5. Principal components analysis
</p>
      <p>
PCA analyses were performed for allotetraploids, autotetraploids and cultivated varieties separately and biplots projecting individuals and variables were obtained (

). The two allotetraploids 4xAL2 and 4xAL4 showed very contrasting behaviors and the diploid parental hybrid 2xPIH was intermediate between them (

). Amino acids were located around 4xAL4, while monoterpenes and most of the sesquiterpenes were nearby 4xAL2.
</p>
      <p>
Whilst in the autotetraploid group the distribution of metabolites was not strongly associated with a particular genotype as in the allotetraploid group and many compounds located in the middle of the plot, there was still differentiation among lines, where each autotetraploid located diametrically opposite to the other two (

). Most terpenoids were related to 4xAuL3, while most amino acids were around 4xAuL2 and 2xPL. The line 4xAuL1 was abundant with non-isoprenoids.
</p>
      <p>The cultivated varieties behaved similarly to the autotetraploid group, since most compounds located on the center of the plot and no class was associated to one particular genotype.</p>
      <p>3.6. Hierarchal clustering analysis of amino acids
</p>
      <p>
A hierarchical clustering analysis (HCA) was carried out to compare allotetraploids, autotetraploids and cultivated varieties by their AAs content. A heat-map was obtained showing two dendrograms corresponding to the clustering of individuals and AAs (

). In the top dendrogram one cluster gathers the three cultivated varieties and a sister cluster groups the autotetraploids and their diploid parental line, except 4xAuL2. Outside of those clusters is located a third cluster with the two allotetraploids and the diploid hybrid. The other dendrogram presents two main clusters: the top one gets together seven amino acids, which are abundant in the cultivated varieties and in line 4xAuL2; and the below one consists of two subgroups: one with 5 AAs with higher concentration in the autotetraploid group and the other with 6 AAs highly present in the allotetraploid group, particularly in 4xAL4.
</p>
      <p>4. Discussion
</p>
      <p>In a previous work, we observed that allotetraploid and autotetraploid potato lines showed higher vigor in morphological traits as compared with diploid parental lines 2xPIH and 2xPL, respectively (Marfil et al., 2018). Therefore, in this study we expected that these tetraploid lines would be accompanied by modifications in the metabolic profiling of AAs and VOCs. In effect, this is the first report that analyzes these compounds in potato allopolyploid lines.</p>
      <p>
Regarding the AAs assessed in this work, two tetraploids, 4xAL4 and 4xAuL1, significantly exceeded the values found in the parental lines. These high levels of free AAs in leaves could play a role in stress response, as reported by Less and Galili (2008), who suggested that the increase of free amino acids in leaves of 
Arabidopsis thaliana
plants subjected to drought, could be the result of protein degradation to
</p>
      <p>
produce osmolytes activated during the water stress. In that way, the polyploidization in potato may produce some genotypes or lines more tolerant to drought than their diploid parental lines. Also, it has been reported that 
S. commersonii
tetraploids increased the concentration of L-glutamic acid, a key molecule in amino acids metabolism (Fasano et al., 2016). In agreement with this data, in our study 4xAL4 and 4xAuL2 lines augmented the content of L-glutamic acid in more than 300% and 50% respect to their diploid parents, respectively. L-glutamic acid contributes to the redox balance of the cells due to its role as a precursor of glutathione, L-proline and polyamines, well known ROS
</p>
      <p>scavengers (Dolezˇel et al., 2007; Kocsy et al., 2000a; Murashige and Skoog, 1962; Kov´acs et al., 2011). Concerning the amino acid L-proline, the highest concentration was observed in the tetraploid lines 4xAL4 and 4xAuL3. It has been stated that the accumulation of L-proline, the amino acid related to water stress, may have a key role in plant tolerance (Joshi et al., 2011). In this sense, L-proline can be mobilized to synthesize proteins needed to cope with water deficit or alternatively to serve as osmotic adjuster (Murcia et al., 2017). Histidine showed a significant increase in the two evaluated allotetraploid lines compared with the diploid parent. This AA plays important roles in plant</p>
      <p>reproduction and growth, in the regulation of biosynthesis of other amino acids and in chelation and transport of metal ions (Stepansky and Leustek, 2006) and its variation could participate in the high phenotypic variability observed in allotetraploids compared with its diploid parent (Marfil et al., 2018). Interestingly, the cultivated varieties presented higher amount of amino acids compared to the allo- and autotetraploid lines.</p>
      <p>
Among the isoprenoid VOCs, terpenes are secondary metabolites with antioxidant properties playing a protective role against abiotic (Alonso et al., 2015; Gil et al., 2012; Kolb et al., 2001; Leicach et al., 2010) and biotic (Escoriaza et al., 2013; Leitner et al., 2008; Pontin et al., 2015) stresses. In this study, we detected several terpenes in the tetraploid lines that exceeded the contents in the parental lines. Among the non-isoprenoids, the compounds (NI01) furan-2-ethyl, (NI02) methyl-2-ethylhexanoate, (NI05) undecane, (NI06) 2-dodecanol, (NI07) 1-hepten-3-ol, (NI08) 1-hexanol, (NI09) 3-hexen-1-ol, (NI11) 2,4-heptadienal, (NI13) 2-hexenal, (NI14) iso-propyl salicylate, (NI17) phenylethyl alcohol and (NI18) 2-propyl-1-pentanol are associated to bactericidal and fungicidal activities, which are augmented in some tetraploid lines (Chen et al., 2018; Krajicek et al., 2016). Putting all together, these compounds may benefit the plant, at least at the vegetative stages, with a battery of different compounds with defined function as plant-protectors towards biotic stresses. Our results suggest that it could not be predicted if a polyploidization event in potato would produce more tolerant lines or genotypes. Taking into account the scarce information regarding the effect of polyploidization on amino acids and VOCs in potato leaves, it is noteworthy that in autopolyploid lines amino acids enhancement was accompanied by an increase of terpenoids and non-isoprenoids contents. On the other hand, allopolyploid lines showed a different response: enhancement of AAs contents in 4xAuL4 was accompanied by a decrease of terpenoids and non-isoprenoids contents and 
vice versa
, decrease of AAs contents in 4xAuL2 was accompanied by
</p>
      <p>an increase of terpenoids and non-isoprenoids contents. Moreover, both allo- and autotetraploid lines presented significantly higher amounts of sesquiterpenes with respect to cultivated varieties.</p>
      <p>These results demonstrate that the content of compounds varied greatly among these tetraploid lines, which could be explained by changes in gene expression induced by genomic rearrangements, as proposed by Marfil et al. (2018). In this sense, the allotetraploids showed the highest changes in several compounds compared with the autotetraploids. It is possible that the genomic instability originated by the hybridization in allopolyploids induced novel epigenetic variability and alteration in gene expression. Amongst these, terpenes were the most significantly affected led by the sesquiterpenes both in quantity and diversity. This fact supports the idea that genome duplication is a stochastic source of variability (Aversano et al., 2013).</p>
      <p>5. Conclusions
</p>
      <p>It is known that amino acids are important as primary metabolites, and that non isoprenoids are also essential intermediates or precursors of important metabolic pathways. As it can be seen from our results, terpenes showed qualitative and quantitative differences among tetraploids, that play a fundamental role in cell metabolism and physiology in response to abiotic/biotic stresses (Murcia et al., 2018; Salomon et al., 2014). The evaluated lines responded unequally to polyploidization, showing an increase or decrease on different metabolites content compared with their respective diploid parental lines.</p>
      <p>
Potato crop is threatened by several biotic and abiotic stresses such as pests, diseases, heat, and drought. Expensive and environmentally harmful chemical methods are used for pest and disease control in commercial potato crop (Hawkes, 1990; Ross, 1986). Our results are important for breeders since we showed an increase of terpenoids content in leaves of tetraploid genotypes, compared to diploid parental lines and cultivated varieties, that may confer resistance to several stresses. On the other hand, tetraploid genotypes of 
S. kurtzianum
may be directly used for introgression of resistances in the 4x gene pool of the cultivated potato by sexual hybridization.
</p>
      <p>Declaration of competing interest
</p>
      <p>We do not declared any conflict of interest.</p>
      <p>Acknowledgments
</p>
      <p>This work was financially supported by Agencia Nacional de Promoci´on Científica y T´ecnica (ANPCyT) PICT 1243, Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y T´ecnicas (PIP 0685), and Universidad Nacional de Cuyo, SECTYP 06/A597.</p>
      <p>Appendix A. Supplementary data
</p>
      <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi. org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112516.</p>
      <p>References
</p>
      <p>Alonso, R., Berli, F.J., Bottini, R., Piccoli, P., 2015. Acclimation mechanisms elicited by sprayed abscisic acid, solar UV-B and water deficit in leaf tissues of field-grown grapevines. Plant Physiol. Biochem. 91, 56–60. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.</p>
      <p>PLAPHY.2015.03.011.</p>
      <p>
Aversano, R., Caruso, I., Aronne, G., De Micco, V., Scognamiglio, N., Carputo, D., 2013. Stochastic changes affect 
Solanum
wild species following autopolyploidization.
</p>
      <p>J. Exp. Bot. 64, 625–635. https://doi.org/10.1093/jxb/ers357.</p>
      <p>
Berkov, S., Philipov, S., 2002. Alkaloid production in diploid and autotetraploid plants of 
Datura stramonium
. Pharm. Biol. 40, 617–621. https://doi.org/10.1076/ phbi.40.8.617.14650.
</p>
      <p>
Caruso, I., Dal Piaz, F., Malafronte, N., De Tommasi, N., Aversano, R., Wulff Zottele, C., Scarano, M.-T., Carputo, D., 2013. Impact of ploidy change on secondary metabolites and photochemical efficiency in 
Solanum bulbocastanum
. Nat. Prod. Commun. 8, 1387–1392. https://doi.org/10.1177/1934578X1300801011.
</p>
      <p>
Chao, D.-Y., Dilkes, B., Luo, H., Douglas, A., Yakubova, E., Lahner, B., Salt, D.E., 2013. Polyploids exhibit higher potassium uptake and salinity tolerance in 
Arabidopsis
.
</p>
      <p>Science 341, 658–659. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1240561.</p>
      <p>
Chen, R., Jiang, W., Li, Q., Li, X., Chen, X., Yang, Y., Wu, H., 2016. Comparison of seven colchicine-induced tetraploid clones with their original diploid clones in purple coneflower (
Echinacea purpurea
L.). Euphytica 207, 387–399. https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s10681-015-1556-3.
</p>
      <p>
Chen, W., Zou, L., Chen, W., Hu, Y., Chen, H., 2018. Effects of black pepper (
Piper nigrum
L.) chloroform extract on the enzymatic activity and metabolism of 
Escherichia coli
and 
Staphylococcus aureus
. J. Food Qual. https://doi.org/10.1155/2018/9635184.
</p>
      <p>de Mendiburu, F., 2019. Agricolae: Statistical Procedures for Agricultural Research. URL. https://cran.r-project.org/package=agricolae.</p>
      <p>Dehghan, E., H¨akkinen, S.T., Oksman-Caldentey, K.-M., Shahriari Ahmadi, F., 2012.</p>
      <p>
Production of tropane alkaloids in diploid and tetraploid plants and in vitro hairy root cultures of Egyptian henbane (
Hyoscyamus muticus
L.). Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult. 110, 35–44. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11240-012-0127-8.
</p>
      <p>
Del Pozo, J.C., Ramirez-Parra, E., 2014. Deciphering the molecular bases for drought tolerance in 
Arabidopsis autotetraploids
. Plant Cell Environ. 37, 2722–2737. https:// doi.org/10.1111/pce.12344.
</p>
      <p>Dhooghe, E., van Laere, K., Eeckhaut, T., Leus, L., van Huylenbroeck, J., 2011. Mitotic chromosome doubling of plant tissues in vitro. Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult. 104, 359–373. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11240-010-9786-5.</p>
      <p>Doleˇzel, J., Greilhuber, J., Suda, J., 2007. Estimation of nuclear DNA content in plants using flow cytometry. Nat. Protoc. 2, 2233–2244. https://doi.org/10.1038/ nprot.2007.310.</p>
      <p>
Escoriaza, G., Sansberro, P., García-Lampasona, S., Gatica, M., Bottini, R., Piccoli, P., 2013. In vitro cultures of Vitis vinifera L. cv. Chardonnay synthesize the phytoalexin nerolidol upon infection by 
Phaeoacremonium parasiticum
. Phytopathol. Mediterr. 52, 289–297. https://doi.org/10.14601/Phytopathol_Mediterr-10509.
</p>
      <p>Evans, W.C., Evans, D., 2009. Phytochemical variation within a species. Trease and Evans’ Pharmacognosy. W.B. Saunders, London, pp. 106–116. https://doi.org/ 10.1016/B978-0-7020-2933-2.00014-9.</p>
      <p>
Fasano, C., Diretto, G., Aversano, R., D’ Agostino, N., Di Matteo, A., Frusciante, L., Giuliano, G., Carputo, D., 2016. Transcriptome and metabolome of synthetic 
Solanum
autotetraploids reveal key genomic stress events following polyploidization. New Phytol. 210, 1382–1394. https://doi.org/10.1111/nph.13878.
</p>
      <p>Flagel, L.E., Wendel, J.E., 2009. Gene duplication and evolutionaary novelty in plants. New Phytol. 183, 557–564. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02923.x.</p>
      <p>
Gao, R., Wang, H., Dong, B., Yang, X., Chen, S., Jiang, J., Zhang, Z., Liu, C., Zhao, N., Chen, F., 2016. Morphological, genome and gene expression changes in newly induced autopolyploid 
Chrysanthemum lavandulifolium
. Fisch. ex Trautv.) Makino.
</p>
      <p>Int. J. Mol. Sci. 17, 1690. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms17101690.</p>
      <p>
Gil, M., Pontin, M., Berli, F., Bottini, R., Piccoli, P., 2012. Metabolism of terpenes in the response of grape (
Vitis vinifera
L.) leaf tissues to UV-B radiation. Phytochemistry 77, 89–98. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2011.12.011.
</p>
      <p>Hawkes, J.G., 1990. The Potato: Evolution, Biodiversity, and Genetic Resources.</p>
      <p>Smithsonian Institution Press, Washington, DC.</p>
      <p>
Joshi, P.K., Saxena, S.C., Arora, S., 2011. Characterization of 
Brassica juncea
antioxidant potential under salinity stress. Acta Physiol. Plant. 33, 811–822. https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s11738-010-0606-7.
</p>
      <p>Karban, R., Yang, L.H., Edwards, K.F., 2014. Volatile communication between plants that affects herbivory: a meta-analysis. Ecol. Lett. 17, 44–52. https://doi.org/10.1111/ ele.12205.</p>
      <p>Kassambara, A., Mundt, F., 2017. Factoextra: extract and visualize the results of multivariate data analyses. URL. https://cran.r-project.org/package=factoextra.</p>
      <p>
Kegge, W., Ninkovic, V., Glinwood, R., Welschen, R.A.M., Voesenek, L.A.C.J., Pierik, R., 2015. Red:far-red light conditions affect the emission of volatile organic compounds from barley (
Hordeum vulgare
), leading to altered biomass allocation in neighbouring plants. Ann. Bot. 115, 961–970. https://doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcv036.
</p>
      <p>Kesselmeier, J., Staudt, M., 1999. Biogenic volatile organic compounds (VOC): an overview on emission, physiology and ecology. J. Atmos. Chem. 33, 23–88. https:// doi.org/10.1023/A:1006127516791.</p>
      <p>Kocsy, G., Szalai, G., V´agújfalvi, A., St´ehli, L., Orosz, G., Galiba, G., 2000. Genetic study of glutathione accumulation during cold hardening in wheat. Planta 210, 295–301. https://doi.org/10.1007/PL00008137.</p>
      <p>Kolb, C.A., K¨aser, M.A., Kopecký, J., Zotz, G., Riederer, M., Pfündel, E.E., 2001. Effects of natural intensities of visible and ultraviolet radiation on epidermal ultraviolet screening and photosynthesis in grape leaves. Plant Physiol. 127, 863–875. https:// doi.org/10.1104/pp.010373.</p>
      <p>Kondorosi, E., Roudier, F., Gendreau, E., 2000. Plant cell-size control: growing by ploidy? Curr. Opin. Plant Biol. 3, 488–492. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1369-5266 (00)00118-7.</p>
      <p>Konig ¨, M.A.E., Wiklund, C., Ehrl´en, J., 2014. Context-dependent resistance against butterfly herbivory in a polyploid herb. Oecologia 174, 1265–1272. https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s00442-013-2831-4.</p>
      <p>Kov´acs, Z., Simon-Sarkadi, L., Sov´any, C., Kirsch, K., Galiba, G., Kocsy, G., 2011.</p>
      <p>Differential effects of cold acclimation and abscisic acid on free amino acid composition in wheat. Plant Sci. 180, 61–68. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.</p>
      <p>plantsci.2010.08.010.</p>
      <p>Krajicek, J., Havlikova, M., Bursova, M., Ston, M., Cabala, R., Exnerova, A., Stys, P., Bosakova, Z., 2016. Comparative analysis of volatile defensive secretions of three species of pyrrhocoridae (Insecta: heteroptera) by gas chromatography-mass spectrometric method. PloS One 11, e0168827. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.</p>
      <p>pone.0168827.</p>
      <p>Lavania, U.C., 2005. Genomic and ploidy manipulation for enhanced production of phyto-pharmaceuticals. Plant Genet. Resour. Charact. Util. 3, 170–177. https://doi. org/10.1079/PGR200576.</p>
      <p>Lˆe, S., Josse, J., Husson, F., 2008. FactoMineR: an R package for multivariate analysis. J. Stat. Software 25, 1–18. https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v025.i01.</p>
      <p>
Leicach, S.R., Garau, A.M., Guarnaschelli, A.B., Yaber Grass, M.A., Sztarker, N.D., Dato, A., 2010. Changes in 
Eucalyptus camaldulensis
essential oil composition as response to drought preconditioning. J. Plant Interact. 5, 205–210. https://doi.org/ 10.1080/17429145.2010.483744.
</p>
      <p>Leitner, M., Kaiser, R., Rasmussen, M.O., Driguez, H., Boland, W., Mith¨ofer, A., 2008.</p>
      <p>
Microbial oligosaccharides differentially induce volatiles and signalling components in 
Medicago truncatula
. Phytochemistry 69, 2029–2040. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. phytochem.2008.04.019.
</p>
      <p>Less, H., Galili, G., 2008. Principal transcriptional programs regulating plant amino acid metabolism in response to abiotic stresses. Plant Physiol. 147, 316–330. https://doi. org/10.1104/pp.108.115733.</p>
      <p>Loreto, F., Schnitzler, J.-P., 2010. Abiotic stresses and induced BVOCs. Trends Plant Sci. 15, 154–166. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.TPLANTS.2009.12.006.</p>
      <p>Majdi, M., Karimzadeh, G., Malboobi, M.A., Omidbaigi, R., Mirzaghaderi, G., 2010.</p>
      <p>
Induction of tetraploidy to feverfew (
Tanacetum parthenium
schulz-bip.): morphological, physiological, cytological, and phytochemical changes. Hortscience 45, 16–21. https://doi.org/10.21273/HORTSCI.45.1.16.
</p>
      <p>Marfil, C.F., Duarte, P.F., Masuelli, R.W., 2018. Phenotypic and epigenetic variation induced in newly synthesized allopolyploids and autopolyploids of potato. Sci.</p>
      <p>Hortic. (Amst.) 234, 101–109. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scienta.2018.02.022.</p>
      <p>
Marfil, C.F., Masuelli, R.W., Davison, J., Comai, L., 2006. Genomic instability in 
Solanum tuberosum
x 
Solanum kurtzianum
interspecific hybrids. Genome 49, 104–113.
</p>
      <p>Masterson, J., 1994. Stomatal size in fossil plants: evidence for polyploidy in majority of angiosperms. Science 264, 421–424. https://doi.org/10.1126/ science.264.5157.421.</p>
      <p>Murashige, T., Skoog, F., 1962. A revised medium for rapid growth and bio assays with tobacco tissue cultures. Physiol. Plantarum 15, 473–497. https://doi.org/10.1111/ j.1399-3054.1962.tb08052.x.</p>
      <p>Murcia, G., Fontana, A., Pontin, M., Baraldi, R., Bertazza, G., Piccoli, P.N., 2017. ABA and GA3 regulate the synthesis of primary and secondary metabolites related to alleviation from biotic and abiotic stresses in grapevine. Phytochemistry 135, 34–52.</p>
      <p>https://doi.org/10.1016/J.PHYTOCHEM.2016.12.007.</p>
      <p>
Murcia, G., Pontin, M., Piccoli, P., 2018. Role of ABA and Gibberellin A3 on gene expression pattern of sugar transporters and invertases in 
Vitis vinifera
cv. Malbec during berry ripening. Plant Growth Regul. 84, 275–283. https://doi.org/10.1007/ s10725-017-0338-4.
</p>
      <p>Ninkovic, V., Markovic, D., Dahlin, I., 2016. Decoding neighbour volatiles in preparation for future competition and implications for tritrophic interactions. Perspect. Plant Ecol. Evol. Systemat. 23, 11–17. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.PPEES.2016.09.005.</p>
      <p>
Nuismer, S.L., Cunningham, B.M., 2005. Selection for phenotypic divergence between diploid and autotetraploid 
Heuchera grossulariifolia
. Evolution 59, 1928–1935.
</p>
      <p>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.0014-3820.2005.tb01062.x.</p>
      <p>Otto, F., 1990. Chapter 11 DAPI staining of fixed cells for high-resolution flow cytometry of nuclear DNA. Methods Cell Biol. 33, 105–110. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0091- 679X(08)60516-6.</p>
      <p>Otto, S.P., 2007. The evolutionary consequences of polyploidy. Cell 131, 452–462.</p>
      <p>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2007.10.022.</p>
      <p>Pe˜nuelas, J., Farr´e-Armengol, G., Llusia, J., Gargallo-Garriga, A., Rico, L., Sardans, J., Terradas, J., Filella, I., 2014. Removal of floral microbiota reduces floral terpene emissions. Sci. Rep. 4, 6727. https://doi.org/10.1038/srep06727.</p>
      <p>Pichersky, E., Gang, D.R., 2000. Genetics and biochemistry of secondary metabolites in plants: an evolutionary perspective. Trends Plant Sci. 5, 439–445. https://doi.org/ 10.1016/S1360-1385(00)01741-6.</p>
      <p>Pichersky, E., Gershenzon, J., 2002. The formation and function of plant volatiles: perfumes for pollinator attraction and defense. Curr. Opin. Plant Biol. 5, 237–243.</p>
      <p>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1369-5266(02)00251-0.</p>
      <p>Pierik, R., Visser, E.J.W., de Kroon, H., Voesenek, L.A.C.J., 2003. Ethylene is required in tobacco to successfully compete with proximate neighbours. Plant Cell Environ. 26, 1229–1234. https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-3040.2003.01045.x.</p>
      <p>
Pires, J.C., Zhao, J., Schranz, M.E., Leon, E.J., Quijada, P.A., Lukens, L.N., Osborn, T.C., 2004. Flowering time divergence and genomic rearrangements in resynthesized 
Brassica
polyploids (Brassicaceae). Biol. J. Linn. Soc. 82, 675–688. https://doi.org/ 10.1111/j.1095-8312.2004.00350.x.
</p>
      <p>
Pontin, M., Bottini, R., Burba, J.L., Piccoli, P., 2015. 
Allium sativum
produces terpenes with fungistatic properties in response to infection with Sclerotium cepivorum.
</p>
      <p>Phytochemistry 115, 152–160. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2015.02.003.</p>
      <p>Ramsey, J., Schemske, D.W., 1998. Pathways, mechanisms, and rates of polyploid formation in flowering plants. Annu. Rev. Ecol. Systemat. 29, 467–501. https://doi. org/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.29.1.467.</p>
      <p>Ross, H., 1986. Potato Breeding Problems and Perspectives. Paul Parey, Berlin.</p>
      <p>Saleh, B., Allario, T., Dambier, D., Ollitrault, P., Morillon, R., 2008. Tetraploid citrus rootstocks are more tolerant to salt stress than diploid. C. R. Biol. 331, 703–710.</p>
      <p>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.crvi.2008.06.007.</p>
      <p>
Salomon, M.V., Bottini, R., de Souza Filho, G.A., Cohen, A.C., Moreno, D., Gil, M., Piccoli, P., 2014. Bacteria isolated from roots and rhizosphere of 
Vitis vinifera
retard water losses, induce abscisic acid accumulation and synthesis of defense-related terpenes in in vitro cultured grapevine. Physiol. Plantarum 151, 359–374. https:// doi.org/10.1111/ppl.12117.
</p>
      <p>Seabra, A.R., Silva, L.S., Carvalho, H.G., 2013. Novel aspects of glutamine synthetase (GS) regulation revealed by a detailed expression analysis of the entire GS gene</p>
      <p>
family of 
Medicago truncatula
under different physiological conditions. BMC Plant Biol. 13, 137. https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-13-137.
</p>
      <p>Segraves, K.A., Anneberg, T.J., 2016. Species interactions and plant polyploidy. Am. J. Bot. 103, 1326–1335. https://doi.org/10.3732/ajb.1500529.</p>
      <p>Soltis, D.E., Albert, V.A., Leebens-Mack, J., Bell, C.D., Paterson, A.H., Zheng, C., Sankoff, D., DePamphilis, C.W., Wall, P.K., Soltis, P.S., 2009. Polyploidy and angiosperm diversification. Am. J. Bot. 96, 336–348. https://doi.org/10.3732/ ajb.0800079.</p>
      <p>
Stanys, V., Weckman, A., Staniene, G., Duchovskis, P., 2006. In vitro induction of polyploidy in Japanese quince (
Chaenomeles japonica
). Plant Cell. Tissue Organ Cult 84, 263–268. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11240-005-9029-3.
</p>
      <p>Stepansky, A., Leustek, T., 2006. Histidine biosynthesis in plants. Amino Acids 30, 127–142. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00726-005-0247-0.</p>
      <p>Sturn, A., Quackenbush, J., Trajanoski, Z., 2002. Genesis: cluster analysis of microarray data. Bioinformatics 18, 207–208. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/ 18.1.207.</p>
      <p>
Sugiyama, S.-I., 2005. Polyploidy and cellular mechanisms changing leaf size: comparison of diploid and autotetraploid populations in two species of 
lolium
. Ann. Bot. 96, 931–938. https://doi.org/10.1093/aob/mci245.
</p>
      <p>
Xu, C., Tang, T., Chen, R., Liang, C., Liu, X., Wu, C., Yang, Y., Yang, D., Wu, H., 2014. A comparative study of bioactive secondary metabolite production in diploid and tetraploid 
Echinacea purpurea
(L.) Moench. Plant Cell. Tissue Organ Cult 116, 323–332. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11240-013-0406-z.
</p>
      <p>
Zhang, X.Y., Hu, C.G., Yao, J.L., 2010. Tetraploidization of diploid 
Dioscorea
results in activation of the antioxidant defense system and increased heat tolerance. J. Plant Physiol. 167, 88–94. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jplph.2009.07.006.
</p>
      <p>Zielinski, M.-L., Mittelsten Scheid, O., 2012. Meiosis in polyploid plants. In: Soltis, P.S., Soltis, D.E. (Eds.), Polyploidy and Genome Evolution. Springer, Heidelberg,</p>
      <p>pp. 33–55. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-31442-1_3.</p>
   </body>
</article>
