<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-37976-8</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Unique skull network complexity of Tyrannosaurus rex among land
               vertebrates</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> OPEN </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Received: 23 April 2018</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Accepted: 13 December 2018 Published: xx xx xxxx</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Unique skull network complexity of Tyrannosaurus rex among land vertebrates </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Ingmar Werneburg 1,2,3 , Borja Esteve-Altava 4,8 , Joana Bruno 5 , MartaTorres Ladeira
            6 &amp; Rui Diogo 7 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Like other diapsids, Tyrannosaurus rex has two openings in the temporal skull region.
            In addition, like in other dinosaurs, its snout and lower jaw show large cranial
            fenestrae. In T . rex , they are thought to decrease skull weight, because, unlike most
            other amniotes, the skull proportion is immense compared to the body. Understanding
            morphofunctional complexity of this impressive skull architecture requires a broad scale
            phylogenetic comparison with skull types different to that of dinosaurs with
            fundamentally diverging cranial regionalization. Extant fully terrestrial vertebrates
            (amniotes) provide the best opportunities in that regard, as their skull performance is
            known from life. We apply for the first time anatomical network analysis to study skull
            bone integration and modular constructions in tyrannosaur and compare it with five
            representatives of the major amniote groups in order to get an understanding of the
            general patterns of amniote skull modularity. Our results reveal that the tyrannosaur
            has the most modular skull organization among the amniotes included in our study, with
            an unexpected separation of the snout in upper and lower sub-modules and the presence of
            a lower adductor chamber module. Independent pathways of bone reduction in opossum and
            chicken resulted in different degrees of cranial complexity with chicken having a
            typical sauropsidian pattern. The akinetic skull of opossum, alligator, and leatherback
            turtle evolved in independent ways mirrored in different patterns of skull modularity.
            Kinetic forms also show great diversity in modularity.The complex tyrannosaur skull
            modularity likely represents a refined mosaic of phylogenetic and ecological factors
            with food processing being probably most important for shaping its skull architecture.
            Mode of food processing primarily shaped skull integration among amniotes, however,
            phylogenetic patterns of skull integration are low in our sampling. Our general
            conclusions on amniote skull integrity are obviously preliminary and should be tested in
            subsequent studies. As such, this study provides a framework for future research
            focusing on the evolution of modularity on lower taxonomic levels. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The hypercarnivore Tyrannosaurus rex (Theropoda) is an icon of paleontology and
            evolution. Its unique anatomy, including an immense skull and small forelimbs, has
            inspired a number of morphofunctional experiments 1,2 . Its skull length is about a
            sixth of the total body length, and cranial performance analyses resulted in
            reconstructions of a very powerful bite force 3–7 . In addition to the ancestral
            temporal fenestrae, large cranial openings in the snout and the lower jaw are thought to
            decrease skull weight and to better distribute strain when processing food, but also
            other morphofunctional reasons have been discussed such as specific muscle insertions,
            shock absorption, pneumaticity, and internal skull mobility 6,8, 9 . As a result, the
            skull shows a complex architecture made of several bone bars, typical also for other
            theropod dinosaurs. Theropod skull diversity 10,11 , like that of dinosaurs as a whole 8
            , is very high. A general understanding on the relationship between modular and
            functional patterns of amniote skulls is needed to understand the morphofunctional
            diversity of those groups. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Among fully terrestrial vertebrates (amniotes), a great diversity of skull types exists
            12 . For example, the temporal skull region behind the eye can be closed, can have one
            or, like in tyrannosaurs, two openings, or can display marginal reductions between
            bones. In addition, the snout, braincase, and palatal region experienced great
            modifications through evolution related to behavioral (e.g., neurobiological) and
            ecological (e.g., feeding, fossorial) adaptations 13 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Here we present the first study of the cranial complexity and modularity of T . rex in
            comparison with a sample representing all the major clades of extant amniotes
            (lepidosaurs, turtles, crocodylians, birds, and mammals) using Anatomical Network
            Analysis (AnNA) 14,15 . This methodology allows us to detect deeper anatomical aspects
            that cannot be examined otherwise and can provide crucial information about potential
            functional entities. AnNA complements the more traditional approach to morphological
            integration and modularity using morphometrics, which focuses on co-variations in size
            and shape 16 . Specifically, AnNA uses algorithms from network theory to quantify and
            compare the anatomy of organisms 14,15 . This approach starts with the modeling of
            anatomical structures as networks, in which nodes represent anatomical parts (e.g.,
            bones) and links represent their physical connections (e.g., articulations). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> We hypothesized that life performance of the tyrannosaur skull can be deduced from
            patterns of bone integration in extant amniote skulls, for which functional morphology
            is better understood than in any fossil. To better understand the skull of T . rex ,
            here we provide a function-related discussion of modularity in an evolutionary context
            17 . As representatives of the major extant amniote clades, we studied skull networks of
            the Virginian opossum, tuatara, leatherback turtle, alligator, and the chicken, which in
            our sampling represents the closest relative of tyrannosaurs ( Fig. 1A ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Results </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Network parameters describing skull anatomy. Tyrannosaurus rex and chicken have the
            skulls and lower jaws with the highest and lowest number of bones of the sample (N = 63
            and 34, respectively) ( Fig. 1B ). The number of bones in the chicken is close to that
            of the opossum (N = 35), whereas tyrannosaur is closer to the other diapsids: tuatara (N
            = 58) and alligator (N =53) ( Fig. 1C ). The leatherback turtle takes intermediate
            values (N = 46). The same pattern observed for nodes is visible for the number of links
            (connections between bones: K) ( Fig. 1D ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> When considering the density of connections (D), tyrannosaur (D = 0.095) falls close to
            chicken and other sauropsids (i.e., reptiles), as is expected by its phylogenetic
            position ( Fig. 1A,E ). The parameter D has been interpreted in past works as a proxy of
            morphological complexity, with a higher value of D meaning a greater complexity of the
            skull 18 . In this regard, the chicken skull is as complex as that of other sauropsids,
            while the opossum (D = 0.139) has the skull with the greatest morphological complexity
            of all. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The chicken shows a relatively low mean clustering coefficient (C = 0.304) that sets it
            apart from the other taxa of the sample, with about 10% less C than others. Tyrannosaur
            (C =0.438), however, falls close to the leatherback turtle (C =0.444) ( Fig. 1B,F ). C
            has been interpreted in the past as a proxy of anatomical integration, with higher
            values of C meaning greater integration 18 . In this context, integration refers to the
            degree of inter-connectivity among the parts of the skull; having a greater integration
            is related to stronger constraints or co-dependences, such as those affecting
            co-evolution or co-variation of skull regions 15 . This means that chickens have evolved
            a less integrated skull anatomy. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> All taxa except the opossum show a similarly large mean shortest path length (L),
            although opossum has a relatively small value (L = 2.066) ( Fig. 1G ). The shortest path
            length is a network parameter or topological variable. It measures the minimum amount of
            connections separating two nodes (e.g., two connected nodes have an L = 1; if they are
            not directly connected, L will be&gt;1; thus, the higher their L the more separated they
            are). L has been interpreted in the past as proxy of integration, with smaller values of
            L meaning greater integration 18 . In this context, the chicken skull (L = 3.371) is
            less integrated than those of reptiles, while the opossum skull is the least integrated
            of all. The tyrannosaur (L =3.431) falls together with all other sauropsids, clearly
            deviating from the opossum. As stated above, overall skull integration at a topology has
            been suggested to affect other aspects of phenotypic organization and variation 19 .
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Regarding heterogeneity of connections, the chicken (H = 0.493) shows intermediate
            values between the other sauropsids and the opossum ( Fig. 1B,H ). H has been
            interpreted as a proxy of anisomerism (i.e., irregularity, differentiation, or
            specialization) with higher H meaning greater anisomerism 18 . In this context, chicken
            skull bones have a degree of differentiation (in terms of connectivity) between other
            sauropsids (low) and the opossum (high), with tyrannosaur (H = 0.345) falling together
            with the chicken and the other reptiles, with values similar to that of tuatara (H
            =0.323), which would suggest a phylogenetic linkage. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Modularity. The tyrannosaur shows a more modular skull and has, in terms of network
            theory, a less consistent pattern (Q-modules =7, Qmax = 0.551, Qmax.error = 0.035) than
            any other amniote studied here (Q-modules = 5 or 6; Figs 1–3 ). An internal separation
            of the left anterior skull side exists (red module in figures, p = 0.001; Figs 2A and 4A
            ) consisting of upper jaw and anterior palatal bones in its lower part (pink module) and
            anterior skull roof and circumorbital bones in its upper part (purple module, p =
            0.001). Posterior skull roof bones (green module) and braincase bones (yellow module)
            form modular patterns on each side. The sphenoids and the ethmoid form a close
            association (blue module). A close relation of bones situated in the lower part of the
            adductor chamber (orange module), including quadrate, palatoquadrate, pterygoid, and
            epipterygoid, exists on each side. In contrast to all other amniotes studied, the
            detailed composition of bones in the modules of the tyrannosaur skull is very
            inconsistent on each side and the association of modules differs as well. This means
            that modules are largely independent from each other and internal integrity is not as
            consistent/stable in a topological sense. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> In the chicken, the palate and beak form one single module (pink in Fig. 2B ), the left
            and the right zygomatic arch form distinct modules (red), and all other bones,
            surrounding and including the braincase, form the other module (yellow) ( Figs 2B and 4B
            ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> In alligator, the left and right snout parts are split into two separate modules (red
            in figures, p =0.05). Anteriorly, the snout tip forms a separate module (light red) (
            Figs 2C and 5A ), like in the opossum ( Figs 3C and 6B ), being limited posteriorly by
            canine-like large teeth from the lower jaw, and bearing the nose opening dorsally ( Fig.
            5A ). Similar to tuatara ( Figs 3B and 6A ), the temporal bones of alligator form a
            module (orange) within a higher integration of other skull elements on each side. The
            pterygoid is part of the module that comprises the large snout related bones (red). The
            small braincase (yellow) is loosely integrated to the temporal and the skull roof
            region. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The leatherback turtle shows a separation in a bilateral snout module (red in figures),
            a left and a right module (p = 0.01) combining the skull roof (green) and the cheek
            bones (orange), and a module composed of braincase and associated elements (yellow) (
            Figs 3A and 5B ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The tutatara has a clear modular pattern distinguished into left and right sides of the
            skull ( Figs 3B and 6A ). Temporal bones (orange in figures), skull roof bones (green),
            and braincase bones (yellow) are modular entities in tuatara, nested within each skull
            side, although they do not show a clearly positioned integration to each other. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The opossum shows one module made of snout bones from both body sides (red in figures)
            (p =0.01), including palatal and upper jaw elements ( Figs 3C and 6B ). The posterior
            part of the skull with the braincase and associated bones, such as the squamosals and
            parietals, form the second module (yellow). The tip of the snout, as a third module
            (light red), is made of the nasals and premaxillas. The ear ossicles form completely
            separated modules on each side (white, p =0.01), because they are not connected to other
            bones. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>In addition to the above-mentioned modules of the skull, each sauropsid has two
            separated lower jaw modules with species-specific integration of the particular bones
            (grey in figures). Except for the beak-bearing chicken, the articular, which articulates
            with the quadrate, is less integrated to the other lower jaw elements. Importantly, in
            the opossum both mandibles (dentaries) form a single module (grey), providing a further
            example of a phylogenetic pattern (i.e., contralateral bone fusion in mammals) revealed
            by AnNA. The tyrannosaur does not show a particularly different modular system although
            a large fenestra is present on the mesial side of its lower jaw.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Discussion </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The tyrannosaur has the most complex and least consistent modular pattern among the
            sample representatives of each major extant amniote clade. In terms of its topology, the
            tyranosaur skull is clearly peculiar, displaying a high number of modular subdivisions.
            Single bones are not necessarily fixed to a particular module. Moreover, modules are
            largely independent from each other on each body side. These important findings suggest
            a highly flexible skull, in terms of functional morphology. We detected diverse modular
            patterns for all amniotes studied here. These patterns are highly specific for each
            taxon and are likely related to specific functional demands, because despite some clear
            cases of phylogenetic patterns that were revealed by AnNA, only little phylogenetic
            correlation was detected ( Fig. 1B ). The comparative discussion of skull modularity
            among amniotes, highlighting common and diverging patterns, permits us to provide here a
            refined morphofunctional characterization of the tyrannosaur, a taxon deeply nested
            within amniote phylogeny ( Fig. 1A ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Bone reduction. The number of bones in the tyrannosaur is similar to that of all other
            sauropsids except for the chicken. Through fusion processes during ontogeny, this
            relatively close relative of the tyrannosaur shows great reduction of ossification
            centers 20 and, convergent to opossum, accordingly shows great bone reduction (low N-
            and K-values). The complexity of the chicken skull (estimated by D) is, however, similar
            to that of other sauropsids illustrating that bone connections were established
            differently when compared to opossum. This observation is further supported by the low
            integration (as estimated by C and L) in chicken, showing that bone contacts arranged in
            a different, less compact way when compared to those of the opossum. In the latter
            taxon, inter-connections among close bones produced a very compact skull (high D and C,
            low L) and although heterogeneity (H-value) is higher in the chicken when compared to
            other sauropsids, it is still far from that achieved in opossum. The higher compactness
            in opossum, however, does not necessarily imply less modularity – which is similar in
            chicken and opossum (i.e., number of Q-modules, Fig. 1B ) – meaning that individual bone
            size and anatomical differentiation are, of course, also important to establish modular
            patterns in the skull. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Kinetic and akinetic forms. Kinesis of the skull not only refers to mobile joints
            between bones, but cranial kinesis can also be developed in skulls with immobile sutures
            by having relatively thin and elastic bones in gracile crania that eventually enable the
            same range of motion 21 . Cranial kinesis of tuatara is highly disputed. Although a
            single cineradiography experiment failed to demonstrate (joint based) cranial kinesis 22
            , anatomical conditions such as the presence of constrictor dorsalis musculature,
            indicate that at least some degrees of skull kinesis are actually present in this
            species 23–25 . Kinesis appears to be largely reduced in adult tuatara by strong sutures
            between bones, although the gracile architecture of the skull is generally compatible
            with elasticity-related cranial kinesis, particularly in juveniles, which have a
            different feeding behavior compared to adults 25 . Given the lightweight design of the
            tuatara skull 26 , we define it as kinetic herein. Also dinosaurs do not have
            well-developed intracranial joints when compared to many lizards or birds; however,
            little is known about actual intracranial mobility in their comparably gracile skulls 23
            . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> In this regard, we found a clear distinction between species with a suspected skull
            kinesis (i.e., tyrannosaur, chicken, tuatara) and species with fully akinetic skulls
            (i.e., alligator, leatherback turtle, opossum). Akinetic species, have to withstand
            extremely strong biting forces 27–29 . As a result, they have fewer bones (N ≤ 53) than
            tyrannosaur and tuatara and relatively high network density, meaning they have to build
            broader sutures (e.g., in contrast to tuatara) to each other to keep integrity.
            Suspected kinetic species have more bones (N ≥ 58) and, in average, a lower network
            density ( Fig. 1 ), meaning that, overall, smaller sutures might enable high mobility in
            the articulations and/or bones are more flexible/elastic than in akinetic species. Among
            kinetic species, however, the tyrannosaur has the greatest density, a bit larger than
            the akinetic alligator, which appears to relate to its supposedly hypercarnivor behavior
            and powerful food processing. The chicken skull is an exception in this regard, because
            it has fewer bones (N = 34) but, as mentioned above, its network density is relatively
            high. This is because its braincase bones are highly fused to support the brain 30,31 ;
            the remainder of the skull, including palate, break, and skull roof, consists of very
            fragile and highly kinetic elements 32 . Overall skull network construction is highly
            diverse, and has little affinity to phylogenetic relationship as noted above. Even if
            the turtle and archosaurs (tyrannosaur, chicken, alligator) are relatively closely
            related 33 , the physical joints differ in number and position. The akinetic skulls
            obviously evolved independent from each other in these lineages. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Individual skull modularity. Patterns of modularity show a clear correspondence to
            skull architecture in each species. We first discuss the modularity of opossum, as the
            mammalian outgroup, and then continue along the tree ( Fig. 1A ) with tuatara,
            leatherback turtle, alligator, and finally chicken as the taxon more closely related to
            the tyrannosaur. By doing this comparison, we hope to contribute to a better
            understanding of the evolutionary history of tyrannosaur skull complexity and
            modularity. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The integration of left and right body side elements in individual bilateral modules
            nicely illustrates the compact nature of the akinetic mammal skull, as seen in the
            example of opossum ( Figs 3C and 6B ). In mammals such as the opossum food processing
            occurs in the middle of the snout module. The snout includes the zygomatic bone ( Fig.
            6B ), from which the chewing muscle, the masseter, mainly originates. The main bite
            forces appear in the posterior part of the skull, from which the jaw closing muscle, the
            temporalis, originates 34 . Associated to that, the sphenoid, which braces the lateral
            braincase 35 , is part of the posterior skull module ( Figs 3C and 6B ). The separate
            module at the snout tip corresponds to the macrosmathic nature of most mammalian skulls.
            The canines, which have to resist much biting force 36 , are situated posterior to this
            module. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Tuatara shows a very independent nature of its modules in the global context of the
            gracile skull, the architecture of which is made of several bony bars, loosely embracing
            the modules. The skull of tuatara is principally constructed as kinetic (see above) and
            the certain independency of modules ( Figs 3C and 6B ) might enable a better flexibility
            when processing food 37 . For that, highly differentiated jaw adductor musculature of
            lepidosaurs allows for handling agile prey 23,38,39 . The epipterygoid ( Fig. 6B ),
            which supposedly moves the palatal shelve in lizards, is a part of the braincase module
            in tuatara, which also highlights the diverse labor division in the adductor chamber.
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The snout of turtles is very broad and left and right sides are strongly fused, likely
            as an adaptation of the akinetic skull. Early in turtle evolution, the skull was still
            kinetic as indicated by a pterygoid-braincase articulation. In extant turtles, without
            such articulation, the pterygoid ( Figs 2C and 5B ) is an integrated part of the
            braincase module 40–42 . In addition, the braincase is broadly fused with the quadrate
            in crown turtles making cranial mobility impossible 41,43,44 . In crown turtles,
            development of the akinetic skull is completed by the formation of a secondary lateral
            braincase wall, mainly made of a descending process of the parietal 45 . As such, the
            skull roof - present as a submodule in the leatherback turtle - also covers the brain
            laterally. The cheek submodule is composed of jugal, quadratojugal, and squamosal ( Figs
            3A and 5B ) bones to which the superficial external adductor musculature attaches 46–49
            . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The alligator also has an akinetic skull. However, it has evolved a different modular
            pattern of skull bones compared to the opossum and leatherback turtle, and a unique mode
            of skull fixation took place 50 . Like in opossum, the snout tip is not as much involved
            in bite force distribution as the rest of the snout 19 , making it a separate module (
            Figs 2C and 5A ). Apparently, the double-fenestrated temporal region in the alligator
            resulted in a separate temporal module such as in tuatara. In both species, the external
            jaw musculature attaches to the temporal region in a complex manner 51 . In alligator,
            however, most biting force is transmitted via pterygoid-related internal jaw musculature
            making the pterygoid a part of the snout module 52,53 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The specific avian adaptation of having both large eyes and beaks is clearly mirrored
            in the detected modularity ( Figs 2B and 4B ). The posterior part of the skull forms a
            dense capsule of bones 31 . The kinetics are highly derived when compared to the
            ancestral diapsid condition (with two temporal openings), which is still partly
            preserved in tuatara 37 , and the beak is moveable against the skull roof (prokinesis)
            thanks to the lever of the zygomatic arch 32 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Tyrannosaur skull performance. The highly complex modularity detected for the
            tyrannosaur ( Figs 2A and 4A ) indicates a very flexible skull regarding bite force
            distribution. Although loosely associated to others, the best-resolved modular
            associations are established by the lateral sides of the skull. The comparison to other
            amniotes and biological considerations result in the following assumptions. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 1. Like all supposedly or clear kinetic forms studied herein (tuatara, chicken), a high
            degree of cranial mobility is possible in the tyrannosaur when compared to clear
            akinetic forms. This is consistent with the flexible sutures 11 and the great number of
            links in the network of its cranial bones. This flexibility should be taken into account
            when reconstructing cranial performance 54 . Like in alligator, a large snout is formed;
            however, different to alligator, streptostylic movement (via the epipterygoid, which
            connects the laterosphenoid and the quadrate process of the pterygoid) might have
            existed in the tyrannosaur. Although quite robust 8 , the epipterygoid might have
            enabled some independent movements of the snout against the rest of the skull, like in
            tuatara, and an internal mobility between the upper and lower snout regions might have
            been beneficial in prey processing. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 2. Internal snout mobility is supported by the formation of large fenestrations in the
            snout, which are mainly thought to enable pneumaticity, reduction of skull weight, and
            to buffer bite forces 6,9 , but also reduces the contact area between bones and as such
            triggers higher mobility between them. The modular separation of the snout in upper and
            lower parts, related to snout fenestrations, not necessarily mirrors bite force
            distribution. It was reconstructed to travel from the canine-like teeth upwards when
            puncturing prey 6,10 , a pattern also found in mammals, which do not have such a facial
            fenestration 55 . The tyrannosaur was hypothesized to have not only punctured but also
            pulled its food 6,10,54 . Associated to the presence of thecodont teeth, nesting in jaw
            alveoles, strain travels mainly along the upper jaw via the maxillar-jugal contact 6 in
            the lower part of the snout module. Pulling food, as such, might have had a major
            influence in separating a lower and an upper snout submodule. In this context it is
            worth noting that, in contrary to the opossum, although specialized teeth are present on
            the premaxillary, no snout tip module was formed. Finite element analyses might be able
            to confirm this refined hypothesis for tyrannosaur when considering suture anatomy [
            sensu 56 ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 3. Although having a typical diapsid skull (like tuatara and alligator), a separation
            of a temporal bone module does not exist in tyrannosaur. This indicates that bite force
            might have been concentrated on a different aspect of the skull, namely the lower part
            of the adductor chamber, to which the muscles adductor mandibulae posterior and
            pseudotemporalis insert 57–59 . The lower adductor chamber represents a separate module
            in our analysis. Voluminous jaw muscles have also been reconstructed for the upper part
            of the adductor chamber. However, within particular muscles, the distribution of
            different muscle fiber types 60,61 and different fiber orientation 62 , which generate
            specific force distributions, were not yet considered in any finite element analysis.
            Moreover, reconstructing fiber distribution in extinct species would be extremely time
            consuming. As such, AnNA, as presented here, in combination with biomechanic analysis is
            crucial to provide a first approximation to a more reasonable reconstruction of feeding
            biology in tyrannosaurs - and other fossil vertebrates. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Conclusions </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>In summary, the results of this study highlight how the use of AnNA can offer a new
            perspective on long-standing anatomical problems and help to better understand the
            evolvability of amniote skulls and their adaptations to different feeding behaviors.
            “Hidden” kinetics, not obvious due to the absence of movable joints but enabled by
            elastic bone and gracile skull constructions permit better estimation of skull
            performances. Using the extant bracketing approach and broad scale phylogenetic
            comparison helps understanding functional constraints and possibilities in extinct
            species for which no direct data on life performances are available. Our results show a
            relatively low correlation between the network skull integration and modularity with
            phylogenetic relationships, which suggest that the patterns of integration and
            modularity revealed in the present work are more likely related to ecological factors,
            such as the mode of food processing. In all species, however, a trade-off exists between
            phylogenetic and general functional constraints, such as lowering skull weight in
            tyrannosaur or brain encapsulation in birds on the one hand, and feeding adaptations on
            the other hand. Future studies may concentrate on modular patterns on lower taxonomic
            levels, for example, comparing different non-avian theropod or bird species to test the
            general conclusions of our work and to specify functional integrity of specific skull
            regions. Moreover, studies relating muscle and bone integration will help detailing the
            functional derivations hypothesized herein. We believe this founding study will pave the
            way for more comprehensive analyses of reptile evolution in particular and of anatomical
            evolution in general, and for the further use of AnNA to tackle morphological
            complexity, integration, and modularity in evolution.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Methods </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Taxonomic sampling. We selected a sample of species from all major amniote groups for
            the analysis, including the opossum Didelphis virginiana 63 (Mammalia), the tuatara
            Sphenodon puctatus 25,38,64 (Lepidosauria), the leatherback turtle Dermochelys coriacea
            65 (Testudines), the alligator Alligator mississippiensis 66,67 (Crocodylia), the
            chicken Gallus gallus 20,30 (Aves), and the tyrannosaur Tyrannosaurus rex 68–70
            (Tyrannosauridae). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> For D . virginiana , the sphenoid was coded as a single bone because its subparts
            (e.g., the alisphenoid) are not completely separated (by sutures) bones in the adult
            (for a recent review, see 63 ]. D . coriacea is a representative of cryptodire turtles
            with a fully formed dermal armor above the adductor chamber. In this regard, it
            resembles the morphotype of stem turtles such as Proganochelys quenstedt 40 . However,
            it must be noted that skull diversity is enormous among turtles and marine turtles such
            as D . coriacea show a secondary formation of a full temporal armor 12 . Development and
            fusion of ossification centers is well traceable in G . gallus 20 . In the adult
            condition (coded herein), however, the braincase shows comprehensive fusion. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Anatomical network analysis. We built unweighted, undirected network models of the
            skull anatomy of the six amniote taxa. Anatomical networks were coded as adjacency
            matrices in Excel sheets, with each contact between two nodes coded as “1” and the
            absence of contact between those nodes coded as “0”. In defining nodes and links, we did
            not include cartilaginous elements because this information is not known for fossils
            and/or homology of cartilaginous elements is not fully resolved in most taxa. Data were
            analyzed with R 71 using the package igraph 72 . For every network, parameters were
            measured using functions implemented in the package igraph (see below and Supplementary
            information). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Identification of network modules. We delimited the modules of the anatomical networks
            using a hierarchical clustering of the generalized topological overlap similarity matrix
            among nodes (GTOM) 14,73 . The heuristic of GTOM is that nodes that connect to the same
            other nodes (i.e., share neighbors) have a higher chance of belonging to the same
            module. Topological overlap between two nodes is defined by the number of common
            neighbors between them as, TO i , j = J ( n i , n j )/min( k i , k j ), where J( ni , nj
            ) is the number of neighbors in common between nodes k i and j . TO is 1 when the two
            nodes share all their neighbors, that is, they connect to exactly the same other nodes.
            TO is 0 when the two nodes have no neighbor in common. Using the values of TO as a
            distance or dissimilarity matrix, we then group nodes into clusters using an
            agglomerative hierarchical cluster analysis (do not confuse this with the parameter
            clustering coefficient). The output is a hierarchical grouping of nodes as in a
            dendrogram. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> To identify the modules of the network we needed to cut the dendrogram at an
            appropriate height. To make this decision we used the optimization function modularity Q
            defined by Clauset et al . 74 , which is commonly used to assess whether the best
            partition identified by a community detection algorithm is better that what is expected
            at random. For each possible partition of the dendrogram we measured Q, the best
            partition is the one having the highest Q or Qmax (dashed red lines in Figs 2 and 3 ).
            Thus, quality of the identified partitions is given by its Q value: Q will be close to
            0, if the number of links within modules is no better than that expected at random; Q
            will be closer to 1 if the modules identified deviate from what is expected for a random
            network. According to Clauset et al .’s 74 observations, usual values of strongly
            modular networks range between 0.3 and 0.7. The expected error of Q was calculated using
            a jackknife procedure, where every link is an independent observation. Modules
            identified using the cutting of the dendrogram at Qmax were called Q-modules. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> We also calculated the statistical significance of every cluster of the dendrogram.
            This was done by performing a two-sample Wilcoxon rank-sum test on the internal vs.
            external connections of every module.According to the general definition of a module as
            a group of nodes highly connected among themselves and poorly connected to nodes in
            other groups, we expect internal connections to be significantly higher than external
            connections (H 0 : Kinternal = Kexternal ; HA: Kinternal &gt; Kexternal ). Lower
            p-values tell us to reject H 0 , and hence we can assume the alternative hypothesis,
            that the nodes of the module are more connected among themselves than to other nodes
            outside the module, is supported. In other words, the module identified is not expected
            by a random grouping of nodes. Figures 2 and 3 show the statistical significance of each
            cluster using colored circles (no-circle, p-value≥0.5, white, p-value&lt;0.05; grey,
            p-value&lt;0.01; black, p-value &lt;0.001). Modules identified using the p-value of the
            two-sample Wilcoxon rank-sum test were called S-modules.For a meaningful biological
            interpretation, a balanced discussion between Q- and S-modules is necessary. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Availability of Data and Material </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Four online supplementary files are associated to this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> References </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 1. Bakker, R. T. Speed in tyrannosaurs . Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology 22 , 34A (
            2002 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 2. Biewener, A.A. Walking with tyrannosaurs . Nature 415 , 971–972 ( 2002 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 3. Samman, T. Tyrannosaurid Craniocervical Mobility: A Preliminary Assessment . In
            Tyrannosaurid Paleobiology (eds Parrish, J. M. , Molnar, R.E. , Currie, P.J. &amp;
            Koppelhus, E. B. ) 195–210 ( 2013 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 4. Snively, E. &amp; Russell, A. P. Craniocervical feeding dynamics of Tyrannosaurus
            rex . Paleobiology 33 , 610–638 , https://doi. org/10.1666/06059.1 ( 2007 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 5. Snively,E. &amp; Russell,A.P. Functional variation of neck muscles and their
            relation to feeding style in Tyrannosauridae and other large theropod dinosaurs . The
            Anatomical Record: Advances in Integrative Anatomy and Evolutionary Biology 290 ,
            934–957 , https://doi. org/10.1002/ar.20563 ( 2007 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 6. Rayfield, E. J. Cranial mechanics and feeding in Tyrannosaurus rex . Proceedings of
            the Royal Society of London, Series B 271 , 1451–1459 ( 2004 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 7. Gignac, P. M. &amp; Erickson, G. M. The biomechanics behind extreme osteophagy in
            Tyrannosaurus rex . Scientific Reports 7 , https:// doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-02161-w (
            2017 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 8. Weishampel,D. B. , Dodson, P. &amp; Osmólska, H. The Dinosauria . 2 edn , (
            University of California Press 2004 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 9. Witmer, L.M. The evolution of the antorbital cavity of archosaurs:A study in
            soft-tissue reconstruction in the fossil record with an analysis of the function of
            pneumaticity . Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology 17 , 1–73 ( 1997 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 10. Rayfield, E. J. Aspects of comparative cranial mechanics in the theropod dinosaurs
            Coelophysis , Allosaurus and Tyrannosaurus . Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society
            144 , 309–316 ( 2005 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 11. Rayfield, E. J. Using finite-element analysis to investigate suture morphology: a
            case study using large carnivorous dinosaurs . The anatomical record.Part A, Discoveries
            in molecular, cellular, and evolutionary biology 283 , 349–365 ( 2005 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 12. Werneburg, I. Temporal bone arrangements in turtles: an overview . Journal of
            Experimental Zoology. Part B: Molecular and Developmental Evolution. 318 , 235–249 (
            2012 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 13. Lakjer, T. Studien über die Gaumenregion bei Sauriern im Vergleich mit Anamniern
            und primitiven Sauropsiden . Zoologische Jahrbücher 49 , 57–356 ( 1927 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 14. Esteve-Altava, B. Challenges in identifying and interpreting organizational modules
            in morphology . Journal of Morphology 278 , 960–974 , https://doi.org/10.1002/jmor.20690
            ( 2017 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 15. Rasskin-Gutman, D. &amp; Esteve-Altava, B. Connecting the dots: anatomical network
            analysis in morphological Evo Devo . Biological Theory 9 , 178–193 ( 2014 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 16. Esteve-Altava, B. In search of morphological modules: A systematic review .
            Biological Reviews 92 , 1332–1347 , https://doi. org/10.1111/brv.12284 ( 2017 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 17. Witmer, L.M. The extant phylogenetic bracket and the importance of reconstructing
            soft tissues in fossils .In Functional Morphology in Vertebrate Paleontology (ed.
            Thomason, J. ) Ch.2 , 19–33 ( University Press 1995 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 18. Esteve-Altava, B. , Marugan-Lobon, J. , Botella, H. &amp; Rasskin-Gutman, D.
            Structural constraints in the evolution of the tetrapod skull complexity:Williston’s Law
            revisited using network models . Evolutionary Biology 40 , 209–219 ,
            https://doi.org/10.1007/s11692-012-9200-9 ( 2013 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 19. Sellers, K. C. , Middleton, K. M. , Davis, J. L. &amp; Holliday, C. M. Ontogeny of
            bite force in a validated biomechanical model of the American alligator . Journal of
            Experimental Biology 220 , 2036–2046 , https://doi.org/10.1242/jeb.156281 ( 2017 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 20. Jollie, M. T. The head skeleton of the chicken and remarks on the anatomy of this
            region in other birds . Journal of Morphology 100 , 389–436 ( 1957 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 21. Natchev, N. , Handschuh , Lukanov, S. , Tzankov, N. , Naumov, B. &amp; Werneburg,
            I. Contributions to the functional morphology of caudate skulls: Kinetic and akinetic
            forms . PeerJ 5 , 1–15 ( 2016 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 22. Metzger,K. Cranial kinesis in lepidosaurs:skulls in motion .In Topics in Functional
            and Ecological Vertebrate Morphology (eds Aerts, P. , D’Août, K. , Herrel, A. &amp; Van
            Damme, R. ) 15–46 ( Shaker Publishing 2002 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 23. Holliday, C. M. &amp; Witmer, L. M. Cranial kinesis in dinosaurs: Intracranial
            joints, protractor muscles, and their significance for cranial evolution and function in
            diapsids . Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology 28 , 1073–1088 ( 2008 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 24. Ostrom, J. H. On the constrictor dorsalis muscles of Sphenodon . Copeia 1962 ,
            732–735 ( 1962 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 25. Jones, M. E. H. , Curtis, N. , Fagan, M. J. , O’Higgins, P. &amp; Evans, S. E. Hard
            tissue anatomy of the cranial joints in Sphenodon (Rhynchocephalia):Sutures, kinesis,
            and skull mechanics . Palaeontologia Electronica 14 , 92p ( 2011 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 26. Curtis, N. et al . Predicting muscle activation patterns from motion and anatomy:
            modelling the skull of Sphenodon (Diapsida: Rhynchocephalia) . Journal of the Royal
            Society, Interface/the Royal Society 7 , 153–160 ( 2010 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 27. Schwenk, K. Feeding: Form , Function and Evolution in Tetrapod Vertebrates (
            Academic Press, San Diego 2000 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 28. Novacek, M. J. Patterns of Diversity in the Mammalian Skull . In The Skull , Volume
            2: Patterns of Structural and Systematic Diversity (eds Hanken, J. &amp; Hall, B. K. )
            438–545 ( University of Chicago Press 1993 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 29. Herring, S. W. Functional anatomy of mammalian mastication . American Zoologist 33
            , 289–299 ( 1993 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 30. Bittner, F. Über die Schläfenregion am Schädel der Vögel und dessen Beziehungen zu
            dem der Reptilien . Archiv für Naturgeschichte 78 , 1–23 , Tafel I ( 1912 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 31. Zusi, R.L. Patterns of Diversity in the Avian Skull .In The Skull , Volume 2:
            Patterns of Structural and Systematic Diversity [ 580p. ] (eds Hanken, J. &amp; Hall, B.
            K. ) Ch. 8 , 391–437 ( University of Chicago Press 1993 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 32. Bock,W. J. Kinetics of the avian skull . Journal of Morphology 114 , 1–42 ( 1964 ).
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 33. Rieppel, O. The Relationships of Turtles within Amniotes . In Biology of Turtles
            (eds Wyneken, J. , Godfrey, M. H. &amp; Bels, V. ) Ch. 13 , 345–353 ( CRC Press 2008 ).
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 34. Lautenschlager, S. , Gill, P. , Luo, Z.-X. , Fagan, M. J. &amp; Rayfield, E. J.
            Morphological evolution of the mammalian jaw adductor complex.Biological Reviews 92,
            1910–1940 (2017). 35. Maier, W. The ontogenetic development of the orbitotemporal region
            in the skull of Monodelphis domestica (Didelphidae, Marsupialia), and the problem of the
            mammalian alisphenoid. In Morphogenesis of the mammalian skull . Mammalia depicta -
            Beihefte zur Zeitschrift für Säugetierkunde (eds Kuhn H.J., Zeller, U. &amp; Röhrs, M.)
            (Verlag Paul Parey 1987). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>36. Wroe, S., Clausen, P., McHenry, C., Moreno, K. &amp; Cunningham, E. Computer
            simulation of feeding behavior in the thylacine and dingo as a novel test for
            convergence and niche overlap. Proceedings.Biological sciences/The Royal Society 274,
            2819–2828 (2007).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>37. Curtis, N. et al. Functional relationship between skull form and feeding mechanics
            in Sphenodon, and implications for diapsid skull development.Plos One 6, e29804
            (2011).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>38. Evans, S. E. The S kull of the Lepidosauria. In Biology of the Reptilia (eds Gans,
            C., Gaunt, A. S. &amp; Adler, A.) Ch. 1, 1–347 (Society for the Study of Amphibians and
            Reptiles 2008).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>39. Iordansky, N.N. Cranial kinesis in lizards (Lacertilia): Origin, biomechanics, and
            evolution.Biological Bulletin 38, 852–861 (2011).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>40. Gaffney, E. S. The comparative osteology of the Triassic turtle Proganochelys.
            Bulletin of the American Museum of Natural History 194, 1–263 (1990).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>41. Werneburg, I. &amp; Maier, W.Considerations on the development of the akinetic skull
            in pleurodire and cryptodire turtles. In Turtle Evolution Symposium. Program &amp;
            Abstracts (eds Hirayama, R. et al.) 86–87 (Scidinge Hall Tübingen 2018).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>42. Rabi, M., Zhou, C.-F., Wings,O., Ge, S.&amp; Joyce, W.G.A new xinjiangchelyid turtle
            from the Middle Jurassic of Xinjiang, China and the evolution of the basipterygoid
            process in Mesozoic turtles.BMC Evolutionary Biology 13, 1–28 (2013).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>43. Joyce,W. G. Phylogenetic relationships of Mesozoic turtles. Bulletin of the Peabody
            Museum of Natural History 48, 3–102 (2007).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>44. Gaffney, E. S. Comparative cranial morphology of recent and fossil turtles.Bulletin
            of the American Museum of Natural History 164, 67–376 (1979a).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>45. Esswein, S. E. Zur phylogenetischen und ontogenetischen Entwicklung des akinetischen
            Craniums der Schildkröten. Natürliche Konstruktionen - Mitteilungen des SFB 230(7),
            51–55 (1992).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>46. Schumacher, G. H. Die Kopf- und Halsregion der Lederschildkröte Dermochelys coriacea
            (LINNAEUS 1766) - Anatomische Untersuchungen im Vergleich zu anderen rezenten
            Schildkröten (Akademie-Verlag 1972).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 47. Werneburg, I. The cranial musculature in turtles.Palaeontologia Electronica 14,
            15a: 99 pages (2011) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>48. Werneburg, I. Jaw musculature during the dawn of turtle evolution. Organisms,
            Diversity &amp; Evolution 13, 225–254 (2013b).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>49. Ferreira, G.S. &amp; Werneburg,I. Evolution,Diversity, and Development of the
            Craniocervical System in Turtles with Special Reference to Jaw Musculature. In Heads,
            Jaws and Muscles - Anatomical, Functional and Developmental Diversity in Chordate
            Evolution Fascinating Life Science (eds Ziermann, J. M., Diaz, R. E. &amp; Diogo, R.)
            (Springer, in press).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 50. Klembara, J. Ontogeny of the partial secondary wall of the otoccipital region of
            the endocranium in prehatching Alligator mississippiensis (Archosauria, Crocodylia).
            Journal of Morphology 266, 319–330, https://doi.org/10.1002/Jmor.10380 (2005). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 51. Holliday, C. M.&amp; Witmer, L. M.Archosaur adductor chamber evolution:Integration
            of musculoskeletal and topological criteria in jaw muscle homology. Journal of
            Morphology 268, 457–484, https://doi.org/10.1002/Jmor.10524 (2007). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>52. Witzmann, F.&amp; Werneburg, I. The palatal interpterygoid vacuities of
            temnospondyls and the implications for the associated eye- and jaw
            musculature.Anatomical Record 300, 1240–1269 (2017).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>53. Lautenschlager, S., Witzmann, F. &amp; Werneburg, I. Palate anatomy and
            morphofunctional aspects of interpterygoid vacuities in temnospondyl cranial
            evolution.Naturwissenschaften 103, 1–10 (2016).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 54. Lautenschlager, S. Estimating cranial musculoskeletal constraints in theropod
            dinosaurs.Royal Society Open Scienc e 2, https://doi. org/ 10.1098/rsos.150495 (2015).
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>55. Wroe, S. Cranial mechanics compared in extinct marsupial and extant African lions
            using a finite-element approach. Journal of Zoology 274, 332–339 (2008).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>56. Curtis, N., Jones, M.E.H., Evans, S.E., O’Higgins,P.&amp; Fagan,M.J. Cranial sutures
            work collectively to distribute strain throughout the reptile skull.Interface 10, 1–8
            (2013).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>57. Holliday, C. M.New insights into dinosaur jaw muscle anatomy. The Anatomical Record
            292, 1246–1265 (2009).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>58. Molnar, R. E. The Cranial Morphology and Mechanics of Tyrannosaurus rex (Reptilia:
            Saurischia) PhD thesis thesis, University of California (1973).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>59. Molnar, R.E.In Tyrannosaurus rex. The Tyrant King (eds Larson, P.&amp; Carpenter,
            K.) 255–286 (2008).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 60. Schantz, P., Randallfox, E., Hutchison, W., Tyden, A.&amp; Astrand, P.O.
            Muscle-fiber type distribution, muscle cross-sectional area and maximal voluntary
            strength in humans.Acta Physiol Scand 117, 219–226,
            https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1748-1716.1983.tb07200.x (1983). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 61. Neufuss, J. et al. Fibre type composition in the lumbar perivertebral muscles of
            primates: Implications for the evolution of orthogrady in hominoids.Journal of Anatomy
            224, 113–131, https://doi.org/10.1111/joa.12130 (2014). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>62. Dickinson, E., Stark, H. &amp; Kupczik, K. Non-destructive determination of muscle
            architectural variables through the use of DiceCT. Anatomical Record (in press).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 63. Diogo, R., Bello-Hellegouarch,G., Kohlsdorf, T., Esteve-Altava,B.&amp; Molnar,
            J.L.Comparative myology and evolution of marsupials and other vertebrates, with notes on
            complexity, bauplan, and “scala naturae”. Anatomical Record 299, 1224–1255, https://doi.
            org/ 10.1002/ar.23390 (2016). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>64. Tanner, W.W. &amp; Avery, D. F.Buccal floor of reptiles, a summary.The Great Basin
            Naturalist 42, 273–349 (1982).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 65. Wegner, R.N.Der Schädelbau der Lederschildkröte Dermochelys coriacea Linné (1766).
            Abhandlungen der Deutschen Akademie der Wissenschaften zu Berlin. Klasse für Chemie,
            Geologie und Biologie 4, 1–80, 17 plates (1959). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 66. Holliday, C. https://sketchfab.com/holliday/collections/adult-alligator-skull-atlas
            [access: 2018-12-20]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>67. Iordansky, N. N. The Skull of the Crocodylia. In Biology of the Reptilia Vol. 4
            Morphology D (eds Gans, C. &amp; Parsons, T. S.) Ch. 3, 201–262 (Academic Press
            1973).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>68. Brochu, C.A.Osteology of Tyrannosaurus rex: Insights from a nearly complete skeleton
            and highresolution computed tomographic analysis of the skull.Journal of Vertebrate
            Paleontology 22 (2003).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 69. Carr, T. D. Craniofacial ontogeny in Tyrannosauridae (Dinosauria, Coelurosauria).
            Journal of Vertebrate Paleontology 19, 497–520,
            https://doi.org/10.1080/02724634.1999.10011161 (1999). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>70. Molnar, R. E. The cranial morphology of Tyrannosaurus rex. Palaeontographica
            Abteilung A, 137–176 (1991).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 71. R-Core-Team.R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation
            for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. ISBN 3-900051-07-0,
            http://www.R-project.org/ (2013). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>72. Csardi, G. &amp; Nepusz, T.The igraph software package for complex network research.
            InterJournal Complex Syst. 1659, 1–9 (2006).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 73. Esteve-Altava, B., Marugan-Lobon, J., Botella, H., Bastir, M. &amp; Rasskin-Gutman,
            D. Grist for Riedl’s mill: A network model perspective on the integration and modularity
            of the human skull. Journal of Experimental Zoology Part B-Molecular and Developmental
            Evolution 320, 489–500, https://doi.org/10.1002/jez.b.22524 (2013). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 74. Clauset, A., Newman, M. E. J.&amp; Moore, C. Finding community structure in very
            large networks. Physical Review E 70, https://doi. org/ 10.1103/PhysRevE.70.066111
            (2004). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 75. Shedlock, A. M. &amp; Edwards, S. V. Amniotes (Amniota). In The TimeTree of Life
            (eds Hedges, S. B. &amp; Kumar, S. ) Ch. 52 , 375–379 (Oxford University Press 2009 ).
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 76. Benton, M. J.Origin and relationships of Dinosauria.In The Dinosauria, 2nd edition
            (eds Weishampel, D.B., Dodson,P.&amp; Osmólska, H.) 7–24 (University of California
            Press, 2004). Acknowledgements </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> We are particularly thankful to Octavio Mateus for helping coding the connectivity
            matrix of the tyrannosaur and to Janine M. Ziermann for sharing the connectivity matrix
            of Didelphis . We wish to thank one anonymous reviewer for valuable comments. IW was
            supported by SNF-grant P300PA_164720. BE-A has received financial support through the
            Postdoctoral Junior Leader Fellowship Programme from “la Caixa” Banking Foundation
            (LCF/BQ/LI18/11630002). Part of this project was funded - to RD and BE-A - by an
            American Association of Anatomists Innovation Award. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Author Contributions </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Conceptualization. I.W., B.E.-A., R.D. Data collection: I.W., R.D., M.T.L., J.B. Data
            analysis: B.E.-A. Writing paper: I.W., B.E.-A. Revising manuscript: I.W., R.D., B.E.-A.,
            M.T.L., J.B. Illustrations: J.B. (skull drawings), I.W., B.E.-A.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Additional Information </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Supplementary information accompanies this paper at
            https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37976-8. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Competing Interests: The authors declare no competing interests. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Publisher’s note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims
            in published maps and institutional affiliations. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
            International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and
            reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the
            original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre- ative Commons license, and
            indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article
            are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a
            credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative
            Commons license and your intended use is not per- mitted by statutory regulation or
            exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the
            copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit
            http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>© The Author(s) 2019</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
