<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nature</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1137-z</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A new Jurassic scansoriopterygid and the loss of membranous wings in theropod dinosaurs</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>09</day>
            <month>05</month>
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

https://doi.org/ 
10.1038/s41586-019-1137-z
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A new Jurassic scansoriopterygid and the loss of membranous wings in theropod dinosaurs

</title>
         <p>
Min Wang

, 

*
, 
Jingmai K. O’Connor

, 


, 
Xing Xu

, 


&amp; 
Zhonghe Zhou

, 

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Powered flight evolved independently in vertebrates in the pterosaurs, birds and bats, each of which has a different configuration of the bony elements and epidermal structures that form the wings


, 


. Whereas the early fossil records of pterosaurs and bats are sparse, mounting evidence (primarily from China) of feathered non-avian dinosaurs and stemward avians that derive primarily from the Middle–Upper Jurassic and Lower Cretaceous periods has enabled the slow piecing together of the origins of avian flight



, 


. These fossils demonstrate that, close to the origin of flight, dinosaurs closely related to birds were experimenting with a diversity of wing structures



, 


. One of the most surprising of these is that of the scansoriopterygid (Theropoda, Maniraptora) 
Yi qi
, which has membranous wings—a flight apparatus that was previously unknown among theropods but that is used by both the pterosaur and bat lineages



. This observation was not universally accepted



. Here we describe a newly identified scansoriopterygid—which we name 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ambopteryx longibrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
gen. et sp. nov.
—from the Upper Jurassic period. This specimen provides support for the widespread existence of membranous wings and the styliform element in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
, as well as evidence for the diet of this enigmatic theropod clade. Our analyses show that marked changes in wing architecture evolved near the split between the 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
and the avian lineage, as the two clades travelled along very different paths to becoming volant. The membranous wings supported by elongate forelimbs that are present in scansoriopterygids probably represent a short-lived experimentation with volant behaviour, and feathered wings were ultimately favoured during the later evolution of Paraves.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Theropoda Marsh, 1881
</title>
         <p>
Maniraptora Gauthier, 1986
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae Czerkas and Yuan, 2002</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Ambopteryx longibrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Ambo
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
longibrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
A. longibrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
A. longibrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Archaeopteryx
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Deinocheirus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Microraptor
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new Jurassic scansoriopterygid and the loss of membranous wings in theropod dinosaurs</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1137-z</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A235FFC976436969FFAEFFCAFF8FDF1B</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1137-z</pub-id>
               <source>Nature</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Ambopteryx longibrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. et sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>
Etymology.
‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ambo
</tp:taxon-name>
’, both (Latin); ‘ 
pteryx
’, wing (Latin), referring to the pterosaur-like wing that is present in this non-avian dinosaur; ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
longibrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
’ refers to the elongate forelimb (
brachium
, upper arm (Latin)).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>
Holotype
.

Institute of Vertebrate Paleontology and Paleoanthropology (
IVPP
) 

V24192

, an articulated and nearly complete skeleton with associated soft tissue preserved on a slab and counter slab (

, Extended Data 

).
</p>
               <p>
Locality and horizon.
Near Wubaiding Village, Reshuitang Town, Lingyuan City, 
Liaoning Province
, 
China
; early 
Upper Jurassic
, stratigraphic equivalent of the 
Haifanggou Formation
, 
Yanliao Biota
(
Oxfordian
stage, 163 million years ago (Ma) 

8
, 
9

; see Methods for the provenance of the holotype specimen).
</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>
Diagnosis.
A scansoriopterygid theropod that preserves the following synapomorphies of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
: scapula distally expanded; reduced deltopectoral crest of humerus; and metacarpal III longer than II, and elongate manual digit III that is longer than other digits. The presence of a rod-like styliform element and short tibia ally the 
Ambopteryx
specimen with the genus 
Yi
, but 
Ambopteryx
is distinguishable on basis of the following features: (1) ulna substantially wider (2×) than radius; (2) short tail that lacks a transition point and that ends in a fused pygostyle; (3) elongate forelimb 1.3× longer than the hindlimb; (4) straight, rod-like postacetabular process of ilium; and (5) tibia shorter than humerus (see Methods for differential diagnosis; the three manual digits of Pennaraptora are here denoted as I, II and III, although the homologies of the manus in tetanuran theropods are debated 

3

). Features (1), (2) and (4) are probable autapomorphies that are thus far unique to 
Ambopteryx
, but that cannot be compared across all scansoriopterygids.
</p>
            <p>
IVPP 
V24192
is interpreted as a subadult or adult on the basis of the fusion of the pygostyle, and the absence of striations or pits to indicate periosteal ossification was incomplete. Osteohistological examination was attempted but no information could be extracted, owing to poor preservation and diagenetic alteration (Extended Data 

). IVPP 
V24192
is estimated to be 32 cm in body length and to have had a body mass approximately 306 g, using an empirical equation based on femur circumference 

10

(see Methods).
</p>
            <p>
The skull is anteroposteriorly short and dorsoventrally high (Extended Data 

), similar to other scansoriopterygids 

6

. The neck is complete and consists of eight-to-ten articulated cervicals (axis and atlas included) (

). As in some oviraptorosaurs and therizinosaurs 

11

—but unlike most other non-avian pennaraptorans 

12

— the tail is short and ends in a pygostyle.In contrast to most other non-avian theropods 

13

and stemward avians 

12

, the free caudals lack a transition point.
</p>
            <p>
The forelimb is gracile and markedly elongate (

, Extended Data 

), with an intermembral index ((humerus + ulna)/ (femur + tibia)) of about 1.3, which surpasses that of other scansoriopterygids, as well as most non-avian theropods and stem avians (Supplementary Tables 1–3). The proximal margin of the humerus is strongly convex, whereas in 
Yi
it is relatively flat. The straight ulna is shorter than the humerus and is nearly twice the transverse width of the radius, which is in stark contrast to the subtle difference between the ulna and the radius that is present in other scansoriopterygids 

6
, 
14
, 
15

and many non-avian theropods 

16

. An elongate bone is preserved that extends from the distal end of the left ulna; this bone is morphologically identical to the anomalous structure reported in 
Yi
6
, being rod-like, slightly curved and tapered distally (Extended Data 

). No comparable structure has hitherto been found in other dinosaurs 

6

. We consider this bone homologous to that of 
Yi
, and hereafter use the same terminology in referring to this bone as the styliform element 

6

. The styliform element is shorter than the humerus in 
Ambopteryx
, which is not the case in 
Yi
. The hand morphology is characteristic of scansoriopterygids in that it shows a metacarpal III that is longer than metacarpal II, and an elongate digit III that is substantially longer than digit II 

6
, 
14

(

). The manual phalangeal formula is 2-3-4. Phalanx I-1 terminates level with the distal end of metacarpal II, whereas in 
Yi
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
this phalanx extends further distally (Extended Data 

).
</p>
            <p>
The postacetabular process of the ilium is dorsoventrally narrow (less than one-third of the height of the preacetabular process) and strap-like in lateral view (Extended Data 

), which contrasts with both the triangular form as in some oviraptorosaurs and troodontids 

17
, 
18

and the ventrally curved condition as in dromaeosaurids and stem avians 

19

. As in 
Yi
, the tibia is shorter than the humerus; the opposite is true in other non-avian pennaraptorans (Supplementary Table 3). 
Ambopteryx
preserves approximately 20 stones and unidentified bony fragments just anterior to the pelvis and ventral to the vertebral column, which are interpreted as gastroliths and ingested remains, respectively (

, Extended Data 

). The diet of scansoriopterygids has been unknown; the gastroliths and possible stomach contents preserved in 
Ambopteryx
provide the some direct clues from which we can draw dietary inferences. The small number of gastroliths in 
Ambopteryx
suggests that this taxon may not have been herbivorous—this also finds some support in the stomach contents, which appear to contain bone. Considering the unusual dental morphology of the scansoriopterygid clade, we suggest this group may have been omnivorous.
</p>
            <p>
Feathers are densely preserved around the head, neck and the shoulder regions (

, Extended Data 

). The matrix that surrounds the left hand, right forelimb and abdomen is coated in a brownish continuous layer that bears ripple-like striations (

), which is reminiscent of the membranous tissues reported in 
Yi
6
. Scanning electron microscopy reveals densely packed microscopic elliptic moulds within the neck feathers and membranous tissues (Extended Data 

). Following recent studies 

20

, these moulds are interpreted as being produced by eumelanosomes (see Supplementary Information for additional description and discussion of diet).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
Our phylogenetic analysis recovered 
Ambopteryx
as the sister taxon to 
Yi
within the clade 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
(

, Extended Data 

). The nearly complete postcranial skeleton of 
Ambopteryx
provides a great deal of important morphological and ecological information that is not accessible from previously known scansoriopterygid specimens. The fused pygostyle in 
Ambopteryx
adds to the known distribution of this feature among non-avian dinosaurs. The abbreviated tail and elongate forelimbs in scansoriopterygids—which evolved in parallel similar morphologies in Aves—would have increased stability during possible volant behaviour by shifting the centre of weight more anteriorly, closer to the centre of lift 

7

.
</p>
            <p>
The presence of a styliform element in 
Ambopteryx
lends further credibility to previous interpretations of this structure in 
Yi
6
and confirms that this element is a genuine feature. Comparable elements (whether homologous or not) are otherwise unknown among dinosaurs 

6

, but have evolved independently in some other tetrapod lineages that are adapted for volant behaviour 

21
, 
22

. Where the styliform element is present in extant vertebrates, it supports an expanded patagium and thus increases the viable area of the aerodynamic surface 

21
, 
22

. 
Yi
and 
Ambopteryx
preserve membranous tissue in situ around the styliform element 

6

, which indicates a similar patagium-supporting role for this structure in this clade. Unfortunately, the preservation in 
Ambopteryx
and 
Yi
makes it impossible to reconstruct the configuration of the membranous tissue, which prevents further assessment of its exact function. Although previously a gliding function was ascribed to these structures in 
Yi
6
, other functions are also possible—for example, in display and ornamentation, or in contributing to wing-assisted incline running 

23

. The hyper-elongate manual digit III of scansoriopterygids was previously interpreted as a feeding adaptation for extracting grubs during foraging, using a strategy similar to that of the extant aye-aye 

15

. This interpretation is not supported in light of new data that indicate that the manual digits were surrounded by membranous tissues 

6

, and in light of the limited mobility that we inferred from the morphology of the manual phalangeal joints. We suggest the primary function of the elongated digit III was the attachment of the wing membrane rather than feeding behaviour.
</p>
            <p>
Scansoriopterygids truly are one of the most bizarre clades of nonavian theropods. In addition to their membranous wings, their body plan is unique among theropods. Morphometric analyses indicate that scansoriopterygids occupy a distinct morphospace that is separated from most other non-avian coelurosaurians and Mesozoic avians, which suggests that substantial changes in limb proportions evolved after scansoriopterygids diverged from the rest of Paraves (

, Methods). The forelimb underwent considerable elongation in scansoriopterygids (paralleling changes in other volant paravians), and achieved proportions that are only otherwise observed in Aves. Scansoriopterygids have unusually short metacarpals—the elongation of their forelimb is primarily achieved through the elongation of the humerus and ulna. By contrast, the forelimb elongation in nonscansoriopterygid pennaraptorans (including birds) is largely driven by the elongation of the metacarpals. The presence of an elongate manual digit III and a styliform element in scansoriopterygids probably compensate for the relatively short metacarpals by providing support for membranous wings. By contrast, selection for relatively elongate metacarpals in most paravians may have been driven by the need for increased area for the attachment of the primary remiges (for example, over half of the primary remiges attach to the carpometacarpus in living birds 

24

). The co-occurrence of short metacarpals with membranous wings—as opposed to long metacarpals and feathered wingsdemonstrates how these two markedly different flight apparatuses can affect the overall forelimb structure. Membranous wings are unknown among Cretaceous theropods, which indicates that the combination of an avian-like body plan (for example, elongate forelimbs and a short tail) with membranous wings that evolved in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
represents a previously unknown adaptation of vertebrates with volant behaviour. Feathered wings, which are first documented in some Upper Jurassic non-avian theropods, were further refined through the evolution of numerous other musculoskeletal modifications and eventually gave rise to the current success of modern birds, which represent the most-diverse extant clade of tetrapods.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Online content

</title>
         <p>Any methods, additional references, Nature Research reporting summaries, source data, statements of data availability and associated accession codes are available at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-1137-z.</p>
         <p>Received: 21 January 2019; Accepted: 25 March 2019;</p>
         <p>Published online 8 May 2019.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>

1. 
Gatesy,S.M.
&amp; 
Middleton,K. M.
in 

Fins Into Limbs: Evolution, Development, and Transformation

(ed. 
Hall,B.K.
) 
269–283
(
Univ.Chicago Press,Chicago
, 
2007
).

</p>
         <p>

2. 
Norberg,U.
Vertebrate Flight: Mechanics, Physiology, Morphology, Ecology and Evolution

(
Springer, Berlin
, 
1990
).

</p>
         <p>

3. 
Xu, X.
et al. 
An integrative approach to understanding bird origins
. 

Science

346

, 
1253293
(
2014
).

</p>
         <p>
4
. 
Gatesy,S.M.
&amp; 
Middleton,K. M.
Bipedalism, flight,and the evolution of theropod locomotor diversity
. 

J. Vertebr.Paleontol
.

17

, 
308–329
(
1997
).

</p>
         <p>

5. 
Chatterjee,S.
&amp; 
Templin, R.J.

Biplane wing planform and flight performance of the feathered dinosaur 
Microraptor gui

. 

Proc. Natl Acad.Sci. USA

104

, 
1576–1580
(
2007
).

</p>
         <p>

6. 
Xu, X.
et al. 
A bizarre Jurassic maniraptoran theropod with preserved evidence of membranous wings
. 

Nature

521

, 
70–73
(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

7. 
Padian,K.
Dinosaur up in the air
. 

Nature

521

, 
40–41
(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

8. 
Liu, Y.
, 
Liu, Y.
, 
Ji, S. A.
&amp; 
Yang, Z.
U–Pb zircon age for the Daohugou Biota at Ningcheng of Inner Mongolia and comments on related issues
. 

Chin. Sci.Bull
.

51

, 
2634–2644
(
2006
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
9. 
Huang,D.
Yanliao biota and Yanshan movement
(in Chinese). 

Acta Palaeontologica Sin
.


54

, 
501–546
(
2015
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
10. 
Campione,N. E.
, 
Evans,D. C.
, 
Brown, C.M.
&amp; 
Carrano,M. T.
Body mass estimation in non-avian bipeds using a theoretical conversion to quadruped stylopodial proportions
. 

Methods Ecol.Evol
.


5

, 
913–923
(
2014
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
11. 
Persons,W.S.
, 
Currie,P. J.
&amp; 
Norell, M. A.
Oviraptorosaur tail forms and functions
. 

Acta Palaeontol. Pol
.


59

, 
553–567
(
2013
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
12. 
O’Connor,J.K.
&amp; 
Sullivan,C.

Reinterpretation of the Early Cretaceous maniraptoran (Dinosauria: Theropoda) 
Zhongornis haoae
as a scansoriopterygid-like non-avian, and morphological resemblances between scansoriopterygids and basal oviraptorosaurs

. 

Vertebr. Palasiat
.


52

, 
3–30
(
2014
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
13. 
Gatesy,S.M.
&amp; 
Thomason, J.
in 

Functional Morphology in Vertebrate Paleontology

(ed. 
Thomason,J.J
.) 
219–234
(
Cambridge Univ
. 
Press, Cambridge
, 
1995
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
14. 
Zhang,F.
, 
Zhou,Z.
, 
Xu,X.
, 
Wang,X.
&amp; 
Sullivan,C.
A bizarre Jurassic maniraptoran from China with elongate ribbon-like feathers
. 

Nature


455

, 
1105–1108
(
2008
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
15. 
Zhang,F.
, 
Zhou,Z.
, 
Xu,X.
&amp; 
Wang,X.
A juvenile coelurosaurian theropod from China indicates arboreal habits
. 

Naturwissenschaften


89

, 
394–398
(
2002
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
16. 
Turner,A.H.
, 
Makovicky, P. J.
&amp; 
Norell, M.A.
A review of dromaeosaurid systematics and paravian phylogeny
. 

Bull.Am. Mus. Nat.Hist
.


371

, 
1–206
(
2012
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
17. 
Xu, X.
et al. 
A new feathered maniraptoran dinosaur fossil that fills a morphological gap in avian origin
. 

Chin. Sci.Bull
.


54

, 
430–435
(
2009
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
18. 
Balanoff,A.M.
&amp; 
Norell,M.A.

Osteology of 
Khaan mckennai
(Oviraptorosauria: Theropoda)

. 

Bull.Am. Mus. Nat. Hist
.


372

, 
1–77
(
2012
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
19. 
Hutchinson,J.R.
The evolution of pelvic osteology and soft tissues on the line to extant birds (Neornithes)
. 

Zool. J.Linn.Soc
.


131

, 
123–168
(
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
20. 
Zhang,F.
et al. 
Fossilized melanosomes and the colour of Cretaceous dinosaurs and birds
. 

Nature


463

, 
1075–1078
(
2010
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
21. 
Thorington,J.R. W.
, 
Darrow,K.
&amp; 
Anderson,C.G.
Wing tip anatomy and aerodynamics in flying squirrels
. 

J.Mamm
.


79

, 
245–250
(
1998
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
22. 
Oshida,T.
, 
Hiraga, H.
, 
Nojima, T.
&amp; 
Yoshida, M. C.

Anatomical and histological notes on the origin of the long accessory styliform cartilage of the Russian flying squirrel, 
Pteromys volans orii

. 

Mammal Study


25

, 
41–48
(
2000
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
23. 
Dial,K. P.
Wing-assisted incline running and the evolution of flight
. 

Science


299

, 
402–404
(
2003
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
24. 
Lovette, I. J.
&amp; 
Fitzpatrick, J. W.

Handbook of Bird Biology
3rd edn

(
John Wiley &amp; Sons,Hoboken
, 
2016
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Acknowledgements
We thank S.-X. Jiang, D.-Y. Huang, Y.-H. Pan and Z.-Q. Yu for discussion, Q.-R. Meng for help in the field, T. Zhao for taking scanning electron microscopy photographs, D.-H. Li for specimen preparation and W. Gao for photographing. This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (41688103; 41722202), Youth Innovation Promotion Association CAS (2016073) and the State Key Laboratory of Lithospheric Evolution (Z201604).
</p>
         <p>
Reviewer information
Nature
thanks Thomas Richard Holtz, Peter Makovicky and Kevin Padian for their contribution to the peer review of this work.
</p>
         <p>
Author contributions
Z.Z. and M.W.designed the research project;Z.Z. and M.W. conducted the fieldwork; M.W.performed the phylogenetic, histological and phylogenetic principal component analyses; and M.W., J.K.O., X.X.and Z.Z. wrote the manuscript.
</p>
         <p>
Competing interests
The authors declare no competing interests.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Additional information

</title>
         <p>
Extended data
is available for this paper at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586- 019-1137-z.
</p>
         <p>
Supplementary information
is available for this paper at https://doi.org/ 10.1038/s41586-019-1137-z.
</p>
         <p>
Reprints and permissions information
is available at http://www.nature.com/ reprints.
</p>
         <p>
Correspondence and requests for materials
should be addressed to M.W. 
Publisher’s note:
Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
METHODS

</title>
         <p>

Systematic palaeontology of 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
.

Phylogenetic definition.
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
is the most inclusive clade that contains 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus ningchengensis
Zhang, Zhou and Xu 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. longibrachium
</tp:taxon-name>
, but not 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dromaeosaurus albertensis
Matthew and Brown 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oviraptor philoceratops
Osborn 1924
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Passer domesticus
Linnaeus 1758
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>

Diagnosis of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
.

The 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
differ from all other theropods on the basis of the following combination of characters:skull anteroposteriorly short and dorsoventrally deep; large external mandibular fenestra; scapula distally expanded; reduced deltopectoral crest of humerus; metacarpals I–III short; metacarpal III longer than II; and elongate manual digit III longer than other digits. 

Differential diagnosis of 
Ambopteryx
.

Ambopteryx
is distinguishable from all other scansoriopterygids on the basis of the following combination of characters: styliform element shorter than humerus, opposite to the condition in 
Yi
(this element is not preserved in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidexipteryx
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
); proximal margin of humerus more convex, and deltopectoral crest more elongate, than in 
Yi
; manual phalanx I-1 terminates level with the distal end of metacarpal II (this phalanx extends further distally in 
Yi
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
); manual phalanx I-1 is much shorter than metacarpal II (length ratio is 0.62, compared to 0.91 in 
Yi
and 0.9 in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
); manual digit III is proportionally shorter than in 
Yi
; length ratio of manual phalanx III-1 to III-2 is greater than in 
Yi
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
(1.29, 1.04 and 1.07 in 
Ambopteryx
, 
Yi
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
, respectively); and tibia is shorter than humerus (as in 
Yi
), which contrasts with the condition in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidexipteryx
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>

Provenance of IVPP 
V24192
.

IVPP 
V24192
was collected from Jurassic strata exposed near Wubaiding Village in Reshuitang Subdistrict,Linyuan City, Liaoning Province. Before this specimen, the only known vertebrates collected from this locality were two salamanders 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pangerpeton sinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chunerpeton tianyiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
25
. A U–Pb date obtained using laser ablation inductively coupled mass spectrometry 
26
from a lava breccia layer below the horizons that contain these salamander fossils produced a date of 164 ± 4 Ma.Strata cropping out near Wubaiding Village were previously considered to belong to the Tiaojishan Formation 
26
. However, a few recent lithostratigraphic studies and biostratigraphic studies (mainly based on insects) have argued that the strata that are exposed in Wubaiding Village belong to the underlying Haifanggou Formation, and the main salamander-bearing sediments were deposited during the Callovian age 
9
. The Tiaojishan Formation is mainly exposed in localities near Linglongta (Jianchang County, Liaoning Province), Nanshimen, Bawanggou and Fanzhangzi (Qinglong County, Hebei Province). An age of 161–160 Myr has previously been reported 
27
for the fossiliferous vertebrate (for example, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anchiornis
</tp:taxon-name>
)-bearing horizons that are interbedded within the Tiaojishan Formation, as exposed in Linglongta Town. More recently, these fossil horizons in Linglongta Town have been further constrained to an interval that spans 160.89–160.25 Ma on the basis of high-precision U–Pb dating, which places this site in the late Oxfordian stage 
28
. Although stratigraphic correlation between the Middle-to-Upper Jurassic strata in which the Yanliao Biota is distributed is still debated, growing evidence suggests that the Haifanggou Formation preserves the early phase of this biota (early Oxfordian), and the overlying Tiaojishan Formation records the later phase (Oxfordian) 
9,29
; these two phases are separated by approximately 2–3 million years. Unpublished results of secondary ionization mass spectrometry U–Pb dating using tuff samples from below the 
Ambopteryx
- bearing bed produced an age of 163 Myr (H. He, personal communication), which indicates that this bed was deposited in the early Oxfordian stage of the Upper Jurassic.
</p>
         <p>
IVPP 
V24192
was prepared by D. Li, a professional technician from the IVPP, under the supervision of the authors.
</p>
         <p>
Bone histological analysis.
Most of the limb elements were poorly preserved in IVPP 
V24192
; among these limb elements, we could extract only one sample from the left humerus for bone histological analysis (Extended Data 
Fig. 1a
). We also took a sample from the unidentified fragment preserved near the gastroliths (
Fig. 1
). The bone samples were embedded in one-component resin (EXAKT Technovit 7200) and hardened in a light polymerization device (EXAKT 520) for over 24 h. Thin cross-sections were cut using an accurate circular saw (EXAKT 300CP), and then were ground down using the EXAKT 400CS grinding system. The slides were ground to 40 µm—half the thickness that is typically necessary to visualize bone structure in similarly sized birds from the Jehol Biota—but the slides remained opaque.Images were taken using a digital camera (Zeiss AxioCam MRc5) under normal light (Zeiss AX10). Because of diagenetic alteration and breakage, the humeral cross-section provides little histological information; this information cannot be used to infer the ontogenetic stage of IVPP 
V24192
(Extended Data 
Fig. 2a, b
). Although also poorly preserved, the cross-section of the unidentified element shows that it is bone tissue (Extended Data 
Fig. 2c, d
).
</p>
         <p>
Body mass estimate.
Estimating the body mass of extinct animals is notoriously difficult, as it contains numerous unknown variables. The common practice used in palaeontology is based on empirical scaling relationships of limb bones (stylopodial length, circumference and so on) with body mass measurements obtained from living tetrapods 
30–32
. As such, large differences occur between studies that use different empirical equations.Given the diverse limb proportions in extant and extinct tetrapods—for example, between terrestrial and arboreal forms—it is expected that using a single parameter from a single element across a large clade over million years of evolution is highly speculative. The scansoriopterygids 
Yi
(STM31-2) 
6
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidexipteryx
</tp:taxon-name>
(IVPP 
V15471
) 
14
were previously estimated to have a body mass of 380 g and 164 g, respectively,using the empirical equation in term of femoral length 
31
. Using the same equation, the body mass of 
Ambopteryx
(IVPP 
V24192
) is 57 g—a surprisingly low value that is apparently far from realistic. 
Ambopteryx
has a forelimb (combined length of humerus and ulna is 116.95 mm) that is intermediate in length between that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidexipteryx
</tp:taxon-name>
(IVPP 
V15471
, 92 mm) and 
Yi
(STM31-2, 183.3 mm).Because the forelimb is longer than the hindlimb in all known scansoriopterygids, and because the forelimb probably has a major role in locomotion, it is impossible to accept such a low body mass estimate for 
Ambopteryx
. The fact that the body mass estimate for 
Ambopteryx
is erroneous indicates that femoral length is not a reliable parameter from which to infer body mass for non-avian paravians that approach the body shape of avians. Recent studies show that there is a correlation between stylopodial circumference and body mass 
33
, and have been applied to estimate the body mass of non-avian dinosaurs 
10,30
. Therefore—using an equation based on the circumference of the femur (log 
10
(body mass) = 2.749 × log 
10
(femoral circumference × 2 
0.5
) – 1.104) as previously described 
10,30
—we alternatively estimated the body mass of 
Ambopteryx
(IVPP 
V24192
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidexipteryx
</tp:taxon-name>
(IVPP 
V15471
), and 
Yi
(STM31-2) to be 306 g, 391 g and 697 g, respectively. Our intention here is not to argue for one equation being more accurate than the other—although, in this instance, the equation based on femur circumference provides a more-realistic estimate. However, all estimates of body mass in extinct organisms should be treated with caution.
</p>
         <p>
Scanning electron microscopy of soft tissues.
Two samples from the feathers associated with the neck, and two samples from the potential traces of the membranous wings, in IVPP 
V24192
were taken for scanning electron microscopy analysis. These samples were mounted on stubs with carbon tape without gold coating.The samples were observed and photographed using a field emission scanning electron microscope equipped with a SE2 detector, at Key Laboratory of Unconventional Oil and Gas Geology, China Geology Survey.
</p>
         <p>
Phylogenetic analysis.
The phylogenetic position of 
Ambopteryx
was analysed using a comprehensive data matrix that has recently become available for coelurosaurian phylogeny 
6
, with the addition of IVPP 
V24192
and a stemward pygostylian 
Chongmingia zhengi
(Supplementary Information).The dataset was analysed under equally weighted parsimony using the TNT v.1.5 software package 
34
. The analysis was performed using the ‘New Technology search’ algorithm with sectorial search, ratchet, tree drift and tree fusion using the default settings in TNT, and the minimum tree length was found in ten replicates to recover as many tree islands as possible.We carried out a second round of branch-swapping using the traditional tree–bisection–reconnection method on the trees obtained in previous steps, to find the most-parsimonious trees. The branches of the most-parsimonious trees were collapsed if the minimal length was zero. Decay indices (Bremer support values) were calculated using the Bremer script embedded in TNT, and the absolute frequency of the bootstrap was calculated using 1,000 replicates using the default settings in TNT.
</p>
         <p>
In total, 192 most-parsimonious trees were recovered with a length of 1,436 steps (consistency index = 0.315, retention index = 0.739). 
Ambopteryx
was resolved within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
and formed a sister to 
Yi
in the strict consensus tree (Extended Data 
Fig. 7
). This sister taxon relationship is supported by a single synapomorphy:the deltopectoral crest of humerus is very weakly developed and the proximal margin of humerus has rounded edges (character 140:2). 
Time-scaled Mesozoic coelurosaurian phylogeny.
To estimate the divergence times of the major Mesozoic coelurosaurian clades, the strict consensus tree that we recovered was time-scaled. The temporal ranges of the fossil taxa were constrained using the first and last appearance datum of the geological stages or epochs in which each taxon was found 
35
. When phylogenies that involve fossil taxa are time-calibrated, branches of zero length frequently occur 
36,37
. These zerolength branches were smoothed using the ‘minimal branch length’ method used in recent studies 
35,37
, which sets a minimum branch length (here, 1 million years). All these analyses were conducted using the timePaleoPhy function in the R package paleotree 
38
.
</p>
         <p>
Phylogenetic principal component analysis.
To investigate the ecomorphospace disparity of 
Ambopteryx
relative to other non-avian coelurosaurians and Mesozoic avians, we conducted a phylogenetic principal components analysis (PPCA) 
39
. A dataset of the lengths of six appendicular elements (humerus, ulna, metacarpal II, femur, tibia and metatarsal III) from major groups of non-avian coelurosaurians and Mesozoic avians was assembled from direct measurements and the literature (Supplementary Table 3). Because the scaling relationships of the appendicular bones are poorly understood, we included only specimens that preserve complete lengths for all six bones, to avoid potential bias (see a previous publication 
40
, and the references therein, for regression methods for estimating missing elements). The dataset comprises 57 taxa—including 35 non-avian coelurosaurians and 22 Mesozoic avians—and spans nearly the whole spectrum of the Mesozoic coelurosaurian phylogeny.
</p>
         <p>
A composite super tree of the sampled coelurosaurians was created from the results of the present study combined with the results of recent phylogenetic studies 
16,41
(Extended Data 
Fig. 8
). Because the complete length of metacarpal II is unknown for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidexipteryx
</tp:taxon-name>
, this taxon was removed from the tree. Polytomies were resolved randomly using the multi2di function in the R package ape 
42
. The tree was time-calibrated using the ‘minimal branch length’ method on the basis of the absolute ages of the terminal taxa; this was carried out using the timePaleoPhy function in the R package paleotree 
38
.
</p>
         <p>
PPCA is a statistical method that not only performs a traditional principal component analysis (PCA) but also considers the phylogenetic non-independence between taxa when summarizing principal axes of variation 
39,43
. All the measurements were log 
10
-transformed to extract the non-allometric shape changes of the limb before performing the PPCA. The PPCA was performed using the phyl.pca function in the R package phytools 
44
, which reconstructs the states of ancestral nodes using maximum likelihood under a Brownian model of evolution, with all branch lengths set to those obtained in previous time-calibrated phylogeny. To visualize the ecomorphospace, the principal component values of terminal taxa were projected on the phylogeny using the two-dimensional plotting function of phylomorphospace in the R package phytools 
44
. The resulting phylomophospace displays both the magnitude and the direction of morphometric changes inferred along each branch.
</p>
         <p>
The first three principal component values collectively account for over 98% of the variance, and could statically cover the whole ecomorphological diversity of sampled coelurosaurians (Supplementary Table 4). The first principal component axis (PC1) explained over 92% of the variance and negatively correlated with all measurements, which reflects the fact that it mainly represents size variation. Therefore, our analysis of ecomorphological diversity used only the scores of PC2 versus PC3. The eigenvector coefficients of PC2 are negatively correlated with the forelimb elements but positively correlated with hindlimb elements, which indicates that PC2 represents the relative elongation of the forelimb compared to the hindlimb. PC3 contains eigenvector coefficients that are negatively correlated with metacarpal II, the femur and the tibia, but positively correlated with other elements. The opposite signs of the eigenvector coefficients of PC3 describe the shortening of the metacarpal II or the femur relative to the ulna or metatarsal III. Among coelurosaurians, 
Ambopteryx
and 
Yi
have metacarpals that are unusually short, as depicted by the large gap between the 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
and other coelurosaurian clades along PC3. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epidendrosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
was recovered in a position relatively distant from that of 
Yi
and 
Ambopteryx
, which strongly suggests that—in scansoriopterygids—limb proportion is heavily affected by ontogeny.
</p>
         <p>A separate PPCA was performed using only the forelimb measurements (Supplementary Table 5). The first two principal component values account for over 99% of the variance; therefore, a binary plot of these two axes was used. PC1 negatively correlates with all measurements, and thus mainly accounts for size variation. PC2 explains over 26% of the variance, and contains eigenvector coefficients that positively correlate with metacarpal II but negatively correlate with the humerus and ulna. The relatively high loading of metacarpal II indicates that PC2 mainly represents the elongation of this element relative to the humerus and ulna. Taken together, the binary plot of PC1 and PC2 generally describes whether the increase of the forelimb largely results from the elongation of the proximal (humerus and ulna) or the distal (metacarpal) forelimb elements. Scansoriopterygids deviate from other coelurosaurians in the morphospace formed by PC1 and PC2, and are plotted on the bottom right corner of the morphospace; this reveals that the elongation of their forelimb largely derives from the elongation of the humerus and ulna. The morphospace occupied by Mesozoic avians, dromaeosaurids and troodontids largely overlapped with one another (as well as with that of oviraptorosaurs and some more basal coelurosaurians); all of these clades centre on the top of the morphospace, along PC2. This distribution indicates that the elongation of the forelimb in non-scansoriopterygid pennaraptorans (including birds) is largely driven by the elongation of the metacarpals.</p>
         <p>
Reporting summary.
Further information on research design is available in the Nature Research Reporting Summary linked to this paper.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Data availability

</title>
         <p>
All data—including the measurements, source data for morphometric analysis and phylogenetic data matrix—that support the findings of this research are included as Supplementary Information. The specimen (IVPP 
V24192
) described in this study is archived and available on request from the IVPP.A Life Science Identifier for the newly described species has been registered at ZooBank (http://zoobank. org/): urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act:0A2DE2F0-CE78-4149-B0BD-A0DE91FC1328. Any other relevant data are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
25. Sullivan, C.et al. The vertebrates of the Jurassic Daohugou biota of northeastern China. 
J. Vertebr. Paleontol
. 
34
, 243–280 (2014).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>26. Liu, Y.,Liu, Y.&amp; Zhang,H. LA-ICPMS zircon U-Pb dating in the Jurassic Daohugou beds and correlative strata in Ningcheng of Inner Mongolia.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Acta Geol. Sin
. 
80
, 733–742 (2006).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
27. Liu, Y.-Q.et al. Timing of the earliest known feathered dinosaurs and transitional pterosaurs older than the Jehol biota. 
Palaeogeogr. Palaeoclimatol. Palaeoecol
. 
323–325
, 1–12 (2012).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
28. Chu,Z. et al. High-precision U-Pb geochronology of the Jurassic Yanliao biota from Jianchang (western Liaoning Province,China): age constraints on the rise of feathered dinosaurs and eutherian mammals. 
Geochem. Geophys. Geosyst
. 
17
, 3983–3992 (2016).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
29. Xu, X.,Zhou, Z., Sullivan,C.,Wang,Y.&amp; Ren,D. An updated review of the Middle–Late Jurassic Yanliao Biota:chronology, taphonomy, paleontology and paleoecology. 
Acta Geol.Sin
. 
90
, 2229–2243 (2016).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>30. Benson,R.B. J. et al.Rates of dinosaur body mass evolution indicate 170 million years of sustained ecological innovation on the avian stem lineage.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
PLoS Biol
. 
12
, e1001853 (2014).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
31. Christiansen,P.&amp; Fariña,R.A.Mass prediction in theropod dinosaurs. 
Hist. Biol
. 
16
, 85–92 (2004).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
32. Serrano,F.J., Palmqvist,P.&amp; Sanz,J. L. Multivariate analysis of neognath skeletal measurements:implications for body mass estimation in Mesozoic birds. 
Zool.J. Linn. Soc
. 
173
, 929–955 (2015).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
33. Campione,N. E.&amp; Evans, D.C.A universal scaling relationship between body mass and proximal limb bone dimensions in quadrupedal terrestrial tetrapods. 
BMC Biol
. 
10
, 60 (2012).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
34. Goloboff, P. A. &amp; Catalano,S. A.TNT version 1.5, including a full implementation of phylogenetic morphometrics. 
Cladistics
32
, 221–238 (2016).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
35. Brusatte,S. L. in 
Computational Paleontology
(ed. Elewa,A.M. T.) 53–74 (Springer,Heidelberg,2011).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
36. Laurin,M. The evolution of body size,Cope’s rule and the origin of amniotes. 
Syst. Biol
. 
53
, 594–622 (2004).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
37. Wang,M. &amp; Lloyd, G.T.Rates of morphological evolution are heterogeneous in Early Cretaceous birds. 
Proc. R.Soc. Lond.B
283
, 20160214 (2016).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
38. Bapst,D. W. paleotree: an R package for paleontological and phylogenetic analyses of evolution. 
Methods Ecol.Evol
. 
3
, 803–807 (2012).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
39. Revell,L. J. Size-correction and principal components for interspecific comparative studies. 
Evolution
63
, 3258–3268 (2009).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
40. Benson,R.B. J. &amp; Choiniere, J. N. Rates of dinosaur limb evolution provide evidence for exceptional radiation in Mesozoic birds. 
Proc.R. Soc.Lond. B
280
, 20131780 (2013).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
41. Hu, D. et al. A bony-crested Jurassic dinosaur with evidence of iridescent plumage highlights complexity in early paravian evolution. 

<tp:taxon-name>Nat</tp:taxon-name>
. Commun

. 
9
,
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>217 (2018).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
42. Paradis, E., Claude,J. &amp; Strimmer,K. APE:analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R language. 
Bioinformatics
. 
20
, 289–290 (2004).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
43. Felsenstein,J. Phylogenies and the comparative method. 

Am. 
<tp:taxon-name>Nat</tp:taxon-name>

. 
125
, 1–15 (1985).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
44. Revell,L. J. phytools: an R package for phylogenetic comparative biology (and other things). 
Methods Ecol. Evol
. 
3
, 217–223 (2012).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Extended Data 
Fig. 2

| 

Bone histology of 
Ambopteryx
. a–d

, Thin cross-section of the left humerus (
a
, 
b
) and the unidentified bony stomach content (
c
, 
d
). The arrowheads indicate the osteocyte lacunae. Scale bars, 100 µm (
a–c
), 200 µm (
d
).
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
