<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Royal Society Open Science</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.201441</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Natural Frequency Method: estimating the preferred walking speed of
               Tyrannosaurus rex based on tail natural frequency</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> royalsocietypublishing.org/journal/rsos </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Research </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Cite this article: van Bijlert PA, van Soest AJK, Schulp AS. 2021 Natural Frequency
            Method: estimating the preferred walking speed of <tp:taxon-name> Tyrannosaurus rex
            </tp:taxon-name> based on tail natural frequency . R. Soc. Open Sci. 8 : 201441 .
            https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.201441 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Received: 12 August 2020 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Accepted: 15 March 2021 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Subject Category: </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Locomotor energetics are an important determinant of an animal’ s ecological niche. It
            is commonly assumed that animals minimize locomotor energy expenditure by selecting gait
            kinematics tuned to the natural frequencies of relevant body parts. We demonstrate that
            this allows estimation of the preferred step frequency and walking speed of
               <tp:taxon-name> Tyrannosaurus rex </tp:taxon-name> , using an approach we introduce
            as the Natural Frequency Method. Although the tail of bipedal dinosaurs was actively
            involved in walking, it was suspended passively by the caudal interspinous ligaments.
            These allowed for elastic energy storage, thereby reducing the metabolic cost of
            transport. In order for elastic energy storage to be high, step and natural frequencies
            would have to be matched. Using a 3D morphological reconstruction and a spring-suspended
            biomechanical model, we determined the tail natural frequency of <tp:taxon-name> T. rex
            </tp:taxon-name> (0.66 s −1 , range 0.41–0.84), and the corresponding walking speed
            (1.28 m s −1 , range 0.80–1.64), which we argue to be a good indicator of preferred
            walking speed (PWS). The walking speeds found here are lower than earlier estimations
            for large theropods, but agree quite closely with PWS of a diverse group of extant
            animals. The results are most sensitive to uncertainties regarding ligament moment arms,
            vertebral kinematics and ligament composition. However, our model formulation and method
            for estimation of walking speed are unaffected by assumptions regarding muscularity, and
            therefore offer an independent line of evidence within the field of dinosaur locomotion.
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Organismal and evolutionary biology </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Subject Areas: </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> biomechanics/palaeontology/biomechanics </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Keywords: </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> locomotion, cost of transport, theropoda, tetanurae, optimal walking speed </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Author for correspondence: </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Pasha A. van Bijlert e-mail: pasha.vanbijlert@naturalis.nl </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Electronic supplementary material is available online at
            https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.c. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>5369033.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Natural </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Frequency </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Method: </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> estimating </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> the </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> preferred walking </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> speed </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>of</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-name> Tyrannosaurus rex </tp:taxon-name>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> based </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> on tail </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> natural </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> frequency </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Pasha A. van Bijlert 1,3 , A. J. ‘ Knoek ’ van Soest 1,4 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> and Anne S. Schulp 2,3,5 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 1 Department of Human Movement Sciences, Faculty of Behavioural and Movement Sciences,
            and 2 Department of Earth Sciences, Faculty of Science, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam,
            Amsterdam, The Netherlands </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 3 Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Leiden, The Netherlands </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 4 Research Institute Amsterdam Movement Sciences, Amsterdam, The Netherlands </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 5 Faculty of Geosciences, Utrecht University, Utrecht, The Netherlands </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> PAvB, 0000-0002-5567-7022 ; AJKvS, 0000-0002-1959-1061 ; </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> AS, 0000-0001-9389-1540 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 1. Introduction </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Animals display a variety of gaits and walking speeds. Two locomotor extremes are of
            particular interest: the maximal speed, and the energetically optimal walking speed, at
            which the metabolic cost of transport (MCOT, in J m −1 kg −1 ) is minimal for walking
            gait. In the absence of external task constraints, optimal walking speed is very close
            to preferred walking speed (PWS) in humans [1,2], ratites [ ], horses [ ] and elephants
            [ ]. It is likely that they are related in all terrestrial animals, and that animals
            would tend to forage at this speed. During locomotion at preferred speed, animals tend
            to make use of resonance by matching locomotor frequencies to the (undamped) natural
            frequencies of their relevant body parts, sometimes tuned through muscular contractions
            [ – ]. Indeed, it has been demonstrated that mammalian quadrupedal taxa have convergent
            natural frequencies between fore- and hindlimbs despite differing limb morphologies
            [14,15]. An important advantage of moving a body part close to its natural frequency is
            that this reduces mechanical work [16,17]. Based on the commonly adopted idea that PWS
            is chosen to minimize MCOT [ – ], it has been argued that preferred step frequencies are
            close to the natural frequencies of relevant body parts [7,11,12]. Determination of the
            natural frequency of a body part relevant to locomotion can, therefore, constrain
            preferred (and presumably, optimal) step frequencies and walking speeds of extinct taxa
            [ ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Theropod dinosaurs had tails that were actively involved in locomotion [18,19], but
            were passively supported through the caudal interspinous ligaments [ – ], thus forming a
            mass-spring system. <tp:taxon-name> Tyrannosaurus rex </tp:taxon-name> has been the
            focus of many locomotor studies [ – ]. Its largest muscle, M. caudofemoralis longus
            (CFL), retracted the femur to produce forward propulsion for locomotion [18,25,33–35] (
            figure 1 a , c ). The tail was subject to flexion torque due to gravity and CFL
            contractions, which was counteracted at zero metabolic cost by the caudal interspinous
            ligaments, leading to metaplastic adaptations [ – ] ( figure 1 b ). Elastic energy
            storage in these ligaments improved locomotor efficiency, and like a mass on a spring,
            the tail would have oscillated at the step frequency. This is conceptually similar to
            elastic storage in ungulate neck movement [ – ]. The tail would resonate if step
            frequency was matched to the tail natural frequency, and this would maximize strain and
            thus elastic storage [ ]. The principle of elastic energy storage has previously been
            used to simulate more realistic running gaits of the smaller theropod <tp:taxon-name>
               Allosaurus fragilis </tp:taxon-name> [ ]. Elastic storage of the caudal interspinous
            ligaments likely played a smaller role in quadrupedal dinosaurs, due to the less
            pronounced centre of mass excursions. However, because extant quadrupeds display similar
            energysaving mechanisms [ – ], our method should also be applicable to the locomotion of
            quadrupedal dinosaurs, provided their necks or tails were passively suspended by
            ligamentous structures. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> In recent biomechanical models of non-avian dinosaurs, the focus has been on detailed
            hindlimb muscular reconstructions, while the tail was simplified to a single rigid
            structure (for instance: [30,41]). It is our view, however, that tail flexibility is an
            essential aspect of the locomotion of nonavian dinosaurs. We, therefore, chose to focus
            on the tail, because investigating the dynamic effects of a compliant tail may provide
            interesting insights into locomotor capabilities. The primary goal of this study was to
            develop a reductionist method to estimate PWS for non-avian dinosaurs. To this end, we
            performed a detailed morphological reconstruction of the tail, including the caudal
            interspinous ligaments. By incorporating their spring-like properties in a biomechanical
            model, we subsequently estimated the natural frequency of the vertical swaying of the
            tail. Using this as an analogue for step frequency, we then combined the tail natural
            frequency with trackway data to estimate the PWS. We will refer to this approach as the
            Natural Frequency Method (NFM), and demonstrate its application by determining the PWS
            for <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> . We have also investigated which
            morphological features of the tail have the largest impact on tail natural frequency. In
            doing so, we hope to encourage researchers to incorporate a non-rigid tail into their
            locomotor simulations, while also demonstrating that the relatively simple NFM can be a
            valuable expansion of the toolkit of palaeo-biomechanists. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 2. Material and methods </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> We estimated tail natural frequency of <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> , by
            numerically determining the lowest eigenfrequency of a biomechanical model. Essentially,
            we constructed this model by estimating inertial parameters of the tail, dividing it
            into five segments, and then fitting joint spring parameters based on inverse-dynamic
            relationships of different postures of the skeleton. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Inertial parameters of this model were based on a 3D volumetric musculoskeletal
            reconstruction. This reconstruction was performed on adult <tp:taxon-name> T. rex
            </tp:taxon-name> specimen RGM.792000 (nicknamed ‘Trix’, figure 1 a ), in the collection
            of Naturalis Biodiversity Center in Leiden, The Netherlands . This is a large, adult
            specimen with exceptional surface preservation, making it possible to accurately
            distinguish the attachment sites of the interspinous ligaments. We articulated 3D scans
            of the caudal skeleton ( figure 1 c , electronic supplementary material, figure S1 ),
            after which we reconstructed the major caudal musculature to estimate inertial
            parameters ( figure 1 c , electronic supplementary material, figures S2–S 4). Using
            osteological landmarks combined with the physical articulation of 3D prints, we
            determined the axes of rotation between the vertebrae (electronic supplementary
            material, figures S5 and S6). Subsequently, we reconstructed the caudal interspinous
            ligaments ( figure 1 b ), which enabled the determination of moment arms and
            cross-sectional area ( figure 1 b , electronic supplementary material, figure S7). The
            morphological reconstruction of the ligaments made it possible to quantify the kinematic
            relation between vertebral flexion/extension and length of the individual ligaments
            (i.e. strain), which was used to construct the biomechanical model. Parameters of the
            reconstruction are provided in electronic supplementary material, table S1 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Taking the morphological reconstruction as starting point, we then defined a simplified
            biomechanical model consisting of five rigid bodies, connected in hinge joints, with a
            nonlinear rotational spring at each joint ( figure 1 and figure 2 for angle
            definitions). During walking, the most prominent movements and forces occur in the
            sagittal plane, and the moment arm of the CFL is also the largest in this plane.
            Furthermore, the exchange between gravitational and elastic potential energy is most
            meaningfully studied in this plane. Therefore, similar to previous researchers [27,30],
            we elected to perform a sagittal plane analysis. Inertial properties of the rigid bodies
            were acquired from the corresponding segments of the morphological reconstruction. Each
            of the rotational springs was assumed to generate a torque that increased quadratically
            with joint angle when stretched [ ]. As a result, each joint spring has two parameters:
            joint angle at which the spring torque is zero, and a stiffness parameter. To assign
            values to these parameters, the biomechanical model was aligned with the morphological
            reconstruction in two different postures in which the spring torques were known ( figure
            2 ). We acquired the first posture by defining passive horizontal equilibrium, which
            implies that the ligaments are strained in horizontal posture to counteract gravity (
            figure 2 a , b ). It has been shown that the interspinous ligaments could generate ample
            force to maintain this pose [ ], which our models confirm (see the electronic
            supplementary material). In the second posture, all interspinous ligaments were at
            resting length, and thus, all spring torques equalled zero. We determined this posture
            on the basis of an assumption regarding the ligament strain in horizontal equilibrium.
            Tendons and ligaments can be roughly divided into low-stress and high-stress varieties,
            with the high-stress varieties providing more energy savings at the cost of lower safety
            factors [ ]. We imposed an intermediate 4% strain in horizontal equilibrium ( ε hor =
            0.04), and used this to find a pose where the ligaments are not strained ( figure 2 c ,
            d ). This is analogous to passive equilibrium in the absence of gravity, or a
               <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> lying on its side. After aligning the
            biomechanical model with the morphological reconstruction in both postures, the
            mechanical equilibrium conditions were used to calculate the parameter values of each
            rotational spring. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> In the absence of damping, the resonance of the tail would occur at the undamped
            natural frequency ( fn ) of the system [ ]. In reality, damping is omnipresent. In that
            case, resonance occurs at a forcing frequency of fn · (1 – 2 β 2 ) 0.5 , with β being
            the damping ratio [ ]. Ligaments (like tendons) display relatively little energy loss
            during work-loop experiments [39,44], so they have low damping ratios. However, damping
            of dorsoventral oscillations would be dependent on more than just the ligaments, and a
            structure-based estimate of damping would be difficult, if not impossible. Therefore, we
            will use the undamped natural frequency of the biomechanical model as a proxy for the
            resonance frequency. To calculate the natural frequency of the biomechanical model, we
            first linearized the equations of motion in horizontal equilibrium using standard
            numerical methods. Next, the five pairs of conjugated purely imaginary eigenvalues of
            the system matrix were determined using the ‘eig’ function in MATLAB. Subsequently, the
            natural frequency was calculated as the oscillation frequency pertaining to the
            fundamental resonance mode, i.e. the mode with the lowest eigenfrequency. Finally,
            walking speed was estimated by multiplying the natural frequency of each model by step
            length, defined as half the distance between two consecutive footfalls of the same foot.
            We determined a step length of 1.94 m by scaling a large tyrannosaurid trackway [ ]
            based on footprint length of RGM.792000 (see the electronic supplementary material for
            details). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>As was done in previous studies on dinosaur dimensions [27,33,46,47], we subjected the
            major inputs to a sensitivity analysis. Since we hope to see future studies of dinosaur
            locomotion incorporate our tail model, we intentionally chose wide bounds for the
            sensitivity analysis. This serves to inform researchers which individual steps in the
            modelling process induce the largest variation in the result. These steps could then be
            the focus of future research in an attempt to reduce the uncertainty.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> To account for uncertainty in inertial estimates, we individually varied length (and
            thus moment of inertia) and mass. Because we assumed 4% ligament strain in horizontal
            equilibrium, we investigated the effects of low- and high-stress ligaments on the
            result, by imposing 3% and 5% strain in horizontal equilibrium, respectively [ ].
            Although each ligament is well-bounded by the skeleton, the effective point of force
            application of each ligament was unknown. In the baseline model, we based the moment
            arms on the area centroids of the ligaments. We used the ligament reconstruction to
            determine bounds for the moment arms (electronic supplementary material, figures S5 and
            S7). Lastly, whereas the proximal tail shows pronounced articulations between the
            zygapophyses, after approximately the 13th caudal this is no longer the case (electronic
            supplementary material, figure S5). This shifts the rotational axes in the distal tail
            ventrally, towards the vertebral centra, with the vertical position dependent on whether
            the tail is in flexion or extension (electronic supplementary material, figure S6 shows
            the baseline and two extreme possibilities). We, therefore, bounded the rotational axes
            in tail segments 3 and 4, which affected joint springs 3–5. The dorsal axes are
            unrealistically high, ensuring a wide bound for the sensitivity analysis. The ventral
            axes are located at the vertebral articulation with the chevrons, and represent their
            mechanical effect when the tail is flexed. In total, the aforementioned bounds led to 11
            different models. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> To encourage the adoption of our compliant tail model for dinosaur locomotion, we have
            provided in-depth descriptions of reconstruction and biomechanical modelling steps,
            mathematical derivations, scaling relationships and supplementary results in a combined
            document titled ‘Supplementary texts’ as electronic supplementary material.
            Reconstructions, 3D modelling and measurements were all done in Rhinoceros 6 (McNeel and
            Associates, Seattle, WA, USA). The biomechanical model was constructed using custom-code
            written in MATLAB 2019b (MathWorks, Natick, MA, USA). A 3D model of the iliosacrum and
            caudal skeleton of RGM.792000, and all custom MATLAB scripts are provided as electronic
            supplementary material. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 3. Results </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Natural frequencies and walking speeds determined in this study, as well as key
            outcomes of the sensitivity analysis, are reported in table 1 . The natural frequency of
            our baseline model of the tail was 0.66 s −1 , which we interpreted as the preferred
            step frequency for <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> . This corresponds to a PWS
            of 1.28 m s −1 . To provide the reader with an impression of the dynamic behaviour that
            results, we have provided a simulation of a lightly damped version of the baseline model
            (electronic supplementary material, video S1). In this simulation, the only input to the
            tail was a sinusoidal motion at the base of the tail with an amplitude of 0.08 m.
            Assuming pendular walking, this is the vertical motion that results from taking 1.94 m
            long steps at a hip height of 3.1 m. No muscle forces were included, so the phase
            relationship between the vertical oscillations of the hip and tail may not be
            representative of a muscle-actuated tail. In this simulation, a small amount of damping
            was introduced in order to obtain a finite tail amplitude. The damping ratio of the
            fundamental eigenmode was 0.16, which has a negligible effect on the resonant frequency
            [ ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The effects of changes in length (and thus inertia), mass and strain are mathematically
            predictable in our model, and we have thus derived general scaling laws for these
            parameters in the electronic supplementary material. Mass had zero effect on the natural
            frequency. Length ( L ) and strain in the horizontal position ( ε hor ) are related to
            the natural frequency ( fn ) as follows: fn ∝ L −0.5 and fn ∝ 1 hor — 0:5 . These
            relations can also be applied to the altered moment arms or distal axes models. For
            instance, a 6% longer tail, with 10% more strain in horizontal equilibrium (4.4% strain
            instead of 4%), using the maximal moment arms, would lead to a natural frequency of 0.79
            × 1.06 −0.5 × 1.1 −0.5 = 0.73 s −1 . The a These models only changed the moment arms
            within the 3rd – 5th segments; segments 1 and 2 remained unchanged from the baseline
            model. moment arms models cannot be combined with the distal axes models in this way,
            because these models are based on measurements of morphological traits, instead of
            systematic parameter variations. Their combinations are reported in electronic
            supplementary material, table S2, and the above proportionality relations can be applied
            to those combination effects as well. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Varying the moment arms had the largest overall effect on tail natural frequency,
            followed by the models accounting for strain magnitude. Together, these models accounted
            for uncertainty in the effective point of force application and composition of the
            caudal interspinous ligaments. We have supplied a spreadsheet as electronic
            supplementary material that interactively calculates natural frequency and walking
            speed, depending on parameter changes input by the user.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 4. Discussion </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The primary goal of this study was to develop a reductionist method to estimate the
            tail natural frequency of <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> , and to combine the
            results of this method with trackway data for a baseline estimate of PWS ( table 1 ).
            Our secondary goal was to determine which morphological features of the tail have the
            largest effect on its natural frequency, and these are represented by all the other
            models in table 1 . Overall, results are most sensitive to uncertainties regarding
            ligament composition and vertebral kinematics in the tail of <tp:taxon-name> T. rex
            </tp:taxon-name> , while being minimally sensitive to length (and thus moment of
            inertia), and not affected by mass. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Our model predicts several scaling laws which provide insight into the locomotion of
               <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> (derivations are provided in the electronic
            supplementary material). Natural frequency scales with the inverse square root of tail
            length ( table 1 ). This implies an ontogenetic decrease in step frequency, but an
            increase in PWS proportional to L 0.5 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> It has previously been proposed that the distal tail may act as a ‘dynamic stabilizer’
            [ ]. Varying the distal rotational axes revealed that even though the distal three
            segments accounted for only 14.5% of the total caudal mass, they still had a meaningful
            effect on the natural frequency ( table 1 ). Our results support the notion that the
            medio-distal tail plays an important role in overall tail dynamics. Furthermore, the
            ventral axes model suggests that the chevrons increase locomotor speed when the tail is
            in slight flexion, by increasing the moment arm of the interspinous ligaments. Combining
            altered moment arms with alternative rotational axes strengthened this effect
            (electronic supplementary material, table S2). However, this table should be interpreted
            with caution because the distal axes models do not represent axes that would have been
            used throughout the whole step cycle. Instead, the rotational axes would migrate
            ventrally during flexion, and dorsally during extension of the tail, which could
            potentially be influenced by contraction of the epaxial and hypaxial musculature. Thus,
            the bounds in electronic supplementary material, table S2 are unrealistically wide, due
            to the assumptions underlying this table. Yet, to acknowledge the uncertainties in
            dinosaur gait reconstruction, we used these as the reported range in our result. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Varying the amount of strain imposed on the ligaments in the horizontal posture ( ε hor
            , expressed as a fraction) had a similar effect as varying the length: fn ∝ 1 hor — 0:5
            . This is analogous to increasing or decreasing the stiffness at a constant moment of
            inertia. Ligaments that are subject to high levels of strain have increased
            energy-saving properties [ ]. Our high-strain model displayed a lower natural frequency,
            implying that selective pressures for higher PWS may result in less energy-efficient
            locomotion, and vice versa. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Our baseline model suggests a PWS of 1.28 m s −1 for <tp:taxon-name> T. rex
            </tp:taxon-name> , which we interpret to be near its energetically optimal walking
            speed. There are no extant analogues for tail-dependent obligate bipedal locomotion,
            especially combined with such a heavy emphasis on elastic storage. In fact,
            energetically optimal walking speed has only been measured in a few species, so
            comparisons are limited to these studies. In the animal kingdom, optimal walking speed
            is reported to be 1.0 m s −1 for ratites [ ] (average of the net and total MCOT) and
            elephants [ ], 1.34–1.42 m s −1 for humans [1,2] and 1.25 m s −1 for horses [ ], and
            these speeds are closely related to their respective PWS. PWS for giraffes [ ] (reported
            as ‘semi-selected’) and migratory gnus and gazelles [ ] have also been determined to lie
            close to this range. This is a remarkably close distribution, especially given the wide
            range in body size, shape and locomotor modes. Most of our estimates of <tp:taxon-name>
               T. rex </tp:taxon-name> walking speed fall within this range, with two of them only
            slightly exceeding it. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Very little work has been done to directly investigate PWS of dinosaurs. Limb natural
            frequencies have been used to estimate ‘comfortable walking speeds’ of several sauropod
            taxa [ ], and dynamic simulations were used to estimate PWS of <tp:taxon-name>
               Argentinosaurus </tp:taxon-name> [ ]. To our knowledge, no such work has been done on
            theropods. Until now, most estimates for (submaximal) dinosaur walking speeds are based
            on dynamic similarity (DS). Based on a regression of predominantly mammalian walking
            data, Alexander proposed an equation to estimate walking speed from trackways [ ]. Of
            importance is the relative stride length, defined as the ratio between the stride length
            and hip height. This necessitates inferral of the hip height of the trackmaker, leading
            to uncertainties in the estimate. Despite qualitatively similar scaling predictions, our
            proposed NFM predicts lower speeds than trackway estimates using DS [23,24,32,45,50].
            Such trackway estimates are not strictly energetically optimal, but we would expect them
            to tend towards the preferred speed if the sample of trackways is large enough. For
            large theropods, estimates tend to range between 2 and 3 m s −1 , which is much higher
            than the narrow range reported for extant animals. These higher speeds are commonly
            attributed to allometric effects [23,24,32,45,50]. A large source of potential errors,
            however, lies in the equation that relates relative stride length to walking speed, in
            which the step frequencies are implicit [24,51]. Alexander himself noted the high
            variability in his walking data, which leads to errors in speed estimates [ ]. Not only
            is this true for dinosaurs, but even for the walking speed of the animals (including
            humans) on which the regression is based [ ]. It has been shown that limb natural
            frequencies provided better predictions for elephants and giraffes near the preferred
            speed [ ]. Near preferred speeds, DS consistently overestimated walking speeds, but the
            accuracy of the predictions improved at speeds substantially higher than the preferred
            speeds [ ]. When compared to walking speeds of extant animals in a variety of sizes and
            gaits, DS also appears to overestimate the walking speed of bipedal dinosaurs.
            Neglecting tail dynamics may, therefore, be one of the oversimplifications inherent to
            DS, when applied to the inverted pendulum model of walking. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Recent amendments have been proposed to improve DS-based estimations, either by
            focusing on swing phase dynamics [ ], or by incorporating taxon-specific morphological
            parameters to reduce uncertainty [ ]. The latter are of course difficult to obtain from
            a fossilized trackway. Our method can help in this regard, by providing a range of
            plausible step frequencies for any given taxon. With this goal in mind, it would be most
            effective to estimate the natural frequencies of taxa that are wellrepresented in the
            trackway record. That way, it would be possible to combine step length data from several
            trackways, increasing confidence that the average result should tend towards preferred
            (and therefore optimal) gait. Unfortunately, this was not possible in the present study,
            because large theropod trackways with reasonably close taxonomic proximity to
               <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> are exceedingly rare [ ]. Bipedal dinosaurs
            seem to have preferred to walk at a relative stride length of 1.3, and it has been
            suggested that this might have been energetically optimal [24,45]. This relation
            implicitly relates footprint length to stride length, by first estimating hip height
            from footprint length, and also assumes leg kinematics are known. Instead, we preferred
            to relate footprint length directly to stride length from a trackway that could be
            ascribed to <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> with reasonable certainty [ ]. This
            ensures sufficient geometric similarity to RGM.792000. The resulting step lengths
            differed by less than 4% from the suggested preferred relative stride length. Whenever
            considering trackway data, substrate-related uncertainties will prevent any
            straightforward interpretation [53,54], although presumably, these would not affect tail
            natural frequency. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> DS does not incorporate MCOT, and therefore cannot be used to estimate PWS of
            dinosaurs. Therefore, when estimating dinosaur foraging costs, researchers have used DS
            to scale the walking speed [ ], or even kept it at a constant 2 m s −1 for larger taxa [
            ]. However, methods to calculate MCOT are heavily dependent on both speed and mass [ ],
            so we suggest that any comparison of foraging costs should use the PWS of the respective
            taxa as a starting point. This could be done using the natural frequency of the legs [
            ], musculoskeletal simulations [ ], or NFM as we propose it. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> To our knowledge, musculoskeletal simulation models have not been used to estimate how
            MCOT varied with walking speed in <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> , although
            this has been done for <tp:taxon-name> Argentinosaurus </tp:taxon-name> [ ]. A
            simulation model requires estimation of joint rotational axes, body mass and moment arms
            for both the musculature and the ligaments [27,30,34,41,49]. The muscular reconstruction
            then provides further uncertainties in fibre composition type and architecture, both of
            which would significantly influence power output. Simulation studies have generally
            focused on maximal speed, and have contributed to the consensus that a long flight phase
            for large theropods would be unlikely [25,27,30,35]. However, the extensive muscular
            reconstructions often strongly affect the biomechanical simulations [41,49]. The largest
            uncertainty in the present study is related to the moment arms of the interspinous
            ligaments. This is an encouraging finding, because their extent is well-bounded by the
            skeleton. Essentially, one of the more certain parameters provides the most uncertainty.
            Future research on in vivo vertebral kinematics, dynamics and ligament compositions of
            crocodilian tails could reduce this uncertainty. Similarly encouraging is that our
            results are minimally sensitive to estimates of muscularity or inertial parameters in
            general. Indeed, when isolating mass as a free parameter in our sensitivity analysis, we
            have shown that our predicted speeds are unaffected by mass-estimates ( table 1 ). This
            is due to the assumption that the ligaments could passively support the tail: adding
            muscle mass would make the ligaments proportionately stiffer, leading to the same
            natural frequency (see the scaling relationships in the electronic supplementary
            material). This assumption mimics the adaptations that naturally would have occurred in
            the connective tissue, to keep the tail horizontal as the animal gained mass throughout
            its life. It has been shown that body mass does not affect PWS in humans [ ], and this
            is also in accordance with DS [ ]. Minimal sensitivity to muscular and inertial
            estimates implies that our inverse dynamic approach to constructing a non-rigid tail
            could be incorporated into more sophisticated hindlimb simulation models, without adding
            much to the overall uncertainty of the result. This could have implications for maximal
            running speeds of large taxa like <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> : maximum
            running speed was shown to be limited by peak stresses on the limbs [ ], but a compliant
            tail may serve to reduce these stresses. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Our method for walking speed estimation is meant to be a reductionist analysis, so we
            have only incorporated the interspinous ligaments, since we expect their mechanical
            effect to dominate overall tail dynamics. Natural frequencies play an important role in
            animal locomotion [ – ], and NFM, therefore, provides a reasonable starting point for
            investigating how the resonant properties of dinosaur tails affect overall locomotion.
            However, in reducing the analysis to the mechanics of a single structure, many of the
            complex interactions are ignored. For instance, animals tune the frequencies of their
            segments through muscular contractions [6,7]. <tp:taxon-name> Tyrannosaurus rex
            </tp:taxon-name> could have contracted its epaxial and hypaxial caudal musculature to
            add rotational stiffness to the tail, which could be beneficial at higher speeds, for
            instance during a pursuit. Our ventral axes model demonstrates a possibility in this
            regard: if <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> were to keep its distal tail in
            slight flexion, thereby migrating the rotational axes of the vertebrae to the
            articulations with the chevrons, the overall natural frequency of the tail would
            increase. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Tail musculature could also be employed to enforce beneficial phase relationships
            between vertical hip and tail oscillations. During walking, vertical oscillations
            between withers and heads in most ungulates are out of phase, which provides them with
            an energetic benefit [36–38,55]. This is theorized to be modulated by natural
            frequencies of the neck segment [37,38], but there is an active component to this
            behaviour as well [ ]. This phase relationship reduces the losses incurred during the
            step-to-step transitions, which are identified as major sources of energy losses in
            inverted pendulum models of walking [ ]. The implications of energy storage are also
            further complicated by the serial elasticity in musculotendon complexes: tendon
            stiffness can substantially impact the mechanical work done by the muscle fibres [ ].
            Finally, the cost of cyclical muscle contractions could also affect metabolic optima,
            depending on the task requirements [16,17]. Such complex interactions would undoubtedly
            affect PWS, but require extensive reconstructions of muscular contractile properties.
            Muscular parameters currently provide the biggest uncertainty in most musculoskeletal
            simulations of dinosaurs [41,49,58], so any investigation of these interactions would
            require careful consideration. Inclusion of our compliant tail model into fully actuated
            hindlimb simulations of <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> may shed further light
            on how the unique tails of non-avian dinosaurs functioned during locomotion. However, in
            such complex simulations, the intricacies of tail dynamics may be overshadowed by the
            uncertainties regarding the contractile properties of the muscles. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>We set out to develop a method that does not require assumptions regarding contractile
            properties, so we accept that this limits the predictive power of our method. Given the
            overall uncertainties we must deal with when investigating the locomotion of extinct
            animals, we consider the simplicity of the method to be one of its strengths. Provided
            the neck or tail posture was supported passively, our method could be used to arrive at
            an estimate of the PWS of any sufficiently complete dinosaur, without the need to
            estimate contractile properties.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 5. Conclusion </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Gait reconstruction of dinosaurs has numerous inherent uncertainties, and therefore it
            is important to compare results from different methods, in an attempt to find a
            convergent point. We have proposed a method based on reconstructing the natural
            frequency of the vertical swaying of the tail, which we refer to as the Natural
            Frequency Method. This method requires relatively few assumptions, which are furthermore
            different assumptions to other methods. Our results for preferred walking speed of
               <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> are lower than previous estimations for large
            theropods, but more closely match the preferred walking speeds of a variety of extant
            animals, regardless of gait pattern and body size. This seems to call in question the
            oft-cited high walking performance of bipedal dinosaurs due to their cursorial
            adaptations. Investigating vertebral kinematics and ligament composition in extant
            archosaurian tails could further constrain predictions based on our method, which could,
            in turn, be used to improve trackway estimates and foraging costs. Using simple, yet
            well-established principles from animal locomotion, the Natural Frequency Method
            provides an independent line of evidence to explore the locomotion of non-avian
            dinosaurs. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Data accessibility. Supplementary texts, figures S1–S 7 and tables S1–S 2, video S1, a
            spreadsheet to calculate all possible parameter effects of our models, custom MATLAB
            code written for the analyses and 3D scans of the iliosacrum and caudal skeleton of
            RGM.792000 are provided as electronic supplementary material. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Authors ’ contributions. P.A.v.B., A.J.K.v.S. and A.S. conceived the project.
            A.J.K.v.S. designed the biomechanical model. P.A.v.B. performed the reconstructions,
            measurements, coding. P.A.v.B., A.J.K.v.S. and A.S. wrote the manuscript. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Competing interests. The authors declare no competing interests; </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Funding. Nothing to declare. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Acknowledgements. We thank K. Lemaire, M. Bobbert and D. Kistemaker for their vital
            role in early discussions. Further thanks to V. Vanhecke for 3D scanning, P. Larson for
            providing excavation maps and D. Tanke for providing photographs. H. Mallison and P.
            Manning are thanked for in-depth discussion and feedback on earlier versions of this
            manuscript. Discussions with W. Sellers, K. Bates and F. van Diggelen further helped us
            to contextualize our work. Lastly, we extend our gratitude to two anonymous reviewers
            whose constructive feedback and insights helped shape the final manuscript. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> References </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 1. Browning RC , Baker EA , Herron JA , Kram R. 2006 Effects of obesity and sex on the
            energetic cost and preferred speed of walking . J. Appl. Physiol. 100 , 390 – 398 .
            (doi: 10.1152/ japplphysiol.00767.2005 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 2. Gast K , Kram R , Riemer R. 2019 Preferred walking speed on rough terrain: is it all
            about energetics? J. Exp. Biol. 222 , jeb185447. (doi: 10. 1242/jeb.185447 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 3. Watson RR , Rubenson J , Coder L , Hoyt DF , Propert MWG , Marsh RL . 2011
            Gait-specific energetics contributes to economical walking and running in emus and
            ostriches . Proc. R. Soc. B 278 , 2040 – 2046 . (doi: 10.1098/rspb.2010.2022) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 4. Hoyt DF , Taylor R. 1981 Gait and the energetics of locomotion in horses . Nature
            292 , 239 – 240 . (doi: 10.1038/292239a0) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 5. Langman VA , Roberts TJ , Black J , Maloiy GM , Heglund NC , Weber J-M , Kram R ,
            Taylor CR . 1995 Moving cheaply: energetics of walking in the African elephant . J. Exp.
            Biol. 198 , 629 – 632 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 6. Ahlborn BK , Blake RW . 2002 Walking and running at resonance . Zoology 105 , 165 –
            174 . (doi: 10.1078/0944-2006-00057) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 7. Ahlborn BK , Blake RW , Megill WM . 2006 Frequency tuning in animal locomotion .
            Zoology 109 , 43 – 53 . (doi: 10.1016/j.zool.2005. 11.001 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 8. Wagenaar RC , Van Emmerik REA . 2000 Resonant frequencies of arms and legs identify
            different walking patterns . J. Biomech. 33 , 853 – 861 . (doi:
            10.1016/S0021-9290(00)00020-8) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 9. Huat OJ , Ghista DN , Beng NK , John TCC . 2004 Optimal stride frequency computed
            from the double-compound pendulum of the leg, and verified experimentally as the
            preferred stride frequency of jogging . Int. J. Comput. Appl.Technol. 21 , 46 – 51 .
            (doi: 10.1504/ijcat.2004.005338) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 10. Christian A , Müller RHG , Christian G , Preuschoft H. 1999 Limb swinging in
            elephants and giraffes and implications for the reconstruction of limb movements and
            speed estimates in large dinosaurs . Foss. Rec. 2 , 81 – 90 . (doi:
            10.5194/fr-2-81-1999) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 11. Holt KG , Hamill J , Andres RO . 1990 The forcedriven harmonic oscillator as a
            model for human locomotion . Hum. Mov. Sci. 9 , 55 – 68 . (doi:
            10.1016/0167-9457(90)90035-C) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 12. Holt KG , Hamill J , Andres RO . 1991 Predicting the minimal energy costs of human
            walking . Med. Sci. Sports Exerc. 23 , 491 – 498 . (doi: 10.
            1249/00005768-199104000-00016 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 13. Lee LF , Krovi VN . 2008 Musculoskeletal simulation-based parametric study of
            optimal gait frequency in biped locomotion . In Proc. of 2nd Biennial IEEE/RAS-EMBS Int.
            Conf. on Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics, BioRob 2008, Scottsdale, AZ, 19–22
            October , pp. 354 – 359 . IEEE . (doi: 10.1109/BIOROB.2008. 4762864 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 14. Myers MJ , Steudel K. 1997 Morphological conservation of limb natural pendular
            period in the domestic dog ( Canis familiaris ): implications for locomotor energetics .
            J. Morphol. 234 , 183 – 196 . (doi: 10.1002/(SICI)1097-
            4687(199711)234:2&lt;183::AID-JMOR5&gt;3.0.CO;2-D ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 15. Raichlen DA . 2004 Convergence of forelimb and hindlimb natural pendular period in
            baboons ( Papio cynocephalus ) and its implication for the evolution of primate
            quadrupedalism . J.Hum. Evol. 46 , 719 – 738 . (doi: 10.1016/j.jhevol.2004.04.002) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 16. Doke J , Donelan JM , Kuo AD . 2005 Mechanics and energetics of swinging the human
            leg . J.Exp.Biol. 208 , 439 – 445 . (doi: 10.1242/jeb.01408) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 17. Dean JC , Kuo AD . 2011 Energetic costs of producing muscle work and force in a
            cyclical human bouncing task . J. Appl. Physiol. 110 , 873 – 880 . (doi:
            10.1152/japplphysiol.00505.2010) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 18. Gatesy SM . 1990 Caudofemoral musculature and the evolution of theropod locomotion
            . Paleobiology 16 , 170 – 186 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 19. Farlow JO , Gatesy SM , Holtz TR , Hutchinson JR , Robinson JM . 2000 Theropod
            locomotion . Am. Zool. 40 , 640 – 663 . (doi: 10.1093/icb/40.4.640) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 20. Hengst R. 2004 Gravity and the <tp:taxon-name> T. rex </tp:taxon-name> backbone .
            J. Vertebr. Paleontol. 24 , 69 A – 70A. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 21. Carpenter K. 2013 A closer look at the hypothesis of scavenging versus predation by
            Tyrannosaurus rex . In Tyrannosaurid paleobiology (eds JM Parrish , RE Molnar , PJ
            Currie , EB Koppelhus ), pp. 265 – 277 . Bloomington, Indiana: Indiana University Press
            . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 22. Wilson JP , Woodruff DC , Gardner JD , Flora HM , Horner JR , Organ CL . 2016
            Vertebral adaptations to large body size in theropod dinosaurs . PLoS ONE 11 , e 0158962
            . (doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0158962) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 23. Alexander RM . 1976 Estimates of speeds of dinosaurs . Nature 261 , 129 – 130 .
            (doi: 10.1038/ 261129a0 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 24. Thulborn RA . 1984 Preferred gaits of bipedal dinosaurs . Alcheringa Australas J.
            Palaeontol. 8 , 243 – 252 . (doi: 10.1080/03115518408618947) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 25. Hutchinson JR , Garcia M. 2002 Tyrannosaurus was not a fast runner . Nature 416 ,
            1018 – 2021 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 26. Hutchinson JR . 2004 Biomechanical modeling and sensitivity analysis of bipedal
            running ability. II. Extinct taxa. J. Morphol. 262 , 441 – 461 . (doi:
            10.1002/jmor.10240 ) 27. Sellers WI , Manning PL . 2007 Estimating dinosaur maximum
            running speeds using evolutionary robotics . Proc. R. Soc. B 274 , 2711 – 2716 . (doi:
            10.1098/rspb.2007.0846 ) 28. Pontzer H , Allen V , Hutchinson JR . 2009 Biomechanics of
            running indicates endothermy in bipedal dinosaurs . PLoS ONE 4 , e 7783 . (doi:
            10.1371/journal.pone.0007783 ) 29. Kane A , Healy K , Ruxton GD , Jackson AL . 2016 Body
            size as a driver of scavenging in theropod dinosaurs . Am. Nat. 187 , 706 – 716 . (doi:
            10. 1086/686094 ) 30. Sellers WI , Pond SB , Brassey CA , Manning PL , Bates KT . 2017
            Investigating the running abilities of Tyrannosaurus rex using stressconstrained
            multibody dynamic analysis . PeerJ 5 , 1 – 19 . (doi: 10.7717/peerj.3420 ) 31. Dececchi
            TA , Mloszewska AM , Holtz TR , Habib MB , Larsson HCE . 2020 The fast and the frugal:
            divergent locomotory strategies drive limb lengthening in theropod dinosaurs . PLoS ONE
            15 , e 0223698 . (doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0223698 ) 32. Ruiz J. 2018 Comments on ‘ A
            tyrannosaur trackway at Glenrock, Lance Formation (Maastrichtian), Wyoming ’ (Smith et
            al ., Cretaceous Research, v. 61, pp. 1 – 4, 2016). Cretac. Res. 82 , 81 – 82 . (doi:
            10.1016/j.cretres. 2017.05.033 ) 33. Bates KT , Manning PL , Hodgetts D , Sellers WI .
            2009 Estimating mass properties of dinosaurs using laser imaging and 3D computer
            modelling . PLoS ONE 4 , e 4532 . (doi: 10.1371/ journal.pone.0004532 ) 34. Bates KT ,
            Benson RBJ , Falkingham PL . 2012 A computational analysis of locomotor anatomy and body
            mass evolution in Allosauroidea (Dinosauria: Theropoda) . Paleobiology 38 , 486 – 507 .
            (doi: 10.5061/dryad.09kf4g02 ) 35. Persons WS , Currie PJ . 2011 The tail of
            Tyrannosaurus : reassessing the size and locomotive Importance of the M. caudofemoralis
            in non-avian theropods . Anat. Rec. 294 , 119 – 131 . (doi: 10.1002/ar.21290 ) 36.
            Gellman KS , Bertram JEA . 2002 The equine nuchal ligament 2: passive dynamic energy
            exchange in locomotion . Vet. Comp. Orthop. Traumatol. 15 , 7 – 14 . (doi:
            10.1055/s-0038-1632706 ) 37. Loscher DM , Meyer F , Kracht K , Nyakatura JA . 2016
            Timing of head movements is consistent with energy minimization in walking ungulates .
            Proc. R. Soc. B 283 , 20161908 . (doi: 10.1098/ rspb.2016.1908 ) 38. Basu C , Wilson AM
            , Hutchinson JR . 2019 The locomotor kinematics and ground reaction forces of walking
            giraffes . J. Exp. Biol. 222 , jeb 159277 . (doi: 10.1242/jeb.159277 ) 39. Biewener AA .
            2008 Tendons and ligaments: structure, mechanical behavior and biological function . In
            Collagen (ed. P Fratzl ), pp. 269 – 284 . Boston, MA: Springer . (doi: 10.1007/
            978-0-387-73906-9_10 ) 40. Manning PL . 2008 Spring in the tail? In Grave secrets of
            dinosaurs: soft tissues and hard science , pp. 292 – 295 . Washington: National
            Geographic Society . 41. Bishop PJ , Cuff AR , Hutchinson JR . 2020 How to build a
            dinosaur: musculoskeletal modeling and simulation of locomotor biomechanics in extinct
            animals . Paleobiology 47 , 1 – 38 . (doi: 10.1017/ pab.2020.46 ) 42. Scholz MN ,
            Bobbert MF , van Soest AJ , Clark JR , van Heerden J. 2008 Running biomechanics: shorter
            heels, better economy . J. Exp. Biol. 211 , 3266 – 3271 . (doi: 10.1242/jeb.018812 ) 43.
            Ruina A , Pratap R. 2019 Mechanics Toolset, Statics and Dynamics . See http://ruina.tam.
            cornell.edu/Book/ . 44. Alexander RM . 2006 Principles of animal locomotion . Princeton,
            NJ: Princeton University Press . 45. McCrea RT , Buckley LG , Farlow JO , Lockley MG ,
            Currie PJ , Matthews NA , Pemberton SG . 2014 A ‘ terror of tyrannosaurs ’ : the first
            trackways of tyrannosaurids and evidence of gregariousness and pathology in
            Tyrannosauridae . PLoS ONE 9 , e 103613 . (doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0103613 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 46. Hutchinson JR , Bates KT , Molnar J , Allen V , Makovicky PJ . 2011 A computational
            analysis of limb and body dimensions in Tyrannosaurus rex with implications for
            locomotion, ontogeny, and growth . PLoS ONE 6 , e 26037 . (doi: 10.1371/
            journal.pone.0026037 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 47. Mallison H. 2011 Defense capabilities of Kentrosaurus aethiopicus Hennig, 1915 .
            Palaeontol. Electron. 14 , 1 – 25 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 48. Pennycuick CJ . 1975 On the running of the gnu ( Connochaetes taurinus ) and other
            animals . J. Exp. Biol. 63 , 775 – 799 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 49. Sellers WI , Margetts L , Coria RA , Manning PL . 2013 March of the titans: the
            locomotor capabilities of sauropod dinosaurs . PLoS ONE 8 , e 78733 . (doi:
            10.1371/journal.pone.0078733 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 50. Smith SD , Persons WS , Xing L. 2016 A tyrannosaur trackway at Glenrock, Lance
            Formation (Maastrichtian) , Wyoming. Cretac. Res. 61 , 1 – 4 . (doi:
            10.1016/j.cretres.2015.12.020 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 51. Alexander RM . 2006 Dinosaur biomechanics . Proc. R. Soc. B 273 , 1849 – 1855 .
            (doi: 10.1098/ rspb.2006.3532 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 52. Raichlen DA , Pontzer H , Shapiro LJ . 2013 A new look at the dynamic similarity
            hypothesis: the importance of swing phase . Biol. Open 2 , 1032 – 1036 . (doi:
            10.1242/bio.20135165 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 53. Marmol-Guijarro A , Nudds R , Folkow L , Codd J. 2020 Examining the accuracy of
            trackways for predicting gait selection and speed of locomotion . Front.Zool. 17 , 17 .
            (doi: 10.1186/s12983-020-00363-z ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 54. Manning PL . 2004 A new approach to the analysis and interpretation of tracks:
            examples from the dinosauria . Geol. Soc. Lond. Spec. Publ. 228 , 93 – 123 . (doi:
            10.1144/GSL.SP.2004.228.01.06 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 55. Gellman K , Bertram J. 2002 The equine nuchal ligament 1: structural and material
            properties . Vet. Comp. Orthop. Traumatol. 15 , 1 – 6 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 56. Kuo AD . 2007 The six determinants of gait and the inverted pendulum analogy: a
            dynamic walking perspective . Hum. Mov. Sci. 26 , 617 – 656 . (doi:
            10.1016/j.humov.2007.04.003 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 57. Orselli MIV , Franz JR , Thelen DG . 2017 The effects of Achilles tendon compliance
            on triceps surae mechanics and energetics in walking . J. Biomech. 60 , 227 – 231 .
            (doi: 10.1016/j. jbiomech.2017.06.022 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 58. Bates KT , Falkingham PL . 2018 The importance of muscle architecture in
            biomechanical reconstructions of extinct animals:a case study using Tyrannosaurus rex .
            J.Anat. 233 , 625 – 635 .(doi: 10.1111/joa.12874 ) </p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
