<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nature</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2169-0</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Identifying SARS-CoV-2related coronaviruses in Malayan pangolins</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>26</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>

https://doi.org/ 
10.1038/s41586-020-2169-0
</title>
         <p>
Accelerated Article Preview

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Identifying SARS-CoV-2related coronaviruses in Malayan pangolins

</title>
         <p>
Received: 

7 February 
2020
</p>
         <p>

Accepted: 
17 March 2020

</p>
         <p>
Accelerated Article Preview Published

online 


26 March 
2020

</p>
         <p>
Cite this article as: Lam, T. T. et al.
Identifying SARS-CoV-2 related coronavi-

ruses in Malayan pangolins. 

Nature


https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2169-0
(2020).

Tommy Tsan-Yuk Lam
, 
Marcus Ho-Hin Shum
, 
Hua-Chen Zhu
, 
Yi-Gang Tong
, 
Xue-Bing Ni
, 
Yun-Shi Liao
, 
Wei Wei
, 
William Yiu-Man Cheung
, 
Wen-Juan Li
, 
Lian-Feng Li
, 
Gabriel M. Leung
,


Edward C. Holmes
, Yan-Ling Hu &amp; 
Yi Guan
</p>
         <p>This is a PDF file of a peer-reviewed paper that has been accepted for publication. Although unedited, the content has been subjected to preliminary formatting. Nature is providing this early version of the typeset paper as a service to our authors and readers.The text and figures will undergo copyediting and a proof review before the paper is published in its final form. Please note that during the production process errors may be discovered which could affect the content,and all legal disclaimers apply.</p>
         <p>
Nature | www.nature.com
</p>
         <p>
Article

</p>
         <p>
Identifying SARS-CoV-2related
</p>
         <p>
coronaviruses in Malayan pangolins
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2169-0
</p>
         <p>

Received: 
7 February 2020

</p>
         <p>

Accepted: 
17 March 2020

</p>
         <p>

Published online: 
26 March 2020

Tommy Tsan-Yuk Lam
1,2,8
, Marcus Ho-Hin Shum
2
, Hua-Chen Zhu
1,2
, Yi-Gang Tong
3,8
,
</p>
         <p>
Xue-Bing Ni
2
, Yun-Shi Liao
2
, Wei Wei
4
, William Yiu-Man Cheung
2
, Wen-Juan Li
3
, Lian-Feng Li
6
, Gabriel M. Leung
2
, Edward C. Holmes
7
, Yan-Ling Hu
4,5
✉ 
&amp; Yi Guan
1,2
✉ The ongoing outbreak of viral pneumonia in 
China
and beyond is associated with a novel coronavirus,SARS-CoV-2 1. This outbreak has been tentatively associated with a seafood market in Wuhan, 
China
, where the sale of wild animals may be the source of zoonotic infection2. Although bats are likely reservoir hosts for SARS-CoV-2,the identity of any intermediate host that might have facilitated transfer to humans is unknown.Here, we report the identification of SARS-CoV-2-related coronaviruses in Malayan pangolins (
<tp:taxon-name>
Manis javanica
</tp:taxon-name>
) seized in anti-smuggling operations in southern 
China
.Metagenomic sequencing identified pangolin-associated coronaviruses that belong to two sub-lineages of SARS-CoV-2-related coronaviruses,including one that exhibits strong similarity to SARS-CoV- 
2 in
the receptor-binding domain. The discovery of multiple lineages of pangolin coronavirus and their similarity to SARS- CoV-2 suggests that pangolins should be considered as possible hosts in the emergence of novel coronaviruses and should be removed from wet markets to prevent zoonotic transmission.
</p>
         <p>
An outbreak of serious pneumonia disease was reported in Wuhan, 
China
on 
30 December 2019
.The causative agent was soon identified as a novel coronavirus 
1
, which was later named SARS-CoV-2.Case num- bers grew rapidly from 
27 in
December 2019
to 64,473 globally as of14 
February 2020
3
, such that the WHO have declared a public health emer- gency.Many of the early cases were linked to Huanan seafood market in Wuhan city, 
Hubei province
,from where the probable zoonotic source is speculated to originate 
2
. Currently, only environmental samples taken from the market have been reported as positive for SARS-CoV-2 by the 
China
CDC 
4
. However,as similar wet markets were implicated in the SARS outbreak of 
2002-2003
5
, it seems likely that wild animals were also involved in the emergence of SARS-CoV-2.Indeed,a number of mammalian species were available for purchase in the Huanan seafood market prior to the outbreak 
4
. Unfortunately,because the market was cleared soon after the outbreak began,determining the source virus in the animal population from the market is challenging.Although a coronavirus closely related to SARS-CoV-2 sampled from a 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
affinis
</tp:taxon-name>
bat in 
Yunnan
in 2013 has now been identified 
6
, similar viruses have not yet been detected in other wildlife species.Here, we present the identification of SARS-CoV-2 related viruses in pangolins smuggled into southern 
China
.
</p>
         <p>
We investigated the virome composition of pangolins (mammalian order 
<tp:taxon-name>Pholidota</tp:taxon-name>
).These animals are of growing importance and interest because they are the most illegally trafficked mammal:they are used as both a food source and their scales are utilized in traditional Chinese medicine.A number of pangolin species now are regarded as critically endangered on the International Union for Conservation of Nature Red List of Threatened Species.We received frozen tissue (lungs,intestine, blood)samples collected from18 Malayan pangolins (
<tp:taxon-name>
Manis javanica
</tp:taxon-name>
) during 
August2017
- 
January 2018
.These pangolins were obtained during anti-smuggling operations performed by 
Guangxi
Customs.Strik- ingly,high-throughput sequencing of their RNA revealed the presence of coronaviruses in six (two lung,two intestine,one lung-intestine mix, one blood from five individual pangolins;Extended Data Table1) of 43 samples.With the sequence read data,and by filling gaps with amplicon sequencing,we were able to obtain six complete or near complete genome sequences - denoted GX/P1E, GX/P2V, GX/P3B,GX/P4L,GX/ P5E and GX/P5L -that fall into the SARS-CoV-2 lineage (within the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Betacoronavirus
</tp:taxon-name>
of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Coronaviridae
</tp:taxon-name>
) in a phylogenetic analysis (Figure 1b). The genome sequence of the virus isolate (GX/P2V) has very high similarity (99.83-99.92%) to the five sequences obtained through the metagenomic sequencing of the raw samples,and all have similar genomic organizations to SARS-CoV-2,with eleven predicted open reading frames (

; Extended Data Table 2;two are overlapping ORFs). We were also able to successfully isolate the virus using the Vero E6 cell line (Extended Data 

). Based on these new genome sequences,we designed primers for qPCR detection to confirm that the raw samples were positive for the coronavirus.We conducted further qPCR testing on another batch of archived pangolin samples collected between May-July2018.Among the 19 samples(nine intestine tissues,
</p>
         <p>ten lung tissues) tested from12 animals,three lung tissue samples from three individual pangolins were coronavirus positive.</p>
         <p>
In addition to the animals from 
Guangxi
, after the start of the SARS-CoV-2 outbreak the Guangzhou Customs Technology Center re-examined their five archived pangolin samples (two skin swabs, two unknown tissue,one scale) obtained in anti-smuggling operations performed in 
March 2019
.Following high-throughput sequencing the scale sample was found to contain coronavirus reads,and from these data we assembled a partial genome sequence of 21,505bp (denoted as GD/P2S),representing approximately 72% of the SARS-CoV-2 genome. Importantly,this virus sequence,obtained from a pangolin scale sample,may in fact be derived from contaminants of other infected tissues. Notably,another study of diseased pangolins in 
Guangdong
performed in 2019 also identified viral contigs from lung samples that were similarly related to SARS-CoV-2 
7
. Different assembly methods and manual curation were performed to generate a partial genome sequence that comprised 86.3% of the full-length virus genome (denoted as GD/P1L in the phylogeny shown in 

).
</p>
         <p>
These novel pangolin coronavirus genomes have 85.5% to 92.4% sequence similarity to SARS-CoV-2,and represent two sub-lineages of SARS-CoV-2 related viruses in the phylogenetic tree, one of which (comprising GD/P1L and GDP2S) is very closely related to SARS-CoV-2 (

; red circles).It has previously been noted that members of the subgenus 
Sarbecovirus
have experienced widespread recombination 
8
.In support of this,a recombination analysis (

)performed here revealed that bat coronaviruses ZC45 and ZXC21are likely recombinants, containing genome fragments derived from multiple SARS- CoV related lineages (genome regions 2, 5, 7) as well as SARS-CoV-2 related lineages including that from pangolins (regions 1, 3, 4, 6, 8).
</p>
         <p>
More notable,however,was the observation of putative recombination signals between the pangolins coronaviruses,bat coronaviruses RaTG13,and human SARS-CoV-2 (

). In particular,SARS-CoV-2 exhibits very high sequence similarity to the 
Guangdong
pangolin coronaviruses in the receptor-binding domain (RBD;97.4% amino acid similarity;indicated by red arrow in 

and 

), even though it is most closely related to bat coronavirus RaTG 
13 in
the remainder of the viral genome.Indeed,the 
Guangdong
pangolin coronaviruses and SARS-CoV-2 possess identical amino acids at the five critical residues of the RBD,whereas RaTG13 only shares one amino acid with SARS- CoV-2(residue 442,human SARS-CoV numbering 
9
) and these latter two viruses have only89.2% amino acid similarity in the RBD.Interestingly,a phylogenetic analysis of synonymous sites only from the RBD revealed that the topological position of the 
Guangdong
pangolin is consistent with that in the remainder of the viral genome, rather than being the closest relative of SARS-CoV-2 (

). Hence,it is possible that the amino acid similarity between the RBD of the 
Guangdong
pangolin coronaviruses and SARS-CoV-2 is due to selectively-mediated convergent evolution rather than recombination,although it is difficult to choose between these scenarios on current data.This observation is consistent with the fact that ACE2 sequence similarity is higher between humans and pangolins (84.8%) than those between humans and bats (80.8% - 81.4%; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp.) (Extended Data Table 3). The occurrence of either recombination and/or convergent evolution further highlights the role played by intermediate animal hosts in human virus emergence. Importantly, however, all the pangolin coronaviruses identified to date lack the insertion of a polybasic (furin-like) S1/S2 cleavage site in the spike protein that distinguishes human SARS-CoV-2 from related betacoronaviruses (including RaTG13) 
10
, and which may have helped facilitate its emergence and rapid spread through human populations.
</p>
         <p>
To date,pangolins are the only mammals other than bats documented to be infected by a SARS-CoV-2 related coronavirus.It is striking that two related lineages of CoVs are found in pangolins independently sampled in different Chinese provinces and that both are also related to SARS- CoV-2. This suggests that these animals may be important hosts for these viruses,which is surprising as pangolins are solitary animals with relatively small population sizes,reflecting their endangered status 
11
. Indeed,on current data it cannot be excluded that pangolins acquired their SARS-CoV-2 related viruses independently from bats or another animal host,so that their role in the emergence of human SARS-CoV-2 remains unproven.In this context it is notable that both lineages of pangolin coronaviruses were obtained from trafficked Malayan pangolins, likely originating from Southeast Asia, and there is a marked lack of knowledge of the viral diversity maintained by this animal in regions where it is indigenous.Undoubtedly,the extent of virus transmission in pangolin populations requires additional investigation.However,the repeated occurrence of infections with SARS-CoV-2 related coronaviruses in 
Guangxi
and 
Guangdong
provinces suggests that this animal may play an important role in the community ecology of coronaviruses.
</p>
         <p>
Coronaviruses,including those related to SARS-CoV-2,are clearly present in many wild mammals in Asia 
5–7,12
. Although the epidemiology, pathogenicity, interspecies infectivity and transmissibility of coronaviruses in pangolins remains to be studied,the data presented here strongly suggests that handling these animals requires considerable caution,and that their sale in wet markets should be strictly prohibited.Further surveillance on pangolins in the natural environment in 
China
and Southeast Asia are clearly needed to understand their role in the emergence of coronaviruses and the risk of future zoonotic transmission.
</p>
         <p>
Online content

</p>
         <p>Any methods,additional references,Nature Research reporting summaries, source data, extended data, supplementary information, acknowledgements, peer review information; details of author contributions and competing interests; and statements of data and code availability are available at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2169-0.</p>
         <p>

1. 
Wu,F.
et al
. 
A new coronavirus associated with human respiratory disease in China
. 

Nature

(
2020
). 
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2008-3
.

</p>
         <p>

2. 
Lu,R.
et al
. 
Genomic characterisation and epidemiology of 2019 novel coronavirus: implications for virus origins and receptor binding
. 

Lancet

, (
2020
). 
https://doi. org/10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30251-8
.

</p>
         <p>

3. 
World Health Organization
. 
WHO Novel Coronavirus
(
2019
- 
nCoV) situation reports
. 
https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/situation-reports/
</p>
         <p>

4. 
Cohen,J. Mining
coronavirus genomes for clues to the outbreak’s origins
. 

Science

, (
2020
) 
https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2020/01/mining-coronavirus-genomes-clues-outbreak-s-origins
.

</p>
         <p>

5. 
Wang,M.
et al
. 
SARS-CoV infection in a restaurant from palm civet
. 

Emerg Infect Dis

11

: 
1860-5
,(
2005
).

</p>
         <p>

6. 
Zhou,P.
et al
. 
A pneumonia outbreak associated with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin
. 

Nature

(
2020
). 
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7
.

</p>
         <p>

7. 
Liu,P.
et al
. 
Viral Metagenomics Revealed Sendai Virus and Coronavirus Infection of Malayan Pangolins (Manis javanica)
. 

Viruses

11

, (
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

8. 
Hon,C.C.
et al. 
Evidence of the recombinant origin of a bat severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)-like coronavirus and its implications on the direct ancestor of SARS coronavirus
. 

J Virol

82

, 
1819-1826
,(
2008
).

</p>
         <p>

9. 
Wan, Y.
et al
. 
Receptor recognition by novel coronavirus from Wuhan: An analysis based on decade-long structural studies of SARS
. 

J Virol

, (
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

10. 
Coutard,B.
et al
. 
The spike glycoprotein of the new coronavirus
2019
-nCoV contains a furin-like cleavage site absent in CoV of the same clade. 

Antiviral Res

, 
104742
, 
https://doi. org/10.1016/j.antiviral.2020.104742
(2020).

</p>
         <p>

11. 
Heinrich,S.
et al
. 
The global trafficking of pangolins:A comprehensive summary of seizures and trafficking routes from 2010
–2015. 

Trafficking

, (
2017
).

</p>
         <p>

12. 
Wang,W.
et al
. 2017. 
Discovery of a highly divergent coronavirus in the Asian house shrew from China illuminates the origin of the alphacoronaviruses
. 

J Virol

91

, (
2017
).

</p>
         <p>
Publisher’s note
Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.
</p>
         <p>
Methods
</p>
         <p>
Ethics Statement

</p>
         <p>
The animals studied here were rescued and treated by the 
Guangxi Zhuang
Autonomous Region Terrestrial Wildlife Medical-aid and Monitoring Epidemic Diseases Research Center under the ethics approval (wild animal treatment regulation No.[2011] 85).The samples were collected following the procedure guideline (Pangolins Rescue Procedure,November,2016).
</p>
         <p>

Sample collection, viral detection and sequencing of pangolins in 
Guangxi
</p>
         <p>
We received frozen tissue samples of 18 pangolins (
<tp:taxon-name>
Manis javanica
</tp:taxon-name>
) from 
Guangxi
Medical University, 
China
,that were collected between 
August 2017
– 
January 2018
.These pangolins were seized by the 
Guangxi
Customs during their routine anti-smuggling operations. All animal individuals comprised samples from multiple organs including lungs, intestine and blood,with the exception of six individuals for which only lung tissues were available,five with mixed intestine and lung tissues only, one with intestine tissues only, and one comprising two blood samples.Using the intestine-lung mixed sample we were able to isolate a novel 
<tp:taxon-name>
Betacoronavirus
</tp:taxon-name>
using the Vero-E6 cell line (from ATCC;Extended Data 

). The cell line was subjected to species identification and authentication by microscopic morphologic evaluation and growth curve analysis, and was tested free of mycoplasma contamination. The cell line was not on the list of common misidentified cell lines by ICLAC.A High Pure Viral RNA Kit (Roche, 
Switzerland
) was used for RNA extraction on all 43samples.For RNA sequencing (GX/P2V and GX/P3B), a sequencing library was constructed using an Ion Total RNA-Seq Kit v2 (Thermo Fisher Scientific,MA, 
USA
),and the library was subsequently sequenced using an Ion Torrent S5 sequencer (Thermo Fisher Scientific).For other samples,reverse transcription was performed using an SuperScript III First-Strand Synthesis System for RT-PCR (Thermo Fisher Scientific,MA, 
USA
).DNA libraries were constructed using the NEBNext Ultra II DNA Library Prep Kit and sequenced on a MiSeq sequencer. The NGS (next-generation sequencing) QC Toolkit V2.3.3 was used to remove low-quality and short reads. Both BLASTn and BLASTx were used to search against a local virus database,utilizing the data available at NCBI/GenBank.Genome sequences were assembled using the CLC Genomic Workbench v.9.0.To fill gaps in high throughput sequencing and obtain the whole viral genome sequence,amplicon primers based on the bat SARS-like coronavirus ZC45 (GenBank accession number 
MG772933
)sequence and the coronavirus contigs obtained in the initial sequencing were designed for further amplicon-based sequencing.
</p>
         <p>
A total of six samples (including the virus isolate) contained reads that matched members of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Betacoronavirus
</tp:taxon-name>
(Extended Data Table 1). We obtained near complete viral genomes from these samples (98%,compared to SARS-CoV-2),which were designated GX/P1E, GX/ P2V, GX/P3B,GX/P4L,GX/P5E and GX/P 
5L.
Their average sequencing coverage ranged from approximately 8.4X to 8,478X (Extended Data 

a-f). Based on these genome sequences, we designed primers for qPCR to confirm the positivity of the original tissue samples (Extended Data Table 4). This revealed an original lung tissue sample that was also qPCR positive,in addition to the six original samples with coronavirus reads. We further tested an additional 19 samples (nine intestine tissues,ten lung tissues),from 12 smuggled pangolins sampled between May-July 2018 by the group from 
Guangxi
Medical University.The genome sequences of GX/P1E,GX/P2V,GX/P3B,GX/ P4L,GX/P5E and GX/P5L have been submitted to GISAID database and assigned accession numbers EPI_ISL_410538 - EPI_ISL_410543.
</p>
         <p>

Sample collection, viral detection and sequencing of pangolins in 
Guangdong
</p>
         <p>After the start of the SARS-CoV-2 outbreak, the Guangzhou Customs Technology Center re-examined their five archived pangolin</p>
         <p>
samples (two skin swabs, two unknown tissue,one scale) obtained in anti-smuggling operations undertaken in 
March 2019
. RNA was extracted from all five samples (Qiagen, 
USA
), and was subjected to high-throughput RNA sequencing on the Illumina HiSeq platform by Vision medicals, 
Guangdong
, 
China
. The scale sample was found to contain coronavirus reads using a BLAST-based approach. These reads were quality assessed,cleaned and assembled into contigs by both 
de novo
(MEGAHIT v1.1.3 
13
) and using reference (BWA v0.7.13 
14
) assembly methods,using BetaCoV/Wuhan/WIV04/2019 as a reference. The contigs were combined, and approximately 72% of the coronavirus genome (21,505bp) was obtained. This sequence has about 6.6X sequencing coverage(Extended Data 

) and denoted pangolin CoV GD/P2S.This sequence has been deposited on GISAID with accession number EPI_ISL_410544.
</p>
         <p>
Liu 
et al
. recently published a meta-transcriptomic study of pangolins 
7
and deposited 21 RNA-seq raw files on the SRA database (https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra). We screened these raw read files using BLAST methods and found that five (SRR10168374, SRR10168376,SRR10168377,SRR10168378 and SRR10168392) contained reads that mapped to SARS-CoV-2.These reads were subjected to quality assessment, cleaning and then 
de novo
assembly using MEGAHIT 
13
and reference assembly using BWA 
14
. These reads were then merged and curated in a pileup alignment file to obtain the consensus sequences.This combined consensus sequence is 25,753bp in length (about 86.3% of BetaCoV/Wuhan/WIV04/2019; about 6.9X coverage) and denoted pangolin CoV GD/P1L (available in the Supplementary Information Data Set).Notably,it has 66.8% overlap and a sequence identify of 99.79% with the GD/P2S sequence. Since the genetic distance between these viruses is very low, for the recombination analysis we merged the GD/P1L and GD/P2S sequences into a single consensus sequence to minimize gap regions within any sequences.
</p>
         <p>
The viral genome organizations of the 
Guangxi
and 
Guangdong
pangolin coronaviruses were similar to SARS-CoV-2.They possessed nine non-overlapping open reading frames (ORFs) plus two overlapping ORFs,and shared the same gene order of ORF1ab replicase,envelope glycoprotein spike (S),envelope (E),membrane (M),nucleocapsid (N), plus other predicted ORFs. A detailed comparison of the ORF length and similarity with SARS-CoV-2and bat coronavirus RaTG13 is provided in Extended Data Table 2.
</p>
         <p>
Sequence, phylogenetic and recombination analyses

</p>
         <p>
The human SARS-CoV-2and bat RaTG13 coronavirus genome sequences were downloaded from Virological.org (http://virological.org)and the GISAID (https://www.gisaid.org) databases in 
January 2020
, with the data kindly shared by the submitters (Extended Data Table 5). Other coronaviruses (subgenus 
Sarbecovirus
) were downloaded from Gen- Bank (Extended Data Table 6)and compared to those obtained here.We constructed a multiple sequence alignment of their complete genomes and individual genes using MAFFT v7.273 
15
. Maximum likelihood phylogenies were estimated using RAxML v8.2.12 
16
from 100 inferences, utilizing the GTRGAMMA model of nucleotide substitution with 1,000 bootstrap replicates.To investigate potential recombination events,we used SimPlot v3.5.1 
17
to conduct a window sliding analysis to determine the changing patterns of sequence similarity and phylogenetic clustering between the query and the reference sequences.A full plot for the recombination analysis is provided in Extended Data 

.We also examined phylogenetic clusters performed directly from the multiple sequence alignment.Maximum likelihood trees were estimated from each window extraction (i.e. genome regions 1 to 8) using RAxML as described above 
18–39
.
</p>
         <p>
Reporting summary

</p>
         <p>Further information on research design is available in the Nature Research Reporting Summary linked to this paper.</p>
         <p>
Data Availability

</p>
         <p>Data that support the findings of this study have been deposited in GISAID database with accession numbers EPI_ISL_410538 - EPI_ISL_410544 and to the SRA database under BioProject number PRJNA606875,and are available in the supplementary information file of this paper.</p>
         <p>

13. 
Li,D.
et al
. 
MEGAHIT:an ultra-fast single-node solution for large and complex metagenomics assembly via succinct de Bruijn graph
. 

Bioinformatics

31

, 
1674-1676
, (
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

14. 
Li,H.
and 
Durbin,R.
Fast and accurate long-read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform
. 

Bioinformatics

26

, 
589-595
, (
2010
).

</p>
         <p>

15. 
Rozewicki,J.
et al
. 
MAFFT-DASH:integrated protein sequence and structural alignment
. 

Nucleic Acids Res

47

, W5-W 
10
,(
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

16. 
Stamatakis,A.
RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies
. 

Bioinformatics

30

, 
1312-1313
,(
2014
).

</p>
         <p>

17. 
Lole,KS
. 

et al
. Full-length human immunodeficiency virus type 1 genomes from subtype C-infected seroconverters in India,with evidence of intersubtype recombination

. 

J Virol

73

(
1
): 
152-60
, (
1999
).

</p>
         <p>

18. 
He,R.
et al
. 
Analysis of multimerization of the SARS coronavirus nucleocapsid protein
. 

Biochem Biophys Res Commun

316

, 
476-483
,(
2004
).

</p>
         <p>

19. 
Snijder,E.J.
et al
. 
Unique and conserved features of genome and proteome of SARScoronavirus, an early split-off from the coronavirus group 2 lineage
. 

J Mol Biol

331

, 
991-1004
,(
2003
).

</p>
         <p>

20. 

Marra, 
M
. 
A
.

et al
. 
The Genome sequence of the SARS-associated coronavirus
. 

Science

300

, 
1399-1404
,(
2003
).

</p>
         <p>

21. 

Song, 
H
. D.

et al
. 
Cross-host evolution of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus in palm civet and human
. 


Proc Natl Acad Sci 
U
S
A
102

, 
2430-2435
,(
2005
).

</p>
         <p>

22. 

Han, 
Y
.

et al
. 
Identification of Diverse Bat Alphacoronaviruses and Betacoronaviruses in China Provides New Insights Into the Evolution and Origin of Coronavirus-Related Diseases
. 

Front Microbiol

10

, 
1900
, (
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

23. 

Tao, 
Y
.

&amp; 

Tong, 
S
.

Complete Genome Sequence of a Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome- Related Coronavirus from Kenyan Bats
. 

Microbiol Resour Announc

8

, (
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

24. 
Hu, D.
et al
. 
Genomic characterization and infectivity of a novel SARS-like coronavirus
in Chinese bats. 

Emerg Microbes Infect

7

, 
154
,(
2018
).

</p>
         <p>

25. 

Hu, 
B
.

et al. 
Discovery of a rich gene pool of bat SARS-related coronaviruses provides new insights into the origin of SARS coronavirus
. 

PLoS Pathog

13

, e 
1006698
,(
2017
).

</p>
         <p>

26. 

Wu, 
Z
.

et al
. 
ORF8-Related Genetic Evidence for Chinese Horseshoe Bats as the Source of Human Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus
. 

J
Infect Dis


213

, 
579-583
, (
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

27. 

Wu, 
Z
.

et al
. 
Deciphering the bat virome catalog to better understand the ecological diversity of bat viruses and the bat origin of emerging infectious diseases
. 


ISME 
J
10

, 
609-620
,(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

28. 

Yang, 
L
.

et al
. 
Novel SARS-like betacoronaviruses in bats, China
,2011. 

Emerg Infect Dis

19

, 
989-991
, (
2013
).

</p>
         <p>

29. 

Xu, 
L
.

et al
. 
Detection and characterization of diverse alpha- and betacoronaviruses from bats in China
. 

Virol Sin

31

, 
69-77
,(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

30. 

He, 
B
.

et al
. 
Identification of diverse alphacoronaviruses and genomic characterization of a novel severe acute respiratory syndrome-like coronavirus from bats in China
. 

J
Virol


88

, 
7070-7082
,(
2014
).

</p>
         <p>

31. 

Ge,X. 
Y
.

et al
. 

Isolation and characterization of a bat SARS-like coronavirus that uses the 
ACE
2 receptor

. 

Nature

503

, 
535-538
,(
2013
).

</p>
         <p>

32. 

Li, 
W
.

et al
. 
Bats are natural reservoirs of SARS-like coronaviruses
. 

Science

310

, 
676-679
, (
2005
).

</p>
         <p>

33. 

Drexler, 
J
. 
F
.

et al
. 
Genomic characterization of severe acute respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus in European bats and classification of coronaviruses based on partial RNA-dependent RNA polymerase gene sequences
. 

J
Virol


84

, 
11336-11349
, (
2010
).

</p>
         <p>

34. 

Lau, 
S
. 
K
.

et al
. 
Ecoepidemiology and complete genome comparison of different strains of severe acute respiratory syndrome-related Rhinolophus bat coronavirus in China reveal bats as a reservoir for acute,self-limiting infection that allows recombination events
. 

J
Virol


84

, 
2808-2819
,(

2010

).

</p>
         <p>

35. 

Yuan, 
J
.

et al
. 
Intraspecies diversity of SARS-like coronaviruses in Rhinolophus sinicus and its implications for the origin of SARS coronaviruses in humans
. 

J
Gen Virol


91

, 

1058
- 
1062

, (

2010

).

</p>
         <p>

36. 

Guan, 
Y
.

et al
. 
Isolation and characterization of viruses related to the SARS coronavirus from animals in southern China
. 

Science

302

, 
276-278
,(

2003

).

</p>
         <p>

37. 

Tang,X. 
C
.

et al
. 

Prevalence and genetic diversity of coronaviruses in bats from 
China

. 

J
Virol


80

, 
7481-7490
,(

2006

).

</p>
         <p>

38. 

Yeh, 
S
. 
H
.

et al
. 

Characterization of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus genomes in 
Taiwan
:molecular epidemiology and genome evolution

. 


Proc Natl Acad Sci 

U
S
A
101

, 

2542
- 
2547

,(

2004

).

</p>
         <p>

39. 

Vega, 
V
. 
B
.

et al
. 

Mutational dynamics of the 
SARS
coronavirus in cell culture and human populations isolated in 2003

. 

BMC Infect Dis

4

, 
32
,(
2004
).

</p>
         <p>
Acknowledgements
We thank Prof.Wu-Chun Cao,Dr.Na Jia, Dr.Ya-Wei Zhang,Dr.Jia-Fu Jiang, Dr. Bao-Gui Jiang,and their team in State Key Laboratory of Pathogen and Biosecurity,Beijing Institute of Microbiology and Epidemiology,Beijing for their substantial contributions to this study,including coordinating among research parties, conducting virus isolation,qPCR and sequencing.We also thank the Guangzhou Customs Technology Center,Guangzhou for reexamining their archived pangolin samples and providing the data.All the above persons agree on the content of the study,authorship arrangement and publication. We thank the staff of the the Guangxi and Guangdong Custom Bureau for their laborious anti-smuggling operations. We thank all the scientists who kindly shared their genomic sequences of the coronaviruses used in this study. The computations were performed using research computing facilities offered by Information Technology Services,the University of 
Hong Kong
. This work was supported by research grants from The National Natural Science Foundation of 
China
(NSFC) Excellent Young Scientists Fund (
Hong Kong
and 
Macau
) (31922087),National Key Plan for Scientific Research and Development of 
China
(2016YFD0500302; 2017YFE0190800), funding for Guangdong-Hongkong-Macau Joint Laboratory (2019 
B
121205009), Li Ka Shing Foundation,National Institutes of Health (HHSN272201400006 
C
), 
Guangxi
scientific and technological research (2020AB39264) and 
Guangxi
Medical University Training Program for Distinguished Young Scholars,and the Australian Research Council (FL170100022).
</p>
         <p>
Author contributions
Y
. 
G
.and 
Y
. 
L
. 
H
.designed and supervised research.W.W.,W.J.L.and L.F.L. collected samples and conducted genome sequencing. M.H.H.S,X.B.N. and T.T. 
Y
. 
L
.performed genome assembly and annotation. 
Y
. 
G
. 
T
., 
T
.T.Y.L.,M.H.H.S, X.B.N,W.Y.M.C.,E.C.H.and Y.S.L. performed genome analysis and interpretation.T.T.Y.L.and E.C.H. wrote the paper.H.C.Z., Y.L.H.,G.M.L and Y.G.joined the data interpretation and edited the paper.
</p>
         <p>
Competing interests
The authors declare no competing interests.
</p>
         <p>
Additional information

</p>
         <p>
Supplementary information
is available for this paper at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020- 2169-0.
</p>
         <p>
Correspondence and requests for materials
should be addressed to Y.-L.H.,Y.G.,Y.-L.H. or Y.G. 
Peer review information
Nature
thanks Paul Kellam,Ian Lipkin and the other,anonymous, reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work.
</p>
         <p>
Reprints and permissions information
is available at http://www.nature.com/reprints. 


Extended Data Table 2 | Genomic comparison of SARS-CoV-2 with Bat-Cov RaTG13, 
Guangdong
pangolin CoV and 
Guangxi
pangolin CoV.


</p>
         <p>
Source location

Sample type

Sample number

Accession IDs of consensus sequence / read data

Guangxi
Intestine
GX/P1E
EPI_ISL_410539 / SAMN14115945
Guangxi
Virus isolate from intestine-lung mixed samples
GX/P2V
EPI_ISL_410542 / SAMN14115940
Guangxi
Blood
GX/P3B
EPI_ISL_410543 / SAMN14115941
Guangxi
Lung
GX/P4L
EPI_ISL_410538 / SAMN14115942
Guangxi
Intestine
GX/P5E
EPI_ISL_410541 / SAMN14115943
Guangxi
Lung
GX/P5L
EPI_ISL_410540 / SAMN14115944
Guangdong
Scale
GD/P2S
EPI_ISL_410544 / SAMN14116618
</p>
         <p>
Sequencing reads have been deposited in the SRA database (https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra) under BioProject PRJNA606875.
</p>
         <p>
Bat-Cov RaTG13#
Guangdong pangolin CoV #
Guangxi pangolin CoV #
Length bat/ SARS-CoV- 2 (bp)
nt aa Identity % Identity %
Length GD/ SARS-CoV-2 (bp)
nt Identity %
aa Identity %
Length GX/ SARS-CoV-2 (bp)
nt Identity %
aa Identity %
ORF1ab
21287/21290
96.5
98.6
20076*/21290
90.7
97.1
21266/21290
84.9
92.5
S
3810/3822
93.1
97.7
3548*/3822
84.9
90.7
3804/3822
83.6
92.6
ORF3a
828/828
96.3
97.8
828/828
93.6
97.4
828/828
87.0
89.3
E
228/228
99.6
100
228/228
99.1
100
228/228
97.4
100
M
666/669
95.9
100
669/669
93.4
98.6
669/669
91.3
98.2
ORF6
186/186
98.4
100
186/186
95.7
96.6
186/186
90.9
95.0
ORF7a
366/366
95.6
97.5
366/366
93.4
97.5
366/366
86.6
87.7
ORF8
366/366
97.0
94.9
366/366
92.3
94.9
366/366
80.6
86.8
N
1260/1260
96.9
99.0
1260/1260
96.2
97.8
1254/1260
91.4
94.3
</p>
         <p># Wuhan-Hu-1 SARS-CoV-2 (NC_045512.2) was used for comparison with Bat-CoV RaTG13 (EPI_ISL_402131),Guangdong pangolin CoV (merged of GD/P1L and GD/P2S),and Guangxi pangolin CoV (GX/P5L)</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Homo
sapiens

</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Manis
javanica

</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus sinicus
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
pearsonii

</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus ferrumequinum
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Homo sapiens
</tp:taxon-name>
100%
<tp:taxon-name>
Manis javanica
</tp:taxon-name>
84.85%
100%
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
sinicus

</tp:taxon-name>
80.75%
82.86%
100%
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus pearsonii
</tp:taxon-name>
81.37%
82.98%
94.41%
100%
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus ferrumequinum
</tp:taxon-name>
81.24%
82.98%
93.04%
92.42%
100%
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus macrotis
</tp:taxon-name>
80.87%
83.73%
95.78%
94.91%
92.55%
</p>
         <p>
Extended Data Table 4 | Primers used for qPCR detection of pangolin associated coronavirus

</p>
         <p>
pCov-Forward
AGGTGACGAGGTTAGACAAATAG
pCov-Reverse
CCAAGCAATAACACAACCAGTAA
pCov-Probe
ACCCGGACAAACTGGTGTTATTGCT
</p>
         <p>
Accession ID
Virologal.org sequence (NC_045512.2)

Virus name
BetaCoV/Wuhan- Hu-1/2019

Location
China / Wuhan

Collection date
2019-12

Originating lab
National Institute for Communicable Disease Control and Prevention (ICDC) Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention (China CDC)

Submitting lab
National Institute for Communicable Disease Control and Prevention (ICDC) Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention (China CDC)

Authors
Zhang,Y.-Z., Wu,F., Chen,Y.-M., Pei,Y.-Y., Xu,L., Wang,W., Zhao,S., Yu,B., Hu,Y., Tao,Z.-W., Song,Z.-G., Tian,J.-H., Zhang,Y.- L., Liu,Y., Zheng,J.-J., Dai,F.-H., Wang,Q.- M., She,J.-L. and Zhu,T.-Y.

EPI_ISL_ 402131
BetaCoV/bat/ Yunnan/ RaTG13/2013
China / Yunnan Province / Pu'er City
2013-07- 24
Wuhan Institute of Virology, Chinese Academy of Sciences
Wuhan Institute of Virology, Chinese Academy of Sciences
Yan Zhu, Ping Yu, Bei Li, Ben Hu, Hao-Rui Si, Xing-Lou Yang, Peng Zhou, Zheng-Li Shi
EPI_ISL_ 402121
BetaCoV/Wuhan/ IVDC-HB- 05/2019
China / Hubei Province / Wuhan City
2019-12- 30
National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, China CDC
National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, China CDC
Wenjie Tan Xuejun Ma Xiang Zhao Wenling Wang Yongzhong Jiang Roujian Lu Ji Wang Peihua Niu, Weimin Zhou, Faxian Zhan Weifeng Shi Baoying Huang Jun Liu Li Zhao Yao Meng Fei Ye Na Zhu, Xiaozhou He Peipei Liu, Yang Li Jing Chen Wenbo Xu George F. Gao Guizhen Wu
EPI_ISL_ 402120
BetaCoV/Wuhan/ IVDC-HB- 04/2020
China / Hubei Province / Wuhan City
2020-01- 01
National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, China CDC
National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, China CDC
Wenjie Tan Xiang Zhao Wenling Wang Xuejun Ma Yongzhong Jiang Roujian Lu Ji Wang Weimin Zhou Peihua Niu Peipei Liu Faxian Zhan Weifeng Shi Baoying Huang Jun Liu Li Zhao Yao Meng Xiaozhou He Fei Ye Na Zhu Yang Li Jing Chen Wenbo Xu George F. Gao Guizhen Wu
EPI_ISL_ 402124
BetaCoV/Wuhan/ WIV04/2019
China / Hubei Province / Wuhan City
2019-12- 30
Wuhan Jinyintan Hospital
Wuhan Institute of Virology, Chinese Academy of Sciences
Peng Zhou, Xing-Lou Yang, Ding-Yu Zhang, Lei Zhang, Yan Zhu, Hao-Rui Si, Zhengli Shi
EPI_ISL_ 402123
BetaCoV/Wuhan /IPBCAMS-WH- 01/2019
China / Hubei Province / Wuhan City
2019-12- 24
Institute of Pathogen Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College
Institute of Pathogen Biology, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences &amp; Peking Union Medical College
Lili Ren, Jianwei Wang, Qi Jin, Zichun Xiang, Zhiqiang Wu, Chao Wu, Yiwei Liu
</p>
         <p>
We gratefully thank the authors listed below for sharing their genomic sequences of coronaviruses analyzed in this study.
</p>
         <p>
Extended Data Table 6 | GenBank accession numbers of coronavirus sequences used in this study.

</p>
      </sec>
      <p>
Accession ID

Strain name

Host

Publication

NC_004718.3
Tor2
Human

He 
etal.
Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 316(2):476-83 (2004) 18 Snijder 
etal.
J. Mol. Biol. 331 (5), 991-1004 (2003) 19 Marra 
etal.
Science 300 (5624), 1399-1404 (2003) 20 Song 
etal.
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 102(7):2430-5 (2005) 21

AY313906.1
GD69
Human
MK211377.1
BtRs-BetaCoV/ YN2018C BtRs-BetaCoV/ YN2018B BtRl-BetaCoV/ SC2018 BtKY72
Rhinolophusafinis


Han 
etal.
Front Microbiol. 10:1900 (2019)22

MK211376.1
Rhinolophusafinis


Han 
etal.
Front Microbiol. 10:1900 (2019) 22

MK211374.1
Rhinolophusp.


Han 
etal.
Front Microbiol. 10:1900 (2019) 22

KY352407.1
Rhinolophusp.


Tao 
etal.
Microbiol Resour Announc 8 (28), e00548-19 (2019) 23

MG772934.1
bat-SL-CoVZXC21
Rhinolophusinicus

Huetal. EmergMicrobesInfect. 12;7(1):154(2018) 24
MG772933.1
bat-SL-CoVZC45
Rhinolophusinicus

Huetal. EmergMicrobes Infect. 12;7(1):154 (2018) 24
KY417151.1
Rs7327
Rhinolophusinicus


Hu 
etal.
PLoSPathog. 13 (11), e1006698 (2017) 25

KY417147.1
Rs4237
Rhinolophusinicus


Hu 
etal.
PLoSPathog. 13 (11), e1006698 (2017) 25

KY417146.1
Rs4231
Rhinolophussinicus


Hu 
etal.
PLoSPathog. 13 (11), e1006698 (2017) 25

KY417143.1
Rs4081
Rhinolophussinicus


Hu 
etal.
PLoSPathog. 13 (11), e1006698 (2017) 25

KJ473816.1
BtRs-YN2013
Rhinolophussinicus


Wu 
etal.
J. Infect. Dis. 213 (4), 579-583 (2016) 26 Wu 
etal.
ISMEJ10 (3), 609-620 (2016) 27 Wu 
et al.
J. Infect. Dis. 213 (4), 579-583 (2016) 26 Wu 
et al.
ISMEJ10 (3), 609-620 (2016) 27 Wu 
et al.
J. Infect. Dis. 213 (4), 579-583 (2016) 26 Wu 
et al.
ISMEJ10 (3), 609-620 (2016) 27 Wu 
et al.
J. Infect. Dis. 213 (4), 579-583 (2016) 26 Wu 
et al.
ISMEJ10 (3), 609-620 (2016) 27 Yang 
et al.
Emerging Infect. Dis. 19 (6) (2013) 28 Wu 
et al.
J. Infect. Dis. 213 (4), 579-583 (2016) 26 Wu 
et al.
ISME J 10 (3), 609-620 (2016) 27 Yang 
et al.
Emerging Infect. Dis. 19 (6) (2013) 28 Wu 
et al.
J. Infect. Dis. 213 (4), 579-583 (2016) 26 Wu 
et al.
ISME J 10 (3), 609-620 (2016) 27 Xu 
et al.
Virol Sin 31 (1), 69-77 (2016) 29

KJ473815.1
BtRs-GX2013
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
sinicus

</tp:taxon-name>
KJ473814.1
BtRs-HuB2013
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus sinicus
</tp:taxon-name>
KJ473812.1
BtRf-HeB2013
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus ferrumequinum
</tp:taxon-name>
JX993988.1
Cp/Yunnan2011
<tp:taxon-name>
Chaerephon plicata
</tp:taxon-name>
JX993987.1
Rp/Shaanxi2011
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
pusillus

</tp:taxon-name>
KU182964.1
JTMC15
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus ferrumequinum
</tp:taxon-name>
KP886808.1
YNLF_31C
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus ferrumequinum
</tp:taxon-name>
Journal information is not available in the GenBank record

KF569996.1
LYRa11
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus affinis
</tp:taxon-name>

He 
et al.
J. Virol. 88 (12), 7070-7082 (2014) 30

KC881006.1
Rs3367
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
sinicus

</tp:taxon-name>

Ge 
et al.
Nature 503, 535-538 (2013) 31

DQ412043.1
Rm1
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus macrotis
</tp:taxon-name>

Li 
et al.
Science 310 (5748), 676-679 (2005) 32

DQ412042.1
Rf1
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus ferrumequinum
</tp:taxon-name>

Li 
et al.
Science 310 (5748), 676-679 (2005) 32

GU190215.1
BtCoV/BM48- 31/BGR/2008 HKU3-12
<tp:taxon-name>

Rhinolophus 
blasii

</tp:taxon-name>

Drexler 
et al.
J. Virol. 84 (21), 11336-11349 (2010) 33

GQ153547.1
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
sinicus

</tp:taxon-name>

Lau 
et al.
J. Virol. 84 (6), 2808-2819 (2010) 34

GQ153543.1
HKU3-8
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus sinicus
</tp:taxon-name>

Lau 
et al.
J. Virol. 84 (6), 2808-2819 (2010) 34

GQ153541.1
HKU3-6
<tp:taxon-name>

Rhinolophus 
sinicus

</tp:taxon-name>

Lau 
et al.
J. Virol. 84 (6), 2808-2819 (2010) 34

FJ588686.1
Rs672
<tp:taxon-name>

Rhinolophus 
sinicus

</tp:taxon-name>

Yuan 
et al.
J. Gen. Virol. 91 (PT 4), 1058-1062 (2010) 35

DQ071615.1
Rp3
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
pearsoni

</tp:taxon-name>

Li 
et al.
Science 310 (5748), 676-679 (2005) 32

AY304488.1
SZ16
Civet

Guan 
et al.
Science 302 (5643), 276-278 (2003) 36

DQ648856.1
BtCoV/273/2005
<tp:taxon-name>

Rhinolophus 
ferrumequinum

</tp:taxon-name>

Tang 
et al.
J. Virol. 80 (15), 7 
481-7490
(2006) 37

AY572034.1
civet007
Civet

Wang 
et al.
Emerging Infect. Dis. 11 (12), 1860-1865 (2005) 5

AY502924.1
TW11
Human

Yeh 
et al.
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 101 (8), 2542-2547 (2004) 38

AY613948.1
PC4_13
Civet

Song 
et al.
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 102 (7), 2430-2435 (2005) 21

AY613947.1
GZ0402
Human

Song 
et al.
Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 102 (7), 2430-2435 (2005) 21

AY559095.1
Sin847
Human

Vega 
et al.
BMC Infect. Dis. 4, 32 (2004) 39

KF294457.1
Longquan-140
<tp:taxon-name>

Rhinolophus 
monoceros

</tp:taxon-name>
Journal information is not available in the GenBank record

DQ648857.1
BtCoV/279/2005
<tp:taxon-name>

Rhinolophus 
macrotis

</tp:taxon-name>

Tang 
et al.
J. Virol. 80 (15), 7481-7490 (2006) 37

</p>
   </body>
</article>
