<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Phytochemistry</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113267</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Metabolic adaptation of diatoms to hypersalinity</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>30</day>
            <month>09</month>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Metabolic adaptation of diatoms to hypersalinity </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Vera Nikitashina 1 , Daniel Stettin 1 , Georg Pohnert * </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Institute for Inorganic and Analytical Chemistry, Bioorganic Analytics, Friedrich
            Schiller University Jena, 07743, Jena, Germany </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ARTICLE INFO Keywords: <tp:taxon-name> Phaeodactylum tricornutum </tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Phaeodactylaceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Microalgae are important primary producers and <tp:taxon-name>form the</tp:taxon-name>
            basis for the marine food web. As global climate changes, so do salinity levels that
            algae are exposed to. A metabolic response of algal cells partly alleviates the
            resulting osmotic stress. Some metabolites involved in the response are well studied,
            but the full metabolic implications of adaptation remain unclear. Improved analytical
            methodology provides an opportunity for additional insight. We can now follow responses
            to stress in major parts of the metabolome and derive comprehensive charts of the
            resulting metabolic re-wiring. In this study, we subjected three species of diatoms to
            high salinity conditions and compared their metabolome to controls in an untargeted
            manner. The three well- investigated species with sequenced genomes <tp:taxon-name>
               Phaeodactylum tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Thalassiosira pseudonana
            </tp:taxon-name> , and Skel- etonema <tp:taxon-name>marinoi</tp:taxon-name> were
            selected for our survey. The microalgae react to salinity stress with common adaptations
            in the metabolome by amino acid up-regulation, production of saccharides, and inositols.
            But also species-specific dysregulation of metabolites is common. Several metabolites
            previously not connected with osmotic stress reactions are identified, including
            4-hydroxyproline, pipecolinic acid, myo-inositol, threonic acid, and acylcarnitines.
            This expands our knowledge about osmoadaptation and calls for further functional
            characterization of metabolites and pathways in algal stress physiology. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name> Thalassiosira pseudonana </tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Thalassiosiraceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name> Skeletonema marinoi </tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Skeletonemataceae</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Diatomic algae</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Hypersalinity stress response</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Osmolytes</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Untargeted metabolite profiling ABSTRACT</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 1. Introduction </title>
         <p> Phytoplankton is estimated to be responsible for roughly 50% of global primary
            production and forms the basis of the marine food web ( ). Algal cells forming the
            phytoplankton experience environmental fluctuations in their habitat during sinking or
            transport by currents. Shifts in nutrient availability, light, and temperature ( ) can
            lead to a change in the species composition of the phytoplanktonic community. However,
            these factors also influence the physiology of the persisting cells. In the long term,
            global warming alters the productivity and composition of phytoplankton ( ). Additional
            parameters connected to temperature, like dissolved CO 2 and salinity, influence the
            algae as well ( ). Surface salinity patterns, mainly influenced by increasing
            evaporation and precipitation or other freshwater influx, are becoming more important on
            a global level due to climate change ( ; ). Because algae are surface-dwelling primary
            producers, they are directly affected by such changes in ocean salinity. Considering the
            importance of phytoplankton for global primary production, it is vital that we
            understand the effect of alterations in salinity concerning growth, community
            composition, and metabolism. </p>
         <p> A change in salinity in the aqueous environment of a phytoplankton cell subjects it to
            osmotic stress. This can be alleviated by water flux in or out of the cell or adjustment
            of the intracellular salt concentration. These salts include inorganic ions and organic
            compatible solutes, called osmolytes ( ). The accumulation of osmolytes is believed to
            be the most widespread and long-term successful mechanism of osmoadaptation to increased
            salinity in free-living algae ( ). </p>
         <p> The main body of literature about the identity and quantity of organic osmolytes in
            microalgae stems from targeted analytics ( ; ). Modern untargeted screening using
            high-resolution mass spectrometry can offer additional insight ( ) and reveal previously
            unrecognized metabolic connections. The opportunity to unravel novel aspects in algal
            physiology prompted us to perform a salt-stress experiment on diatoms and analyze
            extracts with liquid- and gas-chromatography coupled to high-resolution mass
            spectrometry in an untargeted manner. This revealed metabolites and pathways responding
            to salinity changes and allowed us to document metabolic networks connected to
            osmoadaptation. </p>
         <p> For this study, we choose three diatom species – <tp:taxon-name> Phaeodactylum
               tricornutum Bohlin </tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name>Phaeodactylaceae</tp:taxon-name>
            ), <tp:taxon-name> Thalassiosira pseudonana Hasle &amp; Heimdal </tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Thalassiosiraceae</tp:taxon-name> ) and <tp:taxon-name> Skeletonema
               marinoi Sarno &amp; Zingone </tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Skeletonemataceae</tp:taxon-name> ) – as model organisms. These algae
            are wellinvestigated with sequenced genomes and a wealth of knowledge on their
            physiology ( ; ; ). Since different microalgal species may react to hypersalinity with
            individual changes in their metabolic profile, we aimed to compare the three diatom
            responses to unravel joint and unique physiological adaptations ( ; ; ). We observed
            dysregulation of 5%– 46% from all detected compounds. We connect multiple new compounds
            including 4-hydroxyproline, pipecolinic acid, myo-inositol, threonic acid, and
            acylcarnitines to osmoadaptation in microalgae. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 2. Results </title>
         <p> To best mimic natural non-limiting conditions and at the same time obtain a high number
            of cells for extraction, salinity stress experiments were performed with algal cultures
            in the later logarithmic growth phase. Relatively high salt concentration for the stress
            (initially 60 PSU) was selected so that it could induce significant changes in the algal
            endometabolome. We adjusted salinity stress so that it does not lead to algal cell death
            since otherwise changes in the endometabolome would be associated with cell death
            processes. The elevation of medium salinity to values close to 60 PSU was previously
            performed to investigate the effect of increased salinity on the growth, and metabolome
            of diatoms ( ; ; ; ). </p>
         <p> In this study, analysis of the stress response was performed at two time points after
            salinity increase. A short-term salinity stress response was analyzed 24 h after the
            stress, which is on average less than doubling time of diatoms ( ). Thus, direct
            response of the cells was analyzed. The long-term response was examined 96 h after the
            increase in salt content when algal cells could divide at least two times. Consequently,
            salinity stress adaptation of the next generations could be examined. </p>
         <p> 2.1. Effect of the salinity stress on the growth rate of diatoms </p>
         <p>To analyze the effect of increased salinity on the growth of the algae, chlorophyll
            fluorescence intensity and cell density of the cultures were monitored.</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana
            </tp:taxon-name> tolerated the salinity stress at 60 PSU and exhibited growth during at
            least four days after the stress ( Fig. S1 , S 2 ). However, lower cell numbers and
            chlorophyll fluorescence intensity compared to the control were observed (statistically
            significant p -value &lt; 0.05) for both time points for both diatoms. </p>
         <p> Elevation of salinity of <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> cultures led to
            the dramatic decrease almost to zero in both chlorophyll fluorescence intensity and cell
            density 96 h after 60 PSU treatment, while the control cultures showed normal growth.
            Furthermore, this diatom showed no growth under 55 PSU salinity stress ( Fig. S3 ). At
            50 PSU <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> cultures showed almost no decrease in
            both chlorophyll fluorescence intensity and cell density 24 h after the treatment and
            grew at least 4 day at elevated salinity ( Fig. S4 ). The reduction of chlorophyll and
            cell counts after salinity stress treatment was statistically significant compared to
            control cultures for both time points. </p>
         <p> Therefore, for diatoms <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and
               <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> analysis of endometabolome changes in
            response to salinity increase was performed at 60 PSU and endometabolic changes of
               <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> were analyzed in response to the salinity
            increase to 50 PSU. </p>
         <p> 2.2. Changes in the endometabolome composition of <tp:taxon-name>T.
               pseudonana</tp:taxon-name> in response to the short-term salinity stress </p>
         <p> Salinity stress led to significant changes in the <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana
            </tp:taxon-name> endometabolome as indicated by a clear separation in PCA plots of
            stressed and control cultures after 24 h ( Fig. 1 ). </p>
         <p> A volcano plot analysis was conducted to assess significantly dysregulated metabolites
            ( Fig. S5 , S6). Compounds were considered to be significantly dysregulated in response
            to the salinity stress when their fold change in comparison to the controls was more
            than 2 or less than 0.5, with a p -value less than 0.05. In response to the short-term
            salinity stress, volcanoe plots revealed a statistically significant dysregulation of
            102 compounds for the GC-MS results for <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> ,
            which was around a quarter of all detected compounds. Only three dysregulated compounds
            were down-regulated; all others increased in concentration (cell count normalized data). </p>
         <p> Among the identified metabolites detected with GC-MS, pipecolinic acid and proline
            exhibited the highest increase in concentration. In total, up-regulation of 11 amino
            acids was observed. Also, increase in content of 8 sugars (one disaccharide, five
            monosaccharides, and two inositols) was detected ( Table S1 ). </p>
         <p> Statistical analysis of the LC-MS results of <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana
            </tp:taxon-name> short-term salinity stress response revealed significant increase in
            concentrations for 50 compounds. That was almost half of all detected compounds, and
            only of one compound the concentration decreased significantly in comparison to the
            controls. The most up-regulated among the identified metabolites were arginine, the
            ectoine precursor N γ- acetyldiaminobutyrate, and ectoine ( Table S1 ). </p>
         <p> 2.3. Changes in the endometabolome composition of <tp:taxon-name>T.
               pseudonana</tp:taxon-name> in response to the long-term salinity stress </p>
         <p> In response to the long-term salinity stress, statistically significant dysregulation
            was shown for 85 compounds detected with GC-MS. Six of them were down-regulated, and the
            content of 79 was increased (cell count normalized data) (Fig. S7). Among identified
            metabolites, only citric acid showed a decrease in content, while contents of others
            were increased. Similar to the short-term salinity stress response, the most upregulated
            identified compounds were amino acids and amines, including proline and pipecolinic
            acid. Their fold changes increased compared to the values at the 24 h time point. Also
            increase of pyrrole-2-carboxylic acid and threonine was observed ( Table S1 ). </p>
         <p>Statistical analysis of the LC-MS results for the long-term salinity stress response
            revealed dysregulation of 39 compounds (Fig. S8). This complementary analytical method
            confirmed the increase in proline and pipecolinic acid. Also, up-reguation of ectoine
            and its precursor was detected.</p>
         <p> 2.4. Comparison of the short- and long-term salinity stress responses of
               <tp:taxon-name>T. pseudonana</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>The number of significantly dysregulated metabolites detected with both analytical
            methods decreased over the diatom’ s salinity stress adaptation period. In GC-MS data,
            56 up-regulated compounds at both time points were detected. For 29 of them, an increase
            in fold change during the adaptation was shown. LC-MS results revealed 34 commonly
            up-regulated metabolites, and the fold changes for 26 of them increased in the sample
            extracted after 96 h in comparison to the 24 h time point. Thus, for the majority of the
            common compounds an increase in fold change was detected with both methods 96 h after
            the stress. Consequently, it can be hypothesized that the reduction in number of
            upregulated compounds over time is due to them being replaced by higher concentrations
            of compatible solutes that serve to support cells in long-term stress situations.
            Examples of such compounds would be proline and two betaines – glycine betaine and
            proline betaine, which were not among significantly dysregulated compounds 24 h after
            the stress but up-regulated after 96 h.</p>
         <p> The four treatments formed separate groups when control and stress GC-MS samples from
            two time points were compared in a PCA. In data from LC-MS analysis, there is an overlap
            in principal components 1 and 2 (samples 24 h control and 96 h high salinity) that was
            resolved by plotting three principal components ( Fig. 1 , Fig. S9). </p>
         <p> 2.5. Changes in the endometabolome composition of <tp:taxon-name>P.
               tricornutum</tp:taxon-name> in response to the short- and long-term salinity stresses </p>
         <p> For <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> , salinity stress also triggered
            significant changes in endometabolome composition. Separation between stressed and
            control cultures was observed in the PCA analysis of GC-MS and LC-MS data for both time
            points ( Fig. 2 ). </p>
         <p>In response to the short-term salinity stress, the statistical analysis revealed an
            increase in content for the majority of the dysregulated compounds normalized to cell
            count. Only for one out of 69 dysregulated compounds detected with GC-MS down-regulation
            was shown, all 89 statistically significant compounds detected with LC-MS were
            upregulated (Fig. S10, S11).</p>
         <p> Among metabolites detected with GC-MS, the highest increase was observed for a
            putatively identified glyceryl-glycoside in response to short- and long-term salinity
            stresses. Interestingly, up-regulation of the same metabolite was also detected for
               <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> at both time points but with
            comparatively lower fold changes. </p>
         <p> As for <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> , mainly amino acids and
            saccharides were among the identified up-regulated compounds. Also, similarly to
               <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> , up-regulation of
            pyrrole-2-carboxylic and threonic acid, ectoine, and its precursor N γ-
            acetyldiaminobutyrate was detected for this alga ( Table 1 ). </p>
         <p> In contrast to <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> , increased
            concentrations of methyl palmitate, putrescine, and butyrylcarnitine were detected for
               <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> in response to the short-term
            salinity stress. Interestingly, in response to the long-term salinity stress
            butyrylcarnitine was not present among significantly up-regulated compounds, but
            increase in content of another acylcarnitine – propionylcarnitine was detected.
            Furthermore, statistically significant increase in the content of cysteinolic and
            pipecolinic acids, methionine, and adenosine was detected 96 h but not 24 h after the
            salinity stress for <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> (Table S2). </p>
         <p> No clear pattern was found for the long-term adaptation. The amount of significantly
            dysregulated compounds detected with GC-MS decreased from 69 to 49 during the 96 h
            salinity stress adaptation of the algae (Fig. S12). For the LC-MS analysis, the number
            of statistically significantly changed metabolites conversely rose from 89 to 113 in
            course of time (Fig. S13). </p>
         <p> PCA also showed two different trends for GC- and LC-MS analysis. According to the GC-MS
            results, the endometabolome composition of <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum
            </tp:taxon-name> was affected to a larger extent by the cultivation time than by
            salinity elevation ( Fig. 2E ). Cultures extracted at different time points were located
            further from each other than control and treated cultures from the same time point.
            Whereas, for LC-MS the clustering of treated and control cultures can be observed. High
            variation among stressed cultures at 24 h led to overlap with both control at 24 h and
            stressed cultures at 96 h ( Fig. 2F ). </p>
         <p> 2.6. Changes in the endometabolome composition of <tp:taxon-name>S.
               marinoi</tp:taxon-name> in response to the short- and long-term salinity stresses </p>
         <p> Both <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana
            </tp:taxon-name> were subjected to salinity stress of 60 PSU. However, <tp:taxon-name>
               S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> showed no further growth at salinities of 60 or 55 PSU.
            For this reason, the analysis of the endometabolome composition for this diatom was
            investigated in response to the increase in salt concentration to 50 PSU where it still
            grew. </p>
         <p> Similar to the results obtained for two other diatoms, salinity stress led to
            significant changes in the endometabolome composition ( Fig. 3 ). Consitently with the
            data from the other diatoms, increase in cell count normalized metabolite concentrations
            was also observed for <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> as a response to the
            salinity stress. </p>
         <p> An increase in amino acid content, especially in proline and 4-hydroxyproline, was
            detected in salinity stressed cultures of <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name>
            (Table S3). Interestingly, conversely to results obtained for <tp:taxon-name> P.
               tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> , no
            saccharide accumulation was detected for <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> in
            response to the elevation of the salt content at any time point. However, the
            up-regulation of both myo- and scylloinositols and putatively identified
            glyceryl-glycoside was observed for <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> in
            response to the long-term salinity stress. Also, similar to the two other diatoms, the
            concentration of pyrrole-2-carboxylic acid was increased in stressed cultures of
               <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> at both analyzed time points. </p>
         <p> Furthermore, an increase in the content of four different acylcarnitines was observed
            for this diatom in response to the short-term salinity stress. Butyrylcarnitine and
            propionylcarnitine were also detected in <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name>
            , two others unique to <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> were acetylcarnitine
            and isovalerylcarnitine. Moreover, similar to <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum
            </tp:taxon-name> , content of cysteinolic acid increased in salinity stressed cultures
            at both analyzed time points ( Table 1 ). </p>
         <p> Similar to <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> , an increase in glycine
            betaine content was observed in high-salinity cultures of <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi
            </tp:taxon-name> . Statistically significant up-regulation of glycine betaine was
            detected at both time points for this diatom. </p>
         <p>Overall, the number of significantly dysregulated compounds detected with GC-MS
            increased from 21 to 51 over time of salinity stress adaptation (Fig. S14, S16). Almost
            all significantly increased metabolites after 24 h were also significantly up-regulated
            96 h after the treatment (19 out of 21). Conversely, the number of metabolites detected
            with LC-MS 24 h after the stress was higher than at 96 h time point (62 compounds
            detected for the 24 h time point, compared to 22 detected for the 96 h time point) (Fig.
            S15, S17). In turn, 18 out of 22 upregulated metabolites after 96 h were the same as at
            24 h. Downregulation was detected only with LC-MS for three compounds 96 h after the
            treatment. Two of these metabolites (one of them leucine) were elevated 24 h after the
            stress exhibiting a transient maximum.</p>
         <p> 2.7. Comparison of salinity stress responses of <tp:taxon-name>P.
               tricornutum</tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name>T. pseudonana</tp:taxon-name> , and
               <tp:taxon-name>S. marinoi</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p> We compared the amount of unique and shared metabolites regulated in response to
            salinity stress between the three diatoms. Surprisingly, only ca. 6% after 24 h and 4%
            after 96 h of the metabolites were common for a salinity adaptation in all three
            investigated species. This corresponds to 22 common metabolites (8 detected in GC-MS, 13
            in LC- MS, and proline detected with both methods) that were significantly dysregulated
            in all species at least at one time point. All of them were upregulated. </p>
         <p> A pairwise analysis shows that <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and
               <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> share more commonly dysregulated
            metabolites compared to <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>
               T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> and
               <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> ( Figs. 4 and 5 ). The largest share
            of dysregulated metabolites was unique for individual algal species and the vast
            majority of all dysregulated metabolites were upregulated upon salinity increase. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 3. Discussion </title>
         <p> 3.1. Influence of the salinity stress on the growth of diatoms </p>
         <p> Salinity is almost constant in the open oceans and varies only little between 33 and 37
            PSU. In nearshore waters, however, salinity fluctuations are substantial. Future climate
            change scenarios predict increased changes in water salinity due to evaporation or
            reduced freshwater intake from rivers due to low precipitation ( ). </p>
         <p> Diatoms can tolerate much higher salinity changes than the salinity ranges of their
            original habitat ( ). It was, however, observed that an increase in salinity negatively
            correlates with growth rates and affects the chemical composition of diatoms ( ; ; ; ).
            We opted to evaluate the physiological and metabolic response of three model diatoms to
            extreme salinity stress. We initially tested their tolerance to hypersalinity to avoid
            stress resulting in culture death. After salinity increase to 60 PSU <tp:taxon-name> P.
               tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name>
            responded with a strongly reduced growth compared to the control. Both algae continued
            to divide and the chlorophyll content of the culture increased under control and
            salinity stress conditions ( Fig. S1-S 2 ). This confirms previous findings of salt
            tolerance for these two algae ( ). <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> was not
            as tolerant towards increased salinity regimes and did not grow at a salinity over 50
            PSU ( Fig. S3-S 4 ). This is in accordance with a survey of Branda, who determined
            growth of this alga at 5 to 45 PSU ( ). </p>
         <p> Kirst suggested that growth rate is affected due to the inhibitory effect of high ion
            concentration on the metabolic processes. Moreover, the synthesis of organic osmolytes
            could take resources from general metabolism ( ). The negative effect of the salinity
            stress on the photosystems could be caused by increased permeability of the thylakoid
            membrane to ions, including Na + and CI, inhibiting both photosystems. This effect was
            previously shown in the unicellular green alga <tp:taxon-name> Dunaliella tertiolecta
            </tp:taxon-name> ( , ). </p>
         <p> </p>
         <p> 3.2. Significantly dysregulated metabolites and their possible interconnections </p>
         <p> The most widespread adaptation mechanism of diatoms to osmotic changes in their
            environment is the adjustment of the cellular concentration of compatible solutes ( ).
            Many studies address the regulation of such metabolites mainly based on the targeted
            analysis of candidate compounds. Amino acids and their metabolites are common
            up-regulated compounds upon hypersalinity stress. Also, organic sulfur compounds,
            including the dominant dimethylsulfoniopropionate (DMSP), have been quantitatively
            surveyed ( ; ). We set out here to determine the metabolome changes of three model
            diatoms with an untargeted approach. This allows the identification of common and unique
            compatible solutes in the diatoms and linking the dysregulated metabolites to metabolic
            pathways. We used an analytical approach based on high-resolution mass spectrometry. By
            combining GC-MS and LC-MS analysis, we could reach an unprecedentedly broad metabolic
            coverage of up to 344 features with GC-MS and 548 features with LC-MS. </p>
         <p> The survey of three diatom species introduced in this study indicates that all of them
            respond predominantly with increasing concentrations of intracellular metabolites to
            hypersalinity stress. Only a few compounds were found in lower concentrations, which is
            in accordance with the concept of increasing intracellular osmolyte production upon
            hypersalinity stress. We identified surprisingly few metabolites that are upregulated in
            all three investigated species. These include amino acids, amines and a myo-inositol.
            Most of these metabolites were previously identified in targeted analyses of diatom
            responses ( ; ; ). The majority of identified metabolites were, however, unique to the
            respective species, which indicates a surprising individuality within diatoms. This
            uniqueness is not caused by their phylogenetic position, with <tp:taxon-name> T.
               pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> belonging
            to the order <tp:taxon-name>Thalassiosirales</tp:taxon-name> and the Raphid
               <tp:taxon-name>Bacillariophyceae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> to the Baccilariales ( ). Despite this
            relation, no increased metabolic overlap was detected in <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana
            </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> ( Figs. 4 and 5 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 3.2.1. Amino acids and their derivatives </title>
         <p> *For <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> ectoine was detected by evaluation of
            the ion trace. </p>
         <p> **Derivatisation of arginine results in its conversion to ornithine, and these two
            metabolites cannot be distinguished with the GC-MS method ( ). </p>
         <p> Amino acids play an important role as compatible solutes. Accordingly, they comprise
            the most significant group among the identified dysregulated compounds in response to
            hyperosmotic stress ( Table 1 ). Their accumulation was explained with continuing de
            novo amino acid biosynthesis and due to reduced protein synthesis ( ; ). Alternatively,
            the high content of amino acids in response to osmotic stress could be caused by protein
            degradation, as shown for higher plants ( ; ). </p>
         <p> In many organisms, proline is one of the main osmolytes accumulated in response to
            hyperosmotic stress ( ). Over time, the increase in proline content was also detected
            for all three diatoms in this study under increased salinity. Similar responses were
            previously shown for diatoms, such as the small euryhaline <tp:taxon-name> Cyclotella
               meneghiniana </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> C. cryptica </tp:taxon-name> .
            These algae accumulate proline in response to the osmotic shock via biosynthesis using
            arginine and glutamate as substrates ( ). In our study, arginine was also up-regulated
            by <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> at both time points. </p>
         <p> Accumulation of 4-hydroxyproline and pyrrole-2-carboxylic acid was detected for all
            studied diatoms. These two metabolites are biosynthetically derived from proline.
            Accumulation of 4-hydroxyproline in response to salinity stress and its osmolytic
            function was reported in bacteria ( ; ). Increase in pyrrole-2-carboxylic acid upon salt
            and drought stress has also been found in higher plants ( ; ). The role as an
            osmoprotectant in other species points towards a similar role in diatoms. </p>
         <p> An increase in lysine content was detected for <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum
            </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>T. pseudonana</tp:taxon-name> . This amino acid is
            accumulated during water stress in plants ( ). In the bacterium <tp:taxon-name>
               Silicibacter pomeroyi </tp:taxon-name> , lysine helps to cope with osmotic stress.
            Moreover, lysine might serve as a precursor to produce pipecolinic acid. This
            transformation is common for bacteria and plants, where pipecolinic acid plays a role as
            osmoprotectant ( ; ). Based on the results obtained in this work, the osmoprotectant
            role of pipecolinic acid is also plausible for diatoms, because its accumulation was
            detected for all three species. </p>
         <p> Ectoine is a heterocyclic amino acid, which acts as compatible solute in halophilic and
            halotolerant prokaryotes. It is also found in some halophilic protists and microalgae (
            ; ; ; ). Ectoine is synthesized from aspartate with intermediate production of N γ-
            acetyldiaminobutyrate ( ). Elevated levels of ectoine in response to salinity stress
            were detected for all studied diatoms at both time points analyzed. Accumulation of
            ectoine was previously described for diatoms, and an increase in its content in response
            to salinity stress was shown for <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> ( ; ).
            Analysis of biosynthetic pathways, enabled by our metabolomics approach, can link the
            observed elevated levels of N γ- acetyldiaminobutyrate in <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana
            </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> under salt stress
            to the up-regulation of ectoine biosynthesis. </p>
         <p> For <tp:taxon-name>S. marinoi</tp:taxon-name> , dysregulation of leucine was detected.
            Notably, the amino acid was up-regulated in response to the short-term salinity stress
            and down-regulated in response to the long-term salinity stress. Possibly, this amino
            acid initially accumulated due to the general reduction of the protein synthesis or
            protein degradation. Later, it might be consumed in catabolism, providing an alternative
            source of acetyl- CoA to maintain the general metabolism ( ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 3.2.2. Saccharides and polyols </title>
         <p> Saccharides and polyols can serve as osmolytes themselves or be used for amino acid
            biosynthesis. The accumulation of saccharides in response to salinity stress was
            detected for <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> P.
               tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> . Among identified saccharides, glucose, mannose, and
            cellobiose were common for these two algae. Accumulation of glucose and mannose was
            previously detected in the diatom <tp:taxon-name> Nitzschia constricta </tp:taxon-name>
            when the alga was exposed to a salinity of 50 PSU ( ). In turn, mannose could be a
            substrate for threonic acid biosynthesis ( ). Previously, accumulation of threonate was
            shown in response to salinity stress in soybean ( ). An increase in the content of
            threonic acid was also detected for <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> and
               <tp:taxon-name>P. tricornutum</tp:taxon-name> . Interestingly, the fold change of
            mannose was higher than for threonic acid. Mannose is not only required for the
            synthesis of threonate but might play a role as an osmolyte by itself. </p>
         <p> In addition to structural and signaling functions, inositols are also known as
            osmolytes ( ). Durin g myo-inositol bi osynthesis, glucose-6-phosphate is converted to
            myo-inositol, which protects cells from salinity-induced damage. For instance, kiwifruit
            accumulate myo-inositol in the first 24 h after salinity stress ( ). In the current
            study, up-regulation of myo-inositol was detected for <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum
            </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> at 24 h, and
               <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> at 96 h. Myo-inositol can be converted to
            scyllo-inositol ( ). This metabolite is suggested as an osmolyte in, for example,
            invertebrates of the deep-sea ( ; ). Up-regulation of both inositols was detected for
               <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>S.
               marinoi</tp:taxon-name> . </p>
         <p> In conclusion, this work confirms that saccharides are modulated in adaptation to the
            salinity stress for <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and
               <tp:taxon-name>T. pseudonana</tp:taxon-name> . For <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi
            </tp:taxon-name> no significant dysregulation of any saccharide was detected. </p>
         <p> 3.2.3. Quaternary ammonium and tertiary sulfonium derivatives </p>
         <p> Quaternary ammonium compounds are another major class of osmolytes ( ). For the algae
            investigated, quaternary ammonium compounds, such as glycine betaine, proline betaine
            (stachydrine), and acylcarnitines could be identified among the significantly increased
            metabolites upon salinity stress. </p>
         <p> Up-regulation of several acylcarnitines was detected for <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum
            </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> in response to
            hypersalinity. For <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> , an increase in the
            content of two acylcarnitines was detected after 24 and 96 h. In <tp:taxon-name>S.
               marinoi</tp:taxon-name> , four acylcarnitines were in the list of up-regulated
            compounds 24 h after salinity stress. A study on <tp:taxon-name> Lactobacillus plantarum
            </tp:taxon-name> showed that acylcarnitines could play a role as osmoprotectants,
            although not as effectively as carnitine itself. In contrast to our work, the carnitine
            derivative up-regulation went ahead with a reduction in accumulated amino acids in the
            bacteria ( ). If the observed changes in acylcarnitines are connected to osmoadaptation
            or if they can be considered as a secondary response to altered amino acid biosynthesis
            has to be clarified in future studies. </p>
         <p> Glycine betaine is a compatible solute found in pro- and eukaryotes ( ). Its
            accumulation in response to the salinity stress was described for several diatom
            species, including <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>
               T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> ( ; ; ). During this work, up-regulation of glycine
            betaine was detected in <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> at both time points
            and in <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> at 96 h. Accumulation of proline
            betaine was detected for <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> in response to
            the long-term salinity stress. Its accumulation in response to salinity stress was
            reported for several plants and algae, including the diatom <tp:taxon-name> Nitzschia
               lecointei </tp:taxon-name> ( ; ; ; ). </p>
         <p> Interestingly, dimethylsulfoniopropionate, a metabolite often discussed as diatom
            compatible solute was not among those compounds that were up-regulated according to our
            criteria. The metabolite was detected in all investigated diatoms but significant
            up-regulation could not be confirmed. This is in accordance with observations that more
            subtle osmoadaptations go ahead with the regulation of amino acids and quartery
            ammounium metabolites, while DMSP, that is highly abundant, only compensates salinity
            changes under extreme stress conditions ( ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4. Conclusions </title>
         <p> This work addresses the orchestrated metabolic response of diatom metabolism in
            response to hypersalinity. We can distinguish between universally up-regulated
            metabolites in all three diatoms under hypersalinity stress that support a common
            adaptation mechanism. Amino acids, saccharides and inositols were most conserved ( ; ).
            The majority of regulated metabolites was specific to one or two species. The common
            repertoire of regulated metabolites is thus accompanied by species-specific
            physiological responses. </p>
         <p> The untargeted screening introduced here allowed not only the detection of previously
            identified candidates. It led to the identification of several metabolites that were
            previously not associated with salinity stress response in diatoms, e.g.
            4-hydroxyproline, pipecolinic acid, myoinositol, threonic acid, and acylcarnitines. For
            some of these metabolites their osmoprotectant role was described in plants or bacteria
            ( ; ; ; ; ). Up-regulation of these metabolites was detected in at least for two of
            three studied diatoms. </p>
         <p>We could also show that certain metabolites were specific for only short-term or
            long-term adaptation to hypersalinity. The data set introduced here, which is publicly
            accessible in the MetaboLights database, thus allows identifying common and specific
            processes in response to hypersalinity in diatoms. It will serve as a basis for future
            analysis of metabolic re-wiring of these unicellular algae under stress.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5. Experimental </title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.1. Solvents </title>
         <p> For endometabolome extraction, LC-, GC-MS sample, and analytical standard preparation
            (if not stated otherwise), the following reagents were used: methanol (SupraSolv, Merck,
            Germany ), ethanol (LiChrosolv, Supelco, Merck, Germany ), chloroform (HPLC grade,
            Fisher Scientific, UK ), acetonitrile (CHEMSOLUTE, Th. Geyer, Germany ), water
            (Chromasolv Plus for HPLC, Honeywell, Germany ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.2. Strains and culture conditions </title>
         <p> Strains of <tp:taxon-name> Phaeodactylum tricornutum Bohlin </tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Phaeodactylaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) CCMP 2561 and <tp:taxon-name>
               Thalassiosira pseudonana Hasle &amp; Heimdal </tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Thalassiosiraceae</tp:taxon-name> ) CCMP 1335 were obtained from the
            Bigelow National Center for Marine Algae and Microbiota (East Boothbay, USA ),
               <tp:taxon-name> Skeletonema marinoi Sarno &amp; Zingone </tp:taxon-name> (
               <tp:taxon-name>Skeletonemataceae</tp:taxon-name> ) RCC 75 was obtained from the
            Roscoff Culture Collection (Roscoff, France ). All cultures are maintained in the algae
            culture collection of the laboratory. </p>
         <p> Cultures were grown in 50 mL cell culture flasks containing 40 mL of artificial
            seawater medium (ASW) ( ). Stock cultures at the stationary phase were used for
            inoculation. Starting cell densities were 0.025 ⋅ 10 6 cells mL 1 for <tp:taxon-name> P.
               tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonan </tp:taxon-name> , and
            0.085 ⋅ 106 cells mL 1 for <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name> . The standard
            temperature was 13 ◦ C and the light adjusted to 55–65 μmol photons m 2 s 1 with 14/10
            light/dark cycle; all cultures were incubated with shaking at 80 rpm. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.3. Experimental design </title>
         <p>Pre-cultures of the algae were grown in triplicates until they reached stationary phase.
            Five culture replicates were inoculated for each treatment for the salinity stress
            experiments. ASW media blanks of the same volume were prepared in duplicates for each
            treatment. Salinity stress was initiated when cultures were at the late log-phase and
            the endometabolome was extracted 24 and 96 h afterwards.</p>
         <p> For <tp:taxon-name> P. tricornutum </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>T.
               pseudonana</tp:taxon-name> , salinity stress was performed by increasing the salt
            content in the medium from 35 to 60 PSU as described below. </p>
         <p> To establish the upper salt concentration in the medium at which <tp:taxon-name> S.
               marinoi </tp:taxon-name> could grow, experiments with three different salt
            concentrations of 50, 55, and 60 PSU, were performed. Because negative growth was
            observed for salt concentrations above 50 PSU, the endometabolome analysis was performed
            for cultures subjected to the salt increase in the medium to 50 PSU. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.4. Growth curves </title>
         <p>For growth curve determination, cell amounts and growth rates were monitored by cell
            counting and chlorophyll fluorescence intensity. Samples were taken once every two to
            three days during the cultivation period and right before, as well as one, two, and four
            days after the salinity stress.</p>
         <p> Cell counting was conducted using a Fuchs Rosenthal Counting Chamber (Glaswarenfabrik
            Karl Hecht, Germany ) under the light microscope Leica DM 2000 (Leica Microsystems,
            Wetzlar, Germany ). </p>
         <p> Chlorophyll fluorescence intensity measurement was conducted with a Varioskan Flash
            spectral scanning multimode reader (Thermo Scientific, Schwerte, Germany ). The
            excitation wavelength was 430 nm , and the emission wavelength was 665 nm . Measurements
            were performed in the 96 well-plate format with 200 μL of well-mixed culture per well,
            each culture was measured in triplicates. </p>
         <p> The final cell amount was normalized taking into account the extra medium added during
            the experiment. Statistical analysis was performed using two-sample t -test. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.5. Salinity stress experiment </title>
         <p> To perform the salinity stress experiments, 5 mL of 35 PSU ASW enriched with either
            0.135 g mL 1 , 0.180 g mL 1 , or 0.225 g mL 1 of NaCl (Carl Roth, Germany ) were added
            to 40 mL of cultures and media blanks (35 PSU) to reach the final salt concentrations of
            50, 55, and 60 PSU respectively. The same volume of ASW without elevated salt level was
            added to the control cultures and another set of media blanks. Before addition to the
            cultures ASW solutions were sterilized by filtration through Filtropur S 0.2 μm filters
            (Sarstedt AG and Co. KG, Germany ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.6. Extraction </title>
         <p> Extraction of the cultures was performed as described in with modifications. Briefly,
            after collection of the cells from 40 mL of cultures on Whatman GF/C filters (1.2 μm
            pore size) (GE Healthcare, US ) under vacuum (750 mbar), the endometabolome was
            extracted by addition of ice-cold extraction mix (1 mL methanol: ethanol: choloroform,
            1:3:1, v:v:v) to the filters in 1.5 mL Eppendorf Safe-Lock tubes (Eppendorf Quality,
            Eppendorf AG, Germany ). Cells were disrupted with ultrasonication in an ultrasonic
            cleaner Emmi-D280 (Emag AG, Germany ) for 10 min, and cell debris was sedimented by
            centrifugation at 30,000 g at 4 ◦ C for 15 min. Supernatants were transferred in 1.5 mL
            glass vials. Volumes for GC- and LC-MS samples were normalized according to the cell
            amounts in the cultures. For the media blanks the average volume of the culture’ s
            samples was prepared. The samples were evaporated under vacuum. Dried samples were kept
            under argon and stored at 20 ◦ C before analysis. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.7. Sample preparation </title>
         <p> Samples for the GC-MS analysis were prepared as described in with modifications.
            Briefly, dried samples contained aliquots equivalent to 5 • 106 cells and pooled quality
            control (QC) samples with equal volumes from each extract were reconstituted in 25 μL of
            pyridine (Chromasolv Plus, Sigma-Aldrich) containing 20 mg mL 1 methoxyamine
            monohydrochloride (Sigma-Aldrich), heated at 60 ◦ C for 1 h and incubated at a room
            temperature overnight. 20 μL of samples were transferred into vials with inserts, and to
            each sample 20 μL of N,O- bis(trimethylsilyl)trifluoroacetamide (Thermo) were added. To
            one QC samples 1 μL of a C7–C40 alkane standard mix, 100 μg mL 1 in hexane (diluted 1:10
            from the 1 mg mL 1 standard from Sigma-Aldrich) was added. Samples were heated at 60 ◦ C
            for 1 h and directly measured. </p>
         <p> For the LC-MS analysis aliquots equivalent to 3 • 10 6 cells and pooled quality control
            (QC) samples with equal volumes from each extract were reconstituted in 150 μL of a
            mixture of methanol: acetonitrile: water (5:9:1, v:v:v). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.8. Standards </title>
         <p> For GC-MS measurement, samples of standards were dried under vacuum and derivatised in
            the same way as experimental samples. Final concentrations of standards made up 100 μg
            mL 1 . To 40 μl of each standard sample 1 μL of a C7–C40 alkane standard mix, 100 μg mL
            1 in hexane was added (final concentration of C7–C40 alkane standard mix was 2.44 μg mL
            1 ). </p>
         <p> For LC-MS measurement, solutions of the standards were prepared by dissolving the
            standard in a mixture of methanol: acetonitrile: water (5:9:1, v:v:v) with the final
            concentration of 1 mg mL 1 . N γ- acetyldiaminobutyrate and cysteinolic acid were
            dissolved in water. </p>
         <p>The list of measured standards is presented in the supplementary information (Appendix
            S1).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.9. GC-MS measurement </title>
         <p> GC-MS measurements were performed on a Q-Exactive Orbitrap mass spectrometer connected
            to a Trace 1310 Gas Chromatograph with a TriPlus RSH Autosampler (Thermo Scientific,
            Bremen , Germany ). The gas chromatograph was equipped with a Zebron ZB-SemiVolatiles
            column ( 30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm, Phenomenex, USA ). Helium was used as a carrier gas
            with a flow rate of 1 mL min 1 . </p>
         <p> For the electron ionization (EI) mode temperature of the injector was 250 ◦ C, transfer
            line 250 ◦ C, the auxiliary zone 280 ◦ C, and the ion source 300 ◦ C. For the chemical
            ionization (CI) mode temperature of the ion source was 180 ◦ C, methane was used as an
            ionization gas with a flow rate of 1.5 mL min 1 . The injected volume of samples was 1
            μL, for EI mode split ratio varied (Table S4), CI samples were recorded in the splitless
            mode. </p>
         <p> Data were recorded in full scan profile mode across a mass range from 50 to 600 m/z in
            EI mode. Full scan profile mode with a mass range from 80 to 1000 m/z was used for the
            CI mode, the ionization energy was 70 eV. </p>
         <p>Due to the high intensity of the proline peak at the beginning of the GC chromatogram
            (Fig. S18), split ratios had to be high enough to not overload column and detector.
            However, detection of low concentrated metabolites was limited at those split ratios. To
            circumvent this, all samples were injected twice and measured with two different
            methods. The first method (“Proline method”) was run at a sufficiently high split rate
            to detect proline without overloading the system and MSacquisition was terminated after
            elution of proline (Table S4; Appendix S2). The second method (“After proline method”)
            was run with a lower split ratio, the same temperature gradient (Appendix S3), but
            acquisition started after the elution of proline. For data analysis, preprocessed data
            for both measurements were combined, with data up to retention time of proline taken
            from the first measurement and data after retention time of proline taken from the
            second one.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.10. LC-MS measurement </title>
         <p> Samples for LC-MS analysis were measured with a Dionex Ultimate 3000 system coupled to
            a Q-Exactive Plus Orbitrap mass spectrometer (Thermo Scientific, Bremen , Germany ). The
            measurements were performed in positive and negative modes, heated electrospray
            ionization was used to generate molecular ions. The duration of the method was 14.5 min
            with an MS runtime from 0.5 min to 9 min. Separation of the samples was performed on a
            SeQuant ZIC-HILIC column (5 μm, 200 Å, 150 × 2.1 mm , Merck, Germany ), equipped with
            SeQuant ZIC-HILIC guard column (20 × 2.1 mm , Merck, Germany ). Eluent A consisted of
            water with 2% acetonitrile and 0.1% formic acid, eluent B of 90% acetonitrile with 10%
            water and 1 mmol L 1 ammonium acetate. The flow rate was set to 0.6 mL min 1 , the
            gradient started with 85% solvent B which was held for 4.0 min, gradient to 0% of
            solvent B (4.0–5.0 min), hold 0% B (5.0–9.0 min), gradient to 100% of B (9.0–10.0 min),
            hold 100% B (10.0–12.0 min), gradient to 85% of B (12.0–12.5 min), hold 85% B (12.5–14.5
            min). </p>
         <p>The instrument settings can be found in the supplementary information Appendix S4.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.11. GC-MS data pre-processing </title>
         <p> GC-MS data pre-processing was performed as described in . Briefly, raw files were
            converted into. mzXML format using Proteowizard Suite (proteowizard.sourceforge.net)
            with vendor peak picking enabled. Data were pre-processed with an R script ( ), which
            includes the XCMS package ( ), CAMERA package ( ), and MetaMS package ( ). Obtained data
            was processed further with StatTarget package ( ) for quality control based signal drift
            correction. All settings were used as published except minimum fragments for features
            grouping was set to 5 ( ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.12. LC-MS data pre-processing </title>
         <p>Obtained raw data were preprocessed using Compound Discoverer version 3.1 (Thermo Fisher
            Scientific). The standard workflow (Untargeted Metabolomics with Statistics Detect
            Unknowns with ID Using Online Databases and mzLogic) with default settings was applied.
            Peak picking and deconvolution were performed for each algae species experiment
            separately.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.13. Statistical analysis </title>
         <p> Statistical analysis was performed for signals of which the average peak area of
            treated or control cultures was at least 5 times higher than in blank samples.
            Statistical analysis was conducted using Metaboanalyst 4.0 ( ). Data was log-transformed
            and auto-scaled. Statistically significantly dysregulated compounds were detected using
            volcano plots with fold change more than 2 and false discovery rate adjusted p -value
            less than 0.05 with unequal group variance. </p>
         <p> Comparison of dysregulated unidentified metabolites compositions between species was
            performed by comparing retention time and m / z values of the molecular ion for LC-MS
            results, and retention index, MSspectrum, and m / z value of the fragment with the
            highest intensity for GC-MS results. </p>
         <p> Since for one LC-MS sample of <tp:taxon-name> T. pseudonana </tp:taxon-name> control
            culture (extracted 96 h after the treatment) values highly differed from the rest of the
            samples, the sample was considered an outlier and was not included in further analysis
            (Fig. S19). One LC-MS control sample of <tp:taxon-name> S. marinoi </tp:taxon-name>
            (extracted 96 h after the treatment) was lost during workup. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.14. Venn diagrams </title>
         <p>The Venn diagrams were made using the web application BioVenn</p>
         <p> ( ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5.15. Identification of metabolites </title>
         <p> Identification of metabolites detected with GC-MS analysis was conducted using the NIST
            2011 Mass Spectral Library database (National Institute of Standards and Technology, USA
            ), MetFrag ( ) and MS-Finder platforms ( ). Results were manually checked for processing
            artifacts. </p>
         <p> Since EI spectra in Orbitrap GC/MS often lack the molecular ion, we supported the
            identification of candidate metabolites by additional CImeasurements. The CI mass
            spectra were checked for the presence of molecular ions – CH 4 neutral loss and +C 2 H 5
            and +C 3 H 4 adducts to confirm the elemental composition. </p>
         <p>The final verification of unknowns was done by comparison of mass spectra and retention
            index (accepted difference ≤3 units) with analytical standards.</p>
         <p> Identification of unknowns detected with LC-MS analysis was performed using Sirius
            version 4.4.29 ( ). Depending on the tree fragmentation score ( ), and the percentage of
            CSI:FingerID tool ( ) putative identification of unknowns was performed. </p>
         <p> The identity of unknowns was established by comparison of retention time and MS1
            spectra with chemical standards (accepted difference ≤0.2 min, &lt; 5 ppm). For betaine,
            pipecolinic acid, cysteinolic acid, methionine sulfoxide, N , N -dimethylarginine,
            ectoine, N γ- acetyldiaminobutyrate, acetylcarnitine, propionylcarnitine,
            butyrylcarnitine, and isovalerylcarnitine also MS2 spectra for both external and
            internal standards were recorded and compared manually. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Declaration of competing interest </title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal
            relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title> Acknowledgements </title>
         <p> The authors would like to thank Dr. Steffen Neumann (IPB Halle) for the help in
            repositing the MS-data in the MetaboLights database. We acknowledge funding by the state
            of Thuringia (2015) FGI0021 cosupported by the EU EFRE program and by the Deutsche
            Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG, German Research Foundation) under Germany’ s Excellence
            Strategy – EXC 2051 – Project-ID 081021–42 “Balance of the Microverse”. VN and GP thank
            the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation for funding within the Symbiochip project. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> Appendix A. Supplementary data </title>
         <p>Supplementary data to this article can be found online at https://doi.
            org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2022.113267.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title> References </title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Adams, P. , Thomas, J.C. , Vernon, D.M. , Bohnert, H.J. , Jensen,
                  R.G. , 1992 . Distinct cellular and organismic responses to salt stress . Plant
                  Cell Physiol. 33 , 1215–1223 . https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordjournals.pcp.a078376
                  . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Bergeijk, S.A. Van , Zee, C. Van Der , Stal, L.J. , 2003 . Uptake
                  and excretion of dimethylsulphoniopropionate is driven by salinity changes in the
                  marine benthic diatom Cylindrotheca closterium . Eur. J. Phycol. 38 , 341–349 .
                  https://doi.org/ 10.1080/09670260310001612600 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Blunden, G. , Smith, B.E. , Irons, M.W. , Yang, M.-H. , Roch, O.G. ,
                  Patel, A.V. , 1992 . Betaines and tertiary sulphonium compounds from 62 species of
                  marine algae . Biochem. Systemat. Ecol. 20 , 373–388 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1016/0305-1978(92) 90050-N . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> B¨ocker, S. , Dührkop, K. , 2016 . Fragmentation trees reloaded . J.
                  Cheminf. 8 , 1–26 . https://doi.org/10.1186/s13321-016-0116-8 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Branda, L.E. , 1984 . The salinity tolerance of forty-six marine
                  phytoplankton isolates. Estuar. Coast Shelf Sci. 18 , 543–556 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1016/0272-7714(84) 90089-1 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Chong, J. , Soufan, O. , Li, C. , Caraus, I. , Li, S. , Bourque, G.
                  , Wishart, D.S. , Xia, J. , 2018 . MetaboAnalyst 4.0: towards more transparent and
                  integrative metabolomics analysis . Nucleic Acids Res. 46 , 486–494 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gky310 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Czech, L. , Hermann, L. , St¨oveken, N., Richter, A.A. , Id, A.H. ,
                  Smits, S.H.J. , Heider, J. , Bremer, E. , 2018 . Role of the extremolytes ectoine
                  and hydroxyectoine as stress protectants and nutrients: genetics, phylogenomics,
                  biochemistry, and structural analysis . Genes 9 , 1–58 .
                  https://doi.org/10.3390/genes9040177 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Dawson, H.M. , Heal, K.R. , Boysen, A.K. , Carlson, L.T. , Ingalls,
                  A.E. , Young, J.N. , 2020 . Potential of temperature- and salinity-driven shifts
                  in diatom compatible solute concentrations to impact biogeochemical cycling within
                  sea ice . Elem. Sci. Anthr. 8 , 25 . https://doi.org/10.1525/elementa.421 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Dickson, D.M. , Kirst, G.O. , 1987 . Osmotic adjustment in marine
                  eukaryotic algae: the role of inorganic ions, quaternary ammonium, tertiary
                  sulphonium and carbohydrate solutes . New Phytol. 106 , 645–655 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.1987. tb00165.x. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Durack, P.J. , Wijffels, S.E. , 2010 . Fifty-year trends in global
                  ocean salinities and their relationship to broad-scale warming . J. Clim. 23 ,
                  4342–4362 . https://doi.org/ 10.1175/2010JCLI3377.1 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Dührkop, K. , Shen, H. , Meusel, M. , Rousu, J. , Bocker¨, S., 2015
                  . Searching molecular structure databases with tandem mass spectra using
                  CSI:FingerID . Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. Unit. States Am. 112 , 12580–12585 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1073/ pnas.1509788112 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Fenizia, S. , Thume, K. , Wirgenings, M. , Pohnert, G. , 2020 .
                  Ectoine from bacterial and algal origin is a compatible solute in microalgae. Mar
                  . Drugs 18 , 1–13 . https://doi. org/10.3390/md18010042 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Field, C.B. , Behrenfeld, M.J. , Randerson, J.T. , Falkowski, P. ,
                  1998 . Primary production of the biosphere: integrating terrestrial and oceanic
                  components . Science 281 , 237–240 . https://doi.org/10.1126/science.281.5374.237
                  . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Fukutoku, Y. , Yamada, Y. , 1981 . Sources of proline-nitrogen in
                  water-stressed soybean ( Glycine max L.) I. protein metabolism and proline
                  accumulation . Plant Cell Physiol. 22 , 1397–1404 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordjournals.pcp.a076292 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Gilmour, D.J. , Hipkins, M.F. , Webber, A.N. , Baker, N.R. , Boney,
                  A.D. , 1985 . The effect of ionic stress on photosynthesis in Dunaliella
                  tertiolecta . Chlorophyll fluorescence kinetics and spectral characteristics .
                  Planta 163 , 250–256 . https://doi.org/10.1007/ BF00393515 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Glaser, K. , Karsten, U. , 2020 . Salinity tolerance in
                  biogeographically different strains of the marine benthic diatom Cylindrotheca
                  closterium (Bacillariophyceae) . J. Appl. Phycol. 32 , 3809–3816 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s10811-020-02238-6 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hellebust, J.A. , 1976 . Osmoregulation . Annu. Rev. Plant Physiol.
                  27 , 485–505 . https:// doi.org/10.1146/annurev..27.060176.002413 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Hulsen, T. , Vlieg, J. De , Alkema, W. , 2008 . BioVenn – a web
                  application for the comparison and visualization of biological lists using
                  area-proportional Venn diagrams . BMC Genom. 9, 1–6.
                  https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-9-488. Jaramillo-Madrid, A.C. , Ashworth, J. ,
                  Ralph, P.J. , 2020 . Levels of diatom minor sterols respond to changes in
                  temperature and salinity . J. Mar. Sci. Eng. 8 , 1–14 . https://
                  doi.org/10.3390/jmse8020085 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Johansson, O.N. , T¨opel, M., Pinder, M.I.M. , Kourtchenko, O. ,
                  Blomberg, A. , Godhe, A. , Clarke, A.K. , 2019 . Skeletonema marinoi as a new
                  genetic model for marine chainforming diatoms . Nat. Sci. Reports 9 , 1–10 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019- 41085-5 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Joshi, V. , Fei, Z. , Joung, J. , Jander, G. , 2010 .
                  Interdependence of threonine, methionine and isoleucine metabolism in plants
                  accumulation and transcriptional regulation under abiotic stress . Amino Acids 39
                  , 933–947 . https://doi.org/10.1007/s00726- 010-0505-7 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kanehisa, M. , Goto, S. , 2000 . KEGG: kyoto encyclopedia of genes
                  and genomes . Nucleic Acids Res. 28 , 27–30 . https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/28.1.27
                  . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Keller, M.D. , Kiene, R.P. , Matrai, P.A. , Bellows, W.K. , 1999 .
                  Production of glycine betaine and dimethylsulfoniopropionate in marine
                  phytoplankton. I. Batch cultures . Mar. Biol. 135 , 237–248 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s002270050621 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kets, E.P.W. , Bont, J.A.M. De , 1997 . Effect of carnitines on
                  Lactobacillus plantarum subjected to osmotic stress . FEMS Microbiol. Lett. 146 ,
                  205–209 . https://doi.org/ 10.1111/j.1574-6968.1997.tb10194.x . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kim, K.H. , Jia, B. , Jeon, C.O. , 2017 . Identification of
                  trans-4-hydroxy-l-proline as a compatible solute and its biosynthesis and
                  molecular characterization in Halobacillus halophilus . Front. Microbiol. 8 , 1–11
                  . https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.02054 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kirst, G.O. , 1989 . Salinity tolerance of eukaryotic marine algae .
                  Annu. Rev. Plant Physiol. Plant Mol. Biol. 40 , 21–53 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev , 41.060190.000321. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kissoudis, C. , Kalloniati, C. , Flemetakis, E. , Madesis, P. ,
                  Labrou, N.E. , Tsaftaris, A. , Nianiou-Obeidat, I. , 2015 . Stress-inducible
                  GmGSTU4 shapes transgenic tobacco plants metabolome towards increased salinity
                  tolerance . Acta Physiol. Plant. 37 , 102 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s11738-015-1852-5 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Klages, K. , Boldings, H. , Smith, G.S. , 1999 . Accumulation of
                  myo-inositol in Actinidia seedlings subjected to salt stress . Ann. Bot. 84 ,
                  521–527 . https://doi.org/10.1006/ anbo.1999.0946 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Kuhl, C. , Tautenhahn, R. , Bo, C. , Larson, T.R. , Neumann, S. ,
                  2012 . CAMERA: an integrated strategy for compound spectra extraction and
                  annotation of liquid chromatography/mass spectrometry data sets . Anal. Chem. 84 ,
                  283–289 . https:// doi.org/10.1021/ac 202450g . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Landa, M. , Burns, A.S. , Roth, S.J. , Moran, M.A. , 2017 .
                  Bacterial transcriptome remodeling during sequential co-culture with a marine
                  dinoflagellate and diatom . ISME J. 11 , 2677–2690 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2017.117 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Laws, E.A. , 2013 . Evaluation of in situ phytoplankton growth
                  rates: a synthesis of data from varied approaches . Ann. Rev. Mar. Sci 5 , 247–268
                  . https://doi.org/10.1146/ annurev-marine-121211-172258 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Leimer, K.R. , Rice, R.H. , Gehrke, C.W. , 1977 . Complete mass
                  spectra of the pertrimethylsilylated amino acids . J. Chromatogr. A 141 , 355–375
                  . https://doi.org/ 10.1016/S0021-9673(00)93539-8 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Liu, M.S. , Hellebust, J.A. , 1976 . Regulation of proline
                  metabolism in the marine centric diatom Cyclotella cryptica . Can. J. Bot. 54 ,
                  949–959 . https://doi.org/10.1139/b76- 099 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Luan, H. , Ji, F. , Chen, Y. , Cai, Z. , 2018 . statTarget: a
                  streamlined tool for signal drift correction and interpretations of quantitative
                  mass spectrometry-based omics data . Anal. Chim. Acta 1036 , 66–72 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aca.2018.08.002 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Maier, I. , Calenberg, M. , 1994 . Effect of extracellular Ca2+ and
                  Ca2+-antagonists on the movement and chemoorientation of male gametes of
                  Ectocarpus siliculosus (Phaeophyceae) . Bot. Acta 107 , 451–460 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1438- 8677.1994.tb00820.x . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Martino, A. De , Meichenin, A. , Shi, J. , Pan, K. , Bowler, C. ,
                  2007 . Genetic and phenotypic characterization of Phaeodactylum tricornutum
                  (Bacillariophyceae) accessions . J. Phycol. 43 , 992–1009 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1529-8817.2007.00384.x . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Medlin, L.K. , Kaczmarska, I. , 2004 . Evolution of the diatoms: V .
                  Morphological and cytological support for the major clades and a taxonomic
                  revision. Phycologia 43 , 245–270 . https://doi.org/10.2216/i0031-8884-43-3-245.1
                  . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Mentzen, W.I. , Peng, J. , Ransom, N. , Nikolau, B.J. , Wurtele,
                  E.S. , 2008 . Articulation of three core metabolic processes in Arabidopsis: fatty
                  acid biosynthesis, leucine catabolism and starch metabolism . BMC Plant Biol. 8 ,
                  1–15 . https://doi.org/ 10.1186/1471-2229-8-76 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Mimura, H. , Nagata, S. , Matsumoto, T. , 1994 . Concentrations and
                  compositions of internal free amino acids in a halotolerant Brevibacterium sp . in
                  response to salt stress. Biosci. Biotechnol . Biochem. 58 , 1873–1874 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1271/ bbb.58.1873 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Moulin, M. , Deleu, C. , Larher, F. , 2000 . L-Lysine catabolism is
                  osmo-regulated at the level of lysine-ketoglutarate reductase and saccharopine
                  dehydrogenase in rapeseed leaf discs . Plant Physiol. Biochem. 38 , 577–585 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1016/S0981-9428 (00)00777-4 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Neshich, I.A.P. , Kiyota, E. , Arruda, P. , 2013 . Genome-wide
                  analysis of lysine catabolism in bacteria reveals new connections with osmotic
                  stress resistance . ISME J. 7 , 2400–2410 . https://doi.org/10.1038/ismej.2013.123
                  . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ochsenkühn, M.A. , R¨othig, T., D’ Angelo, C. , Wiedenmann, J. ,
                  Voolstra, C.R. , 2017 . The role of floridoside in osmoadaptation of
                  coral-associated algal endosymbionts to high-salinity conditions . Sci. Adv. 3 , e
                  1602047 https://doi.org/10.1126/ sciadv.1602047 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Peters, P. , Galinski, E.A. , Trüper, H.G. , 1990 . The biosynthesis
                  of ectoine . FEMS Microbiol. Lett. 71 , 157–162 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6968.1990.tb03815. x . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Rijstenbil, J.W. , 2003 . Effects of UVB radiation and salt stress
                  on growth, pigments and antioxidative defence of the marine diatom Cylindrotheca
                  closterium . Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser. 254 , 37–47 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Ruttkies, C. , Schymanski, E.L. , Wolf, S. , Hollender, J. ,
                  Neumann, S. , 2016 . MetFrag relaunched: incorporating strategies beyond in silico
                  fragmentation . J. Cheminf. 8 , 1–16 . https://doi.org/10.1186/s13321-016-0115-9 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Scholz, B. , Liebezeit, G. , 2012 . Compatible solutes in three
                  marine intertidal microphytobenthic Wadden Sea diatoms exposed to different
                  salinities . Eur. J. Phycol. 47 , 393–407 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1080/09670262.2012.720714 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Smith, C.A. , Want, E.J. , O’ Maille, G. , Abagyan, R. , Siuzdak, G.
                  , 2006 . XCMS: processing mass spectrometry data for metabolite profiling using
                  nonlinear peak alignment, matching, and identification . Anal. Chem. 78 , 779–787
                  . https://doi.org/10.1021/ ac051437y . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Stettin, D. , Poulin, R.X. , Pohnert, G. , 2020 . Metabolomics
                  benefits from GC Orbitrap – comparison of low- and high-resolution GC-MS .
                  Metabolites 10 , 143 . https://doi. org/10.3390/metabo10040143 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Sugie, K. , Fujiwara, A. , Nishino, S. , Kameyama, S. , Harada, N. ,
                  2020 . Impacts of temperature, CO2, and salinity on phytoplankton community
                  composition in the western Arctic Ocean. Front. Mar. Sci. 6 , 821 .
                  https://doi.org/10.3389/ fmars.2019.00821 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Thomas, M.K. , Kremer, C.T. , Klausmeier, C.A. , Litchman, E. , 2012
                  . A global pattern of thermal adaptation in marine phytoplankton . Science 338 ,
                  1085–1088 . https://doi. org/10.1126/science.1224836 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Thume, K. , Gebser, B. , Chen, L. , Meyer, N. , Kieber, D.J. ,
                  Pohnert, G. , 2018 . The metabolite dimethylsulfoxonium propionate extends the
                  marine organosulfur cycle . Nature 563 , 412–415 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-018-0675-0 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Tsugawa, H. , Kind, T. , Nakabayashi, R. , Yukihira, D. , Tanaka, W.
                  , Cajka, T. , Saito, K. , Fiehn, O. , Arita, M. , 2016 . Hydrogen rearrangement
                  rules: computational ms/ms fragmentation and structure elucidation using MS-FINDER
                  software . Anal. Chem. 88 , 7946–7958 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.analchem.6b00770 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Vidoudez, C. , Pohnert, G. , 2012 . Comparative metabolomics of the
                  diatom Skeletonema marinoi in different growth phases . Metabolomics 8 , 654–669 .
                  https://doi.org/ 10.1007/s11306-011-0356-6 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Wehrens, R. , Weingart, G. , Mattivi, F. , 2014 . metaMS: an
                  open-source pipeline for GC – MS-based untargeted metabolomics . J. Chromatogr. B
                  966 , 109–116 . https://doi. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Weinisch, L. , Ku, S. , Roth, R. , Grimm, M. , Roth, T. , Daili, J.
                  , Netz, A. , Pierik, A.J. , Filker, S. , 2018 . Identification of osmoadaptive
                  strategies in the halophile, heterotrophic ciliate Schmidingerothrix salinarum .
                  PLoS Biol. 16 , 1–29 . https://doi. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Yamamoto, M. , Chiba, T. , Tuji, A. , 2017 . Salinity responses of
                  benthic diatoms inhabiting tidal flats . Diatom Res. 32 , 243–250 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1080/ 0269249X.2017.1366951 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Yancey, P.H. , 2005 . Organic osmolytes as compatible, metabolic and
                  counteracting cytoprotectants in high osmolarity and other stresses . J. Exp.
                  Biol. 208 , 2819–2830 . https://doi.org/10.1242/jeb.01730 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhang, J. , Chen, G. , Zhao, P. , Zhou, Q. , Zhao, X. , 2017 . The
                  abundance of certain metabolites responds to drought stress in the highly drought
                  tolerant plant Caragana korshinskii . Acta Physiol. Plant. 39 , 116 .
                  https://doi.org/10.1007/s11738-017-2412- y . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zhang, J. , Yang, D. , Li, M. , Shi, L. , 2016 . Metabolic profiles
                  reveal changes in wild and cultivated soybean seedling leaves under salt stress .
                  PLoS One 11 , 1–17 . https://doi. org/10.1371/journal.pone.0159622 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> Zika, J.D. , Skliris, N. , Blaker, A.T. , Marsh, R. , Nurser, A.J.G.
                  , Josey, S.A. , 2018 . Improved estimates of water cycle change from ocean
                  salinity: the key role of ocean warming . Environ. Res. Lett. 13 , 074036
                  https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/aace42 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
