<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Science</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1112158</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Gender-Specific Reproductive Tissue in Ratites and Tyrannosaurus rex</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2005</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ResearchGate
</title>
         <p>See discussions, stats, and author profiles for this publication at: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/7809392</p>
         <p>

Gender-Specific Reproductive Tissue in Ratites and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus rex</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Article
in
Science
• July 
2005
DOI: 
10.1126/science.1112158
• Source: PubMed
</p>
         <p>CITATIONS</p>
         <p>107</p>
         <p>
3 authors
, including:
</p>
         <p>Mary H Schweitzer</p>
         <p>North Carolina State University</p>
         <p>
129
PUBLICATIONS 
2,651
CITATIONS
</p>
         <p>SEE PROFILE</p>
         <p>
Some of the authors of this publication are also working on these related projects:
</p>
         <p>project Tail evolution: dinosaurs to birds View project</p>
         <p>dinosaur ontogeny View project</p>
         <p>All content following this page was uploaded by Mary H Schweitzer on 31 May 2014.</p>
         <p>READS</p>
         <p>720</p>
         <p>
John R. Horner
</p>
         <p>Montana State University</p>
         <p>
211
PUBLICATIONS 
6,666
CITATIONS
</p>
         <p>SEE PROFILE</p>
         <p>The</p>
         <p>user</p>
         <p>has</p>
         <p>requestedenhancement</p>
         <p>ofthedownloaded</p>
         <p>file</p>
         <p>.</p>
         <p>
Gender-Specific Reproductive Tissue in Ratites and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus rex</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>Mary H. Schweitzer,1,2,3** Jennifer L. Wittmeyer,1 John R. Horner3</p>
         <p>
Unambiguous indicators of gender in dinosaurs are usually lost during fossilization, along with other aspects of soft tissue anatomy. We report the presence of endosteally derived bone tissues lining the interior marrow cavities of portions of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus rex</tp:taxon-name>
(
Museum of the Rockies specimen number 1125
) hindlimb elements, and we hypothesize that these tissues are homologous to specialized avian tissues known as medullary bone. Because medullary bone is unique to female birds, its discovery in extinct dinosaurs solidifies the link between dinosaurs and birds, suggests similar reproductive strategies, and provides an objective means of gender differentiation in dinosaurs.
</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus rex</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Gender-Specific Reproductive Tissue in Ratites and Tyrannosaurus rex</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1126/science.1112158</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F57B2942FFA7FF9CFFA63039216EFFE7</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1112158</pub-id>
               <source>Science</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>

A relatively small (femur length, 107 cm) 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus rex</tp:taxon-name>
[
<tp:material-citation>Museum of the Rockies (MOR) specimen number 1125</tp:material-citation>
] was discovered at the base of the Hell Creek Formation (dated at ~70 million years ago) as an association of disarticulated elements with excellent preservation (1). At death, 
<tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
was estimated to be 18 T 2 years (2), on the basis of lines of arrested growth (LAG).

</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Interior femur fragments from 
<tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
were reserved without preservatives for chem­ ical and molecular analyses. Gross examination revealed a thin layer of bone tissue lining the inner (medullary) surfaces of the bone fragments that was structurally distinct from other described bone types (

) but possessed characteristics in common with avian medullary bone (MB).
</p>
            <p>
MB is an ephemeral tissue, deposited on the endosteal surface of avian long bones 
(3-10).
Its formation in female birds is triggered by increasing levels of gonadal hor­ mones produced upon ovulation (
4
, 
10
, 
11
), but it can also be artificially induced in male birds by the administration of estrogen (
3
, 
4
, 
12
). Because MB is densely mineralized and extremely well vascularized, it provides an easily mobilized source of calcium necessary for the production of calcareous eggshells (
13
). We compare MB from emu and ostrich (
14
) at different stages of the laying cycle with newly identified dinosaur tissues, because these basal birds share more primitive features with nonavian dinosaurs than do extant neognaths (
15-18
).
</p>
            <p>
Our investigations show that ratite MB differs from that seen in better-studied neognaths. We observed substantial variation between emu and ostrich MB tissues and between both ratites and reported neognath tissues (

and fig. S1). MB (

) may be thick (chicken and ostrich) or quite thin (emu) at midshaft; and it may be separated by a distinct layer of endosteal laminar bone (ELB) as described by Chinsamy et al. (19) (chicken and emu), or not (ostrich). The innermost layer of MB in the ostrich Eadjacent to the endosteal surface of cortical bone (CB)] appears to arise from dense sheets to form tubular structures that parallel the long axis of the bone (

). Thin hairlike spicules (

) of mineralized bone protrude from the tubes and may be intimately involved in their formation from the basal layer. Mineralized spicules were also noted arising from emu MB (fig. S2), but the tubelike structures were not so apparent or distinct. The MB tissues are morphologically distinct from overlying CB and are similarly distributed in both dinosaur (

) and ratite (

, E and F) samples. Higher magnifications of T. rex (

) and ratite (

, H and I) tissues show the open, crystalline, and fibrous structure of these highly vascular tissues, in contrast to the denser CB.
</p>
            <p>
In a fresh fracture, dense and relatively homogenous dinosaur CB is distinct from the loosely organized and highly vascular MB internal to it (

). A distinct layer corresponding to ELB (19) separates the two bone types. A large erosion room is visible at this boundary, lined with laminar tissue. An emu bone fragment (

) in similar orientation shows MB tissues with a distinctive, less organized and Bcrumbly[texture relative to overlying CB. It is interspersed with or laid down between large erosion rooms within the deep cortex and ELB of the tibial shaft. The dense cortex and laminar structure of the ELB are easily distinguished from surrounding MB. The ostrich MB (

) differs in both texture and orientation, with open cavities that are bordered by tubelike bone spicules.
</p>
            <p>
The lacy vascularity of the T. rex tissues (

) is consistent with the larger vascular canals and whorled pattern of the emu (

) and especially with the ostrich (

), where wide blood-filled sinuses separate forming bone spicules. In ground section (

), 
<tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
femur cortical bone is characterized by well-developed multigeneration Haversian systems with obvious and defined cement lines, supporting a mature status for this dinosaur (2). A region of decreased vascularity and laminar structure marks the ELB. In contrast, the medullary tissues arising from the ELB are densely vascularized but show no evidence of Haversian remodeling or cement lines, indicating that this tissue is newly deposited, or younger bone. A fresh cut section of emu bone (

) in comparable orientation shows dense CB and vascular, crystalline, and loosely organized MB, separated by a thin, dense, and less vascular ELB. MB in the ostrich (

) is more extensive than in the emu samples, most likely because shelling had not yet begun (14). No distinct ELB is visible. MB appears laminar rather than spiculated in 

, because the tubules formed by bony spicules are oriented longitudinally rather than in cross section as in 

, but it is the same tissue.
</p>
            <p>
Additional pattern similarities are seen in demineralized (14) ratite (

, B and C) and T. rex (

) medullary tissues. In all cases, the matrix is fibrous and randomly organized. The reddish color in extant tissues is due to blood retained in sinuses that separate the bone spicules. The T. rex tissues are similarly pigmented, due either to diagenetic alteration or to close association of bony tissues with blood-producing marrow during the life of the dinosaur.
</p>
            <p>
In all MB tissues shown, large vascular sinuses are easily discerned (

, D to F), but in the T. rex, vascular openings are surrounded by circumferentially oriented matrix fibers (

) that are less apparent in extant bone. The ostrich medullary tissues are denser than either the emu (

) or T. 
rex
samples, particularly closer to the cortex, but the variation in the size and density of vascular sinuses (

) 
is
similar to that seen in the T. 
rex
tissues. In planar view, 
<tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
undemineralized tissues show a random orientation of fibers, and vascular openings penetrate deep into the tissues (

, inset) and exhibit an unusual doublet or triplet pattern, where multiple vessels penetrate an osteonlike core (arrows), also seen in the emu (

, arrows). The ostrich medullary tissues (

) are more variable, denser, and less random in appearance than those of the emu, but the morphology changes as the tissues extend into the medullary cavity. Close to the cortex (

, inset, and fig. S3), the bone 
is
sheetlike, relatively dense, and punctured by vascular sinuses exhibiting the doublet pattern (arrows) noted above. As tissues extend into the medullary cavity (

), this pattern becomes obscured. Inset bone has been stained (14) for better contrast.
</p>
            <p>
In regions of 
<tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
bone where most of the medullary tissues have eroded (

), patches of denser CB can be seen, emphasizing the random mazelike pattern and large vascular sinuses of medullary tissues, a pattern also seen in the emu bone (

). The ostrich MB shows a similar pattern of bony spicules surrounding large and small blood sinuses (

).
</p>
            <p>
Scanning electron micrographs (14) reveal the distinctive grainy texture and disorganized morphology of demineralized T. 
rex
and avian MB (

). This contrasts with the smooth and fibrous texture of demineralized CB from the same specimens (

). Higher magnifications of demineralized CB (

) emphasize the smooth, fibrous, and more ordered nature of all specimens, although in 
<tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
(

), degradation 
is
apparent.
</p>
            <p>
MB occurs naturally only in extant female birds, although it varies in amount and distribution among taxa and with ovulatory phase (5, 20). It 
is
chemically, functionally, and structurally distinct from both overlying CB and internal trabecular bone (21, 22). Although "medullary" and "trabecular" bone are terms often used interchangeably in the literature, MB has a larger surface area and 
is
more vascular than other bone types, allowing rapid calcium mobilization (5). It 
is
more highly mineralized, with a greater apatite-tocollagen ratio (5, 7, 
20-22),
and incorporates acidic mucopolysaccharides and glycosaminoglycans that are not present in CB (
5
, 
11
). Additionally, the matrix of MB 
is
higher in noncollagenous proteins and lower in collagen, and has a higher collagen III-to-collagen I ratio (
22
) relative to other bone types. If preservation allows, these characteristics will be used as part of ongoing research to chemically distinguish the two bone types in this dinosaur.
</p>
            <p>
The existence of avian-type MB in dinosaurs has been hypothesized (
9
, 
23
) but not identified. In part, this could be because of taphonomic bias, because the death and fossilization of an ovulating dinosaur would be comparatively rare. Additionally, MB in extant birds 
is
fragile, the spicules separating easily from the originating layer (fig. S1). Dinosaur MB may separate and be lost from overlying CB in a similar manner during diagenesis.
</p>
            <p>
The location, origin, morphology, and microstructure of the new 
T. rex
tissues support homology with ratite MB. The 
T. rex
tissues line the medullary cavities of both femora of 
<tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
, suggesting an organismal response. The tissues are similar in distribution to those of extant ratites, being more extensive in proximal regions of the bone. They are clearly endosteal in origin, and the microstructure with large vascular sinuses 
is
consistent with the function of MB as a rapidly deposited and easily mobilized calcium source. The random, woven character indicates rapidly deposited, younger bone. Finally, the robustly supported relationship between theropods and extant birds (
15-18
, 
24
, 
25
) permits the application of phylogenetic inference to support the identification of these tissues (
26
, 
27
).
</p>
            <p>
The morphology of these dinosaur tissues 
is
not identical to that of extant neognaths (fig. S1), but is more similar to that seen in ratites. T. 
rex
medullary tissues are less extensive than those reported for neognaths, which may be explained by many factors. First, there 
is
a wide range of MB morphologies in extant taxa (20), varying with both reproductive phase and the position of the egg within the reproductive tract (6). Medullary tissues become thinner as shelling progresses and disappear completely with deposition of the last egg. If the same was true of dinosaurs, 
<tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
may have died toward the end of the laying cycle. Second, MB in extant birds 
is
hypothesized to provide a buffer against excessive and debilitating bone resorption during shelling (4, 28). It 
is
most extensive in smaller taxa with high reproductive rates, because of the demand for rapid mobilization of skeletal calcium for shelling. Extinct theropods produced hardshelled eggs, as did other dinosaurs and all extant birds (29, 30). Although egg size is not known, eggs were most likely smaller relative to overall body size than in extant birds, resulting in less demand for bone calcium reserves and reducing the need to offset resorption. These factors may also contribute to the smaller ratio of medullary to cortical thickness in theropods than in extant birds. Finally, T. 
rex
, although phylogenetically close to extant birds 
(15-18, 24, 25),
was distinct in size, biomechanical constraints, and, to some degree, physiology (
31
); therefore, slight variations in bone and tissue types would be expected.
</p>
            <p>
MB most likely first evolved within the lineage in early, small theropods with high productivity. A relatively thicker tyrannosaur bone cortex would reduce the need for MB, and its presence in 
<tp:material-citation>MOR 1125</tp:material-citation>
may reflect the retention of a primitive trait. This hypothesis may be tested by examination of the limb bones of the recently reported oviraptor containing eggs in the reproductive tract (
32
). The existence of MB in crocodiles has been referred to anecdotally (
3
, 
21
), but although they do resorb CB during shelling, experimental evidence suggests that they do not form MB (
6
, 
9
, 
11
, 
12
), even after stimulation with estrogen (
33
). The identification of medullary tissues in dinosaurs supports a closer relationship to birds than to other extant archosaurs, sheds light on reproductive strategies of nonavian theropods, and provides an objective means of gender determination in extinct dinosaurs.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>
References and Notes

</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1. 

M. H. 
Schweitzer

, 

J. L. 
Wittmeyer

, 

J. R. 
Horner

, 

J. A. 
Toporski

, 

Science


307

, 
1952
(
2005
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
2. 

J. R. 
Horner

, 

K. 
Padian

, 


Proc
. 
R
. 
Soc
. 
London

Ser. 
B


271

, 
1875
(
2004
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
3
. 

T. 
Yamamoto

, 

H. 
Nakamura

, 

T. 
Tsuji

, 

A. 
Hirata

, 

Anat
. 
Rec
.


264

, 
25
(
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
4. 

S. C. 

Miller


, 

B. M. 
Bowman

, 

Dev. 
Biol
.


87
, 
52

(
1981
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
5
. 

C. G. 
Dacke

et al
., 

J
. 
Exp
. 
Biol
.


184

, 
63
(
1993
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
6. 

M. A
. 
Bloom

, 

L. V. 
Domm

, 

A. V. 
Nalbandov

, 

W. 
Bloom

, 

Am
. 
J
. 
Anat
.

102
, 
411
(
1958
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
7. 

T. G
. 
Taylor

, 

K. 
Simkiss

, 

D
. A. Stringer

, in 


Physiology
and 
Biochemistry of
the Domestic 
Fowl

(Volume 2)

, 


D
. J. 
Bell

, 
B. M. Freeman

, Eds. (


Academic Press, 
London


, 
1971
), pp. 
621-640
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
8. 

E. 
Bonucci

, 

G. 
Gherardi

, 

Cell 
Tissue Res
.


163

, 
81
(
1975
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
9. 

A. 
Chinsamy

, 

P. M. 
Barrett

, 

J
. 
Vertebr
. Paleontol.


17

, 
450
(
1997
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
10. 
A. Ascenzi
, 
C. Francois
, 

D
. S. Bocciarelli

, 

J
. Ultrastruct. 
Res
.


8

, 
491
(
1963
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
11. 
T. Sugiyama
, 
S. Kusuhara
, 

Asian-Australas. 
J
. Anim. 
Sci
.

14
, 
82
(
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
12. 
T. Ohashi
, 
S. Kusuhara
, 
K. Ishida
, 

Br
. Poult. 
Sci
.


28

, 
727
(
1987
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
13. 

J. L. 
Arias

, 
M. S. Fernandez
, 

World's
Poult. 
Sci
. 
J
.


57

, 
349
(
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
15. 
J. A. Gauthier
, 

Mem
. 
Calif
. 
Acad
.


Sci

. 

8

, 
1
(
1986
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
16. 
L. M. Chiappe
, 
Nature
378
, 
349
(
1995
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
17. 
K. Padian
, 
L. M. Chiappe
, 

Sci
. 
Am
.


278

, 
38
(
1998
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
18. 

J. 
Cracraft

, 
J. A. Clarke
, in 

New Perspectives
on the Origin and 
Early
Evolution 
of Birds
. Proceedings 
of
the International 
Symposium
in Honor 
of J
. 
H
. Ostrom

, 
J. Gauthier
, 

L. F. 
Gall

, Eds. (
Special Publication of the Peabody Museum of Natural History, New Haven, CT
, 
2001
), pp. 
143-147
.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
19. 
A. Chinsamy
, 
L. M. Chiappe
, 
P. Dodson
, 
Paleobiology

21

, 
561
(
1995
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
20. 
H. Schraer
, 
S. J. Hunter
, 

Comp
. 
Biochem
. Physiol. 
A


82

, 
13
(
1985
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
21. 
C. C. Whitehead
, 

Poult. 
Sci
.


83

, 
193
(
2004
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
22. 
L. Knott
, 
A. J. Bailey
, 

Br
. Poult. 
Sci
.


40

, 
371
(
1999
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
23. 

D
. M. Martill

, 
M. J. Barker
, 
C. G. Dacke
, 
Nature
379
, 
778
(
1996
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
24. 
C. A. Forster
, 

S. 
D
. Sampson

, 
L. M. Chiappe
, 

D
. W. Krause

, 

Science


279

, 
1915
(
1998
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
25. 
P. C. Sereno
, 

Annu. 
Rev
. 
Earth
Planet. 
Sci
.


25

, 
435
(
1997
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
26. 
H. N. Bryant
, 

A. P. 
Russell

, 

Philos. 
Trans
. 
R
. 
Soc
. 
London Ser
. 
B


337

, 
405
(
1992
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
27. 
L. M. Witmer
, in 

Functional 
Morphology
in 
Vertebrate
Paleontology

, 
J. J. Thomason
, Ed. (
Cambridge Univ. Press, New York
, 
1995
), pp. 

19- 
33

.
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
28. 

S. 
Wilson

, 
B. H. Thorpe
, 

Calcif
. 
Tissue Int
.


62

, 
506
(
1998
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
29. 
K. Carpenter
, Ed., 

Eggs
, Nests, and 
Baby Dinosaurs
: 
A Look at Dinosaur Reproduction

(
Indiana Univ. Press, Bloomington, IN
, 
1999
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
30. 
K. E. Mikhailov
, 

Spec
. 
Pap
. Palaeontol.

56
, 
1
(
1997
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
31. 
M. H. Schweitzer
, 
C. L. Marshall
, 

J
. 
Exp
. Zoolog. Part 
B Mol
. Dev. 
Evol
.


291

, 
317
(
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
33
. 

R. M. 
Elsey

, 
C. S. Wink
, 

Comp. 
Biochem
. 
Biophys
.


84

A, 
107
(
1986
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Materials and Methods</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Figs. S1 to S3</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>11 March 2005; accepted 21 April 2005 10.1126/science.1112158</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Ivory-billed Woodpecker (Campephilus principalis) Persists in Continental North America</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>John W. Fitzpatrick,1* Martjan Lammertink,1,2 M. David Luneau Jr.,3 Tim W. Gallagher,1 Bobby R. Harrison,4 Gene M. Sparling,5 Kenneth V. Rosenberg,1 Ronald W. Rohrbaugh,1 Elliott C. H. Swarthout,1 Peter H. Wrege,1 Sara Barker Swarthout,1 Marc S. Dantzker,1 Russell A. Charif,1 Timothy R. Barksdale,6 J. V. Remsen Jr.,7 Scott D. Simon,8 Douglas Zollner8</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The ivory-billed woodpecker (Campephilus principalis), long suspected to be extinct, has been rediscovered in the Big Woods region of eastern Arkansas. Visual encounters during 2004 and 2005, and analysis of a video clip from April 2004, confirm the existence of at least one male. Acoustic signatures consistent with Campephilus display drums also have been heard from the region. Extensive efforts to find birds away from the primary encounter site remain unsuccessful, but potential habitat for a thinly distributed source population is vast (over 220,000 hectares).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The ivory-billed woodpecker is one of seven North American bird species that are suspected or known to have become extinct since 1880 (1). One of the world_s largest woodpeckers, this species of considerable beauty and lore was uncommon but widespread across lowland primary forest of the southeastern United States until midway through the 19th century (2, 3). Its disappearance coincided with the systematic annihilation of virgin tall forests across the southeastern United States between 1880 and the 1940s. Relentless pursuit by professional collectors accelerated the species_ decline from 1890 to the early 1920s. The last well-documented population occupied a stand of old-growth bottomland hardwood forest in northeastern Louisiana (the</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>1Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology, Cornell University, 159 Sapsucker Woods Road, Ithaca, NY 14850, USA. 2Institute for Biodiversity and Ecosystem Dynamics, Universiteit van Amsterdam, Mauritskade 61, 1092 AD Amsterdam, Netherlands. 3Department of Engineering Technology and Department of Information Technology, University of Arkansas at Little Rock, Little Rock, AR 72204, USA. 4Department of Communications, Oakwood College, Huntsville, AL 35896, USA. 5107 Stillmeadow Lane, Hot Springs, AR 71913, USA. 6Birdman Productions, Post Office Box 1124, 65 Mountain View Drive, Choteau, MT 59422, USA. 7Museum of Natural Science, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA 70803, USA. 8The Nature Conservancy, Arkansas Chapter, 601 North University Avenue, Little Rock, AR 72205, USA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Singer Tract) during the late 1930s (3-6). That population disappeared as the Singer Tract was logged amid cries for protection of both forest and bird. The final individual in the Singer Tract, an unpaired female, was last seen in cut-over forest remnants in 1944 (7).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>A resident subspecies of ivory-billed woodpecker (Campephilus principalis bairdii) occupied tall forests throughout Cuba, and a small population was mapped and photographed in eastern Cuba as late as 1956 (8). Fleeting observations of at least two individuals in 1986 and 1987 by several experts are widely accepted as valid (9), but repeated efforts to confirm the continued existence of that population have failed (10).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Anecdotal reports of ivory-billed woodpeckers in the southern United States continue to this day. Such reports are suspect because of the existence and relative abundance throughout this region of the superficially similar pileated woodpecker (Dryocopus pileatus). Three reports were accompanied by physical evidence, but their veracity continues to be questioned Esupporting online material (SOM) text]. Thus, no living ivorybilled woodpecker has been conclusively documented in continental North America since 1944.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>At approximately 13:30 Central Standard Time (CST) on 11 February 2004, while kayaking alone on a bayou in the Cache River National Wildlife Refuge, Monroe County, Arkansas, G. Sparling spotted an unusually large red-crested woodpecker flying toward him and landing near the base of a tree about 20 m away. Several field marks suggested that the bird was a male ivory-billed woodpecker (SOM text), and Sparling hinted at his sighting on a Web site. T. Gallagher and B. Harrison were struck by the apparent authenticity of this sighting and arranged to be guided through the region by Sparling. At 13:15 CST on 27 February 2004, within 0.5 km of the original sighting, an ivory-billed woodpecker (sex unknown) flew directly in front of their canoe with the apparent intention of landing on a tree near the canoe, thereby fully revealing its dorsal wing pattern. The bird instead veered into the forest, apparently landed briefly several times (each time blocked from the observers_ sight by trees), and then flew off (SOM text and fig. S1). Efforts to locate the bird over the next several days failed, but subsequent surveys by teams of experienced observers yielded a minimum of five additional visual encounters between 5 April 2004 and 15 February 2005 (SOM text). All seven convincing sightings were within 3 km of one another.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>At 15:42 Central Daylight Time on 25 April 2004, M. D. Luneau secured a brief but crucial video of a very large woodpecker perched on the trunk of a water tupelo (Nyssa aquatica), then fleeing from the approaching canoe (fig. S2 and movie S1). The woodpecker remains in the video frame for a total of 4 s as it flies rapidly away. Even at its closest point, the woodpecker occupies only a small fraction of the video. Its images are blurred and pixilated owing to rapid motion, slow shutter speed, video interlacing artifacts, and the bird_s distance beyond the video camera_s focal plane. Despite these imperfections, crucial field marks are evident both on the original and on deinterlaced and magnified video fields (11) (fig. S3). At least five diagnostic features allow us to identify the subject as an ivory-billed woodpecker.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>1) Size. When the woodpecker first begins to take flight from the left side of a tupelo trunk, two video fields reveal the dorsal surface of the right wing and a large black tail (Fig. 1). The minimum distances between the Bwrist[and the tip of its tailmeasured independently on each of the two video fields and compared to known scales (the diameter of the tupelo trunk at two places)—are 34 to 38 cm. These values exceed comparable values for the pileated woodpecker and correspond to the upper range for the ivory-billed woodpecker (fig. S4).</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
