<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Science</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aav0379</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Amphibian fungal panzootic causes catastrophic and ongoing loss of biodiversity</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>26</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2019</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
WILDLIFE DISEASE

</title>
         <p>
Amphibian fungal panzootic causes catastrophic and ongoing loss
of biodiversity

</p>
         <p>
Ben C. Scheele

1,2,3

×, 

Frank Pasmans

4


, 
Lee F. Skerratt
3


, 
Lee Berger
3


, 
An Martel
4


, 
Wouter Beukema
4


, 
Aldemar A. Acevedo
5,6


, 
Patricia A. Burrowes
7


, 
Tamilie Carvalho
8


, 
Alessandro Catenazzi
9


, 
Ignacio De la Riva
10


, 
Matthew C. Fisher
11


, 
Sandra V. Flechas
12,13


, 
Claire N. Foster
1


, 
Patricia Frías-Álvarez
3


, 
Trenton W. J. Garner
14,15


, 
Brian Gratwicke
16


, 
Juan M. Guayasamin
17,18,19


, 
Mareike Hirschfeld
20


, 
Jonathan E. Kolby
3,21,22

,

Tiffany A. Kosch

3,23


, 
Enrique La Marca
24


, 
David B. Lindenmayer
1,2


, 
Karen R. Lips
25


, 
Ana V. Longo
26


, 
Raúl Maneyro
27


, 

Cait A. 
McDonald
28


, 
Joseph Mendelson III
29,30

,

Pablo Palacios-Rodriguez

12


, 
Gabriela Parra-Olea
31


, 
Corinne L. Richards-Zawacki
32


, 
Mark-Oliver Rödel
20


, 
Sean M. Rovito
33


, 
Claudio Soto-Azat
34


, 
Luís Felipe Toledo
8

,

Jamie Voyles

35


, 
Ché Weldon
15


, 
Steven M. Whitfield
36,37


, 
Mark Wilkinson
38

,

Kelly R. Zamudio

28


, 
Stefano Canessa
4

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Anthropogenic trade and development have broken down dispersal barriers, facilitating the spread of diseases that threaten Earth’ s biodiversity.We present a global, quantitative assessment of the amphibian chytridiomycosis panzootic, one of the most impactful examples of disease spread, and demonstrate its role in the decline of at least 501 amphibian species
over the past half-century, including 90 presumed extinctions.The effects of chytridiomycosis have been greatest in large-bodied, range-restricted anurans in wet climates in the Americas and 
Australia
. Declines peaked in the 1980s, and only 12% of declined species show signs

of recovery, whereas 39% are experiencing ongoing decline. There is risk of further chytridiomycosis outbreaks in new areas. The chytridiomycosis panzootic represents the greatest recorded loss of biodiversity attributable to a disease.
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
ighly virulent wildlife diseases are con-
tributing to Earth ’s sixth mass extinction 
H
(

1

). One of these is chytridiomycosis, which has caused mass amphibian die-offs worldwide (

2

, 

3

). Chytridiomycosis is caused by 

two fungal species, 
Batrachochŋtrium
dendrobatidis
[discovered in 1998, (

4

)] and 
B. salamandrioorans
[discovered in 2013, (

5

)]. Both 
Batrachochŋtrium
species likely originated in Asia, and their recent spread has been facilitated by humans (

5

, 

6

). 
Twenty years after the discovery of chytridio-
</title>
         <p>
mycosis, substantial research has yielded insights

about its epidemiology (

2

, 

3

, 

7

, 

8

), yet major

knowledge gaps remain. First, the global extent
of species declines associated with chytridio-
mycosis is unknown [see (

2
, 
9

) for initial assessments]. Second, although some regional declines are well studied, global spatial and temporal patterns of chytridiomycosis impacts remain poorly quantified. Third, ecological and life history traits have been examined only for a portion of declined 

species (

10

, 

11

). Finally, after initial declines, it is

</p>
         <p>
unknown what proportion of declined species
</p>
         <p>
exhibit recovery, stabilize at lower abundance, or
</p>
         <p>
continue to decline. Here we present a global
</p>
         <p>
epidemiological analysis of the spatial and tem-
</p>
         <p>
poral extent of amphibian biodiversity loss caused by chytridiomycosis.
</p>
         <p>

We conducted a comprehensive examination of evidence from multiple sources, including the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) Red List of Threatened Species (

12

), peerreviewed literature, and consultation with amphibian experts worldwide (data S1). We classified declined species into five decline-severity categories corresponding to reductions in abundance. Species declines were attributed to chytridiomycosis on the basis of diagnosis of infection causing mortalities in the wild or, if this was unavailable, evidence consistent with key epidemiological characteristics of this disease. Most evidence is retrospective because many species declined before the discovery of chytridiomycosis (data S1).

</p>
         <p>

We conservatively report that chytridiomycosis has contributed to the decline of at least 501 amphibian species (6.5% of described amphibian species; 

and 

). This represents the greatest documented loss of biodiversity attributable to a pathogen and places 
B. dendrobatidis
among the most destructive invasive species, comparable to rodents (threatening 420 species) and cats (

<tp:taxon-name>Felis</tp:taxon-name>
catus

) (threatening 430 species) (

13

). Losses associated with chytridiomycosis are orders of magnitude greater than for other high-profile wildlife pathogens, such as white-nose syndrome (
Pseudogŋmnoascus destructans
) in bats (six species) (

14

) or West Nile virus (
Flaoioirus
sp.) in birds (23 species) (

15

). Of the 501 declined amphibian species, 90 (18%) are confirmed or presumed extinct in the wild, with a further 124 (25%) experiencing a&gt;90% reduction in abundance (

and 

). The declines of all species except one (

<tp:taxon-name>Salamandra</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>salamandra</tp:taxon-name>

affected by 
B. salamandrioorans
) were attributed to 
B. dendrobatidis.

</p>
         <p>

Declines were proportional to taxonomic 
abundance, with anurans having 93% of severe
</p>
         <p>
1
Fenner School of Environment and Society, Australian National University, Canberra, ACT 2601, Australia. 
2
National Environmental 
Science
Programme, Threatened Species Recovery Hub, Canberra, ACT 2601, Australia. 
3
One Health Research Group, Melbourne Veterinary School, The University of Melbourne, Werribee, VIC 3030, Australia. 
4
Wildlife Health Ghent, Department of Pathology, Bacteriology, and Avian Diseases, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Ghent University, B-9820 Merelbeke, Belgium. 
5
Programa de Doctorado en Ciencias BiolÓgicas, Laboratorio de Biología Evolutiva, Pontificia Universidad CatÓlica de Chile, Avenida Libertador Bernardo O 
’
Higgins 340, Santiago, Chile. 
6
Grupo de InvestigaciÓn en Ecología y Biogeografía, Universidad de Pamplona, Barrio El Buque, Km 1, Vía a Bucaramanga, Pamplona, Colombia. 
7
Department of Biology, University of Puerto Rico, P.O. Box 23360, San Juan, Puerto Rico. 
8
LaboratÓrio de HistÓria Natural de Anfíbios Brasileiros (LaHNAB), Departamento de Biologia Animal, Instituto de Biologia, Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Campinas, Brazil. 
9
Department of Biological Sciences, Florida International University, Miami, FL 33199, USA. 
10
Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales-CSIC, C/ José Gutiérrez Abascal 2, Madrid 28006, Spain. 
11
MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis, School of Public Health, Imperial College London, London W2 1PG, UK. 
12
Department of Biological Sciences, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia. 
13
Instituto de InvestigaciÓn de Recursos BiolÓgicos Alexander von Humboldt, Sede Venado de Oro, Paseo Bolívar 16-20, Bogotá, Colombia. 
14
Institute of Zoology, Zoological Society London, Regents Park, London NW1 4RY, UK. 
15
Unit for Environmental Sciences and Management, North-West University, Potchefstroom 2520, South Africa. 
16
Smithsonian National Zoological Park and Conservation Biology Institute, Washington, DC 20008, USA. 
17
Universidad San Francisco de Quito USFQ, Colegio de Ciencias BiolÓgicas y Ambientales COCIBA, Instituto de Investigaciones BiolÓgicas y Ambientales BIOSFERA, Laboratorio de Biología Evolutiva, Campus Cumbayá, Quito, Ecuador. 
18
Centro de InvestigaciÓn de la Biodiversidad y Cambio Climático (BioCamb), Ingeniería en Biodiversidad y Cambio Climático, Facultad de Medio Ambiente, Universidad TecnolÓgica Indoamérica, Calle Machala y Sabanilla, Quito, Ecuador. 
19
Department of Biology, Colorado State University, Fort Collins, CO 80523, USA. 
20
Museum für Naturkunde, Leibniz Institute for Evolution and Biodiversity Science, Invalidenstr. 43, Berlin 10115, Germany. 
21
Honduras Amphibian Rescue and Conservation Center, Lancetilla Botanical Garden and Research Center, Tela, Honduras. 
22
The Conservation Agency, Jamestown, RI 0 2835, USA. 
23
AL Rae Centre for Genetics and Breeding, Massey University, Palmerston North 4442, New Zealand. 
24
School of Geography, Faculty of Forestry Engineering and Environmental Sciences, University of Los Andes, Merida, Venezuela. 
25
Department of Biology, University of Maryland, College Park, MD 20742, USA. 
26
Department of Biology, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA. 
27
Laboratorio de Sistemática e Historia Natural de Vertebrados. Facultad de Ciencias, Universidad de la República. Igua 4225, CP 11400, Montevideo, Uruguay. 
28
Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY 14853, USA. 
29
Zoo Atlanta, Atlanta, GA 30315, USA. 
30
School of Biological Sciences, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA 30332, USA. 
31
Departamento de Zoología, Instituto de Biología, Universidad Nacional AutÓnoma de México, Mexico City, México. 
32
Department of Biological Sciences, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA 15260, USA. 
33
Unidad de GenÓmica Avanzada (Langebio), Centro de InvestigaciÓn y de Estudios Avanzados del Instituto Politécnico Nacional, km 9.6 Libramiento Norte Carretera Irapuato-LeÓn, Irapuato, Guanajuato CP36824, México. 
34
Centro de InvestigaciÓn para la Sustentabilidad, Facultad de Ciencias de la Vida, Universidad Andres Bello, Santiago 8370251, Chile. 
35
Department of Biology, University of Nevada, Reno, NV 89557, USA. 
36
Zoo Miami, Conservation and Research Department, Miami, FL 33177, USA. 
37
Florida International University School of Earth, Environment, and Society, 11200 SW 8th St., Miami, FL 33199, USA. 
38
Department of Life Sciences, The Natural History Museum, London SW7 5BD, UK.

</p>
         <p>
*Corresponding author. Email: ben.scheele@anu.edu.au
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

declines (they comprise 89% of all amphibian species). Within anurans, there has been marked taxonomic clustering of declines, with 45% of severe declines and extinctions occurring in the Neotropical genera 
<tp:taxon-name>
Atelopus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Craugastor
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Telmatobius
</tp:taxon-name>
(

) (

16

). Chytridiomycosis is lethal to caecilians (

17

), but there have been no caecilian declines due to the disease,although data are limited. The capacity for 
B. dendrobatidis
to cause major declines is attributable to its maintenance of high pathogenicity (

2

, 

18

), broad host range (

8

), high transmission rate within and among host species (

2

, 

7

), and persistence in reservoir host species and the environment (

19

). For many species, chytridiomycosis is the principal driver of decline, exemplified by precipitous mass mortalities in undisturbed environments (

2

). In other species, chytridiomycosis acts in concert with habitat loss, altered climatic conditions, and invasive species to exacerbate species declines (

20

).

</p>
         <p>

Most amphibian declines have occurred in the tropics of 
Australia
, Mesoamerica, and South America (

), supporting the hypothesis that 
B. dendrobatidis
spread from Asia into the New World (

6

). Asia,Africa, Europe, and North America have had notably low numbers of declines attributable to chytridiomycosis, despite widespread occurrence of 
B. dendrobatidis
(

8

). Relative lack of documented declines could reflect less knowledge of amphibian populations in Asia and Africa (

3

, 

21

), early introduction and potential coevolution of amphibians and 
B. dendrobatidis
in parts of Africa and the Americas [e.g., (

22

)], the comparatively recent emergence of 
B. dendrobatidis
in Western and Northeast Africa (

6

), or unsuit- able conditions for chytridiomycosis. It remains unknown whether chytridiomycosis contributed to widespread amphibian declines reported in North America and Europe in the 1950s to 1960s (

3

, 

21

, 

22

) or current enigmatic salamander declines in eastern North America. Although the number of new declines has now eased (

), additional declines could occur if 
B. dendrobatidis
or 
B. salamandrioorans
are introduced into new areas, highly virulent lineages are introduced into areas that currently have less-virulent lineages (

6

), and/or environmental changes alter previously stable pathogen-host dynamics (

3

).

</p>
         <p>

Chytridiomycosis-associated declines peaked globally in the 1980s, between one and two decades before the discovery of the disease (

and table S1), and coincident with anecdotal recognition of amphibian declines in the 1990s (

23

). A second, smaller peak occurred in the early 2000s, associated with an increase in declines in western South America (

and fig. S1). Regionally, temporal patterns of decline are variable (fig. S1). For example, in some areas of South America and 
Australia
, declines commenced in the late 1970s (

2

, 

24

), whereas in other areas, declines started in the 2000s (

25

). 
B. dendrobatidis
is associated with ongoing declines in 197 assessed species. Ongoing declines after a transition to enzootic disease dynamics (

19

) might be driven by a lack of effective host defenses, maintenance of high pathogenicity (

18

), and presence of 
B. dendrobatidis
in amphibian and nonamphibian reservoirs (

7

, 

19

).

</p>
         <p>

We examined host life history traits and environmental conditions to understand why some species declined more severely than others, using multinomial logistic regression and accounting for the degree of evidence that chytridiomycosis was implicated in each species’ s decline (fig. S2 and table S2). Decline severity was greatest for larger-bodied species, those occurring in consistently wet regions, and those strongly associated with perennial aquatic habitats. These patterns are likely due to favorable environmental conditions for 
B. dendrobatidis
in wet regions (

7

), because the fungus dies when desiccated, as well as the general pattern of increased time to maturity in large-bodied amphibians resulting in less reproductive potential to offset mortality due to chytridiomycosis (

26

). Declines were less severe for species with large geographic and elevational ranges (

), potentially owing to the greater chance of their range encompassing environmental conditions unfavorable for 
B. dendrobatidis
(

3

) and/or information bias, because population extinctions can be assessed with more certainty in restricted-range species. Our results are consistent with previous studies that show that the risk of chytridiomycosis is associated with host aquatic habitat use, large body size, and narrow elevational range (

10

, 

11

).

</p>
         <p>

Encouragingly, of the 292 surviving species for which population trends are known, 60 (20%) have shown initial signs of recovery. However, recoveries generally represent small increases in abundance of individual populations, not complete recovery at the species level. Logistic regression showed the probability of recovery was lower for species that experienced more recent or more severe declines, for large-bodied or nocturnal species, and for species occurring at higher elevations (fig. S2 and table S3). When holding those predictors of recovery at their mean value, the chance of a species recovering from a severe (&gt;90%) decline was less than 
1 in
10. Low probability of recovery for high-elevation species might be related to suitable climatic conditions for fungal persistence as well as limited connectivity to source populations and/or longer host generation time (

26

). Some recoveries may be underpinned by selection for increased host resistance (

18

), whereas management of concurrent threats may have facilitated other recoveries (a promising avenue for conservation interventions) (

27

). Unfortunately, the remaining 232 species have shown no signs of recovery.

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>

The unprecedented lethality of a single disease affecting an entire vertebrate class highlights the threat from the spread of pathogens in a globalized world. Global trade has recreated a functional Pangaea for infectious diseases in wildlife, with far-reaching impacts on biodiversity (this study), livestock (

28

), and human health (

29

). Effective biosecurity and an immediate reduction in wildlife trade are urgently needed to reduce the risk of pathogen spread. As mitigation of chytridiomycosis in nature remains unproven (

30

), new research and intensive monitoring that utilizes emerging technologies are needed to identify mechanisms of species recovery and develop new mitigation actions for declining species.

</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
</p>
         <p>
REFERENCES AND NOTES

</p>
         <p>

1. 
M. C. Fisher
et al
., 

Nature

484

, 

186 
–
194

(
2012
).

</p>
         <p>

2. 
L. F. Skerratt
et al
., 

EcoHealth

4

, 

125 
–
134

(
2007
).

</p>
         <p>

3. 
K. R. Lips
, 

Philos. Trans. 
R. Soc
. 
Lond
. 
B Biol
. 
Sci
.


371

, 
20150465
(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

4. 
L. Berger
et al
., 

Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A
.


95

, 

9031 
–
9036

(
1998
).

</p>
         <p>

5. 
A. Martel
et al
., 

Science

346

, 

630 
–
631

(
2014
).

</p>
         <p>

6. 
S. J. O
’

Hanlon 
et al
.

, 

Science

360

, 

621 
–
627

(
2018
).

</p>
         <p>

7. 
T. Y. James
et al
., 

Ecol. Evol
.


5

, 

4079 
–
4097

(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

8. 
D. H. Olson
et al
., 

PLOS ONE

8

, e 
56802
(
2013
).

</p>
         <p>

9. 
S. N. Stuart
et al
., 

Science

306

, 


1783 
–
1786


(
2004
).

</p>
         <p>

10. 
J. Bielby
, 
N. Cooper
, 
A. A. Cunningham
, 
T. W. J. Garner
, 
A. Purvis
, 

Conserv. Lett
.


1

, 

82 
–
90

(
2008
).

</p>
         <p>

11. 
K. R. Lips
, 
J. D. Reeve
, 
L. R. Witters
, 

Conserv. Biol
.


17

, 


1078 
–
1088


(
2003
).

</p>
         <p>

12. 
The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species, Version 2017
-3 (
IUCN Species Survival Commission, Gland, Switzerland
); 
www.iucnredlist.org
.

</p>
         <p>

13. 
T. S.Doherty
, 
A.S.Glen
, 
D.G.Nimmo
, 
E. G.Ritchie
, 
C.R.Dickman
, 

Proc. Natl.Acad. Sci. U.S.A
.


113

, 

11261 
–
11265

(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

14. 
W. E. Thogmartin
et al
., 

Biol. Conserv
.


160

, 

162 
–
172

(
2013
).

</p>
         <p>

15. 
T. L. George
et al
., 

Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A
.


112

, 

14290 
–
14294

(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

16. 
E. La Marca
et al
., 

Biotropica

37

, 

190 
–
201

(
2005
).

</p>
         <p>

17. 
D. J. Gower
et al
., 

EcoHealth

10

, 

173 
–
183

(
2013
).

</p>
         <p>

18. 
J. Voyles
et al
., 

Science

359

, 


1517 
–
1519


(
2018
).

</p>
         <p>

19. 
A. Valenzuela-Sánchez
et al
., 

Proc. Biol. Sci
.


284

, 
20171176
(
2017
).

</p>
         <p>

20. 
D. B. Wake
, 
V. T. Vredenburg
, 

Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.
105

(
suppl.
1
), 

11466 
–
11473

(
2008
).

</p>
         <p>

21. 
J. E. Houlahan
, 
C. S. Findlay
, 
B. R. Schmidt
, 
A. H. Meyer
, 
S. L. Kuzmin
, 

Nature

404

, 

752 
–
755

(
2000
).

</p>
         <p>

22. 
B. L. Talley
, 
C. R. Muletz
, 
V. T. Vredenburg
, 
R. C. Fleischer
, 
K. R. Lips
, 

Biol. Conserv
.


182

, 

254 
–
261

(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

23. 
D. B. Wake
, 

Science

253

, 

860 
–
860

(
1991
).

</p>
         <p>

24. 
K. R. Lips
, 
J. Diffendorfer
, 
J. R. Mendelson III
, 
M. W. Sears
, 

PLOS Biol
.


6

, e 
72
(
2008
).

</p>
         <p>

25. 
A. Catenazzi
, 
E. Lehr
, 
L. O. Rodriguez
, 
V. T. Vredenburg
, 

Conserv. Biol
.


25

, 

382 
–
391

(
2011
).

</p>
         <p>

26. 
C. Morrison
, 
J. M. Hero
, 

J. Anim
. 
Ecol
.


72

, 

270 
–
279

(
2003
).

</p>
         <p>

27. 
R. A. Knapp
et al
., 

Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A
.


113

, 

11889 
–
11894

(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

28. 
A. K. Wiethoelter
, 
D. Beltrán-Alcrudo
, 
R. Kock
, 
S. M. Mor
, 

Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A
.


112

, 

9662 
–
9667

(
2015
).

</p>
         <p>

29. 
K. J. Olival
et al
., 

Nature

546

, 

646 
–
650

(
2017
).

</p>
         <p>

30. 
T. W. Garner
et al
., 

Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. 
B Biol
. 
Sci
.


371

, 
20160207
(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>
ACKNOWLEDGMENTS

</p>
         <p>

We thank M. Arellano, E. Courtois, A. Cunningham, K. Murray, S. Ron, R. Puschendorf, J. Rowley, and V. Vredenburg for discussions on amphibian declines. Comments from two anonymous reviewers greatly improved the manuscript. 
Funding:
B.C.S. and D.B.L. were supported by the Australian National Environmental Science Program. L.B., L.F.S., T.A.K., and B.C.S. were supported by the Australian Research Council (grants FT100100375, LP110200240, and DP120100811),


the NSW Office of Environment and Heritage, and the Taronga Conservation Science Initiative. S.C., W.B., A.M., and F.P. were supported by Research Foundation Flanders grants FWO3E001916 and FWO11ZK916N 
‐
11ZK918N and Ghent University grant BOF16/ 
GOA
/024. S.C. was supported by Research Foundation Flanders grant FWO16/PDO/019.

A.A.A. was supported by the Conservation Leadership Program (0621310), Vicerrectoría de Investigaciones, Universidad de Pamplona-Colombia, and Colciencias (1121-659-44242).
T.C. was supported by the Coordination for the Improvement

of Higher Education Personnel. A.C. was supported by the Amazon Conservation Association, the Amphibian Specialist Group, the Disney Worldwide Conservation Fund, the Eppley Foundation, the Mohammed bin Zayed Species Conservation Fund, the NSF, the Rufford Small Grants Foundation, and the Swiss National Foundation. I.D.l.R. was supported by the Spanish Government (CGL2014-56160-P). M.C.F. was supported by the NERC (NE/K014455/1), the Leverhulme Trust (RPG-2014-273), and the Morris Animal Foundation (D16ZO-022). S.V.F. was supported by the USFWS Wildlife without Borders (96200-0-G228), the AZA 
–
Conservation Endowment Fund (08-836), and the Conservation International Critically Endangered Species Fund. P.F.Á. was supported by a Postdoctoral Research fellowship from the Mexican Research Council (CONACYT, 171465). T.W.J.G. was supported by the NERC (NE/N009967/1 and NE/K 
012509
/1). J.M.G. was supported by the Universidad


San Francisco de Quito (collaboration grants 11164 and 5447). M.H. was supported by scholarships from the Elsa-Neumann- Foundation and the German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD). C.A.M. was supported by the Atkinson Center for a Sustainable Future and the Cornell Center for Vertebrate Genomics. G.P.-O. was supported by DGAPA-UNAM and CONACYT while on sabbatical at the University of 
Otago
, 
New Zealand
. C.L.R.-Z. was supported by the NSF (1660311). S.M.R. was supported by a CONACYT Problemas Nacionales grant (PDCPN 2015-721) and a UC Mexus-Conacy cooperative grant.

C.S.-A. was supported by the Chilean National Science and Technology Fund (Fondecyt no. 1181758). L.F.T. was supported
by the São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP 2016/25358-3)

and the National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq 
300896
/2016-6). J.V. was supported by the NSF (DEB- 1551488 and IOS-1603808).C.W. was supported by the South African National Research Foundation. 
Author contributions:


B.C.S., F.P., L.B., L.F.S., A.M., and S.C. conceived the research. B.C.S. collated the data and coordinated data collection. All authors contributed ideas and data. S.C. conducted the analysis, with input from B.C.S., F.P., A.M., C.N.F., and W.B. B.C.S., F.P., L.B., L.F.S., A.M., C.N.F., and S.C. wrote the paper with input from all authors. 
Competing interests:
The authors declare no competing interests. 
Data and materials availability:
All data are available in the manuscript or the supplementary materials.

</p>
         <p>
SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS

</p>
         <p>
www.sciencemag.org/content/363/6434/1459/suppl/DC1 Materials and Methods
</p>
         <p>

and S 

</p>
         <p>
Tables S1 to S4
</p>
         <p>

References (
31–47
)

</p>
         <p>
Data S1
</p>
         <p>
9 August 2018
; accepted 
6 February 2019
10.1126/science.aav0379

</p>
         <p>
Amphibian fungal panzootic causes catastrophic and ongoing loss of biodiversity

</p>
         <p>
Ben
C. Scheele, Frank Pasmans, Lee F. Skerratt, Lee Berger, An Martel, Wouter Beukema, Aldemar A. Acevedo, Patricia A. Burrowes, Tamilie Carvalho, Alessandro Catenazzi, Ignacio De la Riva, Matthew C. Fisher, Sandra V. Flechas, Claire N.

</p>
         <p>
Foster, Patricia Frías-Álvarez, Trenton W. J. Garner, Brian Gratwicke, Juan M. Guayasamin, Mareike Hirschfeld, Jonathan E. Kolby, Tiffany A. Kosch, Enrique La Marca, David B. Lindenmayer, Karen R. Lips, Ana V. Longo, Raúl Maneyro, Cait A.
</p>
         <p>
McDonald
, Joseph Mendelson III, Pablo Palacios-Rodriguez, Gabriela Parra-Olea, Corinne L. Richards-Zawacki, Mark-Oliver Rödel, Sean M. Rovito, Claudio Soto-Azat, Luís Felipe Toledo, Jamie Voyles, Ché Weldon, Steven M. Whitfield, Mark Wilkinson, Kelly R. Zamudio and Stefano Canessa

</p>
         <p>
Science
363
(6434), 
1459-1463
.

</p>
         <p>
DOI: 10.1126/science.aav0379
</p>
         <p>
The demise of amphibians?

</p>
         <p>

Rapid spread of disease is a hazard in our interconnected world. The chytrid fungus 
Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis
was identified in amphibian populations about 20 years ago and has caused death and species extinction at a global scale. Scheele 
et al.
found that the fungus has caused declines in amphibian populations everywhere except at its origin in Asia (see the Perspective by Greenberg and Palen). A majority of species and populations are still experiencing decline, but there is evidence of limited recovery in some species. The analysis also suggests some conditions that predict resilience.

</p>
         <p>
Science
, this issue p. 1459; see also p. 1386

</p>
         <p>
ARTICLE TOOLS

</p>
         <p>
http://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6434/1459
</p>
         <p>
SUPPLEMENTARY

</p>
         <p>
MATERIALS

</p>
         <p>

http://science.sciencemag.org/content/suppl/ 
2019/03/27
/363.6434.1459.DC1

</p>
         <p>
RELATED

</p>
         <p>
CONTENT

</p>
         <p>
http://science.sciencemag.org/content/sci/363/6434/1386.full
</p>
         <p>
REFERENCES

</p>
         <p>
This article cites 41 articles, 12 of which you can access for free http://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6434/1459#BIBL
</p>
         <p>
PERMISSIONS

</p>
         <p>
http://www.sciencemag.org/help/reprints-and-permissions
</p>
         <p>
Use of this article is subject to the Terms of Service
</p>
         <p>
Science
(print ISSN 0036-8075; online ISSN 1095-9203) is published by the American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1200 
New York
Avenue NW, 
Washington
, DC 20005. 2017 © The Authors, some rights reserved; exclusive

</p>
         <p>
licensee
American Association for the Advancement of Science. No claim to original 
U.S.
Government Works. The title 
Science
is a registered trademark of AAAS.

</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
