<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nature</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2096-0</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Late Cretaceous neornithine from Europe illuminates the origins of crown birds</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>18</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Article

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Late Cretaceous neornithine from Europe illuminates the origins of crown birds
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

https://doi.org/ 
10.1038/s41586-020-2096-0
Received: 19 November 2019 Accepted: 4 February 2020 Published online: 

18 March 
2020

Check for updates 
Daniel J. Field

✉, 
Juan Benito

, 

, 
Albert Chen

, 

, 
John W. M. Jagt

&amp; 
Daniel T. Ksepka

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>

Our understanding of the earliest stages of crown bird evolution is hindered by an 
exceedingly sparse avian fossil record from the Mesozoic era. The most ancient
phylogenetic divergences among crown birds are known to have occurred in the 

Cretaceous period 

– 

, but stem-lineage representatives of the deepest subclades of crown birds—Palaeognathae (ostriches and kin), Galloanserae (landfowl and waterfowl) and Neoaves (all other extant birds)—are unknown from the Mesozoic era. As a result, key questions related to the ecology 

, 

, biogeography 

, 

, 

and divergence times 

, 

– 

of ancestral crown birds remain unanswered. Here we report a new Mesozoic fossil that occupies a position close to the last common ancestor of Galloanserae and fills a key phylogenetic gap in the early evolutionary history of crown birds 

, 

.

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 

gen. et sp. nov.
, from the Maastrichtian age of Belgium (66.8–66.7 million years ago), is represented by a nearly complete, three-dimensionally preserved skull and associated postcranial elements. The fossil represents one of the only well-supported crown birds from the Mesozoic era



, and is the first Mesozoic crown bird with well-represented cranial remains.

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibits a previously undocumented combination of galliform (landfowl)-like and anseriform (waterfowl)-like features, and its presence alongside a previously reported
Ichthyornis
-like taxon from the same locality


provides direct evidence of the co-occurrence of crown birds and avialan stem birds. Its occurrence in the Northern Hemisphere challenges biogeographical hypotheses of a Gondwanan origin of crown birds



, and its relatively small size and possible littoral ecology may corroborate proposed ecological filters 

, 

, 



that influenced the persistence of crown birds through the end-Cretaceous mass extinction. By any measure,crown birds (
<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
) are among the most diverse and conspicuous of the extant tetrapods,yet their early evolutionary history is poorly understood. Apart from birds,all major groups of extant tetrapods—lissamphibians 


, squamates 

, turtles 

, mammals


and crocodylians 

—are well-known from pre-Cenozoic crown-group fossils. By contrast, the Mesozoic record of well-supported crown birds is restricted to a single latest Maastrichtian taxon, 
Vegavis iaai

. Several fragmentary Mesozoic fossils have at times been referred to 

<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>

, although the justifications for such assignments are questionable and these records have not unambiguously withstood re-evaluation 

, 

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
We report a new crown bird from the Late Cretaceous of Belgium.
The fossil is between 66.8 and 66.7 million years old—making it the oldest unambiguous crown bird fossil yet discovered—and provides important insight into the extent of Mesozoic neornithine diversifica- tion before the end-Cretaceous mass-extinction event,66.02 million 
years ago (Ma)


. Uniquely among crown birds from the Mesozoic and earliest Palaeocene, the new fossil includes a nearly complete, three-

dimensionally preserved skull,yielding direct insights into the nature of the crown bird skull early in neornithine evolutionary history.The 


specimen exhibits a previously unseen combination of features that are diagnostic of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Anseriformes</tp:taxon-name>
,which together form the crown cladeGalloanserae—one of the most deeply diverging clades of crown birds and the sister group to the hyperdiverse extant clade Neo-

<tp:taxon-name>aves</tp:taxon-name>

– 


. Our most parsimonious phylogenetic hypothesis suggests that the fossil sits on the stem lineage of Galloanserae,which would make it the only stem galloanseran yet known and would fill a conspicuous phylogenetic gap in the neornithine fossil record.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Systematic palaeontology
</p>
         <p>
Avialae Gauthier,1986
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Neornithes Gadow,1892
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Neognathae Pycraft,1900
</p>
         <p>
Pangalloanserae Gauthier and de Queiroz,2001
</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Dromaeosauridae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Troodontidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Aves sensu Gauthier,1986</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Anser anser
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Gallus gallus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Passer domesticus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
A.maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteria
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Asteria</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Anatidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Presbyornithidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Anseriformes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
A. maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Anseriformes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Alectura
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Late Cretaceous neornithine from Europe illuminates the origins of crown birds</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2096-0</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFA5A453FC5CFFEC356DAA328E07DF59</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2096-0</pub-id>
               <source>Nature</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen.et sp.nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>

Remarks.We use Avialae to refer to theropods crownward of 
<tp:taxon-name>Dromaeosauridae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Troodontidae</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
is equivalent to the bird crown



group (
<tp:taxon-name>Aves sensu Gauthier,1986</tp:taxon-name>
23

).Pangalloanserae defines the most


inclusive clade including 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anser anser
</tp:taxon-name>
and
<tp:taxon-name>
Gallus gallus
</tp:taxon-name>
but not
<tp:taxon-name>
Passer domesticus
</tp:taxon-name>
(that is,the galloanseran total group).Further phylogenetic definitions are presented in the Supplementary Information.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>
Etymology.
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
from the name of the Titan goddess
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteria
</tp:taxon-name>
and the Greek
ornis

for bird.In Greek mythology 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteria</tp:taxon-name>
is the goddess of falling stars and transforms herself into a quail—attributes that are reflected by both the impending Cretaceous–Palaeogene(K–Pg) asteroid impact and the galloanseran affinities of

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
The specific epithet
<tp:taxon-name>
maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
reflects the provenance of the holotype—the Maastricht Formation (the type locality of the Late Cretaceous Maastrichtian stage).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>
Holotype
. Natuurhistorisch Museum Maastricht (
NHMM
) 
2013 008
, a nearly complete, articulated skull including mandibles and associated postcranial remains preserved in four blocks (

, Extended Data 

;see Supplementary Information for videos,character information,measurements,additional description and discussion). Preserved elements include the premaxillae,maxillae,nasals,frontals, laterosphenoid,basisphenoid,mesethmoid, left quadrate,left jugal, right palatine and lower jaws.Associated postcranial elements include incomplete femora,tibiotarsi,tarsometatarsus and radius.

</p>
               <p>

Locality and age. 
CBR-Romontbos Quarry,Eben-Emael,Liège
, 
Belgium
. 
Valkenburg Member(66.8–66.7million years old
24

), Maastricht Formation,Late Maastrichtian,Cretaceous.Additional details regarding the locality and stratigraphic setting are presented in the Supplementary Information.

</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>
Diagnosis.
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
is unique among known taxa in exhibiting caudally pointed nasals that overlie the frontals and meet at the midline of the skull,and a slightly rounded, unhooked tip of the premaxilla. Additional character combinations from phylogenetic analyses that dif- ferentiate
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
are presented in the Supplementary Information.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description

</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is a small pan-galloanseran, with an estimated mean body mass from hindlimb scaling regressions of 394 g (around the 21st percentile among extant Galloanserae

25

; Extended Data 

).Complete measurements of NHMM 2013 008 are provided in the Supplementary Information.

</p>
            <p>

Most major cranial components are in their original anatomical positions.The general appearance of the premaxillary beak resembles that of extant 
<tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
,particularly in its gently down-curved tip and delicate construction,with no ossified joints among the rostral components 

26

. The contralateral frontal processes of the premaxillae are unfused along their length,and the premaxillae and nasals are unfused at both their tomial and narial contacts. The beak tip is unhooked, which distinguishes

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

from most Galloanserae except certain 
<tp:taxon-name>Anatidae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Presbyornithidae</tp:taxon-name>
.

</p>
            <p>

The skull lacks a distinct nasofrontal hinge.As such,the architecture of this region more closely resembles that of extant 
<tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
than 
<tp:taxon-name>Anseriformes</tp:taxon-name>
.At the midpoint of the orbits the frontals are constricted,yielding an hourglass-shaped cranial roof with wider rostral and caudal extremities. Indorsolateralview,therightpostorbitalprocesssweepsstronglyventrally beforedeflectingrostrallytodefinepartoftheventralmarginoftheorbit.

</p>
            <p>
The left quadrate is well-preserved in three dimensions and is generally similar to the quadrate of the fossil pan-anseriform
<tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
27
</p>
            <p>

(

, Extended Data 

). The prootic and squamosal heads are divided by a well-developed incisure,as in almost all Neognathae;this contrasts with the condition in crownward stem birds such as

Ichthyornis
, 

in which the division between these condyles is poorly marked,and Palaeognathae,in which the condyles merge into a single head.Two pneumatic foramina pierce the quadrate:the foramen pneumaticum rostromediale and the foramen pneumaticum basiorbitale.A tuberculum subcapitulare is moderately developed on the lateral face of the otic process.This characteristic has been considered a derived feature of Galloanserae 

27

; however,it is present in many Neoaves,and given its absence in Palaeognathae and

Ichthyornis
it might instead represent a synapomorphy of Neognathae.The cotyla quadratojugalis of the quadrate is fairly deep,with a complete,un-notched rim.The pterygoid articulation is more widely separated dorsally from the mandibular condyle than in most extant Galloanserae,and is very similar to that of
<tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
As in all known Galloanserae,the mandible of
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibits two cotylae for articulation with the bicondylar quadrate and a bladelike retroarticular process.This process is strongly hooked,and in its shape and proportions bears a strong resemblance to the condition in the pan-anseriform
Anatalavis oxfordi

(

, Extended Data 

). An elongate,slightly dorsally oriented processus medialis is preserved on the right jaw,as in all Galloanserae.

</p>
            <p>
The left distal femur is well-preserved,exhibiting a medial condyle with a bluntly angular profile between the articular surface of the condyle and its cranial margin. A detailed anatomical description of the skull and postcranium is provided in the Supplementary Information.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Phylogenetic analysis

</title>
         <p>
We investigated the phylogenetic position of
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

under alternative optimality criteria,with and without molecular scaffolds 


, 


, using a matrix of 39 taxa and 297 characters modified from previous studies 


, 


(
Fig. 3
, Extended Data Fig. 9; see Methods and Supplementary Information).We added recently described taxa such as

Protodontopteryx


, and revised the scorings for several taxa,including

Anatalavis
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
and
Conflicto
. 
Our analyses were uniformly consistent with a position of
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
near the last common ancestor of Galloanserae.Under parsimony we recovered a single most parsimonious tree with
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
as the sister taxon to crown Galloanserae,and analyses under a tip-dated Bayesian framework recovered
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
as the stemward-most pan-galliform.We are cautious in the interpretation of this result because few unambiguous synapomorphies can be optimized in support of a sister group relationship between
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
to the exclusion of 
<tp:taxon-name>Anseriformes</tp:taxon-name>
. The few potential synapomorphies for such a clade that are observable in

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
also occur in early pan-anseriforms such as
Conflicto
(see Methods and Supplementary Information).Likewise,only one or two steps are required to move
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
to an alternate placement as a stem anseriform or stem galliform,respectively,in the parsimony analysis.The difficulty in resolving the precise placement of the fossil, as well as its notable combination of anseriform- and galliform-like anatomical features, is consistent with
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

occupying a short phylogenetic branch proximal to the most recent common ancestor of Galloanserae—one of the deepest nodes in the neornithine tree of life 

.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>
Discussion

</title>
         <p>
The latest Cretaceous fossil record of crown birds is extremely sparse.
</p>
         <p>
Other than
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
, 
Vegavis
</tp:taxon-name>
iaai

(dated to around 66.5 Ma 

) is the only Cretaceous neornithine known from a partial skeleton to have been thoroughly examined 

. However, its phylogenetic position is debated 

—studies have suggested variable positions within Neognathae 


, 

, 

– 


and even outside 
<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>

—emphasizing the importance of obtaining new information on

Vegavis
and Mesozoic crown birds in general. Under parsimony,we recovered
Vegavis

as the sister taxon to 
<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
(that is,the crownward-most stem bird),whereas under a Bayesian framework

Vegavis
was recovered in an unresolved position at the base of Neognathae.
</p>
         <p>
Galloanseran cranial anatomy

</p>
         <p>
All discernible character evidence is consistent with neornithine (crown
</p>
         <p>
bird) affinities for
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 

and supports its hierarchical placement within 
<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
(local synapomorphies such as a toothless beak;no coronoid bone;a bony mandibular symphysis), crown Neognathae (for example, palatine–premaxilla contact;an incisure between the prootic and squamosal cotylae of the quadrate) and Pangalloanserae (for example,a dorsoventrally deep and lateromedially compressed maxillary process of the premaxilla;palatines that are long, thin and widely separated rostrally;a bicondylar mandibular process of the quadrate;a long, dorsally oriented internal articular process of the mandible;a retroarticular process that is long, curving and strongly compressed lateromedially) 


– 


(
Fig. 1
). Given the scarcity of threedimensional skulls from the earliest stages of the crown bird radiation,

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

provides a key reference point for understanding how the marked variability of the crown bird skull came to be, and will inform estimates of early neornithine cranial disparity and rates of phenotypic evolution 


, 


.

</p>
         <p>
With the exception of the autapomorphic morphology of the posterior nasals,almost none of the discernible cranial anatomy of
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

falls outside of the range of variation that is exhibited by extant galloanserans,despite the widely differing cranial morphology of extant 
<tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Anseriformes</tp:taxon-name>

. Although galloanseran monophyly is now widely accepted(and was first suggested on the basis of basicranial morphology as early as the mid-nineteenth century 

), the validity of this clade has been questioned 


, 


,with some authors listing numerous anatomical dissimilarities between these groups 

.Notably,

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

reveals a previously undocumented combination of ‘galliform’ features,such as weakly fused rostral elements and rostrally forked nasals, and ‘anseriform’ features,such as a rostrally projecting postorbital process and a tall and strongly hooked retroarticular process (
Fig. 1
, Extended Data 
Figs. 1–6
)—revealing the plesiomorphic condition of the galloanseran skull.The fact that such distinctive features of extant galloanseran anatomy are observable in this approximately66.7-millionyear-old fossil corroborates the hypothesis of beak shape canalization arising early in,or predating,crown bird evolutionary history 


, 


, emphasizing the modular nature of the skull and bill of crown birds 

.

</p>
         <p>

Biogeography and the origin of 
<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>

Much of the species-level and higher clade diversity of extant birds is confined to vestiges of Gondwana,which suggests that crown birds originated in the Southern Hemisphere 

. Reports of Mesozoic crown

</p>
         <p>

birds in Antarctica appear to support this hypothesis 


, 


. However,the Palaeogene fossil record provides many examples of crown bird fossils that are well outside of the ranges of their closest extant relatives 


, 

, 

, 


, which casts some doubt on the hypothesis of a Gondwanan cradle for crown bird evolution and suggests that factors such as Cenozoic climate shifts may have overprinted ancestral neornithine biogeographical patterns 


, 


. As the oldest and one of the most deeply diverging crown birds yet identified,

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

provides conclusive Mesozoic evidence of 
<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
in the Northern Hemisphere,emphasizing that the discovery of further Mesozoic fossils will be necessary to convincingly identify the neornithine centre of origin.

</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
provides a firm calibration point for the minimum age of divergence of the major bird clades Galloanserae and Neoaves.We recommend that a minimum age of66.7 million years is assigned to this pivotal neornithine node in future divergence time studies,reflecting the youngest possible age of the
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

holotype including geochronological uncertainty.The paucity of crown bird remains from the Mesozoic is such that our current understanding of the deepest stages of the neornithine evolutionary timescale depends on the outcome of molecular divergence time analyses 

. However,molecular-clock-based estimates for the deepest divergences of crown birds differ markedly depending on factors such as node calibration decisions and alternative parameterizations of statistical probability distributions 


, 


. Furthermore, such estimates could be affected by the interplay of nucleotide substitution rates and deep-time directional selectivity on life history variables and body size, leading to disagreement as to the extent of neornithine survivorship across the end-Cretaceous mass-extinction event 


– 


. We suggest that the terminal-Cretaceous age and rootward phylogenetic position of

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

are consistent with a limited diversification of crown birds in the Late Cretaceous, and restricted survivorship of crown birds across the end-Cretaceous mass-extinction event.This interpretation is in line with the emerging consensus from molecular divergence time studies 


, 

, 

– 


, as well as evidence for a mass extinction of stem birds at the K–Pg boundary 

. Furthermore, the oldest credible occurrences of crown birds in both the Northern(this study) and Southern Hemispheres 

derive from terminal Mesozoic sediments,which might confirm the recently proposed null expectation of a rapid evolutionary transition between stem birds and crown birds 

. The occurrence of a large

Ichthyornis

-like avialan 

from the same horizon and quarry as the

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
holotype (with temporal separation amounting to no more than tens of thousands of years;see Supplementary Information) provides evidence of crown birds and avialan stem birds occurring in the same environment in the immediate lead-up to the K–Pg mass extinction.
</p>
         <p>

Considerable discussion has focused on hypothetical scenarios of neornithine survivorship across the end-Cretaceous mass extinction 

. A consensus hypothesis is emerging in which survivors are thought to have exhibited a suite of features that proved selectively beneficial through the extinction event,including a relatively small body size to limit total metabolic requirements 

, flying ability and a non-arboreal ecology 


, 


; an advanced digestive system 

; and dietary flexibility to capitalize on sparse resources that might have included insects and seeds 

. However, owing to the scarcity of latest Cretaceous and earliest Palaeocene neornithine fossils,little direct fossil evidence can be applied to this question.

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

could therefore provide the best direct insight into the probable biology of neornithine K–Pg survivors, and—notably—no discernible aspects of its palaeobiology are inconsistent with these hypothetical expectations. Indeed, its relatively small size (less than50% of the median body size of known latest Maastrichtian avialans 

), narrow and elongate hindlimbs (Supplementary

</p>
         <p>

Information)and provenance from nearshore marine sediments might indicate a littoral ecology,which could validate an ecological—though not a phylogenetic—prediction of the hypothesis of ‘shorebird’-like origins for much of crown bird diversity 

.

</p>
         <p>
Fossils that clarify the Mesozoic origins of the extant bird radiation are among the rarest and most sought-after palaeontological discoveries.
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
helps to fill a phylogenetic and stratigraphic gap between the most crownward-known stem birds and the rich Cenozoic neornithine fossil record.This record of a Mesozoic neornithine from Europe provides key insights into the origin of extant bird diversity, and shows that future discoveries of even earlier Cretaceous neornithines could be as likely to derive from the Northern as the Sourthern Hemisphere.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Online content

</title>
         <p>
Any methods,additional references,Nature Research reporting summaries, source data, extended data, supplementary information, acknowledgements,peer review information;details of author con- tributions and competing interests;and statements of data and code availability are available at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2096-0.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1. 
Prum, R. O.
et al. 
A comprehensive phylogeny of birds (Aves) using targeted nextgeneration DNA sequencing
. 

Nature


526

, 
569–573
(
2015
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
2. 
Jarvis, E.D.
et al. 
Whole-genome analyses resolve early branches in the tree of life of modern birds
. 

Science


346

, 
1320–1331
(
2014
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
3. 
Claramunt,S.
&amp; 
Cracraft,J.
A new time tree reveals Earth history’s imprint on the evolution of modern birds
. 

Sci. Adv
.


1

, e 
1501005
(
2015
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
4. 
Field,D.J.
et al. 
Early evolution of modern birds structured by global forest collapse at the end-Cretaceous mass extinction
. 

Curr.Biol
.


28

, 
1825–1831
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
5. 
Larson, D. W.
, 
Brown,C.M.
&amp; 
Evans,D.C.
Dental disparity and ecological stability in bird-like dinosaurs prior to the end-Cretaceous mass extinction
. 

Curr. Biol
.


26

, 
1325–1333
(
2016
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
6. 
Mayr,G.
Avian higher level biogeography:Southern Hemispheric origins or Southern Hemispheric relicts?

J. Biogeogr
.


44

, 
956–958
(
2017
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
7. 
Saupe,E. E.
et al. 
Climatic shifts drove major contractions in avian latitudinal distributions throughout the Cenozoic
. 

Proc.Natl Acad.Sci. USA


116

, 
12895–12900
(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
8. 
Ksepka,D. T.
&amp; 
Phillips,M. J.
Avian diversification patterns across the K–Pg boundary: influence of calibrations,datasets,and model misspecification
. 

Ann. Mo. Bot. Gard
.


100

, 
300–328
(
2015
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
9. 
Berv,J.S.
&amp; 
Field,D. J.
Genomic signature of an avian Lilliput effect across the K–Pg extinction
. 

Syst.Biol
.


67

, 
1–13
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
10. 
Field,D.J.
et al. 
Timing the extant avian radiation:the rise of modern birds,and the importance of modeling molecular rate variation
. 

PeerJ Preprints


7

, e 
27521
v1 (
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
11. 
Mayr,G.

Avian Evolution

(
Wiley
, 
2016
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
12. 
Clarke, J.A.
, 
Tambussi,C.P.
, 
Noriega, J.I.
, 
Erickson,G.M.
&amp; 
Ketcham,R. A.
Definitive fossil evidence for the extant avian radiation in the Cretaceous
. 

Nature


433

, 
305–308
(
2005
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
13. 
Dyke,G. J.
et al. 
Europe’s last Mesozoic bird
. 

Naturwissenschaften


89

, 
408–411
(
2002
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
14. 
Xing,L.
, 
Stanley,E. L.
, 
Bai, M.
&amp; 
Blackburn,D. C.
The earliest direct evidence of frogs in wet tropical forests from Cretaceous Burmese amber
. 

Sci. Rep
.


8

, 
8770
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
15. 
Simões,T.R.
et al. 
The origin of squamates revealed by a Middle Triassic lizard from the Italian Alps
. 

Nature


557

, 
706–709
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
16. 
Evers,S. W.
, 
Barrett,P. M.
&amp; 
Benson, R. B.J.

Anatomy of 
Rhinochelys pulchriceps
(Protostegidae) and marine adaptation during the early evolution of chelonioids

. 

PeerJ


7

, e 
6811
(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
17. 
Bi, S.
et al. 
An Early Cretaceous eutherian and the placental–marsupial dichotomy
. 

Nature


558

, 
390–395
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
18. 
Lee,M. S.Y.
&amp; 
Yates,A. M.
Tip-dating and homoplasy:reconciling the shallow molecular divergences of modern gharials with their long fossil record
. 

Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B


285

, 
20181071
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
19. 
Hope, S.
in 

Mesozoic Birds: Above the Heads of Dinosaurs

(eds 
Chiappe,L. M.
&amp; 
Witmer, L. M.
) 
339–388
(
Univ.California Press
, 
2002
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
20. 
Longrich, N. R.
, 
Tokaryk,T.
&amp; 
Field, D.J.
Mass extinction of birds at the Cretaceous– Paleogene (K–Pg) boundary
. 

Proc.Natl Acad.Sci. USA


108

, 
15253–15257
(
2011
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
21. 
Mayr,G.

Paleogene Fossil Birds

(
Springer
, 
2009
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
22. 
Clyde, W.C.
, 
Ramezani, J.
, 
Johnson,K.R.
, 
Bowring,S.A.
&amp; 
Jones,M. M.
Direct highprecision U–Pb geochronology of the end-Cretaceous extinction and calibration of Paleocene astronomical timescales
. 

Earth Planet. Sci.Lett
.


452

, 
272–280
(
2016
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
23. 
Gauthier, J.A.
&amp; 
de Queiroz,K.
in 

New Perspectives on the Origin and Early Evolution of Birds: Proceedings of the International Symposium in Honor of John H. Ostrom

(eds 
Gauthier, J.
&amp; 
Gall,L. F.
) 
7–41
(
Peabody Museum of Natural History,Yale University
, 
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
24. 
Keutgen,N.
A bioclast-based astronomical timescale for the Maastrichtian in the type area (southeast Netherlands, northeast Belgium) and stratigraphic implications:the legacy of PJ Felder
. 

Neth. J. Geosci
.


97

, 
229–260
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
25. 
Field,D. J.
, 
Lynner,C.
, 
Brown,C.
&amp; 
Darroch, S. A.F.
Skeletal correlates for body mass estimation in modern and fossil flying birds
. 

PLoS One


8

, e 
82000
(
2013
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
26. 
Olson,S.L.
&amp; 
Feduccia,A.

Presbyornis
and the origin of the Anseriformes (Aves: Charadriomorphae)

. 

Smithson. 
Contrib.Zool
.


323

, 
1–24
(
1980
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
27. 
Elzanowski,A.
&amp; 
Stidham,T.A.

Morphology of the quadrate in the Eocene anseriform 
Presbyornis
and extant galloanserine birds

. 

J. Morphol
.


271

, 
305–323
(
2010
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
28. 
Worthy, T.H.
, 
Degrange, F.J.
, 
Handley,W.D.
&amp; 
Lee,M. S.Y.
The evolution of giant flightless birds and novel phylogenetic relationships for extinct fowl (Aves, Galloanseres)
. 

R. Soc. Open Sci
.


4

, 
170975
(
2017
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
29. 
Tambussi,C.P.
, 
Degrange,F. J.
, 
De Mendoza,R.S.
, 
Sferco,E.
&amp; 
Santillana,S.
A stem anseriform from the early Palaeocene of Antarctica provides new key evidence in the early evolution of waterfowl
. 

Zool. J.Linn. Soc
.


186

, 
673–700
(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
30. 
Mayr,G.
, 
De Pietri,V.L.
, 
Love,L.
, 
Mannering,A.
&amp; 
Scofield,R.P.
Oldest, smallest and phylogenetically most basal pelagornithid,from the early Paleocene of New Zealand, sheds light on the evolutionary history of the largest flying birds
. 

Pap. Palaeontol
.

https:// doi.org/10.1002/spp2.1284
(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
31. 
Budd,G.E.
&amp; 
Mann,R.P.
The dynamics of stem and crown groups
. 

Sci. Adv
.


6

, eaaz 
1626
(
2020
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
32. 
Ksepka, D.T.
&amp; 
Clarke,J.
Phylogenetically vetted and stratigraphically constrained fossil calibrations within Aves
. 

Palaeontologia Electronica


18

, 18.1.3FC (
2015
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
33. 
Mayr,G.
, 
De Pietri,V.L.
, 
Scofield,R. P.
&amp; 
Worthy,T.H.
On the taxonomic composition and phylogenetic affinities of the recently proposed clade Vegaviidae Agnolín et al., 2017 – neornithine birds from the Upper Cretaceous of the Southern Hemisphere
. 

Cretaceous Research


86

, 
178–185
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
34. 
Clarke,J. A.
et al. 
Fossil evidence of the avian vocal organ from the Mesozoic
. 

Nature


538

, 
502–505
(
2016
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
35. 
Agnolín,F.L.
, 
Egli,F. B.
, 
Chatterjee,S.
, 
Marsà,J.A.G.
&amp; 
Novas, F.E.
Vegaviidae, a new clade of southern diving birds that survived the K/T boundary
. 

Naturwissenschaften


104

, 
87
(
2017
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
36. 
O’Connor,J.K.
, 
Chiappe,L. M.
&amp; 
Bell, A.
in 

Living Dinosaurs: The Evolutionary History of Modern Birds

(eds 
Dyke,G.
&amp; 
Kaiser,G.
) 
39–114
(
Wiley-Blackwell
, 
2011
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
37. 
Cracraft,J.
in 

The Phylogeny and Classification of the Tetrapods

Vol. 1 (ed. 
Benton,M. J.
) 
339–361
(
Oxford Univ.Press
, 
1988
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
38. 
Livezey,B.C.

A phylogenetic analysis of basal Anseriformes,the fossil 
Presbyornis
, and the interordinal relationships of waterfowl

. 

Zool. J. Linn. Soc
.


121

, 
361–428
(
1997
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
39. 
Cracraft,J.
&amp; 
Clarke,J.
The basal clades of modern birds
.In 

New Perspectives on the Origin and Early Evolution of Birds: Proceedings of the International Symposium in Honor of John H. Ostrom

(eds 
Gauthier,J.
&amp; 
Gall,L. F.
) 
143–156
(
Peabody Museum of Natural History,Yale University
, 
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
40. 
Felice, R. N.
&amp; 
Goswami,A.
Developmental origins of mosaic evolution in the avian cranium
. 

Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA


115

, 
555–560
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
41. 
Field,D. J.
Endless skulls most beautiful
. 

Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA


115

, 
448–450
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
42. 
Huxley,T.H.
On the classification of birds;and on the taxonomic value of the modifications of certain of the cranial bones observable in that class
. 

Proc. Zool.Soc. Lond
. 
1867

, 
415–472
(
1867
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
43. 
Ericson,P.G.P.
Systematic relationships of the Palaeogene family Presbyornithidae (Aves: Anseriformes)
. 

Zool. J.Linn. Soc
.


121

, 
429–483
(
1997
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
44. 
Cooney,C. R.
et al. 
Mega-evolutionary dynamics of the adaptive radiation of birds
. 

Nature


542

, 
344–347
(
2017
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
45. 
Bright, J.A.
, 
Marugán-Lobón,J.
, 
Rayfield,E. J.
&amp; 
Cobb,S.N.
The multifactorial nature of beak and skull shape evolution in parrots and cockatoos (Psittaciformes)
. 

BMC Evol.Biol
.


19

, 
104
(
2019
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
46. 
Field,D. J.
&amp; 
Hsiang,A.Y.
A North American stem turaco,and the complex biogeographic history of modern birds
. 

BMC Evol. Biol
.


18

, 
102
(
2018
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
47. 
Mourer-Chauviré,C.
Les oiseaux fossiles des phosphorites du Quercy (Éocène supérieur a Oligocène supérieur):implications paléobiogéographiques
. 

Geobios


15

, 
413–426
(
1982
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
48. 
Mayr,G.
Two-phase extinction of “Southern Hemispheric” birds in the Cenozoic of Europe and the origin of the Neotropic avifauna
. 

Palaeobiodivers.Palaeoenviron
.


91

, 
325–333
(
2011
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
49. 
O’Connor,J.K.
&amp; 
Zhou, Z.
The evolution of the modern avian digestive system:insights from paravian fossils from the Yanliao and Jehol biotas
. 

Palaeontology


63

, 
13–27
(
2020
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
50. 
Feduccia, A.
Explosive evolution in tertiary birds and mammals
. 

Science


267

, 
637–638
(
1995
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>
Preparation and imaging of specimens

</title>
         <p>
Methods
</p>
         <p>
Owing to the fragility of the
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
holotype,only minor mechanical preparation was performed to reduce the volume of rock matrix for improved computed tomography(CT)scans.Scans of NHMM 2013 008, UW
<tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
specimens and all extant taxa were performed at the Cambridge Biotomography Centre (CBC).
<tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
UMNH.VP.29030 and UMNH.VP.29031 were scanned at the small-animal-imaging core research facilities of the University of Utah Health Science Cores.
Anatalavis oxfordi
NHMUK PV A5922 was scanned at the Natural History Museum London.All scanned material was digitally segmented and rendered using VGStudio Max 3.3.0. Full CT scanning details are provided in the Supplementary Information.
</p>
         <p>
Phylogenetic analyses

</p>
         <p>
To assess the phylogenetic position of
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 

we scored it into a considerably modified version of a recent phylogenetic matrix that targets deep neornithine divergences and focuses on Galloanserae 
29
, which in turn was modified from a previous study 
28
. We also added the crownward stem bird

Ichthyornis dispar

as an outgroup taxon to improve the inference of character polarity at the base of crown birds,on the basis of direct examination of specimens and previously published literature 
51,52
. We scored the stem galliform

<tp:taxon-name>
Gallinuloides wyomingensis
</tp:taxon-name>

through direct examination and reference to published descriptions 
53,54
, and scored the pelagornithids

Protodontopteryx ruthae

30
and

<tp:taxon-name>
Pelagornis chilensis
</tp:taxon-name>
55
on the basis of published literature. The phylogenetic position of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pelagornithidae</tp:taxon-name>
is debated,and they have been posited as early-diverging pan-neognaths or pan-galloanserans in previous studies 
56,57
. A right humerus and ulna associated with the

Protodontopteryx

holotype are of questionable assignment to the taxon 
30
and were therefore disregarded for the purposes of scoring.Additional details of matrix modifications and taxon sampling are presented in the Supplementary Information.

</p>
         <p>

Maximum parsimony analyses were conducted in TNT v.1.5 
58
. After increasing the maximum number of trees to 10,000,a new technology search was run in which a minimum length tree was found in 10 replicates and default parameters were set for sectorial search,ratchet, tree drift and tree fusion.After this,the maximum number of trees was set to 100 and a traditional search with default parameters was run on the trees in RAM to explore treespace more extensively.Absolute bootstrap frequencies were obtained from 1,000 replicates under a traditional search with default parameters.The tree length induced by alternative phylogenetic topologies was evaluated by unchecking the ‘lock trees’ option in TNT and manually moving branches to alternative phylogenetic positions.

</p>
         <p>

Bayesian phylogenetic analyses were conducted in MrBayes 
59
using the CIPRES Science Gateway 
60
. Data were analysed under the Mkv model 
61
, taking into account the absence of invariant characters in our dataset.To allow for variation in evolutionary rate across different characters,gamma-distributed rate variation was assumed.Analyses were conducted using four chains and two independent runs,with a tree sampled every 4,000generations and a burn-in of 25%.We performed Bayesian tip-dating under the fossilized birth–death model 
62
, implemented in MrBayes following established procedures 
63
. An independent-gamma rates (IGR) clock model was used.The clock rate prior was set at a diffuse,uninformative rate,whereas the IGR variation,speciation,extinction and fossilization priors were set at the MrBayes default distributions:exp(10) for the former two parameters and beta(1,1) for the latter two.These settings follow other recent tip-dating studies 
64,65
. Given that our extant taxon sample did not reflect the relative diversity of extant bird groups—focusing primarily on galloanserans (which represent 72% of our extant taxon sample,in contrast with around 4% of extant bird diversity based on recent species counts 
66
)—we assumed a random instead of a diversified sampling strategy.Taxon sampling

</p>
         <p>

probability was assigned a value of 0.0023,based on the fact that our extant taxon sample covers roughly 0.23% of extant bird diversity 
66
. To account for ongoing controversies about the timing of crown bird diversification,two tip-dating analyses were run, each with different

</p>
         <p>

prior age probability distributions. In one analysis,a soft-maximum upper bound was set at 86.5 Ma for crown birds, following previous justifications 
1
. This represents the age of the Niobrara Formation,a well-sampled Upper Cretaceous fossil-bearing formation from which no crown bird fossils have been recovered despite an abundance of small vertebrates and crownward stem-bird fossils 
52,67
.A previous study 
9
found evidence for increased nucleotide substitution rates at the base of 
<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
.The authors suggested that this phenomenon might be partially responsible for the older ages estimated by other studies 
68,69
and outlined criteria under which the use of “appropriately conservative” age priors are justified,concluding that crownbirds—like placental mammals 
70
—are one clade for which such conservative treatment could be warranted 
9
. As such,a more restrictive soft maximum of 72.72 Ma was used for the second tip-dating analysis, based on the estimated age of crown birds in a previous study 
1
. For both tip-dating analyses, a soft maximum of 120 Ma was assigned to the root (the divergence between

Ichthyornis

and 
<tp:taxon-name>Neornithes</tp:taxon-name>
) reflecting the minimum age of the Jiufotang Formation,the youngest phase of the Jehol Biota 
71
. This assemblage preserves an abundance of Lower Cretaceous avialan fossils, but none that are phylogenetically crownward of

Ichthyornis

72
. Given that no fossil crown neoavians were included in our dataset, a prior age probability distribution was assigned to the neoavian clade 
<tp:taxon-name>Gruiformes</tp:taxon-name>
,with a minimum age of 53.95 million years (the age of

<tp:taxon-name>
Pellornis mikkelseni
</tp:taxon-name>
, 

the oldest well-established crown gruiform 
73
) and a soft maximum of 66million years (the age of the K–Pg boundary,prior to which no well-corroborated crown neoavian fossils have been identified 
74
). An exponential distribution was used for all of these age priors, allowing for a5%prior probability of each clade having originated earlier than its specified soft maximum.

</p>
         <p>

The ages of fossil taxa were fixed at the minimum age constraints for the specimens that were used to score our morphological dataset, in line with best practices 
75
and the results of experimentally testing alternative calibrations on an empirical dataset 
76
.

<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>

was accordingly assigned a minimum age of 66.7 million years.Most minimum age calibrations for taxa previously included in our dataset follow published ages 
28
.Following the recommended ages of relevant fossil-bearing localities,

<tp:taxon-name>
Gallinuloides
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Green River Formation was assigned an age of51.57 million years and
Anatalavis

from the London Clay Formation was assigned an age of 53.5 million years 
32
. Despite being known from younger strata,

<tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>

was also assigned an age of 51.57 million years because it had been scored into the dataset on the basis of specimens held at the National Museum of Natural History in Washington,DC 
77
, which had primarily been collected from the Green River Formation.

Ichthyornis

was assigned an age of 86.5 million years 
78
,

Conflicto

was assigned an age of 61 million years 
29
,

<tp:taxon-name>
Pelagornis
</tp:taxon-name>

was assigned an age of 4.8 million years 
55
and

Protodontopteryx

was assigned an age of 61.5 million years 
30
.

</p>
         <p>

Undated Bayesian analyses were run for 30,000,000 generations, whereas tip-dated analyses were run for 60,000,000generations.Analytical convergence was assessed using standard diagnostics provided in MrBayes (average standard deviation of split frequencies &lt;0.02, potential scale reduction factors = 1, effective sample sizes&gt; 200). Results of independent runs of the same analyses were summarized using the sump and sumt commands in MrBayes.Morphological synapomorphies were optimized under parsimony onto resulting tree topologies using TNT. Molecular scaffolds followed the consensus from previous phylogenomic studies 
1,2,79–81
.

</p>
         <p>
Estimation of body size

</p>
         <p>
The minimum mediolateral cross-sectional diameter of the tarsometatarsus shaft (3.32 mm) was taken from high-resolution CT scans.
</p>
         <p>

This measurement was incorporated into a published scaling equa- tion for estimating the body masses of volant birds 
25
(

R

2
= 0.93) and compared with a published compilation of the body sizes of extant galloanserans 
82
.

</p>
         <p>
Reporting summary

</p>
         <p>
Further information on research design is available in the Nature Research Reporting Summary linked to this paper.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Data availability

</title>
         <p>
The holotype specimen of
<tp:taxon-name>
A. maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is deposited in the permanent collection of the Natuurhistorisch Museum Maastricht under collection number NHMM 2013 008. Digital models of the
<tp:taxon-name>
A. maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
skull and postcranial elements,.tre files from phylogenetic analyses and CT scans of the
<tp:taxon-name>
A.maastrichtensis
</tp:taxon-name>
holotype are available at Zenodo (doi:10.5281/zenodo.3610226).The Life Science Identifier for
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
is urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub:32192A46-4A43-48CE-8F17- 447900FCC6DF.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
51. Clarke,J.A. Morphology,phylogenetic taxonomy,and systematics of 
Ichthyornis
and 
Apatornis
(Avialae: Ornithurae). 
Bull. Am. Mus.Nat. Hist
. 
286
, 1–179 (2004).
</p>
         <p>
52. Field, D.J. et al. Complete 
Ichthyornis
skull illuminates mosaic assembly of the avian head. 
Nature
557
, 96–100 (2018).
</p>
         <p>
53. Mayr,G. &amp; Weidig, I. The early Eocene bird 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gallinuloides wyomingensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– a stem group representative of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galliformes</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Acta Palaeontol.Pol
. 
49
, 211–217 (2004).
</p>
         <p>
54. Ksepka,D. T.Broken gears in the avian molecular clock:new phylogenetic analyses support stem galliform status for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gallinuloides wyomingensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and rallid affinities for 
Amitabha urbsinterdictensis
. 
Cladistics
25
, 173–197 (2009).
</p>
         <p>
55. Mayr,G. &amp; Rubilar-Rogers,D. Osteology of a new giant bony-toothed bird from the Miocene of Chile,with a revision of the taxonomy of Neogene 
<tp:taxon-name>Pelagornithidae</tp:taxon-name>
. 
J. Vertebr. Paleontol
. 
30
, 1313–1330 (2010).
</p>
         <p>
56. Bourdon, E.Osteological evidence for sister group relationship between pseudo-toothed birds (
<tp:taxon-name>Aves</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Odontopterygiformes</tp:taxon-name>
) and waterfowls (
<tp:taxon-name>Anseriformes</tp:taxon-name>
). 
Naturwissenschaften
92
, 586–591 (2005).
</p>
         <p>
57. Mayr,G. Cenozoic mystery birds - on the phylogenetic affinities of bony-toothed birds (
<tp:taxon-name>Pelagornithidae</tp:taxon-name>
). 
Zool. Scr
. 
40
, 448–467 (2011).
</p>
         <p>
58. Goloboff,P.A. &amp; Catalano,S.A. TNT version 1.5,including a full implementation of phylogenetic morphometrics. 
Cladistics
32
, 221–238 (2016).
</p>
         <p>
59. Ronquist,F.et al. MrBayes 3.2: efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space. 
Syst. Biol
. 
61
, 539–542 (2012).
</p>
         <p>
60. Miller,M. A., Pfeiffer,W.&amp; Schwartz,T.Creating the CIPRES Science Gateway for inference of large phylogenetic trees.In 
Gateway Computing Environments Workshop (GCE 2010)
45–53 (IEEE,2010).
</p>
         <p>
61. Lewis,P.O.A likelihood approach to estimating phylogeny from discrete morphological character data. 
Syst. Biol
. 
50
, 913–925 (2001).
</p>
         <p>
62. Heath, T.A., Huelsenbeck, J.P.&amp; Stadler,T.The fossilized birth–death process for coherent calibration of divergence-time estimates. 
Proc.Natl Acad.Sci. USA
111
, E2957–E2966 (2014).
</p>
         <p>
63. Zhang,C., Stadler,T.,Klopfstein,S., Heath,T.A.&amp; Ronquist,F. Total-evidence dating under the fossilized birth–death process. 
Syst. Biol
. 
65
, 228–249 (2016).
</p>
         <p>
64. Kealy,S.&amp; Beck,R. Total evidence phylogeny and evolutionary timescale for Australian faunivorous marsupials (Dasyuromorphia). 
BMC Evol. Biol
. 
17
, 240 (2017).
</p>
         <p>
65. Vinther,J., Parry,L., Briggs,D. E.&amp; Van Roy,P. Ancestral morphology of crown-group molluscs revealed by a new Ordovician stem aculiferan. 
Nature
542
, 471–474
</p>
         <p>(2017).</p>
         <p>
66. Gill, F., Donsker,D &amp; Rasmussen,P.(eds) 
IOC World Bird List (v.10.1)
https://www. worldbirdnames.org/ioc-lists/crossref/ (2020).
</p>
         <p>
67. Field,D. J.,LeBlanc, A.,Gau, A.&amp; Behlke,A. D.B. Pelagic neonatal fossils support viviparity and precocial life history of Cretaceous mosasaurs. 
Palaeontology
58
, 401–407 (2015).
</p>
         <p>
68. Ericson,P.G.P.et al. Diversification of Neoaves:integration of molecular sequence data and fossils. 
Biol.Lett
. 
2
, 543–547 (2006).
</p>
         <p>
69. Jetz,W.,Thomas, G.H., Joy,J. B., Hartmann, K. &amp; Mooers,A.O. The global diversity of birds in space and time. 
Nature
491
, 444–448 (2012).
</p>
         <p>
70. Phillips,M. J. Geomolecular dating and the origin of placental mammals. 
Syst. Biol
. 
65
, 546–557 (2016).
</p>
         <p>
71. He, H. Y.et al. Timing of the Jiufotang Formation (Jehol Group) in Liaoning,northeastern China,and its implications. 
Geophys.Res. Lett
. 
31
, (2004).
</p>
         <p>
72. Wang,X.et al.The earliest evidence for a supraorbital salt gland in dinosaurs in new Early Cretaceous ornithurines. 
Sci. Rep
. 
8
, 3969 (2018).
</p>
         <p>
73. Musser,G., Ksepka, D.T.&amp; Field, D.J. New material of Paleocene-Eocene 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pellornis
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Aves</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Gruiformes</tp:taxon-name>
) clarifies the pattern and timing of the extant Gruiform radiation. 
Diversity
11
, 102 (2019).
</p>
         <p>
74. Ksepka, D.T., Stidham,T.A.&amp; Williamson,T.E. Early Paleocene landbird supports rapid phylogenetic and morphological diversification of crown birds after the K–Pg mass extinction. 
Proc.Natl Acad.Sci. USA
114
, 8047–8052 (2017).
</p>
         <p>
75. Parham,J.F.et al.Best practices for justifying fossil calibrations. 
Syst.Biol
. 
61
, 346–359 (2012).
</p>
         <p>
76. Püschel,H. P.,O'Reilly, J.E., Pisani,D.&amp; Donoghue,P.C. J. The impact of fossil stratigraphic ranges on tip-calibration, and the accuracy and precision of divergence time estimates. 
Palaeontology
63
, 67–83 (2020).
</p>
         <p>
77. Worthy, T.H. et al. Osteology supports a stem-galliform affinity for the giant extinct flightless bird 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sylviornis neocaledoniae
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Sylviornithidae,Galloanseres</tp:taxon-name>
). 
PLoS One
11
, e0150871 (2016).
</p>
         <p>
78. Benton, M. J.&amp; Donoghue,P.C. J. Paleontological evidence to date the tree of life. 
Mol. Biol. Evol
. 
24
, 26–53 (2007).
</p>
         <p>
79. Reddy,S. et al. Why do phylogenomic data sets yield conflicting trees? Data type influences the avian tree of life more than taxon sampling. 
Syst. Biol
. 
66
, 857–879 (2017).
</p>
         <p>
80. Hackett,S. J.et al. A phylogenomic study of birds reveals their evolutionary history. 
Science
320
, 1763–1768 (2008).
</p>
         <p>
81. Kimball, R. T.et al.A phylogenomic supertree of birds. 
Diversity
11
, 109 (2019).
</p>
         <p>
82. Dunning,J.B. 
CRC Handbook of Avian Body Masses
2nd edn (CRC Press,2007).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Acknowledgements
We thank M. van Dinther for collecting and donating the specimen; J. Vellekoop for advice on geochronology; K. Smithson, T.Thompson and V.Fernandez for scanning support; M. Brooke,M. Lowe,M.Clementz,L. Vietti, J.Cooper, J.White,C.Levitt, R.Irmis, K. MacKenzie and J.Sertich for collections assistance;B.Creisler for etymological information;and T.Worthy and J.Watanabe for anatomical advice. We are grateful to L. Witmer and F. Degrange for sharing three-dimensional models of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Presbyornis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Conflicto
, respectively,and to P.Krzeminski for his artwork.D.J.F.acknowledges support from the UK Research and Innovation Future Leaders Fellowship MR/S032177/1,the Royal Society Research Grant RGS/R2/192390,a Systematics Association Research Grant and the Isaac Newton Trust; J.B. acknowledges the Hesse Award from the American Ornithological Society and grants from the Jurassic Foundation,Geological Association and Paleontological Society; and D.T.K. acknowledges support from the NSF award DEB 1655736.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Additional information

</title>
         <p>
Author contributions
J.W.M.J. provided the material and stratigraphic data;D.J.F.prepared the specimens; D.J.F. and J.B.acquired CT scans and discovered the skull; D.J.F.,J.B. and A.C. performed digital segmentation of the material and created figures; D.J.F.,J.B., A.C. and D.T. K. performed anatomical comparisons;J.B. and A.C.performed the phylogenetic analyses;and D.J.F.wrote the paper, with contributions from all authors.
</p>
         <p>
Competing interests
The authors declare no competing interests.
</p>
         <p>
Supplementary information
is available for this paper at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020- 2096-0.
</p>
         <p>
Correspondence and requests for materials
should be addressed to D.J.F.
</p>
         <p>
Peer review information
Nature
thanks Jingmai O’Connor and Kevin Padian for their contribution to the peer review of this work.
</p>
         <p>
Reprints and permissions information
is available at http://www.nature.com/reprints.
</p>
         <p>
Extended Data Fig.9 | Expanded phylogenetic results.a, Results of the parsimony analysis.
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
(pink)resolves as the sister taxon to crown Galloanserae.b, Results of the tip-dated Bayesian analysis with a soft-maximum neornithine root age of 86.5 million years.An estimated timescale is shown on the
x
axis,although see caveats relating to divergence times in
</p>
         <p>
the Supplementary Information.
<tp:taxon-name>
Asteriornis
</tp:taxon-name>
(pink)resolves as the stemwardmost member of Pangalliformes.Colours match those in 
Fig.3
and extinct taxa are denoted with daggers.See Supplementary Information for full details of phylogenetic analyses,character information,synapomorphies of key clades, support values and tree files.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
