<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1300764110</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>2.4.6-Trichloroanisole is a potent suppressor of olfactory signal
               transduction</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>01</day>
            <month>10</month>
            <year>2013</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 2.4.6-Trichloroanisole is a potent suppressor of olfactory signal transduction </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Hiroko Takeuchi aıbı1 ı Hiroyuki Kato c ı and Takashi Kurahashi aıb </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> a Department of Biophysical Dynamics, Graduate School of Frontier Biosciences, Osaka
            University, Osaka 560-8531, Japan; b Department of Neurophysiology, </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Mie University Graduate School of Medicine, Tsu 514-8507, Japan; and c Daiwa Can
            Company, Tokyo 100-7009, Japan </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Edited by Stephen D. Roper, Miller School of Medicine, University of Miami, Miami, FL,
            and accepted by the Editorial Board August 15, 2013 (received for</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>review January 13, 2013)</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> We investigated the sensitivity of single olfactory receptor cells to
            2ı4ı6-trichloroanisole (TCA)ı a compound known for causing cork taint in wines. Such
            off- fl avors have been thought to originate from unpleasant odor qualities evoked by
            contaminants. Howeverı we here show that TCA attenuates olfactory transduction by
            suppressing cyclic nucleotide-gated channelsı without evoking odorant responses.
            Surprisinglyı suppression was observed even at extremely low (i.e.ı attomolar) TCA
            concentrations. The high sensitivity to TCA was associated with temporal integration of
            the suppression effect. We con fi rmed that potent suppression by TCA and similar
            compounds was correlated with their lipophilicityı as quanti fi ed by the partition coef
            fi cient at octanol/water boundary (pH 7.4)ı suggesting that channel suppression is
            mediated by a partitioning of TCA into the lipid bilayer of plasma membranes. The rank
            order of suppression matched human recognition of offfl avors: TCA equivalent to
            2ı4ı6-tribromoanisoleı which is much greater than 2ı4ı6-trichlorophenol. Furthermoreı
            TCA was detected in a wide variety of foods and beverages surveyed for odor losses. Our
            fi ndings demonstrate a potential molecular mechanism for the reduction of fl avor. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>olfactory masking | ion channel | patch-clamp</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> T by hroughout naturally culinary generated history off-fl, avor consumers substances
            have that been can disturbed greatly reduce the palatability of foods and beverages.
            Because off-flavors appear at very low concentrations of contaminants, chemical
            identification of responsible compounds has been limited. One of the most potent
            off-flavor compounds identified to date is 2,4,6- trichloroanisole (TCA), known
            specifically for inducing a cork taint in wines (1). In general, off-flavor compounds
            have been thought to induce unpleasant exogenous smells (2–9), and would therefore be
            expected to excite specific olfactory receptors (10) transducing malodors. However, we
            found that TCA did not generate excitatory responses in single olfactory receptor cells
            (ORCs), but potently suppressed cyclic nucleotide-gated (CNG) channels in these cells.
            Because CNG channels play a key role in olfactory transduction, suppression of these
            channels suggests a reduction of endogenous odors, rather than an addition of exogenous
            odors. Surprisingly, TCA exerted a much more potent suppressive effect on CNG channels
            (100–1,000-fold) than other known olfactory masking agents that have been widely used in
            perfumery. It was also more potent than a well-known CNG channel blocker, L- cis
            -diltiazem. We could account for such high suppressive potency in terms of temporal
            integration and slow recovery from suppression by TCA. The order of potency of CNG
            suppression by TCA analogues or precursors was identical to that of the human detection
            of the corresponding off-flavors, i.e., TCA equivalent to 2,4,6-tribromoanisole(TBA),
            which is much greater than 2,4,6-trichlorophenol (TCP; precursor of TCA), suggesting
            that cork taint is related to TCA suppression of CNG channels. We further confirmed that
            potent suppression was caused by a haloarene structure having a side chain that
            increases the partition coefficient at octanol/water boundary at pH 7.4 (LogD). The
            present findings not only reveal a likely mechanism of flavor loss, </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>but also suggest certain molecular structures as possible olfactory</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>masking agents and powerful channel blockers.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Results </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Suppression by TCA of Odorant- and cAMP-Induced Currents in Single </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ORCs. We examined the effects of TCA on ORCs in whole-cell electrophysiological
            recordings. Considering its low effective concentration for producing off-flavors, we
            expected TCA to </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>elicit excitatory responses in ORCs at low concentrations or in</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>a majority of cells. However, we did not detect any ORC</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>responses to TCA application. Instead, we were surprised to find</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>that TCA actually suppressed ORC transduction currents. To</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>identify the mechanism underlying this effect, we activated CNG</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>channels by photolysis of caged cAMP introduced into the cy-</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> toplasm of ORCs via the whole-cell pipette ( Fig. 1 A ). In this experimental protocol,
            UV stimulation opens CNG channels </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>directly, bypassing the transduction cascade upstream from</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>adenylyl cyclase, and therefore enabled us to evaluate the effect</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>of TCA on transduction channels. When 10 nM TCA was ap-</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>plied to a recorded cell by puffer pipette, the inward current</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> induced by uncaging cytoplasmic cAMP was attenuated ( Fig. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 1 B ). As no excitatory current was observed in response to TCA </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>puffing alone, it is unlikely that the reduction in cAMP-induced</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>response was caused by adaptation of the olfactory transduction mechanism (11–14).
            Attenuation by 10 nM TCA was observed in</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> all tested cells ( N = 19; 1-μm diameter of puff pipette opening), </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>consistent with suppression of a channel conductance (15) rather</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>than inhibition via olfactory receptors (16). The inward current</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Signi fi cance </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Off- fl avor substances generated naturally in foods/beverages deteriorate the quality
            of products considerably. Generallyı it has been thought that off- fl avor substances
            induce unpleas- ant smells exogenously. Hereı howeverı we show that 2ı4ı6-
            trichroloanisole (TCA)ı known as one of the strongest off- fl avorsı inhibits ciliary
            transduction channels. Surprisinglyı suppression was caused with 1-aM solution. The TCA
            effect showed slow kineticsı with an integration time of approximately 1 sı and
            positively correlated with the partition coef fi cient at octanol/ water boundary (pH
            7.4) of derivatives. These results indicate that the channels are inhibited through a
            partitioning of those substances into the lipid bilayer of plasma membranes. Fur-
            thermoreı TCA was detected in varieties of foods/beverages surveyed for odor losses and
            is likely to be related to the re- duction of fl avor. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Author contributions: T.K. designed research; H.T. performed cell experiments; H.K.
            performed human sensory research; H.T. and T.K. analyzed data; H.K. contributed new
            reagents/analytic tools; and H.T. and T.K. wrote the paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>This article is a PNAS Direct Submission. S.D.R. is a guest editor invited by the
            Editorial Board.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Freely available online through the PNAS open access option.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 1 To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: hiroko@bpe.es.osaka-u.ac.jp. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>This article contains supporting information online at www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:
            10. 1073/pnas. 1300764110/-/DCSupplemental.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> response induced by an odorant (1 mM cineole) was also suppressed by 1 μM TCA ( Fig. S1
            ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Current suppression by TCA was concentration-dependent ( Fig. 1 C–E ). As the effect of
            TCA was not a simple channel blockade (as discussed later), the dose-suppression
            relation could not be fitted by a Michaelis–Menten or Hill equation. The relationship
            between suppression ratio (SR) and concentration was well fitted by a straight line when
            concentration was plotted on a logarithmic scale ( Fig. 1 F ). ORC transduction currents
            are generated by sequential activation of CNG channels and Ca 2+ -activated Cl [Cl (Ca)
            ] channels, with the latter contributing a large proportion of the total current
            (17–23). Suppression by TCA appears to target CNG channels, because we did not detect
            any TCA effects on Cl (Ca) channels activated directly by uncaging cytoplasmic Ca 2+ (
            Fig. S2 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> With the same experimental protocols, two other compounds were compared with TCA for
            their channel suppression effects ( Fig. 2 A ). One was L- cis -diltiazem, a well-known
            blocking agent of the CNG channel (24). The other was geraniol, a strong olfactory
            masking agent used in perfumery, which has been shown to suppress the CNG channel (8).
            Both agents suppressed ORC currents induced by photolysis ( Fig. 2 B and C ), but the
            effects were much weaker compared with TCA. The EC 50 values were 0.19 μM for TCA, 5.8
            μM for L- cis -diltiazem, and 29 μM for geraniol ( Fig. 2 D ; note that actual
            concentration at the cell was much lower). It seems likely that the TCA effect will also
            be stronger than for other drugs that have been shown to block the CNG channel (25).
            Thus, TCA may be a member of a new class of potent inhibitors of CNG channels. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Least Effective Concentration. So far, the TCA concentrations we have reported refer to
            solutions contained in the puffer pipettes. To better understand mechanism of
            suppression by TCA, it is important to estimate the effective concentration delivered to
            the ORC membrane. These are expected to be significantly lower, depending on the tip
            diameter of the puffer ( Fig. S3 ). Furthermore, the degree of suppression was a
            function of TCA preexposure time (i.e., several seconds) before CNG channel activation
            by photolysis ( Fig. 3 A and B ), and recovery was relatively slow (50% recovery at
            approximately 10 s; Fig. 3 C and D ). These time lags suggest that cumulative
            partitioning into the ciliary membrane may increase the concentration of TCA in the
            vicinity of CNG channels, thereby increasing their sensitivity to suppression. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> To estimate the minimal effective concentration, we determined the combination of
            pipette tip size and preexposure time for saturating responses, and then decreased the
            pipette concentration to find the smallest effective dose. For example, we detected a
            slight suppression when 10 aM TCA solution was applied to the cell with a puffer pipette
            with a tip diameter of 3.2 μm ( Fig. 4 A ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> We further applied TCA and other drugs with a U-tube system (26), by which the
            chemicals can be directly applied at more accurate concentrations ( Fig. 4 B ).
            Surprisingly, we could detect a reduction in cAMP-induced current even when 1 aM TCA
            solution was applied (SR = 0.12 ± 0.02; three of three cells; Fig. 4 C ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> When we perceive contamination of wines by TCA, the contaminant evaporates from a
            solution phase and is then transported in gas phase by convection and diffusion
            (orthonasally or retronasally) to the olfactory epithelium, where only a small fraction
            of the molecules dissolve into the mucosa and reach ORCs. To determine if the
            concentration of TCA after such a transport process can suppress CNG channels, we
            mimicked the process by in vitro experiments ( Fig. 4 D and E ). A concentration of 30
            pM TCA (detection threshold in humans; Table 1) in </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> When dose-suppression relations obtained with U-tube experiments were plotted for
            geraniol and TCA, the threshold values (i.e., SR = 0) obtained by extrapolation were 150
            pM and 0.3 aM, respectively ( Fig. 4 F ). Thus, the effective concentration was much
            higher for geraniol than for TCA as expected, confirming the validity of our dilution
            protocol. In addition, it was confirmed that the low concentration effect was unique to
            TCA. solution placed inside a syringe was evaporated into air, this air was applied to
            filter paper wetted with Ringer solution, and the Ringer solution was then squeezed out
            and used to stimulate cells ( Fig. 4 D ; see also ref. 8). We found that this solution
            was able to suppress the CNG current ( Fig. 4 E ). The concentration of TCA in the
            suppressive solution was measured in parallel by GC-MS. With 10 μM TCA in the syringe,
            the final suppressive solution contained ∼1 nM TCA, which is near the detection limit of
            GC- MS. Indeed, we could not detect any TCA by GC-MS when 1 μM was used as the source in
            the syringe. Therefore, the dilution factor was ∼10 4 fold, and 30 pM TCA in the
            original solution would yield ∼3 fM in the suppressive solution, which is still higher
            than the minimal effective concentration of TCA (10 aM with the puffer) we found for
            suppression of the CNG channel. Reduction of Wine Odors by TCA and TBA. Effects of TCA
            on wine flavor have long been reported. However, previous surveys were conducted in the
            context of TCA contributing additional odors (1). In the present study, we showed that
            TCA suppressed the olfactory transduction current. Therefore, we reexamined human
            olfactory perception to look for reductions in wine odor. In addition, we investigated
            the relative potency of odor reductions among TCA analogues or derivatives to compare
            against their CNG channel suppression properties ( Channel Suppression by Related
            Substances and Correlation with Human Sensation ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Twenty panelists were asked to evaluate whether original odors of wines were reduced
            when they were contaminated by off-flavor substances. For evaluation, the triangle test
            that has been approved in Japanese Industrial Standards (JIS) Committee or British
            Standards Institution (BSI)/International Organization for Standardization (ISO) was
            used. The strongest reduction in odor was observed when wine was contaminated with TCA
            (Table 1). The off-flavor recognition thresholds were 47 pM (10 ppt) for red wine and 71
            pM (15 ppt) for white wine. TBA also caused similar effects with slightly higher
            concentrations (290 pM for red and white wines; Table 1). Reduction of odor perception
            was also observed with TCP at concentrations four to five orders of magnitude higher
            (1.5 μM for red wine, 0.5 μM for white wine) than those of TCA or TBA (Table 1).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>In another set of experiments, we also examined the concentration at which the musty
            odor of TCA was recognized in wine. In evaluation with white wines, the reduction of
            original odor and the extrinsic musty smell from TCA were discriminated, and detected at
            approximately 2 to 4 ppt. Thus, even when the panelists attended to different sensory
            parameters, the recognition threshold was almost the same between reduction of wine odor
            and addition of extrinsic odor.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Channel Suppression by Related Substances and Correlation with Human Sensation. We also
            tested the suppressive actions of TCA analogues on cAMP responses of ORCs ( Fig. 5 A–C
            ). TBA reduced the amplitude of cAMP-induced current with a half SR </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Table 1. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Numbers of correct judgments for off- fl avor substances in triangle tests </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Substance/solvent Concentration/judgments </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> *According to binominal tables, 11 or more correct judgments are significantly above
            chance at P &lt;0.05 ( n = 20). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> of 1.4 μM ( Fig. 5 D ), comparable to that of TCA. TCP (a precursor of TCA) and phenol
            (natural precursor of TCP) suppressed the current with half SRs of 37.6 μM (TCP; Fig. 5
            D ) and 74.9 μM (phenol), which were approximately 200- and 400-fold higher,
            respectively, than that of TCA ( Fig. 5 D ). Thus, the channel suppression induced by
            these substances showed a good agreement with the reduction of human olfactory sensation
            (Table 1). Because much weaker suppressors of CNG channels can mask human olfactory
            sensations in air phase delivery (8), it is highly likely that TCA also reduces human
            olfactory perception. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Suppression by High-LogD Substances. It has been shown that odorant suppression of ion
            channels becomes stronger as the LogD of the molecule is increased across a range of
            compounds (26). LogD is a partition coefficient at the octanol/water boundary at fixed
            pH, a measure of lipophilicity. In the present study, we also studied if such a trend is
            observed in TCA and phenol derivatives. This information is important for molecular
            design of novel modifiers of olfaction. As an example, we focused on trichlorophenetole
            (TCPT), an artificially synthesized TCA derivative with a longer side chain (C 2 H 5
            instead of CH 3 ) and higher LogD value (LogD = 4.61) than TCA (LogD = 4.10). Channel
            suppression by TCPT was slightly stronger than by TCA (half suppression with 15.5 nM in
            pipette; Fig. 6 A and B ). We also examined TBP, toluene, benzyl alcohol, and ethyl
            benzene. When LogD was plotted against half SR concentration, we observed a positive
            correlation ( Fig. 6 C and D ). This result may support the notion that the channel
            suppression is caused by the partitioning of volatile substances into the lipid bilayer.
            This would be consistent with the temporal integration seen in the TCA effect ( Fig. 3 )
            being caused by slow accumulation of the substance in the ciliary membrane. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> TCA Is Generated in Varieties of Products. The present study shows that TCA suppresses
            CNG channel current, which is predicted to reduce olfactory sensation. These
            observations led us to examine the presence of TCA in foods and beverages that received
            negative ratings for odor loss but not the presence of a musty odor. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>In GC-MS measurements, TCA molecules were detected with high concentrations in a variety
            of foods and beverages (in ppt; banana peel, 1,500; starch, 100; chicken, 60; peanuts,
            20; Japanese sake, 10; cashew nuts, &lt;10; green tea, 5; beer, 1).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Moreover, with GC-olfactometry (GC-O; “GC-sniffing”) and GC-MS, presence of TCA was also
            recognized in mineral water, tap water, whiskey, apples, chestnuts, eggs, flours, green
            onions, raisins, sea urchin, shrimp, building materials, food packing films, paper bags,
            and resin for computers. These products do not include TCA normally (or include TCA at
            quantities lower than the GC-MS detection threshold). TCA was detected when these
            products were judged to be of low qualities (i.e., flavor loss and/or unpleasant odor)
            by their industrial specialists. It thus seems likely that TCA degrades the olfactory
            quality not only of wines, but also of a wide variety of foods and beverages that have
            not yet been well investigated.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Discussion </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> In this study, we showed that TCA and TBA suppress the activity of CNG channels in
            olfactory cilia. It has been shown that the density of CNG channels in cilia is 100 to
            1,000/μm 2 (27, 28). The diameter of cilia is 100 to 200 nm, and the length is 10 to 100
            μm. As each ORC has approximately 10 cilia, the total transduction current is carried by
            an enormous number of CNG channels (e.g., approximately 100,000). Our data showed that a
            remarkably small number of TCA molecules can significantly suppress transduction
            currents. For the 1-aM effective concentration we observed, 1 μL (1 mm 3 ) of solution
            contains 0.6 TCA molecules. In our U-tube experiments, ∼1 mL of solution was perfused
            onto the cell, so the total number of molecules delivered was ∼600. Only a small
            fraction of these 600 molecules will have a chance to impact the recorded cell and bind
            or partition into the ciliary membrane. If suppression is caused by direct binding of
            TCA molecules to ion channels, only a small fraction of the ion channels would be
            suppressed, which would not be detectable as a significant reduction of total current.
            Thus, it seems likely that one TCA molecule suppresses many channels. The TCA effect
            exhibited temporal integration over a period of tens of seconds and was correlated with
            LogD when compared across structurally related compounds. This suggests that TCA may
            partition into the lipid bilayer and achieve an elevated concentration in the lipid
            microenvironment, or it may affect multiple channels simultaneously by disrupting
            membrane order. The suppression of individual channels may be visible in macroscopic
            currents because a high density of CNG channels in olfactory cilia increases the
            signal-to-noise ratio for the observation of channel perturbations (27–31). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> TCA has been well documented as one of the strongest known off-flavor substances, and
            has been detected in the drinking water (7), beer (5), Japanese sake (6), coffee (3, 9),
            and various foods (1, 2, 4). It was pointed out in these reports that TCA causes an
            unpleasant musty odor. Therefore, previous attention was given to TCA only when musty
            odors were present. Unfortunately, we currently do not have a clear understanding of how
            extremely low concentrations of TCA can evoke a musty odor. The simplest hypothesis is
            that TCA molecules bind certain olfactory receptors and activate transduction currents
            in ORCs at very low concentrations. However, the smallest effective concentration of
            odorants known to induce responses in individual ORCs is approximately 1 μM (20, 28,
            29). On the contrary, the levels of TCA that would evoke musty odors (&lt;5 pM
            concentration, or 10 −4 fold lower) are extremely low for receptor-mediated biological
            mechanisms, even taking into consideration the expected 10 2 - to 10 3 -fold
            amplification of afferent signals achieved by convergence of ORC synaptic inputs at
            olfactory glomeruli (32). We did not observe any detectable ORC excitatory responses in
            the experiments in which very low concentrations of TCA were applied to ORCs. However,
            we cannot assume that we surveyed all possible olfactory receptors in the newt. We also
            note that the repertoire of functional olfactory receptor genes is different between
            amphibians and mammals, so we cannot rule out the expression of receptors with very high
            TCA sensitivity in humans. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The rank order of suppression of CNG currents by TCA and its analogues perfectly matched
            the human recognition of offflavors, TCA equivalent to TBA, which is much greater than
            TCP. It is also noteworthy that, in the sensory evaluation, the perceived attenuation of
            wine odor and the identification of extrinsic TCA odor exhibited almost the same
            thresholds. Based on these observations, we propose that the reduction of CNG channel
            activity may induce some kind of pseudoolfactory sensation by inducing an off-response
            (33), or the suppression of ORC output may itself induce an olfactory sensation. One
            possibility is a change in central odor coding through inhibitory circuits, e.g.,
            lateral inhibition in the olfactory bulb. In this regard, we may need to revisit past
            reports of an association between olfactory sensations and odorant effects on membrane
            fluidity (34). Another possible explanation for the altered quality of perceived odors
            in the presence of TCA could be a selective differential block of transduction in ORCs
            expressing some subset of olfactory receptors, thereby distorting the odor code relayed
            to the brain from the periphery. This might occur if there were a nonuniform transport
            of TCA to different dorsoventral zones of receptor expression in the olfactory
            epithelium (35). For instance, TCA or food/beverage odorants released in the oral cavity
            might have different access to different receptors via a retronasal pathway (36).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The suppression of CNG channels has been reported for compounds that are used in
            perfumery for the purpose of olfactory masking (8). It is surprising to see that
            off-flavors in foods/beverages actually exhibit the same effect. In the present study,
            it was confirmed that potent suppression was caused by similar compounds having a side
            chain that increases LogD. Our findings not only reveal a likely mechanism of odor loss,
            but also reveal potential molecular architectures for the development of novel
            odor-masking agents and potent ion channel inhibitors.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Methods </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Cell Dissociation. Single ORCs were dissociated enzymatically from the ol- </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> factory epithelium of the newt ( cynops pyrrhogaster ) as described previously </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>(37, 38). The experiments were performed under the latest ethical guidelines</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>for animal experimentation at Osaka University, based on international experimental
            animal regulations. Animals were chilled on ice and double-</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>pithed. After decapitation, olfactory epithelia were removed. The mucosae</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> were incubated (37 °C, 5 min) in 0.1% (wt/wt) collagenase solution (Ca 2+ - </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> and Mg 2+ -free) containing (in mM) 110 NaCl, 3.7 KCl, 10 Hepes, 15 glucose, </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>1 pyruvate, and 0.001% phenol red, with pH adjusted to 7.4 with NaOH, and</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>cells were mechanically isolated. Cells were adhered onto the surface of concanavalin
            A-coated glass coverslip that replaced the bottom of the Petri dish, bathed in normal
            Ringer solution containing (in mM) 110 NaCl, 3.7 KCl,</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 3 CaCl 2 , 1 MgCl 2 , 10 Hepes, 15 glucose, 1 pyruvate (pH adjusted to 7.4 with </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>NaOH before use), and examined with an inverted microscope with</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Nomarski optics during recording. Cells were maintained at 4 °C until use.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Experiments were performed at room temperature (23–25 °C).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Electrophysiology. Unless otherwise indicated,cells that did not show odorant responses
            were selected for experiments. Membrane currents were recorded with the whole-cell
            recording configuration (39). Patch pipettes were fabricated from borosilicate tubing
            with filament (outer diameter, 1.2 mm; World Precision Instruments) by using a two-stage
            vertical patch electrode puller (PP-830; Narishige Scientific Instruments). The
            recording pipette was normally filled with a 119 mM CsCl solution (37). In all pipette
            solutions, pH was adjusted with CsOH to 7.4 with 10 mM Hepes buffer. For cAMP
            experiments, 1 mM CaCl 2 , 5 mM EGTA, and 1 mM of caged cAMP were added ( Figs. 1–6 and
            Figs. S1 and S 3 ). For caged Ca 2+ experiments, 5 mM CaCl 2 and 10 mM
            dimethoxy-nitrophenamine (DM-nitrophen) were added without EGTA ( Fig. S2 ).Whole-cell
            pipette resistance was 10 to 15 MΩ. In all experiments, normal Ringer solution (as
            described earlier) was used as superfusate. The recording pipette was connected to a
            patch-clamp amplifier (Axopatch 200B; MDS Analytical Technologies). Signals were
            low-pass filtered at 0.5 kHz and digitized by an A/D converter (sampling frequency, 1
            kHz) connected to a PC operating MS-DOS (PC9821, 80486CPU; NEC) or Windows (xw8600
            workstation; HP) with pClamp 8 (MDS Analytical Technologies). Simultaneously, signals
            were monitored on an oscilloscope and recorded on a chart recorder. UV light and odorant
            stimulation and data acquisition were regulated by the same computer by using custom
            software. The results were analyzed by a workstation computer and plotted in Microcal
            Origin 7.5 software (OriginLab). For curve plots, data were smoothed by 50 Hz averaging,
            or data sampled at 1/16 kHz were used. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Photolysis of Caged Compound. The ORC was loaded with caged cAMP (adenosine 3-5-cyclic
            monophosphate,P1-(2-nitrophenyl) ethyl ester of cAMP; EMD) or with caged Ca 2+
            (DM-nitrophen; EMD). Caged cAMP was initially dissolved in DMSO at 100 mM, and caged Ca
            2+ was dissolved in 10 mM CsOH at 100 mM and stored frozen at −20 °C in complete
            darkness. The stock solution was diluted into the pipette solution to a final
            concentration of 1 mM (caged cAMP) or 10 mM (caged Ca 2+ ) before each experiment. For
            photolysis, UV light from a 100-W xenon arc was directed onto the cilia of solitary
            cells by an epifluorescence attachment.Light stimuli were applied at&gt;20 s intervals
            to avoid response adaptation.The timing and duration of light illumination were
            controlled by a magnetic shutter (Copal), and the light intensity was adjusted by a
            wedge filter under computer control. The light source was mechanically isolated from the
            microscope to exclude transmission of vibrations (38). Throughout the experiments, we
            paid particular attention to avoid current saturation. For measurements of suppression
            by odorants or TCA derivatives, we adjusted light intensity to evoke cAMP responses of
            80% to 90% saturating level to ensure we measured the SR at the same level of internal
            cAMP. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Chemicals and Stimulation. Chemicals (TCA, TBA, TCP, TBP, 1,8-cineole, ethyl benzene,
            toluene, benzyl alcohol), were purchased from Tokyo Chemical Industry, phenol from Wako
            Pure Chemical, geraniol from Katayama Chemical, and L- cis -diltiazem from Enzo Life
            Sciences. TCPT was synthetized in the laboratory of Daiwa Can Company. All LogD values
            were obtained from the ChemSpider database of the Royal Society of Chemistry on July 10,
            2013. For stimuli, chemicals were dissolved in Ringer solution, and this solution was
            applied to cells by pressure ejection (40) from a glass puffer pipette with a tip
            diameter ∼1 μm, unless otherwise indicated.As shown in the present study, the solution
            in the puffer pipette was diluted by one or two orders of magnitude when ejected into
            the superfusion bath. Stimulus solutions were also applied by using a U-tube system
            (26). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> GC-MS. For GC and MS measurements, we used a 7890A GC system (Agilent Technologies) and
            a Jms-Q1000GC MKII system (JEOL), respectively. The column was a model DB-5MS (30 m ×
            0.32 mm × 0.5 μm film thickness; Agilent Technologies). The GC conditions were as
            follows: column temperature, 60 °C (for 5 min) to 250 °C at a rate of 10 °C/min;
            injector temperature, 250 °C; ion source temperature, 23 °C; ionization voltage, 70 eV
            (electron ionization); and selected ion monitoring measurement ion m / z , deuterium
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> labeled TCA (TCAd5) 197, 199, 215; and TCA, 195, 197, and 210. A spiked surrogate
            reagent was used as an internal standard for quantification. The value of TCA for TCAd5
            was 0.87 (coefficient of variation = 3.6%; n = 5). Under these conditions, the
            off-flavor causing substance was at 0.001 ppb, and a linear relationship was obtained in
            the range of 0.001 to 10 ppb. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> GC-O. GC-O was performed by using a 6890GC device (Agilent Technologies) with a DB-5
            column (30 m × 0.53 mm × 1.0 μm film thickness; Agilent Technologies).The GC conditions
            were as follows: column temperature,100 °C (for 5 min) to 250 °C at a rate of 10 °C/min;
            injector temperature, 250 °C; injector mode, splitless; and injection amount, 2 μL. The
            gas obtained by branching immediately before entering the flame ionization detector
            (4:1) was subjected to GC-O. The GC-O experiments were performed by four panelists ( n =
            2 male and n = 2 female; age, 24–56 y) trained in-house to detect musty odors in foods
            and beverages. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Evaluation of Wine Odor. Detection thresholds of off-flavor substances were examined by
            panelists who were selected from employees of Daiwa Can Company. The evaluation complied
            with the guidelines for ethics regarding human epidemiological studies at Osaka
            University, Daiwa Can Company, and Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and
            Technology of Japan. Human sensory tests were approved by the Ethics committee of Daiwa
            Can Company. The triangle test approved by JIS or BSI/ISO was used for the determination
            of threshold. Protocols are described in SI Methods . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ACKNOWLEDGMENTS. We thank Drs. King-Wai Yau and Graeme Lowe for their detailed
            comments, Dr. Saho Ayabe for her advice on the sensory evaluation, Mr. Takeomi Sato for
            his expert advice on cork taint and flavor loss, Mr. Hisao Watanabe for his advice on
            chemicals and discussions, and Mr. Katsuyoshi Syudo for collecting sensory evaluation
            data. This work was supported by Japan Society for the Promotion of Science Grants
            22700414 (to H.T.) and 22500357 (to T.K.). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>1</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> . Buser HR , Zanier C , Tanner H ( 1982 ) Identification of 2,4,6-trichloroanisole as a
            potent compound causing cork taint in wine . J Agric Food chem 30 : 359–362 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 2. Henricks DM , Lamond DR ( 1972 ) 2,3,4,6- tetrachloroanisole association with musty
            taint in chickens and microbiological formation . Nature 235 ( 5335 ): 222–223 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 3. Spadone JC , Takeoka G , Liardon R ( 1990 ) Analytical investigation of Rio
            off-flavor in green coffee . J Agric Food chem 38 : 226–233 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 4. Engel CP , de Groot AP , Weurman C ( 1966 ) Tetrachloroanisol: A source of musty
            taste in eggs and broilers . Science 154 ( 3746 ): 270–271 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 5. McGarrity MJ , McRoberts C , Fitzpatrick M ( 2003 ) Identification, cause, and
            prevention of musty off-flavors in beer . MBAA TQ 40 : 44–47 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 6. Miki A , Isogai A , Utsunomiya H , Iwata H ( 2005 ) Identification of
            2,4,6-trichloroanisole (TCA) causing a musty/muddy off-flavor in sake and its production
            in rice koji and moromi mash . J Biosci Bioeng 100 ( 2 ): 178–183 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 7. Qi F , et al. ( 2009 ) Ozonation catalyzed by the raw bauxite for the degradation of
            2,4,6-trichloroanisole in drinking water . J Hazard Mater 168 ( 1 ): 246–252 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 8. Takeuchi H , Ishida H , Hikichi S , Kurahashi T ( 2009 ) Mechanism of olfactory
            masking in the sensory cilia . J Gen Physiol 133 ( 6 ): 583–601 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 9. Kato H , Sato K , Takui T ( 2011 ) Analysis of iodine-like (chlorine) flavor-causing
            components in Brazilian coffee with Rio flavor . Food Sci Technol Res 17 : 347–352 .
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 10. Buck L , Axel R ( 1991 ) A novel multigene family may encode odorant receptors: A
            molecular basis for odor recognition . cell 65 ( 1 ): 175–187 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 11. Kurahashi T , Menini A ( 1997 ) Mechanism of odorant adaptation in the olfactory
            receptor cell . Nature 385 ( 6618 ): 725–729 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 12. Takeuchi H , Kurahashi T ( 2003 ) Identification of second messenger mediating
            signal transduction in the olfactory receptor cell . J Gen Physiol 122 ( 5 ): 557–567 .
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 13. Takeuchi H , Kurahashi T ( 2005 ) Mechanism of signal amplification in the
            olfactory sensory cilia . J Neurosci 25 ( 48 ): 11084–11091 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 14. Takeuchi H , Kurahashi T ( 2008 ) Distribution, amplification, and summation of
            cyclic nucleotide sensitivities within single olfactory sensory cilia . J Neurosci 28 (
            3 ): 766–775 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 15. Chen TY , Takeuchi H , Kurahashi T ( 2006 ) Odorant inhibition of the olfactory
            cyclic nucleotide-gated channel with a native molecular assembly . J Gen Physiol 128 ( 3
            ): 365–371 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 16. Ache BW ( 2010 ) Odorant-specific modes of signaling in mammalian olfaction . chem
            Senses 35 ( 7 ): 533–539 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 17. Kleene SJ , Gesteland RC ( 1991 ) Calcium-activated chloride conductance in frog
            olfactory cilia . J Neurosci 11 ( 11 ): 3624–3629 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 18. Kurahashi T , Yau KW ( 1993 ) Co-existence of cationic and chloride components in
            odorant-induced current of vertebrate olfactory receptor cells . Nature 363 ( 6424 ):
            71–74 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 19. Lowe G , Gold GH ( 1993 ) Nonlinear amplification by calcium-dependent chloride
            channels in olfactory receptor cells . Nature 366 ( 6452 ): 283–286 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 20. Lowe G , Gold GH ( 1995 ) Olfactory transduction is intrinsically noisy . Proc Natl
            Acad Sci USA 92 ( 17 ): 7864–7868 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 21. Reisert J , Bauer PJ , Yau KW , Frings S ( 2003 ) The Ca-activated Cl channel and
            its control in rat olfactory receptor neurons . J Gen Physiol 122 ( 3 ): 349–363 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 22. Stephan AB, et al. (2009) ANO2 is the cilial calcium-activated chloride channel
            that may mediate olfactory amplification. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 106(28):11776–11781.
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 23. Sagheddu C, et al. (2010) Calcium concentration jumps reveal dynamic ion
            selectivity of calcium-activated chloride currents in mouse olfactory sensory neurons
            and TMEM16b-transfected HEK 293T cells. J Physiol 588(pt 21):4189–4204. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 24. Cook NJ, Hanke W, Kaupp UB (1987) Identification, purification, and functional
            reconstitution of the cyclic GMP-dependent channel from rod photoreceptors. Proc Natl
            Acad Sci USA 84(2):585–589. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 25. Breunig E, Kludt E, Czesnik D, Schild D (2011) The styryl dye FM1-43 suppresses
            odorant responses in a subset of olfactory neurons by blocking cyclic nucleotidegated
            (CNG) channels. J Biol chem 286(32):28041–28048. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 26. Kishino Y, Kato H, Kurahashi T, Takeuchi H (2011) Chemical structures of odorants
            that suppress ion channels in the olfactory receptor cell. J Physiol Sci 61(3):231–245.
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 27. Kurahashi T, Kaneko A (1991) High density cAMP-gated channels at the ciliary
            membrane in the olfactory receptor cell. Neuroreport 2(1):5–8. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 28. Bhandawat V, Reisert J, Yau KW (2005) Elementary response of olfactory receptor
            neurons to odorants. Science 308(5730):1931–1934. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 29. Menini A, Picco C, Firestein S (1995) Quantal-like current fluctuations induced by
            odorants in olfactory receptor cells. Nature 373(6513):435–437. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 30. Larsson HP, Kleene SJ, Lecar H (1997) Noise analysis of ion channels in
            non-spaceclamped cables: Estimates of channel parameters in olfactory cilia. Biophys J
            72(3): 1193–1203. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 31. Kurahashi T, Kaneko A (1993) Gating properties of the cAMP-gated channel in toad
            olfactory receptor cells. J Physiol 466:287–302. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 32. van Drongelen W, Holley A, DØving KB (1978) Convergence in the olfactory system:
            Quantitative aspects of odour sensitivity. J Theor Biol 71(1):39–48. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 33. Kurahashi T, Lowe G, Gold GH (1994) Suppression of odorant responses by odorants in
            olfactory receptor cells. Science 265(5168):118–120. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 34. Kashiwayanagi M, Kurihara K (1985) Evidence for non-receptor odor discrimination
            using neuroblastoma cells as a model for olfactory cells. Brain Res 359(1-2):97–103.
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 35. Miyamichi K, Serizawa S, Kimura HM, Sakano H (2005) Continuous and overlapping
            expression domains of odorant receptor genes in the olfactory epithelium determine the
            dorsal/ventral positioning of glomeruli in the olfactory bulb. J Neurosci 25(14):
            3586–3592. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 36. Furudono Y, Cruz G, Lowe G (2013) Glomerular responses to retronasal airflow
            revealed by optical imaging in the mouse olfactory bulb. BMc Neurosci 14:45. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 37. Kurahashi T (1989) Activation by odorants of cation-selective conductance in the
            olfactory receptor cell isolated from the newt. J Physiol 419:177–192. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 38. Takeuchi H, Kurahashi T (2002) Photolysis of caged cyclic AMP in the ciliary
            cytoplasm of the newt olfactory receptor cell. J Physiol 541(pt 3):825–833. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 39. Hamill OP, Marty A, Neher E, Sakmann B, Sigworth FJ (1981) Improved patch-clamp
            techniques for high-resolution current recording from cells and cell-free membrane
            patches. Pflugers Arch 391(2):85–100. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 40. Ito Y, Kurahashi T, Kaneko A (1995) [Pressure control instrumentation for drug
            stimulation]. Nippon Seirigaku Zasshi 57(3):127–133, Japanese. </p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
