<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1038/s41586-022-04532-4</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Bat coronaviruses related to SARS-CoV-2 and infectious for human cells</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Bat coronaviruses related to SARS-CoV-2 and infectious for human cells
Sarah Temmam
1,2,11, 
Khamsing Vongphayloth
3,11, 
Eduard Baquero
4,11, 
Sandie Munier
5,11, 
Massimiliano Bonomi
6,11, 
Béatrice Regnault
1,2, 
Bounsavane Douangboubpha
7, 
Yasaman Karami
6, 
Delphine Chrétien
1,2, 
Daosavanh Sanamxay
7, 
Vilakhan Xayaphet
7, 
Phetphoumin Paphaphanh
7, 
Vincent Lacoste
3, 
Somphavanh Somlor
3, 
Khaithong Lakeomany
3, 
Nothasin Phommavanh
3, 
Philippe Pérot
1,2, 
Océane Dehan
6,8, 
Faustine Amara
5, 
Flora Donati
6,8, 
Thomas Bigot
1,9, 
Michael Nilges
6, 
Félix A. Rey
4, Sylvievan der Werf6,8, 
Paul T. Brey
3 &amp; 
Marc Eloit
1,2,10

✉
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <p>

Theanimalreservoirof SARS-CoV-2 isunknowndespitereportsof SARS-CoV-2-related virusesin Asian 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophus</tp:taxon-name>
bats1–4, includingtheclosestvirusfrom 
<tp:taxon-name>R. affinis</tp:taxon-name>
,RaTG13 (refs.5,6), andpangolins7–9. SARS-CoV-2 hasamosaicgenome,towhichdifferent progenitorscontribute.Thespikesequencedeterminesthebindingaffinityand accessibilityof itsreceptor-bindingdomaintothecellularangiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptorandisresponsibleforhostrange10–12. SARS-CoV-2 progenitor batvirusesgeneticallycloseto SARS-CoV-2 andabletoenterhumancellsthrougha human ACE2 (hACE2) pathwayhavenotyetbeenidentified, althoughtheywouldbe keyinunderstandingtheoriginof theepidemic. Hereweshowthatsuchviruses circulateincavebatslivinginthelimestonekarsticterraininnorthern Laos,inthe Indochinesepeninsula.Wefoundthatthereceptor-bindingdomainsof theseviruses differfromthatof SARS-CoV-2 byonlyoneortworesiduesattheinterfacewith ACE2, bindmoreefficientlytothehACE2 proteinthanthatof the SARS-CoV-2 strainisolated in Wuhanfromearlyhumancases,andmediatehACE2-dependententryand replicationinhumancells,whichisinhibitedbyantibodiesthatneutralize SARS-CoV-2. Noneof thesebatvirusescontainsafurincleavagesiteinthespikeprotein.Our findingsthereforeindicatethatbat-borne SARS-CoV-2-likevirusesthatarepotentially infectiousforhumanscirculatein 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinolophus</tp:taxon-name>
spp. inthe Indochinesepeninsula.

</p>
         <p>
Theorigin of SARS-CoV-2, as wellas its mode of introduction into the human population, are unknown at present. Since its emergence, numerous animal specieshave been studied toidentify possiblereservoirsand/orintermediatehostsof thevirus,includingalargediversityof insectivorous batsof thegenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
</tp:taxon-name>
. Despitetherecent reportof various SARS-CoV-2-relatedvirusesin 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
shameli
</tp:taxon-name>
(isolatedin 
Cambodiain 201013
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
(China, 2020 and 

2019, respectively2), 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
acuminatus
</tp:taxon-name>
(Thailand,20203

) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
cornutus
</tp:taxon-name>
(Japan,20134
), theclosestSARS-CoV-2 bat-bornegenomestillremains 

theonefrom 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
affinis
</tp:taxon-name>
,RaTG13 (China,20135

,6),with 96.1% identityatthe whole-genomelevel.Severalstudiesalsosuggestedtheinvolvementof 
pangolincoronavirusesintheemergenceof SARS-CoV-2 (refs.7–9
).Since itsappearancein humans, SARS-CoV-2 hasevolvedthrough sporadic 
mutationsandrecombinationevents14
, someof whichcorrespondto gains in fitness allowingthe virustospread morewidely,or toescape 
neutralizingantibodies15
.
</p>
         <p>
Todeciphertheoriginof SARS-CoV-2,itisthereforeessentialtoascertain thediversity of animal coronaviruses,andmorespecifically,that ofbatcoronaviruses.Althoughtheidentificationof SARS-CoV-2 inbats is amain goal, amore realisticobjective is to identify the sequences that contribute to its mosaicism. The spike sequence seems essential, as it determines the binding affinity and accessibility of the receptor-binding domain (RBD) to the cellular ACE2 receptor and is thereforeresponsibleforhost range10–12. The closest relatedbat strainidentified so far (RaTG13) hasa low RBD sequencesimilarityto SARS-CoV-2, and with only 11/17 hACE2 contact amino acid residues conserved with SARS-CoV-2, itsaffinityfor hACE2 isverylimited16. Moreover, SARS-CoV-2 poorly infects bats and bat cells tested so far17. In addition,nobat SARS-CoV-2-like virus hasbeenshowntouse hACE2 toefficientlyenterhumancells,andnone hasthefurincleavage site thatisassociatedwithanincreased pathogenicityin humans18.
The SARS-CoV-2 RBD binds to 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
macrotis
</tp:taxon-name>
ACE2 with a lower affinity 
thanto hACE2 (ref. 19). Anessentialpieceof information—finding bat viruseswithan RBD motif geneticallyclose tothatof SARS-CoV-2 and capableof bindingtohACE2 with high affinity—is therefore missing.
</p>
         <p>
1 
Institut Pasteur, Université de Paris,Pathogen Discovery Laboratory,Paris,France
.2 
Institut Pasteur,Université de Paris,The OIE Collaborating Center for the Detection and Identification in Humans of Emerging Animal Pathogens,Paris, France
.3 
Institut Pasteur du Laos,Vientiane,Lao People’s Democratic Republic
.4 
Institut Pasteur,Université de Paris,CNRS UMR 3569,Structural Virology Unit,Paris,France
.5 
Institut Pasteur,Université de Paris,CNRS UMR 3569,Molecular Genetics of RNA Viruses Unit, Paris,France
.6 
Institut Pasteur,Université de Paris,CNRS UMR 3528, Structural Bioinformatics Unit,Paris,France
.7 
Faculty of Environmental Sciences, National University of Laos,Vientiane,Lao People’s Democratic Republic
.8 
Institut Pasteur,Université de Paris, National Reference Center for Respiratory Viruses,Paris,France
.9 
Institut Pasteur,Université de Paris,Bioinformatic and Biostatistic Hub - Computational Biology Department,Paris,France
. 10 
Ecole Nationale Vétérinaire d’Alfort,University of Paris-Est,Maisons-Alfort,France
.11These authors contributed equally:Sarah Temmam, Khamsing Vongphayloth,Eduard Baquero,Sandie Munier, Massimiliano Bonomi. ✉e-mail: 
marc.eloit@pasteur.fr
</p>
         <p>
Wespeculatedthatthistypeof viruscouldbeidentifiedinbatsliving inthelimestonekarsticterraincommonto China,Laosand Vietnamin the Indochinesepeninsula.Herewereportthepresenceof sarbecovirusescloseto SARS-CoV-2 whose RBDsdifferfromthatof SARS-CoV-2 byonlyoneortwocontactresidues,stronglybindtothehACE2protein andmediatehACE2-dependententryandreplicationintohumancells. Despitethe absence of the furincleavage site,these virusesmayhave contributed to the origin of SARS-CoV-2 and may intrinsically pose a future riskof direct transmission tohumans.
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>
Diversityofbatandcoronavirusspecies

</p>
      <p>

Atotal of 645 bats belonging to 6 families and 46 species were captured (Supplementary Table 1). Two hundred andforty-seven blood samples, 608 saliva, 539 anal/faecal and 157 urine swabs were collectedfrombats inthenorthernpartof Laos (Supplementary Table 2). We first screened all 539 faecal samples through a pan-coronavirus nested RT-PCR analysis 
20
. Overall, 24 individuals of 10 species were positive,and 1 individual (BANAL-27) was concomitantlyinfected by analphacoronavirus andabetacoronavirus (Supplementary Table 3). BLAST analysisof amplicons identifiedalphacoronavirussequences of the 
Decacovirus
, 
Pedacovirus
and 
Rhinacovirus
subgenera and betacoronavirus sequences of the 
Nobecovirus
and 
Sarbecovirus
subgenera.Sequences of the 
Sarbecovirus
subgenus were all identified from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
</tp:taxon-name>
individuals belonging to three differentspecies (
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
marshalli
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Positiveindividuals were trapped in three different districts, and those infected with a sarbecovirus were all from the Fueng district in Vientiane province (

, site 1).

</p>
      <p>

Next-generationsequencing (NGS)and Sangersequencingwereused toobtaina completegenomicsequenceoffiveof thesevensarbecoviruses(

and Supplementary Table 4). Thecoverageof thegenomeof theremainingtwosarbecoviruses (BANAL-27 and BANAL-242 sampled from 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
bats, respectively) was 90%; therefore,theywerenotincludedinthefinalanalyses.Phylogeneticanalyses performedonthe receptor-bindingproteindomainoflineages Aand Bhuman SARS-CoV-2 (ref. 
21
), andonrepresentativebatandpangolin sarbecoviruses,placedthe Laotian 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-52, 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-103 and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
marshalli
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-236coronavirusesclosetohuman SARS-CoV-2 and pangolin coronavirusescollected in 2019, whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-116 and BANAL-247 coronavirusesbelongedtoa sistercladewithotherbatcoronaviruses (RmYN02,RacCS203,RpYN06 and PrC31) fromdifferent 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
</tp:taxon-name>
species.Pangolincoronaviruses sampled in 2017 exhibited a basal position relative to these strains (

). Very similar SARS-CoV-2-like viruses are sharedby different bat species,suggesting possible circulation of viruses between different species living sympatrically in the same caves. These results are consistent with thesimilarity plot analysis showing that RaTG13 and BANAL-52 batcoronavirusesexhibithighnucleotideidentitywith SARS-CoV-2 throughoutthelengthof thegenome(96.8% for BANAL-52 and96.1% for RaTG13).Notably,BANAL-52 hasahigherlevelof nucleotide conservation than RaTG13 inthe S1 domain of the spike protein, and especially in the amino-terminal domain (NTD) and RBD of the spike protein (

). These observationsare congruent with amino acididentitiesbetweenhuman SARS-CoV-2 andrepresentativebat and pangolincoronaviruses,whichhaveahighlevelof conservation,except for the open reading frame 8 (ORF8) of bat BANAL-116, BANAL-247, Rc-o319 and RmYN02 (Supplementary 

).The S1domainof thespike protein (andespeciallythe NTD) has alowerdegreeof conservationin several bat coronaviruses,suggesting thatthis domain may reflect a relativedegreeof adaptationof thevirustoitsmammalianhost(

and Extended Data 

).

</p>
      <p>

Bat 
Sarbecovirus
evolutionaryhistory


</p>
      <p>

Followinganalysisusingageneticalgorithmforrecombinationdetection (GARD), we identified 14 recombinant breakpoints during the evolutionaryhistoryof sarbecoviruses,whichwerefurtherconfirmed by phylogeneticanalysesperformedonthe 15 fragmentsof sequences defined bythebreakpoints (

and Supplementary 

). No specific signature was identified in the breakpoints (Supplementary Table 5). SARS-CoV-2 hasamosaicgenome,towhichmorethanfive sequences close to sequences published or determinedduring this study contributed: 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
RmYN02 and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R. pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
RpYN06 virusesfoundin Chinain 2019, 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
affinis
</tp:taxon-name>
RaTG13 coronavirus foundin Chinain 2013, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-52 and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-103 found in northern Laosin 2020 (this study).No pangolin coronavirus sequence was immediately associatedwith a recombination event at theorigin of SARS-CoV-2. Laotian 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
</tp:taxon-name>
bat coronaviruses had a lower degree of recombination compared to SARS-CoV-2. Such recombinationeventsoccurredbetweenother BANALvirusesisolated from batsliving sympatricallyin caves in the samearea.

</p>
      <p>

Notably, the origin of several fragments of SARS-CoV-2 genomes could be assigned to several donor strainsand not a unique donor sequence. For example, a breakpoint was identified seven nucleotides upstream of the RBD region of S1: the downstream fragmentof SARS-CoV-2,which comprisesthe RBDandthebeginningof S2,could involvethe 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-52, 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-103 and 
R
. 
marshalli
BANAL-236 viruses,whichformedahighlysupportedsisterclade of SARS-CoV-2 (fragment 11, Supplementary 

). In a more basal positionare 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
shameli
</tp:taxon-name>
batcoronavirusesandpangolin-2019 coronaviruses,consistentwith theconservationof RBDaminoacid sequences among SARS-CoV-2 andrepresentativebatandpangolincoronaviruses (Extended Data 

). Amongthe17 residuesthatinteractwithhACE2, 16 areconserved between SARS-CoV-2 and BANAL-52 or BANAL-103 (one mismatch,H498Q), and 15/17 areconservedfor BANAL-236 (two mismatches,K493Q and H498Q) whereasonly 13/17 residuesareconservedforthe Cambodianbat 
R
. 
shameli
virusand 11/17forthe Chinese bat 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
affinis
</tp:taxon-name>
RaTG13 virus. Atthe fullspike protein level,bat 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
affinis
</tp:taxon-name>
RaTG13 and pangolin-2017 P4L viruses seemed closer to SARS-CoV-2 thanbat 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-52,butthiseffectisduetoahigherdegree of conservation in S2. Allof thesevirusessharedtheabsenceof afurin cleavagesiteandtheconservationof theinternalfusionpeptide (Supplementary 

and 

and Extended Data 

).

</p>
      <p>
Interactionof BANALRBDswith ACE2

</p>
      <p>

Biolayer interferometry experiments to measure the interaction betweenhACE2andthe RBDsof BANAL-52/103(whichhaveidenticalresiduesinthereceptor-binding motif;Extended Data 

), BANAL-236 and SARS-CoV-2 (residues 233–524) resultedinadissociationconstant 
K
d
threetimeslowerfor the BANALRBDscompared to SARS-CoV-2 (

). Thishigheraffinitycanbeattributedto the Q498H mismatch that hasbeenreportedtoincreasethe affinityof the SARS-CoV-2 RBD for hACE2, and also to be involved in the host range expansion of SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV-2-like viruses 
22–29
.

</p>
      <p>

Tostudythe effectof the alterationsatthe interfacebetweenthese RBDsandhACE2,weperformedmoleculardynamics (MD) simulations of the complexes between the RBDs of SARS-CoV-2, BANAL-236 and BANAL-52/103 and hACE2 initiated from the crystal structure and homology models of these systems, respectively (Supplementary Table 6). Cluster analysis of the MD trajectories showed that, at the RBD–hACE2 interface,both BANAL complexes were identical to the complexbetweenthe SARS-CoV-2 RBDandhACE2within 2 Åbackbone root mean square deviation (RMSD; Extended Data 

), except for one of the BANAL-52/103 simulations that exhibited larger conformational variabilityof the RBD residues S443–Y449 (Supplementary Methodsand Extended Data 

). Empirical scoring functions 

predictedasimilar RBD–hACE2 bindingenergyin allthreecomplexes (Extended Data 

).


</p>
      <p>

Theanalysisof the persistence of hydrogenbonds and salt bridges provided further insights into the effect of the substitutions at the RBD–hACE2 interface (Fig. 3b and Extended Data 

). The H498Q mismatch present in both BANAL-52/103 and BANAL-236 RBDsdisruptedthe hydrogenbondsbetween RBDQ498 andbothhACE2 K353 and Q42. However,these hydrogenbondswere onlytransiently formed inthe SARS-CoV-2 complex: more persistent hydrogen bondsin this region (RBD T500 tohACE2 D355; RBDG502 tohACE2 K353; and RBD

Y505 tohACE2 E37) were not affected. The K493Q mismatch enabled 
the formationof two salt bridges between RBD and hACE2 that were not present in the SARS-CoV-2 complex (RBD K493 to hACE2 E35 and RBD K493 tohACE2 D38).

</p>
      <p>

Forfurther insight intothe molecular detailsof these interactions, we determined the crystal structure of the complex between the BANAL-236 RBD and the hACE2 peptidase domainto 2.9 Åresolution (Supplementary Table 7). The overallstructureof this RBDisidentical to that of SARS-CoV-2 (RMSD 0.360 Å, 150 Cα). The only significant difference isintheregion betweenamino acids D363and S375 (Fig. 3c, arrow).In thisregion,BANALspikes havethe A372T mismatch,which convertsthesequence 
370
NSA 
372
to 
370
NST 
372

, an 
N
-linkedglycosylation sequon.Thecrystalsindeedshowedclearelectrondensityforthefirst 
N
-acetylglucosamine residue of glycan attached to N370. The main chain at residue T372 makes a hydrogenbond with the glycan residue, alteringthe conformationof themain chaindownstream,which resultsinpartialunwindingofhelix H4 in RBD 236.Thecalculationof a simulatedannealingcompositeomitmapforthesegment D363–S375 confirmsthecorrectassignmentof thestructureforthispolypeptide segmentandthe 
N
-glycosylationatresidue N370(Extended Data 

).

</p>
      <p>

of the BANAL-236 spike-pseudotypedlentivirusintohACE2-expressing HEK-293T cells, but no such entry into control cells not expressing hACE2 (

). Entry was blocked by human sera neutralizing SARS-CoV-2,butnotbycontrolnon-neutralizingsera,demonstrating thatneutralizationof BANAL-236 wasspecificforepitopesshared with the spike proteinof SARS-CoV-2 (

).

</p>
      <p>

Toisolateinfectiousviruses,rectalswabswereinoculatedon VeroE6 cells.Nocytopathiceffect (CPE)wasobserved3 and 4daysafterinfection,butviral RNAsweredetected forone of the two wellsinoculated withthe BANAL-236 sample(cyclethreshold (Ct) = 25.1 atday 3, Ct = 21.7 atday 4). Theculturesupernatant (C1) formedplaques on VeroE6 and thetitrewas 3,800 pfu ml 
−1
.A C2 viralstockwaspreparedbyamplificationon VeroE6 atamultiplicityof infection (MOI) of 10 
−4
. Theculture supernatantwascollectedonday 4when CPEwasobservedandtitrated on VeroE6 (Extended Data 

). Theplaques’ phenotypewas small, butthetitrereached 2.6. 
106
pfu ml 
−1
.TherandomNGSperformedonthe RNAextractedfromthisstockconfirmedthattheculturewaspureand corresponded tothe BANAL-236 virus,without anynon-synonymous mutations between theoriginal BANAL-236 genome and the C2 viral stock.Replicationof BANAL-236 in VeroE6wasefficientlyinhibitedby soluble hACE2, thus showing that entry and propagation was largely ACE2 dependent (

Extended Data 

). Furthermore, BANAL-236replicatedinhumancelllinesexpressingendogenouslevels of ACE2,Calu-3and Caco-2(

).Thekineticsof RNAsynthesiswere

</p>
      <p>

Asexpected,most of the interactions observed inthe SARS-CoV-2 RBD–hACE2 complex 
30
arealsopresentinthestructureof thecomplex betweenthe BANAL-236 RBDandhACE2.Intheseinterfaces,thereare threemainclustersof interactions asindicated in 

(insets). The sequencemismatchesareinclusters2 (makingthesaltbridgebetween RBD K493 and hACE2 E35) and 3 (hydrogen bond between RBD H498 and D38). Althoughtheinteraction K493–E35 contributestostabilizing thecomplex,itdoesnotseemto markedlyaffectthebindingto hACE2 becauseboth BANALRBDshavesimilar 
K
d
values.

</p>
      <p>
Virusreplicationinhumancells

</p>
      <p>

To assess whetherthe BANAL-236 spike proteincould mediate entry intocellsexpressinghACE2,wegeneratedlentiviralparticlespseudotypedwithspikefromthe SARS-CoV-2 strainfirstdetected in Wuhanor BANAL-236 (Supplementary 

). Wedetectedspike-mediatedentry

</p>
      <p>

slowercompared to those for SARS-CoV-2. Infectious viral particles were produced at day 4 inthe supernatant of Caco-2 and Calu-3 cells (respectively 
104.7
and 
102.9
pfu ml 
−1

). 

Discussion

</p>
      <p>

Manysarbecovirusescirculatein 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
</tp:taxon-name>
colonieslivingin caves in Chinaandprobablyalsoinneighbouringcountriesfurthersouth 
31–33
. During the course of a prospective study in northern Laos, we have identified,amongothercoronaviruses,fivesarbecovirusesfor which we obtained full-length sequences.Among these, three (BANAL-52, BANAL-103 and BANAL-236)wereconsideredtobecloseto SARS-CoV-2 because of thesimilarity of one of the S1 domains (NTD or RBD) or S2 tothat of SARS-CoV-2.

</p>
      <p>
Asgenomicregionssubjecttorecombinationareprobablycontributing to host–virus interactions,we compared SARS-CoV-2 strains
fromthetwolineagesidentifiedattheonsetof thecoronavirusdisease 

2019 (COVID-19) outbreak 
21

tothesenew batsarbecovirusesandto pangolin strains in the SARS-CoV-2 clade.Strains close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
RpYN06, 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
RmYN02 and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. PrC31 isolated in Chinain 2018–2019, alongwith 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-52, 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-103 and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
marshalli
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-236 isolatedin Laosin 2020, contributed to theappearance of SARS-CoV-2 in differentregions of the genome.No closer viralgenome has yet been identified as a possible contributor,andpangolincoronavirusesseemmoredistantlyrelated than bat coronaviruses. We identified potential recombination sites, allowing for the reconstruction of the phylogenetic history of early isolated SARS-CoV-2 strainsbetweenhomologousregionsdefinedby recombination points.Weidentifieda breakpointatthe beginningof the SARS-CoV-2 RBD, resulting in a downstream fragment keyfor the virus tropism and host spectrum composed of the RBD and the furin cleavage site, andending inthe N-terminal region of S2. Despite the absence of the furinsite, phylogeneticreconstruction of this fragment showed that the Laotian 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-52, 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>

BANAL-103 and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
marshalli
</tp:taxon-name>
BANAL-236 coronaviruses are the closestancestorsof SARS-CoV-2 knownso far.ORF8 washighly divergent between SARS-CoV-2 relatedgenomes.The ORF8genesfromthestrains BANAL-52,BANAL-103 and BANAL-236,likethatof RaTG13,werecloser tothat of SARS-CoV-2thantothoseof pangolinstrains. 
ORF8
encodes aproteinthathasbeenproposedtoparticipateinimmuneevasion 
34
andisdeletedin manyhuman SARS-CoV-2strains thatappearedafter March 
202035
, whichisreminiscentof thedeletionsidentifiedduring the 2003 severeacuterespiratorysyndromeepidemic 
36
.Therefore,the presenceof ORF8 is consistent with batsacting as a natural reservoir of early strainsof SARS-CoV-2.

</p>
      <p>

theymaysharecavesasroostsitesandforaginghabitats 
44
.Withthenew virusesdescribed here,understanding theemergenceof SARS-CoV-2 doesnot requirespeculation of recombination or natural selection for increased RBD affinity for hACE2 in an intermediatehost such as thepangolinbefore spillover 
45
, nornatural selectioninhumans following spillover 
46
. However, wefoundnofurincleavagesiteinanyof these viruses onsequences determined directlyfrom original faecal swab samples,whichprevent fromanyriskof counterselectionof the furinsitebyamplificationin Verocells 
18
. Thelackof thefurincleavage site maybeexplained byinsufficientsampling inbats.Onthebasis of comparisonof thesequencesaroundthecleavagesitebetween S1 and S2(Extended Data 

), ithasbeensuggestedthatthefurincleavage sitein SARS-CoV-2 couldoriginatefromrecombinationeventsbetween SARS-CoV-2-related coronavirusesco-circulatingin bats 
2,47
, meaning that BANAL-116, BANAL-247, bat RmYN02 (ref. 
2
) and bat RacCS203 (ref. 
3
) coronavirusesmaysharea commonhistorywith SARS-CoV-2. Alternatively,thefurincleavagesitecouldhavebeenacquiredthrough passages of thevirus in an alternative host or during an earlypoorly symptomatic unreportedcirculation in humans. Finally,the epidemiological link between these batviruses and the first human cases remains tobe established.

</p>
      <p>

Structuraland functionalbiology studies have identified the RBD domainthatmediatestheinteractionwithhACE2 andhostrange,aswell asthemainaminoacidsthatareinvolved 
30,37,38
. The RBDs (BANAL-52, BANAL-103 and BANAL-236)areclosertothatof SARS-CoV-2 thanthatof anyotherbatstraindescribedsofar,includingthat of RaTG13,thevirus identified in 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
affinis
</tp:taxon-name>
fromthe Mojiang mineshaft wherepneumonia cases with clinical characteristics a posteriori interpreted as similar to COVID-19 (ref. 
6
) wererecordedin 
201239

,40

. Overall, one (H498Q (BANAL-103 and BANAL-52)) or two (K493Qand H498Q (BANAL-236)) aminoacids interactingwithhACE2 aresubstitutedin thesestrainsin comparison to SARS-CoV-2. These substitutions did not destabilize theinterfacebetween BANAL-236 andhACE2,asshownbythebiolayer interferometryexperiments(

) andanalysedby MDsimulations.

</p>
      <p>

Asexpectedfromthehighaffinityfor hACE2 of the Sectodomainof BANAL-236,pseudovirusesexpressing itwere abletoefficientlyenter humancellsexpressingendogenoushACE2 usingan ACE2-dependent pathway.However,alternativeroutesof entrymaystillexist,especially incellsthatdonotexpress ACE2 (ref. 
48
). Entrywasblockedbyaserum neutralizing SARS-CoV-2.The RaTG13 strain,theclosestto SARS-CoV-2 known previously,had never been isolated.Bycontrast, preliminary studies show that BANAL-236 replicated in primate VeroE6 cells with a small plaquephenotype compared tothat of SARS-CoV-2. Further analysis mayindicatemoreclearly whichsteps shape infectivity.

</p>
      <p>

Ourresultsthereforesupportthehypothesisthat SARS-CoV-2 could originallyresult from a recombinationof sequences pre-existing in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinolophus
</tp:taxon-name>
bats living in the extensive limestone cave systems of Southeast Asiaand South China 
41,42
. Manyspeciesforagein thesame cave areas,including 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
43
. In addition,the distributionsof 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
marshalli
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
malayanus
and
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
R
. 
pusillus
</tp:taxon-name>
overlap in the Indochinesesubregion (Supplementary 

), whichmeans that

</p>
      <p>

Toconclude,ourresultspinpointthepresenceof newbatsarbecovirusesthatseem tohavethesamepotentialforinfectinghumansasearly strainsof SARS-CoV-2.Guanocollectors,certainasceticreligiouscommunitieswhospendtimein orveryclosetocavesandtourists visiting caves areparticularlyatrisk ofbeing exposed. Furtherinvestigations are needed to assess whether such exposed populations have been infected,symptomaticallyornot,by oneof theseviruses,andwhether infectioncouldconferprotectionagainstsubsequent SARS-CoV-2infections. In this context,it is noteworthy that SARS-CoV-2 with the furin site deletedreplicates in hamsters and in transgenicmice expressing hACE2,butleadstolessseveredisease andprotectsfromrechallenge withwild-type SARS-CoV-2 (ref. 
18

).
</p>
      <p>
Onlinecontent

</p>
      <p>
Anymethods,additionalreferences,Nature Researchreportingsummaries, source data, extended data, supplementary information, acknowledgements,peerreviewinformation;detailsof authorcontributionsandcompetinginterests;andstatementsof dataandcodeavailabilityareavailable
athttps://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-04532-4.
</p>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <p>

1. 
Delaune,D.
etal. 
AnovelSARS-CoV-2 relatedcoronavirusinbatsfromCambodia
. 

Nat. Commun.

12

, 
6563
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

2. 
Zhou, H.
etal. 
Identificationofnovelbatcoronavirusesshedslightontheevolutionary originsof SARS-CoV-2 and related viruses
. 

Cell

184

, 
4380–4391
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

3. 
Wacharapluesadee,S.
etal. 
EvidenceforSARS-CoV-2 relatedcoronavirusescirculatingin bats and pangolins in Southeast Asia
. 

Nat. Commun.

12

, 
972
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

4. 
Murakami,S.
etal. 
Detectionandcharacterizationofbatsarbecovirusphylogenetically relatedto SARS-CoV-2,Japan
. 

Emerg. Infect.Dis.

26

, 
3025–3029
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

5. 
Zhou, P.
etal. 
Apneumoniaoutbreakassociatedwithanewcoronavirusofprobablebat origin
. 

Nature

579

, 
270–273
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

6. 
Rahalkar,M. C.
&amp; 
Bahulikar,R. A.
LethalpneumoniacasesinMojiangminers (2012) and the mineshaftcould provide important clues to the origin of SARS-CoV-2
. 

Front.Public Health

https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2020.581569
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

7. 
Liu, P.
etal. 
Arepangolinstheintermediatehostofthe 2019 novelcoronavirus (SARS-CoV-2)?
PLoS Pathog.

16

, e 
1008421
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

8. 
Xiao,K.
etal. 
IsolationofSARS-CoV-2-relatedcoronavirusfromMalayanpangolins
. 

Nature

583

, 
286–289
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

9. 
Wahba,L.
etal. 
Anextensivemeta-metagenomicsearchidentifiesSARS-CoV- 2-homologous sequences in pangolin lung viromes
. 

mSphere

5

, 
e00160-20
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

10. 
Letko,M.
, 
Marzi,A.
&amp; 
Munster,V.
Functionalassessmentofcellentryandreceptorusage for SARS-CoV-2 and other lineage B betacoronaviruses
. 

Nat.Microbiol.

5

, 
562–569
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

11. 
Shang,J.
etal. 
StructuralbasisofreceptorrecognitionbySARS-CoV-2
. 

Nature

581

, 
221–224
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

12. 
Wang,Q.
etal. 
StructuralandfunctionalbasisofSARS-CoV-2 entrybyusinghuman ACE2
. 

Cell

181

, 
894–904
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

13. 
Delaune,D.
etal. 
AnovelSARS-CoV-2 relatedcoronavirusinbatsfromCambodia
. 

Nat. Commun.

12

, 
6563
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

14. 
Jackson,B.
etal. 
Generationandtransmissionofinterlineagerecombinantsinthe SARS-CoV-2 pandemic
. 

Cell

184

, 
5179–5188
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

15. 
Rochman,N.D.
etal. 
OngoingglobalandregionaladaptiveevolutionofSARS-CoV-2
. 

Proc.NatlAcad.Sci. USA

118

, e 
2104241118
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

16. 
Liu, K.
etal. 
BindingandmolecularbasisofthebatcoronavirusRaTG13 virustoACE2 in humans and other species
. 

Cell

184

, 
3438–3451
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

17. 
Aicher,S.-M.
etal. 
Species-specificmolecularbarrierstoSARS-CoV-2 replicationinbat cells
. 

Preprint at 
bioRxiv

https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.31.446374
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

18. 
Johnson,B.A.
etal. 
LossoffurincleavagesiteattenuatesSARS-CoV-2 pathogenesis
. 

Nature

591

, 
293–299
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

19. 
Liu, K.
etal. 
Cross-speciesrecognitionofSARS-CoV-2 tobatACE2
. 

Proc.NatlAcad.Sci. USA

118

, e 
2020216118
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

20. 
Chu,D. K.W.
etal. 
Aviancoronavirusinwildaquaticbirds
. 

J. Virol.

85

, 
12815–12820
(
2011
).

</p>
         <p>

21. 
Rambaut,A.
etal. 
AdynamicnomenclatureproposalforSARS-CoV-2 lineagestoassist genomicepidemiology
. 

Nat.Microbiol.

5

, 
1403–1407
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

22. 
Wrapp,D.
etal. 
Cryo-EMstructureofthe 2019-nCoVspikeintheprefusionconformation
. 

Science

367

, 
1260–1263
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

23. 
Laffeber,C.
, 
deKoning,K.
, 
Kanaar,R.
&amp; 
Lebbink,J.H. G.
Experimentalevidencefor enhanced receptor binding by rapidly spreading SARS-CoV-2 variants
. 

J.Mol.Biol.

433

, 
167058
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

24. 
Lei, C.
etal. 
NeutralizationofSARS-CoV-2 spikepseudotypedvirusbyrecombinant ACE2-Ig
. 

Nat.Commun
.


11

, 
2070
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

25. 
Walls,A.C.
etal. 
Structure,function,andantigenicityoftheSARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein
. 

Cell

181

, 
281–292
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

26. 
Niu,S.
etal. 
Molecularbasisofcross-speciesACE2 interactionswithSARS-CoV-2-like viruses of pangolin origin
. 

EMBO J.

40

, e 
107786
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

27. 
Zhang,Y.
etal. 
SARS-CoV-2 rapidlyadaptsinagedBALB/cmiceandinducestypical pneumonia
. 

J.Virol.

95

, 
e02477–20
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

28. 
Huang,K.
etal. 
Q493KandQ498HsubstitutionsinSpikepromoteadaptationof SARS-CoV-2 in mice
. 

EBioMedicine

67

, 
103381
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

29. 
Zhang,S.
etal. 
Batandpangolincoronavirusspikeglycoproteinstructuresprovide insights into SARS-CoV-2 evolution
. 

Nat. Commun.

12

, 
1607
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

30. 
Lan,J.
etal. 
StructureoftheSARS-CoV-2 spikereceptor-bindingdomainboundtothe ACE2 receptor
. 

Nature

581

, 
215–220
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

31. 
Hu,B.
etal. 
DiscoveryofarichgenepoolofbatSARS-relatedcoronavirusesprovidesnew insights into the origin of SARScoronavirus
. 

PLoS Pathog.

13

, e 
1006698
(
2017
).

</p>
         <p>

32. 
Ge,X.-Y.
etal. 
IsolationandcharacterizationofabatSARS-likecoronavirusthatusesthe ACE2 receptor
. 

Nature

503

, 
535–538
(
2013
).

</p>
         <p>

33. 
Latinne,A.
etal. 
Originandcross-speciestransmissionofbatcoronavirusesinChina
. 

Nat.Commun.

11

, 
4235
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

34. 
Tan,Y.
, 
Schneider,T.
, 
Leong,M.
, 
Aravind,L.
&amp; 
Zhang,D.
Novelimmunoglobulindomain proteins provide insightsinto evolution and pathogenesis of SARS-CoV-2-related viruses
. 

mBio

https://doi.org/10.1128/mBio.00760-20
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

35. 
Su, Y.C.F.
etal. 
Discoveryandgenomiccharacterizationofa 382-nucleotidedeletion in ORF7b and ORF8 during the early evolution of SARS-CoV-2
. 

mBio

11

, 
e01610-20
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

36. 
ChineseSARSMolecularEpidemiologyConsortium
. 
MolecularevolutionoftheSARS coronavirus during the course of the SARS epidemic in China
. 

Science

303

, 
1666–1669
(
2004
).

</p>
         <p>

37. 
Conceicao,C.
etal. 
TheSARS-CoV-2 Spikeproteinhasabroadtropismformammalian ACE2 proteins
. 

PLoS Biol.

18

, e 
3001016
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

38. 
Damas,J.
etal. 
BroadhostrangeofSARS-CoV-2 predictedbycomparativeandstructural analysisofACE2 invertebrates
. 

Proc.NatlAcad.Sci.USA

117

, 
22311–22322
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

39. 
Cohen,J.
WuhancoronavirushunterShiZhenglispeaksout
. 

Science

369

, 
487–488
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

40. 
Ge,X.-Y.
etal. 
Coexistenceofmultiplecoronavirusesinseveralbatcoloniesinan abandoned mineshaft
. 

Virol.Sin.

31

, 
31–40
(
2016
).

</p>
         <p>

41. 
Clements,R.
, 
Sodhi,N. S.
, 
Schilthuizen,M.
&amp; 
Ng, P. K.L.
LimestonekarstsofSoutheast Asia:imperiled arks of biodiversity
. 

BioScience

56

, 
733–742
(
2006
).

</p>
         <p>

42. 
Hassanin,A.
, 
Tu,V.T.
, 
Curaudeau,M.
&amp; 
Csorba,G.

Inferringtheecologicalnicheofbat viruses closely related to SARS-CoV-2 using phylogeographic analyses of 
Rhinolophus
species

. 

Sci. Rep.

11

, 
14276
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

43. 
Soisook,P.
etal. 

Ataxonomicreviewof 
Rhinolophusstheno
and 
R.malayanus
(Chiroptera: Rhinolophidae) from continental Southeast Asia:an evaluation of echolocation call frequency in discriminating between cryptic species

. 

Acta Chiropt.

10

, 
221–242
(
2008
).

</p>
         <p>

44. 
Francis,C.
FieldGuidetotheMammalsofSouth-eastAsia
2ndedn

(
BloomsburyWildlife
, 
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

45. 
Makarenkov,V.
, 
Mazoure,B.
, 
Rabusseau,G.
&amp; 
Legendre,P.
Horizontalgenetransferand recombination analysis of SARS-CoV-2 genes helps discover its close relatives and shed light on its origin
. 

BMC Ecol. Evol.

21

, 
5
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

46. 
Andersen,K. G.
, 
Rambaut,A.
, 
Lipkin,W.I.
, 
Holmes,E. C.
&amp; 
Garry,R.F.
Theproximalorigin of SARS-CoV-2
. 

Nat.Med.

26

, 
450–452
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

47. 

Lytras,S. 
TheSarbecovirusoriginofSARS-CoV-

2’sfurincleavagesite. 

Virologicalhttps
:// virological.org/t/the-sarbecovirus-origin-of-sars-cov-2-s-furin-cleavage-site/536/6

(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

48. 
Puray-Chavez,M.
etal. 
SystematicanalysisofSARS-CoV-2 infectionofanACE2-negative human airway cell
. 

Cell Rep.

36

, 
109364
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

49. 
Katoh,K.
, 
Rozewicki,J.
&amp; 
Yamada,K.D.
MAFFTonlineservice:multiplesequence alignment,interactive sequence choice and visualization
. 

Brief.Bioinform.

20

, 
1160–1166
(
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

50. 
Lemoine,F.
etal. 
NGPhylogeny.fr:newgenerationphylogeneticservicesfor non-specialists
. 

NucleicAcidsRes.

47

, 
W260–W265
(
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

51. 
Lole,K. S.
etal. 
Full-lengthhumanimmunodeficiencyvirustype 1 genomesfromsubtype C-infected seroconverters in India,with evidence of intersubtype recombination
. 

J.Virol.

73

, 
152–160
(
1999
).

</p>
         <p>
Methods

</p>
      </sec>
      <p>
Ethicalandlegal statements

</p>
      <p>

Thebat study wasapproved bythe wildlife authorities of the Department of Forest Resource Management (DFRM), and the Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry (MAF), Lao People’s Democratic Republic, no. 2493/DFRM, issued on 21 May 2020 andno. 0755/MAF issued on 2June 2020.Allanimalswerecaptured,handledandsampledfollowing previouslypublishedprotocolsand ASMguidelines 
52,53
. Exportation from Laos and importation in France were conducted according to national regulations.Human serum samples usedfor neutralization assayswerealreadyavailable 
54
andselectedonthebasisof theirstatus regardingseroneutralizationof SARS-CoV-2.Theywerecollectedfollowingaprotocolapprovedbythe Lao National Ethics Committee for Health Research (NECHR; referenceno. 052/2020).

</p>
      <p>
Biosafety

</p>
      <p>
Boththe Institut Pasteurdu Laos (IPL)andthe Facultyof Environmental Sciencehaveextensiveexperienceinsafelycollectingbats (appropriate biosafetytrainingandpersonalprotectiveequipment (PPE) forcollectors). Inthis study, training before fieldwork was organizedonce for fieldworkparticipants.Theaimwastoteachparticipantsthetransmissionrisksof infectiousagentsfrombatsand howtoidentify,assessand mitigatetheserisks,as welltopracticethe useof PPE.
</p>
      <p>
During field collection, sampling stations were selected to minimize potential exposure to infectious agents and stress on the animalsduring thehandlingtimebyselecting:anareaeasytodisinfect; an area out of view of the general public; a location that would not causeexposure of the generalpopulation (suchas a picnicarea);and procedures that reduce time andstress on batscaused by handling. For handling batsand bat samples, the following minimum PPE was required: eye protection, an N95 respirator, long clothing/coverall andlatexgloves (2 pairs).All wastewasdisposed of inbiohazardbags andwastransportedtoadisposal siteof IPL in Vientianecapital.Each sample box containing 81 cryovial tubes was placed inside an individualplasticziplockand transportedfromthe field to IPLondryice in a polystyrene foam box. At IPL, samples were stored in a specific −80 °C freezer until analysis.
</p>
      <p>
For initial sample analysis at IPL, samples were transferred to a BSL-3 roomfornucleicacidextraction.Initialcoronavirusscreening by nested RT-PCR was then performed under internalregulation on biosafetyandsecurityof IPL. Sample-extractedproducts (50 Μl) were storedin NucleoSpin8 sampleboxes (8 × 12)andsentto IP-Parispacked inindividualplasticziplockbagsondryice.Aliquotsof analswabsamplesweresentindividuallytriplepackagedondryiceinaseparatebox.
</p>
      <p>
All experiments on potentially infectious samples performed at Institut Pasteur (Paris)wereconductedin BSL-3 laboratoriesaccording toproceduresadapted for respiratory viruses.
</p>
      <p>
Batsamplingareas andsamplecollection

</p>
      <p>

Trappingsessionswereconductedatfoursites,inthe Fuengand Meth districts, Vientiane province, and in the Namor and Xay districts, Oudomxayprovince,between July 2020 and January 2021 (

Supplementary Tables 1 and 2). Bats were captured using four-bank harp traps 
55
andmistnetssetinforestpatchesbetweenricefieldsor orange/banana plantations andkarst limestoneformations, for 5–8 nightsdepending on accessibility.Harp traps were setacross natural trailsinpatches offorestunderstorey.Mistnets weresetacrossnatural trails,at the edges of forests, at entrances of caves andin areas near caveentrances,aswellasinopenareasorthosewithhighforestcanopy. Batsweremorphologically identified followingmorphological criteria 
55–57
.Otherdatasuchasforearmlength (FA),sex,developmentalstage (adultorjuvenile) andreproductivecondition (pregnantorlactating) werealsorecorded.Batsweresampledforsaliva,faeces and/or urine, andblood beforerelease atthe capture site. Speciesidentificationof


PCR-positiveindividualswasconfirmedbysequencingthemitochondrialcytochromeoxidase 1 (ref. 
20

).
</p>
      <p>
Initialcoronavirusscreening

</p>
      <p>

Total RNA was extractedfrom faecal samples using the NucleoSpin 8 viruskit (Macherey Nagel).cDNAwas synthesizedusingthe Maxima H minusfirststrandcDNAsynthesiskit(Thermo Scientific)andrandom hexamers following the manufacturer’sinstructions. Thepresence of coronaviruseswas tested bya nested RT-PCR approach using PCR mastermix (Promega) andbytargetingthe RNA-dependent RNAPolymerase gene using combinations of degenerateand non-degenerate consensus primersaspreviously described 
20
. PCR productsof the expected size were directly sequenced on both strands by Sanger sequencing using the nested PCR primers.The sequences obtained were confirmed bysimilarity analysisusing the NCBI BLASTnsearch (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST).

</p>
      <p>

Primerdesignfor 
Betacoronavirus
enrichmentbefore NGS


</p>
      <p>
Betacoronavirus
enrichment was performed atthe genus level by adapting a previously described protocol 
58
based on 
k
-mers for targeted-sequence enrichment before NGS. Briefly,2,000 complete 
Betacoronavirus
genomes were downloaded from the GenBank and GISAID databasesandthenclusteredtoa 95% sequenceidentityusing CD-HIT-EST (ref. 
59
). Overall,185 representativesequencesof allbetacoronaviruses wereused for further analysis. Owingto the high diversity inthe genus 
Betacoronavirus
, thefull genomes belonging tothe subgenera 
Sarbecovirus
, 
Nobecovirus
, 
Merbecovirus
and 
Embecovirus
were separately aligned using MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software andused to design 13-merspiked primers for each cluster. The genomicpositionof thefullsetof primerswasextractedfromsome representativesubgenerasequencesand closeprimerswereremoved. Finally,416 spikedprimers weresynthesizedby Eurofins Genomics.

</p>
      <p>
Sample preparationfor sequencing

</p>
      <p>

Reverse transcription was performed using the mix of spiked primers and random hexamers at a 10:1 ratio using the SuperScript IV First-Strand Synthesis System (Invitrogen).Aftera denaturationstep at 95 °Cfor 3 min in thepresenceof dNTPs (500 ΜM), DTT (5 mM) and RNaseOUT inhibitor,thereversetranscriptionreactionwas incubated for 10 thermalcyclesconsistingof 6 stepsat8 °Cfor 12 s,15 °Cfor 45 s, 20 °Cfor 45 s,30 °Cfor30 s,35 °Cfor 2 minand 42 °Cfor 3 min,followed byafinalincubationstepat 42 °Cfor20 min,aspreviouslydescribed 
60
. Double-stranded cDNA was generated using the Sequenase 2.0 DNA Polymerasekit (Applied Biosystems)inthepresenceof dNTPs andthen purified using the Beckman Coulter Agencourt AMPure XP.

</p>
      <p>
For samples witha low nucleic acidcontent,a random amplificationstepwasperformedusingthe MALBACSingle Cell WGAkit(Yikon Genomics,Promega). Theamplified productwas then purifiedusing AMPure XP Beads, eluted in afinal volume of 20 Μl of low TE (10 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8,0), 0,1 mM EDTA), and quantified with the Qubit DNA HS Assay (Life Technologies,Thermo Fisher Scientific).
</p>
      <p>
Libraries were generated using the NEBNext Ultra II DNALibrary Prep kit (New England Biolabs) after afragmentation step using the Covaris M220 Focused-ultrasonicator usingmicroTUBE-15 (peakincidentpower = 18 W, dutyfactor = 20%,cyclesperburst = 50, treatment time = 60 s). The PCR-amplifiedlibraries were cleanedup using 0.9× AMPure XP Beads and checked onthe 2100 Bioanalyzer system with the High-Sensitivity DNAkit (Agilent Technologies) andquantifiedwith the Qubit DNA HS Assay.Finally,the dual-multiplexed libraries were pooled (six samples per pool) and run on the Illumina NextSeq500 platform with High Output Kitversion 2.5 (150 cycles).
</p>
      <p>
Amplicon sequencing

</p>
      <p>In addition to enrichment-based sequencing, cDNA was amplified usingthe AmpliSeqfor Illumina SARS-CoV-2 Research Panel (catalogue number 20020496), applying 26 amplification cycles in PCR1 and 9 cycles in PCR2. Primers at the end of the amplicons were partially digestedduringthelibrarypreparation,followingthemanufacturer’s instructions.Libraries werebarcoded individually using the Illumina UDdualindicesandnormalizedwiththe AmpliSeq Library Equalizerfor Illumina (cataloguenumber20019171),andthenpooledandsequenced onthe Illumina NextSeq500 instrument using a Mid Output version 2.5 kit (SR 150 cycles). To eliminate residual PCRprimer sequences, rawreads weretrimmedby 15 bases ateachend andspecial attention was paidto checkingthatinternalsequencescorrespondingtoprimer regionsinoverlappingampliconsdidnotderivefromprimersequences of themultiplex PCR.Asaninternalcontrol,weverifiedthatsequences of the complete genome of sample BANAL-236 obtained from the enrichment-based sequencing approach and from the AmpliSeq approach wereidentical.</p>
      <p>
Genomeassembly andfinishing
</p>
      <p>
Raw reads from the enrichment-based sequencing were processed withanin-housebioinformaticspipeline (Microseek;Bigot T. etal., unpublished observations) comprising quality check and trimming, readnormalization,denovoassembly,and ORF predictionof contigs and singletons, followedby threelevelsof taxonomicassignation 
61
. Sequencesidentifiedas 
Sarbecovirus
werethenmappedontoappropriatereference sequences using CLCGenomics Workbench 20.0 (Qiagen). Trimmedreads from the ampliconsequencing weremapped to the SARS-CoV-2 genome first,and then mappedagain (refined mapping) totheclosestgenomerelative.Whenneeded,completegenomes were obtained by conventional PCR and Sanger sequencing. Briefly, viral RNA was reverse transcribed using SuperScript IV reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen) andcDNAwassubsequentlyusedtofillthegaps in the genomes using Phusion High Fidelity DNA polymerase (New England Biolabs) and specific primers flanking the missingregions. Positive PCRproductswerefurther purifiedandsequencedby Sanger sequencing at Eurofins Genomics. 

Recombinationandphylogeneticanalyses

Identificationof recombinationeventsoccurringduringtheevolutionaryhistoryofbatsarbecoviruseswasperformedusingthe IDPlotpackage 
62
, aweb-basedworkflowthatincludesmultiplesequencealignment andphylogeny-basedbreakpointpredictionusingthe GARDalgorithm fromthe HyPhygeneticanalysissuite 
63
.First,acomprehensiveanalysis comprising 106 sequencesand covering all non-human 
Sarbecovirus
and 
Sarbecovirus
-related complete genomes available in GenBank and GISAIDdatabaseswasperformed,includingprototype strainsof SARS-CoV-2 isolatedin 2019. Special attention was paid to including bat-borneandpangolin-borneviralsequencestomaximizetheability tocapturea largediversityof thesarbecoviruses.Then, areducedset of 36 sequenceswas chosen because of theirphylogeneticproximity to SARS-CoV-2, and the GARD algorithm was run to identify recombinationbreakpointsin Laotianandrepresentativehuman, batand pangolin sarbecoviruses.Breakpointcoordinates wereconfirmedby performing phylogenetic analyses on thecorresponding fragments usingPhyMLimplementedthroughthe NGPhylogenyportal 
50
.Branch support wasevaluatedwith the aBayesparameter.
</p>
      <p>
Rectalswabswereinoculatedinduplicatein 24-wellplatescontaining VeroE6 cells (ATCC CRL-1586) (1/5 dilution in 100 Μl DMEM without FCS supplemented with 1% penicillin–streptomycin,1% Fungizone and 1 Μgml 
−1 TPCK-treatedtrypsin).After 1 hofadsorptionat 37 °C, inoculum was removed and 1 ml of the medium described above was added. At 3 and 4 days after infection, CPE was monitored and 100 Μl of supernatant was collectedfor RNA extraction.Quantitative RT-PCR targeting a conserved sequence in the Egene was performed asdescribedpreviously66
. Culturesupernatant (C1) was collectedat day 4 and titrated by plaque assay on VeroE6 overlaid with 0.5% carboxymethylcellulosecontaining 1 Μgml 
−1 TPCK-treatedtrypsin.Aviral stockwaspreparedbyamplificationon VeroE6 cellsatanMOIof 10−4
. Culturesupernatant (C2)wascollectedatday 4whenamassive CPEwas observed and titratedby plaqueassay on VeroE6 as described above. A C3 viralstockwasproducedbyasubsequentviralamplificationatan MOIof 10 
−4
for3dayson VeroE6.RNAwasextractedfromtheviralstock and submitted to random NGS analysis using the SMARTer Stranded Total RNA-Seq Kitversion 3 - Pico Input Mammalian (Takara Bio). Raw readswereprocessedwiththe Microseekpipeline,asdescribedabove. Forinfectionexperiments,VeroE6orthehumancelllinesCalu-3(lung cells,ATCC HTB-55) and Caco-2 (intestinal cells, ATCC HTB-37) were infected intriplicate in 24-well plateswith viral stocks of BANAL-236 (C3) or SARS-CoV-2 (strain BetaCoV/France/IDF0372/2020) atan MOIof 0.0001 and 0.01, respectively.Humansoluble ACE2 waspre-incubated at 25 Μgml 
−1 (ref. 67) for 30 minwiththeviralinoculumbefore VeroE6 infection. Infections werecarried out without TPCK in the medium described above for 3 and 4 days. Supernatants were recovered at 0,
3 and 4 days post-infection and genome copy number and viraltitres werequantifiedas described above.
</p>
      <p>
Generationof lentiviralpseudoviruses

Thesynthetic genesencoding spikein BANAL-236 and in SARS-CoV-2 (strain BetaCoV/France/IDF0372/2020, GISAID accessionnumber EPI_ISL_406596) were cloned into thepVAX1 vector with acytoplasmictailtruncationof 19 aminoacids.Pseudotypedlentiviralparticles werepreparedusing HEK-293T cells (ATCCCRL-3216)seededin 10-cm dishes.HEK-293T cells wereco-transfectedwith5 Μgof spike-encoding plasmid, 10 Μg oflentiviral backbone plasmidexpressing the firefly luciferase (pHAGE-CMV-Luc2-IRES-ZsGreen-W) and 3.3 Μg of each lentiviral helper plasmid expressing HIV Gag-Pol (HDM-Hgpm2), Tat (HDM-tat1b)and Rev (pRC-CMV-Rev1b) usingcalciumphosphateprecipitation 
64
. Themediumwasreplaced 5 hpost-transfectionby 6 mlof DMEMwithoutfetalcalf serum (FCS)andphenolred.Pseudotypedparticleswerecollected 48 hpost-transfection,clarifiedbycentrifugation at 2,500 
g
for 5 minandfrozenat −80 °C. Mockpseudotypedlentivirus wasgeneratedasabovebutintheabsenceof an S-expressingplasmid.
</p>
      <p>
Spike-pseudotypedlentivirus entryassays

</p>
      <p>
HEK-293T cellsstablyexpressinghACE2weretransducedinsuspension bymixing 50 Μlof threefoldserialdilutionsof S-pseudotypedlentiviruseswith 50 Μlof cellsat 4 × 
105 cellspermlin 96-well white culture plates65
. At60–72 hpost-transduction,100 Μlof Bright-Gloluciferase substrate (Promega) was added to the wells and luminescence was measured using a Berthold Centro XSluminometer.
</p>
      <p>
NeutraliZation assays
</p>
      <p>
Seraneutralizing SARS-CoV-2 andnon-neutralizingseraweredescribed inref. 54
.Theyweredecomplementedat56 °Cfor30 minand 2.5 Μlwas incubated with 0.5 Μl of S-pseudotyped lentivirusesin a final volume of 50 Μl DMEM–10% FCS without phenol red in 96-well white culture plates.After 30 min at room temperature,50 Μl of hACE2-expressing HEK-293T cellsinsuspensionat 4 × 
105
cellspermlwasmixedintothe wells.Luminescence was measured at 60–72 h post-transduction as described above. Neutralization wascalculated using the following formula:1 − (RLU in presence of serum/(mean of RLU in absence of serum determinedin 12 wells − 3 × s.d.).
</p>
      <p>
Virusisolationandmultiplication

</p>
      <p>
Proteinexpressionandpurification

</p>
      <p>
BANAL-52/103, BANAL-236 and SARS-CoV-2 RBDs (residues 233–524, withcarboxy-terminal 8×His-Strepand AVItags) andhACE2 peptidase domain (residues 19–615,with C-terminal8×His tag)wereexpressedin Expi293F cellsat 37 °Cand 8% CO 
2
(GnTI- Expi293,ThermoFisher Scientific).Cell culturesupernatantswerecollected5 daysposttransfection and purified by affinity chromatography followedby size-exclusion 
chromatography(SEC)usinga 20010/300 GLcolumnpre-equilibrated in 20 mMTris-HCl pH 8.0, 100 mMNaCl.
</p>
      <p>
Forcrystallizationexperiments,the sameconstructswereexpressed in Expi293F GnTI cells.The protein tagswere cleaved overnight with thrombin anddeglycosylated with EndoH.The RBD wasmixed with a 1.3 molar excess ofhACE2 and thecomplexwas purifiedby SEC.
</p>
      <p>
Biolayerinterferometry

</p>
      <p>
Purified Avi-tagged RBDwasbiotinylated using a BirA biotin–protein ligase kit according to the manufacturer’s instructions (Avidity). Thebiotinylated RBDsat100 nMwereimmobilizedto SAsensors.A 1:2 dilutionseriesofhACE2 startingat 100 nMin PBS–BSAbufferwasused in cyclesof 200-s associationfollowed by 200-s dissociationsteps to determineprotein–proteinaffinity.Thedatawerebaseline-subtracted andthe plotswerefitted usingthe Pall FortéBio/Sartorius analysis software (version 12.0). Datawereplotted in Prism 9.1.0.
</p>
      <p>
CrystalliZationanddatacollection

</p>
      <p>

Crystalsof thecomplex BANAL-236 RBD–hACE2 wereobtainedat 4 °Cin sittingdropsbymixing 200 nlof theproteincomplexat8 mg ml 
−1
with 200 nlof reservoirsolutioncontaining0.2 Mlithium sulfate,0.1 MTris 8.5,30% w/v PEG 4000. Thecrystals weresoakedin reservoirsolution containing 20% glycerolasacryoprotectantbeforebeingflash-frozen inliquidnitrogen.X-raydiffractiondatawerecollectedonthebeamline PROXIMA 1 atthe SOLEILsynchrotron (St Aubin,France)andreduced usingtheXDSpackage 
68
. Thestructureofthecomplexwasdetermined bymolecularreplacementwith Phasersoftware 
69
usingthecoordinates of the SARS-CoV-2 RBD in complex with hACE2 as asearch template (Protein Data Bank (PDB) 6M0J). The model was manually corrected in COOT (ref. 
70
) andrefinedwithphenix.refine (ref. 
71
). Thefinalcoordinatesweredepositedinthe PDBwiththeaccessioncode 7PKI.

</p>
      <p>
MDsimulationsof RBD–hACE2 complexes

</p>
      <p>

Generationof homologymodels.Homologymodelsof thecomplexes betweenthe RBDsof BANAL-236 and BANAL-52/103 andhACE2 were constructed using the X-ray structureof the complex between the SARS-CoV-2 RBDandhACE2 (PDBcode 6M0J; resolution 2.45 Å) as atemplateusing MODELLERversion 10.1 (ref. 
72
). These modelsincluded the fragments S19–D615 and T333–G526 of hACE2 and RBD, respectively, which were the regions resolved in the template. In these regions,BANAL-236 and BANAL-52/103 RBDs have asequence identity to SARS-CoV-2 RBD equal to 96.9% and 97.4%, respectively. Thealignmentreportedin Extended Data 

wasused.Thezinc and chlorideatomsin thetemplate wereretainedduringhomology modelling; 
N
-acetylglucosamine (NAG) andwaterresidueswereremoved. Seven disulfide bonds were detectedby MODELLER in the template (three in hACE2 and four in the RBD) and enforced in thegeneration of the homology models using CHARMM-like distance anddihedral anglesrestraints.Foreachconstruct,100homologymodels werebuilt andrankedonthebasisof thenormalized DOPEscore 
73
.Thetopthree scoringmodelsof eachcomplexwereusedas startingpointsof three independent MDsimulations,as described inthe followingsection.

</p>
      <p>

Set-up, equilibration and production of the MD simulations. The six homology models described in the previous section along with the X-raystructureof the SARS-CoV-2 RBD–hACE2 complex (PDBcode 6M0J) wereusedasinputtothe CHARMM-GUIserver 
74
. Inthecaseof the X-raystructure,for consistency with the homology models, the zinc and chloride atoms in 6M0Jwere retained whereas the NAGand water residues were removed. The seven systems were solvated in a triclinic box of initial 
xyZ
dimensions of ~13.5 nm × 9.2 nm × 8.3 nm. Potassium and chloride ions were added to ensure charge neutrality at a salt concentration of 0.15 M. The total number of atoms was ~104,000. Further details of the systems are reported in Supplementary Table 4. The CHARMM36m force field 
75
wasusedforthe protein


and ions, and the TIP3P model 
76
wasusedfor the water molecules. CHARMM36m force field parametersfor the seven pairs of cysteines linked by disulfidebonds wereused.The CHARMM-GUImodelswere first energy-minimized usingthe steepest descent algorithm.After minimization,thesystemswereequilibratedusinga 1-ns-longsimulationinthe NPT ensemblefollowedbya 1-ns-longsimulationinthe NVT ensemble.Thetemperature 
T
wassetat 300 Kandthe pressure 
P
was setto 1 atmusingthe Bussi–Donadio–Parrinello thermostat 
77
andthe Berendsenbarostat 
78
, respectively. During equilibration, harmonic restraintsonthepositionsof theproteinbackboneandsidechainheavy atoms wereapplied.Foreachsystemstudied,productionsimulations were performed in the NVT ensemble for 1 Μs.Atime stepof 2 fs was usedtogetherwith LINCSconstraintsonhydrogenbonds 
79
.Thevander Waalsinteractionsweregraduallyswitchedoff at 1.0 nmandcutoff at 1.2 nm; theparticlemesh Ewaldmethodwasusedtocalculateelectrostaticinteractionswithacutoff at 1.2 nm (ref. 
80
). Production simulations were performedat room temperature forconsistency withthe biolayer interferometryexperiments.

</p>
      <p>

Details of the analysis.Toevaluatethestabilityof thestartingmodel duringtheproductionsimulations,wecalculatedthebackbone RMSD with respecttothe energy-minimizedstructure foreachframe of the trajectories.The RMSD was calculatedseparately forthe residues in the RBD (Extended Data 

), thehACE2 (Extended Data 

), the RBD–hACE2 interface(Extended Data 

) andtheentire complex (Extended Data 

). Interfacial residues weredefined as the residuesin onesubunitcloserthan 0.8 nmtothe residuesintheother subunitinthe X-raystructureof thecomplexbetweenthe SARS-CoV-2 RBD and hACE2. RMSD calculationswere performed using the driver utilityof PLUMEDversion 2.7(ref. 
81
). Tocharacterizeconformational heterogeneity at the RBD–hACE2 interface, we performed a cluster analysis of the MDtrajectories using as similarity metrics the backbone RMSD of the interfacial residues and the GROMOS clustering approach 
82
with acutoff equalto 0.2 nm. The ninetrajectorieswere first concatenated, clustering was then performed, and finally the populationof eachclusterwascalculatedseparatelyforeachtrajectory (Extended Data 

). Toestimatethebindingenergybetween RBD andhACE2,weusedthe InterfaceAnalyzertoolin ROSETTAversion 3.11 (ref. 
83
; Extended Data 

) andthe AnalyseComplextoolin FoldX version 4 (ref. 
84
; Extended Data 

). Toidentifyrelevantinteractionsatthe RBD–hACE2 interfacethatcouldcontributetothebinding affinity of the complex, we quantified thefrequency of formation of inter-subunitsaltbridges (

)andhydrogenbonds (Extended Data 

) duringthe course of the MDsimulations.For eachframeof the trajectories,weused PLUMED tocalculatethe distances between the side-chainchargedgroupsof asparticacids (OD1/OD2),glutamicacids (OE1/OE2), lysines(NZ)andarginines (NH1/NH2). Aninter-subunitsalt bridgewasthendefinedasformedif thedistancebetweengroupswith opposite chargewaslowerthan0.32 nm.Weconfirmedthiscalculation usingthe Salt Bridgestoolavailablein VMD (ref. 
85
). Tomonitorthe formation of inter-subunit hydrogen bonds, weused the Hydrogen Bond Analysismoduleof the MDAnalysislibraryversion 1.0.0(ref. 
86
). A donor–acceptordistanceandangularcutoff of 0.3 nmand 150° were used todefine the formation of a hydrogen bond. We confirmed this calculation using the Hydrogen Bondstoolavailable in VMD.

</p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Reporting summary

</title>
         <p>
Further information on research design is available in the Nature Research Reporting Summarylinked tothis paper.
</p>
         <p>
Dataavailability

</p>
         <p>
Sequencedatathatsupportthefindingsof thisstudyhavebeendeposited in the GenBankand GISAID (https://www.gisaid.org/)databases with the following accessionnumbers:MZ937000/EPI_ISL_4302644

(BANAL-52), MZ937001/EPI_ISL_4302645 (BANAL-103), MZ937002/ EPI_ISL_4302646 (BANAL-116), MZ937003/EPI_ISL_4302647 (BANAL- 236) and MZ937004/EPI_ISL_4302648 (BANAL-247).Rawsarbecovirus NGSreadsand Sangersequencing.ab1 fileshavebeendepositedinthe National Centerfor Biotechnology Information Sequence Read Archive repositoryunderthe BioProjectcode PRJNA796968 (SAMN24959173– SAMN24959177).Thecrystalstructurepresentedinthismanuscripthas beendepositedinthe PDBwiththeaccessioncode 7PKI. The GROMACS topology and input filesas well as the analysis scriptsused are freely available on PLUMED-NEST (www.plumed-nest.org) underaccession IDplumID:21.037. Sourcedata areprovidedwith this paper. 
<p>
Codeavailability
</p>
         </p>
         <p>

MODELLERversion10.1 (https://salilab.org/modeller/) and GROMACS version 2020.4 (http://www.gromacs.org) were used for MD simulations.XDS(version5 February 2021), CCP4 (v 7.0), COOT(version0.8.6) and PHENIX (version 1.19.2-4158) software programs were used for X-ray diffraction data processing, model buildingand refinement of thecomplexbetweenthe BANAL-236 RBDandhACE2.PyMOL(version 2.4.2) was used forstructural imagerendering. PLUMEDversion 2.7 (https://www.plumed.org), ROSETTAversion 3.11 (https://www.rosettacommons.org/), FoldXversion4 (http://foldxsuite.crg.eu/), MDAnalysis version 1.0.0 (https://www.mdanalysis.org/), MDTraj version 1.9.5 (https://www.mdtraj.org/1.9.5/index.html) and in-housescripts availableathttps://github.com/maxbonomi/bat-MDwereusedfor MD simulations. hyphy 2.5.31, PhyMLand MAFFT implemented through NGPphylogeny (https://ngphylogeny.fr/) and Simplot 3.5.1wereused for phylogenetic and recombination analyses.MSSPE 1 was usedfor 
Betacoronavirus
primerenrichmentdesignandisavailable athttps:// github.com/chiulab/MSSPE-design.MICROSEEKisanin-housepipeline thatuses ALIENTRIMMERversion 2.0(https://gitlab.pasteur.fr/GIPhy/ AlienTrimmer) for read trimming/clipping, BBNORM from BBMAP version 38.86package (https://sourceforge.net/projects/bbmap/) for coveragenormalization,MEGAHIT version1.2.9(https://github.com/ voutcn/megahit)forassembly,anin-houseORF-finder(https://figshare. com/articles/code/translateReads_py/7588592), and then DIAMOND version 2.0.4 (https://github.com/bbuchfink/diamond/) and NCBI BLAST version 2.12.0+ (ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/blast/executables/ blast+/2.12.0/) both for sequencesearching.

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <p>

52. 
PREDICTOneHealthConsortium
. 

ProtocolforBatandRodentSamplingMethods

(
2013
).


53. 
Sikes,R.S.
, 
Gannon,W.L.
&amp; 
theAnimalCareandUseCommitteeoftheAmericanSociety of Mammalogists.Guidelines of the American Societyof Mammalogists for the use of wild mammals in research
. 

J.Mammal.

92

, 
235–253
(
2011
).

</p>
         <p>

54. 
Virachith,S.
etal. 
LowseroprevalenceofCOVID-19 inLaoPDR,late 2020
. 

LancetReg. Health West Pac.

13

, 
100197
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

55. 
Francis,C.
Acomparisonofmistnetsandtwodesignsofharptrapsforcapturingbats
. 

J.Mammal.

70

, 
865–870
.

</p>
         <p>

56. 
Corbet,G.B.
&amp; 
Hill,J. E.
MammalsoftheIndomalayanRegion: aSystematicReview

(
Oxford Univ.Press &amp; Natural History Museum
, 
1992
).

</p>
         <p>

57. 
Csorba,G.
, 
Ujhelyi,P.
&amp; 
Thomas,N.
HorseshoeBatsoftheWorld (Chiroptera: rhinolophidae)

(
Alana Books
, 
2003
).

</p>
         <p>

58. 
Deng,X.
etal. 
Metagenomicsequencingwithspikedprimerenrichmentforviral diagnostics andgenomic surveillance
. 

Nat.Microbiol.

5

, 
443–454
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

59. 
Fu, L.
, 
Niu,B.
, 
Zhu,Z.
, 
Wu,S.
&amp; 
Li, W.
CD-HIT:acceleratedforclusteringthe next-generation sequencingdata
. 

Bioinformatics

28

, 
3150–3152
(
2012
).

</p>
         <p>

60. 
Regnault,B.
etal. 
Deepimpactofrandomamplificationandlibraryconstructionmethods on viral metagenomics results
. 

Viruses

13

, 
253
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

61. 
Bratuleanu
, 
B.E
.etal. 

Theviromeof 
Rhipicephalus
, 
Dermacentor
and 
Haemaphysalis
ticksfrom Eastern Romaniaincludes novel viruses with potential relevance for public health

. 

Transbound. Emerg.Dis
.

https://doi.org/10.1111/tbed.14105
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

62. 
KosakovskyPond,S.L.
, 
Posada,D.
, 
Gravenor,M. B.
, 
Woelk,C.H.
&amp; 
Frost,S.D.W.
Automatedphylogenetic detectionof recombinationusingagenetic algorithm
. 

Mol.Biol.Evol.

23

, 
1891–1901
(
2006
).

</p>
         <p>

63. 
KosakovskyPond,S.L.
, 
Posada,D.
, 
Gravenor,M. B.
, 
Woelk,C.H.
&amp; 
Frost,S.D.W.
GARD: agenetic algorithm for recombination detection.
Bioinformatics

22

, 
3096–3098
(
2006
).

</p>
         <p>

64. 
Crawford,K.H.D.
etal. 
Protocolandreagentsforpseudotypinglentiviralparticleswith SARS-CoV-2 spike protein for neutralization assays
. 

Viruses

12

, E 
513
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

65. 
Anna,F.
etal. 
Highseroprevalencebutshort-livedimmuneresponsetoSARS-CoV-2 infection in Paris
. 

Eur.J.Immunol.

51

, 
180–190
(
2021
).

</p>
         <p>

66. 
Corman,V.M.
etal. 
Detectionof 2019 novelcoronavirus (2019-nCoV) byreal-time RT-PCR
. 

Euro Surveill.

25

, 
2000045
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

67. 
Monteil, V.
etal. 
InhibitionofSARS-CoV-2 infectionsinengineeredhumantissuesusing clinical-grade soluble human ACE2
. 

Cell

181

, 
905–913
(
2020
).

</p>
         <p>

68. 
Kabsch,W.
XDS
. 

ActaCrystallogr.D

66

, 
125–132
(
2010
).

</p>
         <p>

69. 
McCoy,A.J.
etal. 
Phasercrystallographicsoftware
. 

J.Appl. Crystallogr.

40

, 
658–674
(
2007
).

</p>
         <p>

70. 
Emsley,P.
&amp; 
Cowtan,K.
Coot: model-buildingtoolsformoleculargraphics
. 

Acta Crystallogr.D

60

, 
2126–2132
(
2004
).

</p>
         <p>

71. 
Liebschner,D.
etal. 
MacromolecularstructuredeterminationusingX-rays,neutronsand electrons:recent developments in Phenix
. 

Acta Crystallogr.D

75

, 
861–877
(
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

72. 
Sali,A.
&amp; 
Blundell, T.L.
Comparativeproteinmodellingbysatisfactionofspatial restraints
. 

J.Mol. Biol.

234

, 
779–815
(
1993
).

</p>
         <p>

73. 
Shen,M.-Y.
&amp; 
Sali,A.
Statisticalpotentialforassessmentandpredictionofprotein structures
. 

Protein Sci.

15

, 
2507–2524
(
2006
).

</p>
         <p>

74. 
Jo,S.
, 
Kim,T.
, 
Iyer,V.G.
&amp; 
Im,W.
CHARMM-GUI:aweb-basedgraphicaluserinterfacefor CHARMM
. 

J.Comput.Chem.

29

, 
1859–1865
(
2008
).

</p>
         <p>

75. 
Huang,J.
etal. 
CHARMM36m:animprovedforcefieldforfoldedandintrinsically disordered proteins
. 

Nat.Methods

14

, 
71–73
(
2017
).

</p>
         <p>

76. 
Jorgensen,W.L.
, 
Chandrasekhar,J.
, 
Madura,J.D.
, 
Impey,R.W.
&amp; 
Klein,M.L.
Comparison of simple potential functions for simulating liquid water
. 

J.Chem. Phys.

79

, 
926–935
(
1983
).

</p>
         <p>

77. 
Bussi,G.
, 
Donadio,D.
&amp; 
Parrinello,M.
Canonicalsamplingthroughvelocityrescaling
. 

J.Chem. Phys.

126

, 
014101
(
2007
).

</p>
         <p>

78. 
Berendsen,H.J.C.
, 
Postma,J.P.M.
, 
vanGunsteren,W.F.
, 
DiNola,A.
&amp; 
Haak,J.R.
Molecular dynamics with coupling to an external bath
. 

J.Chem. Phys.

81

, 
3684–3690
(
1984
).

</p>
         <p>

79. 
Hess,B.
, 
Bekker,H.
, 
Berendsen,H. J.C.
&amp; 
Fraaije,J. G.E.M.
LINCS:alinearconstraint solver for molecular simulations
. 

J.Comput.Chem.

18

, 
1463–1472
(
1997
).

</p>
         <p>

80. 
Essmann,U.
etal. 
AsmoothparticlemeshEwaldmethod
. 

J.Chem.Phys.

103

, 
8577–8593
(
1995
).

</p>
         <p>

81. 
ThePLUMEDconsortium
. 
Promotingtransparencyandreproducibilityinenhanced molecular simulations
. 

Nat.Methods

16

, 
670–673
(
2019
).

</p>
         <p>

82. 
Daura,X.
etal. 
Peptidefolding:whensimulationmeetsexperiment
. 

Angew.Chem.Int. Ed.

38

, 
236–240
(
1999
).

</p>
         <p>

83. 
Stranges,P.B.
&amp; 
Kuhlman,B.
Acomparisonofsuccessfulandfailedproteininterface designs highlights the challenges of designing buriedhydrogen bonds
. 

Protein Sci.

22

, 
74–82
(
2013
).

</p>
         <p>

84. 
Schymkowitz,J.
etal. 
TheFoldXwebserver:anonlineforcefield
. 

NucleicAcidsRes.

33

, 
W382–W388
(
2005
).

</p>
         <p>

85. 
Humphrey,W.
, 
Dalke,A.
&amp; 
Schulten,K.
VMD:visualmoleculardynamics
. 

J.Mol. Graph.

14

, 
33–38
(
1996
).

</p>
         <p>

86. 
Michaud-Agrawal,N.
, 
Denning,E. J.
, 
Woolf,T.B.
&amp; 
Beckstein,O.
MDAnalysis:atoolkitfor the analysis of molecular dynamics simulations
. 

J.Comput.Chem.

32

, 
2319–2327
(
2011
).

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <p>
Acknowledgements
We thank S.Mohamed Ali,N.Da Rocha,A.Brisebarre,T.Xaybounsou and S.Chonephetsarath for their help at the bench;A.Haouz and the staff of the protein crystallogenesis facility at Institut Pasteur for help with crystallization trials;P.England from the Molecular Biophysics facility at Institut Pasteur for his support and access to the BLI equipment; P.Legrand from the PX1 beamline at Synchrotron SOLEIL for data collection support;and P.Guardado-Calvo for discussion and support with BLI experiments.NGS was performed with the helpof the Biomics Platform,Center for Technological Resources and Research,Institut Pasteur,Paris,France,supported by France Génomique (ANR- 10-INBS-09-09),Inclusive Blockchain Insuranceusing Space Assets andthe Illumina COVID-19 Projects’ offer.The work was granted access to the High Performance Computing resources of the Institute for Development and Resourcesin Intensive Scientific Computing under the allocation 2020-101592 made by Grand Équipement National de Calcul Intensif.We thankthe Ministry of Health and the Ministry of Natural Resourcesand Environments,Lao People’s Democratic Republic,for their authorization of the field work and the Faculty of Environmental Science for its authorizationof the field research collaboration.The work was supported by an Institut Pasteur 'Covid Taskforce' and in part by the H2020 project 101003589 (RECOVER) and Labex IBEID (ANR-10-LABX62-IBEID) grants.Field and laboratory work at IPLwas also supported by a UK embassy grant (grant no. INT 2021/LOV C1902) and a Luxembourg Development special grant (grant no. LAO/030·202324).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Author contributions
S.T.,K.V., P.T.B.and M.E.conceived the study design.K.V.,B.D., K.L.,N.P., D.S.,V.X.and P.Paphaphanh carried out sample procurement andbat species identification. S.M.and F.D. performed virus isolation,entry and neutralizationassays.B.R., D.C. and P.Pérot prepared the NGS libraries and carried out the NGS.S.T.,B.R.and T.B.carried out the genome assembly,recombinationandphylogeneticanalyses.V.L.,S.S., K.L. andN.P.implementedthe pan-coronavirus PCRtesting.E.B.S.and F.A.R.performed and analysed the structure and binding studies.M.B.,Y.K.and M.N. performed and analysed the MD simulations.M.E.and S.T. wrote the manuscript with input from allother authors.
</p>
         <p>
Competing interests
All authors of the manuscript are listed as inventors on US provisional patent number entitled 'New isolated bat SARS-COV able to infect human cells and harboring receptor-binding domains close to SARS-COV-2'.The patent covers medical applications (including diagnostics and vaccination) for the sequences described in the manuscript.
</p>
         <p>
Additionalinformation Supplementary information
The online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-04532-4.
</p>
         <p>
Correspondence andrequestsformaterials
should be addressed to Marc Eloit.
</p>
         <p>
Peerreviewinformation
Nature
thanks Michael Worobeyandtheother,anonymous, reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work.Peerreviewer reportsare available.
</p>
         <p>
Reprints andpermissions information
isavailable at http://www.nature.com/reprints.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
