<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Nature</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02699</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Gigantism and comparative life-history parameters of tyrannosaurid dinosaurs</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>24</day>
            <month>03</month>
            <year>2016</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Gigantism and comparative life-history parameters of tyrannosaurid dinosaurs

</p>
         <p>
Gregory M. Erickson

, 


, 

Peter J. Makovicky


, 

Philip J. Currie


, 

Mark A. Norell


, 

Scott A. Yerby

&amp; 
Christopher A. Brochu
</p>
         <p>
1
Department of Biological Science, Florida State University, Tallahassee, Florida 32306-1100, USA
</p>
         <p>
2
Division of Paleontology, American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West at 79th Street, New York, New York 10024-5192, USA
</p>
         <p>
3
Department of Geology, The Field Museum, 1400 S. Lake Shore Drive, Chicago, Illinois 60605, USA
</p>
         <p>
4
Royal Tyrrell Museum of Palaeontology, Drumheller, Alberta T0J 0Y0, Canada

Department of Biomechanical Engineering, Stanford University, Stanford, California 94305, USA
</p>
         <p>
6 
Department of Geoscience, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa 52242, USA
............................................................................................................................................................................. 

How evolutionary changes in body size are brought about by variance in developmental timing and/or growth rates (also known as heterochrony) is a topic of considerable interest in evolutionary biology 

. In particular, extreme size change leading to gigantism occurred within the dinosaurs on multiple occasions 

. Whether this change was brought about by accelerated growth, delayed maturity or a combination of both processes is unknown. A better understanding of relationships between non-avian dinosaur groups and the newfound capacity to reconstruct their growth curves make it possible to address these questions quantitatively 

. Here we study growth patterns within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosauridae</tp:taxon-name>
, the best known group of large carnivorous dinosaurs, and determine the developmental means by which 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tyrannosaurus rex
</tp:taxon-name>
, weighing 5,000 kg and more, grew to be one of the most enormous terrestrial carnivorous animals ever. 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
had a maximal growth rate of 2.1 kg d 
–1
, reached skeletal maturity in two decades and lived for up to 28 years. 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
’s great stature was primarily attained by accelerating growth rates beyond that of its closest relatives.

</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosauridae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Albertosaurus sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Gorgosaurus libratus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Daspletosaurus torosus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosauridae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
A. sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
D. torosus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Daspletosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Tyrannosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Giganotosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosauridae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
D. torosus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Dinosauria</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Gorgosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Alligator mississippiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
A. mississippiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Tyrannosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Tyrannosaurus rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Gorgosaurus libratus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Albertosaurus sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Daspletosaurus torosus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
A. sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
A. sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Gigantism and comparative life-history parameters of tyrannosaurid dinosaurs</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/nature02699</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFB0FFBE350EFFB5FFE6DF44FFC69C4B</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02699</pub-id>
               <source>Nature</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>

Stemming from more than a century of investigation, considerable understanding of tyrannosaurid osteology 

4

, myology 

5

, neurology 

6

, behaviour 

7
, 
8

, physiology 

3
, 
9

, physical capabilities 

10
, 
11

and phylogeny 

12
, 
13

have been gained. Lacking are empirical data on tyrannosaurid life history such as growth rates, longevity and somatic maturity (adult size) from which the developmental possibilities for how 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
attained gigantism can be formally tested.

</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Recent advances in techniques for determining the ages at death of dinosaurs by using skeletal growth line counts 

3
, 
14

, coupled with developmental size estimates 

3

, make quantitative growth-curve reconstructions for dinosaurs feasible. These methods have been used to study growth rates in two small theropods, a small and a large ornithischian and a medium-sized and a gigantic sauropodomorph 

3

. These data were used to derive a regression of body mass against growth rate and to generalize broadly about non-avian dinosaur growth 

3

. However, because of the phylogenetically disparate nature of these data (that is, none are close outgroups to one another) it has not been possible to use them to infer how specific cases of size change occurred within dinosaurian sub-clades such as the 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosauridae</tp:taxon-name>
. Such an understanding requires multi-species sampling at low taxonomic levels (that is, among closely related species) and access to growth series spanning juvenile through adult stages, a rarity among extinct dinosaurs 

15

. Furthermore, it requires the capacity to account for growth line losses due to medullar cavity hollowing and cortical remodelling 

16

, two processes that are pervasive in the major weight-bearing bones from large theropods such as tyrannosaurids.
</p>
            <p>
The sampling problem has been overcome in North American tyrannosaurids. A flurry of recent discoveries has greatly increased the number of substantially complete specimens representing various growth stages available for study. For example, more than 30 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
specimens are known 

4
, 
17

, compared with only 11 reported in 1993 (ref. 18; see Supplementary Information). Recent work has broadened the developmental representation of these animals by showing that several purported ‘dwarf’ tyrannosaur species are juveniles of larger, previously recognized forms such as 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
12
, 
13
, 
19
, 
20

. Finally, preliminary analyses for this research revealed that several non-weight-bearing bones in tyrannosaurids (for example pubes, fibulae, ribs, gastralia and postorbitals) did not develop hollow medullar cavities and showed negligible intracortical remodelling during their entire life history (

). Like major long bones, these elements are effective for assessing longevity in living reptiles (

) 

21
, 
22

and hence provide a viable alternative method for determining the age at death of extinct reptiles such as tyrannosaurids.
</p>
            <p>
Here we exploit these findings to determine the pattern of growth in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
and three of its close tyrannosaurid relatives. We then use character optimization methods 

23

to infer how 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
attained giant proportions among tyrannosaurids. Finally, this new evidence is used to further our understanding of tyrannosaurid biology. In performing these analyses, we sampled several amedullar bones from adolescent, juvenile, sub-adult and adult representatives of the North American Late Cretaceous tyrannosaurids 
<tp:taxon-name>
Albertosaurus sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gorgosaurus libratus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Daspletosaurus torosus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
. Longevity in each of the 20 specimens was assessed from line counts in histological sections by using polarizing, dissecting and reflected-light microscopy (

) 

3
, 
14

. Conservative estimates of body mass (see Supplementary Information) were made by using femoral circumference measures 

24

. Longevity and size data were plotted and least-squares regression was used to determine the first empirical growth curves for tyrannosaurids 

3

. The length and timing of the various developmental stages and the maximal growth rates for each taxon were compared 

25

. The results were examined in an evolutionary context 

23

by using two competing phylogenetic hypotheses for the 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosauridae</tp:taxon-name>
12
, 
13

.
</p>
            <p>
Sampled longevities for 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
ranged from 2 to 28 years and corresponding body mass estimates ranged from 29.9 to 5,654 kg (
Table 1
). The transition to somatic maturity in this taxon seems to have begun at about 18.5 years of age (

). At least one individual (exemplified by 
<tp:material-citation>FMNH (The Field Museum) PR 2081</tp:material-citation>
), showed evidence for prolonged senescence in the form of conspicuously narrow pericortical growth-line spacing (

). Maximal growth rates in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
were 2.07 kg d 

‾
1

and such exponential rates were maintained for about 4 years (

). The longevity estimates for 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
outgroups ranged from 2 to 24 years and corresponding body sizes spanned from 50.3 to 1,791 kg (
Table 1
). Somatic maturity occurred at between 14 and 16 years in these taxa (

). Like 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
, at least some exceptionally large individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. torosus
</tp:taxon-name>
showed narrow pericortical growth-line spacing indicative of the onset of senescence. The maximal growth rates for the three smaller tyrannosaurid taxa ranged from 0.31 to 0.48 kg d 

‾
1

; such exponential stage rates were also maintained for about 4 years (

). Optimization of growth rates onto the two current phylogenetic hypotheses of tyrannosaurid relationships suggests that a 1.5-fold acceleration in maximal growth rate might diagnose 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurinae</tp:taxon-name>
(the clade comprising 

<tp:taxon-name>Daspletosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
13
, 
19

, 

). A second substantial increase in growth rate optimizes as a physiological autapomorphy of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tyrannosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
irrespective of phylogenetic hypothesis and optimization criterion.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
is notable for its great size, which is at least 15-fold greater than the largest living terrestrial carnivorous animals today and second only to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Giganotosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
26

among theropod dinosaurs. How did it attain such great proportions within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosauridae</tp:taxon-name>
? From the two competing hypotheses of tyrannosaurid phylogeny it is most parsimonious to conclude that 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
acquired the majority of its giant proportions after diverging from the common ancestor of itself and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. torosus
</tp:taxon-name>
, a species with an optimized body mass of about 1,800 kg. Direct comparison between the tyrannosaurid growth curves shows that the transition to the exponential and stationary phases of development occurred about 2–4 years later in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
(

). However, such temporal post-displacement had little to do with the evolution of its gigantism because the exponential stage, during which most body size is accrued 
25
, was not extended beyond the ancestral, 4-year condition observed in other tyrannosaurids. Rather, the key developmental modification that propelled 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
to giant proportions was primarily through evolutionary acceleration in the exponential stage growth rate and the transition zones bounding it. This is reflected in the regions of maximal slope on the growth curves depicted in 

and holds true regardless of which evolutionary hypothesis is correct and how the maximum growth rates are optimized. Notably, this method of attaining gigantism contrasts with that in the largest crocodilians and lizards, where ancestral growth rates were retained and the exponential stages lengthened 
27
. How other dinosaurs attained gigantism within their respective sub-clades will serve as an interesting line of inquiry in the future. Does the same pattern of acceleratory growth seen here characterize the means by which all or most members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Dinosauria</tp:taxon-name>
attained great size?
</p>
            <p>
Taxon Specimen no. Elements examined Femoral length (cm) Body mass (kg) Longevity (years); no. of growth lines in EFS ...................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................
<tp:taxon-name>
Tyrannosaurus rex
</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:material-citation>FMNH PR 2081</tp:material-citation>
G, R, F, OLB
134.5
5654
28; 9
<tp:material-citation>RTMP 81.12.1</tp:material-citation>
R, OLB
128.4 est.
5040
22
<tp:material-citation>RTMP 81.6.</tp:material-citation>
1

G, R, OLB
120
3230
18
<tp:material-citation>ICM 2001.90.</tp:material-citation>
1

G, R
116.8 est.
2984
16
<tp:material-citation>LACM 23845</tp:material-citation>
P, OLB
98.9
1807
14
<tp:material-citation>AMNH 30564</tp:material-citation>
G, R, F
98
1761
15
<tp:material-citation>LACM 28471</tp:material-citation>
R, C
25.2 est.
29.9
2
<tp:taxon-name>
Gorgosaurus libratus
</tp:taxon-name>
RTMP 94.12.602
R, G, OLB
91.6
1105
18
RTMP 73.30.1
F, OLB
80.4 est.
747
14
RTMP 99.33.1
G, F, OLB
75
607
14
RTMP 86.144.1
R, F, OLB
54.2
229
7
FMNH PR 2211
G, R, F, OLB
44.5
127
5
<tp:taxon-name>
Albertosaurus sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
RTMP 81.10.1
G, R, F, OLB
89.5
1142
24; 2
AMNH 5432
P, F
99.3 est.
1282
22
USNM 12814/AMNH 5428
R
86.0 est.
1013
18
RTMP 86.64.01
R, F, OLB
78.2 est.
762
15
RTMP 2002.45.46
F, OLB
31.6 est.
50.3
2
<tp:taxon-name>
Daspletosaurus torosus
</tp:taxon-name>
FMNH PR 308
G, R
96.0 est.
1791
21; 5
AMNH 5438
R
84.1 est.
1518
17
RTMP 94.143.1
G, OLB
62.6 est.
496
10
</p>
            <p>...................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................</p>
            <p>

FMNH, The Field Museum; RTMP, Royal Tyrrell Museum of Palaeontology; ICM, Indianapolis Children’s Museum; LACM, Los Angeles County Museum; AMNH, American Museum of Natural History; USNM, United States National Museum. R, rib; G, gastralia; F, fibula; P, pubis; C, dermal skull bones; OLB, other long bones; est., estimated; EFS, external fundamental system 
16
.

</p>
            <p>
Besides revealing how the evolution of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
gigantism was obtained, the data garnered here provide for a more comprehensive understanding of tyrannosaurid biology. For instance the presence of thin, tightly packed growth lines late in development (

) shows that these animals, like nearly all (if not all) dinosaurs, had determinate growth 
3
, 
14
. They would not have gained an appreciably greater size than the largest specimens studied here and could spend nearly 30% of their lives as full-grown adults (

). In addition, the maximal growth rates for these tyrannosaurid species are only 33–52% of the rates expected for non-avian dinosaurs of their size when compared with the more broadly sampled data of Erickson 
et al.
3
. This provides the first evidence of its kind pointing to major differences in whole body growth rates among a non-avian dinosaur sub-clade. Such findings are not unexpected because similar patterns (for example primates within Eutheria) occur within living vertebrate groups 
28
. Our findings also have a bearing on the biomechanical capacities of tyrannosaurids. 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. rex
</tp:taxon-name>
’s capacity for ‘fast running’ was biomechanially infeasible after a body mass of about 1,000 kg was attained 

11

. This corresponds to a juvenile-sized animal just 13 years of age on the basis of our longevity data and conservative estimates of body mass (

). If we assume that the same relationship held true for the smaller tyrannosaurid species studied here, such locomotory limitations would not have emerged until these animals were much closer to adult size (

). Finally, a glimpse into the potential population age structure for a dinosaur is also afforded from these data. Currie 

7

has described a catastrophic death assemblage consisting of eight or nine 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
specimens thought to represent an entire pack or a subset of one. On the basis of femoral lengths, the age and developmental stage of each animal can now be estimated. The group seems to have consisted of two or three older adults ~21 or more years of age, one ~17-year-old young adult, four ~12–17- year-old sub-adults that were undergoing exponential stage growth at the time of death, and one ~10-year-old juvenile that was beginning the transition to exponential stage growth. A reopening of the site has revealed at least one more specimen (RTMP (Royal Tyrrell Museum of Palaeontology) 2002.45.46) shown here to be only 2 years old (
Table 1
). This indicates that 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. sarcophagus
</tp:taxon-name>
groups, whether temporary or permanent, might have been composed of individuals spanning the age spectrum from adolescents to very old, senescent adults, a finding consistent with trackway evidence for other theropod dinosaurs 

7

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Methods

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Assessments of tyrannosaurid longevity

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Growth lines have been shown to form throughout the cranial and post-cranial skeletons of living tetrapods 


, 

, 

, 


and their annual formative rhythms have been shown in lepidosaurian and archosaurian (that is crocodilian) outgroups to dinosaurs 


, 

, 


. This indicates that similar annual genesis might have occurred in non-avian dinosaurs such as tyrannosaurids 

. Here we used fibulae, pubes, gastralia, ribs and cranial bones and a few selected long-bone elements in which medullar cavity expansion and remodelling was not pervasive. Bones such as these have been shown to have excellent efficacy for assessing longevity in snakes 

and lizards 

, and our own multi-element histological studies on lizards and crocodilians of known ages from the Florida Museum of Natural History, Gainesville, and the Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission, Gainesville, confirm this (
Fig.1
).In cases where some of the earliest-forming tyrannosaur growth rings were remodelled,losses were accounted for by examining younger individuals in which the rings were still present or through back-calculation methods 

. Inter-elemental comparisons revealed longevity estimates to within 1 year in all cases, the higher values of which were used in the longevity assessments.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Body size estimates

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
To permit comparisons of growth rates between tyrannosaurids and living taxa and to negate the effects of shape differences,the data were standardized to body mass 

by using a femoral circumference/body mass regression equation 

. This method produces conservative estimates of body mass 

(see Supplementary Information). Subadult sizes were determined with the Developmental Mass Extrapolation femoral scaling principle 

. In cases in which the femora were not preserved, the tyrannosaurid long-bone regression equations of Currie 

were used to estimate the missing measurements.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Reconstruction of growth curves

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Age and mass data were contrasted to reveal growth curves for the four tyrannosaurid species (
Fig. 2
). All vertebrates show logistic (S-shaped) growth patterns such as these during post-parturition/hatching development 


, 


. Hence a logistic equation and leastsquares regression analysis were used to describe the relationship between the data. The terminology used to refer to the various stages of development is as follows 

. The initial, slow growth phase is referred to as the lag stage.This is followed by the linear exponential stage during which maximal slope is observed and maximal growth rates occur. Finally, growth reaches a plateau during the stationary stage. Here we refer to animals in the lag stage as adolescents, those in transition to the exponential stage as juveniles, those in the exponential stage as sub-adults,those in transition to the stationary stage as young adults, and finally animals in the stationary stage as senescent adults.Here,adulthood refers to the onset of somatic maturity whereby adult size is first attained. Is not known when sexual maturity for non-avian dinosaurs occurred,because gender has not been established with certainty for any taxon.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Character evolution analysis

</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Maximum growth rates were optimized as a continuous character onto two competing phylogenies for the 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosauridae</tp:taxon-name>

, 


. The topologies as they pertain to the taxa sampled are (
<tp:taxon-name>
Albertosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gorgosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>
Daspletosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tyrannosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
)) 

and (( 
<tp:taxon-name>
Albertosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gorgosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
) (
<tp:taxon-name>
Daspletosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tyrannosaurus
</tp:taxon-name>
)) 

. Because no basal tyrannosaurids have been sampled, the basal theropod 
<tp:taxon-name>
Syntarsus
</tp:taxon-name>

was used to root the trees. Both linear and squared-changes optimizations were applied 

. Both optimality criteria and all possible topologies suggest that a large increase in growth rate is diagnostic of the 

<tp:taxon-name>Daspletosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
– 
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus</tp:taxon-name>

clade (
<tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurinae</tp:taxon-name>
) 

, and a second large increment in growth rate optimizes as unique to 

<tp:taxon-name>T. rex</tp:taxon-name>
.

The actual magnitude of the growth rate change reconstructed at ancestral nodes differs with topology and more drastically with the optimization method. Linear parsimony yields a punctuated pattern with higher changes at individual nodes, whereas squared-changes parsimony forces a ‘smoother’ distribution on the data but also incurs some counterintuitive deceleration in growth for the slower-growing basal taxa.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Received 3 March; accepted 26 May 2004; doi:10.1038/nature02699.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
1. 
Gould, S. J.

Ontogeny and Phylogeny

(
Harvard Univ. Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts
, 
1977
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
2. 
Carrano, M. T.
in 

Amniote Paleobiology: Perspectives on the Evolution of Mammals, Birds, and Reptiles

(eds 
Carrano,M. T.
, 
Blob, R.W.
, 
Gaudin, T.
&amp; 
Wible, J.
) (
Univ. Chicago Press,Chicago
, in the press).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
3. 
Erickson,G.M.
, 
Curry-Rogers,K.
&amp; 
Yerby,S.
Dinosaur growth patterns and rapid avian growth rates
. 

Nature


412
,

429–433
(
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
4. 
Brochu, C. A.

Osteology of 
Tyrannosaurus rex
: Insights from a nearly complete skeleton and highresolution computed tomographic analysis of the skull

. 

J.Vert. Paleontol.Mem.


22
(

7
), 
1–138
(
2003
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
5. 
Carrano, M. T.
&amp; 
Hutchinson, J. R.

Pelvic and hindlimb musculature of 
Tyrannosaurus rex
(Dinosauria: Theropoda)

. 

J. Morphol.


253
,

207–228
(
2002
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
6. 
Brochu, C. A.

A digitally rendered endocast for 
Tyrannosaurus rex

. 

J. Vert. Paleontol.


20
,

1–6
(
2003
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
7. 
Currie, P. J.
Possible evidence of gregarious behavior in tyrannosaurids
. 

GAIA


15
,

271–277
(
1998
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
8. 
Erickson, G. M.

Breathing life into 
Tyrannosaurus rex

. 

Scient. Am.


9
,

42–49
(
1999
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
9. 
Chin, K.
, 
Tokaryk, T. T.
, 
Erickson, G. M.
&amp; 
Calk, L. C.
A king-sized theropod coprolite
. 

Nature


393
,

680–682
(
1998
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
10. 
Erickson, G. M.
et al.

Bite-force estimation for 
Tyrannosaurus rex
from tooth-marked bones

. 

Nature


382
,

706–708
(
1996
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
11. 
Hutchinson, J.
&amp; 
Garcia, M.

Tyrannosaurus
was not a fast runner

. 

Nature


415
,

1018–1021
(
2002
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
12. 
Holtz, T. R.
in 

Mesozoic Vertebrate Life

(eds 
Tanke, D.
&amp; 
Carpenter, K.
) 
64–83
(
Indiana Univ. Press, Bloomington
, 
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
13. 
Currie,P.J.
Cranial anatomy of tyrannosaurid dinosaurs from the Late Cretaceous of Alberta,Canada
. 

Acta Palaeontol. Pol.


48
,

191–226
(
2003
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
14. 
Chinsamy, A.

Physiological implications of the bone histology of 
Syntarsus rhodesiensis
(Saurischia: Theropoda)

. 

Palaeontol. Afr.


27
,

77–82
(
1993
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
15. 
Weishampel, D. B.
&amp; 
Horner, J. R.
in 

Dinosaur Eggs and Babies

(eds 
Carpenter, K.
, 
Hirsch, K. F.
&amp; 
Horner, J. R.
) 
229–243
(
Cambridge Univ. Press, Cambridge
, 
1994
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
16. 
Francillon-Viellot, H.
, 
et al.
in 

Biomineralization: Patterns and Evolutionary Trends

(ed. 
Carter, J. G.
) 
471–530
(
Van Nostrand Reinhold, New York
, 
1990
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
17. 
Larson, P.
&amp; 
Donnan, K.

Rex Appeal

(
Invisible Cities Press, Montpelier
, 
2002
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
18. 
Horner, J. R.
&amp; 

Lessem, D. 
The

Complete T. rex
(
Simon &amp; Schuster, New York
, 
1993
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
19. 
Currie, P. J.
, 
Hurum, J.H.
&amp; 
Sabath, K.
Skull structure and evolution in tyrannosaurid dinosaurs
. 

Acta Palaeontol. Pol.


48
,

227–234
(
2003
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
20. 
Carr, T. D.
Craniofacial ontogeny in Tyrannosauridae (Dinosauria, Coelurosauria)
. 

J.Vert.Paleontol.


19
,

497–520
(
1999
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
21. 
Castanet, J.
&amp; 
Naulleau, G.

Données expérimentales sur la valeur des marques squelettiques comme indicateur de l’ age chez 
Vipera aspis
(L.) (Ophidia, Viperidae)

. 

Zool. Scripta


3
,

201–208
(
1974
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
22. 
de Buffrenil, V.
&amp; 
Castanet, J.

Age estimation by skeletochronology in the Nile monitor (
Varanus niloticus
), a highly exploited species

. 

J. Herpetol.


34
,

414–424
(
2000
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
23. 
Maddison,W.P.
&amp; 
Maddison,D.R.

MacClade Version 3; Analysis of Phylogeny and Character Evolution

(
Sinauer Associates, Sunderland, MA
, 
1992
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
24. 
Anderson, J. F.
, 
Hall-Martin, A.
&amp; 
Russell, D. A.
Long bone circumference and weight in mammals, birds, and dinosaurs
. 

J. Zool. A


207
,

53–61
(
1985
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
25. 
Sussman, M.

Growth and Development

(
Prentice-Hall, Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey
, 
1964
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
26. 
Coria,R.A.
&amp; 
Salgado,L.
A new giant carnivorous dinosaur from the Cretaceous of Patagonia
. 

Nature


377
,

224–226
(
1995
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
27. 
Erickson, G.M.
, 
de Ricqles, A.
, 
de Buffrenil, V.
, 
Molnar, R. E.
&amp; 
Bayless, M. A.

Vermiform bones and the evolution of gigantism in 
Megalania
—how a reptilian fox became a lion

. 

J. Vert. Paleontol.


23
,

966–970
(
2003
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
28. 
Case, T. E.
On the evolution and adaptive significance of post-natal growth rates in the terrestrial vertebrates
. 

Q. Rev. Biol.


53
,

243–282
(
1978
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
29. Seebacher, F. A new method to calculate allometric length-mass relationships of dinosaurs. 

J. Vert. 
Paleontol
.


21
,

51–60
(
2001
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation>
30. 
Currie, P. J.
Allometric growth in tyrannosaurids (Dinosauria: Theropoda) from the Upper Cretaceous of North America and Asia
. 

Can. J. Earth Sci


40
,

651–665
(
2003
).
</mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>
Supplementary Information
accompanies the paper on 
www.nature.com/nature
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Acknowledgements
We thank O. Rieppel and B. Simpson (The Field Museum), L. Chiappe (Los Angeles County Museum of Natural History), P. Larson and N. Larson (Black Hills Institute), B. Stein and M. Triebold (Triebold Paleontology), D. Evans (Indianapolis Children’s Museum), C. Mehling (American Museum of Natural History), S. Williams, M. Henderson and L.Cranford (Burpee Museum of Natural History), J. Gardner, D. Tanke and D. Brinkman (Royal Tyrrell Museum of Palaeontology), T. Carr (University of Toronto), F. W. King and K. Krysco (Florida Museum of Natural History), K. Womble (Florida State University), M. Bayless (Berkeley, California) and A. Woodward (Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission) for assistance with this research. The NSF and the College of Arts and Sciences of Florida State University generously funded this project.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Competing interests statement
The authors declare that they have no competing financial interests.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>
Correspondence
and requests for materials should be addressed to G.M.E. (gerickson@bio.fsu.edu).
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
