<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Royal Society Open Science</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.201617</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Are publications on zoological taxonomy under attack?</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>10</day>
            <month>02</month>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group/>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> royalsocietypublishing.org/journal/rsos </title>
         <p> Research </p>
         <p> Cite this article: Pinto ÂP, Mejdalani G, Mounce R, Silveira LF, Marinoni L, Rafael JA.
            2021 Are publications on zoological taxonomy under attack? R. Soc. Open Sci. 8 : 201617.
            https://doi.org/ 10.1098/rsos.201617 </p>
         <p> Received: 9 September 2020 </p>
         <p> Accepted: 25 January 2021 </p>
         <p> Subject Category: </p>
         <p> Organismal and evolutionary biology </p>
         <p> Subject Areas: </p>
         <p> taxonomy and systematics/evolution/ </p>
         <p> biogeography </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title> Keywords: </title>
         <p> bibliometrics, biodiversity crisis, Journal Impact Factor (JIF), scientometrics,
            systematics </p>
         <p> Author for correspondence: </p>
         <p> Ângelo Parise Pinto </p>
         <p> e-mail: appinto@ufpr.br </p>
         <p> Electronic supplementary material is available online at
            https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.c. </p>
         <p>5291246.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="document_head">
         <title> Are publications on zoological taxonomy under attack? </title>
         <p> Ângelo Parise Pinto 1 , Gabriel Mejdalani 2 , Ross Mounce 3 , Luís Fábio Silveira 4 ,
            Luciane Marinoni 1 and José Albertino Rafael 5 </p>
         <p> 1 Departamento de Zoologia, Universidade Federal do Paraná , PO Box 19020, 81531-980,
            Curitiba, Paraná , Brazil </p>
         <p> 2 Departamento de Entomologia, Museu Nacional, Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro ,
            Rio de Janeiro , Rio de Janeiro , Brazil </p>
         <p> 3 Arcadia Fund, Sixth Floor, 5 Young Street, London W8 6 EH, UK </p>
         <p> 4 Museu de Zoologia da Universidade de São Paulo , São Paulo , São Paulo , Brazil </p>
         <p> 5 Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas da Amazônia, Manaus, Amazonas , Brazil </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> ÂPP, 0000-0002-1650-5666 </title>
         <p> Taxonomy is essential to biological sciences and the priority field in face of the
            biodiversity crisis. The industry of scientific publications has made extensive
            promotion and display of bibliometric indexes, resulting in side effects such as the
            Journal Impact Factor™ (JIF) mania. Inadequacies of the widely used indexes to assess
            taxonomic publications are among the impediments for the progress of this field. Based
            on an unusually high proportion of self-citations, the mega-journal Zootaxa , focused on
            zoological taxonomy, was suppressed from the Journal Citation Reports (JCR, Clarivate™).
            A prompt reaction from the scientific community against this decision took place
            exposing myths and misuses of bibliometrics. Our goal is to shed light on the impact of
            misuse of bibliometrics to the production in taxonomy. We explored JCR’ s metrics for
            2010–2018 of 123 zoological journals publishing taxonomic studies. Zootaxa , with around
            15 000 citations, received 311% more citations than the second most cited journal, and
            shows higher levels of self-citations than similar journals. We consider Zootaxa ’s
            scope and the fact that it is a mega-journal are insufficient to explain its high level
            of self-citation. Instead, this result is related to the ‘ Zootaxa phenomenon’, a
            sociological bias that includes visibility and potentially harmful misconceptions that
            portray the journal as the only one that publishes taxonomic studies. Menaces to
            taxonomy come from many sources and the low bibliometric indexes, including JIF, are
            only one factor among a range of threats. Instead of being focused on statistically
            illiterate journal metrics endorsing the villainy of policies imposed by
            profit-motivated companies, taxonomists should be engaged with renewed strength in
            actions directly connected to the promotion and practice of this science without regard
            for citation analysis. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 1. Introduction </title>
         <p> Every middle of year large scientific data analytics companies, the American-British
            Clarivate™ (InCites™) and the Dutch RELX™ Elsevier B.V. (Scopus ® ), release their
            metrics for scientific journals indexed in their databases, among them the Journal
            Impact Factor™ (JIF) and the CiteScore™, respectively. These metrics have been adopted
            as major means of research assessment by many countries as the sole measure of the
            quality of the research produced in their universities and institutes. Generally,
            funding for research in these institutions is derived from the taxes paid by the
            citizens of their respective countries. This policy produces a sort of quest or JIF
            mania for publishing in higher-ranked journals [ ]. Therefore, depending on the impact
            factor, a researcher is perceived to have better chances of advancing in her/his career,
            earning prestige, winning grants, etc. Thus, these metrics have a strong impact on how
            and what scientific investigation can currently be conducted. </p>
         <p> On the last day of June of 2020, an interruption to concerns about the Covid-19
            pandemic affected taxonomists around the world. An issue broke through the media due to
            the involvement of zoologists from many countries: the suppression of the mega-journal
            Zootaxa , a journal focused on zoological taxonomy, from the Journal Citation Reports™
            (JCR) Science Edition metrics by Clarivate. Based on a high proportion of
            self-citations, along with another 32 journals from the 12 000 in the JCR database,
            Zootaxa would not receive a value of Journal Impact Factor (JIF) for 2019; however, it
            would keep the values for previous years and still be indexed on the Clarivate Analytics
            platform. </p>
         <p> By this time, with the publication of JIF 2019 by JCR, which called the attention of
            editors and authors who were eager to see how journals were ranked, passionate
            discussions arose because of Zootaxa ’s suppression. A prompt reaction, rarely seen
            before in this community, through many letters of support to Zootaxa and petitions from
            several societies and researchers, forced Clarivate to review its decision. We believe
            that the suppression of Zootaxa entails so many unique elements that it needs a closer
            inspection. Some supporting letters could actually be considered political manifestos
            and others were very naive, not to say alarmist or simply inaccurate in interpreting the
            suppression as a new attack to taxonomy as a science. Among the utterly passionate
            arguments was the one that Zootaxa is the single vehicle to publish taxonomic papers
            nowadays, a statement obviously far away from the truth. At the end of July, in a short
            statement on Twitter, Clarivate announced that Zootaxa and the International Journal of
            Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology would be reconsidered in the regular refresh of
            the JCR, which was published in September. Cases of suppression are common and not
            unique to the Clarivate platform, most of them being due to accusations of artificial
            boost or inflation of impact factors (e.g. [ ]). A particular case, almost a decade ago,
            had a wide repercussion among researchers when four journals edited in Brazil were
            suppressed under accusation of a citationstacking scheme, a sort of cartel in which
            self-citations are exchanged among a group of journals [ ]. Noticeably, cases of
            suppression in the past hardly received any sympathy from the scientific community,
            except from people directly involved as editors, perhaps as a signal that sectors of the
            academic community agreed with the suppression and considered that the affected journals
            deserved such ‘punishment.’ Once discarded from JIF, a journal is excluded from the gold
            rush of academia targeting high-impact outlets. </p>
         <p> In a system full of anachronisms, in which traditional journals supported by museums or
            scientific societies are struggling to survive and the commercialized scientific
            publishing industry is led by giant publishers such as John Wiley &amp; Sons, Elsevier
            and Springer Nature, among others, with profit margins higher than those of major
            players in drug, bank and auto companies [ ], it is at least curious to perceive the
            commotion around the suppression of Zootaxa . We became intrigued and thus decided to
            provide some reflections aiming to shed light on underlying aspects of this issue. We
            believe that many of the arguments that were given in the supporting letters are based
            on misunderstandings about these metrics or are biased by personal interests due to the
            pressure to publish in high-impact journals. In addition, some points are also
            potentially misplaced. Bibliometric data are plagued by myths and misunderstandings [ ]. </p>
         <p> Our goal is to shed some light on the impacts of the adoption of bibliometrics to the
            production in taxonomy by discussing the following questions. Can the suppression of any
            journal from JIF really affect the volume and quality of production in the taxonomic
            field? What are the consequences of Zootaxa suppression to taxonomy as a science? What
            does journal ‘self-citation’ mean? What is the average JIF for taxonomic journals? Is
            Zootaxa a victim of its success? So, what is actually going on? To properly address
            these questions, we first need to clarify a few concepts and dig further into the
            relationship between bibliometrics and taxonomic journals, impact measures of scientific
            publications, and the role of individuals and mega-corporations in this arena. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 2. Material and methods </title>
         <p> Data on a total of 123 journals were compiled after the filtering described below. We
            explored citation data including JIF, most-cited journals and self-citation metrics from
            the Journal Citation Reports (Web of Science Core Collection™) of the last 9 years
            (2010–2018) of eight of the top 10 zoological journals (TTJ, only eight are included in
            JCR) when the number of new available names (based on the last 5 years of ION/Zoological
            Records™—ZR [ ]) is considered. We also checked up for journals focused on or regularly
            publishing taxonomic papers included in the Zoology and Entomology categories. The
            period of 9 years was adopted because Zootaxa was suppressed from the current edition of
            JCR and only reappeared in September of 2020 after conclusion of this study. Among 168
            journals in Zoology and 101 in Entomology, 73 and 48 (both numbers include ‘plus’
            Zootaxa and TTJ) were selected. Journals included in both Zoology and Entomology
            categories were subsequently considered in the Zoology category. For the analysis
            including all data, after excluding duplicates from the three selected categories, the
            top 10 journals (TTJ) were considered independently with eight, Zoology with 69 and
            Entomology with 46 journals. The strategy for journal selection is depicted graphically
            as a Venn diagram ( figure 1 ). </p>
         <p> In order to analyse the selected journals with available data from 2010 to 2018, a
            descriptive statistics approach including arithmetic mean of the bibliometric variables,
            their standard deviations, and the ratio between JIF without self-citations (journal)
            and JIF (including journal self-citations) was used to investigate the influence of
            self-citations on JIF. This approach was conducted among the top 10 journals (TTJ) in ZR
            and those in Zoology and Entomology categories when all data were analysed together. The
            percentage of self-citations and the ratio between JIF without self-citations and JIF
            per year of the journals between quartiles 2 and 3 (Q2 and Q3) in their categories
            (Entomology and Zoology) and TTJ totalling 68 periodicals were analysed with one-way
            ANOVA using permutations for linear models via lmPerm package [ ] followed by a Tukey
            honestly significant difference (Tukey HSD) test in R software [ ]. Thus, journals with
            similar scope and JIF to Zootaxa were considered. In practice, all journals publishing
            taxonomic papers with JIF 2019 ranging from 0.25 to 2.315 in the categories Zoology and
            Entomology were included. This last criterion can be considered arbitrary because the
            proportion of taxonomic papers is very dissimilar among the journals. Clearly, Zootaxa
            and ZooKeys , for example, have a greater number of taxonomic papers, even when the fact
            that these journals accept studies on different subjects of biological sciences is
            considered. However, for the purposes of our discussion, it is reasonable to consider
            such journals as similar in scope. The comparison is not easy because the original scope
            of Zootaxa is unique, due to its intent of ‘rapid publication of high-quality papers on
            any aspect of systematic zoology’ and its focus on long papers. However, Zootaxa
            publishes today virtually any subject associated with zoological taxonomy/ systematics,
            including biographies and points of view on theoretical subjects. Therefore, it is fair
            to conclude that all kinds of zoological papers are published in that journal, except
            those essentially dealing with ecological or experimental issues. The list of the
            journals, their publishing model and selected metrics are available in table 1 and
            electronic supplementary material, file 1. Note that the categorization of journals
            follows Web of Science’ s criteria, so that many taxonomic journals that publish studies
            in the areas of zoology or entomology may not have been included simply because they are
            listed in any one of the other 178 categories in the Science Edition database. The
            publishing model was determined based on journals guidelines/instructions to authors.
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 3. Results </title>
         <p> A small fraction of the 123 taxonomic journals investigated adopt mandatory Article
            Processing Charges for Gold Open Access (APC-GOA) models (18.7%). Diamond open access
            (DOA) represents 22.0%, whereas the largest percentage (59.3%) of journals are based on
            hybrid models with paywall to access their content, usually through readers’
            payment/subscription ( table 1 ). A few journals, published in distinct platforms
            maintained by societies, require page charges from authors, irrespective of them being
            associated or not to the society, they also have their contents paywalled; thus, these
            journals have both authors’ and readers’ charges (e.g. Journal of the Kansas
            Entomological Society and Malacologia ). </p>
         <p> The average levels of self-citations in the period of 2010–2018 range from 0.0 to 24.2%
            in Zoology, 0.0–34.9% in Entomology and 4.6–34.9% in TTJ. For the last 5 years
            (2014–2018), these levels are 0.0– 27.3% in Zoology, 0.0–36.4% in Entomology and
            4.5–36.4% in TTJ. The upper bounds of self-citation in the Entomology and TTJ categories
            are due to Systematic and Applied Acarology ; excluding this journal, the maximum level
            of self-citation for Entomology is 21.4% ( Coleopterists Bulletin ) for 2010– 2018 and
            27.3% ( Odonatologica ) for 2014–2018, while for TTJ they are 26.3% and 27.5% (both
            correspond to Cretaceous Research ). In comparison to all other journals, excluding
            Systematic and Applied Acarology , the mean levels of self-citation are higher for
            Zootaxa than for any other journal in Zoology ( figure 2 ), Entomology ( figure 3 ) and
            TTJ categories ( figure 4 ), being 34.9% for 2010–2018 and 37.6% for 2014–2018 in
            Zootaxa . The levels of self-citation have gradually increased in Zootaxa from 27.99% in
            2010 to 52.7% in 2018 (electronic supplementary material, file 2). The percentage of
            self-citations for 2010–2018 is higher in Zootaxa and similar only to Systematic and
            Applied Acarology ( figure 5 ). The one-way ANOVA with permutation of the Q2 and Q3
            journals, plus TTJ (68 journals), was significant (d.f. = 67, p &lt;0.001) for both the
            ratio of JIF without self-citation and JIF (JIF ratio), as well as to the proportion of
            self-citation (level of self-citation). The Tukey HSD test revealed that Zootaxa ’s JIF
            ratio is significantly different from almost all journals except the TTJ Journal of
            Palaeontology and Systematic and Applied Acarology and the following Zoology journals:
            Asian Herpetological Research , Ichthyological Exploration of Freshwaters ,
            International Journal of Odonatology , Nematology , Neotropical Ichthyology , Nota
            Lepidopterologica and Vertebrate Zoology ( p -value &lt;0.001). Zootaxa ’s level of
            self-citation is also significantly different from most journals except for the TTJ
            Cretaceous Research , Journal of Palaeontology , and Systematic and Applied Acarology ,
            and the Zoology journal Nematology ( p -value &lt;0.001). </p>
         <p> Influence of self-citations on JIF comparing all 123 journals is almost insignificant
            to boost this metric because most journals from the three categories (Entomology,
            Zoology and TTJ) have similar means of the ratio between JIF without self-citations and
            JIF for 2010–2018, except Shilap-Revista de Lepidopterologia , a journal devoted to
            butterflies and moths, Insects , published by Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing
            Institute (MDPI), and Zootaxa ( figure 6 ). Some journals have large intervals based on
            s.d. in the influence of self-citation on JIF, while journals such as Zootaxa have a
            more constant influence of self-citation. For instance, in Zootaxa this ratio ranges
            from 0.55 to 0.60 and JIF reduces 39.6–45.6% when self-citations are excluded ( figure 6
            ; electronic supplementary material, file 1). Zootaxa, with around 15 000 citations,
            received 311% more citations than the second most cited journal, ZooKeys , during
            2010–2018 (electronic supplementary material, files 1, 3). Electronic supplementary
            material, file 3 shows the number of citations and journals with similar effects in the
            assessed metrics. Levels of self-citation are unrelated to number of citations. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ( Continued. ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ( Continued. ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ( Continued. ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ( Continued. ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ( Continued. ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ( Continued. ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ( Continued. ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 4. Discussion </title>
         <p> 4.1. What are journal-level metrics? </p>
         <p> As non-bibliometric researchers, we assume that measures in bibliometric science were
            created with some genuine purposes, which entail goals other than supposedly assessing
            the quality of research or researchers. Originally, these indexes aimed to be objective
            tools for helping librarians in the development of journal collections [ ]. According to
            Keith Collier (Senior Vice President of Product, Science Group Clarivate,
            https://bit.ly/31gOMg3), the JIF mission is ‘to provide a thorough, publisher-neutral,
            multifaceted view of journal performance, reflecting the world’ s highest-quality
            scientific and scholarly literature.’ The hope for the consumers of JIF relies on the
            citation frequency that would reflect a journal value, and on the use made of it, and
            shows the average citations per published paper in a given journal (see [ ]). </p>
         <p> Apart from the controversies of whether JIF actually assesses a journal ‘quality’, it
            aims, together with other bibliometric indexes, to highlight citation patterns and
            trends in publications. Since its creation in the beginning of the 1970s ([ ], however,
            mentioned that it was designed in 1955; see also [ ]), the metric became popular and has
            been adopted as a major parameter for evaluating the quality of research, a topic
            certainly controversial [12,13]. The index is a very simple measure calculated from the
            ratio between the number of citations along a year (numerator) and the number of papers
            published along the two previous years (denominator)—i.e. JIF 2019 is the number of
            citations in 2019 from papers published in 2017 and 2018 divided by the number of
            published papers in 2017 and 2018—[ ]. So it shows how trendy papers or subjects
            published by a journal are, as well as if they are achieving a wide audience. The bad
            twist occurred when organizations, including governmental funding agencies, reached the
            conclusion that, since journals are evaluated by their citation impact, bingo, the
            scientific production in universities, institutes and graduate courses, as well as the
            researchers themselves, should be evaluated in the same manner. However, there is a
            flawed logic in extrapolating indexes such as JIF to evaluate work and careers. Hence,
            the JIF is recognized without doubt as being the most widely misused and abused
            bibliometric index in academic science [1,9,12]. </p>
         <p> The adoption of scientific bibliometric indexes such as JIF has grown, especially in
            the last two decades, as a way to evaluate the strongly competitive field of academic
            careers with numbers given to three decimal places that give a false impression of
            ‘objectivity’. However, there are many studies showing perverse pitfalls, for both
            researchers and organizations, of this use and interpretation of JIF (e.g. [ – ]). The
            quest and struggle for publishing in high impact journals produced the JIF mania [ ]. </p>
         <p> Although the use of JIF is not recommended for ranking human beings [ ], its impact in
            the real-life academic career is crystal clear. It is widely perceived that an academic
            researcher can only evolve in her/ his career by means of publishing in journals with
            high JIF values. The metric has well-known limitations when used to evaluate both
            journals or individual papers, because the index is strongly sensitive to what is
            considered a citable item [ ]; also, it is characterized by a misuse of statistics by
            using the wrong measure of central tendency (mean rather than mode) given the typical
            skew in the distribution of citations across articles in a journal [ ] and may be
            radically influenced by a single or few papers (e.g. [ ]). Its widespread adoption leads
            to several distortions such as unjustified multi-authored papers and schemes by journals
            to artificially increase JIF or impact inflation; these schemes are among the most
            common outcomes of the JIF mania. Because of the metrics inflation, the bibliometric
            platforms act as judges to prevent these types of distortion, excluding or punishing
            ‘deviant’ journals. Indexing platforms such as Clarivate/JCR, for instance, adopt no
            less than 24 criteria into a putatively unreproducible method of analysis. When a
            journal disagrees or does not fulfil one of these criteria, it is suppressed [ ]. The
            lack of transparency greatly affects our ability to properly evaluate journal
            suppressions. The philosophical dilemma ‘Who watches the watchmen?’, eternalized in the
            famous graphic novel Watchmen , written by Alan Moore, fits well here. </p>
         <p> 4.2. Metrics and taxonomy </p>
         <p> Undeniably, exploring biodiversity is a core issue for the entire biological sciences
            (and humanity). In this context, taxonomic research is an essential priority in face of
            the current biodiversity crisis [ ]. The concept of taxonomy in biological sciences has
            a wide range of meanings, varying from the reductionist, atomized and merely descriptive
            harmful view known as alpha taxonomy (e.g. [ ])— largely denoted as a minor science, old
            fashioned, and intellectually poor—to a wide sense of taxonomy as the biggest among all
            biological sciences (e.g. [ ]), equivalent to the whole field of comparative biology.
            This wider view, which is adopted here, embraces from primary data acquisition in field
            expeditions to morphological, genomic and even ecosystem analyses. Thus, it considers
            taxonomy as a relevant hypothesis-driven science. However, ordinary taxonomic research
            executed day by day is a generally low-cost activity that employs few technological
            tools. It is focused on the study of natural history collections with the goal of
            characterizing and making available basic data on biological entities. This work often
            involves the study of the morphology of poorly known taxa, an unknown sex of a given
            species or developmental stages, as well as undescribed taxa. Taxonomists must
            frequently work with poorly known subjects, looking for the novelty, odd, and thus
            dealing with unpopular or even neglected topics. Therefore, there are many cases of
            fine, well-written and beautifully fully illustrated comprehensive taxonomic monographs
            on animal groups that will probably rarely be cited. The small number of citations might
            even be related to the fact that such monographs successfully solve most of the basic
            taxonomic questions affecting one taxon. One colourful example was voiced by one of us
            (J.A.R.) during the Brazilian Congress of Zoology: ‘I am studying one of the smallest
            orders of insects [Zoraptera, the angel insects] with no more than four dozens of extant
            species, so what is the chance of citation, within only two years, of a paper that
            provides a great contribution on this group, including the description of new species?’
            Problems with the low rate of citations in taxonomy are widely discussed and the
            inadequacy of JIF for the research assessment of basic sciences is often mentioned (e.g.
            [22,23]). This is a paradox caused by the fact that taxonomy must, in part, necessarily
            deal with basic descriptive subjects, the new and unexpected, focusing on small parts of
            the tree of life. </p>
         <p> Taxonomy is currently considered a science in crisis affected by losses of positions in
            institutions and reduction of funding resources. In addition to this scenario of gradual
            loss of workforce and grants, the discipline is also damaged by the biases or
            inadequacies of these so-called indexes of ‘quality’ (see [ ]). This situation is not
            exclusive to zoological taxonomy, Botany, for instance, has been suffering a drastic
            devaluing process [ ]. Some solutions for low citations suggested the mandatory citation
            of references in which authorities erected new taxa (original descriptions) whenever a
            name was mentioned in a study, a rule endorsed by Zootaxa (https://bit.ly/34kXmgm) but
            not strictly enforced by the journal. This rule would partially explain its high level
            of self-citations. However, this strategy is deeply misleading, because original
            descriptions, especially the old ones, are often not adequate for species
            characterization and recognition. A more straightforward approach would be to make clear
            which concept of species is being adopted and provide the bibliographic source (see [
            ]). Another important point is that multidisciplinarity in biological sciences has
            blurred the limits among traditional disciplines, even the descriptive ones. All these
            aspects were suggested as reasonable explanations for the high levels of Zootaxa
            self-citations. However, they are not valid because there are many other journals
            currently accepting taxonomic studies, being either purely descriptive or including
            broader analytical approaches; these journals are obviously attractive in the context of
            the JIF mania game (electronic supplementary material, file 1). </p>
         <p> 4.3. Zootaxa phenomenon and suppression quarrel </p>
         <p> As authors of papers on distinct zoological taxa, editors of special issues, and
            reviewers of manuscripts submitted to Zootaxa during the last 10 years, we feel
            comfortable to offer an opinion on the journal and its impact in the taxonomic world, an
            actual phenomenon that transformed it into the leading vehicle for making new zoological
            names available. </p>
         <p> Since its establishment, Zootaxa has become a prestigious forum for promotion and
            discussion of all topics of taxonomic science and thus reached a distinguished position
            among other similar journals. Unquestionably, the birth of the journal was a milestone
            to the field of zoological taxonomy. Started in 2001 with a hybrid platform of
            publication (i.e. the payment of Article Processing Charges, APC, by authors is optional
            for making the paper Open Access, OA), when 300 pages were published, the journal
            increased to 32 330 pages in 2010 [ ] and ended 2019 with the impressive record of 47
            528 pages; the latter comprising 2400 papers in 176 volumes (data compiled from Zootaxa
            ’s site). In its first decade, Zootaxa has made available about 20–25% of the new nomina
            per year [ ]. In the last 5 years, it has become the main journal, truly the leader in
            the field of descriptive taxonomy, with 24 722 (26.57% of the total) newly erected taxa
            made available [ ]. Despite its few years of existence, the journal has received
            remarkable status and visibility among zoologists. Papers published in it have
            potentially higher chances of being cited by fellow taxonomists, unlike the situation in
            many other similar journals in the field that clearly have a lower visibility. Zootaxa
            has been the first choice for a legion of young taxonomists for their very first papers.
            The relatively high JIF of the journal is certainly among the reasons for this choice.
            Furthermore, for those zoologists who are not primarily taxonomists but who eventually
            decide to publish a taxonomic paper, the journal is also probably the first choice, if
            not the single one known. Indeed, Zootaxa is so influential nowadays that a somewhat
            pejorative term, ‘ Zootaxa author,’ has been coined, meaning those researchers who only
            publish in the journal or have a massive amount of their papers in it, reaching 80% or
            more. Why this phenomenon? Why does a journal congregate such a huge parcel of
            publications in a field? Is this situation actually good for taxonomy? </p>
         <p> For almost a decade, Zootaxa was the single big (or mega) journal in the field designed
            to attend taxonomic science, even though several smaller journals also published most of
            their issues with a high amount of taxonomic papers. Today, Zootaxa has competitors with
            the advantage of having either Gold Open Access ( GOA ) or DOA policies, such as the
            European Journal of Taxonomy (first issue published in 2011) and ZooKeys (first issue in
            2008). However, in the case of ZooKeys , a minimum APC of €700 is required for mandatory
            open access; this is a huge obstacle, especially for researchers from developing
            countries, outside the group of those countries considered of lowest income, who do not
            automatically qualify for a fee waiver. The Zootaxa initiative from Magnolia Press Ltd
            was so successful that it stimulated the creation of some new journals, including
            Phytotaxa , its sibling version dedicated to plant sciences. Data on Magnolia Press,
            which is based in New Zealand , is not easy to obtain; for instance, it is not clear to
            us whether it is a for-profit or not-for-profit organization. </p>
         <p> The great significance of Zootaxa cannot be denied and it has become the most important
            vehicle for the publication of taxonomic studies. However, it is obviously not the
            single journal devoted to taxonomic science, such as depicted by some of the supporting
            letters. So, why has the suppression caused that enormous commotion? A quick answer is
            because in some megadiverse countries, such as Brazil in which most of the fauna remains
            undescribed, the higher education and scientific organizations evaluation systems have
            entirely embraced bibliometric indexes (e.g. [ – ]). Therefore, these metrics play an
            important role in the system and, for instance, a Brazil-based author’ s choice of a
            scientific journal is largely based on values such as JIF. Consequently, the suppression
            of Zootaxa was received as a serious setback for taxonomists in such countries,
            especially so of course for those who publish most or even all their papers in the
            journal. This last aspect has a clear influence on the high rate of self-citations, as
            well as on the JIF of Zootaxa ( figures 2–6 ), even considering that Clarivate
            recognized that 20% of papers on zoology were published by the journal. </p>
         <p> 4.4. What is self-citation and its consequences? </p>
         <p> An important distinction should be made between two categories of self-citation,
            individual (author) and collective (journal) self-citation, although both potentially
            result in a boost of bibliometric indexes. There are many legitimate reasons for a
            researcher to cite her/his earlier works; in many cases, self-citations are unavoidable,
            depending on the circumstances or subject [ ]. For example, an author could have been
            the single authority on a taxon during the last 30 years or present a high production in
            a specialized field. In these situations, self-citation alone is not necessarily
            fraudulent. Concerns arise when similar citations are not received in the work of other
            researchers in the field [ ] or, more commonly, based on the myth that self-citations
            help to artificially increase one’ s own position in the community [ ]. Differently,
            collective (journal) self-citation would be more problematic and is most probably a
            side-effect of the JIF mania, caused by the competition among journals for higher
            journal ranking, prestige and higher monetary earnings through higher subscription
            pricing, which is often connected to journal-level bibliometrics. Dear readers, do not
            be naive: academic publications are million-dollars businesses, truly having high profit
            margins [4,32]. It is thus not surprising that journals engage in ‘impact factor wars’
            to manipulate their metrics using strategies such as citation stacking, enlargement of
            cited references during the review process to include papers from their own journal
            (sometimes even coercive self-citation) and rejection of studies with low potential of
            citation [ ]. Thus, a high level of self-citations in a journal is not easy to
            understand and should be evaluated with caution. </p>
         <p> Self-citation phenomena, either of author or journal types , have been deeply
            investigated from various perspectives, including sociological and bibliometric aspects.
            A review focused on author selfcitation and all its technical nuances was presented by
            Szomszor et al . [ ]. Generally, high levels of self-citation are condemned,
            particularly when journal self-citation is interpreted as the result of manipulation for
            boosting indexes; in these situations, it has of course been determined that the biased
            metrics should not be considered for analyses of influence or impact [ ]. However,
            self-citation can be legitimate in certain circumstances [ ]. Consequently, levels of
            self-citation are not easy to analyse. Ioannidis &amp; Thombs [ ] argued that these
            levels naturally vary, and high levels may be justifiable in highly specialized journals
            or in disciplines with few available journals. </p>
         <p> Zootaxa hardly meets the aforementioned criteria for reasonable justification of high
            self-citations. Also, self-citation has increased in the journal over the years
            (electronic supplementary material, file 2). Zootaxa is clearly not highly specialized.
            A quick examination of its issues will confirm this point and taxonomy as a whole is far
            from having only a few other available journals, at least to most groups. We compiled
            123 journals that publish taxonomic papers, solely in the JCR database ( table 1 ).
            Therefore, there are clearly many options since these journals surely publish a great
            deal of descriptive taxonomy ( figures 2 and 3 ). If specialization were true for
            Zootaxa , we would expect that more specialized journals devoted to small groups, such
            as Odonatologica (dragonflies) and Acarologia (mites), which together represent a small
            part of extant diversity, would present similar or even higher self-citation levels,
            which is not the case ( figures 3 and 5 ). On the other hand, we would also expect that
            journals specialized in megadiverse groups, such as beetles, bees, moths, butterflies,
            spiders, etc. would likewise have high levels of self-citation, which again is not the
            case ( figures 2 , 3 and 5 ). Even journals dealing with taxa from a specific region of
            the world, such as Neotropical Ichthyology or South American Journal of Herpetology ,
            also present significantly lower levels of self-citation. Therefore, the scope of
            Zootaxa , with its focus on taxonomy, does not explain the high level of self-citations.
            Instead, an explanation should be looked for in the elements of the Zootaxa phenomenon
            depicted above. A relevant aspect to be observed in this discussion is that the great
            majority of the citations given to the analysed journals came from Zootaxa ( figures 2–4
            ). </p>
         <p> In addition, Chorus &amp; Waltman [ ] carefully studied journal self-citation and
            proposed a measure to evaluate boosts in the JIF, detecting disproportional and
            potentially unethical behaviour (Impact Factor Biased Self-Citation Practices). They did
            not consider their measure unfailing and discussed a few cases when self-citation would
            be legitimated. The latter include distinct situations. For instance, a researcher could
            be inspired by recent studies published in a journal and thus decides to conduct similar
            research; accordingly, that journal would naturally be an important source and her/his
            first choice for publication. Also, there are situations when, after finishing a
            manuscript, an author realizes that most of the cited references are from a given
            journal; the latter becomes again a naturally expected option. We believe that such
            cases are strongly associated with the Zootaxa mega-journal phenomenon and appear to
            partially explain its high levels of self-citation. </p>
         <p> We are confident that a journal can publish high-quality, robust science regardless of
            its level of selfcitation. There is not necessarily any relationship between the rate of
            journal-level self-citation and the quality of the research published in a given
            journal, particularly in the case of high-output journals such as Zootaxa . Clarivate
            appears to want to promote a sense of competition among journals, so that it can sell
            its journal ranking data and analytics—clearly, zoological taxonomists and their
            publishing and citing behaviours do not fit the model that Clarivate seemingly wants to
            promote. Who is wrong here? The community of scientists producing taxonomic science for
            which they were specifically trained, or the profit-driven analytics company that
            appears to know nothing about taxonomy and yet still wants to rank and supposedly
            provide sound judgement on the quality of taxonomic journals? We think of course that
            the scientific community knows best, whereas Clarivate appears to know or indeed care
            very little about the robustness of science. </p>
         <p> 4.5. Is the suppression a new attack on taxonomy? </p>
         <p> Based on the Zootaxa suppression and the academic engagement into a bandwagon
            sympathetic commotion, opinions in social media, and letters from societies and
            researchers (e.g. [ – ]), mainly from megadiverse countries, which appear to be in
            favour of the journal and ask Clarivate to review its decision, two main conclusions
            could be unearthed: (i) JIF appears very important to taxonomists and (ii) taxonomy is
            ‘under attack’. We seriously doubt both conclusions and invite the reader to carefully
            consider these aspects. </p>
         <p> Why do researchers choose to publish in Zootaxa ? Several reasons influence the
            preference of a researcher for a specific journal. Certainly, scope, visibility,
            prestige in the field and JIF are among the most influential criteria. It is realistic
            to assume that most of the authors of Zootaxa are looking for a journal that has fast
            reviewing and production processes, is free of charge to authors (no APC), has a
            comparatively high JIF, and has no limit of pages for a manuscript. Authors and readers
            of the journal seem not to be concerned about the hybrid policy with paywall, with few
            published articles having open access, achieved through payment by authors (APC-OA).
            Among the reasons for this complaisance are the article-processing charges for most open
            access journals with values of hundreds of Euros or US Dollars, generally excessively
            expensive for researchers from developing countries, the possible economic situation of
            most contributors (e.g. Brazilian researchers are authors of most papers in the journal,
            https://bit.ly/2Y0hSQ9, [ ]), and the open access is viable through platforms of
            selfarchiving, such as ResearchGate, or websites, such as Sci-Hub; the latter illegally
            makes paywalled content available for free and is regarded as ‘piracy’. High APC costs
            are clearly impeditive for researchers from most countries and for small research groups
            lacking big budgets. Also, there are certainly many other priorities for spending
            limited research money. Nevertheless, open access through platforms such as Sci-Hub is
            deprived of respect for the intellectual property or copyright laws and certainly raises
            many moral issues. Therefore, it is at least controversial that authors are opposed to
            paying fees to APC-GOA journals and are in favour of hybrid platforms because it is
            possible to break paywalls to access payment-based content. </p>
         <p> The holy grail quest for diamond open access (no APC for authors, DOA) versus paywall
            policies creates a paradox: how can journals cover the considerable costs involved in
            publishing, copyediting, DOI generation, data insertion into biodiversity databases,
            file archiving, etc.? These controversies concerning OA were depicted with vibrant
            colours during the gradual transition of big publishers’ journals, such as Diversity and
            Distributions , from readers’ payment to authors’ payment in an APC-OA model [ ].
            Gradually, the scientific scholarship publications are changing from paywall to GOA with
            authors paying the charges (APC-GOA) for publication in biodiversity journals.
            Certainly, this is the best business model option for the profit-seeking commercial
            publishers because it avoids losses generated by white (sometimes named black OA) or
            green platforms such as Sci-Hub, ResearchGate or Academia Inc. (site: academia.edu).
            Here, it is important to highlight that authors never received messages from Zootaxa
            demanding the removal of files from any such platforms, quite unlike the crusade carried
            out by big publishers against these kinds of storage and access-granting. </p>
         <p> We are aware of the leading role that bibliometric indexes play in the science
            publishing industry, as well as their considerable influence on how and where science is
            done nowadays. However, JIF cannot determine the development of a whole scientific
            field, even when supporting agencies adopt it as a criterion of quality. A high JIF does
            not necessarily come from a high-quality taxonomic study; it is probably much more
            connected to the scope and diversity of methods and sources of data that are usually
            portrayed by high JIF ranked journals. Another aspect to be considered is that Zootaxa
            was focused initially on long papers on descriptive taxonomy; subsequently, it gradually
            changed its scope and started accepting short notes and studies on various subjects
            associated with zoological taxonomy/systematics. Curiously, soon after Clarivate
            announced the reinstatement of the JIF of Zootaxa [ ], the journal’ s website refreshed
            its JIF, showing perhaps that it is willingly taking part in the JIF games. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> 5. Conclusion </title>
         <p> Menaces to taxonomy as a science come from distinct sources and the relatively low
            bibliometric indexes including citation rates of its journals is only one factor that
            contributes to establishing the so-called taxonomic impediment. The reversion of the
            suppression of Zootaxa by Clarivate is irrelevant to biological sciences and taxonomy
            because Journal Impact Factors are statistically illiterate [ ] and cause a great deal
            of harm to science. This reinstatement should certainly not be regarded by taxonomists
            as a victory for the field. As a community we should not endorse the villainy of
            bibliometric policies that bring more harm than benefit to our field. </p>
         <p> We hope the community of taxonomists gets engaged with renewed strength in actions
            directly connected to the development and promotion of our science. Instead of being
            deeply focused on gaming irreproducible journal metrics sold to our institutions and
            research funders, controlled by a USA /UK-based company, which itself was acquired in
            2016 by two private equity funds (Onex Corporation and Baring Private Equity
            Asia—ONEX/BPEA; see [ ], https://prn.to/31nGDYC, [43], https://bit.ly/3hm9yC4), we
            should perhaps concentrate, for instance, on securing professional positions for young
            talented taxonomists, who are much needed for the proper development and maintenance of
            museums, scientific collections and publicly accessible digital databases. We are sure
            that Zootaxa has provided an invaluable service to the field of taxonomy. Suppression
            from JIF will not change or diminish this remarkable contribution. </p>
         <p> We emphasize that menace to taxonomy comes not much from the suppression of any
            specific journal from a bibliometric platform belonging to a big company. Much more harm
            is caused by the limited renewal of professional positions and the loss of collections,
            such as the huge ones that were housed at the Museu Nacional of the Federal University
            of Rio de Janeiro . These are the real issues that should motivate the engagement and
            action of taxonomists around the world. In short and loud, taxonomy is produced by
            taxonomists, not by journals. We recognize the deep impact the JIF mania has on the
            careers of taxonomists, due to governmental policies that embraced bibliometric
            evaluations in a highly competitive environment, with researchers struggling for limited
            grants. However, our current challenges cannot be dealt with through endorsement of the
            status quo. We need to change the focus. Also, it is contradictory to argue in favour of
            the reinstatement of Zootaxa to the JIF without considering that this journal has this
            index influenced by the currently high levels of self-citation. Regardless of its real
            significance, JIF is lamentably considered by many to be one of the attractive qualities
            of Zootaxa . An honourable choice would be to reject bibliometric indexes altogether,
            including JIF, instead of considering them when convenient. We are witnessing a moral
            bankruptcy of the system of scientific publications devoted to the knowledge on
            biodiversity; it would be much better if the system could be somehow reinvented with
            ways to support DOA as its main goal. </p>
         <p> Taxonomic groups that still need massive descriptive studies, with many species waiting
            to be discovered, such as Coleoptera, Hymenoptera, Lepidoptera, Diptera and Arachnida,
            have many journals devoted specifically to them. The JIF of these journals is similar to
            that of Zootaxa and, of course, research on those taxa can also be published in more
            general outlets in Entomology or Zoology categories. Therefore, the high levels of
            self-citation in Zootaxa are hardly justifiable. It appears to us that these high levels
            are caused by a sociological bias, being a side effect of the Zootaxa phenomenon. Myths
            about Zootaxa as the unique journal that publishes taxonomic studies are clearly harmful
            to the field. In addition, an urgent question must be answered: if Zootaxa decides to
            ignore JIF altogether, would it remain a good vehicle for the publication of taxonomic
            papers? If your answer is no, there is certainly a big problem with the community of
            practitioners in the taxonomic world. </p>
         <p> Data accessibility. Primary compiled data were arranged in electronic supplementary
            material, file 1. </p>
         <p> Authors ’ contributions. Â.P.P. designed the study, compiled, organized and analysed
            the data, wrote the manuscript, revised and approved its final version; G.M., L.F.S. and
            R.M. wrote the manuscript, revised and approved its final version; L.M. and J.A.R.
            discussed concepts, revised and approved the final version. </p>
         <p> Competing interests. The authors declare no competing interests and their organizations
            had no role in any steps of the development of this study, from its design to submission
            for publication. </p>
         <p> Funding. This study was partially supported by grants from National Council for
            Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq) through research productivity
            fellowships to G.M. (proc. 303229/2018-7), J.A.R. (proc. 300019/2017-3), L.F.S. (proc.
            308337/2019-0) and L.M. (proc. 308994/2018-3). </p>
         <p> Acknowledgements. André Adrian Padial (DBot—UFPR) helped a great deal with the
            statistical analysis. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title> References </title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 1. Ioannidis JPA , Thombs BD . 2019 A user ’ s guide to inflated and
                  manipulated impact factors. Eur. J. Clin. Invest . 49, e13151 [ 1 – 6 ]. (doi:10.
                  1111/eci.13151) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 2. Cortegiani A et al . 2020 Inflated citations and metrics of
                  journals discontinued from Scopus for publication concerns: the GhoS(t)copus
                  Project . F1000Research 9 , 415 . (doi:10.12688/ f1000research.23847.1)
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 3. Van Norden R. 2013 Brazilian citation scheme outed. Thomson
                  Reuters suspends journals from its rankings for ‘ citation stacking ’ . Nature 500
                  , 510 – 511 . ( doi:10.1038/500510a) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 4. Larivière V , Haustein S , Mongeon P. 2015 The oligopoly of
                  academic publishers in the digital era . PLoS ONE 10 , e 0127502 . (doi:10.1371/
                  journal.pone.0127502) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 5. Glänzel W. 2008 Seven myths in bibliometrics: about facts and
                  fiction in quantitative science studies . COLLNET J. Scientometrics Inf. Manage. 2
                  , 9 – 17 . ( doi:10.1080/09737766.2008 .10700836) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 6. Index to Organism Names (ION)/Zoological Records. 2020 Top
                  systematics journals. See http://www.organismnames.com/metrics.htm?page=tsj
                  (accessed 26 August 2020 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 7. Wheeler B , Torchiano M. 2016 lmPerm: Permutation Tests for
                  Linear Models. See https://github.com/mtorchiano/lmPerm . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 8. R Core Team . 2018 [Version 3.50] R: A language and environment
                  for statistical computing . Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical
                  Computing . https://www.R-project.org . 9. Haustein S , Larivière V. 2015 The use
                  of bibliometrics for assessing research: possibilities, limitations and adverse
                  effects . In Incentives and performance (eds I Welpe, J Wollersheim, S Ringelhan,
                  M Osterloh). Cham, Switzerland : Springer . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 10. Garfield E. 1972 Analysis as a tool in journal evaluation .
                  Science 178 , 471 – 479 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 11. Garfield E. 2006 The history and meaning of the journal impact
                  factor . JAMA 295 , 90 . (doi:10.1001/jama.295.1.90) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 12. Hecht F , Hecht BK , Sandberg AA . 1998 The journal ‘ impact
                  factor ’ : a misnamed, misleading, misused measure. Cancer Genet. Cytogenet . 104
                  , 77 – 81 . (doi: 10.1016/S0165-4608(97)00459-7 ) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 13. Alberts B. 2013 Impact factor distortions . Science 340 , 787 .
                  ( doi:10.1126/science.1240319) 14. Chapman CA et al. 2019 Games academics play and
                  their consequences: how authorship, h-index and journal impact factors are shaping
                  the future of academia. Proc. R. Soc. B 286 , 20192047 . (doi: 10.1098/
                  rspb.2019.2047 ) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 15. The PLoS Medicine Editors . 2006 The impact factor game . PLoS
                  Med. 3 , e 291 . (doi:10.1371/ journal.pmed.0030291) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 16. Vanclay JK . 2012 Impact factor: outdated artefact or
                  stepping-stone to journal certification? Scientometrics 92 , 211 – 238 .(
                  doi:10.1007/s11192-011-0561-0) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 17. Dimitrov J , Kaveri S , Bayry J. 2010 Metrics: journal ’ s
                  impact factor skewed by a single paper. Nature 466 , 179 . (doi:10.1038/ 466179b)
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 18. Clarivate Analytics . 2020 Web of Science Journal Citation
                  Reports: Suppression Policy. See http://
                  help.incites.clarivate.com/incitesLiveJCR/ JCRGroup/titleSuppressions.html
                  (accessed 15 August 2020 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 19. Wheeler QD et al. 2012 Mapping the biosphere: exploring species
                  to understand the origin, organization and sustainability of biodiversity . Syst.
                  Biodivers. 10 , 1 – 20 . (doi:10.1080/ 14772000.2012.665095) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 20. Mayr E. 1969 Principles of systematic zoology . New York, NY:
                  McGraw-Hill . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 21. Wheeler QD . 2008 Introductory: toward the New Taxonomy . In The
                  New Taxonomy, Systematics Association special volume series (ed. QD Wheeler). Boca
                  Raton, FL: CRC Press. </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 22. Krell FT . 2000 Impact factors aren ’ t relevant to taxonomy.
                  Nature 405 , 507 – 508 . (doi:10.1038/ 35014664) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 23. Rafael JA , Aguiar AP , Amorim DS . 2009 Knowledge of insect
                  diversity in Brazil: challenges and advances . Neotrop. Entomol. 38 , 565 – 570 .
                  ( doi:10.1590/s1519- 566x2009000500001) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 24. Ebach MC , Valdecasas AG , Wheeler QD . 2011 Impediments to
                  taxonomy and users of taxonomy: accessibility and impact evaluation . Cladistics
                  27 , 550 – 557 . ( doi:10.1111/j.1096- 0031.2011.00348.x) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 25. Crisci JV , Katinas L , Apodaca MJ , Hoch PC . 2020 The end of
                  botany . Trends Plant Sci. 25 , 1173 – 1176 . ( doi:10.1016/j.tplants.2020
                  .09.012) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 26. Meier R. 2017 Citation of taxonomic publications: the why, when,
                  what and what not . Syst. Entomol. 42 , 301 – 304 . (doi:10.1111/ syen.12215)
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 27. Zhang Z-Q. 2011 Accelerating biodiversity descriptions and
                  transforming taxonomic publishing: the first decade of Zootaxa . Zootaxa 2896 , 1
                  – 7 . ( doi:10.11646/zootaxa . 2896.1.1 ) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 28. Zhang Z-Q. 2014 Sustaining the development of world ’ s foremost
                  journal in biodiversity discovery and inventory: Zootaxa editors and their
                  contributions. Zootaxa 3753 , 597 – 600 . ( doi:10.11646/zootaxa.3753.6.6) 29.
                  Curry S. 2018 Let ’ s move beyond the rhetoric: it ’ s time to change how we judge
                  research. Nature 554 , 147 . ( doi:10.1038/d41586-018- 01642-w) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 30. Krüger AK . 2020 Quantification 2.0? Bibliometric
                  infrastructures in academic evaluation . Polit.Gov. 8 , 58 – 67 . (
                  doi:10.17645/pag.v8i2.2575) 31. Reategui E , Pires A , Carniato M , Franco SRK .
                  2020 Evaluation of Brazilian research output in education:confronting
                  international and national contexts . Scientometrics 125 , 427 – 444 . (doi:10.
                  1007/s11192-020-03617-z) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 32. Monbiot G. 2011 Academic publishers make Murdoch look like a
                  socialist. The Guardian, Monday 29 August 2011 . [A fully referenced version
                  available at: https://www.monbiot.com/ 2011/08/29 /the-lairds-of-learning/]
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 33. Szomszor M , Pendlebury DA , Adams J. 2020 How much is too much?
                  The difference between research influence and self-citation excess .
                  Scientometrics 123 , 1119 – 1147 . (doi:10.1007/ s11192-020-03417-5)
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 34. Chorus C , Waltman L. 2016 A large-scale analysis of impact
                  factor biased journal selfcitations . PLoS ONE 11 , e 0161021 . (doi:10.1371/
                  journal.pone.0161021) </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 35. Brazilian Society of Herpetology (SBH). 2020 Letter to Clarivate
                  . http://sbherpetologia.org.br/ assets//Documentos/C%C3%B3pia%20de%
                  20SBH%20Zootaxa.docx . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 36. Sociedad de Odonatologia Latinoamericana – SOL . 2020 Letter to
                  Marian Hollingsworth Clarivate Analytic. 3 July 2020 . See http://www.
                  odonatasol.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/ SOL-support-for-ZOOTAXA-1.pdf (accessed
                  20 August 2020 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 37. Van Damme K. 2020 Zootaxa Suppressed from 2019 JCR Data (2020
                  release). 16 July 2020 . See
                  https://www.gopetition.com/petitions/zootaxasuppressed-from-2019-jcr-data-2020-release.
                  html?fbclid=IwAR3dL0dntvkIw_ xBdx00rB7Os9e6y-NvRCC_ i8WMvo2I0KJJEa1VXuMDoP8
                  (accessed 20 August 2020 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 38. Zootaxa . 2015 Statistics . See https://www.
                  mapress.com/zootaxa/support/Statistics.htm . 39. Peterson AT et al . 2019 Open
                  access solutions for biodiversity journals: do not replace one problem with
                  another. Divers. Distrib. 25 , 5 – 8 . ( doi:10.1111/ddi.12888) 40. Clarivate
                  Analytics . 2020 Statement on suppression. Clarivate Web of Science @webofscience
                  on Twitter . 28 July 2020 , 10:24 a.m. See https://twitter.com/webofscience/
                  status/1288103038121648128?s=08 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 41. Curry S. 2012 Sick of Impact Factors. Occam ’ s Typewriter. 13
                  August 2012 . See http:// occamstypewriter.org/scurry/ 2012/08/13
                  /sick-ofimpact-factors/ (accessed 30 August 2020 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 42. Cision Ltd/PR Newswire. 2016 Acquisition of the Thomson Reuters
                  Intellectual Property and Science Business by Onex and Baring Asia completed. 3
                  October 2016 . See https://www.prnewswire.com/
                  news-releases/acquisition-of-the-thomson-reuters-intellectual-property-and-science-
                  business-by-onex-and-baring-asia-completed-300337402.html (accessed 20 August 2020
                  ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 43. Baring Private Equity Asia – BPEA . 2019 Baring Private Equity
                  Asia and Onex Partners announce secondary offering of Clarivate Analytics. 4
                  December 2019 . See https://www.bpeasia.com/
                  news/191204-joint-press-release-on-clarivateanalytics/ (accessed 26 August 2020 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
