<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Science</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aal4853</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>An elephant-sized Late Triassic synapsid with erect limbs</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>22</day>
            <month>11</month>
            <year>2018</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> PALEONTOLOGY </p>
         <p> An elephant-sized Late Triassic synapsid with erect limbs </p>
         <p> Tomasz Sulej 1 and Grzegorz Niedźwiedzki 2 * </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Here, we describe the dicynodont <tp:taxon-name>Lisowicia</tp:taxon-name> bojani , from
            the Late Triassic of Poland, a gigantic synapsid with seemingly upright subcursorial
            limbs that reached an estimated length of more than 4.5 meters, height of 2.6 meters,
            and body mass of 9 tons. <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name> is the youngest
            undisputed dicynodont and the largest nondinosaurian terrestrial tetrapod from the
            Triassic.The lack of lines of arrested growth and the highly remodeled cortex of its
            limb bones suggest permanently rapid growth and recalls that of dinosaurs and mammals.
            The discovery of <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name> overturns the established
            picture of the Triassic megaherbivore radiation as a phenomenon restricted to dinosaurs
            and shows that stem-group mammals were capable of reaching body sizes that were not
            attained again in mammalian evolution until the latest Eocene. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> The time interval from the end of the Permian to the beginning of the Jurassic (252 to
            201 million years ago) coincided with a trophic and taxonomic restructur- ing of
            terrestrial ecosystems ( ). During the middle Permian, the predominant large herbivores
            were dinocephalians — stem-group mammals (in the clade Synapsida, “ mammal-like reptiles
            ” ) such as <tp:taxon-name> Tapinocephalus </tp:taxon-name> , which was up to 3 m in
            length and weighed an estimated 2 tons ( ). These ani- mals were associated with faunas
            of nonsynapsid pareiasaurian parareptiles and a rich variety of other synapsids. In the
            late Permian, the largesize synapsid herbivores (rhachiocephalid dicynodonts) and the
            last pareiasaurians played the role of largest terrestrial herbivores ( ). By the Early
            Jurassic, no stem-group mammals were larger than a half meter in length, and most were
            much smaller ( , ), whereas herbivorous dinosaurs exceeded 15 m in length and 10 tons in
            weight; virtually all mid-sized to large tetrapods were archosaurs. Until now, this
            pattern has appeared clear-cut, with Triassic synapsids approaching the largest Permian
            forms in size but with no forms reaching sizes of the first large sauropodomorphs. </p>
         <p> Dicynodonts were among the most abundant and diverse synapsids from the middle Permian
            to the early Late Triassic ( , ). There were two episodes of body size increase in their
            evolution: the first in the late Permian, exemplified by <tp:taxon-name> Rhachiocephalus
            </tp:taxon-name> , and the second in the Middle to Late Triassic, when dicynodonts such
            as <tp:taxon-name> Placerias </tp:taxon-name> were the dominant herbivores in some
            ecosystems ( ). There have been comparatively few rigorous estimates of dicynodont or
            dinocephalian body masses presented in the literature. The largest of these dicynodonts
            (such as kannemeyeriiforms) are estimated previously to have reached lengths of 3 to 3.5
            m and weights of up to 1 to 2 tons </p>
         <p> ( , ), which is very similar to the largest middle Permian dinocephalians, such as
               <tp:taxon-name> Tapinocephalus </tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name> Moschops
            </tp:taxon-name> ( ). </p>
         <p> Fossils of Triassic dicynodonts are extremely abundant in African, Asian, and North and
            South American deposits but are comparatively poorly known from other regions ( , ).
            Dicynodonts were seemingly rare in the European Late Triassic, being known only from a
            single mandible ( ) and questionable isolated bones ( ). The Late Triassic dicynodont
            fossils described here, of <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia bojani </tp:taxon-name> , are the
            first substantial finds from Europe ( , ). </p>
         <p> Many previous authors have analyzed the structure of the pelvic girdle of Triassic
            dicyn- odonts, resulting in the unanimous opinion that the posture of the hindlimbs was
            erect ( ). By contrast, most authors agree that Triassic dicyn- odonts had sprawling
            forelimbs with the hori- zontal position of the humerus ( ). <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia
            </tp:taxon-name> has a relatively conventional dicynodont hindlimb construction but
            departs from the standard forelimb posture ( Fig. 1 ). In many respects, its forelimb
            position resembles that of large quadrupedal dinosaurs, but forelimb elements of
               <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name> are morphologically similar to other
            dicynodonts ( Fig. 2 ). The result is a subcursorial tetrapod with upright limb posture,
            unlike any other known stem-group mammal but comparable with that of large crown-group
            mammals such as rhinoceroses and hippopotami, as well as quadrupedal dinosaurs such as
            sauropodomorphs and ceratopsians. </p>
         <p> Histological data from limb bones of <tp:taxon-name>Lisowicia</tp:taxon-name> provide
            life history data that complement its dis- tinctness. Like other large dicynodonts,
               <tp:taxon-name>Lisowicia</tp:taxon-name> shows a large area of bone resorption in the
            inner cortex. However, unlike in other genera, there is no clear sign of growth-slowing
            later in life. The presence of potential lines of arrested growth in the studied tibia
            might be indicative of slower, more episodic growth. However, the lack of characteristic
            slow-growing tissue on the periphery </p>
         <p> of the largest bones of <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name> suggests that the
            studied material represents either a fastgrowing taxon or juvenile/subadult individuals
            of extremely large body size. However, the second explanation is rather unlikely because
            of its size and that these two bones are well ossified. </p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name> demonstrates that Late Triassic dicynodonts
            became specialized herbivores. It displays several features in the limb skeleton that
            suggest that this group evolved new postural adaptations. The massive scapula of
               <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name> lacks a distinct acromion process for
            articulation with the clavicle, the scapula articulates with the humerus on its
            posteroventrally (instead of posterolaterally) located glenoid, and distal articulation
            surfaces of the humerus are in the same plane instead of being rotated (formal taxonomic
            description is provided in the supplementary materials). </p>
         <p> On the basis of published scaling relationships ( ), we estimate an adult body mass of
            9000 kg, which approaches that of an African elephant [the largest recorded individual
            stood 4 m at the shoulders and weighed 10,000 kg ( )]. This confirms that
               <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name> was certainly the largest Triassic land
            nondinosaur tetrapod. Gigantism in herbivorous dinosaurs first emerged in the Late
            Triassic, with the evolution of the first large sauropodomorphs ( , ) and then the
            earliest true sauropods ( ). Until now, gigantism in the Triassic appeared to be
            entirely a dinosaur adaptation ( ), and previously known Triassic dicynodonts were
            substantially smaller. The discovery of <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name>
            suggests that general ecological factors may have been driving the process, rather than
            clade-specific attributes of dinosaurs ( ). </p>
         <p> The find of <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name> shows that at least one
            dicynodont lineage also participated in the “ push for gigantism ” at the same time as
            the sauropodomorphs ( ) but also suggests that their evolutionary history in the Late
            Triassic is poorly documented ( Fig. 3A ). In addition, recognition of <tp:taxon-name>
               Lisowicia </tp:taxon-name> as a placeriine dicynodont together with the resurrection
            and recent description of <tp:taxon-name> Pentasaurus </tp:taxon-name> from South Africa
            ( ) alters our understanding of the Late Triassic fossil record of dicynodonts. Although
            their relatively lower abundance and richness compared with those of Middle and early
            Late Triassic faunas suggest evolutionary decline, the concept of the Late Triassic
            kannemeyeriiforms as highly geographically restricted relicts is no longer valid ( ).
            The recognition of dicynodonts in the late Norian – earliest Rhaetian of Europe ( ) and
            Karoo Basin ( ) conflicts with some ideas on early Late Triassic dicynodont extinction
            and survival, namely their supposed absence during the radiation of early
            sauropodomorphs ( Fig. 3B ). </p>
         <p> Upright posture has been associated with decreased joint stress and energetic cost of
            locomotion ( ). Selection pressures on some aspects of lifestyle or ecology were likely
            drivers of the evolution of the distinct posture of <tp:taxon-name> Lisowicia
            </tp:taxon-name> among dicynodonts. Increase in the body size of dicynodonts across the
            Late Triassic may have been driven by selection pressure to reach a size refuge from
            large predators ( ). It is possible also that the gigantism of the latest dicynodonts
            was a metabolic adaptation that allowed these animals to maximize food retention time
            and consequently the energy gain ( ). It took Late Triassic dicynodonts some 20 million
            years to produce giant forms ( Fig. 3 , B and C), and it was a rather gradual size
            increase and a similar pace </p>
         <p> to that observed in the evolution of herbivorous dinosaurs in the Mesozoic and
            mammalian lineages in the mid-late Paleogene ( ). All suggest that in the Late Triassic,
            there was a substantial temporal overlap in the occurrence of very large herbivores: the
            previously dominant dicynodonts and their emerging ecological analogs among archosaurs,
            the sauropodomorph dinosaurs. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title> REFERENCES AND NOTES </title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 1. H.-D. Sues , N. C. Fraser , Triassic Life on Land: The Great
                  Transition ( Columbia Univ. Press , 2010 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 2. G. M. King , Anomodontia, Encyclopedia of Paleoherpetology (Part
                  17C) ( Gutsav Fischer Verlag , 1988 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 3. Z. Kielan-Jaworowska , R. L. Cifelli , Z.-X. Luo , Mammals from
                  the Age of Dinosaurs: Origins, Evolution, and Structure ( Columbia Univ. Press ,
                  2004 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 4. T. S. Kemp , The Origin and Evolution of Mammals ( Oxford Univ.
                  Press , 2005 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 5. J. Fröbisch , Earth Sci. Rev . 95 , 119 – 157 ( 2009 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 6. J. Fröbisch , PLOS ONE 3 , e 3733 ( 2008 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 7. A. R. Fiorillo , K. Padian , C. Musikasinthorn , Palaios 15 , 373
                  – 386 ( 2000 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 8. R. R. Schoch , Neues Jahrb. Geol. Palaontol. Abh . 263 , 119 –
                  123 ( 2012 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 9. M. W. Maisch , C. S. Vega , R. R. Schoch , Palaeodiversity 2 ,
                  271 – 278 ( 2009 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 10. J. Dzik , T. Sulej , G. Niedźwiedzki , Acta Palaeontol. Pol . 53
                  , 733 – 738 ( 2008 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 11. T. Sulej , R. Bronowicz , M. Tałanda , G. Niedzwiedzki , Proc.
                  R. Soc. Edinb . 101 , 261 – 269 ( 2011 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 12. J. Fröbisch , Can. J. Earth Sci . 43 , 1297 – 1308 ( 2006 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 13. L. R. Walter , in The Beginning of the Age of Dinosaurs (
                  Cambridge Univ. Press , 1986 ), pp. 89 – 97 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 14. N. E. Campione , D. C. Evans , BMC Biol . 10 , 60 ( 2012 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 15. D. Macdonald , The New Encyclopedia of Mammals ( Oxford Univ.
                  Press , 2001 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 16. A. M. Yates , Palaeontology 46 , 317 – 337 ( 2003 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 17. P. M. Sander et al ., Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc . 86 , 117 –
                  155 ( 2011 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 18. A. M. Yates , J. W. Kitching , Proc. Biol. Sci . 270 , 1753 –
                  1758 ( 2003 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 19. P. C. Sereno , Science 284 , 2137 – 2147 ( 1999 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 20. R. B. Sookias , R. J. Butler , R. B. J. Benson , Proc. Biol. Sci
                  . 279 , 2180 – 2187 ( 2012 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 21. Ch. F. Kammerer , Palaeontologia Africana 52 , 102 – 128 ( 2018
                  ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 22. C. F. Kammerer , J. Fröbisch , K. D. Angielczyk , PLOS ONE 8 , e
                  64203 ( 2013 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 23. A. A. Biewener , Science 245 , 45 – 48 ( 1989 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 24. G. Niedźwiedzki , P. Gorzelak , T. Sulej , Lethaia 44 , 87 – 92
                  ( 2011 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 25. P. Bajdek , K. Owocki , G. Niedźwiedzki , Palaeogeogr.
                  Palaeoclimatol. Palaeoecol . 411 , 1 – 17 ( 2014 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 26. D. Prothero , Rhinoceros Giants: The Palaeobiology of
                  Indricotheres ( Indiana Univ. Press , 2013 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 27. S. Fujiwara , J. Vertebr . Paleontol . 29 , 1136 – 1147 ( 2009
                  ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title> ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </title>
         <p>We thank J. Dzik (Institute of Paleobiology, PAS) for proposing this research and
            support, M. Dec (Institute of Paleobiology,</p>
         <p> PAS) for help with preparation of dicynodont shoulder girdle virtual model, P. E.
            Ahlberg (Uppsala University) for discussion, D. Snitting (Uppsala University) for help
            with phylogenetic and computed tomography data, N. Campione (University of New England)
            for his help with body mass estimate, and K. Zaremba-Niedźwiedzka (Uppsala University)
            for help during preparation of the manuscript. We are very thankful to anonymous
            reviewers whose comments radically improved the final version of the paper. Funding: The
            study was supported by Polish grant (2012/07/B/NZ8/02707) and Swedish Vetenskapsrådet
            grant (2017-05248). Author contributions: T.S. designed the study. T.S. and G.N.
            performed the comparative and analytical work, participated in morphological studies,
            and wrote the paper. Competing interests: The authors declare no competing interests.
            Data and materials availability: All described specimens are accessioned at the
            Institute of Paleobiology, PAS (Poland). </p>
         <p> SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS </p>
         <p>www. sciencemag.org/content/363/6422/78/suppl/DC1</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Materials and Methods</p>
         <p>Supplementary Text</p>
         <p> Figs. S1 to S16 </p>
         <p>Tables S1 to S7</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> An elephant-sized Late Triassic synapsid with erect limbs </title>
         <p> References ( 28–74 ) </p>
         <p>Movies S1 to S4</p>
         <p>28 November 2016; resubmitted 4 August 2018</p>
         <p>Accepted 19 October 2018</p>
         <p>Published online 22 November 2018</p>
         <p>10.1126/science.aal4853</p>
         <p> Tomasz Sulej and Grzegorz Niedzwiedzki </p>
         <p> Science 363 (6422), 78-80. </p>
         <p>DOI: 10.1126/science.aal4853originally published online November 22, 2018</p>
         <p> A proto-mammalian giant </p>
         <p>Early terrestrial amniotes evolved into two groups: the sauropsids, which led to the
            bird and dinosaur lineages, and the synapsids, which led to mammals. Synapsids were
            diverse during the Permian but were greatly reduced after the end-Permian extinction
            (about 252 million years ago). The few groups that survived into the Triassic were
            mostly small a nd retained a sprawling gait. Sulej and Niedzwiedzki, however, describe a
            dicynodont from the Late Triassic of Poland that is as large as some coexisting
            dinosaurs and appears to have had an erect gait like modern mammals. Thus,
            megaherbivores in the Triassic were not only dinosaurs.</p>
         <p> Science , this issue p. 78 </p>
         <p> ARTICLE TOOLS </p>
         <p> http://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6422/78 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title> SUPPLEMENTARY </title>
         <p> MATERIALS </p>
         <p>http://science.sciencemag.org/content/suppl/2018/11/19/science.aal4853.DC1</p>
         <p> RELATED </p>
         <p> CONTENT </p>
         <p>http://science.sciencemag.org/content/sci/362/6417/897.full</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title> REFERENCES </title>
         <p>This article cites 49 articles, 5 of which you can access for free
            http://science.sciencemag.org/content/363/6422/78#BIBL</p>
         <p> PERMISSIONS </p>
         <p>http://www.sciencemag.org/help/reprints-and-permissions</p>
         <p> Use of this article is subject to the Terms of Service </p>
         <p> Science (print ISSN 0036-8075; online ISSN 1095-9203) is published by the American
            Association for the Advancement of Science, 1200 New York Avenue NW, Washington, DC
            20005. 2017 © The Authors, some rights reserved; exclusive licensee American Association
            for the Advancement of Science. No claim to original U.S. Government Works. The title
            Science is a registered trademark of AAAS. </p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
