<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>The journal of infectious diseases</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.1145711</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Placebo-Controlled Phase 3 Trial of a Recombinant Glycoprotein 120
               Vaccine to Prevent HIV-1 Infection</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>31</day>
            <month>12</month>
            <year>2005</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Placebo-Controlled Phase 3 Trial of a Recombinant</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Glycoprotein 120 Vaccine to Prevent HIV-1 Infection</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group a </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> (See the article by Gilbert et al., on pages 666–77, and the editorial commentary by
            Graham and Mascola, on pages 647–9.) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Background. A vaccine is needed to prevent human immunodeficienc virus type 1 (HIV-1)
            infection. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Methods. A double-blind, randomized trial of a recombinant HIV-1 envelope glycoprotein
            subunit (rgp120) vaccine was conducted among men who have sex with men and among women
            at high risk for heterosexual transmission of HIV-1. Volunteers received 7 injections of
            either vaccine or placebo (ratio, 2:1) over 30 months. The primary end point was HIV-1
            seroconversion over 36 months. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Results. A total of 5403 volunteers (5095 men and 308 women) were evaluated. The
            vaccine did not prevent HIV-1 acquisition: infection rates were 6.7% in 3598 vaccinees
            and 7.0% in 1805 placebo recipients; vaccineefficac (VE) was estimated as 6% (95%
            confidenc interval, 17% to 24%). There were no significan differences in viral loads,
            rates of antiretroviral-therapy initiation, or the genetic characteristics of the
            infecting HIV-1 strains between treatment arms. Exploratory subgroup analyses showed
            nonsignifican trends toward efficac inpreventinginfection in the highest risk (VE, 43%;
            n p 247) and nonwhite (VE, 47%; n p 914) volunteers ( P p.10, adjusted for multiple
            subgroup comparisons). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Conclusions. There was no overall protective effect. The efficac trends in subgroups
            may provide clues for the development of effective immunization approaches. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The creation of a vaccine to combat the global HIV-1 pandemic is an international
            public-health priority [ , ]. Although infection leads to the development of an
            HIV-specifi immune response, the immune system is generally unable to effectively
            control replication of the virusortopreventimmunosuppression[ ].Nonetheless, there is
            evidence of a protective immune response in certain special circumstances [ – ]. There
            has also been considerable debate with regard to whether antibodymediated or
            cell-mediated responses are of primary importance in providing protective immunity [ , ,
            ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Protection of chimpanzees from intravenous and mucosal challenge with homologous and
            heterologous HIV-1 strains has been achieved with recombinant HIV- 1 envelope
            glycoprotein subunit (rgp120 and rgp160) vaccines [ – ]. Phase 1 and 2 studies in
            uninfected humans have demonstrated that rgp120 is safe and able to generate antibody
            responses similar to those observed in the protected chimpanzees [ – ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Two versions of an rgp120 vaccinecandidateadvanced to phase 3 studies in 1998–1999. The
            firs study was to evaluate a bivalent subtype B/B rgp120 vaccine in individuals in North
            AmericaandTheNetherlandswhowere at risk for infection via sexual exposure, whereas the
            second study was to evaluate a bivalent subtype B/E rgp120 vaccine in injection drug
            users in Thailand [ , ]. Here, we report the resultsofthefirs ofthesestudies designed to
            evaluate whether an rgp120 vaccine canconfer protection against HIV-1 infection. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Vaccine and Placebo Preparations </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The study vaccine contained 2 rgp120 HIV-1 envelope antigens (300 mg each of MN and GNE8
            rgp120/HIV-1) (AIDSVAX B/ B; VaxGen) that had been derived from 2 different subtype B
            strains and that were adsorbed onto 600 mg of alum. GNE8 gp120 was cloned directly from
            peripheral-blood mononuclear cells and had the CCR5 phenotype; the GNE8 gp120 DNA
            sequence was deposited in GenBank (accession no. AY771703). Placebo consisted of alum
            only.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Ethics Considerations </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The present study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and
            local institutional review board requirements and with approval from appropriate
            regulatory authorities. Written, informed consent was obtained from all volunteers.
            Before enrollment in the study, a thorough discussion of possible issues and risks
            associated with participation was conducted with each potential volunteer [ ]. At each
            visit that included screening, trained counselors provided comprehensive education and
            pre- or post-HIV test and risk-reduction counseling, according to a comprehensive
            manual. Safety was monitored every 6 months by an independent data and safety monitoring
            board, which performed 1 interim efficac analysis 40 months after initiation of the
            study. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Vaccination and Study Assessments </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Vaccine or placebo was administered by intramuscularinjection at months 0, 1, 6, 12, 18,
            24, and 30, with a fina follow-up visit at month 36. At each visit, adverse events and
            possible social harms were assessed; blood was obtained for assessment of HIV-1 status
            and immunogenicity. HIV-1 status was determined by detection of HIV-1 antibodies, using
            a standard HIV- 1 ELISA and confi matory immunoblot. The date of HIV-1 infection was
            estimated as follows: if HIV-1 RNA was undetectable in serum by a highly sensitive and
            specifi nucleicacid– based amplificatio test (NAT; Procleix HIV-1 Discriminatory Assay)
            at the date of the last seronegative test, then the date of HIV-1 infection was
            estimated as the midpoint of the dates of the last negative and firs positive
            ELISA/immunoblot test results. Otherwise, the infection date was estimated as the date
            of the earliest sample with detectable HIV-1 RNA. For volunteers who became infected
            during the study, plasma HIV-1 RNA load and CD4+ lymphocyte counts were assessed at!1
            month and at months 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, and 24 afterdiagnosis of infection.
            Self-reported risk behaviors, including sexual activity and alcohol and drug use, and
            occurrence of sexually transmitted diseases were assessed by use of standard
            interviewer-administeredquestionnairesatbaselineandevery6months thereafter.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Sequencing of Viral gp120 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>HIV-1 RNA was isolated from the earliest postinfection plasma sample; full-length gp120
            genes were amplifie and cloned. Three full-length gp120 sequences were recovered from
            each of 336 of 368 infected volunteers. With the exception of 1 subtype C virus, all
            isolates were subtype B.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Immune Responses to the rgp120 Vaccine </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> A cytopathicity bioassay was used to determine 50% neutralizing titers for HIV-1MN
            infection of MT-4 cells. Binding antibodies were measured in 5 indirect ELISAs with
            anMN/GNE8 gp120 mixture and GNE8 V2, MN V2, GNE8 V3, and MN V3 peptides as the antigens.
            Two competitive ELISAs were used to measure antibody blocking of the binding of MN or
            GNE8 gp120 to recombinant soluble CD4 [ , ]. The 8 assays were performed on samples
            obtained 2 weeks after the last immunization before HIV-1 infection for infected
            vaccinees and on samples obtained 2 weeks after each immunization for a 5% random sample
            of uninfected vaccinees. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Statistical Analysis </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Primary end-point analysis. Vaccine efficac (VE) was define as (1 the relative risk of
            infection) 100 and was estimated by use of a Cox proportional hazards model, with time
            to HIV infection grouped over six 6-month intervals and with the Efron method used for
            correction for ties [ ]. The sample size of the trial was selected as that which would
            provide, by a 2-sided log-rank test, 90% power to reject the null hypoth-esis—VE 30% if
            the true VE 60%. The Lan-DeMets implementation of the O’Brien-Fleming stopping boundary
            was used for 1 interim efficac analysis. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Secondary end-point analyses. A generalized-estimatingequations model, which was based
            on all viral loads from samples obtained before initiation of antiretroviral therapy
            (ART), was used to estimate the mean difference between the vaccine and placebo arms in
            pre-ART viral load at each of the 9 postinfection visits. The time between detection of
            HIV infection and initiation of ART was compared between the 2 study arms by use of a
            log-rank test. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Exploratory analyses. Tests for interaction in Cox proportional hazards models were
            used to evaluate whether VE differed by age (30 or 1 30 years), sex, education (less
            than a college degree or a college or graduate degree), race (white, black, Hispanic,
            Asian, and other and white vs. nonwhite), and baseline behavioral risk (low, medium, and
            high) [ ]. The binary categories for age and education were determinedbefore the
            unblinded analysis was conducted by collapsing the 5 age categories and the 4 education
            categories into 2 binary categories with approximately equal sample size. Because there
            was limited power to evaluate the VE for particular nonwhite subgroups, race was also
            dichotomized as white and nonwhite, with the latter category including volunteers who
            designated their race as Hispanic. Volunteers were classifie as having low, medium, or
            high baseline behavioral risk on the basis of selfreported behaviors during the 6 months
            before enrollment that were predictive of HIV infection in men pooled over the treatment
            arms. Behaviors that were statistically significan ( P !.05) in univariate Cox
            proportional hazards models were further assessed in multivariate models. Nine behaviors
            were identifie as independent predictors of HIV infection. A behavioral risk score for
            each volunteer was computed as the total number of these behaviors the person reported
            at baseline. The score was highly predictive of HIV infection, with
            anestimatedhazardratio of 1.66 (95% confidenc interval [CI], 1.56 to 1.77) per 1
            riskfactor increase ( P !.0 0 0 1). Behavioral risk scores ranged from 0 to 7; 0 was
            categorized as low, 1–3 was categorized as medium, and 4–7 was categorized as high. The
            baseline behavioral risk score was based on data for men only, because only 6 HIV-1
            infections were observed among the 308 female volunteers and because the important risk
            factor of insertive anal sex does not apply to women. The results reported below on VE
            by behavioral risk category did not change appreciably when the risk model was based on
            data for both men and women. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> To account for multiple comparisons in subgroup analyses, a rerandomization
            procedure(with10,000permutations)wasused to testtheomnibusnullhypothesisthat VE p 0
            forallsubgroups versus the alternative hypothesis that VE (0 for at least 1 subgroup. A
            bootstrap resampling procedure was used to compute adjusted P values [ ]. The estimate
            and 95% CI of the VE value within each subgroup was also computed by use of a Cox
            proportional hazards model. A Cox proportional hazards modelwas used to estimate VE
            values for particular HIV-1 genotypes and to test whether VE differed by viral genotype
            [ ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> RESULTS </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Demographics, Risk Behavior, and Conduct of Study </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Between June 1998 and October 1999, 7185 volunteers were screened for study eligibility
            criteria ( figu e 1 ). Of these, 5417 eligible volunteers (5108 men and 309 women) were
            enrolled and were randomized to receive either vaccine or placebo. Of the 1768
            volunteers not enrolled, 966 did not return after the initial screening visit, 328 met
            the study eligibility criteria but chose not to enroll, and 474 were excluded; the major
            reasons for exclusion were HIV-1 infection (161), serious underlying disease (148), and
            not meeting risk-behavior criteria (141). Despite being HIV-1 antibody negative at
            screening, 14 (11 vaccinees and 3 placebo recipients) volunteers had HIV-1infection
            detected at baseline (month 0) and were excluded from all efficac, but not safety,
            analyses. Of these, 12 were positive by NAT at month 0, although they were antibody
            negative; 1 was positive by NAT and intermediate by immunoblot; and 1 was positive by
            NAT and antibody positive. The vaccineandplacebo arms were similar in terms of
            demographiccharacteristics( table 1 ). The study population was predominantly male
            (94%),white (83%), young (median age, 36 years), and well educated (61% had a college or
            graduate degree). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Self-reported risk behaviors, including sexual activity and alcohol and drug use, and
            rates of sexually transmitted diseases were similar in the vaccine and placebo arms at
            baseline and during follow-up ( table 1 and figu e 2 ); they were also similar when
            stratifie by race ( figu e 3 ) and by behavioral risk group ( figu e 4 ). For the 9
            behaviors reported at baseline that were predictive of HIV-1 infection, borderline
            statisticallysignifican differences between the vaccine and placebo arms were observed
            for unprotected receptive anal sex with an HIV-1–uninfected partner reported at month 6
            (i.e., occurring during the interval between baseline and the month 6 visit) and
            unprotected receptive anal sex with an HIV-1–infected partner reported at month 18. Most
            behaviors, except amphetamine use and unprotected receptive anal sex with an
            HIV-1–uninfected partner, decreased over time, with the major decrease occurring between
            baseline and month 6. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The rate of compliance with study vaccinations and the rate of loss to follow-up were
            well balanced between the vaccine and placebo arms ( figu e 1 and table 2), although, in
            the high behavioral risk subgroup, the dropout rate was higher in the placebo arm (24%)
            than in the vaccine arm (13%) ( P p.0 52, Fisher’s exact test). There were no
            statistically significan differences in the 9 baseline risk behaviors between the
            vaccinees and placebo recipients who dropped out of the study. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 656 • JID 2005:191 (1 March) • rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group Adverse Events </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The vaccine was generally well tolerated. The most common adverse events were mild or
            moderate reactogenicitysymptoms that occurred during the firs 3 days after a
            vaccination. Rates of local symptoms at the injection site were higher in the vaccinees;
            local edema, induration, or a subcutaneous nodule reported on at least 1 of the 14 days
            after any of the vaccinations was reported by 36%, 29%, and 21% of the vaccinees and by
            17%, 15%, and 12% of the placebo recipients, respectively. There were no other major
            differences in the frequency and type of reported adverse events.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Rates of Infection and VE </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Overall, 368 (6.8%) volunteers became HIV-1 infected during the study, giving an annual
            incidence rate of 2.6% (2.7% in men and 0.8% in women). No reduction of infection in
            vaccine recipients was observed (VE, 6% [95% CI, to ]; P p.59) ( table 3 ). Kaplan-Meier
            curves of the time-to-infection showed approximately constant rates of HIV-1 infection;
            the rates were similar in the vaccine and placebo arms during the 36 months of follow-up
            (figu e 5 A ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Postinfection Markers of Disease Progression </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Among the volunteers who acquired HIV-1 infection, pre-ART viral loads over the course
            of the 9 visits were similar in the vaccine and placebo arms ( P p.81). The mean
            difference (the mean of the vaccine arm minus the mean of the placebo arm) in pre-ART
            viral load at the visit 2 months after detection was 4.26 4.33 p 0.07 log10 (95% CI,
            0.33 to 0.18 log10). The Downloaded from
            https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by Aerztegemeinschaft
            fuer Anaesthesie user </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> NOTE. Data are no. (%) of volunteers, unless otherwise noted. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>a One volunteer missing education data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>was b Risk defined the total of risk factors reported from the following: (1)
            unprotected receptive anal with score was as no. sex an</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>HIV-1–infected male partner; (2) unprotected insertive anal sex with an HIV-1–infected
            male partner; (3) unprotected receptive anal</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>sex with an HIV-1–uninfected male partner; (4) 5 acts of unprotected receptive anal sex
            with a male partner of unknown HIV-1</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>status; (5) 10 sex partners; (6) anal herpes; (7) hepatitis A; (8) use of poppers; and
            (9) use of amphetamines. Behavioral risk scores</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ranged from 0 to 7; 0 was categorized as low, 1–3 was categorized as medium, and 4–7 was
            categorized as high.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> rate of initiation of ART was similar in the vaccine (99/225 [ %]) and placebo (53/122
            [ %]) arms ( P p.61, log-rank test). No significan effects of vaccination on any
            postinfection end points were observed. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Exploratory Subgroup Analyses </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> There were no significan interactions with treatment for sex, age, or education level,
            but interaction tests in Cox proportional hazards models that included both baseline
            behavioral risk score (low, medium, or high) and race (white or nonwhite) demonstrated
            that VE significantl differed by behavioral risk level ( P p.0 41) and by race ( P p.0 0
            7). There was no evidence that the pattern of increasing VE with risk group was
            restricted to white or nonwhite volunteers, although power was low for assessment of
            treatment by race by risk interaction. The rerandomization procedure used to account for
            multiple testing in the 15 subgroups yielded P p.102, indicating a nonsignificant trend
            toward VE being different from 0 in 1 subgroups. Subgroup-specifi estimates of VE values
            with unadjusted 95% CIs and unadjusted and multiplicity adjusted P values are shown in
            table 3 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Both overall and in subgroups, multivariateanalysesinwhich either baseline covariates
            (sex, age, race, education level, geographic region, and risk behavior) or risk behavior
            over time was controlled for yielded covariate adjusted point and CI estimates of VE
            that were nearly identical to the unadjustedvalues (data not shown). Because only 6
            female volunteers acquired HIV-1 infection (4 black placebo recipients, 1 black
            vaccinee, and 1 Hispanic vaccinee), the above analyses of risk and race were repeated
            for men only; these analyses gave subgroupspecifi point estimates of VE and 95% CIs that
            were very similar to those obtained for both sexes combined. Because site of enrollment
            could confound estimates of VE, the analyses of VE were repeated with stratificatio by
            site. Generally, the results were very similar to the unstratifie results, except that
            estimates of VE decreased appreciably for the high behavioral risk subgroup (from 43% to
            19%).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Antibody Responses, Viral Sequencing, and Selective VE </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> All vaccinees assessed demonstrated HIV-1–specifi antibody responses [ ]. The vaccinees
            with higher peak levels of MN CD4–blocking, GNE8 CD4–blocking, or MN-neutralizing
            responses tended to have a lower rate of HIV-1 infection; these analyses are described
            and interpreted elsewhere [ ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The subtype B consensus sequence at the tip of the gp120 V3 domain, GPGRAF, which is
            present in both the MN and GNE8 vaccine antigens, was selected as the main region for
            detection of the effects of vaccine on virus population dynamics. Overall, there was no
            evidence of selective efficac on the basis of virus type. VE was estimated as 0% for
            viruses with 658 • JID 2005:191 (1 March) • rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group the GPGRAF
            sequence and 19% forviruseswithouttheGPGRAF sequence. In exploratory analyses, there was
            no evidence of differential efficac in any behavioral risk group between viruses with
            and those without the GPGRAF sequence. A nonsignifican trend was found for nonwhite
            volunteers, with an estimated VE of 73% (95% CI, 35% to 88%) for viruses with the GPGRAF
            sequence versus an estimated VE of 24% (95% CI, 59% to 63%) for viruses without the
            GPGRAF sequence ( P p.077). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> DISCUSSION </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> VAX004 was the firs phase 3 placebo-controlled efficac study of a vaccine to prevent
            HIV-1 infection [ ]. More than 5000 MSMs were enrolled, in whom the predominant site of
            infection was rectal. A relatively small number (308) of women at high risk for
            heterosexual transmission of HIV-1 were also enrolled. Because only 6 women acquired
            HIV-1 infection during follow-up, compared with 362 men, the study had very little power
            to assess VE in women. Every analysis of VE gave very similar results, regardless of
            whether both sexes or only men were evaluated. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Despite producing neutralizing and CD4-blocking antibody responses in all vaccinees
            assessed for immunogenicity [ ], the vaccine was ineffective in preventing HIV-1
            infection or in modifying postinfection markers of disease progression. This failure to
            protect likely derived from the lack of induction of antibodies capable of neutralizing
            genetically diverse primary HIV-1 isolates. Additionally, results from a phase 3 trial
            of a B/E rgp120 vaccine in Thailand showed no evidence of efficac, although the presumed
            mode of transmission in that study differed in that it was intravenous [ ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The rgp120 vaccine used in the present trial appeared to be safe; other than the rate
            of local reactogenicity, no other rates of adverse events were meaningfully increased in
            vaccinees versus placebo recipients. Furthermore, although it has been hypothesized that
            a more rapid disease progression due to “immune enhancement” is a possible risk for
            vaccinees [ , ], pre-ART viral loads and time to initiation of ART in the 368 volunteers
            who acquired HIV-1 infection provided no evidence of such a phenomenon. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The finding of the present study should reassure those who have been worried about the
            difficultie of conducting a phase 3 trial of an HIV-1 vaccine [ – ]—concerns with regard
            to recruiting, retaining, and reducing the pool of participants for future trials [ ];
            the potential for increased high-risk behavior by participants [ ]; and conducting such
            a trial ethically should be allayed [ ]. Also, this trial was conducted with the
            understanding that it is possible to inflic social harm on individuals who volunteer for
            HIV-vaccine trials. To minimize the risk of social harm, advice and training were given
            to staff and volunteers; in the end, minimal harm occurred [ ]. In addition, at least
            with this rgp120 vaccine, the chance of falsepositive serologic test results was minimal
            [ ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The finding with regard to risk-reduction counseling are less reassuring. Volunteers
            received comprehensive counseling by trained counselors at each study visit.
            Self-reported baseline risk behavior was a good predictor of subsequent infection, with
            infection rates at least 10-fold greater in the high-risk subgroup than in the low-risk
            subgroup, and overall self-reported risk behavior decreased over the course of the
            trial, although amphetamine use remained constant andunprotected receptive anal sex with
            an HIV-1–uninfected partner increased slightly. Despite the intensive counseling, the
            HIV-1 infection rate in the study population (which predominantly consisted of
            well-educated MSM) remained high and was steady during the 3 years of follow-up. In the
            absence of more-effectivecounseling, an effective HIV-1 vaccine, or other
            preventivemethods, the HIV-1 epidemic may continue unchecked and might, in some
            populations, approximate the current prevalence in sub- Saharan African adults.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> On the basis of interaction tests, VE estimates differed significantl by behavioral
            risk levelandrace.Thisresultmotivated exploratory subgroup analyses, which indicated
            possible effi cacy of the vaccine in certain subgroups, such as in the high behavioral
            risk subgroup (VE, 43%) andinnonwhitevolunteers (VE, 47%). However, the largest of these
            subgroups (the nonwhite volunteers) comprised only 17% of the study population, and the
            VE estimates for these 2 subgroups were not signifi cantly different from 0% after
            adjustment for the multiplicity of tests performed. Because there was evidence of effect
            modificatio and because the high behavioral risk and nonwhite subgroups each had a
            substantial number of infections (58 and 59, respectively), we here discuss 4 possible
            explanations for the finding of the exploratory subgroup analyses. There is precedent
            for the possibility that VE can differ by demographic factors: a similar recombinant
            glycoprotein vaccine has been reported to confer protection against genital herpes
            infection in women but not in men [ ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>The firs possible explanation is that the variation in VE estimates across subgroups
            could simply be attributable to statistical variation and, therefore, not reflec any
            underlying pattern in the true VE values. Second, a findin of VE within a subgroup could
            have been caused by greater exposure to HIV- 1 in the placebo arm because of possible
            imbalances in risky behavior or other host or virologic factors. However, our
            multivariate analyses, which took baseline attributes into account, suggested that
            imbalances between the 2 treatment arms (if there were any) did not account for observed
            VE, and risk behaviors over time were similar in the vaccine and placebo arms. Within
            the racial subgroups and within the behavioral low- and medium-risk subgroups, the rate
            of loss to followup was well balanced between the treatment arms, and the behavioral
            risk factors of volunteers who were lost to followup were well balanced. Within the high
            behavioral risk subgroup, placebo recipients had a higher dropout rate than did
            vaccinees. Also, for volunteers who dropped out in this subgroup, placebo recipients
            reported higher rates of unprotect- ed receptive anal sex with an HIV-1–uninfected
            partner (81%) than did vaccine recipients (43%). However, neither of these differences
            would explain the higher observed VE in the high behavioral risk subgroup.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Third, the findin of an apparently higher VE in the high behavioral risk subgroup could
            be the result of synergybetween the vaccine-induced immune response and a natural
            “priming” of the immune response by frequent exposure to HIV-1without infection, which
            has been proposed as a possible explanation for the phenomenon of highly exposed yet
            persistently uninfected sex workers [ – ]. Although there was no evidence of increased
            antibody responses in the high behavioral risk subgroup in the present study [ ], there
            may have been priming of cellular or humoral immune responses undetected by any of the
            assays carried out to date. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Fourth, biological differences, such as differences in immune responses or in genetic
            markers of resistance to HIV-1 infection [ – ], could explain why the vaccine appeared
            to be effective only in nonwhite volunteers. Differences in immune responses by sex and
            race have been reported [ , ]. In the present study, lower vaccine-induced antibody
            responses correlated with higher infection rates in all racial subgroups [ ]. Given that
            the overall VE estimate (6%) was near 0%, this result cannot be interpreted to imply
            that higher antibody responses were the cause of protection. Although it may be
            implausible to group Asian and black volunteers on the basis of genetic similarities,
            possible differences in exposure among racial subgroups to environmental factors or
            other infecting pathogens that could increase [ , ] or decrease susceptibility [ – ] to
            HIV-1 infection might help to account for differingVEestimates. For example, some
            studies have demonstrated that coinfection with GB virus C (GBV-C)—a flavivi us whose
            prevalence varies widely and appears to correlate with injection drug use, highrisk
            sexual activity, and certain geographic areas—has an apparently beneficia effect on
            progression of HIV-1 disease [ , ]. Proposed mechanisms include GBV-C–mediated reduction
            in expression of CCR5, induction of anti–HIV-1 cytokines, and enhancement of natural
            immunity[ ], anyofwhichcouldwork synergistically with a vaccine-induced antibody
            response. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> What conclusions can be drawn from the present phase 3 660 • JID 2005:191 (1 March) •
            rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group Downloaded from
            https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by Aerztegemeinschaft
            fuer Anaesthesie user </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Table 2. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Rates of immunization and study completion. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Dose no.a Dose 1 (month 0) 3391 (100) 1704 (100) 207 (100) 101 (100) 3598 (100) 1805
            (100) Dose 2 (month 1) 3344 (99) 1681 (99) 196 (95) 99 (98) 3540 (99) 1780 (99) Dose 3
            (month 6) 3202 (96) 1609 (96) 180 (87) 95 (94) 3382 (95) 1704 (96) Dose 4 (month 12)
            3051 (92) 1511 (92) 162 (79) 86 (87) 3213 (91) 1597 (91) Dose 5 (month 18) 2920 (89)
            1450 (89) 158 (77) 81 (82) 3078 (89) 1531 (88) Dose 6 (month 24) 2811 (87) 1379 (85) 147
            (72) 78 (79) 2958 (86) 1457 (85) Dose 7 (month 30) Received all scheduled immunizations
            b Final visit c 2720 (85) 2851 (84) 1323 (83) 1397 (82) 139 (68) 130 (63) 74 (76) 75
            (74) 2859 (84) 2981 (83) 1397 (83) 1472 (82) HIV-1 uninfected at final visit 2632 (78)
            1292 (76) 151 (73) 78 (77) 2783 (77) 1370 (76) HIV-1 infected before or at final visit
            239 (7) 123 (7) 2 (1) 4 (4) 241 (7) 127 (7) HIV-1 status unknown at final visit (lost to
            follow-up) 520 (15) 289 (17) 54 (26) 19 (19) 574 (16) 308 (17) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> NOTE. Data are no. (%) of volunteers. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>a Rates of immunization were calculated as the no. vaccinated during each visit divided
            by the no. who were uninfected (i.e., not diagnosed with HIV-1 infection before or
            during the indicated visit).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>b No. who received either all 7 doses or all doses before infection divided by the no.
            enrolled. Volunteers, once diagnosed with HIV-1 infection, were not scheduled for
            further vaccination visits.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>c The final visit was at month 36.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> study about the use rgp120 as a preventive vaccine? The lack of protection demonstrates
            that monomeric rgp120 is insufficientl immunogenic against fiel HIV-1 isolates and that
            improved or different rgp120 constructs, or different approaches, will be required. The
            trends toward efficac observed in the exploratory subgroup analyses, if real [ , ],
            raise the possibility that improved rgp120 immunogens can protect in certain
            circumstances; these trends also may provide clues that can inform the design of new
            HIV-1 vaccines, whether they are based on rgp120 or other approaches. Improvement of an
            rgp120vaccine might require additional, more representative, or modifie subtype envelope
            antigens (e.g., oligomeric vs. monomeric forms); newer adjuvants that enhance innate
            immunity or promote a Th1-biased response [ – ]; or combination with vaccines that
            promote cellular immunity to HIV-1 [ , , ]. A phase 3 trial using the latter approach
            was recently initiated in Thailand; in the trial, immunization with rgp120 is combined
            with a canarypox vector vaccine [ ]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>To further aid the interpretation of the results of VAX004 and to provide information
            that is helpful to the HIV-1 vaccine field additional analyses are either ongoing or
            planned, including analyses of the ability of participant serum to neutralize a spectrum
            of primary HIV-1 isolates, of T cell responses, of the occurrence of genetic
            polymorphisms of infecting strains, and of the prevalence of GBV-C coinfection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>THE RGP120 HIV VACCINE STUDY GROUP</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group Writing and Analysis Committee members. The following
            persons are members of the rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group Writing and Analysis
            Committee, which assumes responsibility for the content of this article: rgp120 HIV
            Vaccine Investigators are Neil M. Flynn (University of California at Davis Medical
            Center, Davis), Donald N. Forthal (University of California at Irvine College of
            Medicine, Irvine), Clayton D. Harro (Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health,
            Baltimore, MD), Franklyn N. Judson (Denver Department of Public Health, Denver, CO),
            Kenneth H. Mayer (Fenway Community Health Center, Boston, MA, and the Miriam Hospital,
            Providence, RI), and Michael F. Para (Ohio State University, Columbus); other members of
            thecommittee, affiliate with the Statistical Center for HIV/AIDS Research and
            Prevention, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center (Seattle, WA), are Peter B. Gilbert,
            Michael G. Hudgens (present affiliation School of Public Health, University of North
            Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill), Barbara J. Metch, and Steven G. Self; and other
            members of the committee, affiliate with VaxGen (Brisbane, CA), are Phillip W. Berman
            (present affiliation Global Solutions for Infectious Diseases, Brisbane, CA), Donald P.
            Francis (present affiliation Global Solutions for Infectious Diseases,
            Brisbane,CA),MarcGurwith, William L. Heyward (present affiliation Quattro Clinical
            Research, Oakland, CA), David V. Jobes, Michael L. Peterson, Vladimir Popovic (present
            affiliation Janssen Ortho, Toronto, Ontario, Canada), and Faruk M. Sinangil. Potential
            conflict of interest are as follows: Marc Gurwith, David V. Jobes, Michael L. Peterson,
            and Faruk M. Sinangil are employees of VaxGen; Phillip W. Berman, Donald P. Francis,
            William L. Heyward, and Vladimir Popovic are former employees of VaxGen; Downloaded from
            https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by Aerztegemeinschaft
            fuer Anaesthesie user </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Rate of HIV-1 infection P Category, parameter Vaccine Placebo VE (95% CI) Unadjusted a
            Adjusted b </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> NOTE. Data are no. of infected volunteers/no. of total volunteers (%) in category. CI,
            confidence interval. a Two-sided values from log-rank P a test. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>b Two-sided values from nonparametric bootstrap procedure that conducted with 10,000
            resampled data Wald statistics</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> P a was sets; from univariate Cox proportional hazards models were used [25]. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>c All 5 infected black women were from 1 site. gp120 sequence analysis of the 5 isolates
            from these women indicated that 3 of the</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>isolates (all from placebo recipients) were clustered together in a phylogenetic tree,
            which suggests at least a phylogenetic linkage.The</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>3 phylogenetically linked infections occurred during 3 separate calendar years.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>d One volunteer was missing education data.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>e Risk score was defined as the total no. of risk factors reported from the following:
            (1) unprotected receptive anal sex with an HIV-</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>1–infected male partner; (2) unprotected insertive anal sex with an HIV-1–infected male
            partner; (3) unprotected receptive anal sex with</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>an HIV-1–uninfected male partner; (4) 5 acts of unprotected receptive anal sex with a
            male partner of unknown HIV-1 status; (5) 10</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>sex partners; (6) anal herpes; (7) hepatitis A; (8) use of poppers; and (9) use of
            amphetamines. Behavioral risk scores ranged from 0 to</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>7; 0 was categorized as low, 1–3 was categorized as medium, and 4–7 was categorized as
            high.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>and Peter B. Gilbert, Michael G. Hudgens, Barbara J. Metch, and Steven G. Self have
            received consulting fees from VaxGen in the past.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group members. Thefollowing persons are members of the rgp120
            HIV Vaccine Study Group: Angeli Adamczyk (ACRC/Arizona Clinical Research Center, Tucson,
            AZ); Robert L. Baker (Community Medical Research Institute, Indianapolis, IN); David
            Brand (North Texas Center for AIDS and Clinical Research, Dallas); Stephen J. Brown
            (AIDS Research Alliance, West Hollywood, CA); Susan Buchbinder (San Francisco Department
            of Public Health, San Francisco, CA); Brian P. Buggy (Wisconsin AIDS Research
            Consortium, Milwaukee); Jerry Cade (Wellness Center, Las Vegas, NV); Michael C. Caldwell
            (Dutchess County Department of Health, Poughkeepsie, NY); Connie Celum (University of
            Washington/Seattle HPTU, Seattle); Catherine Creticos (Howard Brown Health Center,
            Chicago, IL); Roel A. Coutinho and Karen Lindenburg (GG&amp;GD/Municipal Health Service
            Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands); Patrick Daly (Nelson- Tebedo Health Resource
            Center, Dallas, TX); Edwin DeJesus (IDC Research Initiative, Altamonte Springs, FL);
            Richard Di- Carlo (Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center, New Orleans);
            Martin Fenstersheib (Crane Center, San Jose, CA); Neil Flynn (University of California
            at Davis Medical Center, 662 • JID 2005:191 (1 March) • rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group
            Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by
            Aerztegemeinschaft fuer Anaesthesie user </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by
            Aerztegemeinschaft fuer Anaesthesie user</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Figure </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Infectious Diseases, Sacramento); Donald Forthal (University of California at Irvine
            College of Medicine, Orange); Barbara Gripshover (University Hospitals of
            Cleveland,Cleveland,OH); Geoffrey J. Gorse and Robert Belshe (Saint Louis University,
            St. Louis, MO); Howard Grossman (Polaris Medical Group, New York, NY); Clayton D. Harro
            (Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD); Keith Henry (Hennepin
            County Medical Center, Minneapolis, MN); Ross G. Hewitt (Erie County Medical Center,
            Buffalo, NY); Robert Hogg (BC Centre for Excellence in HIV/AIDS, Vancouver,British
            Columbia, Canada); Jeffrey M. Jacobson (Beth Israel Medical Center, New York, NY);
            Joseph Jemsek (Jemsek Clinic, Huntersville, NC); Franklyn Judson (Denver Department of
            Public Health, Denver, CO); James O. Kahn (University of California at San Francisco
            Positive Health Program, San Francisco); Michael C. Keefer (University of Rochester,
            Rochester, NY); Harold Kessler (Chicago Center for Clinical Research, Chicago, IL);
            Beryl Koblin (New York Blood Center, New York, NY); Jay Kostman (Philadelphia
            Fight,Philadelphia,PA);Michelle Lally (The Miriam Hospital, Providence, RI); Ken Logue
            (CascAids Research, Toronto, Ontario, Canada); Michael Marmor (New York University
            School of Medicine, New York, NY); Kenneth Mayer (Fenway Community Health, Boston, MA);
            David McKinsey (Antibiotic Research Associates, Kansas City, MO); Barry M. Miskin (Palm
            Beach Research Center, West Palm Beach, FL); Javier O. Morales (Clinical Research Puerto
            Rico, San Juan, Puerto Rico); Mark J. Mulligan (University of Alabama at Birmingham,
            Birmingham); RobertA.Myers(Body Positive, Phoenix, AZ); Richard Novak (University of
            Illinois at Chicago, Chicago); Michael Para (Ohio State University,Columbus); Peter
            Piliero (Albany Medical College, Albany, NY); Ronald Poblete (North Jersey Community
            Research Initiative, Newark, NJ); Frank Rhame (Abbott Northwestern Hospital,
            Minneapolis, MN); Sharon Riddler (University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA); Ralph W.
            Richter (Clinical PharmaceuticalTrials, Tulsa, OK); James H. Sampson (Research and
            Education Group, Portland, OR); Michael Sands (University of Florida at Jacksonville,
            Jacksonville); Steven Santiago (Care Resource, Coral Gables, FL); Cecilia Shikuma
            (HawaiiAIDSClinicalTrials Unit, Honolulu); Michael S. Somero (Offic of Michael S.
            Somero, MD, Palm Springs, CA); Elaine Thomas (University of New Mexico Health Sciences
            Center, Albuquerque); Melanie Thompson (AIDS Research Consortium of Atlanta, Atlanta,
            GA); Stephen K. Tyring (University of Texas Medical Branch Center for Clinical Studies,
            Houston); Jean Vincelette (Hoˆpital Saint-Luc du CHUM, Montreal, Quebec, Canada); Peter
            S. Vrooman, Jr. (ALL TRIALS Clinical Research, Winston–Salem, NC); and Bienvenido G.
            Yangco (Infectious Disease Research Institute, Tampa, FL).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Acknowledgments</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>We thank the VAX004 trial participants, for their contribution and dedication to this
            trial; the study coordinators, in recognition of their hard work and commitment to
            quality; and the following individuals, for their significan contributions to the trial
            and its interpretation: Dale Hu, Ann Wang, Alan Greenberg, Elizabeth Li, Tim Mastro, Jim
            Young, Brad Bartholow, Adrian Hirsh, Marta Ackers, Michael Longhi, Eleanor McLellan,
            Gina Rossen, Marlene Chernow, John Curd, Nzeera Virani-Ketter, John Jermano, Patti
            Cronin, Mike Busch, Nathan Winslow, Chip Sheppard, Valerie Smith, Karin Orelind, Lynne
            Deans, Marc Drucker, Jim Key, Mark McLaughlin, Lisa Brooks, Donna Eastman, Mike Lock,
            Lavon Riddle, Andrew McCluskey, and Tina Ippolito.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>References</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 1. Esparza J , Bhamarapravati N. Accelerating the development and future availability
            of HIV-1 vaccines: why, when, where, and how ? Lancet 2000 ; 355 : 2061–6 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 2. Spearman P. HIV vaccine development: lessons from the past and promise for the
            future . Curr HIV Res 2003 ; 1 : 101–20 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 3. Nathanson N , Mathieson BJ. Biological considerations in the development of a human
            immunodeficienc virus vaccine . J Infect Dis 2000 ; 182 : 579–89 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 4. Fowke KR , Nagelkerke NJD , Kimani J , et al. Resistance to HIV-1 infection among
            persistently seronegative prostitutes in Nairobi, Kenya . Lancet 1996 ; 348 : 1347–51 .
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 5. Sharon A , Stranford SA , Skurnick J , et al. Lack of infection in HIVexposed
            individuals is associated with a strong CD8+ cell noncytotoxic anti-HIV response . Proc
            Natl Acad Sci USA 1999 ; 96 : 1030–5 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 6. Jennes W , Vuylsteke B , Borget M-Y , et al. HIV-specifi T helper responses and
            frequency of exposure among HIV-exposed seronegative female sex workers in Abidjan,
            Coˆte d’Ivoire . J Infect Dis 2003 ; 187 : 1053–63 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 7. Quillent C , Oberlin E , Braun J , et al. HIV-1–resistance phenotype conferred by
            combination of two separate inherited mutationsofCCR5 gene . Lancet 1998 ; 351 : 14–8 .
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 8. Samson M , Libert F , Doranz BJ , et al. Resistance to HIV-1 infection in Caucasian
            individuals bearing mutant alleles of the CCR-5 chemokine receptor gene . Nature 1996 ;
            382 : 722–5 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 9. Liu R , Paxton WA , Choe S , et al. Homozygous defect in HIV-1 coreceptor accounts
            for resistance of some multiply-exposed individuals to HIV-1 infection . Cell 1996 ; 86
            : 367–77 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 10. Zinkernagel RM. Are HIV-specifi CTL responses salutary or pathogenic ? Curr Opin
            Immunol 1995 ; 7 : 462–70 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 11. McMichael AJ , Hanke T. HIV vaccines 1983–2003 . Nat Med 2003 ; 9 : 874–80 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 12. Berman PW , Gregory TJ , Riddle L , et al. Protection of chimpanzeesfrom infection
            by HIV-1 after vaccination with recombinant glycoprotein gp120 but not gp160 . Nature
            1990 ; 345 : 622–5 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 13. el Amad Z , Murthy KK , Higgins K , et al. Resistance of chimpanzees immunized with
            recombinant gp120SF2 to challenge byHIV-1SF2 . AIDS 1995 ; 9 : 1313–22 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 14. Berman PW , Murthy KK , Wrin T , et al. Protection of MN-rgp120– immunized
            chimpanzees from heterologous infection with a primary isolate of human immunodeficienc
            virus type 1 . J Infect Dis 1996 ; 173 : 52–9 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 15. Belshe RB , Graham BS , Keefer MC , et al. Neutralizing antibodies to HIV-1 in
            seronegative volunteers immunized with recombinant gp120 from the MN strain of HIV-1.
            NIAID AIDS Vaccine Clinical Trials Network . JAMA 1994 ; 272 : 475–80 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 16. Pitisuttithum P , Berman PW , Phonrat B , et al. Phase I/II study of a candidate
            vaccine designed against the B and E subtypes of HIV-1 . J Acquir Immune Defi Syndr 2004
            ; 37 : 1160–5 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 17. Francis DP , Gregory T , McElrath MJ , et al. Advancing AIDSVAX to phase 3: safety,
            immunogenicity, and plans for phase 3 . AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses 1998 ; 14 (Suppl 3):S
            325–31 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 18. Berman PW , Huang W , Riddle L , et al. Development of bivalent (B/ E) vaccines
            able to neutralize CCR5-dependent viruses fromtheUnited States and Thailand . Virology
            1999 ; 265 : 1–9 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 19. Harro CD , Judson FN , Gorse GJ , et al. Recruitment and baseline epidemiologic
            profil of participants in the firs phase 3 HIV vaccine efficac trial . J Acquir Immune
            Defi Syndr 2004 ; 37 : 1385–92 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 20. Francis DP , Heyward WL , Popovic V , et al. Candidate HIV/AIDS vaccines: lessons
            learned from the world’s firs phase III efficac trials . AIDS 2003 ; 17 : 147–56 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 21. Peterson ML , Good JW , Zaharias EM , et al. Development of a novel assay to
            measure antigen-specifi immune responses to multivalent vaccines for HIV-1 [abstract
            769] . In: Program and abstracts of the 7th Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic
            Infections (San Francisco) . Alexandria, VA: Foundation for Retrovirology and Human
            Health , 2000 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 22. Gilbert PB , Peterson ML , Follmann D , et al. Correlation between immunologic
            responses to a recombinant glycoprotein 120 vaccine and incidence of HIV-1 infection in
            a phase 3 HIV-1 preventive vaccine trial . J Infect Dis 2005 : 191 : 666-77 (in this
            issue). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 23. Allison PD. Survival analysis using the SAS system: a practical guide . Cary, NC:
            SAS Institute , 1995 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 24. Bristol DR. p-value adjustments for subgroup analyses . J Biopharm Stat 1997 ; 7 :
            313–21 /323–31. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 25. Pollard KS , van der Laan MJ. Choice of a null distribution in resampling-based
            multiple testing . J Statist Plann Inference 2004 ; 125 : 85–100 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 26. Lunn M , McNeil D. Applying Cox regression to competing risks . Biometrics 1995 ;
            51 : 524–32 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 27. Choopanya K , Tappero JW , Pitisuttithum P , et al. Preliminary results of a phase
            III HIV vaccine efficac trial among injecting drug users in Thailand [abstract
            ThOrA1427] . In: Program and abstracts of the XV International AIDS Conference 2004
            (Bangkok, Thailand). Bangkok, Thailand: Clung Wicha Press , 2004 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 28. Morens DM. Antibody-dependent enhancement of infection and the pathogenesis of
            viral disease . Clin Infect Dis 1994 ; 19 : 500–12 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 29. Burke DS. Human HIV vaccine trials: does antibody-dependent enhancement pose a
            genuine risk ? Perspect Biol Med 1992 ; 35 : 511–30 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 30. King RT. FDA allows large-scale trial of AIDS vaccine . Wall Street Journal. 3 June
            1998 : 1 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 31. Chesney MA , Chambers D , Kahn JO. Risk behavior for HIV infection in participants
            in preventive HIV vaccine trials: a cautionary note . J Acquir Immune Defi Syndr Hum
            Retrovirol 1997 ; 16 : 266–71 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 32. Bloom BR. The highest attainable standard: ethical issues in AIDS vaccines .
            Science 1998 ; 279 : 186–8 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 33. Ackers M-L , Parekh B , Evans TG , et al. Human immunodeficienc virus (HIV)
            seropositivity among uninfected HIV vaccine recipients . J Infect Dis 2003 ; 187 :
            879–86 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 34. Stanberry LR , Spruance SL , Cunningham AL , et al. Glycoprotein-d– adjuvant
            vaccine to prevent genital herpes . N Engl J Med 2002 ; 347 : 1652–61 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 35. Whitacre CC , Reingold SC , O’Looney PA , et al. Biomedicine: a gender gap in
            autoimmunity . Science 1999 ; 283 : 1277–8 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 36. Sugimoto K , Stadanlick J , Ikeda F , et al. Influenc of ethnicity in the outcome
            of hepatitis C virus infection and cellular immune response . Hepatology 2003 ; 37 :
            590–9 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 37. Schacker T , Zeh J , Hu HL , Hill J , Corey L. Frequency of symptomatic and
            asymptomatic HSV-2 reactivations among HIV-infected men . J Infect Dis 1998 ; 178 :
            1616–22 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 38. Wald A , Link K. Risk of human immunodeficienc virus infection in herpes simplex
            virus type 2–seropositive persons: a meta-analysis . J Infect Dis 2002 ; 185 : 45–52 .
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 39. Xiang J , Wunschmann S , Diekema DJ , et al. Effect of coinfection with GB virus C
            on survival among patients with HIV infection . N Engl J Med 2001 ; 345 : 707–14 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 40. George SL , Wunschmann S , McCoy J , Xiang J , Stapleton JT. Interactions between
            GB virus type C and HIV . Curr Infect Dis Rep 2002 ; 4 : 550–8 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 41. Williams CF , Klinzman D , Yamashita TE , et al. Persistent GB virus C infection
            and survival in HIV-infected men . N Engl J Med 2004 ; 350 : 981–90 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 42. Pomerantz RJ , Nunnari G. HIV and GB virus C: can two viruses be better than one ?
            N Engl J Med 2004 ; 350 : 963–5 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 43. Dawson GJ , Schlauder GG , Pilot-Matias TJ , et al. Prevalence studies of GB
            virus–C infection using reverse transcriptase–polymerase chain reaction . J Med Virol
            1996 ; 50 : 97–103 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 44. Assmann SF , Pocock SJ , Enos LE , et al. Subgroup analysis and other (mis)uses of
            baseline data in clinical trials . Lancet 2000 ; 355 : 1064–9 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 45. Klinman DM , Kamstrup S , Verthelyi D , et al. Activation of the innate immune
            system by CpG oligodeoxynucleotides: immunoprotectiveactivity and safety . Springer
            Semin Immunopathol 2000 ; 22 : 173–83 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 46. Moore A , McCarthy L , Mills KH. The adjuvant combination monophosphoryl lipid A
            and QS21 switches T cell responses induced with a soluble recombinant HIV protein from
            Th2 to Th1 . Vaccine 1999 ; 17 : 2517–27 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 47. Frank FM , Petray PB , Cazorla SI , Munoz MC , Corral RS , Malchiodi EL. Use of a
            purifie Trypanosoma cruzi antigen and CpG oligodeoxynucleotides for immunoprotection
            against a lethal challenge with trypomastigotes . Vaccine 2003 ; 22 : 77–86 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 48. Verthelyi D , Kenney RT , Seder RA , Gam AA , Friedag B , Klinman DM. CpG
            oligodeoxynucleotides as vaccine adjuvants in primates . J Immunol 2002 ; 168 : 1659–63
            . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 49. Nabel GJ. Challenges and opportunities of development of an AIDS vaccine . Nature
            2001 ; 410 : 1002–6 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 50. Schultz AM , Bradac JA. The HIV vaccine pipeline, from preclinical to phase III .
            AIDS 2001 ; 15 (Suppl 5):S 147–58 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 51. Nitayaphan S , Pitisuttithum P , de Souza M , et al. Safety and immunogenicity of
            live recombinant ALVAC-HIV (vCP 1521 ) priming with AIDSVAX B/E gp120 boosting in Thai
            HIV-negative adults (abstract WePeB6049). In: Program and abstracts of the XIV
            International AIDS Conference 2002 (Barcelona, Spain) . Barcelona, Spain: Prous Science
            , 2002 . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by
            Aerztegemeinschaft fuer Anaesthesie user</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
