<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.5281/zenodo.1145711</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Placebo-Controlled Phase 3 Trial of a Recombinant Glycoprotein 120 Vaccine to Prevent HIV-1 Infection</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2005</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <p>Placebo-Controlled Phase 3 Trial of a Recombinant</p>
      <p>Glycoprotein 120 Vaccine to Prevent HIV-1 Infection</p>
      <p>The rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Groupa</p>
      <p>(See the article by Gilbert et al., on pages 666–77, and the editorial commentary by Graham and Mascola, on pages 647–9.)</p>
      <p>Background.
A vaccine is needed to prevent human immunodeficienc virus type 1 (HIV-1) infection.
</p>
      <p>Methods.
A double-blind, randomized trial of a recombinant HIV-1 envelope glycoprotein subunit (rgp120) vaccine was conducted among men who have sex with men and among women at high risk for heterosexual transmission of HIV-1. Volunteers received 7 injections of either vaccine or placebo (ratio, 2:1) over 30 months. The primary end point was HIV-1 seroconversion over 36 months.
</p>
      <p>Results.
A total of 5403 volunteers (5095 men and 308 women) were evaluated. The vaccine did not prevent HIV-1 acquisition: infection rates were 6.7% in 3598 vaccinees and 7.0% in 1805 placebo recipients; vaccineefficac (VE) was estimated as 6% (95% confidenc interval, 17% to 24%). There were no significan differences in viral loads, rates of antiretroviral-therapy initiation, or the genetic characteristics of the infecting HIV-1 strains between treatment arms. Exploratory subgroup analyses showed nonsignifican trends toward efficac inpreventinginfection in the highest risk (VE, 43%; 
n
p 247) and nonwhite (VE, 47%; 
n
p 914) volunteers (
P
p.10, adjusted for multiple subgroup comparisons).
</p>
      <p>Conclusions.
There was no overall protective effect. The efficac trends in subgroups may provide clues for the development of effective immunization approaches.
</p>
      <p>
The creation of a vaccine to combat the global HIV-1 pandemic is an international public-health priority [
1
, 
2
]. Although infection leads to the development of an HIV-specifi immune response, the immune system is generally unable to effectively control replication of the virusortopreventimmunosuppression[
3
].Nonetheless, there is evidence of a protective immune response in certain special circumstances [
4
– 
9
]. There has also been considerable debate with regard to whether antibodymediated or cell-mediated responses are of primary importance in providing protective immunity [
3
, 
10
, 
11
].
</p>
      <p>
Protection of chimpanzees from intravenous and mucosal challenge with homologous and heterologous HIV-1 strains has been achieved with recombinant HIV- 1 envelope glycoprotein subunit (rgp120 and rgp160) vaccines [
12
– 
14
]. Phase 1 and 2 studies in uninfected humans have demonstrated that rgp120 is safe and able to generate antibody responses similar to those observed in the protected chimpanzees [
15
– 
17
].
</p>
      <p>
Two versions of an rgp120 vaccinecandidateadvanced to phase 3 studies in 1998–1999. The firs study was to evaluate a bivalent subtype B/B rgp120 vaccine in individuals in North AmericaandTheNetherlandswhowere at risk for infection via sexual exposure, whereas the second study was to evaluate a bivalent subtype B/E rgp120 vaccine in injection drug users in Thailand [
17
, 
18
]. Here, we report the resultsofthefirs ofthesestudies designed to evaluate whether an rgp120 vaccine canconfer protection against HIV-1 infection.
</p>
      <p>
Received 13 July 2004; accepted 15 November 2004; electronically published 27 January 
2005
.
</p>
      <p>Reprints or correspondence: Dr. Marc Gurwith, VaxGen, 1000 Marina Blvd., Ste. 200, Brisbane, CA 94005-1841 (mgurwith@vaxgen.com).</p>
      <p>Presented in part: 43rd Annual Interscience Meeting on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy, Chicago, 14–17 September 2003 (abstract H-1942); AIDS Vaccine 2003, New York, September 18–21 (abstract 148).</p>
      <p>Financial support: VaxGen; Centers for Disease Control and Prevention;National Institutes of Health; Science Applications International Corporation–Frederick (contract 23XS119).</p>
      <p>VOLUNTEERS, MATERIALS, AND METHODS</p>
      <p>Potential conflicts of interest: listed after the text with the members of the Writing and Analysis Committee.</p>
      <p>a Study group members and members of the Writing and Analysis Committee are listed after the text.</p>
      <p>Study Design</p>
      <p>
In this double-blind, randomized trial (known as “VAX004”), the volunteers were healthy, 18–62 years old, did not use intravenous drugs, and were either men who have sex with men (MSM) or women at high risk for heterosexual transmission of HIV-1. Men were eligible if they had had any anal intercourse during the preceding 12 months but were excluded if they had had a continuously monogamous sexual relationship with an HIV-1–uninfected male partner for 12 months. Women were eligible if they had had sexual intercourse with an HIV-1–infected male during the preceding 30 days or met at least 1 of the following criteria: had smoked crack cocaine during the preceding 12 months, had exchanged sex for drugs or money during the preceding 12 months, or had 5 male sex partners during the preceding 12 months. A computer-generated block randomization list, stratifie by the 61 sites that participated in the study, was designed to satisfy a 2:1 vaccinee to placebo recipient ratio. The eligibility criteria for and screening and enrollmentofthesevolunteershave been described in detail elsewhere [
19
]. Volunteers who met the eligibility criteria, which included a negative test for HIV-1, were to be enrolled within 30 days of screening. The actual screening interval ranged from 1 to 51 days (median, 15 days), and 99% were enrolled within the required 30 days.
</p>
      <p>The Journal of Infectious Diseases
2005; 
191
:654–65
</p>
      <p>2005 by the Infectious Diseases Society of America. All rights reserved. 0022-1899/2005/19105-0003$15.00</p>
      <p>Vaccine and Placebo Preparations</p>
      <p>The study vaccine contained 2 rgp120 HIV-1 envelope antigens (300 mg each of MN and GNE8 rgp120/HIV-1) (AIDSVAX B/ B; VaxGen) that had been derived from 2 different subtype B strains and that were adsorbed onto 600 mg of alum. GNE8 gp120 was cloned directly from peripheral-blood mononuclear cells and had the CCR5 phenotype; the GNE8 gp120 DNA sequence was deposited in GenBank (accession no. AY771703). Placebo consisted of alum only.</p>
      <p>Ethics Considerations</p>
      <p>
The present study was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and local institutional review board requirements and with approval from appropriate regulatory authorities. Written, informed consent was obtained from all volunteers. Before enrollment in the study, a thorough discussion of possible issues and risks associated with participation was conducted with each potential volunteer [
20
]. At each visit that included screening, trained counselors provided comprehensive education and pre- or post-HIV test and risk-reduction counseling, according to a comprehensive manual. Safety was monitored every 6 months by an independent data and safety monitoring board, which performed 1 interim efficac analysis 40 months after initiation of the study.
</p>
      <p>Vaccination and Study Assessments</p>
      <p>Vaccine or placebo was administered by intramuscularinjection at months 0, 1, 6, 12, 18, 24, and 30, with a fina follow-up visit at month 36. At each visit, adverse events and possible social harms were assessed; blood was obtained for assessment of HIV-1 status and immunogenicity. HIV-1 status was determined by detection of HIV-1 antibodies, using a standard HIV- 1 ELISA and confi matory immunoblot. The date of HIV-1 infection was estimated as follows: if HIV-1 RNA was undetectable in serum by a highly sensitive and specifi nucleicacid– based amplificatio test (NAT; Procleix HIV-1 Discriminatory Assay) at the date of the last seronegative test, then the date of HIV-1 infection was estimated as the midpoint of the dates of the last negative and firs positive ELISA/immunoblot test results. Otherwise, the infection date was estimated as the date of the earliest sample with detectable HIV-1 RNA. For volunteers who became infected during the study, plasma HIV-1 RNA load and CD4+ lymphocyte counts were assessed at!1 month and at months 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, and 24 afterdiagnosis of infection. Self-reported risk behaviors, including sexual activity and alcohol and drug use, and occurrence of sexually transmitted diseases were assessed by use of standard interviewer-administeredquestionnairesatbaselineandevery6months thereafter.</p>
      <p>Sequencing of Viral gp120</p>
      <p>HIV-1 RNA was isolated from the earliest postinfection plasma sample; full-length gp120 genes were amplifie and cloned. Three full-length gp120 sequences were recovered from each of 336 of 368 infected volunteers. With the exception of 1 subtype C virus, all isolates were subtype B.</p>
      <p>Immune Responses to the rgp120 Vaccine</p>
      <p>
A cytopathicity bioassay was used to determine 50% neutralizing titers for HIV-1MN infection of MT-4 cells. Binding antibodies were measured in 5 indirect ELISAs with anMN/GNE8 gp120 mixture and GNE8 V2, MN V2, GNE8 V3, and MN V3 peptides as the antigens. Two competitive ELISAs were used to measure antibody blocking of the binding of MN or GNE8 gp120 to recombinant soluble CD4 [
21
, 
22
]. The 8 assays were performed on samples obtained 2 weeks after the last immunization before HIV-1 infection for infected vaccinees and on samples obtained 2 weeks after each immunization for a 5% random sample of uninfected vaccinees.
</p>
      <p>Statistical Analysis</p>
      <p>Primary end-point analysis.
Vaccine efficac (VE) was define as (1 the relative risk of infection) 100 and was estimated by use of a Cox proportional hazards model, with time to HIV infection grouped over six 6-month intervals and with the Efron method used for correction for ties [
23
]. The sample size of the trial was selected as that which would provide, by a 2-sided log-rank test, 90% power to reject the null hypothesis—VE 30% if the true VE 60%. The Lan-DeMets implementation of the O’Brien-Fleming stopping boundary was used for 1 interim efficac analysis.
</p>
      <p>Secondary end-point analyses.
A generalized-estimatingequations model, which was based on all viral loads from samples obtained before initiation of antiretroviral therapy (ART), was used to estimate the mean difference between the vaccine and placebo arms in pre-ART viral load at each of the 9 postinfection visits. The time between detection of HIV infection and initiation of ART was compared between the 2 study arms by use of a log-rank test.
</p>
      <p>Exploratory analyses.
Tests for interaction in Cox proportional hazards models were used to evaluate whether VE differed by age (30 or 1 30 years), sex, education (less than a college degree or a college or graduate degree), race (white, black, Hispanic, Asian, and other and white vs. nonwhite), and baseline behavioral risk (low, medium, and high) [
24
]. The binary categories for age and education were determinedbefore the unblinded analysis was conducted by collapsing the 5 age categories and the 4 education categories into 2 binary categories with approximately equal sample size. Because there was limited power to evaluate the VE for particular nonwhite subgroups, race was also dichotomized as white and nonwhite, with the latter category including volunteers who designated their race as Hispanic. Volunteers were classifie as having low, medium, or high baseline behavioral risk on the basis of selfreported behaviors during the 6 months before enrollment that were predictive of HIV infection in men pooled over the treatment arms. Behaviors that were statistically significan (
P
!.05) in univariate Cox proportional hazards models were further assessed in multivariate models. Nine behaviors were identifie as independent predictors of HIV infection. A behavioral risk score for each volunteer was computed as the total number of these behaviors the person reported at baseline. The score was highly predictive of HIV infection, with anestimatedhazardratio of 1.66 (95% confidenc interval [CI], 1.56 to 1.77) per 1 riskfactor increase (
P
!.0 0 0 1). Behavioral risk scores ranged from 0 to 7; 0 was categorized as low, 1–3 was categorized as medium, and 4–7 was categorized as high. The baseline behavioral risk score was based on data for men only, because only 6 HIV-1 infections were observed among the 308 female volunteers and because the important risk factor of insertive anal sex does not apply to women. The results reported below on VE by behavioral risk category did not change appreciably when the risk model was based on data for both men and women.
</p>
      <p>
To account for multiple comparisons in subgroup analyses, a rerandomization procedure(with10,000permutations)wasused to testtheomnibusnullhypothesisthat 
VE
p 0 forallsubgroups versus the alternative hypothesis that 
VE
(0 for at least 1 subgroup. A bootstrap resampling procedure was used to compute adjusted 
P
values [
25
]. The estimate and 95% CI of the VE value within each subgroup was also computed by use of a Cox proportional hazards model. A Cox proportional hazards modelwas used to estimate VE values for particular HIV-1 genotypes and to test whether VE differed by viral genotype [
26
].
</p>
      <p>RESULTS</p>
      <p>Demographics, Risk Behavior, and Conduct of Study</p>
      <p>
Between June 1998 and October 1999, 7185 volunteers were screened for study eligibility criteria (

). Of these, 5417 eligible volunteers (5108 men and 309 women) were enrolled and were randomized to receive either vaccine or placebo. Of the 1768 volunteers not enrolled, 966 did not return after the initial screening visit, 328 met the study eligibility criteria but chose not to enroll, and 474 were excluded; the major reasons for exclusion were HIV-1 infection (161), serious underlying disease (148), and not meeting risk-behavior criteria (141). Despite being HIV-1 antibody negative at screening, 14 (11 vaccinees and 3 placebo recipients) volunteers had HIV-1infection detected at baseline (month 0) and were excluded from all efficac, but not safety, analyses. Of these, 12 were positive by NAT at month 0, although they were antibody negative; 1 was positive by NAT and intermediate by immunoblot; and 1 was positive by NAT and antibody positive. The vaccineandplacebo arms were similar in terms of demographiccharacteristics(
table 1
). The study population was predominantly male (94%),white (83%), young (median age, 36 years), and well educated (61% had a college or graduate degree).
</p>
      <p>
Self-reported risk behaviors, including sexual activity and alcohol and drug use, and rates of sexually transmitted diseases were similar in the vaccine and placebo arms at baseline and during follow-up (
table 1
and 

); they were also similar when stratifie by race (

) and by behavioral risk group (

). For the 9 behaviors reported at baseline that were predictive of HIV-1 infection, borderline statisticallysignifican differences between the vaccine and placebo arms were observed for unprotected receptive anal sex with an HIV-1–uninfected partner reported at month 6 (i.e., occurring during the interval between baseline and the month 6 visit) and unprotected receptive anal sex with an HIV-1–infected partner reported at month 18. Most behaviors, except amphetamine use and unprotected receptive anal sex with an HIV-1–uninfected partner, decreased over time, with the major decrease occurring between baseline and month 6.
</p>
      <p>
The rate of compliance with study vaccinations and the rate of loss to follow-up were well balanced between the vaccine and placebo arms (

and table 2), although, in the high behavioral risk subgroup, the dropout rate was higher in the placebo arm (24%) than in the vaccine arm (13%) (
P
p.0 52, Fisher’s exact test). There were no statistically significan differences in the 9 baseline risk behaviors between the vaccinees and placebo recipients who dropped out of the study.
</p>
      <p>
656 • 
JID 2005:191 (1 March)
• rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group 
Adverse Events</p>
      <p>The vaccine was generally well tolerated. The most common adverse events were mild or moderate reactogenicitysymptoms that occurred during the firs 3 days after a vaccination. Rates of local symptoms at the injection site were higher in the vaccinees; local edema, induration, or a subcutaneous nodule reported on at least 1 of the 14 days after any of the vaccinations was reported by 36%, 29%, and 21% of the vaccinees and by 17%, 15%, and 12% of the placebo recipients, respectively. There were no other major differences in the frequency and type of reported adverse events.</p>
      <p>Rates of Infection and VE</p>
      <p>
Overall, 368 (6.8%) volunteers became HIV-1 infected during the study, giving an annual incidence rate of 2.6% (2.7% in men and 0.8% in women). No reduction of infection in vaccine recipients was observed (VE, 6% [95% CI, 
17
to 
24
]; 
P
p.59) (
table 3
). Kaplan-Meier curves of the time-to-infection showed approximately constant rates of HIV-1 infection; the rates were similar in the vaccine and placebo arms during the 36 months of follow-up (figu e 5 
A
).
</p>
      <p>Postinfection Markers of Disease Progression</p>
      <p>
Among the volunteers who acquired HIV-1 infection, pre-ART viral loads over the course of the 9 visits were similar in the vaccine and placebo arms (
P
p.81). The mean difference (the mean of the vaccine arm minus the mean of the placebo arm) in pre-ART viral load at the visit 2 months after detection was 4.26 4.33 p 0.07 log10 (95% CI, 0.33 to 0.18 log10). The Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by Aerztegemeinschaft fuer Anaesthesie user
</p>
      <p>MenWomenAllVaccinePlaceboVaccinePlaceboVaccinePlaceboCategory, parameter
(
n
p 3391)

(
n
p 1704)

(
n
p 207)

(
n
p 101)

(
n
p 3598)

(
n
p 1805)
Age, yearsMedian363537383635Range18–6218–6218–5520–5518–6218–62RaceWhite (non-Hispanic)2930 (86)1468 (86)64 (31)27 (27)2994 (83)1495 (83)NonwhiteHispanic211 (6)114 (7)28 (14)14 (14)239 (7)128 (7)Black (non-Hispanic)121 (4)59 (3)112 (54)57 (56)233 (6)116 (6)Asian56 (2)21 (1)0056 (2)21 (1)Other Education level a73 (2)42 (3)3 (1)3 (3)76 (2)45 (2)Less than a college degree1238 (37)627 (37)171 (83)86 (85)1409 (39)713 (40)College or graduate degree Baseline behavioral risk score b2152 (63)1077 (63)36 (17)15 (15)2188 (61)1092 (60)Low risk1077 (32)538 (32)134 (65)71 (70)1211 (34)609 (34)Medium risk2156 (64)1077 (63)73 (35)30 (30)2229 (62)1107 (61)High risk158 (5)89 (5)00158 (4)89 (5)</p>
      <p>NOTE.
Data are no. (%) of volunteers, unless otherwise noted.
</p>
      <p>a One volunteer missing education data.</p>
      <p>was b Risk defined the total of risk factors reported from the following: (1) unprotected receptive anal with score was as no. sex an</p>
      <p>HIV-1–infected male partner; (2) unprotected insertive anal sex with an HIV-1–infected male partner; (3) unprotected receptive anal</p>
      <p>sex with an HIV-1–uninfected male partner; (4) 5 acts of unprotected receptive anal sex with a male partner of unknown HIV-1</p>
      <p>status; (5) 10 sex partners; (6) anal herpes; (7) hepatitis A; (8) use of poppers; and (9) use of amphetamines. Behavioral risk scores</p>
      <p>ranged from 0 to 7; 0 was categorized as low, 1–3 was categorized as medium, and 4–7 was categorized as high.</p>
      <p>
rate of initiation of ART was similar in the vaccine (99/225 [
44
%]) and placebo (53/122 [
43
%]) arms (
P
p.61, log-rank test). No significan effects of vaccination on any postinfection end points were observed.
</p>
      <p>Exploratory Subgroup Analyses</p>
      <p>
There were no significan interactions with treatment for sex, age, or education level, but interaction tests in Cox proportional hazards models that included both baseline behavioral risk score (low, medium, or high) and race (white or nonwhite) demonstrated that VE significantl differed by behavioral risk level (
P
p.0 41) and by race (
P
p.0 0 7). There was no evidence that the pattern of increasing VE with risk group was restricted to white or nonwhite volunteers, although power was low for assessment of treatment by race by risk interaction. The rerandomization procedure used to account for multiple testing in the 15 subgroups yielded 
P
p.102, indicating a nonsignificant trend toward VE being different from 0 in 1 subgroups. Subgroup-specifi estimates of VE values with unadjusted 95% CIs and unadjusted and multiplicity adjusted 
P
values are shown in 
table 3
.
</p>
      <p>Both overall and in subgroups, multivariateanalysesinwhich either baseline covariates (sex, age, race, education level, geographic region, and risk behavior) or risk behavior over time was controlled for yielded covariate adjusted point and CI estimates of VE that were nearly identical to the unadjustedvalues (data not shown). Because only 6 female volunteers acquired HIV-1 infection (4 black placebo recipients, 1 black vaccinee, and 1 Hispanic vaccinee), the above analyses of risk and race were repeated for men only; these analyses gave subgroupspecifi point estimates of VE and 95% CIs that were very similar to those obtained for both sexes combined. Because site of enrollment could confound estimates of VE, the analyses of VE were repeated with stratificatio by site. Generally, the results were very similar to the unstratifie results, except that estimates of VE decreased appreciably for the high behavioral risk subgroup (from 43% to 19%).</p>
      <p>Antibody Responses, Viral Sequencing, and Selective VE</p>
      <p>
All vaccinees assessed demonstrated HIV-1–specifi antibody responses [
22
]. The vaccinees with higher peak levels of MN CD4–blocking, GNE8 CD4–blocking, or MN-neutralizing responses tended to have a lower rate of HIV-1 infection; these analyses are described and interpreted elsewhere [
22
].
</p>
      <p>
The subtype B consensus sequence at the tip of the gp120 V3 domain, GPGRAF, which is present in both the MN and GNE8 vaccine antigens, was selected as the main region for detection of the effects of vaccine on virus population dynamics. Overall, there was no evidence of selective efficac on the basis of virus type. VE was estimated as 0% for viruses with 658 • 
JID 2005:191 (1 March)
• rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group the GPGRAF sequence and 19% forviruseswithouttheGPGRAF sequence. In exploratory analyses, there was no evidence of differential efficac in any behavioral risk group between viruses with and those without the GPGRAF sequence. A nonsignifican trend was found for nonwhite volunteers, with an estimated VE of 73% (95% CI, 35% to 88%) for viruses with the GPGRAF sequence versus an estimated VE of 24% (95% CI, 59% to 63%) for viruses without the GPGRAF sequence (
P
p.077).
</p>
      <p>DISCUSSION</p>
      <p>
VAX004 was the firs phase 3 placebo-controlled efficac study of a vaccine to prevent HIV-1 infection [
20
]. More than 5000 MSMs were enrolled, in whom the predominant site of infection was rectal. A relatively small number (308) of women at high risk for heterosexual transmission of HIV-1 were also enrolled. Because only 6 women acquired HIV-1 infection during follow-up, compared with 362 men, the study had very little power to assess VE in women. Every analysis of VE gave very similar results, regardless of whether both sexes or only men were evaluated.
</p>
      <p>
Despite producing neutralizing and CD4-blocking antibody responses in all vaccinees assessed for immunogenicity [
22
], the vaccine was ineffective in preventing HIV-1 infection or in modifying postinfection markers of disease progression. This failure to protect likely derived from the lack of induction of antibodies capable of neutralizing genetically diverse primary HIV-1 isolates. Additionally, results from a phase 3 trial of a B/E rgp120 vaccine in Thailand showed no evidence of efficac, although the presumed mode of transmission in that study differed in that it was intravenous [
27
].
</p>
      <p>
The rgp120 vaccine used in the present trial appeared to be safe; other than the rate of local reactogenicity, no other rates of adverse events were meaningfully increased in vaccinees versus placebo recipients. Furthermore, although it has been hypothesized that a more rapid disease progression due to “immune enhancement” is a possible risk for vaccinees [
28
, 
29
], pre-ART viral loads and time to initiation of ART in the 368 volunteers who acquired HIV-1 infection provided no evidence of such a phenomenon.
</p>
      <p>
The finding of the present study should reassure those who have been worried about the difficultie of conducting a phase 3 trial of an HIV-1 vaccine [
30
– 
32
]—concerns with regard to recruiting, retaining, and reducing the pool of participants for future trials [
30
]; the potential for increased high-risk behavior by participants [
31
]; and conducting such a trial ethically should be allayed [
32
]. Also, this trial was conducted with the understanding that it is possible to inflic social harm on individuals who volunteer for HIV-vaccine trials. To minimize the risk of social harm, advice and training were given to staff and volunteers; in the end, minimal harm occurred [
20
]. In addition, at least with this rgp120 vaccine, the chance of falsepositive serologic test results was minimal [
33
].
</p>
      <p>The finding with regard to risk-reduction counseling are less reassuring. Volunteers received comprehensive counseling by trained counselors at each study visit. Self-reported baseline risk behavior was a good predictor of subsequent infection, with infection rates at least 10-fold greater in the high-risk subgroup than in the low-risk subgroup, and overall self-reported risk behavior decreased over the course of the trial, although amphetamine use remained constant andunprotected receptive anal sex with an HIV-1–uninfected partner increased slightly. Despite the intensive counseling, the HIV-1 infection rate in the study population (which predominantly consisted of well-educated MSM) remained high and was steady during the 3 years of follow-up. In the absence of more-effectivecounseling, an effective HIV-1 vaccine, or other preventivemethods, the HIV-1 epidemic may continue unchecked and might, in some populations, approximate the current prevalence in sub- Saharan African adults.</p>
      <p>
On the basis of interaction tests, VE estimates differed significantl by behavioral risk levelandrace.Thisresultmotivated exploratory subgroup analyses, which indicated possible effi cacy of the vaccine in certain subgroups, such as in the high behavioral risk subgroup (VE, 43%) andinnonwhitevolunteers (VE, 47%). However, the largest of these subgroups (the nonwhite volunteers) comprised only 17% of the study population, and the VE estimates for these 2 subgroups were not signifi cantly different from 0% after adjustment for the multiplicity of tests performed. Because there was evidence of effect modificatio and because the high behavioral risk and nonwhite subgroups each had a substantial number of infections (58 and 59, respectively), we here discuss 4 possible explanations for the finding of the exploratory subgroup analyses. There is precedent for the possibility that VE can differ by demographic factors: a similar recombinant glycoprotein vaccine has been reported to confer protection against genital herpes infection in women but not in men [
34
].
</p>
      <p>The firs possible explanation is that the variation in VE estimates across subgroups could simply be attributable to statistical variation and, therefore, not reflec any underlying pattern in the true VE values. Second, a findin of VE within a subgroup could have been caused by greater exposure to HIV- 1 in the placebo arm because of possible imbalances in risky behavior or other host or virologic factors. However, our multivariate analyses, which took baseline attributes into account, suggested that imbalances between the 2 treatment arms (if there were any) did not account for observed VE, and risk behaviors over time were similar in the vaccine and placebo arms. Within the racial subgroups and within the behavioral low- and medium-risk subgroups, the rate of loss to followup was well balanced between the treatment arms, and the behavioral risk factors of volunteers who were lost to followup were well balanced. Within the high behavioral risk subgroup, placebo recipients had a higher dropout rate than did vaccinees. Also, for volunteers who dropped out in this subgroup, placebo recipients reported higher rates of unprotect- ed receptive anal sex with an HIV-1–uninfected partner (81%) than did vaccine recipients (43%). However, neither of these differences would explain the higher observed VE in the high behavioral risk subgroup.</p>
      <p>
Third, the findin of an apparently higher VE in the high behavioral risk subgroup could be the result of synergybetween the vaccine-induced immune response and a natural “priming” of the immune response by frequent exposure to HIV-1without infection, which has been proposed as a possible explanation for the phenomenon of highly exposed yet persistently uninfected sex workers [
4
– 
6
]. Although there was no evidence of increased antibody responses in the high behavioral risk subgroup in the present study [
22
], there may have been priming of cellular or humoral immune responses undetected by any of the assays carried out to date.
</p>
      <p>
Fourth, biological differences, such as differences in immune responses or in genetic markers of resistance to HIV-1 infection [
4
– 
9
], could explain why the vaccine appeared to be effective only in nonwhite volunteers. Differences in immune responses by sex and race have been reported [
35
, 
36
]. In the present study, lower vaccine-induced antibody responses correlated with higher infection rates in all racial subgroups [
22
]. Given that the overall VE estimate (6%) was near 0%, this result cannot be interpreted to imply that higher antibody responses were the cause of protection. Although it may be implausible to group Asian and black volunteers on the basis of genetic similarities, possible differences in exposure among racial subgroups to environmental factors or other infecting pathogens that could increase [
37
, 
38
] or decrease susceptibility [
39
– 
43
] to HIV-1 infection might help to account for differingVEestimates. For example, some studies have demonstrated that coinfection with GB virus C (GBV-C)—a flavivi us whose prevalence varies widely and appears to correlate with injection drug use, highrisk sexual activity, and certain geographic areas—has an apparently beneficia effect on progression of HIV-1 disease [
42
, 
43
]. Proposed mechanisms include GBV-C–mediated reduction in expression of CCR5, induction of anti–HIV-1 cytokines, and enhancement of natural immunity[
43
], anyofwhichcouldwork synergistically with a vaccine-induced antibody response.
</p>
      <p>
What conclusions can be drawn from the present phase 3 660 • 
JID 2005:191 (1 March)
• rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by Aerztegemeinschaft fuer Anaesthesie user
</p>
      <p>Table 2.</p>
      <p>Rates of immunization and study completion.</p>
      <p>MenWomenAllVaccinePlaceboVaccinePlaceboVaccinePlaceboCategory
(
n
p 3391)

(
n
p 1704)

(
n
p 207)

(
n
p 101)

(
n
p 3598)

(
n
p 1805)
</p>
      <p>Dose no.aDose 1 (month 0)3391 (100)1704 (100)207 (100)101 (100)3598 (100)1805 (100)Dose 2 (month 1)3344 (99)1681 (99)196 (95)99 (98)3540 (99)1780 (99)Dose 3 (month 6)3202 (96)1609 (96)180 (87)95 (94)3382 (95)1704 (96)Dose 4 (month 12)3051 (92)1511 (92)162 (79)86 (87)3213 (91)1597 (91)Dose 5 (month 18)2920 (89)1450 (89)158 (77)81 (82)3078 (89)1531 (88)Dose 6 (month 24)2811 (87)1379 (85)147 (72)78 (79)2958 (86)1457 (85)Dose 7 (month 30) Received all scheduled immunizations b Final visit c2720 (85) 2851 (84)1323 (83) 1397 (82)139 (68) 130 (63)74 (76) 75 (74)2859 (84) 2981 (83)1397 (83) 1472 (82)HIV-1 uninfected at final visit2632 (78)1292 (76)151 (73)78 (77)2783 (77)1370 (76)HIV-1 infected before or at final visit239 (7)123 (7)2 (1)4 (4)241 (7)127 (7)HIV-1 status unknown at final visit (lost to follow-up)520 (15)289 (17)54 (26)19 (19)574 (16)308 (17)</p>
      <p>NOTE.
Data are no. (%) of volunteers.
</p>
      <p>a Rates of immunization were calculated as the no. vaccinated during each visit divided by the no. who were uninfected (i.e., not diagnosed with HIV-1 infection before or during the indicated visit).</p>
      <p>b No. who received either all 7 doses or all doses before infection divided by the no. enrolled. Volunteers, once diagnosed with HIV-1 infection, were not scheduled for further vaccination visits.</p>
      <p>c The final visit was at month 36.</p>
      <p>
study about the use rgp120 as a preventive vaccine? The lack of protection demonstrates that monomeric rgp120 is insufficientl immunogenic against fiel HIV-1 isolates and that improved or different rgp120 constructs, or different approaches, will be required. The trends toward efficac observed in the exploratory subgroup analyses, if real [
24
, 
44
], raise the possibility that improved rgp120 immunogens can protect in certain circumstances; these trends also may provide clues that can inform the design of new HIV-1 vaccines, whether they are based on rgp120 or other approaches. Improvement of an rgp120vaccine might require additional, more representative, or modifie subtype envelope antigens (e.g., oligomeric vs. monomeric forms); newer adjuvants that enhance innate immunity or promote a Th1-biased response [
45
– 
48
]; or combination with vaccines that promote cellular immunity to HIV-1 [
3
, 
49
, 
50
]. A phase 3 trial using the latter approach was recently initiated in Thailand; in the trial, immunization with rgp120 is combined with a canarypox vector vaccine [
51
].
</p>
      <p>To further aid the interpretation of the results of VAX004 and to provide information that is helpful to the HIV-1 vaccine field additional analyses are either ongoing or planned, including analyses of the ability of participant serum to neutralize a spectrum of primary HIV-1 isolates, of T cell responses, of the occurrence of genetic polymorphisms of infecting strains, and of the prevalence of GBV-C coinfection.</p>
      <p>THE RGP120 HIV VACCINE STUDY GROUP</p>
      <p>rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group Writing and Analysis Committee members.
The following persons are members of the rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group Writing and Analysis Committee, which assumes responsibility for the content of this article: rgp120 HIV Vaccine Investigators are Neil M. Flynn (University of California at Davis Medical Center, Davis), Donald N. Forthal (University of California at Irvine College of Medicine, Irvine), Clayton D. Harro (Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD), Franklyn N. Judson (Denver Department of Public Health, Denver, CO), Kenneth H. Mayer (Fenway Community Health Center, Boston, MA, and the Miriam Hospital, Providence, RI), and Michael F. Para (Ohio State University, Columbus); other members of thecommittee, affiliate with the Statistical Center for HIV/AIDS Research and Prevention, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center (Seattle, WA), are Peter B. Gilbert, Michael G. Hudgens (present affiliation School of Public Health, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill), Barbara J. Metch, and Steven G. Self; and other members of the committee, affiliate with VaxGen (Brisbane, CA), are Phillip W. Berman (present affiliation Global Solutions for Infectious Diseases, Brisbane, CA), Donald P. Francis (present affiliation Global Solutions for Infectious Diseases, Brisbane,CA),MarcGurwith, William L. Heyward (present affiliation Quattro Clinical Research, Oakland, CA), David V. Jobes, Michael L. Peterson, Vladimir Popovic (present affiliation Janssen Ortho, Toronto, Ontario, Canada), and Faruk M. Sinangil. Potential conflict of interest are as follows: Marc Gurwith, David V. Jobes, Michael L. Peterson, and Faruk M. Sinangil are employees of VaxGen; Phillip W. Berman, Donald P. Francis, William L. Heyward, and Vladimir Popovic are former employees of VaxGen; Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by Aerztegemeinschaft fuer Anaesthesie user
</p>
      <p>Rate of HIV-1 infectionPCategory, parameterVaccinePlaceboVE (95% CI)Unadjusted aAdjusted b</p>
      <p>All volunteers241/3598 (6.7)127/1805 (7.0)6(17 to24).591.5Men239/3391 (7.0)123/1704 (7.2)4(20 to23).731.5Women2/207 (1.0)4/101 (4.0)74(42 to95).0 93.41RaceWhite (non-Hispanic)211/2994 (7.0)98/1495 (6.6)6(35 to16).601.5Men211/2930 (7.2)98/1468 (6.7)6(35 to16).61…Women0/64 (0)0/27 (0)………Hispanic14/239 (5.9)9/128 (7.0)15(96 to63).701.5Men13/211 (6.2)9/114 (7.9)20(88 to66).61…Women1/28 (3.6)0/14 (0)………Black (non-Hispanic)6/233 (2.6)9/116 (7.8)67(6to 88).0 28.24Men Women c5/121 (4.1) 1/112 (0.9)5/59 (8.5) 4/57 (7.0)54 87((61 to 19 to87) 98).21.0 33… …Asian (all men)3/56 (5.4)3/21 (14.3)66(70 to93).171.5Other7/76 (9.2)8/45 (17.8)50(39 to82).181.5Men7/73 (9.6)8/42 (19.0)51(34 to82).16…Nonwhite30/604 (5.0)29/310 (9.4)47(12 to 68).0 12.13Men28/461 (6.1)25/236 (10.6)43(3to 67).0 36…Women2/143 (1.4)4/74 (5.4)74(43 to95).10…Age30 years84/971 (8.7)43/504 (8.5)1(46 to30).951.51 30 years Education level d157/2627 (6.0)84/1301 (6.5)8(19 to30).511.5Less than a college degree95/1409 (6.7)52/713 (7.3)8(29 to34).631.5College or graduate degree Baseline behavioral risk score e146/2188 (6.7)75/1092 (6.9)4(27 to27).771.5Low risk32/1211 (2.6)11/609 (1.8)48(193 to 26).261.5Medium risk177/2229 (7.9)90/1107 (8.1)3(25 to25).821.5High risk32/158 (20.3)26/89 (29.2)43(4to 66).0 32.29</p>
      <p>NOTE.
Data are no. of infected volunteers/no. of total volunteers (%) in category. CI, confidence interval. a Two-sided values from log-rank 
P
a test.
</p>
      <p>b Two-sided values from nonparametric bootstrap procedure that conducted with 10,000 resampled data Wald statistics</p>
      <p>P
a was sets; from univariate Cox proportional hazards models were used [25].
</p>
      <p>c All 5 infected black women were from 1 site. gp120 sequence analysis of the 5 isolates from these women indicated that 3 of the</p>
      <p>isolates (all from placebo recipients) were clustered together in a phylogenetic tree, which suggests at least a phylogenetic linkage.The</p>
      <p>3 phylogenetically linked infections occurred during 3 separate calendar years.</p>
      <p>d One volunteer was missing education data.</p>
      <p>e Risk score was defined as the total no. of risk factors reported from the following: (1) unprotected receptive anal sex with an HIV-</p>
      <p>1–infected male partner; (2) unprotected insertive anal sex with an HIV-1–infected male partner; (3) unprotected receptive anal sex with</p>
      <p>an HIV-1–uninfected male partner; (4) 5 acts of unprotected receptive anal sex with a male partner of unknown HIV-1 status; (5) 10</p>
      <p>sex partners; (6) anal herpes; (7) hepatitis A; (8) use of poppers; and (9) use of amphetamines. Behavioral risk scores ranged from 0 to</p>
      <p>7; 0 was categorized as low, 1–3 was categorized as medium, and 4–7 was categorized as high.</p>
      <p>and Peter B. Gilbert, Michael G. Hudgens, Barbara J. Metch, and Steven G. Self have received consulting fees from VaxGen in the past.</p>
      <p>rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group members.
Thefollowing persons are members of the rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group: Angeli Adamczyk (ACRC/Arizona Clinical Research Center, Tucson, AZ); Robert L. Baker (Community Medical Research Institute, Indianapolis, IN); David Brand (North Texas Center for AIDS and Clinical Research, Dallas); Stephen J. Brown (AIDS Research Alliance, West Hollywood, CA); Susan Buchbinder (San Francisco Department of Public Health, San Francisco, CA); Brian P. Buggy (Wisconsin AIDS Research Consortium, Milwaukee); Jerry Cade (Wellness Center, Las Vegas, NV); Michael C. Caldwell (Dutchess County Department of Health, Poughkeepsie, NY); Connie Celum (University of Washington/Seattle HPTU, Seattle); Catherine Creticos (Howard Brown Health Center, Chicago, IL); Roel A. Coutinho and Karen Lindenburg (GG&amp;GD/Municipal Health Service Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands); Patrick Daly (Nelson- Tebedo Health Resource Center, Dallas, TX); Edwin DeJesus (IDC Research Initiative, Altamonte Springs, FL); Richard Di- Carlo (Louisiana State University Health Sciences Center, New Orleans); Martin Fenstersheib (Crane Center, San Jose, CA); Neil Flynn (University of California at Davis Medical Center, 662 • 
JID 2005:191 (1 March)
• rgp120 HIV Vaccine Study Group Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by Aerztegemeinschaft fuer Anaesthesie user
</p>
      <p>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by Aerztegemeinschaft fuer Anaesthesie user</p>
      <p>Figure</p>
      <p>Infectious Diseases, Sacramento); Donald Forthal (University of California at Irvine College of Medicine, Orange); Barbara Gripshover (University Hospitals of Cleveland,Cleveland,OH); Geoffrey J. Gorse and Robert Belshe (Saint Louis University, St. Louis, MO); Howard Grossman (Polaris Medical Group, New York, NY); Clayton D. Harro (Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD); Keith Henry (Hennepin County Medical Center, Minneapolis, MN); Ross G. Hewitt (Erie County Medical Center, Buffalo, NY); Robert Hogg (BC Centre for Excellence in HIV/AIDS, Vancouver,British Columbia, Canada); Jeffrey M. Jacobson (Beth Israel Medical Center, New York, NY); Joseph Jemsek (Jemsek Clinic, Huntersville, NC); Franklyn Judson (Denver Department of Public Health, Denver, CO); James O. Kahn (University of California at San Francisco Positive Health Program, San Francisco); Michael C. Keefer (University of Rochester, Rochester, NY); Harold Kessler (Chicago Center for Clinical Research, Chicago, IL); Beryl Koblin (New York Blood Center, New York, NY); Jay Kostman (Philadelphia Fight,Philadelphia,PA);Michelle Lally (The Miriam Hospital, Providence, RI); Ken Logue (CascAids Research, Toronto, Ontario, Canada); Michael Marmor (New York University School of Medicine, New York, NY); Kenneth Mayer (Fenway Community Health, Boston, MA); David McKinsey (Antibiotic Research Associates, Kansas City, MO); Barry M. Miskin (Palm Beach Research Center, West Palm Beach, FL); Javier O. Morales (Clinical Research Puerto Rico, San Juan, Puerto Rico); Mark J. Mulligan (University of Alabama at Birmingham, Birmingham); RobertA.Myers(Body Positive, Phoenix, AZ); Richard Novak (University of Illinois at Chicago, Chicago); Michael Para (Ohio State University,Columbus); Peter Piliero (Albany Medical College, Albany, NY); Ronald Poblete (North Jersey Community Research Initiative, Newark, NJ); Frank Rhame (Abbott Northwestern Hospital, Minneapolis, MN); Sharon Riddler (University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA); Ralph W. Richter (Clinical PharmaceuticalTrials, Tulsa, OK); James H. Sampson (Research and Education Group, Portland, OR); Michael Sands (University of Florida at Jacksonville, Jacksonville); Steven Santiago (Care Resource, Coral Gables, FL); Cecilia Shikuma (HawaiiAIDSClinicalTrials Unit, Honolulu); Michael S. Somero (Offic of Michael S. Somero, MD, Palm Springs, CA); Elaine Thomas (University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center, Albuquerque); Melanie Thompson (AIDS Research Consortium of Atlanta, Atlanta, GA); Stephen K. Tyring (University of Texas Medical Branch Center for Clinical Studies, Houston); Jean Vincelette (Hoˆpital Saint-Luc du CHUM, Montreal, Quebec, Canada); Peter S. Vrooman, Jr. (ALL TRIALS Clinical Research, Winston–Salem, NC); and Bienvenido G. Yangco (Infectious Disease Research Institute, Tampa, FL).</p>
      <p>Acknowledgments</p>
      <p>We thank the VAX004 trial participants, for their contribution and dedication to this trial; the study coordinators, in recognition of their hard work and commitment to quality; and the following individuals, for their significan contributions to the trial and its interpretation: Dale Hu, Ann Wang, Alan Greenberg, Elizabeth Li, Tim Mastro, Jim Young, Brad Bartholow, Adrian Hirsh, Marta Ackers, Michael Longhi, Eleanor McLellan, Gina Rossen, Marlene Chernow, John Curd, Nzeera Virani-Ketter, John Jermano, Patti Cronin, Mike Busch, Nathan Winslow, Chip Sheppard, Valerie Smith, Karin Orelind, Lynne Deans, Marc Drucker, Jim Key, Mark McLaughlin, Lisa Brooks, Donna Eastman, Mike Lock, Lavon Riddle, Andrew McCluskey, and Tina Ippolito.</p>
      <p>References</p>
      <p>
1. 
Esparza J
, 
Bhamarapravati N.Accelerating the development and future availability of HIV-1 vaccines: why, when, where, and how
? 
Lancet2000
; 
355
: 
2061–6
.
</p>
      <p>
2. 
Spearman P. HIVvaccine development: lessons from the past and promise for the future
. 
Curr HIV Res2003
; 
1
: 
101–20
.
</p>
      <p>
3. 
Nathanson N
, 
Mathieson BJ.Biological considerations in the development of a human immunodeficienc virus vaccine
. 
J Infect Dis2000
; 
182
: 
579–89
.
</p>
      <p>
4. 
Fowke KR
, 
Nagelkerke NJD
, 
Kimani J
, et al. 
Resistance to HIV-1 infection among persistently seronegative prostitutes in Nairobi, Kenya
. 
Lancet1996
; 
348
: 
1347–51
.
</p>
      <p>
5. 
Sharon A
, 
Stranford SA
, 
Skurnick J
, et al. 
Lack of infection in HIVexposed individuals is associated with a strong CD8+ cell noncytotoxic anti-HIV response
. 
Proc Natl Acad Sci USA1999
; 
96
: 
1030–5
.
</p>
      <p>
6. 
Jennes W
, 
Vuylsteke B
, 
Borget M-Y
, et al. 
HIV-specifi T helper responses and frequency of exposure among HIV-exposed seronegative female sex workers in Abidjan, Coˆte d’Ivoire
. 
J Infect Dis2003
; 
187
: 
1053–63
.
</p>
      <p>
7. 
Quillent C
, 
Oberlin E
, 
Braun J
, et al. 
HIV-1–resistance phenotype conferred by combination of two separate inherited mutationsofCCR5 gene
. 
Lancet1998
; 
351
: 
14–8
.
</p>
      <p>
8. 
Samson M
, 
Libert F
, 
Doranz BJ
, et al. 
Resistance to HIV-1 infection in Caucasian individuals bearing mutant alleles of the CCR-5 chemokine receptor gene
. 
Nature1996
; 
382
: 
722–5
.
</p>
      <p>
9. 
Liu R
, 
Paxton WA
, 
Choe S
, et al. 
Homozygous defect in HIV-1 coreceptor accounts for resistance of some multiply-exposed individuals to HIV-1 infection
. 
Cell1996
; 
86
: 
367–77
.
</p>
      <p>
10. 
Zinkernagel RM.Are HIV-specifi CTL responses salutary or pathogenic
? 
Curr Opin Immunol1995
; 
7
: 
462–70
.
</p>
      <p>
11. 
McMichael AJ
, 
Hanke T. HIVvaccines 1983–2003
. 
Nat Med2003
; 
9
: 
874–80
.
</p>
      <p>
12. 
Berman PW
, 
Gregory TJ
, 
Riddle L
, et al. 
Protection of chimpanzeesfrom infection by HIV-1 after vaccination with recombinant glycoprotein gp120 but not gp160
. 
Nature1990
; 
345
: 
622–5
.
</p>
      <p>
13. 
el Amad Z
, 
Murthy KK
, 
Higgins K
, et al. 
Resistance of chimpanzees immunized with recombinant gp120SF2 to challenge byHIV-1SF2
. 
AIDS1995
; 
9
: 
1313–22
.
</p>
      <p>
14. 
Berman PW
, 
Murthy KK
, 
Wrin T
, et al. 
Protection of MN-rgp120– immunized chimpanzees from heterologous infection with a primary isolate of human immunodeficienc virus type 1
. 
J Infect Dis1996
; 
173
: 
52–9
.
</p>
      <p>
15. 
Belshe RB
, 
Graham BS
, 
Keefer MC
, et al. 
Neutralizing antibodies to HIV-1 in seronegative volunteers immunized with recombinant gp120 from the MN strain of HIV-1. NIAID AIDS Vaccine Clinical Trials Network
. 
JAMA1994
; 
272
: 
475–80
.
</p>
      <p>
16. 
Pitisuttithum P
, 
Berman PW
, 
Phonrat B
, et al. 
Phase I/II study of a candidate vaccine designed against the B and E subtypes of HIV-1
. 
J Acquir Immune Defi Syndr2004
; 
37
: 
1160–5
.
</p>
      <p>
17. 
Francis DP
, 
Gregory T
, 
McElrath MJ
, et al. 
Advancing AIDSVAX to phase 3: safety, immunogenicity, and plans for phase 3
. 
AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses1998
; 
14
(Suppl 3):S 
325–31
.
</p>
      <p>
18. 
Berman PW
, 
Huang W
, 
Riddle L
, et al. 
Development of bivalent (B/ E) vaccines able to neutralize CCR5-dependent viruses fromtheUnited States and Thailand
. 
Virology1999
; 
265
: 
1–9
.
</p>
      <p>
19. 
Harro CD
, 
Judson FN
, 
Gorse GJ
, et al. 
Recruitment and baseline epidemiologic profil of participants in the firs phase 3 HIV vaccine efficac trial
. 
J Acquir Immune Defi Syndr2004
; 
37
: 
1385–92
.
</p>
      <p>
20. 
Francis DP
, 
Heyward WL
, 
Popovic V
, et al. 
Candidate HIV/AIDS vaccines: lessons learned from the world’s firs phase III efficac trials
. 
AIDS2003
; 
17
: 
147–56
.
</p>
      <p>
21. 
Peterson ML
, 
Good JW
, 
Zaharias EM
, et al. 
Development of a novel assay to measure antigen-specifi immune responses to multivalent vaccines for HIV-1 [abstract 769]
. In: 
Program and abstracts of the 7th Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections (San Francisco)
. 
Alexandria, VA: Foundation for Retrovirology and Human Health
, 
2000
.
</p>
      <p>
22. 
Gilbert PB
, 
Peterson ML
, 
Follmann D
, et al. 
Correlation between immunologic responses to a recombinant glycoprotein 120 vaccine and incidence of HIV-1 infection in a phase 3 HIV-1 preventive vaccine trial
. 
J Infect Dis2005
: 
191
: 
666-77
(in this issue).
</p>
      <p>
23. 
Allison PD.Survival analysis using the SAS system: a practical guide
. 
Cary, NC: SAS Institute
, 
1995
.
</p>
      <p>
24. 
Bristol DR.p-value adjustments for subgroup analyses
. 
J Biopharm Stat1997
; 
7
: 
313–21
/323–31.
</p>
      <p>
25. 
Pollard KS
, 
van der Laan MJ.Choice of a null distribution in resampling-based multiple testing
. 
J Statist Plann Inference2004
; 
125
: 
85–100
.
</p>
      <p>
26. 
Lunn M
, 
McNeil D.Applying Cox regression to competing risks
. 
Biometrics1995
; 
51
: 
524–32
.
</p>
      <p>
27. 
Choopanya K
, 
Tappero JW
, 
Pitisuttithum P
, et al. 
Preliminary results of a phase III HIV vaccine efficac trial among injecting drug users in Thailand [abstract ThOrA1427]
. In: 
Program and abstracts of the XV International AIDS Conference2004(Bangkok, Thailand). Bangkok, Thailand: Clung Wicha Press
, 
2004
.
</p>
      <p>
28. 
Morens DM.Antibody-dependent enhancement of infection and the pathogenesis of viral disease
. 
Clin Infect Dis1994
; 
19
: 
500–12
.
</p>
      <p>
29. 
Burke DS.Human HIV vaccine trials: does antibody-dependent enhancement pose a genuine risk
? 
Perspect Biol Med1992
; 
35
: 
511–30
.
</p>
      <p>
30. 
King RT. FDAallows large-scale trial of AIDS vaccine
. 
Wall Street Journal. 3 June1998
: 
1
.
</p>
      <p>
31. 
Chesney MA
, 
Chambers D
, 
Kahn JO.Risk behavior for HIV infection in participants in preventive HIV vaccine trials: a cautionary note
. 
J Acquir Immune Defi Syndr Hum Retrovirol1997
; 
16
: 
266–71
.
</p>
      <p>
32. 
Bloom BR.The highest attainable standard: ethical issues in AIDS vaccines
. 
Science1998
; 
279
: 
186–8
.
</p>
      <p>
33. 
Ackers M-L
, 
Parekh B
, 
Evans TG
, et al. 
Human immunodeficienc virus (HIV) seropositivity among uninfected HIV vaccine recipients
. 
J Infect Dis2003
; 
187
: 
879–86
.
</p>
      <p>
34. 
Stanberry LR
, 
Spruance SL
, 
Cunningham AL
, et al. 
Glycoprotein-d– adjuvant vaccine to prevent genital herpes
. 
N Engl J Med2002
; 
347
: 
1652–61
.
</p>
      <p>
35. 
Whitacre CC
, 
Reingold SC
, 
O’Looney PA
, et al. 
Biomedicine: a gender gap in autoimmunity
. 
Science1999
; 
283
: 
1277–8
.
</p>
      <p>
36. 
Sugimoto K
, 
Stadanlick J
, 
Ikeda F
, et al. 
Influenc of ethnicity in the outcome of hepatitis C virus infection and cellular immune response
. 
Hepatology2003
; 
37
: 
590–9
.
</p>
      <p>
37. 
Schacker T
, 
Zeh J
, 
Hu HL
, 
Hill J
, 
Corey L.Frequency of symptomatic and asymptomatic HSV-2 reactivations among HIV-infected men
. 
J Infect Dis1998
; 
178
: 
1616–22
.
</p>
      <p>
38. 
Wald A
, 
Link K.Risk of human immunodeficienc virus infection in herpes simplex virus type 2–seropositive persons: a meta-analysis
. 
J Infect Dis2002
; 
185
: 
45–52
.
</p>
      <p>
39. 
Xiang J
, 
Wunschmann S
, 
Diekema DJ
, et al. 
Effect of coinfection with GB virus C on survival among patients with HIV infection
. 
N Engl J Med2001
; 
345
: 
707–14
.
</p>
      <p>
40. 
George SL
, 
Wunschmann S
, 
McCoy J
, 
Xiang J
, 
Stapleton JT.Interactions between GB virus type C and HIV
. 
Curr Infect Dis Rep2002
; 
4
: 
550–8
.
</p>
      <p>
41. 
Williams CF
, 
Klinzman D
, 
Yamashita TE
, et al. 
Persistent GB virus C infection and survival in HIV-infected men
. 
N Engl J Med2004
; 
350
: 
981–90
.
</p>
      <p>
42. 
Pomerantz RJ
, 
Nunnari G. HIVand GB virus C: can two viruses be better than one
? 
N Engl J Med2004
; 
350
: 
963–5
.
</p>
      <p>
43. 
Dawson GJ
, 
Schlauder GG
, 
Pilot-Matias TJ
, et al. 
Prevalence studies of GB virus–C infection using reverse transcriptase–polymerase chain reaction
. 
J Med Virol1996
; 
50
: 
97–103
.
</p>
      <p>
44. 
Assmann SF
, 
Pocock SJ
, 
Enos LE
, et al. 
Subgroup analysis and other (mis)uses of baseline data in clinical trials
. 
Lancet2000
; 
355
: 
1064–9
.
</p>
      <p>
45. 
Klinman DM
, 
Kamstrup S
, 
Verthelyi D
, et al. 
Activation of the innate immune system by CpG oligodeoxynucleotides: immunoprotectiveactivity and safety
. 
Springer Semin Immunopathol2000
; 
22
: 
173–83
.
</p>
      <p>
46. 
Moore A
, 
McCarthy L
, 
Mills KH.The adjuvant combination monophosphoryl lipid A and QS21 switches T cell responses induced with a soluble recombinant HIV protein from Th2 to Th1
. 
Vaccine1999
; 
17
: 
2517–27
.
</p>
      <p>
47. 
Frank FM
, 
Petray PB
, 
Cazorla SI
, 
Munoz MC
, 
Corral RS
, 
Malchiodi EL.
Use of a purifie 
Trypanosoma cruzi
antigen and CpG oligodeoxynucleotides for immunoprotection against a lethal challenge with trypomastigotes

. 
Vaccine2003
; 
22
: 
77–86
.
</p>
      <p>
48. 
Verthelyi D
, 
Kenney RT
, 
Seder RA
, 
Gam AA
, 
Friedag B
, 
Klinman DM.CpG oligodeoxynucleotides as vaccine adjuvants in primates
. 
J Immunol2002
; 
168
: 
1659–63
.
</p>
      <p>
49. 
Nabel GJ.Challenges and opportunities of development of an AIDS vaccine
. 
Nature2001
; 
410
: 
1002–6
.
</p>
      <p>
50. 
Schultz AM
, 
Bradac JA.The HIV vaccine pipeline, from preclinical to phase III
. 
AIDS2001
; 
15
(Suppl 5):S 
147–58
.
</p>
      <p>
51. 
Nitayaphan S
, 
Pitisuttithum P
, 
de Souza M
, et al. 
Safety and immunogenicity of live recombinant ALVAC-HIV (vCP1521
) priming with AIDSVAX B/E gp120 boosting in Thai HIV-negative adults (abstract WePeB6049). In: 
Program and abstracts of the XIV International AIDS Conference 2002 (Barcelona, Spain)
. 
Barcelona, Spain: Prous Science
, 
2002
.
</p>
      <p>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/jid/article-abstract/191/5/654/1234535 by Aerztegemeinschaft fuer Anaesthesie user</p>
   </body>
</article>
