<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Science</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1154284</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Molecular phylogenetics of Mastodon and Tyrannosaurus rex</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <year>2008</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p> Science IW aaas </p>
         <p> Molecular Phylogenetics of Mastodon and <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus
               rex</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p> Author(s): Chris L. Organ , Mary H. Schweitzer , Wenxia Zheng , Lisa M. Freimark ,
            Lewis C. Cantley and John M. Asara </p>
         <p> Source: Science, New Series, Vol. 320 , No. 5875 (Apr. 25, 2008 ), p. 499 </p>
         <p>Published by: American Association for the Advancement of Science</p>
         <p>Stable URL: https://www.jstor.org/stable/20055088</p>
         <p>Accessed: 16-04-2020 15:22 UTC</p>
         <p>JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students
            discover, use, and build upon a wide range of content in a trusted digital archive. We
            use information technology and tools to increase productivity and facilitate new forms
            of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact support@jstor.org.</p>
         <p>Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of
            Use, available at</p>
         <p>https://about.jstor.org/terms</p>
         <p>JSTOR</p>
         <p>American Association for the Advancement of Science is collaborating with JSTOR to
            digitize, preserve and extend access to Science</p>
         <p>This content downloaded from 154.59.124.40 on Thu, 16 Apr 2020 15:22:22 UTC All use
            subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms</p>
         <p> out of four methods for the <tp:taxon-name>T. rex</tp:taxon-name> despite the problem
            of missing sequence data. The recovered sequences contain informative phylogenetic
            signal consistent with predictions based on genetic and morphological data for mastodon
            ( , ) and on morphological data for <tp:taxon-name>T. rex</tp:taxon-name> ( , ) These
            results support the endogenous origin of the preserved collagen molecules and confirm
            the prediction based on morphology that, ifbiomolecules could be retrieved from a
            nonavian dinosaur, they would share a higher degree of similarity with birds than with
            other extant vertebrates. Our findings suggest that molecular data from long-extinct
            organisms may have the potential for resolving relationships at critical areas of the
            vertebrate evolutionary tree that have, so far, been intractable. The findings presented
            here also bolster the use ofmorphology in phylogenetics because our results are
            consistent with studies on the evolutionary relationships of fossil forms that rely on
            morphology ( , ). </p>
         <p> Molecular Phylogenetics of Mastodon and <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus
               rex</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>.</p>
         <p>Chris L. Organ,1'2 Mary H. Schweitzer,3'4 Wenxia Zheng,3 Lisa M. Freimark,5 Lewis C.
            Cantley,5'6 John M. Asara5'6*</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ' Protein sequences from bone-derived collagen P as old as 68 million years have been
            detected by using mass spectrometry ( , ). A BLAST search of the resulting peptide
            sequences found the highest similarities between the collagen peptides obtained from
            extracts of <tp:taxon-name>Tyrannosaurus rex</tp:taxon-name> fossil bone and those
            ofbirds ( <tp:taxon-name>Gallus gallus</tp:taxon-name> ) and between mastodon (
               <tp:taxon-name>Mammut americanum</tp:taxon-name> ) and other mam­ mals, including
            elephant ( <tp:taxon-name>Loxodonta africana</tp:taxon-name> ). We performed
            phylogenetic analyses to infer the evolutionary relationships of the <tp:taxon-name>T.
               rex</tp:taxon-name> [Museum of the Rockies ( MOR) 1125 ] and mastodon (MOR 605). The
            results extend our knowledge of trait evo­ lution within nonavian dinosaurs into the
            macro­ molecular level of biological organization. We used 21 extant organisms in the
            analyses. Collagen a 1(I) and a2(I) protein sequences from 19 extant organisms (3) were
            obtained from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) and ENSEMBL
            databases. Collagen a1(I) and a2(I) peptide sequences from a metacarpal of Alligator
            mississippiensis were obtained by mi­ crocapillary liquid chromatography tandem mass
            spectrometry (LC/MS/MS) with an ion trap mass spectrometer using the Sequest algorithm (
            , ) and the Paragon algorithm ( ). Ostrich collagen se­ quences were determined
            elsewhere ( , ). Sequences from alligator (Crocodilia) and ostrich (Aves) rep­ resent
            63% and 43% of the full-length collagen a1(I) protein available for other organisms,
            respec­ tively. The collagen a1(I) and a2(I) sequences for elephant (L. africana),
            tenrec (Echinops telfairi), and </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> with less support (approximate likelihood ratio test; aLRT = 0.855 for Elephantinae and
            0.872 for Afrotheria). Maximum parsimony analysis also groups mastodon, elephant, and
            tenrec together (fig. S1, B to D). For the <tp:taxon-name>T. rex</tp:taxon-name> sample,
            we used five peptide sequences from collagen a1(I) and one from collagen a2(I) ( , , )
            for a total of 89 amino acids ( Fig. 1 ). The <tp:taxon-name>T. rex</tp:taxon-name>
            clusters within the Archosauria (posterior probability of 0.92), more closely related to
            birds (chicken and ostrich, 0.9) than alligator, although a lack of informative sites in
            the ostrich and <tp:taxon-name>T. rex</tp:taxon-name> leaves Dinosauria unresolved. The
            likelihood tree is identical to the Bayesian tree, except for higher support at these
            locations in the tree (aLRT = 0.969 for Archosauria and 0.907 for Dinosauria). Branch
            lengths (expected rates of change per site) indicate a relatively stable and uniform
            rate of evolution, lacking evidence for a deviation from a molecular clock. Maximum par­
            simony analysis also groups the <tp:taxon-name>T. rex</tp:taxon-name> with the chicken
            and ostrich, although bootstrap support is low (fig. S1, B to D). Neighbor joining
            groups the <tp:taxon-name>T. rex</tp:taxon-name> with the birds, but miscalculates the
            branching order and misplaces alligator, mastodon, and several extant organisms (fig.
            S1, B to D). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <ref-list>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 1. J. M. Asara , M. H. Schweitzer , L. M. Freimark , M. Phillips ,
                  L. C. Cantley , Science 316 , 280 ( 2007 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 2. J. M. Asara et al., Science 317 , 1324 ( 2007 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 4. I. V. Shilov et al., Mol. Cell. Proteomics 6 , 1638 ( 2007 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 7. M. S. Springer , W. J. Murphy , E. Eizirik , S. J. O'Brien ,
                  Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 100 , 1056 ( 2003 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 8. J. M. Asara , M. H. Schweitzer , Science 319 , 33 ( 2008 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 9. J. J. Wiens , Syst. Biol. 52 , 528 ( 2003 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 10. N. Rohland et al., PLoS Biol. 5 , 1663 ( 2007 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 11. M. G. Thomas et al., Proc. R. Soc. London Ser. B 267 , 2493 (
                  2000 ). </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 12. M. J. Benton , in The Dinosauria , D. B. Weishampel , P. Dodson
                  , H. Osmolska , Eds. ( Univ. of California Press, Berkeley , 2004 ), pp. 7-19 .
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 13. T. R. Holtz , H. Osmolska , in The Dinosauria , D. B. Weishampel
                  , P. Dodson , H. Osmolska , Eds. ( Univ. of California Press, Berkeley , 2004 ),
                  pp. 21-24 . </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref>
               <mixed-citation> 14. M. S. Springer et al., Syst. Biol. 56 , 673 ( 2007 ).
               </mixed-citation>
            </ref>
         </ref-list>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>N/A</title>
         <p>Materials and Methods</p>
         <p>SOM Text</p>
         <p>Figs. S1 and S2</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>References and Notes</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Appendices 1 and 2</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>17 December 2007; accepted 25 February 2008</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>10.1126/science.1154284</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Harvard University, Cambridge, MA 02138, USA. 2Museum of Comparative Zoology, Cambridge,
            MA 02138, USA. 3North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC 27695, USA. 4North Carolina
            Museum of Natural Sciences, Raleigh, NC 27601, USA. 5Beth Israel Deaconess Medical
            Center, Boston, MA 02115, USA. Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA 02115, USA.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: jasara@bidmc.harvard.edu</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
