<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id journal-id-type="other">N/A</journal-id>
         <journal-title-group>
            <journal-title>Science</journal-title>
         </journal-title-group>
         <issn>N/A</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aab3564</article-id>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Keeping cool: Enhanced optical reflection and radiative heat dissipation
               in Saharan silver ants</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date date-type="pub">
            <day>17</day>
            <month>07</month>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
         <kwd-group>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cataglyphis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cataglyphis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cataglyphis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
            <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
               <tp:taxon-name>Cataglyphis</tp:taxon-name>
            </kwd>
         </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Keeping cool: Enhanced optical reflection and radiative heat dissipation in Saharan
            silver ants </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Norman Nan Shi , 1 Cheng-Chia Tsai , 1 Fernando Camino , 2 Gary D. Bernard , 3 Nanfang
            Yu , 1 * Rüdiger Wehner 4 * </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Saharan silver ants, <tp:taxon-name>Cataglyphis</tp:taxon-name> bombycina , forage
            under extreme temperature conditions in the African desert. We show that the ants’
            conspicuous silvery appearance is created by a dense array of triangular hairs with two
            thermoregulatory effects. They enhance not only the reflectivity of the ant’ s body
            surface in the visible and near-infrared range of </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>the spectrum, where solar radiation culminates, but also the emissivity of the ant in
            the mid-infrared. The latter effect enables the animals to efficiently dissipate heat
            back to the surroundings via blackbody radiation under full daylight conditions. This
            biological solution for a thermoregulatory problem may lead to the development of
            biomimetic coatings for passive radiative cooling of objects.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> he silver ants of the Sahara desert, </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> T wide-ranging the niche Earth <tp:taxon-name>Cataglyphis</tp:taxon-name> hottest, of
            where foraging a “thermophilic terrestrial bombycina they journeys occupy environments
            scavenger,, inhabit they the ecological search ” one ( ). for on In of </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> corpses of insects and other arthropods that have </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> succumbed to the thermally harsh desert condi- </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> tions, which they themselves are able to withstand more successfully. On hot summer
            days, they may reach maximal foraging activities when temperatures of the desert surface
            are as high as 60° to 70°C and their body temperatures measured as “operative
            environmental temperatures” are in the range of 48° to 51°C ( , ). In order to survive
            under these conditions, occasionally the ants must unload excess heat by pausing on top
            of stones or dry vegetation, where, because of the steep temperature gradient above the
            sand surface, they encounter considerably lower temperatures. Under the midday sun of a
            summer day, the ants may resort to this thermal respite (cooling off) up to 70% of their
            entire foraging time ( ). In keeping their body temperature below their critical thermal
            maximum of 53.6°C ( ), they need not only to reduce heat absorption from the environment
            but also to be able to efficiently dissipate excess heat, so that they can minimize the
            amount of time spent in thermal refuges. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> As we showed, through a series of optical and thermodynamic measurements, full-wave
            simulations, and heat-transfer modeling, a dense array of triangularly shaped hairs,
            characteristic of <tp:taxon-name>Cataglyphis</tp:taxon-name> bombycina , enables the
            ants to main- tain lower body temperatures by (i) reflecting a </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> large portion of the solar radiation in the visible </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> and near-infrared (NIR) range of the spectrum </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> and (ii) radiating heat to the surrounding envi- </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>ronment by enhancing the emissivity in the midinfrared (MIR), where the blackbody
            radiation spectrum of the ant’ s body culminates.The thermoregulatory solutions that the
            silver ants have evolved to cope with thermally stressful conditions show that these
            animals are able to control electromagnetic waves over an extremely broad range of the
            electromagnetic spectrum (from the visible to the MIR) and that different physical
            mechanisms are employed in different spectral ranges to realize an important biological
            function.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Specimens of <tp:taxon-name>Cataglyphis</tp:taxon-name> bombycina collected in Tunisia
            (34°10′N, 08°18′E) were used for all of the optical and thermodynamic measurements. In
            these ants, the dorsal and lateral sides of the body have a silvery glare ( Fig. 1A )
            and are covered by dense and uniform arrays of hairs ( Fig. B and fig. S4). As scanning
            electron microscopy (SEM) images show, the hairs, which gradually taper off at the tip,
            are locally aligned in the same direction ( Fig. 1C ). Their most remarkable structural
            feature is the triangular cross-section characterized by two corrugated top facets and a
            flat bottom facet facing the ant’ s body ( Fig. 1 , D and E). Cross-sectional views
            obtained by focused ion beam (FIB) milling show that the gap between the bottom hair
            facet and the cuticular surface also varies but is generally larger than a few hundred
            nanometers. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Optical reflectivity measurements of ant specimens were obtained with two Fourier
            transform spectrometers, one collecting spectra in the visible and NIR (wavelengths from
            0.45 to 1.7 µm) and the other in the MIR (wavelengths from 2.5 to 16 µm). The visible
            and NIR measurements showed that hemispherical reflection [i.e., the sum of specular and
            diffuse reflection collected through an integrating sphere ( 2 )] is substantially
            enhanced </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> in regions with intact hair coverage as compared to regions from which the hairs had
            been removed ( Fig. 2A and fig. S1). The hair-covered region reflects 67% of the
            incoming solar radiation rather than only 41%, as is the case after their removal. This
            enhancement is due to scattering within the triangular hairs (Mie scattering), where
            light gets trapped and then reradiates out in all directions ( – ). Individual hairs of
            given cross-sectional dimensions generate enhanced reflection due to scattering at
            specific wavelengths where fundamental and higher-order Mie resonance modes are
            supported ( Fig. 2C and fig. S5). Due to the variation in cross-sectional areas,
            resonance peaks from individual hairs are averaged out, so that the hair cover
            effectively acts as a coating with enhanced broadband reflection. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Because of the ellipsoidal shape of the ant’ s body, about two-thirds of the
            dorsolateral surface is obliquely hit by solar radiation (fig. S4). This prompted us to
            examine the reflectivity as a function of the incidence angle of radiation,which was
            varied from 0° to 80°, with 0° representing the direction normal to the surface.As the
            results show, Mie scattering enhances reflectivity over all angles when regions with
            intact hair cover are compared to those with hairs removed ( Fig. 2B ). With increasing
            angle of incidence, reflectivity enhancement becomes particularly strong at beyond 30°.
            This is the critical angle at which total internal reflection starts to occur at the
            bottom facets of the hairs ( Fig. 2D , II). At angles approaching 90°, reflectivity
            drops off when total internal reflection at one of the top facets starts to direct more
            of the radiation toward the ant’ s body ( Fig. 2D , III). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Next, we performed finite-difference timedomain (FDTD) simulations in order to
            demonstrate the functional significance of the triangular cross section of the hairs in
            enhancing reflectivity in the visible and NIR ranges (figs. S5 to S8). These simulations
            compared the reflective properties of triangular and circular hairs of the same cross
            sectional area. Even though the enhancement of reflectivity at normal incidence is
            comparable in both cases, triangular hairs produce an extra enhancement at higher angles
            of incidence ( Fig. 2B ). The reason is that although Mie scattering of similar strength
            occurs in both circular and triangular hairs, in the latter the total internal
            reflection at the bottom facets of the hairs enhances reflectivity substantially
            further. The high reflectivity disappeared when the specimens were wetted by an
            ethanol-water solution (fig.S3), which removed the refractive index contrast between air
            and hairs and thus destroyed the conditions required for Mie scattering and total
            internal reflection. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Reflectivity measurements performed in the MIR range revealed a second important point
            in the silver ant thermotolerance story. When proceeding from lower to higher
            wavelengths, at about 8 m m, the enhanced reflectivity of regions with hair cover as
            compared to those without hairs reverses to reduced reflectivity ( Fig. 2E ). As
            Kirchhoff’ s law of thermal radiation states, reduced reflectivity corresponds to
            enhanced emissivity ( ). At a body temperature of 50°C, which the silver ants may reach
            when foraging at peak activity times, the blackbody radiation of the ant’ s surface
            would lie in the range of 6 to 16 m m (peaked at ~9 m m) and thus allow the silver ants
            to offload heat more efficiently through radiative heat transfer. The latter decreases
            the steady-state body temperature and reduces the respite time. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> How does the hair cover with its enhanced reflectivity in the visible and NIR and its
            enhanced emissivity in the MIR affect the radiative heat transfer between the ant’ s
            body and the environment? To investigate this question, we performed thermodynamic
            experiments, which mimicked all radiative heat transfer effects in the silver ants’
            natural foraging environment (fig. S2). To accomplish this task, we used a high-power
            xenon lamp to simulate the solar spectral distribution at the desert sand surface ( )
            and a thermoelectrically cooled high-emissivity metal plate to simulate the clear sky
            with its low level of blackbody radiation ( ). The ant specimens were suspended on thin
            threads to minimize thermal conduction. Thermodynamic experiments were conducted in
            vacuum to study thermal radiation, as well as in still air to study the interplay of
            thermal radiation and convection. Under both conditions, the specimens with their
            natural hair covers were able to maintain significantly lower steadystate body
            temperatures than the same specimens with the hairs removed ( Fig. 3 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> The thermodynamic experiments conducted in vacuum comparing specimens before and after
            hair removal further revealed that the hair cover decreases the time constants of
            temperature change ( Fig. 3 , B and E). The shortened time constants indicate an
            increased rate of radiative heat transfer and are a direct confirmation of the effect of
            the hairs in enhancing the MIR emissivity. By using the time constants and the heat
            transfer model, we computed that the hair cover enhances emissivity by about 15% (table
            S1). This enhanced emissivity is due to the fact that at large MIR wavelengths (i.e., at
            wavelengths much larger than the dimensions of the cross sections of the hairs), the
            hair structure acts as a gradient refractive index layer (fig. S9) ( 11– ), which
            provides the surface with broadband, broad-angle antireflective properties in the MIR (
            Fig. 2 , E and F). Because of the influence of convection, the time constants of
            temperature change decreased by a factor of about 3 when the specimens were brought from
            vacuum into air ( Fig. ). This indicates that radiative heat dissipation amounted to
            about one-half of convection and, therefore, still played a significant role in the
            presence of natural convection. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Applying experimentally extracted parameters to the heat transfer model revealed that
            the enhanced visible and NIR reflectivity and enhanced MIR emissivity make comparable
            contributions to reducing the steady-state temperature in the presence of natural
            convection (figs. S and S11). On hot summer days in the Sahara, the foraging activities
            of silver ants often occur under low wind or even still air conditions, when the ants
            have to rely on enhanced visible and NIR reflectivity and enhanced MIR emissivity
            equally heavily to reduce their body temperature during the respite behavior. </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>It is interesting to note that the hairs cover only the top and the sides of the ant’ s
            body, where they are responsible for the effects described above. The absence of hairs
            on the bottom surface reduces the radiative energy transfer between the hot sand and the
            cooler ant body, so that the animals can reduce the absorption of blackbody radiation
            from the desert floor.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> In conclusion, Saharan silver ants are covered with a dense array of triangular hairs
            on the top and sides of their bodies. These silvery hairs protect the ants against
            getting overheated in at least three ways. First, as a result of Mie scattering and
            total internal reflection, the hairs enhance reflectivity in the visible and NIR, where
            solar radiation culminates. Second, in the MIR, where solar radiation becomes negligible
            for wavelengths&gt;2.5 m m, the hairs acting as an antireflection layer enhance
            emissivity and thus increase the ants’ ability to offload excess heat via blackbody
            radiation. Third, the ants’ bare bottom surface reflects MIR radiation from the hot
            desert floor more efficiently than if it were covered by hairs. Taken together, these
            effects result in decreasing the ants’ steady-state body temperature and thus enable
            these thermophilic scavengers to forage at exceedingly high environmental temperatures.
            Finally, the present interdisciplinary account on the silver ants could have a
            significant technological impact by inspiring the development of biomimetic coatings for
            the passive cooling of objects ( – ). A recent article reported the demonstration of a
            multilayered film that can cool down an object by using essentially the same mechanisms
            as the silver ants: high reflectivity in the solar spectrum and high emissivity in the
            MIR ( ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> REFERENCES AND NOTES </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 1 . R. Wehner , S. Wehner , Physiol. Entomol. 36 , 271 – 281 ( 2011 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 2 . Materials and methods are available as supplementary materials on Science Online .
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 3 . R. Wehner , A. C. Marsh , S. Wehner , Nature 357 , 586 – 587 ( 1992 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 4 . W. J. Gehring , R. Wehner , Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 92 , 2994 – 2998 ( 1995
            ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 5 . C. F. Bohren , D. R. Huffman , Absorption and Scattering of Light by Small
            Particles (Wiley, New York, 1998) . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 6. J. Schuller , T. Taubner , M. L. Brongersma , Nat . Photonics 3 , 658 – 661 ( 2009
            ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 7 . D. Lin , P. Fan , E. Hasman , M. L. Brongersma , Science 345 , 298 – 302 ( 2014 ).
         </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 8 . J. R. Howell , R. Siegel , M. P. Mengüç , Thermal Radiation Heat Transfer (CRC
            Press, Boca Raton, FL, ed. 5, 2010) . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 9 . K. L. Coulson , Solar and Terrestrial Radiation: Methods and Measurements (Academic
            Press, New York, 1975) . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 10 . J. Monteith , M. Unsworth , Principles of Environmental Physics ( Academic Press,
            Oxford, ed. 3, 2007 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 11. C.-H. Sun , P. Jiang , B. Jiang , Appl. Phys. Lett. 92 , 0 61112 ( 2008 ) . </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 12. J.-Q. Xi et al ., Nat. Photon. 1 , 176 – 179 (2007). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 13 . M. J. Minot , J. Opt . Soc. Am. 66 , 515 – 519 ( 1976 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 14 . C. G. Granqvist , A. Hjortsberg , Appl. Phys. Lett. 36 , 139 – 141 ( 1980 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 15 . P. Berdahl , Appl. Opt. 23 , 370 – 372 ( 1984 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 16 . E. Rephaeli , A. Raman , S. Fan , Nano Lett . 13 , 1457 – 1461 ( 2013 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 17 . A. P. Raman , M. A. Anoma , L. Zhu , E. Rephaeli , S. Fan , Nature 515 , 540 – 544
            ( 2014 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> 18 . R. Wehner , Jahrb. Akad. Wiss. Lit. Mainz 89 , 101 – 112 ( 1989 ). </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> We acknowledge intriguing discussions with N. Pierce; help with experiments from Z. Li,
            M.-H. Kim, B. Patterson, and M. Y. Sfeir; and R. F. Foelix for kindly preparing and
            providing Fig. 1B . The work was supported by NSF (grants PHY-1411445 and ECCS-1307948)
            and the Air Force Office of Scientific Research, Multidisciplinary University Research
            Initiative program (grant FA9550-14-1-0389). Research was carried out in part at the
            Center for Functional </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Nanomaterials, Brookhaven National Laboratory, which is supported by the U.S. Department
            of Energy, Office of Basic Energy Sciences, under contract no. DE-SC0012704. Data
            reported in this paper are archived at http://datadryad.org/
            resource/doi:10.5061/dryad.2bm50. Author contributions are as follows: R.W. and G.D.B.
            initiated the study, N.N.S., C.-C. Tsai, and N.Y. designed the study and conducted the
            analyses, and all authors contributed to developing the study and to drafting the
            manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>www.sciencemag.org/content/349/6245/298/suppl/DC1 Materials and Methods</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Supplementary Text</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> Figs. S1 to S11 </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p> References ( 19–29 ) </p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>Movie S1</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="inferred">
         <title>Orphanage</title>
         <p>15 April 2015; accepted 11 June 2015 Published online 18 June 2015
            10.1126/science.aab3564</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
