<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>http://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4136.3.3</journal-id>
         <issn>1175-5326</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Dragons in the mist: three new species of Pseudocalotes Fitzinger (Squamata: Agamidae) from the sky island archipelago of Peninsular Malaysia</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2016</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Dragons in the mist: three new species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes
Fitzinger
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Squamata</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Agamidae</tp:taxon-name>
) from the sky island archipelago of Peninsular 
Malaysia</p>
         <p>
L. LEE GRISMER 
1
, EVAN S. H. QUAH 
2
, PERRY L. WOOD, JR. 
3
, SHAHRUL ANUAR 
2
, ABDUL MUIN 
2
, HAYDEN R. DAVIS 
1
, MATTHEW L. MURDOCH 
1
, JESSE L. GRISMER 
4
, MICHAEL COTA 
5
&amp; ANTHONY J. COBOS 
1</p>
         <p>1
Herpetology Laboratory, Department of Biology, La Sierra University, 
4500
Riverwalk Parkway, Riverside, California 
92515USA
. E-mail: lgrismer@lasierra.edu
</p>
         <p>2
School of Biological Sciences, Universiti Sains 
Malaysia
, 
11800USM
, 
Pulau
Pinang, Penang, 
Malaysia
. E-mail: shahrulanuar@gmail.com;; E-mail: evanquah@yahoo.com; E-mail: mamuin@gmail.com
3
Department of Biology, Brigham Young University, 
150
East Bulldog Boulevard, Provo, Utah 
84602USA
. E-mail: pwood@byu.edu
4
Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of Kansas, Lawrence, Kansas 
66045
- 
7651
, 
USA
. E-mail: grismer@ku.edu
</p>
         <p>5
Natural History Museum, National Science Museum, 
Thailand
, Technopolis, Khlong 
5
, Khlong Luang, Pathum Thani 
12120Thailand
. E-mail: herpetologe@gmail.com
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>
An integrative taxonomic analysis is used to delimit and describe three new species of 
Pseudocalotoes
from the sky island archipelago of the Banjaran (=mountain range) Titiwangsa of Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, from Fraser’s Hill, Pahang is basal to the sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
from Bukit Larut, Perak in the Banjaran Bintang and the new species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rha</tp:taxon-name>
e ga l
sp. nov.
from Cameron Highlands, Pahang. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other species of 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a flat rostrum; seven postrostrals; an interparietal; 
11
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one scale between the rostral and nasal; nine supralabials; eight infralabials; 
10
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; five or six sublabials; five or six chinshields; 
47
smooth, wide, gular scales; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; enlarged upper and low- er posttemporals; a single enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; three large scales bordering the dorsal margin of the ear opening; large pretympanic scales; eight scales in the nuchal crest not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to the tip of the tail; keeled and non-plate-like scales on flanks; 
51
midbody scales; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19
subdigital lamellae on the fourth finger; 
23
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; preaxial scales on third toe enlarged and spinose; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.52
; HL/SVL 
0.31
; no elbow or knee patches; and a male dewlap color of lime-green bearing a central yellow spot. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a convex rostrum; 
6–8
postrostrals; an interparietal; nine or 
10
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one or two scales between the rostral and nasal scales; eight or nine supralabials; seven or eight infralabials; 
11
or 
12
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; four or five chinshields; 
40–45
smooth, wide, gular scales; no transverse gular fold; a weak antehumeral fold; three or four enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; no large scales bordering the upper margin of the ear opening or in the pretympanic region; 
6–8
enlarged nuchal crest scales not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to the base of the tail; weakly keeled, non-plate-like scales on the flanks; 
52– 58
midbody scales; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19–21
subdigital lamellae on the fourth finger; 
22–26
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; preaxial scales on the third enlarged and rounded; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.50–0.54
; HL/SVL 
0.28–0.30
; no elbow or knee patches; and female dewlap color yellow bearing a purple base. The analyses also indicated that the new species, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from Genting Highlands, Pahang in the southern section of the Banjaran Titiwangsa is the sister species of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
from Cameron Highlands 
121 km
to the north and can be separated from all other species of 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of three postrostrals; 
10
circumorbitals; four or five canthals; 
5–7
superciliaries; rostral and nasals in contact; supralabials contacting the nasal; six or seven supralabials; six or seven infralabials; two or three postmentals; 
47
or 
48
smooth, flat, gular scales; three chinshields; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; 
7–9
nuchal crest scales lacking gaps and not extending beyond midbody; weakly keeled and plate-like scales on the flanks; 
35–38
midbody scales; ventrals smaller than dorsals; 
22
or 
23
subdigital lamellae on the fourth finger; 
26
or 
27
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; preaxial scales on the third toe not modified; subdigital scales not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.62
; no white marking below the eye; dewlap in males yellow; and no elbow or knee patches. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
most likely occurs in syntopy with 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula
in Tanah Rata
</tp:taxon-name>
at Cameron Highlands and its discovery adds to a growing body of literature detailing the recent descriptions of several new, upland, closely related, sympatric species in Peninsular 
Malaysia
. Another new population referred to here as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from the Hala-Bala Wildlife Sanctuary, Betong District, Yala Province, 
Thailand
is discussed. The discovery and description of these three new 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
from the upland regions of Peninsular 
Malaysia
continues to underscore the remarkably high herpetological diversity and ecological complexity in this sky island archipelago that is still underestimated, unappreciated, and unprotected.
</p>
         <p>Key words:
Peninsular 
Malaysia
, 
Thailand
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Agamidae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
,
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
, uplands
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>
Globally, upland ecosystems in tropical rainforests are renown for their high levels of endemism (

Blackburn &amp; Measey, 
2009
; 

Bell 
et al.,2010
, 

Grismer, 
2011
; 

Grismer 
et al.,2010
a

, 
b
; 

Tolley 
et al.,2011
). This has become patently clear in the sky island archipelago of Peninsular 
Malaysia
that remarkably has yielded 
33
new, codistributed species of amphibians and reptiles across five different mountain systems in only the last nine years of exploration (Chan 
et al.
2009, 2014; 

Grismer 
2006
a

, 
b
, 
2007
, 2008; 

Grismer 
et al.
2004

, 2008, 
2009
a,b, 
2010
a,b, 2011, 2012, 
2013
a,b, 
2014
a,b, 
2015
a,b; Grismer &amp; Quah 
2015
; 

Loredo 
et al.2013
; 

Matsui 
et al.,
2009

, 2014; Wood 
et al.
2008, 2009) with at least 
13
more species awaiting description (Grismer 
et. al.
in prep.; Quah 
et al.
in prep.). Joining this growing list of newly discovered montane taxa is the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
whose species content is increased here with the discovery of three new populations from the Banjaran (=mountain range) Titiwangsa. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
comprises a morphologically diverse group of arboreal agamid lizards ranging from the normal to the bizarre in appearance (Manthey 
2012
). The 
21
species of this genus currently recognized generally inhabit upland areas in tropical regions and collectively extend from 
India
to southern 
China
and thence southward to Sumatra and Java (Hallerman 
et al.2010
). Although the latest phylogeny thus far indicates this genus is monophyletic (J. Grismer 
et al.2016
), the broader interspecific relationships have yet to be the focus of a phylogenetic systematic analysis.
</p>
         <p>
Currently there are four cloud forest species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
known from the Thai-Malay Peninsula that represent two distinct morphological groups (

Grismer 
2011
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaonanensis</tp:taxon-name>
Chan-ard, Cota, Makchai, &amp; Laoteow from the Nakhon Si Thammarat Mountains in southern 
Thailand
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis
Hallermann &amp; McGuire
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Banjaran Bintang near the west coast in northern Peninsular 
Malaysia
have small, uniformly keeled dorsal and flank scales and a relatively narrow head with an elongate snout. Whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula
(Smith)
</tp:taxon-name>
from the centrally located Banjaran Titiwangsa and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi
Hallermann &amp; Böhme
</tp:taxon-name>
from the eastern Banjaran Timur in Peninsular 
Malaysia
have large, plate-like, flank scales (much more pronounced in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
) and a wider head and shorter snout (

). Our ongoing fieldwork in the sky-island archipelago of Peninsular 
Malaysia
has resulted in the discovery of three new populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
and the collection of additional specimens from the 
type
localities of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
(Appendix). Two of the three new populations come from Cameron Highlands and Fraser’s Hill, Pahang (

) and bear the 
P. larutensis-khaonanensis
morphology as well as having relatively short tails, a naked tympanum, prominent nuchal crests that do not extend onto the body, and no elongate postorbital and nuchal spines—characters that separate them from all other agamid genera from the Thai-Malaya Peninsula and align them with the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes
(

Grismer 
2011
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. The third population from Genting Highlands, Pahang resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
in body shape and general coloration but differs discretely from it in squamation. We have obtained a series of close-up color photographs of a fourth specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
from the mountains in the Hala-Bala Wildlife Sanctuary, Betong District, Yala Province, 
Thailand
along the Thai-Malay border that, like the specimens from Genting Highlands, appears superficially similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
but differs from it in squamation. Molecular analyses indicate that the three new populations from Peninsular 
Malaysia
do not form a monophyletic group and morphological and color pattern analyses indicate that each new population is discretely diagnosable from each other and all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The intent of this paper is to describe these three new species. We want to be clear that the phylogenetic component of this study is not intended to be inclusive of all or even most of the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
and was constructed only from tissue samples on hand and augmented by sequences available on GenBank. The phylogeny generated herein is simply a tool to aid in establishing the specific identity of each new population, the potential relationships of the Malaysian species to one another, and to establish the percent sequence divergence among them.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Materials and method</title>
         <p>Molecular analysis.
Ingroup sampling consisted of 
16
individuals of eight species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
(

Table 
1
). Outgroups used to root the tree were 
<tp:taxon-name>Japalura slendida
Barbour &amp; Dunn
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Acanthosaura cardamomensis
Wood, Grismer, Grismer, Neang, Chav
</tp:taxon-name>
, &amp; Holden, and 
<tp:taxon-name>A. crucigera
Boulenger
</tp:taxon-name>
based on the relationships of J. Grismer 
et al.
(
2016
). Sequence data were generated for the three new populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
from Peninsular 
Malaysia
as well as additional specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
from Cameron Highlands, Pahang, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
from Bukit Larut, Perak, and 
P. f l ow e r i
from the Bokor Plateau, 
Cambodia
. Sequences for all other species and the outgroups were downloaded from GenBank (

Table 
1
). All new sequences are deposited in GenBank (

Table 
1
).
</p>
         <p>TABLE 1.
Specimens used for the molecular analyses of this study with species localities and GenBank accession numbers for ND2 and tRNAs.
</p>
         <p>Voucher numberSpeciesLocalityGenBank #LSUHC 7393<tp:taxon-name>Acanthosaura cardamomensis</tp:taxon-name>Cardamom Mountains, CambodiaGU817394CAS 229582<tp:taxon-name>Acanthosaura crucigera</tp:taxon-name>unknownGU817389LSUMZ 81212<tp:taxon-name>Japalura splendida</tp:taxon-name>unknownAF288230MVZ 224106<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes brevipes</tp:taxon-name>unknownAF128502LSUHC 12223<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>Fraser’s Hill, MalaysiaKX258211LSUHC 12420<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>Cameron Highlands, MalaysiaKX258212LSUHC 12580<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>Cameron Highlands, MalaysiaKX258213LSUHC 12581<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>Cameron Highlands, MalaysiaKX258214LSUHC 8572<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes floweri</tp:taxon-name>Bokor Plateau, CambodiaKX258215CAS 207492<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes kakhienensis</tp:taxon-name>unknownGQ502784LSUHC 10285<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes larutensis</tp:taxon-name>Bukit Larut, MalaysiaKX258216LSUHC 11289<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes larutensis</tp:taxon-name>Bukit Larut, MalaysiaKX258217LSUHC 12434<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes larutensis</tp:taxon-name>Bukit Larut, MalaysiaKX258218LSUHC 9052<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes larutensis</tp:taxon-name>Bukit Larut, MalaysiaKX258219TNHC 58040<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes larutensis</tp:taxon-name>Bukit Larut, MalaysiaAF128503LSUHC 12000<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>Cameron Highlands, MalaysiaKX258220LSUHC 12179<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>Cameron Highlands, MalaysiaKX258221LSUHC 12114<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>Genting Highlands, MalaysiaKX258222LSUHC 12227<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>Genting Highlands, MalaysiaKX258223</p>
         <p>
Genomic 
DNA
was isolated from liver or skeletal muscle samples stored in 
95
% ethanol using the Qiagen DNeasy TM tissue kit (Valencia, CA, 
USA
). ND 
2
was amplified using a double-stranded Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) under the following conditions: 1.0 µl (~ 
10–30
µg of 
DNA
) genomic 
DNA
, 1.0 µl (
10
µM) light strand primer, 1.0 µl (
10
µM) heavy strand primer, 
1
µl (
10
µM) dinucleotide pairs, 2.0 µl (
1.5
mM) 
5
x

buffer, 1.0 µl (
1.5
mM) MgCl 
10
x

buffer, 
2.5
ul Taq polymerase, and 
7.56
µl ultra-pure H 
2
O (

Table 
2
). PCR reactions were executed on an Eppendorf Mastercycler gradient thermal cycler under the following conditions: initial denaturation at 
95
°C for 
2
min, followed by a second denaturation at 
95
°C for 
35
s, annealing at 
50
°C for 
35
s, followed by a cycle extension at 
72
°C for 
35
s, for 
31
cycles. All PCR products were visualized on a 
1
% agarose gel electrophoresis. Successful PCR products were vacuum purified using 
MANU30
PCR plates (Millipore) and purified products were resuspended in ultra-pure water. Purified PCR products were sequenced using the 
ABI
Big-Dye Terminator v 
3.1
Cycle Sequencing Kit in an 
ABI
GeneAmp PCR 
9700
thermal cycler. Cycle sequencing reactions were purified with Sephadex G- 
50
Fine (GE Healthcare) and sequenced on an 
ABI3730
xl 
DNA
Analyzer at the 
BYUDNA
Sequencing center. Primers used for amplification and sequencing are presented in 

Table 
2
. Sequences were analyzed from both the 
3
' and the 
5
' ends separately to confirm congruence between the reads. Both the forward and the reverse sequences were uploaded and edited in Geneious TM version v5.5.6 (

Drummond 
et al.2011
). The protein-coding region of the ND 
2
sequence was aligned by eye. Mesquite v 
3.02
(

Maddison &amp; Maddison 
2015
) was used to calculate the correct amino acid reading frame and to confirm the lack of premature stop codons. Pairwise sequence divergence were calculated in 
MEGA
v 
6.06
(Tamaura 
et al.2013
).
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 2.
Distribution of the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
on the Thai-Malay Peninsula. Starred circles are type localities. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaonanensis</tp:taxon-name>
from Kaho Nan National Park, Nakkon Si Thammarat Province, Thailand. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from the Hala-Bala Wildlife Sanctuary, Yala Province, Thailand. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes dringi</tp:taxon-name>
from the type locality at Gunung Tahan, Pahang and Gunung Lawit, Terengganu, Peninsular Malaysia. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
from Bukit Larut, Perak, Peninsular Malaysia. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from Robinson Falls, Cameron Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular Malaysia. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from Fraser’s Hill, Pahang, Peninsular Malaysia. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
from Gunung Brinchang, Cameron Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular Malaysia. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular Malaysia.
</p>
         <p>TABLE 2.
Primers used for PCR amplification and sequencing.
</p>
         <p>
L 
4437
b 
5
’-AAGCAGTTGGGCCCATACC- 
3
’ 

Macey 
et al.
(
1999
)

H 
59345
’- AGRGTGCCAATGTCTTTGTGRTT- 
3
’ 

Macey 
et al.
(
1999
)

For the phylogenetic analyses we applied two model-based methods, Maximum Likelihood and Bayesian Inference. The Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC) as implemented in IQ-TREE (

Nguyen 
et al.2015
) calculated TPM 
3
+G 
4
, HKY+G 
4
, and TPM 
3
u+G 
4
to be the best-fit models of evolution for the first, second, and third codon positions, respectively. Maximum Likelihood analysis was performed using RAxML 
HPC
v7.5.4 (

Stamatakis 
2008
) via the command line, with an initial search of 
200
replicates for the best tree. Nodal support was calculated with 
1000
bootstrap pseudoreplicates via the rapid hill-climbing algorithm (

Stamatakis 
2008
). Nodes that had bootstrap values (ML) of 
95
and above were considered significantly supported. The Bayesian analysis was carried out in MrBayes v 
3.2
(

Ronquist 
et al.2012
) via command line. Two simultaneous runs were performed with eight chains per run, seven hot and one cold following default priors. The analysis was run for 
5,000,000
generations and sampled every 
5000
generations from the Markov Chain Monte Carlo (
MCMC
). The analysis was halted after the average standard deviation split frequency was below 
0.01
. Conservatively, the first 
25
% of the trees from each run were discarded as burnin. A consensus tree was computed from the two parallel runs using the sumt function in MrBayes v 
3.2
(

Ronquist 
et al.2012
). Nodes that had posterior probabilities (
BI
) of 
0.95
or above were considered significantly supported (

Wilcox 
et al.2002
).
</p>
         <p>Morphological analysis.
Color notes were taken from digital images of living specimens. The following measurements were taken with Mitutoyo dial calipers to the nearest 
0.1 mm
under a Nikon SMZ 
1500
dissecting microscope on the left side of the body where appropriate: head length (HL), measured from the posterior margin of the retroarticular process of the lower jaw to the tip of the snout; head width (HW), measured at the widest part of the temporal region; snout-vent length (SVL), taken from the tip of snout to the vent; and tail length (TL), taken from the vent to the tip of the tail. Scale counts taken include postrostrals (numbers of scales contacting the rostral scale not including the first supralabials); postnasal-suborbital (number of scales extending from the nasal scale to below the posterior margin of the orbit [

]); canthals (number of enlarged scales between the postnasal and the anteriormost superciliary [

]); circumorbitals (enlarged scales forming a semicircular arc extending from the anterior margin of the orbit [where they are small] and grading into larger scales that terminate at the posterior margin of the orbit 

]); superciliaries (number of flat, elongate, imbricating scales immediately above the orbit); supralabials (number of scales extending from the rostral to just beyond the rictus [see 

Harvey 
et al.2015
: 

); infralabials (number of scales extending from the mental to the scales positioned beneath the last supralabial [see 

Harvey 
et al.2015
: 

]); postmentals (number of scales, excluding the first infralabials, in contact with the mental); chinshields (number of enlarged scales between the mental that extend posteriorly along the margin of the mandible medial to the infralabials and terminate with the scale anterior to the posteriormost scale in the series that is equal in size to the adjacent medial scale [

]); gular scales (number of scales between an imaginary transverse line level with the prebrachial margin and the postmentals or infralabials if the latter are in contact); nuchal crest (number of elongate, lancolate, vertebral scales on the nape of the neck); midbody scales (number of contiguous scales counted around the body equidistant between the forelimb and hind limb insertions); fourth finger lamellae (number of transverse, subdigital lamellae on the fourth finger counted from the base of the finger where it contacts the body of the manus to the claw [including the claw sheath]); and fourth toe lamellae (number of transverse, subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe counted from the base of the toe where it contacts the body of the pes to the claw [including the claw sheath]). The remaining scale characters scored were the presence or absence of an interparietal scale; the presence or absence of a scale(s) separating the rostral and first supralabial; the presence or absence of transverse gular and antehumeral folds (Figs. 3,4); condition of gular scales (flat, wide, keeled, smooth, acuminate); number of enlarged scales between the eye and the ear (

); the presence or absence of enlarged crest scales on the body; the presence or absence and extent of large vertebral scales on the body and tail; the number and position of enlarged posttemporals and supratympanics (Figs. 3,4); size of scales bordering dorsal margin of the ear opening; size of scales in pretympanic region (pretympanics); the presence or absence of gap in the nuchal crest scale series; the size and condition of the flank scales (plate-like, small, keeled, smooth); number of keels on subdigital lamelae; relative size of ventral and dorsal scales; and the condition of preaxial lamellae of the third toe (

). Color pattern among 
Pseudoclaotes
varies tremendously both within and between species (

Manthey 
2010
) making it difficult to quantify particular components as diagnostic characters for comparisons across all species. However, dewlap color pattern is less variable and species specific. Dewlaps of males are generally more colorful than that of females, but in many species, females bear the same color characteristics as the males but to a lesser extent. Therefore, in species where males are unknown, the female color pattern is noted and used as a proxy for that of the male. Because sample sizes were small for many of the species in this analysis—including the new species being described—the utility of some of the characters purported to be diagnostic may break down with increases in samples sizes. Conversely, new diagnostic characters may also be discovered. Therefore, all taxonomic decisions are based on an integrative interpretation of both the morphological, color pattern, and molecular data. The above morphological and color pattern characters are scored across all species where possible in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 3.
Lateral view of the head of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(LSUDPC 9909) from Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular Malaysia illustrating descriptive scale characteristics. Photograph by Kurt Orion.
</p>
         <p>
Although the majority of the character states listed in 

Table 
3
come from 

Harvey 
et al.
(
2015
: 
230
), their data matrix is augmented here by filling in missing character states for some species; the modification of various counts for 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula
(Smith)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. floweri
(Boulenger)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. kingdonwardi
(Smith)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. kakhienensis
(Anderson)
</tp:taxon-name>
based on the examination of additional material; and the addition to the matrix of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. andamanensis
(Boulenger)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. austeniana
(Annandale)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaonanensis</tp:taxon-name>
(Chan-ard, Cota, Makchai, &amp; Laoteow, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis
Hallermann &amp; McGuire
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. saravacensis
Inger &amp; Steubing
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. ziegleri
Hallermann, Truong, Orlov
</tp:taxon-name>
, &amp; Ananjeva. The additional specimens examined are listed in the Appendix. Literature sources for additional character states are 

Anderson (
1879
)

, 

Annandale (
1908
)

, Chan-nard 
et al.
(
2008
); 

Boulenger (
1891
)

, 

Harikrishnan &amp; Vasdevan (
2013
)

, 

Hallermann, &amp; Böhme (
2000
)

, 

Hallermann 
et al.
(
2010
)

, 

Inger &amp; Steubing (
1994
)

, and 

Mahony (
2010
)

. 
LSUHC
refers to the La Sierra University Herpetological Collection, La Sierra University, Riverside, California, 
USA
; 
ZRC
refers to the Zoological Reference Collection at the Lee Kong Chian Natural History Museum, National University of 
Singapore
, 
Singapore
; 
CAS
refers to the California Academy of Sciences, San Francisco, California, 
USA
; 
TNHC
refers to the Texas Natural History Collection, Texas Memorial Museum, Austin, TX, 
USA
; 
THNHM
refers to the 
Thailand
Natural History Museum, National Science Museum, Khlong Luang, Pathum Thani, Bangkok; and LSUDPC refers to the La Sierra University Digital Photo Collection.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>
Although the monophyly of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
is not supported by the ML analysis (ML 
65
) it is supported by the Bayesian analysis (
BI0.95
). However, there is no significant support for any of the deeper nodes in the tree (

). The analyses do indicate that the Peninsular Malaysian species bearing different body scale and snout morphologies are likely to not form a monophyletic group but are only distantly related to one another. Support (1.00/ 
88
) does exists for a clade where 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is basal to the sister species (1.00/ 
80
) 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
and where 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
are sister species (1.00/ 
100
)—although the latter pair have a 
22
% uncorrected pairwise sequence divergence between them (

). The morphological and color pattern analyses support the molecular analyses in that 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
,
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
are discretely diagnosable from one another and from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
(Tables 3,4,5). Additionally, the morphological and color pattern analyses indicate that although 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
are more similar to each other than they are to any other species in Peninsular 
Malaysia
, they are discretely diagnosable from one another as well as differing from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
in having greatly enlarged, plate-like flank scales. Given the molecular, morphological, and color pattern data above, the three new populations are described below.
</p>
         <p>TABLE 3.
Distribution of characters states across the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
tympanistriga rhammanotus cybelidermus guttalineatus 
<tp:taxon-name>kingdonwardi</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>kakhienensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
poliani
</p>
         <p>
Postrostrals 

4 
–
7
5
4 
–
6

5 
–
7
3
or 
4
5 
–
7

4 
–
6
7
or 
8</p>
         <p>Interparietal No Yes Yes No Yes Yes No Variable</p>
         <p>
Cicrcumorbitals 

9 
–
13
9
or 
10
9 
–
13
9–
13 

7 
–10
9 
–
12
10
or 
11
10 
–
12
</p>
         <p>
Canthals 
5
or 
665
or 
6
5 
–
7

4 
–
6

4 
–
7
4
or 
56
or 
7</p>
         <p>
Superciliaries 

6 
–
8

5 
–
7

4 
–
7

5 
–
8

4 
–
6

5 
–
7

5 
–
7

5 
–
9
</p>
         <p>Scale between No No Yes/no No No/yes No/Yes No No</p>
         <p>rostral and nasal</p>
         <p>
Supralabials contacting nasal 
1
or 
22
0 
–
2

0 
–
2
1
or 
2211</p>
         <p>
Supralabials 

9 
–
11
9
7 
–
10
9
or 
10
6 
–
8
7
or 
8
6 
–
10
8
or 
9</p>
         <p>
Infralabials 

9 
–
11
8
7 
–
9

7 
–
10

6 
–
8

6 
–
8

7 
–
9
9
or 
10</p>
         <p>
Postmentals 

2 
–
5
4
or 
5
2 
–
5

2 
–
4
2
or 
3
1 
–
3
3
or 
41
or 
2</p>
         <p>
Gulars / / / / 
36
42 
–
48

40 
–
46

/
</p>
         <p>Gulars smooth or keeled Keeled Keeled Keeled Keeled Smooth Smooth Smooth Smooth</p>
         <p>Gulars granular or flat Flat Flat Flat Flat Flat Flat Flat Flat</p>
         <p>Transverse gular fold No No No No No Yes Weak Yes</p>
         <p>Antehumeral fold Yes Yes No No Yes Yes Weak Yes</p>
         <p>
Enlarged scales between 
3
or 
42
1 
–
4
2
or 
3
1 
–
3
2
or 
32
or 
3
1 
–
3

and ear
</p>
         <p>
Enlarged posttemporals 
111
or 
212
or 
3123
or 
4</p>
         <p>Enlarged supratympanic Yes Yes Yes Yes Yes Yes No Yes</p>
         <p>Enlarged postrictals No No Yes Yes No Yes/no No No</p>
         <p>
Nuchal crest 

4 
–
11
8
9 
–
13

10 
–12
8 
–
11

7 
–
13

5 
–
10

7 
–
9 in

nuchal crest 
2
or 
37
4 
–
7

4 
–
8

0 
–
2

0 
–
3

no 
3
or 
4</p>
         <p>Enlarged crest scales No Yes Yes Yes No No No No</p>
         <p>beyond midbody</p>
         <p>Flank scales keeled No Yes Yes Yes Yes Yes weak Yes</p>
         <p>Flank scales plate-like no No No No No No Yes No</p>
         <p>
Scales around midbody 
46–4051
51 
–
65

45 
–
55

42 
–
54

59 
–
66

41 
–
44

54 
–
62
</p>
         <p>Midventrals smaller than Yes Yes No Yes Yes Yes Yes Yes</p>
         <p>dorsals</p>
         <p>
finger lamellae 

22 
–
26
21
22 
–
29

22 
–
28

20 
–
24

20 
–
22

22 
–
28
18
toe lamellae 

26 
–
32
24
24 
–
30

26 
–
32

23 
–
27

23 
–
27

26 
–
30
23</p>
         <p>Preaxial lamellae No No Basally Basally Basally Yes No Serrate</p>
         <p>modified on toe III Fringe</p>
         <p>Unicarinate lamellae No No No No Variable Variable No No</p>
         <p>beneath distal phalanges</p>
         <p>
/HL 
60.8–
69.0 
64.5
60.5 
–
76.2

65.5 
–
76.8

68.4 
–
83.3

68.9 
–
81.5

54 
–
67

62.2 
–
73.7
</p>
         <p>Elbow &amp; knee patches No No No No No No No No dewlap color Same color as Brown with Light green Grayish blue No pigmented Longitudinal Yellow / venter White center with cyan lines patch stripes</p>
         <p>center</p>
         <p>……continued on the next page
Male dewlap color Purple Brown Purple Purple Yellow/White No color patch on purple
</p>
         <p>TABLE 3.
(Continued)
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>floweri</tp:taxon-name>microlepis<tp:taxon-name>brevipes</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>dringi</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>andamanensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>austeniana</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>khaonanensis</tp:taxon-name>
Postrostrals 4 
–
6
6 or 7
5 
–
7
5
4 
–
6 3 or 4
/Interparietal YesVariableVariable/Yes No/
Circumorbitals 10 
–
12
10
9 
–
13
/11 //Canthals 5 or 6
5 
–
7

5 
–
7
54 or 5 36Superciliaries 86 or 7
5 
–
7
/7 or 8 /8Scale(s) between Yes/noNoVariableNoYes NoYesrostral and nasalSupralabials contacting 1 or 210 or 1YesYes Yesyesnasal
Supralabials 8 
–
10
7 or 8
6 
–
10
89 or 10 5 or 68
Infralabials 9 
–
11

7 
–
9

7 
–
10
7 or 8
10 
–
12 7 or 8
9Postmentals 1 or 211 or 222 2/Gulars 42//// /AcuminateGulars smooth or keeled SmoothKeeledKeeledSmoothKeeled SmoothAcuminateGulars granular or flat flatFlatAcuminateFlatFlat FlatFlatTransverse gular fold YesYesYesNoNo NoNoAntehumeral fold YesNoYesNoYes YesYes
Enlarged scales between 2 
–
4

1 
–
4

1 
–
4
2
3 
–
5 4
1eye and earEnlarged posttemporals 111 or 2yesyes Yes1Enlarged supratympanics NoNoYes/noNoNo NoNoEnlarged postrictals NoNoNoNoNo NoNoNuchal crest 9
8 
–
10

7 
–
13
6
11 
–
14 7
9Gap in nuchal crest 3//NoNo NoNoEnlarged crest scales NoNoNoNoNo yesNobeyond midbodyFlank scales keeled YesWeakYesWeakNo WeakWeakFlank scales plate-like NoNoNoNoNo NoNoScales around midbody 44
71 
–
74

66 
–
76

48 
–
52

57 
–
62 51

72 
–
75
Ventrals smaller than dorsals YesNoNoYesYes /No
4th finger lamellae 21 
–
22
18 or 19
16 
–
21
20/ 19214th toe lamellae 24, 25
21 
–
25

20 
–
27
26
27 
–
30 31
27Preaxial lamellae SerrateSerrateSerrateNoYes /Nomodified on toe III FringeFringeFringeUnicarinate lamellae NoNoNoNoNo /Nobeneath distal phalangesHW/lHL 67.5
62.2 
–
70.3

68.1 
–
73.6
0.510.59 //Elbow &amp; knee patches NoNoYesNo/ NoNo</p>
         <p>throat</p>
         <p>
……continued on the next page 
<tp:taxon-name>saravacensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>ziegleri</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            <tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            <tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>TABLE 3.
(Continued)
</p>
         <p>Postrostrals /7
5 
–
7
7
6 
–
8
3Interparietal //YesYesYesNo/yesCicrcumorbitals //
11 
–
14
119 or 1010Canthals 4
5 
–
7

4 
–
6
554 or 5Supraciliaries //
6 
–
8

7 
–
10

7 
–
10

5 
–
7
Scale(s) between YesNoYesYesYesnorostral and nasalSuperlabials contacting YesYesYesYesYesyes</p>
         <p>
Supralabials 
7
8 
–
11

8 
–1098
or 
96
or 
7
Infralabials 
7
7 
–
11

8 
–1087
or 
86
or 
7
Postmentals 
22
or 
33
or 
4442
or 
3
Gulars 

55 
–
69
47
40 
–
45
47
or 
48
Gulars smooth or keeled Keeled Smooth Weak Smooth Smooth Smooth Gulars granular or flat Flat Flat Flat Flat Flat Flat Transverse gular fold No No No Weak No Weak Antehumeral fold No / Yes Weak Weak Weak Enlarged scales between 
322
or 
323
or 
42</p>
         <p>and ear</p>
         <p>
Enlarged posttemporals 
2
no 
1111
Enlarged posttympanics yes / No no No No Enlarged postrictals No No No No No No Nuchal crest 
76
or 
7
5 
–
9
8
6 
–
8

7 
–
9
</p>
         <p>in nuchal crest No No No No No No Enlarged crest scales No No No yes Yes No beyond midbody</p>
         <p>
Flank scales keeled Weak Smooth Weak Keeled Weak Weak Flank scales plate-like No No No No No Yes Scales around midbody 
68
57 
–
64

52 
–
55
51
52 
–
58

35 
–
38

Ventrals smaller than / Yes Yes Yes Yes Yes dorsals
</p>
         <p>
finger lamellae 
16
/ 

17 
–
20
19
19 
–
21
22
or 
23</p>
         <p>
toe lamellae 
2024
22 
–
25
23
22 
–
26
26
or 
27
Preaxial lamellae / Yes No Enlarged and spinose Enlarged and rounded No modified on toe III
</p>
         <p>Unicarinate lamellae No No No No No No beneath distal phalanges</p>
         <p>
/lHL 
0.590.54
0.50 
–
0.65
0.52
0.50 
–
0.54
0.62
Elbow &amp; knee patches No No No No No No
</p>
         <p>dewlap color Black speckles Blue Yellow/Purple Lime-green w/ yellow Cyan w/ purple center Yellow</p>
         <p>center</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Taxonomy</title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
P. 
rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Psedocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Psedocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dragons in the mist: three new species of Pseudocalotes Fitzinger (Squamata: Agamidae) from the sky island archipelago of Peninsular Malaysia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4136.3.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/531CFF91FFB4FFA52D34B822017C6822</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4136.3.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Drogon’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Rhaegal’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Viserion’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult male 
LSUHC12223
collected on 
24
March 
2015
by L. Lee Grismer, Evan S. H. Quah, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brando R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos at 
2030
hrs 
1 km
south of Air Terjun Jeriau, Fraser’s Hill, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(
3
° 
43.283
N
101
° 
43.035
E

; 
1066 m
in elevation).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a flat rostrum; seven postrostrals; an interparietal; 
11
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one scale between the rostral and nasal; nine supralabials; eight infralabials; 
10
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; five or six sublabials; five or six chinshields; 
47
smooth, wide, gular scales; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; enlarged upper and lower posttemporals; a single enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; three large scales bordering the dorsal margin of the ear opening; large pretympanic scales; eight scales in the nuchal crest not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to the tip of the tail; keeled and non-plate-like scales on flanks; 
51
midbody scales; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19
subdigital scales on the fourth finger; 
23
subdigital scales on the fourth toe; preaxial scales on third toe enlarged and spinose; subdigital scales not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.52
; HL/SVL 
0.31
; no elbow or knee patches; and a male dewlap color of lime-green bearing a central yellow spot. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult male SVL 
91.4 mm
; head relatively large with a somewhat elongate flat snout, subtriangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.52
; HL/SVL 
0.31
; interorbital region flat; rostrum sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of five large canthal scales; supraorbital scales slightly enlarged, keeled; a single scale separating rostral and nasal scale; single row of 
11
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region, scales largest posteriorly; eight, flat, imbricate superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; short series of two enlarged, acuminate, postorbital scales extending to above anterior margin of tympanum; dorsal, head scales acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, posteriorly by seven smaller scales; external nares set in slightly elevated single, rectangular, large, nasal scale; five enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region forming a Y-shaped series with two larger, keeled scales on each side of midline; parietal, occipital, and upper postorbital region covered with slightly enlarged, elevated, acuminate to keeled scales; an enlarged parietal scale on each side of midline bordered by a clump of four, contiguous, enlarged, acuminate, occipital scales; interparietal small, lacking eyespot; temporal scales unequal with small scales intermixed with enlarged, weakly keeled scales; single, raised, enlarged, keeled scale in temporal region followed by a single, enlarged, spinose, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked; auditory meatus bodered dorsally by three large supratympanic scales; nine (R,L) supralabials; 
10
postnasal-suborbital scales; mental triangular, larger than adjacent infralabials; two larger postmentals, separated medially and forming first of a series of five(R) or six(L) enlarged chinshields that are separated from infralabials by one anteriorly and two posteriorly rows of smaller scales; eight (R,L) infralabials; gular scales flat, wide, directed posteromedially, 
47
at midline; dewlap small; and transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak; nuchal crest composed of eight, large, contiguous, lanceolate scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composing a single row of slightly enlarged keeled scales extending to base of tail; body laterally compressed; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse, and posteroventrally oriented rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales; ventrals same size as dorsals; 
51
scales around midbody; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs slender, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, slightly more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; preaxial lamellae on toe III enlarged and spinose (

); 
19
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
23
lamellae beneath fourth toe; tail laterally compressed, slightly swollen at base, covered with keeled scales, vertebral row forming a serrate, dorsal ridge, 
1.89
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).
Dark phase—
Dorsal ground color of head, body, limbs, and tail very dark-grey; labials cyan; row of white scales between supralabials and orbit; scattered white spots on anterior portion of flanks and sides of neck; four wide, diffuse, darker, transverse, dorsal bands between limb insertions extending to ventral edge of flanks; one band in pelvic region; nine bands on tail; limbs generally immaculate, dark-grey; groups of white scales in lateral margins of gular region; anterior gular region dull-white bearing dark-brown oblique lines; dewlap dingy lime-green with a dingy yellow center; ventral surfaces, beige, immaculate. 
Light phase—
Dorsal body pattern same as dark phase but ground color a much lighter grey; dark dorsal bands prominent against dullwhite interspace; cyan labials faded; gular region whitish bearing light-brown, oblique lines; dewlap lime-green with yellow center, dewlap scales bearing brownish centers; venter whitish, immaculate.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from the 
type
locality 
1 km
south of Air Terjun Jeriau, Fraser’s Hill, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

). It is expected however to be found further south to at least Genting Highlands.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>drogon</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the dark dragon, Drogon—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
            <p>Natural history.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
was collected at night at 
2000
hrs while sleeping on a thin, horizontal branch of small tree in the vicinity of a small stream in hill dipterocarp forest (

). The adult male was in the light color phase at the time of collection but became much darker during the day (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
by having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center and the unique combination of numerous other characteristics (

Table 
3
). With the exception of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
most closely resembles the other geographically proximate Thai-Malay Peninsula species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and 

P. dr i ng i. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from the former two species by a number of characteristics (

Table 
3
), the most notable of which is the lack of enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks (compare 

with Figs. 10,12). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 
104.5 mm
; five as opposed to six canthals; eight as opposed to nine infralabials; smooth as opposed to acuminate gular scales; 
51
as opposed to 
72–75
scales around midbody; ventral scales being smaller as opposed to being larger than dorsal scales; 
23
as opposed to 
27
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a purple dewlap (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 81.0 mm; 
11
versus 
11–14
circumorbitals; smooth as opposed to weakly keeled gular scales; males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a yellow dewlap with a purple, horizontal, centrally positioned marking (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is separated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 
70.3 mm
; seven versus five postrostrals; the rostral and nasal scale not contacting as opposed to contacting; four as opposed to two postmentals; a weak, antehumeral fold as opposed to lacking a fold; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a purple dewlap (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having 
11
as opposed nine or 
10
circumorbitals; 
10
as opposed to 
11
or 
12
postnasal-suborbitals; 
47
as opposed to 
40–45
gular scales; a row of two versus three or four enlarged scales between the ear and eye; large as opposed to small pretympanic scales; a flat versus a convex rostrum; having as opposed to lacking enlarged vertebral scales on the tail; and 
51
versus 
52–58
midbody scales; enlarged, spinose, preaxial scales on the third toe as opposed to enlarged, rounded preaxial scales on the third toe; longer head (HL/ SVL = 
0.31
versus 
0.28–0.30
); and a row of white scales extending from the nasal scale to just beyond the posterior border of the orbit as opposed to a suborbital white patch (

Table 
4
). Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>Sex PostrostralsLSUHC 12223 Holotype Male 7LSUHC 12000 Paratype Female 8LSUHC 12178 Holotype Female 8LSUHC 12179 Paratype Female 6Interparietal Circumorbitals Canthalsyes 11 5yes 10 5yes 9 5yes 10 5Superciliaries Scale between rostral and nasal Rostrum8 1 Flat10 2 Convex8 1,2 Convex7 1 ConvexSupralabial-nasal contact Supralabials InfralabialsYes 9 8Yes 9 8Yes 9 7Yes 8 8Postnasal-suborbitals Postmentals Chinshields10 4 5,611,11 4 5,612,11 4 5,412,11 4 DamagedGulars Gulars wide or granular Gulars smooth or keeled47 Wide Smooth42 Wide Smooth40 Wide Smooth45 Wide SmoothTransverse gular fold Antehumeral fold Enlarged scales between eye and earWeak Weak 2No Weak 3No Weak 3,4No Weak 4Enlarged posttemporals Posttympanics modified Enlarged supratympanics1 0 11 0 11 0 11 0 1Pretympanic scales large Enlarged postrictals RostrumYes 0 FlatNo 0 ConvexNo 0 ConvexNo 0 ConvexNuchal crest Gap in crest Nuchal crest scales on body8 No No7 No No6 No No8 No No</p>
            <p>
......continued on the next page 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12178
collected on 
18
March 
2015
by L. Lee Grismer, Evan S. H. Quah, Shahrul Anuar, Mohd A. Muin, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brandon R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos at 
2030
hrs at Robinson Falls, Cameron Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(04° 
43.283
N
101
° 
23.129
E

; 
1411 m
in elevation).
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12179
bears the same locality collecting data as the 
holotype
. Adult female 
LSUHC12000
bears the same collecting locality and collectors but was collected on 
4
September 
2014
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a convex rostrum; 
6–8
postrostrals; an interparietal; nine or 
10
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one or two scales between the rostral and nasal scales; eight or nine supralabials; seven or eight infralabials; 
11
or 
12
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; 
4–6
chinshields; 
40–45
smooth, wide, gular scales; no transverse gular fold; weak antehumeral fold; three or four enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; no large scales bordering the upper margin of the ear opening or in the pretympanic region; 
6–8
enlarged nuchal crest scales not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to base of tail; weakly keeled, non-plate-like scales on flanks; 
52–58
scales around midbody; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19–21
subdigital lamellae on fourth finger; 
22–26
subdigital lamellae on fourth toe; preaxial scales on third toe enlarged and rounded; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.50–0.54
; HL/SVL 
0.28–0.30
; no elbow or knee patches; and female dewlap bearing a purple base. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult female SVL 
83.7 mm
; head relatively large subtriangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.54
; HL/SVL 
0.30
; interorbital region flat; rostrum convex, sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of five large canthal scales; supraorbital scales slightly enlarged, keeled; single row of nine or 
10
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region; eight flat, imbricate to subimbrictae, superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; short row of three (R) four (L) enlarged, acuminate, postorbital scales extend to above anterior margin of tympanum; dorsal, head scales acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, posteriorly by eight smaller scales; external nares in slightly elevated, rectangular, large, nasal scale; seven enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region forming a Y-shaped series; parietal and occipital regions covered with enlarged, elevated, acuminate to keeled scales; an enlarged parietal scale on each side of midline; interparietals small, irregularly shaped, centralmost bearing a small eyespot; temporal scales unequal with small scales intermixed with enlarged, weakly keeled scales; one, enlarged, keeled, scale in temporal region followed by a single, enlarged, spinose, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked, not bordered dorsally by large supratympanic scales; nine (R,L) supralabials; 
12
(R), 
11
(L) large, postnasal-suborbital scales; mental triangular, larger than adjacent infralabials; four larger postmentals, separated medially by two small scales and forming first of a series of five (R) four (L) enlarged chinshields separated from infralabials by one anteriorly and two posteriorly rows of smaller scales; seven (R,L) infralabials; gular scales wide, smooth, directed posteromedially, 
40
at midline; dewlap small; transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak.
</p>
            <p>
Nuchal crest composed of six, large, contiguous, lanceolate scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composing a single row of slightly enlarged, keeled vertebral scales extending to base of tail; body laterally compressed; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse, and posteroventrally oriented rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales; ventrals same size as dorsals; 
52
scales around midbody; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs slender, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, slightly more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; preaxial lamellae on toe III enlarged and rounded (

); 
20
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
25
lamellae beneath fourth toe; and tail laterally compressed, slightly swollen at base, covered with keeled scales but lacking an enlarged vertebral row, 
1.67
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).

Dorsal ground color of head, body, and limbs, brown, mottled with shades of slightly darker brown; linear patch of light-colored suborbital scales beneath eye; four very faint, diffuse, dark bands between forelimb and hind limb insertions not extending to base of flanks; lighter interspace between bands mottled; scattered greenish scales in postorbital, temporal, lower flank, and pelvic regions; scales of forearms greenish with dark bands; seven dark caudal bands anteriorly separated by dull-green interspaces, dark bands fade on posterior one-third of tail; gular region beige with irregularly shaped, brown, thin, submandibular bands; gular pouch small, base of pouch cyan with purple center.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

).
LSUHC12179
very closely approximates the 
holotype
in overall body coloration and pattern, except for being lighter overall. 
LSUHC12000
bears the same general color pattern as the 
holotype
and 
LSUHC12178
but differs greatly from them in being overall more green in coloration and having four dark, diffuse, dorsal bands between the forelimb and hind limb insertions that are more prominent. Additionally, the tail is distinctly banded for nearly its entire length. Variation in squamation is presented in 

Table 
4
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from Robinson Falls, Cameron Highlands, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

) but is expected to range more widely along the Banjaran Titiwangsa.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the greenish dragon, Rhaegal—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
            <p>Natural history.
All 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
were collected at night between at 
2000
and 
2300
hrs while sleeping on thin, horizontal branches of small trees in the vicinity of a river flowing through the hill dipterocarp forest at Robinson Falls (

). All were gravid females collected during mid-March or mid- September, indicating that this species may breed year-round.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
by having a cyan dewlap with a purple center (females) and the unique combination of numerous other characteristics (

Table 
3
). With the exception of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
most closely resembles the other geographically proximate Thai-Malay Peninsula species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, by several characteristics the most notable of which is the lack of enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks (Figs. 9,10). From 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
85.2 mm
versus 
104.5 mm
; five as opposed to six canthals; seven or eight as opposed to nine infralabials; smooth as opposed to acuminate gular scales; three or four versus one enlarged scale between the eye and the ear; enlarged vertebral scales extending beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; 
52–58
as opposed to 
72–75
scales around midbody; ventral scales being smaller as opposed to being larger than dorsal scales; 
22–26
as opposed to 
27
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, rounded, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and having a cyan dewlap with a purple center (female) versus a purple dewlap in males (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having nine or 
10
versus 
11–14
circumorbitals; 
40–45
versus 
55–69
gulars; smooth as opposed to weakly keeled gular scales; enlarged vertebral scales extending beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; preaxial scales on third toe bearing enlarged, rounded, scales versus being unmodified; having a cyan dewlap with a purple tip (females) versus a yellow dewlap with a purple, horizontal, centrally positioned marking (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is separated by having a maximum SVL of 
85.2 mm
versus 
70.3 mm
; 
6–8
versus five postrostrals; four as opposed to two postmentals; a weak, antehumeral fold as opposed to lacking a fold; having three or four versus two enlarged scales between eye and ear; enlarged vertebral scales extend beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; 
52–58
scales around midbody versus 
48–52
; 
23
versus 
26
fourth toe subdigital lamellae; and having a cyan dewlap with a purple tip (females) versus a purple dewlap in males (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having nine or 
10
as opposed to 
11
circumorbitals; 
11
or 
12
as opposed to 
10
postnasalsuborbitals; 
40–45
as opposed to 
47
gular scales; a row of three or four versus two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; lacking as opposed to having three large supratympanic scales; pretympanic scales small as opposed to large; a convex versus a flat rostrum; lacking versus having enlarged vertebral scales on the tail; 
52–58
versus 
51
midbody scales; having enlarged, rounded, preaxial scales on the third toe as opposed to enlarged preaxial scales on the third toe being spinose; shorter snout (HL/SVL = 
0.28–0.30
versus 
0.31
); and having a white patch of suborbital scales as opposed to lacking a white patch of suborbital scales (

Table 
4
). Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12227
collected on 
26
March 
2015
by Evan S. H. Quah at 
1000
hrs crossing the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(03° 
26.166
N
101
° 
47.021
E

; 
1754 m
in elevation).
</p>
            <p>Paratype
.

Adult male 
LSUHC12141
found dead on the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(03° 
26.12
N
101
° 
47.345
E

; 
1750 m
in elevation) by L. Lee Grismer, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brandon R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be separated from all other species of 
Psuedocalotes
by having a combination of three postrostrals; 
10
circumorbitals; four or five canthals; 
5–7
superciliaries; rostral and nasal in contact; supralabials contacting nasal; six or seven supralabials; seven or eight infralabials; two or three postmentals; three enlarged chinshields; 
47
or 
48
smooth, flat, gular scales; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; 
7–9
nuchal crest scales lacking gaps and not extending beyond midbody; weakly keeled and plate-like scales on flanks; 
35–38
scales around midbody; ventrals smaller than dorsals; 
22
or 
23
subdigital lamellae on fourth finger; 
26
or 
27
subdigital lamellae on fourth toe; preaxial scales on third not modified; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.62
; no white marking below the eye; dewlap in males yellow; and no elbow or knee patches. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult female SVL 
71 mm
; head relatively large, triangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.62
; HL/SVL 
0.30
; interorbital and frontal regions flat; snout not elongate but convex, sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of four scales; supraorbital scales enlarged, keeled; single row of 
10
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region, posteriormost of series enlarged and tuberculate; five, flat, imbricate superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; three enlarged postorbital scales, posteriormost scale acuminate, keeled; dorsal, head scales weakly acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, dorsolaterally by nasal scale, and posteriorly by three smaller scales; external nares in slightly elevated single, rectangular, large, nasal scale; three enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region; parietal, occipital, and upper postorbital region covered with slightly enlarged, irregularly shaped, weakly acuminate scales; an enlarged, keeled parietal scale on right side of midline followed by a large, raised occipital scale; enlarged parietal on left side of midline broken up and adjacent occipital scale not as large or raised as the corresponding scale on right; interparietal small, bearing eyespot; temporal scales irregular in size; single enlarged, raised postorbital scale; two, raised, enlarged, keeled, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked, scales on dorsal margin not enlarged; six (R,L) supralabials; nine (R,L) postnasal-supraorbital scales; mental triangular; two large postmentals in medial point contact forming first in a series of three enlarged chinshields separated from infralabials by three anteriorly and 
10
posteriorly rows of smaller scales; 
7
(R), 
8
(L) infralabials; gular scales smooth, flat, directed posteromedially, 
47
at midline; dewlap small; transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak.
</p>
            <p>
Seven, large, lanceolate nuchal scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composed of a single row of keeled, slightly enlarged scales that extend onto base of tail where they are largest; body round in cross-section; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales, plate-like; ventrals smaller than dorsals; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs moderate in stature, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; 
22
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
27
lamellae beneath fourth toe; preaxial scales of third toe unmodified; tail laterally compressed, not swollen at base, covered with keeled scales, 
1.68
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).

Dorsal ground color of body and tail dull yellow; labials, lateral regions of throat, proximal region of brachia and anterior portion of flanks white; ground color of top of head light-green, randomly mottled with small, irregularly shaped, dark markings; four very faint, wide, diffuse, dark vertebral patches between forelimb and hind limb insertions extending onto dorsal margins of flanks; ground color of forelimbs yellow-green, mottled with darkly edged scales; ground color of hind limbs dingy green, limbs faintly banded; wide, diffuse faint bands on anterior region of tail fading posteriorly; gular region beige, bearing a series of faint, diffuse, obliquely oriented, brown stripes in lateral margins; gular pouch yellow; subcaudal region gray; rest of venter beige, generally immaculate; bottoms of hands and feet slightly darker.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

).

The male 
paratype
(
LSUHC12141
) resembles the female 
holotype
(
LSUHC12227
) in aspects of color pattern but the overall ground color is brown, not dull-yellow. It also has a greatly swollen tail base. Differences in scalation are presented in 

Table 
5
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

).
</p>
            <p>LSUHCLSUHCLSUHCLSUHCLSUHCZRCFMNHEtymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the yellowish dragon, Viserion—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Natural history.
The 
holotype
(
LSUHC12227
) was collected during mid-morning at 
1000
hrs under broken cloud cover as it was crossing the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands. The 
paratype
(
LSUHC12141
) was found freshly killed on the same road at 
1500
hrs. This short stretch of road runs along the crest of Ulu Kali and winds through a mossy cloud forest between 
1,700
and 
1,800 m
in elevation (

). The 
holotype
was a gravid female that had just ovulated indicating that the reproductive season of this species extends through March.
</p>
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is readily differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
except it sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
by having enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks. It can be separated from 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
by having larger, plate-like scales on the flanks (compare 

and 

) as evidenced by having fewer midbody scale rows (
35–38
versus 
41–44
); having more gular scales (
47
or 
48
versus 
40–46
); fewer subdigital lamellae on the fourth finger (
22
or 
23
versus 
22–28
); and fewer subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe (
26
or 
27
versus 
26–30
) (

Table 
5
). There appears to be less yellow coloration in the gular region of 
P. f l a v i g ul a
in that the yellow does not extend onto the region of the throat anterior to the forelimb insertions as it does in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and the skin between the scales is white in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
as opposed to being yellow in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(Figs. 10,12). Additionally, these two species share a 
22
% uncorrected pairwise sequence divergence between them. Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Variation in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
Smith (
1924
)

described 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
from a single specimen collected from the mossy forest along Brinchang Trail in Cameron Highlands (

). Smith’s (
1924
) description was rather brief but was significantly augmented by 

Grismer (
2011
)

with the examination of another specimen collected from Brinchang Trail (
ZRC2.5162
) reported by (

Leong 
2001
) and an additional specimen from Tanah Rata (
FMNH143903
). Meristic variation among five of the six known specimens is presented in 

Table 
5
. The color pattern in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
is quite variable (

). The dark, dorsal bands range from brown to black and from to distinct and diffuse to barely visible. The light-colored upper lip, lateral throat and proximal section of the brachium can range from immaculate white to lime-green and it may or may not extend onto the anterior portion of the flanks. There is considerable variation in overall ground color that ranges from dull-white to lime-green which we attribute to substrate matching (

).
</p>
            <p>
We obtained a series of close-up photographs of a juvenile male 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
(
THNHM25890
) collected at 
1400 m
in elevation from a montane region in the Hala-Bala Wildlife Sanctuary, Betong District, Yala Province, 
Thailand
along the Thai-Malay border. This habitat is contiguous with the Banjaran Titiwangsa and the data taken from the photographs—most notably the color pattern and the enlarged, plate-like flank scales (

)—clearly align this specimen with the 
flavigula-viserion
clade but until the specimen can be examined it will be recognized here as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <p>LSUHC 12223 HolotypeLSUHC 12000 ParatypeLSUHC 12178 HolotypeLSUHC 12179 ParatypeEnlarged vertebral scales on tailYesNoNoNoFlank scales keeledWeakWeakWeakWeakFlank scales plate-likeNoNoNoNoMidbody scales51545258Midventrals smaller than dorsalsSame sizeSame sizeYesYes4th finger lamellae191920214th toe lamellae23222526Preaxial lamellae modified on toe IIIEnlarged/spinoseEnlarged/roundedEnlarged/roundedEnlarged/roundedUnicarinate lamellae on toesNoNoNoNoSuborbital white patchNoYesYesYes</p>
      <p>Broken white line extending from nares Yes to beyond posterior margin of eyeNoNoNoHW/HL 0.520.540.540.50Body bands extend to base of flanks YesNoNoNo</p>
      <p>Male dewlap colorLime-green with Cyan w/ purple yellow center center (female)Cyan w/ purple center (female)Cyan w/ purple center (female)HL/SVL0.31 0.290.300.28SVL91.4 75.183.785.2TL173 123140140TL/SVL1.89 1.631.671.64</p>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
P. 
rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Psedocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Psedocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dragons in the mist: three new species of Pseudocalotes Fitzinger (Squamata: Agamidae) from the sky island archipelago of Peninsular Malaysia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4136.3.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/531CFF91FFB4FFA52D34B822017C6822</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4136.3.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Drogon’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Rhaegal’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Viserion’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult male 
LSUHC12223
collected on 
24
March 
2015
by L. Lee Grismer, Evan S. H. Quah, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brando R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos at 
2030
hrs 
1 km
south of Air Terjun Jeriau, Fraser’s Hill, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(
3
° 
43.283
N
101
° 
43.035
E

; 
1066 m
in elevation).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a flat rostrum; seven postrostrals; an interparietal; 
11
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one scale between the rostral and nasal; nine supralabials; eight infralabials; 
10
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; five or six sublabials; five or six chinshields; 
47
smooth, wide, gular scales; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; enlarged upper and lower posttemporals; a single enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; three large scales bordering the dorsal margin of the ear opening; large pretympanic scales; eight scales in the nuchal crest not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to the tip of the tail; keeled and non-plate-like scales on flanks; 
51
midbody scales; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19
subdigital scales on the fourth finger; 
23
subdigital scales on the fourth toe; preaxial scales on third toe enlarged and spinose; subdigital scales not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.52
; HL/SVL 
0.31
; no elbow or knee patches; and a male dewlap color of lime-green bearing a central yellow spot. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult male SVL 
91.4 mm
; head relatively large with a somewhat elongate flat snout, subtriangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.52
; HL/SVL 
0.31
; interorbital region flat; rostrum sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of five large canthal scales; supraorbital scales slightly enlarged, keeled; a single scale separating rostral and nasal scale; single row of 
11
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region, scales largest posteriorly; eight, flat, imbricate superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; short series of two enlarged, acuminate, postorbital scales extending to above anterior margin of tympanum; dorsal, head scales acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, posteriorly by seven smaller scales; external nares set in slightly elevated single, rectangular, large, nasal scale; five enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region forming a Y-shaped series with two larger, keeled scales on each side of midline; parietal, occipital, and upper postorbital region covered with slightly enlarged, elevated, acuminate to keeled scales; an enlarged parietal scale on each side of midline bordered by a clump of four, contiguous, enlarged, acuminate, occipital scales; interparietal small, lacking eyespot; temporal scales unequal with small scales intermixed with enlarged, weakly keeled scales; single, raised, enlarged, keeled scale in temporal region followed by a single, enlarged, spinose, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked; auditory meatus bodered dorsally by three large supratympanic scales; nine (R,L) supralabials; 
10
postnasal-suborbital scales; mental triangular, larger than adjacent infralabials; two larger postmentals, separated medially and forming first of a series of five(R) or six(L) enlarged chinshields that are separated from infralabials by one anteriorly and two posteriorly rows of smaller scales; eight (R,L) infralabials; gular scales flat, wide, directed posteromedially, 
47
at midline; dewlap small; and transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak; nuchal crest composed of eight, large, contiguous, lanceolate scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composing a single row of slightly enlarged keeled scales extending to base of tail; body laterally compressed; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse, and posteroventrally oriented rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales; ventrals same size as dorsals; 
51
scales around midbody; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs slender, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, slightly more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; preaxial lamellae on toe III enlarged and spinose (

); 
19
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
23
lamellae beneath fourth toe; tail laterally compressed, slightly swollen at base, covered with keeled scales, vertebral row forming a serrate, dorsal ridge, 
1.89
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).
Dark phase—
Dorsal ground color of head, body, limbs, and tail very dark-grey; labials cyan; row of white scales between supralabials and orbit; scattered white spots on anterior portion of flanks and sides of neck; four wide, diffuse, darker, transverse, dorsal bands between limb insertions extending to ventral edge of flanks; one band in pelvic region; nine bands on tail; limbs generally immaculate, dark-grey; groups of white scales in lateral margins of gular region; anterior gular region dull-white bearing dark-brown oblique lines; dewlap dingy lime-green with a dingy yellow center; ventral surfaces, beige, immaculate. 
Light phase—
Dorsal body pattern same as dark phase but ground color a much lighter grey; dark dorsal bands prominent against dullwhite interspace; cyan labials faded; gular region whitish bearing light-brown, oblique lines; dewlap lime-green with yellow center, dewlap scales bearing brownish centers; venter whitish, immaculate.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from the 
type
locality 
1 km
south of Air Terjun Jeriau, Fraser’s Hill, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

). It is expected however to be found further south to at least Genting Highlands.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>drogon</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the dark dragon, Drogon—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
            <p>Natural history.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
was collected at night at 
2000
hrs while sleeping on a thin, horizontal branch of small tree in the vicinity of a small stream in hill dipterocarp forest (

). The adult male was in the light color phase at the time of collection but became much darker during the day (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
by having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center and the unique combination of numerous other characteristics (

Table 
3
). With the exception of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
most closely resembles the other geographically proximate Thai-Malay Peninsula species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and 

P. dr i ng i. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from the former two species by a number of characteristics (

Table 
3
), the most notable of which is the lack of enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks (compare 

with Figs. 10,12). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 
104.5 mm
; five as opposed to six canthals; eight as opposed to nine infralabials; smooth as opposed to acuminate gular scales; 
51
as opposed to 
72–75
scales around midbody; ventral scales being smaller as opposed to being larger than dorsal scales; 
23
as opposed to 
27
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a purple dewlap (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 81.0 mm; 
11
versus 
11–14
circumorbitals; smooth as opposed to weakly keeled gular scales; males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a yellow dewlap with a purple, horizontal, centrally positioned marking (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is separated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 
70.3 mm
; seven versus five postrostrals; the rostral and nasal scale not contacting as opposed to contacting; four as opposed to two postmentals; a weak, antehumeral fold as opposed to lacking a fold; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a purple dewlap (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having 
11
as opposed nine or 
10
circumorbitals; 
10
as opposed to 
11
or 
12
postnasal-suborbitals; 
47
as opposed to 
40–45
gular scales; a row of two versus three or four enlarged scales between the ear and eye; large as opposed to small pretympanic scales; a flat versus a convex rostrum; having as opposed to lacking enlarged vertebral scales on the tail; and 
51
versus 
52–58
midbody scales; enlarged, spinose, preaxial scales on the third toe as opposed to enlarged, rounded preaxial scales on the third toe; longer head (HL/ SVL = 
0.31
versus 
0.28–0.30
); and a row of white scales extending from the nasal scale to just beyond the posterior border of the orbit as opposed to a suborbital white patch (

Table 
4
). Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>Sex PostrostralsLSUHC 12223 Holotype Male 7LSUHC 12000 Paratype Female 8LSUHC 12178 Holotype Female 8LSUHC 12179 Paratype Female 6Interparietal Circumorbitals Canthalsyes 11 5yes 10 5yes 9 5yes 10 5Superciliaries Scale between rostral and nasal Rostrum8 1 Flat10 2 Convex8 1,2 Convex7 1 ConvexSupralabial-nasal contact Supralabials InfralabialsYes 9 8Yes 9 8Yes 9 7Yes 8 8Postnasal-suborbitals Postmentals Chinshields10 4 5,611,11 4 5,612,11 4 5,412,11 4 DamagedGulars Gulars wide or granular Gulars smooth or keeled47 Wide Smooth42 Wide Smooth40 Wide Smooth45 Wide SmoothTransverse gular fold Antehumeral fold Enlarged scales between eye and earWeak Weak 2No Weak 3No Weak 3,4No Weak 4Enlarged posttemporals Posttympanics modified Enlarged supratympanics1 0 11 0 11 0 11 0 1Pretympanic scales large Enlarged postrictals RostrumYes 0 FlatNo 0 ConvexNo 0 ConvexNo 0 ConvexNuchal crest Gap in crest Nuchal crest scales on body8 No No7 No No6 No No8 No No</p>
            <p>
......continued on the next page 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12178
collected on 
18
March 
2015
by L. Lee Grismer, Evan S. H. Quah, Shahrul Anuar, Mohd A. Muin, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brandon R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos at 
2030
hrs at Robinson Falls, Cameron Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(04° 
43.283
N
101
° 
23.129
E

; 
1411 m
in elevation).
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12179
bears the same locality collecting data as the 
holotype
. Adult female 
LSUHC12000
bears the same collecting locality and collectors but was collected on 
4
September 
2014
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a convex rostrum; 
6–8
postrostrals; an interparietal; nine or 
10
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one or two scales between the rostral and nasal scales; eight or nine supralabials; seven or eight infralabials; 
11
or 
12
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; 
4–6
chinshields; 
40–45
smooth, wide, gular scales; no transverse gular fold; weak antehumeral fold; three or four enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; no large scales bordering the upper margin of the ear opening or in the pretympanic region; 
6–8
enlarged nuchal crest scales not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to base of tail; weakly keeled, non-plate-like scales on flanks; 
52–58
scales around midbody; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19–21
subdigital lamellae on fourth finger; 
22–26
subdigital lamellae on fourth toe; preaxial scales on third toe enlarged and rounded; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.50–0.54
; HL/SVL 
0.28–0.30
; no elbow or knee patches; and female dewlap bearing a purple base. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult female SVL 
83.7 mm
; head relatively large subtriangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.54
; HL/SVL 
0.30
; interorbital region flat; rostrum convex, sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of five large canthal scales; supraorbital scales slightly enlarged, keeled; single row of nine or 
10
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region; eight flat, imbricate to subimbrictae, superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; short row of three (R) four (L) enlarged, acuminate, postorbital scales extend to above anterior margin of tympanum; dorsal, head scales acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, posteriorly by eight smaller scales; external nares in slightly elevated, rectangular, large, nasal scale; seven enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region forming a Y-shaped series; parietal and occipital regions covered with enlarged, elevated, acuminate to keeled scales; an enlarged parietal scale on each side of midline; interparietals small, irregularly shaped, centralmost bearing a small eyespot; temporal scales unequal with small scales intermixed with enlarged, weakly keeled scales; one, enlarged, keeled, scale in temporal region followed by a single, enlarged, spinose, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked, not bordered dorsally by large supratympanic scales; nine (R,L) supralabials; 
12
(R), 
11
(L) large, postnasal-suborbital scales; mental triangular, larger than adjacent infralabials; four larger postmentals, separated medially by two small scales and forming first of a series of five (R) four (L) enlarged chinshields separated from infralabials by one anteriorly and two posteriorly rows of smaller scales; seven (R,L) infralabials; gular scales wide, smooth, directed posteromedially, 
40
at midline; dewlap small; transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak.
</p>
            <p>
Nuchal crest composed of six, large, contiguous, lanceolate scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composing a single row of slightly enlarged, keeled vertebral scales extending to base of tail; body laterally compressed; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse, and posteroventrally oriented rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales; ventrals same size as dorsals; 
52
scales around midbody; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs slender, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, slightly more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; preaxial lamellae on toe III enlarged and rounded (

); 
20
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
25
lamellae beneath fourth toe; and tail laterally compressed, slightly swollen at base, covered with keeled scales but lacking an enlarged vertebral row, 
1.67
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).

Dorsal ground color of head, body, and limbs, brown, mottled with shades of slightly darker brown; linear patch of light-colored suborbital scales beneath eye; four very faint, diffuse, dark bands between forelimb and hind limb insertions not extending to base of flanks; lighter interspace between bands mottled; scattered greenish scales in postorbital, temporal, lower flank, and pelvic regions; scales of forearms greenish with dark bands; seven dark caudal bands anteriorly separated by dull-green interspaces, dark bands fade on posterior one-third of tail; gular region beige with irregularly shaped, brown, thin, submandibular bands; gular pouch small, base of pouch cyan with purple center.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

).
LSUHC12179
very closely approximates the 
holotype
in overall body coloration and pattern, except for being lighter overall. 
LSUHC12000
bears the same general color pattern as the 
holotype
and 
LSUHC12178
but differs greatly from them in being overall more green in coloration and having four dark, diffuse, dorsal bands between the forelimb and hind limb insertions that are more prominent. Additionally, the tail is distinctly banded for nearly its entire length. Variation in squamation is presented in 

Table 
4
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from Robinson Falls, Cameron Highlands, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

) but is expected to range more widely along the Banjaran Titiwangsa.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the greenish dragon, Rhaegal—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
            <p>Natural history.
All 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
were collected at night between at 
2000
and 
2300
hrs while sleeping on thin, horizontal branches of small trees in the vicinity of a river flowing through the hill dipterocarp forest at Robinson Falls (

). All were gravid females collected during mid-March or mid- September, indicating that this species may breed year-round.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
by having a cyan dewlap with a purple center (females) and the unique combination of numerous other characteristics (

Table 
3
). With the exception of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
most closely resembles the other geographically proximate Thai-Malay Peninsula species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, by several characteristics the most notable of which is the lack of enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks (Figs. 9,10). From 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
85.2 mm
versus 
104.5 mm
; five as opposed to six canthals; seven or eight as opposed to nine infralabials; smooth as opposed to acuminate gular scales; three or four versus one enlarged scale between the eye and the ear; enlarged vertebral scales extending beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; 
52–58
as opposed to 
72–75
scales around midbody; ventral scales being smaller as opposed to being larger than dorsal scales; 
22–26
as opposed to 
27
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, rounded, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and having a cyan dewlap with a purple center (female) versus a purple dewlap in males (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having nine or 
10
versus 
11–14
circumorbitals; 
40–45
versus 
55–69
gulars; smooth as opposed to weakly keeled gular scales; enlarged vertebral scales extending beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; preaxial scales on third toe bearing enlarged, rounded, scales versus being unmodified; having a cyan dewlap with a purple tip (females) versus a yellow dewlap with a purple, horizontal, centrally positioned marking (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is separated by having a maximum SVL of 
85.2 mm
versus 
70.3 mm
; 
6–8
versus five postrostrals; four as opposed to two postmentals; a weak, antehumeral fold as opposed to lacking a fold; having three or four versus two enlarged scales between eye and ear; enlarged vertebral scales extend beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; 
52–58
scales around midbody versus 
48–52
; 
23
versus 
26
fourth toe subdigital lamellae; and having a cyan dewlap with a purple tip (females) versus a purple dewlap in males (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having nine or 
10
as opposed to 
11
circumorbitals; 
11
or 
12
as opposed to 
10
postnasalsuborbitals; 
40–45
as opposed to 
47
gular scales; a row of three or four versus two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; lacking as opposed to having three large supratympanic scales; pretympanic scales small as opposed to large; a convex versus a flat rostrum; lacking versus having enlarged vertebral scales on the tail; 
52–58
versus 
51
midbody scales; having enlarged, rounded, preaxial scales on the third toe as opposed to enlarged preaxial scales on the third toe being spinose; shorter snout (HL/SVL = 
0.28–0.30
versus 
0.31
); and having a white patch of suborbital scales as opposed to lacking a white patch of suborbital scales (

Table 
4
). Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12227
collected on 
26
March 
2015
by Evan S. H. Quah at 
1000
hrs crossing the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(03° 
26.166
N
101
° 
47.021
E

; 
1754 m
in elevation).
</p>
            <p>Paratype
.

Adult male 
LSUHC12141
found dead on the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(03° 
26.12
N
101
° 
47.345
E

; 
1750 m
in elevation) by L. Lee Grismer, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brandon R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be separated from all other species of 
Psuedocalotes
by having a combination of three postrostrals; 
10
circumorbitals; four or five canthals; 
5–7
superciliaries; rostral and nasal in contact; supralabials contacting nasal; six or seven supralabials; seven or eight infralabials; two or three postmentals; three enlarged chinshields; 
47
or 
48
smooth, flat, gular scales; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; 
7–9
nuchal crest scales lacking gaps and not extending beyond midbody; weakly keeled and plate-like scales on flanks; 
35–38
scales around midbody; ventrals smaller than dorsals; 
22
or 
23
subdigital lamellae on fourth finger; 
26
or 
27
subdigital lamellae on fourth toe; preaxial scales on third not modified; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.62
; no white marking below the eye; dewlap in males yellow; and no elbow or knee patches. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult female SVL 
71 mm
; head relatively large, triangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.62
; HL/SVL 
0.30
; interorbital and frontal regions flat; snout not elongate but convex, sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of four scales; supraorbital scales enlarged, keeled; single row of 
10
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region, posteriormost of series enlarged and tuberculate; five, flat, imbricate superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; three enlarged postorbital scales, posteriormost scale acuminate, keeled; dorsal, head scales weakly acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, dorsolaterally by nasal scale, and posteriorly by three smaller scales; external nares in slightly elevated single, rectangular, large, nasal scale; three enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region; parietal, occipital, and upper postorbital region covered with slightly enlarged, irregularly shaped, weakly acuminate scales; an enlarged, keeled parietal scale on right side of midline followed by a large, raised occipital scale; enlarged parietal on left side of midline broken up and adjacent occipital scale not as large or raised as the corresponding scale on right; interparietal small, bearing eyespot; temporal scales irregular in size; single enlarged, raised postorbital scale; two, raised, enlarged, keeled, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked, scales on dorsal margin not enlarged; six (R,L) supralabials; nine (R,L) postnasal-supraorbital scales; mental triangular; two large postmentals in medial point contact forming first in a series of three enlarged chinshields separated from infralabials by three anteriorly and 
10
posteriorly rows of smaller scales; 
7
(R), 
8
(L) infralabials; gular scales smooth, flat, directed posteromedially, 
47
at midline; dewlap small; transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak.
</p>
            <p>
Seven, large, lanceolate nuchal scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composed of a single row of keeled, slightly enlarged scales that extend onto base of tail where they are largest; body round in cross-section; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales, plate-like; ventrals smaller than dorsals; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs moderate in stature, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; 
22
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
27
lamellae beneath fourth toe; preaxial scales of third toe unmodified; tail laterally compressed, not swollen at base, covered with keeled scales, 
1.68
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).

Dorsal ground color of body and tail dull yellow; labials, lateral regions of throat, proximal region of brachia and anterior portion of flanks white; ground color of top of head light-green, randomly mottled with small, irregularly shaped, dark markings; four very faint, wide, diffuse, dark vertebral patches between forelimb and hind limb insertions extending onto dorsal margins of flanks; ground color of forelimbs yellow-green, mottled with darkly edged scales; ground color of hind limbs dingy green, limbs faintly banded; wide, diffuse faint bands on anterior region of tail fading posteriorly; gular region beige, bearing a series of faint, diffuse, obliquely oriented, brown stripes in lateral margins; gular pouch yellow; subcaudal region gray; rest of venter beige, generally immaculate; bottoms of hands and feet slightly darker.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

).

The male 
paratype
(
LSUHC12141
) resembles the female 
holotype
(
LSUHC12227
) in aspects of color pattern but the overall ground color is brown, not dull-yellow. It also has a greatly swollen tail base. Differences in scalation are presented in 

Table 
5
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

).
</p>
            <p>LSUHCLSUHCLSUHCLSUHCLSUHCZRCFMNHEtymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the yellowish dragon, Viserion—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Natural history.
The 
holotype
(
LSUHC12227
) was collected during mid-morning at 
1000
hrs under broken cloud cover as it was crossing the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands. The 
paratype
(
LSUHC12141
) was found freshly killed on the same road at 
1500
hrs. This short stretch of road runs along the crest of Ulu Kali and winds through a mossy cloud forest between 
1,700
and 
1,800 m
in elevation (

). The 
holotype
was a gravid female that had just ovulated indicating that the reproductive season of this species extends through March.
</p>
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is readily differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
except it sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
by having enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks. It can be separated from 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
by having larger, plate-like scales on the flanks (compare 

and 

) as evidenced by having fewer midbody scale rows (
35–38
versus 
41–44
); having more gular scales (
47
or 
48
versus 
40–46
); fewer subdigital lamellae on the fourth finger (
22
or 
23
versus 
22–28
); and fewer subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe (
26
or 
27
versus 
26–30
) (

Table 
5
). There appears to be less yellow coloration in the gular region of 
P. f l a v i g ul a
in that the yellow does not extend onto the region of the throat anterior to the forelimb insertions as it does in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and the skin between the scales is white in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
as opposed to being yellow in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(Figs. 10,12). Additionally, these two species share a 
22
% uncorrected pairwise sequence divergence between them. Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Variation in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
Smith (
1924
)

described 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
from a single specimen collected from the mossy forest along Brinchang Trail in Cameron Highlands (

). Smith’s (
1924
) description was rather brief but was significantly augmented by 

Grismer (
2011
)

with the examination of another specimen collected from Brinchang Trail (
ZRC2.5162
) reported by (

Leong 
2001
) and an additional specimen from Tanah Rata (
FMNH143903
). Meristic variation among five of the six known specimens is presented in 

Table 
5
. The color pattern in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
is quite variable (

). The dark, dorsal bands range from brown to black and from to distinct and diffuse to barely visible. The light-colored upper lip, lateral throat and proximal section of the brachium can range from immaculate white to lime-green and it may or may not extend onto the anterior portion of the flanks. There is considerable variation in overall ground color that ranges from dull-white to lime-green which we attribute to substrate matching (

).
</p>
            <p>
We obtained a series of close-up photographs of a juvenile male 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
(
THNHM25890
) collected at 
1400 m
in elevation from a montane region in the Hala-Bala Wildlife Sanctuary, Betong District, Yala Province, 
Thailand
along the Thai-Malay border. This habitat is contiguous with the Banjaran Titiwangsa and the data taken from the photographs—most notably the color pattern and the enlarged, plate-like flank scales (

)—clearly align this specimen with the 
flavigula-viserion
clade but until the specimen can be examined it will be recognized here as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
P. 
rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Psedocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Psedocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dragons in the mist: three new species of Pseudocalotes Fitzinger (Squamata: Agamidae) from the sky island archipelago of Peninsular Malaysia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4136.3.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/531CFF91FFB4FFA52D34B822017C6822</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4136.3.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Drogon’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Rhaegal’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Viserion’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult male 
LSUHC12223
collected on 
24
March 
2015
by L. Lee Grismer, Evan S. H. Quah, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brando R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos at 
2030
hrs 
1 km
south of Air Terjun Jeriau, Fraser’s Hill, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(
3
° 
43.283
N
101
° 
43.035
E

; 
1066 m
in elevation).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a flat rostrum; seven postrostrals; an interparietal; 
11
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one scale between the rostral and nasal; nine supralabials; eight infralabials; 
10
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; five or six sublabials; five or six chinshields; 
47
smooth, wide, gular scales; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; enlarged upper and lower posttemporals; a single enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; three large scales bordering the dorsal margin of the ear opening; large pretympanic scales; eight scales in the nuchal crest not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to the tip of the tail; keeled and non-plate-like scales on flanks; 
51
midbody scales; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19
subdigital scales on the fourth finger; 
23
subdigital scales on the fourth toe; preaxial scales on third toe enlarged and spinose; subdigital scales not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.52
; HL/SVL 
0.31
; no elbow or knee patches; and a male dewlap color of lime-green bearing a central yellow spot. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult male SVL 
91.4 mm
; head relatively large with a somewhat elongate flat snout, subtriangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.52
; HL/SVL 
0.31
; interorbital region flat; rostrum sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of five large canthal scales; supraorbital scales slightly enlarged, keeled; a single scale separating rostral and nasal scale; single row of 
11
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region, scales largest posteriorly; eight, flat, imbricate superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; short series of two enlarged, acuminate, postorbital scales extending to above anterior margin of tympanum; dorsal, head scales acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, posteriorly by seven smaller scales; external nares set in slightly elevated single, rectangular, large, nasal scale; five enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region forming a Y-shaped series with two larger, keeled scales on each side of midline; parietal, occipital, and upper postorbital region covered with slightly enlarged, elevated, acuminate to keeled scales; an enlarged parietal scale on each side of midline bordered by a clump of four, contiguous, enlarged, acuminate, occipital scales; interparietal small, lacking eyespot; temporal scales unequal with small scales intermixed with enlarged, weakly keeled scales; single, raised, enlarged, keeled scale in temporal region followed by a single, enlarged, spinose, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked; auditory meatus bodered dorsally by three large supratympanic scales; nine (R,L) supralabials; 
10
postnasal-suborbital scales; mental triangular, larger than adjacent infralabials; two larger postmentals, separated medially and forming first of a series of five(R) or six(L) enlarged chinshields that are separated from infralabials by one anteriorly and two posteriorly rows of smaller scales; eight (R,L) infralabials; gular scales flat, wide, directed posteromedially, 
47
at midline; dewlap small; and transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak; nuchal crest composed of eight, large, contiguous, lanceolate scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composing a single row of slightly enlarged keeled scales extending to base of tail; body laterally compressed; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse, and posteroventrally oriented rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales; ventrals same size as dorsals; 
51
scales around midbody; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs slender, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, slightly more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; preaxial lamellae on toe III enlarged and spinose (

); 
19
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
23
lamellae beneath fourth toe; tail laterally compressed, slightly swollen at base, covered with keeled scales, vertebral row forming a serrate, dorsal ridge, 
1.89
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).
Dark phase—
Dorsal ground color of head, body, limbs, and tail very dark-grey; labials cyan; row of white scales between supralabials and orbit; scattered white spots on anterior portion of flanks and sides of neck; four wide, diffuse, darker, transverse, dorsal bands between limb insertions extending to ventral edge of flanks; one band in pelvic region; nine bands on tail; limbs generally immaculate, dark-grey; groups of white scales in lateral margins of gular region; anterior gular region dull-white bearing dark-brown oblique lines; dewlap dingy lime-green with a dingy yellow center; ventral surfaces, beige, immaculate. 
Light phase—
Dorsal body pattern same as dark phase but ground color a much lighter grey; dark dorsal bands prominent against dullwhite interspace; cyan labials faded; gular region whitish bearing light-brown, oblique lines; dewlap lime-green with yellow center, dewlap scales bearing brownish centers; venter whitish, immaculate.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from the 
type
locality 
1 km
south of Air Terjun Jeriau, Fraser’s Hill, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

). It is expected however to be found further south to at least Genting Highlands.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>drogon</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the dark dragon, Drogon—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
            <p>Natural history.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
was collected at night at 
2000
hrs while sleeping on a thin, horizontal branch of small tree in the vicinity of a small stream in hill dipterocarp forest (

). The adult male was in the light color phase at the time of collection but became much darker during the day (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
by having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center and the unique combination of numerous other characteristics (

Table 
3
). With the exception of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
most closely resembles the other geographically proximate Thai-Malay Peninsula species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and 

P. dr i ng i. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from the former two species by a number of characteristics (

Table 
3
), the most notable of which is the lack of enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks (compare 

with Figs. 10,12). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 
104.5 mm
; five as opposed to six canthals; eight as opposed to nine infralabials; smooth as opposed to acuminate gular scales; 
51
as opposed to 
72–75
scales around midbody; ventral scales being smaller as opposed to being larger than dorsal scales; 
23
as opposed to 
27
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a purple dewlap (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 81.0 mm; 
11
versus 
11–14
circumorbitals; smooth as opposed to weakly keeled gular scales; males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a yellow dewlap with a purple, horizontal, centrally positioned marking (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is separated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 
70.3 mm
; seven versus five postrostrals; the rostral and nasal scale not contacting as opposed to contacting; four as opposed to two postmentals; a weak, antehumeral fold as opposed to lacking a fold; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a purple dewlap (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having 
11
as opposed nine or 
10
circumorbitals; 
10
as opposed to 
11
or 
12
postnasal-suborbitals; 
47
as opposed to 
40–45
gular scales; a row of two versus three or four enlarged scales between the ear and eye; large as opposed to small pretympanic scales; a flat versus a convex rostrum; having as opposed to lacking enlarged vertebral scales on the tail; and 
51
versus 
52–58
midbody scales; enlarged, spinose, preaxial scales on the third toe as opposed to enlarged, rounded preaxial scales on the third toe; longer head (HL/ SVL = 
0.31
versus 
0.28–0.30
); and a row of white scales extending from the nasal scale to just beyond the posterior border of the orbit as opposed to a suborbital white patch (

Table 
4
). Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>Sex PostrostralsLSUHC 12223 Holotype Male 7LSUHC 12000 Paratype Female 8LSUHC 12178 Holotype Female 8LSUHC 12179 Paratype Female 6Interparietal Circumorbitals Canthalsyes 11 5yes 10 5yes 9 5yes 10 5Superciliaries Scale between rostral and nasal Rostrum8 1 Flat10 2 Convex8 1,2 Convex7 1 ConvexSupralabial-nasal contact Supralabials InfralabialsYes 9 8Yes 9 8Yes 9 7Yes 8 8Postnasal-suborbitals Postmentals Chinshields10 4 5,611,11 4 5,612,11 4 5,412,11 4 DamagedGulars Gulars wide or granular Gulars smooth or keeled47 Wide Smooth42 Wide Smooth40 Wide Smooth45 Wide SmoothTransverse gular fold Antehumeral fold Enlarged scales between eye and earWeak Weak 2No Weak 3No Weak 3,4No Weak 4Enlarged posttemporals Posttympanics modified Enlarged supratympanics1 0 11 0 11 0 11 0 1Pretympanic scales large Enlarged postrictals RostrumYes 0 FlatNo 0 ConvexNo 0 ConvexNo 0 ConvexNuchal crest Gap in crest Nuchal crest scales on body8 No No7 No No6 No No8 No No</p>
            <p>
......continued on the next page 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12178
collected on 
18
March 
2015
by L. Lee Grismer, Evan S. H. Quah, Shahrul Anuar, Mohd A. Muin, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brandon R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos at 
2030
hrs at Robinson Falls, Cameron Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(04° 
43.283
N
101
° 
23.129
E

; 
1411 m
in elevation).
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12179
bears the same locality collecting data as the 
holotype
. Adult female 
LSUHC12000
bears the same collecting locality and collectors but was collected on 
4
September 
2014
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a convex rostrum; 
6–8
postrostrals; an interparietal; nine or 
10
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one or two scales between the rostral and nasal scales; eight or nine supralabials; seven or eight infralabials; 
11
or 
12
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; 
4–6
chinshields; 
40–45
smooth, wide, gular scales; no transverse gular fold; weak antehumeral fold; three or four enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; no large scales bordering the upper margin of the ear opening or in the pretympanic region; 
6–8
enlarged nuchal crest scales not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to base of tail; weakly keeled, non-plate-like scales on flanks; 
52–58
scales around midbody; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19–21
subdigital lamellae on fourth finger; 
22–26
subdigital lamellae on fourth toe; preaxial scales on third toe enlarged and rounded; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.50–0.54
; HL/SVL 
0.28–0.30
; no elbow or knee patches; and female dewlap bearing a purple base. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult female SVL 
83.7 mm
; head relatively large subtriangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.54
; HL/SVL 
0.30
; interorbital region flat; rostrum convex, sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of five large canthal scales; supraorbital scales slightly enlarged, keeled; single row of nine or 
10
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region; eight flat, imbricate to subimbrictae, superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; short row of three (R) four (L) enlarged, acuminate, postorbital scales extend to above anterior margin of tympanum; dorsal, head scales acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, posteriorly by eight smaller scales; external nares in slightly elevated, rectangular, large, nasal scale; seven enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region forming a Y-shaped series; parietal and occipital regions covered with enlarged, elevated, acuminate to keeled scales; an enlarged parietal scale on each side of midline; interparietals small, irregularly shaped, centralmost bearing a small eyespot; temporal scales unequal with small scales intermixed with enlarged, weakly keeled scales; one, enlarged, keeled, scale in temporal region followed by a single, enlarged, spinose, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked, not bordered dorsally by large supratympanic scales; nine (R,L) supralabials; 
12
(R), 
11
(L) large, postnasal-suborbital scales; mental triangular, larger than adjacent infralabials; four larger postmentals, separated medially by two small scales and forming first of a series of five (R) four (L) enlarged chinshields separated from infralabials by one anteriorly and two posteriorly rows of smaller scales; seven (R,L) infralabials; gular scales wide, smooth, directed posteromedially, 
40
at midline; dewlap small; transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak.
</p>
            <p>
Nuchal crest composed of six, large, contiguous, lanceolate scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composing a single row of slightly enlarged, keeled vertebral scales extending to base of tail; body laterally compressed; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse, and posteroventrally oriented rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales; ventrals same size as dorsals; 
52
scales around midbody; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs slender, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, slightly more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; preaxial lamellae on toe III enlarged and rounded (

); 
20
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
25
lamellae beneath fourth toe; and tail laterally compressed, slightly swollen at base, covered with keeled scales but lacking an enlarged vertebral row, 
1.67
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).

Dorsal ground color of head, body, and limbs, brown, mottled with shades of slightly darker brown; linear patch of light-colored suborbital scales beneath eye; four very faint, diffuse, dark bands between forelimb and hind limb insertions not extending to base of flanks; lighter interspace between bands mottled; scattered greenish scales in postorbital, temporal, lower flank, and pelvic regions; scales of forearms greenish with dark bands; seven dark caudal bands anteriorly separated by dull-green interspaces, dark bands fade on posterior one-third of tail; gular region beige with irregularly shaped, brown, thin, submandibular bands; gular pouch small, base of pouch cyan with purple center.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

).
LSUHC12179
very closely approximates the 
holotype
in overall body coloration and pattern, except for being lighter overall. 
LSUHC12000
bears the same general color pattern as the 
holotype
and 
LSUHC12178
but differs greatly from them in being overall more green in coloration and having four dark, diffuse, dorsal bands between the forelimb and hind limb insertions that are more prominent. Additionally, the tail is distinctly banded for nearly its entire length. Variation in squamation is presented in 

Table 
4
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from Robinson Falls, Cameron Highlands, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

) but is expected to range more widely along the Banjaran Titiwangsa.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the greenish dragon, Rhaegal—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
            <p>Natural history.
All 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
were collected at night between at 
2000
and 
2300
hrs while sleeping on thin, horizontal branches of small trees in the vicinity of a river flowing through the hill dipterocarp forest at Robinson Falls (

). All were gravid females collected during mid-March or mid- September, indicating that this species may breed year-round.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
by having a cyan dewlap with a purple center (females) and the unique combination of numerous other characteristics (

Table 
3
). With the exception of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
most closely resembles the other geographically proximate Thai-Malay Peninsula species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, by several characteristics the most notable of which is the lack of enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks (Figs. 9,10). From 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
85.2 mm
versus 
104.5 mm
; five as opposed to six canthals; seven or eight as opposed to nine infralabials; smooth as opposed to acuminate gular scales; three or four versus one enlarged scale between the eye and the ear; enlarged vertebral scales extending beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; 
52–58
as opposed to 
72–75
scales around midbody; ventral scales being smaller as opposed to being larger than dorsal scales; 
22–26
as opposed to 
27
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, rounded, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and having a cyan dewlap with a purple center (female) versus a purple dewlap in males (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having nine or 
10
versus 
11–14
circumorbitals; 
40–45
versus 
55–69
gulars; smooth as opposed to weakly keeled gular scales; enlarged vertebral scales extending beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; preaxial scales on third toe bearing enlarged, rounded, scales versus being unmodified; having a cyan dewlap with a purple tip (females) versus a yellow dewlap with a purple, horizontal, centrally positioned marking (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is separated by having a maximum SVL of 
85.2 mm
versus 
70.3 mm
; 
6–8
versus five postrostrals; four as opposed to two postmentals; a weak, antehumeral fold as opposed to lacking a fold; having three or four versus two enlarged scales between eye and ear; enlarged vertebral scales extend beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; 
52–58
scales around midbody versus 
48–52
; 
23
versus 
26
fourth toe subdigital lamellae; and having a cyan dewlap with a purple tip (females) versus a purple dewlap in males (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having nine or 
10
as opposed to 
11
circumorbitals; 
11
or 
12
as opposed to 
10
postnasalsuborbitals; 
40–45
as opposed to 
47
gular scales; a row of three or four versus two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; lacking as opposed to having three large supratympanic scales; pretympanic scales small as opposed to large; a convex versus a flat rostrum; lacking versus having enlarged vertebral scales on the tail; 
52–58
versus 
51
midbody scales; having enlarged, rounded, preaxial scales on the third toe as opposed to enlarged preaxial scales on the third toe being spinose; shorter snout (HL/SVL = 
0.28–0.30
versus 
0.31
); and having a white patch of suborbital scales as opposed to lacking a white patch of suborbital scales (

Table 
4
). Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12227
collected on 
26
March 
2015
by Evan S. H. Quah at 
1000
hrs crossing the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(03° 
26.166
N
101
° 
47.021
E

; 
1754 m
in elevation).
</p>
            <p>Paratype
.

Adult male 
LSUHC12141
found dead on the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(03° 
26.12
N
101
° 
47.345
E

; 
1750 m
in elevation) by L. Lee Grismer, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brandon R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be separated from all other species of 
Psuedocalotes
by having a combination of three postrostrals; 
10
circumorbitals; four or five canthals; 
5–7
superciliaries; rostral and nasal in contact; supralabials contacting nasal; six or seven supralabials; seven or eight infralabials; two or three postmentals; three enlarged chinshields; 
47
or 
48
smooth, flat, gular scales; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; 
7–9
nuchal crest scales lacking gaps and not extending beyond midbody; weakly keeled and plate-like scales on flanks; 
35–38
scales around midbody; ventrals smaller than dorsals; 
22
or 
23
subdigital lamellae on fourth finger; 
26
or 
27
subdigital lamellae on fourth toe; preaxial scales on third not modified; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.62
; no white marking below the eye; dewlap in males yellow; and no elbow or knee patches. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult female SVL 
71 mm
; head relatively large, triangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.62
; HL/SVL 
0.30
; interorbital and frontal regions flat; snout not elongate but convex, sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of four scales; supraorbital scales enlarged, keeled; single row of 
10
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region, posteriormost of series enlarged and tuberculate; five, flat, imbricate superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; three enlarged postorbital scales, posteriormost scale acuminate, keeled; dorsal, head scales weakly acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, dorsolaterally by nasal scale, and posteriorly by three smaller scales; external nares in slightly elevated single, rectangular, large, nasal scale; three enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region; parietal, occipital, and upper postorbital region covered with slightly enlarged, irregularly shaped, weakly acuminate scales; an enlarged, keeled parietal scale on right side of midline followed by a large, raised occipital scale; enlarged parietal on left side of midline broken up and adjacent occipital scale not as large or raised as the corresponding scale on right; interparietal small, bearing eyespot; temporal scales irregular in size; single enlarged, raised postorbital scale; two, raised, enlarged, keeled, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked, scales on dorsal margin not enlarged; six (R,L) supralabials; nine (R,L) postnasal-supraorbital scales; mental triangular; two large postmentals in medial point contact forming first in a series of three enlarged chinshields separated from infralabials by three anteriorly and 
10
posteriorly rows of smaller scales; 
7
(R), 
8
(L) infralabials; gular scales smooth, flat, directed posteromedially, 
47
at midline; dewlap small; transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak.
</p>
            <p>
Seven, large, lanceolate nuchal scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composed of a single row of keeled, slightly enlarged scales that extend onto base of tail where they are largest; body round in cross-section; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales, plate-like; ventrals smaller than dorsals; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs moderate in stature, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; 
22
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
27
lamellae beneath fourth toe; preaxial scales of third toe unmodified; tail laterally compressed, not swollen at base, covered with keeled scales, 
1.68
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).

Dorsal ground color of body and tail dull yellow; labials, lateral regions of throat, proximal region of brachia and anterior portion of flanks white; ground color of top of head light-green, randomly mottled with small, irregularly shaped, dark markings; four very faint, wide, diffuse, dark vertebral patches between forelimb and hind limb insertions extending onto dorsal margins of flanks; ground color of forelimbs yellow-green, mottled with darkly edged scales; ground color of hind limbs dingy green, limbs faintly banded; wide, diffuse faint bands on anterior region of tail fading posteriorly; gular region beige, bearing a series of faint, diffuse, obliquely oriented, brown stripes in lateral margins; gular pouch yellow; subcaudal region gray; rest of venter beige, generally immaculate; bottoms of hands and feet slightly darker.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

).

The male 
paratype
(
LSUHC12141
) resembles the female 
holotype
(
LSUHC12227
) in aspects of color pattern but the overall ground color is brown, not dull-yellow. It also has a greatly swollen tail base. Differences in scalation are presented in 

Table 
5
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

).
</p>
            <p>LSUHCLSUHCLSUHCLSUHCLSUHCZRCFMNHEtymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the yellowish dragon, Viserion—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Natural history.
The 
holotype
(
LSUHC12227
) was collected during mid-morning at 
1000
hrs under broken cloud cover as it was crossing the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands. The 
paratype
(
LSUHC12141
) was found freshly killed on the same road at 
1500
hrs. This short stretch of road runs along the crest of Ulu Kali and winds through a mossy cloud forest between 
1,700
and 
1,800 m
in elevation (

). The 
holotype
was a gravid female that had just ovulated indicating that the reproductive season of this species extends through March.
</p>
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is readily differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
except it sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
by having enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks. It can be separated from 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
by having larger, plate-like scales on the flanks (compare 

and 

) as evidenced by having fewer midbody scale rows (
35–38
versus 
41–44
); having more gular scales (
47
or 
48
versus 
40–46
); fewer subdigital lamellae on the fourth finger (
22
or 
23
versus 
22–28
); and fewer subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe (
26
or 
27
versus 
26–30
) (

Table 
5
). There appears to be less yellow coloration in the gular region of 
P. f l a v i g ul a
in that the yellow does not extend onto the region of the throat anterior to the forelimb insertions as it does in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and the skin between the scales is white in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
as opposed to being yellow in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(Figs. 10,12). Additionally, these two species share a 
22
% uncorrected pairwise sequence divergence between them. Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Variation in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
Smith (
1924
)

described 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
from a single specimen collected from the mossy forest along Brinchang Trail in Cameron Highlands (

). Smith’s (
1924
) description was rather brief but was significantly augmented by 

Grismer (
2011
)

with the examination of another specimen collected from Brinchang Trail (
ZRC2.5162
) reported by (

Leong 
2001
) and an additional specimen from Tanah Rata (
FMNH143903
). Meristic variation among five of the six known specimens is presented in 

Table 
5
. The color pattern in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
is quite variable (

). The dark, dorsal bands range from brown to black and from to distinct and diffuse to barely visible. The light-colored upper lip, lateral throat and proximal section of the brachium can range from immaculate white to lime-green and it may or may not extend onto the anterior portion of the flanks. There is considerable variation in overall ground color that ranges from dull-white to lime-green which we attribute to substrate matching (

).
</p>
            <p>
We obtained a series of close-up photographs of a juvenile male 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
(
THNHM25890
) collected at 
1400 m
in elevation from a montane region in the Hala-Bala Wildlife Sanctuary, Betong District, Yala Province, 
Thailand
along the Thai-Malay border. This habitat is contiguous with the Banjaran Titiwangsa and the data taken from the photographs—most notably the color pattern and the enlarged, plate-like flank scales (

)—clearly align this specimen with the 
flavigula-viserion
clade but until the specimen can be examined it will be recognized here as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
P. 
rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Psedocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Psedocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dragons in the mist: three new species of Pseudocalotes Fitzinger (Squamata: Agamidae) from the sky island archipelago of Peninsular Malaysia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4136.3.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/531CFF91FFB4FFA52D34B822017C6822</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4136.3.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Drogon’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Rhaegal’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Viserion’s False Garden Lizard 

, 

, 
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult male 
LSUHC12223
collected on 
24
March 
2015
by L. Lee Grismer, Evan S. H. Quah, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brando R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos at 
2030
hrs 
1 km
south of Air Terjun Jeriau, Fraser’s Hill, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(
3
° 
43.283
N
101
° 
43.035
E

; 
1066 m
in elevation).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a flat rostrum; seven postrostrals; an interparietal; 
11
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one scale between the rostral and nasal; nine supralabials; eight infralabials; 
10
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; five or six sublabials; five or six chinshields; 
47
smooth, wide, gular scales; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; enlarged upper and lower posttemporals; a single enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; three large scales bordering the dorsal margin of the ear opening; large pretympanic scales; eight scales in the nuchal crest not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to the tip of the tail; keeled and non-plate-like scales on flanks; 
51
midbody scales; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19
subdigital scales on the fourth finger; 
23
subdigital scales on the fourth toe; preaxial scales on third toe enlarged and spinose; subdigital scales not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.52
; HL/SVL 
0.31
; no elbow or knee patches; and a male dewlap color of lime-green bearing a central yellow spot. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult male SVL 
91.4 mm
; head relatively large with a somewhat elongate flat snout, subtriangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.52
; HL/SVL 
0.31
; interorbital region flat; rostrum sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of five large canthal scales; supraorbital scales slightly enlarged, keeled; a single scale separating rostral and nasal scale; single row of 
11
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region, scales largest posteriorly; eight, flat, imbricate superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; short series of two enlarged, acuminate, postorbital scales extending to above anterior margin of tympanum; dorsal, head scales acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, posteriorly by seven smaller scales; external nares set in slightly elevated single, rectangular, large, nasal scale; five enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region forming a Y-shaped series with two larger, keeled scales on each side of midline; parietal, occipital, and upper postorbital region covered with slightly enlarged, elevated, acuminate to keeled scales; an enlarged parietal scale on each side of midline bordered by a clump of four, contiguous, enlarged, acuminate, occipital scales; interparietal small, lacking eyespot; temporal scales unequal with small scales intermixed with enlarged, weakly keeled scales; single, raised, enlarged, keeled scale in temporal region followed by a single, enlarged, spinose, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked; auditory meatus bodered dorsally by three large supratympanic scales; nine (R,L) supralabials; 
10
postnasal-suborbital scales; mental triangular, larger than adjacent infralabials; two larger postmentals, separated medially and forming first of a series of five(R) or six(L) enlarged chinshields that are separated from infralabials by one anteriorly and two posteriorly rows of smaller scales; eight (R,L) infralabials; gular scales flat, wide, directed posteromedially, 
47
at midline; dewlap small; and transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak; nuchal crest composed of eight, large, contiguous, lanceolate scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composing a single row of slightly enlarged keeled scales extending to base of tail; body laterally compressed; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse, and posteroventrally oriented rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales; ventrals same size as dorsals; 
51
scales around midbody; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs slender, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, slightly more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; preaxial lamellae on toe III enlarged and spinose (

); 
19
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
23
lamellae beneath fourth toe; tail laterally compressed, slightly swollen at base, covered with keeled scales, vertebral row forming a serrate, dorsal ridge, 
1.89
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).
Dark phase—
Dorsal ground color of head, body, limbs, and tail very dark-grey; labials cyan; row of white scales between supralabials and orbit; scattered white spots on anterior portion of flanks and sides of neck; four wide, diffuse, darker, transverse, dorsal bands between limb insertions extending to ventral edge of flanks; one band in pelvic region; nine bands on tail; limbs generally immaculate, dark-grey; groups of white scales in lateral margins of gular region; anterior gular region dull-white bearing dark-brown oblique lines; dewlap dingy lime-green with a dingy yellow center; ventral surfaces, beige, immaculate. 
Light phase—
Dorsal body pattern same as dark phase but ground color a much lighter grey; dark dorsal bands prominent against dullwhite interspace; cyan labials faded; gular region whitish bearing light-brown, oblique lines; dewlap lime-green with yellow center, dewlap scales bearing brownish centers; venter whitish, immaculate.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from the 
type
locality 
1 km
south of Air Terjun Jeriau, Fraser’s Hill, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

). It is expected however to be found further south to at least Genting Highlands.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>drogon</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the dark dragon, Drogon—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
            <p>Natural history.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
was collected at night at 
2000
hrs while sleeping on a thin, horizontal branch of small tree in the vicinity of a small stream in hill dipterocarp forest (

). The adult male was in the light color phase at the time of collection but became much darker during the day (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
by having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center and the unique combination of numerous other characteristics (

Table 
3
). With the exception of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
most closely resembles the other geographically proximate Thai-Malay Peninsula species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and 

P. dr i ng i. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from the former two species by a number of characteristics (

Table 
3
), the most notable of which is the lack of enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks (compare 

with Figs. 10,12). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 
104.5 mm
; five as opposed to six canthals; eight as opposed to nine infralabials; smooth as opposed to acuminate gular scales; 
51
as opposed to 
72–75
scales around midbody; ventral scales being smaller as opposed to being larger than dorsal scales; 
23
as opposed to 
27
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a purple dewlap (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 81.0 mm; 
11
versus 
11–14
circumorbitals; smooth as opposed to weakly keeled gular scales; males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a yellow dewlap with a purple, horizontal, centrally positioned marking (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is separated by having a maximum SVL of 
91.4 mm
versus 
70.3 mm
; seven versus five postrostrals; the rostral and nasal scale not contacting as opposed to contacting; four as opposed to two postmentals; a weak, antehumeral fold as opposed to lacking a fold; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and males having a lime-green dewlap with a yellow center versus a purple dewlap (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having 
11
as opposed nine or 
10
circumorbitals; 
10
as opposed to 
11
or 
12
postnasal-suborbitals; 
47
as opposed to 
40–45
gular scales; a row of two versus three or four enlarged scales between the ear and eye; large as opposed to small pretympanic scales; a flat versus a convex rostrum; having as opposed to lacking enlarged vertebral scales on the tail; and 
51
versus 
52–58
midbody scales; enlarged, spinose, preaxial scales on the third toe as opposed to enlarged, rounded preaxial scales on the third toe; longer head (HL/ SVL = 
0.31
versus 
0.28–0.30
); and a row of white scales extending from the nasal scale to just beyond the posterior border of the orbit as opposed to a suborbital white patch (

Table 
4
). Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>Sex PostrostralsLSUHC 12223 Holotype Male 7LSUHC 12000 Paratype Female 8LSUHC 12178 Holotype Female 8LSUHC 12179 Paratype Female 6Interparietal Circumorbitals Canthalsyes 11 5yes 10 5yes 9 5yes 10 5Superciliaries Scale between rostral and nasal Rostrum8 1 Flat10 2 Convex8 1,2 Convex7 1 ConvexSupralabial-nasal contact Supralabials InfralabialsYes 9 8Yes 9 8Yes 9 7Yes 8 8Postnasal-suborbitals Postmentals Chinshields10 4 5,611,11 4 5,612,11 4 5,412,11 4 DamagedGulars Gulars wide or granular Gulars smooth or keeled47 Wide Smooth42 Wide Smooth40 Wide Smooth45 Wide SmoothTransverse gular fold Antehumeral fold Enlarged scales between eye and earWeak Weak 2No Weak 3No Weak 3,4No Weak 4Enlarged posttemporals Posttympanics modified Enlarged supratympanics1 0 11 0 11 0 11 0 1Pretympanic scales large Enlarged postrictals RostrumYes 0 FlatNo 0 ConvexNo 0 ConvexNo 0 ConvexNuchal crest Gap in crest Nuchal crest scales on body8 No No7 No No6 No No8 No No</p>
            <p>
......continued on the next page 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
               <tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12178
collected on 
18
March 
2015
by L. Lee Grismer, Evan S. H. Quah, Shahrul Anuar, Mohd A. Muin, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brandon R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos at 
2030
hrs at Robinson Falls, Cameron Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(04° 
43.283
N
101
° 
23.129
E

; 
1411 m
in elevation).
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12179
bears the same locality collecting data as the 
holotype
. Adult female 
LSUHC12000
bears the same collecting locality and collectors but was collected on 
4
September 
2014
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is differentiated from all other 
Psuedocalotes
by having the combination of a convex rostrum; 
6–8
postrostrals; an interparietal; nine or 
10
circumorbitals; five canthals; 
7–10
superciliaries; one or two scales between the rostral and nasal scales; eight or nine supralabials; seven or eight infralabials; 
11
or 
12
postnasal-suborbital scales; four postmentals; 
4–6
chinshields; 
40–45
smooth, wide, gular scales; no transverse gular fold; weak antehumeral fold; three or four enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; no large scales bordering the upper margin of the ear opening or in the pretympanic region; 
6–8
enlarged nuchal crest scales not separated by a gap; enlarged vertebral scales extending to base of tail; weakly keeled, non-plate-like scales on flanks; 
52–58
scales around midbody; midventrals smaller than dorsals; 
19–21
subdigital lamellae on fourth finger; 
22–26
subdigital lamellae on fourth toe; preaxial scales on third toe enlarged and rounded; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.50–0.54
; HL/SVL 
0.28–0.30
; no elbow or knee patches; and female dewlap bearing a purple base. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult female SVL 
83.7 mm
; head relatively large subtriangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.54
; HL/SVL 
0.30
; interorbital region flat; rostrum convex, sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of five large canthal scales; supraorbital scales slightly enlarged, keeled; single row of nine or 
10
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region; eight flat, imbricate to subimbrictae, superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; short row of three (R) four (L) enlarged, acuminate, postorbital scales extend to above anterior margin of tympanum; dorsal, head scales acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, posteriorly by eight smaller scales; external nares in slightly elevated, rectangular, large, nasal scale; seven enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region forming a Y-shaped series; parietal and occipital regions covered with enlarged, elevated, acuminate to keeled scales; an enlarged parietal scale on each side of midline; interparietals small, irregularly shaped, centralmost bearing a small eyespot; temporal scales unequal with small scales intermixed with enlarged, weakly keeled scales; one, enlarged, keeled, scale in temporal region followed by a single, enlarged, spinose, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked, not bordered dorsally by large supratympanic scales; nine (R,L) supralabials; 
12
(R), 
11
(L) large, postnasal-suborbital scales; mental triangular, larger than adjacent infralabials; four larger postmentals, separated medially by two small scales and forming first of a series of five (R) four (L) enlarged chinshields separated from infralabials by one anteriorly and two posteriorly rows of smaller scales; seven (R,L) infralabials; gular scales wide, smooth, directed posteromedially, 
40
at midline; dewlap small; transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak.
</p>
            <p>
Nuchal crest composed of six, large, contiguous, lanceolate scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composing a single row of slightly enlarged, keeled vertebral scales extending to base of tail; body laterally compressed; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse, and posteroventrally oriented rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales; ventrals same size as dorsals; 
52
scales around midbody; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs slender, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, slightly more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; preaxial lamellae on toe III enlarged and rounded (

); 
20
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
25
lamellae beneath fourth toe; and tail laterally compressed, slightly swollen at base, covered with keeled scales but lacking an enlarged vertebral row, 
1.67
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).

Dorsal ground color of head, body, and limbs, brown, mottled with shades of slightly darker brown; linear patch of light-colored suborbital scales beneath eye; four very faint, diffuse, dark bands between forelimb and hind limb insertions not extending to base of flanks; lighter interspace between bands mottled; scattered greenish scales in postorbital, temporal, lower flank, and pelvic regions; scales of forearms greenish with dark bands; seven dark caudal bands anteriorly separated by dull-green interspaces, dark bands fade on posterior one-third of tail; gular region beige with irregularly shaped, brown, thin, submandibular bands; gular pouch small, base of pouch cyan with purple center.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

).
LSUHC12179
very closely approximates the 
holotype
in overall body coloration and pattern, except for being lighter overall. 
LSUHC12000
bears the same general color pattern as the 
holotype
and 
LSUHC12178
but differs greatly from them in being overall more green in coloration and having four dark, diffuse, dorsal bands between the forelimb and hind limb insertions that are more prominent. Additionally, the tail is distinctly banded for nearly its entire length. Variation in squamation is presented in 

Table 
4
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from Robinson Falls, Cameron Highlands, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

) but is expected to range more widely along the Banjaran Titiwangsa.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the greenish dragon, Rhaegal—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
            <p>Natural history.
All 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
were collected at night between at 
2000
and 
2300
hrs while sleeping on thin, horizontal branches of small trees in the vicinity of a river flowing through the hill dipterocarp forest at Robinson Falls (

). All were gravid females collected during mid-March or mid- September, indicating that this species may breed year-round.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
by having a cyan dewlap with a purple center (females) and the unique combination of numerous other characteristics (

Table 
3
). With the exception of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
most closely resembles the other geographically proximate Thai-Malay Peninsula species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated from 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, by several characteristics the most notable of which is the lack of enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks (Figs. 9,10). From 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes khaononensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having a maximum SVL of 
85.2 mm
versus 
104.5 mm
; five as opposed to six canthals; seven or eight as opposed to nine infralabials; smooth as opposed to acuminate gular scales; three or four versus one enlarged scale between the eye and the ear; enlarged vertebral scales extending beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; 
52–58
as opposed to 
72–75
scales around midbody; ventral scales being smaller as opposed to being larger than dorsal scales; 
22–26
as opposed to 
27
subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, rounded, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; and having a cyan dewlap with a purple center (female) versus a purple dewlap in males (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having nine or 
10
versus 
11–14
circumorbitals; 
40–45
versus 
55–69
gulars; smooth as opposed to weakly keeled gular scales; enlarged vertebral scales extending beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; preaxial scales on third toe bearing enlarged, rounded, scales versus being unmodified; having a cyan dewlap with a purple tip (females) versus a yellow dewlap with a purple, horizontal, centrally positioned marking (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. dringi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is separated by having a maximum SVL of 
85.2 mm
versus 
70.3 mm
; 
6–8
versus five postrostrals; four as opposed to two postmentals; a weak, antehumeral fold as opposed to lacking a fold; having three or four versus two enlarged scales between eye and ear; enlarged vertebral scales extend beyond midbody as opposed to not extending beyond midbody; having as opposed to lacking enlarged, spinose, preaxial lamellae on the third toe; 
52–58
scales around midbody versus 
48–52
; 
23
versus 
26
fourth toe subdigital lamellae; and having a cyan dewlap with a purple tip (females) versus a purple dewlap in males (

). From 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be differentiated by having nine or 
10
as opposed to 
11
circumorbitals; 
11
or 
12
as opposed to 
10
postnasalsuborbitals; 
40–45
as opposed to 
47
gular scales; a row of three or four versus two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; lacking as opposed to having three large supratympanic scales; pretympanic scales small as opposed to large; a convex versus a flat rostrum; lacking versus having enlarged vertebral scales on the tail; 
52–58
versus 
51
midbody scales; having enlarged, rounded, preaxial scales on the third toe as opposed to enlarged preaxial scales on the third toe being spinose; shorter snout (HL/SVL = 
0.28–0.30
versus 
0.31
); and having a white patch of suborbital scales as opposed to lacking a white patch of suborbital scales (

Table 
4
). Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
.

Adult female 
LSUHC12227
collected on 
26
March 
2015
by Evan S. H. Quah at 
1000
hrs crossing the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(03° 
26.166
N
101
° 
47.021
E

; 
1754 m
in elevation).
</p>
            <p>Paratype
.

Adult male 
LSUHC12141
found dead on the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
(03° 
26.12
N
101
° 
47.345
E

; 
1750 m
in elevation) by L. Lee Grismer, Perry L. Wood, Jr., Hayden R. Davis, Matthew L. Murdoch, Brandon R. Burch, and Anthony J. Cobos.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be separated from all other species of 
Psuedocalotes
by having a combination of three postrostrals; 
10
circumorbitals; four or five canthals; 
5–7
superciliaries; rostral and nasal in contact; supralabials contacting nasal; six or seven supralabials; seven or eight infralabials; two or three postmentals; three enlarged chinshields; 
47
or 
48
smooth, flat, gular scales; weak transverse gular and antehumeral folds; two enlarged scales between the ear and eye; an enlarged upper and lower posttemporal; an enlarged supratympanic; no enlarged postrictals; 
7–9
nuchal crest scales lacking gaps and not extending beyond midbody; weakly keeled and plate-like scales on flanks; 
35–38
scales around midbody; ventrals smaller than dorsals; 
22
or 
23
subdigital lamellae on fourth finger; 
26
or 
27
subdigital lamellae on fourth toe; preaxial scales on third not modified; subdigital lamellae not unicarinate; HW/HL 
0.62
; no white marking below the eye; dewlap in males yellow; and no elbow or knee patches. These characters or a subset of them are scored across all species in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
.

Adult female SVL 
71 mm
; head relatively large, triangular in lateral and dorsal profile; HW/HL 
0.62
; HL/SVL 
0.30
; interorbital and frontal regions flat; snout not elongate but convex, sloped anteriorly, canthus rostralis sharp, composed of four scales; supraorbital scales enlarged, keeled; single row of 
10
enlarged, circumorbital scales bordering medial margins of supraorbital region, posteriormost of series enlarged and tuberculate; five, flat, imbricate superciliary scales; scales of orbit (surrounding eye) granular; three enlarged postorbital scales, posteriormost scale acuminate, keeled; dorsal, head scales weakly acuminate; rostral low, rectangular, bordered laterally by first supralabials, dorsolaterally by nasal scale, and posteriorly by three smaller scales; external nares in slightly elevated single, rectangular, large, nasal scale; three enlarged, acuminate, median scales in prefrontal region; parietal, occipital, and upper postorbital region covered with slightly enlarged, irregularly shaped, weakly acuminate scales; an enlarged, keeled parietal scale on right side of midline followed by a large, raised occipital scale; enlarged parietal on left side of midline broken up and adjacent occipital scale not as large or raised as the corresponding scale on right; interparietal small, bearing eyespot; temporal scales irregular in size; single enlarged, raised postorbital scale; two, raised, enlarged, keeled, posttemporal scale; tympanum naked, scales on dorsal margin not enlarged; six (R,L) supralabials; nine (R,L) postnasal-supraorbital scales; mental triangular; two large postmentals in medial point contact forming first in a series of three enlarged chinshields separated from infralabials by three anteriorly and 
10
posteriorly rows of smaller scales; 
7
(R), 
8
(L) infralabials; gular scales smooth, flat, directed posteromedially, 
47
at midline; dewlap small; transverse gular and antehumeral folds weak.
</p>
            <p>
Seven, large, lanceolate nuchal scales beginning on occiput, reaching maximum height on nape, tapering to a low, vertebral crest on body composed of a single row of keeled, slightly enlarged scales that extend onto base of tail where they are largest; body round in cross-section; dorsal body and flank scales weakly keeled, subimbricate, rectangular, arranged in indistinct, transverse rows; flank scales larger than dorsal body scales, plate-like; ventrals smaller than dorsals; scales of pectoral region, belly, and precloacal regions strongly keeled; limbs moderate in stature, covered dorsally with keeled scales; five digits on pes and manus; hind limbs larger, more robust than forelimbs; subdigital lamellae of toes I, II, IV, and V bicarinate; 
22
lamellae beneath fourth finger; 
27
lamellae beneath fourth toe; preaxial scales of third toe unmodified; tail laterally compressed, not swollen at base, covered with keeled scales, 
1.68
times SVL.
</p>
            <p>
Coloration in life (

).

Dorsal ground color of body and tail dull yellow; labials, lateral regions of throat, proximal region of brachia and anterior portion of flanks white; ground color of top of head light-green, randomly mottled with small, irregularly shaped, dark markings; four very faint, wide, diffuse, dark vertebral patches between forelimb and hind limb insertions extending onto dorsal margins of flanks; ground color of forelimbs yellow-green, mottled with darkly edged scales; ground color of hind limbs dingy green, limbs faintly banded; wide, diffuse faint bands on anterior region of tail fading posteriorly; gular region beige, bearing a series of faint, diffuse, obliquely oriented, brown stripes in lateral margins; gular pouch yellow; subcaudal region gray; rest of venter beige, generally immaculate; bottoms of hands and feet slightly darker.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

).

The male 
paratype
(
LSUHC12141
) resembles the female 
holotype
(
LSUHC12227
) in aspects of color pattern but the overall ground color is brown, not dull-yellow. It also has a greatly swollen tail base. Differences in scalation are presented in 

Table 
5
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is known only from the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands, Pahang Peninsular 
Malaysia
(

).
</p>
            <p>LSUHCLSUHCLSUHCLSUHCLSUHCZRCFMNHEtymology.
The specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>viserion</tp:taxon-name>
refers to this species’ resemblance in form and color to the yellowish dragon, Viserion—one of three dragons born in the Dothraki Sea and commanded by Daenerys Targaryen—the Mother of Dragons—in George R. R. Martin’s fictional work 
Game of Thrones.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Natural history.
The 
holotype
(
LSUHC12227
) was collected during mid-morning at 
1000
hrs under broken cloud cover as it was crossing the radar tower road at Ulu Kali at Genting Highlands. The 
paratype
(
LSUHC12141
) was found freshly killed on the same road at 
1500
hrs. This short stretch of road runs along the crest of Ulu Kali and winds through a mossy cloud forest between 
1,700
and 
1,800 m
in elevation (

). The 
holotype
was a gravid female that had just ovulated indicating that the reproductive season of this species extends through March.
</p>
            <p>Comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is readily differentiated from all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
except it sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
by having enlarged, plate-like scales on the flanks. It can be separated from 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
by having larger, plate-like scales on the flanks (compare 

and 

) as evidenced by having fewer midbody scale rows (
35–38
versus 
41–44
); having more gular scales (
47
or 
48
versus 
40–46
); fewer subdigital lamellae on the fourth finger (
22
or 
23
versus 
22–28
); and fewer subdigital lamellae on the fourth toe (
26
or 
27
versus 
26–30
) (

Table 
5
). There appears to be less yellow coloration in the gular region of 
P. f l a v i g ul a
in that the yellow does not extend onto the region of the throat anterior to the forelimb insertions as it does in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and the skin between the scales is white in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
as opposed to being yellow in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(Figs. 10,12). Additionally, these two species share a 
22
% uncorrected pairwise sequence divergence between them. Differences from other species are listed in 

Table 
3
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Variation in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
Smith (
1924
)

described 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
from a single specimen collected from the mossy forest along Brinchang Trail in Cameron Highlands (

). Smith’s (
1924
) description was rather brief but was significantly augmented by 

Grismer (
2011
)

with the examination of another specimen collected from Brinchang Trail (
ZRC2.5162
) reported by (

Leong 
2001
) and an additional specimen from Tanah Rata (
FMNH143903
). Meristic variation among five of the six known specimens is presented in 

Table 
5
. The color pattern in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
is quite variable (

). The dark, dorsal bands range from brown to black and from to distinct and diffuse to barely visible. The light-colored upper lip, lateral throat and proximal section of the brachium can range from immaculate white to lime-green and it may or may not extend onto the anterior portion of the flanks. There is considerable variation in overall ground color that ranges from dull-white to lime-green which we attribute to substrate matching (

).
</p>
            <p>
We obtained a series of close-up photographs of a juvenile male 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
(
THNHM25890
) collected at 
1400 m
in elevation from a montane region in the Hala-Bala Wildlife Sanctuary, Betong District, Yala Province, 
Thailand
along the Thai-Malay border. This habitat is contiguous with the Banjaran Titiwangsa and the data taken from the photographs—most notably the color pattern and the enlarged, plate-like flank scales (

)—clearly align this specimen with the 
flavigula-viserion
clade but until the specimen can be examined it will be recognized here as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
With phylogenies and phylogeographies for species across the sky island archipelago of Peninsular 
Malaysia
beginning to accumulate, interesting biogeographic patterns are beginning to emerge. One such pattern involves lineages from Cameron Highlands in the central section of the Banjaran Titiwangsa being more closely related to lineages from Bukit Larut in the separate Banjaran Bintang, 
77 km
to the west across uninhabitable terrene, rather than being more closely related to lineages farther south at Fraser’s Hill or Genting Highlands in the same mountain range. This pattern is seen with 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes rhaegal</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, from Cameron Highlands being more closely related to 
<tp:taxon-name>P. larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
from Bukit Larut than to 
<tp:taxon-name>P. drogon</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from Fraser’s Hill (

). This same pattern occurs in the Slug Snake 
<tp:taxon-name>Asthenodipsas lasgalanensis
(

Loredo 
et al
. 
2013
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, certain species of Reed Snakes 
<tp:taxon-name>Macrocalamus</tp:taxon-name>
(Quah 
et al.
in prep.), and the Larut Skinks 
<tp:taxon-name>Larutia
(

Grismer 
et al.2011
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Another pattern seen is the deep genetic divergences between populations from Cameron Highlands and those from farther south at Fraser’s Hill or Genting Highlands. Such is the case for 
<tp:taxon-name>P. flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
from Cameron Highlands and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. viserion</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from Genting Highlands; the Mourning Geckos 
<tp:taxon-name>Hemiphyllodactylus titiwangsaensis
Zug
</tp:taxon-name>
from Cameron Highlands versus populations from Fraser’s Hill and Genting Highlands (

Cobos 
et al.2016
); the Rock Geckos 
<tp:taxon-name>Cnemaspis temiah
Grismer 
et al.</tp:taxon-name>
from Cameron Highlands and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cnemaspis flavolineata
(Nicholls)
</tp:taxon-name>
from Fraser’s Hill (

Grismer 
et. al.2014
b

); the Bent-toed Geckos 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyrtodactylus trilatofasciata
Grismer, Wood, Jr., Quah, Anuar, Muin, Sumontha, Norhayati, Bauer, Wangkulangkul, Grismer
</tp:taxon-name>
, &amp; Pauwels and 
<tp:taxon-name>C. sharkai
Grismer, Wood
</tp:taxon-name>
, anuar, Quah, Muin, Mohamed, Onn, Sumarli, Loredo, &amp; Heinz from Cameron Highlands and Merapoh, respectively, being distinct from 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyrtodactylus australotitiwangsaensis
Grismer, Wood, Jr., Quah, Anuar, Muin, Sumontha, Norhayati, Bauer, Wangkulangkul, Grismer
</tp:taxon-name>
, &amp; Pauwels from Frasers Hill and Genting Highlands (

Grismer 
et al.2014
a

); and multiple species of Reed Snakes in the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Macrocalamus
Günther
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Calamaria
Boie
</tp:taxon-name>
(Quah 
et al.
in prep.).
</p>
         <p>
As noted above, recent field work in the montane regions of Peninsular 
Malaysia
has resulted in the discovery of 
33
new species of amphibians and reptiles. Thus, discovering new species from such a bizarre group of montane lizards such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes</tp:taxon-name>
is exciting but not completely unexpected. The most remarkable aspect of these statistics is that these discoveries, for the most part, are not the result of searching previously unexplored regions or generated by the use of molecular analyses. Rather the majority of these species are newly discovered lineages that are easily diagnosed on the basis of morphology and color pattern and they come from areas that have been popular collecting localities for well over a century (e.g. Penang Hill, Bukit Larut, Cameron Highlands, Fraser’s Hill, Genting Highlands, etc.; see 

Grismer 
2011
for a discussion). Few collections have been made in the largely unexplored Banjaran Timur of northeastern Peninsular 
Malaysia
(see 

Grismer 
et al.2010
c

and Sumarli 
et al.2015
for discussions) and essentially nothing has been collected in the 
150 km
of the Banjaran Titiwangsa that extends south of Genting Highlands into the states of Negeri Sembilan and Johor. As we begin to focus our research on these southern and northeastern areas, we expect that a plethora of new species will be discovered. The obvious overarching message is that these upland regions serve as incredibly important, vast reservoirs of known and unrealized biodiversity whose content is being severely underestimated, unappreciated and unprotected (e.g. the rapid urbanization of Cameron Highlands and the proposed cable car up to Bukit Larut). If we want to implement any sort of sustainable management programs in order to conserve this biodiversity and these unique, fragile upland habitats, then field-based taxonomy not only must continue, it must be considered paramount.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>
We wish to thank Brandon R. Burch and Ruper G. Lewis for assistance in the field. Funding for LLG came from grants from the College of Arts and Sciences at La Sierra University and from a National Geographic Society Explorers Grant (
9277
- 
15
). Shahrul Anuar was supported by Universiti Sains 
Malaysia
and Ministry of Higher Education Research Grants. Field work for 
PLWJ
was supported in part by a NSF grant EF- 
1241885
issued to Jack W. Sites Jr.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Anderson, J.
(
1879
) 
Reptilia and amphibia
. In: 

Anatomical and Zoological Researches: Comprising an Account of the Zoological Results of the Two Expeditions to Western Yunnan in 
1868
and
1875
. 
Volume I
, 
703–860
, 
969
– 
975
. Bernard Quarich, London, Vol. I, 
705– 860
,[
1878
]
</p>
         <p>Annandale, N.
(
1908
) 

Description of a new Species of Lizard of the Genus 
Salea
from Assam

. 
Records of the Indian Museum
, 
2
, 

37– 
38
.
</p>
         <p>Bell, R.C.
, 
Parra, J.L.
, 
Tonione, M.
, 
Hoskin, C.J.
, 
MacKenzie, J.B.
, 
Williams, S.E.
&amp; 
Moritz, C.
(
2010
) 
Patterns of persistence and isolation indicate resilience to climate change in montane rainforest lizards
. 
Molecular Ecology19
, 2531– 
455
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1365
- 
294
x. 
2010.04676
.x
</p>
         <p>Blackburn, D.C.
&amp; 
Measey, G.J.
(
2009
) 
Dispersal to or from an African biodiversity hotspot
? 
Molecular Ecology
, 
18
, 

1904– 
1915
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1365
- 
294
X. 
2009.04156
.x
</p>
         <p>Boulenger, G.A.
(
1891
) 
On new or little known Indian and Malayan reptiles and batrachians
. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History
, 
8
, 
288
– 
292
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/00222939109460437
</p>
         <p>Chan, K.O.
, 
Grismer, L.L.
, 
Norhayati, A.
&amp; 
Belabut, D.
(
2009
) 

A new species of 
Gastrophrynoides
(Anura: Microhylidae): an addition to a previously monotypic genus and a new genus for Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
2124
, 

63– 
68
.
</p>
         <p>Chan, K.O.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Anuar, S.
, 
Muin, M.A.
, 
Quah, E.S.H.
, 
Sumarli, A.X.
&amp; 
Grismer, L.L.
(
2014
) 

A new species of upland Stream Toad of the genus 
Ansonia
Stoliczka (Aunra: Bufonidae) from northeastern Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
3764
(
4
), 
427–440
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3764.4.3
</p>
         <p>Chan-ard, T.
, 
Cota, M.
, 
Mekchai, S.
&amp; 
Laoteow, S.
(
2008
) 

A new species of the genus 
Pseudocalotes
(Squamata: Agamidae) from peninsular 
Thailand
. 

The 
Thailand
Natural History Museum Journal

,
3
, 

25– 
31
.
</p>
         <p>Cobos, A.
, 
Grismer, L.L.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Quah, E.S.H.
, 
Anuar, S.
&amp; 
Muin, M.A.
(
2016
) 

Phylogenetic relationships of geckos of the 
Hemiphyllodactylus harterti
group, a new species from Penang 
Island
, Peninsular 
Malaysia
, and a likely case of true cryptic speciation

. 
Zootaxa
,
4107
(
3
), 
367–380
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.4107.3.5
</p>
         <p>Drummond, A.J.
, 
Ashton, B.
, 
Buxton, S.
, 
Cheung, M.
, 
Cooper, A.
, 
Duran, C.
, 
Field, M.
, 
Heled, J.
, 
Kearse, M.
, 
Markowitz, S.
, 
Moir, R.
, 
Stones-Havas, S.
, 
Sturrock, S.
, 
Thierer, T.
&amp; 
Wilson, A.
(
2011
) 

Geneious V 
5.6
, Available from http:// www.Geneious

. 
Com (Accessed5
Jul. 
2016
)
</p>
         <p>Grismer, J.L.
, 
Schulte II, J.A.
, 
Alexander, A.
, 
Wagner, P.
, 
Travers, S.L.
, 
Buehler, M.D.
, 
Welton, L.J.
&amp; 
Brown, R.M.
(
2016
) 
The Eurasian Invasion: Phylogenomic data reveal multiple Southeast Asian origins for Indian Dragon Lizards
. 
BMC Evolutionary Biology
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1186
/s 
12862
-016-0611- 
6</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
(
2006
a) 

A new species of 
Ansonia
Stoliczka 
1872
(Anura: Bufonidae) from Central Peninsular 
Malaysia
and a revised taxonomy for Ansonia from the Malay Peninsula

. 
Zootaxa
, 
1327
, 

1– 
21
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
(
2006
b) 

Two new species of skinks (Genus 
Sphenomorphus
Fitzinger 
1843
) from the Seribuat Archipelago, West 
Malaysia
. 
Herpetological Natural History
, 
9
, 
151
– 
162
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
(
2007
) 

A new species of small montane forest floor skink (Genus 
Sphenomorphus
Fitzinger 
1843
) from southern Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Herpetologica
, 
63
, 
544
– 
551
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1655
/0018-0831(
2007
) 
63
[
544
:ANSOSM]2.0.CO; 
2</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
(
2008
) 

A new species of insular skink (Genus 
Sphenomorphus
Fitzinger 
1843
) from the Langkawi Archipelago, Kedah, West 
Malaysia
with the first report of the herpetofauna of 
Pulau
Singa Besar and an updated checklist of the herpetofauna of 
Pulau
Langkawi

. 
Zootaxa
, 
1691
, 

53– 
56
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
(
2011
) 

Lizards of Peninsular 
Malaysia
, 
Singapore
and Their Adjacent Archipelagos

.
Edition Chimaira, Frankfürt am Main
. 
728
pp.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
Anuar, S., Muin M.A., Quah, E.S.H. &amp; Wood, P.L. Jr. (
2013
a) 

Phylogenetic relationships and description of a new upland species of Bent-toed Gecko (
Cyrtodactylus
Gray, 
1827
) of the 
C. sworderi
complex from northeastern Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
3616
(
3
), 
239–252
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3616.3.2
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
&amp; 
Chan, K.O.
(
2010
a) 

Another new rock gecko (genus 
Cnemaspis
Strauch 
1887
) from 
Pulau
Langkawi, Kedah, Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
2419
, 

51– 
62
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Chan, K.O.
, 
Grismer, J.L
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr. &amp; 
Norhayati, A.
(
2010
c) 

A checklist of the herpetofauna of the Banjaran Bintang, Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Russian Journal of Herpetology
, 
17
, 
147
– 
160
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Chan, K.O.
, 
Quah, E.
, 
Mohd, A.M.
, A.E. Savage, A.E., Grismer, J.L. Norhayati, A., Greer 

III 
1
, L.F. &amp; Remegio, A.-C. (
2010
b) 

Another new, diminutive Rock Gecko (
Cnemaspis
Strauch) from Peninsular 
Malaysia
and a discussion of resource partitioning in sympatric species pairs

. 
Zootaxa
, 
2569
, 

55– 
66
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Grismer, J.L.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr. &amp; 
Chan, K.O.
(
2008
) 

The distribution, taxonomy, and redescription of the geckos 
Cnemaspis affinis
(Stoliczka 
1887
) and 
C. flavolineata
(Nicholls 
1949
) with descriptions of a new montane species and two new lowland, karst-dwelling species from Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
1931
, 

1– 
24
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Grismer, J.L.
&amp; 
Youmans, T.M.
(
2004
) 

A new species of 
Leptolalax
(Anura: Megophryidae) from 
Pulau
Tioman, West 
Malaysia
. 

Asiatic 
Herpetological Research
, 
10
, 

8– 
11
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Norhayati, A.
&amp; 
Chan, K.O.
(
2009
a) 

A new, diminutive, upland 
Sphenomorphus
Fitzinger 
1843
(Squamata; Scincidae) from the Belum-Temengor Forest Complex, Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
2312
, 

27– 
38
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Norhayati, A.
, 
Chan, K.O.
, 
Belabut, D.
, 
Muin, M.A.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr. &amp; 
Grismer, J.L.
(
2009
b) 

Two new diminutive species of 
Cnemaspis
Strauch 
1887
(Squamata: Gekkonidae) from Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
2019
, 

40– 
56
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
&amp; 
Quah, E.S.H.
(
2015
) 

The Rediscovery of 
Sphenomorphus malayanus
Doria

, 
1888
(Squamata: Scincidae) from the Titiwangsa Mountain Range of Peninsular 
Malaysia
and its re-description as 
S. senja
sp. nov. 
Zootaxa
, 
63–70
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3931.1.4
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Quah, E.S.H.
, 
Siler, C.D.
, 
Chan, K.O.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Grismer, J.L.
, 
Anuar, S.
&amp; 
Norhayati, A.
(
2011
) 

Peninsular Malaysia’s first limbless lizard: a new species of the genus 
Larutia
(Böhme) from 
Pulau
Pinang with a phylogeny of the genus

. 
Zootaxa
, 
2799
, 

29– 
40
.
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Anuar, S.
, 
Muin, M.A.
, 
Quah, E.S.H.
, 
McGuire, J.A.
, 
Brown, R.A.
, 
Ngo, V.T.
&amp; 
Pham, H.
(
2013
b) 

Integrative taxonomy uncovers high levels of cryptic species diversity in 
Hemiphyllodactylus
Bleeker, 
1860
(Squamata: Gekkonidae) and the description of a new species from Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society
, 
169
, 
849
– 
880
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/zoj. 
12064</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
Wood, P.L. Jr., Anuar, S., Quah, E.S.H., Muin, M.A., Mohamed, M., Chan, K.O., Sumarli, A.X., Loredo, A.I. &amp; Heinz, H.M. (
2014
a) 

The phylogenetic relationships of three new species of the 
Cyrtodactylus pulchellus
complex (Squamata: Gekkonidae) from poorly explored regions in northeastern Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
3786
(
3
), 
359–381
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3786.3.6
</p>
         <p>Grismer, LL.
, 
Wood, PL.
Jr., 
Anuar, S.
, 
Quah, ESH.
, 
Muin, MA.
, 
Chan, KO.
, 
Sumarli, AX.
, &amp; 
Loredo A.L.
(
2015
a) 

Repeated evolution of sympatric, paleoendemic species in closely related, co-distributed lineages of 
Hemiphyllodactylus
Bleeker, 
1860
(Squamata: Gekkonidae) across a sky-island archipelago in Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society
,
174
, 
859
– 
876
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/zoj. 
12254</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Anuar, S.
, 
Riyanto, A.
, 
Norhayati, A.
, 
Muin, M.A
, 
Sumontha, M.
, 
Grismer, J.L.
, 
Chan, K.O.
, 
Quah, E.S.H.
&amp; 
Pauwels, O.S.G.
(
2014
b) 

Systematics and natural history of Southeast Asian Rock Geckos (genus 
Cnemaspis
Strauch, 
1887
) with descriptions of eight new species from 
Malaysia
, 
Thailand
, and 
Indonesia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
3880
(
1
), 
1–147
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3880.1.1
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Lee, C.H.
, 
Quah, E.S.H.
, 
Anuar, S.
, 
Ngadi, E.
&amp; 
Sites, J.W. Jr.
(
2015
b) 

An integrative taxonomic review of the agamid genus 
Bronchocela
(Kuhl, 
1820
) from Peninsular 
Malaysia
with descriptions of new montane and insular endemics

. 
Zootaxa
, 
3948
(
1
), 
1–23
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3948.1.1
</p>
         <p>Grismer, L.L.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Quah, E.S.H.
, 
Anuar, S.
, 
Muin, M.A.
Sumontha, M., Norhayati, A., Bauer, A.M., Wangkulangkul, S., Grismer, J.L. &amp; Pauwels, O.S.G. (
2012
) 

A phylogeny and taxonomy of the Thai-Malay Peninsula Bent-toed Geckos of the 
Cyrtodactylus pulchellus
complex (Squamata: Gekkonidae): combined morphological and molecular analyses with descriptions of seven new species

. 
Zootaxa
, 
3520
, 

1– 
55
.
</p>
         <p>Hallermann, J.
&amp; 
Böhme, W.
(
2000
) 

A review of the genus 
Pseudocalotes
(Squamata: Agamidae), with description of a new species from West 
Malaysia
. 
Amphibia-Reptilia
,
21
, 
193
– 
210
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1163
/ 
156853800507372</p>
         <p>Hallermann, J.
, 
Truong, N.Q.
, 
Orlov, N.
&amp; 
Ananjeva, N.
(
2010
) 

A new species of the genus 
Pseudocalotes
(Squamata: Agamidae) from 
Vietnam
. 
Russian Journal of Herpetology
, 
17
, 

31– 
40
.
</p>
         <p>Harikrishnan, S.
&amp; 
Vasudevan, K.
(
2013
) 

Rediscovery of 
Calotes andamanensis
Boulenger, 
1891
, and assessment of its generic allocation (Squamata: Sauria: Agamidae)

. 
Herpetozoa
,
26
, 

3– 
13
.
</p>
         <p>Harvey, M.B.
, 
Hamidy, A.
, 
Kurniawan, N.
, 
Shaney, K.
&amp; 
Smith, E.N.
(
2015
) 

Three new species of 
Pseudocalotes
(Squamata: Agamidae) from southern Sumatra, 
Indonesia
. 
Zootaxa
,
3841
(
2
), 
211–238
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3841.2.3
</p>
         <p>Inger, R.F.
&amp; 
Stuebing, R.B.
(
1994
) 

First record of the lizard genus 
Pseudocalotes
(Lacertilia: Agamidae) in Borneo, with description of a new species

. 
Raffles Bulletin of Zoology
, 
42
, 
961
– 
965
.
</p>
         <p>Leong, T.M.
(
2001
) 

A first female topotype of the montane agamid 
Pseudocalotes flavigula
(Smith, 
1924
) from Peninsular 
Malaysia
, with description of coloration in life

. 
Hamadryad
, 
26
, 
364
– 
366
.
</p>
         <p>Loredo, A.I.
, 
Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Quah, E.S.H.
, 
Anuar, S.H.
, 
Greer, L.
, 
Norhayati, A.
&amp; 
Grismer, L.L.
(
2013
) 

Cryptic speciation within 
Asthenodipsas vertebralis
(Boulenger, 
1900
) (Squamata: Pareatidae), the description of a new species from Peninsular 
Malaysia
, and the resurrection of 
A. tropidonotus
(Lidth de Jude, 
1923
) from Sumatra: an integrative taxonomic analysis

. 
Zootaxa
, 
3664
(
4
), 
505–524
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3664.4.5
</p>
         <p>Macey, J.R.
, 
Schulte, J.A.
, 
Larson, A.
, 
Tuniyev, B.S.
, 
Orlov, N.
&amp; 
Papenfuss, T.J.
(
1999
) 
Molecular phylogenetics, tRNA evolution, and historical biogeography in anguid lizards and related taxonomic families
. 
Molecular phylogenetics and evolution
, 
12
(
3
), 
250–272
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1006
/mpev. 
1999.0615</p>
         <p>Maddison, W.
&amp; 
Maddison, D.
(
2015
) 

Mesquite: a modular system for evolutionary analysis. version 
3.04
. 
2015
. 
Avaliable from
: 
http://mesquiteproject.org
(Accessed 
5
Jul. 
2016
)
</p>
         <p>Mahony, S.
(
2010
) 

Systematic and taxonomic revaluation of four little known Asian agamid species, 
Calotes kingdonwardi
Smith, 
1935
, 
Japalura kaulbacki
Smith, 
1937
, 
Salea kakhienensis
Anderson, 
1879
and the monotypic genus 
Mictopholis
Smith, 
1935
(Reptilia: Agamidae)

. 
Zootaxa
, 
2514
, 

1– 
23
.
</p>
         <p>Manthey, U.
(
2010
) 

Terralog 
7
b. Agamid Lizards of Southern Asia/ Agamen des südlichen Asien. Draconinae 
2
Leiolepinae

. 
Chimaira, Frankfurt
. 
168
pp

Matsui, M., Belabut, D. &amp; Norhayati, A. (
2014
) Two new fanged frogs from Peninsular 
Malaysia
(Anura: Dicroglossidae). 
Zootaxa
, 
3881
(
1
), 
75–93
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3881.1.6
</p>
         <p>Matsui, M.
, 
Belabut, D.M.
, 
Ahmad, N.
&amp; 
Yong, H.S.
(
2009
) 

A new species of 
Leptolalax
(Amphibia, Anura, Megophryidae) from Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zoological Science
. Tokyo
26
, 
243
– 
247
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.2108
/zsj. 
26.243</p>
         <p>Minh, B.Q.
, 
Nguyen, M.A.T.
, &amp; 
von Haeseler, A.
(
2013
) 
Ultrafast approximation for phylogenetic bootstrap
. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
,
30
, 

1188– 
1195
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/molbev/mst024
</p>
         <p>Nguyen, L.-T.
, 
Schmidt, H.A.
, 
Haeseler, A. von
. &amp; Minh, B.Q. (
2015
) 
IQ-TREE: A fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum likelihood phylogenies
. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
, 
32
, 
268
– 
274
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/molbev/msu 
300</p>
         <p>Ronquist, F.
, 
Teslenko, M.
, 
van der Mark, P.
, 
Ayres, D.L.
, 
Darling, A.
, 
Höhna, S.
, 
Larget, B.
, 
Liu, L.
, 
Suchard, M.A.
&amp; 
Huelsenbeck, J.P.
(
2012
) 

Mr. Bayes 
3.2
: Efficient Bayesian Phylogenetic Inference and Model Choice across a Large Model Space

. 
Systematic Biology
, 
61
, 
539
– 
542
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/sysbio/sys029
</p>
         <p>Smith, M.A.
(
1924
) 
Two new lizards and a new tree frog from the Malay Peninsula
. 
Journal of the Federated States Museum
. 
11
, 
183
– 
186
.
</p>
         <p>Stamatakis, A.
(
2008
) 
Raxml-Vi-Hpc: maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed models
. 
Bioinformatics (Oxford)
,
22
, 

2688– 
2690
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/bioinformatics/btl 
446</p>
         <p>Sumarli, A.X.
, 
Grismer, L.L.
, 
Anuar, S.
, 
Muin, M.A.
&amp; 
Quah, E.S.H.
(
2015
) 

First report on the amphibians and reptiles of a remote mountain, Gunung Tebu in northeastern Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Checklist
, 
11
, 

1– 
32
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.15560
/ 
11.4.1679</p>
         <p>Tamura, K.
, 
Stecher, G.
, 
Peterson, D.
, 
Filipski, A.
, &amp; 
Kumar, S.
(
2013
) 
MEGA6
: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0. 
Molecular biology and evolution
, mst
197
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/molbev/mst 
197</p>
         <p>Tolley, K.A.
, 
Colin, R.T.
, 
Measey, G.J.
, 
Menegon, M.
, 
Branch, W.R.
&amp; 
Matthee, C.
(
2011
) 
Ancient forest fragmentation or recent radiation? Testing refugial speciation models in chameleons within an African biodiversity hot spot
. 
Journal of Biogeography
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1365
-2699.2011.02529.x
</p>
         <p>Wilcox, T.P.
, 
Zwickl, D.J.
, 
Heath, T.A.
&amp; 
Hillis, D.M.
(
2002
) 
Phylogenetic relationships of the Dwarf Boas and a comparison of Bayesian and bootstrap measures of phylogenetic support
. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution
,
25
, 
361
– 
371
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1016
/S 
1055-7903
(02)00244-0
</p>
         <p>Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Grismer, J.L.
, 
Grismer, L.L.
, 
Norhayati, A.
, 
Chan, K.O.
&amp; 
Bauer, A.M.
(
2009
) 

Two new montane species of 
Acanthosaura
Gray, 
1831
(Squamata: Agamidae) from Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Zootaxa
,
2012
, 

28– 
46
.
</p>
         <p>Wood, P.L.
Jr., 
Grismer, L.L.
, 
Norhayati A.
&amp; 
Juliana S.
(
2008
) 

Two new species of torrent-dwelling toads 
Ansonia
Stoliczka

, 
1870
(Anura: Bufonidae) from Peninsular 
Malaysia
. 
Herpetologica
, 
64
/ 
3
, 

321– 
340
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1655
/07-065.1
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>APPENDIX</title>
         <p>The following specimens were examined.</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes floweri</tp:taxon-name>
.—
Cambodia
; 
LSUHC8673
Bokor Plateau, Kampot Province.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes flavigula</tp:taxon-name>
.—West 
Malaysia
, Pahang; 
LSUHC
12420, 12581 Cameron Highlands, Tanah Rata. 
FMNH143903
, 
ZRC2.5162
, 
LSUHC12580
Cameron Highlands, Brinchang Trail.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes kakhienensis</tp:taxon-name>
.—
China
; 
CAS
241969, 242381 
Yunan
Province.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes kingdonwardi</tp:taxon-name>
.—
China
; 
CAS242579Yunan
Province.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pseudocalotes larutensis</tp:taxon-name>
.—West 
Malaysia
, Perak, Bukit Larut 
LSUHC
9052, 9141–42, 10265, 10285, 11289, 
12434
.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
