<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4237.3.4</journal-id>
         <issn>1175-5326</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Morphology, songs and genetics identify two new cicada species from Morocco: Tettigettalna afroamissa sp. nov. and Berberigetta dimelodica gen. nov. &amp; sp. nov. (Hemiptera: Cicadettini)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2017</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Morphology, songs and genetics identify two new cicada species from 
Morocco
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. nov.</named-content>
&amp; sp. nov. (
<tp:taxon-name>Hemiptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
)
</p>
         <p>GONÇALO JOÃO COSTA, VERA L. NUNES, EDUARDO MARABUTO, RAQUEL MENDES, TELMA G. LAURENTINO, JOSÉ ALBERTO QUARTAU,</p>
         <p>OCTÁVIO S. PAULO &amp; PAULA CRISTINA SIMÕES1</p>
         <p>
Computational Biology and Population Genomics Group, 
Centre
for Ecology, Evolution and Environmental Changes, Departamento de Biologia Animal, Faculdade de Ciências, Universidade de 
Lisboa
, Campo Grande, 1749-016 
Lisboa
, 
Portugal
.
1Corresponding author. E-mail: pcsimoes@fc.ul.pt</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>Morocco
has been the subject of very few expeditions on the last century with the objective of studying small cicadas. In the summer of 2014 an expedition was carried out to 
Morocco
to update our knowledge with acoustic recordings and genetic data of these poorly known species. We describe here two new small-sized cicadas that could not be directly assigned to any species of North African cicadas: 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. nov.</named-content>
&amp; 
sp. nov.
In respect to 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
it is the first species of the genus to be found outside Europe and we frame this taxon within the evolutionary history of the genus. Acoustic analysis of this species allows us to confidently separate 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
from its congeners. With 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
,

a small species showing a remarkable calling song characterized by an abrupt frequency modulation, a new genus had to be erected. Bayesian inference and maximum likelihood phylogenetic analyses with DNA-barcode sequences of Cytochrome C Oxidase 1 support the monophyly of both species, their distinctness and revealed genetic structure within 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
.

Alongside the descriptions we also provide GPS coordinates of collection points, distributions and habitat preferences.
</p>
         <p>Key words
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new genus</named-content>
, new species, 
Morocco</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>
Cicadas (
<tp:taxon-name>Hemiptera</tp:taxon-name>
: Cicadoidea) are a successful insect group with a unique sound production system and thousands of species worldwide (
Sanborn 2014
). Males produce species-specific acoustic signals, mainly to attract females for pairing and reproduction. These signals have influence in reproductive isolation and thus can be used as important taxonomic characters (
Claridge 1985
; 
Boulard 2006
; Quartau &amp; Simões 2006; Simões &amp; Quartau 2006), enabling taxonomists to confidently diagnose a specimen even when belonging to cryptic species (

Simões 
et al.
2000

; 
Sueur &amp; Puissant 2007
; Mendes 
et al.
2014; 

Hertach 
et al.
2015

).
</p>
         <p>
As for a wide range of biological groups, the Mediterranean basin was recently confirmed as a hotspot for cicada diversity. There, the Iberian Peninsula is particularly relevant, and recent studies on the group have unveiled new species and provided novel contributions in distribution and ecology (
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
; 

Simões 
et al.
2013

; 

Nunes 
et al.
2014a

). However, the underlying idea is that our knowledge is far from complete, particularly in North Africa, where despite an initial boost in species’ description and collection of samples in the past century, little has been investigated—or published—during the last decade. In fact, specimens from the Maghreb countries of 
Morocco
, 
Algeria
and 
Tunisia
are available in several museum collections and represent a rather large number of cicada species (
Villiers 1943
; 
Boulard 1980
, 
1981
, 
1987
). Regrettably, associated with this invaluable data is neither ecology nor the recordings of specific acoustic signals produced by the males, as these descriptions were based almost exclusively on external morphology. Cryptic species complexes, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta brevipennis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. l.</named-content>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
are extremely difficult to distinguish this way (Mendes 
et al.
2014; 

Hertach 
et al.
2016

). Therefore, in order to truly understand this biodiversity hotspot, and other relevant biological data, such as genetics, multivariate morphometric analyses, habitat preferences, distribution range, emergence periods or phenology should be assessed.
</p>
         <p>
In particular, the genetic data coupled with behavioural sound analysis may provide a recommended approach for a more accurate and thorough species description and delimitation incicadas. This is still missing for many cicadas, namely from North Africa, compromising comparative studies with those from other regions. On what concerns molecular genetics, sequence data is highly desirable in modern taxonomy, as these enable clarification of the taxonomic status of closely-related taxa, such as in the recognition of sibling species, and in addition offering useful phylogenetic information (

Hebert 
et al.
2004

). More recently, 
DNA
barcoding (

Hebert 
et al.
2003

) and massive sequencing of large amounts of specimens have fostered a renewal of taxonomic procedures and applications. This is particularly relevant for groups with several, very similar species, as trained specialists are currently in high demand but in short supply.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 1.
Distribution map of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
with approximate distribution areas extracted from bibliography. The distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
is not shown as it is widespread across the Iberian Peninsula. Collection points in Morocco of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
(white triangle) and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
(white circle). Black triangles indicate sites where 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
was heard but not collected. Distributions’ code: 1— 
<tp:taxon-name>T. estrellae</tp:taxon-name>
; 2— 
<tp:taxon-name>T. josei</tp:taxon-name>
; 3— 
<tp:taxon-name>T. mariae</tp:taxon-name>
; 4— 
<tp:taxon-name>T. armandi</tp:taxon-name>
; 5— 
<tp:taxon-name>T. defauti</tp:taxon-name>
; 6— 
<tp:taxon-name>T. aneabi</tp:taxon-name>
; 7— 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi helianthemi</tp:taxon-name>
; 8— 
<tp:taxon-name>T. h. galantei</tp:taxon-name>
; 9— 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
. Scale bar indicates 100 km.
</p>
         <p>
A paradigmatic case within cicadas is the European genus 
<tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
. Using the current concept of the genus, it is known to comprise several, usually parapatric, species. This genus shows a pattern of increased diversity in the southern area of the Iberian Peninsula (

), with many narrow endemics bordering the coastline with the Mediterranean sea (
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
; 

Simões 
et al.
2013

, 2014; Nunes 
et al.
2014b) but a widespread member reaching 
Slovenia
to the east (
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata
(Olivier, 1790))
</tp:taxon-name>
. The current knowledge on the distribution boundaries of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. is far from being properly known, and extensive field surveys for these cicadas are still needed. Given this southern increased species diversity in the genus, its presence in North Africa had long been expected but not yet investigated.
</p>
         <p>
Fieldwork towards a first screening of cicada biodiversity in the northern part of 
Morocco
(Rif and Middle Atlas mountains) was carried out during the summer of 2014. Among the several 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
collected and recorded, there was a medium-sized species phenotypically similar to the European 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
, singing on holm-oaks and tall shrubs. In the understory there was sometimes a smaller species, mostly singing among middle-sized shrubs. Further analysis of both entities revealed they belong to two undescribed species, namely the first African member of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, and a second one, belonging to the new genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. nov.</named-content>
, 

i.e., 
<tp:taxon-name>dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
Descriptions of both species are here provided and are based on distinctive morphological, bioacoustic and genetic information.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Materials and methods</title>
         <p>
Collection of specimens was performed by hand or sweeping net and GPS data was assigned to each capture site. Acoustic data was recorded whenever possible with a 
CANON
EOS 70D camera with an upper frequency limit of over 20 KHz. Distance of the insect to the camera varied between close recordings to up to 
0.5–1 m
of total distance.
</p>
         <p>
Specimens were photographed or filmed and respective habitats were characterized 
in loco
. In the lab, each specimen was assigned a tracking number, pinned and assigned to a morphotype. For most specimens, a front leg was removed and preserved in alcohol for posterior genetic analysis. Acoustic recordings and specimens are stored at the Department of Animal Biology of the Faculty of Sciences, University of 
Lisbon
, 
Portugal
.
</p>
         <p>Morphology
Morphological terminology follows 
Moulds (2005)
and higher systematics follows 
Sanborn (2014)
. Both species here described belong to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadidae Latreille, 1802</tp:taxon-name>
: subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettinae</tp:taxon-name>
Buckton, 1889 and tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
Buckton, 1889.
</p>
         <p>
Body, pygophore and aedeagus measurement images were taken on a Zeiss SteREO Lumar 
V.12
coupled to a TIS DFK 5MPixel camera with IC Capture v.2.1 and calibrated with a 
0.01 mm
Olympus micrometer. Wing measurements were obtained using photographs taken on a 
CANON
EOS 450D. Each measurement was performed on a single image. Images were calibrated and measured on 
FIJI
(

Schindelin 
et al.
2012

). Measurement codes and procedure explanation are described on 
Table 1
and S4. Male genitalia were extracted and placed on a heated 0.1M KOH solution for removal of soft tissues and clarification. Pygophore and aedeagus were conserved on Kaiser gelatin.
</p>
         <p>Sound
Acoustic analysis was performed on AviSoft 
SAS
(
Specht 2004
). Calling songs were initially trimmed to remove bad quality sections of the recordings and a time domain filter (FIR) was applied with a high pass of 4 kHz for the calling song of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and of 2.5 kHz for 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
to remove background noise. A frequency domain transformation was also applied at frequencies ranging 15.59–15.80 kHz to remove electromagnetic interference.
</p>
         <p>
For 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, spectrograms were generated with a FFT length of 512, Hamming 
type
window and 50% temporal overlap. Echemes were labeled with a single automatic threshold and temporal and frequency based variables were generated as described in 

Pinto-Juma 
et al.
2005

. For 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>gen. &amp; sp. nov
, due to song peculiarities, an additional Hamming 
type
window with FFT length= 128 was generated.
</p>
         <p>Discrete values are shown as median ± SD and continuous values as average ± SD followed by (minimum– maximum, total number of observations).</p>
         <p>Genetics
For the genetic analysis, whole-genome 
DNA
was isolated from a front leg of each specimen with the DNeasy Blood &amp; Tissue Kit (Qiagen). Primers LepF and LepR (

Hajibabaei 
et al.
2006

) were used to obtain 648 bp of the 5’ region of the cytochrome C oxidase I (
COI
) mitochondrial gene (the ‘barcode’ region), using the same PCR conditions as 

Nunes 
et al.
(2014a)

. PCR products were purified with SureClean (Bioline) and sequencing was carried out by Macrogen Europe. Sequences were first corrected in Sequencher 4.0.5 (Gene Codes Co.), then aligned with 
MAFFT
7.273 (
Katoh &amp; Standley 2013
) and visually inspected in BioEdit 7.0.9.0 (
Hall 1999
) and trimmed to the final, same length of 581 bp. The alignment has no gaps or stop codons. Sequences were deposited in GenBank (accession numbers 
KX582146
to 
KX582168
, see 
Table 2
).
</p>
         <p>TABLE 1.
List and description of the 23 morphological variables analyzed in 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
,

described with codes and abbreviations (Abbr.).
</p>
         <p>Body region Code Abbr. Description</p>
         <p>Head and 1 TL Total length measured from tip of the head to end of the wings in resting position</p>
         <p>thorax 2 HL Head length measured from the front to the end of the head measured by the dorsal median</p>
         <p>line</p>
         <p>3 HW Maximum head width measured between exterior eye margins 4 EO Eye-ocellum distance between the margin of a compound eye and the margin of the nearest ocellum</p>
         <p>5 OO Greatest distance between the two dorsal ocelli</p>
         <p>6 LrL Labrum length measured between the margin of the anteclypeus to the end of the labrum 7 LiL Labium length distance between end of labrum and tip of labium 8 VW Vertex width measured with the smallest interocular distance 9 FR Front length measured along the dorsal median line 10 PC Postclypeus length measured along the median line 11 PL Pronotum length</p>
         <p>12 PW Pronotal width measured at the maximum width of pronotal collar 13 ML Mesonotum length measured along dorsal midline until end of scutellum</p>
         <p>Abdomen 14 OP Greatest width of operculum as exemplified on Image 1. 15 LS Sternite VII length measured along ventral midline 16 TyL Tymbal length as exemplified on Image 1.</p>
         <p>17 TyW Tymbal width as exemplified on Image 1.</p>
         <p>Legs 18 PF Profemur length measured along median line</p>
         <p>Wings 19 FwL Forewing length measured from intersection of costal vein and CuP+1A vein until apex of</p>
         <p>wing.</p>
         <p>20 FwW Forewing width measured from intersection of R+Sc vein and node until intersection of CuP+1A vein and CuA2 vein.</p>
         <p>
21 
BCL
Basal cell length measured from intersection of costal vein and CuP+1A vein until beginning of M+CuA vein
</p>
         <p>22 MCuA Length of M+CuA vein</p>
         <p>23 RCL Radial cell length measured from beginning of M+CuA until intersection of R+Sc vein and node.</p>
         <p>
Genetic distances (Kimura-2-parameter and p-distances) were obtained with Mega 6 (

Tamura 
et al.
2013

). Sequences generated for this study were aligned with sequences available in GenBank from Mediterranean species published by 

Nunes 
et al.
(2014a)

and Simões 
et al.
(2014) from genera 
<tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>TettigettaculaPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna
Boulard,1982
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada
Linnaeus, 1758
</tp:taxon-name>
, (see Table S1 for accession numbers). For comparative purposes, specimens from two additional Mediterranean genera were also sequenced: 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes
(Waltl, 1837)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei
Boulard, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The complete matrix with 58 taxa was converted from fasta to nexus with Concatenator 1.1.0 (
Pina-Martins &amp; Paulo 2008
). A Bayesian phylogenetic tree was generated by MrBayes 3.2.1 (

Ronquist 
et al.
2012

). The best model of sequence evolution (HKY+ G) was selected under the corrected Akaike information criterion (AICc), as implemented in MrModeltest 2.3 (

Nylander 
et al.
2004

). The Metropolis-coupled Markov chain Monte Carlo analysis was carried out with four chains. The posterior probabilities for each node were generated from 10 8 generations, sampling at every 100th iteration. The burn-in was set to the first 25% trees, and the remaining trees were used to generate a consensus tree by the 50% majority rule. For maximum likelihood analysis, we used RaxML (
Stamatakis 2014
) with a GTRCAT model and ran with 10 0 0 0 generations. 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara
(Stål, 1866)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni</tp:taxon-name>
L. 1758, two species belonging to tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadini</tp:taxon-name>
and occurring both in the Iberian Peninsula and 
Morocco
, were set as outgroup taxa for Bayesian and ML analyses.
</p>
         <p>TABLE 2.
Description of the collection sites and NCBI accession numbers for COI DNA barcoding of the paratypical series of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
. Bold sample IDs indicate the type specimens. Collectors name code: EM—E. Marabuto; VN—VL Nunes; TL—T. Laurentino.
</p>
         <p>Species Sample ID Sex Population Locality Coll. GPS coordinates GenBank</p>
         <p>Accession n.</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
SP18_3779 
♂
Rif Mountains Chefchaouane EM 
35° 11' 2.53'' N
(1)
</p>
         <p>5° 13' 25.93' W</p>
         <p>SP18_3780♀Rif MountainsChefchaouaneEM35° 11' 2.53'' N 5° 13' 25.93' W(1)SP18_3781♂Rif MountainsChefchaouaneEM35° 11' 2.53'' N 5° 13' 25.93' WKX582158SP18_3782♂Rif MountainsChefchaouaneEM35° 11' 2.53'' N 5° 13' 25.93' WKX582159SP18_3783♂Rif MountainsChefchaouaneEM35° 11' 2.53'' N 5° 13' 25.93' WKX582160SP18_3786♀Middle AtlasAfouzarEM33° 52' 16.73'' N 4° 1' 42.75'' WKX582161SP18_3805♀East RifBni HadifaEM35° 01' 48'' N 4° 9' 51.85'' W(1)SP18_3806♂East RifBni HadifaEM35° 01' 48'' N 4° 9' 51.85'' WKX582162SP18_3807♂East RifBni HadifaVN35° 01' 48'' N 4° 9' 51.85'' WKX582163SP18_3808♂East RifBni HadifaVN35° 01' 48'' N 4° 9' 51.85'' WKX582164SP18_3813♂East RifTarguistEM34° 57' 54.58'' N 4° 20' 38.73'' WKX582165SP18_3814♂East RifTizi TchenEM34° 55' 44.18'' N 4° 29´31.87'' WKX582166SP18_3815♂East RifTizi TchenEM34° 55' 44.18'' N 4° 29´31.87'' WKX582167</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
SP19_3787 
♀
Middle Atlas Afouzar 
VN33° 52' 16.73'' N
(1)
</p>
         <p>4° 1' 42.75'' W</p>
         <p>SP19_3788♂Middle AtlasAfouzarVN33° 52' 16.73'' N 4° 1' 42.75'' W(1)SP19_3789♂Middle AtlasAfouzarVN33° 52' 16.73'' N 4° 1' 42.75'' W(1)SP19_3790♂Middle AtlasAfouzarEM33° 52' 16.73'' N 4° 1' 42.75'' WKX582146SP19_3791♂Middle AtlasAfouzarEM33° 52' 16.73'' N 4° 1' 42.75'' WKX582147SP19_3792♂Middle AtlasAfouzarEM33° 52' 16.73'' N 4° 1' 42.75'' WKX582148SP19_3793♂Middle AtlasAfouzarTL33° 52' 16.73'' N 4° 1' 42.75'' WKX582149SP19_3794♂BerkaneBerbersVN34° 47' 59.1'' N 2° 23' 59.5'' W(1)</p>
         <p>
. 
.....continued on the next page
Species Sample ID Sex Population Locality Coll. GPS coordinates GenBank Accession n. (1)These specimens were not sequenced in order to preserve their morphology for collection purposes.
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>SP19_3795♂BerkaneBerbersVN34° 47' 59.1'' N 2° 23' 59.5'' W(1)SP19_3796♂BerkaneBerbersVN34° 47' 59.1'' N 2° 23' 59.5'' WKX582150SP19_3797♂BerkaneBerbersVN34° 47' 59.1'' N 2° 23' 59.5'' WKX582151SP19_3798♂BerkaneBerbersTL34° 47' 59.1'' N 2° 23' 59.5'' WKX582152SP19_3799♂BerkaneBerbersEM34° 47' 59.1'' N 2° 23' 59.5'' WKX582153SP19_3803♂El HoceimaAssihelVN35° 11' 15.86''N 3° 24' 38.93'' WKX582154</p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Results</title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. aneabi
(
Boulard, 2000
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. armandiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. defautiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. estrellae
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi
(Rambur, 1840)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. josei
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. mariae
(Quartau &amp; Boulard, 1995)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>afroamissa
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna gastrica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrelae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi helianthemi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi galantei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. barbara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. orni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. defauti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. mariae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cistus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Abies pinsapo
var. 
marocana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cedrus atlantica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Prunus dulcis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. baenai(Boulard, 2000))</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta
Kolenati, 1857
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta montana
(Scopoli, 1772))
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. montana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Total
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pinus halepensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tetraclinis articulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Chamaerops humilis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rosmarinus officinalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Stipa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Morphology, songs and genetics identify two new cicada species from Morocco: Tettigettalna afroamissa sp. nov. and Berberigetta dimelodica gen. nov. &amp; sp. nov. (Hemiptera: Cicadettini)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4237.3.4</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/68618D0CFF8A6406FFAF9E2FFFDFFF9A</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4237.3.4</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant 2010</tp:taxon-name>
Originally described and diagnosed by 
Puissant &amp; Sueur (2010)
, encompasses nine European species: 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. aneabi
(
Boulard, 2000
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. armandiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. defautiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. estrellae
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi
(Rambur, 1840)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. josei
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T. mariae
(Quartau &amp; Boulard, 1995)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Only 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
is widespread, reaching, France, Italy, Switzerland and Slovenia to the east. The remaining are (rather) narrow Iberian endemics (see 

).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
nov. gen. Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
Paratypical series consist of 13 specimens (ten males and three females). Designated holotype is SP18_3779 (♂) and female paratype is SP18_3780 (♀). See 
Table 2
for additional information on the paratypical series, specimen IDs, collection sites and GPS data. See 

for images of male holotype, female paratype and for details of the male genitalia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Male morphology</p>
            <p>Head
Head slightly less broad than pronotum; Supra-antennal plates nearly meeting the eye and produced into a pointed lobe; Postclypeus rounded to subquadrate in frontal view, rounded between top and sides in lateral view, transversely grooved towards distal ends; Rostrum brown, reaching the center of mid-trochanters (in rest). Antennae dark-brown, 7-segmented. Dorsal surface of head brown with front bearing a yellowish stripe extending to outer borders; Yellowish stripe at beginning of epicranial suture extending to pronotum. Eyes brown, three red ocelli. Postclypeus dark brown, with apical yellowish-brown spot extending to frons, grooves light-brown or yellowish. Supra-antennal plates dark-brown and yellowish-brown towards distal ends. Gena and lorum brown to dark-brown covered in long white pilosity. Anteclypeus brown to dark-brown with a lighter brownish fascia surrounding a central dark-brown spot.
</p>
            <p>Thorax
Pronotal collar slightly larger than head width, widened, sloping laterally and evenly rounded dorsally. Pronotal tooth present mid-laterally. Scutellum wider than long. Epimeral lobe not reaching operculum. Submedian sigillae well defined. Metanotum partly visible at dorsal midline not expanded over tymbals. Pronotum with an olive-green arrow shaped stripe at dorsal midline bordered with dark-brown in fresh specimens (in preserved specimens this fades away to light brown). Remainder of pronotum brown, with dark-brown markings bearing yellowish borders. Mesonotum on overall brown, with a lighter “crown-like” marking, lateral margins of mesonotum yellowish. Scutellum brown, with a longitudinal dark-brown fascia at midline expanding towards the ends, reaching metanotum. Sides of scutellum with a dense pilosity on lateral-anterior ends with a fading gradient of dark-brown to yellowish towards the posterior end with defined, longitudinal, slightly transverse grooves. Metanotum brown, with a dark-brown patch at dorsal midline. Ventral side of thorax brown.
</p>
            <p>Legs
Profemur with three to four dark-brown erect spines. Primary spine clearly separated. Metatibiae with three to four long fine spurs on inner side, and two smaller spurs on outer side with finely dispersed white pilosity. Apex of metatibia surrounded by smaller numerous brown spurs. Tarsal formula: 3-3-3. Legs generally brown in colour. Coxae and trochanters yellowish with a central dark-brown stripe, better defined on the hind legs. Femurs and tibiae brown with two dark-brown longitudinal fasciae. Profemurs with a swollen dark brown fascia surrounded by two yellowish/ light brown stripes, varying somewhat among individuals. Dark-brown border along the spines. Tarsi dark-brown on dorsal side, brown on ventral side. Protarsi darker in colour.
</p>
            <p>Wings
Forewing and hindwing with eight and six apical cells, respectively. Ulnar cell 3 angled towards radial cell; Forewing costa parallel-sided to radial cell; Pterostigma present. CuA vein weakly bowed; M+CuA meeting at basal cell with stems fused. Vein RA1 aligned closely with subcostal for its length. CuA1 divided by a crossvein with shorter proximal part. CuP and 1A unfused at their bases. Veins C and R+Sc close together. Outer forewing margin developed for its total length. Hindwing first cubital cell width at distal end much greater than second cubital cell. Hindwing anal lobe broad with 3A vein long and strongly curved at distal end. Hindwing RP and M veins fused at their base. Larger forewing proximal veins yellowish with smaller apical veins brown, same for hindwing. Forewing basal membrane yellow. Hindwing plaga yellow.
</p>
            <p>Opercula
More or less confluent with distal margin of tympanal cavity, well developed towards abdominal midline with sharply rounded apices facing midline. Opercula extending but not reaching posterior border of StII. Opercula distally yellow, dark-brown at base. Meracanthus triangular, following same colour pattern as opercula.
</p>
            <p>Tymbals
Tymbals lacking a tymbal cover. Five ribs, four of which arising from top of a large basal dome, covering about half the tymbal width, and expanding in width towards the posterior side. Fifth rib as an extension of basal dome more or less defined, varying between specimens. First and second anterior ribs, slender, with a transverse break at about halfway of basal dome. Tymbal plate light-grey, ribs and basal dome brownish-grey.
</p>
            <p>Abdomen
Abdomen with somewhat scattered white pilosity. T1 uniformly dark-brown; T2 uniformly darkbrown with a transversal stripe, slightly pointed towards posterior end of abdomen on each side; T3 to T7 darkbrown anteriorly becoming lighter on posterior side; T8 dark-brown. StI mainly dark-brown, yellow posterior margin; StII mainly dark-brown, with yellow lateral borders. StIII to StVI light brown, with a brown spot at midline, forming a well-defined stripe. StVII large, brown, as long as or slightly longer than StVIII; StVIII brown, densely covered in pilosity. Epipleurites brown with yellow posterior border.
</p>
            <p>Genitalia
(

E to 2H) Pygophore dark-brown on dorsal surface and brown on lateral sides. Pygophore distal shoulder not developed. Pygophore inner tooth absent. Upper lobe flat and moderately developed, distant from dorsal beak with a sharply rounded tip; Basal lobe present, moderately developed and rounded in lateral view. Dorsal beak present and part of chitinized pygophore. Claspers dark-brown, medium-sized, closely aligned ending on a rounded, sharp tip. Uncus brown, duck-bill shaped, small and flat, not dominant. Uncus lateral lobes absent. Aedeagus basal plate, in lateral view, with an undulated ventral surface skewed towards the proximal end; In ventral view, apically broad with a small constriction mid-ventrally expanding afterwards with a midgroove between two longitudinally expanded lobes; Basal portion of basal plate directed forwards and away from thecal shaft; Basal plate ventral rib not apparent; Basal plate attached with a functional membranous “hinge”. Theca, in lateral view, curved into a gentle arc; Thecal pseudoparamers present, dorsal of theca, originating closer to theca than its base; Endothecal ventral support present; Thecal aperture upper diagonal in lateral view.
</p>
            <p>Female morphology
Females overall slightly darker than males. Pronotal posterior border light-brown. Mesonotal “crown-like” mark much more faded and smaller than males. Scutellum light-brown. Meso- and metatarsi lighter in colour, light-brown turning brown towards claws. Opercula almost reaching posterior border of StII but much smaller. T1 and T2 totally dark-brown. Abdominal ventral midline fascia dark-brown very well defined. StVII yellowish and split, with a light-brown groove on each side. Stigma dorsal beak dark-brown. Ovipositor brown with dark-brown tip.
</p>
            <p>
Body measurements for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
males (n=10)

Total length: 27.17 ± 
1.25 mm
; Pronotal length: 2.79 ± 
0.13 mm
; Mesonotal length: 4.35 ± 
0.26 mm
; Forewing length: 21.26 ± 
0.97 mm
; M+CuA length: 1.26 ± 
0.19 mm
. Female and additional body measurements can be found on 
Table 3
.
</p>
            <p>Bioacoustics
The male acoustic signals here described are based on the analysis of the calling song of six males recorded at T= 38–40 °C (see 

). The typical calling song is composed by the repetition of a phrase subdivided into two parts: A—a first single, short echeme and B—a longer group composed of 9 ± 7.461 echemes (6–50, n=124) and the interval between parts A and B has a duration of 155±53 ms (112–539 ms; n=99). In 23.6% of the phrases part A was absent. We also report a single calling song with a continuous phrase without any apparent pauses.
</p>
            <p>Peak frequency of all calling songs is at 11.72 ± 0.79 kHz, maximum and minimum frequencies are 18.45 ± 1.74 kHz and 4.14 ± 0.44 kHz, respectively.</p>
            <p>
Additional temporal and frequency-based variables are indicated in 
Table 4
. Because of the similarities in frequencies of parts A and B, these were grouped in the same analysis.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
is morphologically similar to all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. but presents some peculiarities, allowing for its ready separation from its closest relatives. With an average total body length of 
27 mm
, it seems to be the genus’ largest species (Mendes 
et al.
2014, Simões 
et al
. 2014, 
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
). 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
shows unique colour traits: all examined specimens have a black stripe running across the entire length of the ventral surface of the abdomen and an olive-green arrow-shaped stripe in the pronotum midline, which, upon death, fades over time to a paler shade of green in dry specimens (see image S5 for a live male bearing the typical olive-green stripe on the pronotum).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>Male (n=10) Female (n=3) Male (n=13) Female (n=1)</p>
            <p>Bođy region Cođe Mean ± SD Min%Max Mean ± SD Min%Max Mean ± SD Min%Max</p>
            <p>Heađ anđ thorax TL 27.31 ± 1.11 25.93%29.21 25.84 ± 1.16 24.72%27.03 16.99 ± 0.78 15.59%18.30 17.30</p>
            <p>HL 2.05 ± 0.12 1.86%2.20 1.98 ± 0.06 1.93%2.02 1.47 ± 0.11 1.24%1.61 - HW 5.97 ± 0.21 5.72%6.29 5.64 ± 0.32 5.41%5.86 3.86 ± 0.15 3.56%4.13 - EO 0.77 ± 0.04 0.71%0.84 0.76 ± 0.03 0.73%0.78 0.54 ± 0.05 0.46%0.61 - OO 1.37 ± 0.05 1.3%1.46 1.34 ± 0.18 1.22%1.47 0.89 ± 0.04 0.81%0.96 - LrL 1.15 ± 0.11 1.01%1.37 1.05 ± 0.16 0.94%1.16 0.85 ± 0.08 0.76%1.04 - LiL 2.92 ± 0.14 2.66%3.10 2.62 ± 0.07 2.57%2.67 1.97 ± 0.11 1.70%2.15 - VW 2.91 ± 0.12 2.71%3.10 2.82 ± 0.25 2.64%2.99 1.91 ± 0.12 1.68%2.06 - FR 0.62 ± 0.05 0.55%0.69 0.6 ± 0.03 0.59%0.62 0.40 ± 0.06 0.31%0.52 - PC 2.36 ± 0.11 2.23%2.50 2.28 ± 0.01 2.28%2.29 1.54 ± 0.09 1.36%1.66 - PL 2.82 ± 0.09 2.67%2.95 2.66 ± 0.25 2.48%2.83 1.74 ± 0.15 1.46%1.98 - PW 6.71 ± 0.37 6.20%7.34 6.31 ± 0.43 6.01%6.62 4.31 ± 0.26 3.65%4.58 - ML 4.40 ± 0.19 4.15%4.68 4.12 ± 0.52 3.76%4.49 2.67 ± 0.11 2.43%2.85 -</p>
            <p>Abđomen OP 3.92 ± 0.17 3.64%4.17 1.76 ± 0.22 1.60%1.91 2.55 ± 0.16 2.09%2.73 - LS 1.62 ± 0.09 1.52%1.77 - - 1.32 ± 0.13 1.03%1.49 - TyL 1.53 ± 0.06 1.43%1.64 - - 0.99 ± 0.07 0.90%1.14 - TyW 2.84 ± 0.06 2.76%2.95 - - 1.93 ± 0.10 1.67%2.06 -</p>
            <p>Legs PF 3.20 ± 0.11 3.05%3.36 3.08 ± 0.06 3.04%3.13 2.10 ± 0.15 1.78%2.26 -</p>
            <p>Wings FwL 21.37 ± 0.85 20.16%22.84 20.28 ± 0.91 19.42%21.23 13.39 ± 0.54 12.42%14.27 13.59</p>
            <p>
FwW 7.50 ± 0.27 7.13%7.88 7.11 ± 0.48 6.67%7.62 5.37 ± 0.84 4.87%8.10 5.10 
BCL
1.85 ± 0.14 1.68%2.06 1.72 ± 0.10 1.62%1.81 1.23 ± 0.11 1.09%1.42 1.24 McuA 1.26 ± 0.18 0.92%1.48 1.34 ± 0.21 1.10%1.50 1.21 ± 0.18 0.94%1.41 1.22 RCL 8.53 ± 0.36 7.93%9.16 8.32 ± 0.39 7.95%8.72 6.12 ± 0.36 5.20%6.59 6.24 
<tp:taxon-name>afroamissa
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>variables
Mean±SD Min%Max n Mean±SD Min%Max n Mean±SD Min%Max n Duration (ms) 726 ± 582 314%3749 124 10 ± 4.5 5%27 97 720 ± 580 309%3733 124 Echeme đuration (ms) - - - Same as above 20.97 ± 8.26 5%43 1364 Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) - - - - - - 16.21 ± 1.73 10.88%19.42 1364 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara</tp:taxon-name>
12.0 18.6 19.6 18.6 18.9 20.0 19.5 19.6 19.4 19.5 19.3 18.4 19.4 19.1 19.4 19.9 20.2 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni</tp:taxon-name>
13.3 17.2 19.3 19.3 19.1 20.0 19.7 19.5 19.4 20.6 18.4 19.3 19.2 18.9 18.7 19.0 18.7 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes</tp:taxon-name>
21.5 19.6 11.4 12.4 11.2 11.7 12.4 12.3 12.0 12.0 11.2 10.9 11.3 11.4 10.9 12.9 9.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei</tp:taxon-name>
22.9 22.4 12.5 9.6 8.1 10.8 10.7 10.6 10.3 9.7 10.0 9.2 9.0 9.6 9.4 11.4 9.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna gastrica</tp:taxon-name>
21.5 22.4 13.8 10.4 9.8 12.4 13.5 13.2 13.3 12.7 11.4 11.4 11.6 12.4 11.3 12.4 11.5 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai</tp:taxon-name>
21.9 22.2 12.3 8.7 10.7 10.4 10.6 10.6 10.3 9.6 11.0 9.0 8.6 9.0 8.9 11.5 9.7 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrelae</tp:taxon-name>
23.4 23.3 12.9 11.7 13.7 11.3 
7.7 7.4 7.8 5.3 9.2 5.8 5.1 5.4 4.8 9.5
11.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 23.0 13.7 11.7 15.0 11.6 
8.3 1.7 1.9 7.4 9.6 6.3 6.6 6.4 7.3 10.4
11.1 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae</tp:taxon-name>
22.8 22.7 13.7 11.6 14.7 11.6 
8.0 1.8 1.2 7.1 9.4 6.1 6.2 6.1 6.9 10.8
10.7. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 22.6 13.3 11.2 14.8 11.2 
8.4 1.9 1.2 7.3 8.8 5.9 6.7 6.0 7.2 10.4
10.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
22.8 24.2 13.2 10.5 14.0 10.3 
5.6 7.9 7.6 7.8 9.2 5.6 4.3 5.4 4.9 9.8
11.6. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei</tp:taxon-name>
22.5 21.1 12.2 10.7 12.5 11.9 
10.0 10.4 10.2 9.5 10.0 8.0 8.7 7.9 8.5 9.6
10.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi helianthemi</tp:taxon-name>
21.3 22.4 11.9 9.9 12.5 9.7 
6.1 6.7 6.4 6.3 5.9 8.5 3.4 5.2 5.2 9.2
10.5. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi galantei</tp:taxon-name>
22.6 22.3 12.4 9.6 12.7 9.2 
5.3 7.0 6.6 7.1 4.5 9.4 3.6 5.0 4.3 9.0
11.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi</tp:taxon-name>
22.2 21.9 12.5 10.4 13.7 9.6 
5.7 6.8 6.5 6.4 5.7 8.5 5.5 5.2 3.7 9.0
10.4. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 21.6 11.9 10.1 12.3 9.5 
5.0 7.8 7.3 7.7 5.2 9.1 5.5 4.5 3.9 8.3
10.9 Acoustic analysis enables easy and accurate identification of all 
Tetigettalna
species. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
is no exception. Its calling song is structurally different from all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp., although reminiscent of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Interval (ms)326 ± 116186%90694---51.20 ± 7.0726%63 1340Frequency variablesPeak frequencyMin frequencyMax frequencyBanđwiđthQuartile 25Quartile 50Quartile 75Quartile (75%-25%)Mean ± SD Min%Max11.72 ± 0.79 7.21%14.254.14 ± 0.44 3.93%8.8118.45 ± 1.74 15.46%23.8114.30 ± 1.87 7.68%19.879.93 ± 0.56 7.59%10.9611.50 ± 0.48 10.03%12.7512.82 ± 0.45 11.25%14.342.89 ± 0.55 1.41%4.69</p>
            <p>
The song of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
can be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
for it has higher echeme rate (t= 16.21 ± 1.73 echemes.s -1 vs t= 12.82 ± 1.49 echemes.s -1) and a shorter inter-echeme interval (t= 51.20 ± 7.07 ms vs t= 71.00 ± 13.00 ms) (Mendes 
et al.
2014).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
has a typical calling song with a short echeme (t= 200 ± 110 ms) followed by a long echeme (t= 2.17 ± 
0.30 s
), whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
this initial echeme is even shorter (t= 10 ± 4.5 ms), followed by a succession of very short echemes (t=720 ± 580 ms), instead of a single one. Inter-phrase interval is also much shorter for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
(t= 326 ± 116 ms) than for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
(t= 3270 ± 680 ms). For additional time and frequency measurements regarding 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
see 
Puissant &amp; Sueur (2010)
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>DNA barcoding
Males from all sampled locations were sequenced for COI. Four haplotypes were recovered in a total of 10 sequences. The dataset includes one non-synonymous mutation and a total of 14 polymorphic sites, corresponding to a nucleotide diversity of π=0.1075. All 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
sequences grouped in a fully supported monophyletic clade (

) and intraspecific pairwise distances (K2P) varied from 0.5 to 2.1 %. This clade clusters with remaining 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. in an unresolved polytomy. Mean genetic distances among 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and all other species of the genus are shown in 
Table 5
, and vary from 8.9% (with 
<tp:taxon-name>T. defauti</tp:taxon-name>
) to 11.9 % (with 
<tp:taxon-name>T. mariae</tp:taxon-name>
). Thus, the genetic distance associated with the fragment of COI used here, the “barcode gap”, is high enough to be used for DNA barcoding of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Habitat
(

) An arboreal species, inhabiting open Mediterranean-type woodland and tall scrubland. This species has been scored singing mainly on holm-oak trees (
<tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
) and bushes such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cistus</tp:taxon-name>
spp. but locally, in the Rif, it was found on pine trees (
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
spp.) (

B), 
<tp:taxon-name>Abies pinsapo
var. 
marocana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cedrus atlantica</tp:taxon-name>
(

C) and almond trees 

(
<tp:taxon-name>Prunus dulcis</tp:taxon-name>
)

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>DistributionNorthernMorocco
, along the Rif Mountains and nearby Mediterranean coastline between Tetuan and Al Hoceima. Also found in the northern parts of the Middle Atlas, near Taza (

). Not found near 
Ceuta
or 
Tangier
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Specific epithet formed by combining the suffix 
afro
(pertaining to Africa) and the prefix 
amissa
, feminine of the latin āmissus, meaning “having been lost” or “let go”. Literal translation would be “cicada (of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
) left / lost in Africa” as this new species is the only 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. known so far to occur in Africa, the remaining being European.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
This genus can be readily distinguished from other morphologically similar genera by the analysis of the male genitalia. The type species has a very large tube-like aedeagus with two pseudoparamers fused until three quarters of total thecal length, ending in a sharp-tip and about of the same length as the endotheca (see 

F). Therefore, it can be distinguished from the similar genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
(type species: 
<tp:taxon-name>T. baenai(Boulard, 2000))</tp:taxon-name>
for the latter has two unfused thick pseudoparamers arising dorsally from base of the theca, and separate from the endotheca (
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta
Kolenati, 1857
</tp:taxon-name>
(type species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta montana
(Scopoli, 1772))
</tp:taxon-name>
in aedeagus morphology: 
<tp:taxon-name>C. montana</tp:taxon-name>
shows a similarly long aedeagus, yet the pseudoparamers are exceedingly long and partly unfused, surpassing the distal end of theca by about half its length (
Moulds 2012
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type species<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
designed by monotypy.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Name formed by combining the suffix 
Berber
(pertaining to the Maghrebian Roman region, Barbaria, and the prevailing ethnic group in northern Maghreb) and the prefix –getta, an arbitrary combination of letters associated with small cicada species, as in 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigetta</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
Paratypical series consists of a total of 14 specimens (13 males and one female). Designated holotype is SP19_3795 (♂), and female paratype is SP19_3787 (♀). See 
Table 2
for additional information on paratypical series, specimen IDs, collection sites and GPS data. See 

for images on male holotype, female paratype (see supplementary image, S6 for live specimens) and details of the male genitalia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Male morphology</p>
            <p>Head
Supra-antennal plate produced into a pointed lobe; Supra-antennal plate nearly meeting the eye. Postclypeus subquadrate to round in front view; Postclypeus transversely grooved towards distal ends. Rostrum brown, reaching the center of mid-trochanters when in resting position. Antennae brown, 7-segmented. Postclypeus dark brown, with apical yellowish-brown spot, grooves light-brown or yellowish; Anteclypeus yellowish with a brown central spot. Gena and lorum brown to light-brown covered with white long pilosity. Supra-antennal plates light brown distally near the eye, becoming dark-brown towards midline. Three red ocelli. Eyes light-brown. Dorsal surface of head dark-brown, supraocular border brown, with yellowish stripe on epicranial suture.
</p>
            <p>Thorax
Pronotal collar broad, slightly greater than eye width; Pronotal lateral development ampliate, sloping in lateral view, evenly rounded in dorsal view. Pronotal mid-lateral tooth absent. Scutellum wider than long. Epimeral lobe not reaching operculum. Metanotum partly visible at dorsal midline, not expanded over tymbals. Pronotum brown with a dark-brown stripe along dorsal midline, ending posteriorly in dark-brown spot. Mesonotum with two yellowish fasciae bordering between parapsidal suture and submedian sigillae prolonging to anterior arms of scutellum; Mesonotal lateral dorsal margins yellowish. 
Central
area of scutellum brown with yellowish arms. Metanotum yellowish, brown at dorsal midline.
</p>
            <p>Legs
Profemur with a large primary erect spine plus two smaller secondary spines dark-brown/ brownish in colour, some individuals with a much smaller fourth spine. Meracanthus triangular. Tarsal formula 3-3-3. General brown to yellowish in colour. Metatibiae with four long fine reddish spurs on inner side and two smaller reddish spurs on outer side. Coxae yellowish, with a central dark-brown stripe, becoming gradually browner and less yellowish towards metacoxae. Trochanters brown. Meso and metafemurs yellowish with dark-brown to brownish stripes. Tarsi and tibia light-brown.
</p>
            <p>Wings
Forewing with eight apical and four subapical cells. Ulnar cell 3 angled to radial cell. Costal vein parallel-sided to node. Pterostigma present becoming darker towards distal end. CuA weakly bowed. M and CuA meeting at basal cell with stems completely fused. RA1 slightly diverging from subcostal at subapical region before crossvein. C and R+Sc close together. CuP and 1A non-fused at their bases. Forewing outer margin developed for its total length. Membrane hyaline. Hindwing vein 2A with an infuscation running alongside total length of vein. First cubital cell width at distal end much greater than second cubital cell. Anal lobe broad, with vein 3A bowed at distal end. Larger forewing proximal veins yellowish with smaller apical veins brown, same vein colour pattern for hindwing. Costal vein yellowish. Basal membrane and plaga yellowish.
</p>
            <p>Opercula
More or less confluent with distal margin of tympanal cavity, well developed towards abdominal midline with sharply rounded apices facing midline. General opercula colour yellowish becoming brown at the base. Meracanthus following the same colour pattern as opercula.
</p>
            <p>Tymbals
Tymbal covers absent. Four to five ribs, broadening apically, three of which arising from anterior proximal part of a large basal dome covering over half total length of tymbal. First anterior rib is slender, with a break at about a third of its length. Fourth rib arising from anterior distal side of basal dome more or less evident amongst individuals. Some specimens present a fifth less defined rib arising from posterior distal end of the basal dome, transversal to fourth rib and converging in a sharp end. Tymbal ribs and basal dome brownish-grey; tymbal plate light-grey.
</p>
            <p>Abdomen
Tergites T2 and T3 much enlarged accounting for about a third of total abdominal length. StVIII greater in length than StVII. T1 and T2 dark-brown; T4–7 dark-brown on dorsal midline, sides red and covered in fine silvery pubescence; T8 dark-brown on dorsal midline, sides yellowish. Sternite I brown; StII yellowish with a brown patch on elevated central area; StIII–VIII yellowish. Epipleurites yellowish.
</p>
            <p>Genitalia
(

C to 6F) Pygophore distal shoulder not developed; Pygophore inner tooth absent; Upper lobe present, small and rounded, distant from dorsal beak; Basal lobe small to moderately developed ending in a sharp, rounded tip, in lateral view. Dorsal beak well developed, sharp and part of chitinized pygophore. Ventrobasal pocket absent. Claspers small-medium sized, hooked slightly outwards on distal end, rounded tip. Uncus duck-bill shaped, small and flat, not dominant and retractable within pygophore; Uncus lateral lobes absent. Aedeagal basal plate, undulated in lateral view, weakly depressed on dorsal midline; Basal plate apically broad, flat and rounded in ventral view, with a medial small sharp-tipped lobe on both sides, followed by a tubelike constriction leading to theca, gradually narrowing, slight medial lateral depression; Basal plate bearing a ripple-like pattern in dorsal view. Basal portion directed forwards away from thecal shaft; Ventral rib not apparent; Basal plate completely fused to theca without mobility. Theca very long and J-shaped in lateral view. Thecal pseudoparamers lateral of theca, dorsally fused until two thirds of theca length, very flat, as long as endotheca, ending on an upward pointed, sharp tip; Ventral support absent. Pygophore dorsal surface lightbrown to yellow. Claspers dark-brown. Uncus brown.
</p>
            <p>Female morphology
Only one female known so far (see supplementary image, S6 for the live specimen). Generally lighter in colour than male. Postclypeus yellowish with brown grooves, genae and lora light brown; Legs generally light brown; Dorsal surface of head light-brown with brown patterns; thorax and scutellum lightbrown. Abdomen light brown laterally, with a lighter brown on dorsal midline.
</p>
            <p>
Body measurements for 
13 males
of
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Total
</tp:taxon-name>
length: 16.99 ± 
0.78 mm
; Pronotal length: 1.74 ± 
0.15 mm
; Mesonotal length: 2.67 ± 
0.11 mm
; Forewing length: 13.39 ± 
0.54 mm
; M+CuA length: 1.21 ± 
0.18 mm
. Female and additional body measurements can be found on 
Table 3
.
</p>
            <p>Bioacoustics
The calling song here described is based on the analysis of recordings of three males singing at T=39–40 °C. A typical phrase is structured into four sequential parts (

): A, a single echeme; B, a series of 16 ± 2.60 echemes (10–21, n=52) in rapid succession; C, a group of 8 ± 3.68 echemes (5–18, n= 53) ending on D, a single, long echeme. In 21.15% and 9.61% of the phrases part A and part D are missing, respectively.
</p>
            <p>Calling song frequency-based analysis revealed an interesting frequency modulation in part B. Peak frequency for parts A, C and D is 13.88 ± 0.79 kHz, with maximum frequency of 20.65 ± 0.54 kHz. During part B there is an abrupt reduction of the frequency with a peak frequency of 7.91 ± 1.62 kHz, yet, maintaining the maximum frequency at 21.62 ± 1.11 kHz.</p>
            <p>
For additional time and frequency variables consult 
Table 6
. Note that, due to frequency modulation in part B, it was separated from parts A, C and D in our analysis.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>Time variables Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n</p>
            <p>
Duration (ms) 2218 ± 559 1357–3448 52 30 ± 
10 15–56
47 335 ± 52 212–411 52
</p>
            <p>Echeme duration (ms) - - - Same as above 2.14 ± 1.06 0.8–7 849</p>
            <p>Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) - - - - - - 49.16 ± 6.08 36.08–72.67 52</p>
            <p>Interval (ms) 259 ± 82 195–614 49 - - - 19.55 ± 5.31 2.8–55 797</p>
            <p>Part C Part D</p>
            <p>Time variables Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n</p>
            <p>Duration (ms) 1364 ± 679 632–2992 53 252. 29 ± 79.23 97–430 41</p>
            <p>Echeme duration (ms) 49.2 ±20.6 5–253 487 Same as above</p>
            <p>Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) 7.10 ± 1.04 3.34–10.32 53 - - -</p>
            <p>Interval (ms) 108.83 ± 22.24 34–260 435 - - -</p>
            <p>continued.</p>
            <p>Frequency variables Peak frequency Min frequency Max frequency Bandwidth</p>
            <p>Part ACD Mean ± SD 13.88 ± 0.79 4.65 ± 0.96 20.65 ± 0.54 15.94 ± 1.31 Min–Max 11.50–15.50 1.96–6.00 18.70–22.40 12.80–19.78</p>
            <p>Part B Mean ± SD 7.91 ± 1.62 4.39 ± 1.01 21.62 ± 1.11 17.14 ± 1.59 Min–Max 5.60–16.50 0.30–5.80 13.92–23.40 9.04–22.80</p>
            <p>Frequency variables Quartile 25 Quartile 50 Quartile 75 Quartile (75%–25%)</p>
            <p>Part ACD Mean ± SD 11.91 ± 0.22 13.48 ± 0.27 14.89 ± 0.32 2.98 ± 0.26</p>
            <p>Min–Max 10.70–12.50 12.28–14.40 13.40–15.80 1.87–4.10</p>
            <p>Part B Mean ± SD 7.54 ± 0.61 9.57 ± 0.79 11.61 ± 1.26 4.07 ± 0.93</p>
            <p>
Min–Max 6.30–12.00 7.50–13.50 9.70–17.50 2.70–8.20 
DNA
barcoding

Four haplotypes were recovered among the 
COI
sequences of nine males of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, with a nucleotide diversity of π= 0.0164. Sequences were clustered into two well supported sister clades (

) diverging by 2.9 % (K2P distance). These clades are, according to our currently knowledge, geographically segregated. Among the 18 segregating sites observed, 16 are fixed for each clade, being two of them non-synonymous mutations. Mean interspecific genetic distances for 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
are presented in 
Table 5
. The new species is clearly distinguishable within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura</tp:taxon-name>
), with mean pairwise genetic distances&gt;10%. The 
COI
fragment is therefore apparently proficient for 
DNA
barcoding of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
, though the genetic structure reported here must be taken into account.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution
(

) 
Morocco
, in the northern parts of Middle Atlas Mountains, near Taza and along the eastern Rif mountains (Al Hoceima), eastward to Berkane (Beni-Snassen Mountains), as the extreme western foot of the Tellian Atlas Mountains. On biogeographical grounds it is possible that this species is also in western 
Algeria
.
</p>
            <p>Habitat
(

) Open scrubland or light xerothermophilous woodland dominated by holm-oak (
<tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
) in the northern Middle Atlas or mixed pinewoods of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus halepensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraclinis articulata</tp:taxon-name>
with a rich understory of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Chamaerops humilis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Rosmarinus officinalis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Stipa</tp:taxon-name>
spp. Males sing mainly perched on these shrubs, and sometimes on the lower branches of trees (&lt;
3 m
height).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
arises from the dual sound production during the calling song of this species, meaning “two melodies”. It consists of two distinct sound patterns, with the second part severely downshifted in frequency and resembling a human-produced unvoiced linguolabial trill, often referred as “Blowing a raspberry”.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. aneabi
(
Boulard, 2000
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. armandiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. defautiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. estrellae
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi
(Rambur, 1840)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. josei
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. mariae
(Quartau &amp; Boulard, 1995)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>afroamissa
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna gastrica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrelae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi helianthemi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi galantei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. barbara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. orni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. defauti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. mariae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cistus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Abies pinsapo
var. 
marocana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cedrus atlantica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Prunus dulcis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. baenai(Boulard, 2000))</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta
Kolenati, 1857
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta montana
(Scopoli, 1772))
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. montana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Total
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pinus halepensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tetraclinis articulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Chamaerops humilis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rosmarinus officinalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Stipa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Morphology, songs and genetics identify two new cicada species from Morocco: Tettigettalna afroamissa sp. nov. and Berberigetta dimelodica gen. nov. &amp; sp. nov. (Hemiptera: Cicadettini)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4237.3.4</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/68618D0CFF8A6406FFAF9E2FFFDFFF9A</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4237.3.4</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant 2010</tp:taxon-name>
Originally described and diagnosed by 
Puissant &amp; Sueur (2010)
, encompasses nine European species: 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. aneabi
(
Boulard, 2000
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. armandiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. defautiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. estrellae
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi
(Rambur, 1840)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. josei
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T. mariae
(Quartau &amp; Boulard, 1995)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Only 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
is widespread, reaching, France, Italy, Switzerland and Slovenia to the east. The remaining are (rather) narrow Iberian endemics (see 

).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
nov. gen. Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
Paratypical series consist of 13 specimens (ten males and three females). Designated holotype is SP18_3779 (♂) and female paratype is SP18_3780 (♀). See 
Table 2
for additional information on the paratypical series, specimen IDs, collection sites and GPS data. See 

for images of male holotype, female paratype and for details of the male genitalia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Male morphology</p>
            <p>Head
Head slightly less broad than pronotum; Supra-antennal plates nearly meeting the eye and produced into a pointed lobe; Postclypeus rounded to subquadrate in frontal view, rounded between top and sides in lateral view, transversely grooved towards distal ends; Rostrum brown, reaching the center of mid-trochanters (in rest). Antennae dark-brown, 7-segmented. Dorsal surface of head brown with front bearing a yellowish stripe extending to outer borders; Yellowish stripe at beginning of epicranial suture extending to pronotum. Eyes brown, three red ocelli. Postclypeus dark brown, with apical yellowish-brown spot extending to frons, grooves light-brown or yellowish. Supra-antennal plates dark-brown and yellowish-brown towards distal ends. Gena and lorum brown to dark-brown covered in long white pilosity. Anteclypeus brown to dark-brown with a lighter brownish fascia surrounding a central dark-brown spot.
</p>
            <p>Thorax
Pronotal collar slightly larger than head width, widened, sloping laterally and evenly rounded dorsally. Pronotal tooth present mid-laterally. Scutellum wider than long. Epimeral lobe not reaching operculum. Submedian sigillae well defined. Metanotum partly visible at dorsal midline not expanded over tymbals. Pronotum with an olive-green arrow shaped stripe at dorsal midline bordered with dark-brown in fresh specimens (in preserved specimens this fades away to light brown). Remainder of pronotum brown, with dark-brown markings bearing yellowish borders. Mesonotum on overall brown, with a lighter “crown-like” marking, lateral margins of mesonotum yellowish. Scutellum brown, with a longitudinal dark-brown fascia at midline expanding towards the ends, reaching metanotum. Sides of scutellum with a dense pilosity on lateral-anterior ends with a fading gradient of dark-brown to yellowish towards the posterior end with defined, longitudinal, slightly transverse grooves. Metanotum brown, with a dark-brown patch at dorsal midline. Ventral side of thorax brown.
</p>
            <p>Legs
Profemur with three to four dark-brown erect spines. Primary spine clearly separated. Metatibiae with three to four long fine spurs on inner side, and two smaller spurs on outer side with finely dispersed white pilosity. Apex of metatibia surrounded by smaller numerous brown spurs. Tarsal formula: 3-3-3. Legs generally brown in colour. Coxae and trochanters yellowish with a central dark-brown stripe, better defined on the hind legs. Femurs and tibiae brown with two dark-brown longitudinal fasciae. Profemurs with a swollen dark brown fascia surrounded by two yellowish/ light brown stripes, varying somewhat among individuals. Dark-brown border along the spines. Tarsi dark-brown on dorsal side, brown on ventral side. Protarsi darker in colour.
</p>
            <p>Wings
Forewing and hindwing with eight and six apical cells, respectively. Ulnar cell 3 angled towards radial cell; Forewing costa parallel-sided to radial cell; Pterostigma present. CuA vein weakly bowed; M+CuA meeting at basal cell with stems fused. Vein RA1 aligned closely with subcostal for its length. CuA1 divided by a crossvein with shorter proximal part. CuP and 1A unfused at their bases. Veins C and R+Sc close together. Outer forewing margin developed for its total length. Hindwing first cubital cell width at distal end much greater than second cubital cell. Hindwing anal lobe broad with 3A vein long and strongly curved at distal end. Hindwing RP and M veins fused at their base. Larger forewing proximal veins yellowish with smaller apical veins brown, same for hindwing. Forewing basal membrane yellow. Hindwing plaga yellow.
</p>
            <p>Opercula
More or less confluent with distal margin of tympanal cavity, well developed towards abdominal midline with sharply rounded apices facing midline. Opercula extending but not reaching posterior border of StII. Opercula distally yellow, dark-brown at base. Meracanthus triangular, following same colour pattern as opercula.
</p>
            <p>Tymbals
Tymbals lacking a tymbal cover. Five ribs, four of which arising from top of a large basal dome, covering about half the tymbal width, and expanding in width towards the posterior side. Fifth rib as an extension of basal dome more or less defined, varying between specimens. First and second anterior ribs, slender, with a transverse break at about halfway of basal dome. Tymbal plate light-grey, ribs and basal dome brownish-grey.
</p>
            <p>Abdomen
Abdomen with somewhat scattered white pilosity. T1 uniformly dark-brown; T2 uniformly darkbrown with a transversal stripe, slightly pointed towards posterior end of abdomen on each side; T3 to T7 darkbrown anteriorly becoming lighter on posterior side; T8 dark-brown. StI mainly dark-brown, yellow posterior margin; StII mainly dark-brown, with yellow lateral borders. StIII to StVI light brown, with a brown spot at midline, forming a well-defined stripe. StVII large, brown, as long as or slightly longer than StVIII; StVIII brown, densely covered in pilosity. Epipleurites brown with yellow posterior border.
</p>
            <p>Genitalia
(

E to 2H) Pygophore dark-brown on dorsal surface and brown on lateral sides. Pygophore distal shoulder not developed. Pygophore inner tooth absent. Upper lobe flat and moderately developed, distant from dorsal beak with a sharply rounded tip; Basal lobe present, moderately developed and rounded in lateral view. Dorsal beak present and part of chitinized pygophore. Claspers dark-brown, medium-sized, closely aligned ending on a rounded, sharp tip. Uncus brown, duck-bill shaped, small and flat, not dominant. Uncus lateral lobes absent. Aedeagus basal plate, in lateral view, with an undulated ventral surface skewed towards the proximal end; In ventral view, apically broad with a small constriction mid-ventrally expanding afterwards with a midgroove between two longitudinally expanded lobes; Basal portion of basal plate directed forwards and away from thecal shaft; Basal plate ventral rib not apparent; Basal plate attached with a functional membranous “hinge”. Theca, in lateral view, curved into a gentle arc; Thecal pseudoparamers present, dorsal of theca, originating closer to theca than its base; Endothecal ventral support present; Thecal aperture upper diagonal in lateral view.
</p>
            <p>Female morphology
Females overall slightly darker than males. Pronotal posterior border light-brown. Mesonotal “crown-like” mark much more faded and smaller than males. Scutellum light-brown. Meso- and metatarsi lighter in colour, light-brown turning brown towards claws. Opercula almost reaching posterior border of StII but much smaller. T1 and T2 totally dark-brown. Abdominal ventral midline fascia dark-brown very well defined. StVII yellowish and split, with a light-brown groove on each side. Stigma dorsal beak dark-brown. Ovipositor brown with dark-brown tip.
</p>
            <p>
Body measurements for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
males (n=10)

Total length: 27.17 ± 
1.25 mm
; Pronotal length: 2.79 ± 
0.13 mm
; Mesonotal length: 4.35 ± 
0.26 mm
; Forewing length: 21.26 ± 
0.97 mm
; M+CuA length: 1.26 ± 
0.19 mm
. Female and additional body measurements can be found on 
Table 3
.
</p>
            <p>Bioacoustics
The male acoustic signals here described are based on the analysis of the calling song of six males recorded at T= 38–40 °C (see 

). The typical calling song is composed by the repetition of a phrase subdivided into two parts: A—a first single, short echeme and B—a longer group composed of 9 ± 7.461 echemes (6–50, n=124) and the interval between parts A and B has a duration of 155±53 ms (112–539 ms; n=99). In 23.6% of the phrases part A was absent. We also report a single calling song with a continuous phrase without any apparent pauses.
</p>
            <p>Peak frequency of all calling songs is at 11.72 ± 0.79 kHz, maximum and minimum frequencies are 18.45 ± 1.74 kHz and 4.14 ± 0.44 kHz, respectively.</p>
            <p>
Additional temporal and frequency-based variables are indicated in 
Table 4
. Because of the similarities in frequencies of parts A and B, these were grouped in the same analysis.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
is morphologically similar to all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. but presents some peculiarities, allowing for its ready separation from its closest relatives. With an average total body length of 
27 mm
, it seems to be the genus’ largest species (Mendes 
et al.
2014, Simões 
et al
. 2014, 
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
). 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
shows unique colour traits: all examined specimens have a black stripe running across the entire length of the ventral surface of the abdomen and an olive-green arrow-shaped stripe in the pronotum midline, which, upon death, fades over time to a paler shade of green in dry specimens (see image S5 for a live male bearing the typical olive-green stripe on the pronotum).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>Male (n=10) Female (n=3) Male (n=13) Female (n=1)</p>
            <p>Bođy region Cođe Mean ± SD Min%Max Mean ± SD Min%Max Mean ± SD Min%Max</p>
            <p>Heađ anđ thorax TL 27.31 ± 1.11 25.93%29.21 25.84 ± 1.16 24.72%27.03 16.99 ± 0.78 15.59%18.30 17.30</p>
            <p>HL 2.05 ± 0.12 1.86%2.20 1.98 ± 0.06 1.93%2.02 1.47 ± 0.11 1.24%1.61 - HW 5.97 ± 0.21 5.72%6.29 5.64 ± 0.32 5.41%5.86 3.86 ± 0.15 3.56%4.13 - EO 0.77 ± 0.04 0.71%0.84 0.76 ± 0.03 0.73%0.78 0.54 ± 0.05 0.46%0.61 - OO 1.37 ± 0.05 1.3%1.46 1.34 ± 0.18 1.22%1.47 0.89 ± 0.04 0.81%0.96 - LrL 1.15 ± 0.11 1.01%1.37 1.05 ± 0.16 0.94%1.16 0.85 ± 0.08 0.76%1.04 - LiL 2.92 ± 0.14 2.66%3.10 2.62 ± 0.07 2.57%2.67 1.97 ± 0.11 1.70%2.15 - VW 2.91 ± 0.12 2.71%3.10 2.82 ± 0.25 2.64%2.99 1.91 ± 0.12 1.68%2.06 - FR 0.62 ± 0.05 0.55%0.69 0.6 ± 0.03 0.59%0.62 0.40 ± 0.06 0.31%0.52 - PC 2.36 ± 0.11 2.23%2.50 2.28 ± 0.01 2.28%2.29 1.54 ± 0.09 1.36%1.66 - PL 2.82 ± 0.09 2.67%2.95 2.66 ± 0.25 2.48%2.83 1.74 ± 0.15 1.46%1.98 - PW 6.71 ± 0.37 6.20%7.34 6.31 ± 0.43 6.01%6.62 4.31 ± 0.26 3.65%4.58 - ML 4.40 ± 0.19 4.15%4.68 4.12 ± 0.52 3.76%4.49 2.67 ± 0.11 2.43%2.85 -</p>
            <p>Abđomen OP 3.92 ± 0.17 3.64%4.17 1.76 ± 0.22 1.60%1.91 2.55 ± 0.16 2.09%2.73 - LS 1.62 ± 0.09 1.52%1.77 - - 1.32 ± 0.13 1.03%1.49 - TyL 1.53 ± 0.06 1.43%1.64 - - 0.99 ± 0.07 0.90%1.14 - TyW 2.84 ± 0.06 2.76%2.95 - - 1.93 ± 0.10 1.67%2.06 -</p>
            <p>Legs PF 3.20 ± 0.11 3.05%3.36 3.08 ± 0.06 3.04%3.13 2.10 ± 0.15 1.78%2.26 -</p>
            <p>Wings FwL 21.37 ± 0.85 20.16%22.84 20.28 ± 0.91 19.42%21.23 13.39 ± 0.54 12.42%14.27 13.59</p>
            <p>
FwW 7.50 ± 0.27 7.13%7.88 7.11 ± 0.48 6.67%7.62 5.37 ± 0.84 4.87%8.10 5.10 
BCL
1.85 ± 0.14 1.68%2.06 1.72 ± 0.10 1.62%1.81 1.23 ± 0.11 1.09%1.42 1.24 McuA 1.26 ± 0.18 0.92%1.48 1.34 ± 0.21 1.10%1.50 1.21 ± 0.18 0.94%1.41 1.22 RCL 8.53 ± 0.36 7.93%9.16 8.32 ± 0.39 7.95%8.72 6.12 ± 0.36 5.20%6.59 6.24 
<tp:taxon-name>afroamissa
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>variables
Mean±SD Min%Max n Mean±SD Min%Max n Mean±SD Min%Max n Duration (ms) 726 ± 582 314%3749 124 10 ± 4.5 5%27 97 720 ± 580 309%3733 124 Echeme đuration (ms) - - - Same as above 20.97 ± 8.26 5%43 1364 Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) - - - - - - 16.21 ± 1.73 10.88%19.42 1364 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara</tp:taxon-name>
12.0 18.6 19.6 18.6 18.9 20.0 19.5 19.6 19.4 19.5 19.3 18.4 19.4 19.1 19.4 19.9 20.2 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni</tp:taxon-name>
13.3 17.2 19.3 19.3 19.1 20.0 19.7 19.5 19.4 20.6 18.4 19.3 19.2 18.9 18.7 19.0 18.7 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes</tp:taxon-name>
21.5 19.6 11.4 12.4 11.2 11.7 12.4 12.3 12.0 12.0 11.2 10.9 11.3 11.4 10.9 12.9 9.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei</tp:taxon-name>
22.9 22.4 12.5 9.6 8.1 10.8 10.7 10.6 10.3 9.7 10.0 9.2 9.0 9.6 9.4 11.4 9.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna gastrica</tp:taxon-name>
21.5 22.4 13.8 10.4 9.8 12.4 13.5 13.2 13.3 12.7 11.4 11.4 11.6 12.4 11.3 12.4 11.5 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai</tp:taxon-name>
21.9 22.2 12.3 8.7 10.7 10.4 10.6 10.6 10.3 9.6 11.0 9.0 8.6 9.0 8.9 11.5 9.7 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrelae</tp:taxon-name>
23.4 23.3 12.9 11.7 13.7 11.3 
7.7 7.4 7.8 5.3 9.2 5.8 5.1 5.4 4.8 9.5
11.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 23.0 13.7 11.7 15.0 11.6 
8.3 1.7 1.9 7.4 9.6 6.3 6.6 6.4 7.3 10.4
11.1 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae</tp:taxon-name>
22.8 22.7 13.7 11.6 14.7 11.6 
8.0 1.8 1.2 7.1 9.4 6.1 6.2 6.1 6.9 10.8
10.7. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 22.6 13.3 11.2 14.8 11.2 
8.4 1.9 1.2 7.3 8.8 5.9 6.7 6.0 7.2 10.4
10.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
22.8 24.2 13.2 10.5 14.0 10.3 
5.6 7.9 7.6 7.8 9.2 5.6 4.3 5.4 4.9 9.8
11.6. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei</tp:taxon-name>
22.5 21.1 12.2 10.7 12.5 11.9 
10.0 10.4 10.2 9.5 10.0 8.0 8.7 7.9 8.5 9.6
10.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi helianthemi</tp:taxon-name>
21.3 22.4 11.9 9.9 12.5 9.7 
6.1 6.7 6.4 6.3 5.9 8.5 3.4 5.2 5.2 9.2
10.5. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi galantei</tp:taxon-name>
22.6 22.3 12.4 9.6 12.7 9.2 
5.3 7.0 6.6 7.1 4.5 9.4 3.6 5.0 4.3 9.0
11.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi</tp:taxon-name>
22.2 21.9 12.5 10.4 13.7 9.6 
5.7 6.8 6.5 6.4 5.7 8.5 5.5 5.2 3.7 9.0
10.4. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 21.6 11.9 10.1 12.3 9.5 
5.0 7.8 7.3 7.7 5.2 9.1 5.5 4.5 3.9 8.3
10.9 Acoustic analysis enables easy and accurate identification of all 
Tetigettalna
species. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
is no exception. Its calling song is structurally different from all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp., although reminiscent of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Interval (ms)326 ± 116186%90694---51.20 ± 7.0726%63 1340Frequency variablesPeak frequencyMin frequencyMax frequencyBanđwiđthQuartile 25Quartile 50Quartile 75Quartile (75%-25%)Mean ± SD Min%Max11.72 ± 0.79 7.21%14.254.14 ± 0.44 3.93%8.8118.45 ± 1.74 15.46%23.8114.30 ± 1.87 7.68%19.879.93 ± 0.56 7.59%10.9611.50 ± 0.48 10.03%12.7512.82 ± 0.45 11.25%14.342.89 ± 0.55 1.41%4.69</p>
            <p>
The song of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
can be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
for it has higher echeme rate (t= 16.21 ± 1.73 echemes.s -1 vs t= 12.82 ± 1.49 echemes.s -1) and a shorter inter-echeme interval (t= 51.20 ± 7.07 ms vs t= 71.00 ± 13.00 ms) (Mendes 
et al.
2014).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
has a typical calling song with a short echeme (t= 200 ± 110 ms) followed by a long echeme (t= 2.17 ± 
0.30 s
), whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
this initial echeme is even shorter (t= 10 ± 4.5 ms), followed by a succession of very short echemes (t=720 ± 580 ms), instead of a single one. Inter-phrase interval is also much shorter for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
(t= 326 ± 116 ms) than for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
(t= 3270 ± 680 ms). For additional time and frequency measurements regarding 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
see 
Puissant &amp; Sueur (2010)
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>DNA barcoding
Males from all sampled locations were sequenced for COI. Four haplotypes were recovered in a total of 10 sequences. The dataset includes one non-synonymous mutation and a total of 14 polymorphic sites, corresponding to a nucleotide diversity of π=0.1075. All 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
sequences grouped in a fully supported monophyletic clade (

) and intraspecific pairwise distances (K2P) varied from 0.5 to 2.1 %. This clade clusters with remaining 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. in an unresolved polytomy. Mean genetic distances among 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and all other species of the genus are shown in 
Table 5
, and vary from 8.9% (with 
<tp:taxon-name>T. defauti</tp:taxon-name>
) to 11.9 % (with 
<tp:taxon-name>T. mariae</tp:taxon-name>
). Thus, the genetic distance associated with the fragment of COI used here, the “barcode gap”, is high enough to be used for DNA barcoding of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Habitat
(

) An arboreal species, inhabiting open Mediterranean-type woodland and tall scrubland. This species has been scored singing mainly on holm-oak trees (
<tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
) and bushes such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cistus</tp:taxon-name>
spp. but locally, in the Rif, it was found on pine trees (
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
spp.) (

B), 
<tp:taxon-name>Abies pinsapo
var. 
marocana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cedrus atlantica</tp:taxon-name>
(

C) and almond trees 

(
<tp:taxon-name>Prunus dulcis</tp:taxon-name>
)

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>DistributionNorthernMorocco
, along the Rif Mountains and nearby Mediterranean coastline between Tetuan and Al Hoceima. Also found in the northern parts of the Middle Atlas, near Taza (

). Not found near 
Ceuta
or 
Tangier
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Specific epithet formed by combining the suffix 
afro
(pertaining to Africa) and the prefix 
amissa
, feminine of the latin āmissus, meaning “having been lost” or “let go”. Literal translation would be “cicada (of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
) left / lost in Africa” as this new species is the only 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. known so far to occur in Africa, the remaining being European.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
This genus can be readily distinguished from other morphologically similar genera by the analysis of the male genitalia. The type species has a very large tube-like aedeagus with two pseudoparamers fused until three quarters of total thecal length, ending in a sharp-tip and about of the same length as the endotheca (see 

F). Therefore, it can be distinguished from the similar genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
(type species: 
<tp:taxon-name>T. baenai(Boulard, 2000))</tp:taxon-name>
for the latter has two unfused thick pseudoparamers arising dorsally from base of the theca, and separate from the endotheca (
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta
Kolenati, 1857
</tp:taxon-name>
(type species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta montana
(Scopoli, 1772))
</tp:taxon-name>
in aedeagus morphology: 
<tp:taxon-name>C. montana</tp:taxon-name>
shows a similarly long aedeagus, yet the pseudoparamers are exceedingly long and partly unfused, surpassing the distal end of theca by about half its length (
Moulds 2012
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type species<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
designed by monotypy.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Name formed by combining the suffix 
Berber
(pertaining to the Maghrebian Roman region, Barbaria, and the prevailing ethnic group in northern Maghreb) and the prefix –getta, an arbitrary combination of letters associated with small cicada species, as in 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigetta</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
Paratypical series consists of a total of 14 specimens (13 males and one female). Designated holotype is SP19_3795 (♂), and female paratype is SP19_3787 (♀). See 
Table 2
for additional information on paratypical series, specimen IDs, collection sites and GPS data. See 

for images on male holotype, female paratype (see supplementary image, S6 for live specimens) and details of the male genitalia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Male morphology</p>
            <p>Head
Supra-antennal plate produced into a pointed lobe; Supra-antennal plate nearly meeting the eye. Postclypeus subquadrate to round in front view; Postclypeus transversely grooved towards distal ends. Rostrum brown, reaching the center of mid-trochanters when in resting position. Antennae brown, 7-segmented. Postclypeus dark brown, with apical yellowish-brown spot, grooves light-brown or yellowish; Anteclypeus yellowish with a brown central spot. Gena and lorum brown to light-brown covered with white long pilosity. Supra-antennal plates light brown distally near the eye, becoming dark-brown towards midline. Three red ocelli. Eyes light-brown. Dorsal surface of head dark-brown, supraocular border brown, with yellowish stripe on epicranial suture.
</p>
            <p>Thorax
Pronotal collar broad, slightly greater than eye width; Pronotal lateral development ampliate, sloping in lateral view, evenly rounded in dorsal view. Pronotal mid-lateral tooth absent. Scutellum wider than long. Epimeral lobe not reaching operculum. Metanotum partly visible at dorsal midline, not expanded over tymbals. Pronotum brown with a dark-brown stripe along dorsal midline, ending posteriorly in dark-brown spot. Mesonotum with two yellowish fasciae bordering between parapsidal suture and submedian sigillae prolonging to anterior arms of scutellum; Mesonotal lateral dorsal margins yellowish. 
Central
area of scutellum brown with yellowish arms. Metanotum yellowish, brown at dorsal midline.
</p>
            <p>Legs
Profemur with a large primary erect spine plus two smaller secondary spines dark-brown/ brownish in colour, some individuals with a much smaller fourth spine. Meracanthus triangular. Tarsal formula 3-3-3. General brown to yellowish in colour. Metatibiae with four long fine reddish spurs on inner side and two smaller reddish spurs on outer side. Coxae yellowish, with a central dark-brown stripe, becoming gradually browner and less yellowish towards metacoxae. Trochanters brown. Meso and metafemurs yellowish with dark-brown to brownish stripes. Tarsi and tibia light-brown.
</p>
            <p>Wings
Forewing with eight apical and four subapical cells. Ulnar cell 3 angled to radial cell. Costal vein parallel-sided to node. Pterostigma present becoming darker towards distal end. CuA weakly bowed. M and CuA meeting at basal cell with stems completely fused. RA1 slightly diverging from subcostal at subapical region before crossvein. C and R+Sc close together. CuP and 1A non-fused at their bases. Forewing outer margin developed for its total length. Membrane hyaline. Hindwing vein 2A with an infuscation running alongside total length of vein. First cubital cell width at distal end much greater than second cubital cell. Anal lobe broad, with vein 3A bowed at distal end. Larger forewing proximal veins yellowish with smaller apical veins brown, same vein colour pattern for hindwing. Costal vein yellowish. Basal membrane and plaga yellowish.
</p>
            <p>Opercula
More or less confluent with distal margin of tympanal cavity, well developed towards abdominal midline with sharply rounded apices facing midline. General opercula colour yellowish becoming brown at the base. Meracanthus following the same colour pattern as opercula.
</p>
            <p>Tymbals
Tymbal covers absent. Four to five ribs, broadening apically, three of which arising from anterior proximal part of a large basal dome covering over half total length of tymbal. First anterior rib is slender, with a break at about a third of its length. Fourth rib arising from anterior distal side of basal dome more or less evident amongst individuals. Some specimens present a fifth less defined rib arising from posterior distal end of the basal dome, transversal to fourth rib and converging in a sharp end. Tymbal ribs and basal dome brownish-grey; tymbal plate light-grey.
</p>
            <p>Abdomen
Tergites T2 and T3 much enlarged accounting for about a third of total abdominal length. StVIII greater in length than StVII. T1 and T2 dark-brown; T4–7 dark-brown on dorsal midline, sides red and covered in fine silvery pubescence; T8 dark-brown on dorsal midline, sides yellowish. Sternite I brown; StII yellowish with a brown patch on elevated central area; StIII–VIII yellowish. Epipleurites yellowish.
</p>
            <p>Genitalia
(

C to 6F) Pygophore distal shoulder not developed; Pygophore inner tooth absent; Upper lobe present, small and rounded, distant from dorsal beak; Basal lobe small to moderately developed ending in a sharp, rounded tip, in lateral view. Dorsal beak well developed, sharp and part of chitinized pygophore. Ventrobasal pocket absent. Claspers small-medium sized, hooked slightly outwards on distal end, rounded tip. Uncus duck-bill shaped, small and flat, not dominant and retractable within pygophore; Uncus lateral lobes absent. Aedeagal basal plate, undulated in lateral view, weakly depressed on dorsal midline; Basal plate apically broad, flat and rounded in ventral view, with a medial small sharp-tipped lobe on both sides, followed by a tubelike constriction leading to theca, gradually narrowing, slight medial lateral depression; Basal plate bearing a ripple-like pattern in dorsal view. Basal portion directed forwards away from thecal shaft; Ventral rib not apparent; Basal plate completely fused to theca without mobility. Theca very long and J-shaped in lateral view. Thecal pseudoparamers lateral of theca, dorsally fused until two thirds of theca length, very flat, as long as endotheca, ending on an upward pointed, sharp tip; Ventral support absent. Pygophore dorsal surface lightbrown to yellow. Claspers dark-brown. Uncus brown.
</p>
            <p>Female morphology
Only one female known so far (see supplementary image, S6 for the live specimen). Generally lighter in colour than male. Postclypeus yellowish with brown grooves, genae and lora light brown; Legs generally light brown; Dorsal surface of head light-brown with brown patterns; thorax and scutellum lightbrown. Abdomen light brown laterally, with a lighter brown on dorsal midline.
</p>
            <p>
Body measurements for 
13 males
of
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Total
</tp:taxon-name>
length: 16.99 ± 
0.78 mm
; Pronotal length: 1.74 ± 
0.15 mm
; Mesonotal length: 2.67 ± 
0.11 mm
; Forewing length: 13.39 ± 
0.54 mm
; M+CuA length: 1.21 ± 
0.18 mm
. Female and additional body measurements can be found on 
Table 3
.
</p>
            <p>Bioacoustics
The calling song here described is based on the analysis of recordings of three males singing at T=39–40 °C. A typical phrase is structured into four sequential parts (

): A, a single echeme; B, a series of 16 ± 2.60 echemes (10–21, n=52) in rapid succession; C, a group of 8 ± 3.68 echemes (5–18, n= 53) ending on D, a single, long echeme. In 21.15% and 9.61% of the phrases part A and part D are missing, respectively.
</p>
            <p>Calling song frequency-based analysis revealed an interesting frequency modulation in part B. Peak frequency for parts A, C and D is 13.88 ± 0.79 kHz, with maximum frequency of 20.65 ± 0.54 kHz. During part B there is an abrupt reduction of the frequency with a peak frequency of 7.91 ± 1.62 kHz, yet, maintaining the maximum frequency at 21.62 ± 1.11 kHz.</p>
            <p>
For additional time and frequency variables consult 
Table 6
. Note that, due to frequency modulation in part B, it was separated from parts A, C and D in our analysis.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>Time variables Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n</p>
            <p>
Duration (ms) 2218 ± 559 1357–3448 52 30 ± 
10 15–56
47 335 ± 52 212–411 52
</p>
            <p>Echeme duration (ms) - - - Same as above 2.14 ± 1.06 0.8–7 849</p>
            <p>Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) - - - - - - 49.16 ± 6.08 36.08–72.67 52</p>
            <p>Interval (ms) 259 ± 82 195–614 49 - - - 19.55 ± 5.31 2.8–55 797</p>
            <p>Part C Part D</p>
            <p>Time variables Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n</p>
            <p>Duration (ms) 1364 ± 679 632–2992 53 252. 29 ± 79.23 97–430 41</p>
            <p>Echeme duration (ms) 49.2 ±20.6 5–253 487 Same as above</p>
            <p>Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) 7.10 ± 1.04 3.34–10.32 53 - - -</p>
            <p>Interval (ms) 108.83 ± 22.24 34–260 435 - - -</p>
            <p>continued.</p>
            <p>Frequency variables Peak frequency Min frequency Max frequency Bandwidth</p>
            <p>Part ACD Mean ± SD 13.88 ± 0.79 4.65 ± 0.96 20.65 ± 0.54 15.94 ± 1.31 Min–Max 11.50–15.50 1.96–6.00 18.70–22.40 12.80–19.78</p>
            <p>Part B Mean ± SD 7.91 ± 1.62 4.39 ± 1.01 21.62 ± 1.11 17.14 ± 1.59 Min–Max 5.60–16.50 0.30–5.80 13.92–23.40 9.04–22.80</p>
            <p>Frequency variables Quartile 25 Quartile 50 Quartile 75 Quartile (75%–25%)</p>
            <p>Part ACD Mean ± SD 11.91 ± 0.22 13.48 ± 0.27 14.89 ± 0.32 2.98 ± 0.26</p>
            <p>Min–Max 10.70–12.50 12.28–14.40 13.40–15.80 1.87–4.10</p>
            <p>Part B Mean ± SD 7.54 ± 0.61 9.57 ± 0.79 11.61 ± 1.26 4.07 ± 0.93</p>
            <p>
Min–Max 6.30–12.00 7.50–13.50 9.70–17.50 2.70–8.20 
DNA
barcoding

Four haplotypes were recovered among the 
COI
sequences of nine males of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, with a nucleotide diversity of π= 0.0164. Sequences were clustered into two well supported sister clades (

) diverging by 2.9 % (K2P distance). These clades are, according to our currently knowledge, geographically segregated. Among the 18 segregating sites observed, 16 are fixed for each clade, being two of them non-synonymous mutations. Mean interspecific genetic distances for 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
are presented in 
Table 5
. The new species is clearly distinguishable within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura</tp:taxon-name>
), with mean pairwise genetic distances&gt;10%. The 
COI
fragment is therefore apparently proficient for 
DNA
barcoding of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
, though the genetic structure reported here must be taken into account.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution
(

) 
Morocco
, in the northern parts of Middle Atlas Mountains, near Taza and along the eastern Rif mountains (Al Hoceima), eastward to Berkane (Beni-Snassen Mountains), as the extreme western foot of the Tellian Atlas Mountains. On biogeographical grounds it is possible that this species is also in western 
Algeria
.
</p>
            <p>Habitat
(

) Open scrubland or light xerothermophilous woodland dominated by holm-oak (
<tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
) in the northern Middle Atlas or mixed pinewoods of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus halepensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraclinis articulata</tp:taxon-name>
with a rich understory of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Chamaerops humilis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Rosmarinus officinalis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Stipa</tp:taxon-name>
spp. Males sing mainly perched on these shrubs, and sometimes on the lower branches of trees (&lt;
3 m
height).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
arises from the dual sound production during the calling song of this species, meaning “two melodies”. It consists of two distinct sound patterns, with the second part severely downshifted in frequency and resembling a human-produced unvoiced linguolabial trill, often referred as “Blowing a raspberry”.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. aneabi
(
Boulard, 2000
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. armandiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. defautiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. estrellae
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi
(Rambur, 1840)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. josei
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. mariae
(Quartau &amp; Boulard, 1995)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>afroamissa
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna gastrica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrelae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi helianthemi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi galantei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. barbara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. orni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. defauti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. mariae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cistus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Abies pinsapo
var. 
marocana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cedrus atlantica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Prunus dulcis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. baenai(Boulard, 2000))</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta
Kolenati, 1857
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta montana
(Scopoli, 1772))
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. montana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Total
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pinus halepensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tetraclinis articulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Chamaerops humilis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rosmarinus officinalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Stipa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Morphology, songs and genetics identify two new cicada species from Morocco: Tettigettalna afroamissa sp. nov. and Berberigetta dimelodica gen. nov. &amp; sp. nov. (Hemiptera: Cicadettini)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4237.3.4</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/68618D0CFF8A6406FFAF9E2FFFDFFF9A</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4237.3.4</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant 2010</tp:taxon-name>
Originally described and diagnosed by 
Puissant &amp; Sueur (2010)
, encompasses nine European species: 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. aneabi
(
Boulard, 2000
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. armandiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. defautiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. estrellae
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi
(Rambur, 1840)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. josei
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T. mariae
(Quartau &amp; Boulard, 1995)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Only 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
is widespread, reaching, France, Italy, Switzerland and Slovenia to the east. The remaining are (rather) narrow Iberian endemics (see 

).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
nov. gen. Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
Paratypical series consist of 13 specimens (ten males and three females). Designated holotype is SP18_3779 (♂) and female paratype is SP18_3780 (♀). See 
Table 2
for additional information on the paratypical series, specimen IDs, collection sites and GPS data. See 

for images of male holotype, female paratype and for details of the male genitalia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Male morphology</p>
            <p>Head
Head slightly less broad than pronotum; Supra-antennal plates nearly meeting the eye and produced into a pointed lobe; Postclypeus rounded to subquadrate in frontal view, rounded between top and sides in lateral view, transversely grooved towards distal ends; Rostrum brown, reaching the center of mid-trochanters (in rest). Antennae dark-brown, 7-segmented. Dorsal surface of head brown with front bearing a yellowish stripe extending to outer borders; Yellowish stripe at beginning of epicranial suture extending to pronotum. Eyes brown, three red ocelli. Postclypeus dark brown, with apical yellowish-brown spot extending to frons, grooves light-brown or yellowish. Supra-antennal plates dark-brown and yellowish-brown towards distal ends. Gena and lorum brown to dark-brown covered in long white pilosity. Anteclypeus brown to dark-brown with a lighter brownish fascia surrounding a central dark-brown spot.
</p>
            <p>Thorax
Pronotal collar slightly larger than head width, widened, sloping laterally and evenly rounded dorsally. Pronotal tooth present mid-laterally. Scutellum wider than long. Epimeral lobe not reaching operculum. Submedian sigillae well defined. Metanotum partly visible at dorsal midline not expanded over tymbals. Pronotum with an olive-green arrow shaped stripe at dorsal midline bordered with dark-brown in fresh specimens (in preserved specimens this fades away to light brown). Remainder of pronotum brown, with dark-brown markings bearing yellowish borders. Mesonotum on overall brown, with a lighter “crown-like” marking, lateral margins of mesonotum yellowish. Scutellum brown, with a longitudinal dark-brown fascia at midline expanding towards the ends, reaching metanotum. Sides of scutellum with a dense pilosity on lateral-anterior ends with a fading gradient of dark-brown to yellowish towards the posterior end with defined, longitudinal, slightly transverse grooves. Metanotum brown, with a dark-brown patch at dorsal midline. Ventral side of thorax brown.
</p>
            <p>Legs
Profemur with three to four dark-brown erect spines. Primary spine clearly separated. Metatibiae with three to four long fine spurs on inner side, and two smaller spurs on outer side with finely dispersed white pilosity. Apex of metatibia surrounded by smaller numerous brown spurs. Tarsal formula: 3-3-3. Legs generally brown in colour. Coxae and trochanters yellowish with a central dark-brown stripe, better defined on the hind legs. Femurs and tibiae brown with two dark-brown longitudinal fasciae. Profemurs with a swollen dark brown fascia surrounded by two yellowish/ light brown stripes, varying somewhat among individuals. Dark-brown border along the spines. Tarsi dark-brown on dorsal side, brown on ventral side. Protarsi darker in colour.
</p>
            <p>Wings
Forewing and hindwing with eight and six apical cells, respectively. Ulnar cell 3 angled towards radial cell; Forewing costa parallel-sided to radial cell; Pterostigma present. CuA vein weakly bowed; M+CuA meeting at basal cell with stems fused. Vein RA1 aligned closely with subcostal for its length. CuA1 divided by a crossvein with shorter proximal part. CuP and 1A unfused at their bases. Veins C and R+Sc close together. Outer forewing margin developed for its total length. Hindwing first cubital cell width at distal end much greater than second cubital cell. Hindwing anal lobe broad with 3A vein long and strongly curved at distal end. Hindwing RP and M veins fused at their base. Larger forewing proximal veins yellowish with smaller apical veins brown, same for hindwing. Forewing basal membrane yellow. Hindwing plaga yellow.
</p>
            <p>Opercula
More or less confluent with distal margin of tympanal cavity, well developed towards abdominal midline with sharply rounded apices facing midline. Opercula extending but not reaching posterior border of StII. Opercula distally yellow, dark-brown at base. Meracanthus triangular, following same colour pattern as opercula.
</p>
            <p>Tymbals
Tymbals lacking a tymbal cover. Five ribs, four of which arising from top of a large basal dome, covering about half the tymbal width, and expanding in width towards the posterior side. Fifth rib as an extension of basal dome more or less defined, varying between specimens. First and second anterior ribs, slender, with a transverse break at about halfway of basal dome. Tymbal plate light-grey, ribs and basal dome brownish-grey.
</p>
            <p>Abdomen
Abdomen with somewhat scattered white pilosity. T1 uniformly dark-brown; T2 uniformly darkbrown with a transversal stripe, slightly pointed towards posterior end of abdomen on each side; T3 to T7 darkbrown anteriorly becoming lighter on posterior side; T8 dark-brown. StI mainly dark-brown, yellow posterior margin; StII mainly dark-brown, with yellow lateral borders. StIII to StVI light brown, with a brown spot at midline, forming a well-defined stripe. StVII large, brown, as long as or slightly longer than StVIII; StVIII brown, densely covered in pilosity. Epipleurites brown with yellow posterior border.
</p>
            <p>Genitalia
(

E to 2H) Pygophore dark-brown on dorsal surface and brown on lateral sides. Pygophore distal shoulder not developed. Pygophore inner tooth absent. Upper lobe flat and moderately developed, distant from dorsal beak with a sharply rounded tip; Basal lobe present, moderately developed and rounded in lateral view. Dorsal beak present and part of chitinized pygophore. Claspers dark-brown, medium-sized, closely aligned ending on a rounded, sharp tip. Uncus brown, duck-bill shaped, small and flat, not dominant. Uncus lateral lobes absent. Aedeagus basal plate, in lateral view, with an undulated ventral surface skewed towards the proximal end; In ventral view, apically broad with a small constriction mid-ventrally expanding afterwards with a midgroove between two longitudinally expanded lobes; Basal portion of basal plate directed forwards and away from thecal shaft; Basal plate ventral rib not apparent; Basal plate attached with a functional membranous “hinge”. Theca, in lateral view, curved into a gentle arc; Thecal pseudoparamers present, dorsal of theca, originating closer to theca than its base; Endothecal ventral support present; Thecal aperture upper diagonal in lateral view.
</p>
            <p>Female morphology
Females overall slightly darker than males. Pronotal posterior border light-brown. Mesonotal “crown-like” mark much more faded and smaller than males. Scutellum light-brown. Meso- and metatarsi lighter in colour, light-brown turning brown towards claws. Opercula almost reaching posterior border of StII but much smaller. T1 and T2 totally dark-brown. Abdominal ventral midline fascia dark-brown very well defined. StVII yellowish and split, with a light-brown groove on each side. Stigma dorsal beak dark-brown. Ovipositor brown with dark-brown tip.
</p>
            <p>
Body measurements for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
males (n=10)

Total length: 27.17 ± 
1.25 mm
; Pronotal length: 2.79 ± 
0.13 mm
; Mesonotal length: 4.35 ± 
0.26 mm
; Forewing length: 21.26 ± 
0.97 mm
; M+CuA length: 1.26 ± 
0.19 mm
. Female and additional body measurements can be found on 
Table 3
.
</p>
            <p>Bioacoustics
The male acoustic signals here described are based on the analysis of the calling song of six males recorded at T= 38–40 °C (see 

). The typical calling song is composed by the repetition of a phrase subdivided into two parts: A—a first single, short echeme and B—a longer group composed of 9 ± 7.461 echemes (6–50, n=124) and the interval between parts A and B has a duration of 155±53 ms (112–539 ms; n=99). In 23.6% of the phrases part A was absent. We also report a single calling song with a continuous phrase without any apparent pauses.
</p>
            <p>Peak frequency of all calling songs is at 11.72 ± 0.79 kHz, maximum and minimum frequencies are 18.45 ± 1.74 kHz and 4.14 ± 0.44 kHz, respectively.</p>
            <p>
Additional temporal and frequency-based variables are indicated in 
Table 4
. Because of the similarities in frequencies of parts A and B, these were grouped in the same analysis.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
is morphologically similar to all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. but presents some peculiarities, allowing for its ready separation from its closest relatives. With an average total body length of 
27 mm
, it seems to be the genus’ largest species (Mendes 
et al.
2014, Simões 
et al
. 2014, 
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
). 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
shows unique colour traits: all examined specimens have a black stripe running across the entire length of the ventral surface of the abdomen and an olive-green arrow-shaped stripe in the pronotum midline, which, upon death, fades over time to a paler shade of green in dry specimens (see image S5 for a live male bearing the typical olive-green stripe on the pronotum).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>Male (n=10) Female (n=3) Male (n=13) Female (n=1)</p>
            <p>Bođy region Cođe Mean ± SD Min%Max Mean ± SD Min%Max Mean ± SD Min%Max</p>
            <p>Heađ anđ thorax TL 27.31 ± 1.11 25.93%29.21 25.84 ± 1.16 24.72%27.03 16.99 ± 0.78 15.59%18.30 17.30</p>
            <p>HL 2.05 ± 0.12 1.86%2.20 1.98 ± 0.06 1.93%2.02 1.47 ± 0.11 1.24%1.61 - HW 5.97 ± 0.21 5.72%6.29 5.64 ± 0.32 5.41%5.86 3.86 ± 0.15 3.56%4.13 - EO 0.77 ± 0.04 0.71%0.84 0.76 ± 0.03 0.73%0.78 0.54 ± 0.05 0.46%0.61 - OO 1.37 ± 0.05 1.3%1.46 1.34 ± 0.18 1.22%1.47 0.89 ± 0.04 0.81%0.96 - LrL 1.15 ± 0.11 1.01%1.37 1.05 ± 0.16 0.94%1.16 0.85 ± 0.08 0.76%1.04 - LiL 2.92 ± 0.14 2.66%3.10 2.62 ± 0.07 2.57%2.67 1.97 ± 0.11 1.70%2.15 - VW 2.91 ± 0.12 2.71%3.10 2.82 ± 0.25 2.64%2.99 1.91 ± 0.12 1.68%2.06 - FR 0.62 ± 0.05 0.55%0.69 0.6 ± 0.03 0.59%0.62 0.40 ± 0.06 0.31%0.52 - PC 2.36 ± 0.11 2.23%2.50 2.28 ± 0.01 2.28%2.29 1.54 ± 0.09 1.36%1.66 - PL 2.82 ± 0.09 2.67%2.95 2.66 ± 0.25 2.48%2.83 1.74 ± 0.15 1.46%1.98 - PW 6.71 ± 0.37 6.20%7.34 6.31 ± 0.43 6.01%6.62 4.31 ± 0.26 3.65%4.58 - ML 4.40 ± 0.19 4.15%4.68 4.12 ± 0.52 3.76%4.49 2.67 ± 0.11 2.43%2.85 -</p>
            <p>Abđomen OP 3.92 ± 0.17 3.64%4.17 1.76 ± 0.22 1.60%1.91 2.55 ± 0.16 2.09%2.73 - LS 1.62 ± 0.09 1.52%1.77 - - 1.32 ± 0.13 1.03%1.49 - TyL 1.53 ± 0.06 1.43%1.64 - - 0.99 ± 0.07 0.90%1.14 - TyW 2.84 ± 0.06 2.76%2.95 - - 1.93 ± 0.10 1.67%2.06 -</p>
            <p>Legs PF 3.20 ± 0.11 3.05%3.36 3.08 ± 0.06 3.04%3.13 2.10 ± 0.15 1.78%2.26 -</p>
            <p>Wings FwL 21.37 ± 0.85 20.16%22.84 20.28 ± 0.91 19.42%21.23 13.39 ± 0.54 12.42%14.27 13.59</p>
            <p>
FwW 7.50 ± 0.27 7.13%7.88 7.11 ± 0.48 6.67%7.62 5.37 ± 0.84 4.87%8.10 5.10 
BCL
1.85 ± 0.14 1.68%2.06 1.72 ± 0.10 1.62%1.81 1.23 ± 0.11 1.09%1.42 1.24 McuA 1.26 ± 0.18 0.92%1.48 1.34 ± 0.21 1.10%1.50 1.21 ± 0.18 0.94%1.41 1.22 RCL 8.53 ± 0.36 7.93%9.16 8.32 ± 0.39 7.95%8.72 6.12 ± 0.36 5.20%6.59 6.24 
<tp:taxon-name>afroamissa
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>variables
Mean±SD Min%Max n Mean±SD Min%Max n Mean±SD Min%Max n Duration (ms) 726 ± 582 314%3749 124 10 ± 4.5 5%27 97 720 ± 580 309%3733 124 Echeme đuration (ms) - - - Same as above 20.97 ± 8.26 5%43 1364 Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) - - - - - - 16.21 ± 1.73 10.88%19.42 1364 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara</tp:taxon-name>
12.0 18.6 19.6 18.6 18.9 20.0 19.5 19.6 19.4 19.5 19.3 18.4 19.4 19.1 19.4 19.9 20.2 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni</tp:taxon-name>
13.3 17.2 19.3 19.3 19.1 20.0 19.7 19.5 19.4 20.6 18.4 19.3 19.2 18.9 18.7 19.0 18.7 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes</tp:taxon-name>
21.5 19.6 11.4 12.4 11.2 11.7 12.4 12.3 12.0 12.0 11.2 10.9 11.3 11.4 10.9 12.9 9.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei</tp:taxon-name>
22.9 22.4 12.5 9.6 8.1 10.8 10.7 10.6 10.3 9.7 10.0 9.2 9.0 9.6 9.4 11.4 9.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna gastrica</tp:taxon-name>
21.5 22.4 13.8 10.4 9.8 12.4 13.5 13.2 13.3 12.7 11.4 11.4 11.6 12.4 11.3 12.4 11.5 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai</tp:taxon-name>
21.9 22.2 12.3 8.7 10.7 10.4 10.6 10.6 10.3 9.6 11.0 9.0 8.6 9.0 8.9 11.5 9.7 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrelae</tp:taxon-name>
23.4 23.3 12.9 11.7 13.7 11.3 
7.7 7.4 7.8 5.3 9.2 5.8 5.1 5.4 4.8 9.5
11.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 23.0 13.7 11.7 15.0 11.6 
8.3 1.7 1.9 7.4 9.6 6.3 6.6 6.4 7.3 10.4
11.1 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae</tp:taxon-name>
22.8 22.7 13.7 11.6 14.7 11.6 
8.0 1.8 1.2 7.1 9.4 6.1 6.2 6.1 6.9 10.8
10.7. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 22.6 13.3 11.2 14.8 11.2 
8.4 1.9 1.2 7.3 8.8 5.9 6.7 6.0 7.2 10.4
10.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
22.8 24.2 13.2 10.5 14.0 10.3 
5.6 7.9 7.6 7.8 9.2 5.6 4.3 5.4 4.9 9.8
11.6. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei</tp:taxon-name>
22.5 21.1 12.2 10.7 12.5 11.9 
10.0 10.4 10.2 9.5 10.0 8.0 8.7 7.9 8.5 9.6
10.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi helianthemi</tp:taxon-name>
21.3 22.4 11.9 9.9 12.5 9.7 
6.1 6.7 6.4 6.3 5.9 8.5 3.4 5.2 5.2 9.2
10.5. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi galantei</tp:taxon-name>
22.6 22.3 12.4 9.6 12.7 9.2 
5.3 7.0 6.6 7.1 4.5 9.4 3.6 5.0 4.3 9.0
11.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi</tp:taxon-name>
22.2 21.9 12.5 10.4 13.7 9.6 
5.7 6.8 6.5 6.4 5.7 8.5 5.5 5.2 3.7 9.0
10.4. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 21.6 11.9 10.1 12.3 9.5 
5.0 7.8 7.3 7.7 5.2 9.1 5.5 4.5 3.9 8.3
10.9 Acoustic analysis enables easy and accurate identification of all 
Tetigettalna
species. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
is no exception. Its calling song is structurally different from all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp., although reminiscent of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Interval (ms)326 ± 116186%90694---51.20 ± 7.0726%63 1340Frequency variablesPeak frequencyMin frequencyMax frequencyBanđwiđthQuartile 25Quartile 50Quartile 75Quartile (75%-25%)Mean ± SD Min%Max11.72 ± 0.79 7.21%14.254.14 ± 0.44 3.93%8.8118.45 ± 1.74 15.46%23.8114.30 ± 1.87 7.68%19.879.93 ± 0.56 7.59%10.9611.50 ± 0.48 10.03%12.7512.82 ± 0.45 11.25%14.342.89 ± 0.55 1.41%4.69</p>
            <p>
The song of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
can be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
for it has higher echeme rate (t= 16.21 ± 1.73 echemes.s -1 vs t= 12.82 ± 1.49 echemes.s -1) and a shorter inter-echeme interval (t= 51.20 ± 7.07 ms vs t= 71.00 ± 13.00 ms) (Mendes 
et al.
2014).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
has a typical calling song with a short echeme (t= 200 ± 110 ms) followed by a long echeme (t= 2.17 ± 
0.30 s
), whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
this initial echeme is even shorter (t= 10 ± 4.5 ms), followed by a succession of very short echemes (t=720 ± 580 ms), instead of a single one. Inter-phrase interval is also much shorter for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
(t= 326 ± 116 ms) than for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
(t= 3270 ± 680 ms). For additional time and frequency measurements regarding 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
see 
Puissant &amp; Sueur (2010)
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>DNA barcoding
Males from all sampled locations were sequenced for COI. Four haplotypes were recovered in a total of 10 sequences. The dataset includes one non-synonymous mutation and a total of 14 polymorphic sites, corresponding to a nucleotide diversity of π=0.1075. All 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
sequences grouped in a fully supported monophyletic clade (

) and intraspecific pairwise distances (K2P) varied from 0.5 to 2.1 %. This clade clusters with remaining 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. in an unresolved polytomy. Mean genetic distances among 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and all other species of the genus are shown in 
Table 5
, and vary from 8.9% (with 
<tp:taxon-name>T. defauti</tp:taxon-name>
) to 11.9 % (with 
<tp:taxon-name>T. mariae</tp:taxon-name>
). Thus, the genetic distance associated with the fragment of COI used here, the “barcode gap”, is high enough to be used for DNA barcoding of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Habitat
(

) An arboreal species, inhabiting open Mediterranean-type woodland and tall scrubland. This species has been scored singing mainly on holm-oak trees (
<tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
) and bushes such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cistus</tp:taxon-name>
spp. but locally, in the Rif, it was found on pine trees (
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
spp.) (

B), 
<tp:taxon-name>Abies pinsapo
var. 
marocana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cedrus atlantica</tp:taxon-name>
(

C) and almond trees 

(
<tp:taxon-name>Prunus dulcis</tp:taxon-name>
)

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>DistributionNorthernMorocco
, along the Rif Mountains and nearby Mediterranean coastline between Tetuan and Al Hoceima. Also found in the northern parts of the Middle Atlas, near Taza (

). Not found near 
Ceuta
or 
Tangier
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Specific epithet formed by combining the suffix 
afro
(pertaining to Africa) and the prefix 
amissa
, feminine of the latin āmissus, meaning “having been lost” or “let go”. Literal translation would be “cicada (of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
) left / lost in Africa” as this new species is the only 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. known so far to occur in Africa, the remaining being European.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
This genus can be readily distinguished from other morphologically similar genera by the analysis of the male genitalia. The type species has a very large tube-like aedeagus with two pseudoparamers fused until three quarters of total thecal length, ending in a sharp-tip and about of the same length as the endotheca (see 

F). Therefore, it can be distinguished from the similar genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
(type species: 
<tp:taxon-name>T. baenai(Boulard, 2000))</tp:taxon-name>
for the latter has two unfused thick pseudoparamers arising dorsally from base of the theca, and separate from the endotheca (
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta
Kolenati, 1857
</tp:taxon-name>
(type species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta montana
(Scopoli, 1772))
</tp:taxon-name>
in aedeagus morphology: 
<tp:taxon-name>C. montana</tp:taxon-name>
shows a similarly long aedeagus, yet the pseudoparamers are exceedingly long and partly unfused, surpassing the distal end of theca by about half its length (
Moulds 2012
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type species<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
designed by monotypy.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Name formed by combining the suffix 
Berber
(pertaining to the Maghrebian Roman region, Barbaria, and the prevailing ethnic group in northern Maghreb) and the prefix –getta, an arbitrary combination of letters associated with small cicada species, as in 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigetta</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
Paratypical series consists of a total of 14 specimens (13 males and one female). Designated holotype is SP19_3795 (♂), and female paratype is SP19_3787 (♀). See 
Table 2
for additional information on paratypical series, specimen IDs, collection sites and GPS data. See 

for images on male holotype, female paratype (see supplementary image, S6 for live specimens) and details of the male genitalia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Male morphology</p>
            <p>Head
Supra-antennal plate produced into a pointed lobe; Supra-antennal plate nearly meeting the eye. Postclypeus subquadrate to round in front view; Postclypeus transversely grooved towards distal ends. Rostrum brown, reaching the center of mid-trochanters when in resting position. Antennae brown, 7-segmented. Postclypeus dark brown, with apical yellowish-brown spot, grooves light-brown or yellowish; Anteclypeus yellowish with a brown central spot. Gena and lorum brown to light-brown covered with white long pilosity. Supra-antennal plates light brown distally near the eye, becoming dark-brown towards midline. Three red ocelli. Eyes light-brown. Dorsal surface of head dark-brown, supraocular border brown, with yellowish stripe on epicranial suture.
</p>
            <p>Thorax
Pronotal collar broad, slightly greater than eye width; Pronotal lateral development ampliate, sloping in lateral view, evenly rounded in dorsal view. Pronotal mid-lateral tooth absent. Scutellum wider than long. Epimeral lobe not reaching operculum. Metanotum partly visible at dorsal midline, not expanded over tymbals. Pronotum brown with a dark-brown stripe along dorsal midline, ending posteriorly in dark-brown spot. Mesonotum with two yellowish fasciae bordering between parapsidal suture and submedian sigillae prolonging to anterior arms of scutellum; Mesonotal lateral dorsal margins yellowish. 
Central
area of scutellum brown with yellowish arms. Metanotum yellowish, brown at dorsal midline.
</p>
            <p>Legs
Profemur with a large primary erect spine plus two smaller secondary spines dark-brown/ brownish in colour, some individuals with a much smaller fourth spine. Meracanthus triangular. Tarsal formula 3-3-3. General brown to yellowish in colour. Metatibiae with four long fine reddish spurs on inner side and two smaller reddish spurs on outer side. Coxae yellowish, with a central dark-brown stripe, becoming gradually browner and less yellowish towards metacoxae. Trochanters brown. Meso and metafemurs yellowish with dark-brown to brownish stripes. Tarsi and tibia light-brown.
</p>
            <p>Wings
Forewing with eight apical and four subapical cells. Ulnar cell 3 angled to radial cell. Costal vein parallel-sided to node. Pterostigma present becoming darker towards distal end. CuA weakly bowed. M and CuA meeting at basal cell with stems completely fused. RA1 slightly diverging from subcostal at subapical region before crossvein. C and R+Sc close together. CuP and 1A non-fused at their bases. Forewing outer margin developed for its total length. Membrane hyaline. Hindwing vein 2A with an infuscation running alongside total length of vein. First cubital cell width at distal end much greater than second cubital cell. Anal lobe broad, with vein 3A bowed at distal end. Larger forewing proximal veins yellowish with smaller apical veins brown, same vein colour pattern for hindwing. Costal vein yellowish. Basal membrane and plaga yellowish.
</p>
            <p>Opercula
More or less confluent with distal margin of tympanal cavity, well developed towards abdominal midline with sharply rounded apices facing midline. General opercula colour yellowish becoming brown at the base. Meracanthus following the same colour pattern as opercula.
</p>
            <p>Tymbals
Tymbal covers absent. Four to five ribs, broadening apically, three of which arising from anterior proximal part of a large basal dome covering over half total length of tymbal. First anterior rib is slender, with a break at about a third of its length. Fourth rib arising from anterior distal side of basal dome more or less evident amongst individuals. Some specimens present a fifth less defined rib arising from posterior distal end of the basal dome, transversal to fourth rib and converging in a sharp end. Tymbal ribs and basal dome brownish-grey; tymbal plate light-grey.
</p>
            <p>Abdomen
Tergites T2 and T3 much enlarged accounting for about a third of total abdominal length. StVIII greater in length than StVII. T1 and T2 dark-brown; T4–7 dark-brown on dorsal midline, sides red and covered in fine silvery pubescence; T8 dark-brown on dorsal midline, sides yellowish. Sternite I brown; StII yellowish with a brown patch on elevated central area; StIII–VIII yellowish. Epipleurites yellowish.
</p>
            <p>Genitalia
(

C to 6F) Pygophore distal shoulder not developed; Pygophore inner tooth absent; Upper lobe present, small and rounded, distant from dorsal beak; Basal lobe small to moderately developed ending in a sharp, rounded tip, in lateral view. Dorsal beak well developed, sharp and part of chitinized pygophore. Ventrobasal pocket absent. Claspers small-medium sized, hooked slightly outwards on distal end, rounded tip. Uncus duck-bill shaped, small and flat, not dominant and retractable within pygophore; Uncus lateral lobes absent. Aedeagal basal plate, undulated in lateral view, weakly depressed on dorsal midline; Basal plate apically broad, flat and rounded in ventral view, with a medial small sharp-tipped lobe on both sides, followed by a tubelike constriction leading to theca, gradually narrowing, slight medial lateral depression; Basal plate bearing a ripple-like pattern in dorsal view. Basal portion directed forwards away from thecal shaft; Ventral rib not apparent; Basal plate completely fused to theca without mobility. Theca very long and J-shaped in lateral view. Thecal pseudoparamers lateral of theca, dorsally fused until two thirds of theca length, very flat, as long as endotheca, ending on an upward pointed, sharp tip; Ventral support absent. Pygophore dorsal surface lightbrown to yellow. Claspers dark-brown. Uncus brown.
</p>
            <p>Female morphology
Only one female known so far (see supplementary image, S6 for the live specimen). Generally lighter in colour than male. Postclypeus yellowish with brown grooves, genae and lora light brown; Legs generally light brown; Dorsal surface of head light-brown with brown patterns; thorax and scutellum lightbrown. Abdomen light brown laterally, with a lighter brown on dorsal midline.
</p>
            <p>
Body measurements for 
13 males
of
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Total
</tp:taxon-name>
length: 16.99 ± 
0.78 mm
; Pronotal length: 1.74 ± 
0.15 mm
; Mesonotal length: 2.67 ± 
0.11 mm
; Forewing length: 13.39 ± 
0.54 mm
; M+CuA length: 1.21 ± 
0.18 mm
. Female and additional body measurements can be found on 
Table 3
.
</p>
            <p>Bioacoustics
The calling song here described is based on the analysis of recordings of three males singing at T=39–40 °C. A typical phrase is structured into four sequential parts (

): A, a single echeme; B, a series of 16 ± 2.60 echemes (10–21, n=52) in rapid succession; C, a group of 8 ± 3.68 echemes (5–18, n= 53) ending on D, a single, long echeme. In 21.15% and 9.61% of the phrases part A and part D are missing, respectively.
</p>
            <p>Calling song frequency-based analysis revealed an interesting frequency modulation in part B. Peak frequency for parts A, C and D is 13.88 ± 0.79 kHz, with maximum frequency of 20.65 ± 0.54 kHz. During part B there is an abrupt reduction of the frequency with a peak frequency of 7.91 ± 1.62 kHz, yet, maintaining the maximum frequency at 21.62 ± 1.11 kHz.</p>
            <p>
For additional time and frequency variables consult 
Table 6
. Note that, due to frequency modulation in part B, it was separated from parts A, C and D in our analysis.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>Time variables Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n</p>
            <p>
Duration (ms) 2218 ± 559 1357–3448 52 30 ± 
10 15–56
47 335 ± 52 212–411 52
</p>
            <p>Echeme duration (ms) - - - Same as above 2.14 ± 1.06 0.8–7 849</p>
            <p>Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) - - - - - - 49.16 ± 6.08 36.08–72.67 52</p>
            <p>Interval (ms) 259 ± 82 195–614 49 - - - 19.55 ± 5.31 2.8–55 797</p>
            <p>Part C Part D</p>
            <p>Time variables Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n</p>
            <p>Duration (ms) 1364 ± 679 632–2992 53 252. 29 ± 79.23 97–430 41</p>
            <p>Echeme duration (ms) 49.2 ±20.6 5–253 487 Same as above</p>
            <p>Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) 7.10 ± 1.04 3.34–10.32 53 - - -</p>
            <p>Interval (ms) 108.83 ± 22.24 34–260 435 - - -</p>
            <p>continued.</p>
            <p>Frequency variables Peak frequency Min frequency Max frequency Bandwidth</p>
            <p>Part ACD Mean ± SD 13.88 ± 0.79 4.65 ± 0.96 20.65 ± 0.54 15.94 ± 1.31 Min–Max 11.50–15.50 1.96–6.00 18.70–22.40 12.80–19.78</p>
            <p>Part B Mean ± SD 7.91 ± 1.62 4.39 ± 1.01 21.62 ± 1.11 17.14 ± 1.59 Min–Max 5.60–16.50 0.30–5.80 13.92–23.40 9.04–22.80</p>
            <p>Frequency variables Quartile 25 Quartile 50 Quartile 75 Quartile (75%–25%)</p>
            <p>Part ACD Mean ± SD 11.91 ± 0.22 13.48 ± 0.27 14.89 ± 0.32 2.98 ± 0.26</p>
            <p>Min–Max 10.70–12.50 12.28–14.40 13.40–15.80 1.87–4.10</p>
            <p>Part B Mean ± SD 7.54 ± 0.61 9.57 ± 0.79 11.61 ± 1.26 4.07 ± 0.93</p>
            <p>
Min–Max 6.30–12.00 7.50–13.50 9.70–17.50 2.70–8.20 
DNA
barcoding

Four haplotypes were recovered among the 
COI
sequences of nine males of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, with a nucleotide diversity of π= 0.0164. Sequences were clustered into two well supported sister clades (

) diverging by 2.9 % (K2P distance). These clades are, according to our currently knowledge, geographically segregated. Among the 18 segregating sites observed, 16 are fixed for each clade, being two of them non-synonymous mutations. Mean interspecific genetic distances for 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
are presented in 
Table 5
. The new species is clearly distinguishable within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura</tp:taxon-name>
), with mean pairwise genetic distances&gt;10%. The 
COI
fragment is therefore apparently proficient for 
DNA
barcoding of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
, though the genetic structure reported here must be taken into account.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution
(

) 
Morocco
, in the northern parts of Middle Atlas Mountains, near Taza and along the eastern Rif mountains (Al Hoceima), eastward to Berkane (Beni-Snassen Mountains), as the extreme western foot of the Tellian Atlas Mountains. On biogeographical grounds it is possible that this species is also in western 
Algeria
.
</p>
            <p>Habitat
(

) Open scrubland or light xerothermophilous woodland dominated by holm-oak (
<tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
) in the northern Middle Atlas or mixed pinewoods of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus halepensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraclinis articulata</tp:taxon-name>
with a rich understory of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Chamaerops humilis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Rosmarinus officinalis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Stipa</tp:taxon-name>
spp. Males sing mainly perched on these shrubs, and sometimes on the lower branches of trees (&lt;
3 m
height).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
arises from the dual sound production during the calling song of this species, meaning “two melodies”. It consists of two distinct sound patterns, with the second part severely downshifted in frequency and resembling a human-produced unvoiced linguolabial trill, often referred as “Blowing a raspberry”.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. aneabi
(
Boulard, 2000
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. armandiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. defautiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. estrellae
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi
(Rambur, 1840)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. josei
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. mariae
(Quartau &amp; Boulard, 1995)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>afroamissa
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna gastrica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrelae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi helianthemi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi galantei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. barbara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. orni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. defauti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. mariae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cistus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Abies pinsapo
var. 
marocana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cedrus atlantica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Prunus dulcis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>T. baenai(Boulard, 2000))</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta
Kolenati, 1857
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta montana
(Scopoli, 1772))
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>C. montana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigetta</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Total
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pinus halepensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tetraclinis articulata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Chamaerops humilis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rosmarinus officinalis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Stipa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Morphology, songs and genetics identify two new cicada species from Morocco: Tettigettalna afroamissa sp. nov. and Berberigetta dimelodica gen. nov. &amp; sp. nov. (Hemiptera: Cicadettini)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4237.3.4</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/68618D0CFF8A6406FFAF9E2FFFDFFF9A</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4237.3.4</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>TettigettalnaPuissant 2010</tp:taxon-name>
Originally described and diagnosed by 
Puissant &amp; Sueur (2010)
, encompasses nine European species: 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. aneabi
(
Boulard, 2000
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. armandiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. defautiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. estrellae
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi
(Rambur, 1840)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. josei
(Boulard, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T. mariae
(Quartau &amp; Boulard, 1995)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Only 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
is widespread, reaching, France, Italy, Switzerland and Slovenia to the east. The remaining are (rather) narrow Iberian endemics (see 

).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
nov. gen. Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Costa, Nunes, Marabuto, Mendes &amp; Simões
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
Paratypical series consist of 13 specimens (ten males and three females). Designated holotype is SP18_3779 (♂) and female paratype is SP18_3780 (♀). See 
Table 2
for additional information on the paratypical series, specimen IDs, collection sites and GPS data. See 

for images of male holotype, female paratype and for details of the male genitalia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Male morphology</p>
            <p>Head
Head slightly less broad than pronotum; Supra-antennal plates nearly meeting the eye and produced into a pointed lobe; Postclypeus rounded to subquadrate in frontal view, rounded between top and sides in lateral view, transversely grooved towards distal ends; Rostrum brown, reaching the center of mid-trochanters (in rest). Antennae dark-brown, 7-segmented. Dorsal surface of head brown with front bearing a yellowish stripe extending to outer borders; Yellowish stripe at beginning of epicranial suture extending to pronotum. Eyes brown, three red ocelli. Postclypeus dark brown, with apical yellowish-brown spot extending to frons, grooves light-brown or yellowish. Supra-antennal plates dark-brown and yellowish-brown towards distal ends. Gena and lorum brown to dark-brown covered in long white pilosity. Anteclypeus brown to dark-brown with a lighter brownish fascia surrounding a central dark-brown spot.
</p>
            <p>Thorax
Pronotal collar slightly larger than head width, widened, sloping laterally and evenly rounded dorsally. Pronotal tooth present mid-laterally. Scutellum wider than long. Epimeral lobe not reaching operculum. Submedian sigillae well defined. Metanotum partly visible at dorsal midline not expanded over tymbals. Pronotum with an olive-green arrow shaped stripe at dorsal midline bordered with dark-brown in fresh specimens (in preserved specimens this fades away to light brown). Remainder of pronotum brown, with dark-brown markings bearing yellowish borders. Mesonotum on overall brown, with a lighter “crown-like” marking, lateral margins of mesonotum yellowish. Scutellum brown, with a longitudinal dark-brown fascia at midline expanding towards the ends, reaching metanotum. Sides of scutellum with a dense pilosity on lateral-anterior ends with a fading gradient of dark-brown to yellowish towards the posterior end with defined, longitudinal, slightly transverse grooves. Metanotum brown, with a dark-brown patch at dorsal midline. Ventral side of thorax brown.
</p>
            <p>Legs
Profemur with three to four dark-brown erect spines. Primary spine clearly separated. Metatibiae with three to four long fine spurs on inner side, and two smaller spurs on outer side with finely dispersed white pilosity. Apex of metatibia surrounded by smaller numerous brown spurs. Tarsal formula: 3-3-3. Legs generally brown in colour. Coxae and trochanters yellowish with a central dark-brown stripe, better defined on the hind legs. Femurs and tibiae brown with two dark-brown longitudinal fasciae. Profemurs with a swollen dark brown fascia surrounded by two yellowish/ light brown stripes, varying somewhat among individuals. Dark-brown border along the spines. Tarsi dark-brown on dorsal side, brown on ventral side. Protarsi darker in colour.
</p>
            <p>Wings
Forewing and hindwing with eight and six apical cells, respectively. Ulnar cell 3 angled towards radial cell; Forewing costa parallel-sided to radial cell; Pterostigma present. CuA vein weakly bowed; M+CuA meeting at basal cell with stems fused. Vein RA1 aligned closely with subcostal for its length. CuA1 divided by a crossvein with shorter proximal part. CuP and 1A unfused at their bases. Veins C and R+Sc close together. Outer forewing margin developed for its total length. Hindwing first cubital cell width at distal end much greater than second cubital cell. Hindwing anal lobe broad with 3A vein long and strongly curved at distal end. Hindwing RP and M veins fused at their base. Larger forewing proximal veins yellowish with smaller apical veins brown, same for hindwing. Forewing basal membrane yellow. Hindwing plaga yellow.
</p>
            <p>Opercula
More or less confluent with distal margin of tympanal cavity, well developed towards abdominal midline with sharply rounded apices facing midline. Opercula extending but not reaching posterior border of StII. Opercula distally yellow, dark-brown at base. Meracanthus triangular, following same colour pattern as opercula.
</p>
            <p>Tymbals
Tymbals lacking a tymbal cover. Five ribs, four of which arising from top of a large basal dome, covering about half the tymbal width, and expanding in width towards the posterior side. Fifth rib as an extension of basal dome more or less defined, varying between specimens. First and second anterior ribs, slender, with a transverse break at about halfway of basal dome. Tymbal plate light-grey, ribs and basal dome brownish-grey.
</p>
            <p>Abdomen
Abdomen with somewhat scattered white pilosity. T1 uniformly dark-brown; T2 uniformly darkbrown with a transversal stripe, slightly pointed towards posterior end of abdomen on each side; T3 to T7 darkbrown anteriorly becoming lighter on posterior side; T8 dark-brown. StI mainly dark-brown, yellow posterior margin; StII mainly dark-brown, with yellow lateral borders. StIII to StVI light brown, with a brown spot at midline, forming a well-defined stripe. StVII large, brown, as long as or slightly longer than StVIII; StVIII brown, densely covered in pilosity. Epipleurites brown with yellow posterior border.
</p>
            <p>Genitalia
(

E to 2H) Pygophore dark-brown on dorsal surface and brown on lateral sides. Pygophore distal shoulder not developed. Pygophore inner tooth absent. Upper lobe flat and moderately developed, distant from dorsal beak with a sharply rounded tip; Basal lobe present, moderately developed and rounded in lateral view. Dorsal beak present and part of chitinized pygophore. Claspers dark-brown, medium-sized, closely aligned ending on a rounded, sharp tip. Uncus brown, duck-bill shaped, small and flat, not dominant. Uncus lateral lobes absent. Aedeagus basal plate, in lateral view, with an undulated ventral surface skewed towards the proximal end; In ventral view, apically broad with a small constriction mid-ventrally expanding afterwards with a midgroove between two longitudinally expanded lobes; Basal portion of basal plate directed forwards and away from thecal shaft; Basal plate ventral rib not apparent; Basal plate attached with a functional membranous “hinge”. Theca, in lateral view, curved into a gentle arc; Thecal pseudoparamers present, dorsal of theca, originating closer to theca than its base; Endothecal ventral support present; Thecal aperture upper diagonal in lateral view.
</p>
            <p>Female morphology
Females overall slightly darker than males. Pronotal posterior border light-brown. Mesonotal “crown-like” mark much more faded and smaller than males. Scutellum light-brown. Meso- and metatarsi lighter in colour, light-brown turning brown towards claws. Opercula almost reaching posterior border of StII but much smaller. T1 and T2 totally dark-brown. Abdominal ventral midline fascia dark-brown very well defined. StVII yellowish and split, with a light-brown groove on each side. Stigma dorsal beak dark-brown. Ovipositor brown with dark-brown tip.
</p>
            <p>
Body measurements for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
males (n=10)

Total length: 27.17 ± 
1.25 mm
; Pronotal length: 2.79 ± 
0.13 mm
; Mesonotal length: 4.35 ± 
0.26 mm
; Forewing length: 21.26 ± 
0.97 mm
; M+CuA length: 1.26 ± 
0.19 mm
. Female and additional body measurements can be found on 
Table 3
.
</p>
            <p>Bioacoustics
The male acoustic signals here described are based on the analysis of the calling song of six males recorded at T= 38–40 °C (see 

). The typical calling song is composed by the repetition of a phrase subdivided into two parts: A—a first single, short echeme and B—a longer group composed of 9 ± 7.461 echemes (6–50, n=124) and the interval between parts A and B has a duration of 155±53 ms (112–539 ms; n=99). In 23.6% of the phrases part A was absent. We also report a single calling song with a continuous phrase without any apparent pauses.
</p>
            <p>Peak frequency of all calling songs is at 11.72 ± 0.79 kHz, maximum and minimum frequencies are 18.45 ± 1.74 kHz and 4.14 ± 0.44 kHz, respectively.</p>
            <p>
Additional temporal and frequency-based variables are indicated in 
Table 4
. Because of the similarities in frequencies of parts A and B, these were grouped in the same analysis.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
is morphologically similar to all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. but presents some peculiarities, allowing for its ready separation from its closest relatives. With an average total body length of 
27 mm
, it seems to be the genus’ largest species (Mendes 
et al.
2014, Simões 
et al
. 2014, 
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
). 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
shows unique colour traits: all examined specimens have a black stripe running across the entire length of the ventral surface of the abdomen and an olive-green arrow-shaped stripe in the pronotum midline, which, upon death, fades over time to a paler shade of green in dry specimens (see image S5 for a live male bearing the typical olive-green stripe on the pronotum).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>Male (n=10) Female (n=3) Male (n=13) Female (n=1)</p>
            <p>Bođy region Cođe Mean ± SD Min%Max Mean ± SD Min%Max Mean ± SD Min%Max</p>
            <p>Heađ anđ thorax TL 27.31 ± 1.11 25.93%29.21 25.84 ± 1.16 24.72%27.03 16.99 ± 0.78 15.59%18.30 17.30</p>
            <p>HL 2.05 ± 0.12 1.86%2.20 1.98 ± 0.06 1.93%2.02 1.47 ± 0.11 1.24%1.61 - HW 5.97 ± 0.21 5.72%6.29 5.64 ± 0.32 5.41%5.86 3.86 ± 0.15 3.56%4.13 - EO 0.77 ± 0.04 0.71%0.84 0.76 ± 0.03 0.73%0.78 0.54 ± 0.05 0.46%0.61 - OO 1.37 ± 0.05 1.3%1.46 1.34 ± 0.18 1.22%1.47 0.89 ± 0.04 0.81%0.96 - LrL 1.15 ± 0.11 1.01%1.37 1.05 ± 0.16 0.94%1.16 0.85 ± 0.08 0.76%1.04 - LiL 2.92 ± 0.14 2.66%3.10 2.62 ± 0.07 2.57%2.67 1.97 ± 0.11 1.70%2.15 - VW 2.91 ± 0.12 2.71%3.10 2.82 ± 0.25 2.64%2.99 1.91 ± 0.12 1.68%2.06 - FR 0.62 ± 0.05 0.55%0.69 0.6 ± 0.03 0.59%0.62 0.40 ± 0.06 0.31%0.52 - PC 2.36 ± 0.11 2.23%2.50 2.28 ± 0.01 2.28%2.29 1.54 ± 0.09 1.36%1.66 - PL 2.82 ± 0.09 2.67%2.95 2.66 ± 0.25 2.48%2.83 1.74 ± 0.15 1.46%1.98 - PW 6.71 ± 0.37 6.20%7.34 6.31 ± 0.43 6.01%6.62 4.31 ± 0.26 3.65%4.58 - ML 4.40 ± 0.19 4.15%4.68 4.12 ± 0.52 3.76%4.49 2.67 ± 0.11 2.43%2.85 -</p>
            <p>Abđomen OP 3.92 ± 0.17 3.64%4.17 1.76 ± 0.22 1.60%1.91 2.55 ± 0.16 2.09%2.73 - LS 1.62 ± 0.09 1.52%1.77 - - 1.32 ± 0.13 1.03%1.49 - TyL 1.53 ± 0.06 1.43%1.64 - - 0.99 ± 0.07 0.90%1.14 - TyW 2.84 ± 0.06 2.76%2.95 - - 1.93 ± 0.10 1.67%2.06 -</p>
            <p>Legs PF 3.20 ± 0.11 3.05%3.36 3.08 ± 0.06 3.04%3.13 2.10 ± 0.15 1.78%2.26 -</p>
            <p>Wings FwL 21.37 ± 0.85 20.16%22.84 20.28 ± 0.91 19.42%21.23 13.39 ± 0.54 12.42%14.27 13.59</p>
            <p>
FwW 7.50 ± 0.27 7.13%7.88 7.11 ± 0.48 6.67%7.62 5.37 ± 0.84 4.87%8.10 5.10 
BCL
1.85 ± 0.14 1.68%2.06 1.72 ± 0.10 1.62%1.81 1.23 ± 0.11 1.09%1.42 1.24 McuA 1.26 ± 0.18 0.92%1.48 1.34 ± 0.21 1.10%1.50 1.21 ± 0.18 0.94%1.41 1.22 RCL 8.53 ± 0.36 7.93%9.16 8.32 ± 0.39 7.95%8.72 6.12 ± 0.36 5.20%6.59 6.24 
<tp:taxon-name>afroamissa
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>variables
Mean±SD Min%Max n Mean±SD Min%Max n Mean±SD Min%Max n Duration (ms) 726 ± 582 314%3749 124 10 ± 4.5 5%27 97 720 ± 580 309%3733 124 Echeme đuration (ms) - - - Same as above 20.97 ± 8.26 5%43 1364 Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) - - - - - - 16.21 ± 1.73 10.88%19.42 1364 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara</tp:taxon-name>
12.0 18.6 19.6 18.6 18.9 20.0 19.5 19.6 19.4 19.5 19.3 18.4 19.4 19.1 19.4 19.9 20.2 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni</tp:taxon-name>
13.3 17.2 19.3 19.3 19.1 20.0 19.7 19.5 19.4 20.6 18.4 19.3 19.2 18.9 18.7 19.0 18.7 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes</tp:taxon-name>
21.5 19.6 11.4 12.4 11.2 11.7 12.4 12.3 12.0 12.0 11.2 10.9 11.3 11.4 10.9 12.9 9.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei</tp:taxon-name>
22.9 22.4 12.5 9.6 8.1 10.8 10.7 10.6 10.3 9.7 10.0 9.2 9.0 9.6 9.4 11.4 9.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna gastrica</tp:taxon-name>
21.5 22.4 13.8 10.4 9.8 12.4 13.5 13.2 13.3 12.7 11.4 11.4 11.6 12.4 11.3 12.4 11.5 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai</tp:taxon-name>
21.9 22.2 12.3 8.7 10.7 10.4 10.6 10.6 10.3 9.6 11.0 9.0 8.6 9.0 8.9 11.5 9.7 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrelae</tp:taxon-name>
23.4 23.3 12.9 11.7 13.7 11.3 
7.7 7.4 7.8 5.3 9.2 5.8 5.1 5.4 4.8 9.5
11.8 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 23.0 13.7 11.7 15.0 11.6 
8.3 1.7 1.9 7.4 9.6 6.3 6.6 6.4 7.3 10.4
11.1 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae</tp:taxon-name>
22.8 22.7 13.7 11.6 14.7 11.6 
8.0 1.8 1.2 7.1 9.4 6.1 6.2 6.1 6.9 10.8
10.7. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 22.6 13.3 11.2 14.8 11.2 
8.4 1.9 1.2 7.3 8.8 5.9 6.7 6.0 7.2 10.4
10.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
22.8 24.2 13.2 10.5 14.0 10.3 
5.6 7.9 7.6 7.8 9.2 5.6 4.3 5.4 4.9 9.8
11.6. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei</tp:taxon-name>
22.5 21.1 12.2 10.7 12.5 11.9 
10.0 10.4 10.2 9.5 10.0 8.0 8.7 7.9 8.5 9.6
10.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi helianthemi</tp:taxon-name>
21.3 22.4 11.9 9.9 12.5 9.7 
6.1 6.7 6.4 6.3 5.9 8.5 3.4 5.2 5.2 9.2
10.5. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. helianthemi galantei</tp:taxon-name>
22.6 22.3 12.4 9.6 12.7 9.2 
5.3 7.0 6.6 7.1 4.5 9.4 3.6 5.0 4.3 9.0
11.0. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi</tp:taxon-name>
22.2 21.9 12.5 10.4 13.7 9.6 
5.7 6.8 6.5 6.4 5.7 8.5 5.5 5.2 3.7 9.0
10.4. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti</tp:taxon-name>
22.7 21.6 11.9 10.1 12.3 9.5 
5.0 7.8 7.3 7.7 5.2 9.1 5.5 4.5 3.9 8.3
10.9 Acoustic analysis enables easy and accurate identification of all 
Tetigettalna
species. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
is no exception. Its calling song is structurally different from all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp., although reminiscent of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(Olivier, 1790)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardiPuissant, 2010</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Interval (ms)326 ± 116186%90694---51.20 ± 7.0726%63 1340Frequency variablesPeak frequencyMin frequencyMax frequencyBanđwiđthQuartile 25Quartile 50Quartile 75Quartile (75%-25%)Mean ± SD Min%Max11.72 ± 0.79 7.21%14.254.14 ± 0.44 3.93%8.8118.45 ± 1.74 15.46%23.8114.30 ± 1.87 7.68%19.879.93 ± 0.56 7.59%10.9611.50 ± 0.48 10.03%12.7512.82 ± 0.45 11.25%14.342.89 ± 0.55 1.41%4.69</p>
            <p>
The song of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
can be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
for it has higher echeme rate (t= 16.21 ± 1.73 echemes.s -1 vs t= 12.82 ± 1.49 echemes.s -1) and a shorter inter-echeme interval (t= 51.20 ± 7.07 ms vs t= 71.00 ± 13.00 ms) (Mendes 
et al.
2014).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
has a typical calling song with a short echeme (t= 200 ± 110 ms) followed by a long echeme (t= 2.17 ± 
0.30 s
), whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
this initial echeme is even shorter (t= 10 ± 4.5 ms), followed by a succession of very short echemes (t=720 ± 580 ms), instead of a single one. Inter-phrase interval is also much shorter for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
(t= 326 ± 116 ms) than for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
(t= 3270 ± 680 ms). For additional time and frequency measurements regarding 
<tp:taxon-name>T. boulardi</tp:taxon-name>
see 
Puissant &amp; Sueur (2010)
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>DNA barcoding
Males from all sampled locations were sequenced for COI. Four haplotypes were recovered in a total of 10 sequences. The dataset includes one non-synonymous mutation and a total of 14 polymorphic sites, corresponding to a nucleotide diversity of π=0.1075. All 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
sequences grouped in a fully supported monophyletic clade (

) and intraspecific pairwise distances (K2P) varied from 0.5 to 2.1 %. This clade clusters with remaining 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. in an unresolved polytomy. Mean genetic distances among 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and all other species of the genus are shown in 
Table 5
, and vary from 8.9% (with 
<tp:taxon-name>T. defauti</tp:taxon-name>
) to 11.9 % (with 
<tp:taxon-name>T. mariae</tp:taxon-name>
). Thus, the genetic distance associated with the fragment of COI used here, the “barcode gap”, is high enough to be used for DNA barcoding of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Habitat
(

) An arboreal species, inhabiting open Mediterranean-type woodland and tall scrubland. This species has been scored singing mainly on holm-oak trees (
<tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
) and bushes such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cistus</tp:taxon-name>
spp. but locally, in the Rif, it was found on pine trees (
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
spp.) (

B), 
<tp:taxon-name>Abies pinsapo
var. 
marocana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cedrus atlantica</tp:taxon-name>
(

C) and almond trees 

(
<tp:taxon-name>Prunus dulcis</tp:taxon-name>
)

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>DistributionNorthernMorocco
, along the Rif Mountains and nearby Mediterranean coastline between Tetuan and Al Hoceima. Also found in the northern parts of the Middle Atlas, near Taza (

). Not found near 
Ceuta
or 
Tangier
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Specific epithet formed by combining the suffix 
afro
(pertaining to Africa) and the prefix 
amissa
, feminine of the latin āmissus, meaning “having been lost” or “let go”. Literal translation would be “cicada (of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
) left / lost in Africa” as this new species is the only 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. known so far to occur in Africa, the remaining being European.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
This genus can be readily distinguished from other morphologically similar genera by the analysis of the male genitalia. The type species has a very large tube-like aedeagus with two pseudoparamers fused until three quarters of total thecal length, ending in a sharp-tip and about of the same length as the endotheca (see 

F). Therefore, it can be distinguished from the similar genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
(type species: 
<tp:taxon-name>T. baenai(Boulard, 2000))</tp:taxon-name>
for the latter has two unfused thick pseudoparamers arising dorsally from base of the theca, and separate from the endotheca (
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta
Kolenati, 1857
</tp:taxon-name>
(type species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta montana
(Scopoli, 1772))
</tp:taxon-name>
in aedeagus morphology: 
<tp:taxon-name>C. montana</tp:taxon-name>
shows a similarly long aedeagus, yet the pseudoparamers are exceedingly long and partly unfused, surpassing the distal end of theca by about half its length (
Moulds 2012
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type species<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
designed by monotypy.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Name formed by combining the suffix 
Berber
(pertaining to the Maghrebian Roman region, Barbaria, and the prevailing ethnic group in northern Maghreb) and the prefix –getta, an arbitrary combination of letters associated with small cicada species, as in 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigetta</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined
Paratypical series consists of a total of 14 specimens (13 males and one female). Designated holotype is SP19_3795 (♂), and female paratype is SP19_3787 (♀). See 
Table 2
for additional information on paratypical series, specimen IDs, collection sites and GPS data. See 

for images on male holotype, female paratype (see supplementary image, S6 for live specimens) and details of the male genitalia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Male morphology</p>
            <p>Head
Supra-antennal plate produced into a pointed lobe; Supra-antennal plate nearly meeting the eye. Postclypeus subquadrate to round in front view; Postclypeus transversely grooved towards distal ends. Rostrum brown, reaching the center of mid-trochanters when in resting position. Antennae brown, 7-segmented. Postclypeus dark brown, with apical yellowish-brown spot, grooves light-brown or yellowish; Anteclypeus yellowish with a brown central spot. Gena and lorum brown to light-brown covered with white long pilosity. Supra-antennal plates light brown distally near the eye, becoming dark-brown towards midline. Three red ocelli. Eyes light-brown. Dorsal surface of head dark-brown, supraocular border brown, with yellowish stripe on epicranial suture.
</p>
            <p>Thorax
Pronotal collar broad, slightly greater than eye width; Pronotal lateral development ampliate, sloping in lateral view, evenly rounded in dorsal view. Pronotal mid-lateral tooth absent. Scutellum wider than long. Epimeral lobe not reaching operculum. Metanotum partly visible at dorsal midline, not expanded over tymbals. Pronotum brown with a dark-brown stripe along dorsal midline, ending posteriorly in dark-brown spot. Mesonotum with two yellowish fasciae bordering between parapsidal suture and submedian sigillae prolonging to anterior arms of scutellum; Mesonotal lateral dorsal margins yellowish. 
Central
area of scutellum brown with yellowish arms. Metanotum yellowish, brown at dorsal midline.
</p>
            <p>Legs
Profemur with a large primary erect spine plus two smaller secondary spines dark-brown/ brownish in colour, some individuals with a much smaller fourth spine. Meracanthus triangular. Tarsal formula 3-3-3. General brown to yellowish in colour. Metatibiae with four long fine reddish spurs on inner side and two smaller reddish spurs on outer side. Coxae yellowish, with a central dark-brown stripe, becoming gradually browner and less yellowish towards metacoxae. Trochanters brown. Meso and metafemurs yellowish with dark-brown to brownish stripes. Tarsi and tibia light-brown.
</p>
            <p>Wings
Forewing with eight apical and four subapical cells. Ulnar cell 3 angled to radial cell. Costal vein parallel-sided to node. Pterostigma present becoming darker towards distal end. CuA weakly bowed. M and CuA meeting at basal cell with stems completely fused. RA1 slightly diverging from subcostal at subapical region before crossvein. C and R+Sc close together. CuP and 1A non-fused at their bases. Forewing outer margin developed for its total length. Membrane hyaline. Hindwing vein 2A with an infuscation running alongside total length of vein. First cubital cell width at distal end much greater than second cubital cell. Anal lobe broad, with vein 3A bowed at distal end. Larger forewing proximal veins yellowish with smaller apical veins brown, same vein colour pattern for hindwing. Costal vein yellowish. Basal membrane and plaga yellowish.
</p>
            <p>Opercula
More or less confluent with distal margin of tympanal cavity, well developed towards abdominal midline with sharply rounded apices facing midline. General opercula colour yellowish becoming brown at the base. Meracanthus following the same colour pattern as opercula.
</p>
            <p>Tymbals
Tymbal covers absent. Four to five ribs, broadening apically, three of which arising from anterior proximal part of a large basal dome covering over half total length of tymbal. First anterior rib is slender, with a break at about a third of its length. Fourth rib arising from anterior distal side of basal dome more or less evident amongst individuals. Some specimens present a fifth less defined rib arising from posterior distal end of the basal dome, transversal to fourth rib and converging in a sharp end. Tymbal ribs and basal dome brownish-grey; tymbal plate light-grey.
</p>
            <p>Abdomen
Tergites T2 and T3 much enlarged accounting for about a third of total abdominal length. StVIII greater in length than StVII. T1 and T2 dark-brown; T4–7 dark-brown on dorsal midline, sides red and covered in fine silvery pubescence; T8 dark-brown on dorsal midline, sides yellowish. Sternite I brown; StII yellowish with a brown patch on elevated central area; StIII–VIII yellowish. Epipleurites yellowish.
</p>
            <p>Genitalia
(

C to 6F) Pygophore distal shoulder not developed; Pygophore inner tooth absent; Upper lobe present, small and rounded, distant from dorsal beak; Basal lobe small to moderately developed ending in a sharp, rounded tip, in lateral view. Dorsal beak well developed, sharp and part of chitinized pygophore. Ventrobasal pocket absent. Claspers small-medium sized, hooked slightly outwards on distal end, rounded tip. Uncus duck-bill shaped, small and flat, not dominant and retractable within pygophore; Uncus lateral lobes absent. Aedeagal basal plate, undulated in lateral view, weakly depressed on dorsal midline; Basal plate apically broad, flat and rounded in ventral view, with a medial small sharp-tipped lobe on both sides, followed by a tubelike constriction leading to theca, gradually narrowing, slight medial lateral depression; Basal plate bearing a ripple-like pattern in dorsal view. Basal portion directed forwards away from thecal shaft; Ventral rib not apparent; Basal plate completely fused to theca without mobility. Theca very long and J-shaped in lateral view. Thecal pseudoparamers lateral of theca, dorsally fused until two thirds of theca length, very flat, as long as endotheca, ending on an upward pointed, sharp tip; Ventral support absent. Pygophore dorsal surface lightbrown to yellow. Claspers dark-brown. Uncus brown.
</p>
            <p>Female morphology
Only one female known so far (see supplementary image, S6 for the live specimen). Generally lighter in colour than male. Postclypeus yellowish with brown grooves, genae and lora light brown; Legs generally light brown; Dorsal surface of head light-brown with brown patterns; thorax and scutellum lightbrown. Abdomen light brown laterally, with a lighter brown on dorsal midline.
</p>
            <p>
Body measurements for 
13 males
of
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Total
</tp:taxon-name>
length: 16.99 ± 
0.78 mm
; Pronotal length: 1.74 ± 
0.15 mm
; Mesonotal length: 2.67 ± 
0.11 mm
; Forewing length: 13.39 ± 
0.54 mm
; M+CuA length: 1.21 ± 
0.18 mm
. Female and additional body measurements can be found on 
Table 3
.
</p>
            <p>Bioacoustics
The calling song here described is based on the analysis of recordings of three males singing at T=39–40 °C. A typical phrase is structured into four sequential parts (

): A, a single echeme; B, a series of 16 ± 2.60 echemes (10–21, n=52) in rapid succession; C, a group of 8 ± 3.68 echemes (5–18, n= 53) ending on D, a single, long echeme. In 21.15% and 9.61% of the phrases part A and part D are missing, respectively.
</p>
            <p>Calling song frequency-based analysis revealed an interesting frequency modulation in part B. Peak frequency for parts A, C and D is 13.88 ± 0.79 kHz, with maximum frequency of 20.65 ± 0.54 kHz. During part B there is an abrupt reduction of the frequency with a peak frequency of 7.91 ± 1.62 kHz, yet, maintaining the maximum frequency at 21.62 ± 1.11 kHz.</p>
            <p>
For additional time and frequency variables consult 
Table 6
. Note that, due to frequency modulation in part B, it was separated from parts A, C and D in our analysis.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica
Phrase Part A Part B
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>Time variables Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n</p>
            <p>
Duration (ms) 2218 ± 559 1357–3448 52 30 ± 
10 15–56
47 335 ± 52 212–411 52
</p>
            <p>Echeme duration (ms) - - - Same as above 2.14 ± 1.06 0.8–7 849</p>
            <p>Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) - - - - - - 49.16 ± 6.08 36.08–72.67 52</p>
            <p>Interval (ms) 259 ± 82 195–614 49 - - - 19.55 ± 5.31 2.8–55 797</p>
            <p>Part C Part D</p>
            <p>Time variables Mean±SD Min–Max n Mean±SD Min–Max n</p>
            <p>Duration (ms) 1364 ± 679 632–2992 53 252. 29 ± 79.23 97–430 41</p>
            <p>Echeme duration (ms) 49.2 ±20.6 5–253 487 Same as above</p>
            <p>Echeme rate (echeme.s -1) 7.10 ± 1.04 3.34–10.32 53 - - -</p>
            <p>Interval (ms) 108.83 ± 22.24 34–260 435 - - -</p>
            <p>continued.</p>
            <p>Frequency variables Peak frequency Min frequency Max frequency Bandwidth</p>
            <p>Part ACD Mean ± SD 13.88 ± 0.79 4.65 ± 0.96 20.65 ± 0.54 15.94 ± 1.31 Min–Max 11.50–15.50 1.96–6.00 18.70–22.40 12.80–19.78</p>
            <p>Part B Mean ± SD 7.91 ± 1.62 4.39 ± 1.01 21.62 ± 1.11 17.14 ± 1.59 Min–Max 5.60–16.50 0.30–5.80 13.92–23.40 9.04–22.80</p>
            <p>Frequency variables Quartile 25 Quartile 50 Quartile 75 Quartile (75%–25%)</p>
            <p>Part ACD Mean ± SD 11.91 ± 0.22 13.48 ± 0.27 14.89 ± 0.32 2.98 ± 0.26</p>
            <p>Min–Max 10.70–12.50 12.28–14.40 13.40–15.80 1.87–4.10</p>
            <p>Part B Mean ± SD 7.54 ± 0.61 9.57 ± 0.79 11.61 ± 1.26 4.07 ± 0.93</p>
            <p>
Min–Max 6.30–12.00 7.50–13.50 9.70–17.50 2.70–8.20 
DNA
barcoding

Four haplotypes were recovered among the 
COI
sequences of nine males of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, with a nucleotide diversity of π= 0.0164. Sequences were clustered into two well supported sister clades (

) diverging by 2.9 % (K2P distance). These clades are, according to our currently knowledge, geographically segregated. Among the 18 segregating sites observed, 16 are fixed for each clade, being two of them non-synonymous mutations. Mean interspecific genetic distances for 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
are presented in 
Table 5
. The new species is clearly distinguishable within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura</tp:taxon-name>
), with mean pairwise genetic distances&gt;10%. The 
COI
fragment is therefore apparently proficient for 
DNA
barcoding of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
, though the genetic structure reported here must be taken into account.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution
(

) 
Morocco
, in the northern parts of Middle Atlas Mountains, near Taza and along the eastern Rif mountains (Al Hoceima), eastward to Berkane (Beni-Snassen Mountains), as the extreme western foot of the Tellian Atlas Mountains. On biogeographical grounds it is possible that this species is also in western 
Algeria
.
</p>
            <p>Habitat
(

) Open scrubland or light xerothermophilous woodland dominated by holm-oak (
<tp:taxon-name>Quercus rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
) in the northern Middle Atlas or mixed pinewoods of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus halepensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Tetraclinis articulata</tp:taxon-name>
with a rich understory of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pistacia lentiscus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Chamaerops humilis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Rosmarinus officinalis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Stipa</tp:taxon-name>
spp. Males sing mainly perched on these shrubs, and sometimes on the lower branches of trees (&lt;
3 m
height).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
Specific epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
arises from the dual sound production during the calling song of this species, meaning “two melodies”. It consists of two distinct sound patterns, with the second part severely downshifted in frequency and resembling a human-produced unvoiced linguolabial trill, often referred as “Blowing a raspberry”.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
The two new species described in this paper based on acoustic, morphological and genetic data, used a more comprehensive species concept according to the contemporaneous perspective on species delimitation (
De Queiroz 2007
, 
2016
; 
Hausdorf 2011
). For cicadas in general, the male calling song is thought to act as a pre-zygotic barrier which leads to specific-mate recognition and pairing (Paterson 1985), allowing for a reproductive, sometimes semipermeable, separation broadly considered as one of the early stages of species differentiation (
Mayr 1963
; 
Nosil 2008
).
</p>
         <p>
The placement of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
under 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
is supported by aedeagus morphology (

D and 3E), size, behaviour and genetic distance. 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. are all morphologically similar but are confidently distinguished through the analysis of their calling songs (
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
). While most 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
species have small distribution ranges in the Iberian Peninsula, 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata</tp:taxon-name>
is an outlier, spreading elsewhere in SW Europe (
Puissant &amp; Sueur 2010
; Nunes 
et al.
2014b). Despite the limited knowledge on the distribution limits of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
, the species apparently shows a broad distribution range in 
NorthernMorocco
and bears some 
COI
genetic variation, but unlike 
<tp:taxon-name>T. argentata
(

Nunes 
et al.
2014a

)
</tp:taxon-name>
, it constitutes a monophyletic clade, with no evidence of geographically structured genetic differentiation.
</p>
         <p>
Although the use of the 5’ end of the 
COI
gene as 
DNA
barcode has been proven relatively inefficient in the unambiguous identification of European 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
spp. (

Nunes 
et al.
2014a

), this was not the case for 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
. Mean pairwise distance between 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
is&gt; 9%, which is well beyond commonly used thresholds for species differentiation with this marker (

Hebert 
et al.
2004

; 
Wiemers &amp; Fiedler 2007
; 

Linares 
et al.
2009

).
</p>
         <p>
Both phylogenetic trees obtained by Bayesian Inference and Maximum Likelihood (

and S3, respectively) agree on the branch topology of the most recent taxa within 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
, but such cannot be said about the deeper-level relationships. The new species found in 
Morocco
appears basally segregated in the genus, alongside 
<tp:taxon-name>T. josei</tp:taxon-name>
.

Asserting which is the basal taxon will need the inclusion of slower-evolution, nuclear genes. A recent work by 

Marshall 
et al.
2015

, includes a dated global phylogeny from the tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
with mitochondrial and nuclear genes, placing 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
very far from all other European genera included in our analyses (
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada</tp:taxon-name>
). Conversely, it is interesting to note that 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
forms a well-definedclade with American, continental Asia, 
Philippines
and Micronesian species. The discovery of the first species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna</tp:taxon-name>
out of Europe is an important step towards understanding the place and time of origin of this genus, its evolution and diversification. Further phylogenetic analyses are thus required, with the inclusion of additional genetic data and divergence time estimates.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta</tp:taxon-name>
had to be erected as a new genus to accommodate a new species found so far only in 
Morocco
. The 
type
species, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
, can be readily separated from other closely related genera (
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadetta</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
) with a set of characters, which include genital morphology and a deep genetic divergence. However, the acoustic behaviour of this species turns up as the most striking feature. The very particular calling song shows a downshift in frequency (about 43% reduction) in part B of the phrase. Frequency shifts inside a phrase have also been reported for Dundubinii and Platypleurinii cicadas of Southern Asia, amongst others, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Meimuna tavoyana
(Distant, 1888)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Purana metallica
Duffels &amp; Schouten, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Maua albigutta
(Walker, 1857)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Kalabita operculata
Moulton, 1923
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Gogala 1995
; Gogala &amp; Trilar 2004; Gogala 
et al.
2004; 
Trilar 2006
; cf. 
<tp:taxon-name>P. metallica</tp:taxon-name>
as 
<tp:taxon-name>P. aff. tigrina</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
         <p>
Some European 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicadettini</tp:taxon-name>
also reveal some degree of frequency modulation within a phrase, namely 
<tp:taxon-name>Pagiphora aschei
Kartal, 1978
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. annulata
(Brullé, 1832)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Euboeana castaneivaga
Gogala 
et al
., 2011
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>H. varipes</tp:taxon-name>
(calling songs and spectrograms available at www.cicadasong.eu) but neither as pronounced nor with an abrupt downshift as seen in 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
. Video recordings of a calling male (see video in appendix, S7, credits to E. Marabuto) reveal that during the downshifted portion of the phrase, the male will slightly raise and tighten its abdomen probably with the help of longitudinal ventral muscles, in a similar fashion as 
<tp:taxon-name>M. albigutta
(Gogala 
et al.
2004)
</tp:taxon-name>
, a species with portions of a phrase with abrupt downshifts in frequency. Although it is difficult to uncouple the effect of tympanal gap, opercula and abdominal muscles have in the production and frequency regulation in cicadas, further studies are still needed to better understand the general mechanisms of frequency modulation in cicadas.
</p>
         <p>
Finally, phylogenetic analysis of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
revealed evidence of population structure. Populations from Berkane and Middle Atlas were recovered as genetically divergent (2.9%) and well resolved sister clades, suggesting two isolated distribution areas. Further fieldwork is required to confirm if they can be separated into different taxa, despite their seemingly alike calling songs. As Berkane is located near the international Morocco- 
Algeria
border, the presence of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
in this latter country cannot be dismissed.
</p>
         <p>
The two new species here presented confirm the need for more data and effort to properly assess and update our knowledge of biodiversity and evolution of the rich cicadofauna of North Africa. Thus, taking into consideration that the 
Western
Mediterranean area encompasses important biogeographical barriers and each part has been differentially affected by climate changes in the recent geological past, understanding the role of the Maghreb as a reservoir of biodiversity in general (
Schmitt 2007
, Husemann 
et al
. 2014), or referring to cicadas in particular, is of the utmost importance.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgments</title>
         <p>Appreciation is due to Sara Ema Silva for introduction to phylogenetic methods and Francisco Pina-Martins for bioinformatics support. Thanks are also due to Tomi Trilar for the help to enumerate European Cicadettinii species with song frequency modulation. We also wish to thank two anonymous reviewers for their contribute which allowed us to improve our manuscript.</p>
         <p>Fieldwork was funded by a grant from the Systematics Research Fund awarded to Paula Simões in 2014 by the Royal Linnean Society and the Systematics Association.</p>
         <p>
Funding was also provided from National Funds through FCT—Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia, under project UID/ 
BIA
/00329/2013.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Boulard, M.
(
1980
) 
Cigales nouvelles ou mal connues d’Afrique du Nord (Homoptera Cicadoidea)
. 
Nouvelle Revue Entomologie
, 
10
(
42
), 
313–324
.
</p>
         <p>Boulard, M.
(
1981
) 
Homoptères Cicadoidea récoltés en algérie par M
. 

J.-M. Maldès. 
Revue Française d’Entomologie
, New Series

, 
3
(
2
), 
37–45
.
</p>
         <p>Boulard, M.
(
1987
) 
Cigales nouvellles d’Afrique du Nord (hom. Cicadoidea)
. 
L’ Entomologiste
, 
43
(
4
), 
215–218
.
</p>
         <p>Boulard, M.
(
2006
) 
Acoustic signals, diversity and behaviour of cicadas
. 
In:Drosopoulos, S.
&amp; 
Claridge M.
(Eds.), 
Insect Sounds and Communication: Physiology
, 
Behaviour
, 
Ecology
, 
and Evolution
. 

CRC Press, 
Florida
, pp. 
331–349
.
</p>
         <p>Claridge, M.
(
1985
) 
Acoustic signals in the Homoptera: Behavior, taxonomy, and evolution
. 
Annual Review of Entomology
, 
30
(
1
), 
297–317
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ento.30.1.297</p>
         <p>Gogala, M.
(
1995
) 

Songs of four cicada species from 
Thailand
. 
Bioacoustics
, 6

(
2
), 
101–116
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1080/09524622.1995.9753278</p>
         <p>Gogala, M.
&amp; 
Trilar, T.
(
2004
) 
Biodiversity of cicadas in Malaysia—A bioacoustic approach
. 
Serangga
, 
9
(1–2), 
63–81
.
</p>
         <p>Gogala, M.
, 
Trilar, T.
, 
Kozina, U.
&amp; 
Duffels, H.
(
2004
) 
Frequency modulated song of the cicada Maua albigutta (Walker, 1856) (Auchenorrhyncha: Cicadoidea) from Southeast Asia
. 
Scopolia
, 
54
, 
1–15
.
</p>
         <p>Hajibabaei, M.
, 
Smith, M.A.
, 
Janzen, D.H.
, 
Rodriguez, J.J.
, 
Whitfield, J.B.
&amp; 
Hebert, P.D.N.
(
2006
) 

A minimalist barcode can identify a specimen whose 
DNA
is degraded

. 
Molecular Ecology Notes
, 6

(
4
), 
959–964
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1111/j.1471-8286.2006.01470.x</p>
         <p>Hall, T.A.
(
1999
) 
Bioedit: A user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for windows 95/98/nt
. 
Nucleic Acids Symposium Series
, 
41
, 
95–98
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/citeulike-article-id:691774</p>
         <p>Hausdorf, B.
(
2011
) 
Progress toward a general species concept
. 
Evolution
, 
65
(
4
), 
923–931
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1111/j.1558-5646.2011.01231.x</p>
         <p>Hebert, P.D.N.
, 
Penton, E.H.
, 
Burns, J.M.
, 
Janzen, D.H.
&amp; 
Hallwachs, W.
(
2004
) 

Ten species in one: 
DNA
barcoding reveals cryptic species in the neotropical skipper butterfly Astraptes fulgerator

. 

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the 
United States of America
, 
101
(
41
), 
14812–14817
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0406166101</p>
         <p>Hebert, P.D.N.
, 
Ratnasingham, S.
&amp; 
de Waard, J.R.
(
2003
) 
Barcoding animal life: Cytochrome C Oxidase subunit1
divergences among closely related species. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences
, 270 (Supplement 1), S96–S
99
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2003.0025</p>
         <p>Hertach, T.
, 
Puissant, S.
, 
Gogala, M.
, 
Trilar, T.
, 
Hagmann, R.
, 
Baur, H.
, 
Kunz, G.
, 
Wade, E.J.
, 
Loader, S.P.
, 
Simon, C.
&amp; 
Nagel, P.
(
2016
) 
Complex within a complex: integrative taxonomy reveals hidden diversity in Cicadetta brevipennis (Hemiptera: Cicadidae) and unexpected relationships with a song divergent relative
. 
PLOS
ONE

, 
11
(
11
), e0165562. https://doi.org/ 
10.1371/journal.pone.0165562</p>
         <p>Hertach, T.
, 
Trilar, T.
, 
Wade, E.J.
, 
Simon, C.
&amp; 
Nagel, P.
(
2015
) 
Songs, genetics, and morphology: revealing the taxonomic units in the European Cicadetta cerdaniensis cicada group, with a description of new taxa (Hemiptera: Cicadidae)
. 
Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society
, 
173
(
2
), 
320–351
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1111/zoj.12212</p>
         <p>Katoh, K.
&amp; 
Standley, D.M.
(
2013
) 
MAFFT
multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability

. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
, 
30
(
4
), 
772–780
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst010</p>
         <p>Linares, M.C.
, 
Soto-Calderón, I.D.
, 
Lees, D.C.
&amp; 
Anthony, N.M.
(
2009
) 

High mitochondrial diversity in geographically widespread butterflies of 
Madagascar
: a test of the 
DNA
barcoding approach

. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution
, 
50
(
3
), 
485–495
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2008.11.008</p>
         <p>Marshall, D.C.
, 
Hill, K.B.R.
, 
Moulds, M.
, 
Vanderpool, D.
, 
Cooley, J.R.
, 
Mohagan, A.B.
&amp; 
Simon, C.
(
2015
) 
Inflation of molecular clock rates and dates: molecular phylogenetics, biogeography, and diversification of a global cicada radiation from Australasia (Hemiptera: Cicadidae: Cicadettini)
. 
Systematic Biology
, 65

(
1
), 
16–34
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1093/sysbio/syv069</p>
         <p>Mayr, E.
(
1963
) 
Animal Species and Evolution
. 
Belknap Press of Harvard University, Cambridge
, 
797 pp.</p>
         <p>Mendes, R.
, 
Nunes, V.L.
, 
Quartau, J.
&amp; 
Simões, P.C.
(
2014
) 
Patterns of acoustic and morphometric variation in species of genus Tettigettalna (Hemiptera: Cicadidae): sympatric populations show unexpected differences
. 
European Journal of Entomology
, 
111
(
3
), 
429–441
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.14411/eje.2014.054</p>
         <p>Moulds, M.S.
(
2005
) 
An appraisal of the higher classification of cicadas (Hemiptera: Cicadoidea) with special reference to the Australian fauna
. 
Records of the Australian Museum
, 
57
(
3
), 
375–446
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.3853/j.0067-1975.57.2005.1447</p>
         <p>Moulds, M.S.
(
2012
) 
A Review of the Genera of Australian Cicadas (Hemiptera: Cicadoidea)
. 
Zootaxa
, 
3287
, 
1–262
.
</p>
         <p>Nosil, P.
(
2008
) 
Speciation with gene flow could be common
. 
Molecular Ecology
, 
17
(
9
), 
2103–2106
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.03715.x</p>
         <p>Nunes, V.L.
, 
Mendes, R.
, 
Marabuto, E.
, 
Novais, B.M.
, 
Hertach, T.
, 
Quartau, J.
, 
Seabra, S.G.
, 
Paulo, O.S.
&amp; 
Simões, P.C.
(
2014
a) 

Conflicting patterns of 
DNA
barcoding and taxonomy in the cicada genus Tettigettalna from southern Europe (Hemiptera: Cicadidae)

. 
Molecular Ecology Resources
, 
14
, 
27–38
.
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.1111/1755-0998.12158</p>
         <p>Nunes, V.L.
, 
Mendes, R.
, 
Quartau, J.
&amp; 
Simões, P.C.
(
2014
)b) 
Current distribution raises concerns on the conservation of Tettigettalna mariae (Quartau &amp; Boulard, 1995) (Hemiptera: Cicadoidea) in portugal
. 
Ecologi
@

, 
7
, 
50–57
.
</p>
         <p>Nylander, J.
, 
Ronquist, F.
, 
Huelsenbeck, J.
&amp; 
Nieves-Aldrey, J.L.
(
2004
) 
Bayesian phylogenetic analysis of combined data
. 
Systematic Biology
, 
53
(
1
), 
47–67
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1080/10635150490264699</p>
         <p>Pina-Martins, F.
&amp; 
Paulo, O.S.
(
2008
) 
Concatenator: sequence data matrices handling made easy
. 
Molecular Ecology Resources
, 
8
(
6
), 
1254–1255
.
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.1111/j.1755-0998.2008.02164.x</p>
         <p>Pinto-Juma, G.
, 
Simões, P.C.
, 
Seabra, S.G.
&amp; 
Quartau, J.
(
2005
) 
Calling song structure and geographic variation in Cicada orni linnaeus (Hemiptera: Cicadidae)
. 
Zoological Studies
, 
44
(
1
), 
81–94
.
</p>
         <p>Puissant, S.
&amp; 
Sueur, J.
(
2010
) 

A hotspot for mediterranean cicadas (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadidae): new genera, species and songs from southern 
Spain
. 
Systematics and Biodiversity
, 
8
(
4
), 
555–574
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1080/14772000.2010.532832</p>
         <p>Quartau, J.
&amp; 
Simões, P.
(
2006
) 
Acoustic evolutionary divergence in cicadas: the species of Cicada L. in southern Europe
. 
Insect Sounds and Communication:Physiology
, 
Behaviour
, 
Ecology
, 
and Evolution
, Chapter 7

, 
227–237
.
</p>
         <p>De Queiroz, K.
(
2007
) 
Species concepts and species delimitation
. 
Systematic Biology
, 56

(
6
), 
879–886
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1080/10635150701701083</p>
         <p>De Queiroz, K.
(
2016
) 
Ernst Mayr and the modern concept of species
. 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
, 
102
, 
6600–6607
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0502030102</p>
         <p>Ronquist, F.
, 
Teslenko, M.
, 
Van Der Mark, P.
, 
Ayres, D.L.
, 
Darling, A.
, 
Höhna, S.
, 
Larget, B.
, 
Liu, L.
, 
Suchard, M.
&amp; 
Huelsenbeck, J.P.
(
2012
) 
MrBayes 3.2: efficient bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space
. 
Systematic Biology
, 
61
(
3
), 
539–542
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/sys029</p>
         <p>Sanborn, A.F.
(
2014
) 
Catalogue of the Cicadoidea (Hemiptera: Auchenorrhyncha)
. 

Academic Press, San Diego, 
California
, 
1010 pp.</p>
         <p>Schindelin, J.
, 
Arganda-Carreras, I
., 
Frise, E.
, 
Kaynig, V
., 
Longair, M.
, 
Pietzsch, T.
, 
Preibisch, S.
, 
Rueden, C.
, 
Saalfeld, S.
, 
Schmid, B.
, 
Tinevez, J.-Y.
, 
White, D.J.
, 
Hartenstein, V
., 
Eliceiri, K.
, 
Tomancak, P.
&amp; 
Cardona, A.
(
2012
) 
Fiji
: an opensource platform for biological-image analysis

. 
Nature Methods
, 9

(
7
), 
676–682
. https://doi.org/ 
10.1038/nmeth.2019</p>
         <p>Schmitt, T.
(
2007
) 
Molecular biogeography of Europe: Pleistocene cycles and postglacial trends
. 
Frontiers in Zoology
, 
4
(
11
), 
1–13
.
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.1186/1742-9994-4-11</p>
         <p>Simões, P.
, 
Nunes, V
., 
Mendes, R.
&amp; 
Quartau, J.
(
2013
) 

First record of tettigettalna mariae quartau &amp; boulard, 1995 (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadoidea) in 
Spain
. 
Biodiversity Data Journal
, 
1
, e 
978
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.1.e978</p>
         <p>Simões, P.
&amp; 
Quartau, J.
(
2006
) 
Selective responsiveness in males of Cicada orni to conspecific and allospecific calling songs (Hemiptera: Cicadidae)
. 
Entomologia generalis
, 
29
(
1
), 047–060.
</p>
         <p>Simões, P.C.
, 
Boulard, M.
, 
Rebelo, M.T.
, 
Drosopoulos, S.
, 
Claridge, M.F.
, 
Morgan, J.C.
&amp; 
Quartau, J.
(
2000
) 

Differences in the male calling songs of two sibling species of Cicada (Hemiptera: Cicadoidea) in 
Greece
. 
European Journal of Entomology
, 
97
(
3
), 
437–440
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.14411/eje.2000.067</p>
         <p>Simões, P.C.
, 
Nunes, V.L.
, 
Mendes, R.
, 
Seabra, S.G.
&amp; 
Paulo, O.S.
(
2014
) 

Tettigettalna josei (Boulard, 1982) (Hemiptera: Cicadoidea): first record in 
Spain
, with notes on the distribution, genetic variation and behaviour of the species

. 
Biodiversity Data Journal
, 
2
, e 
1045
.
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.3897/BDJ.2.e1045</p>
         <p>Specht, R.
(
2004
) 
Avisoft -SASLab Pro
. 
Sound analysis and synthesis laboratory
.
</p>
         <p>Stamatakis, A.
(
2014
) 
RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies
. 
Bioinformatics
, 
30
(
9
), 
1312–1313
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btu033</p>
         <p>Sueur, J.
&amp; 
Puissant, S.
(
2007
) 
Similar look but different song: a new Cicadetta species in the montana complex (Insecta, Hemiptera, Cicadidae)
. 
Zootaxa
, 
68
, 
55–68
.
</p>
         <p>Tamura, K.
, 
Stecher, G.
, 
Peterson, D.
, 
Filipski, A.
&amp; 
Kumar, S.
(
2013
) 
Mega6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0
. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
, 
30
(
12
), 
2725–2729
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst197</p>
         <p>Trilar, T.
(
2006
) 
Frequency modulated song of the cicada Kalabita operculata (Auchenorrhyncha: Cicadoidea) from Borneo
. 
Russian Entomological Journal
, 
15
(
3
), 
341–346
.
</p>
         <p>Villiers, A.
(
1943
) 
Révision des adeniana du nord de l’Afrique (Hemiptera: Cicadidae)
. 
Bulletin du Muséum national d’Histoire Naturelle
, 
6
, 
424–428
.
</p>
         <p>Wiemers, M.
&amp; 
Fiedler, K.
(
2007
) 

Does the 
DNA
barcoding gap exist?—a case study in blue butterflies (Lepidoptera: Lycaenidae)

. 
Frontiers in Zoology
, 
4
(
8
), 
1–16
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1186/1742-9994-4-8</p>
         <p>. Ađđitional taxa sampling incluđeđ in our phylogenetic analysis incluđing collection points anđ GenBank accession numbers.</p>
         <p>
Taxon Sample ID Country Location GPS coorđinates GenBank accession n. Source 
<tp:taxon-name>Cicada barbara
Cba
</tp:taxon-name>
203 
Spain
Sierra 
Nevađa
, Lanjarón 36°54̓57.78"N; 
KC807317
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>3°30̓14.4"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Cicada orni
Cor
</tp:taxon-name>
298 
Portugal
Serra đ̓Aires e Canđeeiros 
39°27'17.6''NKC807318
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>8°45'07.8''W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei
Eco
</tp:taxon-name>
772 
Portugal
Beringel 38°3̓19.5"N; 
KX582155
This paper 7°59̓50.28"W
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei
Eco
</tp:taxon-name>
827 
Portugal
Beringel 38°3̓19.5"N; 
KX582156
This paper 7°59̓50.28"W
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Euryphara contentei
Eco
</tp:taxon-name>
828 
Portugal
Beringel 38°3̓19.5"N; 
KX582157
This paper 7°59̓50.28"W
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Hilaphura varipes</tp:taxon-name>
MVA608 
Spain
Sierra 
Nevađa
, Pinos Genil 37°8̓15.5"N; 
KX582168
This paper 3°28̓34"W
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi
Tam
</tp:taxon-name>
199 
Spain
near 
Gibraltar
36°11̓17.7"N; 
KC807277
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>5°21̓33.6"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna armandi
Tam
</tp:taxon-name>
200 
Spain
near 
Gibraltar
36°11̓17.7"N; 
KC807278
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>5°21̓33.6"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi
Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
250 
Spain
Zagra 37°16̓59.82"N; 
KC807301
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>4°14̓4.02"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna aneabi
Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
255 
Spain
Zagra 37°16̓59.82"N; 
KC807299
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>4°14̓4.02"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata
Tar
</tp:taxon-name>
163 
France
Narbonne 43°9̓16.92"N; 
KC807234
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>2°57̓49.14"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata
Tar
</tp:taxon-name>
256 
Spain
Espiel 38°11̓3.72"N; 
KC807232
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>5°1̓36.12"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata
Tar
</tp:taxon-name>
365 
Spain
Ayamonte 37°16̓3.3"N; 
KC807246
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>7°20̓32.28"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna argentata
Tar
</tp:taxon-name>
43 
PortugalBraga
41°34̓54.48"N; 
KC807229
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>8°19̓14.1"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi
Tbo
</tp:taxon-name>
233 
Spain
Campico đe los López, 
Murcia
37°34̓57"N; 
KC807276
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>1°34̓16.5"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna boulardi
Tbo
</tp:taxon-name>
235 
Spain
Campico đe los López, 
Murcia
37°34̓57"N; 
KC807275
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>1°34̓16.5"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai
Tcb
</tp:taxon-name>
191 
Spain
Grazalema 36°45̓24.18"N; 
KC807311
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>5°24̓6.3"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai
Tcb
</tp:taxon-name>
194 
Spain
Grazalema 36°45̓24.18"N; 
KC807312
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>5°24̓6.3"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula baenai
Tcb
</tp:taxon-name>
195 
Spain
Grazalema 36°45̓39.18"N; 
KC807313
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>5°22̓57.6"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti
Tđe
</tp:taxon-name>
182 
Spain
Puerto đel Viento, Ronđa 36°47̓13.32"N; 
KC807305
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>5°3̓11.88"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti
Tđe
</tp:taxon-name>
183 
Spain
Puerto đel Viento, Ronđa 36°47̓13.32"N; 
KC807307
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>5°3̓11.88"W</p>
         <p>......continued on the next page1.
(Continueđ)
</p>
         <p>
Taxon Sample ID Country Location GPS coorđinates GenBank accession n. Source 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti
Tđe
</tp:taxon-name>
185 
Spain
Puerto đel Viento, Ronđa 36°47̓13.32"N; 
KC807309
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>5°3̓11.88"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna defauti
Tđe
</tp:taxon-name>
188 
Spain
Puerto đel Viento, Ronđa 36°47̓13.32"N; 
KC807308
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>5°3̓11.88"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrellae
Tes
</tp:taxon-name>
21 
PortugalBraga
41°34̓54.48"N; 
KC807263
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>8°19̓14.1"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna estrellae
Tes
</tp:taxon-name>
264 
Portugal
Serra đa Estrela 40°21̓17.76"N; 
KC807265
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>7°26̓24.6"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna helianthemi galantei
Thg
</tp:taxon-name>
204 
Spain
Lanjarón, Sierra 
Nevađa
36°54̓57.78"N; 
KC807281
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>3°30̓14.4"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna helianthemi galantei
Thg
</tp:taxon-name>
205 
Spain
Lanjarón, Sierra 
Nevađa
36°54̓57.78"N; 
KC807280
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>3°30̓14.4"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna helianthemi galantei
Thg
</tp:taxon-name>
214 
Spain
Capileira, Sierra 
Nevađa
36°57̓47.88"N; 
KC807286
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>3°20̓26.52"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna helianthemi galantei
Thg
</tp:taxon-name>
240 
Spain
Laroles, Sierra 
Nevađa
37°2̓57.06"N; 
KC807287
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>3°1̓0.9"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna helianthemi helianthemi
Thh
</tp:taxon-name>
230 
Spain
Cabo đe Gata 36°50̓18.3"N; 
KC807297
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>2°17̓35.58"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna helianthemi helianthemi
Thh
</tp:taxon-name>
237 
Spain
Vera 37°12̓48.06"N; 
KC807293
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>1°53̓58.68"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei
Tjo
</tp:taxon-name>
116 
Portugal
Lagoa, Algarve 37°8̓9.36"N; 
KC807271
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>8°23̓4.2"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei
Tjo
</tp:taxon-name>
119 
Portugal
Buđens 37°4̓45.2"N; 
KF977491
Simões 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>8°50̓11.6"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei
Tjo
</tp:taxon-name>
140 
Portugal
Castro Marim, Algarve 37°11̓10.92"N; 
KC807269
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>7°29̓2.1"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei
Tjo
</tp:taxon-name>
562 
Spain
Cartaya 37°15̓38.4"N; 
KF977504
Simões 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>7°7̓43.5"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei
Tjo
</tp:taxon-name>
577 
Spain
Cartaya 37°14̓3.7"N; 
KF977505
Simões 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>7°3̓56.8"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna josei
Tjo
</tp:taxon-name>
64 
PortugalVale
Juđeu, Algarve 37°7̓39.78"N; 
KC807274
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>8°5̓36.06"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae
Tma
</tp:taxon-name>
143 
PortugalVale
đo Lobo, Algarve 37°3̓41.1"N; 
KC807253
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>8°3̓39.12"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae
Tma
</tp:taxon-name>
153 
PortugalVale
đo Lobo, Algarve 37°3̓41.1"N; 
KC807257
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>8°3̓39.12"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tettigettalna mariae
Tma
</tp:taxon-name>
79 
PortugalVale
Juđeu, Algarve 37°6̓20.88"N; 
KC807256
Nunes 
et al
., 2014
</p>
         <p>8°5̓42.66"W</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna gastrica
Tyg
</tp:taxon-name>
180 
Portugal
Sesimbra 38°27̓4.5"N; 
KC807314
Nunes 
et al.
, 2014
</p>
         <p>9°5̓27.9"W</p>
         <p>S2.
GPS coordinates and annotated populations where 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
was heard but not collected.
</p>
         <p>PopulationGPS CoordinatesDateHabitat notesChefchaouane35° 10' 29.34'' N 5° 15' 28.93'' W17-07-2014<tp:taxon-name>
Quercus 
rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
sp., 
<tp:taxon-name>Abies</tp:taxon-name>
sp., 
<tp:taxon-name>Cistus</tp:taxon-name>
spp., 
Juniperus
sp.
Rif35° 17' 53.50'' N 4° 53' 53.60'' W19-07-2014Near the seashore, dominated by small shrubs.</p>
         <p>35° 6' 55.68'' N 4° 40' 45.13'' W19-07-2014<tp:taxon-name>Prunusdulcis</tp:taxon-name>
orchard, arid habitat.
34° 59' 6.76'' N 4° 48' 35.15'' W19-07-2014
Dominated by 
<tp:taxon-name>Quercus
canariensis
</tp:taxon-name>
.
34° 57' 38.06'' N 4° 40' 48.76'' W19-07-2014<tp:taxon-name>Q. rotundifolia
, 
Cupressus</tp:taxon-name>
sp. and small shrubs.
34° 57' 32.05'' N 4° 39' 2.75'' W19-07-2014
Dominated by 
Cupressus
sp.
</p>
         <p>
Taza 
33° 57' 23.00''N4° 3' 5.00'' W17-07-2014
Mainly 
<tp:taxon-name>Q. rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
and some 
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
33° 43' 16.50'' N4° 15' 38.8''W16-07-2014<tp:taxon-name>Q. rotundifolia</tp:taxon-name>
and various shrubs.
</p>
         <p>S3.
Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree obtained with Cytochrome C oxidase subunit I mitochondrial 
DNA
of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
and with other previous published taxa. Bootstrap values are shown next to branch nodes. TET stands for 
<tp:taxon-name>Tettigettacula</tp:taxon-name>
— 
<tp:taxon-name>Euryphara</tp:taxon-name>
— 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanistalna</tp:taxon-name>
clade. Scale bar represents the number of estimated changes per branch length. 
<tp:taxon-name>C. barbara</tp:taxon-name>
(Cba203) and 
<tp:taxon-name>C. orni</tp:taxon-name>
(Cor298) were set as an outgroup. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
taxa IDs are detailed on 
Table 2
. Additional taxa details are included on Table S1. Root was truncated with double dash totalling 0.35 changes per branch length.
</p>
         <p>S4.
Illustration of the 23 variables of external morphology described on 
Table 1
(codes used are the same as in 
Table 1
). All images are from paratypical series of 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
. A—Dorsal view; B—Right wing view; C—Right profemur; D—Head and thorax ventral view; E—Head and thorax dorsal view; F—Right tymbal; E—Left operculum.
</p>
         <p>S5.
Image of a 
<tp:taxon-name>T. afroamissa</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
live male. Notice the olive-green stripe in the pronotum. Images by Eduardo Marabuto.
</p>
         <p>S6.
Image of a live male (left) and a female (right) of 
<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
Images by Eduardo Marabuto.
</p>
         <p>S7.
Video recording of a male 
<tp:taxon-name>Berberigetta dimelodica</tp:taxon-name>
calling. Note the abdomen tightens during part B of the phrase, resounding as “blowing a raspberry”.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
