<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1038/s41598-021-02447-0</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>The first true millipede-1306 legs long</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>OPEN</title>
         <p>The first true millipede—1306 legs long</p>
         <p>Paul E. Marek
1 
*
, 
Bruno A. Buzatto2,3,4
, 
William A. Shear5
, 
Jackson C. Means1,</p>
         <p>Dennis G. Black6
, 
Mark S. Harvey7
&amp; 
Juanita Rodriguez8</p>
         <p>
The name “millipede” translates to a thousand feet (from 
mille
“thousand” and 
pes
“foot”). However, no millipede has ever been described with more than 750 legs. We discovered a new record-setting species of millipede with 1,306 legs, 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
, from 
Western Australia
. This diminutive animal (
0.95 mm
wide, 
95.7 mm
long) has 330 segments, a cone-shaped head with enormous antennae, and a beak for feeding. Adistant relative of the previous record holder, 
<tp:taxon-name>Illacme plenipes</tp:taxon-name>
from California, it belongs to a different order, the 
<tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
. Discovered 
60 m
below ground in a drill hole created for mineral exploration, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
possesses troglomorphic features; it lacks eyes and pigmentation, and it has a greatly elongated body—features that stand in stark contrast to its closest surface-dwelling relatives in 
Australia
and all other members of its order. Using phylogenomics, we found that super-elongation (&gt; 180 segments) evolved repeatedly in the millipede class 
<tp:taxon-name>Diplopoda</tp:taxon-name>
. The striking morphological similarity between 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>I. plenipes</tp:taxon-name>
is a result of convergent evolution, probably for locomotion in similar soil habitats. Discovered in the resource-rich Goldfields- Esperance region and threatened by encroaching surface mining, documentation of this species and conservation of its habitat are of critical importance.
</p>
         <p>
Among the earliest animals to breathe atmospheric oxygen 
1
and with some extinct species that grew to two meters in length 
2
, millipedes have lived on this planetfor more than 400 million years. Important as decomposers in terrestrial ecosystems 
3
, primary knowledge of millipede diversity lags tremendously behind other animal groups. With fossil taxa dated to the Cretaceous 
4
, 
5
, the millipede order 
<tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
includes ca. 70 species with a distribution on all continents except 
Antarctica
. Some of its members exhibit parental care of eggs 
6
, others ooze chemical defenses containing alkaloids 
7
that are sequestered by poison frogs 
8
, 
9
, and some species roll into a ball for protection 
10
. Hatchlings emerge from the egg with four pairs of legs, and continuously add segments during development for an indeterminate period of time, even afer adulthood 
11
. Polyzoniidans have never before been observed in deep soil habitats, and most occur in surficial microhabitats of decaying wood and other detritus. Previously known Australian polyzoniidans have at most 400 legs, eyes with 1–3 ommatidia, most with at least some dark pigmentation, a flat wide body (relative to others in the order), and occurrence in epigeanmicrohabitats 
12
. However, distantly related millipedes, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>Illacme
species
</tp:taxon-name>
and other members of the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
(order 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
), have been recorded from as deep as 
11.5 m
below the soil surface 
13
, 
14
. Tese species possess a suite of adaptations, such as a thin elongated body with up to 750 legs, no eyes, massive antennae, and lack of pigmentation. No siphonorhinid species have been recorded from 
Australia
, and the geographically closest siphonorhinids occur in 
Madagascar
and 
Indonesia13
, 
14
.
</p>
         <p>
Here we report the discovery of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
, the first super-elongated millipede known from 
Australia
, and the new world record holder of the animal with greatest number of legs. It belongs to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonotidae</tp:taxon-name>
(order 
<tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
), yet appears similar to super-elongated millipedes in the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
lives deep underground, and it was only discovered by surveying geological drill holes originally created for mineral exploration that provided access to a cryptic and previously unexplored underground habitat.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>
In 
August 2020
, in the Goldfields region of 
Western Australia
, we discovered a pale, thread-like millipede with 1,306 legs at a depth of 
60 m
in a drill hole created for mineral exploration (

). In total, 56 
4–81 m
deep 150 mm-diameter drill holes located at a site 
100 km
WSW of Norseman, 
Western Australia
(within the Great Western Woodlands) were sampled for millipedes and other subterranean fauna, according to techniques
</p>
         <p>1Virginia
Tech, Blacksburg, 
USA
.
2
Bennelongia Environmental Consultants, Jolimont, 
Australia
. 
3
Macquarie University, Sydney, 
Australia
. 
4
University of 
Western Australia
, Perth, 
Australia
.
5
Hampden-Sydney College, Hampden Sydney, 
USA
.
6
La Trobe University, Melbourne, 
Australia
.
7
Western Australian Museum, Perth, 
Australia
.
8
Australian National Insect Collection, Canberra, 
Australia
. 
*
email: 
paulemarek@gmail.com</p>
         <p>Figure 1.
Te leggiest animal on the planet, 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
, from Australia. (
A
) female with 330 segments and 1,306 legs (paratype specimen, T147124). (
B
) ventral view of legs (male holotype, T147101). (
C
) dorsal view of head and ventral view of gonopods (male holotype, T147101). Scale bars, 0.5 mm.
</p>
         <p>
described in ref. 
16
. Tese geological drill holes provided a portal to access an interstitial habitat composed of bandediron formationsand mafic volcanic rocks, which are known to harbor troglophilicfauna 
16
, 
17
. Eight individuals of the new species were collected from troglofauna traps at depths between 
15–60 m
from three drill holes (
450 m
apart), including five individuals from a trap set at a depth of 
60 m
.

Two juveniles were collected in 
April 2020
and another one in 
January 2021
, always from troglofauna traps, attesting to the species’ true deep subterranean life.
</p>
         <p>
Te specimens superficially appeared to be members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
, due to phenotypic similarity to 
<tp:taxon-name>Illacme plenipes
Cook &amp; Loomis, 1928
</tp:taxon-name>
. We used scanning electron microscopy and genome sequencing to conclude that the remarkable anatomical similarity between 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>I. plenipes</tp:taxon-name>
is a result of convergent evolution of super-elongation (&gt; 180 segments), which we here reveal that has originated at least twice in the millipede class 
<tp:taxon-name>Diplopoda</tp:taxon-name>
(

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
appears unlike any other species in the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
. Its highly elongated and narrowed body, lack of eyes, massive antennae, shortened legs, and lack of pigmentation comprisea suiteof characters consistentwith afossorial 
bauplan
that hasrepeatedly evolvedin the 
<tp:taxon-name>Diplopoda</tp:taxon-name>18
, 
19
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Taxonomy section.</title>
         <p>
Class 
<tp:taxon-name>Diplopoda
de Blainville
</tp:taxon-name>
in Gervais, 1844
</p>
         <p>
Subterclass 
Colobognatha
Brandt, 1834
</p>
         <p>
Order 
<tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida
Cook, 1895
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonotidae
Cook, 1895
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinotini
Hoffman, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes
, Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone
Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonotidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rhinotini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Illacme plenipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Stemmiulida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Chordeumatida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Spirostreptida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Julida, Spirobolida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rhinotus
Cook, 1896
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonoconus
Attems, 1930
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone
Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonotus flavomarginatus
Attems
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">The first true millipede-1306 legs long</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/s41598-021-02447-0</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7B3CE124FFB0FFEDF36DFF84FF83FF8D</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-02447-0</pub-id>
               <source>Scientific Reports</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes
, Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>new genus</tp:taxon-status>
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone
Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>http://zoobank.org/NomenclaturalActs/a258f64e-0d4c-4941-be20-0b5d7 8e1078e.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p>
               <sec sec-type="multiple">Type
species.
</sec>
               <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone
Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Generic placement and diagnosis.
Te genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes</tp:taxon-name>
is placed in the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
, family 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonotidae</tp:taxon-name>
, tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinotini</tp:taxon-name>
based on the following characters 
10
, 
20
; whether the character is diagnostic for the order (O), family (F), or tribe (
T
) is denoted in parentheses. Head capsule small, conical, elongated into a sharp snout (O) (

, Supplementary 

). Prozonites and metazonites of trunk rings the same width (O) (Supplementary 

); prozonites not narrow as in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
. Rings smooth (Supplementary 

), covered with neither cuticular ornaments nor long setae as in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
. Vertex of head with two macrosetae (O) (Supplementary 

). Antennae thick with equally sized antennomeres (O) (

, Supplementary Fig. S3A); antennae not strongly elbowed between antennomeres 3, 4 as in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
). Gnathochilarium reduced to three sclerites: mentum; lef, right stipes (O). Ozopores located
</p>
            <p>
(&gt; 180 segments) is well known from the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
, including 
<tp:taxon-name>Illacme plenipes</tp:taxon-name>
with 192 segments and 750 legs, but it has independently evolved in the Australian order 
<tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
with 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
bearing up to 1,306 legs and 330 segments. Tis feature (dark branches) has evolved between two and four times in diplopods based on a character state reconstruction using parsimony. Maximum likelihood phylogeny of 312 orthologous sequences with 
<tp:taxon-name>Polydesmida</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Stemmiulida</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Chordeumatida</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Spirostreptida</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
as outgroup taxa. 
<tp:taxon-name>Julida, Spirobolida</tp:taxon-name>
, and other diplopod orders omitted from the analysis. Support values on nodes are bootstrap supports. Numbers in parentheses afer species names are the maximum segment count for the taxon. Species with super-elongation present denoted in bold. Millipede silhouettes sized relative to one other. Diagram created with Adobe Illustrator 2021 (adobe.com/products/illustrator.html).
</p>
            <p>
far in from lateral edges of tergites; placed two-thirds the distance from midline laterally to tergal margins (F) (Supplementary 

). Vasa deferentia open through small conical lobes (penes) on the posterior surfaces of the second leg coxae (F). Telson a complete ring around the anal valves (F) (Supplementary 

). Tarsal claw with long sigmoid-shaped accessory claw at its base that exceeds the claw in length (F) (Supplementary 

). Te genus differs from other siphonotid genera by the following characters. Anterior gonopods (i.e., 9th leg pair) strongly modified with podomeres 3–4 fused, not leg-like as in Siphonotini genera (
T
) (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5A). Apex of anterior gonopods distinctly bifurcated into two processes (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5A), not a single process as in the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinotus
Cook, 1896
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonoconus
Attems, 1930
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>http://zoobank.org/NomenclaturalActs/0AFB7037-E517- 4D05-804B-D9AE1C7B3F47</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Adults of 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
canbedifferentiated fromother polyzoniidangenera andspecies (and commonly encountered millipedes co-occurring with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Western Australia
) based on the combination of the following characters. Body extremely long and thread-like (width: 
♂0.92 mm
; 
♀0.95 mm
; length: 
♂54.7 mm
; 
♀95.7 mm
). Exoskeleton uniformly pale, cream-colored (

, Supplementary figs. S6– S8)—with neither dark pigmentation nor longitudinal, nor transverse stripes as in surface-dwelling species (Supplementary Fig. S9). Adult millipedes with an exceptional number of rings and legs: 
♀
up to 330 rings and 1,306 legs, and 
♂
upto 208 rings and 818 legs (Supplementary tab. S1). Headcone-shaped andeyeless (

, Supplementary 

)—lacking eyes as are present in surface-dwelling species. Ninth and 10th leg pairs modified into gonopods (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5). Anterior gonopods (9th leg pair) highly modified, not leg like, and distinctly bifurcated into two processes (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5A). Medial process of the anterior gonopods saddle-shaped—not pointed and recurved as in 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonotus flavomarginatus
Attems
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
191121
. Lateral process sheath-like and cupping the medial process. Posterior gonopods (10th leg pair) stylet-like, and in repose threaded through the bifurcated anterior gonopods (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5B). Sterna of gonopods with four long, slender, curved setae apically studded with spinules (Supplementary figs. S4B, S5A).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined.<tp:material-citation>Maleholotype
(
WAM T147101
)
</tp:material-citation>
, 
<tp:material-citation>two female
and 
one maleparatypes
(
WAM T147100
, T 
147124
, T 
146684
), and 
two juveniles
(
WAM T147122
, 
T147123
) from 
Western Australia
, 

ca. 
100 km
WSW of Norseman

, 
32° 32′ 05.9" S
, 
120° 47′ 42.74" E
, 
27 May–4 August 2020
, collected by 
A.J. Mittra
and 
L.P. Masarei
(Western Australian Museum).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Variation.
Males have fewer segments and legs; specimen 
T
147101 has 198 segments and 778 legs (Supplementary Fig. S7), and 
T
147100 has 208 segments and 818 legs (Supplementary Fig. S8). Female specimen 
T
147124 possesses 330 segments and 1,306 legs (

, Supplementary Fig. S6), and 
T
146684 has 253 segments and 998 legs.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Te genus is named because it is the first true millipede with more than 1000 legs. Te name 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes</tp:taxon-name>
is a combination of the Greek 
eu-
, meaning ‘true’; Latin 
mille
, ‘thousand’; and Latin 
pes
, ‘foot’. It is to be treated as a noun. Te species epithet is derived from the Greek mythological goddess of the underworld, Persephone, who was originally from the surface but was taken to the underworld by Hades.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes
, Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone
Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonotidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rhinotini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Illacme plenipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Polydesmida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Stemmiulida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Chordeumatida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Spirostreptida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Julida, Spirobolida</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Rhinotus
Cook, 1896
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonoconus
Attems, 1930
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone
Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Siphonotus flavomarginatus
Attems
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">The first true millipede-1306 legs long</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/s41598-021-02447-0</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7B3CE124FFB0FFEDF36DFF84FF83FF8D</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-02447-0</pub-id>
               <source>Scientific Reports</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes
, Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>new genus</tp:taxon-status>
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone
Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>http://zoobank.org/NomenclaturalActs/a258f64e-0d4c-4941-be20-0b5d7 8e1078e.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p>
               <sec sec-type="multiple">Type
species.
</sec>
               <tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone
Marek
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Generic placement and diagnosis.
Te genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes</tp:taxon-name>
is placed in the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
, family 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonotidae</tp:taxon-name>
, tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinotini</tp:taxon-name>
based on the following characters 
10
, 
20
; whether the character is diagnostic for the order (O), family (F), or tribe (
T
) is denoted in parentheses. Head capsule small, conical, elongated into a sharp snout (O) (

, Supplementary 

). Prozonites and metazonites of trunk rings the same width (O) (Supplementary 

); prozonites not narrow as in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
. Rings smooth (Supplementary 

), covered with neither cuticular ornaments nor long setae as in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
. Vertex of head with two macrosetae (O) (Supplementary 

). Antennae thick with equally sized antennomeres (O) (

, Supplementary Fig. S3A); antennae not strongly elbowed between antennomeres 3, 4 as in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
). Gnathochilarium reduced to three sclerites: mentum; lef, right stipes (O). Ozopores located
</p>
            <p>
(&gt; 180 segments) is well known from the order 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophorida</tp:taxon-name>
, including 
<tp:taxon-name>Illacme plenipes</tp:taxon-name>
with 192 segments and 750 legs, but it has independently evolved in the Australian order 
<tp:taxon-name>Polyzoniida</tp:taxon-name>
with 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
bearing up to 1,306 legs and 330 segments. Tis feature (dark branches) has evolved between two and four times in diplopods based on a character state reconstruction using parsimony. Maximum likelihood phylogeny of 312 orthologous sequences with 
<tp:taxon-name>Polydesmida</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Stemmiulida</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Chordeumatida</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Spirostreptida</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaerotheriida</tp:taxon-name>
as outgroup taxa. 
<tp:taxon-name>Julida, Spirobolida</tp:taxon-name>
, and other diplopod orders omitted from the analysis. Support values on nodes are bootstrap supports. Numbers in parentheses afer species names are the maximum segment count for the taxon. Species with super-elongation present denoted in bold. Millipede silhouettes sized relative to one other. Diagram created with Adobe Illustrator 2021 (adobe.com/products/illustrator.html).
</p>
            <p>
far in from lateral edges of tergites; placed two-thirds the distance from midline laterally to tergal margins (F) (Supplementary 

). Vasa deferentia open through small conical lobes (penes) on the posterior surfaces of the second leg coxae (F). Telson a complete ring around the anal valves (F) (Supplementary 

). Tarsal claw with long sigmoid-shaped accessory claw at its base that exceeds the claw in length (F) (Supplementary 

). Te genus differs from other siphonotid genera by the following characters. Anterior gonopods (i.e., 9th leg pair) strongly modified with podomeres 3–4 fused, not leg-like as in Siphonotini genera (
T
) (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5A). Apex of anterior gonopods distinctly bifurcated into two processes (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5A), not a single process as in the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinotus
Cook, 1896
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonoconus
Attems, 1930
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>http://zoobank.org/NomenclaturalActs/0AFB7037-E517- 4D05-804B-D9AE1C7B3F47</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Adults of 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
canbedifferentiated fromother polyzoniidangenera andspecies (and commonly encountered millipedes co-occurring with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Western Australia
) based on the combination of the following characters. Body extremely long and thread-like (width: 
♂0.92 mm
; 
♀0.95 mm
; length: 
♂54.7 mm
; 
♀95.7 mm
). Exoskeleton uniformly pale, cream-colored (

, Supplementary figs. S6– S8)—with neither dark pigmentation nor longitudinal, nor transverse stripes as in surface-dwelling species (Supplementary Fig. S9). Adult millipedes with an exceptional number of rings and legs: 
♀
up to 330 rings and 1,306 legs, and 
♂
upto 208 rings and 818 legs (Supplementary tab. S1). Headcone-shaped andeyeless (

, Supplementary 

)—lacking eyes as are present in surface-dwelling species. Ninth and 10th leg pairs modified into gonopods (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5). Anterior gonopods (9th leg pair) highly modified, not leg like, and distinctly bifurcated into two processes (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5A). Medial process of the anterior gonopods saddle-shaped—not pointed and recurved as in 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonotus flavomarginatus
Attems
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
191121
. Lateral process sheath-like and cupping the medial process. Posterior gonopods (10th leg pair) stylet-like, and in repose threaded through the bifurcated anterior gonopods (

, Supplementary figs. S4, S5B). Sterna of gonopods with four long, slender, curved setae apically studded with spinules (Supplementary figs. S4B, S5A).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined.<tp:material-citation>Maleholotype
(
WAM T147101
)
</tp:material-citation>
, 
<tp:material-citation>two female
and 
one maleparatypes
(
WAM T147100
, T 
147124
, T 
146684
), and 
two juveniles
(
WAM T147122
, 
T147123
) from 
Western Australia
, 

ca. 
100 km
WSW of Norseman

, 
32° 32′ 05.9" S
, 
120° 47′ 42.74" E
, 
27 May–4 August 2020
, collected by 
A.J. Mittra
and 
L.P. Masarei
(Western Australian Museum).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Variation.
Males have fewer segments and legs; specimen 
T
147101 has 198 segments and 778 legs (Supplementary Fig. S7), and 
T
147100 has 208 segments and 818 legs (Supplementary Fig. S8). Female specimen 
T
147124 possesses 330 segments and 1,306 legs (

, Supplementary Fig. S6), and 
T
146684 has 253 segments and 998 legs.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Te genus is named because it is the first true millipede with more than 1000 legs. Te name 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes</tp:taxon-name>
is a combination of the Greek 
eu-
, meaning ‘true’; Latin 
mille
, ‘thousand’; and Latin 
pes
, ‘foot’. It is to be treated as a noun. Te species epithet is derived from the Greek mythological goddess of the underworld, Persephone, who was originally from the surface but was taken to the underworld by Hades.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
From studies by Manton 
22
and video footage of siphonorhinid millipedes, the locomotive biomechanics of super-elongated millipedes has only been studied rudimentarily. Navigating by its enlarged antennae (

, Supplementary Fig. S3A, B) equipped with up to five sensillum 
types15
, the millipede’s elongated trunk with telescopic segments facilitates burrowing in a three-dimensional soil matrix. Its antennae wave independently to locate an opening; once a suitable gap is identified, the millipede enters and walks through. Te flexible segments are compressible to squeeze through narrow fissures. Te continuous metachronal gait and musculoskeletal action of the segments, which are composed of concentric tubular rings that slide within one another, provide continuous pushing force; in combination with the legs, longitudinal (Supplementary Fig. S10C) and oblique musclespull the rings togetherand provide forward locomotion 
22
. Tisway of burrowingresembles that usedby geophilomorph centipedes (another group of greatly elongated myriapods that includes the leggiest centipede, 
<tp:taxon-name>Gonibregmatus plurimipes
Chamberlin, 1920
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Fiji
with 191 rings and 382 legs) and earthworms. In contrast with millipedes with incompressible rings such as “bulldozer” ecomorphs that walk in a single plane propelled by the additive force of their legs 
22
, colobognath millipedes are ableto wind theirway through athree-dimensional matrix and can simultaneously walk in up to eight different planes. Tis telescoping locomotion, by sliding trunk segments (Supplementary 

) coupled with the thrust of the legs, propels the animal through a varied and unpredictable underground microhabitat 
22
, and the increase in leg number likely contributes more pushing power to force through small crevices and openings. Super-elongation in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Diplopoda</tp:taxon-name>
has repeatedly evolved in taxa that live in these microhabitats, such as in 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonorhinidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>I. plenipes</tp:taxon-name>
with 192 segments and 
<tp:taxon-name>Nematozonium filum
Verhoeff, 1939
</tp:taxon-name>
with 182 segments), 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophoridae</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophora millepeda
Loomis, 1934
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonacme lyttoni
Cook &amp; Loomis, 1928
</tp:taxon-name>
each with 190 segments), and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
. Each additional ringprovides extra locomotory thrust 
23
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
’s upto 330 rings may bespecially adapted to locomotion in its comparatively deep soil microhabitat at 
60 m
—five-fold greater than the maximum depth of 
<tp:taxon-name>Illacme
species.
</tp:taxon-name>
Trunk super-elongation may also serve to lengthen the digestive canal to increase the absorptive surface area and assimilation efficiency in a resource-limited subterranean habitat, as may be the case for 
<tp:taxon-name>I. plenipes</tp:taxon-name>
, which additionally has an even longer corkscrew-shaped gut than the trunk itself 
15
. Te diet of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
is unknown, but may be similar to other primarily fungivorous colobognath millipedes, such as the platydesmidan 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachycybe lecontii
Wood, 1864
</tp:taxon-name>
that feeds on up to 176 different genera of fungi 
24
.
</p>
         <p>
Current alpha-level knowledge of Australian 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonotidae</tp:taxon-name>
is fragmentary. Although an unpublished dissertation from 1994 documented eight genera and 42 species of the family 
25
, taxonomy of the group remains antiquated with two genera and five species currently listed from thecontinent described about acentury ago 
21
, 
25
, 
26
. Although the phenotypic divergence of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
from surface-dwelling family relatives appears to be associated with adaptations to life underground, extraordinary similarity of its gonopods (species-diagnostic features in diplopods) with 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonotus flavomarginatus</tp:taxon-name>
from Torbay, 
Western Australia
, indicates a genus-level affiliation. Close similarity of gonopod anatomy with extremely divergent somatic features suggests rapid evolution of troglomorphic traits.
</p>
         <p>
Invertebrates that live below the Earth’s surface comprise a cryptic and diverse fauna. Although they are challenging to observe and document, notable recent discoveries include beetles and millipedes in Brazilian iron ore caves 
27
, 
28
, snake millipedes of mesovoid shallow substratum of 
Spain29
, and spiders from caves of the Edwards Plateau of Texas 
30
. Tese habitats are repositories of incredibly rich, but obscure biodiversity. Tese underground habitats, and their inhabitants, are critically understudied, despite their ecological importance in filtration of groundwater and screening of environmental toxins. Te subterranean conditions of Western Australia may consistently be at a much lower temperature and higher humidity and house an evolutionarily closely related mesic-adapted troglofauna. Despite surface temperatures in excess of 46 °C and less than 
300 mm
/year of precipitation 
31
, the groundwater in thesites where 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
was collected never exceeded 22 °C. Surface climatic conditions fluctuated considerably across hundreds of millennia, but underground conditions probably remained comparatively stable. Troglophilic species ofen represent ancient vestiges of formerly widespread lineages that now persist in subterranean refugia 
32
. Although the date of the split between the clade containing 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
and the one containing 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonotus flavomarginatus</tp:taxon-name>
is uncertain, divergence may be linked to aridification of the continent between 15–1.75 Ma. Te so-called “climatic relict” theory has been useful to explain other such close relationships between troglophilic and epigean taxa, such as springtails, isopods, schizomids, pseudoscorpions, and ground beetles in Western Australia 
17
, 
33
. Tis theory suggests that cool-adapted epigean ancestors were gradually driven underground where conditions remained favorable, whilst the surface dried and became uninhabitable; following aridification, epigean lineages underwent extinction thereby fostering allopatric speciation 
33
. Asimilartheory has been invokedfor faunalradiations in caves, where analogousextreme adaptive shifs also occur accompanied by morphological change: eyelessness, elaboration of mechanical sensation, lack of pigmentation, and leg elongation. Elongated limbs in troglobionts have been hypothesized to have originated for more efficiently traversing expansive cavernous space for scarce food and mates 
34
. In the case of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
, and its micro-cavernous habitat, the remarkable number of legs may be associated with a comparable search for limited resources in its “micro-cave”-like interstitial habitat. Short legs are likely advantageous in the small cavities of such a habitat, and perhaps compensated for by an increase in their number, which would maintain pushing power.
</p>
         <p>
Located in the Yilgarn Craton, the Eastern Goldfields Province of 
Western Australia
composes a surficial habitat of shrublands (Supplementary Fig. S11) overlaying an ancient terrane that is among the oldest emergent land masses (2.6–4.4 billion years, ref. 
35
). Alarge quantity of Australia’s gold, nickel, and other minerals are extracted from the Goldfields, and intensive surface mining has occurred in the area for more than a century. Mineral exploration includes surveying underground via millions of drill holes that produced cores for elemental analysis in the region. Tese holes, which are later rehabilitated, provide fleeting access to sample an expansive vadose zone which houses a subterranean biodiversity hotspot 
17
, 
36
.
</p>
         <p>
Whether troglomorphic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes</tp:taxon-name>
exist in other parts of 
Western Australia
is an uncertain, but potentially rich avenue of discovery. Te unexpected discovery of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. persephone</tp:taxon-name>
and other troglomorphic animals fromthe Great Western Woodlands 
37
, 
38
, withinthe Eastern Goldfields Province of 
Western Australia
, highlights the region as an exceptional repository of biodiversity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Methods</title>
         <p>Collections.
Millipedes were collected from drill holes according to ref. 
16
. Drill holes were preexisting and bored by mining companies for mineral exploration. 56 
4–81 m
deep 
150 mm
diameter wide drill holes were sampled with specifically designed traps (trogtraps) that are lowered into holes to sample subterranean invertebrates. Trogtraps consist of cylindrical PVC traps with numerous apertures, which are baited with moist leaf litter and lowered on nylon cord to varying depths. Te leaf litter bait is wetted, allowed to decompose over weeks or months and sterilized via microwaving. Holes in the trogtraps are capped at the surface while traps are set to minimize the collection of surface invertebrates. Trogtraps were lef in the field for approximately two (but up to five) months for troglofauna to be attracted to the aroma of decaying vegetation. At the end of the sampling period, traps were carefully pulled out of each hole and the contents placed in zip lock bags, allowing enough oxygen for transit back to the laboratory. In the laboratory, troglofauna were extracted from the leaf litter in traps using Tullgren funnels under incandescent lamps: light and heat from the lamps drives the animals out of the litter towards the base of the funnel and into a collection vial containing 100% ethanol. Samples were obtained under the auspices of scientific research permit number BA27000150 from the Department of Biodiversity, Conservation and Attractions of 
Western Australia
. Millipede specimens were fixed and preserved in ethanol and deposited in the Western Australian Museum, Perth, 
Australia
with the following catalog numbers 
T
147100, 
T
147101, 
T
147122– 
T
147124, and 
T
146684.
</p>
         <p>DNA extraction and sequencing.
Tissues were dissected from ethanol preserved specimens and DNA extracted from them according to ref. 
39
. 6–10 rings were removed and pulverized with a micro-pestle in 200 uL lysis buffer containing proteinase Kusing a Qiagen DNeasy kit. Purified genomic DNA was quantified and quality assessed using a Nanodrop spectrophotometer and Agilent 5400 fragment analyzer. Genomic DNA was randomly fragmented by sonication, Illumina adapters ligated, amplified by PCR, and libraries constructed followed by quantification and a quality-control step. Te libraries for each sample were pooled to 1–3 sequencing lanes to obtain a targeted 9 GB of data using an Illumina Novaseq 6000 two channel platform with paired-end 150 bp reads. Standard DNA cytochrome oxidase Igene (COI) barcodes for the 
holotype
specimen, and 
two juveniles
were sequenced with the primer pair LCO1490 and HCO2198 according to methods in ref. 
39
(NCBI accession #: 
OK602741
).
</p>
         <p>Phylogenomics.
Raw reads of genomes were data filtered to remove adapter sequences, reads containing&gt; 10% N, and low-quality reads with&gt; 50% of the read with phred ≤ 5. FastQC Version 0.11. 
940
was used to evaluate quality scores, GC content, sequencelength distribution, and duplicated and overrepresented sequences. Reads were deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information SRA with the BioProject accession number, PRJNA769673, and the following catalog numbers: 
<tp:taxon-name>Sphaeropoeus
Brandt, 1833
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE02963
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Choctella cumminsi
Chamberlin, 1918
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE01425
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudotremia salisae
Lewis, 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE04962
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Stemmiulus
Gervais, 1844
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE04756
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Apheloria whiteheadi
(Shelley, 1986)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE05046
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonophora
Brandt, 1837
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE04720
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Siphonorhinus robustus
(Attems, 1938)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE05063
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Nematozonium filum
Verhoeff, 1939
</tp:taxon-name>
(
T
129482), 
<tp:taxon-name>Illacme</tp:taxon-name>
“Santa Ana” (
MPE04624
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Illacme plenipes
Cook &amp; Loomis, 1928
</tp:taxon-name>
(SPC001187), 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachycybe lecontii
Wood, 1864
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE03842
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Gosodesmus claremontus
Chamberlin, 1922
</tp:taxon-name>
(
SPC00941
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Petaserpes
Cope, 1870
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE00887
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Octoglena gracilipes
(Loomis, 1971)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Sass.A.230), 
<tp:taxon-name>Eumillipes persephone</tp:taxon-name>
(
T
147101), 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhinotus purpureus
(Pocock, 1894)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
MPE05072
). Trimmomatic Version 
0.3941
was used to trim low quality bases from the end of the reads using ‘trailing 28’, and omit short reads using ‘minlength 75’. aTRAM version 
2.042
was used to assemble sequencing reads using the python script ‘atram_preprocessor.py’ onto a set of 312 orthologous genes (matrix 4 from ref. 
4
). Aset of BLAST libraries containing sequence shards were assembled with ‘atram.py’ implementing the assembler Velvet Version 

1.2. 
1043
. Assembled genes were translated and placed in individual matrices with exonerate Version 2.2. 
044
in the aTRAM module stitcher, ‘atram_stitcher.py’. Amino acids were independently aligned with Maf V 
7.40745
, allowing for automatic selection of appropriate strategy based on data size, using the Smith-Waterman algorithm for alignment and performing 1000 cycles of iterative refinement. Alignments were then visually inspected, manually refined and concatenated using Geneious Prime 2020.2. A Maximum Likelihood approach was undertaken for phylogenetic reconstruction using IQ-TREE V1.7.0b 
746
with a partitioned scheme, testing the model of molecular evolution for each partition and an ultrafast bootstrap analysis of 1,000 replicates 
47
.
</p>
         <p>Morphology.
Te 
holotype
male (
T
147101) and 
paratype
female (
T
146684) specimens were prepared for scanning electron microscopy (SEM) by removing the anterior, middle, and posterior 10 rings, and air drying them at room temperature until the ethanol preservative evaporated. Dissected structures were then placed on double-sided carbon tape on a 
12.7 mm
aluminum SEM stub, and sputter coated with a 40-nm layer of palladium and platinum in a Leica EM 
ACE
600 plasma sputter coater. Micrographs were taken with a FEI Quanta scanning electron microscope at the Nanoscale Characterization and Fabrication Laboratory in the Institute for Critical Technology and Applied Science at 
Virginia
Tech. Examination of general morphology for descriptive taxonomy was carried out on a Leica M125 stereomicroscope (10–125X) and a Leica DM500 brightfield microscope (50–400X).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Data availability</title>
         <p>
Te datasets analyzed in the current study are available from 
Virginia
Tech’s Digital Repository (https://doi.org/ 10.7294/16850347) and the National Center for Biotechnology Information (https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra/ PRJNA769673). Tis publication and its nomenclatural acts have been registered in Zoobank (www.zoobank. org), the official registry of the International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature. Te LSID (Life Science Identifier) of the article is http://zoobank.org/References/ 
6829E779-7AE8-476E-99FF-DD2311C70199
.
</p>
         <p>
Received: 
16 September 2021
; Accepted: 
16 November 2021</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>
1. 
Wilson, H. M.
&amp; 
Anderson, L. I.Morphology and taxonomy of paleozoic millipedes (Diplopoda: Chilognatha: Archipolypoda) from Scotland
. 
J.Paleontol.78
, 
169–184
. 
https://doi.org/10.1666/0022-3360(2004)078%3c0169:MATOPM%3e2.0.CO;2
(
2004
).
</p>
         <p>
2. 
Lucas, S. G.
, 
Lerner, A. J.
, 
Hannibal, J. T.
, 
Hunt, A. P.
&amp; 
Schneider, J. W.
Trackway of a giant 
Arthropleura
from the Upper Pennsylvanian of El Cobre Canyon, New Mexico

. 
Geology of the Chana Basin
. New Mexico Geological Society, 56th Field Conference Guidebook

. 
279–282
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
3. 
Joly, F. X.et al.Detritivore conversion of litter into faeces accelerates organic matter turnover
. 
Commun. Biol.3
, 
1–9
. 
https://doi. org/10.1038/s42003-020-01392-4
(
2020
).
</p>
         <p>
4. 
Rodriguez, J.et al.Step-wise evolution of complex chemical defenses in millipedes: Aphylogenomic approach
. 
Sci. Rep.8
, 
1–10
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-19996-6
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
5. 
Wesener, T.
&amp; 
Moritz, L.Checklist of the Myriapoda in Cretaceous Burmese amber and a correction of the Myriapoda identified by Zhang (2017)
. 
Check List.14
, 
1131
. 

https://doi.org/10.15560/ 
14.6.1131
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
6. 
Enghoff, H.Phylogeny of millipedes—a cladistic analysis
. 
J. Zool. Syst. Evol. Res.22
, 
8–26
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1439-0469. 1984.tb00559.x
(
1984
).
</p>
         <p>
7. 
Wood, W. F.
, 
Hanke, F.J.
, 
Kubo, I.
, 
Carroll, J. A.
&amp; 
Crews, P.
Buzonamine, a new alkaloid fromthe defensivesecretion of the millipede, 
Buzonium crassipes
. 
Biochem. Syst. Ecol.28
, 
305–312
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0305-1978(99)00068-X
(
2000
).
</p>
         <p>
8. 
Saporito, R. A.
, 
Donnelly, M. A.
, 
Hoffman, R. L.
, 
Garraffo, H. M.
&amp; 
Daly, J. W.
Asiphonotid millipede (
Rhinotus
) as the source of spiropyrrolizidineoximes of dendrobatid frogs

. 
J. Chem. Ecol.29
, 
2781–2786
. 
https://doi.org/10.1023/B:JOEC.0000008065.28364. a0
(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
9. 
Shear, W. A.Te chemical defenses of millipedes (Diplopoda): biochemistry, physiology and ecology
. 
Biochem. Syst. Ecol.61
, 
78–117
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bse.2015.04.033
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
10. 
Shear, W.A.
Redescription of the South African millipede 
Cylichnogaster lawrencei
Verhoeff, 1937 and notes on the family Siphonotidae (Diplopoda, Polyzoniida)

. 
Zootaxa4079
, 
119–128
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4079.1.8
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
11. 
Enghoff, H.
, 
Dohle, W.
&amp; 
Blower, J. G.Anamorphosis in millipedes (Diplopoda)—the present state of knowledge with some developmental and phylogenetic considerations
. 
Zool. J.Linn.Soc-Lond.109
, 
103–234
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.1993. tb00305.x
(
1993
).
</p>
         <p>
12. 
Black, D. G.Diversity and biogeography of Australian millipedes (Diplopoda)
. 
Mem. Mus. Vic.56
, 
557–561
(
1997
).
</p>
         <p>
13. 
Marek, P.E.
&amp; 
Bond, J. E.Rediscovery of the world’s leggiest animal
. 
Nature441
, 
707
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/441707a
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
14. 
Marek, P. E.
, 
Krejca, J. K.
&amp; 
Shear, W. A.
Anew species of 
Illacme
Cook &amp; Loomis, 1928 from Sequoia National Park, California, with a world catalog of the Siphonorhinidae (Diplopoda, Siphonophorida)

. 
ZooKeys626
, 
1–43
. 
https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys. 626.9681
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
15. 
Marek, P. E.
, 
Shear, W. A.
&amp; 
Bond, J. E.
Aredescription of the leggiest animal, the millipede 
Illacme plenipes
, with notes on its natural history and biogeography (Diplopoda, Siphonophorida, Siphonorhinidae)

. 
ZooKeys241
, 
77–112
. 
https://doi.org/10.3897/ 2Fzookeys.241.3831
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
16. 
Halse, S.
&amp; 
Pearson, G. B.Troglofauna in the vadose zone: comparison of scraping and trapping results and sampling adequacy
. 
Subterr. Biol
.
13
, 
17–34
. 
http://www.pensof.net/journals/subtbiol
(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
17. 
Guzik, M. T.et al.Is the Australian subterranean fauna uniquely diverse?
. 
Invertebr. Syst.24
, 
407–418
. 
https://doi.org/10.1071/ is10038
(
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
18. 
Enghoff,H.
Te millipede genus 
Cylindroiulus
on Madeira—an insular species swarm (Diplopoda, Julida:Julidae)

. 
Entomol.Scand.18
, 
1–142
(
1982
).
</p>
         <p>
19. 
Liu, W.
, 
Golovatch, S. I.
, 
Wesener, T.
&amp; 
Tian, M.Convergent evolution of unique morphological adaptations to a subterranean environment in cave millipedes (Diplopoda)
. 
PLoS ONE12
, e 
0170717
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0170717
(
2017
).
</p>
         <p>
20. 
Hoffman, R. L.
On the status of 
Siphonotus brasiliensis
Brandt, and of the diplopod family Siphonotidae (Polyzoniida)

. 
Dtsch. entomol.
Z.
4
, 
425–431
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/mmnd.19770240418
(
1977
).
</p>
         <p>
21. 
Michaelsen, W.
&amp; 
Hartmeyer, R.Attems, C. M.T.Graf Von.Myriopoda excl. Scolopendridae.Gustav Fischer, Jena
.In. 
Die Fauna Südwest-Australiens
.
3
, 
145–204
(
1911
).
</p>
         <p>
22. 
Manton, S. M.Teevolution of arthropodan locomotory mechanisms—Part 4 Testructure, habits andevolution of the Diplopoda
. 
Zool. J.Linn. Soc-Lond.42
, 
299–368
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.1954.tb02211.x
(
1954
).
</p>
         <p>
23. 
Garcia, A.
, 
Priya, S.
&amp; 
Marek, P.Understanding the locomotion and dynamic controls for millipedes: part 1—kinematic analysis of millipede movements
. 
ASME Smart Mater. Adapt.Struct. Intell. Syst
.
https://doi.org/10.1115/SMASIS2015-8894
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
24. 
Macias, A. M.et al.
Diversity and function of fungi associated with the fungivorousmillipede 
Brachycybe lecontii
. 
Fungal Ecol.41
, 
187–197
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.funeco.2019.06.006
(
2019
).
</p>
         <p>
25. 
Black, D. G.Ataxonomic revision of the Australian Siphonotidae (Diplopoda: Polyzoniida)
. 
Dissertation, University of California, Davis
. (
1994
).
</p>
         <p>
26. 
Verhoeff, K. W.Results of Dr. E. Mjöberg’s Swedish Scientific Expeditions to Australia 1910–1913 34 Myriapoda:Diplopoda
. 
Ark. zool.16
, 
1–142
(
1924
).
</p>
         <p>
27. 
Shear, W. A.
, 
Ferreira, R.L.
, 
Iniesta, L.F.M.
&amp; 
Marek, P.Amillipede missing link: Dobrodesmidae, a remarkable new polydesmidan millipede family from Brazil with supernumerary rings (Diplopoda, Polydesmida), and theestablishment of a new suborder Dobrodesmidea
. 
Zootaxa4178
, 
371–390
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4178.3.4
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
28. 
Asenjo, A.
, 
Pietrobon, T.
&amp; 
Ferreira, R. L.
Anew troglobitic species of 
Metopioxys
(Staphylinidae: Pselaphinae) from Brazilianiron ore caves

. 
Zootaxa4576
, 
195–200
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4576.1.13
(
2019
).
</p>
         <p>
29. 
Akkari, N.
, 
Gilgado, J. D.
, 
Ortuno, V. M.
&amp; 
Enghoff, H.
Out of the dark void: 
Ommatoiulus longicornis
n. sp., a new julid from Spain (Diplopoda, Julida) with notes on some troglobiomorphic traits in millipedes

. 
Zootaxa4420
, 
415–429
. 
https://doi.org/10. 11646/zootaxa.4420.3.7
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
30. 
Hedin, M.
, 
Derkarabetian, S.
, 
Blair, J.
&amp; 
Paquin, P.
Sequence capture phylogenomics of eyeless 
Cicurina
spiders from Texas caves, with emphasis on US federally-endangered species from Bexar County (Araneae, Hahniidae)

. 
ZooKeys.769
, 
49–76
. 
https://doi. org/10.3897/2Fzookeys.769.25814
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
31. 
Australian Government
, 
Bureau of Meteorology, Kalgoorlie-Boulder Airport Climate Statistics
.Retrieved 
7 July 2021
. 
http://www. bom.gov.au/climate/averages/tables/cw_012038_All.shtml
.
</p>
         <p>
32. 
Shear, W. A.
&amp; 
Shelley, R.M.
Solved afer 140 years: the identity of the millipede 
Polydesmus cavicola
Packard, 1877, and proposal of 
Packardesmus
n gen (Diplopoda:Polydesmida:Macrosternodesmidae)

. 
Zootaxa4559
, 
384–390
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zoota xa.4559.2.11
(
2019
).
</p>
         <p>
33. 
Giachino, P. M.
, 
Eberhard, S.
&amp; 
Perina, G.Arich fauna of subterranean short-range endemic Anillini (Coleoptera, Carabidae, Trechinae) from semi-arid regions of Western Australia
. 
ZooKeys.1044
, 
269–337
. 
https://doi.org/10.3897/zookeys.1044.58844
(
2021
).
</p>
         <p>
34. 
Christiansen, K.Morphological adaptations
. In 
Encyclopedia of Caves
(eds 
White, W. B.
&amp; 
Culver, D. C.
) 
517–528
(
Elsevier, Amsterdam
, 
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
35. 
Williams, I. R.Yilgarn Block
. 
Geological Survey of Western Australia, Te Geology of Western Australia, Western Australia Geological Survey
, ISBN 978–0–7244–6084–7, 
33–81
(
1975
).
</p>
         <p>
36. 
Hyde, J.
, 
Cooper, S. J. B.
, 
Humphreys, W. F.
, 
Austin, A. D.
&amp; 
Munguia, P.Diversity patterns of subterranean invertebrate fauna in calcretes of the Yilgarn Region, Western Australia
. 
Mar. Freshwater Res.69
, 
114–121
. 
https://doi.org/10.1071/MF17005
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
37. 
Watson, A.
, 
Judd, S.
&amp; 
Watson, J.Flowering plant and vertebrate diversity of the Great Western Woodlands in the Southern Goldfields
. 

In: 
Proceedings of the Goldfield Environmental Management Workshop
(editors: 
A.B. Fourie
, 
M. Tibbett
), 
Australian Centre for Geomechanics, Te University of Western Australia
. 
116–124
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
38. 
Car, C. A.
&amp; 
Harvey, M. S.
Te millipede genus 
Antichiropus
(Diplopoda:Polydesmida:Paradoxosomatidae), part 2: Species of the Great Western Woodlands region of Western Australia

. 
Rec. West.Aust.Mus.29
, 
20–77
. 
https://doi.org/10.18195/issn.0312-3162. 29(1).2014.020-077
(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
39. 
Shorter, P. L.
, 
Hennen, D. A.
&amp; 
Marek, P. E.
Cryptic diversity in 
Andrognathus corticarius
Cope, 1869 and description of a new 
Andrognathus
species from New Mexico (Diplopoda, Platydesmida, Andrognathidae)

. 
ZooKeys786
, 
19–41
. 
https://doi.org/10. 3897/zookeys.786.27631
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
40. 
Andrews, S.FastQC:a quality control tool for high throughput sequence data
. 
https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/proje cts/fastqc/
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>
41. 
Bolger,A.M.
, 
Lohse, M.
&amp; 
Usadel, B.Trimmomatic:Aflexible trimmer for Illumina Sequence Data
. 
Bioinformatics
, btu170. 
http:// www.usadellab.org/cms/?page=trimmomatic
(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
42. 
Allen, J.M.
, 
Lafrance, R.
, 
Folk, R. A.
, 
Johnson, K.P.
&amp; 
Guralnick, R.P.ATRAM 2.0: Animproved, flexible locusassembler for NGS data
. 
Evol. Bioinform
.
https://doi.org/10.1177/1176934318774546
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
43. 
Zerbino, D. R.
&amp; 
Birney, E.Velvet: Algorithms for de novo short read assembly using de Bruijn graphs
. 
Genome Res.18
, 
821–829
. 
https://doi.org/10.1101/gr.074492.107
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
44. 
Slater, G. S. C.
&amp; 
Birney, E.Automated generation of heuristics for biological sequence comparison
. 
BMC Bioinform.6
, 
1–11
. 

https://doi.org/10.1186/1471- 
2105-6-31
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
45. 
Katoh, K.
&amp; 
Standley, D. M.MAFFT multiplesequence alignment sofware version 7: Improvements in performance and usability
. 
Mol. Biol. Evol.30
, 
772–780
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/mst010
(
2013
).
</p>
         <p>
46. 
Minh, B. Q.et al.IQ-TREE 2: New models and efficient methods for phylogenetic inference in the genomic era
. 
Mol. Biol. Evol.37
, 
1530–1534
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msaa015
(
2020
).
</p>
         <p>
47. 
Hoang, D. T.
, 
Chernomor, O.
, 
von Haeseler, A.
, 
Minh, B. Q.
&amp; 
Vinh, L. S.UFBoot2:Improving the ultrafast bootstrap approximation
. 
Mol. Biol. Evol.35
, 
518–522
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msx281
(
2018
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>Tis research was supported by a National Science Foundation grant to PEM (Division of Environmental Biology, Systematics and Biodiversity Sciences, #1916368). Tanks to Charity Hall, Howard Dunleavy, and Bailey Connors for assisting with editing, figure illustration, and specimen measurement. Sergei Golovatch and Henrik Enghoff provided comments on previous versions of the manuscript.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Author contributions</title>
         <p>Conceptualization: P.E.M., B.A.B., W.A.S., M.S.H.; Methodology: P.E.M., B.A.B., W.A.S., M.S.H., J.R.; Analysis: P.E.M., B.A.B., J.C.M., J.R.; Visualization: P.E.M., B.A.B., J.R.; Data curation: P.E.M., B.A.B., M.S.H., J.R.: Writing—original draf: P.E.M.: Writing—review &amp; editing: P.E.M., B.A.B., W.A.S., J.C.M., D.G.B., M.S.H., J.R.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Competing interests</title>
         <p>Te authors declare no competing interests.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Additional information</title>
         <p>Supplementary Information
Te online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi.org/ 10.1038/s41598-021-02447-0.
</p>
         <p>Correspondence
and requests for materials should be addressed to P.E.M.
</p>
         <p>Reprints and permissions information
is available at www.nature.com/reprints.
</p>
         <p>Publisher’s note
Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.
</p>
         <p>Open Access
Tis article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
</p>
         <p>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. Te images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.</p>
      </sec>
      <p>© Te Author(s) 2021</p>
   </body>
</article>
