<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1038/nature07447</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A bizarre Jurassic maniraptoran from China with elongate ribbon-like feathers</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2008</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>LETTERS</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>A bizarre Jurassic maniraptoran from China with elongate ribbon-like feathers</title>
         <p>Fucheng Zhang1
. 
Zhonghe Zhou1
. 
Xing Xu1
. 
Xiaolin Wang1
&amp; 
Corwin Sullivan1</p>
         <p>Recent coelurosaurian discoveries have greatly enriched our knowledge of the transition from dinosaurs to birds, but all reported taxa close to this transition are from relatively well</p>
         <p>known coelurosaurian groups1
– 
3
. Here we report a new basal avialan, 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx hui</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
, from the Middle to Late Ɨurassic of Inner Mongolia, China. This new species is characterized by an unexpected combination of characters seen in several different theropod groups, particularly the Oviraptorosauria. Phylogenetic analysis shows it to be the sister taxon to 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>4,5, forming a new clade at the base of Avialae6
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
also possesses two pairs of elongate ribbon-like tail feathers, and its limbs lack contour feathers for flight. This finding shows that a member of the avialan lineage experimented with
</p>
         <p>integumentary ornamentation as early as the Middle to Late Ɨurassic, and provides further evidence relating to this aspect of the transition from non-avian theropods to birds.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Theropoda Marsh 1881</title>
         <p>Coelurosauria Huene 1914</p>
         <p>Maniraptora Gauthier 1986</p>
         <p>Avialae Gauthier 1986 (Padian, 2004)</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae Czerkas et Yuan 2002</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx hui</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx hui</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx hui</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A bizarre Jurassic maniraptoran from China with elongate ribbon-like feathers</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/nature07447</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8A49EF368624FFAFFFB6500CBF18DC71</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07447</pub-id>
               <source>Nature</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx hui</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>gen. et sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.Epidexi
(Greek): display; 
pteryx
(Greek): wing, feather; 
hui
, in honour of the late young palaeontologist Yaoming Hu, who
</p>
            <p>1
Laboratory of Evolutionary Systematics of Vertebrates̡ Institute of Vertebrate Paleontology and Paleoanthropology̡ Chinese Academy of Sciences̡ PO Box 643̡ Beijing 100044̡ China.
</p>
            <p>contributed significantly to the study of Mesozoic mammals from China. Generic name pronounced ‘ep-id-ecks-IP-ter-icks’.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>Holotype
.

A feathered pigeon-sized skeleton, preserved on part and counterpart slabs, and housed at the Institute of Vertebrate Paleontology and Paleoanthropology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, collection number 
IVPP V15471
(

; see Supplementary Information).
</p>
               <p>Locality and horizon.
Daohugou, 
Ningcheng County
, 
Inner Mongolia
, north 
China
. The age of the Daohugou sediments is contentious, with possible dates ranging from 

Middle Jurassic 
7
to Early Cretaceous. However

, published radioisotopic dating results span a narrower range from 152 to 168 Myr (Middle to Late Jurassic) 
8
– 
10
.
</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Medium-sized avialan with four elongate ribbon-like tail feathers (ETFs), highly procumbent and significantly enlarged anterior teeth, and a distally tapering pygostyle-like structure formed by ten unfused caudals at the end of the tail (

and 

; see Supplementary Information). Differs significantly from 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
, the only other known scansoriopterygid, in caudal morphology (tail 70% of trunk length in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
, compared with more than 300% in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
; 16 caudal vertebrae in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
, compared with more than 40 in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
; caudal prezygapophyses reduced in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
but significantly elongated in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
            <p>Description and comparisons.<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
is estimated to be 164 g in body mass (see Supplementary Information), smaller than most other basal avialans 
3,11
. The holotype probably represents a subadult individual, because the ends of some of the long bones seem imperfectly ossified.
</p>
            <p>
As in oviraptorosaurs 
12
, the skull is high in lateral view (height about 60% of length), the external naris is positioned high on the snout, and the parietal is proportionally long. The teeth of both the upper and lower jaws are highly procumbent, a feature previously known only in the ceratosaurian 
Masiakasaurus
among theropods 
13
. Furthermore, the anterior teeth are much larger than the posterior ones, as in basal oviraptorosaurs 
12
, basal therizinosaurs 
14
and probably 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>4,5
. There are probably 9 cervicals and 14 thoracic vertebrae, and the synsacrum is composed of 7 vertebrae. The caudal series is much shorter than in non-avian theropods or in other basal avialans. The anterior six caudal vertebrae are proportionally short and wide. The posterior ten caudals bear no transverse
</p>
            <sec sec-type="multiple">
               <p>|
Line drawings and close-up photographs of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx hui</tp:taxon-name>
                  <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
a, Skeleton and feather outline, based on both main slab and counterslab, showing that each shafted feather is formed by central rachis and two unbranched vanes (a 
9
). b, d, d 
9
, Proximal regions of non-shafted feathers; barbs are parallel and closely united as an unbranched membranous structure (d, d 
9
), vanes are either layered, indicated by white arrows (b), or arranged irregularly (c). The red arrow indicates the proximal end of the feather (d). e, e 
9
, f, Distal regions of non-shafted feathers, in which 
barbs appear loosely parallel. Abbreviations: as
1 
ca, astragalus and calcaneum; ce, cervical vertebrae; co, coracoid; cv, caudal vertebrae; dt3
1 
4, distal tarsals 3 and 4; f, frontal; fe, femur; fi, fibula; ga, gastralia; hu, humerus; il, ilium; is, ischium; ma, mandible; mtI–IV, metatarsals I–IV; p, phalanges or metacarpals; pa, parietal; pm, premaxilla; pu, pubis; q, quadrate; r, ribs; ra, radius; rc, rachis; sc, scapula; st, sternum; ti, tibia; tv, thoracic vertebrae; u, ungual phalanges; ul, ulna; uv, unbranched vane.</p>
            </sec>
            <p>
processes. They form a structure similar to the elongated, incipient pygostyle in some basal birds 
15,16
but are not fused to each other (

and 

; see Supplementary Information).
</p>
            <p>
The partly preserved sternum is small and convex anteriorly, and seems to comprise two incompletely fused sternal plates, as in the primitive bird 
Jeholornis17
. The scapula is significantly shorter than the humerus, as in some derived maniraptorans, and the coracoid is sub-rectangular. The pelvis has an unexpected combination of features among theropods, as in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>4,5
. The ilium is bird-like in having a long preacetabular process with a strongly convex anterior margin, but differs from the ilia of most non-avian theropods in having a small pubic peduncle. Unusually among theropods, the straight pubis is shorter than the ischium and is significantly shorter than the femur. It is anteroventrally oriented and lacks a pubic boot. The posteriorly curved ischium is laterally compressed, gradually widens towards the distal end, and lacks an obturator process. The humerus is about same length as the femur, proportionally longer than in most other basal avialans. The ulna is posteriorly bowed and the manus is significantly elongated (see Supplementary Information) as in birds and other derived theropods 
18
– 
22
. The curvature of the manual claws falls within the range known for the pedal claws of ground-based foraging birds (see Supplementary Information). The femur is about 160% the length of the metatarsus, and 80% the length of the tibia (

and 

; see Supplementary Information).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Phylogeny and affinity.
Phylogenetic analysis indicates that 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
form a monophyletic 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
(see Supplementary Information), representing a bizarre lineage at the base of the Avialae 
6
(

; see Supplementary Information).
</p>
            <p>
Although possessing many derived features seen in birds, including a humerus as long as the femur, a long preacetabular process of the ilium with a strongly convex margin, and many other features, 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
also show some striking similarities to oviraptorosaurs 
12
and to a lesser degree therizinosauroids 
14,21
, including a short and high skull, an external naris positioned high on the snout, an anteriorly downturned and strongly dorsally convex mandible, a large external mandibular fenestra, and enlarged anterior teeth. Furthermore, some pelvic features, such as a proportionally very short pubis and a distally widening ischium, are not known in any other theropod. The bizarre appearance of scansoriopterygids indicates that morphological disparity among maniraptorans close to the origin of birds is higher than has previously been assumed, and underscores the importance of Jurassic theropods for understanding avian origins.
</p>
            <p>Integument.
The integument bears feather-like structures of two types, ETFs and non-ETFs, which are roughly comparable to shafted and non-shafted feathers, respectively 
23
. The distal part of each non- ETF is composed of filamentous parallel barbs (

9, f), similar to the condition seen in the non-shafted feathers of other feathered dinosaurs and primitive birds 
18,22–25
. However, the free distal barbs of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
arise from the edge of a membranous structure (

9), an arrangement that has never previously been reported.
</p>
            <p>
The four ETFs are tightly attached to the last ten caudal segments (

and 

). These feathers are incomplete distally, but the preserved part of each ETF is identical to the corresponding structure in some primitive birds 
16,26–28
, for example in having a similar central rachis and unbranched vanes (

and 

9; see Supplementary Information). Elongate tail feathers are a normal component of the ornamental plumage in extant birds. In contrast to other feather types, ornamental plumage is used to send visual signals that are essential to a wide range of avian behaviour patterns, particularly relating to courtship 
29
. For example, experiments have shown that, in some species, males with long tail plumage attract more mates than their short-tailed counterparts 
30
. It is highly probable that the ETFs of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
similarly had display as their primary function, rather than serving other purposes such as flight or insulation 
29
. Indeed, pennaceous feathers suitable for flight are not present in 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
, even though the bones and integument are well preserved. Because pennaceous feathers are commonly encountered in other feathered maniraptorans 
2,21,22,25
, their absence constitutes another highly unusual feature of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
, as well as strongly implying that this taxon was non-volant. 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
is the oldest and most phylogenetically basal theropod known to possess display feathers, indicating that basal avialans experimented with integumentary ornament as early as the Middle to Late Jurassic. Unless 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx</tp:taxon-name>
is interpreted as secondarily flightless, the absence of pennaceous limb feathers in this taxon suggests that display feathers appeared before airfoil feathers and flight ability in basal avialan evolution.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Received 14 June; accepted 19 September 2008.</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <p>
1. 
Makovicky
̡ P. J. 
et al.
The earliest dromaeosaurid theropod from South America

. 
Nature437
. 
1007–1011
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
2. 
Xu̡ X.
&amp; 
Norell̡M.A
. 
Non-avian dinosaur fossils from the Lower Cretaceous Jehol Group of western Liaoning̡ China
. 
Geol. J.41
. 
419–438
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
3. 
Turner̡ A. H.et al.A basal dromaeosaurid and size evolution preceding avian flight
. 
Science317
. 
1378–1381
(
2007
).
</p>
         <p>
4. 
Zhang̡ F.-C.et al.A juvenile coelurosaurian theropod from China indicates arboreal habits
. 
Naturwissenschaften89
. 
394–398
(
2002
).
</p>
         <p>
5. 
Czerkas̡ S. A.
&amp; 
Yuan̡ C.
in 
Feathered Dinosaurs and the Origin of Flight
(ed. 
Czerkas̡ S. J.
) 
63–95
(The 
Dinosaur Museum̡ Blanding
̡ 
2002
).
</p>
         <p>
6. 
Padian̡ K.
in 
The Dinosauria
2nd edn

(eds 
Weishampel̡ D. B
.̡ 
Dodson̡ P.̡Osmolska̡ H.
) 
210–231
(
Univ. of California Press̡ Berkeley
̡ 
2004
).
</p>
         <p>
7. 
Gao̡ K.-Q.
&amp; 
Ren̡ D.Radiometric dating of ignimbrite from Inner Mongolia provides no indication of a post-Middle Jurassic age for the Daohugou Beds
. 
Acta Geol. Sin.80
. 
42–45
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
8. 
Chen̡ W.et al.Isotope geochronology of the fossil-bearing beds in the Daohugou area̡ Ningcheng̡ Inner Mongolia
. 
Geol. Bull. Chin.23
. 
1165–1169
(
2004
).
</p>
         <p>
9. 
He̡ H.-Y.et al.40
Ar/ 
39
Ar dating of ignimbrite from Inner Mongolia̡ northeastern China̡ indicates a post-Middle Jurassic age for the overlying Daohugou Bed

. 
Geophys. Res.Lett
.
31
. L 
20609
̡ 
doi:10.1029/2004GL020792
(
2004
).
</p>
         <p>Figure 3|
Phylogenetic relationships of 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx hui</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
The cladogram is simplified from the strict consensus of nine most parsimonious trees (tree length 1,255; consistency index 0.35; retention index 0.75; see Supplementary Information). 
<tp:taxon-name>Scansoriopterygidae</tp:taxon-name>
is defined as the least inclusive clade including 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidendrosaurus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Epidexipteryx
, Avialae
</tp:taxon-name>
as the most inclusive clade including 
<tp:taxon-name>Vultur gryphus</tp:taxon-name>
but not 
<tp:taxon-name>Deinonychus antirrhopus</tp:taxon-name>
, and Aves as the least inclusive clade including 
<tp:taxon-name>Archaeopteryx</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Vultur gryphus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
10. 
Liu̡ Y.-X.̡Liu̡ Y.-Q
. &amp; 
Zhang̡ H
. 
LA-ICPMS zircon U-Pb dating in the Jurassic Daohugou Beds and correlative strata in Ningcheng of Inner Mongolia
. 
Acta Geol. Sin.80
. 
733–742
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
11. 
Christiansen̡ P.
&amp; 
Fariña̡ R. A.Mass prediction in theropod dinosaurs
. 
Hist. Biol.16
. 
85–92
(
2004
).
</p>
         <p>
12. 
Xu̡ X.et al.An unusual oviraptorosaurian dinosaur from China
. 
Nature419
. 
291–293
(
2002
).
</p>
         <p>
13. 
Sampson̡ S.D.̡Carrano̡ M. T.
&amp; 
Forster̡ C.A.
A 
bizarre predatory dinosaur from Madagascar: implications for the evolution of Gondwanan theropods
. 
Nature409
. 
504–505
(
2001
).
</p>
         <p>
14. 
Kirkland̡ J.I.et al.A primitive therizinosauroid dinosaur from the Early Cretaceous of Utah
. 
Nature435
. 
84–87
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
15. 
Hou̡ L.-H
.&amp; 
Chen̡ P.-J.Liaoxiornis delicatus
gen.et sp.nov.̡ the smallest Mesozoic bird

. 
Chin. Sci. Bull.44
. 
834–838
(
1999
).
</p>
         <p>
16. 
Zhang̡ F.-C.
̡ 
Zhou̡ Z.-H.
&amp; 
Benton̡ M. J.A primitive confuciusornithid bird from China and its implications for early avian flight
. 
Sci. China D51
. 
625–639
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
17. 
Zhou̡ Z.
&amp; 
Zhang̡ F.
A 
long-tailed̡ seed-eating bird from the Early Cretaceous of China
. 
Nature418
. 
405–409
(
2002
).
</p>
         <p>
18. 
Zhang̡ F.-C.̡Zhou̡ Z.-H.
&amp; 
Hou̡ L.-H
. in 
The Jehol Biota
(eds 
Chang̡ M.-M.̡Chen̡ P.-J.̡Wang̡ Y.-Q.
&amp; 
Wang̡ Y.
) 
129–149
(
Shanghai Sci. Technol. Publ
.̡ 
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
19. 
Zhou̡ Z.
̡ 
Barrett̡ P.M.
&amp; 
Hilton̡ J.An exceptionally preserved Lower Cretaceous ecosystem
. 
Nature421
. 
807–814
(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
20. 
Zhou̡ Z.-H.
&amp; 
Zhang̡ F.-C.
Anatomy of the primitive bird 
Sapeornis chaoyangensis
from the Early Cretaceous of Liaoning̡ China

. 
Can.J.Earth Sci.40
. 
731–737
(
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
21. 
Weishampel̡ D. B
.̡ 
Dodson̡ P.
&amp; 
Osmólska̡ H.The Dinosauria
2nd edn

(
Univ. of California Press̡ Berkeley̡2004
).
</p>
         <p>
22. 
Xu̡ X.
in 
Originationsı Radiations and Biodiversity Changes
(eds 
Rong̡ J.-Y.et al.
) 
627–642
; 
927–930
(
Sci. Press̡ Beijing
̡ 
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
23. 
Zhang̡ F.-C.
&amp; 
Zhou̡ Z.-H.
in 
Originationsı Radiations and Biodiversity Changes
(eds 
Rong̡ J.-Y.
e 
t al.
) 
611–625
; 
923–925
(
Sci. Press̡ Beijing
̡ 
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
24. 
Prum̡ R. O.
&amp; 
Brush̡ A. H.The evolutionary origin and diversification of feathers
. 
Q. Rev. Biol.77
. 
261–295
(
2002
).
</p>
         <p>
25. 
Xu̡ X.Scales̡ feathers and dinosaurs
. 
Nature440
. 
287–288
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
26. 
Chiappe̡ L. M.et al.Anatomy and systematics of the Confuciusornithidae (Theropoda:Aves) from the Late Mesozoic of Northeastern China
. 
Bull.Am.Mus. Nat. Hist.242
. 
1–89
(
1999
).
</p>
         <p>
27. 
Zhang̡ F.-C.
&amp; 
Zhou̡ Z.-H.A primitive enantiornithine bird and the origin of feathers
. 
Science290
. 
1955–1959
(
2000
).
</p>
         <p>
28. 
Zheng̡ X.-T.̡Zhang̡ Z.-H.
&amp; 
Hou̡ L.-H.A new enantiornithine bird with four long rectrices from the Early Cretaceous of northern Hebei̡ China
. 
Acta Geol. Sin.81
. 
703–708
(
2007
).
</p>
         <p>
29. 
Gill̡ F. B.Ornithology
2nd edn

(
Freeman̡1995
).
</p>
         <p>30. Andersson̡ M. Female choice selects for extreme tail length in a widowbird.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>Nature
299. 818–820 (1982).
</p>
         <p>Supplementary Information
is linked to the online version of the paper at www.nature.com/nature.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <p>Acknowledgements
We thank F.Jin for discussion̡ Y.Li for specimen preparation̡ W. Gao for photography̡ and J. Choiniere for the use of his laptop computer. This research was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China̡ the Chinese Academy of Sciences̡ and Major Basic Research Projects of the Ministry of Science and Technology̡ China.
</p>
         <p>Author Information
Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to F.Z. (zhangfucheng@ivpp.ac.cn).
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
