<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4021.2.2</journal-id>
         <issn>1175-5326</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A review of Galaxiella pusilla (Mack) (Teleostei: Galaxiidae) in south-eastern Australia with a description of a new species</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
A review of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Teleostei: 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiidae</tp:taxon-name>
) in south-eastern 
Australia
with a description of a new species
</p>
         <p>
RHYS A. COLEMAN1, 
2
, ARY A. HOFFMANN 
1
&amp; TARMO A. RAADIK3, 4 
1
Victorian Centre for Aquatic Pollution Identification and Management, Bio 
21
Institute, School of BioSciences, The University of Melbourne, Victoria 
3010
, 
Australia
. E-mail: rhys.coleman@melbournewater.com.au
</p>
         <p>2
Melbourne Water Corporation, Docklands, Victoria 
3008
, 
Australia</p>
         <p>3
Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research, Department of Environment, Land, Water and Planning, Heidelberg, Victoria 
3084
, 
Australia</p>
         <p>4
Department of Ichthyology, Museum Victoria, Melbourne, Victoria 
3001
, 
Australia
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>
The dwarf 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack)
</tp:taxon-name>
, is a small, threatened freshwater fish from coastal south-eastern 
Australia
. Recent genetic studies, using multiple nuclear and mitochondrial 
DNA
markers, found substantial differences between populations in western Victoria and south 
Australia
(‘west region’) compared to eastern Victoria, Flinders Island, and Tasmania (‘east region’) that suggest the presence of a cryptic species. Morphological measurements and meristic counts from multiple populations within each region were undertaken to investigate potential differences between regions. Several characters, found to discriminate between individuals in the regions and to be diagnostic for two taxa, were used to describe a new species, 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
, for the west region. This is only the second species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiidae</tp:taxon-name>
to exhibit sexual dimorphism. The original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
, based on five specimens, is revised following examination of a large number of individuals. Both species are considered nationally threatened and are categorised as ‘endangered’; the revised distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
is reduced by approximately 
60
%. A number of inconsistencies in the most recent revision of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
are also corrected.
</p>
         <p>Key words:
taxonomic revision, dwarf 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
, sexual dimorphism, threatened species, freshwater fish, cryptic species
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>
Within the Southern Hemisphere temperate family 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiidae</tp:taxon-name>
, the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
currently includes three small, freshwater dependent species, namely: 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(

Mack, 
1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata
(

Shipway, 
1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda
McDowall, 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
. The geographic distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
is restricted to coastal southeastern 
Australia
, including Tasmania, while 
<tp:taxon-name>G. nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
are restricted to coastal south-western 
Australia
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
are distinguished from the other genera of Australian galaxiids by: a) their small maximum size, b) dorsal fin origin distinctly behind the anal fin origin, c) strongly developed caudal peduncle flanges with few procurrent rays, d) lack of laterosensory pores beneath the lower jaw, e) less than 
16
principal caudal rays (usually 
13–14
), f) a rounded caudal fin, g) slender, non-flattened, spike-like caudal neural and haemal spines, and h) 
3–4
branchiostegals (

McDowall 
1978
a

; 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
). Another diagnostic feature of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
is the presence of horizontal stripes along the sides of the body, with juveniles having a crenulated stripe along the lower sides that only persists in adult 
<tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
(

McDowall 
1978
a

).
</p>
         <p>
Genetic and morphological studies suggest that the Australian 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
are closely related to the South American 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias</tp:taxon-name>
—sharing an ancient Gondwanan ancestry (

Waters 
et al.2000
; 

McDowall &amp; Waters 
2004
). In addition to their comparatively small size, 
Brachygalaxia
s and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
are unique within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiidae</tp:taxon-name>
for their longitudinal body stripes (including bright yellow to orange-red), and fleshy ventral keel which may play a role in targeted egg placement during mating (

McDowall &amp; Waters 
2004
). 

Waters 
et al.
(
2000
)

estimated the time of separation between 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias</tp:taxon-name>
lineages to be around 
8.6
–30.0 Ma, although more recent estimates with multiple genetic markers indicated the time of separation was much earlier, with a mean age between 
55.8–58
Ma (

Burridge 
et al.2012
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
). The divergence time between 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
from south-eastern 
Australia
and those in south-western 
Australia
has been estimated to be a mean of 
34.3
Ma (

Unmack 
et al.2012
) and 
28.3
Ma (

Galeotti 
et al
. 
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
The dwarf 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
(or eastern little 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
, is of national conservation significance in 
Australia
, listed as ‘vulnerable’ under the national 

Environment Protection and Biodiversity Conservation 
Act1999
and the 
IUCN
Red List of Threatened Species (

Saddlier 
et al
. 
2010
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
was first described in 
1936
with specimens collected from Cardinia Creek, east of Melbourne, Victoria (

Mack 
1936
). Originally placed in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias
Cuvier
</tp:taxon-name>
, it was subsequently placed into 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias</tp:taxon-name>
by 

Scott (
1942
)

, who recognised a number of shared characters between it and the South American species, though this was later regarded as inappropriate (

McDowall 
1973
). Recognising that 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusilla
Mack
</tp:taxon-name>
, and the more recently described 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias nigrostriatus
Shipway
</tp:taxon-name>
, formed a species group along with a new species being described, 

McDowall (
1978
a)

proposed a new genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
for the three species. Based on morphological and genetic similarities, 

Waters 
et al.
(
2000
)

subsequently recommended that the Australian species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
be restored to 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias</tp:taxon-name>
. However, following a detailed morphological study, the status of 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
as separate, monophyletic genera was supported, each diagnosed by distinctive, derived characters (

McDowall &amp; Waters 
2004
).
</p>
         <p>
There are substantial genetic differences between eastern and western populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
(

Coleman 
et al.2010
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
). Within coastal south-eastern 
Australia
, eastern populations occur from the Mitchell River Basin near Bairnsdale, west to Dandenong Creek near Melbourne, Victoria, including Flinders Island in Bass Strait and north-eastern and north-western Tasmania (

Saddlier 
et al.2010
). Also within coastal south-eastern 
Australia
, the western populations occur from the upper Barwon River system near Barwon Downs, Victoria, west to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Cortina Lakes</tp:taxon-name>
, near the Coorong, South 
Australia
(

Saddlier 
et al.2010
). 

Coleman 
et al.
(
2010
)

proposed that 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
, as it is currently recognised, may comprise two distinct taxa —based on a mean 
COI
divergence (Kimura 
2
-parameter distance) of 
8.43
% between populations in the east and west regions, compared to a mean within-genus 
COI
divergence of 
9.93
% amongst 
207
Australian fish species (

Ward 
et al.2005
). In addition, 

Unmack 
et al.
(
2012
)

found fixed differences at eight allozyme loci between eastern and western 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
populations, and reported mean cytochrome 
b p
-distances of 
9.1
% between eastern and western 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
, compared to 
p
-distances ranging from 
15.4–22.4
% between 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
species and 11.0% between 
<tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias</tp:taxon-name>
species. Congruence between multiple nuclear and mitochondrial markers for an eastern and western lineage supports the notion that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Galaxiella pusilla 
sensu</tp:taxon-name>
lato

(s.l.) currently exists as an unresolved species complex of one described species and one candidate taxon (
sensu
Ven ces 
et al.2005
).
</p>
         <p>
Herein we demonstrate that the two taxa proposed within 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
can be diagnosed from each other using morphological and meristic characters, supporting their status as distinct species, and describe as a new species the western lineage. Given that the original description (

Mack 
1936
), referable to the eastern lineage, was based on a small number of specimens and subsequent revisions (

McDowall 
1978
a

; 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
) were also based on a small number of specimens (
15
for morphology, 
8–48
for meristics), we also redescribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Habitat information for both lineages has also been incorporated into the species descriptions. The separation of this currently recognised threatened taxon into two distinct species with smaller geographic ranges has significant implications (

Coleman 
et al.2010
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
), and we discuss issues surrounding their conservation status and management.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Material and methods</title>
         <p>Species concept.
A total-evidence approach was adopted to determine the validity of splitting 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
based on differences in morphology, multiple, conserved, nuclear markers and phylogeny as assessed using multiple mitochondrial 
DNA
gene sections. This is consistent with the ‘unified species concept’ described by de 

Queiroz (
2007
)

that considers species as separately evolving metapopulation lineages and incorporates a range of criteria drawn from other species concepts to diagnose species. Similar to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias olidus</tp:taxon-name>
complex (

Adams 
et al.2014
; Raadik 
2014
) these two 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
taxa also meet the criteria for species under the morphological and phylogenetic species concepts (e.g. 

Turner 
1999
).
</p>
         <p>Specimen collection.
Specimens in various states of preservation and storage can reduce the accuracy of morphometric measurements (e.g. 

McDowall &amp; 
Wallis1996
; Raadik 
2014
), particularly in diminutive species where measurement error may already be higher than usual. Therefore, all specimens used in this study for morphometric analysis were recently collected by the first author and preserved in a consistent manner. 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
is predominantly an annual species (

Massola 
1938
; 

Humphries 
1986
; 

Pen 
et al.1993
; 

Romanowski 
2004
; Coleman 
et al.
in review), therefore specimen collection was made over a short period to minimise potential morphological differences associated with different life history stages. Specimens were collected over a five-week period between 
27
th June and 
2
nd August 
2013
using dip nets and targeting shallow (&lt;
1 m
) vegetated margins of habitats from 
16
sites that spanned much of the known distribution of eastern and western regions (Table 
1
). Historical specimens collected from geographic extremes in Tasmania and South 
Australia
between 
2008
and 
2010
were also included (

Coleman 
et al.2010
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
), however due to preservation in 
100
% ethanol for genetic studies and associated shrinkage, these specimens were only used for meristic analysis and no length data is presented. Additionally, the 
holotype
, four 
paratypes
and 
20
museum specimens collected from the Grampians region in Victoria in 
1996
were included for vertebral counts (see ‘material examined’ sections within species descriptions and Table 
1
for specimen details). Due to the substantial shrinkage and warping of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>holotype
that made morphometric measurements unreliable, only meristic data is presented for that specimen.
</p>
         <p>
Because 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
is sexually dimorphic based on colour, size and shape (

McDowall 
1978
b

), an even ratio of sexes was sought, with a total of 
20
individuals (males and females combined) collected from most sites, i.e. overall total of 
123
individuals from the west region and 
163
individuals from the east region. Fish were euthanized using a lethal dose of clove oil prior to fixation in 
10
% formalin in the field. Following fixation for at least three days, specimens were transitioned to a 
70
% ethanol solution for longer term preservation by exposure to progressively higher concentrations of ethanol over five days (
30
% and 
50
% for two and three days respectively).
</p>
         <p>Morphometric and meristic measurements.
Morphometric and meristic characters were mostly measured or counted following the procedures described by 

Hubbs &amp; Lagler (
1958
)

which have been modified for, and include additional measurements found useful in, other galaxiid taxonomic studies (

McDowall 
1970
; 

McDowall 
1978
a

; 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
; 

McDowall &amp; 
Wallis1996
; Raadik 
2014
). Many of these characters and the method of measurements have been recently re-defined by Raadik (
2014
). With exception of vertebrae, all measurements and counts were conducted using a Nikon SMZ 
800
dissecting stereomicroscope on adult fish (total length (TL) 
19 mm
or greater). Total length and standard length (
SL
) measurements were taken to the nearest 
0.01 mm
with digital display vernier calipers, while other morphometric measurements were made with an eyepiece micrometer for improved accuracy with smaller features. All measurements and counts were conducted on the left hand side (LHS) of specimens, except for gill rakers on the first branchial arch which were counted on the right hand side (
RHS
), to avoid physical damage to the LHS (see below). To increase the accuracy of gill raker counts, particularly small rudimentary and vestigial rakers, the entire first gill arch was carefully removed (by gently pulling towards the snout to reduce the likelihood of removing an incomplete structure) and stained with alizarin to improve definition of individual rakers. Black and white radiographs of the LHS of specimens (or on their backs if laterally bent) were produced on 
AGFA
Structurix D 
4
FW X-ray film that was exposed for 
30
seconds at 
25
kV in a Faxitron X-ray machine. Vertebrae number was then determined by counting vertebrae on enlarged digital images that were created using a Microtec ScanMaker i 
800
scanner. Following Raadik (
2014
), counts were taken from the first vertebral centrum adjacent to the occipital condyle of the cranium and excluded the hypural vertebra. The number of neural spines assisted counts where compressed vertebrae were observed.
</p>
         <p>
Dorsal, anal, pectoral and pelvic fin segmented ray counts were separated into branched and unbranched categories, lower (including the raker in the angle of the arch) and upper limb gill raker counts were recorded separately, and the setback of the origin of the dorsal fin relative to the origin of the anal fin was also measured (see Raadik 
2014
). Unsegmented procurrent fin rays were excluded from fin ray counts.
</p>
         <p>
In addition to TL and 
SL
, 
29
morphometric characters were measured in this study (

). The definition of these characters follows Raadik (
2014
) except for GD (gape depth)—the distance between the tip of the lower jaw to the equidistant point between the posterior margins of the lower jaw, measured from ventral surface; KD (keel depth)—the maximum height of the keel; KL (keel length)—the length between the anterior and posterior extent of the keel, measured from the ventral surface; CL (caudal fin length)—standard length subtracted from total length and 
LCP
(caudal peduncle length)—from the hypural crease, through the midline of the body, to the point above the posterior margin of anal fin base. The following 
14
meristic characters were also enumerated: dorsal fin raysbranched (DRB), dorsal fin rays—total segmented (DRS), longest dorsal fin ray (LDR), anal fin rays—branched (
ARB
), anal fin rays—total segmented (ARS), longest anal fin ray (LAR), caudal fin rays—branched (CRB), caudal fin rays—total segmented (CRS), pectoral fin rays (PecR), pelvic fin rays (PelR), gill rakers lower limb (GRL), gill rakers upper limb (GRU), gill rakers total (GRT) and total number of vertebrae (Ver).
</p>
         <p>
Due to the diminutive size of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
and the possibility of measurement error influencing analysis outcomes, repeatability estimates for morphometric measurements and meristic counts were conducted three times on five female and five male specimens from the Crawford River population (see below for repeatability analysis method).
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 1.
Measurements: a) lateral body and fin; b) dorsal head; c) ventral head; and d) lateral head measurements. ALanal fin length; BDV—body depth at vent; DCP—caudal peduncle depth; DF–AF—dorsal fin to anal fin setback; DL—dorsal fin length; KD—keel depth; KL—keel length; LAB—anal fin base length; CL—caudal fin length; LCP—caudal peduncle length; LDB—dorsal fin base length; PecL—pectoral fin length; PelL—pelvic fin length; PelAn—distance between pelvic and anal fin bases; PecPel—distance between pectoral and pelvic fin bases; PreA—pre-anal fin length; PreD—pre-dorsal fin length; PrePel—pre-pelvic fin length; SL—standard length; TL—total length. ED—eye diameter; GD—gape depth; GWgape width; HD—head depth; HL—head length; HW—head width; IOW—inter-orbital width; LJL—lower jaw length; PoHL—post-orbital head length; SnL—snout length; UJL—upper jaw length.
</p>
         <p>Morphometric and meristic analyses.
Prior to any analyses, scatterplots and box plots were generated to test for outliers. None were identified and all data were used in analyses. To take into account differences in quantitative characters due to sexual dimorphism, analyses comparing differences between eastern and western regions were undertaken for males and females separately. However, for meristic characters no significant difference between sexes were found (based on Mann-Whitney U tests after Bonferroni correction), and data for sexes were combined.
</p>
         <p>
In order to compare our results with those of 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg (
1981
)

, and relate the magnitude of any differences between eastern and western regions of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
to those described for the Western Australian conspecifics 
<tp:taxon-name>G. nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
, various indices of morphometric and meristic characters, including ratios, were computed. In addition, given potential issues surrounding the use of ratios in taxonomic studies (

Atchley 
et al.1976
), an alternative approach was also followed that involved adjusting morphometric measurements for body size (
sensu
Raadik 
2011
; 

Adams 
et al.2014
). This comprised log 
10
transformation of size and trait measurements before correcting for size, using the regression coefficients (
β
) derived from a linear regression: 
yi
= log 
10
(
χi
)— 
β
log 
10
(
SLi
), where 
yi
and 
χi
are the adjusted and raw values for the character in individual 
i
and 
SLi
is the standard length of individual 
i
. Where characters were found to be highly correlated after size correction (i.e. 
r
&gt; 
0.7
), redundant characters were removed from further analyses to facilitate multivariate comparisons (see Results). Similarly, for meristic characters, Spearman rank correlations were computed to test for co-correlated characters and redundant characters removed where correlations were high (
r
s&gt; 
0.7
) (see Results). Spearman rank correlations also indicated that none of the retained meristic characters were highly correlated with size (
r
s &lt;
0.5
).
</p>
         <p>
One-way analyses of variance (
ANOVA
) tested if quantitative characters (corrected for 
SL
) differed significantly between eastern and western populations. 
ANOVA
was also used to estimate measurement repeatability (‘ 
r
’, ranges from 
0 to 1
, and represents the proportion of variation due to differences among individuals, not due to differences within an individual) calculated as 
r
= S 
2
A/(S 
2
+ S 
2
A), where S 
2
A is the between group variance ((mean squares between individuals—mean squares for repeat measurements within individuals)/ number of repeat measurements) and S 
2
is the within group variance (mean squares for repeat measurements within individuals).
</p>
         <p>
For meristic data, east-west comparisons were undertaken with 
Mann
Whitney tests. To investigate separation of the regions based on the traits, a discriminant function analysis (DFA) was undertaken on quantitative (sexes analysed separately) and meristic data. 
ANOVA
was conducted using R version 
2.8
. 
1
(R Development Core Team 
2009
), while 
Mann
Whitney tests, DFA, Pearson correlations and Spearman correlations were conducted with SYSTAT version 
13
(Systat Software Inc, San Jose, 
USA
). For individual traits, the Bonferroni correction was applied when identifying significant differences at the 
5
% level, which equated to an experiment-wide error rate of α = 
0.003
(i.e. 
0.05
/ 
14
) for meristic characters and α = 
0.002
(i.e. 
0.05
/ 
29
) for morphometric characters.
</p>
         <p>Landmark analyses.
Landmarks are increasingly being used to characterize variation in body shape within and between fish populations (e.g. 

Cavalcanti 
et al.1999
; 

Maderbacher 
et al.2008
; 

Chakrabarty 
et al.2010
; 

Ponton 
et al.2013
). In the present study, the LHS of all fish specimens was photographed using a mounted Nikon D 
70
digital SLR camera equipped with a 
105mm
macro lens with enhanced lighting against a white background. A ruler with 
1 mm
increments was included in each image for scale. Each specimen was positioned and photographed twice so that estimates of repeatability could be made. The (
X
, 
Y
) coordinates of 
12
landmarks on each image were digitised with TPSDIG version 
2.17
(

Rohlf 
2013
a

) (

).
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 2.
Positions of 12 landmarks: 1. tip of snout, 2. posterior extent of lower jaw, 3. superior margin of eye, 4. inferior margin of eye, 5. origin of pelvic fin, 6. origin of dorsal fin, 7. posterior insertion of dorsal fin, 8. origin of anal fin, 9. posterior insertion of anal fin, 10. superior insertion of caudal fin, 11. midpoint of caudal fin base, 12. inferior insertion of the caudal fin, *. inferior margin of lower black band directly above ‘5’ used with ‘1’ and ‘11’ to unbend specimens.
</p>
         <p>
The 
12
landmarks were selected to complement key morphometric characters (e.g. position of fins, length of fin bases, length and width of caudal peduncle, length of jaws, eye diameter), whilst representing precise locations to place points, such as the anterior and posterior insertion of fins, maximal extent of snout, jaws and eye. To adjust for the degree of curvature in fish specimens that can develop during preservation, the ‘unbend’ function in TPSUTIL version 
1.58
(

Rohlf 
2013
b

) was applied to all individuals (that fits a quadratic curve as a horizontal straight line, in this case, straightening was based on landmarks ‘ 
1
’, ‘*’ and ‘ 
11
’). Shape information was extracted by Procrustes superimposition (to standardise for specimen size, position and orientation) with MORPHOJ version 
1.05
f (

Klingenberg 
2011
). To determine the ability of body shape to discriminate between eastern and western regions based on Procrustes coordinates, covariance matrix calculations, principal component analysis (PCA), discriminant function analysis (DFA) and Procrustes 
ANOVA
were performed with MORPHOJ. While PCA provides a visual representation of differences without specifying groups, DFA tests the reliability of discrimination between groups using the 
T
-square statistic with significance assessed through a permutation test with 
10,000
runs. Procrustes 
ANOVA
was used to estimate landmarking error based on Goodall's 
F
statistic (
F
) and the associated 
P
- value was derived through comparing variation associated with coordinates generated from duplicate images.
</p>
         <p>Environmental data.
Between 

December 
2007
– 

November 
2008
and 

May 
2009
– 

May 
2010
, habitat assessments at a total of 
75
sites (
35 in
the east region and 
40 in
the west region) were undertaken, and the total length, weight and sex of each 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
individual was recorded. Total length measurements in the field (
1,850
individuals), were also included in 
ANOVA
analyses to test for morphologic differences between eastern and western populations. These sites were targeted based on historical records of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
presence, most notably those listed in 

Saddlier 
et al
. (
2010
)

. Habitat assessments included estimates of maximum water depth, velocity (‘no flow’, ‘slow’, ‘moderate’, ‘fast’), vegetation composition and density, water surface shading, substratum composition and water quality using a WTW Multi 
350
i multi-parameter meter fitted with ConOx (electrical conductivity, dissolved oxygen and water temperature) and SenTix (pH) probes, and a Merck Turbiquant 
1100
turbidity meter. From a broader hydrologic perspective, whether these sites were perennial or intermittently dry is also likely to be important, but could not be reliably assessed for all sites based on short term surveys. Seventeen sites in the east region and 
11
sites in the west region were assessed during both the 
2007–2008
surveys and 
2009–2010
surveys and data included in habitat summaries for both surveys at those sites. Site location coordinates and elevation (m) were also recorded using a Garmin GPS 
45
unit.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>Morphometric and meristic differences.
Meristic and morphometric data from eastern and western regions are summarized in 

Tables 
2–3
and 

. For comparison, data for 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
from 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg (
1981
)

are also presented in 

Tables 
4–5
. Repeatability assessments indicated a high level of repeatability for most morphometric characters i.e.&gt;0.800. The exceptions were SnL (
0.790
), LJL (
0.736
), PecPel (
0.714
), LAB (
0.681
) and HL (
0.681
); they were therefore removed from further analyses (but used in species descriptions).
</p>
         <p>
Total length data collected in the field at various times of the year between 
2007–2010
indicated that adult fish from the western region are significantly smaller than those from the eastern region (
ANOVA
, females 
F
= 
151
, df = 
1
, 
P
-value &lt;
0.001
; males 
F
= 
201.7
, df = 
1
, 
P
-value &lt;
0.001
; 

). Pairwise comparisons between size-adjusted quantitative data indicated that characters HD and 
HW
(
r
= 
0.78 in
females), and HD and GW (
r
= 
0.72 in
males and 
0.75 in
females) were highly correlated. Accordingly HD was removed from further analyses, as were GRL and GRU, which were highly correlated with GRT (GRL 
r
s = 
0.88 in
eastern populations and 
0.78 in
western populations, GRU 
r
s = 
0.74 in
eastern populations).
</p>
         <p>
When females were analysed separately, there were significant differences (
P
-values all &lt;
0.001
) between eastern and western regions for the following morphometric characters after size adjustment: GW, 
DF-AF
, 
LCP
, 
HW
, PrePel, UJL, PreA, PelL, KD, PoHL, and GD (Table S 
1
). When males were analysed separately, there were significant differences (
P
-values all &lt;
0.001
) between eastern and western 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
regions for 
LCP
, GW, 
HW
, PrePel, 
DF-AF
, PreA, PoHL, UJL, KD and BDV. DFA with morphometric characters classified 
96
% of individual females correctly to regions (
P
= &lt;
0.001
) and 
92
% of males (
P
= &lt;
0.001
). For morphometric characters the regions were separated most strongly by 
LCP
, GW, 
IOW
and KD (both sexes), as well as 
DF-AF
(females) and AL (males) based on forward stepwise selection (

).
</p>
         <p>
With sexes combined, significant differences between eastern and western regions were found for the meristic characters LAR, PecR and Ver (
Mann
Whitney 
P
-values of 
0.002
, 
0.001
and &lt;
0.001
, respectively). DFA with meristic data (sexes combined) classified 
93
% of fish correctly (
P
= &lt;
0.001
). The meristic character Ver most strongly separated the regions, along with ARS, 
ARB
, LAR and GRT based on forward stepwise selection. In addition, when combined, morphometric and meristic characters were found to reliably discriminate eastern and western regions.
</p>
         <p>TABLE1
.

Study sites, specimen details and number of individuals used in morphometric measurements and meristic counts. Abbreviations: AMS—Australian Museum, Sydney; NMV—Museum Victoria, Melbourne; SAMA—South Australian Museum, Adelaide. SA = South 
Australia
, SEV = South East Coast (Victoria), Tas = Tasmania, Vic = Victoria.
</p>
         <p>Region West WestState Vic VicDrainage Division SEV SEVRiver Basin Portland PortlandWaterbody Bridgewater Lakes Fitzroy RiverLatitude (S) 38° 19' 13" 38° 4' 33"Longitude (E) 141° 24' 16" 141° 25' 44"Collection date 2/08/2013 2/08/2013n
Morpho- metric 20 1
n
Meristic 20 1
Museum registration code NMV A31211-001, AMS I.46500-001 SAMA F. 14533,14534 NMV A31212-001WestVicSEVPortlandSurrey River38° 8' 48"141° 24' 55"2/08/20132020NMV A31214-001,002,003WestVicSEVGlenelgCrawford River37° 52' 13"141° 43' 45"27/06/20132020NMV A31213-001WestVicSEVPortlandDarlot Creek Tributary38° 9' 29"141° 46' 24"27/06/20132020NMV A31215-001WestVicSEVPortlandMoyne River Tributary38° 12' 48"142° 14' 24"28/06/20132020NMV A31216-001WestVicSEVBarwonGosling Creek38° 26' 17"143° 49' 3"28/06/201322NMV A31217-001WestVicSEVBarwonBarwon River East Branch38° 28' 11"143° 44' 38"17/07/20132020NMV A31218-001WestSASEVMillicentHammerhead Lagoon38° 3' 1"140° 57' 15"08/09/2008012NMV A31219-001WestSASEVMillicentPicks Swamp38° 2' 33"140° 54' 43"12/04/201006NMV A31220-001WestSASEVMillicentReedy Creek Wilmont Drain37° 12' 2"140° 10' 20"14/04/201002NMV A31221-001WestSASEVMillicentDeath Hole Outlet Drain37° 27' 50"140° 5' 55"15/04/201003NMV A31222-001WestVicSEVGlenelgBig Swamp (Grampians)37° 18' 16"142° 11' 31"01/05/1996020NMV A30675-001EastVicSEVBunyipDandenong Creek Tributary37° 57' 37"145° 14' 2"5/07/20132020NMV A31223-001EastVicSEVBunyipTuerong Creek38° 16' 23"145° 4' 16"5/07/20132020NMV A31224-001EastVicSEVBunyipKing Parrot Creek38° 10' 27"145° 52' 7"5/07/20132020NMV A31225-001EastVicSEVLatrobeMoe Main Drain38° 10' 22"146° 14' 52"29/07/20132020NMV A31226-001EastVicSEVLatrobeMorwell River38° 13' 40"146° 21' 39"29/07/20132323NMV A31227-001EastVicSEVSth GippslandMerriman Creek38° 14' 54"146° 49' 26"19/07/20132020NMV A31228-001EastVicSEVThomsonPerry River37° 55' 17"147° 16' 31"26/07/20132020NMV A31229-001EastVicSEVMitchellCobblers Creek37° 51' 17"147° 36' 19"26/07/20132020NMV A31230-001EastTasTasEast coastIcena Creek40° 58' 12"148° 9' 23"27/05/2008010NMV A31231-001East EastTas VicTas SEVRingarooma BunyipBig Waterhouse Lake Cardinia Creek (holotype &amp; paratypes)40° 53' 33" 38° 7' 52"147° 36' 53" 145° 24' 29"28/05/2008 1/07/2009 05/05/19360 09 5NMV A31232-001 NMV A97, A98, A388, A389, A390</p>
         <p>TABLE 2.
Distribution of selected counts for specimens examined of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(‘east’) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(‘west’).
</p>
         <p>CharacterHolotype /ModeMedianSDSE90 %100 %n
East (
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
)

Dorsal fin rays—branched
Allotype 444.00.720.05Range 2–4Range 0–5177Dorsal fin rays—total segmented Longest dorsal ray Anal fin rays—branched67 4 57.0 4.0 5.00.54 0.60 0.920.04 0.04 0.076–7 3–5 3–66–8 2–5 0–7182 180 176Anal fin rays—total segmented Longest anal ray Caudal rays—branched8 98 4 98.0 4.0 9.00.66 0.62 1.590.05 0.05 0.157–9 4–5 7–117–10 3–7 1–11181 178 115Caudal rays—total segmented Pectoral fin rays Pelvic fin rays13 13 513 12 513.0 12.0 5.00.40 0.67 0.130.03 0.05 0.0113–14 11–13 5–511–15 10–13 4–5179 182 182Gill rakers lower Gill rakers upper Gill rakers total1010 6 1611.0 6.0 16.00.85 0.61 1.190.07 0.05 0.099–12 5–6 14–188–13 4–7 13–20168 165 159
Vertebrae 

West (
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
)

Dorsal fin rays—branched
38 4 / 339 339.0 3.00.68 0.900.05 0.0838–40 2–536–41 1–5177 130Dorsal fin rays—total segmented Longest dorsal ray Anal fin rays—branched7 / 6 4 / 3 5 / 57 4 57.0 4.0 5.00.59 0.59 1.120.05 0.05 0.106–7 3–4 3–65–8 2–5 1–7146 145 129Anal fin rays—total segmented Longest anal ray Caudal rays—branched8 / 8 4 / 4 10 / 98 4 98.0 4.0 9.00.68 0.58 1.290.06 0.05 0.127–9 4–5 7–117–10 3–6 2–11145 141 111Caudal rays—total segmented Pectoral fin rays Pelvic fin rays13 / 13 13 / 12 5 / 513 12 513.0 12.0 5.00.30 0.70 0.160.02 0.06 0.0113–14 11–13 5–512–15 8–13 5–6144 146 146Gill rakers lower Gill rakers upper Gill rakers total11 / 10 6 / 6 17 / 1610 5 1610.0 5.5 16.00.87 0.68 1.140.08 0.06 0.119–12 5–6 14–189–12 3–7 13–19122 116 111Vertebrae36 / 373637.00.870.0736–3834–38140</p>
         <p>
Eastern and western regions could also be discriminated based on the 
12
landmarks and associated shape information, including taking into account measurement and placement error (females: Goodall’s 
F
= 
46.82
, 
P
= &lt;
0.001
and males: Goodall’s 
F
= 
39.92
, 
P
= &lt;
0.001
). In the PCA results, separation between individuals was pronounced on PC 
2
for both female and male specimens (

). Distinguishing shape features associated with PC 
2
included a more slender profile, more pronounced setback of the dorsal fin origin to anal fin and shorter prepelvic length for the eastern region compared to the western region. A DFA indicated a significant difference between eastern and western populations based on the Procrustes coordinates (females: 
T
-square = 
271.374
, 
P
= &lt;
0.001
; and males: 
T
-square = 
229.286
, 
P
= &lt;
0.001
) (

). Correct classification of eastern and western females was high at 
89.3
% and 
88.5
%, respectively. Similarly, correct classification of eastern and western males was 91.0 and 
90.3
%, respectively.
</p>
         <p>Habitat assessments.
The habitat characteristics of sites where fish in eastern and western regions were found are summarised in Appendix 
2
. Habitat can be described as low-moderate elevation (range and mean for eastern sites was 
8–111 m
and 
54 m
, and for western sites 
7–376 m
and 
104 m
), shallow (maximum water depth range and Specific measurements for 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>holotype
and allotype are also provided. Excluding total length and standard length, figures are given as percentages
</p>
         <p>TABLE 3.
Morphometric data summary for specimens examined of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(‘east’) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(‘west’) where sexes are separated.
</p>
         <p>the first character over the second character in the first column.</p>
         <p>
East Female (
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
) East Male (
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
) West Female (
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
) West Male (
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
)

Predorsal length/pre anal length 
99.1113.9
107.0 
2.5794.4125.6108.43.49102.997.6110.7104.72.7105.5
100.0 
112.5106.42.76
Number of fish measured 
84796162</p>
         <p>minmaxmeanSDminmaxmeanSDHolotypeminmaxmeanSDAllotypeminmaxmeanSDStandard length21.432.727.22.8618.128.223.62.2029.220.630.624.22.320.716.724.020.21.48Total length23.438.131.53.2820.033.527.52.5333.823.734.628.32.624.519.427.823.71.77Body depth at vent/standard length12.015.513.80.8011.815.413.60.7715.210.316.814.21.013.512.815.814.10.78Length of caudal peduncle/standard18.425.522.21.3620.326.022.91.3620.417.223.820.51.422.717.924.421.11.49Predorsal length/standard length69.080.875.21.7166.077.873.91.7475.270.585.775.62.276.271.378.174.51.59Length of dorsal fin base/standard6.510.28.30.836.810.68.70.819.16.610.98.60.98.27.211.79.00.87Maximum length of dorsal fin/standard12.817.214.60.9212.717.715.10.9116.612.617.315.11.014.412.518.815.21.30Length of anal fin base/standard length9.713.311.00.8010.214.512.10.8810.79.214.211.41.010.59.415.312.61.25Maximum length of anal fin/standard14.119.115.90.8715.219.917.20.9216.112.620.016.41.315.813.819.616.91.27Maximum length of pectoral9.614.011.80.8310.715.212.50.8411.99.815.112.51.013.59.315.912.91.39Maximum length of pelvic fin/standard8.011.39.90.698.712.210.40.6711.99.312.410.70.711.58.913.011.00.83Maximum length of caudal9.320.216.11.6710.520.216.81.6815.912.327.317.22.418.313.720.917.21.54Prepelvic length/standard length46.654.250.51.7345.953.449.71.4352.747.757.452.11.652.446.855.351.41.77Pectoral-pelvic length/standard length22.231.125.71.9019.427.223.71.6124.622.037.425.82.321.019.927.523.21.84Pelvic-anal length/standard length17.924.020.61.3416.922.818.81.1920.818.626.121.21.520.017.322.419.51.23Head length/standard length19.726.823.01.3719.726.923.81.2527.820.628.424.61.528.322.428.325.41.27Dorsal-anal fin setback/standard length0.03.92.20.880.55.73.11.020.4-2.52.80.61.11.5-2.63.92.01.03Keel length/standard length12.119.115.11.3911.217.614.51.3016.810.519.615.41.415.411.317.915.11.37Keel depth/standard length1.32.92.00.370.83.01.90.412.81.63.42.50.42.61.63.32.30.36Head width/head length61.487.570.45.3856.681.965.24.9762.260.287.872.75.656.840.380.466.66.90Head depth/head length55.983.168.14.6460.177.766.83.5961.360.290.570.05.460.258.684.768.35.24Snout length/head length13.626.920.92.0515.924.620.71.8821.013.925.421.01.920.916.024.320.31.99Post-orbital head length/head length42.962.650.53.2143.053.548.92.5253.839.559.049.93.954.542.257.648.93.73Interorbital width/head length37.258.944.84.4436.759.343.44.7938.635.552.042.53.437.130.052.640.24.20Diameter of eye/head length25.336.430.62.1028.135.932.01.7224.424.436.430.23.030.129.337.233.01.93Length of upper jaw/head length18.531.224.22.2118.328.623.72.0027.720.228.825.32.026.715.229.324.12.58Length of lower jaw/head length16.626.922.42.2115.927.422.12.1226.918.827.323.52.225.514.026.722.02.52Width of gape/head length21.338.927.83.9421.134.225.62.6226.923.338.429.63.123.220.833.626.32.96Depth of gape/head length14.927.122.42.1614.026.121.61.9822.717.430.522.52.724.314.627.921.02.77Depth of caudal peduncle/length of34.353.643.83.3036.952.943.23.7254.938.560.148.55.643.336.159.447.25.10</p>
         <p>
mean for both eastern and western sites was 
0.1
–&gt;2.0 m and 
1.1 m
), low water velocity (percentage of sites observed to have ‘no water flow’ or ‘slow water flow’ at the time of surveys of eastern and western sites was 
96.2
% and 
94.1
%, respectively), clay-silt dominated substratum (mean percentage composition of clay and silt for eastern sites was 
32.9
and 
42.7
and for western sites it was 
33.8
and 43.0) and partially shaded (range and mean for eastern sites was 
0–80
% and 
35.9
%, and for western sites was 
0–100
% and 27.0 %).
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 3.
Boxplots of morphometric ratio data for female 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(black) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(grey). Values are given as percentages of the first measurement over the second measurement listed on the x axes. Outliers that are&gt;1.5 times the interquartile range above the upper quartile or below the lower quartile are indicated by a dot. See Fig. 1 for measurement descriptions.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 4.
Boxplots of morphometric ratio data for male 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(black) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(grey). Values are given as percentages of the first measurement over the second measurement listed on the x axes. Outliers that are&gt;1.5 times the interquartile range above the upper quartile or below the lower quartile are indicated by a dot. See Fig. 1 for measurement descriptions.
</p>
         <p>
The vegetation community at sites tended to be dominated by emergent aquatic vegetation (mean percentage cover for eastern and western sites was 45.0 % and 
35.8
%, respectively) particularly species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Juncus
, 
Persecaria, Phragmites</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Triglochin</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Typha</tp:taxon-name>
. Although the cover of submerged aquatic macrophytes tended to be less than the cover of emergent aquatic macrophytes (i.e. mean percentage cover for eastern and western sites was 
12.3
% and 
17.2
%, respectively), at some sites species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Myriophyllum</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Potamogeton</tp:taxon-name>
as well as charophytes were dominant. 
<tp:taxon-name>Melaleuca</tp:taxon-name>
trees were also a dominant feature of the vegetation community at some sites (at 
16
eastern and five western sites, they comprised 
10
% or more of the total aquatic and terrestrial vegetation cover), but in most cases emergent vegetation throughout the water body provided the majority of water surface shading. The cover of coarse particulate organic matter (
CPOM
) at each site tended to be high (mean percentage cover for eastern and western sites was 
30.6
% and 25.0 %, respectively), however, large wood debris cover (pieces of wood longer than 
1 m
and a diameter&gt; 
0.1 m
) was not a dominant feature at most sites (mean percentage cover for eastern and western sites was 
3.6
% and 
1.9
%, respectively).
</p>
         <p>TABLE 4.
Comparison of selected counts for specimens examined of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(‘east’) and and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(‘west’) with McDowall and Frankenberg (1981) for 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>East West</p>
         <p>
(
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
ss

) (
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
) 
<tp:taxon-name>G. nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
Dorsal fin rays 
51</p>
         <p>- segmented 6 77451087 847210248 255n
163
1232037Anal rays 7 2116- segmented 8 1056929 333511110 4331211319125n
163
1231937Caudal rays 1011 112 82113 1411114114 127143215 1112n
163
1212035Pectoral rays 9110 61511 54203912 917914313 12234141n
163
1222228Pelvic rays 34 35 160119192643372n
163
1231937Gill rakers 12- total 13 2114 76115 2923416 48359517 42292418 12823</p>
         <p>......continued on the next page
East West
</p>
         <p>TABLE 4.
(Continued)
</p>
         <p>
(
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
ss

) (
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
) 
<tp:taxon-name>G. nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
Fish from eastern and western regions were found in a broad range of water quality conditions. Water temperatures at the time of surveys (covering conditions during both warmer and cooler months of the year) ranged from 
5.8–24.8
o C (mean 
14.8
) for eastern sites and from 
5.2–26.9
o C (mean 
16.3
) for western sites. Measurements of pH from eastern sites ranged from 5.0– 
7.8
(mean 
6.6
) and for western sites from 
5.3–9.3
(mean 
7.6
), while dissolved oxygen from eastern sites ranged from 
18.2–130
% (mean 
56.9
) and for western sites from 20.0–263.0 % (mean 
81.3
). Water clarity was also quite variable, and ranged from 
1–133
NTU (mean 
26.6
) for eastern sites and 
1–96
NTU (mean 
15.7
) for western sites. Of particular note are observed salinity differences between regions, where levels of water electrical conductivity within eastern sites ranged from 
36–3,070
µS/cm (mean 
708
) and within western sites from 
94–13,620
µS/cm (mean 
2,455
).
</p>
         <p>19 41320 11n
146
1031816Vertebrae 34135636 14337 24138 31262339 10822740 16141541 1818423194324n
159
1175166</p>
         <p>FIGURE 5.
Boxplots of total length (mm) measurements in the field of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(‘east’) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(‘west’) for a) females (east 
n
= 451, west 
n
= 478) and b) males (east 
n
= 459, west 
n
= 462). Outliers that are&gt;1.5 times the interquartile range above the upper quartile or below the lower quartile are indicated by a dot.
</p>
         <p>
TABLE 5. Comparison of morphometric data for specimens examined of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(‘east’) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(‘west’) (where sexes are combined) with McDowall and Frankenberg (1981) for 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda</tp:taxon-name>
. Figures are given as percentages of the first character over the second character in the first column.
</p>
         <p>
East (
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
) West (
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
) 
<tp:taxon-name>G. nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>minmax meanSDminmaxmeanSDminmaxmeanSDminmaxmeanSDStandard length/total length83.291.5 85.91.2878.589.085.31.4483.790.385.91.7582.287.784.91.29Body depth at vent/standard length Length of caudal peduncle/standard length Predorsal length/standard length11.8 18.4 66.015.5 13.7 26.0 22.5 80.8 74.50.79 1.40 1.8410.3 17.2 70.516.8 24.4 85.714.2 20.8 75.10.94 1.48 2.0013.5 18.7 70.518.5 23.5 75.016.5 21.0 72.61.21 1.51 1.0410.5 15.2 70.214.3 22.5 76.712.8 18.9 73.31.12 1.73 1.41Length of dorsal fin base/standard length Length of anal fin base/standard length Prepelvic length/standard length Pectoral-pelvic length/standard length6.5 9.6 45.9 19.410.6 8.5 14.5 11.6 54.2 50.1 31.1 24.80.85 0.99 1.63 2.036.6 9.2 46.8 19.911.7 15.2 57.4 37.48.8 12.0 51.8 24.50.92 1.28 1.76 2.487.1 11.1 46.1 27.48.8 13.8 52.8 31.87.9 12.6 50.6 29.50.61 0.88 1.64 1.196.7 12.3 40.5 23.29.8 16.4 52.6 33.38.3 14.6 49.1 29.40.73 1.07 3.04 2.38Pelvic-anal length/standard length Head length/standard length Width of gape/head length16.9 19.6 21.124.0 19.7 26.9 23.4 38.8 26.81.58 1.37 3.5317.3 20.6 20.826.1 28.4 38.420.3 25.0 27.91.63 1.45 3.4515.0 20.9 21.717.9 23.9 27.816.6 22.4 24.40.90 0.82 1.8515.5 17.4 20.819.7 22.8 30.017.6 19.9 25.41.08 1.16 2.83Head width/head length Head depth/head length Snout length/head length Post-orbital head length/head length56.6 55.8 13.6 42.987.5 67.9 83.1 67.5 26.9 20.8 62.6 49.75.79 4.20 1.96 2.9940.3 58.6 13.9 39.587.8 90.5 25.4 59.069.6 69.2 20.6 49.47.00 5.41 2.01 3.8653.8 55.5 22.2 44.466.7 66.7 29.6 54.259.4 60.3 26.4 48.44.32 3.15 1.93 2.7150.0 50.0 23.1 41.762.5 66.7 35.0 53.655.8 55.9 28.2 46.53.40 4.16 2.49 2.34Interorbital width/head length Diameter of eye/head length Length of upper jaw/head length Length of lower jaw/head length36.7 25.3 18.3 15.959.3 44.1 36.4 31.2 31.2 24.0 27.4 22.34.65 2.05 2.12 2.1630.0 24.4 15.2 13.952.6 37.2 29.3 27.341.3 31.6 24.7 22.84.01 2.88 2.40 2.4933.3 25.0 26.9 25.044.5 30.8 33.3 29.637.9 28.3 29.1 27.23.36 1.57 2.26 1.8734.4 26.5 29.2 26.745.8 35.0 40.0 35.040.8 30.4 32.5 30.52.67 2.41 2.22 2.18Depth of caudal peduncle/length of peduncle Predorsal length/pre anal length Maximum length of dorsal fin/basal length Maximum length of anal fin/basal length34.3 94.4 146.2 116.453.6 43.5 125.6 107.7 218.2 176.1 170.3 143.73.51 3.12 13.49 9.4536.1 97.6 124.0 115.060.1 112.5 217.4 170.447.8 105.5 173.3 139.75.40 2.86 14.81 11.4846.4 104.7 155.6 128.661.9 112.5 188.2 166.755.8 107.8 175.3 144.14.31 1.98 10.33 10.4040.7 105.0 150.0 125.054.5 111.9 200.0 154.547.3 108.3 174.5 137.24.69 1.87 13.91 7.84Pectoral fin length/pectoral-pelvic length Pelvic fin length/pelvic-anal length32.5 37.870.4 49.5 67.1 52.06.06 5.8233.2 42.471.9 73.552.4 53.86.93 6.0741.2 50.051.6 68.847.8 60.43.06 5.0339.1 50.052.9 70.045.2 60.33.58 5.66</p>
         <p>
Number of fish measured 
1631231624</p>
         <p>
- 
0.90
- 
0.90</p>
         <p>-0.95</p>
         <p>depth
- - 
1.05
1.00 
depth
- -1.00 
1.10</p>
         <p>keel
- 
1.10keel
- 
1.20</p>
         <p>
- 
1.15</p>
         <p>Maximum
- - - 
1.201.251.30Maximum
- - 
1.301.40</p>
         <p>-1.50</p>
         <p>
- 
1.35</p>
         <p>
-1.40 - 
1.60
-2.00 - 
1.80
- 
1.60
- 
1.40 -1.85
- 
1.75
- 
1.65
- 
1.55</p>
         <p>Gape width Gape width</p>
         <p>0.30
- 
0.25</p>
         <p>setback0.200.10setback
- - 
0.300.35</p>
         <p>fin
0.00 
fin
- 
0.40</p>
         <p>fin-anal
- - 
0.100.20fin-anal
- - 
0.500.45</p>
         <p>Dorsal
- - 
0.400.30Dorsal
- - - 
0.550.650.60</p>
         <p>
- 
0.50
- 
0.45
- 
0.35
- 
0.25 -0.60
- 
0.50
- 
0.40Caudal peduncle length</p>
         <p>Caudal peduncle length</p>
         <p>41</p>
         <p>40</p>
         <p>39</p>
         <p>Vertebrae3738</p>
         <p>36</p>
         <p>35</p>
         <p>34</p>
         <p>67891011Anal rays segmented</p>
         <p>FIGURE 6.
Scatterplots for characters found by discriminant function analysis (DFA) to strongly separate 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(black) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(grey): a) gape width by maximum keel depth—females, b) caudal peduncle length by dorsal fin-anal fin setback—females, c) gape width by maximum keel depth—males, d) caudal peduncle length by dorsal finanal fin setback—males e) anal rays segmented by vertebrae—sexes combined. Envelopes indicate range of values. Morphometric characters are corrected for standard length.
</p>
         <p>a b c d a Discriminant values b Discriminant values</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Frequency</p>
      <p>Frequency</p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Systematics</title>
         <p>
Material examined is included under each description listed by state, then by drainage division, river basin within each division, and alphabetically within river basins. Length measurements are provided as 
SL
(standard length) of individuals examined in each specimen lot. Except for the museum specimens from Museum Victoria, Melbourne (
NMV
), all new specimens were collected by Rhys A. Coleman (RAC) and James A. Coleman (JAC). 
Type
material for the new species has been lodged in the collection of 
NMV
, Australian Museum, Sydney (AMS), and South Australian Museum, Adelaide (
SAMA
). For 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
, meristic values in the species description are presented for the 
holotype
followed by the 
100
% range in brackets for male and female specimens combined. Morphometric values in the species description for 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
females are given as the 
holotype
followed by the 
100
% range, and given as the allotype followed by the 
100
% range for male specimens. The 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>holotype
is now substantially degraded, so reliable morphometric measurements (and some meristic counts) were not possible. Accordingly, in the revised species description for 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
, morphometric and meristic values are presented as the mean or mode respectively, followed by the 
100
% range in brackets. Where meristic characters for the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s</named-content>holotype
were counted, those values are given after the range.
</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall, 
1978
: 
116</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda
McDowall 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata
(

Shipway 
1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(

Mack 
1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt
Coleman &amp; Raadik
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
Mack, 
1936</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pucillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus flindersiensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
6</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus tasmaniensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
3</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Marengo
, Waterhouse Estate
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A review of Galaxiella pusilla (Mack) (Teleostei: Galaxiidae) in south-eastern Australia with a description of a new species</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4021.2.2</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AB049525FFCD5F3CFFCEA42E9555D911</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4021.2.2</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall
</tp:taxon-name>Gender: feminine.</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
(adapted from 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt
Coleman &amp; Raadik
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
Little 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
Tables 
2
to 3; 

to 4, 9, 
10
a, 
11
and 
12</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
Mack, 
1936</tp:taxon-name>
Dwarf 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
Tables 
2
to 3; 

to 4, 9b, 
10
b, 
11
and 
13</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall, 
1978
: 
116</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
A genus of four valid species endemic to 
Australia
, with two native to south-eastern 
Australia
(including Tasmania) and two native to south-western 
Australia
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
(modified from 

McDowall 
1978
a

and 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
). Small, stocky, horizontallystriped galaxiid fishes with dorsal fin origin usually in line with, or posterior to, anal fin origin (occasionally slightly anterior). Pelvic fins present, usually 
5–6
rays (range 
4–7
); pectoral fins inserted high laterally. Caudal fin rounded, usually with 
13–14
segmented rays (range 
11–15
); caudal peduncle flanges very strongly developed, extending forward ventrally to near anal fin base, but with very few procurrent rays. No submandibular laterosensory pores. No median ethmoid ossification. Postcleithrum present. Epipleural and epineural ribs present; no ossified interneurals. Caudal neural and haemal spines slender spikes, not laterally flattened. Vertebrae few, 
34– 43
; branchiostegals few, 
3–4
. Sexual dimorphism present in two species from south-eastern 
Australia
, including smaller size at maturity, three distinct horizontal black stripes along sides of body and bright orange-red horizontal stripe between lower two black stripes in males.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>1
. Usually 
6
pelvic fin rays (range 
5–7
); usually 
10–11
pectoral fin rays (range 
9–12
); usually 
16–19
total gill rakers (range 
16– 20
); usually 
40–42
vertebrae (range 
38–43
). (Western 
Australia
from near Margaret River in the west, Albany to the east and north of Perth)............................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda
McDowall 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
5
pelvic fin rays (range 
4–6
); usually 
11–13
pectoral fin rays (range 
10–14
); usually 
14–18
total gill rakers (range 
12– 20
) and usually 
36–40
vertebrae (range 
34–43
).............................................................. 
2</p>
            <p>2
. Usually 
14
caudal fin rays (range 
12–15
); 
8
pores in preopercular-suborbital-supramaxillary series; 
2
distinct lateral longitudinal dark stripes. (Western 
Australia
from Augusta in the west and Albany to the east and north of Perth)...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata
(

Shipway 
1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
13
caudal fin rays (range 
11–15
); 
7
pores in preopercular-suborbital-supramaxillary series; 
3
distinct lateral longitudinal dark stripes (mid stripe and particularly dorsal stripe can be poorly defined in females)............................ 
3</p>
            <p>3
. Usually 
39
vertebrae (range 
36–41
); origin of dorsal fin distinctly posterior to that of anal fin, with horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins 
1.4–3.8
% of 
SL
(females 
1.4–2.8
% (range 0.0– 
3.8
), males 
2.4–3.8
% (range 
0.52–5.67
)); caudal peduncle of moderate length, 
21.3–23.8
% of 
SL
(females 
21.3–23.1
% (range 
18.4–25.5
), males 
21.9–23.8
% (range 
20.3
– 26.0)); adult females up to 
32.7 mmSL
(mean 
27.2
) and adult males up to 
28.2 mmSL
(mean 
23.6
); ventral markings distinct, most commonly a ‘v’-shaped dark mark originating in the isthmus and extending as two parallel dotted lines (sometimes discontinuous) to the pelvic fin bases. (South-eastern 
Australia
from Bairnsdale in eastern Victoria to south-east Melbourne, including Flinders Island and north-eastern and north-western Tasmania)................. 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(

Mack 
1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
36
vertebrae (range 
34–38
); origin of dorsal fin is more or less in line with that of anal fin (particularly females), with the horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins usually 0.0– 
2.7
% of 
SL
(females 0.0– 
1.4
% (range - 
2.5–2.8
), males 
1.3–2.7
% (range - 
2.6–3.9
); caudal peduncle relatively short, usually 
19.6–21.9
% of 
SL
(females 
19.6–21.2
% (range 
17.2–23.8
), males 
20.1–21.9
% (range 
17.9–24.4
)); adult females up to 
30.6 mmSL
(mean 
24.2
) and adult males up to 24.0 mm 
SL
(mean 
20.2
); ventral markings reduced, most commonly a small number of dark blotches in the vicinity of the isthmus. (South-eastern 
Australia
from Barwon Downs in western Victoria to near the Coorong in south-eastern South 
Australia
)............................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Andrews 
1976
: 
324
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Scott 
1942
: 
55
(
partim
); 

Whitley 
1956
b

: 
39
(
partim
); 
1957
: 
6
; 
1960
: 
29
; 

Scott 
1966
: 
246
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1967
: 
227
(partim); 

Lake 
1971
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Chessman &amp; Williams 
1974
: 
168
; 

Pollard 
1980
: 
348
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Munro 
1957
: 
18
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1969
: 
185
(
partim
); 
1971
: 
94
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
: 
129
(
partim
); 

Lake 
1978
: 
26
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1978
a

: 
116
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1980
: 
55
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
: 
552
(
partim
); Backhouse 
1983
: 
6
(
partim
); 

Cadwallader &amp; Backhouse 
1983
: 
75
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1983
: 
4
(
partim
); 

Jackson &amp; Davies 
1983
: 
39
; 

Last 
et al.1983
: 
201
(
partim
); 

Merrick &amp; Schmida 
1984
: 
98
(
partim
); 

Beck 
1985
: 
12
; Allen 
1989
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Berra &amp; Allen 
1989
: 
293
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.1989
: 
179
(
partim
); 

Fulton 
1990
: 
39
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Morison 
1990
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Andrews 
1991
: 
59
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Raadik 
1991
: 
77
(
partim
); 

Pen 
et al.1993
: 
848
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1995
: 
1159
(
partim
); 

Unmack &amp; 
Paras1995
: 
398
(
partim
); 

Westbury 
1995
: 
1
(
partim
); 

Chilcott &amp; Humphries 
1996
: 
147
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Fulton 
1996
: 
70
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
1996
: 
13
; 

Koster 
1997
: 
9
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
2000
: 
1123
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
2000
: 
5
; 

Littlejohn 
2001
: 
803
; 

Raadik 
et al.2001
a

: 
9
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
et al.2001
b

: 
110
(
partim
); Unmack 
2001
: 
1060
(
partim
); 

Allen 
et al.2002
: 
111
(
partim
); 

Fields 
2002
; 
3
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
2002
: 
6
; 

Koster 
2003
: 
268
(
partim
); 

Hammer &amp; Horne 
2004
: 
2
; 

Hammer &amp; Walker 
2004
: 
85
; 

Romanowski 
2004
: 
80
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2005
: 
162
, Fig. p 
163
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.2006
: 
408
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
2006
: 
356
(
partim
); 

Threatened Species Section 
2006
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Crook 
et al.2008
: 
10
; Hammer 
2009
: ii; Hammer 
et al.2009
: 
3
; 

Galeotti 
et al.2010
: 
13
(
partim
); 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
: 
3
(
partim
); Hammer 
et al.2012
: 
63
; 

Crook &amp; Gillanders 
2013
: 
207
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
et al.2013
: 
70
(
partim
); 

King 
et al.2013
: 
165
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2013
: 
84
(
partim
), 
8
lower images p. 
86
; 

Lintermans 
2013
c

: 
286
(
partim
); 

Bachmann 
et al.2014
: 
1
; Raadik 
2014
: 
160
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
‘west region’— 

Coleman 
et al.2010
: 
1911
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
: 
1
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
: 
1821
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
II—Unmack 
2013
: 
43
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
sp.– 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
a

: 
15
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
b

: 
297
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotypeNMV
A. 
97
, 
paratypesNMV
A. 
98
(
1
), 
NMV
A. 
388–390
(
3
); 
type
locality ‘Cardinia Creek, about 
30 miles
east of Melbourne, Victoria’)— 

Massola 
1938
: 
129
; 

Whitley 
1939
: 
268
; 

Stokell 
1945
: 
126
; 

Shipway 
1953
; 
173
; 

McDowall 
1971
: 
36
; 

Dixon 
1972
: 
121
; 

McDowall 
1973
: 
193
; 

Andrews 
1976
(
partim
): 
324
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pucillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Mack, 
1936
: 
101
(misprint in legend of 

).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Scott 
1942
: 
55
; 

Stokell 
1954
: 
412
; 

Whitley 
1956
a

: 
34
; 
1956
b: 
39
(
partim
); 
1957
: 
6
; 
1960
: 
29
; 
1964
: 
35
; 

Scott 
1966
: 
246
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1966
a

: 
162
; 
1966
b: 
32
; 
1967
: 
227
(
partim
); 
1968
: 
172
; 

Lake 
1971
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Dixon 
1972
: 
121
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
119
; 

Pollard 
1980
: 
348
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Munro 
1957
: 
18
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1969
: 
185
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1971
: 
94
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1973
: 
193
; 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus flindersiensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
6</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
: 
QVM1969
: 
5
: 
35
(previously 1969.5.25a); 
paratypes
: AMS I. 
16158
-001 (
1
), 
BMNH1972.1
. 
27.1
(
1
), 
QVM1969
: 
5
: 
34
(
12
); 
type
locality: ‘Lackrana, Flinders Island, Furneaux Group, Bass Strait’);– 

Green 
1974
: 
3
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
114
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus tasmaniensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
3</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
: 
QVM1971.5
. 
48
(listed in error as 
1970
/ 
5
/ 
25
a in original description); 
paratypes
: AMS I. 
16159
-001 (
1
), 
BMNH1972.1
. 
27.2
(
1
), 
QVM1971
: 
5
: 
50
(
11
); 
type
locality ‘from a soak from a dam flowing towards the coast (northward) on 
<tp:taxon-name>Marengo
, Waterhouse Estate
</tp:taxon-name>
, Dorset, Tasmania’); 

Green 
1974
: 
3
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
114
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
— 

McDowall 
1978
b

: 
309
; 

Lake 
1978
: 
26
(
partim
); 

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
: 
129
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1980
: 
55
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
: 
552
(
partim
); Backhouse 
1983
: 
6
(
partim
); 

Cadwallader &amp; Backhouse 
1983
: 
75
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1983
: 
4
(
partim
); 

Johnson 
et al.1983
: 
50
; 

Last 
et al.1983
: 
201
(
partim
); 

Merrick &amp; Schmida 
1984
: 
98
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1986
: 
133
; Allen 
1989
: 
44
(
partim
), 
89
; 

Berra &amp; Allen 
1989
: 
293
(
partim
); 

Breen 
et al.1989
: 
1
; 

Paxton 
et al.1989
: 
179
(
partim
); 

Fulton 
1990
: 
39
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Morison 
1990
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Andrews 
1991
: 
59
(
partim
); 

Pen 
et al.1993
: 
848
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1995
: 
1159
(
partim
); 

Unmack &amp; 
Paras1995
: 
398
(
partim
); 

Westbury 
1995
: 
1
(
partim
); 

Chilcott &amp; Humphries 
1996
: 
147
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Fulton 
1996
: 
70
(
partim
); 

Koster 
1997
: 
9
(
partim
); 

Raadik &amp; Zampatti 
1998
: 
6
; 

McDowall 
1999
: 
936
; 
2000
: 
1123
(
partim
); 

Waters 
et al.2000
: 
794
; Unmack 
2001
: 
1060
(
partim
); 

Allen 
et al.2002
: 
111
(
partim
); 

Fields 
2002
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Koster 
2003
: 
268
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Waters 
2004
: 
24
; 

Romanowski 
2004
: 
80
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2005
: 
162
(
partim
); 

Hardie 
et al.2006
: 
238
; 

McDowall 
2006
: 
356
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.2006
: 
408
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
2006
: 
139
; 

Threatened Species Section 
2006
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Galeotti 
et al.2010
: 
13
(
partim
); 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Stoessel 
2010
: 
2
; 

McDowall &amp; Burridge 
2011
: 
9
; 

Burridge 
et al.2012
: 
313
; Hammer 
et al.2012
: 
62
; 

Crook &amp; Gillanders 
2013
: 
207
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
et al.2013
: 
70
(
partim
); 

King 
et al.2013
: 
165
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Kennard 
2013
: 
91
; 

Kuiter 
2013
: 
84
(
partim
), images pp 
84-85
, images top p. 
86
, images p. 
87
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
a

: 
15
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
b

: 
235
; 

Lintermans 
2013
c

: 
286
(
partim
); Raadik 
2014
: 
160
(
partim
); 

Galeotti 
et al
. 
2015
: 
189
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
‘east region’— 

Coleman 
et al.2010
: 
1911
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
: 
1
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
: 
1821
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall, 
1978
: 
116</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda
McDowall 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata
(

Shipway 
1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(

Mack 
1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt
Coleman &amp; Raadik
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
Mack, 
1936</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pucillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus flindersiensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
6</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus tasmaniensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
3</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Marengo
, Waterhouse Estate
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A review of Galaxiella pusilla (Mack) (Teleostei: Galaxiidae) in south-eastern Australia with a description of a new species</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4021.2.2</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AB049525FFCD5F3CFFCEA42E9555D911</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4021.2.2</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall
</tp:taxon-name>Gender: feminine.</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
(adapted from 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt
Coleman &amp; Raadik
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
Little 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
Tables 
2
to 3; 

to 4, 9, 
10
a, 
11
and 
12</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
Mack, 
1936</tp:taxon-name>
Dwarf 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
Tables 
2
to 3; 

to 4, 9b, 
10
b, 
11
and 
13</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall, 
1978
: 
116</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
A genus of four valid species endemic to 
Australia
, with two native to south-eastern 
Australia
(including Tasmania) and two native to south-western 
Australia
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
(modified from 

McDowall 
1978
a

and 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
). Small, stocky, horizontallystriped galaxiid fishes with dorsal fin origin usually in line with, or posterior to, anal fin origin (occasionally slightly anterior). Pelvic fins present, usually 
5–6
rays (range 
4–7
); pectoral fins inserted high laterally. Caudal fin rounded, usually with 
13–14
segmented rays (range 
11–15
); caudal peduncle flanges very strongly developed, extending forward ventrally to near anal fin base, but with very few procurrent rays. No submandibular laterosensory pores. No median ethmoid ossification. Postcleithrum present. Epipleural and epineural ribs present; no ossified interneurals. Caudal neural and haemal spines slender spikes, not laterally flattened. Vertebrae few, 
34– 43
; branchiostegals few, 
3–4
. Sexual dimorphism present in two species from south-eastern 
Australia
, including smaller size at maturity, three distinct horizontal black stripes along sides of body and bright orange-red horizontal stripe between lower two black stripes in males.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>1
. Usually 
6
pelvic fin rays (range 
5–7
); usually 
10–11
pectoral fin rays (range 
9–12
); usually 
16–19
total gill rakers (range 
16– 20
); usually 
40–42
vertebrae (range 
38–43
). (Western 
Australia
from near Margaret River in the west, Albany to the east and north of Perth)............................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda
McDowall 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
5
pelvic fin rays (range 
4–6
); usually 
11–13
pectoral fin rays (range 
10–14
); usually 
14–18
total gill rakers (range 
12– 20
) and usually 
36–40
vertebrae (range 
34–43
).............................................................. 
2</p>
            <p>2
. Usually 
14
caudal fin rays (range 
12–15
); 
8
pores in preopercular-suborbital-supramaxillary series; 
2
distinct lateral longitudinal dark stripes. (Western 
Australia
from Augusta in the west and Albany to the east and north of Perth)...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata
(

Shipway 
1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
13
caudal fin rays (range 
11–15
); 
7
pores in preopercular-suborbital-supramaxillary series; 
3
distinct lateral longitudinal dark stripes (mid stripe and particularly dorsal stripe can be poorly defined in females)............................ 
3</p>
            <p>3
. Usually 
39
vertebrae (range 
36–41
); origin of dorsal fin distinctly posterior to that of anal fin, with horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins 
1.4–3.8
% of 
SL
(females 
1.4–2.8
% (range 0.0– 
3.8
), males 
2.4–3.8
% (range 
0.52–5.67
)); caudal peduncle of moderate length, 
21.3–23.8
% of 
SL
(females 
21.3–23.1
% (range 
18.4–25.5
), males 
21.9–23.8
% (range 
20.3
– 26.0)); adult females up to 
32.7 mmSL
(mean 
27.2
) and adult males up to 
28.2 mmSL
(mean 
23.6
); ventral markings distinct, most commonly a ‘v’-shaped dark mark originating in the isthmus and extending as two parallel dotted lines (sometimes discontinuous) to the pelvic fin bases. (South-eastern 
Australia
from Bairnsdale in eastern Victoria to south-east Melbourne, including Flinders Island and north-eastern and north-western Tasmania)................. 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(

Mack 
1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
36
vertebrae (range 
34–38
); origin of dorsal fin is more or less in line with that of anal fin (particularly females), with the horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins usually 0.0– 
2.7
% of 
SL
(females 0.0– 
1.4
% (range - 
2.5–2.8
), males 
1.3–2.7
% (range - 
2.6–3.9
); caudal peduncle relatively short, usually 
19.6–21.9
% of 
SL
(females 
19.6–21.2
% (range 
17.2–23.8
), males 
20.1–21.9
% (range 
17.9–24.4
)); adult females up to 
30.6 mmSL
(mean 
24.2
) and adult males up to 24.0 mm 
SL
(mean 
20.2
); ventral markings reduced, most commonly a small number of dark blotches in the vicinity of the isthmus. (South-eastern 
Australia
from Barwon Downs in western Victoria to near the Coorong in south-eastern South 
Australia
)............................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Andrews 
1976
: 
324
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Scott 
1942
: 
55
(
partim
); 

Whitley 
1956
b

: 
39
(
partim
); 
1957
: 
6
; 
1960
: 
29
; 

Scott 
1966
: 
246
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1967
: 
227
(partim); 

Lake 
1971
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Chessman &amp; Williams 
1974
: 
168
; 

Pollard 
1980
: 
348
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Munro 
1957
: 
18
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1969
: 
185
(
partim
); 
1971
: 
94
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
: 
129
(
partim
); 

Lake 
1978
: 
26
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1978
a

: 
116
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1980
: 
55
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
: 
552
(
partim
); Backhouse 
1983
: 
6
(
partim
); 

Cadwallader &amp; Backhouse 
1983
: 
75
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1983
: 
4
(
partim
); 

Jackson &amp; Davies 
1983
: 
39
; 

Last 
et al.1983
: 
201
(
partim
); 

Merrick &amp; Schmida 
1984
: 
98
(
partim
); 

Beck 
1985
: 
12
; Allen 
1989
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Berra &amp; Allen 
1989
: 
293
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.1989
: 
179
(
partim
); 

Fulton 
1990
: 
39
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Morison 
1990
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Andrews 
1991
: 
59
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Raadik 
1991
: 
77
(
partim
); 

Pen 
et al.1993
: 
848
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1995
: 
1159
(
partim
); 

Unmack &amp; 
Paras1995
: 
398
(
partim
); 

Westbury 
1995
: 
1
(
partim
); 

Chilcott &amp; Humphries 
1996
: 
147
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Fulton 
1996
: 
70
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
1996
: 
13
; 

Koster 
1997
: 
9
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
2000
: 
1123
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
2000
: 
5
; 

Littlejohn 
2001
: 
803
; 

Raadik 
et al.2001
a

: 
9
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
et al.2001
b

: 
110
(
partim
); Unmack 
2001
: 
1060
(
partim
); 

Allen 
et al.2002
: 
111
(
partim
); 

Fields 
2002
; 
3
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
2002
: 
6
; 

Koster 
2003
: 
268
(
partim
); 

Hammer &amp; Horne 
2004
: 
2
; 

Hammer &amp; Walker 
2004
: 
85
; 

Romanowski 
2004
: 
80
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2005
: 
162
, Fig. p 
163
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.2006
: 
408
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
2006
: 
356
(
partim
); 

Threatened Species Section 
2006
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Crook 
et al.2008
: 
10
; Hammer 
2009
: ii; Hammer 
et al.2009
: 
3
; 

Galeotti 
et al.2010
: 
13
(
partim
); 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
: 
3
(
partim
); Hammer 
et al.2012
: 
63
; 

Crook &amp; Gillanders 
2013
: 
207
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
et al.2013
: 
70
(
partim
); 

King 
et al.2013
: 
165
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2013
: 
84
(
partim
), 
8
lower images p. 
86
; 

Lintermans 
2013
c

: 
286
(
partim
); 

Bachmann 
et al.2014
: 
1
; Raadik 
2014
: 
160
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
‘west region’— 

Coleman 
et al.2010
: 
1911
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
: 
1
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
: 
1821
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
II—Unmack 
2013
: 
43
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
sp.– 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
a

: 
15
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
b

: 
297
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotypeNMV
A. 
97
, 
paratypesNMV
A. 
98
(
1
), 
NMV
A. 
388–390
(
3
); 
type
locality ‘Cardinia Creek, about 
30 miles
east of Melbourne, Victoria’)— 

Massola 
1938
: 
129
; 

Whitley 
1939
: 
268
; 

Stokell 
1945
: 
126
; 

Shipway 
1953
; 
173
; 

McDowall 
1971
: 
36
; 

Dixon 
1972
: 
121
; 

McDowall 
1973
: 
193
; 

Andrews 
1976
(
partim
): 
324
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pucillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Mack, 
1936
: 
101
(misprint in legend of 

).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Scott 
1942
: 
55
; 

Stokell 
1954
: 
412
; 

Whitley 
1956
a

: 
34
; 
1956
b: 
39
(
partim
); 
1957
: 
6
; 
1960
: 
29
; 
1964
: 
35
; 

Scott 
1966
: 
246
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1966
a

: 
162
; 
1966
b: 
32
; 
1967
: 
227
(
partim
); 
1968
: 
172
; 

Lake 
1971
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Dixon 
1972
: 
121
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
119
; 

Pollard 
1980
: 
348
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Munro 
1957
: 
18
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1969
: 
185
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1971
: 
94
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1973
: 
193
; 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus flindersiensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
6</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
: 
QVM1969
: 
5
: 
35
(previously 1969.5.25a); 
paratypes
: AMS I. 
16158
-001 (
1
), 
BMNH1972.1
. 
27.1
(
1
), 
QVM1969
: 
5
: 
34
(
12
); 
type
locality: ‘Lackrana, Flinders Island, Furneaux Group, Bass Strait’);– 

Green 
1974
: 
3
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
114
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus tasmaniensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
3</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
: 
QVM1971.5
. 
48
(listed in error as 
1970
/ 
5
/ 
25
a in original description); 
paratypes
: AMS I. 
16159
-001 (
1
), 
BMNH1972.1
. 
27.2
(
1
), 
QVM1971
: 
5
: 
50
(
11
); 
type
locality ‘from a soak from a dam flowing towards the coast (northward) on 
<tp:taxon-name>Marengo
, Waterhouse Estate
</tp:taxon-name>
, Dorset, Tasmania’); 

Green 
1974
: 
3
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
114
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
— 

McDowall 
1978
b

: 
309
; 

Lake 
1978
: 
26
(
partim
); 

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
: 
129
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1980
: 
55
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
: 
552
(
partim
); Backhouse 
1983
: 
6
(
partim
); 

Cadwallader &amp; Backhouse 
1983
: 
75
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1983
: 
4
(
partim
); 

Johnson 
et al.1983
: 
50
; 

Last 
et al.1983
: 
201
(
partim
); 

Merrick &amp; Schmida 
1984
: 
98
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1986
: 
133
; Allen 
1989
: 
44
(
partim
), 
89
; 

Berra &amp; Allen 
1989
: 
293
(
partim
); 

Breen 
et al.1989
: 
1
; 

Paxton 
et al.1989
: 
179
(
partim
); 

Fulton 
1990
: 
39
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Morison 
1990
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Andrews 
1991
: 
59
(
partim
); 

Pen 
et al.1993
: 
848
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1995
: 
1159
(
partim
); 

Unmack &amp; 
Paras1995
: 
398
(
partim
); 

Westbury 
1995
: 
1
(
partim
); 

Chilcott &amp; Humphries 
1996
: 
147
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Fulton 
1996
: 
70
(
partim
); 

Koster 
1997
: 
9
(
partim
); 

Raadik &amp; Zampatti 
1998
: 
6
; 

McDowall 
1999
: 
936
; 
2000
: 
1123
(
partim
); 

Waters 
et al.2000
: 
794
; Unmack 
2001
: 
1060
(
partim
); 

Allen 
et al.2002
: 
111
(
partim
); 

Fields 
2002
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Koster 
2003
: 
268
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Waters 
2004
: 
24
; 

Romanowski 
2004
: 
80
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2005
: 
162
(
partim
); 

Hardie 
et al.2006
: 
238
; 

McDowall 
2006
: 
356
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.2006
: 
408
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
2006
: 
139
; 

Threatened Species Section 
2006
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Galeotti 
et al.2010
: 
13
(
partim
); 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Stoessel 
2010
: 
2
; 

McDowall &amp; Burridge 
2011
: 
9
; 

Burridge 
et al.2012
: 
313
; Hammer 
et al.2012
: 
62
; 

Crook &amp; Gillanders 
2013
: 
207
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
et al.2013
: 
70
(
partim
); 

King 
et al.2013
: 
165
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Kennard 
2013
: 
91
; 

Kuiter 
2013
: 
84
(
partim
), images pp 
84-85
, images top p. 
86
, images p. 
87
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
a

: 
15
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
b

: 
235
; 

Lintermans 
2013
c

: 
286
(
partim
); Raadik 
2014
: 
160
(
partim
); 

Galeotti 
et al
. 
2015
: 
189
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
‘east region’— 

Coleman 
et al.2010
: 
1911
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
: 
1
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
: 
1821
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall, 
1978
: 
116</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda
McDowall 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata
(

Shipway 
1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(

Mack 
1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt
Coleman &amp; Raadik
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
Mack, 
1936</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pucillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus flindersiensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
6</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus tasmaniensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
3</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Marengo
, Waterhouse Estate
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A review of Galaxiella pusilla (Mack) (Teleostei: Galaxiidae) in south-eastern Australia with a description of a new species</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4021.2.2</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AB049525FFCD5F3CFFCEA42E9555D911</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4021.2.2</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall
</tp:taxon-name>Gender: feminine.</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
(adapted from 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt
Coleman &amp; Raadik
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
Little 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
Tables 
2
to 3; 

to 4, 9, 
10
a, 
11
and 
12</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
Mack, 
1936</tp:taxon-name>
Dwarf 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
Tables 
2
to 3; 

to 4, 9b, 
10
b, 
11
and 
13</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall, 
1978
: 
116</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
A genus of four valid species endemic to 
Australia
, with two native to south-eastern 
Australia
(including Tasmania) and two native to south-western 
Australia
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
(modified from 

McDowall 
1978
a

and 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
). Small, stocky, horizontallystriped galaxiid fishes with dorsal fin origin usually in line with, or posterior to, anal fin origin (occasionally slightly anterior). Pelvic fins present, usually 
5–6
rays (range 
4–7
); pectoral fins inserted high laterally. Caudal fin rounded, usually with 
13–14
segmented rays (range 
11–15
); caudal peduncle flanges very strongly developed, extending forward ventrally to near anal fin base, but with very few procurrent rays. No submandibular laterosensory pores. No median ethmoid ossification. Postcleithrum present. Epipleural and epineural ribs present; no ossified interneurals. Caudal neural and haemal spines slender spikes, not laterally flattened. Vertebrae few, 
34– 43
; branchiostegals few, 
3–4
. Sexual dimorphism present in two species from south-eastern 
Australia
, including smaller size at maturity, three distinct horizontal black stripes along sides of body and bright orange-red horizontal stripe between lower two black stripes in males.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>1
. Usually 
6
pelvic fin rays (range 
5–7
); usually 
10–11
pectoral fin rays (range 
9–12
); usually 
16–19
total gill rakers (range 
16– 20
); usually 
40–42
vertebrae (range 
38–43
). (Western 
Australia
from near Margaret River in the west, Albany to the east and north of Perth)............................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda
McDowall 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
5
pelvic fin rays (range 
4–6
); usually 
11–13
pectoral fin rays (range 
10–14
); usually 
14–18
total gill rakers (range 
12– 20
) and usually 
36–40
vertebrae (range 
34–43
).............................................................. 
2</p>
            <p>2
. Usually 
14
caudal fin rays (range 
12–15
); 
8
pores in preopercular-suborbital-supramaxillary series; 
2
distinct lateral longitudinal dark stripes. (Western 
Australia
from Augusta in the west and Albany to the east and north of Perth)...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata
(

Shipway 
1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
13
caudal fin rays (range 
11–15
); 
7
pores in preopercular-suborbital-supramaxillary series; 
3
distinct lateral longitudinal dark stripes (mid stripe and particularly dorsal stripe can be poorly defined in females)............................ 
3</p>
            <p>3
. Usually 
39
vertebrae (range 
36–41
); origin of dorsal fin distinctly posterior to that of anal fin, with horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins 
1.4–3.8
% of 
SL
(females 
1.4–2.8
% (range 0.0– 
3.8
), males 
2.4–3.8
% (range 
0.52–5.67
)); caudal peduncle of moderate length, 
21.3–23.8
% of 
SL
(females 
21.3–23.1
% (range 
18.4–25.5
), males 
21.9–23.8
% (range 
20.3
– 26.0)); adult females up to 
32.7 mmSL
(mean 
27.2
) and adult males up to 
28.2 mmSL
(mean 
23.6
); ventral markings distinct, most commonly a ‘v’-shaped dark mark originating in the isthmus and extending as two parallel dotted lines (sometimes discontinuous) to the pelvic fin bases. (South-eastern 
Australia
from Bairnsdale in eastern Victoria to south-east Melbourne, including Flinders Island and north-eastern and north-western Tasmania)................. 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(

Mack 
1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
36
vertebrae (range 
34–38
); origin of dorsal fin is more or less in line with that of anal fin (particularly females), with the horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins usually 0.0– 
2.7
% of 
SL
(females 0.0– 
1.4
% (range - 
2.5–2.8
), males 
1.3–2.7
% (range - 
2.6–3.9
); caudal peduncle relatively short, usually 
19.6–21.9
% of 
SL
(females 
19.6–21.2
% (range 
17.2–23.8
), males 
20.1–21.9
% (range 
17.9–24.4
)); adult females up to 
30.6 mmSL
(mean 
24.2
) and adult males up to 24.0 mm 
SL
(mean 
20.2
); ventral markings reduced, most commonly a small number of dark blotches in the vicinity of the isthmus. (South-eastern 
Australia
from Barwon Downs in western Victoria to near the Coorong in south-eastern South 
Australia
)............................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Andrews 
1976
: 
324
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Scott 
1942
: 
55
(
partim
); 

Whitley 
1956
b

: 
39
(
partim
); 
1957
: 
6
; 
1960
: 
29
; 

Scott 
1966
: 
246
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1967
: 
227
(partim); 

Lake 
1971
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Chessman &amp; Williams 
1974
: 
168
; 

Pollard 
1980
: 
348
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Munro 
1957
: 
18
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1969
: 
185
(
partim
); 
1971
: 
94
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
: 
129
(
partim
); 

Lake 
1978
: 
26
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1978
a

: 
116
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1980
: 
55
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
: 
552
(
partim
); Backhouse 
1983
: 
6
(
partim
); 

Cadwallader &amp; Backhouse 
1983
: 
75
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1983
: 
4
(
partim
); 

Jackson &amp; Davies 
1983
: 
39
; 

Last 
et al.1983
: 
201
(
partim
); 

Merrick &amp; Schmida 
1984
: 
98
(
partim
); 

Beck 
1985
: 
12
; Allen 
1989
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Berra &amp; Allen 
1989
: 
293
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.1989
: 
179
(
partim
); 

Fulton 
1990
: 
39
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Morison 
1990
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Andrews 
1991
: 
59
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Raadik 
1991
: 
77
(
partim
); 

Pen 
et al.1993
: 
848
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1995
: 
1159
(
partim
); 

Unmack &amp; 
Paras1995
: 
398
(
partim
); 

Westbury 
1995
: 
1
(
partim
); 

Chilcott &amp; Humphries 
1996
: 
147
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Fulton 
1996
: 
70
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
1996
: 
13
; 

Koster 
1997
: 
9
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
2000
: 
1123
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
2000
: 
5
; 

Littlejohn 
2001
: 
803
; 

Raadik 
et al.2001
a

: 
9
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
et al.2001
b

: 
110
(
partim
); Unmack 
2001
: 
1060
(
partim
); 

Allen 
et al.2002
: 
111
(
partim
); 

Fields 
2002
; 
3
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
2002
: 
6
; 

Koster 
2003
: 
268
(
partim
); 

Hammer &amp; Horne 
2004
: 
2
; 

Hammer &amp; Walker 
2004
: 
85
; 

Romanowski 
2004
: 
80
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2005
: 
162
, Fig. p 
163
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.2006
: 
408
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
2006
: 
356
(
partim
); 

Threatened Species Section 
2006
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Crook 
et al.2008
: 
10
; Hammer 
2009
: ii; Hammer 
et al.2009
: 
3
; 

Galeotti 
et al.2010
: 
13
(
partim
); 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
: 
3
(
partim
); Hammer 
et al.2012
: 
63
; 

Crook &amp; Gillanders 
2013
: 
207
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
et al.2013
: 
70
(
partim
); 

King 
et al.2013
: 
165
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2013
: 
84
(
partim
), 
8
lower images p. 
86
; 

Lintermans 
2013
c

: 
286
(
partim
); 

Bachmann 
et al.2014
: 
1
; Raadik 
2014
: 
160
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
‘west region’— 

Coleman 
et al.2010
: 
1911
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
: 
1
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
: 
1821
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
II—Unmack 
2013
: 
43
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
sp.– 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
a

: 
15
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
b

: 
297
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotypeNMV
A. 
97
, 
paratypesNMV
A. 
98
(
1
), 
NMV
A. 
388–390
(
3
); 
type
locality ‘Cardinia Creek, about 
30 miles
east of Melbourne, Victoria’)— 

Massola 
1938
: 
129
; 

Whitley 
1939
: 
268
; 

Stokell 
1945
: 
126
; 

Shipway 
1953
; 
173
; 

McDowall 
1971
: 
36
; 

Dixon 
1972
: 
121
; 

McDowall 
1973
: 
193
; 

Andrews 
1976
(
partim
): 
324
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pucillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Mack, 
1936
: 
101
(misprint in legend of 

).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Scott 
1942
: 
55
; 

Stokell 
1954
: 
412
; 

Whitley 
1956
a

: 
34
; 
1956
b: 
39
(
partim
); 
1957
: 
6
; 
1960
: 
29
; 
1964
: 
35
; 

Scott 
1966
: 
246
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1966
a

: 
162
; 
1966
b: 
32
; 
1967
: 
227
(
partim
); 
1968
: 
172
; 

Lake 
1971
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Dixon 
1972
: 
121
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
119
; 

Pollard 
1980
: 
348
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Munro 
1957
: 
18
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1969
: 
185
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1971
: 
94
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1973
: 
193
; 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus flindersiensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
6</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
: 
QVM1969
: 
5
: 
35
(previously 1969.5.25a); 
paratypes
: AMS I. 
16158
-001 (
1
), 
BMNH1972.1
. 
27.1
(
1
), 
QVM1969
: 
5
: 
34
(
12
); 
type
locality: ‘Lackrana, Flinders Island, Furneaux Group, Bass Strait’);– 

Green 
1974
: 
3
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
114
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus tasmaniensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
3</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
: 
QVM1971.5
. 
48
(listed in error as 
1970
/ 
5
/ 
25
a in original description); 
paratypes
: AMS I. 
16159
-001 (
1
), 
BMNH1972.1
. 
27.2
(
1
), 
QVM1971
: 
5
: 
50
(
11
); 
type
locality ‘from a soak from a dam flowing towards the coast (northward) on 
<tp:taxon-name>Marengo
, Waterhouse Estate
</tp:taxon-name>
, Dorset, Tasmania’); 

Green 
1974
: 
3
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
114
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
— 

McDowall 
1978
b

: 
309
; 

Lake 
1978
: 
26
(
partim
); 

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
: 
129
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1980
: 
55
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
: 
552
(
partim
); Backhouse 
1983
: 
6
(
partim
); 

Cadwallader &amp; Backhouse 
1983
: 
75
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1983
: 
4
(
partim
); 

Johnson 
et al.1983
: 
50
; 

Last 
et al.1983
: 
201
(
partim
); 

Merrick &amp; Schmida 
1984
: 
98
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1986
: 
133
; Allen 
1989
: 
44
(
partim
), 
89
; 

Berra &amp; Allen 
1989
: 
293
(
partim
); 

Breen 
et al.1989
: 
1
; 

Paxton 
et al.1989
: 
179
(
partim
); 

Fulton 
1990
: 
39
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Morison 
1990
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Andrews 
1991
: 
59
(
partim
); 

Pen 
et al.1993
: 
848
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1995
: 
1159
(
partim
); 

Unmack &amp; 
Paras1995
: 
398
(
partim
); 

Westbury 
1995
: 
1
(
partim
); 

Chilcott &amp; Humphries 
1996
: 
147
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Fulton 
1996
: 
70
(
partim
); 

Koster 
1997
: 
9
(
partim
); 

Raadik &amp; Zampatti 
1998
: 
6
; 

McDowall 
1999
: 
936
; 
2000
: 
1123
(
partim
); 

Waters 
et al.2000
: 
794
; Unmack 
2001
: 
1060
(
partim
); 

Allen 
et al.2002
: 
111
(
partim
); 

Fields 
2002
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Koster 
2003
: 
268
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Waters 
2004
: 
24
; 

Romanowski 
2004
: 
80
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2005
: 
162
(
partim
); 

Hardie 
et al.2006
: 
238
; 

McDowall 
2006
: 
356
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.2006
: 
408
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
2006
: 
139
; 

Threatened Species Section 
2006
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Galeotti 
et al.2010
: 
13
(
partim
); 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Stoessel 
2010
: 
2
; 

McDowall &amp; Burridge 
2011
: 
9
; 

Burridge 
et al.2012
: 
313
; Hammer 
et al.2012
: 
62
; 

Crook &amp; Gillanders 
2013
: 
207
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
et al.2013
: 
70
(
partim
); 

King 
et al.2013
: 
165
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Kennard 
2013
: 
91
; 

Kuiter 
2013
: 
84
(
partim
), images pp 
84-85
, images top p. 
86
, images p. 
87
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
a

: 
15
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
b

: 
235
; 

Lintermans 
2013
c

: 
286
(
partim
); Raadik 
2014
: 
160
(
partim
); 

Galeotti 
et al
. 
2015
: 
189
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
‘east region’— 

Coleman 
et al.2010
: 
1911
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
: 
1
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
: 
1821
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Material examined.</title>
         <p>Holotype
.
NMV
A. 
31214
-001, 
29.2 mmSL
, female, Surrey River, Wrights Swamp Road, Cobboboonee, Victoria, 
38
° 
8
' 
48
"S
141
° 
24
' 
55
"E

, R.A. Coleman, J.A. Coleman 
2
August 
2013
.
</p>
         <p>Paratypes
. Victoria:
NMV
A. 
31214
-002, 
20.7 mmSL
, male, collected with 
holotype
(Allotype); 
NMV
A. 
31218
-001 (
20
), 
19.8–25.8 mmSL
, Barwon River East Branch, Wickhams Road, Barwon Downs, 
38
° 
28
' 
11
"S
143
° 
44
' 
38
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
17
July 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31217
-001 (
2
), 24.0– 
26.1 mmSL
, Gosling Creek, Division Road, Murroon, 
38
° 
26
' 
17
"S
143
° 
49
' 
3
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
28
June 
2013
; AMS I. 
46500
-001 (
2
) female 
21.5 mmSL
and male 
19.6 mmSL
, 
NMV
A. 
31211
-001 (
16
), 
17.8–23.4 mmSL
, 
SAMA
F. 
14533
(
1
), female, 22.0 mm 
SL
, 
SAMA
F. 
14534
(
1
), male, 
19.2 mmSL
, Bridgewater Lakes, Bridgwater Lakes Road, Tarragal, 
38
° 
19
' 
13
"S
141
° 
24
' 
16
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
2
August 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31215
-001 (
20
), 
16.7–25.9 mmSL
, Darlot Creek tributary, Etterick Tyrendarra Road, Tyrendarra, 
38
° 
9
' 
29
"S
141
° 
46
' 
24
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
27
June 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31212
-001 (
1
), 
18.9 mmSL
, Fitzroy River, T and W Road, Cobboboonee, 
38
° 
4
' 
33
"S
141
° 
25
' 
44
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
2
August 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31216
-001 (
20
), 17.0– 
29.5 mmSL
, Moyne River tributary, Woolsthorpe Heywood Road, Moyne, 
38
° 
12
' 
48
"S
142
° 
14
' 
24
"E

, RAC, JAC 
28
June 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31214
-003 (
18
), 
16.9–30.5 mmSL
, collected with 
holotype
, 
NMV
A 
31213
-001 (
20
), 
18.9-27.5 mmSL
, Crawford River, Condah Coleraine Road, Branxholme, 
37
° 
52
' 
13
"S
141
° 
43
' 
45
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
27
June 
2013
.
</p>
         <p>
Non-type material. South 
Australia
:
NMV
A 
31222
-001 (
3
) not measured, Death Hole Outlet Drain, Burkes Island, Homestead Road, Beachport, 
37
° 
27
' 
50
"S
140
° 
5
' 
55
"E

, RAC, E. Furlan, 
15
April 
2010
; 
NMV
A 
31219
- 0 0 
1
(
12
) not measured, Hammerhead Lagoon, Piccaninne Ponds Road, Donovans, 
38
° 
3
' 
1
"S
140
° 
57
' 
15
"E

, RAC, E. Tsyrlin, 
8
September 
2008
; 
NMV
A 
31220
-001 (
6
) not measured, Picks Swamp, ACI Road, Donovans, 
38
° 
2
' 
33
"S
140
° 
54
' 
43
"E

, RAC, E. Furlan, 
12
April 
2010
; 
NMV
A 
31221
-001 (
2
) not measured, Reedy Creek Wilmont Drain, Konetta Road, Greenways, 
37
° 
12
' 
2
"S
140
° 
10
' 
20
"E

, RAC, E. Furlan, 
14
April 
2010
; 
Victoria:NMV
A 
30675
-001 (
20
) not measured, Big Swamp, Henty Highway, Grampians National Park, 
37
° 
18
' 
16
"S
142
° 
11
' 
31
"E

, T.A. Raadik, 
1
May 
1996
.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 9.
a) line drawing of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
holotype, NMV A.31214-001, female, Surrey River, Wrights Swamp Road, Cobboboonee, Vic., 29.2 mm SL (R. Plant); scale bar = 5 mm; b) line drawing of typical anterio-ventral surface markings on 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(left) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(right) (R. Plant).
</p>
         <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
is distinguished from other 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
by: caudal fin rays usually 
13
(
12– 15
), anal fin rays usually 
8
(
7–10
), pectoral fin rays usually 
12
(
8–13
), usually 
36
(
34–38
) vertebrae, 
7
laterosensory pores in the preopercular-supramaxillary series. Adults very small (usually females 
20.6–30.6 mmSL
; males 
16.7
–24.0 mm 
SL
); short caudal peduncle usually 
19.6–21.9
% 
SL
(females 
17.2–23.8
% 
SL
; males 
17.9– 24.4
% 
SL
); origin of dorsal fin more or less in line with anal fin (particularly females) with horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins usually 0.0– 
2.7
% 
SL
(females - 
2.5–2.8
; males - 
2.6–3.9
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
adults with three longitudinal black stripes (easier to discern in adult males) and reduced markings on ventral surface (typically two to three black blotches at isthmus) (

b).
</p>
         <p>Description.
As for genus, except below. Based on 
123
adult

specimens, 
16.7–30.6 mmSL
, and 
43
additional non-type specimens for meristic counts. See 

Table 
2
for summary of meristic variation and 

Table 
4
for frequencies of meristic values. Segmented dorsal fin rays 
7
(
5–8
), of these 
4
(
1–5
) branched; 
4
th dorsal fin ray longest (
2
nd– 
5
th); segmented anal fin rays 
8
(
7–10
), of these 
5
(
1–7
) branched; 
4
th anal fin ray longest (
3
rd– 
6
th); caudal fin rays 
13
(
12– 15
), of these 
10
(
5–11
, excluding single outlier of 
2
) branched; segmented pectoral fin rays 
13
(
8–13
); pelvic fin rays 
5
(
5–6
); total gill raker total count on first gill arch (lower limb and upper limb) 
17
(
13–19
), lower limb 
11
(
9– 12
) and upper limb 
6
(
3–7
); vertebrae 
36
(
34–38
).
</p>
         <p>
See 

and 

Tables 
3
and 
5
for summary of morphometric characters. Small, moderately elongate, mostly fusiform body with greatest depth usually in mid abdominal region (between pectoral and pelvic fins). Body depth at vent 
15.2
(
10.3–16.8
) % 
SL
females and 
13.5
(
12.8–15.8
) % 
SL
males, tapering to moderately short caudal peduncle 
20.4
(
17.2–23.8
) % 
SL
females and 
22.7
(
17.9–24.4
) % 
SL
males. Caudal peduncle deep 
54.9
(
38.5–60.1
) % 
LCP
females and 
43.3
(
36.1–59.4
) % 
LCP
males. Dorsal and ventral trunk profiles moderately arched, flattened around head, narrowing posterior to vent.
</p>
         <p>
Head short (females 
27.8
(
20.6–28.4
) % 
SL
; males 
28.3
(
22.4–28.3
) % 
SL
), broad (females 
62.2
(
60.2–87.8
) %HL; males 
56.8
(
40.3–80.4
) %HL) and similar depth (females 
61.3
(
60.2–90.5
) %HL; males 
60.2
(
58.6–84.7
) %HL), snout round and short (females 21.0 (
13.9–25.4
) %HL; males 
20.9
(16.0– 
24.3
) %HL). Eye diameter large (females 
24.4
(
24.4–36.4
) %HL; males 
30.1
(
29.3–37.2
) %HL), positioned high in head, typically upper margin just below, or level with, dorsal head profile; interorbital generally broad (females 
38.6
(
35.5
–52.0) %HL; males 
37.1
(30.0– 
52.6
) %HL) and flat. Mouth small, extending posterio-ventrally from near tip of snout to almost vertically at anterior margin of eye. Lower jaw slightly shorter (females 
26.9
(
18.8–27.3
) %HL; males 
25.5
(14.0– 
26.7
) %HL) than upper jaw (females 
27.7
(
20.2–28.8
) %HL; males 
26.7
(
15.2–29.3
) %HL), gape width moderate (females 
26.9
(
23.3–38.4
) %HL; males 
23.2
(
20.8–33.6
) %HL) and gape depth slightly shorter in comparison (females 
22.7
(
17.4–30.5
) %HL; males 
24.3
(
14.6–27.9
) %HL). Jaws without enlarged lateral canines; mesopterygoidal teeth few but strong; lingual teeth well developed. Gill rakers generally long, slender and pointed, sometimes rounded. Seven pores in preopercular-supramaxillary series with bow-shape cluster of three closest to jaw; submandibular sensory pores absent.
</p>
         <p>
Fins small, lacking spines, membranous and predominantly rounded. Length of anal fin base (females 
10.7
(
9.2–14.2
) % 
SL
; males 
10.5
(
9.4–15.3
) % 
SL
) greater than dorsal fin base (females 
9.1
(
6.6–10.9
) % 
SL
; males 
8.2
(
7.2–11.7
) % 
SL
) and anal fin of similar length (females 
16.1
(
12.6
–20.0) % 
SL
; males 
15.8
(
13.8–19.6
)% 
SL
) to dorsal fin (females 
16.6
(
12.6–17.3
) % 
SL
; males 
14.4
(
12.5–18.8
) % 
SL
). Dorsal fin and anal fin origins usually almost in line, with fin origin setback more or less zero (females 
0.4
(- 
2.5–2.8
) % 
SL
; males 
1.5
(– 
2.6–3.9
) % 
SL
), though occasionally dorsal fin origin marginally anterior to anal fin origin. Pelvic fin to anal fin distance 
20.8
(
18.6–26.1
) % 
SL
females and 20.0 (
17.3–22.4
) % 
SL
males, pelvic fins narrow and shorter (females 
11.9
(
9.3– 12.4
) % 
SL
; males 
11.5
(
8.9
–13.0) % 
SL
) than dorsal and anal fins, positioned mid-way along ventral surface of body. Pectoral fins with broad, fleshy base, inserted high on lateral surface of body, approximately same level as tip of snout, round to paddle-shaped, and similar length (females 
11.9
(
9.8–15.1
) % 
SL
; males 
13.5
(
9.3–15.9
) % 
SL
) or slightly larger than, pelvic fins. Caudal fin rounded, moderate length (females 
15.9
(
12.3–27.3
) % 
SL
; males 
18.3
(
13.7–20.9
) % 
SL
), generally more broad than long, and vertical width of expanded rays greater than depth of caudal peduncle. Caudal peduncle flanges deep and distinct, extending forward almost to posterior end of anal fin base. Well-developed fleshy keel present (females 
16.8
(
10.5–19.6
) % 
SL
; males 
15.4
(
11.3–17.9
) % 
SL
), extending mid-ventrally from between pelvic fins to vent, maximum depth 
2.8
(
1.6–3.4
) % 
SL
females and 
2.6
(
1.6–3.3
) % 
SL
males.
</p>
         <p>Size.
The smallest species in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
, with females recorded to 
42 mm
TL; (commonly to 
27–32 mm
TL) and males recorded to 
34 mm
TL (commonly to 
25–28 mm
TL). Also the smallest species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiidae</tp:taxon-name>
(e.g. 

McDowall &amp; Waters 
2004
).
</p>
         <p>Colour in life.
The dorsal and upper sides of body are generally pale olive-brown (darker towards dorsal margin) and the ventral and lower sides silvery-white (

). The gills are visible as a large red-pink patch through gill covers on the sides of the head. Adults possess three continuous to semi-continuous, horizontal black stripes along the lateral surfaces of the trunk from near the eye to the origin of the caudal fin (tending to be more distinct and complete in males). Stripes are generally fainter and stippled in females, with the upper two stripes difficult to discern (particularly the dorsal stripe). Adult males possess a bright orange-red stripe between the lower two black stripes, which in females is generally thin and bright silver, gold, mauve or on rare occasions, pale orange. The eyes are mostly silvery-gold, with patches of bright orange in line with the coloured body stripe (of the same colour in males). In adults, the ventral surface has few markings except two to three black blotches at the isthmus and rarely with faint, discontinuous dots between the ventral surface of head and the pelvic fin bases (

b). Juveniles lack the distinct striped patterns and colour of adults, are predominantly pale olive dorsally to beige on the upper sides and silvery-white ventrally. The eyes of juveniles are silvery-gold, with a crenulated stripe of similar colour along the sides.
</p>
         <p>Colour of preserved material.
The body is creamy beige with darker stippling along the dorsal surface (particularly around head) and paler on the lower sides and ventral surface. Adults have three continuous to semicontinuous, horizontal black stripes along the lateral surfaces of the trunk from near the eye to the origin of the caudal fin and tending to be more distinct and complete in males. The stripes are generally fainter and stippled in females, with the upper two stripes difficult to discern (particularly the dorsal stripe). Coloured stripes are absent and the eyes are black. The ventral surface of adults has few markings, except two to three black blotches at the isthmus and rarely with faint, discontinuous dots between the ventral surface of the head and the pelvic fin bases.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 10.
a) 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
male (upper) and female (lower) from Narrow Neck Drain, Hatherleigh, South Australia (Photo by M. Hammer), b) 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
male (lower) and female (upper) from Tuerong Creek, Moorooduc, Victoria (Photo by R. Kuiter).
</p>
         <p>Sexual Dimorphism.
Sexes exhibit dimorphism in colouration and morphological characters which, along with that expressed in 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sensu stricto</named-content>
(s.s.), is a unique feature within 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
and the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiidae</tp:taxon-name>
. Whilst differences in many of the morphological characters measured were evident, key differences between the sexes of adult fish are: females are longer and deeper bodied than males, and the genital papillus in males is low and projects posteriorly slightly further than the vent. The female genital papillus is a distinct fleshy mound. Colour differences between the sexes of adult fish are: males have a bright orange-red lateral body stripe (generally thin and bright silver, gold or mauve in females) and three distinct black lateral body stripes, which are more difficult to discern in females, particularly the most dorsal stripe (

).
</p>
         <p>Etymology.
Pronounced “Too-urt Koo-urt” (or Tu-urt Ku-urt), from the Australian indigenous language groups Tjapwurrung, Korn Kopan noot, and Peekwurrung, meaning ‘little fish in freshwater’. Recommended standard name as ‘Little galaxias’ based on it being the smallest species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiidae</tp:taxon-name>
(e.g. 

McDowall &amp;Waters 
2004
) and consistency with ‘little’ in the indigenous language meaning.
</p>
         <p>Genetics.
Microsatellite and mtDNA analysis of this species can be found in 

Coleman 
et al.
(
2010
; 
2013
; taxon ‘west region’). Allozyme and mtDNA data are presented in 

Unmack 
et al.
(
2012
)

.
</p>
         <p>Distribution.
Known from coastal south-eastern mainland 
Australia
, from the upper Barwon River system near Barwon Downs, Victoria, west to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Cortina Lakes</tp:taxon-name>
, near the Coorong, South 
Australia
(

). Its current known range does not overlap that of its sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
         </p>
         <p>Habitat.
Generally found in swamps, wetlands, shallow lakes, billabongs, small creeks and artificial earthen drains (

) at low elevation (mean 
100 m
above sea level, typically 
22–176 m
above sea level). Habitats are mostly shallow (mean maximum depth 
1.1 m
, typically 
0.5
–2.0 m), with still to low water velocities (or often backwaters in faster flowing conditions) and partial shading (mean 
27
%, typically 
5–50
% surface cover). The substrate tends to be dominated by fine clay (mean 
34
%, typically 
0–50
%) and silt (mean 
43
%, typically 
25–50
%) and occasionally coarser (particularly sand) with deposits of coarse particulate organic matter (mean 
25
%, typically 
0–40
% cover). Frequently captured where the vegetation cover is dense and consists primarily of emergent (mean 
36
%, typically 
15–50
% cover) and submerged (mean 
17
%, typically 
0–23
% cover) aquatic species. Measurements of water quality at the time of collection suggest that 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
can withstand a broad range of conditions, being recorded at water temperatures of 
5.2–26.9
o C, dissolved oxygen levels of 
20–263
% saturation, pH of 
5.3–9.3
, water electrical conductivity of 
94–13,620
µS/cm and turbidity of 
1–96
NTU.
</p>
         <p>Conservation status.
Formerly part of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
, which is currently listed as ‘vulnerable’ nationally (

Environment Protection and Biodiversity Conservation (
EPBC
) 

Act 
1999
) and internationally (
IUCN
Red List of Threatened Species, 

Wager 
1996
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
is currently considered threatened in South 
Australia
where it is also listed as ‘vulnerable’ (Hammer 
et al.2009
). In the state of Victoria, 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
, (listed as ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
sp.’) is considered threatened and has been categorised as ‘vulnerable’ (

DSE 
2013
). According to the 
IUCN
criteria (
IUCN2012
), from data presented here it should be considered nationally ‘endangered’ based on the following criteria: B 
2
a, b(i,ii,iii,iv), c(ii,iii), that relate to an area of occupancy &lt;
500km2
, severe population fragmentation, continuing decline in the extent of occurrence, area of occupancy, area/ extent and/or quality of habitat, number of locations or subpopulations, and extreme fluctuation in the area of occupancy and number of locations or subpopulations. Habitat loss and fragmentation, and negative interactions with invasive fishes (particularly the poecilid 
<tp:taxon-name>Gambusia holbrooki</tp:taxon-name>
), are considered major threats to its long-term survival (

Koster 
2003
; 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
; Coleman 
et al.
in review).
</p>
         <p>General biology.
Non-migratory, freshwater species, that is occasionally found in inland slightly saline waters. The spawning period is possibly during late autumn to spring, but may be variable (

Beck 
1985
; 

Romanowski 
2004
) and although some individuals may overlap breeding seasons, are thought to be predominantly a semelparous species, living one year and dying soon after spawning (

Romanowski 
2004
). Where present, it can occur in high densities, although there may be substantial seasonal and inter-annual variability in population abundances (

Romanowski 
2004
; Coleman 
et al.
in review

). It has developed adaptations to surviving extended seasonal periods of habitat drying, aided via a capacity for air-breathing and the use of moisture retaining habitat features such as vegetation cover and crayfish burrows (

Beck 
1985
; 

Romanowski 
2004
; Coleman 
et al.
in review). It is likely to exist within a metapopulation structure or a ‘population of sub-populations’, where persistence of the population as a whole is facilitated by multiple interconnected sub-populations (
viz.
Levins 
1969
; 

Hanski 
1998
). Natural wetting and drying cycles typical of their habitats (and other environmental factors) can lead to large fluctuations in inter-annual population densities, emphasising the importance of habitat inter-connectivity across the landscape to maintain a balance between local population extinctions and recolonization (Coleman 
et al.
in review). Wetting and drying cycles are also likely to be important for enhancing food resources and reducing competition and predation pressures (Coleman 
et al.
in review).
</p>
         <p>
It is often collected with native fish species, particularly 
<tp:taxon-name>Nannoperca australis</tp:taxon-name>
(
65
% frequency), 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias maculatus</tp:taxon-name>
(
12
% frequency), and burrowing crayfish (e.g. 
<tp:taxon-name>Engaeus</tp:taxon-name>
spp., 
<tp:taxon-name>Geocharax</tp:taxon-name>
spp.) (
18
% frequency). Also often found with the alien fish species 
<tp:taxon-name>Gambusia holbrooki</tp:taxon-name>
(
29
% frequency). Aquatic macroinvertebrates found to occur with 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
include 
<tp:taxon-name>Paratya australiensis</tp:taxon-name>
(
24
% frequency), 
<tp:taxon-name>Notonectidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
35
% frequency), Amphipoda (
20
% frequency), 
<tp:taxon-name>Belostomatidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
18
% frequency), 
<tp:taxon-name>Corixidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
24
% frequency), Coleoptera (
18
% frequency), Odonata (
37
% frequency), Gastropoda (
26
% frequency). It is sometimes found with clusters of trematode cysts within the head region that can cause head enlargement (

Coleman 
2014
).
</p>
         <p>Remarks.<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
primarily by a combination of the following characters: less vertebrae; slightly shorter caudal peduncle; less pronounced dorsal fin-anal fin setback, especially in females; adults are smaller. In preserved material, reduced markings on the ventral surface of adults, typically two to three black blotches at the isthmus (

b), also differentiate it from 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
adults. The shorter dorsal fin-anal fin setback in 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
distinguishes it from 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda</tp:taxon-name>
as well. Additional differences to 
<tp:taxon-name>G. nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
are: less caudal and anal fin rays; one more longitudinal black lateral body stripe; and, less laterosensory pores in the preopercular-supramaxillary series. Also differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
by being shorter overall, having less caudal and anal fin rays, more pectoral fin rays, less vertebrae, and possessing longitudinal dark lateral body stripes in adults.
</p>
         <p>
Other, smaller, differences between 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
have been noted, which may be of secondary taxonomic importance: 
1
) caudal peduncle flanges often appear to only extend to near the posterior end of the anal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
, but frequently extend to near the posterior end of both the anal fin base and dorsal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
; 
2
) subtle difference in the positioning of the eye may also be present, whereby the upper margin of the eye appears to be more consistently just below, or level with, the dorsal head profile in 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
, while it is frequently level with, or extends slightly above, the dorsal head profile in 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
; and, 
3
) during laboratory experiments, when single populations of live fish were held in aquaria at the same time, 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
individuals were distinctly more pale and yellowish than 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
—it is unknown how consistent this last potentially distinguishing feature is across populations and environmental conditions.
</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall, 
1978
: 
116</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda
McDowall 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata
(

Shipway 
1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(

Mack 
1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt
Coleman &amp; Raadik
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
Mack, 
1936</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pucillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus flindersiensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
6</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus tasmaniensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
3</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Marengo
, Waterhouse Estate
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A review of Galaxiella pusilla (Mack) (Teleostei: Galaxiidae) in south-eastern Australia with a description of a new species</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4021.2.2</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AB049525FFCD5F3CFFCEA42E9555D911</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4021.2.2</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall
</tp:taxon-name>Gender: feminine.</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
(adapted from 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt
Coleman &amp; Raadik
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-status>new species</tp:taxon-status>
Little 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
Tables 
2
to 3; 

to 4, 9, 
10
a, 
11
and 
12</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
Mack, 
1936</tp:taxon-name>
Dwarf 
<tp:taxon-name>galaxias</tp:taxon-name>
Tables 
2
to 3; 

to 4, 9b, 
10
b, 
11
and 
13</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella
McDowall, 
1978
: 
116</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
A genus of four valid species endemic to 
Australia
, with two native to south-eastern 
Australia
(including Tasmania) and two native to south-western 
Australia
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
(modified from 

McDowall 
1978
a

and 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
). Small, stocky, horizontallystriped galaxiid fishes with dorsal fin origin usually in line with, or posterior to, anal fin origin (occasionally slightly anterior). Pelvic fins present, usually 
5–6
rays (range 
4–7
); pectoral fins inserted high laterally. Caudal fin rounded, usually with 
13–14
segmented rays (range 
11–15
); caudal peduncle flanges very strongly developed, extending forward ventrally to near anal fin base, but with very few procurrent rays. No submandibular laterosensory pores. No median ethmoid ossification. Postcleithrum present. Epipleural and epineural ribs present; no ossified interneurals. Caudal neural and haemal spines slender spikes, not laterally flattened. Vertebrae few, 
34– 43
; branchiostegals few, 
3–4
. Sexual dimorphism present in two species from south-eastern 
Australia
, including smaller size at maturity, three distinct horizontal black stripes along sides of body and bright orange-red horizontal stripe between lower two black stripes in males.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>1
. Usually 
6
pelvic fin rays (range 
5–7
); usually 
10–11
pectoral fin rays (range 
9–12
); usually 
16–19
total gill rakers (range 
16– 20
); usually 
40–42
vertebrae (range 
38–43
). (Western 
Australia
from near Margaret River in the west, Albany to the east and north of Perth)............................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda
McDowall 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
5
pelvic fin rays (range 
4–6
); usually 
11–13
pectoral fin rays (range 
10–14
); usually 
14–18
total gill rakers (range 
12– 20
) and usually 
36–40
vertebrae (range 
34–43
).............................................................. 
2</p>
            <p>2
. Usually 
14
caudal fin rays (range 
12–15
); 
8
pores in preopercular-suborbital-supramaxillary series; 
2
distinct lateral longitudinal dark stripes. (Western 
Australia
from Augusta in the west and Albany to the east and north of Perth)...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata
(

Shipway 
1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
13
caudal fin rays (range 
11–15
); 
7
pores in preopercular-suborbital-supramaxillary series; 
3
distinct lateral longitudinal dark stripes (mid stripe and particularly dorsal stripe can be poorly defined in females)............................ 
3</p>
            <p>3
. Usually 
39
vertebrae (range 
36–41
); origin of dorsal fin distinctly posterior to that of anal fin, with horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins 
1.4–3.8
% of 
SL
(females 
1.4–2.8
% (range 0.0– 
3.8
), males 
2.4–3.8
% (range 
0.52–5.67
)); caudal peduncle of moderate length, 
21.3–23.8
% of 
SL
(females 
21.3–23.1
% (range 
18.4–25.5
), males 
21.9–23.8
% (range 
20.3
– 26.0)); adult females up to 
32.7 mmSL
(mean 
27.2
) and adult males up to 
28.2 mmSL
(mean 
23.6
); ventral markings distinct, most commonly a ‘v’-shaped dark mark originating in the isthmus and extending as two parallel dotted lines (sometimes discontinuous) to the pelvic fin bases. (South-eastern 
Australia
from Bairnsdale in eastern Victoria to south-east Melbourne, including Flinders Island and north-eastern and north-western Tasmania)................. 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla
(

Mack 
1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
- Usually 
36
vertebrae (range 
34–38
); origin of dorsal fin is more or less in line with that of anal fin (particularly females), with the horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins usually 0.0– 
2.7
% of 
SL
(females 0.0– 
1.4
% (range - 
2.5–2.8
), males 
1.3–2.7
% (range - 
2.6–3.9
); caudal peduncle relatively short, usually 
19.6–21.9
% of 
SL
(females 
19.6–21.2
% (range 
17.2–23.8
), males 
20.1–21.9
% (range 
17.9–24.4
)); adult females up to 
30.6 mmSL
(mean 
24.2
) and adult males up to 24.0 mm 
SL
(mean 
20.2
); ventral markings reduced, most commonly a small number of dark blotches in the vicinity of the isthmus. (South-eastern 
Australia
from Barwon Downs in western Victoria to near the Coorong in south-eastern South 
Australia
)............................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">new species</named-content>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Andrews 
1976
: 
324
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Scott 
1942
: 
55
(
partim
); 

Whitley 
1956
b

: 
39
(
partim
); 
1957
: 
6
; 
1960
: 
29
; 

Scott 
1966
: 
246
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1967
: 
227
(partim); 

Lake 
1971
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Chessman &amp; Williams 
1974
: 
168
; 

Pollard 
1980
: 
348
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Munro 
1957
: 
18
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1969
: 
185
(
partim
); 
1971
: 
94
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
(non 

Mack, 
1936
)— 

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
: 
129
(
partim
); 

Lake 
1978
: 
26
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1978
a

: 
116
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1980
: 
55
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
: 
552
(
partim
); Backhouse 
1983
: 
6
(
partim
); 

Cadwallader &amp; Backhouse 
1983
: 
75
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1983
: 
4
(
partim
); 

Jackson &amp; Davies 
1983
: 
39
; 

Last 
et al.1983
: 
201
(
partim
); 

Merrick &amp; Schmida 
1984
: 
98
(
partim
); 

Beck 
1985
: 
12
; Allen 
1989
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Berra &amp; Allen 
1989
: 
293
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.1989
: 
179
(
partim
); 

Fulton 
1990
: 
39
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Morison 
1990
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Andrews 
1991
: 
59
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Raadik 
1991
: 
77
(
partim
); 

Pen 
et al.1993
: 
848
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1995
: 
1159
(
partim
); 

Unmack &amp; 
Paras1995
: 
398
(
partim
); 

Westbury 
1995
: 
1
(
partim
); 

Chilcott &amp; Humphries 
1996
: 
147
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Fulton 
1996
: 
70
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
1996
: 
13
; 

Koster 
1997
: 
9
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
2000
: 
1123
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
2000
: 
5
; 

Littlejohn 
2001
: 
803
; 

Raadik 
et al.2001
a

: 
9
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
et al.2001
b

: 
110
(
partim
); Unmack 
2001
: 
1060
(
partim
); 

Allen 
et al.2002
: 
111
(
partim
); 

Fields 
2002
; 
3
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
2002
: 
6
; 

Koster 
2003
: 
268
(
partim
); 

Hammer &amp; Horne 
2004
: 
2
; 

Hammer &amp; Walker 
2004
: 
85
; 

Romanowski 
2004
: 
80
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2005
: 
162
, Fig. p 
163
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.2006
: 
408
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
2006
: 
356
(
partim
); 

Threatened Species Section 
2006
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Crook 
et al.2008
: 
10
; Hammer 
2009
: ii; Hammer 
et al.2009
: 
3
; 

Galeotti 
et al.2010
: 
13
(
partim
); 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
: 
3
(
partim
); Hammer 
et al.2012
: 
63
; 

Crook &amp; Gillanders 
2013
: 
207
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
et al.2013
: 
70
(
partim
); 

King 
et al.2013
: 
165
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2013
: 
84
(
partim
), 
8
lower images p. 
86
; 

Lintermans 
2013
c

: 
286
(
partim
); 

Bachmann 
et al.2014
: 
1
; Raadik 
2014
: 
160
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
‘west region’— 

Coleman 
et al.2010
: 
1911
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
: 
1
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
: 
1821
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
II—Unmack 
2013
: 
43
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
sp.– 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
a

: 
15
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
b

: 
297
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pusillus
Mack, 
1936
: 
101</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotypeNMV
A. 
97
, 
paratypesNMV
A. 
98
(
1
), 
NMV
A. 
388–390
(
3
); 
type
locality ‘Cardinia Creek, about 
30 miles
east of Melbourne, Victoria’)— 

Massola 
1938
: 
129
; 

Whitley 
1939
: 
268
; 

Stokell 
1945
: 
126
; 

Shipway 
1953
; 
173
; 

McDowall 
1971
: 
36
; 

Dixon 
1972
: 
121
; 

McDowall 
1973
: 
193
; 

Andrews 
1976
(
partim
): 
324
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxias pucillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Mack, 
1936
: 
101
(misprint in legend of 

).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Scott 
1942
: 
55
; 

Stokell 
1954
: 
412
; 

Whitley 
1956
a

: 
34
; 
1956
b: 
39
(
partim
); 
1957
: 
6
; 
1960
: 
29
; 
1964
: 
35
; 

Scott 
1966
: 
246
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1966
a

: 
162
; 
1966
b: 
32
; 
1967
: 
227
(
partim
); 
1968
: 
172
; 

Lake 
1971
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Dixon 
1972
: 
121
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
119
; 

Pollard 
1980
: 
348
(
partim
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Munro 
1957
: 
18
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1969
: 
185
(
partim
); 

Frankenberg 
1971
: 
94
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1973
: 
193
; 

Scott 
1971
: 
3
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus flindersiensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
6</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
: 
QVM1969
: 
5
: 
35
(previously 1969.5.25a); 
paratypes
: AMS I. 
16158
-001 (
1
), 
BMNH1972.1
. 
27.1
(
1
), 
QVM1969
: 
5
: 
34
(
12
); 
type
locality: ‘Lackrana, Flinders Island, Furneaux Group, Bass Strait’);– 

Green 
1974
: 
3
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
114
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Brachygalaxias pusillus tasmaniensis
Scott, 
1971
: 
3</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
: 
QVM1971.5
. 
48
(listed in error as 
1970
/ 
5
/ 
25
a in original description); 
paratypes
: AMS I. 
16159
-001 (
1
), 
BMNH1972.1
. 
27.2
(
1
), 
QVM1971
: 
5
: 
50
(
11
); 
type
locality ‘from a soak from a dam flowing towards the coast (northward) on 
<tp:taxon-name>Marengo
, Waterhouse Estate
</tp:taxon-name>
, Dorset, Tasmania’); 

Green 
1974
: 
3
; 

Frankenberg 
1974
: 
114
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
— 

McDowall 
1978
b

: 
309
; 

Lake 
1978
: 
26
(
partim
); 

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
: 
129
(
partim
); 

McDowall 
1980
: 
55
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
: 
552
(
partim
); Backhouse 
1983
: 
6
(
partim
); 

Cadwallader &amp; Backhouse 
1983
: 
75
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1983
: 
4
(
partim
); 

Johnson 
et al.1983
: 
50
; 

Last 
et al.1983
: 
201
(
partim
); 

Merrick &amp; Schmida 
1984
: 
98
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1986
: 
133
; Allen 
1989
: 
44
(
partim
), 
89
; 

Berra &amp; Allen 
1989
: 
293
(
partim
); 

Breen 
et al.1989
: 
1
; 

Paxton 
et al.1989
: 
179
(
partim
); 

Fulton 
1990
: 
39
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Morison 
1990
: 
20
(
partim
); 

Andrews 
1991
: 
59
(
partim
); 

Pen 
et al.1993
: 
848
(
partim
); 

Humphries 
1995
: 
1159
(
partim
); 

Unmack &amp; 
Paras1995
: 
398
(
partim
); 

Westbury 
1995
: 
1
(
partim
); 

Chilcott &amp; Humphries 
1996
: 
147
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Fulton 
1996
: 
70
(
partim
); 

Koster 
1997
: 
9
(
partim
); 

Raadik &amp; Zampatti 
1998
: 
6
; 

McDowall 
1999
: 
936
; 
2000
: 
1123
(
partim
); 

Waters 
et al.2000
: 
794
; Unmack 
2001
: 
1060
(
partim
); 

Allen 
et al.2002
: 
111
(
partim
); 

Fields 
2002
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Koster 
2003
: 
268
(
partim
); 

McDowall &amp; Waters 
2004
: 
24
; 

Romanowski 
2004
: 
80
(
partim
); 

Kuiter 
2005
: 
162
(
partim
); 

Hardie 
et al.2006
: 
238
; 

McDowall 
2006
: 
356
(
partim
); 

Paxton 
et al.2006
: 
408
(
partim
); 

Raadik 
2006
: 
139
; 

Threatened Species Section 
2006
: 
44
(
partim
); 

Galeotti 
et al.2010
: 
13
(
partim
); 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
: 
3
(
partim
); 

Stoessel 
2010
: 
2
; 

McDowall &amp; Burridge 
2011
: 
9
; 

Burridge 
et al.2012
: 
313
; Hammer 
et al.2012
: 
62
; 

Crook &amp; Gillanders 
2013
: 
207
(
partim
); 

Hammer 
et al.2013
: 
70
(
partim
); 

King 
et al.2013
: 
165
(
partim
); 

Koehn &amp; Kennard 
2013
: 
91
; 

Kuiter 
2013
: 
84
(
partim
), images pp 
84-85
, images top p. 
86
, images p. 
87
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
a

: 
15
; 

Lieschke 
et al.2013
b

: 
235
; 

Lintermans 
2013
c

: 
286
(
partim
); Raadik 
2014
: 
160
(
partim
); 

Galeotti 
et al
. 
2015
: 
189
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
‘east region’— 

Coleman 
et al.2010
: 
1911
; 

Unmack 
et al.2012
: 
1
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
: 
1821
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Material examined.</title>
         <p>Holotype
.
NMV
A. 
97
, 
22.3 mmSL
[now partially dried, particularly anterior end], male, Cardinia Creek, about 
30 miles
east of Melbourne, Victoria, A. Massola, 
22
May 
1936
.
</p>
         <p>Paratypes
. Victoria:
NMV
A. 
98
and A. 
388
- 
90
, collected with 
holotype
.
</p>
         <p>Non-type material. Victoria:NMV
A. 
31230
-001 (
20
), 
20.9–31.2 mmSL
, Cobblers Creek, Forge Creek Road, Bairnsdale, 
37
° 
51
' 
17
"S
147
° 
36
' 
19
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
26
July 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31229
-001 (
20
), 
18.1–28.7 mmSL
, Perry River, Princes Highway, Delvine, 
37
° 
55
' 
17
"S
147
° 
16
' 
31
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
26
July 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31226
- 0 0 
1
(
20
), 
22.3–31.8 mmSL
, Moe Main Drain, Mitchells Road, Moe, 
38
° 
10
' 
22
"S
146
° 
14
' 
52
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
29
July 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31227
-001 (
23
), 
23.5–32.5 mmSL
, Morwell River, Princes Freeway, Morwell, 
38
° 
13
' 
40
"S
146
° 
21
' 
39
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
29
July 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31228
-001 (
20
), 
19.2–28.8 mmSL
, Merriman Creek, Merton- Vale Road, Willung, 
38
° 
14
' 
54
"S
146
° 
49
' 
26
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
19
July 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31223
-001 (
20
), 20.0– 
32.3 mmSL
, Dandenong Creek tributary, Brady Road, Endeavour Hills, 
37
° 
57
' 
37
"S
145
° 
14
' 
2
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
5
July 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31225
-001 (
20
), 
21.1–28.1 mmSL
, King Parrot Creek, Greenshield Road, Drouin, 
38
° 
10
' 
27
"S
145
° 
52
' 
7
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
5
July 
2013
; 
NMV
A. 
31224
-001 (
20
), 
24.2–32.7 mmSL
, Tuerong Creek, Old Moorooduc Road, Moorooduc, 
38
° 
16
' 
23
"S
145
° 
4
' 
16
"E

, RAC, JAC, 
5
July 
2013
. 
Tasmania:NMV
A. 
31231
-001 (
10
) not measured, Icena Creek, Browns Bridge Road, Gladstone, 
40
° 
58
' 
12
"S
148
° 
9
' 
23
"E

, RAC, M.L. Coleman, 
27
May 
2008
; 
NMV
A. 
31232
-001 (
9
) not measured, Big Waterhouse Lake, Homestead Road, Waterhouse, 
40
° 
53
' 
33
"S
147
° 
36
' 
53
"E

, RAC, M.L. Coleman, 
28
May 
2008
, and same location, RAC, H.T. Coleman, E. Tsyrlin, 
1
July 
2009
.
</p>
         <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
is distinguished from other 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
by: caudal fin rays usually 
13
(
11–15
), anal fin rays usually 
8
(
7–10
), pectoral fin rays usually 
12
(
10–13
), usually 
39
(
36–41
) vertebrae, 
7
laterosensory pores in preopercular-supramaxillary series. Adults small (usually females 
21.4–32.7 mmSL
; males 
18.1–28.2 mmSL
); caudal peduncle length moderate usually 
21.3–23.8
% 
SL
(females 
18.4–25.5
; males 
20.3
–26.0); origin of dorsal fin distinctly posterior to anal fin (particularly males), with horizontal distance between dorsal fin and anal fin origins usually 
1.4–3.8
% 
SL
(females 0.0– 
3.8
; males 
0.52–5.67
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
adults with three longitudinal black stripes (easier to discern in adult males) and distinct markings on ventral surface (typically ‘v’- shaped dark mark originating on isthmus and extending as two parallel dotted lines (sometimes discontinuous) to the pelvic fin bases) (

b).
</p>
         <p>Description.
As for genus, except as below. Based on 
163
adult

non– 
type
specimens, 
18.1–32.7 mmSL
, and 
19
additional non– 
type
specimens for meristic counts. See 

Table 
2
for summary of meristic variation and 

Table 
4
for frequencies of meristic values. Segmented dorsal fin rays 
7
(
6–8
, 
holotype6
), of these 
4
(
0–5
, 
holotype4
) branched; 
4
th dorsal fin ray longest (
2
nd– 
5
th); segmented anal fin rays 
8
(
7–10
, 
holotype8
), of these 
5
(
0–7
) branched; 
4
th anal fin ray longest (
3
rd– 
7
th); caudal fin rays 
13
(
11–15
, 
holotype13
), of these 
9
(
4–11
, excluding a single outlier of 
1
, 
holotype9
) branched; segmented pectoral fin rays 
12
(
10–13
, 
holotype13
); pelvic fin rays 
5
(
4– 5
, 
holotype5
); total gill raker total count on first gill arch (lower limb and upper limb) 
16
(
13–20
), lower limb 
10
(
8–13
) and upper limb 
6
(
4–7
); vertebrae 
39
(
36–41
, 
holotype38
).
</p>
         <p>
See 

and 

Tables 
3
and 
5
for summary of morphometric characters. Small, moderately elongate and mostly fusiform body with greatest body depth usually in mid abdominal region (between pectoral and pelvic fins). Body depth at vent 
13.8
(12.0– 
15.5
) % 
SL
females and 
13.6
(
11.8–15.4
) % 
SL
males, tapering to moderately long caudal peduncle (females 
22.2
(
18.4–25.5
) % 
SL
; males 
22.9
(
20.3
–26.0) % 
SL
). Caudal peduncle moderately deep (females 
43.8
(
34.3–53.6
) % 
LCP
; males 
43.2
(
36.9–52.9
) % 
LCP
). Dorsal and ventral profiles moderately arched, flattened in head region and narrowing behind vent.
</p>
         <p>
Head short (females 23.0 (
19.7–26.8
) % 
SL
; males 
23.8
(
19.7–26.9
) % 
SL
), broad (females 
70.4
(
61.4–87.5
) %HL; males 
65.2
(
56.6–81.9
) %HL) and similar depth (females 
68.1
(
55.9–83.1
) %HL; males 
66.8
(
60.1–77.7
) %HL). Snout rounded and short (females 
20.9
(
13.6–26.9
) %HL; males 
20.7
(
15.9–24.6
) %HL). Eye diameter large (females 
30.6
(
25.3–36.4
) %HL; males 32.0 (
28.1–35.9
) %HL), positioned high in head with upper margin typically level with dorsal head profile or slightly raised above. Interorbital generally broad (females 
44.8
(
37.2– 58.9
) %HL; males 
43.4
(
36.7–59.3
) %HL) and flat. Mouth small, slanting posterio-ventrally from tip of snout to almost in line with anterior margin of eye. Lower jaw slightly shorter (females 
22.4
(
16.6–26.9
) % HL; males 
22.1
(
15.9–27.4
) %HL) than upper jaw (females 
24.2
(
18.5–31.2
) %HL; males 
23.7
(
18.3–28.6
) %HL). Gape width moderate (females 
27.8
(
21.3–38.9
) %HL; males 
25.6
(
21.1–34.2
) %HL) and depth slightly shorter (females 
22.4
(
14.9–27.1
) %HL; males 
21.6
(14.0– 
26.1
) %HL) than width. Jaws without enlarged lateral canines; mesopterygoidal teeth few but strong; lingual teeth well developed. Gill rakers generally long, slender and pointed, sometimes rounded. Seven pores in preopercular-supramaxillary series with bow-shape cluster of three closest to jaw; submandibular sensory pores absent.
</p>
         <p>
Fins small, lacking spines, membranous and predominantly rounded. Length of anal fin base (females 11.0 (
9.7–13.3
) % 
SL
; males 
12.1
(
10.2–14.5
) % 
SL
) greater than dorsal fin base (females 
8.3
(
6.5–10.2
) % 
SL
; males 
8.7
(
6.8–10.6
) % 
SL
). Anal fin similar length (females 
15.9
(
14.1–19.1
) % 
SL
; males 
17.2
(
15.2–19.9
) % 
SL
) to dorsal fin (females 
14.6
(
12.8–17.2
) % 
SL
; males 
15.1
(
12.7–17.7
) % 
SL
). Dorsal fin origin distinctly posterior to anal fin origin (DF–AF setback in females 
2.2
(0.0– 
3.9
) % 
SL
; males 
3.1
(
0.5–5.7
) % 
SL
). Pelvic fin to anal fin distance ranges from 
20.6
(
17.9
–24.0) % 
SL
females and 
18.8
(
16.9–22.8
) % 
SL
males. Pelvic fins narrow and shorter (females 
9.9
(8.0– 
11.3
) % 
SL
; males 
10.4
(
8.7–12.2
) % 
SL
) than dorsal and anal fins, positioned mid-length along ventral surface of body. Pectoral fins with broad, fleshy base, inserted high, approximately same level as tip of snout, round (paddle-like), of similar length to, or slightly larger (females 
11.8
(
9.6
–14.0) % 
SL
; males 
12.5
(
10.7– 15.2
) % 
SL
) than pelvic fins. Caudal fin rounded, moderate length (females 
16.1
(
9.3–20.2
) % 
SL
; males 
16.8
(
10.5–20.2
) % 
SL
), generally broader than long, and vertical width of expanded rays greater than depth of caudal peduncle. Caudal peduncle flanges broad, distinct, extending back almost to posterior ends of anal and dorsal fin bases. Well-developed fleshy keel present mid-ventrally between pelvic fins, extending to vent (females 
15.1
(
12.1–19.1
) % 
SL
; males 
14.5
(
11.2–17.6
) % 
SL
) with maximum depth 2.0 (
1.3–2.9
) % 
SL
in females and 
1.9
(
0.8
– 3.0) % 
SL
in males.
</p>
         <p>Size.
Females recorded to 
47 mm
TL, commonly to 
30–36 mm
TL. Males recorded to 
37 mm
TL, commonly to 
27–31 mm
TL.
</p>
         <p>Colour in life.
The dorsal and upper sides of the body are generally pale olive-brown (darker along the dorsal margin) and the ventral and lower sides silvery-white (

b). The gills are visible as a large red-pink patch through the gill covers on the sides of the head. Adults possess three continuous to semi-continuous, horizontal black stripes along the lateral surface of the trunk, from near the eye to the origin of the caudal fin. In males the black lines are more distinct and complete, and in females the lines are generally fainter, stippled and the upper two stripes more difficult to discern (particularly the dorsal stripe). Adult males possess a bright orange-red stripe between the lower two black stripes, which in females is generally thin and bright silver, gold, pale mauve or on rare occasions, pale orange. The eyes are mostly silvery-gold, with patches of bright orange in line with the coloured body stipe (of the same colour in males). On the ventral surface of adults is a distinct v-shaped black mark often present on the isthmus, which frequently extends posteriorly as two parallel dotted lines to near the pelvic fins (

b). The ventral markings more distinct in males, and the dotted lines are occasionally absent or discontinuous. The v-shape marking is rarely reduced to a few irregular blotches in females. Juveniles lack the distinct striped patterns and colour of adults, are predominantly pale olive dorsally to beige on the upper sides and silvery-white ventrally. The eyes of juveniles are silvery-gold and have a similar colour to the crenulated stripe along the sides.
</p>
         <p>Colour of preserved material.
The body is creamy beige, with darker stippling along the dorsal surface (particularly around head) and paler on the lower sides and ventral surface. Adults have three continuous to semicontinuous, horizontal black stripes along the lateral surfaces of the trunk from near eye to the origin of the caudal fin and tending to be more distinct and complete in males. The stripes are generally fainter and stippled in females, with the upper two stripes difficult to discern (particularly the dorsal stripe). Coloured stripes are absent and the eyes are black. The ventral surface of adults has a distinct v-shaped black mark that is often present on the isthmus and frequently extends posteriorly as two parallel dotted lines to near the pelvic fins. The ventral markings more distinct in males and the dotted lines are occasionally absent or discontinuous. The v-shape marking is rarely reduced to a few irregular blotches in females.
</p>
         <p>Sexual Dimorphism.
Whilst differences in many of the morphological characters measured were evident, key features that summarise sexual dimorphism in 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
adults include: males smaller than females; females tend to be deeper bodied that males; male genital papillus is low and projects slightly more than the vent, while the female genital papillus is a distinct fleshy mound. Colour differences between the sexes of adult fish are: males have a bright orange-red lateral body stripe and three distinct black lateral body stripes on the side, females lack the orange-red lateral body stripe (generally thin and bright silver, gold or mauve in females) and the three black stripes are more difficult to discern, particularly the most dorsal stripe (

b).
</p>
         <p>Etymology.
The name 
<tp:taxon-name>pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
is from the Latin 
<tp:taxon-name>pusillus</tp:taxon-name>
(as originally used by 

Mack, 
1936
), meaning ‘very small’. Recommended standard name as ‘dwarf galaxias’.
</p>
         <p>Genetics.
Microsatellite and mtDNA analysis of this species can be found in 

Coleman 
et al.
(
2010
; 
2013
; taxon ‘east region’). Allozyme and mtDNA data are presented in 

Unmack 
et al.
(
2012
)

.
</p>
         <p>Distribution.
Known in coastal south-eastern mainland 
Australia
, from the Mitchell River Basin near Bairnsdale, west to Dandenong Creek near Melbourne in Victoria, Flinders Island in Bass Strait and north-eastern and north-western Tasmania (

). A translocated population (sourced in the early-mid 
1990
s from Tirhatuan Wetland, Rowville, in the Dandenong Creek catchment) exists in the La Trobe University wildlife reserve, Bundoora, in the Yarra River catchment (

Westbury 
1995
). Its current known range does not overlap that of 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>Habitat.
Generally found in swamps, wetlands, shallow lakes, billabongs, small creeks and artificial earthen drains (

) at very low elevation (mean 
54 m
above sea level, typically 
25–72 m
above sea level). Habitats are mostly shallow (mean maximum depth 
1.1 m
, typically 
0.5–1.5 m
), with still to low water velocities (or often backwaters in faster flowing conditions) and substantial shading (mean 
36
%, typically 
10–60
% surface cover). The substratum composition tends to be dominated by fine clay (mean 
33
%, typically 
10–50
%) and silt (mean 
43
%, typically 
30–50
%) and occasionally coarser (particularly sand) with deposits of coarse particulate organic matter (mean 
31
%, typically 
10–60
% cover). Frequently captured where the vegetation cover is dense and consists primarily of emergent (mean 
45
%, typically 
24–73
% cover) and submerged (mean 
12
%, typically 
0–13
% cover) aquatic species. Measurements of water quality at the time of collection suggest that this species can withstand a broad range of conditions, at least, water temperatures of 
5.8–24.8
o C, dissolved oxygen levels of 
18–130
% saturation and turbidity between 
1–133
NTU. The range for pH measurements was 5.0– 
7.8
and the range for water electrical conductivity was 
36–3,070
µS/cm.
</p>
         <p>Conservation status.<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
is currently listed as ‘vulnerable’ nationally (
EPBC
Act 
1999
)

and internationally (
IUCN
Red List of Threatened Species, 

Wager 
1996
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
should be retained as a nationally threatened taxon, but considered more threatened than previously thought as its newly defined mainland distribution is now approximately 
40
% of that previously known for 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
According to the 
IUCN
criteria (
IUCN2012
) it should qualify as ‘endangered’ based on the following criteria: B 
2
a, b(i,ii,iii,iv), c(ii,iii),), that relate to an area of occupancy &lt;
500km2
, severe population fragmentation, continuing decline in the extent of occurrence, area of occupancy, area/extent and/or quality of habitat, number of locations or subpopulations, and extreme fluctuation in the area of occupancy and number of locations or subpopulations. This is consistent with the conservation status proposed by the State of Victoria in 
Australia
for ‘eastern region’ populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
(

DSE 
2013
). Habitat loss and fragmentation, and negative interactions with invasive fishes (particularly 
<tp:taxon-name>Gambusia holbrooki</tp:taxon-name>
) remain as major threats to their long-term survival (

Koster 
2003
; 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
; Coleman 
et al.
in review).
</p>
         <p>General Biology.
A non-migratory, freshwater species, occasionally found in inland slightly saline waters. The observed spawning period is between late autumn to spring and can be variable (

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
; 

Humphries 
1986
; Coleman 
et al.
in review). It is predominantly an annual species that dies soon after spawning (

Massola 
1938
; 

Humphries 
1986
; 

Pen 
et al.1993
; 

Romanowski 
2004
; Coleman 
et al.
in review). Where present, it can occur in high densities, although there may be substantial seasonal and inter-annual variability in population abundances (Coleman 
et al.
in review). It has developed adaptations to surviving extended periods of habitat drying, aided via a capacity for air-breathing and the use of moisture retaining habitat features such as vegetation cover and crayfish burrows (Coleman 
et al.
in review). It is likely to exist with a metapopulation structure or a ‘population of sub-populations’, where persistence of the population as a whole is facilitated by multiple interconnected sub-populations (
viz.
Levins 
1969
; 

Hanski 
1998
). Natural wetting and drying cycles typical of their habitats (and other environmental factors) can lead to large fluctuations in inter-annual population densities, emphasising the importance of habitat inter-connectivity across the landscape to maintain a balance between local population extinctions and recolonization (Coleman 
et al.
in review). Wetting and drying cycles are also likely to be important for enhancing food resources and reducing competition and predation pressures (Coleman 
et al.
in review).
</p>
         <p>
It is often collected with native fish species, particularly 
<tp:taxon-name>Nannoperca australis</tp:taxon-name>
(
69
% frequency), 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxias maculatus</tp:taxon-name>
(
12
% frequency), and 
Anguilla<tp:taxon-name>australis</tp:taxon-name>
(
10
% frequency). Exotic fish species often collected with 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
are 
<tp:taxon-name>Gambusia holbrooki</tp:taxon-name>
(
39
% frequency) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Carrasius auratus</tp:taxon-name>
(
12
% frequency). Other aquatic life that frequently occurs with 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
include 
<tp:taxon-name>Paratya australiensis</tp:taxon-name>
(
19
% frequency), 
<tp:taxon-name>Notonectidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
40
% frequency), Amphipoda (
10
% frequency), 
<tp:taxon-name>Belostomatidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
25
% frequency), 
<tp:taxon-name>Corixidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
15
% frequency), Coleoptera (
10
% frequency), Odonata (
44
% frequency), and Gastropoda (
10
% frequency). It is sometimes found with clusters of trematode cysts within the head region that can cause head enlargement (

Coleman 
2014
).
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 11.
Collection sites and approximate current geographic distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(light grey) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(dark grey). See Table 1 for site numbers and site details. Type localities are indicated by a white star.
</p>
         <p>Remarks.<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
primarily by a combination of the following characters: more vertebrae; slightly longer caudal peduncle; more pronounced dorsal fin-anal fin setback, especially in females; and, adults are larger. In preserved material, markings on the ventral surface of adults, are typically a distinct v-shaped black mark originating in the isthmus that is often extended posteriorly by two parallel dotted lines to near the pelvic fins (more distinct in males) (

b), also differentiates it from 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
. Less caudal fin and anal fin rays, one more longitudinal black lateral body stripe and less laterosensory pores in the preopercular-supramaxillary series differentiate it from 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
. Differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella munda</tp:taxon-name>
by being shorter overall, having less caudal and anal fin rays, more pectoral fin rays, less vertebrae, and possessing longitudinal dark lateral body stripes in adults.
</p>
         <p>
The 
holotype
has become partially dried, particularly anterior to the insertion of the pelvic fins. Therefore, morphometric and some meristic characters (e.g. gill rakers on upper limb of first gill arch; branched anal fin rays) could not be reliably elucidated. An old register card at 
NMV
states that there were originally five 
paratypes
, and that one was sent on exchange to E.O.G. Scott, Queen Victoria Museum, Launceston, on 
14
May 
1940
. The 
paratype
arrived at 
QVM
(letter from E.O.G. Scott to G. Mack (
NMV
) dated 
22
May 
1940
, seen; 
QVMAG
Administrative Records), but its existence in the collection has not been able to be confirmed to date (David Maynard, 
pers. comm.
August 
2015
).
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 12.
Examples of aquatic habitats occupied by 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
: a) Fitzroy River, T and W Road, Cobboboonee, Victoria, b) Bridgewater Lakes, Bridgwater Lakes Road, Tarragal, Victoria, c) Darlot Creek tributary, Etterick Tyrendarra Road, Tyrendarra, Victoria, d) Moyne River tributary, Woolsthorpe Heywood Road, Moyne, Victoria, e) Crawford River, Condah Coleraine Road, Branxholme, Victoria, f) Gosling Creek, Division Road, Murroon, Victoria.
</p>
         <p>
There are small, additional morphological differences between this species and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
that may be of secondary taxonomic importance: length of the caudal peduncle flanges, positioning of eye and colour in the wild (see Remarks section for 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
). There are also errors with respect to the number of preopercularsupermaxillary pores and gill raker morphology listed in 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg (
1981
)

for this species, and for 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
in general (see Discussion)
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
Morphometric and meristic differences support substantial genetic differentiation of eastern and western populations (

Coleman 
et al.2010
; 

Unmack 
2012
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
) that sufficiently warrant the separation of 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l.</named-content>
into two species. Accordingly, a new species, 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
, was described for the western lineage and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
was redescribed for the eastern lineage based on a greater number of specimens than previous descriptions by 

Mack (
1936
)

and 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg (
1981
)

. Based on the recent update to the number of extant species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Galaxiidae (Raadik 
2014
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, our revision increases the number of species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiidae</tp:taxon-name>
to 
65
, with 
62
species in five genera in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiinae</tp:taxon-name>
. It also increases the number of endemic species in this family in 
Australia
to 
34
, of which 
20
are endemic to the mainland. As well as the inclusion of 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
, several revisions were made to the previous taxonomic key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
by 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg (
1981
)

.
</p>
         <p>
In addition to geographic and genetic distinctness, important differences between 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
include: the size of adults, number of vertebrae, length of caudal peduncle, dorsal fin-anal fin setback (most notably in females) and ventral surface markings in adults. A reduced dorsal fin-anal fin setback in 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
also distinguishes it from 
<tp:taxon-name>G. nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
, as do differences in body length, and the number of caudal and anal fin rays, vertebrae, longitudinal black stripes in adults and laterosensory pores in the preopercular-supramaxillary series.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.l</named-content>
can be typically found in habitats that are shallow, have low flow velocities, are semipermanent and contain dense stands of aquatic vegetation, including lakes, wetlands, swamps, billabongs, small creeks and earthen drains (e.g. 

Backhouse &amp; Vanner 
1978
; 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg 
1981
; 

Beck 
1985
; 

Saddlier 
et al.2010
). During this study, common habitat features at sites where either 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
or 
G. p u s i l l a
s.s. occurred were consistent with those characteristics and also included, partial shading, a substratum dominated by fine clay and silt (occasionally sand) with deposits of coarse particulate organic matter, and dense vegetation comprising mostly emergent and submerged aquatic species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
occur in a wide range of water quality conditions. Observed differences in habitats between 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
include their salinity and elevational ranges; however, these results are based on field observations that may not accurately reflect tolerances associated with these factors.
</p>
         <p>
From a conservation perspective, the formal recognition of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
as distinct taxa will enable independent management strategies to be tailored to account for their uniqueness and potential ecological differences, and is expected to lead to more successful outcomes for both species. For example, 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
have much lower genetic diversity (

Coleman 
et al.2010
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
), are under substantial threat from habitat loss and habitat isolation from rapidly expanding urban areas in near Melbourne, and multiple surveys in 
2008
and 
2009
in northwest Tasmania and Flinders Island suggest that populations in these areas have dramatically contracted (

Coleman 
et al.2010
; 

Coleman 
et al.2013
). Historical decline in distribution and area of occupancy is also indicated by a record of this species (
NMV
A. 
8330
) from Scotchmans Creek in Yarra River catchment, Victoria, an area where extensive wetlands existed prior to urbanisation (e.g. 

Burns 
1984
; 

Presland 
1994
; 

Lacey 
2004
; 

Otto 
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
In addition to the inclusion of 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
, we have made a number of revisions to the previous taxonomic key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
by 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg (
1981
)

. Firstly, there are inconsistencies between their taxonomic key (pg. 
552
), descriptions (pg. 
556, 562, 568
) and illustrations (pg. 
588
) for all species regarding the number of pores in the preopercular-suborbital-supramaxillary series. For example, 
G. p u s i l l a
is listed with: 
8
pores in the key (p. 
552
) and 
8
pores in description (p. 
556
) but 
7
pores in Fig. 
47
(p. 
588
). Another inconsistency in 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg (
1981
)

relates to gill raker morphology in the key, descriptions and illustrations (pg. 
585
) for all species. For example, gill rakers for 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
in the key are described as of ‘moderate length’, while in the species descriptions they are described as ‘long and slender’ (which matches more closely with Fig. 
44
on pg. 
585
). Examination of 
G. p u s i l l a
, 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>G. nigrostriata</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. munda</tp:taxon-name>
specimens at 
NMV
confirmed that the correct number of pores for all 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
are depicted on pg. 
588
of 

McDowall &amp; Frankenberg (
1981
)

. On the other hand, examination of gill raker morphology on the same specimens did not reveal substantial differences between 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
species. Accordingly, we have corrected the number of pores in our 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
key and removed reference to differences in gill raker morphology. Frequency and range information for meristic characters has also been updated for 
<tp:taxon-name>G. pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>G. toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
in the taxonomic key, based on a much larger dataset in this study, and reference to body depth at vent/standard length has been removed due to strongly overlapping ranges between all species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>
We thank Melbourne Water Corporation for funding this research. Special thanks to James Coleman for assistance with collecting specimens, to the Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research (Victorian Department of Environment, Land, Water and Planning) for providing access to laboratory facilities during the study, and to Martin Gomon (Museum Victoria) for use of the X-ray equipment. Thanks also to Dianne Bray (Museum Victoria) for specimen registration and access to registered specimens, Mark McGrouther (Australian Museum) and Ralph Forster (South Australian Museum) for 
paratype
registration, David Maynard (Queen Victoria Museum) for collection details, Ross Smith (Queen Victoria Museum) for locating historical correspondence, and to Rhyll Plant for the scientific illustrations. We are grateful to Denis Rose, Ben Church (Gunditj Mirring Traditional Owners Aboriginal Corporation) and Joel Wright (Victorian Aboriginal Corporation for Languages) who helped identify an appropriate indigenous name for the new 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella</tp:taxon-name>
species. Three anonymous reviewers are thanked for comments that helped substantially improve this paper. Michael Hammer and Rudie Kuiter kindly provided images of fish to use in this manuscript. Research was carried out with The University of Melbourne animal ethics approval (AEC 
1312848.1
) and State of Victoria research permits for threatened species and national parks (
DEPI10006773
), and fisheries (
DEPIRP1147
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>References</p>
      <p>Adams, M.
, 
Raadik, T.A.
, 
Burridge, C.P.
&amp; 
Georges, A.
(
2014
) 
Global biodiversity assessment and hyper-cryptic species complexes: more than one species of elephant in the room
. 
Systematic Biology
, 
63
, 
518
– 
533
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/sysbio/syu017
</p>
      <p>Allen, G.R.
(
1989
) 

Freshwater Fishes of 
Australia
. 

T.F.H. Publications, Neptune City, New 
Jersey
, 
240
pp.
</p>
      <p>Allen, G.R.
, 
Midgley, S.H.
&amp; 
Allen, M.
(
2002
) 

Field Guide to the Freshwater Fishes of 
Australia
. 
Western Australian Museum, Perth
, 
394
pp.
</p>
      <p>Andrews, A.P.
(
1976
) 
A revision of the family Galaxiidae (Pisces) in Tasmania
. 
Australian Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research
, 
27
, 
297
– 
349
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1071
/MF 
9760297</p>
      <p>Andrews, A.P.
(
1991
) 

Observations on the Tasmanian mudfish, 
Galaxias cleaveri
(Pisces: Galaxiidae)

. 
Papers and Proceedings of the Royal Society of Tasmania
, 
125
, 

55– 
59
.
</p>
      <p>Atchley, W.R.
, 
Gaskins, C.T.
&amp; 
Anderson, D.
(
1976
) 
Statistical properties of ratios. I. Empirical results
. 
Systematic Zoology
, 
25
, 
137
– 
148
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.2307
/ 
2412740</p>
      <p>Bachmann, M.
, 
Whiterod, N.
, 
Anderson, D.
&amp; 
Farrington, L.
(
2014
) 

Regional status update of the dwarf galaxis (Galaxiella pusilla) in the south east of South 
Australia
—spring 
2012
– 
13
. Aquasave—Nature Glenelg Trust, Mt Gambier. Available from

: 

http://natureglenelg.org.au/wp-content/uploads/ 
2014
/06/Aquasave-NGT-Dwarf-Galaxias-in-the-South-East-For-
Website.pdf (accessed17
January 
2015
)
</p>
      <p>Backhouse, G.N.
(
1983
) 

The dwarf galaxias, 
Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack 
1936
) in Victoria

. 
Fishes of Sahul
, 
1
, 

5– 
8
.
</p>
      <p>Backhouse, G.N.
&amp; 
Vanner, R.W.
(
1978
) 

Observations on the biology of the dwarf galaxiid, 
Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack) (Pisces: Galaxiidae)

. 
Victorian Naturalist
, 
95
, 
128
– 
132
.
</p>
      <p>Beck, R.G.
(
1985
) 

Field observations upon the Dwarf Galaxiid 
Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack) (Pisces: Galaxiidae) in the south-east of South 
Australia
, 
Australia
. 
South Australian Naturalist
, 
60
, 

12– 
22
.
</p>
      <p>Berra, T.M.
&amp; 
Allen, G.R.
(
1989
) 

Clarification of the differences between 
Galaxiella nigrostriata
(Shipway, 
1953
) and 
Galaxiella munda
McDowall, 
1978
(Pisces: Galaxiidae) from Western 
Australia
. 
Records of the Western Australian Museum
, 
14
, 
293
– 
297
.
</p>
      <p>Breen, P.F.
, 
Condina, P.
, 
Donnelly, A.
&amp; 
Muir, S.
(
1989
) 
Pusilla Flats (Tirhatuan Wetlands)
. 
Ecology, development and management strategy
. 

Technical Report No. 
33
. Dandenong Valley Authority, Dandenong, 
42
pp.
</p>
      <p>Burns, D.
(
1984
) 
A history of Gardiners Creek Valley
. 
Masters Thesis, University of Melbourne, Parkville
, 
89
pp.
</p>
      <p>Burridge, C.P.
, 
McDowall, R.M.
, 
Craw, D.
, 
Wilson, M.V.H.
&amp; 
Waters, J.M.
(
2012
) 
Marine dispersal as a pre-requisite for Gondwanan vicariance among elements of the galaxiid fish fauna
. 
Journal of Biogeography
, 
39
, 
306
– 
321
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1365
-2699.2011.02600.x
</p>
      <p>Cadwallader, P.L.
&amp; 
Backhouse, G.N.
(
1983
) 
A Guide to the Freshwater Fish of Victoria
. 
Victorian Government Printing Office, Melbourne
, 
249
pp.
</p>
      <p>Cavalcanti, M.J.
, 
Monteiro, L.R.
&amp; 
Lopes, P.R.D.
(
1999
) 
Landmark-based morphometric analysis in selected species of Serranid Fishes (Perciformes: Teleostei)
. 
Zoological Studies
, 
38
, 
287
– 
294
.
</p>
      <p>Chakrabarty, P.
, 
Chu, J.
, 
Nahar, L.
&amp; 
Sparks, J.S.
(
2010
) 

Geometric morphometrics uncovers a new species of ponyfish (Teleostei: Leiognathidae: 
Equulites
), with comments on the taxonomic status of 
Equula berbis
Valenciennes

. 
Zootaxa
, 
2427
, 

15– 
24
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.2427.1.2
</p>
      <p>Chessman, B.C.
&amp; 
Williams, W.D.
(
1974
) 

Distribution of fish in inland saline waters in Victoria, 
Australia
. 
Australian Journal of Marine and Freshwater Research
, 
25
, 
167
– 
172
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1071
/MF 
9740167</p>
      <p>Chilcott, S.J.
&amp; 
Humphries, P.
(
1996
) 
Freshwater fish of northeast Tasmania with notes on the dwarf galaxias
. 
Records of the Queen Victoria Museum and Art Gallery
, 
103
, 
145
– 
149
.
</p>
      <p>Coleman, R.A.
(
2014
) 
Conservation of the dwarf galaxias,
Galaxiella pusilla 

(Mack 
1936
) (Teleostei: Galaxiidae), a threatened freshwater fish from south-eastern 
Australia
. 
PhD Thesis, University of Melbourne, Parkville
, 
262
pp.
</p>
      <p>Coleman, R.A.
, 
Pettigrove, V.
, 
Raadik, T.A.
, 
Hoffmann, A.A.
, 
Miller, A.D.
&amp; 
Carew, M.E.
(
2010
) 

Microsatellite markers and mtDNA indicate two distinct groups in dwarf galaxias, 
Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack) (Pisces: Galaxiidae), a threatened freshwater fish from south-eastern 
Australia
. 
Conservation Genetics
, 
11
, 

1911– 
1928
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1007
/s 
10592
-010-0082-z
</p>
      <p>Coleman, R.A.
, 
Raadik, T.A.
, 
Pettigrove, V.
&amp; 
Hoffmann, A.A.
(
2015
) 

Taking advantage of adaptations when managing threatened species within variable environments: the case of the dwarf galaxias 
Galaxiella pusilla
(Teleostei, Galaxiidae)

. 
[in review]</p>
      <p>Coleman, R.A.
, 
Weeks, A.R.
&amp; 
Hoffmann, A.A.
(
2013
) 

Balancing genetic uniqueness and genetic variation in determining conservation and translocation strategies: a comprehensive case study of threatened dwarf galaxias, 
Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack) (Pisces: Galaxiidae)

. 
Molecular Ecology
, 
22
, 

1820– 
1835
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/mec. 
12227</p>
      <p>Crook, D.A.
&amp; 
Gillanders, B.M.
(
2013
) 

Chapter 
8
. Age and growth

. 
In
: 
Humphries, P.
&amp; 
Walker, K.
(Eds.), 
Ecology of Australian Freshwater Fishes
, 
CSIRO
Publishing, Collingwood

, pp. 
195–221
.
</p>
      <p>Crook, D.
, 
Macdonald, J.
, 
Belcher, C.
, 
O’Mahony, D.
, 
Dawson, D.
, 
Lovett, A.
, 
Walker, A.
&amp; 
Bannam, L.
(
2008
) 
Lake Condah Restoration Project—Biodiversity assessment
. 

Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research Technical Report Series No. 
180
. Department of Sustainability and Environment, Heidelberg

, 
38
pp.
</p>
      <p>de Queiroz, K.
(
2007
) 
Species concepts and species delimitation
. 
Systematic Biology
, 
56
, 
879
– 
886
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/ 
10635150701701083</p>
      <p>Dixon, J.M.
(
1972
) 

Catalogue of galaxiid 
types
(Pisces: Galaxiidae) in the National Museum of Victoria, 
Australia
. 
Memoirs of the National Museum of Victoria
, 
33
, 
121
– 
122
.
</p>
      <p>DSE
(
2013
) 
Advisory list of threatened vertebrate fauna in Victoria
. Department of Sustainability and Environment

. 
Victorian Government, Melbourne. Available from
: 

http://www.depi.vic.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0019/ 
210439
/Advisory-Listof-Threatened-Vertebrate-Fauna_FINAL- 
2013
.pdf

(accessed 
17
January 
2015
)
</p>
      <p>Fields, L.
(
2002
) 
Bringing the Eastern Little Galaxia back to Melbourne
. 
ANGFA
Victoria VICNEWS May

, 
3–4
.
</p>
      <p>Frankenberg, J.
(
1971
) 
Nature conservation in Victoria
. 
Victorian National Parks Association, Melbourne
, 
145
pp.
</p>
      <p>Frankenberg, R.S.
(
1966
a) 
Fishes of the family Galaxiidae
. 
Australian Natural History
, 
15
, 
161
– 
164
.
</p>
      <p>Frankenberg, R.S.
(
1966
b) 
Fishes of the family Galaxiidae
. 

The Fisherman 
NSW
, 
2
, 

20– 
23
.
</p>
      <p>Frankenberg, R.S.
(
1967
) 

The vertebrate fauna of the Bass Strait Islands: 
3
. The galaxiid fishes of Flinders and King Islands

. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria
, 
80
, 
225
– 
228
.
</p>
      <p>Frankenberg, R.S.
(
1968
) 
Two new species of galaxiid fishes from the Lake Pedder region of southern Tasmania
. 
Australian Zoologist
, 
14
, 
268
– 
274
.
</p>
      <p>Frankenberg, R.S.
(
1969
) 
Studies on the evolution of galaxiid fishes with particular reference to the Australian fauna
. 
PhD Thesis, University of Melbourne, Parkville
, 
205
pp.
</p>
      <p>Frankenberg, R.S.
(
1974
) 
Native freshwater fish
. 
In:Williams, W.D.
(Ed.), 
Biogeography and ecology in Tasmania
. 
Monographiae Biolicae
, 
25
, 
113
– 
140
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1007
/ 
978
- 
94
-010- 
2337
- 
5
_ 
6</p>
      <p>Fulton, W.
(
1990
) 
Tasmanian Freshwater Fishes
. 

Fauna of Tasmania handbook no. 
7
.

University of Tasmania, Hobart

, 
80
pp.
</p>
      <p>Galeotti, D.M.
, 
Castalanelli, M.A.
, 
Groth, D.M.
, 
McCullough, C.
&amp; 
Lund, M.A.
(
2015
) 

Genotypic and morphological variation between 
Galaxiella nigrostriata
(Galaxiidae) populations: implications for conservation

. 
Marine and Freshwater Research
, 
66
, 
187
– 
194
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1071
/MF 
13289</p>
      <p>Galeotti, D.M.
, 
McCullough, C.D.
&amp; 
Lund, M.A.
(
2010
) 

Black-stripe minnow 
Galaxiella nigrostriata
(Shipway 
1953
) (Pisces: Galaxiidae), a review and discussion

. 

Journal of the Royal Society of Western 
Australia
, 
93
, 

13– 
20
.
</p>
      <p>Green, R.H.
(
1974
) 

A catalogue of the 
type
material in the Queen Victoria Museum, Launceston

. 
Records of the Queen Victoria Museum
, 
52
, 

1– 
15
.
</p>
      <p>Hammer, M.P.
(
2002
) 

The south east fish inventory: distribution and conservation of freshwater fishes of south east South 
Australia
. 

Native Fish 
Australia
(SA) Inc, Adelaide

, 
53
pp.
</p>
      <p>Hammer, M.P.
(
2009
) 

Status assessment for nationally listed freshwater fishes in south east South 
Australia
during extreme drought, spring 
2008
. 
Report for Department for Environment and Heritage, South Australian Government. Aquasave Consultants, Adelaide
, 
39
pp.
</p>
      <p>Hammer, M.P.
, 
Adams, M.
&amp; 
Foster, R.
(
2012
) 
Update to the catalogue of South Australian freshwater fishes (Petromyzontida &amp; Actinopterygii)
. 
Zootaxa
, 
3593
, 

59– 
74
.
</p>
      <p>Hammer, M.P.
, 
Adams, A.
&amp; 
Hughes, J.M.
(
2013
) 

Chapter 
3
. Evolutionary processes and biodiversity

. 
In
: 
Ecology of Australian Freshwater Fishes
. 
Humphries, P.
&amp; Walker, K. (Eds.), 
CSIRO
Publishing, Collingwood

, pp. 
49–79
.
</p>
      <p>Hammer, M.
, &amp; 
Horne, P.
(
2004
) 
Threatened ecological communities of South Australia’s south-east
. 
Fishes of Sahul
, 
18
(
1
), 
2–7
.
</p>
      <p>Hammer, M.P.
&amp; 
Walker, K.F.
(
2004
) 
A catalogue of South Australian freshwater fishes, including new records, range extensions and translocations
. 

Transactions Royal Society of South 
Australia
, 
128
, 

85– 
97
.
</p>
      <p>Hammer, M.
, 
Wedderburn, S.
&amp; 
van Weenen, J.
(
2009
) 
Action Plan for South Australian Freshwater Fishes
. 

Native Fish 
Australia
(SA), Adelaide, and Department of Environment and Heritage, Adelaide

, 
206
pp.
</p>
      <p>Hanski, I.
(
1998
) 
Metapopulation dynamics
. 
Nature
, 
396
, 

41– 
49
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1038
/ 
23876</p>
      <p>Hardie, S.
, 
Jackson, J.E.
, 
Barmuta, L.A.
&amp; 
White, R.W.G.
(
2006
) 

Status of galaxiid fishes in Tasmania, 
Australia
: conservation listings, threats and management issues

. 
Aquatic Conservation: Marine and Freshwater Ecosystems
, 
16
, 
235
– 
250
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1002
/aqc. 
722</p>
      <p>Hubbs, C.L.
&amp; 
Lagler, K.F.
(
1958
) 
Fishes of the Great Lakes Region
. 
Ann Arbor, University of Michigan, Michigan
, 
213
pp.
</p>
      <p>Humphries, P.
(
1983
) 
Aspects of the biology of the dwarf galaxiid, Galaxiella pusilla (Mack) (Salmoniformes: Galaxiidae)
. 
BSc (Hons) Thesis, Monash University, Clayton
, 
94
pp.
</p>
      <p>Humphries, P.
(
1986
) 

Observations on the ecology of 
Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack) (Salmoniformes: Galaxiidae) in Diamond Creek, Victoria

. 
Proceeding of the Royal Society of Victoria
, 
98
, 
133
– 
137
.
</p>
      <p>Humphries, P.
(
1995
) 

Life history, food and habitat of southern pygmy perch, 
Nannoperca australis
, in the 
Macquarie
River, Tasmania

. 
Marine and Freshwater Research
, 
46
, 

1159– 
1169
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1071
/MF 
9951159</p>
      <p>IUCN
(
2012
) 
IUCN
Red List categories and criteria: version 
3.1
. 
2ndEdition
. 
IUCN
, Gland, 
Switzerland
, 
32
pp.
</p>
      <p>Jackson, P.D.
&amp; 
Davies, J.N.
(
1983
) 
Survey of fish fauna in the Grampians region, south-western Victoria
. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria
, 
95
, 

39– 
51
.
</p>
      <p>Johnson, C.R.
, 
Ratowsky, D.A.
&amp; 
White, R.W.G.
(
1983
) 

Multivariate analysis of the phenotypic relationships of the species of 
Paragalaxias
and 
Galaxias
(Pisces: Galaxiidae) in Tasmania

. 
Journal of Fish Biology
, 
23
, 

49– 
63
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1095-8649.1983
.tb02881.x
</p>
      <p>King, A.J.
, 
Humphries, P.
&amp; 
McCasker, N.G.
(
2013
) 

Chapter 
7
. Reproduction and early life history

. 
In
: 
Ecology of Australian Freshwater Fishes
. 
Humphries, P.
&amp; Walker, K. (Eds.), 
CSIRO
Publishing, Collingwood

, pp. 
159–193
.
</p>
      <p>Klingenberg, C.P.
(
2011
) 
MorphoJ: an integrated software package for geometric morphometrics
. 
Molecular Ecology Resources
, 
11
, 
353
– 
357
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1755
-0998.2010.02924.x
</p>
      <p>Koehn, J.D.
&amp; 
Kennard, M.J.
(
2013
) 

Chapter 
4
. Habitats

. 
In
: 
Ecology of Australian Freshwater Fishes
. 
Humphries, P.
&amp; Walker, K. (Eds.), 
CSIRO
Publishing, Collingwood

, pp. 
81–103
.
</p>
      <p>Koehn, J.D.
&amp; 
Morison, A.K.
(
1990
) 
A review of the conservation status of native freshwater fish in Victoria
. 
Victorian Naturalist
, 
107
, 

5– 
12
.
</p>
      <p>Koehn, J.D.
&amp; 
O’Connor, W.G.
(
1990
) 
Threats to Victorian native fish
. 
Victorian Naturalist
, 
107
, 

5– 
12
.
</p>
      <p>Koehn, J.D.
&amp; 
Raadik, T.A.
(
1991
) 

The Tasmanian mudfish, 
Galaxias cleaveri
Scott, 
1934
, in Victoria

. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society of Victoria
, 
103
(
2
), 
77–86
.
</p>
      <p>Koster, W.
(
1997
) 
A study of the interactions between dwarf galaxias (
Galaxiella pusilla
), southern pygmy perch (
Nannoperca australis
) and eastern gambusia (
Gambusia holbrooki
)
. 
BSc (Hons) Thesis, Deakin University, Clayton
, 
88
pp.
</p>
      <p>Koster, W.
(
2003
) 

Threatened species of the world: 
Galaxiella pusilla
(Mack 
1936
) (Galaxiidae)

. 
Environmental Biology of Fishes
, 
68
, 
268
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1023
/A: 
1027339104903</p>
      <p>Kuiter, R.H.
(
2005
) 
More on dwarf galaxias
. 
Fishes of Sahul
, 
19
, 
160
– 
163
.
</p>
      <p>Kuiter, R.H.
(
2006
) 
Wild Tasmania
. 
Fishes of Sahul
, 
20
, 
202
– 
220
.
</p>
      <p>Kuiter, R.H.
(
2013
) 
Pictorial Guide to Victoria’s Freshwater Fishes
. 
Aquatic Photographics, Seaford
, 
178
pp.
</p>
      <p>Lacey, G.
(
2004
) 
Still Glides the Stream:The Natural History of the Yarra from Heidelberg to Yarra Bend
. 
Australian Scholarly Publishing, Melbourne
, 
281
pp.
</p>
      <p>Lake, J.S.
(
1971
) 

Freshwater Fishes and Rivers of 
Australia
. 
Nelson, Melbourne
, 
61
pp.
</p>
      <p>Lake, J.S.
(
1978
) 
Australian Freshwater Fishes
. 
Nelson, Melbourne
, 
160
pp.
</p>
      <p>Last, P.R.
, 
Scott, E.O.G.
&amp; 
Talbot, F.H.
(
1983
) 
Fishes of Tasmania
. 
Tasmanian Fisheries Development Authority, Hobart
, 
563
pp.
</p>
      <p>Levins, R.
(
1969
) 
Some demographic and genetic consequences of environmental heterogeneity for biological control
. 

Bulletin of the Entomological Society of 
America
, 
15
, 
237
– 
240
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/besa/15.3.237
</p>
      <p>Lieschke, J.A.
, 
Dodd, L.
, 
Stoessel, D.
, 
Raadik, T.A.
, 
Steelcable, A.
, 
Kitchingman, A.
and 
Ramsey, D.
(
2013
a) 
The status of fish populations in Victorian rivers2004–2011
– 
Part A
. Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research Technical Report Series No. 
246
. Department of Environment and Primary Industries, Heidelberg, Victoria, 
147
pp.
</p>
      <p>Lieschke, J.A.
, 
Dodd, L.
, 
Stoessel, D.
, 
Raadik, T.A.
, 
Steelcable, A.
, 
Kitchingman, A.
&amp; 
Ramsey, D.
(
2013
b) 
The status of fish populations in Victorian rivers2004–2011
– 
Part B: Individual basin assessments
. Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research Technical Report Series No. 
247
. Department of Environment and Primary Industries, Heidelberg, Victoria, 
353
pp.
</p>
      <p>Lintermans, M.
(
2013
) 

Chapter 
12
. Conservation and management

. 
In
: 
Ecology of Australian Freshwater Fishes
. 
Humphries, P.
&amp; Walker, K. (Eds.), 
CSIRO
Publishing, Collingwood

, pp. 
283–316
.
</p>
      <p>Littlejohn, P.
(
2001
) 
The Little Aussie battler
. 
Fishes of Sahul
, 
15
, 
803
.
</p>
      <p>Mack, G.
(
1936
) 

Victorian species of the genus 
Galaxias,
with descriptions of two new species

. 
Memoirs of the National Museum Victoria
,
9
, 

98– 
101
.
</p>
      <p>Maderbacher, M.
, 
Bauer, C.
, 
Herler, J.
, 
Postl, L.
, 
Makasa, L.
&amp; 
Sturmbauer, C.
(
2008
) 

Assessment of traditional versus geometric morphometrics for discriminating populations of the 
Tropheus moorii
species complex (Teleostei: Cichlidae), a Lake Tanganyika model for allopatric speciation

. 
Journal of Zoological Systematics and Evolutionary Research
, 
46
, 
153
– 
161
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1439
-0469.2007.00447.x
</p>
      <p>Massola, A.
(
1938
) 
Description of a new species of Galaxia
. 
The Aquarium Journal
, 
11
, 
129
– 
130
.
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
(
1970
) 

The galaxiid fishes of 
New Zealand
. 
Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology
, 
139
, 
341
– 
431
.
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
(
1971
) 

The galaxiid fishes of South 
America
. 
Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society
, 
50
, 

33– 
73
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1096-3642.1971
.tb00751.x
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
(
1973
) 

Limitation of the genus 
Brachygalaxias
Eigenmann, 
1928
(Pisces: Galaxiidae)

. 

Journal of the Royal Society of 
New Zealand
, 
3
, 
193
– 
197
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/03036758.1973.10430601
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
(
1978
a) 

A new genus and species of galaxiid fish from 
Australia
(Salmoniformes: Galaxiidae)

. 

Journal of the Royal Society of 
New Zealand
, 
8
, 
115
– 
124
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/03036758.1978.10419420
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
(
1978
b) 
Sexual dimorphism in an Australian galaxiid
. 
Australian Zoologist
, 
19
, 
309
– 
314
.
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
(
1980
) 
10
Family Galaxiidae Galaxiids

. 
In
: 
McDowall, R.M.
(Ed.), 

Freshwater Fishes of South-eastern 
Australia
. 
Reed Books, Sydney
, pp. 
55–69
.
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
(
1999
) 

Caudal skeleton in 
Galaxias
and allied genera (Teleostei: Galaxiidae)

. 
Copeia
, 
4
, 932

– 
929
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.2307
/ 
1447968</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
(
2000
) 
Biogeography of the southern cool-temperate galaxoid fishes: evidence from metazoan macroparasite faunas
. 
Journal of Biogeography
, 
27
, 

1221– 
1229
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1046
/j. 
1365
-2699.2000.00490.x
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
(
2006
) 
Crying wolf, crying foul, or crying shame: alien salmonids and a biodiversity crisis in the southern cool-temperate galaxioid fishes
? 
Reviews in Fish Biology and Fisheries
, 
16
, 
233
– 
422
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1007
/s 
11160
-006- 
9017
- 
7</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
&amp; 
Burridge, C.P.
(
2011
) 
Osteology and relationships of the southern freshwater lower euteleostean fishes
. 
Zoosystematics and Evolution
, 
87
, 

7– 
185
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1002
/zoos. 
201000020</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
&amp; 
Frankenberg, R.S.
(
1981
) 

The galaxiid fishes of 
Australia
. 
Records of the Australian Museum
, 
33
, 
443
– 
605
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.3853
/j.0067-1975.33.1981.195
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
&amp; 
Fulton, W.
(
1996
) 
Family Galaxiidae
. 
In
: 
McDowall, R.M.
(Ed.), 

Freshwater Fishes of South-eastern 
Australia
. 
Reed books, Sydney
, pp. 
52–77
.
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
&amp; 
Wallis
, G.P.

(
1996
) 

Description and redescription of 
Galaxias
species (Teleostei: Galaxiidae) from Otago and Southland

. 

Journal of the Royal Society of 
New Zealand
, 
26
, 
401
– 
427
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/03014223.1996.9517518
</p>
      <p>McDowall, R.M.
&amp; 
Waters, J.M.
(
2004
) 
Phylogenetic relationships in a small group of diminutive galaxiid fishes and the evolution of sexual dimorphism
. 

Journal of the Royal Society of 
New Zealand
, 
34
, 

23– 
57
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/03014223.2004.9517762
</p>
      <p>Merrick, J.R.
&amp; 
Schmida, G.E.
(
1984
) 
Australian Freshwater Fishes: Biology and Management
. 
J.R. Merrick, North Ryde, N.S.W.
, 
409
pp.
</p>
      <p>Munro, I.S.R.
(
1957
) 

Handbook of Australian fishes. No. 
7
. 
Australian. Fisheries Newsletter
, 
16
, 

15– 
18
.
</p>
      <p>Otto, K.
(
2005
) 
Yarra: A Diverting History of Melbourne's Murky River
. 
Text Publishing, Melbourne
, 
245
pp.
</p>
      <p>Paxton, J.R.
, 
Gates, J.E.
, 
Bray, D.J.
&amp; 
Hoese, D.F.
(
2006
) 
Galaxiinae
. 
InHoese, D.F., Bray, D.J., Paxton, J.R.
, 
Allen, G.R. Fishes.In
: 
Beesley, P.L.
&amp; 
Wells, A.
(Eds.), 

Zoological Catalogue of 
Australia
. Vol. 
35
. Part 
1
.
ABRS
and 
CSIRO
Publishing, Collingwood, pp. 
402–411
.
</p>
      <p>Paxton, J.R.
, 
Hoese, D.F.
, 
Allen, G.R.
&amp; 
Hanley, J.E.
(
1989
) 

Zoological Catalogue of 
Australia
. Volume 
7
. Pisces. Petromyzontidae to Carangidae

. 
Australian Government Publishing Service, Canberra
, 
665
pp.
</p>
      <p>Pen, L.J.
, 
Gill, H.S.
, 
Humphries, P.
&amp; 
Potter, I.C.
(
1993
) 

Biology of the black-stripe minnow 
Galaxiella nigrostriata
, including comparisons with the other two 
Galaxiella
species

. 
Journal of Fish Biology
, 
43
, 
847
– 
863
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1095-8649.1993
.tb01160.x
</p>
      <p>Pollard, J.
(Ed.) (
1980
) 
G.P. Whitley’s Handbook of Australian Fishes
.
Jack Pollard Publishing, North Sydney
, 
629
pp.
</p>
      <p>Ponton, D.
, 
Carassou, L.
, 
Raillard, S.
&amp; 
Borsa, P.
(
2013
) 
Geometric morphometrics as a tool for identifying emperor fish (Lethrinidae) larvae and juveniles
. 
Journal of Fish Biology
, 
83
, 

14– 
27
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/jfb. 
12138</p>
      <p>Presland, G.
(
1994
) 
Aboriginal Melbourne: the Lost Land of the Kulin People
. 
McPhee Gribble Publishers, Ringwood
, 
157
pp.
</p>
      <p>Raadik, T.A.
(
1996
) 
Aquatic fauna survey (fish and decapod crustaceans) of the Hamilton water supply system, Grampians National Park
. Report to the Glenelg Region Water Authority

. 
Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research, Victoria
. 
39
pp.
</p>
      <p>Raadik, T.A.
(
2000
) 
Brief environmental assessment of the Barwon Water Supply Headworks (upper Barwon River)
. 
Report to Water Resource Management Branch, Department of Natural Resources and Environment. Freshwater Ecology, Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research, Victoria
, 
32
pp.
</p>
      <p>Raadik, T.A.
(
2006
). 

Chapter 
13
Freshwater Fishes

. 
In Melbourne’s Wildlife. A Field Guide to the Fauna of Greater Melbourne
. Museum Victoria and 
CSIRO
Publishing, Melbourne

, pp. 
113–148
.
</p>
      <p>Raadik, T.A.
(
2011
) 
Systematic revision of the Mountain Galaxias,
Galaxias olidus 

Günther, 
1866
species complex (Teleostei: Galaxiidae) in eastern 
Australia
. 
PhD Thesis, University of Canberra, Canberra
, 
494
pp.
</p>
      <p>Raadik, T.A.
(
2014
) 

Fifteen from one: a revision of the 
Galaxias olidus
Günther, 
1866
complex (Teleostei, Galaxiidae) in south-eastern 
Australia
recognises three previously described taxa and describes 
12
new species

. 
Zootaxa
, 
3898
(
1
), 
1– 198
.
</p>
      <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3898.1.1
</p>
      <p>Raadik, T.A.
, 
O’Connor, J.P.
&amp; 
Mahoney, J.C.
(
2001
a) 

Fish and decapod crustacean survey, Regional Forest Agreement Process, Victoria – 
1997 to 1999
(North-east, Central Highlands, Gippsland and West RFA Regions)

. 
Summary Report. Report to Department of Natural Resources and Environment, Victoria. Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research, Victoria
, 
53
pp.
</p>
      <p>Raadik, T.A.
, 
O’Connor, J.P.
&amp; 
Mahoney, J.C.
(
2001
b) 

Fish and decapod crustacean survey, Regional Forest Agreement Process, Victoria – 
1997 to 1999
(North-east, Central Highlands, Gippsland and West RFA Regions)

. 
Appendices
. Report to Department of Natural Resources and Environment, Victoria. Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research, Victoria, 
129
pp.
</p>
      <p>Raadik, T.A.
&amp; 
Zampatti, B.
(
1998
) 
An assessment of barriers to fish migration in the lower Dandenong and Eumemmering Creek systems
. 
Report to Melbourne Water. Freshwater Ecology Division, Marine and Freshwater Resources Institute, Melbourne
, 
27
pp.
</p>
      <p>Rohlf, F.J.
(
2013
a) 

tpsDig, digitize landmarks and outlines, version 
2.17
. 
Department of Ecology and Evolution, State University of New York at Stony Brook
.
</p>
      <p>Rohlf, F.J.
(
2013
b) 

tpsUtil, file utility program, version 
1.58
. 
Department of Ecology and Evolution, State University of New York at Stony Brook
.
</p>
      <p>Romanowski, N.
(
2004
) 

Notes on dwarf galaxias 
Galaxiella pusilla
. 
Fishes of Sahul
, 
18
, 

80– 
86
.
</p>
      <p>Saddlier, S.
, 
Jackson, J.
&amp; 
Hammer, M.
(
2010
) 
National recovery plan for the dwarf galaxias
Galaxiella pusilla

. 
Department of Sustainability and Environment, Melbourne
, 
21
pp.
</p>
      <p>Scott, E.O.G.
(
1942
) 

Description of Tasmanian mud trout, 
Galaxias
(
Galaxias
) 
upcheri
sp. nov.: with a note on the genus 
Bachygalaxias
Eigenmann, 
1924
, and its occurrence in 
Australia
. 
Records of the Queen Victoria Museum
, 
1
, 

51– 
57
.
</p>
      <p>Scott, E.O.G.
(
1966
) 
The genera of the Galaxiidae
. 
Australian Zoologist
, 
13
, 
244
– 
258
.
</p>
      <p>Scott, E.O.G.
(
1971
) 

On the occurrence in Tasmania and on Flinders Island of 
Brachygalaxias
Eigenmann, 
1928
(Pisces: Galaxiidae) with descriptions of two new subspecies

. 
Records of the Queen Victoria Museum
, 
37
, 

1– 
14
.
</p>
      <p>Shipway, B.
(
1953
) 

Additional records of fishes occurring in the fresh waters of Western 
Australia
. 
Western Australian Naturalist
, 
3
, 
173
– 
177
.
</p>
      <p>Stokell, G.
(
1945
) 

The systematic arrangement of the 
New Zealand
Galaxiidae. Part I. Generic and subgeneric classification

. 

Transactions of the Royal Society of 
New Zealand
, 
75
, 
124
– 
137
.
</p>
      <p>Stokell, G.
(
1954
) 
Contributions to galaxiid taxonomy
. 

Transactions of the Royal Society of 
New Zealand
, 
82
, 
411
– 
418
.
</p>
      <p>Stoessel, D.
(
2010
) 
Needle in a haystack: assessment of the status of Dwarf Galaxias (Galaxiella pusilla) at six sites in the West Gippsland Region, with reference to a pilot sampling protocol
.

Client report 
2010
/ 
95
prepared for the West Gippsland Catchment Management Authority. Arthur Rylah Institute for Environmental Research, Department of Sustainability and Environment, Heidelberg, Victoria

, 
19
pp.
</p>
      <p>Threatened Species Section
(
2006
) 
Recovery Plan: Tasmanian Galaxiidae2006–2010
. 
Department of Primary Industries, Water, Hobart
, 
85
pp.
</p>
      <p>Tucceri, T.
(
2012
) 

Conservation of 
Galaxiella pusilla
re-visited

. 
Fishes of Sahul
, 
26
(
3
), 
694–700
.
</p>
      <p>Turner, G.F.
(
1999
) 
What is a fish species
? 
Reviews in Fish Biology and Fisheries
, 
9
, 
281
– 
297
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1023
/A: 
1008903228512</p>
      <p>Unmack, P.J.
(
2013
) 

Chapter 
2
. Biogeography

. 
In
: 
Ecology of Australian Freshwater Fishes
. 
Humphries, P.
&amp; Walker, K. (Eds.), 
CSIRO
Publishing, Collingwood

, pp. 
25–48
.
</p>
      <p>Unmack, P.J.
, 
Bagley, J.C.
, 
Adams, M.
, 
Hammer, M.P.
&amp; 
Johnson, J.B.
(
2012
) 

Molecular phylogeny and phylogeography of the Australian freshwater fish genus 
Galaxiella
, with an emphasis on dwarf galaxias (
G. pusilla
)

. 
PLoS ONE
, 
7
, e 
38433
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1371
/journal.pone.0038433
</p>
      <p>Unmack, P.J.
&amp; 
Paras
, G.J.

(
1995
) 
Galaxiella pusilla
: around Melbourne, going, going, nearly gone

. 
Fishes of Sahul
, 
9
, 
398
– 
400
.
</p>
      <p>Vences, M.
, 
Thomas, M.
, 
Bonnett, R.M.
&amp; 
Vieites, D.R.
(
2005
) 

Deciphering amphibian diversity through 
DNA
barcoding: chances and challenges

. 
Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B—Biological Sciences
, 
360
, 

1859– 
1868
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1098
/rstb. 
2005.1717</p>
      <p>Wager, R.
(
1996
) 
Galaxiella pusilla
. 

The 
IUCN
Red List of Threatened Species. Version 
2014.3
. Available from http:// www.iucnredlist.org (accessed
6
December 
2014
)
</p>
      <p>Ward, R.D.
, 
Tyler, S.Z.
, 
Innes, B.H.
, 
Last, P.R.
&amp; 
Herbert, P.D.N.
(
2005
) 
DNA
barcoding Australia’s fish species

.
</p>
      <p>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society Biological Sciences
, 
1462
, 
1847
– 
1857
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1098
/rstb. 
2005.1716</p>
      <p>Waters, J.M.
, 
Lopez, J.A.
&amp; 
Wallis
, G.P.

(
2000
) 

Molecular phylogenetics and biogeography of Galaxiid fishes (Osteichthyes: Galaxiidae): dispersal, vicariance, and the position of 
Lepidogalaxias salamandroides
. 
Systematic Biology
, 
49
, 
777
– 
795
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/ 
106351500750049824</p>
      <p>Westbury, T.
(
1995
) 
Conservation ecology of the dwarf galaxias,
Galaxiella pusilla 
(Galaxiidae), with implications for management
. 
BSc (Hons) Thesis, La Trobe University, Bundoora
, 
84
pp.
</p>
      <p>Whitley, G.P.
(
1939
) 

Studies in ichthyology No. 
12
. 
Records of the Australian Museum
, 
20
, 
264
– 
277
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.3853
/j.0067-1975.20.1939.576
</p>
      <p>Whitley, G.P.
(
1956
a) 

The story of 
Galaxias
. 
Australian Museum Magazine
, 
12
, 

30– 
34
.
</p>
      <p>Whitley, G.P.
(
1956
b) 

List of the native freshwater fishes of 
Australia
. 

Proceedings of the Royal Zoological Society of 
NSW
, 
1954
–55

, 

39– 
47
.
</p>
      <p>Whitley, G.P.
(
1957
) 

The freshwater fishes of 
Australia8
- 
Galaxias
(cont’d)

. 
Australasian Aqualife
, 
2
, 

6– 
8
.
</p>
      <p>Whitley, G.P.
(
1960
) 

Native Freshwater Fishes of 
Australia
. 
Jacaranda, Brisbane
, 
127
pp.
</p>
      <p>Whitley, G.P.
(
1964
) 
Presidential address
. 

A survey of Australian ichthyology. 

Proceedings of the Linnean Society of New South 
Wales
, 
89
, 

11– 
127
.
</p>
      <p>
APPENDIX 
1
.

One-way 
ANOVA
tests for differences in size corrected morphometric characters between eastern and western regions. Significant results after Bonferroni correction are in bold.
</p>
      <p>Character FemalesMalesF
value
P
value 
F
value
P
value
Body depth at vent 3.040.084 12.84&lt;0.001Caudal peduncle length 76.28&lt;0.001
84.30
&lt;0.001Caudal peduncle depth 2.950.088 0.580.448Caudal fin length 5.780.018 0.080.775Pre-dorsal fin length 0.440.509 1.320.254Pre-anal fin length 36.18&lt;0.001
27.76
&lt;0.001Dorsal fin to anal fin setback 79.03&lt;0.001
29.08
&lt;0.001Dorsal fin base length 0.620.433 1.430.234Dorsal fin length 1.210.273 &lt;0.010.971Anal fin length 1.060.305 2.040.157Pectoral fin length 6.190.014 0.450.503Pelvic fin length 30.21&lt;0.001
8.89
0.004Pre-pelvic fin length 46.90&lt;0.001
31.00
&lt;0.001Distance between pelvic and anal fin bases 2.650.106 1.020.316Head width 60.20&lt;0.001
31.07
&lt;0.001Post-orbital head length 20.47&lt;0.001
19.81
&lt;0.001Inter-orbital width 0.520.474 0.180.671Eye diameter 7.460.007 1.580.211Upper jaw length 38.56&lt;0.001
17.89
&lt;0.001Gape width 96.66&lt;0.001
77.67
&lt;0.001Gape depth 19.96&lt;0.001
7.76
0.006Keel length 1.020.315 0.660.420Keel depth 26.46&lt;0.001
12.53
&lt;0.001</p>
      <p>
APPENDIX 
2
.

Summary statistics from habitat assessments at sites where 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella pusilla</tp:taxon-name>
         <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s.s.</named-content>
(‘east’) and 
<tp:taxon-name>Galaxiella toourtkoourt</tp:taxon-name>
(‘west’) were collected between 
2007-2010
.
</p>
      <p>Temperature (o C) Dissolved oxygen (%) pH Conductivity Turbidity Elevation Shading Maximum water depth (m)</p>
      <p>(µS) (NTU) (m) (%)</p>
      <p>EastWestEastWestEastWestEastWestEastWestEastWestEastWestEastWestn52493649524952482341505152515251Minimum 25th percentile5.8 11.05.2 13.818.2 44.520.0 50.35.0 6.45.3 7.236 26794 10131.0 6.01.0 3.88 257 220.0 10.00.0 5.00.1 0.50.1 0.5Mean14.816.356.981.36.67.6708245526.615.75410435.927.01.11.1SE mean Median 75th percentile0.7 14.3 19.60.8 16.8 20.53.8 55.1 68.36.1 77.1 96.10.1 6.6 7.00.1 7.8 8.288 487 959377 1630 29807.1 11.5 29.32.7 11.0 22.94 58 7213 69 1763.7 30.0 60.04.5 10.0 50.00.1 1.0 1.50.1 1.0 2.0</p>
      <p>
maximum 
24.826.9
130.0 263.0 
7.89.3307013620
133.0 96.0 
111376
80.0 100.0&gt;2.0&gt;2.0
</p>
      <p>Clay (%)Silt (%)Sand (%)Gravel (%)Pebble (%)Cobble (%)Boulder (%)CPOM (%)LWD (%)nEast West 52 51East West 52 51East West 52 51East West 52 51East West 52 51East West 52 51East West 52 51East West 52 51East West 52 51Minimum 25th percentile0.0 0.0 10.0 0.00.0 0.0 30.0 25.00.0 0.0 0.0 0.00.0 0.0 0.0 0.00.0 0.0 0.0 0.00.0 0.0 0.0 0.00.0 0.0 0.0 0.00.0 0.0 5.0 0.00.0 0.0 0.0 0.0Mean32.9 33.842.7 43.020.7 17.53.3 2.50.2 2.10.0 2.20.4 2.530.6 25.03.6 1.9SE mean3.3 3.93.0 3.74.2 4.01.3 1.20.2 1.00.0 1.10.3 1.74.1 4.70.6 0.4Median 75th percentile42.5 40.0 50.0 50.050.0 50.0 50.0 50.00.0 0.0 34.0 22.50.0 0.0 0.0 0.00.0 0.0 0.0 0.00.0 0.0 0.0 0.00.0 0.0 0.0 0.020.0 10.0 50.0 40.05.0 0.0 5.0 5.0maximum80.0 100.0100.0 100.0100.0 100.040.0 45.010.0 45.00.0 50.010.0 75.090.0 100.020.0 10.0</p>
      <p>Emergent Floating Submerged Terrestrial exotic Terrestrial native vegetation (%) vegetation (%) vegetation (%) vegetation (%) vegetation (%)</p>
      <p>nEast 52West 51East 52West 51East 52West 51East 52West 51East 52West 51Minimum 25th percentile0.0 23.80.0 15.00.0 0.00.0 0.00.0 0.00.0 0.00.0 0.00.0 0.00.0 5.00.0 0.0Mean45.035.811.23.212.317.21.41.217.17.3SE mean4.34.03.01.32.93.50.40.42.21.7Median 75th percentile35.0 72.525.0 50.00.0 10.00.0 0.00.0 12.55.0 22.50.0 0.00.0 0.015.0 21.30.0 10.0maximum100.0100.080.050.075.090.010.015.065.060.0</p>
   </body>
</article>
