<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112469</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Cytotoxic sesquiterpene lactones from Campuloclinium macrocephalum (=Eupatorium macrocephalum)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Cytotoxic sesquiterpene lactones from 
<tp:taxon-name>Campuloclinium macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>Eupatorium macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
)

M´arcia R. Pereira Cabral a, 
Mariana Cecchetto
b, Jo˜ao M. Batista Jr. c, 
Andrea N.L. Batista
d, 
Mary Ann Foglio
b, 
Ana Lúcia Tasca Gois Ruiz
b, 
Marta R. Barrotto do Carmo
e, 
Willian Ferreira da Costa
a, D´ebora C. Baldoqui a, 
Maria H. Sarragiotto
a, * a Departamento de Química, Universidade Estadual de 

Maring´a, Av. Colombo 5790, 87020-900, 

Maring´a, 
PR
, 
Brazil
b 

Faculdade de 
Ciˆencias Farmacˆeuticas
, Universidade Estadual de Campinas, R. Candido Portinari 200, Cidade 

Universit´aria, 13083871, Campinas, SP, 
Brazil
c 
Instituto de Ciˆencia
e Tecnologia, Universidade Federal de 

S˜ao Paulo, R. Talim 330, 12231-280, 
S˜ao Jose
´dos Campos, SP, 
Brazil
d Instituto de Química, Universidade Federal Fluminense, Outeiro de 

S˜ao 

Jo˜ao Batista s/n, 24020-141, 

Niter´oi, RJ, 
Brazil
e 

Departamento de Biologia Geral, Universidade Estadual de Ponta Grossa, Av. Carlos Cavalcanti, 4748, 84030-910, Ponta Grossa, 
PR
, 
Brazil
ARTICLE INFO
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <p>Keywords:<tp:taxon-name>Campuloclinium macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae Sesquiterpene</tp:taxon-name>
lactones Germacranolide Cytotoxicity ABSTRACT
</p>
         <p>
Three undescribed germacranolide sesquiterpene lactones, named macrocephalides 
A -C
, along with known steroids, triterpenes and flavonoids were isolated from the aerial parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>Campuloclinium macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
.

The structures of the undescribed compounds were elucidated with basis on their 1D and 2D-NMR, and HR-ESI-MS data. Their absolute configurations were assigned by comparison of experimental and calculated electronic circular dichroism (ECD) spectra. Additionally, macrocephalides 
A -C
were evaluated for their 
in vitro
cytotoxic activities against nine human cancer cell lines. Macrocephalides A and B exhibited moderate to potent cytotoxic activity, inhibiting 50% of cell growth (GI50) at concentrations ranging from 0.576 to 6.37 μM. 
1. Introduction</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Campuloclinium macrocephalum
(Less.) DC
</tp:taxon-name>
(synonymy 
<tp:taxon-name>Eupatorium macrocephalum
Less.
</tp:taxon-name>
), belongs to the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
, tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Eupatorieae</tp:taxon-name>
, and is a perennial herb widely distributed in the New World, from 
Mexico
to 
Argentina
(
Cabrera, 1974
). This species originates from South America (
Williams, 1976
; 
Cabrera, 1978
; 
Breedlove, 1986
), being distributed in 
Brazil
, 
Bolivia
, 
Paraguay
, 
Uruguay
and north of 
Argentina
(
Freire, 2008
). The taxon was introduced to 
South Africa
, in the 1970s, where is known as “pompom weed”, and has being described as an invader of grasslands, wetlands and roadsides in several provinces (
Goodall et al., 2010
). On the other hand, this species is reported to be used in Paraguayan folk medicine as anti-inflammatory, sedative and in treatment of cardiac disease (
Gonzalez, 1992
).
</p>
         <p>
The literature reports few studies concerning biological activity and chemical composition of 
<tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
.

In a study conducted by 
Goodall et al. (2010)
the role of its allelopathic effect and competition in invasiveness was investigated using 
<tp:taxon-name>Eragrostis curvula</tp:taxon-name>
(weeping lovegrass, an indigenous grass), 
<tp:taxon-name>E. tef</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Lactuca sativa</tp:taxon-name>
(lettuce) as test species (
Goodall et al., 2010
). Root and shoot extracts of
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
did not inhibit seed germination of any tested species. The antifungal activities of leaf and flower extracts of 
<tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
were evaluated against phytopathogenic fungi (
Mdee et al., 2009
). The leaf extract showed higher activity than that of the extract of flowers, presenting potent activity against 
<tp:taxon-name>Colletotrichum gloeosporioides</tp:taxon-name>
(MIC of 
0.05 mg
mL 
1
).
</p>
         <p>
The chemical studies on 
<tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
, under the synonymy 
<tp:taxon-name>Eupatorium macrocephalum
Less.
</tp:taxon-name>
, reported the isolation and identification of triterpenes, steroids, cinnamic acid derivatives, and flavonoids (
Gonzalez et al., 1972
, 
1973
; 
Vega et al., 2008
). However, to the best of our knowledge, no studies to date have reported the isolation of sesquiterpene lactones from this species. Sesquiterpene lactones (SLs) constitute an important group of specialized products widely distributed in various genus of 
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
, including 
<tp:taxon-name>Eupatorium</tp:taxon-name>
(
Huo et al., 2004
; 
Shen et al., 2005
; 
Zhang et al., 2008
; 
Hensel et al., 2011
; 
Saito et al., 2014
; 
Liu et al., 2015
; 
Wang et al., 2018
; 
Yu et al., 2018
), the genus to which belonged the species 
<tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Eupatorium
species
</tp:taxon-name>
extracts and their isolated sesquiterpene lactones have been reported to exhibit cytotoxic activities against different cancer cell lines (
Huo et al., 2004
; 
Shen et al., 2005
; 
Hensel et al., 2011
; 
Saito et al., 2014
; Yu et al.,
</p>
         <p>
* Corresponding author. 
E-mail address:
mhsarragiotto@uem.br (M.H. Sarragiotto).
</p>
         <p>
https://doi.org/ 
10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112469</p>
         <p>Received 28 March 2020; Received in revised form 27 June 2020; Accepted 23 July 2020</p>
         <p>Available online 14 August 2020</p>
         <p>0031-9422/© 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</p>
         <p>2018).</p>
         <p>Table 1</p>
         <p>
In the present study, three undescribed germacranolide sesquiterpene lactones, named macrocephalides A, B and C (
1–3
), along with known steroids and triterpenes (
4–10
), and the flavonoids taxifolin (
11
) and quercetin-3- 
O -α
-L-rhamnopyranoside-7- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranoside (
12
) were isolated from the aerial parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
. Additionally, the 
in vitro
cytotoxic activities of the germacranolides 
1–3
against nine human cancer cell lines were evaluated. Herein, the isolation, structure elucidation including absolute stereochemistry assignment, and the cytotoxic activities of the undescribed compounds 
1–3
are described.
</p>
         <p>1
H (500 MHz) and 
13
C (125 MHz) NMR data of compounds 
1–3
in CDCl (
δ
in
</p>
         <p>3
ppm, 
J
in Hz).
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>position123δHδCδHδCδHδC1–206.3–206.4–150.726.73,131.16.70,131.15.72, d (5.5)105.4d (12.0)d (11.5)36.29,137.76.29,137.65.87, m117.5d (12.0)d (11.5)4–136.2–136.3–133.655.06,125.75.07,125.64.15, d (9.0)76.6dquintdquint(9.5, 1.0)(9.0, 1.5)66.02, brd75.46.03, brd75.54.93, t (9.0)79.5(9.5)(9.0)72.86, m45.22.88, m44.93.38, m49.285.45, dd75.45.39, dd75.65.87, m75.0(4.0, 3.0)(4.5, 3.0)94.34, t75.54.31,76.54.4, brs80.6(3.0)d (3.0)10–79.9–79.9–74.111–136.0–136.2–134.312–169.8–170.1–168.4136.26,124.26.28,124.16.39, d (3.0)122.9d (1.5)d (1.5)5.75, d (3.0)5.71,5.73,d (1.5)d (1.5)141.65 (s)26.31.61 (s)26.31.30 (s)18.5151.92 (brs)21.81.92 (s)21.82.02 (d, 1.5)19.81′–163.8–163.9–167.52′–127.4–131.0–130.53′6.46, q147.76.30, q143.76.47, q (7.5)143.6(7.5)(7.5)4′2.02,15.82.04, dd15.52.00, d (7.5)15.9d (7.5)(7.0, 1.5)5′4.56,65.44.07,66.04.13,64.1d (12.0)d (11.5)d (11.5)4.91,4.51, dt4.17,d (12.0)(11.5, 1.5)d (11.5)1′′–171.6–2′′2.08 (s)21.1</p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>2. Results and discussion</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>2.1. Isolation and structure elucidation</title>
         <p>
A crude methanol extract of the aerial parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
was subjected to partition into 
n
-hexane, dichloromethane and ethyl acetate. Purification of the dichloromethane fraction on silica gel 
flash
chromatography column afforded compounds 
1–3
(

). The 
n
-hexane fraction yielded known steroids and triterpenes, after purification by CC on silica gel. The compounds were identified as lupeol acetate (
4
), α- amyrin acetate (
5
), β- amyrin acetate (
6
), lupeol (
7
), α- amyrin (
8
), β- amyrin (
9
) and pseudotaraxasterol (
10
) by comparison of their spectroscopic data with those reported (
Mahato and Kundu, 1994
; 
Vega et al., 2008
). Compounds 
4–9
were earlier reported from 
<tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum
(
Vega et al., 2008
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Purification of the ethyl acetate fraction in Sephadex LH-20 afforded the flavonoids taxifolin (
11
) and quercetin-3- 
O -α
-L-rhamnopyranoside-7- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranoside (
12
) (
Agrawal, 1989
).
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
1
, named macrocephalide A, was isolated as an oil with [α] 
D24
117 (
c
0.7, CHCl 
3
). Its molecular formula was determined as C 
22
H 
26
O 
9
based on the protonated molecular ion at 
m/z
435.1651 [M+H] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
27
O 
9m/z
435.1650) in the HR-ESI-MS spectra. The 
1
H-NMR spectrum of 
1
displayed characteristic resonances of an α- methylene-γ- lactone group at 
δH
6.26 (d, 
J
= 1.5 Hz, H-13a) and 
δH
5.71 (d, 
J
= 1.5 Hz, H-13b), three oxymethyne hydrogens at 
δH
6.02 (d, 
J
= 9.5 Hz, H-6), 
δH
5.45 (dd, 
J
= 4.0 and 3.0 Hz, H-8) and 
δH
4.34 (t, 
J
= 3.0 Hz, H-9), and two methyl groups at 
δH
1.65 (14- 
CH3
) and 
δH
1.92 (15- 
CH3
). The 
13
C NMR data confirmed the presence of a α- methyleneγ- lactone moiety (
Table 1
) due the signals at 
δC
136.0 (C-11), 169.8 (C- 12) and 
δC
124.2 (C-13). Among others, the 
13
C NMR spectrum showed signals for a carbonyl group at 
δC
206.3 (C-1), oxygenated carbons at 
δC
75.4 (C-6), 
δC
75.4 (C-8), 
δC
75.5 (C-9) and 
δC
79.9 (C-10) and for methyl groups at 
δC
26.3 (
CH3
-14) and 
δC
21.8 (
CH3
-15). Comparison of these data with those of literature for calealactones A and C indicated that compound 
1
is a germacranolide, containing an α- methylene-γ- lactone group and oxygenated substituents at C-8 and C-9 (
Yamada et al., 2004
; 
Wu et al., 2011
).
</p>
         <p>
Differently from calealactones, compound 
1
showed signals at 
δH
6.29 (d, 
J
= 12.0 Hz, 1H, H-3), 6.73 (d, 
J
= 12.0 Hz, 1H, H-2), correlated in the COSY spectra, and at 5.06 (dquint, 
J
= 9.5 and 1.0 Hz, 1H, H-5), which were consistent with the presence of double bonds between C-2/ C-3 and C-4/C-5 (
Table 1
). The connectivity for germacranolide skeleton was deduced by the COSY correlations between the hydrogens at 
δH
6.73 (H-2) with 
δH
6.29 (H-3), 
δH
5.06 (H-5) with 
δH
6.02 (H-6), 
δH
2.86 (H-7) with 
δH
5.45 (H-8), and at 
δH
5.45 (H-8) with 
δH
4.34 (H-9) (Figures S-9 and S-10, Supporting Information). The 2.4-dienone system was evidenced in the 
13
C NMR spectra by the signals at 
δC
206.3 (C––O), 131.1 (C-2), 137.7 (C-3), 136.2 (C-4) and 125.7 (C-5). The correlations observed in HMBC spectra of H-3 (
δH
6.29) with the carbonyl group (
δC
206.3, C-1), and of H-5 (
δH
5.06) with C-3 (
δC
137.7), corroborated the assignment of carbons and hydrogens of this system (Figures S-7 and S-8, Supporting Information).
</p>
         <p>Fig. 1.
Structures of compounds 
1–3
.
</p>
         <p>
The linkage of the methyl groups to C-4 and C-10 of the germacranolide skeleton was supported by the HMBC correlations of hydrogens at 
δH
1.92 (15- 
CH3
) and 
δH
1.65 (14- 
CH3
) with C-5 (
δC
125.7) and C-1 (
δC
206.3), respectively (

).
</p>
         <p>
The oxymethylene hydrogens at 
δH
4.91 (d, 
J
= 12.0 Hz, H-5 
′
) and 
δH
4.56 (d, 
J
= 12.0 Hz, H-5 
′
), methyl groups at 
δH
2.02 (d, 
J
= 7.5 Hz, H-4 
′
) and 2.08 (s, H-2 
′′
), and an β- hydrogen of a α,β- unsaturated ester group at 
δH
6.46 (q, 
J
= 7.5 Hz, H-3 
′
) could be attributed to the substituent attached to C-8 of the germacranolide skeleton. The carbons at 
δC
163.8 (C-1 
′
), 127.4 (C-2 
′
), 147.7 (C-3 
′
), 
δC
15.8 (C-4 
′
) and 65.4 (C-5 
′
), together with the acetoxy group at 
δC
171.6 (C––O) and 2.02 (
CH3
) evidenced the presence of a 2-acetoxymethyl-2-butenoyl group in compound 
1
. HMBC correlations of H-5’ (
δH
4.91 and 4.56) with the carbonyl groups at 
δC
163.8 (C-1 
′
) and 171.6 (C-1”) confirmed the attachment of the acetoxy group to C-5’. The positioning of this 2-acetoxymethyl-2-butenoyl group at C-8 was deduced from the HMBC correlations of H-6 (
δH
6.02) and H- 8 (
δH
5.45) with the carbons at 
δH
75.4 (C-8) and at 
δC
163.8 (C-1’), respectively.
</p>
         <p>
The NOESY spectra of compound 
1
showed correlation of H-9 (
δH
4.34) with H-14 (
δH
1.65), indicating that H-9 and methyl group at C-10 are in the same face of the molecule. The α- orientation of the hydroxyl groups at C-9 and C-10, and consequent β- orientation of H-9 and methyl group at C-10, were based on NOESY experiment and corroborated by literature for compounds with similar germacranolide skeleton (
Yamada et al., 2004
; 
Wu et al., 2011
).
</p>
         <p>
The geometries of the C-4/C-5 and C-2’/C-3 
′
double bonds were suggested as 
Z
due to the NOESY correlations of H-5 (
δH
5.06) with the methyl group 
CH3
-15 (
δH
1.92), and of H-3 
′
(
δH
6.46) with the methylene hydrogens H-5’ (
δH
4.91; 
δH
4.56), respectively (

). After securing the relative configuration of compound 
1
, comparisons of experimental ECD data with time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) simulated spectra were performed to determine its absolute configuration. The good agreement between observed and calculated (

) data allowed the assignment of ()- 
1
as 6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
R
,10 
R
. The small positive Cotton effect at around 
260 nm
was not reproduced by the calculations due to oppositely signed contributions from different conformers (ESI).
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
2
, macrocephalide B, was isolated as an oil with [α] 
D24</p>
         <p>
150 (
c
0.4, CHCl 
3
). The HR-ESI-MS spectra showed a protonated molecular ion at 
m/z
393.1543 [M+H] 
+
, supporting its molecular formula to be C 
20
H 
24
O 
8
(calcd for C 
20
H 
25
O 

8 
m/z
393.1544). The 
1
H and 
13
C NMR data of 
2
showed a close structural resemblance to that of 
1
, except for the absence of signals for the acetoxy group [
δH
2.08 (H-2 
′′
), 
δC
21.1 (C-2 
′′
) and 
δC
171.6 (C-1 
′′
)] and its replacement by a hydroxyl group, as evidenced by the shielding of H-5’ signals, which appear at 
δH
4.07 and 4.51 for 
2
, and at 
δH
4.56 and 4.91 for compound 
1
. Based on these data, the substituent at C-8 of compound 
2
was determined to be the 2- hydroxymethyl-2-butenoyl, which was confirmed by the signals at 
δC
163.9 (C = 0), 
δC
131.0 (C-2 
′
), 
δC
143.7 (C-3 
′
), 
δC
15.5 (C-4 
′
) and 
δC
66.0 (C-5 
′
) in the 
13
C NMR spectra. These findings were consistent with the difference of 42 units in the protonated ion molecular of 
2
(
m/z
393.1544 [M+H] 
+
) compared to that of compound 
1
(
m/z
435.1651 [M+H] 
+
) (Figure S-12, Supporting Information). The position of the 2- hydroxymethyl-2-butenoyl group at C-8 was confirmed by HMBC correlations (Figures S-17 and S-18, Supporting Information) of H-8 (
δH
5.39) with C-1’ (
δC
163.9) (

).
</p>
         <p>
The NOESY correlations of compound 
2
(Figure S-21, Supporting Information) were similar as those observed for compound 
1
, which supported the same relative configuration for both compounds. The very good correlation between experimental and calculated ECD data for ()- 
2
(

) led to the assignment of its absolute configuration as 6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
R
,10 
R
. In the case of compound 
2
, even the small positive Cotton effect at around 
260 nm
was correctly reproduced by quantum chemical calculations.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
3
, named macrocephalide C, was obtained as an oil, with [α] 
D24
100 (
c
0.2, CHCl 
3
). Its molecular formula, C 
20
H 
24
O 
8
, was deduced from the protonated molecular ion at 
m/z
393.1540 [M+H] 
+
(calcd for C 
20
H 
25
O 
8m/z
393.1544) in the HR-ESI-MS, and from its 
13
C NMR data.
</p>
         <p>
Compound 
3
exhibited the same molecular formula as that of 
2
, which suggested that both compounds have similar structural features. Comparison of NMR spectroscopic data of 
3
with those of compounds 
1
and 
2
(
Table 1
) revealed that 
3
also possesses an α- methylene-γ- lactone moiety due to the signals at 
δC
168.4 (C––O), 
δC
134.3 (C-11), and at 
δH
6.39 (d, 
J
= 3.0 Hz, H-13a) and 5.75 (d, 
J
= 3.0 Hz, H-13b), both correlated with C-13 (
δC
122.9) in the HMBC spectra. This comparison permitted also to evidence the presence of a 2-hydroxymethyl-2-butenoyl group, as in compound 
2
, from the signals at 
δH
6.47 (H-3 
′
), 
δH
2.00 (H-4 
′
) and 
δH
4.13 and 4.17 (H-5’), together with those at 
δC
167.5 (C––O, C-1 
′
), 130.5 (C-2 
′
) and 143.6 (C-3 
′
). The HMBC correlations (Figures S-27, S-28, and S-29, Supporting Information) of the signals at 
δH
2.00 (H-4 
′
), 
δH
4.13 and 4.17 (H-5 
′
) with C-2’ (
δC
130.5), and 
δH
6.47 (H-3 
′
) with C-5’ (
δC
64.1) confirmed the assignments of chemical shifts for this group. Despite some structural similarity of 
3
when compared to 
1
and 
2
, significant differences were observed in its NMR data concerning the germacranolide skeleton. The main differences were the absence of the resonances for the carbonyl group at C-1 and for hydrogens and carbons of the conjugated double bonds between C-2/C-3 and C-4/C-5, which suggests a modification in the germacranolide skeleton at positions C-1 to C-5 for compound 
3
. This proposal was corroborated by the presence of unexpected signals of a quaternary carbon at 
δC
150.7 and of two carbons of the double bond at 
δC
105.4 and 117.5, which are correlated, respectively, to the hydrogens at 5.72 (d, 5.5 Hz, H-2) and 5.87 (m, H-3) in the HSQC spectra. Also, the NMR spectra of 
3
showed signals for four oxymethine groups [
δH
4.15/ 
δC
76.6; 
δH
4.41/ 
δC
80.6; 
δH
4.93/ 
δC
79.5 and 
δH
5.87/ 
δC
75.0], while three oxymethine carbons were present in the structures of the compounds 
1
and 
2
. These data suggested the presence of an oxygen bridge between C-1 and C-5, with a
</p>
         <p>Fig. 2.
Selected HMBC and COSY correlations of compounds 

1– 
3
.
</p>
         <p>Fig. 4.
(Left) Comparison of experimental UV and ECD spectra of ()- 
1
(black) with calculated (CAM-B3LYP/PCM(MeOH)/TZVP, red) spectra for (6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
R
,10 
R
)- 
1
. (Right) Optimized structures, relative energies and Boltzmann populations of the lowest-energy conformers identified for (6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
R
,10 
R
)- 
1
at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.)
</p>
         <p>
formation of a six membered ring, which was confirmed by the HMBC correlations between the signals at 
δH
5.72 (H-2), 5.87 (H-3) and 
δH
4.15 (H-5) with 
δC
150.7 (C-1); 
δH
5.72 (H-2) with 
δC
133.6 (C-4); 
δH
4.15 (H- 5) with 
δC
117.5 (C-3) and 133.6 (C-4). The oxymethyne carbon at 
δC
76.6 was assigned to C-5 from the correlation to 
δH
4.15 (H-5) in HSQC spectra. Further analysis of COSY and HMBC data permitted to complete the assignment of the hydrogens and carbons for germacranolide skeleton of 
3
. The oxymethyne at 
δH
4.93/ 
δC
79.5 was assigned to H-6/C-6 from the COSY and HMBC correlations of 
δH
4.93 with H-5 (
δH
4.15) and with C-5 (
δC
76.6), respectively. The assignments of H-7/C-7 were supported from the COSY correlations (Figures S-30, S-31, and S-32, Supporting Information) of the hydrogen at 
δH
3.38 (H-7) with 
δH
4.93 (H-6) and at long-range with 
δH
6.39 and 5.75 (H-13), together with HSQC correlation between H-7 and the carbon at 
δH
49.2 (C-7). The oxymethynes at 
δH
5.87/ 
δC
75.0 and 
δH
4.41/ 
δC
80.6 were assigned to H- 8/C-8 and H-9/C-9, respectively, based on HMBC correlation of the signal at 
δH
5.87 (H-8) with C-6 (79.5), and at 
δH
1.30 (
CH3
-14) with the signal at 
δC
80.6. The HMBC correlation from H-2 and H-8 to the quaternary carbon at 
δC
74.1 evidenced this carbon as C-10. The HMBC correlation of the methyl hydrogens at 
δH
1.30 (14- 
CH3
) with the carbon C-1 confirmed the assignment and positioning of this group at C-10 (
δC
74.1). The H-8 and H-14 hydrogens were correlated with the oxygenated carbons at 
δC
80.6 (
CH
) and 
δC
74.1 (C 
0
) in the HMBC spectra, confirming the assignment of these signals to C-9 and C-10, respectively. HMBC correlations of the methyl group at 
δH
2.02 (15- 
CH3
) with C-5 confirmed the attachment of this group at C-4. Finally, the positioning of the 2-hydroxymethyl-2-butenoyl group at C-8 was established by the correlation of H-8 (
δH
5.87) with the carbonyl carbon C-1’ (
δC
167.5).
</p>
         <p>Fig. 5.
(Left) Comparison of experimental UV and ECD spectra of ()- 
2
(black) with calculated (CAM-B3LYP/PCM(MeOH)/TZVP, red) spectra for (6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
R
,10 
R
)- 
2
. (Right) Optimized structures, relative energies and Boltzmann populations of the lowest-energy conformers identified for (6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
R
,10 
R
)- 
2
at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the Web version of this article.)
</p>
         <p>
The NOESY spectra of compound 
3
showed correlation of and H-7 (
δH
3.38, m) with H-5 (
δH
4.15) and H-9 (
δH
4.41) (

). The correlations between H-3’ (
δH
6.47) and H-5’ (
δH
4.13; 4.17) indicated a 
Z
configuration for the C-2’/C-3’ double bond, as observed for compounds 
1
and 
2
. In order to determine the absolute configuration of 
3
, comparisons of experimental and simulated ECD spectra were performed. The excellent agreement between the ECD spectra obtained for ()- 
3
in

methanol with that simulated for the 5 
R
,6 
S
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
S
,10 
R
configuration at the CAM-B3LYP/PCM(MeOH)/TZVP level (

) allowed the assignment of ()- 
3
as 5 
R
,6 
S
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
S
,10 
R
.
</p>
         <p>
Macrocephalide C (
3
) contains an undescribed 
type
of germacranolide skeleton, and a proposed pathway for its formation is shown in 

. The suggested pathway was based in the UHPLC-HRMS/MS analysis of the dichloromethane fraction, from which 
3
was isolated. From this analysis, a peak was observed for a protonated ion at 
m/z
411.1646 [M+H] 
+
with the same fragmentation pattern as that of compounds 
1
and 
2
, which is consistent with the structure of the
</p>
         <p>
proposed precursor for 
3
. The opening of epoxide ring of the precursor followed by intramolecular cyclization, and subsequent water elimination, provided compound 
3
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>2.2. Antiproliferative activity</title>
         <p>
Following the protocol developed by the National Cancer Institute for antiproliferative screening of new anticancer drugs (
Fouche et al., 2008
; 
National Cancer Institute, 2015
), we evaluated the antiproliferative potential of the isolated germacranolides 
1–3
, against a panel of human tumor and non-tumor cell lines. According to this protocol, the concentration required to inhibit 50% of cell growth (GI 
50
) was calculate for each cell line to express the cytostatic effect of each sample.
</p>
         <p>
Compounds activities were classified considering the GI 
50
value expressed as logarithm following the NCI’ s criteria for weak (1.1 
&lt;
log GI 
50&lt;
1.5), moderate (0 
&lt;
log GI 
50&lt;
1.1) and potent (log GI 
50&lt;
0) activities (
Fouche et al., 2008
). Besides, considering the cytostatic effect on immortalized keratinocytes HaCaT, we calculated the selectivity index (SI) that relates the concentration required to inhibit 50% of HaCaT proliferation and that required for one tumor cell line, in the same experiment. This parameter allows presuming whether sample would affect normal proliferative tissues (
Muller and Milton, 2012
).
</p>
         <p>
The macrocephalides A (
1
) and B (
2
) exhibited moderate to potent antiproliferative profile, inhibiting 50% of cell growth (GI 
50
) at concentrations ranging from 0.576 to 6.37 μM (
Table 2
). Macrocephalide A (
1
) inhibited more selectively the growth of melanoma (UACC-62, GI 
50
= 0.576 μM, SI = 1.8) and kidney (786–0, GI 
50
= 0.576 μM, SI = 1.8) tumor cells while compound 
2
showed higher activity for adenocarcinoma ovarian cells (OVCAR-03, GI 
50
= 0.637 μM, SI = 6.3). Compound 
3
was the least active weakly inhibiting renal (786–0, GI 
50
= 10.3 μM, SI = 6.2), leukemic (K562, GI 
50
= 14.6 μM, SI = 4.4), ovarian (OVCAR-03, GI 
50
= 15.7 μM, SI = 4.1) and melanoma (UACC-62, GI 
50
= 22.3 μM, SI = 2.9) cell lines (
Table 2
). Considering their molecular structure, the macrocyclic nuclei in macrocephalides A and B seemed to be important for the antiproliferative activity while the substituents modulated this activity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>3. Conclusion</title>
         <p>
In summary, phytochemical investigation on 
<tp:taxon-name>Campuloclinium macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
resulted in the isolation of three undescribed germacranolide sesquiterpene lactones (
1–3
), along with known steroids and triterpenes (
4–10
), and the flavonoids taxifolin (
11
) and quercetin-3- 
O -α
-L-rhamnopyranoside-7- 
O -β
-D-glucopyranoside (
12
). Antiproliferative assays showed that compound 
1
inhibited more selectively the growth of
</p>
         <p>
melanoma (UACC-62, GI 
50
= 0.576 μM, SI = 1.8) and kidney (786–0, GI 
50
= 0.576 μM, SI = 1.8) tumor cells, and compound 
2
showed higher activity for adenocarcinoma ovarian cells (OVCAR-03, GI 
50
= 0.637 μM, SI = 6.3). Our findings corroborate the properties of SLs as antitumor compounds, and may also to contributes with their ecological roles, since that the effect of 
<tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
against phytopathogenic fungi are already described.
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Human Cell lineDoxorubicin a123GI b 50log GI c 50SI dGI b 50log GI c 50SI dGI b 50log GI c 50SI dGI b 50log GI c 50SI dU2510.09 ± 0.031.05.25.76*0.70.26.37*0.80.661.5 ± 10.31.81.0UACC-62&lt;
0.046
&lt;
-1.4
&gt;
12.4
0.576*0.21.8n.t.n.t.n.c.22.3 ± 10.91.32.9MCF-7&lt;
0.046
&lt;
-1.3
&gt;
10.0
1.5 ± 0.70.20.73.5 ± 0.90.51.155.8 ± 0.51.71.1NCI-ADR/RES0.46 ± 0.010.31.01.1 ± 0.50.070.91.6 ± 0.30.22.691.0 ± 36.62.00.7786-O&lt;
0.046
&lt;
-1.3
&gt;
10.0
0.576*0.21.81.2 ± 0.50.13.410.3 ± 0.41.06.2NCI–H460&lt;
0.046
&lt;
-1.3
&gt;
10.0
5.76*0.80.26.37*0.80.663.7*1.81.0OVCAR-030.46*0.31.05.76*0.80.20.637*0.26.315.7 ± 3.41.24.1HT290.77 ± 0.160.10.62.3 ± 0.60.40.54.7 ± 0.60.70.963.7*1.81.0K5620.46*0.31.05.76*0.80.26.37*0.80.614.6 ± 3.01.24.4HaCaT0.46*0.3 Pn.a.1.05 ± 0.090.02n.a.4.0 ± 0.50.6n.a.63.7*1.8n.a.</p>
      <p>*approximated value; n.t.: not tested; n.c.: not calculated; n.a.: not applied. Human tumor cell lines: U251 (glioblastoma); UACC-62 (melanoma); MCF-7 (breast, adenocarcinoma); NCI-ADR/RES (ovary, multi-drug resistant adenocarcinoma); 786–0 (kidney, adenocarcinoma); NCIH460 (lung, large cell carcinoma), OVCAR-03 (ovary, adenocarcinoma), HT-29 (colon, adenocarcinoma), K562 (chronic myeloid leukemia). Human non-tumor cell lines: HaCaT (immortalized keratinocyte).</p>
      <p>a
Doxorubicin: chemotherapeutic drug.
</p>
      <p>b
GI: Growth Inhibition 50, expressed in μM followed by standard error, calculated by sigmoidal regression using Origin 8.0 software.
</p>
      <p>50c
log GI: results expressed as logarithm and classified according to b NCI’ s criteria (weak activity:1.1 
&lt;
log GI 
&lt;
1.5; moderate activity:0 
&lt;
log GI 
&lt;
1.1; potent 
505050
activity: log GI 
50&lt;
0).
</p>
      <p>d SI: selectivity index calculated as GI /GI.</p>
      <p>50 HaCaT 50 Tumor cell line</p>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4. Experimental section</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4.1. General experimental procedures</title>
         <p>Optical
rotations were measured at 24 
◦
C on a 
PerkinElmer Model
343 polarimeter. 1D and 2D NMR spectra were recorded in CD 
3
OD, DMSO 
‑d6
and CDCl 
3
in

a 
Bruker
500 MHz NMR instrument (
Avance
500). 
High-resolution
mass spectra were obtained in a QTOF, 
Bruker Daltonics
, model 
Impact II
spectrometer in electrospray ionization. C18 columns (75 × 2.0 mm i.d.; 1.6 μm 
Shim-pack
XR-ODS III) were used for UHPLC separation using a 
Shimadzu
, model 
Nexera X
2. 
Silica
gel 60 (
0.063–0.200
mm) and silica gel 60 (
0.04–0.063 mm
) were used for purification of the compounds. TLC was performed on normal phase precoated silica gel 60 G or 60 GF 
254
(
Merck
) plates. 
The UV
and ECD spectra of 
1–3
were recorded with a 
Jasco
J-815 spectrometer (
Jasco
, 
Tokyo
, 
Japan
) in the 
195–400 nm
region using the following parameters: bandwidth 
1 nm
; 25 response 1 s; scanning speed 
100 nm
min 
1
; 3 accumulations; room temperature; sample in methanol solution; 
0.1 cm
cell path length; concentration 
0.2 mg
mL 
1
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4.2. Plant material</title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Campuloclinium macrocephalum
(Less.) DC.
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Regina Barrotto</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Cytotoxic sesquiterpene lactones from Campuloclinium macrocephalum (=Eupatorium macrocephalum)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112469</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C97ED8295946053EFFDEE236A81FFFB7</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112469</pub-id>
               <source>Phytochemistry</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Campuloclinium macrocephalum
(Less.) DC.
</tp:taxon-name>
, Asteraceae,
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>The plant material (aerial parts) of</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
was collected in 
Campos Gerais
National Park

(

25 
◦
08 
′
46 
′′
S

, 

049 
◦
057 
′
025 
′′
W

), 
Parana´State
, 
Brazil
on 
March 2012
and identified by 

Dr. Marta 
<tp:taxon-name>Regina Barrotto</tp:taxon-name>
do Carmo

(
Departamento de Biologia Geral
, 
Universidade Estadual de Ponta Grossa
). A voucher specimen (
HUPG, 18905
) has been deposited at the at the 
HUPG
herbarium
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4.3. Extraction and isolation</title>
         <p>
The air-dried powder of aerial parts of 
<tp:taxon-name>C. macrocephalum</tp:taxon-name>
(
698.9 g
) was extracted with methanol (2 × 2.5 L), at room temperature, and the solvent evaporated under vacuum. The methanol extract (
17 g
) was dissolved in methanol: water (50:50) and partitioned into 
n
-hexane, dichloromethane and ethyl acetate. Evaporation of the solvents resulted in the 
n
-hexane (CM-HF, 
4.95 g
), dichloromethane (CM-DF, 
2.33 g
), ethyl acetate (CM-EAF, 
2.15 g
) and aqueous-methanol (CM-AMF, 
7.14 g
) fractions. Part of the dichloromethane fraction (
931 mg
) was subjected to silica gel column chromatography using a gradient solvent system of 
n
-hexane-acetone (98:2 to 0:100) to afford the subfractions CM-DF.1 to CM-DF.11. Purification of subfraction CM-DF.8 (
277 mg
) on silica gel 
flash
CC, using a mixture of 
n
-hexane acetone (95:5 to 10:90) and acetone as eluent, afforded compounds 
1
(
5 mg
) and 
2
(
5 mg
). Another part of the dichloromethane fraction (
450 mg
) was subjected to silica gel CC using a gradient solvent system of 
n
-hexane-acetone (98:2 to 0:100), to afford subfractions CM-DF.1 to CM-DF.11. Purification of CM-DF.5 (
32 mg
) on Sephadex LH-20, using methanol/water (50:50) gave compound 
3
(
8 mg
). The hexane fraction was subjected to silica gel CC eluted with a mixture of 
n
-hexane/ethyl acetate (95:5 to 10:90), to afford the subfractions CM-HF.1 to CM-HF.10. The subfractions CM- HF.3 and CM-HF.4 provided, respectively, a mixture of 
4
, 
5
and 
6
(
48.1 mg
) and 
7
, 
8
, 
9
and 
10
(
50.1 mg
). The ethyl acetate fraction was subjected to purification in Sephadex LH-20 eluted with a mixture of methanol/water (10:90 to 90:10), to afford the subfractions CM-AEF.1 to CM-AEF.7. The subfraction CM-FAE.6 afforded compound 
11
(
5 mg
). Part of methanol-aqueous fraction (
1.2 g
) was subjected to filtration in Sephadex LH-20 using methanol/water (10:90 to 90:10) to afford the subfractions CM-AMF.1 to CM-AMF.7. Purification of subfraction CM-AMF.2 (
60 mg
) by Sephadex LH-20 using a mixture of methanol/ water (50:50) afforded compound 
12
(
3 mg
).
</p>
         <p>Macrocephalide A
(
1
): [α] 
D24
= 117 (
c
0.7, chloroform) 
1
H and 
13
C NMR see 
Table 1
; HR-ESI-MS 
m/z
435.1651 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
22
H 
27
O 
9
, 435.1650).
</p>
         <p>Macrocephalide B
(
2
): [α] 
D24
= 150 (
c
0.4, chloroform) 
1
H and 
13
C NMR see 
Table 1
; HR-ESI-MS 
m/z
393.1543 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
20
H 
25
O 
8
, 393.1544).
</p>
         <p>Macrocephalide C
(
3
): [α] 
D24
= 100 (
c
0.2, chloroform) 
1
H and 
13
C NMR see 
Table 1
; HR-ESI-MS 
m/z
393.1540 [M + H] 
+
(calcd for C 
20
H 
25
O 
8
, 393.1544).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4.4. Calculations of ECD spectra</title>
         <p>
All density functional theory (DFT) and time-dependent-DFT (TDDFT) calculations were carried out at 298 K in the gas phase with Gaussian 09 software (
Frisch et al., 2009
). Calculations were performed for the arbitrarily chosen (6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
R
,10 
R
)- 
1
, (6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
R
,10 
R
)- 
2
and (5 
R
,6 
S
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
S
,10 
R
)- 
3
. Conformational searches were carried out at the molecular mechanics level of theory with the Monte Carlo algorithm employing the MM + force field incorporated in HyperChem 8.0.10 software package. Initially, 100 conformers of (6 
R
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
R
, 10 
R
)- 
1
with relative energy (rel E.) within 10 kcal mol 
1
of the lowest-energy conformer were selected and further geometry optimized at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level. The six conformers with rel E. 
&lt;
2.5 kcal mol 
1
, which corresponded to more than 93% of the total Boltzmann distribution, were selected for UV and ECD spectral calculations. As for 
2
, the same six lowest-energy conformers identified for 
1
were selected. Then, their acetate group at C-5’ was replaced with a hydroxyl group, followed by further geometry optimization at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level resulting in four conformers with rel E. within 2.0 kcal mol 
1
. Regarding 
3
, 56 conformers of (5 
R
,6 
S
,7 
S
,8 
S
,9 
S
,10 
R
)- 
3
with rel E. within 10 kcal mol 
1
of the lowest-energy conformer were selected and further geometry optimized at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level. The ten conformers with rel E. 
&lt;
1.3 kcal mol 
1
, which corresponded to more than 82% of the total Boltzmann distribution, were selected for UV and ECD spectral calculations. Vibrational analysis at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level resulted in no imaginary frequencies for all conformers, confirming them as real minima. TDDFT was employed to calculate the excitation energy (in nm) and rotatory strength 
R
in the dipole velocity (
Rvel
in cgs units: 10 
40
esu 
2
cm
2
) form, at the CAM-B3LYP/PCM(MeOH)/TZVP level. The calculated rotatory strengths from the first 30 singlet → singlet electronic transitions were simulated into an ECD curve using Gaussian bands with a bandwidth of σ 0.25 eV. The predicted wavelength transitions were used without any scaling. The Boltzmann factor for each conformer was calculated based on Gibbs free energies.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4.5. Antiproliferative assay</title>
         <p>
The antiproliferative activities of compounds 
1
, 
2
and 
3
were evaluated 
in vitro
against nine different human cancer cell lines [U251 (glioma), UACC-62 (melanoma), MCF-7 (breast), NCI/ADR-RES (ovarian expressing multiple-drug-resistance phenotype), 786–0 (renal), NCI–H460 (non-small cell lung cancer), OVCAR-3 (ovarian), HT-29 (colon) and K562 (leukemia)]. The tumor cell lines were provided by Frederick Cancer Research &amp; Development Center, National Cancer Institute, Frederick, MA, 
USA
. The antiproliferative activities were also evaluated using a non-tumor cell line HaCat (human keratinocyte), provided by Dr. Ricardo Della Coletta (University of Campinas- UNI- CAMP, 
Brazil
). Stock and experimental cultures were grown in complete medium containing 5 mL RPMI 1640 (GIBCO BRL) supplemented with 5% fetal bovine serum (GIBCO BRL) and 1% Penicillin:Streptomycin mixture (1000 U.mL 
1
:1000 μg.mL 
1
). The sample were previously diluted in DMSO (
100 mg
⋅mL 
1
) followed by serial dilution in complete medium, affording the final concentrations of 0.576, 5.76, 57.6 and 576 μM for compound 
1
, and 0.637, 6.37, 63.7 and 637 μM for compounds 
2
and 
3
. Cells in 96-well plates (100 μL cells well 
1
, inoculation density: 3.5 to 6 x 
104
cell⋅mL 
1
, Table S4, in Supplementary material) were exposed to sample for 48 h, in triplicate, at 37 
◦
C, 5% of CO 
2
in

air. The final DMSO concentration (
&lt;
0.25%) did not affect cell viability. Doxorubicin (0.046–0.46 μM) was used as positive control. Before (T 
0
plate) and after the sample addition (T 
1
plates), cells were fixed with 50% trichloroacetic acid, and cell proliferation was determined by spectrophotometric quantification (
540 nm
) of cellular protein using the sulforhodamine B assay. Cell proliferation was calculated considering (T 
1
- T 
0
) as representing 100% of cell growth when absorbance of treated cells (TS) was higher than T 
0
absorbance; more, when absorbance of treated cells (TS) was lower than T 
0
absorbance, 100% of cell growth was represented by T 
0
. For each sample, one concentration–response curve correlating sample concentration with cell growth was plotted using the software ORIGIN 8.0® (OriginLab Corporation) (
Monks et al., 1991
). The Selectivity Index (SI) was estimated as SI = GI 
50
(HaCat)/GI 
50
(- cancer cell line) (
Muller and Milton, 2012
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Declaration of competing interest</title>
         <p>The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgments</title>
         <p>The authors thank Coordenaçao˜de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de</p>
         <p>
Nível Superior (CAPES, 
Brazil
, Finance code 001) and Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnol´ogico (CNPq, 
Brazil
) for financial support. JMBJ thanks Fundaç˜ao de Amparo a`Pesquisa do Estado de Sao˜Paulo (FAPESP) for funding (grant# 2014/25222–9). This work was supported by the Complexo de Central de Apoio`a Pesquisa (COMCAP) from the Universidade Estadual de Maringa´(UEM). This research was also supported by resources supplied by the Centre for Scientific Computing (NCC/GridUNESP) of São Paulo State University (UNESP).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Appendix A. Supplementary data</title>
         <p>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at https:// doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2020.112469.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Agrawal, P.K.
, 
1989
. 
Carbon-13 NMR of Flavonoids
, 
Studies in Organic Chemistry
, vol. 
39
. Elsevier Science, p. 
39
.
</p>
         <p>Breedlove, D.E.
, 
1986
. 
Listados Florísticos de M´exico
, vol. 
4
, pp. 
1–246
.
</p>
         <p>Cabrera, A.L.
, 
1974
. 
Flora Ilustrada de Entre Rios
, vol. 
6
, pp. 
106–540
.
</p>
         <p>Cabrera, A.L.
, 
1978
. 
Flora de la provincia de Jujuy (Compositae). Coleccion´Científica
. 
Inst Nal Tec Agr13
(
10
), 
1–726
.
</p>
         <p>Fouche, G.
, 
Cragg, G.M.
, 
Pillay, P.
, 
Kolesnikova, N.
, 
Maharaj, V.J.
, 
Senabe, J.
, 
2008
. 
In vitro
anticancer screening of South African plants

. 
J. Ethnopharmacol.28
(
119
), 
455–461
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jep.2008.07.005
.
</p>
         <p>Freire, S.E.
, 
2008
. 
Tribu Eupatorieae (Asteraceae)
. In: 
Zuloaga, F.O.
, 
Morrone, O.
, 
Belgrano, M.
(Eds.), 
Cat´alogo de las Plantas Vasculares del Cono Sur de Am´erica del Sur: Argentina, Sur de Brasil (Paran´a, Santa Catarina y Rio Grande do Sul), Chile, Paraguay y Uruguay
. 
Monographs in Systematic Botany from the Missouri Botanical Garden, vol
. 
114
, pp. 
1277–1302
.
</p>
         <p>Frisch, M.J.
, 
Trucks, G.W.
, 
Schlegel, H.B.
, et al., 
2009
. 
Gaussian 09, Revision A.02.Gaussian, Inc., Wallingford CT
.
</p>
         <p>Gonzalez, T.D.
, 
1992
. 
Cat´alogo de plantas medicinais usadas no Paraguay
. 
Comuneros, Asunci´on
.
</p>
         <p>Gonzalez, A.G.
, 
Bermejo, J.
, 
Breton, J.L.
, 
Massanet, G.M.
, 
1972
. 

Chemistry of the compositae. XI. 
Eupatorium macrocephalum
less

. 
An. Quim. Int. Ed.68
(
3
), 
319–323
.
</p>
         <p>Gonzalez, A.G.
, 
Bermejo, J.
, 
Massanet, G.M.
, 
1973
. 

Chemistry of the compositae. XIV. Flavonoids of 
Eupatorium macrocephalum
Less

. 
An. Quim.69
(
2
), 
229–234
.
</p>
         <p>Goodall, J.
, 
Witkowski, E.T.F.
, 
Ammann, S.
, 
Reinhardt, C.
, 
2010
. 

Does allelopathy explain the invasiveness of 
Campuloclinium macrocephalum
(pompom weed) in the South African grassland biome? Biol

. 
Invasions12
, 
3497–3512
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s10530-010-9747-2
.
</p>
         <p>Hensel, A.
, 
Maas, M.
, 
Sendker, J.
, 
Lechtenberg, M.
, 
Petereit, F.
, 
Deters, A.
, 
Schmidt, T.
, 
Stark, T.
, 
2011
. 
Eupatorium perfoliatum
L.: phytochemistry, traditional use and current Applications. J

. 
Ethnopharmacol.138
, 
641–651
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j. jep.2011.10.002
.
</p>
         <p>Huo, J.
, 
Yang, S.P.
, 
Ding, J.
, 
Yue, J.M.
, 
2004
. 

Cytotoxic sesquiterpene lactones from 
Eupatorium lindleyanum
. 
J. Nat. Prod.67
, 
1470–1475
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np040023h
.
</p>
         <p>Liu, P.Y.
, 
Liu, D.
, 
Wei-Huan Li, W.
, 
Zhao, T.
, 
Sauriol, F.
, 
Gu, Y.
, 
Shi, W.
, 
Zhang, M.
, 
2015
. 

Chemical constituents of plants from the genus 
eupatorium
(1904–2014)

. 

C 
hem.Biodivers.12
, 
1481–1514
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/cbdv.201400227
.
</p>
         <p>Mahato, S.B.
, 
Kundu, A.P.
, 
1994
. 
13C NMR spectra of pentacyclic triterpenoids-a compilation and some salient features
. 
Phytochemistry37
, 
1517–1575
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/S0031-9422(00)89569-2
.
</p>
         <p>Mdee, L.K.
, 
Masoko, P.
, 
Eloff, J.N.
, 
2009
. 
The activity of extracts of seven common invasive plant species on fungal phytopathogens
. 
S. Afr. J. Bot
.
75
, 
375–379
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sajb.2009.02.003
.
</p>
         <p>Monks, A.
, 
Scudiero, D.
, 
SKehan, P.
, 
Shoemaker, R.
, 
Paull, K.
, 
Vistica, D.
, 
Hose, C.
, 
Langley, J.
, 
Cronise, P.
, 
Vaigro-Wolff, A.
, 
Gray-Goodrich, M.
, 
Campbell, H.
, 
Mayo, J.
, 
Boyd, M.
, 
1991
. 
Feasibility of a high-flux anticancer drug screen using a diverse panel of cultured human tumor cell lines
. 
J. Natl. Cancer Inst.83
, 
757–766
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/jnci/83.11.757
.
</p>
         <p>Muller, P.Y.
, 
Milton, M.N.
, 
2012
. 
The determination and interpretation of the therapeutic index in drug development
. 
Nat. Rev. Drug Discov.11
, 
751-761
. 
https://doi.org/10.1038/nrd3801
.
</p>
         <p>National Cancer Institute
- 
NCI
, 
2015
. 
Developmental Therapeutics Program. Standard Operating Procedures for Sample Preparation for NCI60
Screen. Accessed in 06/ 
14
/ 19, Available at: 
https://dtp.cancer.gov/discovery_development/nci-60/handling
.
</p>
         <p>htm.</p>
         <p>Saito, Y.
, 
Mukai, T.
, 
Iwamoto, Y.
, 
Baba, M.
, 
Takiguchi, K.
, 
Okamoto, Y.
, 
Gong, X.
, 
Kawahara, T.
, 
Kuroda, C.
, 
Tori, M.
, 
2014
. 

Germacranolides and their diversity of 
Eupatorium heterophyllum
collected in P. R. China

,. 
Chem. Pharm. Bull.62
, 
1092–1099
. 
https://doi.org/10.1248/cpb.c14-00426
.
</p>
         <p>Shen, Y.C.
, 
Lo, K.L.
, 
Kuo, Y.H.
, 
Khalil, A.T.
, 
2005
. 

Cytotoxic sesquiterpene lactones from 
Eupatorium kiirunense
, a coastal plant of Taiwan

. 
J. Nat. Prod.68
, 
745–750
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/np040214k
.
</p>
         <p>Vega, M.R.G.
, 
Carvalho, M.G.
, 
Vieira, E.J.C.
, 
Braz-Filho, E.R.
, 
2008
. 

Chemical constituents from the Paraguayan medicinal plant, 
Eupatorium macrocephalum
Less

. 
J. Nat. Med.62
, 
122–123
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/s11418-007-0168-1
.
</p>
         <p>Wang, F.
, 
Zhong, H.
, 
Fang, S.
, 
Zheng, Y.
, 
Li, C.
, 
Peng, G.
, 
Shen, X.
, 
2018
. 

Potential antiinflammatory sesquiterpene lactones from 
Eupatorium lindleyanum
. 
Planta Med.84
, 
123–128
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-0043-117742
.
</p>
         <p>Williams, L.O.
, 
1976
. 

Compositae of Central America–V. The genus 
brickellia
(Eupatorieae) in Costa Rica

. 
Fieldiana Bot.24
, 
1–603
.
</p>
         <p>Wu, H.
, 
Fronczek, F.R.
, 
Burandt Jr., C.L.
, 
Zjawiony, J.K.
, 
2011
. 

Antileishmanial germacranolides from 
Calea zacatechichi
. 
Planta Med.77
, 
749–753
. 
https://doi.org/10.1055/s-0030-1250584
.
</p>
         <p>Yamada, M.
, 
Matsura, N.
, 
Suzuki, H.
, 
Kurosaka, C.
, 
Hasegawa, N.
, 
Ubukata, M.
, 
Tanaka, T.
, 
Iinuma, M.
, 
2004
. 

Germacranolides from 
Calea urticifolia
.
</p>
         <p>Phytochemistry65
, 
3107–3111
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.phytochem.2004.08.040
.
</p>
         <p>Yu, X.
, 
Zhang, Q.
, 
Tian, L.
, 
Guo, Z.
, 
Liu, C.
, 
Chen, J.
, 
Ebrahim, W.
, 
Liu, Z.
, 
Proksch, P.
, 
Zou, K.
, 
2018
. 

Germacrane-type sesquiterpenoids with antiproliferative activities from 
Eupatorium chinense
. 
J. Nat. Prod.81
, 
85–91
. 
https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jnatprod.7b00693
.
</p>
         <p>Zhang, M.L.
, 
Wu, M.
, 
Zhang, J.J.
, 
Irwin, D.
, 
Gu, Y.C.
, 
Shi, Q.W.
, 
2008
. 

Chemical constituents of plants from the genus 
Eupatorium
. 
Chem. Biodivers.5
, 
40–55
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/cbdv.200890014
.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
