<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4034.3.6</journal-id>
         <issn>1175-5326</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A new species of bright-eyed treefrog (Mantellidae) from Madagascar, with comments on call evolution and patterns of syntopy in the Boophis ankaratra complex</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
A new species of bright-eyed treefrog (
<tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
) from 
Madagascar
, with comments on call evolution and patterns of syntopy in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex
</p>
         <p>CARL
R. HUTTER 
1
, SHEA M. LAMBERT 
2
, KERRY A. COBB 
1
,
</p>
         <p>
ZO FANIRY ANDRIAMPENOMANANA 
3
&amp; MIGUEL VENCES 
4</p>
         <p>1
Biodiversity Institute and Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of Kansas, Lawrence, KS 
66045
– 
7561
, 
USA2
Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 
85721
, 
USA</p>
         <p>3
Département de Biologie Animale, Universit d’Antananarivo, BP 
906
, Antananarivo 
101
, 
Madagascar4
Zoological Institute, Technical University of Braunschweig, Mendelssohnstr. 4, 38106 Braunschweig, 
Germany</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>
We describe a new species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
treefrog from Ranomafana National Park in the southern central east of 
Madagascar
. This region has remarkably high anuran diversity, and along with neighbouring sites, hosts more than 
35<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is part of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
sub-clade (herein named the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex), previously identified within the monophyletic 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
species group. It occurs sympatrically with two other species of the complex (
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
). Morphological differentiation of species within the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
clade remains elusive, but species are well characterized by distinct advertisement calls, with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
having the longest note duration and inter-note intervals when compared to closely related species. Furthermore, it has moderate differentiation in mitochondrial 
DNA
, with pairwise distances of 
1.9–3.7
% to all other species in sequences of the mitochondrial 
16
S rRNA marker. Additional evidence is given by the lack of haplotype sharing with related species for the nuclear exon DNAH- 
3
. All examples of syntopic occurrence in this complex involve species with strongly different advertisement calls, while allopatric species have more similar calls. Such a pattern might result from adaptive call co-evolution but could also be the result of non-adaptive processes. Thorough clarification of the systematics of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
sub-clade is required, and we outline future directions for both bioacoustic and genetic research.
</p>
         <p>Key words:
Amphibia, 
<tp:taxon-name>Anura, Ranomafana</tp:taxon-name>
National Park, new species, reinforcement, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, taxonomy
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Famintinana</title>
         <p>
Araka ny fikarohana izay nataonay tao amin’ny valan-javaboahary nationaly Ranomafana, faritra atsimo atsinanan’i 
Madagasikara
dia nahita karazana sahon’ala vaovao 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
izahay. Manamarika io faritra io ny fananany ‘diversité’ ambony amin’ny karazana sahona ary ny toerana manodidina dia ahitana karazana 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
mihoatra ny 
35
. Ny 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp.nov.</named-content>
dia anisan’ny karazana 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
ihany izay efa fantatra teo aloha fa izy dia iray fiaviana amin’ny vondron’ny 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
ihany. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
dia miaraka mipetraka amin’ny karazana sahona roa hafa koa izay iray fiaviana aminy dia ny 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
sy ny 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
. Ireo karazany ireo dia tsy voaavaka raha ny endrika ivelany no resahina saingy kosa azo avahana amin’ny feony, izay mitarazoka kokoa sy miavaka ho an’ny 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
.

Fanampin’izany dia misy maha samihafa azy koa amin’ny resaka 
ADN
, izay tafiditra ao anelanelan’ny 
1.9–3.7
% manoloana ny an’ny hafa izay manana ‘séquence mitochondriale 
16
S rARN marqueur’. Nefa kosa fiovana tohin ’ADN kely monja dia mampiova ireo karazana sahona, izay misy hifandraisany amin’ny ‘axone nucléaire DNAH- 
3
’. Marihina fa ny sahona izay mitovy toerana ipetrahana ary mitovy fihaviana dia hita fa manana feo tena samihafa, ho an’ireo izay tsy mitovy toerana ipetrahana kosa dia manana feo somary mitovitovy kokoa. Izany dia mety avy amin’ny fanatsarany miaraka ny feony na mety koa avy amin’ny tsy fivoaran’ny feony mihintsy. Araka izany dia ilaina ny fanazavana ara-tsistematika momba ny 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
sy ireo mitovy fihaviana aminy ary mila jerena koa ny mikasika ny hoavin’ny fikarohana eo amin’ny resaka feo sy eo amin’ny lafiny fototarazo. Eny na dia somary kely aza ny taha-pahaveloman’ity karazana sahona vaovao ity 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
sy kely ny faritra ivelomany izay misy azy dia hita fa tena voaaro tsara izy ao anatin’ny valan-javaboaharin’ny Ranomafana.
</p>
         <p>Teny manan-danja:
Sahona, Amphibia, Valan-javaboahary Nationaly Ranomafana, karazana vaovao, fanamafisana, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, ‘taxonomie’
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>Madagascar
hosts an impressively diverse amphibian fauna comprised of five anuran clades: the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
, the microhylid subfamilies 
<tp:taxon-name>Dyscophinae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Scaphiophryninae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Cophylinae</tp:taxon-name>
, the hyperoliid genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Heterixalus</tp:taxon-name>
, and the most recent arrival, a single species of the African genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Ptychadena
(

Crottini 
et al.2012
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. The vast majority of Madagascar's 
305
currently described frogs (

Perl 
et al.2014
; 

Penny 
et al.2014
; AmphibiaWeb 
2015
) are endemic to this ‘microcontinent’. Recently, this unique biota has been the focus of intensive field surveys (e.g. overviews: 

Goodman &amp; Benstead 
2003
; D'Cruze 
et al.2009
), phylogenetic and biogeographic studies (e.g. 

Wollenberg 
et al.2011
; 

Brown 
et al.2014
), and conservation assessments (e.g. 

Andreone 
et al.2005
; 

Kremen 
et al.2008
). Many of Madagascar's amphibians are remarkably well known, with adult and larval morphology, advertisement calls, and phylogeographic differentiation of the majority of the described species being at least partially characterized. However, this knowledge base includes a large number of lineages that have only provisionally been identified as candidate species and require formal taxonomic description. 

Vieites 
et al.
(
2009
)

listed 
221
such provisional taxonomic units and 

Perl 
et al.
(
2014
)

increased this number to 
241
.
</p>
         <p>
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
Tschudi, 
1838</tp:taxon-name>
constitutes an excellent model of this taxonomic progress. The genus contains a large number of arboreal frogs with 
76
described species (AmphibiaWeb 
2015
) and 
13
additional candidate taxonomic units (

Perl 
et al.2014
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
treefrogs mostly inhabit the eastern rainforest biome in 
Madagascar
(

Cadle 
2003
). Frequently, low variation in external morphology and skin pigments that fade after preservation have contributed to a severe historical underestimation of species diversity in this genus (e.g. 

Vieites 
et al.2009
; Glaw 
et al.2010
). This is especially true for eye coloration, which is an important diagnostic trait in 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
(e.g. Glaw &amp; Vences 
2007
), but typically is not reliably recognizable in preserved specimens. Most importantly, the advertisement calls of most 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
species are loud and characteristic, and have shown to be more taxonomically informative than external morphology or skin pigment (Vences 
et al.2008
).
</p>
         <p>
Bioacoustic comparisons of 
Malagasy
anurans started with the pioneering work of 

Blommers-Schlösser (
1979
)

, and have substantially accelerated the rate of species discovery in this genus (

Köhler 
et al.2005
; Glaw 
et al.2010
). After the widespread application of bioacoustics, species identification and characterization in these frogs has outpaced other 
Malagasy
anuran groups (e.g. 
Andreone 1993
, 
1994
, 
1996
; 

Glaw &amp; Thiesmeier 
1993
; Glaw &amp; Vences 
2002
; Vences &amp; Glaw 
2002
; 

Köhler 
et al.
2007

, 
2008
; 

Wollenberg 
et al.2008
; Glaw 
et al.2010
; Vences 
et al.2010
; 

Penny 
et al.2014
). While 

Blommers-Schlösser &amp; Blanc (
1991
)

listed only five species of green-colored 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
, the latest accounts identify 
34
or more species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albilabris</tp:taxon-name>
group, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. luteus</tp:taxon-name>
group, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. mandraka</tp:taxon-name>
group, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. rappiodes</tp:taxon-name>
group, and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ulftunni</tp:taxon-name>
group (

Glaw &amp; Vences 
2006
; 

Vieites 
et al.2009
; Glaw 
et al.2010
; 

Perl 
et al.2014
; 

Penny 
et al.2014
).
</p>
         <p>
Herein, we describe a new species belonging to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group. The new species is a member of a sub-clade in this group we define as the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex, containing five species (
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
,

and the new species). The 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex lacks a welldistinguished dorsal white-dotted pattern present in the second sub-clade (
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. luciae</tp:taxon-name>
), except for the new species, which often has similar yellowish-white spots. The new species occurs at Ranomafana National Park (RNP) and the surrounding area in the southern central east of 
Madagascar
(

). Ranomafana is one of the most intensively surveyed areas of amphibian diversity in 
Madagascar
with over 
120
species and candidate species known from the reserve and surrounding sites (

Vieites 
et al.2009
), including 
36
species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
. Additionally, the newly described taxon has been previously characterized as a candidate species based on its molecular differentiation and advertisement calls (

Vieites 
et al.2009
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Material and methods</title>
         <p>Terminology
. We follow the unified concept of species (i.e. general lineage concept), which defines a species as a separately evolving lineage within a temporal segment of a population (

Simpson 
1961
; 

Wiley 
1978
; de 
Queiroz 1998
, 
2005
, 
2007
). However, we stress that the new species described herein likely represents a species even if conservative species criteria are applied (e.g. biological species criterion), as it occurs syntopically with close relatives with no evidence of genetic admixture. Importantly, all species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex differ in advertisement call, suggesting they are reproductively isolated (see 

Vences &amp; 
Wake2007
).
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 1.
The distribution of species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group in southeastern Madagascar. The black dotted line shows the boundaries of Ranomafana National Park (RNP), and partially colored circles indicate syntopy of their corresponding species. The numbered localities are as follows (species occurring at each locality abbreviated as BA, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
; BB, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, BL, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. luciae</tp:taxon-name>
; BS, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
): Within RNP: (1) Maharira (BA, BB; type locality of BB); (2) Valohoaka (BL); (3) Vohiparara (BS); (4) Andranoroa river (BA, BB); (5) Sakaroa (BB); (6) Ambatolahy (BL, BS); (7–8) Imaloka (BB, BL); and (9) Andemaka (BB, BL). Outside RNP: (10) Ambohitsara-Ranomafana (BL); (11) Farihimazava (BA, BB); (12) Soamazaka (BA, BB); and (13) Vohisokina (BA, BB). Note that at Ambohitsara, records also exist for another species of the group (
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
) that is not discussed herein.
</p>
         <p>
We use an integrative taxonomic approach in assessing species boundaries, combining data from morphology, phylogenetics, bioacoustics, and biogeography (

Dayrat 
2005
; 

Padial 
et al.2010
; 

Vences 
et al.2013
). This evidence is then weighted equally and used as support for the hypothesis that a given population is an independently evolving lineage and thus a distinct species. Family and generic names follow the taxonomy proposed by 

Glaw &amp; Vences (
2006
)

. Geographic regions for biogeographic analyses are defined according to Glaw &amp; Vences (
2007
). According to this zonation, RNP is within a region named the southern central east of 
Madagascar
.
</p>
         <p>Morphology.
Specimens were collected at night by opportunistic searching or by locating males through their conspicuous advertisement calls. Specimens were sacrificed using 
20
% benzocaine, fixed in ~ 
10
% formalin (buffered with sodium phosphate to ~7.0 
pH
) for 
24
hours and then stored in 
70
% ethanol for long-term preservation. We deposited and examined alcohol-preserved specimens from the amphibian collections at the Biodiversity Institute of the University of Kansas (KU) and Département de Biologie Animale, Université d'Antananarivo (
UADBA
) (Appendix I). Additional collection acronyms used herein are 
FAZC
, 
ZCMV
, 
FGZC
, and LR (field number series of F. Andreone, M. Vences, F. Glaw, and L. Raharivololoniaina respectively), 
FGMV
(field number series shared between M. Vences and F. Glaw), and 
ZSM
(Zoologische Staatssammlung München, 
Germany
).
</p>
         <p>
Morphological measurements were taken by K.A. Cobb with a digital caliper (precision 
0.01 mm
) to the nearest 
0.1 mm
. Terminology and measurements largely follow 

Glaw 
et al.
(
2001
)

and we used the following: (
1
) snout-vent length (SVL); (
2
) head width at the greatest point (HW); (
3
) head length (=rostrum) from snout tip to maxillary commissure (HL); (
4
) horizontal eye diameter (ED); (
5
) interorbital distance (IOD); (
6
) eye-snout tip distance (ESD); (
7
) eye-nostril distance (
END
); (
8
) nostril-snout tip distance (NSD); (
9
) nostril-nostril distance (NND); (
10
) horizontal tympanum diameter (TD); (
11
) forelimb (=radioulna) length from humerus-radioulna articulation point to carpal-metacarpal articulation (RUL); (
12
) hand length from carpal-metacarpal articulation to tip of longest finger (
HAL
); (
13
) Finger I length from outer margin of palmar tubercle to tip of Finger I (FIL); (
14
) Finger II length from outer margin of palmar tubercle to tip of Finger II (
FIIL
); (
15
) femur length from cloaca to the femur-tibia articulation (
FEML
); (
16
) tibia length measured along the shank (
TIBL
); (
17
) foot length from tarsal-metatarsal articulation to tip of longest toe (FOL); (
18
) foot+tarsus length from the tibiotarsal articulation to tip of longest toe (
FOTL
); and (
19
) relative hindlimb length to SVL by (
FEML
+ 
TIBL
)/SVL (RHL). We note that RHL is typically measured by adpressing the hindlimb along the body and noting the point the tibiotarsal articulation reaches (e.g. eye center, beyond snout tip; Glaw 
et al.2010
); however, we were unable to measure this character with formalin preserved specimens as this would damage the specimen. Sexual maturity was determined by male calling activity (all males collected were calling) and by the presence of eggs in females. Description of eye coloration follows 

Glaw &amp; Vences (
1997
)

and webbing formulae follow 

Blommers-Schlösser (
1979
)

.
</p>
         <p>DNA
extraction and sequencing

. Following euthanasia, we extracted whole livers and left hind limb muscles and stored the tissues in 
95
% ethanol. We obtained new genetic data for 
10
specimens

(nine from the newly described species, and one from 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
). Sequences were deposited in GenBank and their associated voucher specimens and accession numbers are provided in Appendix II.
</p>
         <p>
Genomic 
DNA
was extracted from the tissue using proteinase K (final concentration 
20 mg
/ml) and a standard salt-based Guanidine Thiocyanate Extraction extraction protocol (

Esselstyn 
et al.2008
). We amplified a ~ 
1400
bp segment of mitochondrial 
DNA
, corresponding to the almost complete large ribosomal subunit (
16
S rRNA) using polymerase chain reaction (PCR). The forward and reverse primers used were LX 
12
SN 
1
and LX 
16
S 
1
R (Zhang 
et al.2013
). PCR reactions were performed using the following procedure: 
1.5
µL genomic 
DNA
, 
0.2
µM of each primer, 
200
µM of dNTPs, 
1.25
U of OneTaq 
DNA
polymerase, and 
5
µL OneTaq Standard Reaction Buffer (
20
mM Tris-HCl, 
22
mM NH 
4
Cl, 
22
mM KCl, 
1.8
mM MgCl 
2
, 
0.06
% IGEPAL CA- 
630
, and 
0.05
% Tween 
20
). The final volume was brought to 
25
µL with nuclease-free water. We visualized amplification success using 
2
µL of PCR product on 
1.5
% agarose gel. Additionally, a ~ 
900
bp segment of the nuclear gene ‘dynein axonemal heavy chain 
3
’ (DNAH- 
3
) was amplified using the primers and PCR protocol from 

Shen 
et al.
(
2013
)

.
</p>
         <p>
PCR products were purified of excess dNTPs and primers using Shrimp Alkaline Phosphatase (
1
U/µL) and Exonuclease I (
20
U/µL). We used the remaining 
23
µL of PCR product and added 
0.025
µL Exonuclease I, 
0.250
µL Shrimp Alkaline Phosphatase and 
9.725
µL nuclease-free water for a final volume of 
32
µL per reaction. Next, we incubated the samples at 
37
ºC for 
30
minutes and then 
95
ºC for 
5
minutes in a thermocycler. For cycle sequencing, we conducted two separate reactions for the target 
5
’ and 
3
’ end 
DNA
strands per purified PCR product. We prepared a 
7
µL sequencing reaction that included 
2
µL of the purified PCR product, 
1.5
µL of 
5
X

sequencing buffer, 
0.5
µL of the forward or reverse primer (separately), 
0.5
µL of BigDye Terminator (version 
3.1
sequencing standard, Applied Biosystems) and 
2.5
µL of water. The sequence reaction began with 
1
cycle at 
95
ºC for 
60
s, and 
30
cycles of 
95
ºC for 
15
s, 
50
ºC for 
15
s, and 
60
ºC for 
240
s. In preparation for sequencing, we purified the reaction product of BigDye Terminator by filtering the product through Sephadex G- 
50 in
a spin column centrifuged at 
850
rcf for 
5
min. We collected and visualized sequence data on an Applied Biosystems 
3130
automated sequencer. After sequencing, 
DNA
data were manually edited for quality in Geneious R 
8
(Biomatters 
2015
).
</p>
         <p>Phylogenetics.
Initially, we used uncorrected p-distances in a commonly used region of the 
16
S rRNA marker as a preliminary assessment of genetic differentiation (

Vieites 
et al.2009
). However, we did not consider an absolute threshold of genetic distance (e.g. 
2.5
%–3.0%) as primary criterion to delimit species because this approach might be misleading due to introgression, incomplete lineage sorting, low genetic variability of markers, or recently evolved reproductive isolation. This consideration is supported by other recently described 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
species of low genetic divergence to their sister species (e.g. 
<tp:taxon-name>B. narinsi</tp:taxon-name>
vs. 
<tp:taxon-name>B. majori</tp:taxon-name>
;

and other species in the 
B.</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex; Glaw 
et al.2010
; Vences 
et al.2012
). To more directly address whether a species is a separately evolving lineage, we test for strongly supported reciprocal monophyly in mitochondrial genetic data using phylogenetic analyses (

Avise 
2000
).
</p>
         <p>
We supplemented newly generated mitochondrial data with published sequences of the 
16
S rRNA marker of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
specimens we obtained from GenBank (Appendix III). We selected a subset of closely related nominal taxa, using the tree available from 

Vieites 
et al.
(
2009
)

and data from Glaw 
et al.
(
2010
) as guides. For examination of genetic distances, we selected data from a ~ 
600
bp fragment of 
16
S which is commonly used for distance comparisons in 
Malagasy
frogs (

Vieites 
et al.2009
). To test for reciprocal monophyly, we included another ~ 
650
bp fragment of 
16
S, spanned by our primer pair and available on GenBank for most, but not all species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex. Whenever possible, we selected multiple individuals from each selected species to test for reciprocal monophyly of the new species using mitochondrial data.
</p>
         <p>
We included the distantly related 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis periegetes</tp:taxon-name>
(for mtDNA) as an outgroup based on previous phylogenetic studies (

Vieites 
et al.2009
). Our final mtDNA matrices included 
43
individuals of seven species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group spanning 
1,229
bp for phylogenetic analysis, and 
50
individuals from the same species spanning 
583
bp for examination of genetic distances. All matrices were aligned in Geneious using 
MAFFT
v 
7
(

Katoh &amp; Standley 
2013
) and manually inspected for accuracy.
</p>
         <p>
For maximum likelihood (ML) estimation of phylogenetic relationships using 
16
S, we used RAxML 
8.1
. 
17
(

Stamatakis 
2014
). We used the GTR + G model (Generalized Time–Reversible + Gamma) of nucleotide substitution, which accounts for variable base frequencies and includes a gamma-shaped distribution for rates across sites. Next, we performed 
100
tree searches and assessed node support using 
1000
bootstrap replicates, using the standard, non-rapid bootstrap procedure.
</p>
         <p>
For Bayesian Inference analyses (BA) of 
16
S, we used MrBayes 
3.2
. 
4
(

Ronquist 
et al.2012
). First, we used JModelTest 2.0 (

Posada 
2008
) to select the model of sequence evolution that best fits the data, using the Bayesian information criterion (BIC; 

Schwarz 
1978
). We chose not to evaluate models that include both gamma-distributed rate variation across sites (G) and a proportion of invariant sites (I) because their joint estimation can be compromised by correlation between parameters (

Yang 
2006
, p. 
114
). The best-fit model for the 
16
S alignment was TRNef+G. We then conducted analyses for 
10
million generations (sampling every 
1000
) with four Markov chains. All parameters were left at default settings unless otherwise noted. We ran four replicate analyses to ensure convergence to a consistent optimum between independent analyses. To assess convergence we examined the standard deviation of split frequencies to ensure values were below a conservative value of 
0.005
, and plots of –lnL per generation to evaluate stationarity. We discarded the first 
25
% of generations as 'burn-in' for evaluation of convergence and computation of clade credibility trees.
</p>
         <p>
Finally, we assessed if the putative new species was reciprocally monophyletic in reference to all other species of the complex, using the estimated phylogeny. Statistical support for this hypothesis is given through a conservative and high bootstrap support (BS&gt; 
90
%) in ML analyses and high posterior probability support (PP&gt; 
0.95
) in BA analyses for the monophyly of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>As
an additional step to determine the evolutionary independence of the new species we examined haplotypes of the nuclear exon DNAH- 
3
. We chose to represent the DNAH- 
3
sequence data using a minimum-spanning haplotype network because initial phylogenetic trees were weakly resolved. This lack of resolution could be due to insufficient variability of the marker and/or limited taxon sampling for the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex (
4
individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, 
1
of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
, 
1
of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
, 
2
of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
). Our final nDNA matrix included 
11
individuals from 
8
species and spans 
747
bp. After manual editing in Geneious, hapoltypes were determined using 
PHASE
v 
2.1
(

Stephens 
et al.2001
; 

Stephens &amp; Donelly 
2003
). Next, the data was analyzed and visualized using the minimum-spanning algorithm (

Bandelt 
et al.1999
) implemented in PopART v 
1.7
(http://popart.otago.ac.vz).
</p>
         <p>Bioacoustics
. Calling males were located in streams and recorded in the field at less than 
2 m
distance from the calling individual. 
As
species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
call frequently and simultaneously, we ensured that the male being recorded was the same captured through visual inspection of vocal sac movement under a red light. Calling males were observed for extended periods and in varying conditions to ensure that the call being recorded was the advertisement call and not an alternative call 
type
. While the advertisement call is typically the most frequently emitted call 
type
, males might engage each other in territorial behavior using an alternative call 
type
(e.g. 

Wells 
2007
; Glaw 
et al.2010
). We observed this behavior infrequently, but were unable to obtain recordings due to the reduced volume of the alternative call 
type
and its unpredictable occurrence.
</p>
         <p>
Calls were recorded with an Olympus LS- 
10
Linear 
PCM
Field Recorder and a Sennheiser K 
6
-ME 
66
unidirectional microphone. The calls were recorded in uncompressed WAV format at a sampling rate of 
44.1
kHz and 
16
bits resolution. We recorded the air temperature following each call using an analog thermometer. Comparative calls used from the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex are the same audio recordings described in Glaw 
et al.
(
2010
).
</p>
         <p>
We follow 

Duellman &amp; Trueb (
1994
)

in defining a call as the entire assemblage of acoustic signals produced in a given sequence. Under this definition, and following previous call descriptions for the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex (Glaw &amp; Vences 2002, 2007; Glaw 
et al.2010
), we define a series of notes as a call, where notes are temporally distinct segments separated by a return to the background noise between each note. We acknowledge that an alternative approach would be defining each note as a single-noted call and a series of notes could be considered a series of calls. Pulsed notes are those having one or more clear amplitude peaks while tonal notes have relatively constant amplitude throughout the call.
</p>
         <p>
Following 

Hutter &amp; Guayasamin (
2012
; Figure 
3
)

, 

Hutter 
et al.
(
2013
; 

Table 
1
) and Glaw 
et al.
(
2010
), we chose the following call variables: (
1
) note amplitude 
type
(tonal or pulsed); (
2
) call arrangement 
type
(notes singular or in a series); (
3
) number of notes per call; (
4
) call duration (s); (
5
) note duration (ms); (
6
) inter-note interval duration (ms); (
7
) note repetition rate within call (notes/s); (
8
) pulse rate (/s); (
9
) note envelope shape (time at peak amplitude / call duration); (
10
) dominant frequency, measured at peak amplitude (Hz); (
11
) lower fundamental frequency limit (=fundamental frequency) (Hz); (
12
) upper fundamental frequency limit (Hz); and (
13
) 
1
st harmonic frequency (Hz). Measures are reported as the range followed by the mean two standard deviations from the mean.
</p>
         <p>TABLE 1
. Morphometric measurements (in mm) of the holotype (KU 336824) and selected paratypes of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
Specimen The parameters above were measured using the R package SEEWAVE (

Sueur 
et al.2008
; R 

Development Core Team 
2015
). The analysis of calls was automated using a custom script (available upon request), following 

Hutter &amp; Guayasamin (
2015
)

. To test the accuracy of this method, we reanalysed the same audio files used for manual measurements in Glaw 
et al.
(
2010
) and found the results to be generally the same to that of automated measurements. For example, we compared the following for 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
between automated and manual measurements from Glaw 
et al.
(
2010
), respectively: (
1
) dominant frequency, 
2756–3015
vs. 
2750–3000
Hz; (
2
) note duration, 
134
+ 
10.6
vs. 
125
+ 
4
ms; (
3
) note repetition rate, 
2.5
vs. 
2.5
(/s); and (
4
) inter-note interval duration, 
269
+ 
37
vs. 
257
+ 
4
ms (compare 

Table 
2
vs. Glaw 
et al.2010
, 

Table 
1
). We also emphasize that we examined each analysed call visually to ensure it was not another species, background noise, or artefact. Digital recordings are deposited at the University of Kansas Biodiversity Institute and are available upon request.
</p>
         <p>Measure SexKU 336824 MaleKU 336825 MaleKU 336826 MaleKU 336827 MaleKU 336828 MaleKU 336829 FemaleSVL23.423.422.024.420.332.2HW8.59.38.29.18.112.3HL7.98.47.78.46.310.6ED2.52.62.82.82.03.4IOD3.53.94.03.63.65.9ESD3.73.13.73.93.25.5END1.41.71.71.71.72.8NSD2.12.11.61.91.82.1NND2.62.72.53.12.53.5TD1.21.21.21.21.22.1RUL5.35.24.75.14.46.5HAL FIL6.8 3.26.9 3.46.2 3.37.3 3.26.3 2.67.5 5.0FIIL3.63.63.33.73.25.2FEML TIBL12.6 12.211.5 12.111.2 11.011.9 11.811.0 10.716.8 17.2FOL10.910.79.311.59.316.0FOTL16.916.915.816.915.825.2RHL1.051.011.010.971.071.06</p>
         <p>
Finally, we evaluated the amount of bioacoustic differences between species following 

Vieites 
et al.
(
2009
)

. We considered differences in general call structure (e.g. pulsed/tonal notes, consistent note arrangements, amplitude envelope shape; 

Ryan &amp; Rand 
1990
) and such temporal variables that are putatively less influenced by temperature, body size, and behavior (e.g. note duration, pulse rate; 

Gerhardt 
et al.2000
) to be important traits for distinguishing species. We did not correct for temperature as all calls recorded were within a degree of each other, except those of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
(see below for justification).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Taxonomic results</title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa
(Maharira)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana
(Andohahela)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra
(Maharira)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae
(Ambatolahy)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana
(Andohahela)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. madagascariensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. majori</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. popi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. reticulatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
boppa
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
haingana
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisliami</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>liami</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisperiegetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>periegetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophissibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new species of bright-eyed treefrog (Mantellidae) from Madagascar, with comments on call evolution and patterns of syntopy in the Boophis ankaratra complex</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4034.3.6</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EF48FFB98223FFA7EB07FFD4DD4A6B0C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4034.3.6</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>Suggested common English name.
Boppa’s Bright-eyed treefrog 

Suggested common 
Malagasy
name.

Fity maso hazo Sahona ny 
<tp:taxon-name>Boppa</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336830
and UADBA-Uncatalogued (CRH- 
177
).
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336824
(
holotype
), 

KU 
336825
–336829, UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH
080), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH168
), and UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH178
). Ranomafana National Park, Andemaka (
21
°07' 
43.4
"S

, 
47
° 
30
' 
19.4
"E

, 
1237 m
, a.s.l.), Uncatalogued (
CRH775
).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336854
. Ranomafana National Park, Valohoaka (
21
° 
17
' 
51.3
"S

, 
47
° 
26
' 
20.1
"E

; 
1064 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336855
and UADBA- Uncatalogued (
CRH
002).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Ambatolahy (
21
° 
14
' 
38
"S

, 
47
° 
25
' 
34.3
"E

; 
919 m
, a.s.l.), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH818
) and UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH846
).
APPENDIX II
. GenBank accession numbers of newly determined 
DNA
sequences for taxa used in this study. All localities are within 
Madagascar
.

Museum or Species Locality GenBank Accession ID collection ID 
16
S DNAH- 
3APPENDIX III
. Previously available GenBank accession numbers used in this study for the mitochondrial marker 
16
S. GenBank Accession ID’s with an asterisk are those used in the phylogenetic analyses while all sequences listed were used for genetic distances.
KU 336830<tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588032KT588046ZCMV 0 9739<tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, ImalokaKT588047KU 336825<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588033KT588049KU 336828<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588034KT588050KU 336883<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588035UADBA-CRH168<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588036KU 336829<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588037KT588051KU 336827<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588038UADBA-CRH080<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
boppa
</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588039KU 336824<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588040KT588048UADBA-CRH178<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
boppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588041FGZC 2390<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
haingana
</tp:taxon-name>AndohahelaKT588042ZSM 674/2001<tp:taxon-name>Boophisliami</tp:taxon-name>Andasibe, VohidrazanaKT588043ZCMV 0 687<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
luciae</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National ParkKT588044FGZC 2389<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
miadana</tp:taxon-name>AndohahelaKT588045KU 336858<tp:taxon-name>Boophisperiegetes</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588031ZSM 39 2002<tp:taxon-name>Boophissibilans</tp:taxon-name>AndasibeKT588052
Museum or Collection ID Species Genbank Accession ID 
ZCMV4946<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974374ZCMV4942<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974373MRSN
A 
6371<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364574MRSN
A 
6219<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364573MRSN
A 
6197<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364572FGZC291<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848446
* 
ZCMV10348<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609605
* 
ZCMV5989<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974475
* 
ZCMV4917<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974476
* 
FGMV2001
/ 
480<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
AF 
411612FGMV2002
/ 
1699<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>DQ068398FGMV2002
/ 
1697<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>DQ068396
* 
FAZC13998<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
JF 
903873ZCMV
0 
9739<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609604
* 
ZSM1164
/ 
2007<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974477
* 
FAZC11480<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848438
* 
FAZC11462<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848437
* 
FAZC11454<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848436
* 
FGZC239<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848463
* 
FGZC232<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848462
* 
FGZC220<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848461
* 
FGZC219<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848460
* 
FGZC218<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848459
* 
FGZC2390<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
FJ 
559142
*
ZCMV687<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848443ZCMV10501<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609714ZCMV10100<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609745ZCMV
0 
9106<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609730
* 
ZCMV4564<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
975078ZCMV4202<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
975079ZCMV
0 
9744<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610983ZCMV
0 
9740<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610982ZCMV
0 
9731<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610981ZCMV
0 
9192<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610980
* 
ZCMV
0 
9513<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610971ZCMV
0 
9628<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610968ZCMV
0 
9626<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610967FGZC2389<tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
FJ 
559141
*
ZCMV
0 
9349<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610486
* 
ZCMV5090<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974829
* 
ZCMV5080<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974830
*
......continued on the next pageAPPENDIX III.
(Continued)

Museum or Collection ID Species Genbank Accession ID 
FGMV2002
/ 
1804<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068395
* 
FGMV2002
/ 
1800<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068394
* 
FGMV2002
/ 
1790<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068393
* 
ZSM39
/ 
2002<tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
341672
* LR 
269<tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
792492</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
Previously referred to as 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
1
(
<tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Andreone 
et al.2007
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
‘Antoetra slow’ (Glaw &amp; Vences 
2007
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
18
(

Vieites 
et al.2009
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
(

. 
2–3
A)

. 

KU 
336824
, an adult male collected by Carl R. Hutter and Zo F. Andriampenomanana on 
18
January 
2014
, at Maharira within Ranomafana National Park (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, above sea level [a.s.l.]), Fianarantsoa province, 
Madagascar
.
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
. Adult female 

KU 
336829
and adult male 

KU 
336826
collected on 
21
January 
2013
by Carl R. Hutter and Shea M. Lambert with same locality data as 
holotype
. Adult males 

KU 
336828
, 

KU 
336825
, 

KU 
336827
, with same collection data as 
holotype
.
</p>
            <p>Referred specimens.
UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH
080), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH168
), UADBA- Uncatalogued (
CRH178
) with same collection data as 
holotype
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
. This species in named in honor of Nicholas Jay Pritzker, devoted grandfather, father and husband, brilliant businessman, philanthropist, amateur scientist, committed conservationist; and board member, supporter and long-time friend of Conservation International. The name ‘Boppa’ is an affectionate nickname used by his children and grandchildren. This dedication is courtesy of his youngest son Isaac, who has generously supported amphibian research in 
Madagascar
, including this study and future taxonomic research as well. The species name is used as an invariable noun in apposition to the genus name.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(

) is placed in the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
, subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophinae</tp:taxon-name>
, and genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
, as diagnosed by 

Glaw &amp; Vences (
2006
)

. The new species shares the following combination of morphological traits with all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
: presence of intercalary element between ultimate and penultimate phalanges of fingers and toes; presence of nuptial pads and absence of femoral glands in males; absence of gular glands in males; terminal discs of fingers and toes enlarged; lateral metatarsalia separated by webbing; and absence of outer metatarsal tubercle. Furthermore, phylogenetic analyses support the placement of the new species in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is placed in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group as supported by the phylogenetic analyses. Additionally, the following combination of characters provide additional evidence for the inferred phylogenetic relationships: small body size (male SVL &lt;
27 mm
); tubercles or flaps on heel and elbow absent; webbing between fingers present; canthus rostralis indistinct; distinct white tarsal folds present; dorsal coloration translucent green in life and cream-colored in preservative; ventral skin partially transparent in life; red ventral coloration absent; single subgular vocal sac; and vomerine teeth present.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is a member of the monophyletic 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex and cannot easily be distinguished morphologically from other closely related species in the group, which includes 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
(

). Species in this complex lack a dense and regular white-spotted pattern that is present in other members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group; however, most individuals of the new species show some light yellow and white spotting. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
differs from syntopic 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking a yellow parietal peritoneum, which was present in all live photographs and examined live individuals from two different populations for 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
(e.g. Fig. 
3
B and 

A). 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
differs from allopatric 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
by having the smallest, non-overlapping body size among these three species (adult male SVL: 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
= 
20.3–24.4 mm
; 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
= 
25.5–26.8 mm
; 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>24.8
–29.0 mm). However, we could not discern any morphological differences between the new species and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
, which occurs sympatrically at Ranomafana National Park, but has not been observed syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, instead occurring at lower elevations. While we find discernable morphological differences in life, our observations generally agree with previous studies suggesting that reliable morphological differentiation among specimens of these species is difficult (Glaw 
et al.2010
). Despite this difficulty, these species all can be easily diagnosed by advertisement call and/or molecular phylogenetics.
</p>
            <p>
Bioacoustically, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from all other species in this group by having the longest note duration (

) and longest intervals between notes and thus the slowest note repetition rate within calls (

; 

Table 
2
). The most similar species in call is 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
(

B; 

B), which has the second longest note duration and inter-note interval in the group, but does not overlap with the new species in these values. All other species in this complex have much shorter advertisement calls. Additionally, these differences cannot be attributed to temperature, which fall within 
1
ºC across the recordings of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. We did not correct the call of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
for temperature (it was ~ 
5
°C warmer), as it has dramatically shorter note and internote interval durations (
4
-fold and 
7
-fold shorter, respectively) and a much faster note repetition rate than 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, which are differences not likely due to this amount of temperature change. Furthermore, motivation of the calling male was unlikely a factor as the temporal differences remained consistent across hundreds of calls and a variety of motivational states and weather conditions.
</p>
            <p>FIGU
RE 
3
. 
Ex-situ
dorsal and ventral photographs of (
A
) 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
, 

KU 
336824
) and (
B
) 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
(

KU 
336830
) in life.
</p>
            <p>
Phylogenetically, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is reciprocally monophyletic to all other species in the complex with strong support based on 
DNA
sequences of the mitochondrial marker 
16
S (

). The new species also shares no haplotypes of the nuclear exon DNAH- 
3
with other related species (

). Importantly, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
is also monophyletic, which includes individuals from the southern parts of its range and a specimen from Ranomafana National Park that was syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. Although the sister group of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
cannot be determined from the analyses undertaken here, close phylogenetic affinity is suggested with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
, or 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
. Additionally, the low genetic distance among individuals within 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and its monophyly is strong evidence that no genetic admixture is occurring with other species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex. Notably, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
occur syntopically and can commonly be found calling within a meter distance from each other, with consistent and strong call differences (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
also occurs sympatrically with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
(although calling males have thus far not been found together in syntopy) and the calls of these species are highly distinct (

). Finally, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
is distributed allopatrically and has a genetic distance of 
3.5–4.5
% compared to 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of the 
holotype
(

)

. Adult male, SVL 
23.4 mm
. Body moderately slender; head wider than body, HW 
36.3
% of SVL; head slightly shorter than wide, HL 
33.8
% of SVL; snout of moderate length, ESD 
15.8
% of SVL; snout rounded in dorsal and lateral view; nostrils directed dorsolaterally, nearer to eye than to tip of snout; ED larger than 
END
; cranial crests absent; canthus rostralis indistinct, loreal region slightly concave; single subgular vocal sac; gular glands absent. Tympanic annulus distinct, round, TD 48.0% of ED; supratympanic fold barely distinct, tympanic membrane transparent. Vomerine odontophores distinct, well separated in two elongated patches, positioned posteromedial to choanae; choanae medium-sized, rounded. Tongue longer than wide; ovoid in shape, posteriorly bifid, free. Arms slender; subarticular tubercles single, round; metacarpal tubercles not recognizable. Nuptial pad on inner finger 
1
, barely distinguishable; not pigmented, slightly lighter than ground color; fingers moderately webbed and with lateral dermal fringes; webbing formula 
1
(
1.5
), 
2
i

(
1.5
), 
2
e(
1
), 
3
i

(
2
), 
3
e(
1.5
), 
4
(
1
); relative length of fingers 
1
&lt;
2
&lt;
4
&lt;
3
, finger 
2
distinctly shorter than finger 
4
, finger 
1
slightly shorter than finger 
2
; finger discs enlarged. 
Hind
limbs slender; femoral glands absent; white tarsal folds distinct; 
TIBL52.6
% of SVL; FOL 
46.6
% of SVL; lateral metatarsalia separated by webbing; inner metatarsal tubercle small, distinct, elongated; no outer metatarsal tubercle; toes broadly webbed; webbing formula 
1
(
0.5
), 
2
i

(
0.75
), 
2
e(
0.25
), 
3
i

(
1
), 
3
e(
0.25
), 
4
i

(
1.25
), 
4
e(
1.5
), 
5
(
0.5
); relative length of toes 
1
&lt;
2
&lt;
3
&lt;
5
&lt;
4
; toe discs enlarged. Skin smooth on dorsal surfaces, finely granular on throat and chest, coarsely granular on belly and ventral surfaces of thighs. Enlarged tubercles absent in cloacal region. Muscle from right thigh and liver removed for tissue samples; abdominal cavity of right side opened.
</p>
            <p>
After one year in preservative (

), body coloration uniform cream-yellow. Dark pigments are present around nostrils. Dark pigmented spots are present on upper eyelids and along the dorsum. In life (Figs. 
3
A– 
4
), dorsum lime green with numerous white-yellow flecks, dark brown spots present, skin translucent especially on limbs, groin turquoise; upper 
3
/ 
4
visceral peritoneum white, lower peritoneum and flanks transparent; underside of limbs translucent green, joints turquoise. Pupil black; iris coloration reddish-brown around the pupil and outer edges lighter in color, non-uniform; iris outlined in black; iris periphery blue, posterior edges black; eye periphery black. Color sequence from pupil to eye periphery: black, reddish-brown, yellowish-brown, black, blue, and black.
</p>
            <p>
Morphometry of 
type
series

. Measurements of the 
holotype
and 
paratypes
are shown in 

Table 
1
.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

)

. In life, dorsal coloration is lime to a light-lime green, with a white venter that is transparent posteriorly and along the flanks. Some individuals of this species have a white spotting pattern, with some spots being light yellow upon closer examination. Given this, the morphological distinction between the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex and other species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group is weakened; however, these spots can be useful in distinguishing 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
when present. Brown dorsal spots are also variable, as some individuals may have dense, dark patches, several spots, or none at all (

). Additionally, the intensity of the iris coloration is variable (

).
</p>
            <p>
Bioacoustics (

A– 
7
A; 

Table 
2
)

. We recorded and analyzed 
171
notes from six individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
209
notes from two individuals 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
in syntopy with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. All individuals are adult males recorded at night with mist or light rain at a temperature of 
16.9–18.2
°C. The males were calling on the upper surfaces of leaves 
2–4 m
above the ground and were recorded 
1 m
or less from the male. The advertisement call of this species sounds like a long ‘groan’ to the human observer, emitted frequently in slow-paced succession. We define each groan as a note (

A), which are arranged in series (each series we consider a call) of 
5–16
notes separated by extended periods of silence.
</p>
            <p>
Each note in the call of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly amplitude modulated, with the peak amplitude occurring in the last 
50
% of the note. The notes are strongly pulsed, with a rate of 
135–263
(
187
± 
31
) pulses / s. The note duration is 
379–526
(
451.6
± 
42.4
) ms with an inter-note interval of 
989–1659
(
1192
± 
167
) ms. The dominant frequency measured at peak amplitude is 
2929–3531
(
3205
± 
139
) Hz. The dominant frequency is within the fundamental frequency, which has a lower limit of 
2500–2594
(
2702
± 
101
) Hz and an upper limit of 
3001–3431
(
3165
± 
91.8
) Hz. The first harmonic is 
5768–6384
(
6073
± 
148
) Hz. See 

Table 
2
for a comparison among all identified species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex.
</p>
            <p>
comparison are from Glaw 
et al.
(
2010
). Calls were recorded from males calling at night and were
</p>
            <p>subsequently collected as vouchers. Note envelope is the ratio of the time of peak amplitude to note</p>
            <p>duration. RNP is an abbreviation for Ranomafana National Park. Data are the range and then the mean ±</p>
            <p>two standard deviations in parentheses, when appropriate.</p>
            <p>Species</p>
            <p>Parameter<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>LocalityMaharira, RNPMaharira, RNPManjakatompoAndohahelaAndohahelaVohipara, RNPTemp. (Cº)16.9–18.217.918.017.617.623.0n
– individuals
621222n
– calls (note series)
2641222n
– notes
17120966150144108Call duration (s)3.9–22.12 (10.2 ± 3.9)13.5–27.1 (19.7 ± 6.5)25.816.4–28.4 (22.4 ± 8.5)12.8–13.1 (13.0 ± 0.2)13.9–14.8 (14.3 ± 0.6)Note duration (ms)379.0–526.0 (451.6 ± 42.4)104.56– 130 (110.5 ± 8.076)111.5–153.7 (134 ± 10.6)46.6–85.8 (61.7 ± 12.7)208.3–316.4 (249.7 ± 29.8)73.17–169.3 (124.3 ± 20.9)Inter-note989–1659204–341222–318232–352591–910114–248interval (ms)(1192 ± 167)(269 ± 3)(259 ± 37)(238 ± 86)(675 ± 102)(162 ± 42)Noterepetition0.4–0.82.6–2.82.52.6–3.01.0–1.23.4rate (/s)Note envelope shape0.582–0.954 (0.779 ± 0.087)0.550– 0.881 (0.746 ± 0.072)0.539–0.864 (0.72 ± 0.078)0.173– 0.259 (0.216 ± 0.061)0.417–0.807 (0.635 ± 0.094)0.542–0.915 (0.752 ± 0.079)Pulse rate135-263147-323110-169 (143155-17376-203 (12035-234 (119(/s)(187 ± 31)(212 ± 29)± 11)(164 ± 13)± 39)± 46)Dominant frequency (Hz)2929–3531 (3205 ± 139)2584–2756 (2671 ± 68)2756–3015 (2905 ± 72)29292756–3015 (2893 ± 71)3359–3531 (3403 ± 45)Lowerfundamental2500-29722329-25252509-27462700-27332438-25633200-3281frequency(2702 ±(2435 ±(2659 ±(2716 ±(2506 ±(3248 ±(Hz)101.046)55.698)48.378)22.988)29.911)18.165)Higherfundamental3001-34312636-28392802-30282936-29552818-29673289-3350frequency(3165 ±(2757 ±(2960 ±(2946 ±(2902 ±(3318 ±(Hz)91.79)48.063)43.895)12.989)47.896)12.698)First5768-63845930-70745843-62296172-63376128-64156054-6573harmonic(6073 ±(6322 ±(5996 ±(6254 ±(6268 ±(6437 ±(Hz)148.285)295.493)83.465)117.035)78.665)90.211)</p>
            <p>
Phylogenetics (

).

The phylogenetic results support the morphological diagnosis by placing 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
within the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group. At the species level, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is monophyletic with strong support in all analyses (BS&gt; 
90
%; PP&gt; 
0.95
; 

). Uncorrected p-distances using the 
16
S fragment indicate that 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
has the lowest distance to the new species, at 
1.9–3.7
%. Additionally, we find that variation in genetic distance among 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
is not related to geographic proximity. The lowest distance of 
1.9
% (Imaitso Forest; 
FMGV1697
) does not correspond to proximate localities and the highest distance of 
3.7
% is from Ranomafana National Park (Ranomena; 
ZCMV5989
). This variability in distances is likely a result of varying amounts of sequence overlap being compared. Overall, these results provide strong evidence that the species is a separately evolving lineage and does not reproduce with other species in the complex.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>
Distribution (

. 
1
)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is known from Ranomafana National Park (RNP), but has only been found at high elevation sites (~ 
1046–1312 m
, a.s.l.). In addition to the 
type
locality of Maharira, 
DNA
sequences also confirm that specimens 
FAZC
11454, 11462, and 
11480
collected from Farihimazava forest near Antoetra (
20
° 
50
'06"S

, 
47
° 
19
' 
57
"E

, 
1380–1420 m
, a.s.l.; ca. 
55 km
north west of the 
type
locality; see 

Andreone 
et al.2007
) are conspecific. Additionally, tadpoles 
ZCMV9739
collected at Imaloka (RNP: 
21
° 
14
' 
32
"S

, 
47
° 
27
' 
55
"E

, 
1020 m
, a.s.l.) and 
ZSM1164
/ 
2007
from Sakaroa (RNP: 
21
° 
15
'00.1"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
53.6
"E

) belong to 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. The species has a known elevational distribution of ca. 
1020–1400 m
, a.s.l.
</p>
            <p>
Natural history (

)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
was locally abundant but thus far only found in undisturbed, primary forests along fast moving streams and was occasionally found along slow flowing tributaries adjacent to fast streams. Males of the species typically were calling at night from the surfaces of vegetation less than three meters in height (

A–B). Females of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
were rarely encountered and were only observed while in amplexus (

C). We also confirm that 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
at Maharira and that the two species can be found calling less than a meter apart. This is also consistent with 

Andreone 
et al.
(
2007
)

, which found 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(i.e. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
to occur sympatrically. Other syntopic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
at Maharira include: 
<tp:taxon-name>B. madagascariensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. majori</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
aff. 

marojezensis, 
<tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
picturatus
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. popi</tp:taxon-name>
,

and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. reticulatus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Conservation status
. The new species is known from Ranomafana National Park and its vicinity, extending into the Antoetra area. While it is known from a geographic area less than ~ 
5,000 km2
, there are no known immediate threats, reductions in quality or extent of habitat, or observed declines as the species is well protected within Ranomafana National Park. Therefore, the new species meets only criterion (B 
1
), and could become endangered in the future if the situation changes at Ranomafana, for instance through population declines from chytridiomycosis, which has been detected in the park (

Bletz 
et al.2015
). We recommend a conservation status of Near Threatened, following 
IUCN
(
2001
)

criteria.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
The sequence data presented here were insufficient to resolve the phylogenetic relationships among species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex with high confidence. 

Wollenberg 
et al.
(
2011
)

, based on sequences of three mitochondrial genes (
16
S, cytochrome 
b
, cytochrome oxidase subunit I), obtained statistical support for a relationship in agreement with advertisement call structure, placing species characterized by slower note repetition rates (
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
), and species with faster note repetition rates (
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
) as sister taxa, respectively. However, this study did not include 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
for which the 
16
S data suggest a possible sister relationships with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
,

or 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
provides an additional example of syntopic occurrence of closely related species of mantellid frogs (also see 

Andreone 
et al.2007
). Previous examples include the sister species pairs 
<tp:taxon-name>Gephyromantis eiselti</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
<tp:taxon-name>G. thelenae</tp:taxon-name>
(

Wollenberg 
et al.2011
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis majori</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
<tp:taxon-name>B. narinsi
(Vences 
et al.2012
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Instances of syntopic occurrence between species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex (
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
in Andohahela and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
in Ranomafana) are restricted to species with highly distinct advertisement calls. Conversely, allopatric species pairs (
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
<tp:taxon-name>B schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
) have somewhat more similar advertisement calls. The bioacoustic and distributional patterns of these closely related species suggest the possibility of mating signal divergence owing to selection for enhanced pre-mating reproductive isolation, a process known as reinforcement (
sensu
Howard 
1993
). This phenomenon would be expected if there were a fitness cost to inter-specific mating or courtship resulting from imperfect species recognition. We note that some authors (e.g. 

Butlin 
1987
; 

Coyne &amp; Orr 
2004
) restrict the term 'reinforcement' to instances where post-zygotic reproductive isolation is incomplete. Instead, we here follow a definition that extends to cases with complete post-zygotic reproductive isolation, as have other authors (e.g. 

Howard 
1993
; 

Hoskin &amp; Higgie 
2010
; 

Lambert 
et al.2013
). However, the observed patterns are merely suggestive, and future research should include more evidence from species co-occurrences, advertisement calls, and female preference to properly assess such a hypothesis.
</p>
         <p>
Phylogeny should allow for basic inferences about call evolution and biogeography that could be informative about evolutionary processes. However, without a well-supported resolution of the relationships between members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex, it is difficult to use phylogeny to assess the likelihood of particular evolutionary scenarios. Nevertheless, it may be useful to consider two polarized alternatives. First, as found in 

Wollenberg 
et al.
(
2011
)

, it is possible that species with similar advertisement call are also most closely related (thus 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
would be most closely related to 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
, the species with the second slowest note repetition rate). Such a scenario would suggest conservatism in call evolution and allo- or parapatric speciation between northern and southern lineages. An alternative would find 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
phylogenetically most closely related to 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
. This scenario would suggest more recent call evolution occurring in currently syntopic species, a pattern consistent with a hypothesis of mating signal evolution through reinforcement. The placement of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
,

and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
in a polytomy in our analyses suggests at least some call divergence occurring between closely related and geographically overlapping species. It is worth noting that this polytomy could either be a soft polytomy (i.e. caused by insufficient phylogenetic resolution) or a hard polytomy (i.e. caused by essentially simultaneous divergence between the species). However, even with perfect phylogenetic knowledge, reinforcement cannot be demonstrated through phylogenetic evidence alone.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 11
. Close-up photographs of different living specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
showing variation in eye color.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 12
. Reproductive behavior of species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex. (
A
) A typical perch of a male 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
preparing to call; (
B
) a male 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
during emission of advertisement call; and (
C
) amplexus, male not collected, female KU 336829 of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. 
boppa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
More substantial evidence for reinforcement would be demonstration of the ‘classic pattern’ of reproductive character displacement (
sensu
Brown &amp; Wilson 
1956
), where reproductive traits and corresponding preferences are more different in areas of sympatry than in areas of allopatry. This pattern is consistent with the idea that selection for enhanced species recognition is concentrated where species are syntopic, although it could result from processes other than reinforcement (e.g. competition for signal space; 

Hoskin &amp; Higgie 
2010
). Preliminary bioacoustic results suggest that the dominant frequency of the call of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
overlaps with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
in allopatric populations, but is non-overlapping when they are found sympatrically. However, additional evidence on community composition and advertisement call variation is needed to confirm these observations, which might also be related to body size differences between these species. Future work should document the call and female preference variation of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
in sympatric and allopatric populations to look for evidence of reproductive character displacement.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>
We thank Frank Glaw, Jörn Köhler, and the editor Santiago Castroviejo-Fisher for their constructive comments that greatly improved an earlier version of this manuscript. We thank the 
Malagasy
authorities for approving research and export permits. We also thank the organization 
MICET
for logistics assistance for acquiring permits, transportation, and other logistics. We are especially grateful to Centre ValBio, John Cadle, and Eileen Larney for their logistical help and hospitality. We also thank various friends and colleagues for logistic, field, and laboratory help: James Herrera, Russ Mittermeier, Molly Bletz, Emile Rajery, Barbara Korten, Solo Justin, Lova Justin, and Tsimba. 
CRH
and SML thank the National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship Program for funding that helped facilitate this research.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>Literature cited</title>
         <p>
AmphibiaWeb. (
2015
) 
Information on amphibian biology and conservation.
AmphibiaWeb, Berkeley, California. Available from: http://amphibiaweb.org/ (accessed 
24
August 
2015
)
</p>
         <p>Andreone, F.
(
1993
) 

Two new treefrogs of the genus 
Boophis
(Anura: Rhacophoridae) from central-eastern 
Madagascar
. 
Bollettino del Museo Regionale di Scienze Naturali di Torino
, 
11
, 
289
– 
313
.
</p>
         <p>Andreone, F.
(
1994
) 

The amphibians of Ranomafana rain forest, 
Madagascar
- preliminary community analysis and conservation considerations

. 
Oryx
, 
28
, 
207
– 
214
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1017
/S003060530002857X
</p>
         <p>Andreone, F.
(
1996
) 

Another new green treefrog, 
Boophis anjanaharibeensis
n. sp. (Ranidae: Rhacophorinae), from northeastern 
Madagascar
. 
Aqua
, 
2
, 

25– 
32
.
</p>
         <p>Andreone, F.
, 
Cadle, J.E.
, 
Cox, N.
, 
Glaw, F.
, 
Nussbaum, R.A.
, 
Raxworthy, C.J.
, 
Stuart, S.N.
, 
Vallan, D.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2005
) 

Species review of amphibian extinction risks in 
Madagascar
: conclusions from the Global Amphibian Assessment

. 
Conservation Biology
, 
19
, 

1790– 
1802
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1523
-1739.2005.00249.x
</p>
         <p>Andreone, F.
, 
Vences, M.
, 
Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Randrianirina, J.E.
(
2007
) 
Remarkable records of amphibians and reptiles on Madagascar’s central high plateau
. 
Tropical Zoology
, 
20
, 

19– 
39
.
</p>
         <p>Avise, J.C.
(
2000
) 
Phylogeography: the history and formation of species
.
Harvard University Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts
, 
447
pp.
</p>
         <p>Bandelt, H.
, 
Forster, P.
&amp; 
Röhl, A.
(
1999
) 
Median-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogenies
. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
,
16
, 

37– 
48
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/oxfordjournals.molbev.a026036
</p>
         <p>Bletz, M.C.
, 
Rosa, G.M.
, 
Andreone, F.
, 
Courtois, E.A.
, 
Schmeller, D.S.
, 
Rabibisoa, N.H.C.
, 
Rabemananjara, F.C.E.
, 
Raharivololoniaina, L.
, 
Vences, M.
, 
Weldon, C.
, 
Edmonds, D.
, 
Raxworthy, C.J.
, 
Harris, R.N.
, 
Fisher, M.C.
&amp; 
Crottini, A.
(
2015
) 

Widespread presence of the pathogenic fungus 
Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis
in wild amphibian communities in 
Madagascar
. 
Scientific Reports
, 
5
, 
8633
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1038
/srep08633
</p>
         <p>Blommers-Schlösser, R.M.A.
(
1979
) 

Biosystematics of the 
Malagasy
frogs. II. The genus 
Boophis
(Rhacophoridae)

. 
Bijdragen tot de Dierkunde
,
49
, 
261
– 
312
.
</p>
         <p>Blommers-Schlösser, R.M.A.
&amp; 
Blanc, C.P.
(
1991
) 
Amphibiens (première partie)
. 

Faune de 
Madagascar
,
75
, 

1– 
379
.
</p>
         <p>Brown, J.L.
, 
Cameron
, A.

, 
Yoder, A.D.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2014
) 

A necessarily complex model to explain the biogeography of the amphibians and reptiles of 
Madagascar
. 
Nature Communications
, 
5
, e 
5046
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1038
/ncomms 
6046</p>
         <p>Brown, W.L.
&amp; 

Wilson, E. 
O
.

(
1956
) 
Character displacement
. 
Systematic zoology
, 
5
(
2
), 
49-64
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.2307
/ 
2411924</p>
         <p>Butlin, R.
(
1987
) 
Speciation by reinforcement
. 
Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution
, 
2
, 

8– 
13
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1016
/0169- 
5347
(
87
) 
90193
- 
5</p>
         <p>Cadle, J.E.
(
2003
) 
Boophis
. 
In:Goodman, S.M.
&amp; 
Benstead, J.P.
(Eds.), 

The Natural History of 
Madagascar
. 

University of Chicago Press, Chicago, Illinois, 
U.S.A.
, pp. 
916–919
.
</p>
         <p>Coyne, J.A.
&amp; 
Orr, H.A.
(
2004
) 
Speciation
.
Sinauerr Associates, Inc., Sunderland, Massachusetts
, 
545
pp.
</p>
         <p>Crottini, A.
, 

Madsen, 
O
.

, 
Poux, C.
, 
Strau, A.
, 
Vieites, D.R.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2012
) 

Vertebrate time-tree elucidates the biogeographic pattern of a major biotic change around the K–T boundary in 
Madagascar
. 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
, 
109
, 

5358– 
5363
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1073
/pnas. 
1112487109</p>
         <p>Dayrat, B.
(
2005
) 
Towards integrative taxonomy
. 
Biological Journal of the Linnaean Society
, 
85
, 
407
– 
415
. 
http://dx.doi.org
/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1095
-8312.2005.00503.x
</p>
         <p>D'Cruze, N.C.
, 
Henson, D.
, 
Olsson, A.
&amp; 
Emmett, D.A.
(
2009
) 

The importance of herpetological survey work in conserving 
Malagasy
biodiversity: Are we doing enough

? 
Herpetological Review
, 
40
, 

19– 
25
.
</p>
         <p>de Queiroz, K.
(
1998
) 
The general lineage concept of species, species criteria, and the process of speciation: A conceptual unification and terminological recommendations
. 
In:Howard, D.J.
&amp; 
Berlocher, S.H.
(Eds.), 
Endless Forms: Species and Speciation
. 
Oxford University Press, Oxford
, pp. 
57–75
.
</p>
         <p>de Queiroz, K.
(
2005
) 
Ernst Mayr and the modern concept of species
. 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
, 
102
, 
6600–6607
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1073
/pnas.0502030102
</p>
         <p>de Queiroz, K.
(
2007
) 
Species concepts and species delimitation
. 
Systematic Biology
,
56
, 
879
– 
886
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/ 
10635150701701083</p>
         <p>Duellman, W.E.
&amp; 
Trueb, L.
(
1994
) 
Biology of Amphibians
.
Johns Hopkins University Press, London
, 
670
pp.
</p>
         <p>Esselstyn, J.A.
, 
Garcia, H.J.
, 
Saulog, M.G.
&amp; 
Heaney, L.R.
(
2008
) 

A new species of 
Desmalopex
(Pteropodidae) from the 
Philippines
, with a phylogenetic analysis of the Pteropodini

. 
Journal of Mammalogy
, 
89
, 
815
– 
825
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1644
/07-MAMM-A- 
285.1</p>
         <p>Geneious R8
. (
2015
) 
created by Biomatters. Available from
: 
http://www.geneious.com
/ (accessed 
5
October 
2015
)
</p>
         <p>Gerhardt, H.C.
, 
Tanner, S.D.
, 
Corrigan, C.M.
&amp; 
Walton, H.C.
(
2000
) 

Female preference functions based on call duration in the gray tree frog (
Hyla versicolor
)

. 
Behavioral Ecology
, 
11
, 
663
– 
669
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/beheco/11.6.663
</p>
         <p>Glaw, F.
, 
Koehler, J.
, 
De
la Riva, I.

, 
Vieites, D.R.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2010
) 

Integrative taxonomy of 
Malagasy
treefrogs: combination of molecular genetics, bioacoustics and comparative morphology reveals twelve additional species of 
Boophis
. 
Zootaxa
, 
2383
, 
82
.
</p>
         <p>Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Thiesmeier, B.
(
1993
) 

Bioakustische Differenzierung in der 
Boophis luteus
-Gruppe (Anura: Rhacophoridae), mit Beschreibung einer neuen Art und einer neuen Unterart

. 
Salamandra
, 
28
, 
258
– 
269
.
</p>
         <p>Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
1997
) 
Anuran eye colouration: definitions, variation, taxonomic implications and possible functions
. 
In:Böhme, W.
, 
Bischoff, W.
&amp; 
Ziegler, T.
(Eds.), 
Herpetologia Bonnensis
. 

SEH Proceedings, Bonn, 
Germany
, pp. 
125– 138
.
</p>
         <p>Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2002
) 

A new cryptic treefrog species of the 
Boophis luteus
group from 
Madagascar
: bioacoustic and genetic evidence (Amphibia, Anura, Mantellidae)

. 
Spixiana
, 
25
, 
173
– 
181
.
</p>
         <p>Glaw, F.
, 
Vences, M.
, 
Andreone, F.
&amp; 
Vallan, D.
(
2001
) 

Revision of the 
Boophis majori
group (Amphibia: Mantellidae) from 
Madagascar
, with descriptions of five new species

. 
Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society
, 
133
, 
495
– 
529
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1096-3642.2001
.tb00637.x
</p>
         <p>Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2006
) 
Phylogeny and genus-level classification of mantellid frogs
. 
Organisms Diversity &amp; Evolution
, 
6
, 
236
– 
253
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1016
/j.ode.2005.12.001
</p>
         <p>Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2007
) 

A Field Guide to the Amphibians and Reptiles of 
Madagascar
, Third Edition

.
Self published, Köln
, 
496
pp.
</p>
         <p>Goodman, S.M.
&amp; 
Benstead, J.P.
(
2003
) 

Natural history of 
Madagascar
. 
University of Chicago Press, Chicago, Illinois
, 
1709
pp.
</p>
         <p>Hoskin, C.J.
&amp; 
Higgie, M.
(
2010
) 
Speciation via species interactions: the divergence of mating traits withing species
. 
Ecology Letters
, 
13
, 
409
– 
420
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1461
-0248.2010.01448.x
</p>
         <p>Howard, D.J.
(
1993
) 
Reinforcement: origin, dynamics, and fate of an evolutionary hypothesis
. 
In:Harrison, R.G.
(Eds.), 
Hybrid Zones and the Evolutionary Process
.
Oxford University Press, New York
, pp. 
46–69
.
</p>
         <p>Hutter, C.R.
, 
Escobar-Lasso, S.
, 
Rojas-Morales, J.A.
, 
Gutiérrez-Cárdenas, P.D.A.
, 
Imba, H.
&amp; 
Guayasamin, J.M.
(
2013
) 

The territoriality, vocalizations and aggressive interactions of the red–spotted glassfrog, 
Nymphargus grandisonae
, Cochran and Goin, 
1970
(Anura: Centrolenidae)

. 
Journal of Natural History
,
47
, 

3011– 
3032
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/00222933.2013.792961
</p>
         <p>Hutter, C.R.
&amp; 
Guayasamin, J.M.
(
2012
) 

A new cryptic species of glassfrog (Centrolenidae: 
Nymphargus
) from Reserva Las Gralarias, 
Ecuador
. 
Zootaxa
,
3257
, 

1– 
21
.
</p>
         <p>Hutter C.R.
&amp; 
Guayasamin, J.M.
(
2015
) 

Cryptic diversity concealed in the Andean cloud forests of 
Ecuador
: two new species of rainfrogs (
Pristimantis
) uncovered by molecular and bioacoustic data

. 
Neotropical Biodiversity
, in press

. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/23766808.2015.1100376
</p>
         <p>IUCN
. (
2001
) 
IUCN
Red List Categories and Criteria: Version 
3.1
.
IUCN
, 
Switzerland
and Cambridge, 
U.K.</p>
         <p>Katoh, K.
&amp; 
Standley, D.M.
(
2013
) 
MAFFT
Multiple Sequence Alignment Software Version 
7
: Improvements in Performance and Usability

. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
,
30
, 
772
– 
780
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/molbev/mst010
</p>
         <p>Köhler, J.
, 
Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2007
) 

A new green treefrog, genus 
Boophis
Tschudi 
1838
(Anura Mantellidae), from arid western 
Madagascar
: phylogenetic relationships and biogeographic implications

. 
Tropical Zoology
, 
20
, 
215
– 
227
.
</p>
         <p>Köhler, J.
, 
Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2008
) 

Two additional treefrogs of the 
Boophis ulftunni
species group (Anura: Mantellidae) discovered in rainforests of northern and south-eastern 
Madagascar
. 
Zootaxa
, 
1814
, 

37– 
48
.
</p>
         <p>Köhler, J.
, 
Vieites, D.R.
, 
Bonett, R.M.
, 
Hita García, F.
, 
Glaw, F.
, 
Steinke, D.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2005
) 
Boost in species discoveries in a highly endangered vertebrate group: new amphibians and global conservation
. 
BioScience
, 
55
, 
693
– 
696
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1641
/0006- 
3568
(
2005
)055[0693:NAAGCA]2.0.CO; 
2</p>
         <p>Kremen, C.
, 
Cameron
, A.

, 
Moilanen, A.
, 
Phillips, S.J.
, 
Thomas, C.D.
, 
Beentje, H.
, 
Dransfield, J.
, 
Fisher, B.L.
, 
Glaw, F.
, 
Good, T.C.
, 
Harper, G.J.
, 
Hijmans, R.J.
, 
Lees, D.C.
, 
Louis Jr., E.
, 
Nussbaum, R.A.
, 
Raxworthy, C.J.
, 
Razafimpahanana, A.
, 
Schatz, G.E.
, 
Vences, M.
, 
Vieites, D.R.
&amp; 
Zjhra, M.L.
(
2008
) 

Aligning conservation priorities across taxa in 
Madagascar
with high-resolution planning tools

. 
Science
, 
320
, 
222
– 
226
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1126
/science. 
1155193</p>
         <p>Lambert, S.M.
, 
Geneva, A.J.
, 
Mahler, D.L.
&amp; 
Glor, R.E.
(
2013
) 

Using genomic data to revisit an early example of reproductive character displacement in Haitian 
Anolis
lizards

. 
Molecular Ecology
, 
22
, 

3981– 
3995
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/mec. 
12292</p>
         <p>Padial, J.M.
, 
Miralles, A.
, 
De
la Riva, I.

&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2010
) 
The integrative future of taxonomy
. 
Frontiers in Zoology
, 
7
, 

1– 
14
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1186
/ 
1742-9994
- 
7-16</p>
         <p>Penny, S.
, 
Andreone, F.
, 
Crottini, A.
, 
Holderied, M.
, 
Rakotozafy, L.
, 
Schwitzer, C.
&amp; 
Rosa, G.
(
2014
) 

A new species of the 
Boophis rappiodes
group (Anura, Mantellidae) from the Sahamalaza Peninsula, northwest 
Madagascar
, with acoustic monitoring of its nocturnal calling activity

. 
ZooKeys
, 
435
, 
111
– 
132
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.3897
/zookeys. 
435.7383</p>
         <p>Perl, R.B.
, 
Nagy, Z.T.
, 
Sonet, G.
, 
Glaw, F.
, 
Wollenberg, K.C.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2014
) 
DNA
barcoding Madagascar’s amphibian fauna

. 
Amphibia-Reptilia
, 
35
, 
197
– 
206
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1163
/ 
15685381
-00002942
</p>
         <p>Posada, D.
(
2008
) 
jModelTest: phylogenetic model averaging
. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
,
25
, 

1253– 
1256
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/molbev/msn083
</p>
         <p>R Development Core Team
(
2015
) 
R: A language and environment for statistical computing
. 

R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, 
Austria
. Available from

: 
http://www.R-project.org
(accessed 
5
October 
2015
)
</p>
         <p>Ronquist, F.
, 
Teslenko, M.
, 
van der Mark, P.
, 
Ayres, D.L.
, 
Darling, A.
, 
Höhna, S.
, 
Larget, B.
, 
Liu, L.
, 
Suchard, M.A.
&amp; 
Huelsenbeck, J.P.
(
2012
) 

MrBayes 
3.2
: efficient Bayesian phylogenetic inference and model choice across a large model space

. 
Systematic Biology
,
61
, 
539
– 
542
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/sysbio/sys029
</p>
         <p>Ryan, M.J.
&amp; 
Rand, A.S.
(
1990
) 

The sensory basis of sexual selection for complex calls in the túngara frog, 
Physalaemus pustulosus
(sexual selection for sensory exploitation)

. 
Evolution
, 
44
, 
305
– 
314
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.2307
/ 
2409409</p>
         <p>Schwarz, G.
(
1978
) 
Estimating the dimension of a model
. 
The Annals of Statistics
, 
6
, 
461
– 
464
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1214
/aos/ 
1176344136</p>
         <p>Shen, X.X.
, 
Liang, D.
, 

Feng, 
Y
.J.

, 

Chen, M. 
Y
.

&amp; 
Zhang, P.
(
2013
) 

A versatile and highly efficient toolkit including 
102
nuclear markers for vertebrate phylogenomics, tested by resolving the higher level relationships of the Caudata

. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
, 
30
, 

2235– 
2248
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/molbev/mst 
122</p>
         <p>Simpson, G.G.
(
1961
) 
Principles of animal taxonomy
. 
Columbia
University Press, New York, New York

, 
247
pp.
</p>
         <p>Stamatakis, A.
(
2014
) 

RAxML version 
8
: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies

. 
Bioinformatics
, 
30
, 

1312– 
1313
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/bioinformatics/btu033
</p>
         <p>Stephens, M.
&amp; 
Donnelly, P.
(
2003
) 
A comparison of bayesian methods for haplotype reconstruction
. 

American Journal of 
Human
Genetics

, 
73
, 

1162– 
1169
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1086
/ 
379378</p>
         <p>Stephens, M.
, 
Smith, N.J.
&amp; 
Donnelly, P.
(
2001
) 
A new statistical method for haplotype reconstruction from population data
. 

American Journal of 
Human
Genetics

, 
68
, 
978
– 
989
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1086
/ 
319501</p>
         <p>Sueur, J.
, 
Aubin, T.
&amp; 
Simonis, C.
(
2008
) 
Seewave: a free modular tool for sound analysis and synthesis
. 
Bioacoustics
, 
18
, 
213
– 
226
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/09524622.2008.9753600
</p>
         <p>Tschudi, J.J.
v. (
1838
) 
Classification der Batrachier mit Berücksichtigung der fossilen Thiere dieser Abtheilung der Reptilien
. 
Neuchâtel: Petitpierre
. s.n., S.l., 
99
pp.
</p>
         <p>Vences, M.
, 
Andreone, F.
, 
Glos, J.
&amp; 
Glaw, F.
(
2010
) 

Molecular and bioacoustic differentiation of 
Boophis occidentalis
with description of a new treefrog from north-western 
Madagascar
. 
Zootaxa
,
2544
, 

54– 
68
.
</p>
         <p>Vences, M.
, 

Chiari, 
Y
.

, 
Teschke, M.
, 
Randrianiaina, R.D.
, 
Raharivololoniaina, L.
, 
Bora, P.
, 
Vieites, D.R.
&amp; 
Glaw, F.
(
2008
) 

Which frogs are out there? A preliminary evaluation of survey techniques and identification reliability of 
Malagasy
amphibians

. 
In:Andreone, F.
(Eds.), 

A Conservation Strategy for the Amphibians of 
Madagascar
.
Monografie del Museo Regionale di Scienze Naturali di Torino45
, Turin, pp. 
233–253
.
</p>
         <p>Vences, M.
, 
Gehara, M.
, Köhler,. J. &amp; Glaw, F. (
2012
) 

Description of a new 
Malagasy
treefrog (
Boophis
) occurring syntopically with its sister species, and a plea for studies on non-allopatric speciation in tropical amphibians

. 
Amphibia-Reptilia
,
33
, 
503
– 
520
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1163
/ 
15685381
-00002856
</p>
         <p>Vences, M.
&amp; 
Glaw, F.
(
2002
) 

Two new treefrogs of the 
Boophis rappiodes
group from eastern 
Madagascar
. 
Tropical Zoology
, 
15
, 
141
– 
163
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/03946975.2002.10531171
</p>
         <p>Vences, M.
, 
Guayasamin, J.M.
, 
Miralles, A.
&amp; 
De
La Riva, I.

(
2013
) 
To name or not to name: Criteria to promote economy of change in Linnaean classification schemes
. 
Zootaxa
, 
3636
(
2
), 
201–244
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3636.2.1
</p>
         <p>Vences, M.
&amp; 
Wake
, D.B.

(
2007
) 
Speciation, species boundaries and phylogeography of amphibians
. 
In:Heatwole, H.H.
&amp; 
Tyler, M.
(Eds.), 

Amphibian Biology. Vol. 
6
. Systematics

. 

Surrey Beatty &amp; Sons, Chipping Norton, pp. 
2613–2669
.
</p>
         <p>Vieites, D.R.
, 
Wollenberg, K.C.
, 
Andreone, F.
, 
Köhler, J.
, 
Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2009
) 
Vast underestimation of Madagascar's biodiversity evidenced by an integrative amphibian inventory
. 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
, 
106
, 

8267– 
8272
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1073
/pnas.0810821106
</p>
         <p>Wells, K.D.
(
2007
) 
The ecology and behavior of amphibians
. 
The University of Chicago Press, Chicago, Illinois
, 
1400
pp.

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.7208
/chicago/9780226893334.001.0001
</p>
         <p>
Wiley, E. 
O
.

(
1978
) 
The evolutionary species concept reconsidered
. 
Systematic Zoology
, 
27
, 

17– 
26
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.2307
/ 
2412809</p>
         <p>Wollenberg, K.C.
, 
Andreone, F.
, 
Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2008
) 

Pretty in pink: a new treefrog species of the genus 
Boophis
from north-eastern 
Madagascar
. 
Zootaxa
, 
1684
, 

58– 
68
.
</p>
         <p>Wollenberg, K.C.
, 
Vieites, D.R.
, 
Glaw, F.
&amp; 
Vences, M.
(
2011
) 

Speciation in little: the role of range and body size in the diversification of 
Malagasy
mantellid frogs

. 
BMC Evolutionary Biology
, 
11
, 
217
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1186
/ 
1471-2148
- 
11-217</p>
         <p>Yang, Z.
(
2006
) 
Computational molecular evolution
.

Oxford University Press, New York, New York, 
U.S.A.
, 
376
pp.
</p>
         <p>Zhang, P.
, 
Liang, D.
, 
Mao, R.L.
, 
Hillis, D.M.
, 
Wake
, D.B.

&amp; 
Cannatella, D.C.
(
2013
) 
Efficient sequencing of anuran mtDNAs and a mitogenomic exploration of the phylogeny and evolution of frogs
. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution
, 
30
, 

1899– 
1915
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/molbev/mst091
</p>
         <p>APPENDIX I
. Specimens examined and their corresponding museum or collection numbers.
</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa
(Maharira)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana
(Andohahela)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra
(Maharira)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae
(Ambatolahy)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana
(Andohahela)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. madagascariensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. majori</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. popi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. reticulatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
boppa
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
haingana
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisliami</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>liami</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisperiegetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>periegetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophissibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new species of bright-eyed treefrog (Mantellidae) from Madagascar, with comments on call evolution and patterns of syntopy in the Boophis ankaratra complex</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4034.3.6</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EF48FFB98223FFA7EB07FFD4DD4A6B0C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4034.3.6</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>Suggested common English name.
Boppa’s Bright-eyed treefrog 

Suggested common 
Malagasy
name.

Fity maso hazo Sahona ny 
<tp:taxon-name>Boppa</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336830
and UADBA-Uncatalogued (CRH- 
177
).
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336824
(
holotype
), 

KU 
336825
–336829, UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH
080), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH168
), and UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH178
). Ranomafana National Park, Andemaka (
21
°07' 
43.4
"S

, 
47
° 
30
' 
19.4
"E

, 
1237 m
, a.s.l.), Uncatalogued (
CRH775
).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336854
. Ranomafana National Park, Valohoaka (
21
° 
17
' 
51.3
"S

, 
47
° 
26
' 
20.1
"E

; 
1064 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336855
and UADBA- Uncatalogued (
CRH
002).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Ambatolahy (
21
° 
14
' 
38
"S

, 
47
° 
25
' 
34.3
"E

; 
919 m
, a.s.l.), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH818
) and UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH846
).
APPENDIX II
. GenBank accession numbers of newly determined 
DNA
sequences for taxa used in this study. All localities are within 
Madagascar
.

Museum or Species Locality GenBank Accession ID collection ID 
16
S DNAH- 
3APPENDIX III
. Previously available GenBank accession numbers used in this study for the mitochondrial marker 
16
S. GenBank Accession ID’s with an asterisk are those used in the phylogenetic analyses while all sequences listed were used for genetic distances.
KU 336830<tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588032KT588046ZCMV 0 9739<tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, ImalokaKT588047KU 336825<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588033KT588049KU 336828<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588034KT588050KU 336883<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588035UADBA-CRH168<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588036KU 336829<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588037KT588051KU 336827<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588038UADBA-CRH080<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
boppa
</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588039KU 336824<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588040KT588048UADBA-CRH178<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
boppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588041FGZC 2390<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
haingana
</tp:taxon-name>AndohahelaKT588042ZSM 674/2001<tp:taxon-name>Boophisliami</tp:taxon-name>Andasibe, VohidrazanaKT588043ZCMV 0 687<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
luciae</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National ParkKT588044FGZC 2389<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
miadana</tp:taxon-name>AndohahelaKT588045KU 336858<tp:taxon-name>Boophisperiegetes</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588031ZSM 39 2002<tp:taxon-name>Boophissibilans</tp:taxon-name>AndasibeKT588052
Museum or Collection ID Species Genbank Accession ID 
ZCMV4946<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974374ZCMV4942<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974373MRSN
A 
6371<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364574MRSN
A 
6219<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364573MRSN
A 
6197<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364572FGZC291<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848446
* 
ZCMV10348<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609605
* 
ZCMV5989<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974475
* 
ZCMV4917<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974476
* 
FGMV2001
/ 
480<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
AF 
411612FGMV2002
/ 
1699<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>DQ068398FGMV2002
/ 
1697<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>DQ068396
* 
FAZC13998<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
JF 
903873ZCMV
0 
9739<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609604
* 
ZSM1164
/ 
2007<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974477
* 
FAZC11480<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848438
* 
FAZC11462<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848437
* 
FAZC11454<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848436
* 
FGZC239<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848463
* 
FGZC232<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848462
* 
FGZC220<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848461
* 
FGZC219<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848460
* 
FGZC218<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848459
* 
FGZC2390<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
FJ 
559142
*
ZCMV687<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848443ZCMV10501<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609714ZCMV10100<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609745ZCMV
0 
9106<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609730
* 
ZCMV4564<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
975078ZCMV4202<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
975079ZCMV
0 
9744<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610983ZCMV
0 
9740<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610982ZCMV
0 
9731<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610981ZCMV
0 
9192<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610980
* 
ZCMV
0 
9513<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610971ZCMV
0 
9628<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610968ZCMV
0 
9626<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610967FGZC2389<tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
FJ 
559141
*
ZCMV
0 
9349<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610486
* 
ZCMV5090<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974829
* 
ZCMV5080<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974830
*
......continued on the next pageAPPENDIX III.
(Continued)

Museum or Collection ID Species Genbank Accession ID 
FGMV2002
/ 
1804<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068395
* 
FGMV2002
/ 
1800<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068394
* 
FGMV2002
/ 
1790<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068393
* 
ZSM39
/ 
2002<tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
341672
* LR 
269<tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
792492</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
Previously referred to as 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
1
(
<tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Andreone 
et al.2007
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
‘Antoetra slow’ (Glaw &amp; Vences 
2007
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
18
(

Vieites 
et al.2009
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
(

. 
2–3
A)

. 

KU 
336824
, an adult male collected by Carl R. Hutter and Zo F. Andriampenomanana on 
18
January 
2014
, at Maharira within Ranomafana National Park (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, above sea level [a.s.l.]), Fianarantsoa province, 
Madagascar
.
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
. Adult female 

KU 
336829
and adult male 

KU 
336826
collected on 
21
January 
2013
by Carl R. Hutter and Shea M. Lambert with same locality data as 
holotype
. Adult males 

KU 
336828
, 

KU 
336825
, 

KU 
336827
, with same collection data as 
holotype
.
</p>
            <p>Referred specimens.
UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH
080), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH168
), UADBA- Uncatalogued (
CRH178
) with same collection data as 
holotype
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
. This species in named in honor of Nicholas Jay Pritzker, devoted grandfather, father and husband, brilliant businessman, philanthropist, amateur scientist, committed conservationist; and board member, supporter and long-time friend of Conservation International. The name ‘Boppa’ is an affectionate nickname used by his children and grandchildren. This dedication is courtesy of his youngest son Isaac, who has generously supported amphibian research in 
Madagascar
, including this study and future taxonomic research as well. The species name is used as an invariable noun in apposition to the genus name.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(

) is placed in the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
, subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophinae</tp:taxon-name>
, and genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
, as diagnosed by 

Glaw &amp; Vences (
2006
)

. The new species shares the following combination of morphological traits with all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
: presence of intercalary element between ultimate and penultimate phalanges of fingers and toes; presence of nuptial pads and absence of femoral glands in males; absence of gular glands in males; terminal discs of fingers and toes enlarged; lateral metatarsalia separated by webbing; and absence of outer metatarsal tubercle. Furthermore, phylogenetic analyses support the placement of the new species in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is placed in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group as supported by the phylogenetic analyses. Additionally, the following combination of characters provide additional evidence for the inferred phylogenetic relationships: small body size (male SVL &lt;
27 mm
); tubercles or flaps on heel and elbow absent; webbing between fingers present; canthus rostralis indistinct; distinct white tarsal folds present; dorsal coloration translucent green in life and cream-colored in preservative; ventral skin partially transparent in life; red ventral coloration absent; single subgular vocal sac; and vomerine teeth present.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is a member of the monophyletic 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex and cannot easily be distinguished morphologically from other closely related species in the group, which includes 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
(

). Species in this complex lack a dense and regular white-spotted pattern that is present in other members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group; however, most individuals of the new species show some light yellow and white spotting. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
differs from syntopic 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking a yellow parietal peritoneum, which was present in all live photographs and examined live individuals from two different populations for 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
(e.g. Fig. 
3
B and 

A). 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
differs from allopatric 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
by having the smallest, non-overlapping body size among these three species (adult male SVL: 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
= 
20.3–24.4 mm
; 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
= 
25.5–26.8 mm
; 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>24.8
–29.0 mm). However, we could not discern any morphological differences between the new species and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
, which occurs sympatrically at Ranomafana National Park, but has not been observed syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, instead occurring at lower elevations. While we find discernable morphological differences in life, our observations generally agree with previous studies suggesting that reliable morphological differentiation among specimens of these species is difficult (Glaw 
et al.2010
). Despite this difficulty, these species all can be easily diagnosed by advertisement call and/or molecular phylogenetics.
</p>
            <p>
Bioacoustically, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from all other species in this group by having the longest note duration (

) and longest intervals between notes and thus the slowest note repetition rate within calls (

; 

Table 
2
). The most similar species in call is 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
(

B; 

B), which has the second longest note duration and inter-note interval in the group, but does not overlap with the new species in these values. All other species in this complex have much shorter advertisement calls. Additionally, these differences cannot be attributed to temperature, which fall within 
1
ºC across the recordings of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. We did not correct the call of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
for temperature (it was ~ 
5
°C warmer), as it has dramatically shorter note and internote interval durations (
4
-fold and 
7
-fold shorter, respectively) and a much faster note repetition rate than 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, which are differences not likely due to this amount of temperature change. Furthermore, motivation of the calling male was unlikely a factor as the temporal differences remained consistent across hundreds of calls and a variety of motivational states and weather conditions.
</p>
            <p>FIGU
RE 
3
. 
Ex-situ
dorsal and ventral photographs of (
A
) 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
, 

KU 
336824
) and (
B
) 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
(

KU 
336830
) in life.
</p>
            <p>
Phylogenetically, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is reciprocally monophyletic to all other species in the complex with strong support based on 
DNA
sequences of the mitochondrial marker 
16
S (

). The new species also shares no haplotypes of the nuclear exon DNAH- 
3
with other related species (

). Importantly, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
is also monophyletic, which includes individuals from the southern parts of its range and a specimen from Ranomafana National Park that was syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. Although the sister group of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
cannot be determined from the analyses undertaken here, close phylogenetic affinity is suggested with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
, or 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
. Additionally, the low genetic distance among individuals within 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and its monophyly is strong evidence that no genetic admixture is occurring with other species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex. Notably, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
occur syntopically and can commonly be found calling within a meter distance from each other, with consistent and strong call differences (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
also occurs sympatrically with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
(although calling males have thus far not been found together in syntopy) and the calls of these species are highly distinct (

). Finally, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
is distributed allopatrically and has a genetic distance of 
3.5–4.5
% compared to 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of the 
holotype
(

)

. Adult male, SVL 
23.4 mm
. Body moderately slender; head wider than body, HW 
36.3
% of SVL; head slightly shorter than wide, HL 
33.8
% of SVL; snout of moderate length, ESD 
15.8
% of SVL; snout rounded in dorsal and lateral view; nostrils directed dorsolaterally, nearer to eye than to tip of snout; ED larger than 
END
; cranial crests absent; canthus rostralis indistinct, loreal region slightly concave; single subgular vocal sac; gular glands absent. Tympanic annulus distinct, round, TD 48.0% of ED; supratympanic fold barely distinct, tympanic membrane transparent. Vomerine odontophores distinct, well separated in two elongated patches, positioned posteromedial to choanae; choanae medium-sized, rounded. Tongue longer than wide; ovoid in shape, posteriorly bifid, free. Arms slender; subarticular tubercles single, round; metacarpal tubercles not recognizable. Nuptial pad on inner finger 
1
, barely distinguishable; not pigmented, slightly lighter than ground color; fingers moderately webbed and with lateral dermal fringes; webbing formula 
1
(
1.5
), 
2
i

(
1.5
), 
2
e(
1
), 
3
i

(
2
), 
3
e(
1.5
), 
4
(
1
); relative length of fingers 
1
&lt;
2
&lt;
4
&lt;
3
, finger 
2
distinctly shorter than finger 
4
, finger 
1
slightly shorter than finger 
2
; finger discs enlarged. 
Hind
limbs slender; femoral glands absent; white tarsal folds distinct; 
TIBL52.6
% of SVL; FOL 
46.6
% of SVL; lateral metatarsalia separated by webbing; inner metatarsal tubercle small, distinct, elongated; no outer metatarsal tubercle; toes broadly webbed; webbing formula 
1
(
0.5
), 
2
i

(
0.75
), 
2
e(
0.25
), 
3
i

(
1
), 
3
e(
0.25
), 
4
i

(
1.25
), 
4
e(
1.5
), 
5
(
0.5
); relative length of toes 
1
&lt;
2
&lt;
3
&lt;
5
&lt;
4
; toe discs enlarged. Skin smooth on dorsal surfaces, finely granular on throat and chest, coarsely granular on belly and ventral surfaces of thighs. Enlarged tubercles absent in cloacal region. Muscle from right thigh and liver removed for tissue samples; abdominal cavity of right side opened.
</p>
            <p>
After one year in preservative (

), body coloration uniform cream-yellow. Dark pigments are present around nostrils. Dark pigmented spots are present on upper eyelids and along the dorsum. In life (Figs. 
3
A– 
4
), dorsum lime green with numerous white-yellow flecks, dark brown spots present, skin translucent especially on limbs, groin turquoise; upper 
3
/ 
4
visceral peritoneum white, lower peritoneum and flanks transparent; underside of limbs translucent green, joints turquoise. Pupil black; iris coloration reddish-brown around the pupil and outer edges lighter in color, non-uniform; iris outlined in black; iris periphery blue, posterior edges black; eye periphery black. Color sequence from pupil to eye periphery: black, reddish-brown, yellowish-brown, black, blue, and black.
</p>
            <p>
Morphometry of 
type
series

. Measurements of the 
holotype
and 
paratypes
are shown in 

Table 
1
.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

)

. In life, dorsal coloration is lime to a light-lime green, with a white venter that is transparent posteriorly and along the flanks. Some individuals of this species have a white spotting pattern, with some spots being light yellow upon closer examination. Given this, the morphological distinction between the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex and other species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group is weakened; however, these spots can be useful in distinguishing 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
when present. Brown dorsal spots are also variable, as some individuals may have dense, dark patches, several spots, or none at all (

). Additionally, the intensity of the iris coloration is variable (

).
</p>
            <p>
Bioacoustics (

A– 
7
A; 

Table 
2
)

. We recorded and analyzed 
171
notes from six individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
209
notes from two individuals 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
in syntopy with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. All individuals are adult males recorded at night with mist or light rain at a temperature of 
16.9–18.2
°C. The males were calling on the upper surfaces of leaves 
2–4 m
above the ground and were recorded 
1 m
or less from the male. The advertisement call of this species sounds like a long ‘groan’ to the human observer, emitted frequently in slow-paced succession. We define each groan as a note (

A), which are arranged in series (each series we consider a call) of 
5–16
notes separated by extended periods of silence.
</p>
            <p>
Each note in the call of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly amplitude modulated, with the peak amplitude occurring in the last 
50
% of the note. The notes are strongly pulsed, with a rate of 
135–263
(
187
± 
31
) pulses / s. The note duration is 
379–526
(
451.6
± 
42.4
) ms with an inter-note interval of 
989–1659
(
1192
± 
167
) ms. The dominant frequency measured at peak amplitude is 
2929–3531
(
3205
± 
139
) Hz. The dominant frequency is within the fundamental frequency, which has a lower limit of 
2500–2594
(
2702
± 
101
) Hz and an upper limit of 
3001–3431
(
3165
± 
91.8
) Hz. The first harmonic is 
5768–6384
(
6073
± 
148
) Hz. See 

Table 
2
for a comparison among all identified species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex.
</p>
            <p>
comparison are from Glaw 
et al.
(
2010
). Calls were recorded from males calling at night and were
</p>
            <p>subsequently collected as vouchers. Note envelope is the ratio of the time of peak amplitude to note</p>
            <p>duration. RNP is an abbreviation for Ranomafana National Park. Data are the range and then the mean ±</p>
            <p>two standard deviations in parentheses, when appropriate.</p>
            <p>Species</p>
            <p>Parameter<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>LocalityMaharira, RNPMaharira, RNPManjakatompoAndohahelaAndohahelaVohipara, RNPTemp. (Cº)16.9–18.217.918.017.617.623.0n
– individuals
621222n
– calls (note series)
2641222n
– notes
17120966150144108Call duration (s)3.9–22.12 (10.2 ± 3.9)13.5–27.1 (19.7 ± 6.5)25.816.4–28.4 (22.4 ± 8.5)12.8–13.1 (13.0 ± 0.2)13.9–14.8 (14.3 ± 0.6)Note duration (ms)379.0–526.0 (451.6 ± 42.4)104.56– 130 (110.5 ± 8.076)111.5–153.7 (134 ± 10.6)46.6–85.8 (61.7 ± 12.7)208.3–316.4 (249.7 ± 29.8)73.17–169.3 (124.3 ± 20.9)Inter-note989–1659204–341222–318232–352591–910114–248interval (ms)(1192 ± 167)(269 ± 3)(259 ± 37)(238 ± 86)(675 ± 102)(162 ± 42)Noterepetition0.4–0.82.6–2.82.52.6–3.01.0–1.23.4rate (/s)Note envelope shape0.582–0.954 (0.779 ± 0.087)0.550– 0.881 (0.746 ± 0.072)0.539–0.864 (0.72 ± 0.078)0.173– 0.259 (0.216 ± 0.061)0.417–0.807 (0.635 ± 0.094)0.542–0.915 (0.752 ± 0.079)Pulse rate135-263147-323110-169 (143155-17376-203 (12035-234 (119(/s)(187 ± 31)(212 ± 29)± 11)(164 ± 13)± 39)± 46)Dominant frequency (Hz)2929–3531 (3205 ± 139)2584–2756 (2671 ± 68)2756–3015 (2905 ± 72)29292756–3015 (2893 ± 71)3359–3531 (3403 ± 45)Lowerfundamental2500-29722329-25252509-27462700-27332438-25633200-3281frequency(2702 ±(2435 ±(2659 ±(2716 ±(2506 ±(3248 ±(Hz)101.046)55.698)48.378)22.988)29.911)18.165)Higherfundamental3001-34312636-28392802-30282936-29552818-29673289-3350frequency(3165 ±(2757 ±(2960 ±(2946 ±(2902 ±(3318 ±(Hz)91.79)48.063)43.895)12.989)47.896)12.698)First5768-63845930-70745843-62296172-63376128-64156054-6573harmonic(6073 ±(6322 ±(5996 ±(6254 ±(6268 ±(6437 ±(Hz)148.285)295.493)83.465)117.035)78.665)90.211)</p>
            <p>
Phylogenetics (

).

The phylogenetic results support the morphological diagnosis by placing 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
within the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group. At the species level, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is monophyletic with strong support in all analyses (BS&gt; 
90
%; PP&gt; 
0.95
; 

). Uncorrected p-distances using the 
16
S fragment indicate that 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
has the lowest distance to the new species, at 
1.9–3.7
%. Additionally, we find that variation in genetic distance among 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
is not related to geographic proximity. The lowest distance of 
1.9
% (Imaitso Forest; 
FMGV1697
) does not correspond to proximate localities and the highest distance of 
3.7
% is from Ranomafana National Park (Ranomena; 
ZCMV5989
). This variability in distances is likely a result of varying amounts of sequence overlap being compared. Overall, these results provide strong evidence that the species is a separately evolving lineage and does not reproduce with other species in the complex.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>
Distribution (

. 
1
)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is known from Ranomafana National Park (RNP), but has only been found at high elevation sites (~ 
1046–1312 m
, a.s.l.). In addition to the 
type
locality of Maharira, 
DNA
sequences also confirm that specimens 
FAZC
11454, 11462, and 
11480
collected from Farihimazava forest near Antoetra (
20
° 
50
'06"S

, 
47
° 
19
' 
57
"E

, 
1380–1420 m
, a.s.l.; ca. 
55 km
north west of the 
type
locality; see 

Andreone 
et al.2007
) are conspecific. Additionally, tadpoles 
ZCMV9739
collected at Imaloka (RNP: 
21
° 
14
' 
32
"S

, 
47
° 
27
' 
55
"E

, 
1020 m
, a.s.l.) and 
ZSM1164
/ 
2007
from Sakaroa (RNP: 
21
° 
15
'00.1"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
53.6
"E

) belong to 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. The species has a known elevational distribution of ca. 
1020–1400 m
, a.s.l.
</p>
            <p>
Natural history (

)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
was locally abundant but thus far only found in undisturbed, primary forests along fast moving streams and was occasionally found along slow flowing tributaries adjacent to fast streams. Males of the species typically were calling at night from the surfaces of vegetation less than three meters in height (

A–B). Females of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
were rarely encountered and were only observed while in amplexus (

C). We also confirm that 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
at Maharira and that the two species can be found calling less than a meter apart. This is also consistent with 

Andreone 
et al.
(
2007
)

, which found 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(i.e. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
to occur sympatrically. Other syntopic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
at Maharira include: 
<tp:taxon-name>B. madagascariensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. majori</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
aff. 

marojezensis, 
<tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
picturatus
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. popi</tp:taxon-name>
,

and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. reticulatus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Conservation status
. The new species is known from Ranomafana National Park and its vicinity, extending into the Antoetra area. While it is known from a geographic area less than ~ 
5,000 km2
, there are no known immediate threats, reductions in quality or extent of habitat, or observed declines as the species is well protected within Ranomafana National Park. Therefore, the new species meets only criterion (B 
1
), and could become endangered in the future if the situation changes at Ranomafana, for instance through population declines from chytridiomycosis, which has been detected in the park (

Bletz 
et al.2015
). We recommend a conservation status of Near Threatened, following 
IUCN
(
2001
)

criteria.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa
(Maharira)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana
(Andohahela)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra
(Maharira)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae
(Ambatolahy)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana
(Andohahela)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. madagascariensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. majori</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. popi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. reticulatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
boppa
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
haingana
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisliami</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>liami</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisperiegetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>periegetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophissibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new species of bright-eyed treefrog (Mantellidae) from Madagascar, with comments on call evolution and patterns of syntopy in the Boophis ankaratra complex</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4034.3.6</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EF48FFB98223FFA7EB07FFD4DD4A6B0C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4034.3.6</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>Suggested common English name.
Boppa’s Bright-eyed treefrog 

Suggested common 
Malagasy
name.

Fity maso hazo Sahona ny 
<tp:taxon-name>Boppa</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336830
and UADBA-Uncatalogued (CRH- 
177
).
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336824
(
holotype
), 

KU 
336825
–336829, UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH
080), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH168
), and UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH178
). Ranomafana National Park, Andemaka (
21
°07' 
43.4
"S

, 
47
° 
30
' 
19.4
"E

, 
1237 m
, a.s.l.), Uncatalogued (
CRH775
).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336854
. Ranomafana National Park, Valohoaka (
21
° 
17
' 
51.3
"S

, 
47
° 
26
' 
20.1
"E

; 
1064 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336855
and UADBA- Uncatalogued (
CRH
002).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Ambatolahy (
21
° 
14
' 
38
"S

, 
47
° 
25
' 
34.3
"E

; 
919 m
, a.s.l.), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH818
) and UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH846
).
APPENDIX II
. GenBank accession numbers of newly determined 
DNA
sequences for taxa used in this study. All localities are within 
Madagascar
.

Museum or Species Locality GenBank Accession ID collection ID 
16
S DNAH- 
3APPENDIX III
. Previously available GenBank accession numbers used in this study for the mitochondrial marker 
16
S. GenBank Accession ID’s with an asterisk are those used in the phylogenetic analyses while all sequences listed were used for genetic distances.
KU 336830<tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588032KT588046ZCMV 0 9739<tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, ImalokaKT588047KU 336825<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588033KT588049KU 336828<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588034KT588050KU 336883<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588035UADBA-CRH168<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588036KU 336829<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588037KT588051KU 336827<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588038UADBA-CRH080<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
boppa
</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588039KU 336824<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588040KT588048UADBA-CRH178<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
boppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588041FGZC 2390<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
haingana
</tp:taxon-name>AndohahelaKT588042ZSM 674/2001<tp:taxon-name>Boophisliami</tp:taxon-name>Andasibe, VohidrazanaKT588043ZCMV 0 687<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
luciae</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National ParkKT588044FGZC 2389<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
miadana</tp:taxon-name>AndohahelaKT588045KU 336858<tp:taxon-name>Boophisperiegetes</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588031ZSM 39 2002<tp:taxon-name>Boophissibilans</tp:taxon-name>AndasibeKT588052
Museum or Collection ID Species Genbank Accession ID 
ZCMV4946<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974374ZCMV4942<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974373MRSN
A 
6371<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364574MRSN
A 
6219<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364573MRSN
A 
6197<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364572FGZC291<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848446
* 
ZCMV10348<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609605
* 
ZCMV5989<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974475
* 
ZCMV4917<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974476
* 
FGMV2001
/ 
480<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
AF 
411612FGMV2002
/ 
1699<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>DQ068398FGMV2002
/ 
1697<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>DQ068396
* 
FAZC13998<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
JF 
903873ZCMV
0 
9739<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609604
* 
ZSM1164
/ 
2007<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974477
* 
FAZC11480<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848438
* 
FAZC11462<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848437
* 
FAZC11454<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848436
* 
FGZC239<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848463
* 
FGZC232<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848462
* 
FGZC220<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848461
* 
FGZC219<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848460
* 
FGZC218<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848459
* 
FGZC2390<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
FJ 
559142
*
ZCMV687<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848443ZCMV10501<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609714ZCMV10100<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609745ZCMV
0 
9106<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609730
* 
ZCMV4564<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
975078ZCMV4202<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
975079ZCMV
0 
9744<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610983ZCMV
0 
9740<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610982ZCMV
0 
9731<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610981ZCMV
0 
9192<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610980
* 
ZCMV
0 
9513<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610971ZCMV
0 
9628<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610968ZCMV
0 
9626<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610967FGZC2389<tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
FJ 
559141
*
ZCMV
0 
9349<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610486
* 
ZCMV5090<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974829
* 
ZCMV5080<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974830
*
......continued on the next pageAPPENDIX III.
(Continued)

Museum or Collection ID Species Genbank Accession ID 
FGMV2002
/ 
1804<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068395
* 
FGMV2002
/ 
1800<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068394
* 
FGMV2002
/ 
1790<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068393
* 
ZSM39
/ 
2002<tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
341672
* LR 
269<tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
792492</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
Previously referred to as 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
1
(
<tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Andreone 
et al.2007
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
‘Antoetra slow’ (Glaw &amp; Vences 
2007
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
18
(

Vieites 
et al.2009
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
(

. 
2–3
A)

. 

KU 
336824
, an adult male collected by Carl R. Hutter and Zo F. Andriampenomanana on 
18
January 
2014
, at Maharira within Ranomafana National Park (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, above sea level [a.s.l.]), Fianarantsoa province, 
Madagascar
.
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
. Adult female 

KU 
336829
and adult male 

KU 
336826
collected on 
21
January 
2013
by Carl R. Hutter and Shea M. Lambert with same locality data as 
holotype
. Adult males 

KU 
336828
, 

KU 
336825
, 

KU 
336827
, with same collection data as 
holotype
.
</p>
            <p>Referred specimens.
UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH
080), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH168
), UADBA- Uncatalogued (
CRH178
) with same collection data as 
holotype
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
. This species in named in honor of Nicholas Jay Pritzker, devoted grandfather, father and husband, brilliant businessman, philanthropist, amateur scientist, committed conservationist; and board member, supporter and long-time friend of Conservation International. The name ‘Boppa’ is an affectionate nickname used by his children and grandchildren. This dedication is courtesy of his youngest son Isaac, who has generously supported amphibian research in 
Madagascar
, including this study and future taxonomic research as well. The species name is used as an invariable noun in apposition to the genus name.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(

) is placed in the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
, subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophinae</tp:taxon-name>
, and genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
, as diagnosed by 

Glaw &amp; Vences (
2006
)

. The new species shares the following combination of morphological traits with all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
: presence of intercalary element between ultimate and penultimate phalanges of fingers and toes; presence of nuptial pads and absence of femoral glands in males; absence of gular glands in males; terminal discs of fingers and toes enlarged; lateral metatarsalia separated by webbing; and absence of outer metatarsal tubercle. Furthermore, phylogenetic analyses support the placement of the new species in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is placed in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group as supported by the phylogenetic analyses. Additionally, the following combination of characters provide additional evidence for the inferred phylogenetic relationships: small body size (male SVL &lt;
27 mm
); tubercles or flaps on heel and elbow absent; webbing between fingers present; canthus rostralis indistinct; distinct white tarsal folds present; dorsal coloration translucent green in life and cream-colored in preservative; ventral skin partially transparent in life; red ventral coloration absent; single subgular vocal sac; and vomerine teeth present.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is a member of the monophyletic 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex and cannot easily be distinguished morphologically from other closely related species in the group, which includes 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
(

). Species in this complex lack a dense and regular white-spotted pattern that is present in other members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group; however, most individuals of the new species show some light yellow and white spotting. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
differs from syntopic 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking a yellow parietal peritoneum, which was present in all live photographs and examined live individuals from two different populations for 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
(e.g. Fig. 
3
B and 

A). 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
differs from allopatric 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
by having the smallest, non-overlapping body size among these three species (adult male SVL: 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
= 
20.3–24.4 mm
; 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
= 
25.5–26.8 mm
; 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>24.8
–29.0 mm). However, we could not discern any morphological differences between the new species and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
, which occurs sympatrically at Ranomafana National Park, but has not been observed syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, instead occurring at lower elevations. While we find discernable morphological differences in life, our observations generally agree with previous studies suggesting that reliable morphological differentiation among specimens of these species is difficult (Glaw 
et al.2010
). Despite this difficulty, these species all can be easily diagnosed by advertisement call and/or molecular phylogenetics.
</p>
            <p>
Bioacoustically, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from all other species in this group by having the longest note duration (

) and longest intervals between notes and thus the slowest note repetition rate within calls (

; 

Table 
2
). The most similar species in call is 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
(

B; 

B), which has the second longest note duration and inter-note interval in the group, but does not overlap with the new species in these values. All other species in this complex have much shorter advertisement calls. Additionally, these differences cannot be attributed to temperature, which fall within 
1
ºC across the recordings of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. We did not correct the call of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
for temperature (it was ~ 
5
°C warmer), as it has dramatically shorter note and internote interval durations (
4
-fold and 
7
-fold shorter, respectively) and a much faster note repetition rate than 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, which are differences not likely due to this amount of temperature change. Furthermore, motivation of the calling male was unlikely a factor as the temporal differences remained consistent across hundreds of calls and a variety of motivational states and weather conditions.
</p>
            <p>FIGU
RE 
3
. 
Ex-situ
dorsal and ventral photographs of (
A
) 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
, 

KU 
336824
) and (
B
) 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
(

KU 
336830
) in life.
</p>
            <p>
Phylogenetically, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is reciprocally monophyletic to all other species in the complex with strong support based on 
DNA
sequences of the mitochondrial marker 
16
S (

). The new species also shares no haplotypes of the nuclear exon DNAH- 
3
with other related species (

). Importantly, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
is also monophyletic, which includes individuals from the southern parts of its range and a specimen from Ranomafana National Park that was syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. Although the sister group of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
cannot be determined from the analyses undertaken here, close phylogenetic affinity is suggested with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
, or 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
. Additionally, the low genetic distance among individuals within 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and its monophyly is strong evidence that no genetic admixture is occurring with other species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex. Notably, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
occur syntopically and can commonly be found calling within a meter distance from each other, with consistent and strong call differences (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
also occurs sympatrically with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
(although calling males have thus far not been found together in syntopy) and the calls of these species are highly distinct (

). Finally, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
is distributed allopatrically and has a genetic distance of 
3.5–4.5
% compared to 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of the 
holotype
(

)

. Adult male, SVL 
23.4 mm
. Body moderately slender; head wider than body, HW 
36.3
% of SVL; head slightly shorter than wide, HL 
33.8
% of SVL; snout of moderate length, ESD 
15.8
% of SVL; snout rounded in dorsal and lateral view; nostrils directed dorsolaterally, nearer to eye than to tip of snout; ED larger than 
END
; cranial crests absent; canthus rostralis indistinct, loreal region slightly concave; single subgular vocal sac; gular glands absent. Tympanic annulus distinct, round, TD 48.0% of ED; supratympanic fold barely distinct, tympanic membrane transparent. Vomerine odontophores distinct, well separated in two elongated patches, positioned posteromedial to choanae; choanae medium-sized, rounded. Tongue longer than wide; ovoid in shape, posteriorly bifid, free. Arms slender; subarticular tubercles single, round; metacarpal tubercles not recognizable. Nuptial pad on inner finger 
1
, barely distinguishable; not pigmented, slightly lighter than ground color; fingers moderately webbed and with lateral dermal fringes; webbing formula 
1
(
1.5
), 
2
i

(
1.5
), 
2
e(
1
), 
3
i

(
2
), 
3
e(
1.5
), 
4
(
1
); relative length of fingers 
1
&lt;
2
&lt;
4
&lt;
3
, finger 
2
distinctly shorter than finger 
4
, finger 
1
slightly shorter than finger 
2
; finger discs enlarged. 
Hind
limbs slender; femoral glands absent; white tarsal folds distinct; 
TIBL52.6
% of SVL; FOL 
46.6
% of SVL; lateral metatarsalia separated by webbing; inner metatarsal tubercle small, distinct, elongated; no outer metatarsal tubercle; toes broadly webbed; webbing formula 
1
(
0.5
), 
2
i

(
0.75
), 
2
e(
0.25
), 
3
i

(
1
), 
3
e(
0.25
), 
4
i

(
1.25
), 
4
e(
1.5
), 
5
(
0.5
); relative length of toes 
1
&lt;
2
&lt;
3
&lt;
5
&lt;
4
; toe discs enlarged. Skin smooth on dorsal surfaces, finely granular on throat and chest, coarsely granular on belly and ventral surfaces of thighs. Enlarged tubercles absent in cloacal region. Muscle from right thigh and liver removed for tissue samples; abdominal cavity of right side opened.
</p>
            <p>
After one year in preservative (

), body coloration uniform cream-yellow. Dark pigments are present around nostrils. Dark pigmented spots are present on upper eyelids and along the dorsum. In life (Figs. 
3
A– 
4
), dorsum lime green with numerous white-yellow flecks, dark brown spots present, skin translucent especially on limbs, groin turquoise; upper 
3
/ 
4
visceral peritoneum white, lower peritoneum and flanks transparent; underside of limbs translucent green, joints turquoise. Pupil black; iris coloration reddish-brown around the pupil and outer edges lighter in color, non-uniform; iris outlined in black; iris periphery blue, posterior edges black; eye periphery black. Color sequence from pupil to eye periphery: black, reddish-brown, yellowish-brown, black, blue, and black.
</p>
            <p>
Morphometry of 
type
series

. Measurements of the 
holotype
and 
paratypes
are shown in 

Table 
1
.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

)

. In life, dorsal coloration is lime to a light-lime green, with a white venter that is transparent posteriorly and along the flanks. Some individuals of this species have a white spotting pattern, with some spots being light yellow upon closer examination. Given this, the morphological distinction between the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex and other species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group is weakened; however, these spots can be useful in distinguishing 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
when present. Brown dorsal spots are also variable, as some individuals may have dense, dark patches, several spots, or none at all (

). Additionally, the intensity of the iris coloration is variable (

).
</p>
            <p>
Bioacoustics (

A– 
7
A; 

Table 
2
)

. We recorded and analyzed 
171
notes from six individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
209
notes from two individuals 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
in syntopy with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. All individuals are adult males recorded at night with mist or light rain at a temperature of 
16.9–18.2
°C. The males were calling on the upper surfaces of leaves 
2–4 m
above the ground and were recorded 
1 m
or less from the male. The advertisement call of this species sounds like a long ‘groan’ to the human observer, emitted frequently in slow-paced succession. We define each groan as a note (

A), which are arranged in series (each series we consider a call) of 
5–16
notes separated by extended periods of silence.
</p>
            <p>
Each note in the call of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly amplitude modulated, with the peak amplitude occurring in the last 
50
% of the note. The notes are strongly pulsed, with a rate of 
135–263
(
187
± 
31
) pulses / s. The note duration is 
379–526
(
451.6
± 
42.4
) ms with an inter-note interval of 
989–1659
(
1192
± 
167
) ms. The dominant frequency measured at peak amplitude is 
2929–3531
(
3205
± 
139
) Hz. The dominant frequency is within the fundamental frequency, which has a lower limit of 
2500–2594
(
2702
± 
101
) Hz and an upper limit of 
3001–3431
(
3165
± 
91.8
) Hz. The first harmonic is 
5768–6384
(
6073
± 
148
) Hz. See 

Table 
2
for a comparison among all identified species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex.
</p>
            <p>
comparison are from Glaw 
et al.
(
2010
). Calls were recorded from males calling at night and were
</p>
            <p>subsequently collected as vouchers. Note envelope is the ratio of the time of peak amplitude to note</p>
            <p>duration. RNP is an abbreviation for Ranomafana National Park. Data are the range and then the mean ±</p>
            <p>two standard deviations in parentheses, when appropriate.</p>
            <p>Species</p>
            <p>Parameter<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>LocalityMaharira, RNPMaharira, RNPManjakatompoAndohahelaAndohahelaVohipara, RNPTemp. (Cº)16.9–18.217.918.017.617.623.0n
– individuals
621222n
– calls (note series)
2641222n
– notes
17120966150144108Call duration (s)3.9–22.12 (10.2 ± 3.9)13.5–27.1 (19.7 ± 6.5)25.816.4–28.4 (22.4 ± 8.5)12.8–13.1 (13.0 ± 0.2)13.9–14.8 (14.3 ± 0.6)Note duration (ms)379.0–526.0 (451.6 ± 42.4)104.56– 130 (110.5 ± 8.076)111.5–153.7 (134 ± 10.6)46.6–85.8 (61.7 ± 12.7)208.3–316.4 (249.7 ± 29.8)73.17–169.3 (124.3 ± 20.9)Inter-note989–1659204–341222–318232–352591–910114–248interval (ms)(1192 ± 167)(269 ± 3)(259 ± 37)(238 ± 86)(675 ± 102)(162 ± 42)Noterepetition0.4–0.82.6–2.82.52.6–3.01.0–1.23.4rate (/s)Note envelope shape0.582–0.954 (0.779 ± 0.087)0.550– 0.881 (0.746 ± 0.072)0.539–0.864 (0.72 ± 0.078)0.173– 0.259 (0.216 ± 0.061)0.417–0.807 (0.635 ± 0.094)0.542–0.915 (0.752 ± 0.079)Pulse rate135-263147-323110-169 (143155-17376-203 (12035-234 (119(/s)(187 ± 31)(212 ± 29)± 11)(164 ± 13)± 39)± 46)Dominant frequency (Hz)2929–3531 (3205 ± 139)2584–2756 (2671 ± 68)2756–3015 (2905 ± 72)29292756–3015 (2893 ± 71)3359–3531 (3403 ± 45)Lowerfundamental2500-29722329-25252509-27462700-27332438-25633200-3281frequency(2702 ±(2435 ±(2659 ±(2716 ±(2506 ±(3248 ±(Hz)101.046)55.698)48.378)22.988)29.911)18.165)Higherfundamental3001-34312636-28392802-30282936-29552818-29673289-3350frequency(3165 ±(2757 ±(2960 ±(2946 ±(2902 ±(3318 ±(Hz)91.79)48.063)43.895)12.989)47.896)12.698)First5768-63845930-70745843-62296172-63376128-64156054-6573harmonic(6073 ±(6322 ±(5996 ±(6254 ±(6268 ±(6437 ±(Hz)148.285)295.493)83.465)117.035)78.665)90.211)</p>
            <p>
Phylogenetics (

).

The phylogenetic results support the morphological diagnosis by placing 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
within the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group. At the species level, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is monophyletic with strong support in all analyses (BS&gt; 
90
%; PP&gt; 
0.95
; 

). Uncorrected p-distances using the 
16
S fragment indicate that 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
has the lowest distance to the new species, at 
1.9–3.7
%. Additionally, we find that variation in genetic distance among 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
is not related to geographic proximity. The lowest distance of 
1.9
% (Imaitso Forest; 
FMGV1697
) does not correspond to proximate localities and the highest distance of 
3.7
% is from Ranomafana National Park (Ranomena; 
ZCMV5989
). This variability in distances is likely a result of varying amounts of sequence overlap being compared. Overall, these results provide strong evidence that the species is a separately evolving lineage and does not reproduce with other species in the complex.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>
Distribution (

. 
1
)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is known from Ranomafana National Park (RNP), but has only been found at high elevation sites (~ 
1046–1312 m
, a.s.l.). In addition to the 
type
locality of Maharira, 
DNA
sequences also confirm that specimens 
FAZC
11454, 11462, and 
11480
collected from Farihimazava forest near Antoetra (
20
° 
50
'06"S

, 
47
° 
19
' 
57
"E

, 
1380–1420 m
, a.s.l.; ca. 
55 km
north west of the 
type
locality; see 

Andreone 
et al.2007
) are conspecific. Additionally, tadpoles 
ZCMV9739
collected at Imaloka (RNP: 
21
° 
14
' 
32
"S

, 
47
° 
27
' 
55
"E

, 
1020 m
, a.s.l.) and 
ZSM1164
/ 
2007
from Sakaroa (RNP: 
21
° 
15
'00.1"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
53.6
"E

) belong to 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. The species has a known elevational distribution of ca. 
1020–1400 m
, a.s.l.
</p>
            <p>
Natural history (

)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
was locally abundant but thus far only found in undisturbed, primary forests along fast moving streams and was occasionally found along slow flowing tributaries adjacent to fast streams. Males of the species typically were calling at night from the surfaces of vegetation less than three meters in height (

A–B). Females of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
were rarely encountered and were only observed while in amplexus (

C). We also confirm that 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
at Maharira and that the two species can be found calling less than a meter apart. This is also consistent with 

Andreone 
et al.
(
2007
)

, which found 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(i.e. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
to occur sympatrically. Other syntopic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
at Maharira include: 
<tp:taxon-name>B. madagascariensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. majori</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
aff. 

marojezensis, 
<tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
picturatus
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. popi</tp:taxon-name>
,

and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. reticulatus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Conservation status
. The new species is known from Ranomafana National Park and its vicinity, extending into the Antoetra area. While it is known from a geographic area less than ~ 
5,000 km2
, there are no known immediate threats, reductions in quality or extent of habitat, or observed declines as the species is well protected within Ranomafana National Park. Therefore, the new species meets only criterion (B 
1
), and could become endangered in the future if the situation changes at Ranomafana, for instance through population declines from chytridiomycosis, which has been detected in the park (

Bletz 
et al.2015
). We recommend a conservation status of Near Threatened, following 
IUCN
(
2001
)

criteria.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophinae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa
(Maharira)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana
(Andohahela)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra
(Maharira)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae
(Ambatolahy)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana
(Andohahela)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. madagascariensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. majori</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. popi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>B. reticulatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
boppa
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis
haingana
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisliami</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>liami</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophisperiegetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>periegetes</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophissibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A new species of bright-eyed treefrog (Mantellidae) from Madagascar, with comments on call evolution and patterns of syntopy in the Boophis ankaratra complex</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4034.3.6</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EF48FFB98223FFA7EB07FFD4DD4A6B0C</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4034.3.6</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>Suggested common English name.
Boppa’s Bright-eyed treefrog 

Suggested common 
Malagasy
name.

Fity maso hazo Sahona ny 
<tp:taxon-name>Boppa</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336830
and UADBA-Uncatalogued (CRH- 
177
).
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336824
(
holotype
), 

KU 
336825
–336829, UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH
080), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH168
), and UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH178
). Ranomafana National Park, Andemaka (
21
°07' 
43.4
"S

, 
47
° 
30
' 
19.4
"E

, 
1237 m
, a.s.l.), Uncatalogued (
CRH775
).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Maharira (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336854
. Ranomafana National Park, Valohoaka (
21
° 
17
' 
51.3
"S

, 
47
° 
26
' 
20.1
"E

; 
1064 m
, a.s.l.), 

KU 
336855
and UADBA- Uncatalogued (
CRH
002).
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>Madagascar
: 
Fianarantsoa province
: Ranomafana National Park, Ambatolahy (
21
° 
14
' 
38
"S

, 
47
° 
25
' 
34.3
"E

; 
919 m
, a.s.l.), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH818
) and UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH846
).
APPENDIX II
. GenBank accession numbers of newly determined 
DNA
sequences for taxa used in this study. All localities are within 
Madagascar
.

Museum or Species Locality GenBank Accession ID collection ID 
16
S DNAH- 
3APPENDIX III
. Previously available GenBank accession numbers used in this study for the mitochondrial marker 
16
S. GenBank Accession ID’s with an asterisk are those used in the phylogenetic analyses while all sequences listed were used for genetic distances.
KU 336830<tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588032KT588046ZCMV 0 9739<tp:taxon-name>Boophisankaratra</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, ImalokaKT588047KU 336825<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588033KT588049KU 336828<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588034KT588050KU 336883<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588035UADBA-CRH168<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588036KU 336829<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588037KT588051KU 336827<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588038UADBA-CRH080<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
boppa
</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588039KU 336824<tp:taxon-name>Boophisboppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588040KT588048UADBA-CRH178<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
boppa</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588041FGZC 2390<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
haingana
</tp:taxon-name>AndohahelaKT588042ZSM 674/2001<tp:taxon-name>Boophisliami</tp:taxon-name>Andasibe, VohidrazanaKT588043ZCMV 0 687<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
luciae</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National ParkKT588044FGZC 2389<tp:taxon-name>
Boophis 
miadana</tp:taxon-name>AndohahelaKT588045KU 336858<tp:taxon-name>Boophisperiegetes</tp:taxon-name>Fianarantsoa, Ranomafana National Park, MahariraKT588031ZSM 39 2002<tp:taxon-name>Boophissibilans</tp:taxon-name>AndasibeKT588052
Museum or Collection ID Species Genbank Accession ID 
ZCMV4946<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974374ZCMV4942<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974373MRSN
A 
6371<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364574MRSN
A 
6219<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364573MRSN
A 
6197<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
HM 
364572FGZC291<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848446
* 
ZCMV10348<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609605
* 
ZCMV5989<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974475
* 
ZCMV4917<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974476
* 
FGMV2001
/ 
480<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
AF 
411612FGMV2002
/ 
1699<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>DQ068398FGMV2002
/ 
1697<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>DQ068396
* 
FAZC13998<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
JF 
903873ZCMV
0 
9739<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609604
* 
ZSM1164
/ 
2007<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974477
* 
FAZC11480<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848438
* 
FAZC11462<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848437
* 
FAZC11454<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848436
* 
FGZC239<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848463
* 
FGZC232<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848462
* 
FGZC220<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848461
* 
FGZC219<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848460
* 
FGZC218<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848459
* 
FGZC2390<tp:taxon-name>Boophis haingana</tp:taxon-name>
FJ 
559142
*
ZCMV687<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
848443ZCMV10501<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609714ZCMV10100<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609745ZCMV
0 
9106<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
609730
* 
ZCMV4564<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
975078ZCMV4202<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
975079ZCMV
0 
9744<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610983ZCMV
0 
9740<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610982ZCMV
0 
9731<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610981ZCMV
0 
9192<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610980
* 
ZCMV
0 
9513<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610971ZCMV
0 
9628<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610968ZCMV
0 
9626<tp:taxon-name>Boophis luciae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610967FGZC2389<tp:taxon-name>Boophis miadana</tp:taxon-name>
FJ 
559141
*
ZCMV
0 
9349<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
KF 
610486
* 
ZCMV5090<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974829
* 
ZCMV5080<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
GU 
974830
*
......continued on the next pageAPPENDIX III.
(Continued)

Museum or Collection ID Species Genbank Accession ID 
FGMV2002
/ 
1804<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068395
* 
FGMV2002
/ 
1800<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068394
* 
FGMV2002
/ 
1790<tp:taxon-name>Boophis schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>DQ068393
* 
ZSM39
/ 
2002<tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
AY 
341672
* LR 
269<tp:taxon-name>Boophis sibilans</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
792492</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
Previously referred to as 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
1
(
<tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Andreone 
et al.2007
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
‘Antoetra slow’ (Glaw &amp; Vences 
2007
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
18
(

Vieites 
et al.2009
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Holotype
(

. 
2–3
A)

. 

KU 
336824
, an adult male collected by Carl R. Hutter and Zo F. Andriampenomanana on 
18
January 
2014
, at Maharira within Ranomafana National Park (
21
° 
20
'06.3"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
28.31
"E

; 
1233 m
, above sea level [a.s.l.]), Fianarantsoa province, 
Madagascar
.
</p>
            <p>Paratypes
. Adult female 

KU 
336829
and adult male 

KU 
336826
collected on 
21
January 
2013
by Carl R. Hutter and Shea M. Lambert with same locality data as 
holotype
. Adult males 

KU 
336828
, 

KU 
336825
, 

KU 
336827
, with same collection data as 
holotype
.
</p>
            <p>Referred specimens.
UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH
080), UADBA-Uncatalogued (
CRH168
), UADBA- Uncatalogued (
CRH178
) with same collection data as 
holotype
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
. This species in named in honor of Nicholas Jay Pritzker, devoted grandfather, father and husband, brilliant businessman, philanthropist, amateur scientist, committed conservationist; and board member, supporter and long-time friend of Conservation International. The name ‘Boppa’ is an affectionate nickname used by his children and grandchildren. This dedication is courtesy of his youngest son Isaac, who has generously supported amphibian research in 
Madagascar
, including this study and future taxonomic research as well. The species name is used as an invariable noun in apposition to the genus name.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(

) is placed in the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Mantellidae</tp:taxon-name>
, subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophinae</tp:taxon-name>
, and genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
, as diagnosed by 

Glaw &amp; Vences (
2006
)

. The new species shares the following combination of morphological traits with all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
: presence of intercalary element between ultimate and penultimate phalanges of fingers and toes; presence of nuptial pads and absence of femoral glands in males; absence of gular glands in males; terminal discs of fingers and toes enlarged; lateral metatarsalia separated by webbing; and absence of outer metatarsal tubercle. Furthermore, phylogenetic analyses support the placement of the new species in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is placed in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group as supported by the phylogenetic analyses. Additionally, the following combination of characters provide additional evidence for the inferred phylogenetic relationships: small body size (male SVL &lt;
27 mm
); tubercles or flaps on heel and elbow absent; webbing between fingers present; canthus rostralis indistinct; distinct white tarsal folds present; dorsal coloration translucent green in life and cream-colored in preservative; ventral skin partially transparent in life; red ventral coloration absent; single subgular vocal sac; and vomerine teeth present.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is a member of the monophyletic 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex and cannot easily be distinguished morphologically from other closely related species in the group, which includes 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
(

). Species in this complex lack a dense and regular white-spotted pattern that is present in other members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group; however, most individuals of the new species show some light yellow and white spotting. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
differs from syntopic 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking a yellow parietal peritoneum, which was present in all live photographs and examined live individuals from two different populations for 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
(e.g. Fig. 
3
B and 

A). 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
differs from allopatric 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>
by having the smallest, non-overlapping body size among these three species (adult male SVL: 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
= 
20.3–24.4 mm
; 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
= 
25.5–26.8 mm
; 
<tp:taxon-name>B. haingana</tp:taxon-name>24.8
–29.0 mm). However, we could not discern any morphological differences between the new species and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
, which occurs sympatrically at Ranomafana National Park, but has not been observed syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, instead occurring at lower elevations. While we find discernable morphological differences in life, our observations generally agree with previous studies suggesting that reliable morphological differentiation among specimens of these species is difficult (Glaw 
et al.2010
). Despite this difficulty, these species all can be easily diagnosed by advertisement call and/or molecular phylogenetics.
</p>
            <p>
Bioacoustically, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from all other species in this group by having the longest note duration (

) and longest intervals between notes and thus the slowest note repetition rate within calls (

; 

Table 
2
). The most similar species in call is 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
(

B; 

B), which has the second longest note duration and inter-note interval in the group, but does not overlap with the new species in these values. All other species in this complex have much shorter advertisement calls. Additionally, these differences cannot be attributed to temperature, which fall within 
1
ºC across the recordings of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. We did not correct the call of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
for temperature (it was ~ 
5
°C warmer), as it has dramatically shorter note and internote interval durations (
4
-fold and 
7
-fold shorter, respectively) and a much faster note repetition rate than 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
, which are differences not likely due to this amount of temperature change. Furthermore, motivation of the calling male was unlikely a factor as the temporal differences remained consistent across hundreds of calls and a variety of motivational states and weather conditions.
</p>
            <p>FIGU
RE 
3
. 
Ex-situ
dorsal and ventral photographs of (
A
) 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(
holotype
, 

KU 
336824
) and (
B
) 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
(

KU 
336830
) in life.
</p>
            <p>
Phylogenetically, 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is reciprocally monophyletic to all other species in the complex with strong support based on 
DNA
sequences of the mitochondrial marker 
16
S (

). The new species also shares no haplotypes of the nuclear exon DNAH- 
3
with other related species (

). Importantly, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
is also monophyletic, which includes individuals from the southern parts of its range and a specimen from Ranomafana National Park that was syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. Although the sister group of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
cannot be determined from the analyses undertaken here, close phylogenetic affinity is suggested with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
, or 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
. Additionally, the low genetic distance among individuals within 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and its monophyly is strong evidence that no genetic admixture is occurring with other species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex. Notably, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
occur syntopically and can commonly be found calling within a meter distance from each other, with consistent and strong call differences (

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
also occurs sympatrically with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>
(although calling males have thus far not been found together in syntopy) and the calls of these species are highly distinct (

). Finally, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>
is distributed allopatrically and has a genetic distance of 
3.5–4.5
% compared to 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of the 
holotype
(

)

. Adult male, SVL 
23.4 mm
. Body moderately slender; head wider than body, HW 
36.3
% of SVL; head slightly shorter than wide, HL 
33.8
% of SVL; snout of moderate length, ESD 
15.8
% of SVL; snout rounded in dorsal and lateral view; nostrils directed dorsolaterally, nearer to eye than to tip of snout; ED larger than 
END
; cranial crests absent; canthus rostralis indistinct, loreal region slightly concave; single subgular vocal sac; gular glands absent. Tympanic annulus distinct, round, TD 48.0% of ED; supratympanic fold barely distinct, tympanic membrane transparent. Vomerine odontophores distinct, well separated in two elongated patches, positioned posteromedial to choanae; choanae medium-sized, rounded. Tongue longer than wide; ovoid in shape, posteriorly bifid, free. Arms slender; subarticular tubercles single, round; metacarpal tubercles not recognizable. Nuptial pad on inner finger 
1
, barely distinguishable; not pigmented, slightly lighter than ground color; fingers moderately webbed and with lateral dermal fringes; webbing formula 
1
(
1.5
), 
2
i

(
1.5
), 
2
e(
1
), 
3
i

(
2
), 
3
e(
1.5
), 
4
(
1
); relative length of fingers 
1
&lt;
2
&lt;
4
&lt;
3
, finger 
2
distinctly shorter than finger 
4
, finger 
1
slightly shorter than finger 
2
; finger discs enlarged. 
Hind
limbs slender; femoral glands absent; white tarsal folds distinct; 
TIBL52.6
% of SVL; FOL 
46.6
% of SVL; lateral metatarsalia separated by webbing; inner metatarsal tubercle small, distinct, elongated; no outer metatarsal tubercle; toes broadly webbed; webbing formula 
1
(
0.5
), 
2
i

(
0.75
), 
2
e(
0.25
), 
3
i

(
1
), 
3
e(
0.25
), 
4
i

(
1.25
), 
4
e(
1.5
), 
5
(
0.5
); relative length of toes 
1
&lt;
2
&lt;
3
&lt;
5
&lt;
4
; toe discs enlarged. Skin smooth on dorsal surfaces, finely granular on throat and chest, coarsely granular on belly and ventral surfaces of thighs. Enlarged tubercles absent in cloacal region. Muscle from right thigh and liver removed for tissue samples; abdominal cavity of right side opened.
</p>
            <p>
After one year in preservative (

), body coloration uniform cream-yellow. Dark pigments are present around nostrils. Dark pigmented spots are present on upper eyelids and along the dorsum. In life (Figs. 
3
A– 
4
), dorsum lime green with numerous white-yellow flecks, dark brown spots present, skin translucent especially on limbs, groin turquoise; upper 
3
/ 
4
visceral peritoneum white, lower peritoneum and flanks transparent; underside of limbs translucent green, joints turquoise. Pupil black; iris coloration reddish-brown around the pupil and outer edges lighter in color, non-uniform; iris outlined in black; iris periphery blue, posterior edges black; eye periphery black. Color sequence from pupil to eye periphery: black, reddish-brown, yellowish-brown, black, blue, and black.
</p>
            <p>
Morphometry of 
type
series

. Measurements of the 
holotype
and 
paratypes
are shown in 

Table 
1
.
</p>
            <p>
Variation (

)

. In life, dorsal coloration is lime to a light-lime green, with a white venter that is transparent posteriorly and along the flanks. Some individuals of this species have a white spotting pattern, with some spots being light yellow upon closer examination. Given this, the morphological distinction between the 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex and other species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group is weakened; however, these spots can be useful in distinguishing 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
when present. Brown dorsal spots are also variable, as some individuals may have dense, dark patches, several spots, or none at all (

). Additionally, the intensity of the iris coloration is variable (

).
</p>
            <p>
Bioacoustics (

A– 
7
A; 

Table 
2
)

. We recorded and analyzed 
171
notes from six individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
209
notes from two individuals 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
in syntopy with 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. All individuals are adult males recorded at night with mist or light rain at a temperature of 
16.9–18.2
°C. The males were calling on the upper surfaces of leaves 
2–4 m
above the ground and were recorded 
1 m
or less from the male. The advertisement call of this species sounds like a long ‘groan’ to the human observer, emitted frequently in slow-paced succession. We define each groan as a note (

A), which are arranged in series (each series we consider a call) of 
5–16
notes separated by extended periods of silence.
</p>
            <p>
Each note in the call of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly amplitude modulated, with the peak amplitude occurring in the last 
50
% of the note. The notes are strongly pulsed, with a rate of 
135–263
(
187
± 
31
) pulses / s. The note duration is 
379–526
(
451.6
± 
42.4
) ms with an inter-note interval of 
989–1659
(
1192
± 
167
) ms. The dominant frequency measured at peak amplitude is 
2929–3531
(
3205
± 
139
) Hz. The dominant frequency is within the fundamental frequency, which has a lower limit of 
2500–2594
(
2702
± 
101
) Hz and an upper limit of 
3001–3431
(
3165
± 
91.8
) Hz. The first harmonic is 
5768–6384
(
6073
± 
148
) Hz. See 

Table 
2
for a comparison among all identified species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
complex.
</p>
            <p>
comparison are from Glaw 
et al.
(
2010
). Calls were recorded from males calling at night and were
</p>
            <p>subsequently collected as vouchers. Note envelope is the ratio of the time of peak amplitude to note</p>
            <p>duration. RNP is an abbreviation for Ranomafana National Park. Data are the range and then the mean ±</p>
            <p>two standard deviations in parentheses, when appropriate.</p>
            <p>Species</p>
            <p>Parameter<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>B. miadana</tp:taxon-name>B.<tp:taxon-name>ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>haingana</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>schuboeae</tp:taxon-name>LocalityMaharira, RNPMaharira, RNPManjakatompoAndohahelaAndohahelaVohipara, RNPTemp. (Cº)16.9–18.217.918.017.617.623.0n
– individuals
621222n
– calls (note series)
2641222n
– notes
17120966150144108Call duration (s)3.9–22.12 (10.2 ± 3.9)13.5–27.1 (19.7 ± 6.5)25.816.4–28.4 (22.4 ± 8.5)12.8–13.1 (13.0 ± 0.2)13.9–14.8 (14.3 ± 0.6)Note duration (ms)379.0–526.0 (451.6 ± 42.4)104.56– 130 (110.5 ± 8.076)111.5–153.7 (134 ± 10.6)46.6–85.8 (61.7 ± 12.7)208.3–316.4 (249.7 ± 29.8)73.17–169.3 (124.3 ± 20.9)Inter-note989–1659204–341222–318232–352591–910114–248interval (ms)(1192 ± 167)(269 ± 3)(259 ± 37)(238 ± 86)(675 ± 102)(162 ± 42)Noterepetition0.4–0.82.6–2.82.52.6–3.01.0–1.23.4rate (/s)Note envelope shape0.582–0.954 (0.779 ± 0.087)0.550– 0.881 (0.746 ± 0.072)0.539–0.864 (0.72 ± 0.078)0.173– 0.259 (0.216 ± 0.061)0.417–0.807 (0.635 ± 0.094)0.542–0.915 (0.752 ± 0.079)Pulse rate135-263147-323110-169 (143155-17376-203 (12035-234 (119(/s)(187 ± 31)(212 ± 29)± 11)(164 ± 13)± 39)± 46)Dominant frequency (Hz)2929–3531 (3205 ± 139)2584–2756 (2671 ± 68)2756–3015 (2905 ± 72)29292756–3015 (2893 ± 71)3359–3531 (3403 ± 45)Lowerfundamental2500-29722329-25252509-27462700-27332438-25633200-3281frequency(2702 ±(2435 ±(2659 ±(2716 ±(2506 ±(3248 ±(Hz)101.046)55.698)48.378)22.988)29.911)18.165)Higherfundamental3001-34312636-28392802-30282936-29552818-29673289-3350frequency(3165 ±(2757 ±(2960 ±(2946 ±(2902 ±(3318 ±(Hz)91.79)48.063)43.895)12.989)47.896)12.698)First5768-63845930-70745843-62296172-63376128-64156054-6573harmonic(6073 ±(6322 ±(5996 ±(6254 ±(6268 ±(6437 ±(Hz)148.285)295.493)83.465)117.035)78.665)90.211)</p>
            <p>
Phylogenetics (

).

The phylogenetic results support the morphological diagnosis by placing 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
within the 
<tp:taxon-name>B. albipunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
group. At the species level, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is monophyletic with strong support in all analyses (BS&gt; 
90
%; PP&gt; 
0.95
; 

). Uncorrected p-distances using the 
16
S fragment indicate that 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
has the lowest distance to the new species, at 
1.9–3.7
%. Additionally, we find that variation in genetic distance among 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
is not related to geographic proximity. The lowest distance of 
1.9
% (Imaitso Forest; 
FMGV1697
) does not correspond to proximate localities and the highest distance of 
3.7
% is from Ranomafana National Park (Ranomena; 
ZCMV5989
). This variability in distances is likely a result of varying amounts of sequence overlap being compared. Overall, these results provide strong evidence that the species is a separately evolving lineage and does not reproduce with other species in the complex.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>
Distribution (

. 
1
)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is known from Ranomafana National Park (RNP), but has only been found at high elevation sites (~ 
1046–1312 m
, a.s.l.). In addition to the 
type
locality of Maharira, 
DNA
sequences also confirm that specimens 
FAZC
11454, 11462, and 
11480
collected from Farihimazava forest near Antoetra (
20
° 
50
'06"S

, 
47
° 
19
' 
57
"E

, 
1380–1420 m
, a.s.l.; ca. 
55 km
north west of the 
type
locality; see 

Andreone 
et al.2007
) are conspecific. Additionally, tadpoles 
ZCMV9739
collected at Imaloka (RNP: 
21
° 
14
' 
32
"S

, 
47
° 
27
' 
55
"E

, 
1020 m
, a.s.l.) and 
ZSM1164
/ 
2007
from Sakaroa (RNP: 
21
° 
15
'00.1"S

, 
47
° 
24
' 
53.6
"E

) belong to 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
. The species has a known elevational distribution of ca. 
1020–1400 m
, a.s.l.
</p>
            <p>
Natural history (

)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
was locally abundant but thus far only found in undisturbed, primary forests along fast moving streams and was occasionally found along slow flowing tributaries adjacent to fast streams. Males of the species typically were calling at night from the surfaces of vegetation less than three meters in height (

A–B). Females of 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
were rarely encountered and were only observed while in amplexus (

C). We also confirm that 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis boppa</tp:taxon-name>
is syntopic with 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
at Maharira and that the two species can be found calling less than a meter apart. This is also consistent with 

Andreone 
et al.
(
2007
)

, which found 
<tp:taxon-name>B. boppa</tp:taxon-name>
(i.e. 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis
aff. 
ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. ankaratra</tp:taxon-name>
to occur sympatrically. Other syntopic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Boophis</tp:taxon-name>
at Maharira include: 
<tp:taxon-name>B. madagascariensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. majori</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
aff. 

marojezensis, 
<tp:taxon-name>B.</tp:taxon-name>
aff. 
picturatus
, 
<tp:taxon-name>B. popi</tp:taxon-name>
,

and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. reticulatus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>Conservation status
. The new species is known from Ranomafana National Park and its vicinity, extending into the Antoetra area. While it is known from a geographic area less than ~ 
5,000 km2
, there are no known immediate threats, reductions in quality or extent of habitat, or observed declines as the species is well protected within Ranomafana National Park. Therefore, the new species meets only criterion (B 
1
), and could become endangered in the future if the situation changes at Ranomafana, for instance through population declines from chytridiomycosis, which has been detected in the park (

Bletz 
et al.2015
). We recommend a conservation status of Near Threatened, following 
IUCN
(
2001
)

criteria.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
   </body>
</article>
