<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>http://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.700</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Revalidation of Enteromius alberti and presence of Enteromius cf. mimus (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae) in the Lake Edward system, East Africa</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2020</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>DUMMY HEADING</title>
         <p>
Revalidation of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and presence of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Cypriniformes</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyprinidae</tp:taxon-name>
) in the Lake Edward system, East Africa
</p>
         <p>Heleen MAETENS1,*
, 
Maarten VAN STEENBERGE2
, 
Jos SNOEKS3
&amp; 
Eva DECRU4</p>
         <p>1,2,3,4
Section Vertebrates, Biology Department, Royal Museum for Central Africa, Leuvensesteenweg 13, 3080 Tervuren, 
Belgium
. 
2,3,4
Laboratory of Biodiversity and Evolutionary Genomics, Department of Biology, University of Leuven, Ch. Deberiotstraat 32, 3000 Leuven, 
Belgium
. 
2
Operational Directorate Taxonomy and Phylogeny, Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences, Vautierstraat 29, 1000 
Brussels
, 
Belgium
. 
2
Masaryk University, Department of Botany and Zoology, Kotlářská 2, 611 37 Brno, 
Czech Republic
.
</p>
         <p>*
Corresponding author: 
heleen.maetens@africamuseum.be</p>
         <p>2
Email: 
maarten.vansteenberge@naturalsciences.be</p>
         <p>3
Email: 
jos.snoeks@africamuseum.be</p>
         <p>4
Email: 
eva.decru.icht@gmail.com</p>
         <p>1
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author: 
6DBEE3D3-FAC8-438D-B937-54728E17CD1F</p>
         <p>2
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author: 
57C714E0-F233-4B3E-960E-17A7863FBF6F</p>
         <p>3
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author: 
13A8AB26-FF46-437C-9806-D49E11C5E15D</p>
         <p>4
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author: 
1AEB7EED-C939-4702-8590-B3FCA7076324</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>Abstract.
A revision was done on the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Cypriniformes</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyprinidae</tp:taxon-name>
) from the Lake Edward system with a smooth, flexible third unbranched dorsal fin ray without serrations. Specimens with these characteristics had previously been attributed to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
. A combination of a genetic (COI, mtDNA) and a morphometric approach was used. Based on the COI gene, we found two groups with a distance of 8.5%, though neither of the two corresponded to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
. One group revealed to be conspecific with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, previously a synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, described from the Rutshuru River, May-Ya-Moto (
DRC
, Lake Edward system), and revalidated here. In addition, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, described from the Nzoia River (
Kenya
, Lake Victoria basin), is put in synonymy with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. The second group was most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, but differed morphologically somewhat from the 
types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. Therefore, specimens of this group were identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. Morphologically, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
can be separated from 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
based on a higher number of lateral line scales and smaller values for interorbital width, pre-pelvic distance, body depth, maximum and minimum caudal peduncle depth, head width and head depth.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <title>Key Words</title>
         <p>Keywords.<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius perince</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, integrative taxonomy, synonymy.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>DUMMY HEADING</title>
         <p>
Maetens H., Van Steenberge M., Snoeks J. &amp; Decru E. 2020. Revalidation of 
Enteromius alberti
and presence of 
Enteromius
cf. 
mimus
(Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae) in the Lake Edward system, East Africa. 
European Journal of Taxonomy
700: 1–28. https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.700
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>
With an estimated 367 genera and 3006 species, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyprinidae</tp:taxon-name>
is the largest family of freshwater fishes in the world (

Nelson 
et al.
2016

). One of these genera, 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
, occurs only on the African continent and contains about 211 valid species, making it the second largest fish genus in Africa, and the third largest in the world, only exceeded by 
<tp:taxon-name>Schistura
McClelland, 1838
</tp:taxon-name>
(228 valid species), and 
<tp:taxon-name>Haplochromis
Hilgendorf, 1888
</tp:taxon-name>
(229 valid species) (
Froese &amp; Pauly 2019
). The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
, formerly referred to as ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>Barbus</tp:taxon-name>
’ (

Berrebi 
et al.
1996

), represents a non-monophyletic group that includes most small-sized African diploid barbs (

Yang 
et al.
2015

; 
Hayes &amp; Armbruster 2017
).
</p>
         <p>
Taxonomic problems in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
There is a general opinion among ichthyologists that cyprinids are a taxonomically difficult group and that many species ‘look the same’, having a rather uniform body shape (
Lowe-McConnell 1975
; 
Howes 1991
). This specifically holds for 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
. Specimens of this genus can be attributed to three groups based on the morphology of the third unbranched dorsal fin ray: bony with serrations, bony without serrations, or slender and flexible without serrations (

Skelton 
et al.
1991

). While these characters seem to be indicative of a common descent on a small geographic scale, as demonstrated in studies on the species from the basins of the 
Congo
River (

Van Ginneken 
et al.
2017

) and of Lake Edward (

Decru 
et al.
2019

), on a larger geographic scale, they do not seem to give a reliable phylogenetic signal (

Yang 
et al.
2015

; 
Ren &amp; Mayden 2016
; 
Hayes &amp; Armbruster 2017
), and point at convergent evolution at higher levels of hierarchy in the trees. Furthermore, the identification of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
is challenging because of morphological similarities, a limited representation in the literature and because of a lack of identification keys and large-scaled revisions (

Van Ginneken 
et al.
2017

; 

Decru 
et al.
2019

). Consequently, many specimens in museum collections, as well as the voucher specimens of several sequences on GenBank are misidentified (
Hayes &amp; Armbruster 2017
). In addition to the paucity of taxonomic data, recent studies on species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from various regions revealed the presence of many undescribed species (

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

; 

Van Ginneken 
et al.
2017

). This also implies that the species diversity in 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
might be of an even much larger magnitude than currently thought. Indeed, if these findings of hidden diversity can be extrapolated to other regions, then an enormous increase of species numbers among the small African barbs is to be expected, which could render 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
the by far most species-rich, although currently nonmonophyletic, fish genus in the world.
</p>
         <p>
It is intriguing to find these small, inconspicuous fish to be so hyperdiverse. However, the mechanisms driving speciation in 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
have never been investigated. The study of 

Van Ginneken 
et al.
(2017)

on some groups of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from the 
Congo
basin, suggested a mainly allopatric mode of speciation, as most lineages are confined to a certain river stretch. Allopatric speciation is probably the mode of speciation by which the majority of riverine fishes arose (
Seehausen &amp; Wagner 2014
). Still, in the case of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
, it is difficult to envisage how allopatric speciation alone can explain some cases of morphological highly similar species occurring in sympatry, as was found in the study of 

Van Ginneken 
et al.
(2017)

. Furthermore, hybridisation events can also be important in the evolutionary history of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
. This has already been documented for several cichlid and cyprinid lineages in Africa (

Schwarzer 
et al.
2012

; 

Wagner 
et al.
2012

; 

Levin 
et al.
2017

) and specifically for 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
, 

Schmidt 
et al.
(2017)
</tp:taxon-name>
found cases of introgression in some Kenyan species.
</p>
         <p>
Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from the Lake Edward system
</p>
         <p>
The Lake Edward system is situated on the border between 
the Democratic Republic of the Congo
(
DRC
) and 
Uganda
. The system includes Lake Edward (surface area: 
2325 km
²), which is one of the smaller East African Great Lakes, Lake George (surface area: 
250 km
²), the Kazinga Channel, which connects both lakes, and several inflowing rivers and isolated crater lakes. The system is situated in High Africa (sensu 
Roberts 1975
), the southern and eastern part of the African continent that lies almost completely above 300 meters. The rivers in High Africa are characterized by having a poor fish fauna that is dominated by 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyprinidae</tp:taxon-name>
(
Roberts 1975
; 
Skelton 1994
). This especially holds for the rivers of the Lake Edward system, where 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
is mainly found (

Decru 
et al.
2019

). However, not much information is available on the physiochemical characteristics of these rivers (

Mbalassa 
et al.
2014

). The system is situated at the limit of three ichthyofaunal provinces as described by 
Roberts (1975)
: the Nilo-Sudan, the 
Congo
and the East- Coast Provinces. Initially, the system was assigned to the Nilo-Sudan Province (
Roberts 1975
). However, in a recent study on the fish fauna of the Lake Edward system, it was shown that the Lake Edward system has more affinity with the East-Coast ichthyofaunal Province (

Decru 
et al.
2019

), confirming the previous assignment of the basin to this province (

Snoeks 
et al.
2011

).
</p>
         <p>
In the most recent checklist of the ichthyofauna of the Lake Edward system (

Decru 
et al.
2019

), five species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
were listed: 
<tp:taxon-name>E. apleurogramma
(Boulenger, 1911)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. kerstenii
(Peters, 1868)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pellegrini
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
(R̹ppell, 1835) and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. In that study, the need of a revision of these species was already underscored. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius apleurogramma</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. kerstenii</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pellegrini</tp:taxon-name>
all have a bony and serrated third unbranched dorsal fin ray. These species were described from localities in the East Coast Province outside the Lake Edward system. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius perince</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, both with a smooth third unbranched dorsal fin ray, were described from the Nile in 
Egypt
and the 
White Nile
in 
Sudan
, respectively. This renders 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, together with 
<tp:taxon-name>Labeo forskalii
Rüppell, 1835
</tp:taxon-name>
, the only fish species from the Lake Edward system that are not shared with other systems of the East Coast Province, but only with the Nile system within the Nilo- 
Sudan
Province (

Decru 
et al.
2019

). In contrast, the remaining species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
, as well as most other small-sized riverine fishes, are shared with other systems within the East Coast Province and are absent from the Nile. This disparity probably implies an underlying taxonomic problem.
</p>
         <p>
In his review of the Nilotic small barbs, 
Banister (1987)
listed both 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, but noted that they were difficult to distinguish from each other. 
Boulenger (1903)
reported in the original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
that only the anterior scales of the lateral line are pored. 
Banister (1987)
, however, mentioned that the number of pored scales along the lateral line is not a good characteristic to distinguish 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
from other species. The specimens of the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
are small and he found that the pores start to develop when specimens become larger. The same applies to the development of the barbels. 
Boulenger (1903)
mentioned the absence of barbels in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
. However, 
Banister (1987)
found posterior barbels in the larger 
type
specimens. In addition, he stated that the classification of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
relies too much on the number of barbels. In the same study, 
Banister (1987)
mentioned some other characters to distinguish 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
from other species. He found 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
to be more ‘spotted’ than 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
, and adult specimens to differ from spotted specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
in the more anterior position of the middle spot. Additionally, according to the description by 
Banister (1987)
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
has seven well-developed gill rakers on the first ceratobranchial, while 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
has only two that are situated on the dorsal part of the first ceratobranchial and papillate tissue (see 
Banister 1987: 123
, fig. 12) on the ventral part. In the same publication, when redescribing 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, he mentioned two to four large gill rakers on the dorsal part and papillate tissue with zero to three low ridges of unknown homology on the ventral part of the first ceratobranchial. 
Banister (1987)
also put 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
, described from the Rutshuru River, May-Ya-Moto (
DRC
), situated in the southern part of the Lake Edward system, in synonymy with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
. He did this without examining the 
type
specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
During four recent expeditions to the Lake Edward system (
2016–2019
, 

Decru 
et al.
2019

), several specimens resembling 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
were collected. It was, however, not possible to assign the specimens to either of these two species, based on the diagnostic characters proposed by 
Banister (1987)
. In our study, the 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
<tp:taxon-name>perince</tp:taxon-name>
-like specimens were examined using an integrative approach in order to evaluate their taxonomic status, and to assign them to the correct species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Material and methods</title>
         <p>
During the 
HIPE
project (Human impacts on ecosystem health and resources of Lake Edward), four field expeditions to the Ugandan side of the Lake Edward system took place, three during the wet (
October 2016
, 
March 2017
, 
March 2019
) and one during the dry (
January 2018
) season. The Congolese side of the system was not sampled due to security issues. Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
were caught using gillnets with different mesh sizes, scoop nets and a backpack electrofisher. After euthanasia with clove oil, for some specimens, a tissue sample (fin clip) was taken for molecular analyses and stored in 100% ethanol. Specimens were then fixed in formalin. At the 
RMCA
(Royal Museum for Central Africa), specimens were rinsed and transferred to 70% EtOH. For morphological analyses, specimens of the first three expeditions were used and specimens of all four expeditions were used for genetic analyses.
</p>
         <p>
In total, we examined 
214 specimens
, 72 of which both genetically and morphometrically, 
70 specimens
only genetically and 
72 specimens
only morphologically (Supplementary File 
SM
.01). The latter group included the type specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
and of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, as well as four specimens from a marshy area near Tshambi, identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, and mentioned in the original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. One of these specimens was too small to take correct measurements of and consequently was excluded from the analyses. The 
syntypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and the 
holotype
and seven 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
were also examined morphometrically. These species, which stem from other parts of the East Coast and the Nile system (i.e., the regions that border to the Lake Edward system), are most similar to the specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
<tp:taxon-name>perince</tp:taxon-name>
from Lake Edward, and were therefore included in the morphometric study. From the ten 
syntypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, one was not conspecific with the others because it had serrations on the third unbranched dorsal fin ray and it was the only specimen without a clear melanin pattern. Hence it was not included in our analyses. A 
lectotype
was assigned for 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
in this study.
</p>
         <p>DNA extraction, PCR amplification and sequencing, DNA analyses</p>
         <p>
DNA was extracted from finclips using a ‘NucleoSpin 
®
Tissue Kit’ using the standard protocol for human or animal tissue and cultured cells (Macherey-Nagel, 
Germany
). The mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase I (COI) gene was isolated and amplified using the M13-tailed primer cocktail of 

Ivanova 
et al.
(2007)

and the protocol of 

Decru 
et al.
(2016)

, but using 2.0 instead of 1.0 µl extracted DNA. Amplified PCR products were visualised on 1.2% agarose gels and afterwards purified using ExoSAP (Fermentas). The sequences were determined in two directions, forward and reverse, by Sanger sequencing, executed by the external company Macrogen. The DNA sequences were assembled and visually checked in CodonCode Aligner 4.2.7 (CodonCode Corporation). The consensus sequences were aligned in MEGA 7.0.26 (

Kumar 
et al.
2016

) and the primer sequences were deleted.A TCS haplotype network (

Templeton 
et al.
1992

) was generated using PopART (
Leigh &amp; Bryant 2015
) to visualise the haplotype pattern and to examine geographic structuring. Clusters were identified in the TCS-network, based on genetic differences between the haplotypes.
</p>
         <p>
We searched for COI sequences on GenBank (

Clark 
et al.
2016

) of specimens, identified as one of the species examined in this study, in order to compare them with our COI sequences from the Lake Edward system (Supplementary File 
SM
.01). Only five sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
(LC487172.1 – LC487176.1) from El-Kanater station, northern part of the Nile River, 
Egypt
(Dr Fawzia Salah Ali pers. com.) were available (Supplementary File 
SM
.01) (voucher specimens are stored in the National Institute For Oceanography &amp; Fisheries (NIOF), 
Alexandria
, 
Egypt
). The genetic divergence between our sequences and those from GenBank has been assessed.
</p>
         <p>Morphometric analyses</p>
         <p>
Twenty-four morphometric measurements were taken with a dial caliper and 13 meristics were counted on each specimen. Most measurements and all counts were done under a binocular microscope (Wild Heerbrugg M3). Measurements were based on 

Bamba 
et al.
(2011)

with some modifications. Post-dorsal distance I, post-anal distance I and body depth I were not measured, because of the strong correlation with other measurements. The following measurements were added: head width (width of the head at the level of the posterior margin of the pre-operculum), head depth (depth of the head at the level of the posterior occipital margin), anal fin base length (distance between the articulation base of the first and last anal fin rays), anal fin length (distance from the articulation of the first anal fin ray to the tip of the longest anal fin ray), pectoral fin length (distance from the articulation of the first pectoral fin ray to the tip of the longest pectoral fin ray) and pelvic fin length (distance from the articulation of the first pelvic fin ray to the tip of the longest pelvic fin ray). For all meristics, 
Bamba (2012)
was followed.
</p>
         <p>
The multivariate dataset was explored by Principal Component Analyses (PCA) to reduce the large number of variables into a few meaningful axes that are linear combinations of the original variables (
Manly 1994
; 
Snoeks 2004
; 

Decru 
et al.
2012

). Measurements and meristics were analysed separately. Log-transformed data were used for the PCA on the measurements and analysed with a covariance matrix. The first axis of the PCA on log-transformed measurements can be interpreted as a proxy for size (

Bookstein 
et al.
1985

). Hence, subsequent axes can be plotted against the first axis to verify possible size effects. The raw data were used for the PCA on the meristics based on the correlation matrix. Invariable meristics were excluded from the PCAs. Data for the barbels were not included in the analyses, as the barbels were small and difficult to measure and hence their measurements were prone to errors.
</p>
         <p>
A first PCA was performed on the 
72 specimens
from the Lake Edward system that were analysed genetically to evaluate the morphological differences among specimens from different genetic clades. To find possible significant differences between these groups, univariate comparisons were performed with non-parametric Mann-Whitney U-tests (MWU), with sequential Bonferroni corrections (
Rice 1989
). For measurements, these comparisons were restricted to subsets of specimens that belong to a similar size class (
46.4–53.8 mm
SL; with p = 0.6888 for SL). This was done to avoid allometric interference. Scatterplots of individual measurements (% SL) were made to visualize between-group differences taken into account possible size-effects. Based on this first set of analyses, additional specimens for which no genetic data were available, were measured and assigned to one of the groups in order to enlarge the size ranges of these groups. This also allowed for comparison with the 
type
series of similar species. Hence, in a second series of analyses, PCAs were performed to compare each group separately with all of the studied 
type
specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, and with the specimens from Tshambi identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
The statistical analyses were executed in R Studio 1.1.453 (RStudio Team 2016) with R ver. 3.5.1 (
R Core Team 2018
). Scatterplots and PCAs were made using the package ‘vegan’ ver. 2.5-2 (

Oksanen 
et al.
2018

) and the package ‘factoextra’ ver. 1.0.5 (
Kassambara &amp; Mundt 2017
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>
We successfully obtained 137 COI sequences (trimmed to 651 bp) (Supplementary File 
SM
.01). The haplotype network of the specimens from the Lake Edward system (

) showed two clear groups with a genetic divergence of 8.5%. No geographical structuring was observed. We refer to these groups as group A, the smallest group (n = 36), and group B, the largest group (n = 101). The sequences of
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Egypt
, obtained from GenBank, had a genetic difference of 12% from the sequences of our groups A and B, and were therefore not integrated in the haplotype network.
</p>
         <p>Morphometric analyses</p>
         <p>
Of the 
137 specimens
that were analysed genetically, 
71 specimens
were also analysed morphometrically. A first PCA on the log-transformed measurements of these specimens resulted in a separation on PC2 (

) of the two groups that were delineated based on the genetic data. PC1 represented an inverted proxy of size, with larger specimens having lower values on PC1 than smaller specimens. The most important loadings for PC2 were for the post-anal distance and the maximum and minimum caudal peduncle depth (Supplementary File 
SM
.02). In the PCA on meristics, the two groups partially overlapped (not illustrated).
</p>
         <p>
Based on Mann-Whitney U (MWU) tests with sequential Bonferroni correction, 13 measurements and three meristics were significantly different between the two groups, of which the three meristics were highly significant (
Table 1
). Individual scatterplots were made for the most significant measurements (% SL) (

): interorbital width, pre-pelvic distance, body depth, maximum caudal peduncle depth, minimum caudal peduncle depth, head width, and head depth. For all of these measurements, the ranges per se overlapped because of allometry, but for specimens of similar size classes, the two groups could be distinguished from each other, with specimens of group B having higher values for all these measurements. Based on the results of the first series of analyses discussed above, we were able to identify 16 additional specimens as members of group A, and 22 additional specimens as members of group B. These specimens were added to the dataset to enlarge the size ranges of the two groups, allowing for a better comparison of the groups with the 
type
series of the relevant species. Subsequently, each group was compared with the 
types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
and the additional specimens from Tshambi identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>Table 1.</p>
         <p>
Results of the MWU tests with Bonferroni correction on measurements (% SL) of specimens of similar size classes (46.4–53.8 mm), and on meristics of all specimens, on the two groups of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
. Significant values (α = 0.05) are in bold; highly significant values (α = 0.001) are in bold and underlined.
</p>
         <p>Measurements (% SL)Group A (n = 8) × Group B (n = 10)Head length (HL)0.0831Eye diameter (ED)0.0029Snout length (SnL)0.0062Pre-operculum distance (PrOpD)0.0155Interorbital width (IOW)&lt;0.0001Pre-dorsal distance (PrDD)0.0044Post-dorsal distance (PoDD)0.0002Dorsal fin base length (DoFBL)0.5726Dorsal fin lenght (DoFL)0.3599Pre-pectoral distance (PrPecD)1.0000Pre-pelvic distance (PrPelD)&lt;0.0001Pre-anal distance (PrAD)0.0014Post-anal distance (PoAD)0.0009Body depth (BD)&lt;0.0001Maximum caudal peduncle depth (MxCPD)&lt;0.0001Minimum caudal peduncle depth (MnCPD)&lt;0.0001Pre-occipital distance (PreOcD)0.0343Head width (HW)&lt;0.0001Anal fin base length (AnFBL)0.0205Anal fin length (AFL)0.0009Pectoral fin length (PcFL)0.5726Pelvic fin length (PlvFL)0.4082Head depth (HD)&lt;0.0001MeristicsGroup A (n = 22) × Group B (n = 50)Lateral line scales (LLS)&lt;0.0001Total number of lateral line scales (LLS total)&lt;0.0001Pre-dorsal scales (PDSc)0.0266Scales lateral line – pelvic fin (LPSc)0.1268Scales lateral line – belly (L-BSc)0.2653Branched dorsal fin rays (DFR branched)0.1303Branched anal fin rays (AFR branched)0.1450Branched pectoral fin rays (PecFR branched)&lt;0.0001Unbranched pelvic fin rays (PelFR unbranched)0.4942Branched pelvic fin rays (PelFR branched)0.6916Gill rakers upper limb first gill arch (GrUp)0.6935Gill rakers lower limb first gill arch (GrLow)0.8736Total gill rakers (GrTot)0.7320</p>
         <p>
A PCA on log-transformed measurements was performed on the specimens assigned to group A, all the type specimens included in this study and the specimens from Tshambi (

). On a scatterplot of PC2 vs PC1, specimens belonging to group A were separated from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
and the specimens from Tshambi. They were also separated from the types of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, except for one specimen. The 
holotype
and 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
and two of the three types of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
fell, however, into the polygon of group A. The most important loadings for PC2 were the maximum caudal peduncle depth, the interorbital width and the body depth (Supplementary File 
SM
.03).
</p>
         <p>
In a scatterplot of the two main PCs of a PCA on the meristics, the 
type
specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
fell within group A and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
overlapped with group A (

). Here, group A also partially overlapped with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
, due to one specimen, but it was completely separated from the specimens from Tshambi, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
on PC1. The most important loadings for PC1 were the number of scales on the lateral line, the number of branched pectoral fin rays and the number of scales between the origin of the dorsal fin and the lateral line (Supplementary File 
SM
.04). As the specimens from Tshambi, identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, fell separately from the 
types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, these were most probably misidentified. To explore possible differences between group A, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, subsequent PCAs were performed restricted to these three groups. In these analyses, still no separation of the three groups was obtained (not illustrated).
</p>
         <p>
Specimens belonging to group B were also compared with the type specimens of the selected species and the specimens from Tshambi. In the PCA on the log-transformed measurements, group B was separated from most of the type specimens, but partially overlapped with those of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
and with one 
paratype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
on PC2 for specimens with similar sizes (

). Furthermore, one of the specimens from Tshambi was situated within the polygon of group B, while the other one was located just outside of the polygon. The most important loadings for PC2 were the anal fin base length, the interorbital width and the anal fin length (Supplementary File 
SM
.05).
</p>
         <p>
Another PCA was performed on the meristics of group B and the selected 
type
specimens. Here, both specimens from Tshambi fell within group B. Almost all 
types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
were situated within the polygon of group B, except for one, which was located just outside of the polygon. Group B partially overlapped with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
(

). The most important loadings for PC1 were the number of scales on the lateral line, around the caudal peduncle and below the lateral line and, for PC2, the total number of gill rakers, the number of gill rakers on the lower part of the first gill arch and the number of pre-dorsal scales (Supplementary File 
SM
.06).
</p>
         <p>
These PCAs (

) illustrated that the specimens from Tshambi, identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, were most probably conspecific to our group B. This latter group seemed to be most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. Therefore, additional PCAs on meristics and log-transformed measurements were performed including only group B, with the inclusion of the specimens from Tshambi, and the types of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. For the meristics, the 
syntypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
fell completely within the range of group B for the first two axes (not illustrated). For the log-transformed measurements, however, only a partial overlap was observed on PC2 (

). Here, the most important loadings for PC2 were for the snout length, the pelvic fin length and the interorbital width (Supplementary File 
SM
.07).
</p>
         <p>
In the analysis of measurements restricted to group B, one of the 
types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
was situated within the polygon of the 
types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
(

). In that of the measurements of group A (

), the same specimen was situated closest to the polygon of the 
types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. This specimen had an aberrant value for the number of lateral line scales (23) compared to the other 
types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(31 and 32), which corresponds more to the number of lateral line scales found in group B (21 to 31 with median 26). Furthermore, the aberrant specimen had 32 vertebrae in total, while the other two 
types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
had 35 vertebrae. The total number of vertebrae was 34 to 35 for specimens in group A (n = 4) and 
31 to 33 in
group B (n = 4). Based on these results, the aberrant 
type
specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
could be assigned to group B.
</p>
         <p>Nomenclature and synonyms</p>
         <p>
Class 
<tp:taxon-name>Actinopterygii Klein, 1885</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Subclass 
<tp:taxon-name>Neopterygii Regan, 1923</tp:taxon-name>
Division 
<tp:taxon-name>Teleostei</tp:taxon-name>
M̹ller, 1846
</p>
         <p>
Order 
<tp:taxon-name>Cypriniformes Rafinesque, 1810</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Cyprinidae Rafinesque, 1815</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius cercops
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni
(Bailey, 1969)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus
(Boulenger, 1901)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis
(Farm, 2000)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis
(Rendahl, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. toppini
(
Boulenger, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini
(Seegers, 1996)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. anema
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. profundus
(
Greenwood, 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus
(Fowler, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yongei
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus
(Weber, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis
(Boulenger, 1915)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. venustus
(Bailey, 1980)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae
(Boulenger, 1906)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis
(Johnsen, 1926)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(Peters, 1853) (
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae
(Lönnberg, 1907)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. innocens
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura
(Boulenger, 1902)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger, 1903
) (
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. toppini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. anema</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. profundus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yongei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. venustus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. innocens</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Revalidation of Enteromius alberti and presence of Enteromius cf. mimus (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae) in the Lake Edward system, East Africa</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.700</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FF8BFF96F851F31FFFCED72E5D09CC1A</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.700</pub-id>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
The results confirmed the occurrence of two syntopic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
with a smooth dorsal fin ray in the Lake Edward system. Specimens of group A were conspecific with the types of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, except for one type specimen, which was assigned to group B, and with the 
holotype
and 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
used to be considered a synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
.

Based on our results, and following the principle of priority for species names, we propose to revalidate 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
as its junior synonym. A redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
is provided based on the 
lectotype
(here designated) (

) and one 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, the type series of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, here synonymised with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, and the additional specimens from the Lake Edward system examined in this study and identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(n = 37). The other 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, which was revealed not to be conspecific with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, was not included in the redescription. The measurements and meristics can be found in 
Table 2
. An illustration of a fresh specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, captured during the HIPE expeditions is provided in 

.
</p>
            <p>
The specimens of group B were most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, though the PCA on log-transformed measurements (

) suggested some differences. Therefore, we decided to assign the specimens of group B to 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
with “cf” indicating specimens that are comparable to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
but whose identification is uncertain (

Decru 
et al.
2016

). Because of the unsuitable original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
for modern taxonomic purposes, we decided to make a redescription based on the 
lectotype
(here designed) (

) and eight of the nine 
paralectotypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. We found one 
paralectotype
to have a serrated dorsal fin ray; therefore, it was considered not to be conspecific with the other types and excluded from the redescription. Specimens from the Lake Edward system identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, the specimens from Tshambi and the aberrant 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
were not included in the redescription, but their measurements and meristics are given in 
Table 2. A
picture of a fresh specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is given in 

.
</p>
            <p>
For both redescribed species, a 
lectotype
was chosen from the 
syntypes
. For 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, this is the specimen illustrated in the original description by Poll (1939), which is also the largest specimen. The 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is the specimen that resembles most the original figure of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
in the 
Catalogue of the Fresh-water Fishes of Africa in the British Museum (Natural History)
, Volume IV, by 
Boulenger (1916)
. The sampling sites of the two species in the Lake Edward system and the type localities of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
are illustrated in 

. The specimens from Tshambi, initially identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, are indicated as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
on the map, as found in the present study.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
a–b, 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>Previous Treatments</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius cercops
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(here synonymised). syn. nov.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–b) belongs to the group of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
with a flexible last unbranched dorsal fin ray that lacks serrations along its posterior edge. A comparison was made with other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal provinces (list made based on information available in, e.g., 
Greenwood 1962
; 

Okaronon 
et al.
1997

; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

; 

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

; 
Froese &amp; Pauly 2018
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from the other species of this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal regions by the following combination of characteristics (data from original description, unless otherwise stated): a complete lateral line vs an incomplete lateral line in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni
(Bailey, 1969)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus
(Boulenger, 1901)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis
(Farm, 2000)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis
(Rendahl, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. toppini
(
Boulenger, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; two pairs of barbels vs one pair in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini
(Seegers, 1996)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and no barbels in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. anema
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. profundus
(
Greenwood, 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; one to three dark spots on the flanks, which sometimes fuse into a mid-lateral line in preserved specimens, starting posterior to the operculum vs a dark line running from the tip of the snout to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus
(Fowler, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yongei
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and a thin dark line from the beginning of the operculum to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus
(Weber, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 12 scales around the caudal peduncle, with one aberrant specimen in the 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
(16), vs 
8 in<tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis
(Boulenger, 1915)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
9–10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. venustus
(Bailey, 1980)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae
(Boulenger, 1906)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis
(Johnsen, 1926)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 4.5 scales between the dorsal fin base and the lateral line vs 
3.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(Peters, 1853) (
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
5.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
(G̹nther, 1867), and 
6 in<tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae
(Lönnberg, 1907)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a dorsal fin length which is larger than the head length vs a dorsal fin length equal to the head length in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. innocens
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a body depth which is larger than the head length vs a body depth which is equal to the head length in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura
(Boulenger, 1902)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a pectoral fin length which is ⁵⁄₆ of the head length vs ¾ in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and ¾ to ¼ in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger, 1903
) (
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a maximum caudal peduncle depth which is ³⁄₅ of the head length vs ²⁄ 
₅ in<tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a smaller body depth [21.7–31.2% SL (mean 26.9) vs 33.8–37.5 (35.0)], a smaller minimum caudal peduncle depth [10.0–13.6% SL (mean 12.0) vs 15.0–16.4 (15.5)], and a smaller maximum caudal peduncle depth [11.8–15.5% SL (mean 13.6) vs 17.7–19.4 (18.8)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a higher number of lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31) vs 20–25 (21)], a smaller pre-dorsal distance [45.7–51.3% SL (mean 49.0) vs 51.9–55.8 (53.8)] and a smaller pre-occipital distance [16.6-21.8% SL (mean 18.6) vs 22.1–27.3 (24.0)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
by a higher number of lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31) vs 24–27 (25)], a smaller pre-anal distance [65.1–73.0% SL (average 69.3) vs 68.4–74.8 (72.4)], a larger post-anal distance [16.3–24.2% SL (average 21.1) vs 16.3–19.3 (17.8)], a smaller body depth [21.7–31.2% SL (average 26.9) vs 26.5–34.3 (30.1)], a smaller head depth [15.1–19.0% SL (average 17.3) vs 17.8–21.8 (20.2)] and a smaller pelvic fin length [15.0–20.9% SL (average 18.0) vs 18.2–22.4 (20.4)] (
Table 2
). Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differ from the population of 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
from the Lake Edward system by a smaller head depth. In general, a specimen with a head depth smaller than 19% of the standard length can be assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(only one specimen had a higher value). Specimens with a head depth larger than 19% of the standard length can be assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
(only one specimen had a lower value). Other characters to distinguish 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
are the higher number of lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31) vs 21–31 (26)], the smaller interorbital width [5.8–8.3% SL (mean 7.3) vs 6.9–9.9 (8.7)], the smaller pre-pelvic distance [44.8–53.3% SL (mean 49,2) vs 48.4–55.4 (52.1)], the smaller body depth [21.7–31.2% SL (mean 26.9) vs 23.5–35.8 (31.0)], the smaller maximum [11.8– 15.5% SL (mean 13.6) vs 8.7–19.0 (16)] and minimum [10.0–13.6% SL (mean 12) vs 7.1–15.9 (13.7)] caudal peduncle depth, and the smaller head width [10.4–14.2% SL (mean 12) vs 11.6–14.5 (13.2)] (
Table 2
, 

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
Etymology not explained in the original description. Probably, the species epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>alberti</tp:taxon-name>
is derived from the name of the former ‘Parc National Albert’ (now Virunga National Park) in which the 
type
locality is located.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined</p>
            <p>Lectotype
(here designated)
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
Rutshuru River
, 
May-Ya-Moto
; 
5–11 Nov. 1934
; 
de Witte
leg.; 
MRAC 64723
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-209).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Paralectotype</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
1 spec.
; same collection data as for lectotype; 
MRAC 64722
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-210)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>Other material examined</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>KENYA
– 
Lake Victoria
basin
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Luambwa
, 
Nzoia River
, 
Nyanza Province
; 1960; 
BMNH 1960.6.7.37</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>7 specs
[of 
13 in
lot], 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
; same collection data as for holotype; 
BMNH 1960.6.7.38
to 
1960.6.7.50
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-177 to Fiche-183)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>UGANDA
– 
Lake Edward
•
1 spec.
[of 
2 in
lot]; 
Nchwera River
, 
Rwenshama-Ishasha
road; 
0°27ʹ30.8ʺ S
, 
29°48ʹ07.0ʺ E
; 
8 Nov. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251114
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0148
to 
2016.035.P.0149
(Supplementary file SM.01: E31)
</tp:material-citation>
.• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
[of 
2 in
lot]; same collection data as for preceding; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0171
to 
2016.035.P.0172
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP1028)
</tp:material-citation>
.• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Kayanja
, offshore, 
Lake Edward
; 
0°05ʹ31.2ʺ S
, 
29°45ʹ30.3ʺ E
; 
20 Jan. 2018
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251133
; 
RMCA 2018.008.P.0247
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP2599)
</tp:material-citation>
.• 
<tp:material-citation>2 specs
.; 
Nyamweru River
, mouth, 
Kisenji
; 
0°18′42.5″ S
, 
29°51′36.0″ E
; 
31 Jan. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25585
to 
25586
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-118, Fiche-119)
</tp:material-citation>
– 
<tp:material-citation>Lake George
• 
5 specs
; 

River 
2 km
east of Kitongore

; 
0°05ʹ45.6ʺ S
, 
30°40ʹ51.6ʺ E
; 
31 Oct. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251105, MT251120, MT251121, MT251106, MT251107
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0159
to 
2016.035.P.0163
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP592, HP595, HP596, HP600, HP602)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>2 specs
; 
Mpanga River
, mouth, 
Lake George
; 
0°02ʹ20.4ʺ N
, 
30°17ʹ24.0ʺ E
; 
31 Oct. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251119, MT251104
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0164
to 
2016.035.P.0165
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP575, HP579)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Mahoma River
, 
Rwimi-Nyabani road
; 
0°21ʹ00.2ʺ N
, 
30°16ʹ41.0ʺ E
; 
1 Apr. 2017
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251110
; 
RMCA 2017.006.P.0244
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP1878)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Lake George
, 
Kashaka Bay
, south of inlet; 
0°05ʹ04.6ʺ S
, 
30°10ʹ45.6ʺ E
; 
2 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251111
; 
RMCA 2018.008.P.0248
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP3246)
</tp:material-citation>
– 
<tp:material-citation>Kazinga Channel
• 
4 specs
; 
Kyambura River
, mouth, 
Kazinga Channel
; 
0°07ʹ25.8ʺ S
, 
30°03ʹ07.5ʺ E
; 
30 Oct. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251100, MT251101, MT251102, MT251103
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0155
to 
2016.035.P.0158
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP562(2), HP563 to HP565)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>7 specs
; same locality; 
4 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25588
to 
25594
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-143 to Fiche-149)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>4 specs
; same collection data as for preceding; GenBank: 
MT251099, MT251112
; 
RMCA 2018.008.P.0249
to 
2018.008.P.0252
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP3312, HP3314, HP3317, HP3319)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Kyambura River
, 
middle course, north of Lake Katinda
; 
0°12ʹ23.7ʺ S
, 
30°06ʹ24.3ʺ E
; 
2 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25587
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-128)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>5 specs
; 
Kazinga Channel
, 
near Queen Elisabeth Bush Lodge
; 
0°08ʹ09.6ʺ S
, 
30°02ʹ27.6ʺ E
; 
4 Nov. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251123, MT251124, MT251125, MT251108, MT251109
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0166
to 
2016.035.P.0170
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP719 to HP721, HP723, HP724)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>2 specs
; 
Kazinga Channel
, 
opposite of mouth Kyambura River
; 
0°07ʹ17.5ʺ S
, 
30°02ʹ59.0ʺ E
; 
4 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25595
to 
25596
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-121, Fiche-123)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Based on the 
lectotype
and one 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, the type series of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, which is synonymised here as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, and 37 additional specimens from the Lake Edward system, identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. The 
lectotype
is illustrated in 

. Maximum observed size: 
74.3 mm
SL. Morphometric and meristic data are given in 
Table 2
. Body fusiform, largest depth anterior to dorsal fin. Dorsal profile from tip of snout to origin of dorsal fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to base of caudal fin. Ventral profile from operculum to origin of pelvic fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to posterior end of anal fin base, then slightly concave to caudal fin. Head small. Eye large and round, located dorso-laterally, closer to tip of snout than to distal margin of operculum, interorbital profile slightly convex. Snout rounded and mouth subterminal. Two pairs of barbels, anterior barbel usually slightly shorter than posterior with anterior one usually reaching up to vertical through posterior margin of eye, while posterior one usually up to vertical trough posterior margin of pre-operculum. Dorsal fin with 3 unbranched and 7 to 9 branched rays, distal margin straight to slightly concave, origin located slightly anterior [1 or 2 lateral line scale(s)] to vertical through pelvic fin insertion. First branched dorsal fin ray longest, posterior rays decreasing progressively in size. Pectoral fin with 1 unbranched and 13 to 16 branched rays, distal profile straight to slightly convex, not reaching anterior base of pelvic fin. Pelvic fin with 1 unbranched and 6 to 8 branched rays, distal margin slightly convex. Anal fin with 3 unbranched and 5 to 6 branched fin rays, distal margin slightly concave. Caudal fin forked with outer rays twice as long as median ones and both lobes rounded and of similar size. Anus and urogenital opening situated immediately in front of anal fin base. Scales cycloid, rounded and radially striate. Lateral line completely pored with many lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31)], and gently curved downwards over abdomen but running straight along middle of caudal peduncle and ending at base of caudal fin. Lateral-line scales smaller on caudal peduncle than below dorsal fin.
</p>
            <p>Colour pattern</p>
            <p>
No sexual dimorphism observed. In life, overall background colour of body silvery, darker toward dorsum and lighter towards belly (

). Thick yellowish midlateral band, often with one to three darker spots. All fins translucent. In preserved specimens, overall background colour of body yellowish, greyish dorsally (

). One to three dark spots on flanks on thick silvery midlateral band; spots fused into mid-lateral line in some specimens, overlying silvery band and starting posterior to operculum. First spot situated anterior to dorsal fin origin, median one below last ray of dorsal fin and last one at caudal fin base. Specimens with more than three spots are rare (
1 specimen
with 4 spots and another with 6 spots).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>Distribution
(

)
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
occurs in river systems throughout the Lake Edward basin. For the Congolese part of the basin, it is known from its 
type
locality, the Rutshuru River, May-Ya-Moto (Poll 1939). Although the Congolese part of the system was not sampled during the recent expeditions, we identified specimens from the collection at the RMCA (86-01-P-479 to 500 and 86-09-P-70 to 71) from Vitshumbi, located in the southern Congolese part of the Lake Edward system, as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. In the Ugandan part, we collected the species in the Mahoma, Mpanga, Nchwera, Nyamweru and Kyambura (an affluent of the Rusangwe) Rivers, in Lake Edward offshore at Kayanja, and in Lake George at Kashaka Bay. For the Lake Victoria basin, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
is known from the Nzoia River, the Malawa River and the Middle Akagera system (
Whitehead 1960
; 
Greenwood 1966
; 
De Vos &amp; Thys van den Audenaerde 1990
; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
, 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
(

) belongs to the group of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
with a flexible last unbranched dorsal fin ray that lacks serrations along its posterior edge. A comparison was made to other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal provinces (list made based on information available in, e.g., 
Greenwood 1962
; 

Okaronon 
et al.
1997

; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

; 

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

; 
Froese &amp; Pauly 2018
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from the other species of this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal regions by the following combinations of characteristics (data from original description, unless otherwise stated): a complete lateral line vs an incomplete lateral line in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. toppini</tp:taxon-name>
; two pairs of barbels vs one pair in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini</tp:taxon-name>
, and no barbels in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. anema</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. profundus</tp:taxon-name>
; one to three dark spots on the flanks, which sometimes fuse into a mid-lateral line in preserved specimens, starting posterior to the operculum vs a dark line running from the tip of the snout to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yongei</tp:taxon-name>
, and a thin dark line from the beginning of the operculum to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus</tp:taxon-name>
; 11–12 scales around the caudal peduncle vs 
8 in<tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
9–10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. venustus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis</tp:taxon-name>
; 24–27 lateral line scales (median 25) vs 
30 in<tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 31 
<tp:taxon-name>E. innocens</tp:taxon-name>
; 3.5–4.5 scales between the dorsal fin base and the lateral line vs 
5.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
6 in<tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae</tp:taxon-name>
; 3–4 scales between the lateral line and the pelvic fin (median 3) vs 
2 in<tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
2–2.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 7–8 branched dorsal fin rays vs 
9 in<tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
; a body depth which is larger than the head length vs a body depth which is equal to the head length in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis</tp:taxon-name>
; a smaller snout length [4.1–7.1% SL (average 6.0) vs 7.1–10.1] in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a lower number of lateral line scales [24–27 (median 25) vs 29–30 (30)], a lower number of scales between the dorsal fin base and lateral line [3.5–4.5 (median 3.5) vs 5.5], a lower number of scales around the caudal peduncle [11–12 (median 12) vs 14], a smaller interorbital width [6.3–8.3% SL (average 7.8) vs 9.8–10.2 (10.0)], a larger pre-pectoral distance [26.0–29.0% SL (average 27.4) vs 23.1–24.5 (23.8)], a lower minimum caudal peduncle depth [11.1–14.0% SL (average 12.5) vs 15.0–16.4 (15.5)], a lower maximum caudal peduncle depth [12.9–16.5% SL (average 14.6) vs 17.7–19.4 (18.8)], and a smaller anal fin base length [7.3–8.7% SL (average 8.0) vs 8.5–9.6 (9.1)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a smaller pre-pectoral distance [26.0–29.0 (average 27.4) vs 29.1–33.1 (30.8)], and a larger anal fin length [18.0–19.7 (average 19.0) vs 12.6–17.4 (14.8)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
by a lower number of lateral line scales [24–27 (median 25) vs 27–34 (31)], a larger pre-anal distance [68.4–74.8% SL (average 72.4) vs 65.1– 73.0 (69.3)], a smaller post-anal distance [16.3–19.3% SL (average 17.8) vs 16.3–24.2 (21.1)], a larger body depth [26.5–34.3% SL (average 30.1) vs 21.7–31.2 (26.9)], a larger head depth [17.8–21.8% SL (average 20.2) vs 15.1–19.0 (17.3)] and a larger pelvic fin length [18.2–22.4% SL (average 20.4) vs 15.0–20.9 (18.0)] (
Table 2
). Specimens from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differ from the specimens of the population of 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
from the Lake Edward system by a lower number of scales between the origin of the dorsal fin and the lateral line [3.5–4.5 (median 3.5) vs 3.5–4.5 (4.5)], a larger pelvic fin length [18.2–22.4% SL (average 20.4) vs 14.4–21.3 (18.5)], a smaller snout length [4.1–7.1% SL (average 6.0) vs 4.6–8.3 (7.0)], a smaller interorbital width [6.3–8.3% SL (average 7.8) vs 6.9–9.9 (8.7)], a larger post-dorsal distance [34.8–40.4% SL (average 38.1) vs 31.0–39.9 (35.9)] and a larger anal fin length [18.0–19.7% SL (average 19.0) vs 14.4–21.8 (17.7)] (
Table 2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The specific epithet ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>mimus</tp:taxon-name>
’ means ‘imitator’, a reference to the ‘striking resemblance’ to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus</tp:taxon-name>
(
Boulenger 1912
; 
Scharpf &amp; Lazara 2019
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined</p>
            <p>Lectotype
(here designated)
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>KENYA
• 
Euasso Nyiro
, 
bellow falls
, 
British EastAfrica
; 
BMNH1912.3.22.99
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-185).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Paralectotypes</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>KENYA
• 
8 specs
[of 
9 in
lot]; same collection data as for lectotype; 
BMNH 1912.3.22.90
to 
1912.3.22.98
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-184, Fiche-186 to Fiche-188, Fiche-B to Fiche-E)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
The redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is based on the specimens of the type series only (the 
lectotype
and eight 
paralectotypes
).The 
lectotype
is illustrated in 

. Maximum observed size: 
45.6 mm
SL. Morphometric and meristic data are given in 
Table 2
. Body fusiform, largest depth anterior to dorsal fin. Dorsal profile from tip of snout to origin of dorsal fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to base of caudal fin. Ventral profile from operculum to origin of pelvic fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to posterior end of anal fin base, then slightly concave to caudal fin. Head small. Eye large and round, located laterally, closer to tip of snout than distal margin of operculum, interorbital profile slightly convex. Snout rounded. Mouth subterminal. Two pairs of barbels, anterior barbel shorter than posterior with anterior one usually reaching up to vertical through the middle of the eye, while posterior one can reach the vertical trough posterior margin of pre-operculum. Dorsal fin with 3 unbranched and 7 to 8 branched rays, distal margin slightly concave, origin located on vertical through pelvic fin insertion or slightly anterior (1 lateral line scale). First branched dorsal fin ray longest, posterior rays decreasing progressively in size. Pectoral fin with 1 unbranched and 12 to 14 branched rays, distal profile straight to slightly convex, not reaching anterior base of pelvic fin. Pelvic fin with 1 unbranched and 7 branched rays, distal margin convex. Anal fin with 3 unbranched and 5 to 6 branched fin rays, distal margin concave. Caudal fin forked with outer rays twice as long as median ones and both lobes rounded and of similar size. Anus and urogenital opening situated immediately in front of anal fin base. Scales cycloid rounded and radially striate. Lateral line completely pored with many lateral line scales (total) [24–27 (median 25)], gently curved downwards over abdomen but running straight along middle of caudal peduncle and ending at base of caudal fin.
</p>
            <p>Colour pattern</p>
            <p>No sexual dimorphism is observed. No information of in vivo colour pattern is available. In preserved specimens, overall background colour of body brown, darker dorsally. One to three dark spots on flanks on thick silvery midlateral band; spots fused into mid-lateral line in some specimens, overlying silvery band and starting posterior to operculum. First spot situated anterior to dorsal fin origin, median one below or somewhat anterior to last ray of dorsal fin and last one at caudal fin base.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is known from its 
type
locality, the 
Euasso Nyiro River
below the falls, east of Lake 
Baringo
, 
Kenya
, and from the 
Tana River
system (

Seegers 
et al.
2003

). For the time being, the specimens of the Lake Edward system are referred to as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
and are not included in the distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>LectotypeMin.–Max.MeanS.D.LectotypeMin.–Max.MeanS.D.Min.–Max.MeanS.D.Standard length (mm)74.326.5–74.353.412.143.623.2–45.632.48.516.9–55.141.39.0Measurements (%SL)Head length21.620.5–27.522.71.523.523.3–27.825.81.722.1–30.325.11.8Eye diameter6.75.9–9.67.50.87.97.9–9.68.70.57.4–10.08.60.6Snout length6.94.2–6.95.80.75.14.1–7.16.01.04.6–8.37.00.7Pre-opercular distance15.213.9–19.816.11.316.515.6–21.818.21.815.7–20.617.91.1Interorbital width7.55.8–8.37.30.68.16.3–8.37.80.66.9–9.98.70.7Pre-dorsal distance46.945.7–51.349.01.450.048.4–53.251.11.548.9–56.452.01.6Post-dorsal distance41.533.3–43.339.12.139.634.8–40.438.12.131.0–39.935.92.0Dorsal fin base length15.311.0–17.114.31.115.412.4–15.414.21.111.4–15.613.70.9Dorsal fin length24.123.7–31.126.61.631.425.4–31.428.61.923.2–30.726.9*1.5Pre-pectoral distance23.822.7–29.725.11.726.026.0–29.027.41.224.9–32.728.11.6Pre-pelvic distance47.044.8–53.349.21.753.149.1–56.051.42.548.4–55.452.11.7Pre-anal distance67.465.1–73.069.31.874.568.4–74.872.42.268.8–79.173.42.2Post-anal distance22.516.3–24.221.11.716.416.3–19.317.81.114.8–23.918.01.8Body depth26.421.7–31.226.92.334.326.5–34.330.12.223.5–35.831.02.6Maximum caudal peduncle depth12.811.8–15.513.61.016.512.9–16.514.61.18.7–19.016.01.7Minimum caudal peduncle depth11.610.0–13.612.00.813.511.1–14.012.51.07.1–15.913.71.5Pre-occipital distance17.016.6–21.818.61.319.718.9–22.420.81.118.7–23.220.51.1Head width12.410.4–14.212.00.712.212.2–13.712.90.511.6–14.513.20.6Anal fin base length8.46.7–9.38.00.68.57.3–8.78.00.66.2–10.37.50.8Anal fin length18.016.7–21.918.91.218.718.0–19.719.00.614.4–21.817.71.3Pectoral fin length18.116.7–20.418.61.019.716.6–20.819.01.213.9–21.418.51.4Pelvic fin length18.815.0–20.918.0*1.322.418.2–22.420.41.414.4–21.318.51.4Head depth16.515.1–19.017.30.921.817.8–21.820.21.218.8–22.620.60.8</p>
      <p/>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>MeristicsLectotypeMin.–Max. MedianLectotypeMin.–Max. MedianMin.–Max.MecdianTotal number of lateral line scales3127–34312424–272521–3126Scales between dorsal fin and lateral line4.54.5–4.54.53.53.54–4.53.53.5–4.54.5Pre-dorsal scales109–1310109–1099–1210Circumpeduncular scales1212–16121211–121210–1212***Scales between lateral line and pelvic fin22–4343–432–43*Scales between lateral line and belly4.53.5–5.54.5*4.53.5–4.53.53.5–4.54.5**Unbranched dorsal-fin rays33–3333–333–33*Branched dorsal-fin rays87–9887–886–88*Unbranched anal-fin rays33–3333–333–33Branched anal-fin rays55–6555–654–65Unbranched pectoral-fin rays11–1111–111–11Branched pectoral-fin rays1413–1614*1412–141311–1514Unbranched pelvic-fin rays11–2111–111–21Branched pelvic-fin rays76–8777–775–87Gill rakers upper part first ceratobranchial20–31**11–410–31*Gill rakers lower part first ceratobranchial21–53**30–430–63*Total number of gill rakers first ceratobranchial53–85**53–652–95*</p>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius cercops
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni
(Bailey, 1969)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus
(Boulenger, 1901)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis
(Farm, 2000)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis
(Rendahl, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. toppini
(
Boulenger, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini
(Seegers, 1996)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. anema
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. profundus
(
Greenwood, 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus
(Fowler, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yongei
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus
(Weber, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis
(Boulenger, 1915)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. venustus
(Bailey, 1980)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae
(Boulenger, 1906)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis
(Johnsen, 1926)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(Peters, 1853) (
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae
(Lönnberg, 1907)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. innocens
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura
(Boulenger, 1902)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger, 1903
) (
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. toppini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. anema</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. profundus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yongei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. venustus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. innocens</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Revalidation of Enteromius alberti and presence of Enteromius cf. mimus (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae) in the Lake Edward system, East Africa</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.700</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FF8BFF96F851F31FFFCED72E5D09CC1A</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.700</pub-id>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
The results confirmed the occurrence of two syntopic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
with a smooth dorsal fin ray in the Lake Edward system. Specimens of group A were conspecific with the types of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, except for one type specimen, which was assigned to group B, and with the 
holotype
and 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
used to be considered a synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
.

Based on our results, and following the principle of priority for species names, we propose to revalidate 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
as its junior synonym. A redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
is provided based on the 
lectotype
(here designated) (

) and one 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, the type series of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, here synonymised with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, and the additional specimens from the Lake Edward system examined in this study and identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(n = 37). The other 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, which was revealed not to be conspecific with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, was not included in the redescription. The measurements and meristics can be found in 
Table 2
. An illustration of a fresh specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, captured during the HIPE expeditions is provided in 

.
</p>
            <p>
The specimens of group B were most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, though the PCA on log-transformed measurements (

) suggested some differences. Therefore, we decided to assign the specimens of group B to 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
with “cf” indicating specimens that are comparable to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
but whose identification is uncertain (

Decru 
et al.
2016

). Because of the unsuitable original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
for modern taxonomic purposes, we decided to make a redescription based on the 
lectotype
(here designed) (

) and eight of the nine 
paralectotypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. We found one 
paralectotype
to have a serrated dorsal fin ray; therefore, it was considered not to be conspecific with the other types and excluded from the redescription. Specimens from the Lake Edward system identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, the specimens from Tshambi and the aberrant 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
were not included in the redescription, but their measurements and meristics are given in 
Table 2. A
picture of a fresh specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is given in 

.
</p>
            <p>
For both redescribed species, a 
lectotype
was chosen from the 
syntypes
. For 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, this is the specimen illustrated in the original description by Poll (1939), which is also the largest specimen. The 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is the specimen that resembles most the original figure of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
in the 
Catalogue of the Fresh-water Fishes of Africa in the British Museum (Natural History)
, Volume IV, by 
Boulenger (1916)
. The sampling sites of the two species in the Lake Edward system and the type localities of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
are illustrated in 

. The specimens from Tshambi, initially identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, are indicated as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
on the map, as found in the present study.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
a–b, 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>Previous Treatments</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius cercops
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(here synonymised). syn. nov.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–b) belongs to the group of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
with a flexible last unbranched dorsal fin ray that lacks serrations along its posterior edge. A comparison was made with other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal provinces (list made based on information available in, e.g., 
Greenwood 1962
; 

Okaronon 
et al.
1997

; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

; 

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

; 
Froese &amp; Pauly 2018
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from the other species of this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal regions by the following combination of characteristics (data from original description, unless otherwise stated): a complete lateral line vs an incomplete lateral line in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni
(Bailey, 1969)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus
(Boulenger, 1901)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis
(Farm, 2000)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis
(Rendahl, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. toppini
(
Boulenger, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; two pairs of barbels vs one pair in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini
(Seegers, 1996)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and no barbels in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. anema
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. profundus
(
Greenwood, 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; one to three dark spots on the flanks, which sometimes fuse into a mid-lateral line in preserved specimens, starting posterior to the operculum vs a dark line running from the tip of the snout to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus
(Fowler, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yongei
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and a thin dark line from the beginning of the operculum to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus
(Weber, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 12 scales around the caudal peduncle, with one aberrant specimen in the 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
(16), vs 
8 in<tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis
(Boulenger, 1915)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
9–10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. venustus
(Bailey, 1980)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae
(Boulenger, 1906)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis
(Johnsen, 1926)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 4.5 scales between the dorsal fin base and the lateral line vs 
3.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(Peters, 1853) (
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
5.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
(G̹nther, 1867), and 
6 in<tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae
(Lönnberg, 1907)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a dorsal fin length which is larger than the head length vs a dorsal fin length equal to the head length in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. innocens
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a body depth which is larger than the head length vs a body depth which is equal to the head length in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura
(Boulenger, 1902)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a pectoral fin length which is ⁵⁄₆ of the head length vs ¾ in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and ¾ to ¼ in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger, 1903
) (
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a maximum caudal peduncle depth which is ³⁄₅ of the head length vs ²⁄ 
₅ in<tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a smaller body depth [21.7–31.2% SL (mean 26.9) vs 33.8–37.5 (35.0)], a smaller minimum caudal peduncle depth [10.0–13.6% SL (mean 12.0) vs 15.0–16.4 (15.5)], and a smaller maximum caudal peduncle depth [11.8–15.5% SL (mean 13.6) vs 17.7–19.4 (18.8)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a higher number of lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31) vs 20–25 (21)], a smaller pre-dorsal distance [45.7–51.3% SL (mean 49.0) vs 51.9–55.8 (53.8)] and a smaller pre-occipital distance [16.6-21.8% SL (mean 18.6) vs 22.1–27.3 (24.0)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
by a higher number of lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31) vs 24–27 (25)], a smaller pre-anal distance [65.1–73.0% SL (average 69.3) vs 68.4–74.8 (72.4)], a larger post-anal distance [16.3–24.2% SL (average 21.1) vs 16.3–19.3 (17.8)], a smaller body depth [21.7–31.2% SL (average 26.9) vs 26.5–34.3 (30.1)], a smaller head depth [15.1–19.0% SL (average 17.3) vs 17.8–21.8 (20.2)] and a smaller pelvic fin length [15.0–20.9% SL (average 18.0) vs 18.2–22.4 (20.4)] (
Table 2
). Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differ from the population of 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
from the Lake Edward system by a smaller head depth. In general, a specimen with a head depth smaller than 19% of the standard length can be assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(only one specimen had a higher value). Specimens with a head depth larger than 19% of the standard length can be assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
(only one specimen had a lower value). Other characters to distinguish 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
are the higher number of lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31) vs 21–31 (26)], the smaller interorbital width [5.8–8.3% SL (mean 7.3) vs 6.9–9.9 (8.7)], the smaller pre-pelvic distance [44.8–53.3% SL (mean 49,2) vs 48.4–55.4 (52.1)], the smaller body depth [21.7–31.2% SL (mean 26.9) vs 23.5–35.8 (31.0)], the smaller maximum [11.8– 15.5% SL (mean 13.6) vs 8.7–19.0 (16)] and minimum [10.0–13.6% SL (mean 12) vs 7.1–15.9 (13.7)] caudal peduncle depth, and the smaller head width [10.4–14.2% SL (mean 12) vs 11.6–14.5 (13.2)] (
Table 2
, 

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
Etymology not explained in the original description. Probably, the species epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>alberti</tp:taxon-name>
is derived from the name of the former ‘Parc National Albert’ (now Virunga National Park) in which the 
type
locality is located.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined</p>
            <p>Lectotype
(here designated)
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
Rutshuru River
, 
May-Ya-Moto
; 
5–11 Nov. 1934
; 
de Witte
leg.; 
MRAC 64723
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-209).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Paralectotype</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
1 spec.
; same collection data as for lectotype; 
MRAC 64722
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-210)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>Other material examined</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>KENYA
– 
Lake Victoria
basin
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Luambwa
, 
Nzoia River
, 
Nyanza Province
; 1960; 
BMNH 1960.6.7.37</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>7 specs
[of 
13 in
lot], 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
; same collection data as for holotype; 
BMNH 1960.6.7.38
to 
1960.6.7.50
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-177 to Fiche-183)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>UGANDA
– 
Lake Edward
•
1 spec.
[of 
2 in
lot]; 
Nchwera River
, 
Rwenshama-Ishasha
road; 
0°27ʹ30.8ʺ S
, 
29°48ʹ07.0ʺ E
; 
8 Nov. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251114
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0148
to 
2016.035.P.0149
(Supplementary file SM.01: E31)
</tp:material-citation>
.• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
[of 
2 in
lot]; same collection data as for preceding; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0171
to 
2016.035.P.0172
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP1028)
</tp:material-citation>
.• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Kayanja
, offshore, 
Lake Edward
; 
0°05ʹ31.2ʺ S
, 
29°45ʹ30.3ʺ E
; 
20 Jan. 2018
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251133
; 
RMCA 2018.008.P.0247
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP2599)
</tp:material-citation>
.• 
<tp:material-citation>2 specs
.; 
Nyamweru River
, mouth, 
Kisenji
; 
0°18′42.5″ S
, 
29°51′36.0″ E
; 
31 Jan. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25585
to 
25586
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-118, Fiche-119)
</tp:material-citation>
– 
<tp:material-citation>Lake George
• 
5 specs
; 

River 
2 km
east of Kitongore

; 
0°05ʹ45.6ʺ S
, 
30°40ʹ51.6ʺ E
; 
31 Oct. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251105, MT251120, MT251121, MT251106, MT251107
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0159
to 
2016.035.P.0163
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP592, HP595, HP596, HP600, HP602)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>2 specs
; 
Mpanga River
, mouth, 
Lake George
; 
0°02ʹ20.4ʺ N
, 
30°17ʹ24.0ʺ E
; 
31 Oct. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251119, MT251104
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0164
to 
2016.035.P.0165
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP575, HP579)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Mahoma River
, 
Rwimi-Nyabani road
; 
0°21ʹ00.2ʺ N
, 
30°16ʹ41.0ʺ E
; 
1 Apr. 2017
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251110
; 
RMCA 2017.006.P.0244
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP1878)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Lake George
, 
Kashaka Bay
, south of inlet; 
0°05ʹ04.6ʺ S
, 
30°10ʹ45.6ʺ E
; 
2 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251111
; 
RMCA 2018.008.P.0248
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP3246)
</tp:material-citation>
– 
<tp:material-citation>Kazinga Channel
• 
4 specs
; 
Kyambura River
, mouth, 
Kazinga Channel
; 
0°07ʹ25.8ʺ S
, 
30°03ʹ07.5ʺ E
; 
30 Oct. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251100, MT251101, MT251102, MT251103
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0155
to 
2016.035.P.0158
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP562(2), HP563 to HP565)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>7 specs
; same locality; 
4 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25588
to 
25594
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-143 to Fiche-149)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>4 specs
; same collection data as for preceding; GenBank: 
MT251099, MT251112
; 
RMCA 2018.008.P.0249
to 
2018.008.P.0252
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP3312, HP3314, HP3317, HP3319)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Kyambura River
, 
middle course, north of Lake Katinda
; 
0°12ʹ23.7ʺ S
, 
30°06ʹ24.3ʺ E
; 
2 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25587
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-128)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>5 specs
; 
Kazinga Channel
, 
near Queen Elisabeth Bush Lodge
; 
0°08ʹ09.6ʺ S
, 
30°02ʹ27.6ʺ E
; 
4 Nov. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251123, MT251124, MT251125, MT251108, MT251109
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0166
to 
2016.035.P.0170
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP719 to HP721, HP723, HP724)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>2 specs
; 
Kazinga Channel
, 
opposite of mouth Kyambura River
; 
0°07ʹ17.5ʺ S
, 
30°02ʹ59.0ʺ E
; 
4 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25595
to 
25596
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-121, Fiche-123)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Based on the 
lectotype
and one 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, the type series of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, which is synonymised here as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, and 37 additional specimens from the Lake Edward system, identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. The 
lectotype
is illustrated in 

. Maximum observed size: 
74.3 mm
SL. Morphometric and meristic data are given in 
Table 2
. Body fusiform, largest depth anterior to dorsal fin. Dorsal profile from tip of snout to origin of dorsal fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to base of caudal fin. Ventral profile from operculum to origin of pelvic fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to posterior end of anal fin base, then slightly concave to caudal fin. Head small. Eye large and round, located dorso-laterally, closer to tip of snout than to distal margin of operculum, interorbital profile slightly convex. Snout rounded and mouth subterminal. Two pairs of barbels, anterior barbel usually slightly shorter than posterior with anterior one usually reaching up to vertical through posterior margin of eye, while posterior one usually up to vertical trough posterior margin of pre-operculum. Dorsal fin with 3 unbranched and 7 to 9 branched rays, distal margin straight to slightly concave, origin located slightly anterior [1 or 2 lateral line scale(s)] to vertical through pelvic fin insertion. First branched dorsal fin ray longest, posterior rays decreasing progressively in size. Pectoral fin with 1 unbranched and 13 to 16 branched rays, distal profile straight to slightly convex, not reaching anterior base of pelvic fin. Pelvic fin with 1 unbranched and 6 to 8 branched rays, distal margin slightly convex. Anal fin with 3 unbranched and 5 to 6 branched fin rays, distal margin slightly concave. Caudal fin forked with outer rays twice as long as median ones and both lobes rounded and of similar size. Anus and urogenital opening situated immediately in front of anal fin base. Scales cycloid, rounded and radially striate. Lateral line completely pored with many lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31)], and gently curved downwards over abdomen but running straight along middle of caudal peduncle and ending at base of caudal fin. Lateral-line scales smaller on caudal peduncle than below dorsal fin.
</p>
            <p>Colour pattern</p>
            <p>
No sexual dimorphism observed. In life, overall background colour of body silvery, darker toward dorsum and lighter towards belly (

). Thick yellowish midlateral band, often with one to three darker spots. All fins translucent. In preserved specimens, overall background colour of body yellowish, greyish dorsally (

). One to three dark spots on flanks on thick silvery midlateral band; spots fused into mid-lateral line in some specimens, overlying silvery band and starting posterior to operculum. First spot situated anterior to dorsal fin origin, median one below last ray of dorsal fin and last one at caudal fin base. Specimens with more than three spots are rare (
1 specimen
with 4 spots and another with 6 spots).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>Distribution
(

)
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
occurs in river systems throughout the Lake Edward basin. For the Congolese part of the basin, it is known from its 
type
locality, the Rutshuru River, May-Ya-Moto (Poll 1939). Although the Congolese part of the system was not sampled during the recent expeditions, we identified specimens from the collection at the RMCA (86-01-P-479 to 500 and 86-09-P-70 to 71) from Vitshumbi, located in the southern Congolese part of the Lake Edward system, as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. In the Ugandan part, we collected the species in the Mahoma, Mpanga, Nchwera, Nyamweru and Kyambura (an affluent of the Rusangwe) Rivers, in Lake Edward offshore at Kayanja, and in Lake George at Kashaka Bay. For the Lake Victoria basin, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
is known from the Nzoia River, the Malawa River and the Middle Akagera system (
Whitehead 1960
; 
Greenwood 1966
; 
De Vos &amp; Thys van den Audenaerde 1990
; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
, 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
(

) belongs to the group of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
with a flexible last unbranched dorsal fin ray that lacks serrations along its posterior edge. A comparison was made to other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal provinces (list made based on information available in, e.g., 
Greenwood 1962
; 

Okaronon 
et al.
1997

; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

; 

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

; 
Froese &amp; Pauly 2018
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from the other species of this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal regions by the following combinations of characteristics (data from original description, unless otherwise stated): a complete lateral line vs an incomplete lateral line in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. toppini</tp:taxon-name>
; two pairs of barbels vs one pair in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini</tp:taxon-name>
, and no barbels in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. anema</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. profundus</tp:taxon-name>
; one to three dark spots on the flanks, which sometimes fuse into a mid-lateral line in preserved specimens, starting posterior to the operculum vs a dark line running from the tip of the snout to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yongei</tp:taxon-name>
, and a thin dark line from the beginning of the operculum to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus</tp:taxon-name>
; 11–12 scales around the caudal peduncle vs 
8 in<tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
9–10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. venustus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis</tp:taxon-name>
; 24–27 lateral line scales (median 25) vs 
30 in<tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 31 
<tp:taxon-name>E. innocens</tp:taxon-name>
; 3.5–4.5 scales between the dorsal fin base and the lateral line vs 
5.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
6 in<tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae</tp:taxon-name>
; 3–4 scales between the lateral line and the pelvic fin (median 3) vs 
2 in<tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
2–2.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 7–8 branched dorsal fin rays vs 
9 in<tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
; a body depth which is larger than the head length vs a body depth which is equal to the head length in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis</tp:taxon-name>
; a smaller snout length [4.1–7.1% SL (average 6.0) vs 7.1–10.1] in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a lower number of lateral line scales [24–27 (median 25) vs 29–30 (30)], a lower number of scales between the dorsal fin base and lateral line [3.5–4.5 (median 3.5) vs 5.5], a lower number of scales around the caudal peduncle [11–12 (median 12) vs 14], a smaller interorbital width [6.3–8.3% SL (average 7.8) vs 9.8–10.2 (10.0)], a larger pre-pectoral distance [26.0–29.0% SL (average 27.4) vs 23.1–24.5 (23.8)], a lower minimum caudal peduncle depth [11.1–14.0% SL (average 12.5) vs 15.0–16.4 (15.5)], a lower maximum caudal peduncle depth [12.9–16.5% SL (average 14.6) vs 17.7–19.4 (18.8)], and a smaller anal fin base length [7.3–8.7% SL (average 8.0) vs 8.5–9.6 (9.1)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a smaller pre-pectoral distance [26.0–29.0 (average 27.4) vs 29.1–33.1 (30.8)], and a larger anal fin length [18.0–19.7 (average 19.0) vs 12.6–17.4 (14.8)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
by a lower number of lateral line scales [24–27 (median 25) vs 27–34 (31)], a larger pre-anal distance [68.4–74.8% SL (average 72.4) vs 65.1– 73.0 (69.3)], a smaller post-anal distance [16.3–19.3% SL (average 17.8) vs 16.3–24.2 (21.1)], a larger body depth [26.5–34.3% SL (average 30.1) vs 21.7–31.2 (26.9)], a larger head depth [17.8–21.8% SL (average 20.2) vs 15.1–19.0 (17.3)] and a larger pelvic fin length [18.2–22.4% SL (average 20.4) vs 15.0–20.9 (18.0)] (
Table 2
). Specimens from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differ from the specimens of the population of 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
from the Lake Edward system by a lower number of scales between the origin of the dorsal fin and the lateral line [3.5–4.5 (median 3.5) vs 3.5–4.5 (4.5)], a larger pelvic fin length [18.2–22.4% SL (average 20.4) vs 14.4–21.3 (18.5)], a smaller snout length [4.1–7.1% SL (average 6.0) vs 4.6–8.3 (7.0)], a smaller interorbital width [6.3–8.3% SL (average 7.8) vs 6.9–9.9 (8.7)], a larger post-dorsal distance [34.8–40.4% SL (average 38.1) vs 31.0–39.9 (35.9)] and a larger anal fin length [18.0–19.7% SL (average 19.0) vs 14.4–21.8 (17.7)] (
Table 2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The specific epithet ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>mimus</tp:taxon-name>
’ means ‘imitator’, a reference to the ‘striking resemblance’ to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus</tp:taxon-name>
(
Boulenger 1912
; 
Scharpf &amp; Lazara 2019
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined</p>
            <p>Lectotype
(here designated)
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>KENYA
• 
Euasso Nyiro
, 
bellow falls
, 
British EastAfrica
; 
BMNH1912.3.22.99
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-185).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Paralectotypes</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>KENYA
• 
8 specs
[of 
9 in
lot]; same collection data as for lectotype; 
BMNH 1912.3.22.90
to 
1912.3.22.98
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-184, Fiche-186 to Fiche-188, Fiche-B to Fiche-E)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
The redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is based on the specimens of the type series only (the 
lectotype
and eight 
paralectotypes
).The 
lectotype
is illustrated in 

. Maximum observed size: 
45.6 mm
SL. Morphometric and meristic data are given in 
Table 2
. Body fusiform, largest depth anterior to dorsal fin. Dorsal profile from tip of snout to origin of dorsal fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to base of caudal fin. Ventral profile from operculum to origin of pelvic fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to posterior end of anal fin base, then slightly concave to caudal fin. Head small. Eye large and round, located laterally, closer to tip of snout than distal margin of operculum, interorbital profile slightly convex. Snout rounded. Mouth subterminal. Two pairs of barbels, anterior barbel shorter than posterior with anterior one usually reaching up to vertical through the middle of the eye, while posterior one can reach the vertical trough posterior margin of pre-operculum. Dorsal fin with 3 unbranched and 7 to 8 branched rays, distal margin slightly concave, origin located on vertical through pelvic fin insertion or slightly anterior (1 lateral line scale). First branched dorsal fin ray longest, posterior rays decreasing progressively in size. Pectoral fin with 1 unbranched and 12 to 14 branched rays, distal profile straight to slightly convex, not reaching anterior base of pelvic fin. Pelvic fin with 1 unbranched and 7 branched rays, distal margin convex. Anal fin with 3 unbranched and 5 to 6 branched fin rays, distal margin concave. Caudal fin forked with outer rays twice as long as median ones and both lobes rounded and of similar size. Anus and urogenital opening situated immediately in front of anal fin base. Scales cycloid rounded and radially striate. Lateral line completely pored with many lateral line scales (total) [24–27 (median 25)], gently curved downwards over abdomen but running straight along middle of caudal peduncle and ending at base of caudal fin.
</p>
            <p>Colour pattern</p>
            <p>No sexual dimorphism is observed. No information of in vivo colour pattern is available. In preserved specimens, overall background colour of body brown, darker dorsally. One to three dark spots on flanks on thick silvery midlateral band; spots fused into mid-lateral line in some specimens, overlying silvery band and starting posterior to operculum. First spot situated anterior to dorsal fin origin, median one below or somewhat anterior to last ray of dorsal fin and last one at caudal fin base.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is known from its 
type
locality, the 
Euasso Nyiro River
below the falls, east of Lake 
Baringo
, 
Kenya
, and from the 
Tana River
system (

Seegers 
et al.
2003

). For the time being, the specimens of the Lake Edward system are referred to as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
and are not included in the distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius cercops
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni
(Bailey, 1969)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus
(Boulenger, 1901)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis
(Farm, 2000)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis
(Rendahl, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. toppini
(
Boulenger, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini
(Seegers, 1996)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. anema
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. profundus
(
Greenwood, 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus
(Fowler, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yongei
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus
(Weber, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis
(Boulenger, 1915)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. venustus
(Bailey, 1980)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae
(Boulenger, 1906)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis
(Johnsen, 1926)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(Peters, 1853) (
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae
(Lönnberg, 1907)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. innocens
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura
(Boulenger, 1902)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger, 1903
) (
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. toppini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. anema</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. profundus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yongei</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. venustus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. innocens</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Revalidation of Enteromius alberti and presence of Enteromius cf. mimus (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae) in the Lake Edward system, East Africa</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.700</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FF8BFF96F851F31FFFCED72E5D09CC1A</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.700</pub-id>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti
(Poll, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus
(
Boulenger, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
The results confirmed the occurrence of two syntopic species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
with a smooth dorsal fin ray in the Lake Edward system. Specimens of group A were conspecific with the types of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, except for one type specimen, which was assigned to group B, and with the 
holotype
and 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
used to be considered a synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
.

Based on our results, and following the principle of priority for species names, we propose to revalidate 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
as its junior synonym. A redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
is provided based on the 
lectotype
(here designated) (

) and one 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, the type series of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, here synonymised with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, and the additional specimens from the Lake Edward system examined in this study and identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(n = 37). The other 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, which was revealed not to be conspecific with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, was not included in the redescription. The measurements and meristics can be found in 
Table 2
. An illustration of a fresh specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, captured during the HIPE expeditions is provided in 

.
</p>
            <p>
The specimens of group B were most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, though the PCA on log-transformed measurements (

) suggested some differences. Therefore, we decided to assign the specimens of group B to 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
with “cf” indicating specimens that are comparable to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
but whose identification is uncertain (

Decru 
et al.
2016

). Because of the unsuitable original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
for modern taxonomic purposes, we decided to make a redescription based on the 
lectotype
(here designed) (

) and eight of the nine 
paralectotypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. We found one 
paralectotype
to have a serrated dorsal fin ray; therefore, it was considered not to be conspecific with the other types and excluded from the redescription. Specimens from the Lake Edward system identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, the specimens from Tshambi and the aberrant 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
were not included in the redescription, but their measurements and meristics are given in 
Table 2. A
picture of a fresh specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is given in 

.
</p>
            <p>
For both redescribed species, a 
lectotype
was chosen from the 
syntypes
. For 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, this is the specimen illustrated in the original description by Poll (1939), which is also the largest specimen. The 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is the specimen that resembles most the original figure of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
in the 
Catalogue of the Fresh-water Fishes of Africa in the British Museum (Natural History)
, Volume IV, by 
Boulenger (1916)
. The sampling sites of the two species in the Lake Edward system and the type localities of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
are illustrated in 

. The specimens from Tshambi, initially identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, are indicated as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
on the map, as found in the present study.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
a–b, 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>Previous Treatments</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius cercops
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(here synonymised). syn. nov.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(

a–b) belongs to the group of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
with a flexible last unbranched dorsal fin ray that lacks serrations along its posterior edge. A comparison was made with other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal provinces (list made based on information available in, e.g., 
Greenwood 1962
; 

Okaronon 
et al.
1997

; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

; 

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

; 
Froese &amp; Pauly 2018
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from the other species of this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal regions by the following combination of characteristics (data from original description, unless otherwise stated): a complete lateral line vs an incomplete lateral line in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni
(Bailey, 1969)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus
(Boulenger, 1901)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis
(Farm, 2000)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis
(Rendahl, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. toppini
(
Boulenger, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; two pairs of barbels vs one pair in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini
(Seegers, 1996)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and no barbels in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. anema
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. profundus
(
Greenwood, 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; one to three dark spots on the flanks, which sometimes fuse into a mid-lateral line in preserved specimens, starting posterior to the operculum vs a dark line running from the tip of the snout to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus
(Fowler, 1935)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yongei
(
Whitehead, 1960
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and a thin dark line from the beginning of the operculum to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus
(Weber, 1897)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 12 scales around the caudal peduncle, with one aberrant specimen in the 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
(16), vs 
8 in<tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis
(Boulenger, 1915)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
9–10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. venustus
(Bailey, 1980)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae
(Boulenger, 1906)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis
(Johnsen, 1926)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 4.5 scales between the dorsal fin base and the lateral line vs 
3.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(Peters, 1853) (
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
5.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
(G̹nther, 1867), and 
6 in<tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae
(Lönnberg, 1907)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a dorsal fin length which is larger than the head length vs a dorsal fin length equal to the head length in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. innocens
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a body depth which is larger than the head length vs a body depth which is equal to the head length in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura
(Boulenger, 1902)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a pectoral fin length which is ⁵⁄₆ of the head length vs ¾ in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus
(
Boulenger, 1903
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and ¾ to ¼ in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger, 1903
) (
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; a maximum caudal peduncle depth which is ³⁄₅ of the head length vs ²⁄ 
₅ in<tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus
(Pfeffer, 1896)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a smaller body depth [21.7–31.2% SL (mean 26.9) vs 33.8–37.5 (35.0)], a smaller minimum caudal peduncle depth [10.0–13.6% SL (mean 12.0) vs 15.0–16.4 (15.5)], and a smaller maximum caudal peduncle depth [11.8–15.5% SL (mean 13.6) vs 17.7–19.4 (18.8)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a higher number of lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31) vs 20–25 (21)], a smaller pre-dorsal distance [45.7–51.3% SL (mean 49.0) vs 51.9–55.8 (53.8)] and a smaller pre-occipital distance [16.6-21.8% SL (mean 18.6) vs 22.1–27.3 (24.0)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
by a higher number of lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31) vs 24–27 (25)], a smaller pre-anal distance [65.1–73.0% SL (average 69.3) vs 68.4–74.8 (72.4)], a larger post-anal distance [16.3–24.2% SL (average 21.1) vs 16.3–19.3 (17.8)], a smaller body depth [21.7–31.2% SL (average 26.9) vs 26.5–34.3 (30.1)], a smaller head depth [15.1–19.0% SL (average 17.3) vs 17.8–21.8 (20.2)] and a smaller pelvic fin length [15.0–20.9% SL (average 18.0) vs 18.2–22.4 (20.4)] (
Table 2
). Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
differ from the population of 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
from the Lake Edward system by a smaller head depth. In general, a specimen with a head depth smaller than 19% of the standard length can be assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(only one specimen had a higher value). Specimens with a head depth larger than 19% of the standard length can be assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
(only one specimen had a lower value). Other characters to distinguish 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
are the higher number of lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31) vs 21–31 (26)], the smaller interorbital width [5.8–8.3% SL (mean 7.3) vs 6.9–9.9 (8.7)], the smaller pre-pelvic distance [44.8–53.3% SL (mean 49,2) vs 48.4–55.4 (52.1)], the smaller body depth [21.7–31.2% SL (mean 26.9) vs 23.5–35.8 (31.0)], the smaller maximum [11.8– 15.5% SL (mean 13.6) vs 8.7–19.0 (16)] and minimum [10.0–13.6% SL (mean 12) vs 7.1–15.9 (13.7)] caudal peduncle depth, and the smaller head width [10.4–14.2% SL (mean 12) vs 11.6–14.5 (13.2)] (
Table 2
, 

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
Etymology not explained in the original description. Probably, the species epithet 
<tp:taxon-name>alberti</tp:taxon-name>
is derived from the name of the former ‘Parc National Albert’ (now Virunga National Park) in which the 
type
locality is located.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined</p>
            <p>Lectotype
(here designated)
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
Rutshuru River
, 
May-Ya-Moto
; 
5–11 Nov. 1934
; 
de Witte
leg.; 
MRAC 64723
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-209).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Paralectotype</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
1 spec.
; same collection data as for lectotype; 
MRAC 64722
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-210)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>Other material examined</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>KENYA
– 
Lake Victoria
basin
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Luambwa
, 
Nzoia River
, 
Nyanza Province
; 1960; 
BMNH 1960.6.7.37</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>7 specs
[of 
13 in
lot], 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
; same collection data as for holotype; 
BMNH 1960.6.7.38
to 
1960.6.7.50
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-177 to Fiche-183)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>UGANDA
– 
Lake Edward
•
1 spec.
[of 
2 in
lot]; 
Nchwera River
, 
Rwenshama-Ishasha
road; 
0°27ʹ30.8ʺ S
, 
29°48ʹ07.0ʺ E
; 
8 Nov. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251114
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0148
to 
2016.035.P.0149
(Supplementary file SM.01: E31)
</tp:material-citation>
.• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
[of 
2 in
lot]; same collection data as for preceding; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0171
to 
2016.035.P.0172
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP1028)
</tp:material-citation>
.• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Kayanja
, offshore, 
Lake Edward
; 
0°05ʹ31.2ʺ S
, 
29°45ʹ30.3ʺ E
; 
20 Jan. 2018
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251133
; 
RMCA 2018.008.P.0247
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP2599)
</tp:material-citation>
.• 
<tp:material-citation>2 specs
.; 
Nyamweru River
, mouth, 
Kisenji
; 
0°18′42.5″ S
, 
29°51′36.0″ E
; 
31 Jan. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25585
to 
25586
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-118, Fiche-119)
</tp:material-citation>
– 
<tp:material-citation>Lake George
• 
5 specs
; 

River 
2 km
east of Kitongore

; 
0°05ʹ45.6ʺ S
, 
30°40ʹ51.6ʺ E
; 
31 Oct. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251105, MT251120, MT251121, MT251106, MT251107
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0159
to 
2016.035.P.0163
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP592, HP595, HP596, HP600, HP602)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>2 specs
; 
Mpanga River
, mouth, 
Lake George
; 
0°02ʹ20.4ʺ N
, 
30°17ʹ24.0ʺ E
; 
31 Oct. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251119, MT251104
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0164
to 
2016.035.P.0165
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP575, HP579)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Mahoma River
, 
Rwimi-Nyabani road
; 
0°21ʹ00.2ʺ N
, 
30°16ʹ41.0ʺ E
; 
1 Apr. 2017
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251110
; 
RMCA 2017.006.P.0244
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP1878)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Lake George
, 
Kashaka Bay
, south of inlet; 
0°05ʹ04.6ʺ S
, 
30°10ʹ45.6ʺ E
; 
2 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251111
; 
RMCA 2018.008.P.0248
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP3246)
</tp:material-citation>
– 
<tp:material-citation>Kazinga Channel
• 
4 specs
; 
Kyambura River
, mouth, 
Kazinga Channel
; 
0°07ʹ25.8ʺ S
, 
30°03ʹ07.5ʺ E
; 
30 Oct. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251100, MT251101, MT251102, MT251103
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0155
to 
2016.035.P.0158
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP562(2), HP563 to HP565)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>7 specs
; same locality; 
4 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25588
to 
25594
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-143 to Fiche-149)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>4 specs
; same collection data as for preceding; GenBank: 
MT251099, MT251112
; 
RMCA 2018.008.P.0249
to 
2018.008.P.0252
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP3312, HP3314, HP3317, HP3319)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>1 spec.
; 
Kyambura River
, 
middle course, north of Lake Katinda
; 
0°12ʹ23.7ʺ S
, 
30°06ʹ24.3ʺ E
; 
2 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25587
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-128)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>5 specs
; 
Kazinga Channel
, 
near Queen Elisabeth Bush Lodge
; 
0°08ʹ09.6ʺ S
, 
30°02ʹ27.6ʺ E
; 
4 Nov. 2016
; HIPE exped.; GenBank: 
MT251123, MT251124, MT251125, MT251108, MT251109
; 
RMCA 2016.035.P.0166
to 
2016.035.P.0170
(Supplementary file SM.01: HP719 to HP721, HP723, HP724)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>2 specs
; 
Kazinga Channel
, 
opposite of mouth Kyambura River
; 
0°07ʹ17.5ʺ S
, 
30°02ʹ59.0ʺ E
; 
4 Feb. 2018
; HIPE exped.; 
RBINS 25595
to 
25596
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-121, Fiche-123)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Based on the 
lectotype
and one 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, the type series of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
, which is synonymised here as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, and 37 additional specimens from the Lake Edward system, identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. The 
lectotype
is illustrated in 

. Maximum observed size: 
74.3 mm
SL. Morphometric and meristic data are given in 
Table 2
. Body fusiform, largest depth anterior to dorsal fin. Dorsal profile from tip of snout to origin of dorsal fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to base of caudal fin. Ventral profile from operculum to origin of pelvic fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to posterior end of anal fin base, then slightly concave to caudal fin. Head small. Eye large and round, located dorso-laterally, closer to tip of snout than to distal margin of operculum, interorbital profile slightly convex. Snout rounded and mouth subterminal. Two pairs of barbels, anterior barbel usually slightly shorter than posterior with anterior one usually reaching up to vertical through posterior margin of eye, while posterior one usually up to vertical trough posterior margin of pre-operculum. Dorsal fin with 3 unbranched and 7 to 9 branched rays, distal margin straight to slightly concave, origin located slightly anterior [1 or 2 lateral line scale(s)] to vertical through pelvic fin insertion. First branched dorsal fin ray longest, posterior rays decreasing progressively in size. Pectoral fin with 1 unbranched and 13 to 16 branched rays, distal profile straight to slightly convex, not reaching anterior base of pelvic fin. Pelvic fin with 1 unbranched and 6 to 8 branched rays, distal margin slightly convex. Anal fin with 3 unbranched and 5 to 6 branched fin rays, distal margin slightly concave. Caudal fin forked with outer rays twice as long as median ones and both lobes rounded and of similar size. Anus and urogenital opening situated immediately in front of anal fin base. Scales cycloid, rounded and radially striate. Lateral line completely pored with many lateral line scales [27–34 (median 31)], and gently curved downwards over abdomen but running straight along middle of caudal peduncle and ending at base of caudal fin. Lateral-line scales smaller on caudal peduncle than below dorsal fin.
</p>
            <p>Colour pattern</p>
            <p>
No sexual dimorphism observed. In life, overall background colour of body silvery, darker toward dorsum and lighter towards belly (

). Thick yellowish midlateral band, often with one to three darker spots. All fins translucent. In preserved specimens, overall background colour of body yellowish, greyish dorsally (

). One to three dark spots on flanks on thick silvery midlateral band; spots fused into mid-lateral line in some specimens, overlying silvery band and starting posterior to operculum. First spot situated anterior to dorsal fin origin, median one below last ray of dorsal fin and last one at caudal fin base. Specimens with more than three spots are rare (
1 specimen
with 4 spots and another with 6 spots).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>Distribution
(

)
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
occurs in river systems throughout the Lake Edward basin. For the Congolese part of the basin, it is known from its 
type
locality, the Rutshuru River, May-Ya-Moto (Poll 1939). Although the Congolese part of the system was not sampled during the recent expeditions, we identified specimens from the collection at the RMCA (86-01-P-479 to 500 and 86-09-P-70 to 71) from Vitshumbi, located in the southern Congolese part of the Lake Edward system, as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. In the Ugandan part, we collected the species in the Mahoma, Mpanga, Nchwera, Nyamweru and Kyambura (an affluent of the Rusangwe) Rivers, in Lake Edward offshore at Kayanja, and in Lake George at Kashaka Bay. For the Lake Victoria basin, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
is known from the Nzoia River, the Malawa River and the Middle Akagera system (
Whitehead 1960
; 
Greenwood 1966
; 
De Vos &amp; Thys van den Audenaerde 1990
; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
, 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
(

) belongs to the group of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
with a flexible last unbranched dorsal fin ray that lacks serrations along its posterior edge. A comparison was made to other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal provinces (list made based on information available in, e.g., 
Greenwood 1962
; 

Okaronon 
et al.
1997

; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

; 

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

; 
Froese &amp; Pauly 2018
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
can easily be distinguished from the other species of this group from the East Coast and Nilo-Sudan ichthyofaunal regions by the following combinations of characteristics (data from original description, unless otherwise stated): a complete lateral line vs an incomplete lateral line in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. atkinsoni</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pumilus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. serengetiensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. tongaensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. toppini</tp:taxon-name>
; two pairs of barbels vs one pair in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pseudotoppini</tp:taxon-name>
, and no barbels in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. anema</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. profundus</tp:taxon-name>
; one to three dark spots on the flanks, which sometimes fuse into a mid-lateral line in preserved specimens, starting posterior to the operculum vs a dark line running from the tip of the snout to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. bifrenatus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yongei</tp:taxon-name>
, and a thin dark line from the beginning of the operculum to the caudal fin base in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. viviparus</tp:taxon-name>
; 11–12 scales around the caudal peduncle vs 
8 in<tp:taxon-name>E. leonensis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
9–10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. venustus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
10 in<tp:taxon-name>E. magdalenae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yeiensis</tp:taxon-name>
; 24–27 lateral line scales (median 25) vs 
30 in<tp:taxon-name>E. lineomaculatus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 31 
<tp:taxon-name>E. innocens</tp:taxon-name>
; 3.5–4.5 scales between the dorsal fin base and the lateral line vs 
5.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. unitaeniatus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
6 in<tp:taxon-name>E. usambarae</tp:taxon-name>
; 3–4 scales between the lateral line and the pelvic fin (median 3) vs 
2 in<tp:taxon-name>E. trispilopleura</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
2–2.5 in<tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus
(
Boulenger 1907
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 7–8 branched dorsal fin rays vs 
9 in<tp:taxon-name>E. quadripunctatus</tp:taxon-name>
; a body depth which is larger than the head length vs a body depth which is equal to the head length in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. nigeriensis</tp:taxon-name>
; a smaller snout length [4.1–7.1% SL (average 6.0) vs 7.1–10.1] in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. radiatus
(
Greenwood 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a lower number of lateral line scales [24–27 (median 25) vs 29–30 (30)], a lower number of scales between the dorsal fin base and lateral line [3.5–4.5 (median 3.5) vs 5.5], a lower number of scales around the caudal peduncle [11–12 (median 12) vs 14], a smaller interorbital width [6.3–8.3% SL (average 7.8) vs 9.8–10.2 (10.0)], a larger pre-pectoral distance [26.0–29.0% SL (average 27.4) vs 23.1–24.5 (23.8)], a lower minimum caudal peduncle depth [11.1–14.0% SL (average 12.5) vs 15.0–16.4 (15.5)], a lower maximum caudal peduncle depth [12.9–16.5% SL (average 14.6) vs 17.7–19.4 (18.8)], and a smaller anal fin base length [7.3–8.7% SL (average 8.0) vs 8.5–9.6 (9.1)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of a smaller pre-pectoral distance [26.0–29.0 (average 27.4) vs 29.1–33.1 (30.8)], and a larger anal fin length [18.0–19.7 (average 19.0) vs 12.6–17.4 (14.8)]. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
by a lower number of lateral line scales [24–27 (median 25) vs 27–34 (31)], a larger pre-anal distance [68.4–74.8% SL (average 72.4) vs 65.1– 73.0 (69.3)], a smaller post-anal distance [16.3–19.3% SL (average 17.8) vs 16.3–24.2 (21.1)], a larger body depth [26.5–34.3% SL (average 30.1) vs 21.7–31.2 (26.9)], a larger head depth [17.8–21.8% SL (average 20.2) vs 15.1–19.0 (17.3)] and a larger pelvic fin length [18.2–22.4% SL (average 20.4) vs 15.0–20.9 (18.0)] (
Table 2
). Specimens from 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
differ from the specimens of the population of 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
from the Lake Edward system by a lower number of scales between the origin of the dorsal fin and the lateral line [3.5–4.5 (median 3.5) vs 3.5–4.5 (4.5)], a larger pelvic fin length [18.2–22.4% SL (average 20.4) vs 14.4–21.3 (18.5)], a smaller snout length [4.1–7.1% SL (average 6.0) vs 4.6–8.3 (7.0)], a smaller interorbital width [6.3–8.3% SL (average 7.8) vs 6.9–9.9 (8.7)], a larger post-dorsal distance [34.8–40.4% SL (average 38.1) vs 31.0–39.9 (35.9)] and a larger anal fin length [18.0–19.7% SL (average 19.0) vs 14.4–21.8 (17.7)] (
Table 2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The specific epithet ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>mimus</tp:taxon-name>
’ means ‘imitator’, a reference to the ‘striking resemblance’ to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. neglectus</tp:taxon-name>
(
Boulenger 1912
; 
Scharpf &amp; Lazara 2019
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Material examined</p>
            <p>Lectotype
(here designated)
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>KENYA
• 
Euasso Nyiro
, 
bellow falls
, 
British EastAfrica
; 
BMNH1912.3.22.99
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-185).
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Paralectotypes</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>KENYA
• 
8 specs
[of 
9 in
lot]; same collection data as for lectotype; 
BMNH 1912.3.22.90
to 
1912.3.22.98
(Supplementary file SM.01: Fiche-184, Fiche-186 to Fiche-188, Fiche-B to Fiche-E)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
The redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is based on the specimens of the type series only (the 
lectotype
and eight 
paralectotypes
).The 
lectotype
is illustrated in 

. Maximum observed size: 
45.6 mm
SL. Morphometric and meristic data are given in 
Table 2
. Body fusiform, largest depth anterior to dorsal fin. Dorsal profile from tip of snout to origin of dorsal fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to base of caudal fin. Ventral profile from operculum to origin of pelvic fin slightly convex, slightly tapering to posterior end of anal fin base, then slightly concave to caudal fin. Head small. Eye large and round, located laterally, closer to tip of snout than distal margin of operculum, interorbital profile slightly convex. Snout rounded. Mouth subterminal. Two pairs of barbels, anterior barbel shorter than posterior with anterior one usually reaching up to vertical through the middle of the eye, while posterior one can reach the vertical trough posterior margin of pre-operculum. Dorsal fin with 3 unbranched and 7 to 8 branched rays, distal margin slightly concave, origin located on vertical through pelvic fin insertion or slightly anterior (1 lateral line scale). First branched dorsal fin ray longest, posterior rays decreasing progressively in size. Pectoral fin with 1 unbranched and 12 to 14 branched rays, distal profile straight to slightly convex, not reaching anterior base of pelvic fin. Pelvic fin with 1 unbranched and 7 branched rays, distal margin convex. Anal fin with 3 unbranched and 5 to 6 branched fin rays, distal margin concave. Caudal fin forked with outer rays twice as long as median ones and both lobes rounded and of similar size. Anus and urogenital opening situated immediately in front of anal fin base. Scales cycloid rounded and radially striate. Lateral line completely pored with many lateral line scales (total) [24–27 (median 25)], gently curved downwards over abdomen but running straight along middle of caudal peduncle and ending at base of caudal fin.
</p>
            <p>Colour pattern</p>
            <p>No sexual dimorphism is observed. No information of in vivo colour pattern is available. In preserved specimens, overall background colour of body brown, darker dorsally. One to three dark spots on flanks on thick silvery midlateral band; spots fused into mid-lateral line in some specimens, overlying silvery band and starting posterior to operculum. First spot situated anterior to dorsal fin origin, median one below or somewhat anterior to last ray of dorsal fin and last one at caudal fin base.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is known from its 
type
locality, the 
Euasso Nyiro River
below the falls, east of Lake 
Baringo
, 
Kenya
, and from the 
Tana River
system (

Seegers 
et al.
2003

). For the time being, the specimens of the Lake Edward system are referred to as 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
and are not included in the distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Enteromius alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Although the occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
in the Lake Edward system was mentioned in several studies (e.g., Poll 1939; 
Greenwood 1966
; 

Decru 
et al.
2019

), we found that the specimens from the Lake Edward system, previously assigned to these species, clearly differed from the 
syntypes
of these species in morphology. The genetic distance between the specimens from the Lake Edward system and sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
from GenBank was large (12%). Based on our study, we can conclude that 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
do not occur in the system. Instead, the specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from the Lake Edward system with a smooth unbranched dorsal fin ray are assigned to either 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
(“group A”) or 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
(“group B”), which share a very similar colour pattern. However, no correspondence was found between specimens previously identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
and their current identification as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. Specimens from the system, which were historically assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, include both specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. The same applies to specimens historically assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>Banister (1987)
considered 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
to be a synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, although he did not examine the 
syntypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. The synonymy was based on a similar position of the gill rakers, the alignment of pharyngeal tooth rows and the position of the flank spots. However, the number of lateral line scales was different (
Banister, 1987
); 
24 to 26 in<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
, according to 
Banister (1987)
, compared to 
31 in<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
, according to Poll (1939). We found similar differences in the present study: 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
has 27 to 34 and the type series of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
has 20 to 25 lateral line scales. Furthermore, in the original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus
, 
Boulenger (1903)</tp:taxon-name>
mentioned that the 
syntypes
had no barbels. However, 
Banister (1987)
found one pair of posterior barbels in the three largest 
syntypes
, and no sign of anterior barbels, but at the same time emphasized the poor condition of these 
syntypes
. Also in the present study, we did not find distinct anterior barbels. Posterior barbels were found in the larger type specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
. In his redescription, 
Banister (1987)
included additional specimens (amongst which the types of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
) and stated that the anterior barbels appear later in development. The two pairs of barbels in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
are clearly visible.
</p>
         <p>
In the present study, we found the 
holotype
and the examined 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
to be conspecific with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius cercops</tp:taxon-name>
was described in 1960 from the Nzoia River (Nyanza Province, 
Kenya
, Lake Victoria basin) by Whitehead. In addition to its type locality, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
is also known from other rivers in the Lake Victoria basin, such as the Malawa River (
Uganda
) and rivers in the Middle Akagera system (
Rwanda
) (
Whitehead 1960
; 
Greenwood 1966
; 
De Vos &amp; Thys van den Audenaerde 1990
; 

Seegers 
et al.
2003

). We revalidated 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
with 
<tp:taxon-name>E. cercops</tp:taxon-name>
as its junior synonym.
</p>
         <p>
We found the specimens of “group B” to be most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
. The 
syntypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
originated from the Euasso Nyiro River (
Kenya
), which drains to the Indian Ocean and is situated further east in the East Coast ichthyofaunal province (

). Furthermore, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is only known from this type locality and from the 
Tana River
system (

Seegers 
et al.
2003

). The type series of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
is polyspecific as it included a specimen with serrations on the third unbranched dorsal fin ray (not included in the analyses), though 
Boulenger (1912)
clearly mentioned the lack of serrations as a feature of the species. Further comparative research on the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from the coastal river systems in 
Kenya
is required in order to identify this specimen. Since some small differences were observed between “group B” and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
in the results of the PCA on the measurements (

, 
Table 2
), we assigned “group B” to 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, with “cf.” indicating specimens that are comparable to 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
but whose identification is uncertain (

Decru 
et al.
2016

). Furthermore, “group B” and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
occur in distant river systems. Therefore, it is unlikely that the specimens of the Lake Edward system are conspecific with the geographical distant species 
<tp:taxon-name>E. mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, though this possibility cannot be excluded. Genetic studies already revealed that widespread species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
often consist of multiple species that are actually confined to smaller distribution areas (

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

; 

Van Ginneken 
et al.
2017

).While we found 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
not to occur in the Lake Edward system, it is remarkable that we found a comparable set of similarly looking species in this system: 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
, which mirror 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
in the Nile River. Whether or not this implies sister-group relationships between species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
of the two ichthyofaunal provinces, is difficult to say without a more comprehensive genetic study. Furthermore, COI data of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
is lacking. The occurrence of sister relationships between other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from the East Coast and other ichthyofaunal provinces has been suggested by 

Ndeda 
et al.
(2018)

. These authors found sister relationship between 
<tp:taxon-name>E. yongei</tp:taxon-name>
(from Lake Victoria, East Coast) and a lineage containing a specimen identified as 
E.
sp. (region of Conakry) and one as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. stigmatopygus</tp:taxon-name>
(Mafou River, 
Niger
River) with a 12% genetic divergence in the cytochrome b (Cytb) gene (mtDNA). However, in view of the small sample size, especially of the West African lineage, the vast geographical distance and the use of only one mitochondrial marker, these results need further confirmation.
</p>
         <p>
Unknown diversity in 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
In a recent study on species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
from the north-eastern part of the 
Congo
basin (

Van Ginneken 
et al.
2017

), DNA barcodes (COI) indicated the presence of 23 mitochondrial lineages within what initially were assumed to be only four different morphospecies. Genetic distances were mostly well over 5% and even up to 20% between lineages of morphologically similar specimens, clearly exceeding 2% which is the cut-off value that is commonly used to denote intraspecific variation (

Hebert 
et al.
2003

). In the study of 

Van Ginneken 
et al.
(2017)

, clear-cut diagnostic characteristics could, however, not be delineated. Yet, morphologic differences could be demonstrated with multivariate morphometric analyses, which were consistent with the COI lineages. This unrecognised diversity was explained by the occurrence of a cryptic diversity within the species from the 
Congo
basin. In the present study, we found seven characteristics to distinguish the two morphologically similar species of the Lake Edward system. Hence, although, a priori, we failed to distinguish the two species from each other, the concept of cryptic species is not applicable here. Another study (

Schmidt 
et al.
2019

) also revealed unrecognised diversity in 
<tp:taxon-name>E. foutensis</tp:taxon-name>
from the Fouta Djallon (Upper 
Guinea
region) highlands, both genetically (Cytb) and morphologically. 

Schmidt 
et al.
(2017)

also found evidence of high levels of genetic divergence and unrecognized diversity (Cytb) in specimens identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. kerstenii</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>E. apleurogramma</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
paludinosus</tp:taxon-name>
from the East Coast ichthyofaunal province in 
Kenya
. Also, patterns of introgression seem to occur in both closely and distantly related species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
(

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

)
</tp:taxon-name>
, which suggest hybridisation events. Whether this is also the case in the specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. alberti</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>E.
cf. 
mimus</tp:taxon-name>
remains to be studied.
</p>
         <p>The results of these recent integrative studies on other systems raised the expectation to find more species in the Lake Edward system as well. This was, however, not the case for the group with an unbranched third dorsal fin ray. Initially, two species, though misidentified, were reported for this group, and during the present study no additional species were found.</p>
         <p>
The unrecognised diversity found within species complexes in various systems (e.g., 

Schmidt 
et al.
2017

, 
2019
; 

Van Ginneken 
et al
. 2017

), the revalidation of species as found in our study and the study of 

Schmidt 
et al.
(2018)

, and the description of new species, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>E. pinnimaculatus</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Gabon
(Mipounga 
et al.
2019) and 
<tp:taxon-name>E. thespesios</tp:taxon-name>
from the Upper 
Congo
River (

Katemo Manda 
et al.
2019

) all suggest that the species richness of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius</tp:taxon-name>
is much larger than currently thought. Hence, the present number of 211 valid species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
(
Froese &amp; Pauly 2019
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, is certainly a considerable underestimation of the real species diversity.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>
This study is part of the Brain-project 
HIPE
(Human impacts on ecosystem health and resources of Lake Edward), funded by the Belgian Science Policy Office (BELSPO: BR/154/A1/ 
HIPE
). The fieldwork has been financed by travel grants from the Fund for Scientific Research (FWO, 
Belgium
). We would like to thank N. Vranken (KU Leuven), M. Mbalassa (Université officielle de Bukavu, 
DR Congo
), L. Wasswa (Ugandan Fisheries Department) and M. Bifamengo (NaFFIRI, 
Uganda
) for their help during the fieldwork as well as W. Okello (NaFFIRI) for the local logistic support during the field trips. We thank J. Maclaine (
BMNH
) for the loan of specimens under his care. We are also grateful to N. Vranken (KU Leuven) for his help with illustrating the distribution map, to M. Parrent (
RMCA
) for the registration of the specimens and to A. Mertens (Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, KU Leuven), A. Kayenbergh (KU Leuven) and K. Dierickx (University of York, KU Leuven) for their help in barcoding the DNA sequences. We thank Dr F. Salah Ali (National Institute of Oceanography and Fisheries, 
Cairo
, 
Egypt
) for giving us more information about the GenBank sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>E. perince</tp:taxon-name>
used in this study.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Bamba M.2012
. 
The
‘Barbus’ 
species (Cypriniformes, Cyprinidae) from Côte d’Ivoire: A systematic revision of some West African species complexes
. 

PhD Tesis, 
KU Leuven, Belgium
.
</p>
         <p>Bamba M.
, 
Vreven E.J.
&amp; 
Snoeks J.2011
. 

Description of 
Barbus teugelsi
sp. nov. (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae) from the Little Scarcies basin in Guinea, Africa

. 
Zootaxa2998
: 
48–65
. 
https://org/10.11646/zootaxa.2998.1.4</p>
         <p>Banister K.E.1987
. 

The 
Barbus perince -Barbus neglectus
problem and a review of certain Nilotic small 
Barbus
species (Teleostei, Cypriniformes, Cyprinidae)

. 
Bulletin of the Natural History Museum
, 
Zoology
series 53 (
2
): 
115–138
.
</p>
         <p>Berrebi P.
, 
Kottelat M.
, 
Skelton P.
&amp; 
Rab P.1996
. 

Systematics of 
Barbus
: state of the art and heuristic comments

. 
Folia Zoologica45
: 
5–12
.
</p>
         <p>Bookstein F.
, 
Chernoff B.
, 
Elder R.
, 
Humphries J.
, 
Smith G.
&amp; 
Strauss R.1985
. 
Morphometrics in Evolutionary Biology: the geometry of size and shape change, with examples from fishes
. 
Journal of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia
, 
Special publication15
: 
1–277
.
</p>
         <p>Boulenger G.A.1903
. 

Diagnosis of four new species of 
Barbus
from the Nile

. 
Annals and Magazine of Natural History
, Series 7
12
: 
532–533
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/00222930308678890</p>
         <p>Boulenger G.A.1907
. 
Zoology of Egypt: the Fishes of the Nile
. 
Published for the Egyptian Government by Hugh Rees, London
. 
https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.51710</p>
         <p>Boulenger G.A.1912
. 
On a collection of Fishes made by Mr. A. Blayney Percival in British East Africa to the East of Lake Baringo
. 
Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London82
(
3
): 
672–676
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-7998.1912.tb07548.x</p>
         <p>Boulenger G.A.1916
. 
Catalogue of the Fresh-Water Fishes of Africa in the British museum (Natural History)
, 
Vol. IV
. 
British Museum (Natural History), London, UK
. 
https://doi.org/10.5962/bhl.title.8869</p>
         <p>Clark K.
, 
Karsch-Mizrachi I.
, 
Lipman D.J.
, 
Ostell J.
&amp; 
Sayers E.W.2016
. 
GenBank
. 
Nucleic Acids Research44
(D 
1
): D67–D72. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkv1276</p>
         <p>De Vos L.
&amp; 
Thys van den Audenaerde D.F.E.1990
. 

Petit 
Barbus
(Pisces, Cyprinidae) du Rwanda

. 
Revue d’Hydrobiologie tropicale23
(
2
): 
141–159
.
</p>
         <p>Decru E.
, 
Vreven E.
&amp; 
Snoeks J.2012
. 

A revision of the West African 
Hepsetus
(Characiformes: Hepsetidae) with a description of 
Hepsetus akawo
sp. nov. and a redescription of 
Hepsetus odoe
(Bloch, 1794)

. 
Journal of Natural History46
: 
1–23
. 
https://doi.org/10.1080/00222933.2011.622055</p>
         <p>Decru E.
, 
Moelants T.
, 
De Gelas K.
, 
Vreven E.
, 
Verheyen E.
&amp; 
Snoeks J.2016
. 
Taxonomic challenges in freshwater fishes: a mismatch between morphology and DNA barcoding in fish of the north-eastern part of the Congo Basin
. 
Molecular Ecology Resources16
: 
342–352
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/1755-0998.12445</p>
         <p>Decru E.
, 
Vranken N.
, 
Bragança P.H.N.
, 
Snoeks J.
&amp; 
Van Steenberge M.2019
. 
Where ichthyofaunal provinces meet: the fish fauna of the Lake Edward system, East Africa
. 
Journal of Fish Biology96
(
5
): 
1186–1201
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jfb.13992</p>
         <p>Froese R.
&amp; 
Pauly D.
(eds) 
2018
. 
FishBase
. 
Available from www.fishbase.org
[accessed 21 Nov. 2018].
</p>
         <p>Froese R.
&amp; 
Pauly D.
(eds) 
2019
. 
FishBase
. 
Available from www.fishbase.org
[accessed 6 Nov. 2019].
</p>
         <p>Greenwood P.H.1962
. 

A revision of certain 
Barbus
(Pisces, Cyprinidae) from East, Central and South Africa

. 
Bulletin of the Natural History Museum
, 
Zoology
series 8 (
4
): 
151–208
. Available from 
https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/part/118628#/summary
[accessed 
21 Nov. 2018
].
</p>
         <p>Greenwood P.H.1966
. 
The Fishes of Uganda
. 
The Uganda Society, Kampala
.
</p>
         <p>Greenwood P.H.1970
. 

A revision of the cyprinid species 
Barbus
(
Enteromius
) 
radiatus
Peters, 1853, with a note on the synonymy of the subgenera 
Beirabarbus
and 
Enteromius
. 
Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique africaines82
: 
1–13
.
</p>
         <p>Hayes M.M.
&amp; 
Armbruster J.W.2017
. 
The taxonomy and relationships of the African small barbs (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae)
. 
Copeia105
(
2
): 
348–362
. 
https://doi.org/10.1643/CI-15-348</p>
         <p>Hebert P.D.N.
, 
Cywinska A.
, 
Ball S.L.
&amp; 
deWaard J.R.2003
. 
Biological identifications through DNA barcodes
. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B. Biological Sciences270
: 
313–321
. 
https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2002.2218</p>
         <p>Howes G.J.1991
. 
Systematics and biogeography: an overview
. 
In
: 
Winfield I.J.
&amp; 
Nelson J.S.
(eds) 
Cyprinid Fishes: Systematics
, 
Biology and Exploitation
: 
1–33
. 
Chapman &amp; Hall, London, UK
.
</p>
         <p>Ivanova N.V.
, 
Zemlak T.S.
, 
Hanner R.H.
&amp; 
Hebert P.D.2007
. 
Universal primer cocktails for fish DNA barcoding
. 
Molecular Ecology Notes7
: 
544–548
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1471-8286.2007.01748.x</p>
         <p>Kassambara A.
&amp; 
Mundt F.2017
. 
Factoextra: extract and visualize the results of multivariate data analyses. R package version 1.0
.5. Available from 
https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=factoextra
[accessed 
1 Apr. 2020
].
</p>
         <p>Katemo Manda B.
, 
Snoeks J.
, 
Decru E.
, 
Bills R.
&amp; 
Vreven E.2019
. 
Enteromius thespesios
(Teleostei: Cyprinidae): a new minnow species with a remarkable sexual dimorphism from the south-eastern part of the Upper Congo River

. 
Journal of Fish Biology96
(
5
): 
1160–1175
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jfb.14108</p>
         <p>Kumar S.
, 
Stecher G.
&amp; 
Tamura K.2016
. 
MEGA7: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 7.0 for bigger datasets
. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution33
: 
1870–1874
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msw054</p>
         <p>Leigh J.W.
&amp; 
Bryant D.2015
. 
POPART: full-feature software for haplotype network construction
. 
Methods in Ecology and Evolution6
: 
1110–1116
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.12410</p>
         <p>Levin B.A.
, 
Dgebuadze Y.Y.
, 
Tefera F.
, 
Tesfaye G.
&amp; 
Golubtsov A.S.2017
. 

An evidence of past introgressive hybridization between 
Labeobarbus ethiopicus
and 
L. intermedius
in the Ethiopian Rift Valley, East Africa

. 
Ethiopian Journal of Biological Sciences16
(Suppl.): 
45–60
.
</p>
         <p>Lowe-McConnell R.H.1975
. 
Fish Communities in Tropical Freshwaters
. 
Longman, New York, USA
.
</p>
         <p>Manly B.F.J.1994
. 
Multivariate Statistical Methods: A Primer.
2 
nd
Ed. Chapman &amp; Hall

, 
Boca Raton, Florida, USA
.
</p>
         <p>Mbalassa M.
, 
Bagalwa J.J.M.
, 
Nshombo M.
&amp; 
Kateyo M.E.2014
. 
Assessment of physicochemical parameters in relation with fish ecology in Ishasha River and Lake Edward, Albertine Rift Valley, East Africa
. 
International Journal of Current Microbiology and Applied Sciences3
(
6
): 
230-244
.
</p>
         <p>Mipounga H.K.
, 
Cutler J.
, 
Beh J.H.M.
, 
Adam B.
&amp; 
Sidlauskas B.L.Enteromius pinnimaculatus
sp. nov. (Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae) from southern Gabon

. 
Journal of Fish Biology96
(
5
): 
1218–1233
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/jfb.13995</p>
         <p>Ndeda V.M.
, 
Mateos M.
&amp; 
Hurtado L.2018
. 
Evolution of African barbs from the Lake Victoria drainage system, Kenya
. 
PeerJ6
: e 
5762
. 
https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.5762</p>
         <p>Nelson J.S.
, 
Grande T.C.
&amp; 
Wilson M.V.H.2016
. 
Fishes of the World.
5 
th
Ed. John Wiley &amp; Sons

, 
Hoboken, New Jersey
. 
https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119174844</p>
         <p>Okaronon J.O.
, 
Katunzi E.F.B.
&amp; 
Asila A.A.1997
. 
Fish Species Identification Guide for Lake Victoria
, 
Enumerator’s Field Guide
. 
Lake Victoria Fisheries Research Project Phase II, Technical Document 1, Jinja, Uganda
. Available from 
http://aquaticcommons.org/4150/
[accessed 
21 Nov. 2018
].
</p>
         <p>Oksanen J.
, 
Blanchet F.G.
, 
Friendly M.
, 
Kindt R.
, 
Legendre P.
, 
McGlinn D.
, 
Minchin P.R.
, 
O’Hara R.B.
, 
Simpson G.L.
, 
Solymos P.
, 
Stevens M.H.H.
, 
Szoecs E.
&amp; 
Wagner H.2018
. 
Vegan: Community Ecology Package. R package version 2.5
-2.Available from 
https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=vegan
[accessed 
31 Aug. 2019
].
</p>
         <p>Poll M.
1939. 

Poissons. 
Exploration du Parc National Albert. Mission G.F. de Witte (1933-1935
) fasc. 24: 
1–81
. Available from 
http://www.apncb.be/missions/mission-scientifique-au-parc-national-albert-de
[accessed 
8 Jun. 2018
].
</p>
         <p>
R 
Core Team
. 
2018
. 
R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing
. 
R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria
. Available from 
https://www.R-project.org/
[accessed 
29 Feb. 2020
].
</p>
         <p>Ren Q.
&amp; 
Mayden R.L.2016
. 

Molecular phylogeny and biogeography of African diploid barbs, ‘ 
Barbus
’, and allies in Africa and Asia (Teleostei: Cypriniformes)

. 
Zoologica Scripta45
(
6
): 
642–649
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/zsc.12177</p>
         <p>Rice W.R.1989
. 
Analyzing tables of statistical tests
. 
Evolution43
(
1
): 
223–225
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1558-5646.1989.tb04220.x</p>
         <p>Roberts T.R.1975
. 
Geographical distribution of African freshwater fishes
. 
Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society57
: 
249–319
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1096-3642.1975.tb01893.x</p>
         <p>
RStudio Team. 
2016
. 
RStudio: Integrated Development for R
.
RStudio Inc
., 
Boston, MA
. Available from 
http://www.rstudio.com/
[accessed 
3 Jul. 2020
].
</p>
         <p>Scharpf C.
&amp; 
Lazara K.J.2019
. 
The ETYFish Project
. 
Available from www.etyfish.org
[accessed 17 Sep. 2019].
</p>
         <p>Schmidt R.C.
, 
Bart Jr. H.L.
&amp; 
Nyingi W.D.2017
. 
Multi-locus phylogeny reveals instances of mitochondrial introgression and unrecognized diversity in Kenyan barbs (Cyprininae: Smiliogastrini)
. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution111
: 
35–43
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2017.03.015</p>
         <p>Schmidt R.C.
, 
Bart Jr. H.L.
&amp; 
Nyingi W.D.2018
. 

Integrative taxonomy of the red-finned barb, 
Enteromius apleurogramma
(Cyprininae: Smiliogastrini) from Kenya, supports recognition of 
E. amboseli
as a valid species

. 
Zootaxa4482
(
3
): 
566–578
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4482.3.8</p>
         <p>Schmidt R.C.
, 
Dillon M.N.
, 
Kuhn N.M.
, 
Bart Jr. H.L.
&amp; 
Pezold F.2019
. 

Unrecognized and imperilled diversity in an endemic barb (Smiliogastrini, 
Enteromius
) from the Fouta Djallon highlands

. 
Zoologica Scripta48
(
5
): 
605–613
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/zsc.12362</p>
         <p>Schwarzer J.
, 
Swartz E.R.
, 
Vreven E.
, 
Snoeks J.
, 
Cotterill F.P.D.
, 
Misof B.
&amp; 
Schliewen U.K.2012
. 
Repeated trans-watershed hybridization among haplochromine cichlids (Cichlidae) was triggered by Neogene landscape evolution
. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B. Biological Sciences279
(
1746
): 
4389–4398
. 
https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2012.1667</p>
         <p>Seegers L.
, 
De Vos L.
&amp; 
Okeyo D.O.2003
. 
Annotated checklist of the freshwater fishes of Kenya (excluding the lacustrine haplochromines from Lake Victoria)
. 
Journal of East African Natural History92
: 
11–47
. 
https://doi.org/10.2982/0012-8317(2003)92%5B11:ACOTFF%5D2.0.CO;2</p>
         <p>Seehausen O.
&amp; 
Wagner C.E.2014
. 
Speciation in freshwater fishes
. 
Annual Review of Ecology
, 
Evolution
, 
and Systematics45
: 
621–651
. 
https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-120213-091818</p>
         <p>Skelton P.H.1994
. 
Diversity and distribution of freshwater fishes in East and Southern Africa
. 
Annals of the Royal Central Africa Museum (Zoology)275
: 
95–131
.
</p>
         <p>Skelton P.H.
, 
Tweddle D.
&amp; 
Jackson P.B.N.1991
. 
Cyprinids of Africa
. 
In
: 
Winfield I.J.
&amp; 
Nelson J.S.
(eds) 
Cyprinid Fishes: Systematics
, 
Biology and Exploitation
: 
211–239
. 
Chapman &amp; Hall, London, UK
.
</p>
         <p>Snoeks J.2004
. 
The Cichlid Diversity of Lake Malawi/Nyasa/Niassa: Identification
, 
Distribution and Taxonomy
. 
Cichlid Press, El Paso, USA
.
</p>
         <p>Snoeks J.
, 
Harrison I.J.
&amp; 
Stiassny M.L.J.2011
. 
The status and distribution of freshwater fishes
. 
In
: 
Darwall W.R.T.
, 
Smith K.G.
, 
Allen D.J.
, 
Holland R.A.
, 
Harrison I.J.
&amp; 
Brooks E.G.E.
(eds) 
The Diversity of Life in African Freshwaters: Under Water
, 
Under Threat. An Analysis of the Status and Distribution of Freshwater Species throughout Mainland Africa
: 
42–73
. 
IUCN, Cambridge &amp; Gland
.
</p>
         <p>Templeton A.R.
, 
Crandall K.A.
&amp; 
Sing C.F.1992
. 
A cladistic analysis of phenotypic associations with haplotypes inferred from restriction endonuclease mapping and DNA sequence data. III. Cladogram estimation
. 
Genetics132
: 
619–633
.
</p>
         <p>Van Ginneken M.
, 
Decru E.
, 
Verheyen E.
&amp; 
Snoeks J.2017
. 

Morphometry and DNA barcoding reveal cryptic diversity in the genus 
Enteromius
(Cypriniformes: Cyprinidae) from the Congo basin, Africa

. 
European Journal of Taxonomy310
: 
1–32
. 
https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2017.310</p>
         <p>Wagner C.E.
, 
McCuneA.R.
&amp; 
Lovette I.J.2012
. 
Recent speciation between sympatric Tanganyikan cichlid colour morphs
. 
Molecular Ecology21
: 
3283-3292
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2012.05607.x</p>
         <p>Whitehead P.J.P.1960
. 

Three new cyprinid fishes of the genus 
Barbus
from the Lake Victoria basin

. 
Revue de Zoologie et de Botanique africaines62
(1– 
2
): 
106–119
.
</p>
         <p>Yang L.
, 
Sado T.
, 
Hirt M.V.
, 
Pasco-Viel E.
, 
Arunachalam M.
, 
Li J.
, 
Wang X.
, 
Freyhof J.
, 
Saitoh K.
, 
Simons A.M.
, 
Miya M.
, 
He S.
&amp; 
Mayden R.L.2015
. 
Phylogeny and polyploidy: resolving the classification of cyprinine fishes (Teleostei: Cypriniformes)
. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution85
: 
97–116
. 
https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2015.01.014</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>DUMMY HEADING</title>
         <p>
Manuscript received: 
9 April 2020</p>
         <p>
Manuscript accepted: 
23 June 2020</p>
         <p>
Published on: 
11 August 2020</p>
         <p>Topic editor: Rudy Jocqué</p>
         <p>Section editor: Felipe Ottoni</p>
         <p>Desk editor: Pepe Fernández</p>
         <p>
Printed versions of all papers are also deposited in the libraries of the institutes that are members of the 
EJT
consortium: Muséum national d’histoire naturelle, Paris, 
France
; Meise Botanic Garden, 
Belgium
; Royal Museum for Central Africa, Tervuren, 
Belgium
; Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences, 
Brussels
, 
Belgium
; Natural History Museum of 
Denmark
, Copenhagen, 
Denmark
; Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Leiden, 
the Netherlands
; Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales-CSIC, 
Madrid
, 
Spain
; Real Jardín Botánico de 
Madrid
CSIC, 
Spain
; Zoological Research Museum Alexander Koenig, Bonn, 
Germany
; National Museum, 
Prague
, 
Czech Republic
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Supplementary files</title>
         <p>SM
.01. Overview of the specimens used for morphological and genetic analyses.
</p>
         <p>SM
.02. PC loadings and percentages of total variance of the PCA on 24 log-transformed measurements of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
: group A (n = 21) and group B (n = 50).
</p>
         <p>SM
.03. PC loadings and percentages of total variance of the PCA on 24 log-transformed measurements of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
(n = 69).
</p>
         <p>SM
.04. PC loadings and percentages of total variance of the PCA on 15 meristics of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
(n = 62).
</p>
         <p>SM
.05. PC loadings and percentages of total variance of the PCA on 24 log-transformed measurements of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
(n = 105).
</p>
         <p>SM
.06. PC loadings and percentages of total variance of the PCA on 15 meristics of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
(n = 95).
</p>
         <p>SM
.07. PC loadings and percentages of total variance of the PCA on 24 log-transformed measurements of 
<tp:taxon-name>Enteromius
Cope, 1867
</tp:taxon-name>
(n = 83).
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
