<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3768.2.3</journal-id>
         <issn>1175-5326</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Molecular and morphological assessment of Varanus pilbarensis (Squamata: Varanidae), with a description of a new species from the southern Pilbara, Western Australia</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2014</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Molecular and morphological assessment of 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Squamata</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanidae</tp:taxon-name>
), with a description of a new species from the southern Pilbara, Western 
Australia</p>
         <p>BRADMARYAN
1,4,, PAUL M. OLIVER 
2
, ALISON J. FITCH 
3
&amp; MORGAN O’CONNELL 
1¹
Biologic Environmental Survey Pty Ltd, 
50
B Angove Street, North Perth, Western 
Australia6006
, 
AUSTRALIA
. E-mail: 
<tp:taxon-name>Lerista</tp:taxon-name>
. 
2
@bigpond.com.
</p>
         <p>2
Department of Zoology, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, Victoria 
3010
, 
AUSTRALIA
and Museum Victoria, GPO Box 
666
, Melbourne, Victoria 
3001
, 
AUSTRALIA
.
</p>
         <p>3
School of Molecular and Biomedical Science, The University of Adelaide, Adelaide, South 
Australia5000
, 
AUSTRALIA4
Department of Terrestrial Zoology, Western Australian Museum, 
49
Kew Street, Welshpool, Western 
Australia6106
, 
AUSTRALIA</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis
Storr, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
is a specialised saxicolous varanid endemic to the Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
. We present genetic and morphological evidence confirming the existence of a divergent southern lineage, here described as 
<tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
. The new species differs noticeably in having a darker colouration and a reduced pattern of small whitish ocelli on the dorsal surface of the limbs only with a largely unbanded tail. By contrast, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
which is redescribed and restricted to the northern lineage, is paler and more boldly patterned with large greyish ocelli on the dorsal and lateral surfaces of the body and a strongly banded tail. The two species have discrete distributions centred on the Chichester and Hamersley Ranges to the north and south of the Fortescue River Basin. This pattern of intraregional genetic structuring is similar to that found in a number of other saxicolous lizard lineages from the Pilbara.
</p>
         <p>Key words:
goanna, Chichester Range, Hamersley Range, Fortescue River Basin, mtDNA divergence
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>
Varanids are one of the more high profile, well studied and widely recognised groups of lizards in the world (e.g. 

King &amp; Green 
1993
; 

Vincent &amp; Wilson 
1999
; 

Eidenmüller 
2007
). 
Australia
is a global centre of varanid lizard diversity (

Pianka 
et al.2004
); however taxonomic activity over the last decade has focused on varanid taxa distributed across the islands of 
Indonesia
and the 
Philippines
(e.g. 

Ziegler 
et al.2007
; 

Welton 
et al.2010
; 

Koch 
et al.2010
a

; 

Koch 
et al.2013
). Thus, while the total number of recognised varanid species has increased to over 
70 in
recent years (

Koch 
et al.2010
b

), the total number of Australian species has remained relatively stable at around 
27
or 
28
(

Wilson &amp; Swan 
2013
). The last major alpha-taxonomic work on Australian 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanidae</tp:taxon-name>
was published over thirty years ago (

Storr 
1980
). This focused on Western Australian species and included descriptions of five new taxa: 
<tp:taxon-name>V. kingorum</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. panoptes panoptes</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. panoptes rubidus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>V. storri ocreatus</tp:taxon-name>
. Since this revision, two additional species of Australian varanid have been described: 
<tp:taxon-name>V. keithhornei
Wells &amp; Wellington, 
1985</tp:taxon-name>
and 
V. b u s h i
Aplin, Fitch &amp; King, 
2006
. Other significant contributions to the Australian varanid diversity include confirmation that 
<tp:taxon-name>V. doreanus</tp:taxon-name>
occurs on Cape York (

Ziegler 
et al.2001
; S. Wilson pers. comm.), and 
<tp:taxon-name>V. prasinus</tp:taxon-name>
on the Torres Strait islands (

Wilson 
1996
; 

Clarke 
2004
). There however remain unresolved taxonomic issues amongst Australian varanids, mostly involving widespread taxa that show extensive morphological and/or phylogenetic divergence across their distributions (

Fuller 
et al.1998
; 

Ast 
2001
; Fitch 
et al.2006
). The Pilbara region in Western 
Australia
is one of Australia’s herpetological ‘hotspots’ with many endemic lizards and snakes (

How &amp; Cowan 
2006
; 

Powney 
et al.2010
; 

Bush &amp; Maryan 
2011
; 

Doughty 
et al.2011
a

). The varanid fauna of this region is no exception and includes 
10
species (over one-third of the total Australian species diversity). While most 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
species found in the Pilbara are widespread across much of arid and semiarid 
Australia
, there are two endemic species. 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus bushi</tp:taxon-name>
is a small arboreal species widespread in woodlands across the Pilbara, and closely related to two widely distributed arid zone taxa, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. caudolineatus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>V. gilleni
(

Aplin 
et al.2006
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. The other endemic varanid to the Pilbara is 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
, a morphologically distinctive and phylogenetically divergent saxicolous species (Fitch 
et al.2006
). As presently defined, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
is found on rocky ranges and outcrops both to the north (Chichester Range) and south (Hamersley Range) of the Fortescue River Basin in the Pilbara region. The original description of this species was based on nine specimens, eight of which came from north of the Fortescue River Basin. On recent biological surveys by Biologic Environmental Survey in the southern Pilbara (specifically the eastern Hamersley Range) in 
2011
, it was observed that 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
from these sites differed noticeably in colour pattern from northern populations. Further observations during other recent surveys also suggested that two distinct colour forms existed. We present an investigation of the mitochondrial and morphological variation within 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
. Based on the results of this investigation we restrict 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
to the northern Pilbara, and describe the southern populations as a new species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Material and methods</title>
         <p>Genetic analyses.DNA
sequence data was obtained from 
14
specimens

currently referred to as 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
, two published previously (Fitch 
et al.2006
), and 
12
newly sequenced in this study (Appendix 
1
). To provide polarity for character state evolution and to root our phylogeny we included sequences from ten additional closely related species of Australian varanids from the ‘Odatria group’ selected from a published phylogenetic analysis (Fitch 
et al.2006
; Appendix 
2
). Total cellular 
DNA
was extracted from tissues using DNAzol (Life Technologies) as described in Fitch 
et al.
(
2006
). We amplified a fragment of mitochondrial 
DNA
including the 
3
' end of the 
NADH
dehydrogenase 
4
gene (ND 
4
) and tRNA His, tRNA Ser and the 
5
' end of tRNA Leu using primers and protocols as outlined in detail elsewhere (Fitch 
et al.2006
). Polymerase chain reaction products were purified using MultiScreen® PCR Filter Plates (Millipore Billerica), sequenced using the BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing kit v 
3.1
(Applied Biosystems) and sent for capillary separation on an ABI Prism 
3730
xl capillary sequencer at the Australian Genome Research Facility (
AGRF
, Adelaide). New sequences were aligned with published data and translated to check for missense mutations using Maclade V 
4.06
(

Maddison &amp; Maddison 
2003
).
</p>
         <p>
Phylogenetic analyses were performed using Maximum Likelihood methodologies (RaxML 
7.2
. 
8
Stamakakis 
2006
) as implemented in the CIPRES web portal V 
3.1
(www.phylo.org/portal 
2
). Analyses were run using the recommended default settings, the GTRGAMMA model, and ceasing bootstrapping when MRE-bootstrapping criteria had been reached (in this case after 
300
replicates). As analyses included dense intraspecific sampling and many relatively shallow divergences we did not partition the data in order to avoid over-parameterisation. Mean and average uncorrected genetic distances between species were calculated using 
PAUP
*V.b 
8
(

Swofford 
2000
).
</p>
         <p>Morphology.
We examined 
23
specimens

of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
in the collections of the Western Australian Museum, Perth (
WAM
) (Appendix 
1
and 
type
lists in Taxonomy section). Sex was determined by visual inspection of everted hemipenes in males, presence of eggs in heavily gravid females, or internal examination of gonads. Juveniles (
WAM
R 
69695
, 
WAM
R 
125100
) and poorly fixed or damaged specimens (
WAM
R 
13082
) were not included in morphological examination. Methodology for meristic and mensural data collection largely follows 

Aplin 
et al.
(
2006
)

, with two additional measures: head depth and head width. The following linear measurements reported in millimetres (mm) were taken with digital calipers or plastic ruler: snout-vent length (SVL), measured from tip of snout to vent; tail length (TL), measured from vent to tip of complete tail; head and neck length (
HNL
), measured from tip of snout to gular fold; fore limb length (FLL) measured along anterior junction of limb and neck to tip of longest digit (excluding the claw); hind limb length (
HLL
), measured along anterior junction of limb and groin to tip of longest digit (excluding the claw); head depth (HD), measured from a point between the eyes; and head width (HW), measured between the ears. Body length from gular fold to vent (BL) was calculated by subtracting 
HNL
from SVL. Specimens preserved in a circular or twisted position were straightened on a flat surface when measured for snout-vent and tail length. Tails were not measured if they were broken. The following meristic counts were also made: midbody scale rows (
MSR
), number of scales in a circumferential row approximately mid-way between the limbs; ventral scales (VS), number of transverse scale series counted along the ventral midline from gular fold to inguinal fold; and pedal subdigital lamellae (PSL), number of subdigital lamellae rows on fourth digit of pes (the longest digit), from first complete distal row to apical pad. For quantitative data and scale characteristics we present ranges based on mature specimens only.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>Genetics.
Our final alignment of sequence data was 
663
base pairs (bp) long; 
600
bp from the 
5
' end of the 

ND 
4
gene and 
63
bp of 
tRNAHis
. We found no insertion or deletion events or misplaced stop codons, suggesting that the sequence amplified is not paralogous. Amongst samples of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>103
sites were variable, and of these 
90
were parsimony informative. No species was recovered as sister to 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(and we included all potential candidates based on the sampling in Fitch 
et al.2006
). A clade including 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
and seven other mediumsized saxicolous and arboreal species was supported in maximum likelihood bootstrap analysis (ML scores of 
100
; 

). While our sampling of varanids was incomplete, this monophyletic lineage, containing 
<tp:taxon-name>V
. 
glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>V
. 
glebopalma</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>V
. 
mitchelli</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>V
. 
scalaris</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>V
. 
semiremex</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. timorensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>V
. 
tristis</tp:taxon-name>
was also supported by analysis presented in Fitch 
et al.2006
that included all recognized Australian varanid species (not all outgroups included in this study are shown in 

).
</p>
         <p>
The monophyly of all specimens currently referred to 
<tp:taxon-name>V
. 
pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
was strongly supported. Within 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
we identified two divergent and strongly supported clades distributed to the north and south of the Fortescue River Basin (mean uncorrected divergence 
10.2
%, range 
9.7–11.2
%). Within the southern clade we found very little evidence of significant geographic structure (mean uncorrected divergence 
0.5
%, range 0.0– 
1.4
%) over a distance spanning ~ 
300 km
from Newman in the east to Mount Rica in the west (

). In contrast, within the northern clade there was evidence of more significant structure from east to west (mean uncorrected divergence 
4.1
%, range 0.0– 
6.6
%) over a distance spanning ~ 
400 km
from Meentheena in the east to Pannawonica in the west (

). The deepest divergence within this northern clade was between a western lineage including samples from the Burrup Peninsula and around Pannawonica, and a lineage distributed widely through to the east. There was also evidence of further genetic structuring within this western lineage of the northern clade although geographic sampling was insufficient to assess this in detail.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Morphology</title>
         <p>Colouration
. In preservative many aspects of colouration fade considerably. The dark tail colouration however preserves well. Consistent strong banding extending the length of the tail is diagnostic of specimens from the Chichester and other northern ranges while specimens from the Hamersley Range have tails with scattered dark brown spots that (at most) formed very indistinct bands concentrated towards the anterior half. Faint large, pale grey ocelli were also more apparent on the dorsum of preserved specimens from the northern Pilbara (

, 

). In specimens from the Hamersley Range the ocelli were concentrated on the limbs (

, 

).
</p>
         <p>
Differences in colour pattern between populations of adult 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
in the northern and southern Pilbara were more clearly apparent in life. Live specimens from both populations have a reddish ground colour across all dorsal surfaces, however northern individuals were generally paler than southern individuals and characterised by distinctive transverse rows of large pale greyish to black edged ocelli on the neck, body and upper limbs, and alternating highly contrasting off-white and dark brown bands on the digits and tail (

A, B). In contrast, southern populations were characterised by extensive dark brown to black vermiculations across the dorsum of the body (heaviest posteriorly), relatively small pale ocelli on the limbs only, and weak to no banding on the tail (

A, B).
</p>
         <p>Lepidosis.
Two kinds of body scales are present in 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
species are referred to here as ‘primary scales’ and ‘granules’. Granules typically encircle the larger primary scales on one or more sides, however, not all primary scales have this condition. The basic pattern of lepidosis is very similar in the two taxa; however northern individuals have larger and more elongate dorsal scales (

A), while southern individuals have smaller and less elongate dorsal scales (

B).
</p>
         <p>Taxonomic conclusions.
The combination of molecular and morphological data indicates the existence of two geographically discrete lineages characterised by differences in colouration on the dorsum, limbs and tail (

, 

). Each lineage spans an east-west distribution of over 
300 km
(Fig. 
2
) and based on the available preserved material, at a number of sites they come into close geographic proximity: within ~ 
60 km
in the western Pilbara (
WAM
R 
164579
from 
8.5 km
NE Mount Rica v. 
WAM
R 
110941
from 
44 km
W Pannawonica) and ~ 
60 km
in the central Pilbara (
WAM
R 
14901
from Dales Gorge v. 
WAM
R 
39782
from the Cockeraga River) but are not obviously intermediate. Field observations of the two forms have also been made in closer proximity ~ 
40 km
in the eastern Chichester Range at Roy Hill (
22
º 
12
' 
40
"S
119
º04' 
13
"E

) and Hamersley Range at Marillana (
22
º 
12
' 
40
"S
119
º00' 
22
"E

) (Fig. 
2
). While further sampling may reveal contact zones, the two forms are diagnosable and genetically divergent over their respective distributions. We consider this evidence consistent with the presence of two evolutionary distinct and historically independent lineages (species).
</p>
         <p>
Below we provide a brief generic description for 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
, a composite description of the ‘ 
V. pilbarensis’
species-group, restrict 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
to the northern lineage and briefly redescribe it, and describe the southern lineage as a new species.
</p>
         <p>FIGURE 1.
Maximum Likelihood phylogeny of the 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group and selected outgroups estimated from 663 base pairs of ND4 and tRNA data. Branches are not shown for more distant outgroups (
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus acanthurus</tp:taxon-name>
DQ525100, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus baritji</tp:taxon-name>
DQ525106, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus storri</tp:taxon-name>
DQ631869).
</p>
         <p>
Chichester indicate field of boundaries triangles showing. study Solid 
Australia
molecular Western in of examined region
</p>
         <p>
Pilbara specimens in) the indicate squares dot. 
nov
(central. 
sp
with 
<tp:taxon-name>hamersleyensis V.
Basin Symbols.
</tp:taxon-name>
. Hill and River) Roy
</p>
         <p>
(circles Fortescue and 
<tp:taxon-name>pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
intervening Marillana at. 
V
of and proximity Distribution Ranges in close 

FIGURE 
2
.

Hamersley and observations
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Taxonomy</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
            <tp:taxon-name>
Varanidae 

Hardwicke &amp; Gray, 
1827</tp:taxon-name>
         </title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus
Merrem, 
1820</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lacerta varia
Shaw
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus varius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus tristis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. tristis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis
Storr, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. small</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. completely</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Triodia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. large</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. strongly</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Triodia
(Spinifex)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Molecular and morphological assessment of Varanus pilbarensis (Squamata: Varanidae), with a description of a new species from the southern Pilbara, Western Australia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3768.2.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFA1FFB3FFA8FF86F213F602FFAFAB00</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3768.2.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus
Merrem, 
1820</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis
Storr, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
Northern Pilbara Rock Goanna (

, 

, 

)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Southern Pilbara Rock Goanna (

, 

, 

)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
species:
<tp:taxon-name>Lacerta varia
Shaw
</tp:taxon-name>
in: 

White, 
1790
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus varius</tp:taxon-name>
, by subsequent designation of Gray, 
1827
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
The monotypic genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from all other squamate genera in possessing the following combination of character states: head long and flat, neck long; tongue long and forked, legs well developed, each with 
5
strongly-clawed digits; tail long, gradually tapering, in cross section circular, rounded-triangular or laterally compressed; skin smooth to rough, somewhat loose-fitting; head covered by small juxtaposed polygonal scales and body and limbs by oblong or squarish, juxtaposed, non-glossy scales often bearing a low central keel.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Differs from all other Australian 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
in the combination of small size (adult SVL up to 
180 mm
); slender build; tail long (
170–210
% length of body) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
118–128
; dorsal and lateral scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with the larger interoculars; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, and reddish base colouration of the dorsal and lateral surfaces of head and body.
</p>
            <p>Comparisons with other species.
The diagnosis above readily differentiates the 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group from all congeners, however a small number of species warrant additional comparison: 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus tristis</tp:taxon-name>
also occurs in the Pilbara region but is larger (maximum SVL up to 
280 mm
v. 
180 mm
), has more midbody scales (between 
119–152
v. 
118–128
), a less depressed head with a comparatively shorter snout, and a larger and more spinose cloacal scale cluster (

Storr 
et al.1983
). Within the Pilbara, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
is also strictly saxicolous and has a reddish ground colour over most of the dorsum, whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>V. tristis</tp:taxon-name>
is largely arboreal and grey, dark brown to black over the dorsum. 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
from the Kimberley is a saxicolous species similar in appearance to 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(depressed body, long tail and dorsal ocelli); however, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
attains a larger size (maximum SVL up to 
227 mm
v. 
180 mm
), has more midbody scales (between 
122–151
v. 
118–128
) and a proportionally longer tail (between 
183–268
% of SVL v. 
170–211
%).
</p>
            <p>
All subsequent morphological comparisons will involve only the two species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Material examined. 
Holotype
:
WAM
R 
39782
, male, Chichester Range, Cockeraga River (
22
º03'S
118
º 
48
'E

), Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, J.C. Wombey, 
7
April 
1971
. 
Paratypes
:

All from Western 
Australia
. 
WAM
R 
10811
(male)—Abydos (
21
º 
25
'S
118
º 
55
'E

); 
WAM
R 
13082
* (unsexed)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

); 
WAM
R 
14901**
(male)—Dales Gorge, Hamersley Range (
22
º 
30
'S
118
º 
36
'E

); 
WAM
R 
20017
(male)—Black Hill Pool (
21
º 
19
'S
117
º 
15
'E

); 
WAM
R 
28011
– 
12
(males)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

); 
WAM
R 
39158
(male)— 
2 km
W Nullagine (
21
º 
54
'S
120
º05'E

); 
WAM
R 
60432
(female)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

).
</p>
            <p>*Poor specimen not included in morphological examination.</p>
            <p>**
Represents new taxon described below.
</p>
            <p>Extended diagnosis and comparison.
Differs from all Australian congeners by the following combination of characters: size moderately small (SVL up to 
180 mm
); slender build; tail long (between 
170–211
% of SVL) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
118–128
; dorsal and lateral primary scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with larger interoculars; dorsal scales elongate, ovate; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, dorsal and lateral surfaces of body with distinct transverse series of large ocelli on a light reddish-brown background, and tail with prominent alternating light and dark bands.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
differs from its sister species in the Hamersley Range (described below) in its overall paler colouration, large greyish ocelli on the dorsal and lateral surfaces of body and limbs (
<tp:taxon-name>v. small</tp:taxon-name>
whitish ocelli on limbs only), strongly banded tail (
<tp:taxon-name>v. completely</tp:taxon-name>
or mostly unbanded) and larger and more elongate dorsal scales (

A).
</p>
            <p>
Re-description of 
holotype
(

). Small-bodied 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
with a depressed body. Head elongate and depressed in lateral view; upper rostrum slightly protruding over lower jaw, genial groove distinct. Tail long and gradually tapering, moderately dorsoventrally depressed proximally, circular centrally, becoming more triangular distally. Eyes large with scaly upper and lower eyelids, closer to nostril than to ear opening; supraocular brow present above eyes. Snout moderately long, rounded in dorsal and lateral views; nostrils large and visible from above, oriented dorsolaterally, approximately equidistant between tip of snout and anterior edge of eye. Ear openings much higher than wide, oriented distally at 
45
º to the corner of jaw. Head scales small, smooth, supraoculars gradually merging with the larger interoculars; canthus rostralis weak (not entirely absent as stated by 

Storr 
1980
), demarcated by low ridge of larger scales anterior to eye and contacting nostril; rostral and mental scales higher than wide, twice the size of adjacent scales.
</p>
            <p>
Limbs well-developed and moderately slender, ventral surface of digits with enlarged paired circular lamellae, scales on manus and pes otherwise consisting of conical tubercles; claws short and thick, with strongly recurved tips. Dorsal primary scales small, relatively uniform and ovate with small central keel, bordered by row of small granules; ventral scales larger and much longer than wide; caudal scales undifferentiated on dorsal and ventral surfaces, at base of tail similar in size to dorsal scales on torso, grading to larger with moderate keels in central section of tail and narrow with sharp keels towards tip; cloacal region with paired set of 
4–6
curved ventrolateral rows of long, narrow pointed scales, increasing in height, size and spinosity distally.
</p>
            <p>In preservative, ground colour light brown, with reddish tinge on head and limbs, and tending greyer on flanks. Patterning on head includes light brown spotting and similarly coloured bars on labials. Dorsal surfaces and base of tail with dark brown spots (prominent on tail) coalescing to form narrow, wavy transverse lines. Limbs with light grey ocelli, larger and more prominent on hindlimbs. Dark brown transverse bands present from mid to distal point of tail. Ventral surface white with faint light grey bands.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Variation.
Tables 
1–2
summarises the mensural and meristic data for 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
. In preservative, dorsal patterning in most individuals is similar (

), consisting of fine dark brown spots on a lighter brown background. In some individuals (
WAM
R 
100766
, 
WAM
R 
165513
) the entire dorsum has widely scattered spots on individual scales, while in others (
WAM
R 
102103
, 
WAM
R 
163916
, 
WAM
R 
170132
) the spots coalesce to form irregular transverse lines. The smallest individual (
WAM
R 
132659
) is very boldly marked with dorsal spots almost forming wavy bars across dorsum. One individual (
WAM
R 
110941
) has a uniform dark brown body and lighter head with very indistinct ocelli on the dorsum and a strongly banded tail. All specimens have strongly banded tails. The large, pale grey ocelli are faint on some individuals (
WAM
R 
100766
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>MeanRangeSDN MeanRangeSDNSVL139.8105.7–18020.717 136.6120–16018.26TL264222–31630.714 264.8217–29542.84HNL54.142.2–67.88.417 54.246.7–64.58.06FLL39.732.8–53.25.617 40.133.7–44.44.06HLL52.240.2–67.48.017 52.439.4–648.76HD8.46–121.717 8.36–10.31.66HW16.412.1–22.63.017 15.913.2–19.82.86BL85.763.5–112.212.717 82.572.5–95.910.46MSR122.3118–1283.017 121.1120–1221.06VS67.564–722.117 69.365–743.26PSL20.118–221.517 21.921–230.76</p>
            <p>WAM # SEXSVLTLHNLFLLHLLHDHWBLMSRVSPSLR10811 male107.8NA43.736.146.3713.7641266820R14901 male15231658.843.359.910.318.893.21226822R20017 male137.328854.636.750.78.517.582.71246822R28011 male16529264.843.760.29.722.6100.21206620R28012 male15530564.148.560.41220.490.81246622R39158 female12022245.432.841.17.413.474.51246620R39782 male15327758.741.959.69.91994.31286820R60432 female12623548.134.947.67.414.577.81206622R90856 female14025050.838.351.87.61689.21206818R100766 male18030667.853.267.410.820.2112.21186422R102103 male16329664.939.256.210.517.198.11266420R110941 female13723851.736.748.86.414.885.31207218R132659 female105.722242.233.940.2612.163.51226819R139384 female125.123245.43943.46.913.177.71187019R163916 female134.126849.73847.28.416.284.31246820R165513 female137.926551.736.151.56.614.186.11207018R170132 male152.8NA62.145.862.58.917.590.71246822</p>
            <p>Colouration in life.
The following description of colouration in life is based on 

A, B and field observations of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
from the Chichester and surrounding northern ranges. Dorsal ground colour of head, body and limbs light reddish-brown, slightly paler (tending towards yellowish) on head. Dorsal surfaces of head and neck distinctly spotted or flecked with dark reddish-brown, sometimes coalescing to form narrow wavy, transverse bands. Distinct reddish-brown to black vertical bars on labial and temporal regions. Upper surface of dorsum and base of tail with numerous small blackish-brown to black spots that coalesce into narrow (one scale wide) transverse bars or wavy lines. Between these spots are transverse rows of large greyish ocelli. These ocelli vary in degrees of intensity and with body size but are clearly discernible posteriorly at any stage of maturity. Limbs dorsally and laterally with irregular pale grey or whitish ocelli (often dark-edged and/or dark-centred) and, larger and brighter on hindlimbs. Ground colour of proximal section of tail light brown or greyish, often with large greyish ocelli; ground colour of distal section of tail grading from cream to white with dark reddish-brown to black rings, giving a distinct banded appearance. Ventral surfaces of throat, neck, limbs and body greyish-white, often with irregular transverse grey bands or reticulations.
</p>
            <p>Juveniles are more simply and very brightly patterned, with large black-edged pale ocelli on dorsum and limbs, distinct reddish-brown heads and black and white banded tails.</p>
            <p>Habitat.
This species is closely associated with rocky habitats (

), typically undulating granite and greenstone terrain with significant areas of basaltic ranges (tumbled boulder piles are prominent) and dissected plateau, vegetated with 
<tp:taxon-name>Triodia</tp:taxon-name>
, sparse shrubs and eucalypts (Mckenzie 
et al.2009
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.
Endemic to the northern Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
, largely to the north of the Fortescue River Basin and centred on the Chichester Range. Records extend from the Burrup Peninsula and West Intercourse Island in the northwest, east to the Ord Ranges, Yarrie Mine and Carawine Gorge. There is a single record south of the Fortescue River in the western Chichester Range near Pannawonica (Fig. 
2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Named for the Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
, the region to which it is restricted. Used as a noun in apposition.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
This species appears to be secure and widespread throughout the Chichester Range and other northern ranges, and occurs in popular tourist destinations such as at Millstream Chichester National Park. This species can be locally abundant in suitable rocky areas. 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
is illustrated in numerous publications (e.g. 

Storr 
et al.1983
: Plate 
15
; 

Vincent &amp; Wilson 
1999
: 
75
; 

Pianka 
et al.2004
: 
430
; 

Eidenmüller 
2007
: 
105
; 

Wilson &amp; Swan 
2013
: 
429
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Material examined. 
Holotype
:
WAM
R 
145733
, male, Hamersley Range, Weeli Wolli Creek (
22
º 
52
' 
40
"S
119
º 
14
' 
24
"E

), Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, R. Teale &amp; G. Harold, 
28
April 
2003
. Fixed in 
10
% formalin, stored in 
70
% ethanol, liver sample stored in – 
80
ºC ultrafreezer at 
WAM
. 
Paratypes
:

All from Western 
Australia
. 
WAM
R 
125456
(male)— 
30 km
E Newman (
23
º 
19
'S
120
º02'E

); 
WAM
R 
125766
(female)—Circular Pool, Dales Gorge (
22
º 
38
' 
36
"S
118
º 
33
' 
47
"E

); 
WAM
R 
129628
(male)— 
120 km
NW Newman (
22
º 
55
'S
119
º01'E

); 
WAM
R 
140734
(female)—Rocklea Station (
22
º 
56
' 
55
"S
117
º 
16
'0 
7
"E); 
WAM
R 
164579
(male)— 
8.5 km
NE Mount Rica (
21
º 
57
'0 
8
"S 
116
º 
29
' 
18
"E

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis and comparison.
Differs from all Australian congeners by the following combination of characters: size moderately small (SVL up to 
160 mm
); slender build; tail long (between 
168–207
% of SVL) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
120–122
; dorsal and lateral scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with larger interoculars; dorsal scales elongate, ovate; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, dorsal and lateral surfaces of body with subdued irregular dark brown to black spots or vermiculations on a dark reddish-brown background, small ocelli on the dorsal surface of the hindlimbs only, and tail without prominent dark bands.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from its sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
in its overall darker colouration, presence of small whitish ocelli usually on the dorsal surface of the limbs only (
<tp:taxon-name>v. large</tp:taxon-name>
greyish ocelli on the dorsal and lateral surfaces of body and limbs), largely unbanded tail (
<tp:taxon-name>v. strongly</tp:taxon-name>
banded tail) and smaller and less elongate dorsal scales (

B).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
(

). Small-bodied 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
with depressed body. Head elongate and depressed in lateral view; upper rostrum slightly protruding over lower jaw, genial groove distinct. Tail long and gradually tapering, moderately dorsoventrally depressed proximally, circular centrally, becoming more triangular distally. Eyes large with scaly upper and lower eyelids; closer to nostril than to ear opening; supraocular brow present above eyes. Snout moderately long, rounded in dorsal and lateral views; nostrils large and visible from above, wider than high, oriented dorsolaterally, approximately equidistant between tip of snout and anterior edge of eye. Ear openings much higher than wide, oriented distally at 
45
º to the corner of jaw. Head scales small, smooth and unornamented; supraocular scales smaller than those on the rostrum, frontal and parietal regions; canthus rostralis weak; rostral scale twice as large as adjacent scales, almost rounded, slightly narrower anteriorly; mental scale higher than wide and almost rectangular.
</p>
            <p>Limbs well-developed and moderately slender; ventral surface of digits with enlarged paired circular lamellae, scales on manus and pes otherwise consisting of conical tubercles; claws darkly pigmented, relatively short, very thick, laterally compressed and with sharp, recurved tips.</p>
            <p>
Dorsal primary scales small, non-overlapping, relatively uniform and ovate, approximately twice as long as wide and with a small central keel; bordered by row of small granules; ventral scales non-overlapping and more rectangular, approximately 
50
% longer and 
100
% wider than dorsal scales, grading smaller on the throat and vent; caudal scales undifferentiated on dorsal and ventral surfaces, at base of tail similar in size to dorsal scales on torso, grading to larger with moderate keels in central section of tail and narrow with sharp keels towards tip; cloacal region with paired set of 
4-6
curved lateroventral rows of long, narrow pointed scales, increasing in height, size and spinosity distally.
</p>
            <p>In preservative, ground colour of dorsum dark brown, slightly lighter on head and neck. Patterning on head includes black spots on some individual scales and dark brown labial bars, dorsal surfaces of torso with mixture of irregular black spots on individual scales or spots coalesce to form narrow, wavy transverse lines. Light brown tail with irregular dark brown to black spots. Forelimbs light brown, hindlimbs darker brown with small whitish ocelli becoming more prominent distally. Ventral surfaces greyish.</p>
            <p>Variation.
Summary mensural and meristic data for the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is presented in 

Tables 
1
and 
3
. In preservative, the ground colouration is always brown (

). All specimens have irregular dark spots on some individual scales or vermiculations across the dorsum, although these vary in degree and intensity; on one individual (
WAM
R 
125766
) the entire dorsum has very fine spots with barely any indication of alignment, while at the other extreme (
WAM
R 
140734
) the dense spots align to form regular wavy lines. Most individuals have some dark spotting on the tail, although one individual (
WAM
R 
164579
) has almost none. The venter sometimes features relatively bold greyish bands that become more narrow and wavy on neck and throat.
</p>
            <p>
Two juvenile specimens (
WAM
R 
69695
: SVL 
61.6 mm
; 
WAM
R 
125100
: 
70 mm
) are more brightly patterned than adults with much larger spots on dorsum, more contrasting and strongly defined ventral surface bands and obviously ringed tails.
</p>
            <p>WAM #SexSVLTLHNLFLLHLLHDHWBL MSRVSPSLR125456male122.3NA46.736.445.57.51575.6 1207022R125766female121.221748.739.449613.272.5 1206622R129628male1602706444.4649.419.895.9 1227021R140734female120NA47.333.739.46.513.472.9 1227221R145733male155.829564.543.758.49.717.791.3 1227423R164579male124.822648.939.550.57.913.475.8 1206522</p>
            <p>Colouration in life.
The following description of colouration in life is based on 

A, B and a photograph from Mount Channar near Paraburdoo (

Ehmann 
1992
). Dorsal ground colour of head, torso and limbs dark reddishbrown, often tending slightly paler on head. Head and neck with irregular subdued small blackish-brown to black spots, snout forward of nostrils often dark brown, sides of head with yellowish tinge. Labial scales with blackishbrown vertical bars. Dorsal surface of torso with numerous small blackish-brown to black spots, often coalescing into narrow (one scale wide) transverse bars or wavy lines and forming a fine black reticulum. Forelimbs reddish brown with dark flecks, hindlimbs noticeably darker brown with small whitish ocelli. Digits on both limbs with indistinct thin pale yellowish bands. Ground colour of the tail light brown, extensively overlain with darker-brown to black spots along its length. Ventral surface of the throat, neck, limbs and body greyish-white.
</p>
            <p>Habitat and ecology.<tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is strictly saxicolous and closely associated with rocky habitats such as banded ironstone rock faces and gorges (

). It shelters in overhangs, crevices, cavities and occasionally under exfoliated rock slabs. Typical vegetation on these faces varies, but often includes 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Triodia
(Spinifex)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Field observations indicate a preference for flat, horizontal sheet ironstone with an eastwest aspect to allow optimum basking in the morning. It is extremely swift and agile; ascending vertical rock faces with ease, and quickly takes shelter in deep crevices when disturbed.
</p>
            <p>
As with 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(

Ehmann 
1992
; B. Maryan pers. obs.

), this species has been observed active after sunset on warm, humid nights. Field observations indicated that activity periods vary seasonally, peaking during the hotter and humid months from October–April and declining when conditions are dry from May–September. The sex ratio among the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
,

including the misidentified 
paratype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(
WAM
R 
14901
) is skewed (
5
adult

males and 
2
adult

females), a bias which seems to be consistent with museum series of other opportunistically collected varanids (

Greer 
1989
) and may reflect different activity periods of the sexes. During surveys in the eastern Hamersley Range, most individuals captured were also males (B. Maryan and M. O’Connell, unpublished data).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.
Known only from the Hamersley Range, a heavily dissected region of banded ironstone occupying the southern part of the Pilbara craton of Western 
Australia
. Records span the Hamersley Range for over 
300 km
from east of Newman (
WAM
R 
125100
, 
WAM
R 
125456
) west to Mount Rica (
WAM
R 
164579
) and south to Rocklea Station (
WAM
R 
140734
) (Fig. 
2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Named for the Hamersley Range of Western 
Australia
, the region to which it is restricted. This is the most prominent mountainous area in Western 
Australia
(including Mount Meharry, 
1245 m
, and the highest peak in the state) and home to a suite of endemic taxa. Used as a noun in apposition.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
This species appears to be secure and widespread throughout the Hamersley Range, and occurs in popular tourist destinations such as at Karijini National Park (one of the largest National Parks in Western 
Australia
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus
Merrem, 
1820</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lacerta varia
Shaw
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus varius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus tristis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. tristis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis
Storr, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. small</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. completely</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Triodia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. large</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. strongly</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Triodia
(Spinifex)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Molecular and morphological assessment of Varanus pilbarensis (Squamata: Varanidae), with a description of a new species from the southern Pilbara, Western Australia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3768.2.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFA1FFB3FFA8FF86F213F602FFAFAB00</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3768.2.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus
Merrem, 
1820</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis
Storr, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
Northern Pilbara Rock Goanna (

, 

, 

)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Southern Pilbara Rock Goanna (

, 

, 

)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
species:
<tp:taxon-name>Lacerta varia
Shaw
</tp:taxon-name>
in: 

White, 
1790
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus varius</tp:taxon-name>
, by subsequent designation of Gray, 
1827
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
The monotypic genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from all other squamate genera in possessing the following combination of character states: head long and flat, neck long; tongue long and forked, legs well developed, each with 
5
strongly-clawed digits; tail long, gradually tapering, in cross section circular, rounded-triangular or laterally compressed; skin smooth to rough, somewhat loose-fitting; head covered by small juxtaposed polygonal scales and body and limbs by oblong or squarish, juxtaposed, non-glossy scales often bearing a low central keel.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Differs from all other Australian 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
in the combination of small size (adult SVL up to 
180 mm
); slender build; tail long (
170–210
% length of body) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
118–128
; dorsal and lateral scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with the larger interoculars; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, and reddish base colouration of the dorsal and lateral surfaces of head and body.
</p>
            <p>Comparisons with other species.
The diagnosis above readily differentiates the 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group from all congeners, however a small number of species warrant additional comparison: 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus tristis</tp:taxon-name>
also occurs in the Pilbara region but is larger (maximum SVL up to 
280 mm
v. 
180 mm
), has more midbody scales (between 
119–152
v. 
118–128
), a less depressed head with a comparatively shorter snout, and a larger and more spinose cloacal scale cluster (

Storr 
et al.1983
). Within the Pilbara, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
is also strictly saxicolous and has a reddish ground colour over most of the dorsum, whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>V. tristis</tp:taxon-name>
is largely arboreal and grey, dark brown to black over the dorsum. 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
from the Kimberley is a saxicolous species similar in appearance to 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(depressed body, long tail and dorsal ocelli); however, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
attains a larger size (maximum SVL up to 
227 mm
v. 
180 mm
), has more midbody scales (between 
122–151
v. 
118–128
) and a proportionally longer tail (between 
183–268
% of SVL v. 
170–211
%).
</p>
            <p>
All subsequent morphological comparisons will involve only the two species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Material examined. 
Holotype
:
WAM
R 
39782
, male, Chichester Range, Cockeraga River (
22
º03'S
118
º 
48
'E

), Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, J.C. Wombey, 
7
April 
1971
. 
Paratypes
:

All from Western 
Australia
. 
WAM
R 
10811
(male)—Abydos (
21
º 
25
'S
118
º 
55
'E

); 
WAM
R 
13082
* (unsexed)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

); 
WAM
R 
14901**
(male)—Dales Gorge, Hamersley Range (
22
º 
30
'S
118
º 
36
'E

); 
WAM
R 
20017
(male)—Black Hill Pool (
21
º 
19
'S
117
º 
15
'E

); 
WAM
R 
28011
– 
12
(males)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

); 
WAM
R 
39158
(male)— 
2 km
W Nullagine (
21
º 
54
'S
120
º05'E

); 
WAM
R 
60432
(female)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

).
</p>
            <p>*Poor specimen not included in morphological examination.</p>
            <p>**
Represents new taxon described below.
</p>
            <p>Extended diagnosis and comparison.
Differs from all Australian congeners by the following combination of characters: size moderately small (SVL up to 
180 mm
); slender build; tail long (between 
170–211
% of SVL) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
118–128
; dorsal and lateral primary scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with larger interoculars; dorsal scales elongate, ovate; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, dorsal and lateral surfaces of body with distinct transverse series of large ocelli on a light reddish-brown background, and tail with prominent alternating light and dark bands.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
differs from its sister species in the Hamersley Range (described below) in its overall paler colouration, large greyish ocelli on the dorsal and lateral surfaces of body and limbs (
<tp:taxon-name>v. small</tp:taxon-name>
whitish ocelli on limbs only), strongly banded tail (
<tp:taxon-name>v. completely</tp:taxon-name>
or mostly unbanded) and larger and more elongate dorsal scales (

A).
</p>
            <p>
Re-description of 
holotype
(

). Small-bodied 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
with a depressed body. Head elongate and depressed in lateral view; upper rostrum slightly protruding over lower jaw, genial groove distinct. Tail long and gradually tapering, moderately dorsoventrally depressed proximally, circular centrally, becoming more triangular distally. Eyes large with scaly upper and lower eyelids, closer to nostril than to ear opening; supraocular brow present above eyes. Snout moderately long, rounded in dorsal and lateral views; nostrils large and visible from above, oriented dorsolaterally, approximately equidistant between tip of snout and anterior edge of eye. Ear openings much higher than wide, oriented distally at 
45
º to the corner of jaw. Head scales small, smooth, supraoculars gradually merging with the larger interoculars; canthus rostralis weak (not entirely absent as stated by 

Storr 
1980
), demarcated by low ridge of larger scales anterior to eye and contacting nostril; rostral and mental scales higher than wide, twice the size of adjacent scales.
</p>
            <p>
Limbs well-developed and moderately slender, ventral surface of digits with enlarged paired circular lamellae, scales on manus and pes otherwise consisting of conical tubercles; claws short and thick, with strongly recurved tips. Dorsal primary scales small, relatively uniform and ovate with small central keel, bordered by row of small granules; ventral scales larger and much longer than wide; caudal scales undifferentiated on dorsal and ventral surfaces, at base of tail similar in size to dorsal scales on torso, grading to larger with moderate keels in central section of tail and narrow with sharp keels towards tip; cloacal region with paired set of 
4–6
curved ventrolateral rows of long, narrow pointed scales, increasing in height, size and spinosity distally.
</p>
            <p>In preservative, ground colour light brown, with reddish tinge on head and limbs, and tending greyer on flanks. Patterning on head includes light brown spotting and similarly coloured bars on labials. Dorsal surfaces and base of tail with dark brown spots (prominent on tail) coalescing to form narrow, wavy transverse lines. Limbs with light grey ocelli, larger and more prominent on hindlimbs. Dark brown transverse bands present from mid to distal point of tail. Ventral surface white with faint light grey bands.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Variation.
Tables 
1–2
summarises the mensural and meristic data for 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
. In preservative, dorsal patterning in most individuals is similar (

), consisting of fine dark brown spots on a lighter brown background. In some individuals (
WAM
R 
100766
, 
WAM
R 
165513
) the entire dorsum has widely scattered spots on individual scales, while in others (
WAM
R 
102103
, 
WAM
R 
163916
, 
WAM
R 
170132
) the spots coalesce to form irregular transverse lines. The smallest individual (
WAM
R 
132659
) is very boldly marked with dorsal spots almost forming wavy bars across dorsum. One individual (
WAM
R 
110941
) has a uniform dark brown body and lighter head with very indistinct ocelli on the dorsum and a strongly banded tail. All specimens have strongly banded tails. The large, pale grey ocelli are faint on some individuals (
WAM
R 
100766
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>MeanRangeSDN MeanRangeSDNSVL139.8105.7–18020.717 136.6120–16018.26TL264222–31630.714 264.8217–29542.84HNL54.142.2–67.88.417 54.246.7–64.58.06FLL39.732.8–53.25.617 40.133.7–44.44.06HLL52.240.2–67.48.017 52.439.4–648.76HD8.46–121.717 8.36–10.31.66HW16.412.1–22.63.017 15.913.2–19.82.86BL85.763.5–112.212.717 82.572.5–95.910.46MSR122.3118–1283.017 121.1120–1221.06VS67.564–722.117 69.365–743.26PSL20.118–221.517 21.921–230.76</p>
            <p>WAM # SEXSVLTLHNLFLLHLLHDHWBLMSRVSPSLR10811 male107.8NA43.736.146.3713.7641266820R14901 male15231658.843.359.910.318.893.21226822R20017 male137.328854.636.750.78.517.582.71246822R28011 male16529264.843.760.29.722.6100.21206620R28012 male15530564.148.560.41220.490.81246622R39158 female12022245.432.841.17.413.474.51246620R39782 male15327758.741.959.69.91994.31286820R60432 female12623548.134.947.67.414.577.81206622R90856 female14025050.838.351.87.61689.21206818R100766 male18030667.853.267.410.820.2112.21186422R102103 male16329664.939.256.210.517.198.11266420R110941 female13723851.736.748.86.414.885.31207218R132659 female105.722242.233.940.2612.163.51226819R139384 female125.123245.43943.46.913.177.71187019R163916 female134.126849.73847.28.416.284.31246820R165513 female137.926551.736.151.56.614.186.11207018R170132 male152.8NA62.145.862.58.917.590.71246822</p>
            <p>Colouration in life.
The following description of colouration in life is based on 

A, B and field observations of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
from the Chichester and surrounding northern ranges. Dorsal ground colour of head, body and limbs light reddish-brown, slightly paler (tending towards yellowish) on head. Dorsal surfaces of head and neck distinctly spotted or flecked with dark reddish-brown, sometimes coalescing to form narrow wavy, transverse bands. Distinct reddish-brown to black vertical bars on labial and temporal regions. Upper surface of dorsum and base of tail with numerous small blackish-brown to black spots that coalesce into narrow (one scale wide) transverse bars or wavy lines. Between these spots are transverse rows of large greyish ocelli. These ocelli vary in degrees of intensity and with body size but are clearly discernible posteriorly at any stage of maturity. Limbs dorsally and laterally with irregular pale grey or whitish ocelli (often dark-edged and/or dark-centred) and, larger and brighter on hindlimbs. Ground colour of proximal section of tail light brown or greyish, often with large greyish ocelli; ground colour of distal section of tail grading from cream to white with dark reddish-brown to black rings, giving a distinct banded appearance. Ventral surfaces of throat, neck, limbs and body greyish-white, often with irregular transverse grey bands or reticulations.
</p>
            <p>Juveniles are more simply and very brightly patterned, with large black-edged pale ocelli on dorsum and limbs, distinct reddish-brown heads and black and white banded tails.</p>
            <p>Habitat.
This species is closely associated with rocky habitats (

), typically undulating granite and greenstone terrain with significant areas of basaltic ranges (tumbled boulder piles are prominent) and dissected plateau, vegetated with 
<tp:taxon-name>Triodia</tp:taxon-name>
, sparse shrubs and eucalypts (Mckenzie 
et al.2009
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.
Endemic to the northern Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
, largely to the north of the Fortescue River Basin and centred on the Chichester Range. Records extend from the Burrup Peninsula and West Intercourse Island in the northwest, east to the Ord Ranges, Yarrie Mine and Carawine Gorge. There is a single record south of the Fortescue River in the western Chichester Range near Pannawonica (Fig. 
2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Named for the Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
, the region to which it is restricted. Used as a noun in apposition.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
This species appears to be secure and widespread throughout the Chichester Range and other northern ranges, and occurs in popular tourist destinations such as at Millstream Chichester National Park. This species can be locally abundant in suitable rocky areas. 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
is illustrated in numerous publications (e.g. 

Storr 
et al.1983
: Plate 
15
; 

Vincent &amp; Wilson 
1999
: 
75
; 

Pianka 
et al.2004
: 
430
; 

Eidenmüller 
2007
: 
105
; 

Wilson &amp; Swan 
2013
: 
429
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Material examined. 
Holotype
:
WAM
R 
145733
, male, Hamersley Range, Weeli Wolli Creek (
22
º 
52
' 
40
"S
119
º 
14
' 
24
"E

), Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, R. Teale &amp; G. Harold, 
28
April 
2003
. Fixed in 
10
% formalin, stored in 
70
% ethanol, liver sample stored in – 
80
ºC ultrafreezer at 
WAM
. 
Paratypes
:

All from Western 
Australia
. 
WAM
R 
125456
(male)— 
30 km
E Newman (
23
º 
19
'S
120
º02'E

); 
WAM
R 
125766
(female)—Circular Pool, Dales Gorge (
22
º 
38
' 
36
"S
118
º 
33
' 
47
"E

); 
WAM
R 
129628
(male)— 
120 km
NW Newman (
22
º 
55
'S
119
º01'E

); 
WAM
R 
140734
(female)—Rocklea Station (
22
º 
56
' 
55
"S
117
º 
16
'0 
7
"E); 
WAM
R 
164579
(male)— 
8.5 km
NE Mount Rica (
21
º 
57
'0 
8
"S 
116
º 
29
' 
18
"E

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis and comparison.
Differs from all Australian congeners by the following combination of characters: size moderately small (SVL up to 
160 mm
); slender build; tail long (between 
168–207
% of SVL) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
120–122
; dorsal and lateral scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with larger interoculars; dorsal scales elongate, ovate; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, dorsal and lateral surfaces of body with subdued irregular dark brown to black spots or vermiculations on a dark reddish-brown background, small ocelli on the dorsal surface of the hindlimbs only, and tail without prominent dark bands.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from its sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
in its overall darker colouration, presence of small whitish ocelli usually on the dorsal surface of the limbs only (
<tp:taxon-name>v. large</tp:taxon-name>
greyish ocelli on the dorsal and lateral surfaces of body and limbs), largely unbanded tail (
<tp:taxon-name>v. strongly</tp:taxon-name>
banded tail) and smaller and less elongate dorsal scales (

B).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
(

). Small-bodied 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
with depressed body. Head elongate and depressed in lateral view; upper rostrum slightly protruding over lower jaw, genial groove distinct. Tail long and gradually tapering, moderately dorsoventrally depressed proximally, circular centrally, becoming more triangular distally. Eyes large with scaly upper and lower eyelids; closer to nostril than to ear opening; supraocular brow present above eyes. Snout moderately long, rounded in dorsal and lateral views; nostrils large and visible from above, wider than high, oriented dorsolaterally, approximately equidistant between tip of snout and anterior edge of eye. Ear openings much higher than wide, oriented distally at 
45
º to the corner of jaw. Head scales small, smooth and unornamented; supraocular scales smaller than those on the rostrum, frontal and parietal regions; canthus rostralis weak; rostral scale twice as large as adjacent scales, almost rounded, slightly narrower anteriorly; mental scale higher than wide and almost rectangular.
</p>
            <p>Limbs well-developed and moderately slender; ventral surface of digits with enlarged paired circular lamellae, scales on manus and pes otherwise consisting of conical tubercles; claws darkly pigmented, relatively short, very thick, laterally compressed and with sharp, recurved tips.</p>
            <p>
Dorsal primary scales small, non-overlapping, relatively uniform and ovate, approximately twice as long as wide and with a small central keel; bordered by row of small granules; ventral scales non-overlapping and more rectangular, approximately 
50
% longer and 
100
% wider than dorsal scales, grading smaller on the throat and vent; caudal scales undifferentiated on dorsal and ventral surfaces, at base of tail similar in size to dorsal scales on torso, grading to larger with moderate keels in central section of tail and narrow with sharp keels towards tip; cloacal region with paired set of 
4-6
curved lateroventral rows of long, narrow pointed scales, increasing in height, size and spinosity distally.
</p>
            <p>In preservative, ground colour of dorsum dark brown, slightly lighter on head and neck. Patterning on head includes black spots on some individual scales and dark brown labial bars, dorsal surfaces of torso with mixture of irregular black spots on individual scales or spots coalesce to form narrow, wavy transverse lines. Light brown tail with irregular dark brown to black spots. Forelimbs light brown, hindlimbs darker brown with small whitish ocelli becoming more prominent distally. Ventral surfaces greyish.</p>
            <p>Variation.
Summary mensural and meristic data for the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is presented in 

Tables 
1
and 
3
. In preservative, the ground colouration is always brown (

). All specimens have irregular dark spots on some individual scales or vermiculations across the dorsum, although these vary in degree and intensity; on one individual (
WAM
R 
125766
) the entire dorsum has very fine spots with barely any indication of alignment, while at the other extreme (
WAM
R 
140734
) the dense spots align to form regular wavy lines. Most individuals have some dark spotting on the tail, although one individual (
WAM
R 
164579
) has almost none. The venter sometimes features relatively bold greyish bands that become more narrow and wavy on neck and throat.
</p>
            <p>
Two juvenile specimens (
WAM
R 
69695
: SVL 
61.6 mm
; 
WAM
R 
125100
: 
70 mm
) are more brightly patterned than adults with much larger spots on dorsum, more contrasting and strongly defined ventral surface bands and obviously ringed tails.
</p>
            <p>WAM #SexSVLTLHNLFLLHLLHDHWBL MSRVSPSLR125456male122.3NA46.736.445.57.51575.6 1207022R125766female121.221748.739.449613.272.5 1206622R129628male1602706444.4649.419.895.9 1227021R140734female120NA47.333.739.46.513.472.9 1227221R145733male155.829564.543.758.49.717.791.3 1227423R164579male124.822648.939.550.57.913.475.8 1206522</p>
            <p>Colouration in life.
The following description of colouration in life is based on 

A, B and a photograph from Mount Channar near Paraburdoo (

Ehmann 
1992
). Dorsal ground colour of head, torso and limbs dark reddishbrown, often tending slightly paler on head. Head and neck with irregular subdued small blackish-brown to black spots, snout forward of nostrils often dark brown, sides of head with yellowish tinge. Labial scales with blackishbrown vertical bars. Dorsal surface of torso with numerous small blackish-brown to black spots, often coalescing into narrow (one scale wide) transverse bars or wavy lines and forming a fine black reticulum. Forelimbs reddish brown with dark flecks, hindlimbs noticeably darker brown with small whitish ocelli. Digits on both limbs with indistinct thin pale yellowish bands. Ground colour of the tail light brown, extensively overlain with darker-brown to black spots along its length. Ventral surface of the throat, neck, limbs and body greyish-white.
</p>
            <p>Habitat and ecology.<tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is strictly saxicolous and closely associated with rocky habitats such as banded ironstone rock faces and gorges (

). It shelters in overhangs, crevices, cavities and occasionally under exfoliated rock slabs. Typical vegetation on these faces varies, but often includes 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Triodia
(Spinifex)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Field observations indicate a preference for flat, horizontal sheet ironstone with an eastwest aspect to allow optimum basking in the morning. It is extremely swift and agile; ascending vertical rock faces with ease, and quickly takes shelter in deep crevices when disturbed.
</p>
            <p>
As with 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(

Ehmann 
1992
; B. Maryan pers. obs.

), this species has been observed active after sunset on warm, humid nights. Field observations indicated that activity periods vary seasonally, peaking during the hotter and humid months from October–April and declining when conditions are dry from May–September. The sex ratio among the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
,

including the misidentified 
paratype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(
WAM
R 
14901
) is skewed (
5
adult

males and 
2
adult

females), a bias which seems to be consistent with museum series of other opportunistically collected varanids (

Greer 
1989
) and may reflect different activity periods of the sexes. During surveys in the eastern Hamersley Range, most individuals captured were also males (B. Maryan and M. O’Connell, unpublished data).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.
Known only from the Hamersley Range, a heavily dissected region of banded ironstone occupying the southern part of the Pilbara craton of Western 
Australia
. Records span the Hamersley Range for over 
300 km
from east of Newman (
WAM
R 
125100
, 
WAM
R 
125456
) west to Mount Rica (
WAM
R 
164579
) and south to Rocklea Station (
WAM
R 
140734
) (Fig. 
2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Named for the Hamersley Range of Western 
Australia
, the region to which it is restricted. This is the most prominent mountainous area in Western 
Australia
(including Mount Meharry, 
1245 m
, and the highest peak in the state) and home to a suite of endemic taxa. Used as a noun in apposition.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
This species appears to be secure and widespread throughout the Hamersley Range, and occurs in popular tourist destinations such as at Karijini National Park (one of the largest National Parks in Western 
Australia
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus
Merrem, 
1820</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lacerta varia
Shaw
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus varius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus tristis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. tristis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis
Storr, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. small</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. completely</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Triodia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. large</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. strongly</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Triodia
(Spinifex)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Molecular and morphological assessment of Varanus pilbarensis (Squamata: Varanidae), with a description of a new species from the southern Pilbara, Western Australia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3768.2.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFA1FFB3FFA8FF86F213F602FFAFAB00</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3768.2.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus
Merrem, 
1820</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis
Storr, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
Northern Pilbara Rock Goanna (

, 

, 

)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Southern Pilbara Rock Goanna (

, 

, 

)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
species:
<tp:taxon-name>Lacerta varia
Shaw
</tp:taxon-name>
in: 

White, 
1790
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus varius</tp:taxon-name>
, by subsequent designation of Gray, 
1827
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
The monotypic genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from all other squamate genera in possessing the following combination of character states: head long and flat, neck long; tongue long and forked, legs well developed, each with 
5
strongly-clawed digits; tail long, gradually tapering, in cross section circular, rounded-triangular or laterally compressed; skin smooth to rough, somewhat loose-fitting; head covered by small juxtaposed polygonal scales and body and limbs by oblong or squarish, juxtaposed, non-glossy scales often bearing a low central keel.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Differs from all other Australian 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
in the combination of small size (adult SVL up to 
180 mm
); slender build; tail long (
170–210
% length of body) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
118–128
; dorsal and lateral scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with the larger interoculars; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, and reddish base colouration of the dorsal and lateral surfaces of head and body.
</p>
            <p>Comparisons with other species.
The diagnosis above readily differentiates the 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group from all congeners, however a small number of species warrant additional comparison: 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus tristis</tp:taxon-name>
also occurs in the Pilbara region but is larger (maximum SVL up to 
280 mm
v. 
180 mm
), has more midbody scales (between 
119–152
v. 
118–128
), a less depressed head with a comparatively shorter snout, and a larger and more spinose cloacal scale cluster (

Storr 
et al.1983
). Within the Pilbara, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
is also strictly saxicolous and has a reddish ground colour over most of the dorsum, whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>V. tristis</tp:taxon-name>
is largely arboreal and grey, dark brown to black over the dorsum. 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
from the Kimberley is a saxicolous species similar in appearance to 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(depressed body, long tail and dorsal ocelli); however, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
attains a larger size (maximum SVL up to 
227 mm
v. 
180 mm
), has more midbody scales (between 
122–151
v. 
118–128
) and a proportionally longer tail (between 
183–268
% of SVL v. 
170–211
%).
</p>
            <p>
All subsequent morphological comparisons will involve only the two species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Material examined. 
Holotype
:
WAM
R 
39782
, male, Chichester Range, Cockeraga River (
22
º03'S
118
º 
48
'E

), Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, J.C. Wombey, 
7
April 
1971
. 
Paratypes
:

All from Western 
Australia
. 
WAM
R 
10811
(male)—Abydos (
21
º 
25
'S
118
º 
55
'E

); 
WAM
R 
13082
* (unsexed)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

); 
WAM
R 
14901**
(male)—Dales Gorge, Hamersley Range (
22
º 
30
'S
118
º 
36
'E

); 
WAM
R 
20017
(male)—Black Hill Pool (
21
º 
19
'S
117
º 
15
'E

); 
WAM
R 
28011
– 
12
(males)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

); 
WAM
R 
39158
(male)— 
2 km
W Nullagine (
21
º 
54
'S
120
º05'E

); 
WAM
R 
60432
(female)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

).
</p>
            <p>*Poor specimen not included in morphological examination.</p>
            <p>**
Represents new taxon described below.
</p>
            <p>Extended diagnosis and comparison.
Differs from all Australian congeners by the following combination of characters: size moderately small (SVL up to 
180 mm
); slender build; tail long (between 
170–211
% of SVL) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
118–128
; dorsal and lateral primary scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with larger interoculars; dorsal scales elongate, ovate; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, dorsal and lateral surfaces of body with distinct transverse series of large ocelli on a light reddish-brown background, and tail with prominent alternating light and dark bands.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
differs from its sister species in the Hamersley Range (described below) in its overall paler colouration, large greyish ocelli on the dorsal and lateral surfaces of body and limbs (
<tp:taxon-name>v. small</tp:taxon-name>
whitish ocelli on limbs only), strongly banded tail (
<tp:taxon-name>v. completely</tp:taxon-name>
or mostly unbanded) and larger and more elongate dorsal scales (

A).
</p>
            <p>
Re-description of 
holotype
(

). Small-bodied 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
with a depressed body. Head elongate and depressed in lateral view; upper rostrum slightly protruding over lower jaw, genial groove distinct. Tail long and gradually tapering, moderately dorsoventrally depressed proximally, circular centrally, becoming more triangular distally. Eyes large with scaly upper and lower eyelids, closer to nostril than to ear opening; supraocular brow present above eyes. Snout moderately long, rounded in dorsal and lateral views; nostrils large and visible from above, oriented dorsolaterally, approximately equidistant between tip of snout and anterior edge of eye. Ear openings much higher than wide, oriented distally at 
45
º to the corner of jaw. Head scales small, smooth, supraoculars gradually merging with the larger interoculars; canthus rostralis weak (not entirely absent as stated by 

Storr 
1980
), demarcated by low ridge of larger scales anterior to eye and contacting nostril; rostral and mental scales higher than wide, twice the size of adjacent scales.
</p>
            <p>
Limbs well-developed and moderately slender, ventral surface of digits with enlarged paired circular lamellae, scales on manus and pes otherwise consisting of conical tubercles; claws short and thick, with strongly recurved tips. Dorsal primary scales small, relatively uniform and ovate with small central keel, bordered by row of small granules; ventral scales larger and much longer than wide; caudal scales undifferentiated on dorsal and ventral surfaces, at base of tail similar in size to dorsal scales on torso, grading to larger with moderate keels in central section of tail and narrow with sharp keels towards tip; cloacal region with paired set of 
4–6
curved ventrolateral rows of long, narrow pointed scales, increasing in height, size and spinosity distally.
</p>
            <p>In preservative, ground colour light brown, with reddish tinge on head and limbs, and tending greyer on flanks. Patterning on head includes light brown spotting and similarly coloured bars on labials. Dorsal surfaces and base of tail with dark brown spots (prominent on tail) coalescing to form narrow, wavy transverse lines. Limbs with light grey ocelli, larger and more prominent on hindlimbs. Dark brown transverse bands present from mid to distal point of tail. Ventral surface white with faint light grey bands.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Variation.
Tables 
1–2
summarises the mensural and meristic data for 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
. In preservative, dorsal patterning in most individuals is similar (

), consisting of fine dark brown spots on a lighter brown background. In some individuals (
WAM
R 
100766
, 
WAM
R 
165513
) the entire dorsum has widely scattered spots on individual scales, while in others (
WAM
R 
102103
, 
WAM
R 
163916
, 
WAM
R 
170132
) the spots coalesce to form irregular transverse lines. The smallest individual (
WAM
R 
132659
) is very boldly marked with dorsal spots almost forming wavy bars across dorsum. One individual (
WAM
R 
110941
) has a uniform dark brown body and lighter head with very indistinct ocelli on the dorsum and a strongly banded tail. All specimens have strongly banded tails. The large, pale grey ocelli are faint on some individuals (
WAM
R 
100766
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>MeanRangeSDN MeanRangeSDNSVL139.8105.7–18020.717 136.6120–16018.26TL264222–31630.714 264.8217–29542.84HNL54.142.2–67.88.417 54.246.7–64.58.06FLL39.732.8–53.25.617 40.133.7–44.44.06HLL52.240.2–67.48.017 52.439.4–648.76HD8.46–121.717 8.36–10.31.66HW16.412.1–22.63.017 15.913.2–19.82.86BL85.763.5–112.212.717 82.572.5–95.910.46MSR122.3118–1283.017 121.1120–1221.06VS67.564–722.117 69.365–743.26PSL20.118–221.517 21.921–230.76</p>
            <p>WAM # SEXSVLTLHNLFLLHLLHDHWBLMSRVSPSLR10811 male107.8NA43.736.146.3713.7641266820R14901 male15231658.843.359.910.318.893.21226822R20017 male137.328854.636.750.78.517.582.71246822R28011 male16529264.843.760.29.722.6100.21206620R28012 male15530564.148.560.41220.490.81246622R39158 female12022245.432.841.17.413.474.51246620R39782 male15327758.741.959.69.91994.31286820R60432 female12623548.134.947.67.414.577.81206622R90856 female14025050.838.351.87.61689.21206818R100766 male18030667.853.267.410.820.2112.21186422R102103 male16329664.939.256.210.517.198.11266420R110941 female13723851.736.748.86.414.885.31207218R132659 female105.722242.233.940.2612.163.51226819R139384 female125.123245.43943.46.913.177.71187019R163916 female134.126849.73847.28.416.284.31246820R165513 female137.926551.736.151.56.614.186.11207018R170132 male152.8NA62.145.862.58.917.590.71246822</p>
            <p>Colouration in life.
The following description of colouration in life is based on 

A, B and field observations of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
from the Chichester and surrounding northern ranges. Dorsal ground colour of head, body and limbs light reddish-brown, slightly paler (tending towards yellowish) on head. Dorsal surfaces of head and neck distinctly spotted or flecked with dark reddish-brown, sometimes coalescing to form narrow wavy, transverse bands. Distinct reddish-brown to black vertical bars on labial and temporal regions. Upper surface of dorsum and base of tail with numerous small blackish-brown to black spots that coalesce into narrow (one scale wide) transverse bars or wavy lines. Between these spots are transverse rows of large greyish ocelli. These ocelli vary in degrees of intensity and with body size but are clearly discernible posteriorly at any stage of maturity. Limbs dorsally and laterally with irregular pale grey or whitish ocelli (often dark-edged and/or dark-centred) and, larger and brighter on hindlimbs. Ground colour of proximal section of tail light brown or greyish, often with large greyish ocelli; ground colour of distal section of tail grading from cream to white with dark reddish-brown to black rings, giving a distinct banded appearance. Ventral surfaces of throat, neck, limbs and body greyish-white, often with irregular transverse grey bands or reticulations.
</p>
            <p>Juveniles are more simply and very brightly patterned, with large black-edged pale ocelli on dorsum and limbs, distinct reddish-brown heads and black and white banded tails.</p>
            <p>Habitat.
This species is closely associated with rocky habitats (

), typically undulating granite and greenstone terrain with significant areas of basaltic ranges (tumbled boulder piles are prominent) and dissected plateau, vegetated with 
<tp:taxon-name>Triodia</tp:taxon-name>
, sparse shrubs and eucalypts (Mckenzie 
et al.2009
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.
Endemic to the northern Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
, largely to the north of the Fortescue River Basin and centred on the Chichester Range. Records extend from the Burrup Peninsula and West Intercourse Island in the northwest, east to the Ord Ranges, Yarrie Mine and Carawine Gorge. There is a single record south of the Fortescue River in the western Chichester Range near Pannawonica (Fig. 
2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Named for the Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
, the region to which it is restricted. Used as a noun in apposition.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
This species appears to be secure and widespread throughout the Chichester Range and other northern ranges, and occurs in popular tourist destinations such as at Millstream Chichester National Park. This species can be locally abundant in suitable rocky areas. 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
is illustrated in numerous publications (e.g. 

Storr 
et al.1983
: Plate 
15
; 

Vincent &amp; Wilson 
1999
: 
75
; 

Pianka 
et al.2004
: 
430
; 

Eidenmüller 
2007
: 
105
; 

Wilson &amp; Swan 
2013
: 
429
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Material examined. 
Holotype
:
WAM
R 
145733
, male, Hamersley Range, Weeli Wolli Creek (
22
º 
52
' 
40
"S
119
º 
14
' 
24
"E

), Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, R. Teale &amp; G. Harold, 
28
April 
2003
. Fixed in 
10
% formalin, stored in 
70
% ethanol, liver sample stored in – 
80
ºC ultrafreezer at 
WAM
. 
Paratypes
:

All from Western 
Australia
. 
WAM
R 
125456
(male)— 
30 km
E Newman (
23
º 
19
'S
120
º02'E

); 
WAM
R 
125766
(female)—Circular Pool, Dales Gorge (
22
º 
38
' 
36
"S
118
º 
33
' 
47
"E

); 
WAM
R 
129628
(male)— 
120 km
NW Newman (
22
º 
55
'S
119
º01'E

); 
WAM
R 
140734
(female)—Rocklea Station (
22
º 
56
' 
55
"S
117
º 
16
'0 
7
"E); 
WAM
R 
164579
(male)— 
8.5 km
NE Mount Rica (
21
º 
57
'0 
8
"S 
116
º 
29
' 
18
"E

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis and comparison.
Differs from all Australian congeners by the following combination of characters: size moderately small (SVL up to 
160 mm
); slender build; tail long (between 
168–207
% of SVL) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
120–122
; dorsal and lateral scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with larger interoculars; dorsal scales elongate, ovate; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, dorsal and lateral surfaces of body with subdued irregular dark brown to black spots or vermiculations on a dark reddish-brown background, small ocelli on the dorsal surface of the hindlimbs only, and tail without prominent dark bands.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from its sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
in its overall darker colouration, presence of small whitish ocelli usually on the dorsal surface of the limbs only (
<tp:taxon-name>v. large</tp:taxon-name>
greyish ocelli on the dorsal and lateral surfaces of body and limbs), largely unbanded tail (
<tp:taxon-name>v. strongly</tp:taxon-name>
banded tail) and smaller and less elongate dorsal scales (

B).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
(

). Small-bodied 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
with depressed body. Head elongate and depressed in lateral view; upper rostrum slightly protruding over lower jaw, genial groove distinct. Tail long and gradually tapering, moderately dorsoventrally depressed proximally, circular centrally, becoming more triangular distally. Eyes large with scaly upper and lower eyelids; closer to nostril than to ear opening; supraocular brow present above eyes. Snout moderately long, rounded in dorsal and lateral views; nostrils large and visible from above, wider than high, oriented dorsolaterally, approximately equidistant between tip of snout and anterior edge of eye. Ear openings much higher than wide, oriented distally at 
45
º to the corner of jaw. Head scales small, smooth and unornamented; supraocular scales smaller than those on the rostrum, frontal and parietal regions; canthus rostralis weak; rostral scale twice as large as adjacent scales, almost rounded, slightly narrower anteriorly; mental scale higher than wide and almost rectangular.
</p>
            <p>Limbs well-developed and moderately slender; ventral surface of digits with enlarged paired circular lamellae, scales on manus and pes otherwise consisting of conical tubercles; claws darkly pigmented, relatively short, very thick, laterally compressed and with sharp, recurved tips.</p>
            <p>
Dorsal primary scales small, non-overlapping, relatively uniform and ovate, approximately twice as long as wide and with a small central keel; bordered by row of small granules; ventral scales non-overlapping and more rectangular, approximately 
50
% longer and 
100
% wider than dorsal scales, grading smaller on the throat and vent; caudal scales undifferentiated on dorsal and ventral surfaces, at base of tail similar in size to dorsal scales on torso, grading to larger with moderate keels in central section of tail and narrow with sharp keels towards tip; cloacal region with paired set of 
4-6
curved lateroventral rows of long, narrow pointed scales, increasing in height, size and spinosity distally.
</p>
            <p>In preservative, ground colour of dorsum dark brown, slightly lighter on head and neck. Patterning on head includes black spots on some individual scales and dark brown labial bars, dorsal surfaces of torso with mixture of irregular black spots on individual scales or spots coalesce to form narrow, wavy transverse lines. Light brown tail with irregular dark brown to black spots. Forelimbs light brown, hindlimbs darker brown with small whitish ocelli becoming more prominent distally. Ventral surfaces greyish.</p>
            <p>Variation.
Summary mensural and meristic data for the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is presented in 

Tables 
1
and 
3
. In preservative, the ground colouration is always brown (

). All specimens have irregular dark spots on some individual scales or vermiculations across the dorsum, although these vary in degree and intensity; on one individual (
WAM
R 
125766
) the entire dorsum has very fine spots with barely any indication of alignment, while at the other extreme (
WAM
R 
140734
) the dense spots align to form regular wavy lines. Most individuals have some dark spotting on the tail, although one individual (
WAM
R 
164579
) has almost none. The venter sometimes features relatively bold greyish bands that become more narrow and wavy on neck and throat.
</p>
            <p>
Two juvenile specimens (
WAM
R 
69695
: SVL 
61.6 mm
; 
WAM
R 
125100
: 
70 mm
) are more brightly patterned than adults with much larger spots on dorsum, more contrasting and strongly defined ventral surface bands and obviously ringed tails.
</p>
            <p>WAM #SexSVLTLHNLFLLHLLHDHWBL MSRVSPSLR125456male122.3NA46.736.445.57.51575.6 1207022R125766female121.221748.739.449613.272.5 1206622R129628male1602706444.4649.419.895.9 1227021R140734female120NA47.333.739.46.513.472.9 1227221R145733male155.829564.543.758.49.717.791.3 1227423R164579male124.822648.939.550.57.913.475.8 1206522</p>
            <p>Colouration in life.
The following description of colouration in life is based on 

A, B and a photograph from Mount Channar near Paraburdoo (

Ehmann 
1992
). Dorsal ground colour of head, torso and limbs dark reddishbrown, often tending slightly paler on head. Head and neck with irregular subdued small blackish-brown to black spots, snout forward of nostrils often dark brown, sides of head with yellowish tinge. Labial scales with blackishbrown vertical bars. Dorsal surface of torso with numerous small blackish-brown to black spots, often coalescing into narrow (one scale wide) transverse bars or wavy lines and forming a fine black reticulum. Forelimbs reddish brown with dark flecks, hindlimbs noticeably darker brown with small whitish ocelli. Digits on both limbs with indistinct thin pale yellowish bands. Ground colour of the tail light brown, extensively overlain with darker-brown to black spots along its length. Ventral surface of the throat, neck, limbs and body greyish-white.
</p>
            <p>Habitat and ecology.<tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is strictly saxicolous and closely associated with rocky habitats such as banded ironstone rock faces and gorges (

). It shelters in overhangs, crevices, cavities and occasionally under exfoliated rock slabs. Typical vegetation on these faces varies, but often includes 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Triodia
(Spinifex)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Field observations indicate a preference for flat, horizontal sheet ironstone with an eastwest aspect to allow optimum basking in the morning. It is extremely swift and agile; ascending vertical rock faces with ease, and quickly takes shelter in deep crevices when disturbed.
</p>
            <p>
As with 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(

Ehmann 
1992
; B. Maryan pers. obs.

), this species has been observed active after sunset on warm, humid nights. Field observations indicated that activity periods vary seasonally, peaking during the hotter and humid months from October–April and declining when conditions are dry from May–September. The sex ratio among the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
,

including the misidentified 
paratype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(
WAM
R 
14901
) is skewed (
5
adult

males and 
2
adult

females), a bias which seems to be consistent with museum series of other opportunistically collected varanids (

Greer 
1989
) and may reflect different activity periods of the sexes. During surveys in the eastern Hamersley Range, most individuals captured were also males (B. Maryan and M. O’Connell, unpublished data).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.
Known only from the Hamersley Range, a heavily dissected region of banded ironstone occupying the southern part of the Pilbara craton of Western 
Australia
. Records span the Hamersley Range for over 
300 km
from east of Newman (
WAM
R 
125100
, 
WAM
R 
125456
) west to Mount Rica (
WAM
R 
164579
) and south to Rocklea Station (
WAM
R 
140734
) (Fig. 
2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Named for the Hamersley Range of Western 
Australia
, the region to which it is restricted. This is the most prominent mountainous area in Western 
Australia
(including Mount Meharry, 
1245 m
, and the highest peak in the state) and home to a suite of endemic taxa. Used as a noun in apposition.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
This species appears to be secure and widespread throughout the Hamersley Range, and occurs in popular tourist destinations such as at Karijini National Park (one of the largest National Parks in Western 
Australia
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus
Merrem, 
1820</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lacerta varia
Shaw
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus varius</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus tristis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. tristis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis
Storr, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. small</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. completely</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Triodia</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. large</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>v. strongly</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Triodia
(Spinifex)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Molecular and morphological assessment of Varanus pilbarensis (Squamata: Varanidae), with a description of a new species from the southern Pilbara, Western Australia</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3768.2.3</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFA1FFB3FFA8FF86F213F602FFAFAB00</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3768.2.3</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus
Merrem, 
1820</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis
Storr, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
Northern Pilbara Rock Goanna (

, 

, 

)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Southern Pilbara Rock Goanna (

, 

, 

)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
species:
<tp:taxon-name>Lacerta varia
Shaw
</tp:taxon-name>
in: 

White, 
1790
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus varius</tp:taxon-name>
, by subsequent designation of Gray, 
1827
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
The monotypic genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
differs from all other squamate genera in possessing the following combination of character states: head long and flat, neck long; tongue long and forked, legs well developed, each with 
5
strongly-clawed digits; tail long, gradually tapering, in cross section circular, rounded-triangular or laterally compressed; skin smooth to rough, somewhat loose-fitting; head covered by small juxtaposed polygonal scales and body and limbs by oblong or squarish, juxtaposed, non-glossy scales often bearing a low central keel.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.
Differs from all other Australian 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
in the combination of small size (adult SVL up to 
180 mm
); slender build; tail long (
170–210
% length of body) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
118–128
; dorsal and lateral scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with the larger interoculars; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, and reddish base colouration of the dorsal and lateral surfaces of head and body.
</p>
            <p>Comparisons with other species.
The diagnosis above readily differentiates the 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group from all congeners, however a small number of species warrant additional comparison: 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus tristis</tp:taxon-name>
also occurs in the Pilbara region but is larger (maximum SVL up to 
280 mm
v. 
180 mm
), has more midbody scales (between 
119–152
v. 
118–128
), a less depressed head with a comparatively shorter snout, and a larger and more spinose cloacal scale cluster (

Storr 
et al.1983
). Within the Pilbara, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
is also strictly saxicolous and has a reddish ground colour over most of the dorsum, whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>V. tristis</tp:taxon-name>
is largely arboreal and grey, dark brown to black over the dorsum. 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
from the Kimberley is a saxicolous species similar in appearance to 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(depressed body, long tail and dorsal ocelli); however, 
<tp:taxon-name>V. glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
attains a larger size (maximum SVL up to 
227 mm
v. 
180 mm
), has more midbody scales (between 
122–151
v. 
118–128
) and a proportionally longer tail (between 
183–268
% of SVL v. 
170–211
%).
</p>
            <p>
All subsequent morphological comparisons will involve only the two species in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Material examined. 
Holotype
:
WAM
R 
39782
, male, Chichester Range, Cockeraga River (
22
º03'S
118
º 
48
'E

), Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, J.C. Wombey, 
7
April 
1971
. 
Paratypes
:

All from Western 
Australia
. 
WAM
R 
10811
(male)—Abydos (
21
º 
25
'S
118
º 
55
'E

); 
WAM
R 
13082
* (unsexed)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

); 
WAM
R 
14901**
(male)—Dales Gorge, Hamersley Range (
22
º 
30
'S
118
º 
36
'E

); 
WAM
R 
20017
(male)—Black Hill Pool (
21
º 
19
'S
117
º 
15
'E

); 
WAM
R 
28011
– 
12
(males)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

); 
WAM
R 
39158
(male)— 
2 km
W Nullagine (
21
º 
54
'S
120
º05'E

); 
WAM
R 
60432
(female)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'S
118
º 
57
'E

).
</p>
            <p>*Poor specimen not included in morphological examination.</p>
            <p>**
Represents new taxon described below.
</p>
            <p>Extended diagnosis and comparison.
Differs from all Australian congeners by the following combination of characters: size moderately small (SVL up to 
180 mm
); slender build; tail long (between 
170–211
% of SVL) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
118–128
; dorsal and lateral primary scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with larger interoculars; dorsal scales elongate, ovate; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, dorsal and lateral surfaces of body with distinct transverse series of large ocelli on a light reddish-brown background, and tail with prominent alternating light and dark bands.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
differs from its sister species in the Hamersley Range (described below) in its overall paler colouration, large greyish ocelli on the dorsal and lateral surfaces of body and limbs (
<tp:taxon-name>v. small</tp:taxon-name>
whitish ocelli on limbs only), strongly banded tail (
<tp:taxon-name>v. completely</tp:taxon-name>
or mostly unbanded) and larger and more elongate dorsal scales (

A).
</p>
            <p>
Re-description of 
holotype
(

). Small-bodied 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
with a depressed body. Head elongate and depressed in lateral view; upper rostrum slightly protruding over lower jaw, genial groove distinct. Tail long and gradually tapering, moderately dorsoventrally depressed proximally, circular centrally, becoming more triangular distally. Eyes large with scaly upper and lower eyelids, closer to nostril than to ear opening; supraocular brow present above eyes. Snout moderately long, rounded in dorsal and lateral views; nostrils large and visible from above, oriented dorsolaterally, approximately equidistant between tip of snout and anterior edge of eye. Ear openings much higher than wide, oriented distally at 
45
º to the corner of jaw. Head scales small, smooth, supraoculars gradually merging with the larger interoculars; canthus rostralis weak (not entirely absent as stated by 

Storr 
1980
), demarcated by low ridge of larger scales anterior to eye and contacting nostril; rostral and mental scales higher than wide, twice the size of adjacent scales.
</p>
            <p>
Limbs well-developed and moderately slender, ventral surface of digits with enlarged paired circular lamellae, scales on manus and pes otherwise consisting of conical tubercles; claws short and thick, with strongly recurved tips. Dorsal primary scales small, relatively uniform and ovate with small central keel, bordered by row of small granules; ventral scales larger and much longer than wide; caudal scales undifferentiated on dorsal and ventral surfaces, at base of tail similar in size to dorsal scales on torso, grading to larger with moderate keels in central section of tail and narrow with sharp keels towards tip; cloacal region with paired set of 
4–6
curved ventrolateral rows of long, narrow pointed scales, increasing in height, size and spinosity distally.
</p>
            <p>In preservative, ground colour light brown, with reddish tinge on head and limbs, and tending greyer on flanks. Patterning on head includes light brown spotting and similarly coloured bars on labials. Dorsal surfaces and base of tail with dark brown spots (prominent on tail) coalescing to form narrow, wavy transverse lines. Limbs with light grey ocelli, larger and more prominent on hindlimbs. Dark brown transverse bands present from mid to distal point of tail. Ventral surface white with faint light grey bands.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Variation.
Tables 
1–2
summarises the mensural and meristic data for 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
. In preservative, dorsal patterning in most individuals is similar (

), consisting of fine dark brown spots on a lighter brown background. In some individuals (
WAM
R 
100766
, 
WAM
R 
165513
) the entire dorsum has widely scattered spots on individual scales, while in others (
WAM
R 
102103
, 
WAM
R 
163916
, 
WAM
R 
170132
) the spots coalesce to form irregular transverse lines. The smallest individual (
WAM
R 
132659
) is very boldly marked with dorsal spots almost forming wavy bars across dorsum. One individual (
WAM
R 
110941
) has a uniform dark brown body and lighter head with very indistinct ocelli on the dorsum and a strongly banded tail. All specimens have strongly banded tails. The large, pale grey ocelli are faint on some individuals (
WAM
R 
100766
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
            </p>
            <p>MeanRangeSDN MeanRangeSDNSVL139.8105.7–18020.717 136.6120–16018.26TL264222–31630.714 264.8217–29542.84HNL54.142.2–67.88.417 54.246.7–64.58.06FLL39.732.8–53.25.617 40.133.7–44.44.06HLL52.240.2–67.48.017 52.439.4–648.76HD8.46–121.717 8.36–10.31.66HW16.412.1–22.63.017 15.913.2–19.82.86BL85.763.5–112.212.717 82.572.5–95.910.46MSR122.3118–1283.017 121.1120–1221.06VS67.564–722.117 69.365–743.26PSL20.118–221.517 21.921–230.76</p>
            <p>WAM # SEXSVLTLHNLFLLHLLHDHWBLMSRVSPSLR10811 male107.8NA43.736.146.3713.7641266820R14901 male15231658.843.359.910.318.893.21226822R20017 male137.328854.636.750.78.517.582.71246822R28011 male16529264.843.760.29.722.6100.21206620R28012 male15530564.148.560.41220.490.81246622R39158 female12022245.432.841.17.413.474.51246620R39782 male15327758.741.959.69.91994.31286820R60432 female12623548.134.947.67.414.577.81206622R90856 female14025050.838.351.87.61689.21206818R100766 male18030667.853.267.410.820.2112.21186422R102103 male16329664.939.256.210.517.198.11266420R110941 female13723851.736.748.86.414.885.31207218R132659 female105.722242.233.940.2612.163.51226819R139384 female125.123245.43943.46.913.177.71187019R163916 female134.126849.73847.28.416.284.31246820R165513 female137.926551.736.151.56.614.186.11207018R170132 male152.8NA62.145.862.58.917.590.71246822</p>
            <p>Colouration in life.
The following description of colouration in life is based on 

A, B and field observations of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
from the Chichester and surrounding northern ranges. Dorsal ground colour of head, body and limbs light reddish-brown, slightly paler (tending towards yellowish) on head. Dorsal surfaces of head and neck distinctly spotted or flecked with dark reddish-brown, sometimes coalescing to form narrow wavy, transverse bands. Distinct reddish-brown to black vertical bars on labial and temporal regions. Upper surface of dorsum and base of tail with numerous small blackish-brown to black spots that coalesce into narrow (one scale wide) transverse bars or wavy lines. Between these spots are transverse rows of large greyish ocelli. These ocelli vary in degrees of intensity and with body size but are clearly discernible posteriorly at any stage of maturity. Limbs dorsally and laterally with irregular pale grey or whitish ocelli (often dark-edged and/or dark-centred) and, larger and brighter on hindlimbs. Ground colour of proximal section of tail light brown or greyish, often with large greyish ocelli; ground colour of distal section of tail grading from cream to white with dark reddish-brown to black rings, giving a distinct banded appearance. Ventral surfaces of throat, neck, limbs and body greyish-white, often with irregular transverse grey bands or reticulations.
</p>
            <p>Juveniles are more simply and very brightly patterned, with large black-edged pale ocelli on dorsum and limbs, distinct reddish-brown heads and black and white banded tails.</p>
            <p>Habitat.
This species is closely associated with rocky habitats (

), typically undulating granite and greenstone terrain with significant areas of basaltic ranges (tumbled boulder piles are prominent) and dissected plateau, vegetated with 
<tp:taxon-name>Triodia</tp:taxon-name>
, sparse shrubs and eucalypts (Mckenzie 
et al.2009
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.
Endemic to the northern Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
, largely to the north of the Fortescue River Basin and centred on the Chichester Range. Records extend from the Burrup Peninsula and West Intercourse Island in the northwest, east to the Ord Ranges, Yarrie Mine and Carawine Gorge. There is a single record south of the Fortescue River in the western Chichester Range near Pannawonica (Fig. 
2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Named for the Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
, the region to which it is restricted. Used as a noun in apposition.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
This species appears to be secure and widespread throughout the Chichester Range and other northern ranges, and occurs in popular tourist destinations such as at Millstream Chichester National Park. This species can be locally abundant in suitable rocky areas. 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
is illustrated in numerous publications (e.g. 

Storr 
et al.1983
: Plate 
15
; 

Vincent &amp; Wilson 
1999
: 
75
; 

Pianka 
et al.2004
: 
430
; 

Eidenmüller 
2007
: 
105
; 

Wilson &amp; Swan 
2013
: 
429
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
Material examined. 
Holotype
:
WAM
R 
145733
, male, Hamersley Range, Weeli Wolli Creek (
22
º 
52
' 
40
"S
119
º 
14
' 
24
"E

), Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, R. Teale &amp; G. Harold, 
28
April 
2003
. Fixed in 
10
% formalin, stored in 
70
% ethanol, liver sample stored in – 
80
ºC ultrafreezer at 
WAM
. 
Paratypes
:

All from Western 
Australia
. 
WAM
R 
125456
(male)— 
30 km
E Newman (
23
º 
19
'S
120
º02'E

); 
WAM
R 
125766
(female)—Circular Pool, Dales Gorge (
22
º 
38
' 
36
"S
118
º 
33
' 
47
"E

); 
WAM
R 
129628
(male)— 
120 km
NW Newman (
22
º 
55
'S
119
º01'E

); 
WAM
R 
140734
(female)—Rocklea Station (
22
º 
56
' 
55
"S
117
º 
16
'0 
7
"E); 
WAM
R 
164579
(male)— 
8.5 km
NE Mount Rica (
21
º 
57
'0 
8
"S 
116
º 
29
' 
18
"E

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis and comparison.
Differs from all Australian congeners by the following combination of characters: size moderately small (SVL up to 
160 mm
); slender build; tail long (between 
168–207
% of SVL) and thin, circular in cross section at midpoint, midbody scales 
120–122
; dorsal and lateral scales weakly keeled, enlarged keeled ventrolateral scales on each side of and posterior to vent in 
4–6
rows, scales on top of head smooth; supraoculars gradually merging with larger interoculars; dorsal scales elongate, ovate; nostrils high and oriented dorsolaterally, dorsal and lateral surfaces of body with subdued irregular dark brown to black spots or vermiculations on a dark reddish-brown background, small ocelli on the dorsal surface of the hindlimbs only, and tail without prominent dark bands.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from its sister species 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
in its overall darker colouration, presence of small whitish ocelli usually on the dorsal surface of the limbs only (
<tp:taxon-name>v. large</tp:taxon-name>
greyish ocelli on the dorsal and lateral surfaces of body and limbs), largely unbanded tail (
<tp:taxon-name>v. strongly</tp:taxon-name>
banded tail) and smaller and less elongate dorsal scales (

B).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description of 
holotype
(

). Small-bodied 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus</tp:taxon-name>
with depressed body. Head elongate and depressed in lateral view; upper rostrum slightly protruding over lower jaw, genial groove distinct. Tail long and gradually tapering, moderately dorsoventrally depressed proximally, circular centrally, becoming more triangular distally. Eyes large with scaly upper and lower eyelids; closer to nostril than to ear opening; supraocular brow present above eyes. Snout moderately long, rounded in dorsal and lateral views; nostrils large and visible from above, wider than high, oriented dorsolaterally, approximately equidistant between tip of snout and anterior edge of eye. Ear openings much higher than wide, oriented distally at 
45
º to the corner of jaw. Head scales small, smooth and unornamented; supraocular scales smaller than those on the rostrum, frontal and parietal regions; canthus rostralis weak; rostral scale twice as large as adjacent scales, almost rounded, slightly narrower anteriorly; mental scale higher than wide and almost rectangular.
</p>
            <p>Limbs well-developed and moderately slender; ventral surface of digits with enlarged paired circular lamellae, scales on manus and pes otherwise consisting of conical tubercles; claws darkly pigmented, relatively short, very thick, laterally compressed and with sharp, recurved tips.</p>
            <p>
Dorsal primary scales small, non-overlapping, relatively uniform and ovate, approximately twice as long as wide and with a small central keel; bordered by row of small granules; ventral scales non-overlapping and more rectangular, approximately 
50
% longer and 
100
% wider than dorsal scales, grading smaller on the throat and vent; caudal scales undifferentiated on dorsal and ventral surfaces, at base of tail similar in size to dorsal scales on torso, grading to larger with moderate keels in central section of tail and narrow with sharp keels towards tip; cloacal region with paired set of 
4-6
curved lateroventral rows of long, narrow pointed scales, increasing in height, size and spinosity distally.
</p>
            <p>In preservative, ground colour of dorsum dark brown, slightly lighter on head and neck. Patterning on head includes black spots on some individual scales and dark brown labial bars, dorsal surfaces of torso with mixture of irregular black spots on individual scales or spots coalesce to form narrow, wavy transverse lines. Light brown tail with irregular dark brown to black spots. Forelimbs light brown, hindlimbs darker brown with small whitish ocelli becoming more prominent distally. Ventral surfaces greyish.</p>
            <p>Variation.
Summary mensural and meristic data for the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is presented in 

Tables 
1
and 
3
. In preservative, the ground colouration is always brown (

). All specimens have irregular dark spots on some individual scales or vermiculations across the dorsum, although these vary in degree and intensity; on one individual (
WAM
R 
125766
) the entire dorsum has very fine spots with barely any indication of alignment, while at the other extreme (
WAM
R 
140734
) the dense spots align to form regular wavy lines. Most individuals have some dark spotting on the tail, although one individual (
WAM
R 
164579
) has almost none. The venter sometimes features relatively bold greyish bands that become more narrow and wavy on neck and throat.
</p>
            <p>
Two juvenile specimens (
WAM
R 
69695
: SVL 
61.6 mm
; 
WAM
R 
125100
: 
70 mm
) are more brightly patterned than adults with much larger spots on dorsum, more contrasting and strongly defined ventral surface bands and obviously ringed tails.
</p>
            <p>WAM #SexSVLTLHNLFLLHLLHDHWBL MSRVSPSLR125456male122.3NA46.736.445.57.51575.6 1207022R125766female121.221748.739.449613.272.5 1206622R129628male1602706444.4649.419.895.9 1227021R140734female120NA47.333.739.46.513.472.9 1227221R145733male155.829564.543.758.49.717.791.3 1227423R164579male124.822648.939.550.57.913.475.8 1206522</p>
            <p>Colouration in life.
The following description of colouration in life is based on 

A, B and a photograph from Mount Channar near Paraburdoo (

Ehmann 
1992
). Dorsal ground colour of head, torso and limbs dark reddishbrown, often tending slightly paler on head. Head and neck with irregular subdued small blackish-brown to black spots, snout forward of nostrils often dark brown, sides of head with yellowish tinge. Labial scales with blackishbrown vertical bars. Dorsal surface of torso with numerous small blackish-brown to black spots, often coalescing into narrow (one scale wide) transverse bars or wavy lines and forming a fine black reticulum. Forelimbs reddish brown with dark flecks, hindlimbs noticeably darker brown with small whitish ocelli. Digits on both limbs with indistinct thin pale yellowish bands. Ground colour of the tail light brown, extensively overlain with darker-brown to black spots along its length. Ventral surface of the throat, neck, limbs and body greyish-white.
</p>
            <p>Habitat and ecology.<tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is strictly saxicolous and closely associated with rocky habitats such as banded ironstone rock faces and gorges (

). It shelters in overhangs, crevices, cavities and occasionally under exfoliated rock slabs. Typical vegetation on these faces varies, but often includes 
<tp:taxon-name>Eucalyptus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Triodia
(Spinifex)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Field observations indicate a preference for flat, horizontal sheet ironstone with an eastwest aspect to allow optimum basking in the morning. It is extremely swift and agile; ascending vertical rock faces with ease, and quickly takes shelter in deep crevices when disturbed.
</p>
            <p>
As with 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(

Ehmann 
1992
; B. Maryan pers. obs.

), this species has been observed active after sunset on warm, humid nights. Field observations indicated that activity periods vary seasonally, peaking during the hotter and humid months from October–April and declining when conditions are dry from May–September. The sex ratio among the 
type
series of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
,

including the misidentified 
paratype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(
WAM
R 
14901
) is skewed (
5
adult

males and 
2
adult

females), a bias which seems to be consistent with museum series of other opportunistically collected varanids (

Greer 
1989
) and may reflect different activity periods of the sexes. During surveys in the eastern Hamersley Range, most individuals captured were also males (B. Maryan and M. O’Connell, unpublished data).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.
Known only from the Hamersley Range, a heavily dissected region of banded ironstone occupying the southern part of the Pilbara craton of Western 
Australia
. Records span the Hamersley Range for over 
300 km
from east of Newman (
WAM
R 
125100
, 
WAM
R 
125456
) west to Mount Rica (
WAM
R 
164579
) and south to Rocklea Station (
WAM
R 
140734
) (Fig. 
2
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
Named for the Hamersley Range of Western 
Australia
, the region to which it is restricted. This is the most prominent mountainous area in Western 
Australia
(including Mount Meharry, 
1245 m
, and the highest peak in the state) and home to a suite of endemic taxa. Used as a noun in apposition.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Remarks.
This species appears to be secure and widespread throughout the Hamersley Range, and occurs in popular tourist destinations such as at Karijini National Park (one of the largest National Parks in Western 
Australia
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
The Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
is geologically distinctive, including some of the most ancient rock formations on earth (

McKenzie 
et al.2009
) and has a diverse and highly endemic reptile fauna (Pepper 
et al.2010
; 

Pepper 
et al.2013
a

; 

Doughty 
et al.2011
a

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
adds yet another endemic lizard species, and raises the number of endemic varanid species to three, the others being 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
(saxicolous) and 
<tp:taxon-name>V. bushi</tp:taxon-name>
(arboreal).
</p>
         <p>
Recent systematic and phylogeographic studies have revealed significant genetic structure in the many lineages of lizards from the Pilbara: e.g 
<tp:taxon-name>Lucasium stenodactylum
(

Pepper 
et al.2006
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tympanocryptis cephalus
(

Shoo 
et al.2008
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Diplodactylus savagei
(Doughty 
et al.2010
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Crenadactylus ocellatus
(

Oliver 
et al.2010
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Egernia depressa</tp:taxon-name>
(

Doughty 
et al.2011
b

), 
<tp:taxon-name>Diporiphora valens
(

Doughty 
et al.2012
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Heteronotia spelea</tp:taxon-name>
(

Pepper 
et al.2013
b

). While different lineages show an array of distributions (

Pepper 
et al.2013
a

), many taxa closely associated with rocks (i.e. strictly saxicolous) seem to be characterised by distinct northern (Chichester Range) and southern (Hamersley Range) lineages, divided by the Fortescue River Basin. The distribution of genetic and morphological variation within the 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group conforms to this overall pattern. The 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
species-group also provides another instance where this regional geographic structuring within the greater Pilbara ‘hotspot’ has been found to be of taxonomic significance (

Doughty 
et al.2011
a

; 

Pepper 
et al.2013
a

). These previously unrecognised patterns of biological differentiation within the Pilbara herpetofauna underline the importance of carefully designing conservation and management strategies to maintain the evolutionary diversity of the region.
</p>
         <p>
Taxonomic investigations continue to reveal that species diversity in many groups of Australian lizards is higher than widely recognised. However, while there are exceptions, most of this diversity is concentrated in relatively small, non-descript species (e.g. 

Horner 
2007
; 

Smith &amp; Adams 
2007
; 

Oliver 
et al.2010
). In contrast, varanids include many of the world’s largest lizards and are amongst the most high profile and recognisable components of the Australian herpetofauna. There is however evidence of significant diversity within a number of other nominal varanid species from northern 
Australia
and further research may lead to the recognition of additional new species (

Ast 
2001
; Fitch 
et al.2006
). The description of a relatively spectacular new Australian varanid, and the potential existence of additional unrecognised taxa amongst this distinctive and iconic lineage, underlines the fact that we are still far from completing the species inventory of the diverse Australian lizard fauna.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>
We thank M. Brown, B. Bush, S. Ford, G. Gaikhorst, G. Harold, R. Lloyd, T. Rasmussen, R. Teale and J. Turpin, for their support and regular discussions about the diverse Pilbara herpetofauna, in particular their observations of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
. We thank J. Vos for his excellent live photographs of 
<tp:taxon-name>V. pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>
. R. How (University of Western 
Australia
) kindly provided statistical advice and information. We are extremely grateful to A. Heidrich (Ecologia), C. Stevenson (Environmental Protection Authority) and R. Somaweera (Biologic) for preparing some figures. We thank P. Doughty and two anonymous referees for their helpful comments on drafts of the manuscript. For kindly allowing access to specimens at the Western Australian Museum we thank C. Stevenson (formerly), L. Umbrello and P. Doughty.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Aplin, K.P.
, 
Fitch, A.J.
&amp; 
King, D.J.
(
2006
) 

A new species of 
Varanus
Merrem (Squamata: Varanidae) from the Pilbara region of Western 
Australia
, with observations on sexual dimorphism in closely related species

. 
Zootaxa
, 
1313
, 

1– 
38
.
</p>
         <p>Ast, J.C.
(
2001
) 

Mitochondrial 
DNA
evidence and evolution in Varanoidea (Squamata)

. 
Cladistics
, 
17
, 
211
– 
226
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1006
/clad. 
2001.0169</p>
         <p>Bush, B.
&amp; 
Maryan, B.
(
2011
) 

A Field Guide to the Snakes of the Pilbara, Western 
Australia
. 

Western Australian Museum, Welshpool, Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, 
112
pp.
</p>
         <p>Clarke, R.H.
(
2004
) 

A record of the emerald monitor 
Varanus prasinus
from Boigu Island, Torres Strait, 
Australia
. 
Herpetofauna
, 
34
, 

70– 
71
.
</p>
         <p>Doughty, P.
, 
Pepper, M.
&amp; 
Keogh, J.S.
(
2010
) 

Morphological and molecular assessment of the 
Diplodactylus savagei
species complex in the Pilbara region, Western 
Australia
, with a description of a new species

. 
Zootaxa
, 
2393
, 

33– 
45
.
</p>
         <p>Doughty, P.
, 
Rolfe, J.K.
, 
Burbidge, A.H.
, 
Pearson, D.J.
&amp; 
Kendrick, P.G.
(
2011
a) 

Herpetological assemblages of the Pilbara biogeographic region, Western 
Australia
: ecological associations, biogeographic patterns and conservation

. 
Records of the Western Australian Museum
, Supplement 
78
, 

315– 
341
.
</p>
         <p>Doughty, P.
, 
Kealley, L.
&amp; 
Donnellan, S.C.
(
2011
b) 

Revision of the Pygmy Spiny-tailed Skinks (
Egernia depressa
speciesgroup) from Western 
Australia
, with descriptions of three new species

. 
Records of the Western Australian Museum
, 
26
, 
115
– 
137
.
</p>
         <p>Doughty, P.
, 
Kealley, L.
&amp; 
Melville, J.
(
2012
) 

Taxonomic assessment of 
Diporiphora
(Reptilia: Agamidae) dragon lizards from the western arid zone of 
Australia
. 
Zootaxa
, 
3518
, 

1– 
24
.
</p>
         <p>Ehmann, H.
(
1992
) 
Encyclopedia of Australian Animals—Reptiles
. 

Angus &amp; Robertson, New South 
Wales
, 
Australia
, 
495
pp.
</p>
         <p>Eidenmüller, B.
(
2007
) 
Monitor Lizards, Natural History, Captive Care &amp; Breeding
. Revised, enlarged and updated edition

. 

Edition Chimaira, Frankfurt am Main, 
Germany
, 
176
pp.
</p>
         <p>Fitch, A.J.
, 
Goodman, A.E.
&amp; 
Donnellan, S.C.
(
2006
) 

A molecular phylogeny of the Australian monitor lizards (Squamata: Varanidae) inferred from mitochondrial 
DNA
sequences

. 
Australian Journal of Zoology
, 
54
, 
253
– 
269
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1071
/zo05038
</p>
         <p>Fuller, S.
, 
Baverstock, P.
&amp; 
King, D.
(
1998
) 
Biogeographic origins of goannas (Varanidae): a molecular perspective
. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution
, 
9
, 
294
– 
307
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1006
/mpev. 
1997.0476</p>
         <p>Gray, J.E.
(
1827
) 
A synopsis of the genera of saurian reptiles, in which some new genera are indicated, and the others reviewed by actual examination
. 
Annals of Philosophy
, 
3
, 

54– 
58
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1080
/ 
14786442708675620</p>
         <p>Greer, A.E.
(
1989
) 
The Biology and Evolution of Australian Lizards
. 

Surrey Beatty, Sydney, New South 
Wales
, 
Australia
, 
264
pp.
</p>
         <p>Hardwicke, T.
&amp; 
Gray, J.E.
(
1827
) 

A synopsis of the species of saurian reptiles, collected in 
India
by Major-General Hardwicke

. 
Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London
, 
3
, 
214
– 
229
.
</p>
         <p>Horner, P.
(
2007
) 

Systematics of the snake-eyed skinks, 
Cryptoblepharus
Wiegmann (Reptilia: Squamata: Scincidae)—an Australian based review

. 
The Beagle
, 
Records of the Museum and Art Galleries of the Northern Territory
, Supplement 3

, 

1– 
198
.
</p>
         <p>How, R.A.
&amp; 
Cowan, M.A.
(
2006
) 
Collections in space and time: geographical patterning of native frogs, mammals and reptiles through a continental gradient
. 
Pacific Conservation Biology
, 
12
, 
111
– 
133
.
</p>
         <p>King, D.
&amp; 
Green, B.
(
1993
) 
Goanna
: 
The Biology of Varanid Lizards
. 

New South 
Wales
University Press, Sydney, New South 
Wales
, 
Australia
, 
116
pp.
</p>
         <p>Koch, A.
, 
Gaulke, M.
&amp; 
Böhme, W.
(
2010
a) 

Unravelling the underestimated diversity of 
Philippine
water monitor lizards (Squamata: 
Varanus salvator
complex), with the description of two new species and a new subspecies

. 
Zootaxa
, 
2446
, 

1– 
54
.
</p>
         <p>Koch, A.
, 
Auliya, M.
&amp; 
Ziegler, T.
(
2010
b) 
Updated checklist of the living monitor lizards of the world (Squamata: Varanidae)
. 
Bonn Zoological Bulletin
, 
57
, 
127
– 
136
.
</p>
         <p>Koch, A.
, 
Ziegler, T.
, 
Böhme, W.
, 
Arida, E.
&amp; 
Auliya, M.
(
2013
) 

Pressing Problems: Distribution, threats, and conservation status of the monitor lizards (Varanidae: 
Varanus
ssp.) of Southeast Asia and the Indo-Australian Archipelago

. 
Herpetological Conservation and Biology
, 
8
(Monograph
3
), 
1–62
.
</p>
         <p>Maddison, D.R.
&amp; 
Maddison, W.P.
(
2003
) 
MacClade V. 4.0
. 

Sinauer Associates, Sunderland, Massachusetts, 
U.S.A.</p>
         <p>McKenzie, N.L.
, 
van Leeuwen, S.
&amp; 
Pinder, A.M.
(
2009
) 

Introduction to the Pilbara Biodiversity Survey, 
2002–2007
. 
Records of the Western Australian Museum
, Supplement 78

, 

3– 
89
.
</p>
         <p>Merrem, B.
(
1820
) 
Versuch eines Systems Amphibien
. 
Tentamen Systematics Amphibiorum
. Krieger, Marburg

, 
199
pp.
</p>
         <p>Oliver, P.
, 
Adams, M.
&amp; 
Doughty, P.
(
2010
) 

Molecular evidence for ten species and Oligo-Miocene vicariance within a nominal Australian gecko species (
Crenadactylus ocellatus
, Diplodactylidae)

. 
BMC Evolutionary Biology
, 
10
, 
386
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1186
/ 
1471-2148
- 
10-386</p>
         <p>Pepper, M.
, 
Doughty, P.
&amp; 
Keogh, J.S.
(
2006
) 

Molecular phylogeny and phylogeography of the Australian 
Diplodactylus stenodactylus
(Gekkota; Reptilia) species-group based on mitochondrial and nuclear genes reveals an ancient split between Pilbara and non-Pilbara 
D. stenodactylus
. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution
, 
41
, 
539
– 
555
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1016
/j.ympev.2006.05.028
</p>
         <p>Pepper, M.
, 
Fujita, M.K.
, 
Moritz, C.
&amp; 
Keogh, J.S.
(
2010
) 
Palaeoclimate change drove diversification among isolated mountain refugia in the Australian arid zone
. 
Molecular Ecology
, 
20
, 

1529– 
1545
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1365
- 
294
x. 
2011.05036
.x
</p>
         <p>Pepper, M.
, 
Doughty, P.
&amp; 
Keogh, J.S.
(
2013
a) 
Geodiversity and endemism in the iconic Australian Pilbara region: a review of landscape evolution and biotic response in an ancient refugium
. 
Journal of Biogeography
, 
40
, 

1225– 
1239
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/jbi. 
12080</p>
         <p>Pepper, M.
, 
Doughty, P.
, 
Fujita, M.K.
, 
Moritz, C.
&amp; 
Keogh, J.S.
(
2013
b) 

Speciation on the rocks: integrated systematics of the 
Heteronotia spelea
species complex (Gekkota; Reptilia) from Western and central 
Australia
. 
PLoS ONE
, 
11
, e 
78110
, 

1– 
17
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1371
/journal.pone.0078110
</p>
         <p>Pianka, E.R.
, 
King, D.R.
&amp; 
King, R.A.
(
2004
) 
Varanoid Lizards of the World
. 

Indiana University Press, Bloomington, Indiana, 
U.S.A.
, 
588
pp.
</p>
         <p>Powney, G.D.
, 
Grenyer, R.
, 
Orme, C.D.L.
, 
Owens, P.F.
&amp; 
Meiri, S.
(
2010
) 
Hot, dry and different: Australian lizard richness is unlike that of mammals, amphibians and birds
. 
Global Ecology and Biogeography
, 
19
, 
386
– 
396
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1466
-8238.2009.00521.x
</p>
         <p>Shoo, L.P.
, 
Rose, R.
, 
Doughty, P.
, 
Austin, J.J.
&amp; 
Melville, J.
(
2008
) 

Diversification patterns of pebble-mimic dragons are consistent with historical disruption of important habitat corridors in arid 
Australia
. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution
, 
48
, 
528
– 
542
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1016
/j.ympev.2008.03.022
</p>
         <p>Smith, L.A.
&amp; 
Adams, M.
(
2007
) 

Revision of the 
Lerista muelleri
species-group (Lacertilia: Scincidae) in Western 
Australia
with a redescription of 
L. muelleri
(Fischer, 
1881
) and the description of nine new species

. 
Records of the Western Australian Museum
, 
23
, 
309
– 
357
.
</p>
         <p>Stamatakis, A.
(
2006
) 
RaxML-VI-HPC: Maximum Likelihood-based Phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed models
. 
Bioinformatics
, 
22
, 

2688– 
2690
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1093
/bioinformatics/btl 
446</p>
         <p>Storr, G.M.
(
1980
) 

The monitor lizards (Genus 
Varanus
Merrem, 
1820
) of Western 
Australia
. 
Records of the Western Australian Museum
, 
8
, 
237
– 
293
.
</p>
         <p>Storr, G.M.
, 
Smith, L.A.
&amp; 
Johnstone, R.E.
(
1983
) 

Lizards of Western 
Australia
. II. Dragons and Monitors

. 

Western Australian Museum, Perth, Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
, 
113
pp.
</p>
         <p>Swofford, D.L.
(
2000
) 
PAUP
*. 
Phylogenetic analysis using parsimony (*and other methods
, Version
4
. 

Sinauer Associates, Sunderland, Massachusetts, 
U.S.A.</p>
         <p>Vincent, M.
&amp; 
Wilson, S.
(
1999
) 
Australian Goannas
. 
New Holland
Publishers, Sydney, New South 
Wales
, 
Australia
, 
152
pp.
</p>
         <p>Welton, L.J.
, 
Siler, C.D.
, 
Bennett, D.
, 
Diesmos, A.
, 
Duya, M.R.
, 
Dugay, R.
, 
Rico, E.L.
, 
Van Weerd, M.
&amp; 
Brown, R.M.
(
2010
) 

A spectacular new 
Philippine
monitor lizard reveals a hidden biogeographic boundary and a novel flagship species for conservation biology

. 
Biology Letters
, 
6
, 
654
– 
658
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1098
/rsbl. 
2010.0119</p>
         <p>White, J.
(
1790
) 

Journal of a voyage to New South 
Wales
, with sixty-five plates of non descript animals, birds, lizards, serpents, curious cones of trees and other natural productions

.
Debrett, London
, 
299
pp.
</p>
         <p>Wilson, S.
(
1996
) 
Wildlife that crossed the strait
. 
Geo Australasia
, 
18
, 

90– 
97
.
</p>
         <p>Wilson, S.
&amp; 
Swan, G.
(
2013
) 

A Complete Guide to Reptiles of 
Australia
. 
Fourth Edition
. 
New Holland
Publishers, Sydney, New South 
Wales
, 
Australia
, 
592
pp.
</p>
         <p>Ziegler, T.
, 
Böhme, W.
, 
Eidenmüller, B.
&amp; 
Philipp, K.M.
(
2001
) 

A note on the coexistence of three species of Pacific monitor lizards in 
Australia
(Sauria, Varanidae, 
Varanus indicus
group)

. 
Bonn Zoological Bulletin
, 
50
, 

27– 
30
.
</p>
         <p>Ziegler, T.
, 
Schmitz, A.
, 
Koch, A.
&amp; 
Böhme, W.
(
2007
) 

A review of the subgenus 
Euprepiosaurus
of 
Varanus
(Squamata: Varanidae): morphological and molecular phylogeny, distribution and zoogeography, with an identification key for the members of the 
V. indicus
and the 
V. prasinus
species groups

. 
Zootaxa
, 
1472
, 

1– 
28
.
</p>
         <p>
APPENDIX 
1
.

Additional material examined. *Included in the molecular study. ^Molecular study only. All localities are in Western 
Australia
, 
Australia
.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>WAM
: 

R 
90856
(female)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
37
'0 0"S 
119
º01' 
24
"E

); *R 
100766
(male)—Woodstock Station (
21
º 
35
' 
20
"S
118
º 
58
' 
59
"E

); R 
102103
(male)— 
20 km
SSW Cooya Pooya, Millstream Chichester National Park (
21
º 
12
' 
40
"S
117
º04' 
20
"E

); *R 
110941
(female)— 
44 km
W Pannawonica (
21
º 
39
'S
116
º 
19
'E

); ^R 
113094
– 
42 km
NNE Munjina Roadhouse (
21
º 
57
'S
118
º 
50
'E

); *R 
132659
(female)—Burrup Peninsula (
20
º 
32
' 
16
"S
116
º 
49
'0 
7
"E); *R 
139384
(female)—Meentheena (
21
º 
12
' 
59
"S
120
º 
20
' 
26
"E

); R 
163916
(female)— 
47.5 km
ESE Goldsworthy (
20
º 
25
' 
41
"S
119
º 
58
' 
10
"E

); *R 
165513
(female)—West Intercourse Island (
20
º 
40
' 
41
"S
116
º 
37
' 
54
"E

); *R 
170132
(male)— 
30 km
NE Wodgina (
21
º01' 
42
"S
118
º 
55
'0 0"E).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>WAM
: ^R 
125100
(Juvenile)— 
15 km
E Newman (
23
º 
22
'S
119
º 
54
'E

). *R 
125456
, *R 
125766
, *R 
129628
, *R 
140734
, *R 
145733
, *R 
164579
.
</p>
         <p>Genbank details for new sequences included in molecular study.</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus pilbarensis</tp:taxon-name>WAM
: R 
100766
= 

KF 
927721
, R 
110941
= 

KF 
927722
, R 
113094
= 

KF 
927723
, R 
139384
= 

KF 
927727
, R 
165513
= 

KF 
927731
, R 
170132
= 

KF 
927732
.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus hamersleyensis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>WAM
: R 
125456
= 

KF 
927724
, R 
125766
= 

KF 
927725
, R 
129628
= 

KF 
927726
, R 
140734
= 

KF 
927728
, R 
145733
= 

KF 
927729
, R 
164579
= 

KF 
927730
.
</p>
         <p>
APPENDIX 
2
.

Genbank details for sequences from other 
Va r an us
included in molecular study. All sequences are from Fitch 
et al.2006
.
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Varanus acanthurus</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
525100
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus baritji</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
525106
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus glauerti</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
525122
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus glebopalma</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
525129
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus mitchelli</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
525128
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus scalaris</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
525131
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus semiremex</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
525125
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus storri</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
631869
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus timorensis</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
525136
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Varanus tristis</tp:taxon-name>
DQ 
525120
.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
