<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</journal-id>
         <issn>2118-9773</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Integrative taxonomy reveals a rare and new cusk-eel species of Luciobrotula (Teleostei, Ophidiidae) from the Solomon Sea, West Pacific</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2021</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Integrative taxonomy reveals a rare and new cusk-eel species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Teleostei</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Ophidiidae</tp:taxon-name>
) from the Solomon Sea, West Pacific
</p>
         <p>Man-Kwan WONG1
, 
Mao-Ying LEE2
&amp; 
Wei-Jen CHEN3,*</p>
         <p>1,3
Institute of Oceanography, National 
Taiwan
University, No.1, Sec. 4, Roosevelt Road, 
Taipei
10617, 
Taiwan
.
</p>
         <p>2
Marine Fisheries Division, Fisheries Research Institute, Council of Agriculture, No. 199, Heyi Road, 
Keelung
202008, 
Taiwan
.
</p>
         <p>*
Corresponding author: 
wjchen.actinops@gmail.com</p>
         <p>1
Email: 
Jun.
mkwong@gmail.com
</p>
         <p>2
Email: 
coleopetera@gmail.com</p>
         <p>1
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author: 
8369C501-1639-4467-BA9D-D274AE7CF15F</p>
         <p>2
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author: 
761CF9F8-ABD7-4DA5-9326-D4160526731C</p>
         <p>3
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:author: 
4D399FDB-F893-422E-A8A2-ACC18F40FCFD</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <p>Abstract.
With six valid species, 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
is a small genus of the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Ophidiidae</tp:taxon-name>
, commonly known as cusk-eels. They are benthopelagic fishes occurring at depths ranging from 
115–2300 m
in the Atlantic, Indian, and Pacific Oceans. Among them, 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
is the only known species in the West Pacific. Three specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
were collected from the Philippine Sea, Bismarck Sea, and Solomon Sea in the West Pacific during the 
AURORA
, 
PAPUANIUGINI
, and MADEEP expeditions under the 
Tropical Deep-Sea Benthos
program, and all of them were initially identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
. Subsequent examination with integrative taxonomy indicates that they belong to two distinct species, with the specimen collected from the Solomon Sea representing a new species, which is described here. In terms of morphology, 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from its congeners by having a relatively longer lateral line (end of the lateral line below the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray) and fewer vertebrae (abdominal vertebrae 13, total vertebrae 50). In the inferred 
COI
gene tree, the two western Pacific species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
do not form a monophyletic group. The genetic K2P distance between the two species is 13.8% on average at the 
COI
locus.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="key_words">
         <p>Key words.
Biodiversity exploration, DNA barcoding, 
<tp:taxon-name>Ophidiiformes</tp:taxon-name>
, species delimitation, tropical deep-sea benthos.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Wong M.-K., Lee M.-Y. &amp; Chen W.-J. 2021. Integrative taxonomy reveals a rare and new cusk-eel species of 
Luciobrotula
(Teleostei, Ophidiidae) from the Solomon Sea, West Pacific. 
European Journal of Taxonomy
750: 
52–69
. https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
, a rare deep-sea fish genus, is currently classified in the subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Neobythitinae</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Ophidiidae</tp:taxon-name>
). Representatives of this genus differ from other ophidiids by having a much depressed head, much less (3–4) developed long gill rakers on the first gill arch, and one median and a pair of basibranchial tooth patches (
Nielsen 2009
). Currently, six species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
are considered valid (
Nielsen 2009
; 

Fricke 
et al.
2020

): 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensisNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheniNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycterCohen, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata
(Gosline, 1954)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfiCohen, 1981</tp:taxon-name>
. All of them are benthic dwellers and can usually be found in the tropical deep waters of continental slopes worldwide (
Cohen 1974
; 
Nielsen 2009
). They are probably carnivorous, though only a single study mentioned a partially digested caridean shrimp found in the gut of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter
(
Cohen 1964
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Fishes in this genus are rarely caught and usually from benthic trawling over sand or mud bottoms at depths between 110 and 
2300 m
(
Radcliffe 1913
; 
Cohen 1964
; 

Nielsen 
et al
. 1999

; 
Nielsen &amp; Møller 2008
; 

Robertson 
et al
. 2017

). Among them, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
has the widest distribution in the Indo- West Pacific, ranging from the Gulf of Aden and 
South Africa
, east to the Hawaiian Islands, and north to 
Japan
. It is the only species previously known from the West Pacific (
Nielsen 2009
).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
was the first described species of the genus on the basis of a single specimen collected during the 
AlbatrossPhilippines
expedition 1907–1910 from the 
Palawan
Passage at a depth of 
686 m
(
Radcliffe 1913
). Since its discovery and description, several advanced taxonomic studies have been performed. 
Cohen (1964)
conducted the first taxonomic review of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
. He synonymized the monotypic ophidiid genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Volcanus
Gosline, 1954
</tp:taxon-name>
with 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
after examining the 
type
species, 
<tp:taxon-name>Volcanus lineatus
Gosline, 1954
</tp:taxon-name>
, concluding that there were no apparent differences between the two genera. In the same study, he also provided the first identification key for three nominal species including a newly described one, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
, from the Atlantic Ocean. Later, 
Cohen (1981)
described 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
from the East Pacific, which was previously often misidentified as 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
. 

Nielsen 
et al.
(1999)

conducted a thorough revision on the taxonomy of ophidiiform fishes. In that study, they also revised the identification key for four nominal species within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Nielsen (2009)
carried out the latest review study of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
by describing two additional species, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Brazil
in the West Atlantic, and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
from the Gulf of 
Panama
in the East Pacific as well as providing an updated identification key for all known species of the genus.
</p>
         <p>
Over the last 13 years, a total of 498 ophidiid fish samples were collected during 14 biodiversity expeditions (mainly in the tropical West Pacific) undertaken by the 
Tropical Deep-Sea Benthos
(
TDSB
) program (

Bouchet 
et al
. 2008

) and the cooperative project between 
Taiwan
and 
France
entitled “Taiwan- 
France
marine diversity exploration and evolution of deep-sea fauna” (TFDeepEvo, 2013–2016).Among them, only 
three specimens
of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
were collected from the Philippine Sea, Bismarck Sea, and Solomon Sea. These specimens were tentatively identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
as this was the only nominal species known from the West Pacific. However, after re-examining them based on a mitochondrial gene, we found that they are genetically distinct from each other. The purpose of this study is to validate the specimen collected from the Solomon Sea as representing a new species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
by using an integrated approach in taxonomy (
Dayrat 2005
; 

Hung 
et al.
2017

; 

Lo 
et al.
2017

; Lee S.-H. 
et al.
2019). The new species is herein described and an updated identification key for congenic species is provided.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Material and methods</title>
         <p>Sample collection</p>
         <p>
The three examined samples of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
(sample ID: 
ASIZP
0913925, 
PNG
1082, and 
PNG
2363) were collected from the Philippine Sea, Bismarck Sea, and Solomon Sea (

) during three 
TDSB
expeditions, AURORA, 
PAPUA NIUGINI
, and MADEEP, carried out in 2007, 2012, and 2014, respectively. Detailed information about the expeditions can be referenced at https://expeditions.mnhn.fr/. A small piece of muscle was excised from each sample and preserved in 95% ethanol for molecular examination. The specimens were then photographed before fixing with 10% formalin and later transferred to 70% ethanol for long-term preservation. The specimens were deposited in the ichthyological collections of the 
NTUM
and 
ASIZP
.
</p>
         <p>Institutional abbreviations</p>
         <p>NTUM
= National 
Taiwan
University Museums, 
Taipei</p>
         <p>ASIZP
= Academia Sinica, 
Taipei</p>
         <p>Morphological examination</p>
         <p>
The 
three specimens
collected in this study and four voucher specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
(
ASIZP
0070170, 
ASIZP
0063749, 
ASIZP
0066071, and 
ASIZP
0075076) from the East 
China
Sea and South 
China
Sea (

) were morphologically examined (see below and Appendix). Methods for measuring, counting, and general terminology followed 
Nielsen (2009)
. Specimens were measured with a dial caliper to the nearest 
0.1 mm
. Internal osteological characters were examined through radiographs. Color pattern was based on freshly collected specimens and photos, with additional information provided after preservation.
</p>
         <p>DNA data collection</p>
         <p>
Total genomic DNA was extracted from each tissue using a commercial DNA extraction kit and a robot (LabTurbo 48 Compact System extractor, Taigene Biosciences Corp., 
Taipei
, 
Taiwan)
following the manufacturer’s protocols. The cytochrome c oxidase subunit I (
COI
) gene was chosen as a marker for molecular examination of the specimens. A polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was used to amplify the target gene fragment using the universal fish primers provided in 

Ward 
et al
. (2005)

. PCR was carried out in a 25 µl volume containing 9 μl sterile distilled water, 0.5 μl of each primer (10 µM), 12.5 μl of EmeraldAmp MAX HS PCR Master Mix (TaKaRa), and 2.5 μl of DNA template (around 10~ 
20 ng
). The thermal cycling profile for amplification consisted of an initial denaturation stage (95°C, 60 sec), followed by 35 cycles each with a denaturation step (95°C, 30 sec), an annealing step (51°C, 30 sec), and an elongation step (72°C, 40 sec), before a final extension stage (72°C, 7 min). The successfully amplified products were then purified using the AMPure magnetic bead cleanup protocol (Agencourt Bioscience Corp.) and sequenced by Sanger sequencing at Genomics BioSci and Tech (
Taipei
). The same primers used for PCR were also used for sequencing; only the forward 
COI
primer was used.
</p>
         <p>Fig. 1.
Distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(red star) and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe 1913</tp:taxon-name>
(solid circles) based on specimens examined in this study.
</p>
         <p>Sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis</p>
         <p>
The obtained 
COI
sequences were viewed and edited using CodonCode Aligner ver. 7.2.1 (CodonCode Corporation, Dedham, MA, 
USA
) and were then aligned with eight other homologous sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
retrieved from GenBank (NCBI, Nation Center for Biotechnology Information) (n=7) and BOLD (The Barcode of Life Data Systems) (n= 1) (
Table 1
) using the automatic multiplealignment program MUSCLE (
Edgar 2004
). MEGA X (

Kumar 
et al
. 2018

) software was further used to manage the compiled dataset and compute pairwise distances of compared sequences with the Kimura-2-Parameter model (K2P) (
Kimura 1980
). The phylogenetic analysis was conducted based on the compiled 
COI
dataset using the maximum likelihood method (
ML
) with the nucleotide substitution model GTR+G as implemented in the software RAxML ver. 8.0.4 (
Stamatakis 2014
). Nodal support was assessed with bootstrapping (
Felsenstein 1985
) under the 
ML
criterion, based on 1000 pseudoreplicates. 
<tp:taxon-name>Neobythites bimarginatus
Fourmanoir &amp; Rivaton, 1979
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Neobythites stigmosus
Machida, 1984
</tp:taxon-name>
were used as outgroups to root the inferred 
COI
tree.
</p>
         <p>Species delimitation analysis</p>
         <p>
The same 
COI
gene dataset was used in three DNA-based species delimitation analyses, Automatic Barcode Gap Discovery (
ABGD
) (

Puillandre 
et al.
2012

), Bayesian based Poisson Tree Processes (bPTP) (

Zhang 
et al.
2013

), and Character-Based DNA Barcoding (CBB) (

Desalle 
et al.
2005

). 
ABGD
is a tool for detecting significant differences between intra- and interspecific variation (barcode gap) by examining pairwise genetic distances. Operational taxonomic units (OTUs) or putative species were redefined through the analytical algorithm. The analysis was performed at the web interface (https://bioinfo.mnhn.fr/abi/public/abgd/abgdweb.html) with the default value (1.5) for relative gap width (X), and the intraspecific divergence (P) value (0.001 to 0.1) with 20 steps under the K2P distance.
</p>
         <p>
bPTP is a method for delimiting species based on a rooted phylogenetic tree, and mutations are modeled as speciation or branching events. Here, we used the inferred 
COI
gene tree (see above) as the input tree. The bPTP settings are: number of MCMC generations= 100 000; thinning=100; burn-in =0.1; and seed =123. The analysis was performed at the web interface available from https://species.h-its.org/.
</p>
         <p>
CBB is a method derived from the standard DNA barcoding approach (

Hebert 
et al.
2004

; 

Ward 
et al.
2005

). Instead of simple cut-off distance thresholds for delimiting the species presented in the DNA dataset, the putative species are identified through the presence or absence of discrete and unique nucleotide substitutions within the DNA sequences of taxa (

Desalle 
et al.
2005

; 

Rach 
et al.
2008

; 

Brower 
et al.
2010

; 

Guimarães 
et al.
2020

). Here, MEGA X software and inferred 
COI
gene tree were used to determine apomorphic nucleotide sites in 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
at the 
COI
locus. Numbering of the determined nucleotide sites starts from the first nucleotide of the gene defined through sequence alignment with the complete 
COI
sequence retrieved from the whole mitochondrial genome of 
<tp:taxon-name>Neobythites unimaculatus
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe 1913</tp:taxon-name>
(
AP018428
: 5544-7094).
</p>
         <p>
The congruent results from bPTP and 
ABGD
analyses were considered to be primary support of the OTUs (i.e., inferred potential species); other criteria (CBB result, morphological evidence, etc.) were also used for final validation of delimited species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <p>TaxaVoucher specimensSample IDLocality**LatitudeLongitudeDepth (m)GenBank/ BOLD system accession no.<tp:taxon-name>Neobythites bimarginatus</tp:taxon-name>
*
NTUM 17062NC1657Coral Sea23°34′ S169°37′ E340MW315789<tp:taxon-name>Neobythites stigmosus</tp:taxon-name>
*
NTUM 14381WJC7153Japan (Tosa Bay, Mimase fishing port)NANANAMW315788<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi</tp:taxon-name>ASIZP 0075076ASIZP 0916618South China Sea22°12′ N120°23′ E68–347KU943175<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi</tp:taxon-name>ASIZP 0066071ASIZP 0911588South China Sea20°43′ N117°32′ E954KU943157<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi</tp:taxon-name>ASIZP 0068164ASIZP 0913925Philippine Sea (CP2729)15°19′ N121°37′ E593–600MW315786<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi</tp:taxon-name>NTUM 16627PNG1082Bismarck Sea (CP4033)4°52′ S145°53′ E780MW315787<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi</tp:taxon-name>CSIRO H 6593-01BW-A4706Northwest Cape Leveque of Australia14°36′ S121°20′ E705FOAG829-08<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
         <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>NTUM 11915PNG2363Solomon Sea (CP4334)6°08′ S149°10′ E430–620MW218670<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula coheni</tp:taxon-name>USNM 422550MOP110383Off Costa Rica9°12′ N84°29′ W656–668MF956762<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula coheni</tp:taxon-name>USNM 421491MOP110705Gulf of Panama7°24′ N78°7′ W165–183MF956763<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula coheni</tp:taxon-name>USNM 421356MOP110782Off Panama7°0′ N81°43′ W716–842MF956764<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula coheni</tp:taxon-name>USNM 421528MOP110488Gulf of Panama7°37′ N78°41′ W115–116MF956765<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula coheni</tp:taxon-name>USNM 421217MOP110814Off Costa Rica9°25′ N85°9′ W841–920MF956766</p>
      <p>*
= Outgroups used.
</p>
      <p>**
= details on collection information can be referenced at our survey database of the 
TDSB
available from https://expeditions.mnhn.fr/.
</p>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>
Class 
<tp:taxon-name>Actinopterygii Klein, 1885</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Order 
<tp:taxon-name>Ophidiiformes Berg, 1937</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
         <p>
Family 
<tp:taxon-name>Ophidiidae Rafinesque, 1810</tp:taxon-name>
         </p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L
. 
brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Monomitopus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Glyptophidium lucidum
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epigonus atherinoides
(Gilbert, 1905)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epigonidae Poey, 1861</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tunepugettia corbariae
Lee, Richer de Forges &amp; Ng 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae MacLeay, 1838</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensisNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata
(Gosline, 1954)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheniNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycterCohen, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfiCohen, 1981</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; Radcliffe, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Integrative taxonomy reveals a rare and new cusk-eel species of Luciobrotula (Teleostei, Ophidiidae) from the Solomon Sea, West Pacific</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFCBFFA7FF8CFFEF3C46FF9D972E5206</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</pub-id>
               <issn>2118-9773</issn>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to all known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; Radcliffe, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
(
6 specimens
, 
97.9–393.7 mm
SL)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Molecular phylogeny and species delimitation</p>
            <p>
The 
COI
dataset comprised 13 aligned sequences including three newly obtained sequences from the collected specimens, three additional sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
from the South 
China
Sea and Western Australia, five sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
from the Eastern Pacific, plus two outgroup sequences (
Table 1
). The length of the aligned sequences of the dataset is 618 bp. 

shows the phylogenetic tree inferred from the ML analysis based on the dataset. The monophyly of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly supported (bootstrap value =98%), and ingroup sequences form three clades or lineages among which two contain sequences from the two known species (

). While two of our newly obtained sequences (ASIZP 0913925 and 
PNG
1082) fall into the 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
clade, the third one (
PNG
2363) appears to be a previously unknown lineage. Advanced species delimitation analyses with ABGD and bPTP based on the same 
COI
dataset reveal a congruent result with a prediction of three OTUs, corroborating the phylogenetic finding (

). The delimited OTUs (or inferred species) are genetically distinct from each other. The unknown lineage is distinct from others by 37 unique nucleotide sites based on CBB analysis. The average genetic distances measured using the K2P model among them are from 0.130 to 0.138 at the 
COI
locus. Further morphological examination on the specimens indicates that the features of the sample collected from the Solomon Sea (
PNG
2363) are unique among all known 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
(see below), and we validate it herein as a new species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E7C043DA-005E-494F-9E00-21454E6E61BA</p>
            <p>
; 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is morphologically distinct from all congeners by the following combination of characters: lateral line ending below 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray; dorsal-fin rays 86, anal-fin rays 70, precaudal vertebrae 13, total vertebrae 50; gill rakers 17 (3 long rakers and 14 dentigerous plates); longest gill raker 2.1% SL; height of posterior margin of maxilla 3.2% SL; distance from the snout to end of lateral line 60% SL; one interorbital pore and four occipital pores.
</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis</p>
            <p>
The new species is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
because both share the low number of vertebrae. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L
. 
brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
by having a much longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray), a slightly more posterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal ray below dorsal ray no. 22 vs first anal ray below dorsal ray no. 17), more pectoral-fin rays (32 vs 26), more gill rakers (17 vs 13–14), longer gill raker on first arch (2.1% SL vs 1.2% SL).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
(

) in having a slightly longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs the 18 
th
–26 
th
dorsal-fin ray) and narrower posterior margin of maxilla (3.2% SL vs 3.6–4.7% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
by having more anal-fin rays (70 vs 59–65), fewer total gill rakers (17 vs 21–26), a more anterior anal-fin origin (anterior anal-fin ray below 17 
th
vertebra vs anterior anal-fin ray below 21 
st
–22 
nd
vertebrae), a narrower interorbital space (3.5% SL vs 3.9–5.6% SL), and a narrower posterior margin of the maxilla (3.2% SL vs 3.9–4.9% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
by having fewer dorsal-fin rays (86 vs 91–96), fewer gill rakers (17 vs 18–21), and anterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal-fin ray below the 17 
th
vertebra vs first analfin ray below the 20 
th
–22 
nd
vertebrae).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
by having a slightly longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 27 
th
–31 
st
dorsal-fin ray), slightly more anterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal-fin ray below the 17 
th
vertebra vs first anal-fin ray below the 19 
th
–20 
th
vertebrae), smaller head (23.9% SL vs 24.5–28.0% SL), and relatively deeper body (16.3% SL vs 12.5–15.0% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
by having a much longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray), fewer dorsal-fin rays (86 vs 92), more pectoral-fin rays (32 vs 26), shorter pelvic-fin rays (10.9% SL vs 15.0% SL) and longer gill raker on the first arch (2.1% SL vs 0.7% SL). A detailed comparison between the new species and other congeners is provided in 
Table 2
.
</p>
            <p>
Along the 
COI
gene, the following apomorphic sites are unique nucleotides from the only specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
examined here; these nucleotide sites can be used for the molecular diagnosis of the species to differentiate it from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
examined in this study. Nos. 97 (C vs T), 120 (A vs G), 147 (G vs A), 177 (G vs A), 180 (C vs T), 198 (C vs T), 219 (T vs C), 225 (C vs T), 294 (C vs T), 321 (A vs C), 324 (G vs A), 330 (A vs G), 336 (A vs C), 348 (G vs A or C), 363 (G vs T or C), 369 (T vs C), 372 (A vs C or T), 375 (C vs T), 381 (G vs A), 387 (C vs T), 390 (T vs C), 405 (C vs T), 420 (A vs G or C), 426 (T vs C), 465 (A vs C or G), 477 (A vs G), 540 (A vs G), 555 (G vs A), 565 (T vs C), 597 (T vs C), 603 (T vs A), 615 (C vs A), 648 (T vs C), 682 (C vs A or G), 675 (C vs T), 684 (G vs A), 687 (T vs C).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The name 
<tp:taxon-name>polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
is derived from the Greek ‘ 
poly
’, meaning ‘many’ or ‘numerous’, and ‘ 
lepis
’, meaning ‘scales’, in reference to the much longer lateral line and therefore more lateral line scales compared with 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
, the only congener distributed in the West Pacific.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type material</p>
            <p>Holotype</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
SOLOMON SEA • 
168.4 mm
SL, sample ID: 
PNG2363
; 
Ainto Bay
, 
SE of New Britain Island
, 
Papua New Guinea
, 
Solomon Sea
, 
West Pacific
, stn CP4334; 
6°08′ S
, 
149°10′ E
; 
430–620 m
depth

; 
6 May 2014
; R/V 
ALIS
; French beam trawl; MADEEP expedition; GenBank registration: 
MW218670
; 
NTUM 11915
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Measurements and counts of the 
holotype
given in 
Table 2
. Body elongate with tapering caudal portion, snout and head slightly depressed; eye small and round, horizontal eye diameter about half of snout length. Mouth large, oblique; upper jaw reaching a vertical through the posterior margin of orbit, posterior part vertically much extended, slightly protruding beyond lower jaw when mouth closed. Boomerang-formed vomer; palatine, and upper and lower jaw with many small, close-set, rather blunt teeth in several irregular rows; fang-like teeth absent in both jaws. One median and a pair of two large basibranchial tooth patches. Anterior nostril with low rim and placed midway between upper lip and posterior nostril, with small rounded flap rising from anterior rim. Posterior margins of preopercle, interopercle, and subopercle rounded, without spine. First gill arch with four finely dentigerous plates on upper branch, one long raker on the angle, and lower branch with two long rakers interspaced with 10 dentigerous plates (

); gill filaments ca 100, the longest about half as long as longest gill raker; pseudobranchial filament damaged, unavailable count.
</p>
            <p>
Sensory pores are found all over head (

). Supraorbital with group of eight pores behind eye, five pores immediately above eye, and five small pores in a row on tip of snout, larger pore between flaps on tip of snout, and above each nostril, one interorbital pore, four occipital pores, six suborbital pores and four mandibular pores, 10 small pores close to lower jaw, between this row and mandibular having four small pores, and finally a row of six pores above posterior mandibular, two pores behind posterior end of maxilla, and preopercle with six pores.
</p>
            <p>
Sagittal otolith is elongate and thin, about 2.5 times as long as high. Sulcus divided into ostium and cauda. Cauda is about ⅔ of ostium (

). Due to the damaged anterior rim, the presence of an ostial channel could not be ascertained.
</p>
            <p>
Body, top of head, and opercle covered with small cycloid scales, with ca 72 scales in oblique line from origin of anal fin forwards and ca 111 scales from upper part of gill slit to base of caudal fin; single lateral line originating at upper angle of opercle and extending posteriorly in straight line placed about midway between midline and profile of body, ending below 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray. Dorsal-fin origin above end of pectoral fin; anal-fin origin at about mid-body of fish, pectoral fin placed medially and pelvic fin reaching one third from base to anal fin.
</p>
            <p>
Third neural spine pointed, length of first spine half as long as second spine (

), neural spines of posterior 10 pre-caudal vertebrae with blunt tips and broad bases, 4 
th
–11 
th
precaudal vertebrae with broad bases and depressed neural spines, 7 
th
–13 
th
precaudal vertebrae with parapophyses, and pleural ribs on 3 
rd
–6 
th
precaudal vertebrae. Epipleural ribs hard to observe.
</p>
            <p>
Head brown; body brownish-yellow with bluish-brown abdomen (

). Dorsal, pectoral, anal, and caudal fins black. Color of preserved specimen similar to that of fresh specimens, the head and body uniformly brown with dark bluish-brown abdomen (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Possibly endemic to waters off 
Papua New Guinea
; the only known specimen was collected on the SE continental slope of 
New Britain
Island, 
Papua New Guinea
, at depths of 
430–620 m
(

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Accompanying fauna</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Monomitopus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Glyptophidium lucidum
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
were the only two other ophidiids collected along with 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, in addition to 
<tp:taxon-name>Epigonus atherinoides
(Gilbert, 1905)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Epigonidae Poey, 1861</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Okamoto 
et al.
2018

). The mud bottom living invertebrates collected from the same site included sea cradles, sea snails, sea stars, deep-sea barnacles, decapods (https://expeditions.mnhn.fr/campaign/madeep/event/cp4334#les_photos), and a recently described deep-sea spider crab, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tunepugettia corbariae
Lee, Richer de Forges &amp; Ng 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae MacLeay, 1838</tp:taxon-name>
) (Lee B.-Y. 
et al
. 2019).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
(modified from 
Nielsen 2009
)
</p>
            <p>1. Precaudal vertebrae 13; total vertebrae 50 or 51 ............................................................................... 2</p>
            <p>– Precaudal vertebrae 15 or 16; total vertebrae 52–57 ......................................................................... 3</p>
            <p>
2. Lateral line ending at 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray; total gill rakers 13–14 .......................................................... ............................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensisNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
(off 
Brazil
)
</p>
            <p>
– Lateral line ending at 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray; total gill rakers 17 ............................................................... .................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(off 
Papua New Guinea
)
</p>
            <p>
3. Lateral line short and distinct, ending at 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray .... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata
(Gosline, 1954)
</tp:taxon-name>
(off 
Hawaii
)
</p>
            <p>
– Lateral line long, usually indistinct, ending at 19 
th
–37 
th
dorsal-fin ray.............................................. 4
</p>
            <p>
4. Dorsal-fin rays 81–89;anal-fin rays59–65;first gill arch with3developed rakers and 18–23dentigerous plates; longest filaments on first gill arch 2.8–3.6% SL ......... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheniNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
(East Pacific)
</p>
            <p>– Dorsal-fin rays 86–96; anal-fin rays 66–75; first gill arch with 3–4 developed rakers and 12–18 dentigerous plates; longest filaments on fist gill arch 1.3–2.7% SL.................................................. 5</p>
            <p>
5. Four occipital pores, one interorbital pore; first anal-fin ray below 18 
th
–24 
th
dorsal-fin rays; dorsal rim of otolith without concavity (large specimens)............................................................................. ................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
(Indo-West Pacific)
</p>
            <p>
– Pores absent on occipital and interorbital region; first anal-fin ray below 24 
th
–28 
th
dorsal-fin rays; dorsal rim of otolith with or without concavity ................................................................................. 6
</p>
            <p>
6. Head brown; otolith with a distinct concavity in dorsal rim in specimens larger than 
300 mm
SL; total vertebrae 56–57; longest pelvic-fin ray 7.9–9.6% SL ................................................................. .................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycterCohen, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
(
Gulf
of 
Mexico
, Caribbean Sea)
</p>
            <p>
– Head pale; otolith without a distinct concavity in dorsal rim in specimens larger than 
300 mm
SL; total vertebrae 53–55; longest pelvic-fin ray 11.0–12.5% SL.............................................................. ...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfiCohen, 1981</tp:taxon-name>
(tropical East Atlantic)
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
BISMARCK SEA • 
<tp:material-citation>393.7 mm
SL; Cape Croisilles off Papua New Guinea, stn CP4033; 
4°52′ S
, 
145°53′ E
; 
780 m
depth

; R/V ALIS, beam trawl, PAPUA NIUGINI expedition; 
16 Dec. 2012
; 
NTUM 16627
(tissue sample ID: 
PNG1082
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>EAST CHINA SEA</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>181.6 mm
SL; stn CD210, 
24° 28′ N
, 
122° 12′ E
; 
1185 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
30 May 2003
; 
ASIZP0063749</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
PHILIPPINE SEA • 
<tp:material-citation>301.7 mm
SL; stn CP2729, 
15°19′ N
, 
121°37′ E
; 
593–600 m
depth

; R/V DA-BFAR, beam trawl, AURORA expedition; 
31 May 2007
; 
ASIZP 0068164
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP 0913925
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
227.4 mm
SL; Dashi fishing port; 
23 May 2007
; 
ASIZP0070170</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
97.9 mm
SL; 
South China Sea
, 
NE of Dongsha Island
; stn CD321; 
20° 43′ N
, 
117° 32′ E
; 
954 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
19 Aug. 2005
; 
ASIZP 0066071
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP0911588
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
202 mm
SL; 
South China Sea
, 
SE of Little Liuqiu Island
; 
22° 12′ N
, 
120° 23′ E
; 
68–347 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
29 Jul. 2014
; 
ASIZP 0075076
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP 0916618
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <p>Description of new species</p>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L
. 
brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Monomitopus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Glyptophidium lucidum
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epigonus atherinoides
(Gilbert, 1905)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epigonidae Poey, 1861</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tunepugettia corbariae
Lee, Richer de Forges &amp; Ng 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae MacLeay, 1838</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensisNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata
(Gosline, 1954)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheniNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycterCohen, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfiCohen, 1981</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; Radcliffe, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Integrative taxonomy reveals a rare and new cusk-eel species of Luciobrotula (Teleostei, Ophidiidae) from the Solomon Sea, West Pacific</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFCBFFA7FF8CFFEF3C46FF9D972E5206</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</pub-id>
               <issn>2118-9773</issn>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to all known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; Radcliffe, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
(
6 specimens
, 
97.9–393.7 mm
SL)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Molecular phylogeny and species delimitation</p>
            <p>
The 
COI
dataset comprised 13 aligned sequences including three newly obtained sequences from the collected specimens, three additional sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
from the South 
China
Sea and Western Australia, five sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
from the Eastern Pacific, plus two outgroup sequences (
Table 1
). The length of the aligned sequences of the dataset is 618 bp. 

shows the phylogenetic tree inferred from the ML analysis based on the dataset. The monophyly of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly supported (bootstrap value =98%), and ingroup sequences form three clades or lineages among which two contain sequences from the two known species (

). While two of our newly obtained sequences (ASIZP 0913925 and 
PNG
1082) fall into the 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
clade, the third one (
PNG
2363) appears to be a previously unknown lineage. Advanced species delimitation analyses with ABGD and bPTP based on the same 
COI
dataset reveal a congruent result with a prediction of three OTUs, corroborating the phylogenetic finding (

). The delimited OTUs (or inferred species) are genetically distinct from each other. The unknown lineage is distinct from others by 37 unique nucleotide sites based on CBB analysis. The average genetic distances measured using the K2P model among them are from 0.130 to 0.138 at the 
COI
locus. Further morphological examination on the specimens indicates that the features of the sample collected from the Solomon Sea (
PNG
2363) are unique among all known 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
(see below), and we validate it herein as a new species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E7C043DA-005E-494F-9E00-21454E6E61BA</p>
            <p>
; 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is morphologically distinct from all congeners by the following combination of characters: lateral line ending below 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray; dorsal-fin rays 86, anal-fin rays 70, precaudal vertebrae 13, total vertebrae 50; gill rakers 17 (3 long rakers and 14 dentigerous plates); longest gill raker 2.1% SL; height of posterior margin of maxilla 3.2% SL; distance from the snout to end of lateral line 60% SL; one interorbital pore and four occipital pores.
</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis</p>
            <p>
The new species is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
because both share the low number of vertebrae. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L
. 
brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
by having a much longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray), a slightly more posterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal ray below dorsal ray no. 22 vs first anal ray below dorsal ray no. 17), more pectoral-fin rays (32 vs 26), more gill rakers (17 vs 13–14), longer gill raker on first arch (2.1% SL vs 1.2% SL).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
(

) in having a slightly longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs the 18 
th
–26 
th
dorsal-fin ray) and narrower posterior margin of maxilla (3.2% SL vs 3.6–4.7% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
by having more anal-fin rays (70 vs 59–65), fewer total gill rakers (17 vs 21–26), a more anterior anal-fin origin (anterior anal-fin ray below 17 
th
vertebra vs anterior anal-fin ray below 21 
st
–22 
nd
vertebrae), a narrower interorbital space (3.5% SL vs 3.9–5.6% SL), and a narrower posterior margin of the maxilla (3.2% SL vs 3.9–4.9% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
by having fewer dorsal-fin rays (86 vs 91–96), fewer gill rakers (17 vs 18–21), and anterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal-fin ray below the 17 
th
vertebra vs first analfin ray below the 20 
th
–22 
nd
vertebrae).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
by having a slightly longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 27 
th
–31 
st
dorsal-fin ray), slightly more anterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal-fin ray below the 17 
th
vertebra vs first anal-fin ray below the 19 
th
–20 
th
vertebrae), smaller head (23.9% SL vs 24.5–28.0% SL), and relatively deeper body (16.3% SL vs 12.5–15.0% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
by having a much longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray), fewer dorsal-fin rays (86 vs 92), more pectoral-fin rays (32 vs 26), shorter pelvic-fin rays (10.9% SL vs 15.0% SL) and longer gill raker on the first arch (2.1% SL vs 0.7% SL). A detailed comparison between the new species and other congeners is provided in 
Table 2
.
</p>
            <p>
Along the 
COI
gene, the following apomorphic sites are unique nucleotides from the only specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
examined here; these nucleotide sites can be used for the molecular diagnosis of the species to differentiate it from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
examined in this study. Nos. 97 (C vs T), 120 (A vs G), 147 (G vs A), 177 (G vs A), 180 (C vs T), 198 (C vs T), 219 (T vs C), 225 (C vs T), 294 (C vs T), 321 (A vs C), 324 (G vs A), 330 (A vs G), 336 (A vs C), 348 (G vs A or C), 363 (G vs T or C), 369 (T vs C), 372 (A vs C or T), 375 (C vs T), 381 (G vs A), 387 (C vs T), 390 (T vs C), 405 (C vs T), 420 (A vs G or C), 426 (T vs C), 465 (A vs C or G), 477 (A vs G), 540 (A vs G), 555 (G vs A), 565 (T vs C), 597 (T vs C), 603 (T vs A), 615 (C vs A), 648 (T vs C), 682 (C vs A or G), 675 (C vs T), 684 (G vs A), 687 (T vs C).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The name 
<tp:taxon-name>polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
is derived from the Greek ‘ 
poly
’, meaning ‘many’ or ‘numerous’, and ‘ 
lepis
’, meaning ‘scales’, in reference to the much longer lateral line and therefore more lateral line scales compared with 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
, the only congener distributed in the West Pacific.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type material</p>
            <p>Holotype</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
SOLOMON SEA • 
168.4 mm
SL, sample ID: 
PNG2363
; 
Ainto Bay
, 
SE of New Britain Island
, 
Papua New Guinea
, 
Solomon Sea
, 
West Pacific
, stn CP4334; 
6°08′ S
, 
149°10′ E
; 
430–620 m
depth

; 
6 May 2014
; R/V 
ALIS
; French beam trawl; MADEEP expedition; GenBank registration: 
MW218670
; 
NTUM 11915
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Measurements and counts of the 
holotype
given in 
Table 2
. Body elongate with tapering caudal portion, snout and head slightly depressed; eye small and round, horizontal eye diameter about half of snout length. Mouth large, oblique; upper jaw reaching a vertical through the posterior margin of orbit, posterior part vertically much extended, slightly protruding beyond lower jaw when mouth closed. Boomerang-formed vomer; palatine, and upper and lower jaw with many small, close-set, rather blunt teeth in several irregular rows; fang-like teeth absent in both jaws. One median and a pair of two large basibranchial tooth patches. Anterior nostril with low rim and placed midway between upper lip and posterior nostril, with small rounded flap rising from anterior rim. Posterior margins of preopercle, interopercle, and subopercle rounded, without spine. First gill arch with four finely dentigerous plates on upper branch, one long raker on the angle, and lower branch with two long rakers interspaced with 10 dentigerous plates (

); gill filaments ca 100, the longest about half as long as longest gill raker; pseudobranchial filament damaged, unavailable count.
</p>
            <p>
Sensory pores are found all over head (

). Supraorbital with group of eight pores behind eye, five pores immediately above eye, and five small pores in a row on tip of snout, larger pore between flaps on tip of snout, and above each nostril, one interorbital pore, four occipital pores, six suborbital pores and four mandibular pores, 10 small pores close to lower jaw, between this row and mandibular having four small pores, and finally a row of six pores above posterior mandibular, two pores behind posterior end of maxilla, and preopercle with six pores.
</p>
            <p>
Sagittal otolith is elongate and thin, about 2.5 times as long as high. Sulcus divided into ostium and cauda. Cauda is about ⅔ of ostium (

). Due to the damaged anterior rim, the presence of an ostial channel could not be ascertained.
</p>
            <p>
Body, top of head, and opercle covered with small cycloid scales, with ca 72 scales in oblique line from origin of anal fin forwards and ca 111 scales from upper part of gill slit to base of caudal fin; single lateral line originating at upper angle of opercle and extending posteriorly in straight line placed about midway between midline and profile of body, ending below 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray. Dorsal-fin origin above end of pectoral fin; anal-fin origin at about mid-body of fish, pectoral fin placed medially and pelvic fin reaching one third from base to anal fin.
</p>
            <p>
Third neural spine pointed, length of first spine half as long as second spine (

), neural spines of posterior 10 pre-caudal vertebrae with blunt tips and broad bases, 4 
th
–11 
th
precaudal vertebrae with broad bases and depressed neural spines, 7 
th
–13 
th
precaudal vertebrae with parapophyses, and pleural ribs on 3 
rd
–6 
th
precaudal vertebrae. Epipleural ribs hard to observe.
</p>
            <p>
Head brown; body brownish-yellow with bluish-brown abdomen (

). Dorsal, pectoral, anal, and caudal fins black. Color of preserved specimen similar to that of fresh specimens, the head and body uniformly brown with dark bluish-brown abdomen (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Possibly endemic to waters off 
Papua New Guinea
; the only known specimen was collected on the SE continental slope of 
New Britain
Island, 
Papua New Guinea
, at depths of 
430–620 m
(

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Accompanying fauna</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Monomitopus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Glyptophidium lucidum
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
were the only two other ophidiids collected along with 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, in addition to 
<tp:taxon-name>Epigonus atherinoides
(Gilbert, 1905)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Epigonidae Poey, 1861</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Okamoto 
et al.
2018

). The mud bottom living invertebrates collected from the same site included sea cradles, sea snails, sea stars, deep-sea barnacles, decapods (https://expeditions.mnhn.fr/campaign/madeep/event/cp4334#les_photos), and a recently described deep-sea spider crab, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tunepugettia corbariae
Lee, Richer de Forges &amp; Ng 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae MacLeay, 1838</tp:taxon-name>
) (Lee B.-Y. 
et al
. 2019).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
(modified from 
Nielsen 2009
)
</p>
            <p>1. Precaudal vertebrae 13; total vertebrae 50 or 51 ............................................................................... 2</p>
            <p>– Precaudal vertebrae 15 or 16; total vertebrae 52–57 ......................................................................... 3</p>
            <p>
2. Lateral line ending at 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray; total gill rakers 13–14 .......................................................... ............................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensisNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
(off 
Brazil
)
</p>
            <p>
– Lateral line ending at 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray; total gill rakers 17 ............................................................... .................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(off 
Papua New Guinea
)
</p>
            <p>
3. Lateral line short and distinct, ending at 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray .... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata
(Gosline, 1954)
</tp:taxon-name>
(off 
Hawaii
)
</p>
            <p>
– Lateral line long, usually indistinct, ending at 19 
th
–37 
th
dorsal-fin ray.............................................. 4
</p>
            <p>
4. Dorsal-fin rays 81–89;anal-fin rays59–65;first gill arch with3developed rakers and 18–23dentigerous plates; longest filaments on first gill arch 2.8–3.6% SL ......... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheniNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
(East Pacific)
</p>
            <p>– Dorsal-fin rays 86–96; anal-fin rays 66–75; first gill arch with 3–4 developed rakers and 12–18 dentigerous plates; longest filaments on fist gill arch 1.3–2.7% SL.................................................. 5</p>
            <p>
5. Four occipital pores, one interorbital pore; first anal-fin ray below 18 
th
–24 
th
dorsal-fin rays; dorsal rim of otolith without concavity (large specimens)............................................................................. ................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
(Indo-West Pacific)
</p>
            <p>
– Pores absent on occipital and interorbital region; first anal-fin ray below 24 
th
–28 
th
dorsal-fin rays; dorsal rim of otolith with or without concavity ................................................................................. 6
</p>
            <p>
6. Head brown; otolith with a distinct concavity in dorsal rim in specimens larger than 
300 mm
SL; total vertebrae 56–57; longest pelvic-fin ray 7.9–9.6% SL ................................................................. .................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycterCohen, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
(
Gulf
of 
Mexico
, Caribbean Sea)
</p>
            <p>
– Head pale; otolith without a distinct concavity in dorsal rim in specimens larger than 
300 mm
SL; total vertebrae 53–55; longest pelvic-fin ray 11.0–12.5% SL.............................................................. ...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfiCohen, 1981</tp:taxon-name>
(tropical East Atlantic)
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
BISMARCK SEA • 
<tp:material-citation>393.7 mm
SL; Cape Croisilles off Papua New Guinea, stn CP4033; 
4°52′ S
, 
145°53′ E
; 
780 m
depth

; R/V ALIS, beam trawl, PAPUA NIUGINI expedition; 
16 Dec. 2012
; 
NTUM 16627
(tissue sample ID: 
PNG1082
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>EAST CHINA SEA</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>181.6 mm
SL; stn CD210, 
24° 28′ N
, 
122° 12′ E
; 
1185 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
30 May 2003
; 
ASIZP0063749</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
PHILIPPINE SEA • 
<tp:material-citation>301.7 mm
SL; stn CP2729, 
15°19′ N
, 
121°37′ E
; 
593–600 m
depth

; R/V DA-BFAR, beam trawl, AURORA expedition; 
31 May 2007
; 
ASIZP 0068164
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP 0913925
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
227.4 mm
SL; Dashi fishing port; 
23 May 2007
; 
ASIZP0070170</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
97.9 mm
SL; 
South China Sea
, 
NE of Dongsha Island
; stn CD321; 
20° 43′ N
, 
117° 32′ E
; 
954 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
19 Aug. 2005
; 
ASIZP 0066071
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP0911588
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
202 mm
SL; 
South China Sea
, 
SE of Little Liuqiu Island
; 
22° 12′ N
, 
120° 23′ E
; 
68–347 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
29 Jul. 2014
; 
ASIZP 0075076
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP 0916618
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L
. 
brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Monomitopus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Glyptophidium lucidum
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epigonus atherinoides
(Gilbert, 1905)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epigonidae Poey, 1861</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tunepugettia corbariae
Lee, Richer de Forges &amp; Ng 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae MacLeay, 1838</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensisNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata
(Gosline, 1954)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheniNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycterCohen, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfiCohen, 1981</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; Radcliffe, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Integrative taxonomy reveals a rare and new cusk-eel species of Luciobrotula (Teleostei, Ophidiidae) from the Solomon Sea, West Pacific</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFCBFFA7FF8CFFEF3C46FF9D972E5206</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</pub-id>
               <issn>2118-9773</issn>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to all known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; Radcliffe, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
(
6 specimens
, 
97.9–393.7 mm
SL)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Molecular phylogeny and species delimitation</p>
            <p>
The 
COI
dataset comprised 13 aligned sequences including three newly obtained sequences from the collected specimens, three additional sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
from the South 
China
Sea and Western Australia, five sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
from the Eastern Pacific, plus two outgroup sequences (
Table 1
). The length of the aligned sequences of the dataset is 618 bp. 

shows the phylogenetic tree inferred from the ML analysis based on the dataset. The monophyly of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly supported (bootstrap value =98%), and ingroup sequences form three clades or lineages among which two contain sequences from the two known species (

). While two of our newly obtained sequences (ASIZP 0913925 and 
PNG
1082) fall into the 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
clade, the third one (
PNG
2363) appears to be a previously unknown lineage. Advanced species delimitation analyses with ABGD and bPTP based on the same 
COI
dataset reveal a congruent result with a prediction of three OTUs, corroborating the phylogenetic finding (

). The delimited OTUs (or inferred species) are genetically distinct from each other. The unknown lineage is distinct from others by 37 unique nucleotide sites based on CBB analysis. The average genetic distances measured using the K2P model among them are from 0.130 to 0.138 at the 
COI
locus. Further morphological examination on the specimens indicates that the features of the sample collected from the Solomon Sea (
PNG
2363) are unique among all known 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
(see below), and we validate it herein as a new species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E7C043DA-005E-494F-9E00-21454E6E61BA</p>
            <p>
; 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is morphologically distinct from all congeners by the following combination of characters: lateral line ending below 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray; dorsal-fin rays 86, anal-fin rays 70, precaudal vertebrae 13, total vertebrae 50; gill rakers 17 (3 long rakers and 14 dentigerous plates); longest gill raker 2.1% SL; height of posterior margin of maxilla 3.2% SL; distance from the snout to end of lateral line 60% SL; one interorbital pore and four occipital pores.
</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis</p>
            <p>
The new species is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
because both share the low number of vertebrae. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L
. 
brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
by having a much longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray), a slightly more posterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal ray below dorsal ray no. 22 vs first anal ray below dorsal ray no. 17), more pectoral-fin rays (32 vs 26), more gill rakers (17 vs 13–14), longer gill raker on first arch (2.1% SL vs 1.2% SL).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
(

) in having a slightly longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs the 18 
th
–26 
th
dorsal-fin ray) and narrower posterior margin of maxilla (3.2% SL vs 3.6–4.7% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
by having more anal-fin rays (70 vs 59–65), fewer total gill rakers (17 vs 21–26), a more anterior anal-fin origin (anterior anal-fin ray below 17 
th
vertebra vs anterior anal-fin ray below 21 
st
–22 
nd
vertebrae), a narrower interorbital space (3.5% SL vs 3.9–5.6% SL), and a narrower posterior margin of the maxilla (3.2% SL vs 3.9–4.9% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
by having fewer dorsal-fin rays (86 vs 91–96), fewer gill rakers (17 vs 18–21), and anterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal-fin ray below the 17 
th
vertebra vs first analfin ray below the 20 
th
–22 
nd
vertebrae).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
by having a slightly longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 27 
th
–31 
st
dorsal-fin ray), slightly more anterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal-fin ray below the 17 
th
vertebra vs first anal-fin ray below the 19 
th
–20 
th
vertebrae), smaller head (23.9% SL vs 24.5–28.0% SL), and relatively deeper body (16.3% SL vs 12.5–15.0% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
by having a much longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray), fewer dorsal-fin rays (86 vs 92), more pectoral-fin rays (32 vs 26), shorter pelvic-fin rays (10.9% SL vs 15.0% SL) and longer gill raker on the first arch (2.1% SL vs 0.7% SL). A detailed comparison between the new species and other congeners is provided in 
Table 2
.
</p>
            <p>
Along the 
COI
gene, the following apomorphic sites are unique nucleotides from the only specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
examined here; these nucleotide sites can be used for the molecular diagnosis of the species to differentiate it from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
examined in this study. Nos. 97 (C vs T), 120 (A vs G), 147 (G vs A), 177 (G vs A), 180 (C vs T), 198 (C vs T), 219 (T vs C), 225 (C vs T), 294 (C vs T), 321 (A vs C), 324 (G vs A), 330 (A vs G), 336 (A vs C), 348 (G vs A or C), 363 (G vs T or C), 369 (T vs C), 372 (A vs C or T), 375 (C vs T), 381 (G vs A), 387 (C vs T), 390 (T vs C), 405 (C vs T), 420 (A vs G or C), 426 (T vs C), 465 (A vs C or G), 477 (A vs G), 540 (A vs G), 555 (G vs A), 565 (T vs C), 597 (T vs C), 603 (T vs A), 615 (C vs A), 648 (T vs C), 682 (C vs A or G), 675 (C vs T), 684 (G vs A), 687 (T vs C).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The name 
<tp:taxon-name>polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
is derived from the Greek ‘ 
poly
’, meaning ‘many’ or ‘numerous’, and ‘ 
lepis
’, meaning ‘scales’, in reference to the much longer lateral line and therefore more lateral line scales compared with 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
, the only congener distributed in the West Pacific.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type material</p>
            <p>Holotype</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
SOLOMON SEA • 
168.4 mm
SL, sample ID: 
PNG2363
; 
Ainto Bay
, 
SE of New Britain Island
, 
Papua New Guinea
, 
Solomon Sea
, 
West Pacific
, stn CP4334; 
6°08′ S
, 
149°10′ E
; 
430–620 m
depth

; 
6 May 2014
; R/V 
ALIS
; French beam trawl; MADEEP expedition; GenBank registration: 
MW218670
; 
NTUM 11915
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Measurements and counts of the 
holotype
given in 
Table 2
. Body elongate with tapering caudal portion, snout and head slightly depressed; eye small and round, horizontal eye diameter about half of snout length. Mouth large, oblique; upper jaw reaching a vertical through the posterior margin of orbit, posterior part vertically much extended, slightly protruding beyond lower jaw when mouth closed. Boomerang-formed vomer; palatine, and upper and lower jaw with many small, close-set, rather blunt teeth in several irregular rows; fang-like teeth absent in both jaws. One median and a pair of two large basibranchial tooth patches. Anterior nostril with low rim and placed midway between upper lip and posterior nostril, with small rounded flap rising from anterior rim. Posterior margins of preopercle, interopercle, and subopercle rounded, without spine. First gill arch with four finely dentigerous plates on upper branch, one long raker on the angle, and lower branch with two long rakers interspaced with 10 dentigerous plates (

); gill filaments ca 100, the longest about half as long as longest gill raker; pseudobranchial filament damaged, unavailable count.
</p>
            <p>
Sensory pores are found all over head (

). Supraorbital with group of eight pores behind eye, five pores immediately above eye, and five small pores in a row on tip of snout, larger pore between flaps on tip of snout, and above each nostril, one interorbital pore, four occipital pores, six suborbital pores and four mandibular pores, 10 small pores close to lower jaw, between this row and mandibular having four small pores, and finally a row of six pores above posterior mandibular, two pores behind posterior end of maxilla, and preopercle with six pores.
</p>
            <p>
Sagittal otolith is elongate and thin, about 2.5 times as long as high. Sulcus divided into ostium and cauda. Cauda is about ⅔ of ostium (

). Due to the damaged anterior rim, the presence of an ostial channel could not be ascertained.
</p>
            <p>
Body, top of head, and opercle covered with small cycloid scales, with ca 72 scales in oblique line from origin of anal fin forwards and ca 111 scales from upper part of gill slit to base of caudal fin; single lateral line originating at upper angle of opercle and extending posteriorly in straight line placed about midway between midline and profile of body, ending below 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray. Dorsal-fin origin above end of pectoral fin; anal-fin origin at about mid-body of fish, pectoral fin placed medially and pelvic fin reaching one third from base to anal fin.
</p>
            <p>
Third neural spine pointed, length of first spine half as long as second spine (

), neural spines of posterior 10 pre-caudal vertebrae with blunt tips and broad bases, 4 
th
–11 
th
precaudal vertebrae with broad bases and depressed neural spines, 7 
th
–13 
th
precaudal vertebrae with parapophyses, and pleural ribs on 3 
rd
–6 
th
precaudal vertebrae. Epipleural ribs hard to observe.
</p>
            <p>
Head brown; body brownish-yellow with bluish-brown abdomen (

). Dorsal, pectoral, anal, and caudal fins black. Color of preserved specimen similar to that of fresh specimens, the head and body uniformly brown with dark bluish-brown abdomen (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Possibly endemic to waters off 
Papua New Guinea
; the only known specimen was collected on the SE continental slope of 
New Britain
Island, 
Papua New Guinea
, at depths of 
430–620 m
(

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Accompanying fauna</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Monomitopus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Glyptophidium lucidum
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
were the only two other ophidiids collected along with 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, in addition to 
<tp:taxon-name>Epigonus atherinoides
(Gilbert, 1905)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Epigonidae Poey, 1861</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Okamoto 
et al.
2018

). The mud bottom living invertebrates collected from the same site included sea cradles, sea snails, sea stars, deep-sea barnacles, decapods (https://expeditions.mnhn.fr/campaign/madeep/event/cp4334#les_photos), and a recently described deep-sea spider crab, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tunepugettia corbariae
Lee, Richer de Forges &amp; Ng 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae MacLeay, 1838</tp:taxon-name>
) (Lee B.-Y. 
et al
. 2019).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
(modified from 
Nielsen 2009
)
</p>
            <p>1. Precaudal vertebrae 13; total vertebrae 50 or 51 ............................................................................... 2</p>
            <p>– Precaudal vertebrae 15 or 16; total vertebrae 52–57 ......................................................................... 3</p>
            <p>
2. Lateral line ending at 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray; total gill rakers 13–14 .......................................................... ............................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensisNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
(off 
Brazil
)
</p>
            <p>
– Lateral line ending at 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray; total gill rakers 17 ............................................................... .................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(off 
Papua New Guinea
)
</p>
            <p>
3. Lateral line short and distinct, ending at 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray .... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata
(Gosline, 1954)
</tp:taxon-name>
(off 
Hawaii
)
</p>
            <p>
– Lateral line long, usually indistinct, ending at 19 
th
–37 
th
dorsal-fin ray.............................................. 4
</p>
            <p>
4. Dorsal-fin rays 81–89;anal-fin rays59–65;first gill arch with3developed rakers and 18–23dentigerous plates; longest filaments on first gill arch 2.8–3.6% SL ......... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheniNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
(East Pacific)
</p>
            <p>– Dorsal-fin rays 86–96; anal-fin rays 66–75; first gill arch with 3–4 developed rakers and 12–18 dentigerous plates; longest filaments on fist gill arch 1.3–2.7% SL.................................................. 5</p>
            <p>
5. Four occipital pores, one interorbital pore; first anal-fin ray below 18 
th
–24 
th
dorsal-fin rays; dorsal rim of otolith without concavity (large specimens)............................................................................. ................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
(Indo-West Pacific)
</p>
            <p>
– Pores absent on occipital and interorbital region; first anal-fin ray below 24 
th
–28 
th
dorsal-fin rays; dorsal rim of otolith with or without concavity ................................................................................. 6
</p>
            <p>
6. Head brown; otolith with a distinct concavity in dorsal rim in specimens larger than 
300 mm
SL; total vertebrae 56–57; longest pelvic-fin ray 7.9–9.6% SL ................................................................. .................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycterCohen, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
(
Gulf
of 
Mexico
, Caribbean Sea)
</p>
            <p>
– Head pale; otolith without a distinct concavity in dorsal rim in specimens larger than 
300 mm
SL; total vertebrae 53–55; longest pelvic-fin ray 11.0–12.5% SL.............................................................. ...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfiCohen, 1981</tp:taxon-name>
(tropical East Atlantic)
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
BISMARCK SEA • 
<tp:material-citation>393.7 mm
SL; Cape Croisilles off Papua New Guinea, stn CP4033; 
4°52′ S
, 
145°53′ E
; 
780 m
depth

; R/V ALIS, beam trawl, PAPUA NIUGINI expedition; 
16 Dec. 2012
; 
NTUM 16627
(tissue sample ID: 
PNG1082
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>EAST CHINA SEA</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>181.6 mm
SL; stn CD210, 
24° 28′ N
, 
122° 12′ E
; 
1185 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
30 May 2003
; 
ASIZP0063749</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
PHILIPPINE SEA • 
<tp:material-citation>301.7 mm
SL; stn CP2729, 
15°19′ N
, 
121°37′ E
; 
593–600 m
depth

; R/V DA-BFAR, beam trawl, AURORA expedition; 
31 May 2007
; 
ASIZP 0068164
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP 0913925
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
227.4 mm
SL; Dashi fishing port; 
23 May 2007
; 
ASIZP0070170</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
97.9 mm
SL; 
South China Sea
, 
NE of Dongsha Island
; stn CD321; 
20° 43′ N
, 
117° 32′ E
; 
954 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
19 Aug. 2005
; 
ASIZP 0066071
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP0911588
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
202 mm
SL; 
South China Sea
, 
SE of Little Liuqiu Island
; 
22° 12′ N
, 
120° 23′ E
; 
68–347 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
29 Jul. 2014
; 
ASIZP 0075076
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP 0916618
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
The number of vertebrae is an important diagnostic character in distinguishing species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
. Based on that, the species of this genus can be split into two groups, either possessing 13 precaudal vertebrae or possessing 15 or 16 precaudal vertebrae. Our newly described species, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, is grouped together with 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
in having a lower precaudal vertebrae count. Another group with a higher precaudal vertebrae count consists of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
. In this study, 
six specimens
of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
were examined (
Table 2
). We noticed that one of them (
ASIZP
0063749) failed to reach the measurement range of the species. In fact, 
ASIZP
0063749 has fewer precaudal vertebrae (14 instead of 15–16) and fewer total vertebrae (49 instead of 52–55). When we further examined this specimen through radiographs, we observed that the 24 
th
and 25 
th
, and the 28 
th
and 29 
th
vertebrae of 
ASIZP
0063749 were fused together (

) and that it should be regarded as a specimen with abnormal vertebrae. In addition to the number of vertebrae, the lateral line length is another important character for identifying species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
possess lateral lines reaching below the second dorsal-fin ray; others, including 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, possess lateral lines reaching beyond the 19 
th
dorsal-fin ray.
</p>
         <p>
Among the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
is the only known widespread species. In the West Pacific, its distribution ranges from the 
Philippines
north to 
Japan
and west to Hawaii; it was also recorded from Papua New Guinean waters, first by 
Nielsen &amp; Møller (2008)
(n =1), and later by 

Fricke 
et al.
(2014)

(n=1). However, the specimen of ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
’ (
NTUM
10054) examined by 

Fricke 
et al.
(2014)

represented a misidentification. Upon our reexamination, we found that it possesses a combination of characters (a copulatory organ and the caudal fin fused with the dorsal and anal fins) that matches fishes from another ophidiiform family, the 
<tp:taxon-name>Bythitidae Gill, 1861</tp:taxon-name>
(

Møller 
et al.
2016

). Nevertheless, the six samples of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
examined in this study were all collected from sites within the reported range of the species (

). The new species is possibly endemic to 
Papua New Guinea
, as it is so far known from its 
type
locality only. These two western Pacific species appear to share a similar bathymetric range (
430–620 m
vs 
400–2283 m
depth) and habitat (mud bottom), and both are found in Papua New Guinean waters. Certainly, their distribution and ecology require more investigations.
</p>
         <p>
Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
seem to be rare. Despite intensive sampling efforts from either local organizations in 
Taiwan
or international expeditions through the 
TDSB
for over a decade, only a few specimens were made available for scientific investigations. The difficulty in sampling has limited our understanding of biodiversity, phylogeny, biogeography, and ecology of deep-sea fishes such as those from the rare genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
or others (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>Chelidoperca
Boulenger, 1895
</tp:taxon-name>
) (Lee S.-H. 
et al.
2019). In spite of that, in this study we successfully uncover the hidden diversity of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
in the West Pacific using an integrated approach in taxonomy and conduct the first phylogenetic study of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
. From the inferred phylogenetic tree, the two western Pacific species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
are shown to be distantly related to each other despite their geographic proximity. Our preliminary phylogenetic result also indicates that the species (
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
) sharing a similar morphology may not be closely related.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgments</title>
         <p>
We would like to thank the participants of AURORA, 
PAPUA NIUGINI
, and MADEEP oceanography expeditions, and the crew of 
R
/ 
VDA-BFAR
and 
ALIS
in organizing the survey and collecting the samples under the 
TDSB
Program. The 
Papua New Guinea
expeditions were also supported from Papua New Guinea’s National Fisheries Authority and conducted under a Memorandum of Understanding with the University of 
Papua New Guinea
(UPNG), and with a permit from the 
Papua New Guinea
Department of Environment and Conservation (DEC). We also thank S.-P. Huang (
ASIZP
) and H.-C. Lin (
NTUM
) for specimen management and assistance, and the anonymous reviewers and the editor (F.P. Ottoni) whose comments improved the manuscript. This study was supported by research funding from the Ministry of Science and Technology, 
Taiwan
(MOST 102-2923-B-002-001-MY3, MOST 107-2611- M-002-007- and MOST 108-2611-M-002-012-MY2 to W.-J. Chen) and the French National Research Agency (ANR 12-ISV7-0005-01 to S. Samadi).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Bouchet P.
, 
Héros V.
, 
Lozouet P.
&amp; 
Maestrati P.2008
. 
A quarter-century of deep-sea malacological exploration in the South and West Pacific: Where do we stand? How far to go
. 
Tropical Deep-Sea Benthos25
: 
9–40
.
</p>
         <p>Brower A.V.2010
. 

Alleviating the taxonomic impediment of DNA barcoding and setting a bad precedent: names for ten species of ‘ 
Astraptes fulgerator
’ (Lepidoptera: Hesperiidae: Eudaminae) with DNA-based diagnoses

. 
Systematics and Biodiversity8
(
4
): 
485–491
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1080/14772000.2010.534512</p>
         <p>Cohen D.M.1964
. 

A review of the ophidioid fish genus 
Luciobrotula
with the description of a new species from the western North Atlantic

. 
Bulletin of Marine Science14
(
3
): 
387–398
.
</p>
         <p>Cohen D.M.1974
. 

The ophidioid fish genus 
Luciobrotula
in the Hawaiian Islands

. 
Pacific Science28
(
2
): 
109–110
.
</p>
         <p>Cohen D.M.1981
. 
New and rare ophidiiform fishes from the eastern Atlantic: Canary Islands to the Cape of Good Hope
. 
Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington94
(
4
): 
1085–1103
.
</p>
         <p>Dayrat B.2005
. 
Towards integrative taxonomy
. 
Biological Journal of the Linnean Society85
(
3
): 
407– 417
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1095-8312.2005.00503.x</p>
         <p>Desalle R.
, 
Egan M.G.
&amp; 
Siddall M.2005
. 
The unholy trinity: taxonomy, species delimitation and DNA barcoding
. 
Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B360
: 
1905–1916
. 
https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2005.1722</p>
         <p>Edgar R.C.2004
. 
MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput
. 
Nucleic Acids Research32
(
5
): 
1792–1797
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkh340</p>
         <p>Felsenstein J.1985
. 
Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap
. 
Evolution39
(
4
): 
783–791
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1558-5646.1985.tb00420.x</p>
         <p>Fricke R.
, 
Allen G.R.
, 
Andréfouët S.
, 
Chen W.-J.
, 
Hamel M.A.
, 
Laboute P.
, 
Mana R.
, 
Hui T.H.
&amp; 
Uyeno D.2014
. 
Checklist of the marine and estuarine fishes of Madang District, Papua New Guinea, western Pacific Ocean, with 820 new records
. 
Zootaxa3832
(
1
): 
1–247
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3832.1.1</p>
         <p>Fricke R.
, 
Eschmeyer W.N.
&amp; 
Van der Laan R.2020
. 
Catalog of Fishes: Genera, Species, References
.

Available from 
http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/fishcatmain.asp
[accessed 
Oct. 2020
].
</p>
         <p>Guimarães E.C.
, 
de Brito P.S.
, 
Bragança P.H.N.
, 
Santos J.P.
, 
Katz A.M.
, 
Costa L.F.C.
&amp; 
Ottoni F.P.2020
. 

Integrative taxonomy reveals two new cryptic species of 
Hyphessobrycon
Durbin, 1908 (Teleostei: Characidae) from the Maracaçumé and middle Tocantins River basins, Eastern Amazon region

. 
European Journal of Taxonomy723
: 
77–107
. 
https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.723.1145</p>
         <p>Hebert P.D.
, 
Penton E.H.
, 
Burns J.M.
, 
Janzen D.H.
&amp; 
Hallwachs W.2004
. 

Ten species in one: DNA barcoding reveals cryptic species in the neotropical skipper butterfly 
Astraptes fulgerator
. 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences101
(
41
): 
14812–14817
. 
https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0406166101</p>
         <p>Hung K.-W.
, 
Russell B.C.
&amp; 
Chen W.-J.2017
. 
Molecular systematics of threadfin breams and relatives (Teleostei, Nemipteridae)
. 
Zoologica Scripta46
(
5
): 
536–551
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/zsc.12237</p>
         <p>Kimura M.1980
. 
A simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences
. 
Journal of Molecular Evolution16
(
2
): 
111–120
. 
https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01731581</p>
         <p>Kumar S.
, 
Stecher G.
, 
Li M.
, 
Knyaz C.
&amp; 
Tamura K.2018
. 
MEGA X: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis across computing platforms
. 
Molecular Biology and Evolution35
(
6
): 
1547–1549
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msy096</p>
         <p>Lee B.-Y.
, 
De Forges B.R.
&amp; 
Ng P.-K.2019
. 

Deep-sea spider crabs of the family Epialtidae MacLeay, 1838, from Papua New Guinea, with a redefinition of 
Tunepugettia
Ng, Komai &amp; Sato, 2017, and descriptions of two new genera (Crustacea: Decapoda: Brachyura: Majoidea)

. 
Zootaxa4619
(
1
): 
1–44
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4619.1.1</p>
         <p>Lee S.-H.
, 
Lee M.-Y.
, 
Matsunuma M.
&amp; 
Chen W.-J.2019
. 

Exploring the phylogeny and species diversity of 
Chelidoperca
(Teleostei: Serranidae) from the western Pacific Ocean by an integrated approach in systematics, with descriptions of three new species and a redescription of 
C. lecromi
Fourmanoir

, 1982. 
Frontiers in Marine Science6
: 
465
. 
https://doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2019.00465</p>
         <p>Lo P.-C.
, 
Liu S.-H.
, 
Nor S.A.M.
&amp; 
Chen W.-J.2017
. 
Molecular exploration of hidden diversity in the Indo- West Pacific sciaenid clade
. 
PloS One12
(
7
): e 
0176623
. 
https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0176623</p>
         <p>Nielsen J.G.2009
. 

A revision of the bathyal genus 
Luciobrotula
(Teleostei, Ophidiidae) with two new species

. 
Galathea Report
22: 
141–156
.
</p>
         <p>Nielsen J.G.
&amp; 
Møller P.R.2008
. 
New and rare deep-sea ophidiiform fishes from the Solomon Sea caught by the Danish Galathea 3 Expedition
. 
Steenstrupia30
(
1
): 
21–46
.
</p>
         <p>Nielsen J.G.
, 
Cohen D.M.
, 
Markle D.F.
&amp; 
Robins C.R.1999
. 
FAO species catalogue. Volume 18. Ophidiiform fishes of the world (Order Ophidiiformes). An annotated and illustrated catalogue of pearlfishes, cusk-eels, brotulas and other ophidiiform fishes known to date
. 
FAO Fisheries Synopsis125
(
18
): 
1–178
.
</p>
         <p>Møller P.R.
, 
Knudsen S.W.
, 
Schwarzhans W.
&amp; 
Nielsen J.G.2016
. 
A new classification of viviparous brotulas (Bythitidae) – with family status for Dinematichthyidae – based on molecular, morphological and fossil data
. 
Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution100
: 
391–408
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2016.04.008</p>
         <p>Okamoto M.
, 
Chen W.-J.
&amp; 
Shinohara G.2018
. 
Epigonus okamotoi
(Perciformes: Epigonidae), a junior synonym of 
E. draco
, with new distributional records for 
E. atherinoides
and 
E. lifouensis
in the West Pacific

. 
Zootaxa4476
(
1
): 
141–150
. 
https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4476.1.13</p>
         <p>Puillandre N.
, 
Lambert A.
, 
Brouillet S.
&amp; 
Achaz G.2012
. 
ABGD, Automatic Barcode Gap Discovery for primary species delimitation
. 
Molecular Ecology21
(
8
): 
1864–1877
. 
https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05239.x</p>
         <p>Radcliffe L.1913
. 
Descriptions of seven new genera and thirty-one new species of fishes of the families Brotulidae and Carapidae from the Philippine Islands and the Dutch East Indies
. 
Proceedings of the United States National Museum44
(
1948
): 
135–176
. 
https://doi.org/10.5479/si.00963801.44-1948.135</p>
         <p>Rach J.
, 
Desalle R.
, 
Sarkar I.N.
, 
Schierwater B.
&amp; 
Hadrys H.2008
. 
Character-based DNA barcoding allows discrimination of genera, species and populations in Odonata
. 
Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences275
(
1632
): 
237–247
. 
https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2007.1290</p>
         <p>Robertson D.R.
, 
Angulo A.
, 
Baldwin C.C.
, 
Pitassy D.E.
, 
Driskell A.
, 
Weigt L.A.
&amp; 
Navarro I.J.2017
. 
Deep-water bony fishes collected by the B/O Miguel Oliver on the shelf edge of Pacific Central America: an annotated, illustrated and DNA-barcoded checklist
. 
Zootaxa4348
(
1
): 
1–125
.
</p>
         <p>https://doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.4348.1.1</p>
         <p>Stamatakis A.2014
. 
RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies
. 
Bioinformatics30
(
9
): 
1312–1313
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btu033</p>
         <p>Ward R.D.
, 
Zemlak T.S.
, 
Innes B.H.
, 
Last P.R.
&amp; 
Hebert P.D.2005
. 
DNA barcoding Australia’s fish species
. 
Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences360
(
1462
): 
1847– 1857
. 
https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2005.1716</p>
         <p>Zhang J.
, 
Kapli P.
, 
Pavlidis P.
&amp; 
Stamatakis A.2013
. 
A general species delimitation method with applications to phylogenetic placements
. 
Bioinformatics29
(
22
): 
2869–2876
. 
https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btt499</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Manuscript received: 
23 November 2020</p>
         <p>
Manuscript accepted: 
24 March 2021</p>
         <p>
Published on: 
17 May 2021</p>
         <p>Topic editor: Rudy Jocqué</p>
         <p>Section editor: Felipe P. Ottoni</p>
         <p>Desk editor: Kristiaan Hoedemakers</p>
         <p>
Printed versions of all papers are also deposited in the libraries of the institutes that are members of the 
EJT
consortium: Muséum national d’histoire naturelle, Paris, 
France
; Meise Botanic Garden, 
Belgium
; Royal Museum for Central Africa, Tervuren, 
Belgium
; Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences, 
Brussels
, 
Belgium
; Natural History Museum of 
Denmark
, Copenhagen, 
Denmark
; Naturalis Biodiversity Center, Leiden, 
the Netherlands
; Museo Nacional de Ciencias Naturales-CSIC, 
Madrid
, 
Spain
; Real Jardín Botánico de 
Madrid
CSIC, 
Spain
; Zoological Research Museum Alexander Koenig, Bonn, 
Germany
; National Museum, 
Prague
, 
Czech Republic
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Appendix</title>
         <p>Comparative material</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L
. 
brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Monomitopus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Glyptophidium lucidum
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epigonus atherinoides
(Gilbert, 1905)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epigonidae Poey, 1861</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Tunepugettia corbariae
Lee, Richer de Forges &amp; Ng 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae MacLeay, 1838</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensisNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. lineata
(Gosline, 1954)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. coheniNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycterCohen, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. nolfiCohen, 1981</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; Radcliffe, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Integrative taxonomy reveals a rare and new cusk-eel species of Luciobrotula (Teleostei, Ophidiidae) from the Solomon Sea, West Pacific</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFCBFFA7FF8CFFEF3C46FF9D972E5206</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</pub-id>
               <issn>2118-9773</issn>
               <source>European Journal of Taxonomy</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Key to all known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula bartschi
Smith &amp; Radcliffe, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
(
6 specimens
, 
97.9–393.7 mm
SL)
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Molecular phylogeny and species delimitation</p>
            <p>
The 
COI
dataset comprised 13 aligned sequences including three newly obtained sequences from the collected specimens, three additional sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
from the South 
China
Sea and Western Australia, five sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
from the Eastern Pacific, plus two outgroup sequences (
Table 1
). The length of the aligned sequences of the dataset is 618 bp. 

shows the phylogenetic tree inferred from the ML analysis based on the dataset. The monophyly of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly supported (bootstrap value =98%), and ingroup sequences form three clades or lineages among which two contain sequences from the two known species (

). While two of our newly obtained sequences (ASIZP 0913925 and 
PNG
1082) fall into the 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
clade, the third one (
PNG
2363) appears to be a previously unknown lineage. Advanced species delimitation analyses with ABGD and bPTP based on the same 
COI
dataset reveal a congruent result with a prediction of three OTUs, corroborating the phylogenetic finding (

). The delimited OTUs (or inferred species) are genetically distinct from each other. The unknown lineage is distinct from others by 37 unique nucleotide sites based on CBB analysis. The average genetic distances measured using the K2P model among them are from 0.130 to 0.138 at the 
COI
locus. Further morphological examination on the specimens indicates that the features of the sample collected from the Solomon Sea (
PNG
2363) are unique among all known 
<tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
(see below), and we validate it herein as a new species.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E7C043DA-005E-494F-9E00-21454E6E61BA</p>
            <p>
; 
Table 2</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is morphologically distinct from all congeners by the following combination of characters: lateral line ending below 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray; dorsal-fin rays 86, anal-fin rays 70, precaudal vertebrae 13, total vertebrae 50; gill rakers 17 (3 long rakers and 14 dentigerous plates); longest gill raker 2.1% SL; height of posterior margin of maxilla 3.2% SL; distance from the snout to end of lateral line 60% SL; one interorbital pore and four occipital pores.
</p>
            <p>Differential diagnosis</p>
            <p>
The new species is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
because both share the low number of vertebrae. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L
. 
brasiliensis</tp:taxon-name>
by having a much longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray), a slightly more posterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal ray below dorsal ray no. 22 vs first anal ray below dorsal ray no. 17), more pectoral-fin rays (32 vs 26), more gill rakers (17 vs 13–14), longer gill raker on first arch (2.1% SL vs 1.2% SL).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Luciobrotula polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
(

) in having a slightly longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs the 18 
th
–26 
th
dorsal-fin ray) and narrower posterior margin of maxilla (3.2% SL vs 3.6–4.7% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
by having more anal-fin rays (70 vs 59–65), fewer total gill rakers (17 vs 21–26), a more anterior anal-fin origin (anterior anal-fin ray below 17 
th
vertebra vs anterior anal-fin ray below 21 
st
–22 
nd
vertebrae), a narrower interorbital space (3.5% SL vs 3.9–5.6% SL), and a narrower posterior margin of the maxilla (3.2% SL vs 3.9–4.9% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycter</tp:taxon-name>
by having fewer dorsal-fin rays (86 vs 91–96), fewer gill rakers (17 vs 18–21), and anterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal-fin ray below the 17 
th
vertebra vs first analfin ray below the 20 
th
–22 
nd
vertebrae).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfi</tp:taxon-name>
by having a slightly longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 27 
th
–31 
st
dorsal-fin ray), slightly more anterior position of the anal-fin origin (first anal-fin ray below the 17 
th
vertebra vs first anal-fin ray below the 19 
th
–20 
th
vertebrae), smaller head (23.9% SL vs 24.5–28.0% SL), and relatively deeper body (16.3% SL vs 12.5–15.0% SL).
</p>
            <p>
It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata</tp:taxon-name>
by having a much longer lateral line (ending at the 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray vs ending at the 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray), fewer dorsal-fin rays (86 vs 92), more pectoral-fin rays (32 vs 26), shorter pelvic-fin rays (10.9% SL vs 15.0% SL) and longer gill raker on the first arch (2.1% SL vs 0.7% SL). A detailed comparison between the new species and other congeners is provided in 
Table 2
.
</p>
            <p>
Along the 
COI
gene, the following apomorphic sites are unique nucleotides from the only specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
examined here; these nucleotide sites can be used for the molecular diagnosis of the species to differentiate it from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheni</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
examined in this study. Nos. 97 (C vs T), 120 (A vs G), 147 (G vs A), 177 (G vs A), 180 (C vs T), 198 (C vs T), 219 (T vs C), 225 (C vs T), 294 (C vs T), 321 (A vs C), 324 (G vs A), 330 (A vs G), 336 (A vs C), 348 (G vs A or C), 363 (G vs T or C), 369 (T vs C), 372 (A vs C or T), 375 (C vs T), 381 (G vs A), 387 (C vs T), 390 (T vs C), 405 (C vs T), 420 (A vs G or C), 426 (T vs C), 465 (A vs C or G), 477 (A vs G), 540 (A vs G), 555 (G vs A), 565 (T vs C), 597 (T vs C), 603 (T vs A), 615 (C vs A), 648 (T vs C), 682 (C vs A or G), 675 (C vs T), 684 (G vs A), 687 (T vs C).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology</p>
            <p>
The name 
<tp:taxon-name>polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
is derived from the Greek ‘ 
poly
’, meaning ‘many’ or ‘numerous’, and ‘ 
lepis
’, meaning ‘scales’, in reference to the much longer lateral line and therefore more lateral line scales compared with 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi</tp:taxon-name>
, the only congener distributed in the West Pacific.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type material</p>
            <p>Holotype</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>
SOLOMON SEA • 
168.4 mm
SL, sample ID: 
PNG2363
; 
Ainto Bay
, 
SE of New Britain Island
, 
Papua New Guinea
, 
Solomon Sea
, 
West Pacific
, stn CP4334; 
6°08′ S
, 
149°10′ E
; 
430–620 m
depth

; 
6 May 2014
; R/V 
ALIS
; French beam trawl; MADEEP expedition; GenBank registration: 
MW218670
; 
NTUM 11915
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description</p>
            <p>
Measurements and counts of the 
holotype
given in 
Table 2
. Body elongate with tapering caudal portion, snout and head slightly depressed; eye small and round, horizontal eye diameter about half of snout length. Mouth large, oblique; upper jaw reaching a vertical through the posterior margin of orbit, posterior part vertically much extended, slightly protruding beyond lower jaw when mouth closed. Boomerang-formed vomer; palatine, and upper and lower jaw with many small, close-set, rather blunt teeth in several irregular rows; fang-like teeth absent in both jaws. One median and a pair of two large basibranchial tooth patches. Anterior nostril with low rim and placed midway between upper lip and posterior nostril, with small rounded flap rising from anterior rim. Posterior margins of preopercle, interopercle, and subopercle rounded, without spine. First gill arch with four finely dentigerous plates on upper branch, one long raker on the angle, and lower branch with two long rakers interspaced with 10 dentigerous plates (

); gill filaments ca 100, the longest about half as long as longest gill raker; pseudobranchial filament damaged, unavailable count.
</p>
            <p>
Sensory pores are found all over head (

). Supraorbital with group of eight pores behind eye, five pores immediately above eye, and five small pores in a row on tip of snout, larger pore between flaps on tip of snout, and above each nostril, one interorbital pore, four occipital pores, six suborbital pores and four mandibular pores, 10 small pores close to lower jaw, between this row and mandibular having four small pores, and finally a row of six pores above posterior mandibular, two pores behind posterior end of maxilla, and preopercle with six pores.
</p>
            <p>
Sagittal otolith is elongate and thin, about 2.5 times as long as high. Sulcus divided into ostium and cauda. Cauda is about ⅔ of ostium (

). Due to the damaged anterior rim, the presence of an ostial channel could not be ascertained.
</p>
            <p>
Body, top of head, and opercle covered with small cycloid scales, with ca 72 scales in oblique line from origin of anal fin forwards and ca 111 scales from upper part of gill slit to base of caudal fin; single lateral line originating at upper angle of opercle and extending posteriorly in straight line placed about midway between midline and profile of body, ending below 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray. Dorsal-fin origin above end of pectoral fin; anal-fin origin at about mid-body of fish, pectoral fin placed medially and pelvic fin reaching one third from base to anal fin.
</p>
            <p>
Third neural spine pointed, length of first spine half as long as second spine (

), neural spines of posterior 10 pre-caudal vertebrae with blunt tips and broad bases, 4 
th
–11 
th
precaudal vertebrae with broad bases and depressed neural spines, 7 
th
–13 
th
precaudal vertebrae with parapophyses, and pleural ribs on 3 
rd
–6 
th
precaudal vertebrae. Epipleural ribs hard to observe.
</p>
            <p>
Head brown; body brownish-yellow with bluish-brown abdomen (

). Dorsal, pectoral, anal, and caudal fins black. Color of preserved specimen similar to that of fresh specimens, the head and body uniformly brown with dark bluish-brown abdomen (

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution</p>
            <p>
Possibly endemic to waters off 
Papua New Guinea
; the only known specimen was collected on the SE continental slope of 
New Britain
Island, 
Papua New Guinea
, at depths of 
430–620 m
(

).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Accompanying fauna</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Monomitopus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Glyptophidium lucidum
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
were the only two other ophidiids collected along with 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, in addition to 
<tp:taxon-name>Epigonus atherinoides
(Gilbert, 1905)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Epigonidae Poey, 1861</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Okamoto 
et al.
2018

). The mud bottom living invertebrates collected from the same site included sea cradles, sea snails, sea stars, deep-sea barnacles, decapods (https://expeditions.mnhn.fr/campaign/madeep/event/cp4334#les_photos), and a recently described deep-sea spider crab, 
<tp:taxon-name>Tunepugettia corbariae
Lee, Richer de Forges &amp; Ng 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Epialtidae MacLeay, 1838</tp:taxon-name>
) (Lee B.-Y. 
et al
. 2019).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
(modified from 
Nielsen 2009
)
</p>
            <p>1. Precaudal vertebrae 13; total vertebrae 50 or 51 ............................................................................... 2</p>
            <p>– Precaudal vertebrae 15 or 16; total vertebrae 52–57 ......................................................................... 3</p>
            <p>
2. Lateral line ending at 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray; total gill rakers 13–14 .......................................................... ............................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>L. brasiliensisNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
(off 
Brazil
)
</p>
            <p>
– Lateral line ending at 33 
rd
dorsal-fin ray; total gill rakers 17 ............................................................... .................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. polylepis</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(off 
Papua New Guinea
)
</p>
            <p>
3. Lateral line short and distinct, ending at 2 
nd
dorsal-fin ray .... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. lineata
(Gosline, 1954)
</tp:taxon-name>
(off 
Hawaii
)
</p>
            <p>
– Lateral line long, usually indistinct, ending at 19 
th
–37 
th
dorsal-fin ray.............................................. 4
</p>
            <p>
4. Dorsal-fin rays 81–89;anal-fin rays59–65;first gill arch with3developed rakers and 18–23dentigerous plates; longest filaments on first gill arch 2.8–3.6% SL ......... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. coheniNielsen, 2009</tp:taxon-name>
(East Pacific)
</p>
            <p>– Dorsal-fin rays 86–96; anal-fin rays 66–75; first gill arch with 3–4 developed rakers and 12–18 dentigerous plates; longest filaments on fist gill arch 1.3–2.7% SL.................................................. 5</p>
            <p>
5. Four occipital pores, one interorbital pore; first anal-fin ray below 18 
th
–24 
th
dorsal-fin rays; dorsal rim of otolith without concavity (large specimens)............................................................................. ................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. bartschi
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
(Indo-West Pacific)
</p>
            <p>
– Pores absent on occipital and interorbital region; first anal-fin ray below 24 
th
–28 
th
dorsal-fin rays; dorsal rim of otolith with or without concavity ................................................................................. 6
</p>
            <p>
6. Head brown; otolith with a distinct concavity in dorsal rim in specimens larger than 
300 mm
SL; total vertebrae 56–57; longest pelvic-fin ray 7.9–9.6% SL ................................................................. .................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. corethromycterCohen, 1964</tp:taxon-name>
(
Gulf
of 
Mexico
, Caribbean Sea)
</p>
            <p>
– Head pale; otolith without a distinct concavity in dorsal rim in specimens larger than 
300 mm
SL; total vertebrae 53–55; longest pelvic-fin ray 11.0–12.5% SL.............................................................. ...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nolfiCohen, 1981</tp:taxon-name>
(tropical East Atlantic)
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
BISMARCK SEA • 
<tp:material-citation>393.7 mm
SL; Cape Croisilles off Papua New Guinea, stn CP4033; 
4°52′ S
, 
145°53′ E
; 
780 m
depth

; R/V ALIS, beam trawl, PAPUA NIUGINI expedition; 
16 Dec. 2012
; 
NTUM 16627
(tissue sample ID: 
PNG1082
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>EAST CHINA SEA</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>181.6 mm
SL; stn CD210, 
24° 28′ N
, 
122° 12′ E
; 
1185 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
30 May 2003
; 
ASIZP0063749</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
PHILIPPINE SEA • 
<tp:material-citation>301.7 mm
SL; stn CP2729, 
15°19′ N
, 
121°37′ E
; 
593–600 m
depth

; R/V DA-BFAR, beam trawl, AURORA expedition; 
31 May 2007
; 
ASIZP 0068164
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP 0913925
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
227.4 mm
SL; Dashi fishing port; 
23 May 2007
; 
ASIZP0070170</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
97.9 mm
SL; 
South China Sea
, 
NE of Dongsha Island
; stn CD321; 
20° 43′ N
, 
117° 32′ E
; 
954 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
19 Aug. 2005
; 
ASIZP 0066071
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP0911588
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>TAIWAN
• 
202 mm
SL; 
South China Sea
, 
SE of Little Liuqiu Island
; 
22° 12′ N
, 
120° 23′ E
; 
68–347 m
depth

; beam trawl; 
29 Jul. 2014
; 
ASIZP 0075076
(tissue sample ID: 
ASIZP 0916618
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
   </body>
</article>
