<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3826.3.4</journal-id>
         <issn>1175-5326</issn>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Pothea berengeri sp. nov. from Brazil, with taxonomic notes on Pothea furtadoi Gil-Santana &amp; Costa and Pothea jaguaris (Carpintero) and reinstatement of Parapothea Carpintero as junior synonym of Pothea Amyot &amp; Serville (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae: Ectrichodiinae)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2014</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from 
Brazil
, with taxonomic notes on 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
and reinstatement of 
Parapothea
Carpintero as junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Hemiptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Heteroptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
)
</p>
         <p>HÉLCIO R. GIL-SANTANA</p>
         <p>
Laboratório de 
<tp:taxon-name>Diptera</tp:taxon-name>
, and Programa de Pós-Graduação em Biodiversidade e Saúde, Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Rio de Janeiro, 
Brazil
. E-mail: helciogil@uol.com.br; helciogil@ioc.fiocruz.br
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="abstract">
         <title>Abstract</title>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov
.
</named-content>
from 
Brazil
is described based on male and female specimens. Based on intraspecific variation of 

Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
and morphological similarities with the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
studied, the monotypic genus 
Parapothea
Carpintero is reinstated as a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
with the subsequent combination 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Intraspecific morphological and color variations of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
are documented and discussed. Male genitalia of all three species are described and illustrated. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
is recorded from 
French Guiana
for the first time and comments on its sexual dimorphism are provided.
</p>
         <p>Key words:<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
, Neotropical Region, new species, color variation
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="introduction">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <p>
In the Americas, 
23
genera and more than one hundred species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
have been described (Maldonado 
1990
, 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado 
1996
, 

Bérenger &amp; Gil-Santana 
2005
, 

Gil-Santana &amp; Baena 
2009
, 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

).
</p>
         <p>
In the revision of the New World 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
, 

Dougherty (
1995
)

recognized 
19
valid genera, some of which were discordant to the 
17
accepted by 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado (
1996
)

. Among these, 
Parapothea
Carpintero, 
1980
and 
Jorgcoris
Carpintero, 
1980
were considered as synonyms of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843</tp:taxon-name>
by 

Dougherty (
1995
)

. Dougherty argued “these taxa represent unique variations from what is already seen in the diverse 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
the difference does not appear great enough to warrant generic status.” 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado (
1996
)

either did not recognize or overlooked this synonymy (

Forero 
2006
), and since then, the genus has been recognized as valid by 
Forero (2004
, 
2006
). 

Carpintero (
1980
)

also created a new subgenus, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea
(
Brachypothea
) 

Carpintero, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
with 
<tp:taxon-name>P. hepperi
Carpintero, 
1978</tp:taxon-name>
as the 
type
species and described two more species in this subgenus, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. yungaensis
Carpintero, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. carvalhoi
Carpintero, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
. By consequence, in his catalogue, Maldonado (
1990
) considered only these three species as included in 
P.
(
Brachypothea
) and more than 
25
other species as belonging to 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea
(
Pothea
) 

Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843</tp:taxon-name>
. In addition to arguing that 
<tp:taxon-name>P. aeneonitens
Stål, 
1864</tp:taxon-name>
“may fit” in 
P.
(
Brachypothea
), 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado (
1990
)

included five more species in 
P.
(
Brachypothea
) in their species key to this subgenus. 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado (
1996
)

included 
21
species in 
P.
(
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
) and nine species in 
P.
(
Brachypothea
). 

Dougherty (
1995
)

made no mention of the subgenera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
, while 
Forero (2004
, 
2006
) considered them as valid.
</p>
         <p>
Recently, 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. (
2013
a)

included all genera considered valid by 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado (
1996
)

and those described by 

Dougherty (
1995
)

and 

Bérenger &amp; Gil-Santana (
2005
)

in their key to New World genera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
. The genera can be recognized from this compilation.
</p>
         <p>
In 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
, the longitudinal sulcus on the anterior lobe of the pronotum has been considered obsolete, reduced to a medial or discal fovea by 

Carpintero (
1978
)

and 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado (
1996
)

. However, in a footnote (page 
185
), 

Carpintero (
1978
)

mentioned that the longitudinal sulcus on the anterior lobe of the pronotum in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
could be exceptionally straight and profound without reaching the transverse furrow. 

Dougherty (
1995
)

considered the mid-longitudinal furrow well developed or weakly developed anteriorly in this genus. When describing 
Parapothea
, 

Carpintero (
1980
)

considered it close to 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea sensu strictu</tp:taxon-name>
, from which could be distinguished by very strong legs, a divided pronotum and a distinct coloration. In a key to the genera of New World 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
, 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado (
1996
)

diagnosed 
Parapothea
as possessing the anterior lobe of the pronotum with 
1
+ 
1
paramedial lobes, the shiny yellowish-brown with jaguar-like spots, the longitudinal sulcus not reaching transverse constriction and the body size of 
17 mm
. Being the 
type
species and currently only included in 
Parapothea
(

Forero 
2006
), 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris
Carpintero, 
1980</tp:taxon-name>
was described from a single female specimen from 
Bolivia
(

Carpintero 
1980
). This species was later recorded by 

Gil-Santana (
2007
)

from 
Brazil
based on a single female as well. 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado (
1996
)

presented figures of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
that appeared to be based on the 
holotype
. 
Forero (2004
, 
2006
) regarded 
Parapothea
as valid and considered it distinguishable from other Neotropical 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
by the presence of two protuberant hemispherical lobes on the anterior pronotal lobe (

Forero 
2006
). He considered this character consistent between the 
type
species (i.e., 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
) and an undescribed species examined by him, and thus of generic value (

Forero 
2006
). This undescribed species of 
Parapothea
differs notably in coloration from 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris
(

Forero 
2006
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Until formal description of the new species observed by 

Forero (
2006
)

, 
Parapothea
will remain as monotypic. On the other hand, 

Forero (
2004
)

recorded that the undescribed species of 
Parapothea
had a particular feature, which was a small tubercle in the center of gula. This author also considered that if this tubercle could be found in the 
type
species of the genus then it could be regarded as an autapomorphy, since it has not been identified in other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
Interestingly, when describing 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea
, 

Amyot &amp; Serville (
1843
)
</tp:taxon-name>
recorded its prothorax with a pronounced longitudinal furrow that crossed the transverse sulcus. These authors included two species in the genus, 
<tp:taxon-name>P. frontalis
(

Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P
. 
ventralis
(

Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, furnishing only details of their coloration. However, in descriptions of these species as 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduvius frontalis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>R. ventralis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
by 

Lepeletier &amp; Serville (
1825
)

, diagnosis for both included “ 
thorace cruciatim sulcato
”, which seems to correspond to medial or discal fovea (

Carpintero 
1978
, 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado 
1996
), together with the transverse sulcus on the pronotum of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
“ 
<named-content content-type="taxonStatus">s. str
.
</named-content>
” (

Carpintero 
1980
).
</p>
         <p>
Intra-specific variation in coloration and body size have been recorded in several species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
. These characteristics can occur in the same population or suggests geographic variation of the same species (

Wygodzinsky 
1951
, 

Dougherty 
1995
, 

Gil-Santana &amp; Baena 
2009
, 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

). Color variation in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
species was recorded in the revision of the genus by 

Carpintero (
1978
)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa, 
2005</tp:taxon-name>
was described based on two males showing variation in color, particularly in the dark markings of sternites (

Gil-Santana &amp; Costa 
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
The antennae of most New World 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
males are pubescent on all segments with short hairs becoming more abundant on the distal segments. For females, at least the first and often the basal half of the second segment are bare or very sparsely pubescent and the distal segments have increasingly sparse elongate hairs (

Dougherty 
1995
). In 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
, all antennal segments have conspicuous pilosity, and occasionally the first segment is slightly hairy or glabrous in females (

Carpintero 
1978
). Sexual dimorphism varies: females are frequently submacropterous and almost always slightly larger than males, and have reduced eyes and ocelli. Basal antennal segments of females are bare, and the denticulate clypeus frequently seen in males is occasionally found in females (

Dougherty 
1995
). 

Wygodzinsky (
1951
)

recorded absence of hairs on the antennal basal segments in males of 
<tp:taxon-name>Brontostoma decolor
(Walker, 
1873
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>B. rubrum
(

Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Of note, while 

Carpintero (
1980
)

considered these two species as synonymies, Maldonado (
1990
) cited both as valid.
</p>
         <p>
Male genital characteristics have been found to be of little use in the taxonomy of Neotropical 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
(

Dougherty 
1995
; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado 
1996
). 

Dougherty (
1995
)

took the position that there were so few sclerotized structures in the phallus of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
that there were no apparent differences among the various genera, with just a pair of sclerotized plates at the distal tip of the inflated endosoma. 

Carpintero (
1978
)

recorded that the endosoma in some 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
spp. has an apical sclerotized portion and there might be lateral sclerotized processes in it as well. Gil-Santana 
et al.
(
2005
), 

Gil-Santana &amp; Baena (
2009
)

and 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. (
2013
a)

, however, documented differences in the male genitalic structures of some 
<tp:taxon-name>Brontostoma</tp:taxon-name>
species (
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
), highlighting the value of this character system for taxonomic and systematic studies.
</p>
         <p>
On the other hand, in other reduviids, variability in external color and/or diverse geographical origins have been associated with a variation in the structure of male genitalia, 
e.g
., in 
<tp:taxon-name>Triatoma dimidiata
(Latreille, 
1811
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Triatominae</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Lent &amp; Jurberg 
1985
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Zelus tetracanthus
Stål, 
1862</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Zelus luridus
Stål, 
1862
(

Hart 
1986
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Graptocleptes bicolor
(Burmeister, 
1838
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
b

) (
<tp:taxon-name>Harpactorinae</tp:taxon-name>
). Yet, in 
<tp:taxon-name>Apiomerus flaviventris
Herrich-Schäffer, 
1846</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Harpactorinae</tp:taxon-name>
), a considerable variation in color as well as in male genitalia were recorded, with no genitalic patterns corresponding to either color or geographical differences (

Berniker 
et al
. 
2011
). Conversely, in 
<tp:taxon-name>Apiomerus barrocoloradoi
Forero, Berniker &amp; Szerlip, 
2010</tp:taxon-name>
, despite the highly variable coloration, the male genitalia exhibited very little intraspecific variation (

Forero 
et al
. 
2010
). Finally, for 
<tp:taxon-name>Triatoma infestans
(Klug, 
1834
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, which is a species with “stable external characters” (

Lent &amp; Jurberg 
1985
), the dissection of the male genitalia of specimens from different regions or populations showed only a small variability in struts and endosomal processes (

Lent &amp; Jurberg 
1985
, 

Pires 
et al
. 
1998
).
</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov
.
</named-content>
from 
Brazil
is described based on male and female specimens. Intraspecific morphological and color variation of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
are documented and discussed. Male genitalia of all three species are described. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
is recorded from 
French Guiana
for the first time and comments on its sexual dimorphism are provided. Based on intraspecific variation of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
and morphological similarities with the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
studied, 
Parapothea
is reinstated as a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
with the subsequent combination 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Materials and methods</title>
         <p>
Observations were done with a stereoscope microscope (Zeiss Stemi®), and a compound microscope (Leica CME®). Measurements were made with a micrometer eyepiece and expressed in millimeters (mm). Dissections of male genitalia were made by removing the pygophore from the abdomen with a pair of forceps, which was cleared in KOH solution for 
24
hours. The phallus was everted by carefully pulling the dorsal endosomal processes with a pair of fine forceps. Dissected structures were studied and photographed in glycerin. Adults and genitalia images were taken with digital cameras (Sony DSC-W 
570
® and DSC-HX 
200
V®). All drawings were made using a 
camera lucida
.
</p>
         <p>
Specimens are deposited in the Entomological Collections of the “Museu de Entomologia Padre Jesus Santiago Moure” (
DZUP
), Universidade Federal do Paraná, Curitiba, Paraná, “Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas da Amazônia” (
INPA
), Manaus, Amazonas, and “Museu Nacional da Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro” (
MNRJ
), Rio de Janeiro, 
Brazil
.
</p>
         <p>
The [visible] segments of the labium are numbered II to IV, given the first segment is said to be lost or fused to the head capsule (

Weirauch 
2008
). In addition, according to 

Schuh 
et al
. (
2009
)

, for the convention of numbering labial segments in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
, the apical segment should be considered as number four and then counted backward towards the base.
</p>
         <p>
As noted by 

Carpintero (
1978
)

, in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
, there are only six apparent sternites, whereas the first “visible” sternite is really the second. As such, the sternites are numbered II to VII.
</p>
         <p>
The nomenclature of the male genitalia portions used here mostly follows Lent &amp; Wygodzinsky (
1979
). However, “vesica” as recognized by these authors has been considered to be absent in reduviids. The assumed equivalent structure in reduviids is a somewhat sclerotized appendage of the phallosoma or the endosoma (

Forero &amp; Weirauch 
2012
), but not the homologous vesica that occurs in other heteropterans such as Pentatomomorpha (

Rédei &amp; Tsai 
2011
). Thus, this term is used herein for the median process of endosoma, which is named as such.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Taxonomy</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
Subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
         </title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
: 
344</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Reduvius ventralis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
: 
280</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa, 
2005
: 
400</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
P. 
jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pothea berengeri sp. nov. from Brazil, with taxonomic notes on Pothea furtadoi Gil-Santana &amp; Costa and Pothea jaguaris (Carpintero) and reinstatement of Parapothea Carpintero as junior synonym of Pothea Amyot &amp; Serville (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae: Ectrichodiinae)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3826.3.4</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFD1FF98A516FFECFFC4FFC3DD1D3964</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3826.3.4</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Figures 
1
–14, 15– 
28
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
Figures 
29–47
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
, REINSTATED COMBINATION

Figures 
48–71
, 

Tables 
1–4
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
: 
344</tp:taxon-name>
–345 [description]; 

Stål, 
1859
, 176 [key], 
184
[redescription], 
184–185
[checklist of species]; 

Stål, 
1872
: 
101
[key], 
103–104
[checklist and key to species]; 

Walker, 
1873
a

: 
47
[key], 
80
[key]; 

Walker, 
1873
b

: 
63
–64 [checklist and key to four species]; 

Lethierry &amp; Severin, 
1896
: 
131
[catalog]; 

Champion, 
1898
: 
221
[diagnosis, key to Central American species]; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1949
: 
23
[catalog]; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1951
: 
36
[key]; 

Carpintero, 
1978
: 
177
–286 [revision of the genus and Argentinean species]; 

Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
[diagnosis]; 

Putshkov &amp; Putshkov, 
1985
: 
16
[catalog]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
65–67
[catalog]; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
202
[key], 
211–212
[diagnosis, checklist of species]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
126
[key], 
135–136
[diagnosis]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[diagnosis], 
181–182
[key]; 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

: 
71
[key].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduvius ventralis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
: 
280</tp:taxon-name>
, by subsequent designation: 

Van Duzee, 
1916
: 
29
.
</p>
            <p>Anapothea
Miller, 
1956
: 
8
; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1959
: 
297
[as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
]. 
Type
species: 
Anapothea amoena
Miller, 
1956
: 
8
, by original designation.
</p>
            <p>Parapothea
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
[description]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
64
[catalog]; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
211
[as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
126
[key], 
134–135
[diagnosis]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[diagnosis], 
181
[key]; 

Forero, 
2006
: 
8
[discussion on validity]; 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

: 
71
[key]; 
REINSTATED SYNONYMY
.
</p>
            <p>Type
species: 

Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
, by original designation.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking sexual dimorphism in males, with first antennal segment almost completely glabrous and second antennal with short pilosity. The rounded tylus, size of male ocelli equal to females; and eyes somewhat smaller than eyes of female are also diagnostic. Females with hemelytra somewhat longer or reaching the tip of abdomen; male hemelytra shorter, not reaching the tip of the abdomen (Figs. 1, 15, 
24
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description.Male
. MEASUREMENTS: Total length: 
17.3
; head: total length (including collum): 4.0; maximum width across the eyes: 
1.6
; ante-ocular length: 
1.9
; post-ocular length: 
1.6
; interocular space: 
0.9
; transverse width of right eye: 
0.3
; length of right eye, measured from above: 
0.5
; ocellar tubercle width: 
0.6
; right ocellus width: 
0.18
; antennal segments: I: 2.0; II: 3.0; III: 
1.2
; IV: 
0.7
; V: 
0.55
; VI: 
0.4
; VII: 
0.35
; VIII: 
0.5
; labium segments: II [first visible]: 
2.5
; III: 1.0; IV: 
0.5
. Thorax: pronotum: fore lobe length: 
1.2
; hind lobe: length: 
2.4
; width at posterior margin: 
4.2
; scutellum: length: 
1.7
; width at base: 
1.9
. Legs: fore legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 4.0; tarsus: 
1.4
; middle legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 4.0; tarsus: 
1.5
; hind legs: femur: 5.0; tibia: 
5.5
; tarsus: 
1.7
. Abdomen: length: 
8.6
; maximum width: 
5.1
. COLORATION: General coloration yellowish-orange to orange-red, with reddish, brownish or blackish markings (Figs. 1, 5). 
Head
(Fig. 
1
): with reddish markings along midline, more prominent on clypeus, almost all ocellar tubercle red, antennal tubercles and around eyes also red; well marked blackish spots behind ocelli and very faint ones in front of them, both on the ocellar tubercle; eyes blackish. Antenna: first antennal segment orange-yellowish; second segment somewhat dark, orange-yellowish basally; other segments darkened to brownish, except on the joints, which are clear, yellowish to whitish. 
Thorax
(Figs. 1, 5– 
6
). Pronotum: anterior margin, anterior portion of longitudinal sulcus, lateral portions of the transverse sulcus, lateral stripe on anterior portion of propleura, and a somewhat rounded spot on posterior portion of propleura slightly dark to brownish. Central portion and lateral margins of scutellum dark. Meso and metapleura and sterna darkened, intersegmental sutures around metapleura marked with black. Apical third of femora somewhat reddish. Hemelytra: corium somewhat orange-yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum blackish except at base; a pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion; subapical lateral portion somewhat reddish, apex darkened; membrane dark brown. 
Abdomen
(Figs. 1, 7). Connexivum orange in internal portion, dorsally, and reddish in external portion, dorsally and ventrally; sternites orange-yellowish, with the distal portion of sternite VII, posterior to pygophore, as reddish as connexivum; sternite II [first visible] without dark markings; intersegmental area between sternites II and III, where there are canaliculae, somewhat darkened; other sternites with small dark, brownish to blackish markings as follows: lateral subsquared or subrounded markings on segments III–VI; a pair of small dark curved stripes on mid portion of sternites III–IV; curved bands, which are larger in their median portion, on midline of sternites V and VI, the latter smaller; sternite VII with a very faint dark spot just anterior to pygophore and lateral small rounded dark markings; area around spiracles somewhat darkened as well. VESTITURE: Integument almost completely glabrous and shiny (Figs. 
1
–2, 5– 
7
). Antennae with first segment almost completely glabrous, with just a small yellowish-orange seta on the middle of internal face in the right antenna; basal portion of segment II glabrous; remainder of this segment and others covered with moderately short setae and a few longer ones; on segment II, the short setae length are approximately half the width of the segment, while the length of 
PLATE1
.

Figs. 
1–7
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, male 
holotype
, 
1
, dorsal view, 
2
, head, lateral view, 
3–4
, right antenna, dorsal view, 
4
, segment I and proximal portion of segment II, the arrow points to a setae, 
5
, pronotum and scutellum, dorsal view, 
6
, pronotum, lateral view, 
7
, abdomen, ventral view.
</p>
            <p>
the few longer setae are approximately 
1.2
times the width of the segment (Figs. 
3–4
). Labium with yellowish to orange sparse setae on ventral face of basal portion of labial segment II, apex of labial segment III, and on base, dorsally, and apex of labial segment IV (Fig. 
2
). Legs with short hairs on fore and median trochanters and a mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange very short hairs on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration. STRUCTURE: Head elongated; clypeus elevated and rounded; eyes moderate size; ocellar tubercle prominent, undivided; labium thick, segment II longer than the others together and surpassing posterior margin of eyes (Figs. 
1–2
); antennae eight-segmented (Fig. 
3
). Pronotum: anterior margin as a thin collar; surface smooth with a pair of short, rounded tubercles medially just between anterior and posterior lobes of pronotum; longitudinal sulcus on anterior lobe shallow, somewhat more profound in second half; in first half of posterior lobe it is represented only by four small punctures, the most anterior just below the pair of rounded tubercles; transverse (interlobar) sulcus formed by small and shallow impressions (canaliculae); both sulci interrupted medially by the pair of tubercles, not reaching each other. Lateral sulcus of posterior lobe of pronotum weak, formed by shallow canaliculae anteriorly; humeral angles rounded. Scutellum with a deep median depression; prongs short and convergent (Figs. 1, 5– 
6
). Legs slender; fore and mid femora somewhat thicker than hind ones; these latter slightly thick subapically; protibia conspicuously thick at apex, mainly in anterior portion; other tibiae less thick 
PLATE2
.

Figs. 
8–14
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
holotype
, male genitalia, 
8–9
, pygophore and parameres, 
8
, ventral view, 
9
, dorsal view, 
10
, median process of pygophore, 
11
, left paramere, ventral and dorsal view, respectively, 
12–13
, phallus, 
12
, lateral view, 
13
, dorsal view, 
14
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view.
</p>
            <p>
at apex, mid pair a little more than hind tibiae; small spongy fossa on pro and mid tibiae; presence of a median ventral shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted, on fore and mid femora and all tibiae, less marked on hind ones. Hemelytra not reaching tip of abdomen (Fig. 
1
). Connexivum, in lateral view, with postero-lateral angles somewhat prominent, which is more accentuated in segment II. Sternites II and III separated by canaliculae; other intersternite furrow more evident in median portion and almost imperceptible laterally (Fig. 
7
). 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
8–14
): pygophore sub-squared, posterior margin sinuate; parameres apices close in resting position (Figs. 
8–9
). Median process of pygophore sclerotized, apex rounded (Figs. 
9–10
). Parameres symmetrical, curved, somewhat enlarged, truncated at apex, with short slots on median and medial portion and a small tooth at lateral portion of the apex (Figs. 
8
–9, 11). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately short, subretangular; phalothecal dorsal plate somewhat elongated with angles rounded, sinuous in center of anterior margin; struts rather enlarged at basal half, united at the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
12–13
). Median process of endosoma subtriangular, apex rounded, with a central sclerotized structure, which has three divergent branches directed upward (Fig. 
14
). 
Female
: MEASUREMENTS: Total length: 
17–17.5
; head: total length (including collum): 
4.2–4.4
; maximum width across the eyes: 
1.6–1.7
; ante-ocular length: 
1.8
–2.0; post-ocular length: 
1.6–1.8
; interocular space: 
0.9
–1.0; transverse width of right eye: 
0.35
; length of right eye, measured from above: 
0.6–0.7
; ocellar tubercle width: 
0.6–0.8
; right ocellus width: 
0.18–0.20
; antennal segments: I: 
1.9
–2.0; II: 
3.2–3.5
; III: 
1.3–1.4
; IV: 
0.8–0.9
; [V–VIII, absent in one 
paratype
]; V: 
0.6
; VI: 
0.4
; VII: 
0.4
; VIII: 
0.6
; labial segments: II [first visible]: 
2.7–2.8
; III: 
1.2
; IV: 
0.5
. Thorax: pronotum: fore lobe length: 1.0 – 
1.3
; hind lobe: length: 
2.3–2.4
; width at posterior margin: 
4.6–4.7
; scutellum: length: 
1.6–1.8
; width at base: 2.0– 
2.4
. Legs: fore legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 
4.3
; tarsus: 
1.4–1.5
; middle legs: femur: 
4.1–4.2
; tibia: 4.0– 
4.2
; tarsus: 
1.6
; hind legs: femur: 
5.4
; tibia: 
5.8
–6.0; tarsus: 
1.8
. Abdomen: length: 
8.5–9.3
; maximum width: 
5.6–5.9
. COLORATION: similar to male. General coloration is reddish to clear (Figs. 15, 24). 
Head
: the reddish markings on the head smaller than male or absent (Figs. 16, 19). 
Thorax
: a pair of suboval faint brownish median spots present on hind lobe of pronotum (Figs. 15, 19, 24, 27); propleura with a dark faint and irregular stripe on upper portion; meso and metapleurae and sterna fairly dark; pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion of corium of hemelytra present (Fig. 
15
) and can form a darkened larger spot (Fig. 
24
); sternite II with a pair of sublateral brownish faint sublateral stripes, and five pairs of subquadrate to subtriangular lateral spots on sternites III–VII, and a small median spot on sternite III and median bands on sternites IV–VI, which are larger in the middle portion, especially in sternite VI and almost reach the lateral spots on sternites IV–V and right side of sternite VI, joining the lateral spot in left side of sternite VI (Fig. 
22
). STRUCTURE: Head somewhat larger in profile (Fig. 
16
); first antennal segment completely glabrous (Figs. 
17–18
) or with ten setae on the internal face of this segment (Figs. 
25–26
). Hemelytra can reach tip of abdomen (Fig. 
24
). 
Female genitalia
: Posterior view of external genitalia as Fig. 
23
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.Brazil
, states of Mato Grosso and Bahia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The new species is named in honor of the French entomologist, Jean-Michel Bérenger, for his great contribution to the study of 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>PLATE3
.

Figs. 
15–22
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, female 
paratype
, specimen from Bahia, 
Brazil
, 
15
, dorsal view, 
16
, head, lateral view, 
17– 18
, right antenna, proximal segments, dorsal view, 
19
, head and pronotum, dorsal view, 
20
, fore femur, lateral view, 
21
, fore tibia and tarsus, dorsal view, 
22
, ventral view.
</p>
            <p>PLATE4
.

Figs. 
23– 28
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, female 
paratype
, 
23
, specimen from Bahia, external genitalia, posterior view, 
24–28
, 
paratype
from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
24
, dorsal view, 
25–26
, right antenna, dorsal view, 
26
, segment I, 
27
, pronotum and scutellum, dorsal view, 
28
, ventral view.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
The following variability was present in the female 
paratype
of this species: the pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion of corium of hemelytra is somewhat smaller in one 
paratype
(Fig. 
15
) and forms a darkened larger spot in the 
paratype
with reddish coloration (Fig. 
24
); the reddish markings on the head was absent in the 
paratype
with clear coloration. The sternites in the other 
paratype
have a brighter coloration, almost yellowish, while the markings are darker, except on sternite II, in which, besides smaller, forming spots, they are fainter; the median bands are larger in the middle portion and do not reach the lateral spots in any segment; on the sternites V–VI they form subtriangular spots and not bands; the lateral markings on sternite VII are much smaller, simple dots (Fig. 
28
). The 
paratype
with reddish coloration has a somewhat thicker fore and mid femora and the hemelytra reaches the tip of the abdomen. Despite the mentioned variation, all the common features between the females, particularly in the structure of head and pronotum, are prone to consider them as conspecific.
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
Holotype
: 
BRAZIL
, Mato Grosso,

Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
20
.X. 
1983
, J. Becker, O. Roppa &amp; B.S. 
leg.
[
MNRJ
]; 
1
male

. 
Paratypes
: 
BRAZIL
, Bahia,

Encruzilhada, BR 
116
, Divisa, XI.[
19
] 
74
, O. Roppa 
leg
., 
1
female

; 
Mato Grosso,
Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
10
.X. 
1988
, O. Roppa &amp; J. Becker 
leg
. [
MNRJ
], 
1
female

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa, 
2005
: 
400</tp:taxon-name>
–404 [description].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.Male:
Total length: 18.0–21.0; COLORATION: general coloration mostly reddish, but somewhat brighter in a few specimens, with darkened or blackish markings; legs with submedian small markings on femora; variable extent and intensity of darkness on femoral apices and subbasal and apical rings on tibiae; variation also present on the corium of hemelytra, which is reddish on most extension or somewhat brighter to almost yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum, apex and a stripe in the central portion, brownish to blackish, and variable dark coloration (Figs.
</p>
            <p>29
–30, 41, 
44
). Connexivum reddish, without markings (Figs. 29, 41) or yellowish, with approximately two thirds of each segment pink colored distally (Fig. 
44
). Blackish markings on the sternites III–VII form transverse stripes, variable in thickness, enlarged at the lateral portion, anterior extension in front of the respective spiracle in the sternites III–VI sometimes present (Fig. 
32
). These stripes are interrupted or incomplete in two or three segments, in which there are a median and a pair of lateral blackish markings instead of a stripe in some specimens (Figs. 42, 45– 
46
). STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Head: antenna eight segmented, all segments pubescent (Fig. 
31
); clypeus denticulate. Thorax: integument of pronotum smooth and shiny; midlongitudinal sulcus in anterior pronotal lobe not reaching interlobar sulcus, moderately deep; midlongitudinal (in the first half of posterior lobe), transverse (interlobar) and posterolateral sulci formed by canaliculae and well developed; humeral angles rounded (Figs. 
29
–30, 41, 
44
). Legs slender, femora, particularly fore and mid, somewhat thicker, with patches of slightly long yellowish hairs on ventral face of fore and mid trochanters and femora, in the latter, they are more numerous on the basal half; in some specimens these hairs are shorter or less numerous; mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange short hairs on median portion of ventral face of all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration; presence of a median ventral, shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; spongy fossa well developed on pro and mid tibiae. 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
33
–40, 43, 
47
): pygophore subpentagonal, posterior margin sinuate; paramere apices close in resting position (Figs. 
33–34
). Median process of pygophore somewhat elongated, subquadrate and sclerotized (Figs. 
34–35
). Parameres symmetrical, curved, with a short subapical tooth, rounded at apex (Figs. 
33
–34, 36). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately short; dorsal phallothecal plate lozenge shaped, sinuous in center of anterior margin, struts enlarged at basal half and united at the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
37–39
). Endosoma with a pair of lateral conjunctiva processes approximately at the median portion (Figs. 
37–38
). Median process of endosoma rounded, with central sclerotized structure somewhat like a “Y” (Fig. 
40
) or similar to a “T” (Figs. 43, 47).
</p>
            <p>PLATE5
.

Figs. 
29–36
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, males from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
29
, dorsal view, 
30
, head, pronotum and basal portion of hemelytra, dorsal view, 
31
, right antenna, segments I–III, dorsal view, 
32
, abdomen, latero-ventral view, 
33–36
, male genitalia, 
33–34
, pygophore and parameres, 
33
, ventral view, 
34
, dorsal view, 
35
, median process of pygophore, 
36
, right paramere, dorsal and ventral view, respectively.
</p>
            <p>PLATE6
. Figs. 
37–47
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
37–40
, male genitalia, specimen from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
37–39
, phallus, 
37
, lateral view, 
38
, latero-dorsal view, 
39
dorsal view, 
40
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, Figs. 
41–47
, males, 
41–43
, 
paratype
from Minas Gerais, 
Brazil
, 
41
, dorsal view, 
42
, ventral view, 
43
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, 
44–47
, specimen from Maranhão, 
Brazil
, 
44
, dorsal view, 
45
, ventral view, 
46
, latero-ventral view, 
47
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
There is size and morphological differences between the males of this species. The male from the state of Maranhão, for example, has a different coloration in connexivum (Fig. 
44
) and is smaller in total length, being 
17.1
millimeters. Variability in the dark markings of the body was also observed, particularly on the legs, with submedian small markings on femora in two specimens; variable extent and intensity of darkness on femoral apices and subbasal and apical rings on tibiae; variation also present on the corium of hemelytra, which is reddish on most extension or somewhat brighter to almost yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum, apex and a stripe in the central portion, brownish to blackish, and variable dark coloration (Figs. 
29
–30, 41, 
44
). However, as already described by 

Gil-Santana &amp; Costa (
2005
)

, the blackish markings on the sternites III–VII form transverse stripes, with some variability in thickness, enlarged at the lateral portion, where it may have an anterior extension in front of the respective spiracle in the sternites III–VI (Fig. 
32
). The different portions of male genitalia were shown to be similar among the specimens examined. The shapes of the dorsal phallotecal plate and struts are particularly characteristic (Fig. 
39
). The median process of the endosoma in males from different states of 
Brazil
and with very diverse coloration (Figs. 
29
–30, 32, 
41
–42, 44– 
46
) showed minor variation (Figs. 40, 43 and 
47
).
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
BRAZIL
, Bahia,

Encruzilhada, BR 
116
, Divisa, XI.[
19
] 
74
, O. Roppa 
leg
., 
1
male

[
MNRJ
]; 
Goiás
, Mambaí, Gruta [cavern] da Tarimba, 
29
.IV. 
2013
, M. E. Bichuette 
et al
. 
leg
., 
1
male

; 
Maranhão
, Caxias Inhamum (045439S - 
432616
W), 
535 m
, 
17
.V. 
2007
, Luz [light], F.F. Xavier F° &amp; F.L. Oliveira 
leg.
, 
1
male

[
INPA
]; 
Holotype
: Mato Grosso,

Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
30
.IX. 
2002
, E. Furtado 
leg
., 
1
male

; 
20
.X. 
1983
, J.B., O.R. &amp; B.S. 
leg.
, 
2
males

[
MNRJ
]; 
Paratype
: Minas Gerais,

Belo Horizonte (
19
º 
54
´S

– 
43
º 
56
´W

), 

06.X. 
1959
, Evangelista 
leg
., 
1
male

[
MNRJ
]; 
Paraná
, Fênix, Reserva Est.– 
ITCF
, Lev. Ent. PROFAUPAR, 

02.X. 
1986
, lâmpada [at light], 
1
male

[
DZUP
].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
–10, 32 [description]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
64
[catalog]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
129
, 134 [figures, citation as 
type
species]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[citation]; 

Forero, 
2006
: 
8
[citation]; 

Gil-Santana, 
2007
: 
60
[new record].
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
212
[new combination, checklist].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Redescription.Female:
Total length 
16.2–18.5
(

Table 
1
). 
Male
: Total length: 
14.6–18.5
(

Tables 
2–4
). COLORATION: The coloration is quite variable, yellowish-orange and/or with reddish suffusions, to somewhat yellow-brownish general coloration, with blackish markings, variably present in their extent on head, including collum, labium segments, distal portion of labrum, thorax, including legs and corium of hemelytra and sternites (Figs. 
48–60
). Antennae blackish with joints clear; basal portion of segment I yellowish in variable extent in some specimens; hairs and setae of antennae brownish red to yellowish distally (Figs. 54, 58). Thorax: pronotum with three pairs of blackish spots: 
1
—anteriorly on the fore lobe of pronotum; 
2
—suboval spots on central portion of hind lobe of pronotum, variable in size and extent and variably confluent in midportion, in the region of the median sulcus as well; 
3
—on lateral portion of approximately distal half of fore lobe and basal half of hind lobe of pronotum, including the transverse furrow laterally (Figs. 
48
–52, 56, 
59
). Pleurae and sterna with blackish spots and markings in variable extents to almost blackish in darker specimens. Legs: femora with base, submedian distal ring and apex blackish, with some variability in the extent or presence of these markings; tibiae with base and two rings, submedian proximal and distal, blackish, variable as well; in two specimens, tibiae almost all blackish with subbasal ring and distal portion yellowish; tarsi yellowish to yellowish-orange. Corium of hemelytra variably marked with dark spots together with yellowish areas, spots on veins, or some of these latter yellowish-colored to variable extent, to almost completely blackish; membrane of hemelytra blackish (Figs. 48, 51, 56, 59). Connexivum shows alternating blackish and yellow-reddish coloration, but the latter is darker in some specimens (Figs. 48, 51, 56, 59). Sternites yellowish with very variable blackish markings on sternites; sternite II with a transverse blackish band, for which dimensions both in transverse and antero-posterior directions are variable among specimens. Sternites III–VI with lateral large spots accompanied by central bands, which have variable format along the segments, or become a pair of median separated spots, or the latter variably fused, sometimes forming a large dark band, occupying the majority of the segment. Sternite VII with lateral blackish spots of variable size; a median distal band which can be shaped as an inverted “V” or as a smaller spot with variable size, and a pair or two pairs of small subrounded dark spots, of variabe size in some specimens (Figs. 50, 55, 
60
).
</p>
            <p>PLATE7
. Figs. 
48–56
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, 
48–55
, female, 
48–50
, specimen from 
Bolivia
, 
48–49
, dorsal view, 
49
, head and thorax, 
50
, latero-ventral view, 
51
, specimen from Ceará, 
Brazil
, dorsal view, 
52–55
, specimen from Amapá, 
Brazil
, 
52
, head and thorax, dorsal view, 
53
, head, lateral view, 
54
, antennal segment I, dorsal view, 
55
, latero-ventral view, 
56
, male from Acre, 
Brazil
.
</p>
            <p>
STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Integument mostly glabrous shiny and smooth (Figs 
48
–53, 55–57, 59– 
60
). 
Head.
Antenna: eight segmented, with hairs and setae brownish red to yellowish distally; in males, all segments pubescent (Fig. 
58
). First segment thicker than others, bare in mid-dorsal region, hairs somewhat longer than the transverse width of segment (Fig. 
58
); second antennal segment with long hairs, which are two to almost three times as long as width of the segment (Fig. 
58
). Clypeus denticulate in males. Labium thick with sparse setae, more numerous on ventral face of segment II few at the apex of segment III, and some scattered on segment IV; segment II longer than the others together and surpassing posterior margin of the eyes (Figs. 53, 57). 
Thorax
(Figs. 
48
–49, 51–52, 56, 
59
): Integument of pronotum on anterior lobe of pronotum moderately rugous or smooth; midlongitudinal sulcus in anterior pronotal lobe not reaching interlobar sulcus; deep enough to form a pair of protuberant paramedial lobes in some specimens, but in others it is shallow and there is no evidence of such lobes, even in larger specimens; midlongitudinal (in the first half of posterior lobe), transverse (interlobar) and posterolateral sulci formed by canaliculae, which vary in depth among the specimens; humeral angles rounded. Femora, particularly, fore and mid femora, thick in some specimens, with patches of long and numerous yellowish hairs on ventral surface of fore and mid trochanters and femora. In mid trochanters and femora, hairs are more numerous on the basal half; in some specimens these hairs are shorter or less numerous; mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange hairs on median portion of ventral face of all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration; presence of a median ventral shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; in some specimens this crest is not perceptible on femora; spongy fossa well developed on pro and meso tibiae. Hemelytra length varied from shorter than abdomen to slightly surpassing the tip. 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
61–71
): pygophore subrounded, posterior margin rounded; paramere apices close in resting position (Figs. 
61–62
). Median process of pygophore sclerotized, apex rounded or slightly subtriangular (Figs. 
62–63
). Parameres symmetrical, a little curved, with sparse hairs, with a short subapical tooth (Figs. 
61
–62, 64). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately long, subquadrate; dorsal phallothecal plate oval, sinuous in center of anterior margin, lateral margins somewhat bent; struts enlarged at basal half and united in the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
65–67
). Median process of endosoma subquadrate, with central sclerotized structure in the shape of an “X” (Fig. 
70
), or more similar to a “T” (Figs. 69, 71) including other specimen with darker sternites (Fig. 
60
, B).
</p>
            <p>PLATE8
. Figs. 
57–65
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, male, 
57–58
, specimen from Acre, 
Brazil
, 
57
, head, lateral view, 
58
, right antenna, segments I–II, dorsal view, 
59–60
, specimens from 
French Guiana
, 
59
, dorsal view, 
60
, ventral view, 
61–65
, male genitalia, 
61–62
, pygophore and parameres, 
61
, ventral view, 
62
, dorsal view, 
63
, median process of pygophore, 
64
, right paramere, dorsal and ventral view, respectively, 
65
, phallus, dorsal view.
</p>
            <p>PLATE9
. Figs. 
66–71
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, male genitalia, 
66–67
, phallus with expanded endosoma, 
66
, lateral view, 
67
, dorsal view, 
68
, median portion of expanded endosoma, with the median process, dorsal view, 
69–71
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, 
69
, male from Pará, 
Brazil
, 
70–71
, males from 
French Guiana
, 
70
, from male of Fig. 
60
, A, 
71
, from male of Fig. 
60
, B.
</p>
            <p>Female
: COLORATION: same as males. STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Antenna: first and basal half of the second segment of females are bare or very sparsely pubescent; first segment thicker than others, completely bare to 
20
short setae on internal face; second segment with setae shorter or a little longer than the width of the segment, with very few scattered longer erect hairs 
ca.
twice as long as the width of the segment (Fig. 
54
). Clypeus rounded in females; Hemelytra did not reach tip of abdomen in the females examined.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
As possible sexual dimorphism in eyes and ocellus sizes were not clear when examining the specimens, some selected measures were recorded (

Tables 
1–4
) to investigate this. There were other observed variations in the specimens of this taxon: all specimens except the female from 
Bolivia
and a male from 
French Guiana
have a small rounded tubercle on the ventral portion of the head (gula) anteriorly (Figs. 53, 57), as well as size variation of the tubercle among the specimens; while in the male from 
French Guiana
, in which the tubercle is absent, some setae are present on the same area of gula. Investigating the male genitalia, the different portions of male genitalia were shown to be similar among the specimens examined, with very subtle differences in the thickness of parameres or size of teeth; median process of pygophore rounded to slightly subtriangular. Those differences showed intermediate or gradual states, occurring randomly among specimens, negating any association with color pattern or geographical precedence. The median process of the endosoma showed some minor variation as well, with the central sclerotized structure similar in shape to a “T” (Figs. 69, 71) recorded in specimens with more or less dark body markings from 
Brazil
and 
French Guiana
(Fig. 
60
, B), while its structure presented as the shape of an “X” (Fig. 
70
) in a male from 
French Guiana
with paler body markings (Fig. 
60
, A). However, the shapes of the dorsal phallothecal plate and struts (Fig. 
65
) are particularly characteristic and there was no noticeable variation among specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
BOLIVIA
, 
Bolivia
Tropica

, Región Chaparé, 
400m
, 

XII- 
1949
, Zischka [? 
leg.
], 
1
female

; 
BRAZIL
, Acre,
11 km
NE de Rio Branco, 
5–10
.V. 
1981
, Penny &amp; Elias 
leg.
, 
1
male

; 
Amapá
, Serra do Navio, 

VII- 
1959
, J. Lane 
leg.
, 
1
female

, [
MNRJ
]; 
Amazonas
, Campo Petrolífero do Urucu-Coari (

04º 
53
´42,5” S

– 
65
º 
11
´16,2” W

), 
21
.IX–04.X. 
2004
, José A.M. Fernandes 
leg.
, 
2
males

; 
Ceará
, Carquejo, 
1
female

, 

III.1963, 
1
female; 
FRENCH GUIANA
, 
Nourages
[

04º 
52
´N

– 
52
º 
41
´W

], 

IX. 
2009
, window trap, Seag 
leg
., 
7
males

, 
1
female

.
</p>
            <p>New Record:French Guiana
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
: 
344</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Reduvius ventralis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
: 
280</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa, 
2005
: 
400</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
P. 
jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pothea berengeri sp. nov. from Brazil, with taxonomic notes on Pothea furtadoi Gil-Santana &amp; Costa and Pothea jaguaris (Carpintero) and reinstatement of Parapothea Carpintero as junior synonym of Pothea Amyot &amp; Serville (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae: Ectrichodiinae)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3826.3.4</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFD1FF98A516FFECFFC4FFC3DD1D3964</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3826.3.4</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Figures 
1
–14, 15– 
28
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
Figures 
29–47
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
, REINSTATED COMBINATION

Figures 
48–71
, 

Tables 
1–4
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
: 
344</tp:taxon-name>
–345 [description]; 

Stål, 
1859
, 176 [key], 
184
[redescription], 
184–185
[checklist of species]; 

Stål, 
1872
: 
101
[key], 
103–104
[checklist and key to species]; 

Walker, 
1873
a

: 
47
[key], 
80
[key]; 

Walker, 
1873
b

: 
63
–64 [checklist and key to four species]; 

Lethierry &amp; Severin, 
1896
: 
131
[catalog]; 

Champion, 
1898
: 
221
[diagnosis, key to Central American species]; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1949
: 
23
[catalog]; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1951
: 
36
[key]; 

Carpintero, 
1978
: 
177
–286 [revision of the genus and Argentinean species]; 

Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
[diagnosis]; 

Putshkov &amp; Putshkov, 
1985
: 
16
[catalog]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
65–67
[catalog]; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
202
[key], 
211–212
[diagnosis, checklist of species]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
126
[key], 
135–136
[diagnosis]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[diagnosis], 
181–182
[key]; 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

: 
71
[key].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduvius ventralis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
: 
280</tp:taxon-name>
, by subsequent designation: 

Van Duzee, 
1916
: 
29
.
</p>
            <p>Anapothea
Miller, 
1956
: 
8
; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1959
: 
297
[as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
]. 
Type
species: 
Anapothea amoena
Miller, 
1956
: 
8
, by original designation.
</p>
            <p>Parapothea
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
[description]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
64
[catalog]; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
211
[as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
126
[key], 
134–135
[diagnosis]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[diagnosis], 
181
[key]; 

Forero, 
2006
: 
8
[discussion on validity]; 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

: 
71
[key]; 
REINSTATED SYNONYMY
.
</p>
            <p>Type
species: 

Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
, by original designation.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking sexual dimorphism in males, with first antennal segment almost completely glabrous and second antennal with short pilosity. The rounded tylus, size of male ocelli equal to females; and eyes somewhat smaller than eyes of female are also diagnostic. Females with hemelytra somewhat longer or reaching the tip of abdomen; male hemelytra shorter, not reaching the tip of the abdomen (Figs. 1, 15, 
24
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description.Male
. MEASUREMENTS: Total length: 
17.3
; head: total length (including collum): 4.0; maximum width across the eyes: 
1.6
; ante-ocular length: 
1.9
; post-ocular length: 
1.6
; interocular space: 
0.9
; transverse width of right eye: 
0.3
; length of right eye, measured from above: 
0.5
; ocellar tubercle width: 
0.6
; right ocellus width: 
0.18
; antennal segments: I: 2.0; II: 3.0; III: 
1.2
; IV: 
0.7
; V: 
0.55
; VI: 
0.4
; VII: 
0.35
; VIII: 
0.5
; labium segments: II [first visible]: 
2.5
; III: 1.0; IV: 
0.5
. Thorax: pronotum: fore lobe length: 
1.2
; hind lobe: length: 
2.4
; width at posterior margin: 
4.2
; scutellum: length: 
1.7
; width at base: 
1.9
. Legs: fore legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 4.0; tarsus: 
1.4
; middle legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 4.0; tarsus: 
1.5
; hind legs: femur: 5.0; tibia: 
5.5
; tarsus: 
1.7
. Abdomen: length: 
8.6
; maximum width: 
5.1
. COLORATION: General coloration yellowish-orange to orange-red, with reddish, brownish or blackish markings (Figs. 1, 5). 
Head
(Fig. 
1
): with reddish markings along midline, more prominent on clypeus, almost all ocellar tubercle red, antennal tubercles and around eyes also red; well marked blackish spots behind ocelli and very faint ones in front of them, both on the ocellar tubercle; eyes blackish. Antenna: first antennal segment orange-yellowish; second segment somewhat dark, orange-yellowish basally; other segments darkened to brownish, except on the joints, which are clear, yellowish to whitish. 
Thorax
(Figs. 1, 5– 
6
). Pronotum: anterior margin, anterior portion of longitudinal sulcus, lateral portions of the transverse sulcus, lateral stripe on anterior portion of propleura, and a somewhat rounded spot on posterior portion of propleura slightly dark to brownish. Central portion and lateral margins of scutellum dark. Meso and metapleura and sterna darkened, intersegmental sutures around metapleura marked with black. Apical third of femora somewhat reddish. Hemelytra: corium somewhat orange-yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum blackish except at base; a pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion; subapical lateral portion somewhat reddish, apex darkened; membrane dark brown. 
Abdomen
(Figs. 1, 7). Connexivum orange in internal portion, dorsally, and reddish in external portion, dorsally and ventrally; sternites orange-yellowish, with the distal portion of sternite VII, posterior to pygophore, as reddish as connexivum; sternite II [first visible] without dark markings; intersegmental area between sternites II and III, where there are canaliculae, somewhat darkened; other sternites with small dark, brownish to blackish markings as follows: lateral subsquared or subrounded markings on segments III–VI; a pair of small dark curved stripes on mid portion of sternites III–IV; curved bands, which are larger in their median portion, on midline of sternites V and VI, the latter smaller; sternite VII with a very faint dark spot just anterior to pygophore and lateral small rounded dark markings; area around spiracles somewhat darkened as well. VESTITURE: Integument almost completely glabrous and shiny (Figs. 
1
–2, 5– 
7
). Antennae with first segment almost completely glabrous, with just a small yellowish-orange seta on the middle of internal face in the right antenna; basal portion of segment II glabrous; remainder of this segment and others covered with moderately short setae and a few longer ones; on segment II, the short setae length are approximately half the width of the segment, while the length of 
PLATE1
.

Figs. 
1–7
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, male 
holotype
, 
1
, dorsal view, 
2
, head, lateral view, 
3–4
, right antenna, dorsal view, 
4
, segment I and proximal portion of segment II, the arrow points to a setae, 
5
, pronotum and scutellum, dorsal view, 
6
, pronotum, lateral view, 
7
, abdomen, ventral view.
</p>
            <p>
the few longer setae are approximately 
1.2
times the width of the segment (Figs. 
3–4
). Labium with yellowish to orange sparse setae on ventral face of basal portion of labial segment II, apex of labial segment III, and on base, dorsally, and apex of labial segment IV (Fig. 
2
). Legs with short hairs on fore and median trochanters and a mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange very short hairs on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration. STRUCTURE: Head elongated; clypeus elevated and rounded; eyes moderate size; ocellar tubercle prominent, undivided; labium thick, segment II longer than the others together and surpassing posterior margin of eyes (Figs. 
1–2
); antennae eight-segmented (Fig. 
3
). Pronotum: anterior margin as a thin collar; surface smooth with a pair of short, rounded tubercles medially just between anterior and posterior lobes of pronotum; longitudinal sulcus on anterior lobe shallow, somewhat more profound in second half; in first half of posterior lobe it is represented only by four small punctures, the most anterior just below the pair of rounded tubercles; transverse (interlobar) sulcus formed by small and shallow impressions (canaliculae); both sulci interrupted medially by the pair of tubercles, not reaching each other. Lateral sulcus of posterior lobe of pronotum weak, formed by shallow canaliculae anteriorly; humeral angles rounded. Scutellum with a deep median depression; prongs short and convergent (Figs. 1, 5– 
6
). Legs slender; fore and mid femora somewhat thicker than hind ones; these latter slightly thick subapically; protibia conspicuously thick at apex, mainly in anterior portion; other tibiae less thick 
PLATE2
.

Figs. 
8–14
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
holotype
, male genitalia, 
8–9
, pygophore and parameres, 
8
, ventral view, 
9
, dorsal view, 
10
, median process of pygophore, 
11
, left paramere, ventral and dorsal view, respectively, 
12–13
, phallus, 
12
, lateral view, 
13
, dorsal view, 
14
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view.
</p>
            <p>
at apex, mid pair a little more than hind tibiae; small spongy fossa on pro and mid tibiae; presence of a median ventral shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted, on fore and mid femora and all tibiae, less marked on hind ones. Hemelytra not reaching tip of abdomen (Fig. 
1
). Connexivum, in lateral view, with postero-lateral angles somewhat prominent, which is more accentuated in segment II. Sternites II and III separated by canaliculae; other intersternite furrow more evident in median portion and almost imperceptible laterally (Fig. 
7
). 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
8–14
): pygophore sub-squared, posterior margin sinuate; parameres apices close in resting position (Figs. 
8–9
). Median process of pygophore sclerotized, apex rounded (Figs. 
9–10
). Parameres symmetrical, curved, somewhat enlarged, truncated at apex, with short slots on median and medial portion and a small tooth at lateral portion of the apex (Figs. 
8
–9, 11). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately short, subretangular; phalothecal dorsal plate somewhat elongated with angles rounded, sinuous in center of anterior margin; struts rather enlarged at basal half, united at the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
12–13
). Median process of endosoma subtriangular, apex rounded, with a central sclerotized structure, which has three divergent branches directed upward (Fig. 
14
). 
Female
: MEASUREMENTS: Total length: 
17–17.5
; head: total length (including collum): 
4.2–4.4
; maximum width across the eyes: 
1.6–1.7
; ante-ocular length: 
1.8
–2.0; post-ocular length: 
1.6–1.8
; interocular space: 
0.9
–1.0; transverse width of right eye: 
0.35
; length of right eye, measured from above: 
0.6–0.7
; ocellar tubercle width: 
0.6–0.8
; right ocellus width: 
0.18–0.20
; antennal segments: I: 
1.9
–2.0; II: 
3.2–3.5
; III: 
1.3–1.4
; IV: 
0.8–0.9
; [V–VIII, absent in one 
paratype
]; V: 
0.6
; VI: 
0.4
; VII: 
0.4
; VIII: 
0.6
; labial segments: II [first visible]: 
2.7–2.8
; III: 
1.2
; IV: 
0.5
. Thorax: pronotum: fore lobe length: 1.0 – 
1.3
; hind lobe: length: 
2.3–2.4
; width at posterior margin: 
4.6–4.7
; scutellum: length: 
1.6–1.8
; width at base: 2.0– 
2.4
. Legs: fore legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 
4.3
; tarsus: 
1.4–1.5
; middle legs: femur: 
4.1–4.2
; tibia: 4.0– 
4.2
; tarsus: 
1.6
; hind legs: femur: 
5.4
; tibia: 
5.8
–6.0; tarsus: 
1.8
. Abdomen: length: 
8.5–9.3
; maximum width: 
5.6–5.9
. COLORATION: similar to male. General coloration is reddish to clear (Figs. 15, 24). 
Head
: the reddish markings on the head smaller than male or absent (Figs. 16, 19). 
Thorax
: a pair of suboval faint brownish median spots present on hind lobe of pronotum (Figs. 15, 19, 24, 27); propleura with a dark faint and irregular stripe on upper portion; meso and metapleurae and sterna fairly dark; pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion of corium of hemelytra present (Fig. 
15
) and can form a darkened larger spot (Fig. 
24
); sternite II with a pair of sublateral brownish faint sublateral stripes, and five pairs of subquadrate to subtriangular lateral spots on sternites III–VII, and a small median spot on sternite III and median bands on sternites IV–VI, which are larger in the middle portion, especially in sternite VI and almost reach the lateral spots on sternites IV–V and right side of sternite VI, joining the lateral spot in left side of sternite VI (Fig. 
22
). STRUCTURE: Head somewhat larger in profile (Fig. 
16
); first antennal segment completely glabrous (Figs. 
17–18
) or with ten setae on the internal face of this segment (Figs. 
25–26
). Hemelytra can reach tip of abdomen (Fig. 
24
). 
Female genitalia
: Posterior view of external genitalia as Fig. 
23
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.Brazil
, states of Mato Grosso and Bahia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The new species is named in honor of the French entomologist, Jean-Michel Bérenger, for his great contribution to the study of 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>PLATE3
.

Figs. 
15–22
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, female 
paratype
, specimen from Bahia, 
Brazil
, 
15
, dorsal view, 
16
, head, lateral view, 
17– 18
, right antenna, proximal segments, dorsal view, 
19
, head and pronotum, dorsal view, 
20
, fore femur, lateral view, 
21
, fore tibia and tarsus, dorsal view, 
22
, ventral view.
</p>
            <p>PLATE4
.

Figs. 
23– 28
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, female 
paratype
, 
23
, specimen from Bahia, external genitalia, posterior view, 
24–28
, 
paratype
from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
24
, dorsal view, 
25–26
, right antenna, dorsal view, 
26
, segment I, 
27
, pronotum and scutellum, dorsal view, 
28
, ventral view.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
The following variability was present in the female 
paratype
of this species: the pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion of corium of hemelytra is somewhat smaller in one 
paratype
(Fig. 
15
) and forms a darkened larger spot in the 
paratype
with reddish coloration (Fig. 
24
); the reddish markings on the head was absent in the 
paratype
with clear coloration. The sternites in the other 
paratype
have a brighter coloration, almost yellowish, while the markings are darker, except on sternite II, in which, besides smaller, forming spots, they are fainter; the median bands are larger in the middle portion and do not reach the lateral spots in any segment; on the sternites V–VI they form subtriangular spots and not bands; the lateral markings on sternite VII are much smaller, simple dots (Fig. 
28
). The 
paratype
with reddish coloration has a somewhat thicker fore and mid femora and the hemelytra reaches the tip of the abdomen. Despite the mentioned variation, all the common features between the females, particularly in the structure of head and pronotum, are prone to consider them as conspecific.
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
Holotype
: 
BRAZIL
, Mato Grosso,

Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
20
.X. 
1983
, J. Becker, O. Roppa &amp; B.S. 
leg.
[
MNRJ
]; 
1
male

. 
Paratypes
: 
BRAZIL
, Bahia,

Encruzilhada, BR 
116
, Divisa, XI.[
19
] 
74
, O. Roppa 
leg
., 
1
female

; 
Mato Grosso,
Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
10
.X. 
1988
, O. Roppa &amp; J. Becker 
leg
. [
MNRJ
], 
1
female

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa, 
2005
: 
400</tp:taxon-name>
–404 [description].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.Male:
Total length: 18.0–21.0; COLORATION: general coloration mostly reddish, but somewhat brighter in a few specimens, with darkened or blackish markings; legs with submedian small markings on femora; variable extent and intensity of darkness on femoral apices and subbasal and apical rings on tibiae; variation also present on the corium of hemelytra, which is reddish on most extension or somewhat brighter to almost yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum, apex and a stripe in the central portion, brownish to blackish, and variable dark coloration (Figs.
</p>
            <p>29
–30, 41, 
44
). Connexivum reddish, without markings (Figs. 29, 41) or yellowish, with approximately two thirds of each segment pink colored distally (Fig. 
44
). Blackish markings on the sternites III–VII form transverse stripes, variable in thickness, enlarged at the lateral portion, anterior extension in front of the respective spiracle in the sternites III–VI sometimes present (Fig. 
32
). These stripes are interrupted or incomplete in two or three segments, in which there are a median and a pair of lateral blackish markings instead of a stripe in some specimens (Figs. 42, 45– 
46
). STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Head: antenna eight segmented, all segments pubescent (Fig. 
31
); clypeus denticulate. Thorax: integument of pronotum smooth and shiny; midlongitudinal sulcus in anterior pronotal lobe not reaching interlobar sulcus, moderately deep; midlongitudinal (in the first half of posterior lobe), transverse (interlobar) and posterolateral sulci formed by canaliculae and well developed; humeral angles rounded (Figs. 
29
–30, 41, 
44
). Legs slender, femora, particularly fore and mid, somewhat thicker, with patches of slightly long yellowish hairs on ventral face of fore and mid trochanters and femora, in the latter, they are more numerous on the basal half; in some specimens these hairs are shorter or less numerous; mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange short hairs on median portion of ventral face of all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration; presence of a median ventral, shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; spongy fossa well developed on pro and mid tibiae. 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
33
–40, 43, 
47
): pygophore subpentagonal, posterior margin sinuate; paramere apices close in resting position (Figs. 
33–34
). Median process of pygophore somewhat elongated, subquadrate and sclerotized (Figs. 
34–35
). Parameres symmetrical, curved, with a short subapical tooth, rounded at apex (Figs. 
33
–34, 36). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately short; dorsal phallothecal plate lozenge shaped, sinuous in center of anterior margin, struts enlarged at basal half and united at the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
37–39
). Endosoma with a pair of lateral conjunctiva processes approximately at the median portion (Figs. 
37–38
). Median process of endosoma rounded, with central sclerotized structure somewhat like a “Y” (Fig. 
40
) or similar to a “T” (Figs. 43, 47).
</p>
            <p>PLATE5
.

Figs. 
29–36
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, males from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
29
, dorsal view, 
30
, head, pronotum and basal portion of hemelytra, dorsal view, 
31
, right antenna, segments I–III, dorsal view, 
32
, abdomen, latero-ventral view, 
33–36
, male genitalia, 
33–34
, pygophore and parameres, 
33
, ventral view, 
34
, dorsal view, 
35
, median process of pygophore, 
36
, right paramere, dorsal and ventral view, respectively.
</p>
            <p>PLATE6
. Figs. 
37–47
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
37–40
, male genitalia, specimen from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
37–39
, phallus, 
37
, lateral view, 
38
, latero-dorsal view, 
39
dorsal view, 
40
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, Figs. 
41–47
, males, 
41–43
, 
paratype
from Minas Gerais, 
Brazil
, 
41
, dorsal view, 
42
, ventral view, 
43
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, 
44–47
, specimen from Maranhão, 
Brazil
, 
44
, dorsal view, 
45
, ventral view, 
46
, latero-ventral view, 
47
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
There is size and morphological differences between the males of this species. The male from the state of Maranhão, for example, has a different coloration in connexivum (Fig. 
44
) and is smaller in total length, being 
17.1
millimeters. Variability in the dark markings of the body was also observed, particularly on the legs, with submedian small markings on femora in two specimens; variable extent and intensity of darkness on femoral apices and subbasal and apical rings on tibiae; variation also present on the corium of hemelytra, which is reddish on most extension or somewhat brighter to almost yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum, apex and a stripe in the central portion, brownish to blackish, and variable dark coloration (Figs. 
29
–30, 41, 
44
). However, as already described by 

Gil-Santana &amp; Costa (
2005
)

, the blackish markings on the sternites III–VII form transverse stripes, with some variability in thickness, enlarged at the lateral portion, where it may have an anterior extension in front of the respective spiracle in the sternites III–VI (Fig. 
32
). The different portions of male genitalia were shown to be similar among the specimens examined. The shapes of the dorsal phallotecal plate and struts are particularly characteristic (Fig. 
39
). The median process of the endosoma in males from different states of 
Brazil
and with very diverse coloration (Figs. 
29
–30, 32, 
41
–42, 44– 
46
) showed minor variation (Figs. 40, 43 and 
47
).
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
BRAZIL
, Bahia,

Encruzilhada, BR 
116
, Divisa, XI.[
19
] 
74
, O. Roppa 
leg
., 
1
male

[
MNRJ
]; 
Goiás
, Mambaí, Gruta [cavern] da Tarimba, 
29
.IV. 
2013
, M. E. Bichuette 
et al
. 
leg
., 
1
male

; 
Maranhão
, Caxias Inhamum (045439S - 
432616
W), 
535 m
, 
17
.V. 
2007
, Luz [light], F.F. Xavier F° &amp; F.L. Oliveira 
leg.
, 
1
male

[
INPA
]; 
Holotype
: Mato Grosso,

Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
30
.IX. 
2002
, E. Furtado 
leg
., 
1
male

; 
20
.X. 
1983
, J.B., O.R. &amp; B.S. 
leg.
, 
2
males

[
MNRJ
]; 
Paratype
: Minas Gerais,

Belo Horizonte (
19
º 
54
´S

– 
43
º 
56
´W

), 

06.X. 
1959
, Evangelista 
leg
., 
1
male

[
MNRJ
]; 
Paraná
, Fênix, Reserva Est.– 
ITCF
, Lev. Ent. PROFAUPAR, 

02.X. 
1986
, lâmpada [at light], 
1
male

[
DZUP
].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
–10, 32 [description]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
64
[catalog]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
129
, 134 [figures, citation as 
type
species]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[citation]; 

Forero, 
2006
: 
8
[citation]; 

Gil-Santana, 
2007
: 
60
[new record].
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
212
[new combination, checklist].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Redescription.Female:
Total length 
16.2–18.5
(

Table 
1
). 
Male
: Total length: 
14.6–18.5
(

Tables 
2–4
). COLORATION: The coloration is quite variable, yellowish-orange and/or with reddish suffusions, to somewhat yellow-brownish general coloration, with blackish markings, variably present in their extent on head, including collum, labium segments, distal portion of labrum, thorax, including legs and corium of hemelytra and sternites (Figs. 
48–60
). Antennae blackish with joints clear; basal portion of segment I yellowish in variable extent in some specimens; hairs and setae of antennae brownish red to yellowish distally (Figs. 54, 58). Thorax: pronotum with three pairs of blackish spots: 
1
—anteriorly on the fore lobe of pronotum; 
2
—suboval spots on central portion of hind lobe of pronotum, variable in size and extent and variably confluent in midportion, in the region of the median sulcus as well; 
3
—on lateral portion of approximately distal half of fore lobe and basal half of hind lobe of pronotum, including the transverse furrow laterally (Figs. 
48
–52, 56, 
59
). Pleurae and sterna with blackish spots and markings in variable extents to almost blackish in darker specimens. Legs: femora with base, submedian distal ring and apex blackish, with some variability in the extent or presence of these markings; tibiae with base and two rings, submedian proximal and distal, blackish, variable as well; in two specimens, tibiae almost all blackish with subbasal ring and distal portion yellowish; tarsi yellowish to yellowish-orange. Corium of hemelytra variably marked with dark spots together with yellowish areas, spots on veins, or some of these latter yellowish-colored to variable extent, to almost completely blackish; membrane of hemelytra blackish (Figs. 48, 51, 56, 59). Connexivum shows alternating blackish and yellow-reddish coloration, but the latter is darker in some specimens (Figs. 48, 51, 56, 59). Sternites yellowish with very variable blackish markings on sternites; sternite II with a transverse blackish band, for which dimensions both in transverse and antero-posterior directions are variable among specimens. Sternites III–VI with lateral large spots accompanied by central bands, which have variable format along the segments, or become a pair of median separated spots, or the latter variably fused, sometimes forming a large dark band, occupying the majority of the segment. Sternite VII with lateral blackish spots of variable size; a median distal band which can be shaped as an inverted “V” or as a smaller spot with variable size, and a pair or two pairs of small subrounded dark spots, of variabe size in some specimens (Figs. 50, 55, 
60
).
</p>
            <p>PLATE7
. Figs. 
48–56
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, 
48–55
, female, 
48–50
, specimen from 
Bolivia
, 
48–49
, dorsal view, 
49
, head and thorax, 
50
, latero-ventral view, 
51
, specimen from Ceará, 
Brazil
, dorsal view, 
52–55
, specimen from Amapá, 
Brazil
, 
52
, head and thorax, dorsal view, 
53
, head, lateral view, 
54
, antennal segment I, dorsal view, 
55
, latero-ventral view, 
56
, male from Acre, 
Brazil
.
</p>
            <p>
STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Integument mostly glabrous shiny and smooth (Figs 
48
–53, 55–57, 59– 
60
). 
Head.
Antenna: eight segmented, with hairs and setae brownish red to yellowish distally; in males, all segments pubescent (Fig. 
58
). First segment thicker than others, bare in mid-dorsal region, hairs somewhat longer than the transverse width of segment (Fig. 
58
); second antennal segment with long hairs, which are two to almost three times as long as width of the segment (Fig. 
58
). Clypeus denticulate in males. Labium thick with sparse setae, more numerous on ventral face of segment II few at the apex of segment III, and some scattered on segment IV; segment II longer than the others together and surpassing posterior margin of the eyes (Figs. 53, 57). 
Thorax
(Figs. 
48
–49, 51–52, 56, 
59
): Integument of pronotum on anterior lobe of pronotum moderately rugous or smooth; midlongitudinal sulcus in anterior pronotal lobe not reaching interlobar sulcus; deep enough to form a pair of protuberant paramedial lobes in some specimens, but in others it is shallow and there is no evidence of such lobes, even in larger specimens; midlongitudinal (in the first half of posterior lobe), transverse (interlobar) and posterolateral sulci formed by canaliculae, which vary in depth among the specimens; humeral angles rounded. Femora, particularly, fore and mid femora, thick in some specimens, with patches of long and numerous yellowish hairs on ventral surface of fore and mid trochanters and femora. In mid trochanters and femora, hairs are more numerous on the basal half; in some specimens these hairs are shorter or less numerous; mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange hairs on median portion of ventral face of all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration; presence of a median ventral shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; in some specimens this crest is not perceptible on femora; spongy fossa well developed on pro and meso tibiae. Hemelytra length varied from shorter than abdomen to slightly surpassing the tip. 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
61–71
): pygophore subrounded, posterior margin rounded; paramere apices close in resting position (Figs. 
61–62
). Median process of pygophore sclerotized, apex rounded or slightly subtriangular (Figs. 
62–63
). Parameres symmetrical, a little curved, with sparse hairs, with a short subapical tooth (Figs. 
61
–62, 64). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately long, subquadrate; dorsal phallothecal plate oval, sinuous in center of anterior margin, lateral margins somewhat bent; struts enlarged at basal half and united in the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
65–67
). Median process of endosoma subquadrate, with central sclerotized structure in the shape of an “X” (Fig. 
70
), or more similar to a “T” (Figs. 69, 71) including other specimen with darker sternites (Fig. 
60
, B).
</p>
            <p>PLATE8
. Figs. 
57–65
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, male, 
57–58
, specimen from Acre, 
Brazil
, 
57
, head, lateral view, 
58
, right antenna, segments I–II, dorsal view, 
59–60
, specimens from 
French Guiana
, 
59
, dorsal view, 
60
, ventral view, 
61–65
, male genitalia, 
61–62
, pygophore and parameres, 
61
, ventral view, 
62
, dorsal view, 
63
, median process of pygophore, 
64
, right paramere, dorsal and ventral view, respectively, 
65
, phallus, dorsal view.
</p>
            <p>PLATE9
. Figs. 
66–71
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, male genitalia, 
66–67
, phallus with expanded endosoma, 
66
, lateral view, 
67
, dorsal view, 
68
, median portion of expanded endosoma, with the median process, dorsal view, 
69–71
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, 
69
, male from Pará, 
Brazil
, 
70–71
, males from 
French Guiana
, 
70
, from male of Fig. 
60
, A, 
71
, from male of Fig. 
60
, B.
</p>
            <p>Female
: COLORATION: same as males. STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Antenna: first and basal half of the second segment of females are bare or very sparsely pubescent; first segment thicker than others, completely bare to 
20
short setae on internal face; second segment with setae shorter or a little longer than the width of the segment, with very few scattered longer erect hairs 
ca.
twice as long as the width of the segment (Fig. 
54
). Clypeus rounded in females; Hemelytra did not reach tip of abdomen in the females examined.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
As possible sexual dimorphism in eyes and ocellus sizes were not clear when examining the specimens, some selected measures were recorded (

Tables 
1–4
) to investigate this. There were other observed variations in the specimens of this taxon: all specimens except the female from 
Bolivia
and a male from 
French Guiana
have a small rounded tubercle on the ventral portion of the head (gula) anteriorly (Figs. 53, 57), as well as size variation of the tubercle among the specimens; while in the male from 
French Guiana
, in which the tubercle is absent, some setae are present on the same area of gula. Investigating the male genitalia, the different portions of male genitalia were shown to be similar among the specimens examined, with very subtle differences in the thickness of parameres or size of teeth; median process of pygophore rounded to slightly subtriangular. Those differences showed intermediate or gradual states, occurring randomly among specimens, negating any association with color pattern or geographical precedence. The median process of the endosoma showed some minor variation as well, with the central sclerotized structure similar in shape to a “T” (Figs. 69, 71) recorded in specimens with more or less dark body markings from 
Brazil
and 
French Guiana
(Fig. 
60
, B), while its structure presented as the shape of an “X” (Fig. 
70
) in a male from 
French Guiana
with paler body markings (Fig. 
60
, A). However, the shapes of the dorsal phallothecal plate and struts (Fig. 
65
) are particularly characteristic and there was no noticeable variation among specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
BOLIVIA
, 
Bolivia
Tropica

, Región Chaparé, 
400m
, 

XII- 
1949
, Zischka [? 
leg.
], 
1
female

; 
BRAZIL
, Acre,
11 km
NE de Rio Branco, 
5–10
.V. 
1981
, Penny &amp; Elias 
leg.
, 
1
male

; 
Amapá
, Serra do Navio, 

VII- 
1959
, J. Lane 
leg.
, 
1
female

, [
MNRJ
]; 
Amazonas
, Campo Petrolífero do Urucu-Coari (

04º 
53
´42,5” S

– 
65
º 
11
´16,2” W

), 
21
.IX–04.X. 
2004
, José A.M. Fernandes 
leg.
, 
2
males

; 
Ceará
, Carquejo, 
1
female

, 

III.1963, 
1
female; 
FRENCH GUIANA
, 
Nourages
[

04º 
52
´N

– 
52
º 
41
´W

], 

IX. 
2009
, window trap, Seag 
leg
., 
7
males

, 
1
female

.
</p>
            <p>New Record:French Guiana
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
: 
344</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Reduvius ventralis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
: 
280</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa, 
2005
: 
400</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
P. 
jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pothea berengeri sp. nov. from Brazil, with taxonomic notes on Pothea furtadoi Gil-Santana &amp; Costa and Pothea jaguaris (Carpintero) and reinstatement of Parapothea Carpintero as junior synonym of Pothea Amyot &amp; Serville (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae: Ectrichodiinae)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3826.3.4</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFD1FF98A516FFECFFC4FFC3DD1D3964</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3826.3.4</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Figures 
1
–14, 15– 
28
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
Figures 
29–47
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
, REINSTATED COMBINATION

Figures 
48–71
, 

Tables 
1–4
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
: 
344</tp:taxon-name>
–345 [description]; 

Stål, 
1859
, 176 [key], 
184
[redescription], 
184–185
[checklist of species]; 

Stål, 
1872
: 
101
[key], 
103–104
[checklist and key to species]; 

Walker, 
1873
a

: 
47
[key], 
80
[key]; 

Walker, 
1873
b

: 
63
–64 [checklist and key to four species]; 

Lethierry &amp; Severin, 
1896
: 
131
[catalog]; 

Champion, 
1898
: 
221
[diagnosis, key to Central American species]; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1949
: 
23
[catalog]; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1951
: 
36
[key]; 

Carpintero, 
1978
: 
177
–286 [revision of the genus and Argentinean species]; 

Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
[diagnosis]; 

Putshkov &amp; Putshkov, 
1985
: 
16
[catalog]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
65–67
[catalog]; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
202
[key], 
211–212
[diagnosis, checklist of species]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
126
[key], 
135–136
[diagnosis]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[diagnosis], 
181–182
[key]; 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

: 
71
[key].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduvius ventralis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
: 
280</tp:taxon-name>
, by subsequent designation: 

Van Duzee, 
1916
: 
29
.
</p>
            <p>Anapothea
Miller, 
1956
: 
8
; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1959
: 
297
[as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
]. 
Type
species: 
Anapothea amoena
Miller, 
1956
: 
8
, by original designation.
</p>
            <p>Parapothea
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
[description]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
64
[catalog]; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
211
[as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
126
[key], 
134–135
[diagnosis]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[diagnosis], 
181
[key]; 

Forero, 
2006
: 
8
[discussion on validity]; 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

: 
71
[key]; 
REINSTATED SYNONYMY
.
</p>
            <p>Type
species: 

Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
, by original designation.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking sexual dimorphism in males, with first antennal segment almost completely glabrous and second antennal with short pilosity. The rounded tylus, size of male ocelli equal to females; and eyes somewhat smaller than eyes of female are also diagnostic. Females with hemelytra somewhat longer or reaching the tip of abdomen; male hemelytra shorter, not reaching the tip of the abdomen (Figs. 1, 15, 
24
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description.Male
. MEASUREMENTS: Total length: 
17.3
; head: total length (including collum): 4.0; maximum width across the eyes: 
1.6
; ante-ocular length: 
1.9
; post-ocular length: 
1.6
; interocular space: 
0.9
; transverse width of right eye: 
0.3
; length of right eye, measured from above: 
0.5
; ocellar tubercle width: 
0.6
; right ocellus width: 
0.18
; antennal segments: I: 2.0; II: 3.0; III: 
1.2
; IV: 
0.7
; V: 
0.55
; VI: 
0.4
; VII: 
0.35
; VIII: 
0.5
; labium segments: II [first visible]: 
2.5
; III: 1.0; IV: 
0.5
. Thorax: pronotum: fore lobe length: 
1.2
; hind lobe: length: 
2.4
; width at posterior margin: 
4.2
; scutellum: length: 
1.7
; width at base: 
1.9
. Legs: fore legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 4.0; tarsus: 
1.4
; middle legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 4.0; tarsus: 
1.5
; hind legs: femur: 5.0; tibia: 
5.5
; tarsus: 
1.7
. Abdomen: length: 
8.6
; maximum width: 
5.1
. COLORATION: General coloration yellowish-orange to orange-red, with reddish, brownish or blackish markings (Figs. 1, 5). 
Head
(Fig. 
1
): with reddish markings along midline, more prominent on clypeus, almost all ocellar tubercle red, antennal tubercles and around eyes also red; well marked blackish spots behind ocelli and very faint ones in front of them, both on the ocellar tubercle; eyes blackish. Antenna: first antennal segment orange-yellowish; second segment somewhat dark, orange-yellowish basally; other segments darkened to brownish, except on the joints, which are clear, yellowish to whitish. 
Thorax
(Figs. 1, 5– 
6
). Pronotum: anterior margin, anterior portion of longitudinal sulcus, lateral portions of the transverse sulcus, lateral stripe on anterior portion of propleura, and a somewhat rounded spot on posterior portion of propleura slightly dark to brownish. Central portion and lateral margins of scutellum dark. Meso and metapleura and sterna darkened, intersegmental sutures around metapleura marked with black. Apical third of femora somewhat reddish. Hemelytra: corium somewhat orange-yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum blackish except at base; a pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion; subapical lateral portion somewhat reddish, apex darkened; membrane dark brown. 
Abdomen
(Figs. 1, 7). Connexivum orange in internal portion, dorsally, and reddish in external portion, dorsally and ventrally; sternites orange-yellowish, with the distal portion of sternite VII, posterior to pygophore, as reddish as connexivum; sternite II [first visible] without dark markings; intersegmental area between sternites II and III, where there are canaliculae, somewhat darkened; other sternites with small dark, brownish to blackish markings as follows: lateral subsquared or subrounded markings on segments III–VI; a pair of small dark curved stripes on mid portion of sternites III–IV; curved bands, which are larger in their median portion, on midline of sternites V and VI, the latter smaller; sternite VII with a very faint dark spot just anterior to pygophore and lateral small rounded dark markings; area around spiracles somewhat darkened as well. VESTITURE: Integument almost completely glabrous and shiny (Figs. 
1
–2, 5– 
7
). Antennae with first segment almost completely glabrous, with just a small yellowish-orange seta on the middle of internal face in the right antenna; basal portion of segment II glabrous; remainder of this segment and others covered with moderately short setae and a few longer ones; on segment II, the short setae length are approximately half the width of the segment, while the length of 
PLATE1
.

Figs. 
1–7
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, male 
holotype
, 
1
, dorsal view, 
2
, head, lateral view, 
3–4
, right antenna, dorsal view, 
4
, segment I and proximal portion of segment II, the arrow points to a setae, 
5
, pronotum and scutellum, dorsal view, 
6
, pronotum, lateral view, 
7
, abdomen, ventral view.
</p>
            <p>
the few longer setae are approximately 
1.2
times the width of the segment (Figs. 
3–4
). Labium with yellowish to orange sparse setae on ventral face of basal portion of labial segment II, apex of labial segment III, and on base, dorsally, and apex of labial segment IV (Fig. 
2
). Legs with short hairs on fore and median trochanters and a mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange very short hairs on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration. STRUCTURE: Head elongated; clypeus elevated and rounded; eyes moderate size; ocellar tubercle prominent, undivided; labium thick, segment II longer than the others together and surpassing posterior margin of eyes (Figs. 
1–2
); antennae eight-segmented (Fig. 
3
). Pronotum: anterior margin as a thin collar; surface smooth with a pair of short, rounded tubercles medially just between anterior and posterior lobes of pronotum; longitudinal sulcus on anterior lobe shallow, somewhat more profound in second half; in first half of posterior lobe it is represented only by four small punctures, the most anterior just below the pair of rounded tubercles; transverse (interlobar) sulcus formed by small and shallow impressions (canaliculae); both sulci interrupted medially by the pair of tubercles, not reaching each other. Lateral sulcus of posterior lobe of pronotum weak, formed by shallow canaliculae anteriorly; humeral angles rounded. Scutellum with a deep median depression; prongs short and convergent (Figs. 1, 5– 
6
). Legs slender; fore and mid femora somewhat thicker than hind ones; these latter slightly thick subapically; protibia conspicuously thick at apex, mainly in anterior portion; other tibiae less thick 
PLATE2
.

Figs. 
8–14
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
holotype
, male genitalia, 
8–9
, pygophore and parameres, 
8
, ventral view, 
9
, dorsal view, 
10
, median process of pygophore, 
11
, left paramere, ventral and dorsal view, respectively, 
12–13
, phallus, 
12
, lateral view, 
13
, dorsal view, 
14
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view.
</p>
            <p>
at apex, mid pair a little more than hind tibiae; small spongy fossa on pro and mid tibiae; presence of a median ventral shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted, on fore and mid femora and all tibiae, less marked on hind ones. Hemelytra not reaching tip of abdomen (Fig. 
1
). Connexivum, in lateral view, with postero-lateral angles somewhat prominent, which is more accentuated in segment II. Sternites II and III separated by canaliculae; other intersternite furrow more evident in median portion and almost imperceptible laterally (Fig. 
7
). 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
8–14
): pygophore sub-squared, posterior margin sinuate; parameres apices close in resting position (Figs. 
8–9
). Median process of pygophore sclerotized, apex rounded (Figs. 
9–10
). Parameres symmetrical, curved, somewhat enlarged, truncated at apex, with short slots on median and medial portion and a small tooth at lateral portion of the apex (Figs. 
8
–9, 11). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately short, subretangular; phalothecal dorsal plate somewhat elongated with angles rounded, sinuous in center of anterior margin; struts rather enlarged at basal half, united at the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
12–13
). Median process of endosoma subtriangular, apex rounded, with a central sclerotized structure, which has three divergent branches directed upward (Fig. 
14
). 
Female
: MEASUREMENTS: Total length: 
17–17.5
; head: total length (including collum): 
4.2–4.4
; maximum width across the eyes: 
1.6–1.7
; ante-ocular length: 
1.8
–2.0; post-ocular length: 
1.6–1.8
; interocular space: 
0.9
–1.0; transverse width of right eye: 
0.35
; length of right eye, measured from above: 
0.6–0.7
; ocellar tubercle width: 
0.6–0.8
; right ocellus width: 
0.18–0.20
; antennal segments: I: 
1.9
–2.0; II: 
3.2–3.5
; III: 
1.3–1.4
; IV: 
0.8–0.9
; [V–VIII, absent in one 
paratype
]; V: 
0.6
; VI: 
0.4
; VII: 
0.4
; VIII: 
0.6
; labial segments: II [first visible]: 
2.7–2.8
; III: 
1.2
; IV: 
0.5
. Thorax: pronotum: fore lobe length: 1.0 – 
1.3
; hind lobe: length: 
2.3–2.4
; width at posterior margin: 
4.6–4.7
; scutellum: length: 
1.6–1.8
; width at base: 2.0– 
2.4
. Legs: fore legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 
4.3
; tarsus: 
1.4–1.5
; middle legs: femur: 
4.1–4.2
; tibia: 4.0– 
4.2
; tarsus: 
1.6
; hind legs: femur: 
5.4
; tibia: 
5.8
–6.0; tarsus: 
1.8
. Abdomen: length: 
8.5–9.3
; maximum width: 
5.6–5.9
. COLORATION: similar to male. General coloration is reddish to clear (Figs. 15, 24). 
Head
: the reddish markings on the head smaller than male or absent (Figs. 16, 19). 
Thorax
: a pair of suboval faint brownish median spots present on hind lobe of pronotum (Figs. 15, 19, 24, 27); propleura with a dark faint and irregular stripe on upper portion; meso and metapleurae and sterna fairly dark; pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion of corium of hemelytra present (Fig. 
15
) and can form a darkened larger spot (Fig. 
24
); sternite II with a pair of sublateral brownish faint sublateral stripes, and five pairs of subquadrate to subtriangular lateral spots on sternites III–VII, and a small median spot on sternite III and median bands on sternites IV–VI, which are larger in the middle portion, especially in sternite VI and almost reach the lateral spots on sternites IV–V and right side of sternite VI, joining the lateral spot in left side of sternite VI (Fig. 
22
). STRUCTURE: Head somewhat larger in profile (Fig. 
16
); first antennal segment completely glabrous (Figs. 
17–18
) or with ten setae on the internal face of this segment (Figs. 
25–26
). Hemelytra can reach tip of abdomen (Fig. 
24
). 
Female genitalia
: Posterior view of external genitalia as Fig. 
23
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.Brazil
, states of Mato Grosso and Bahia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The new species is named in honor of the French entomologist, Jean-Michel Bérenger, for his great contribution to the study of 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>PLATE3
.

Figs. 
15–22
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, female 
paratype
, specimen from Bahia, 
Brazil
, 
15
, dorsal view, 
16
, head, lateral view, 
17– 18
, right antenna, proximal segments, dorsal view, 
19
, head and pronotum, dorsal view, 
20
, fore femur, lateral view, 
21
, fore tibia and tarsus, dorsal view, 
22
, ventral view.
</p>
            <p>PLATE4
.

Figs. 
23– 28
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, female 
paratype
, 
23
, specimen from Bahia, external genitalia, posterior view, 
24–28
, 
paratype
from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
24
, dorsal view, 
25–26
, right antenna, dorsal view, 
26
, segment I, 
27
, pronotum and scutellum, dorsal view, 
28
, ventral view.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
The following variability was present in the female 
paratype
of this species: the pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion of corium of hemelytra is somewhat smaller in one 
paratype
(Fig. 
15
) and forms a darkened larger spot in the 
paratype
with reddish coloration (Fig. 
24
); the reddish markings on the head was absent in the 
paratype
with clear coloration. The sternites in the other 
paratype
have a brighter coloration, almost yellowish, while the markings are darker, except on sternite II, in which, besides smaller, forming spots, they are fainter; the median bands are larger in the middle portion and do not reach the lateral spots in any segment; on the sternites V–VI they form subtriangular spots and not bands; the lateral markings on sternite VII are much smaller, simple dots (Fig. 
28
). The 
paratype
with reddish coloration has a somewhat thicker fore and mid femora and the hemelytra reaches the tip of the abdomen. Despite the mentioned variation, all the common features between the females, particularly in the structure of head and pronotum, are prone to consider them as conspecific.
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
Holotype
: 
BRAZIL
, Mato Grosso,

Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
20
.X. 
1983
, J. Becker, O. Roppa &amp; B.S. 
leg.
[
MNRJ
]; 
1
male

. 
Paratypes
: 
BRAZIL
, Bahia,

Encruzilhada, BR 
116
, Divisa, XI.[
19
] 
74
, O. Roppa 
leg
., 
1
female

; 
Mato Grosso,
Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
10
.X. 
1988
, O. Roppa &amp; J. Becker 
leg
. [
MNRJ
], 
1
female

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa, 
2005
: 
400</tp:taxon-name>
–404 [description].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.Male:
Total length: 18.0–21.0; COLORATION: general coloration mostly reddish, but somewhat brighter in a few specimens, with darkened or blackish markings; legs with submedian small markings on femora; variable extent and intensity of darkness on femoral apices and subbasal and apical rings on tibiae; variation also present on the corium of hemelytra, which is reddish on most extension or somewhat brighter to almost yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum, apex and a stripe in the central portion, brownish to blackish, and variable dark coloration (Figs.
</p>
            <p>29
–30, 41, 
44
). Connexivum reddish, without markings (Figs. 29, 41) or yellowish, with approximately two thirds of each segment pink colored distally (Fig. 
44
). Blackish markings on the sternites III–VII form transverse stripes, variable in thickness, enlarged at the lateral portion, anterior extension in front of the respective spiracle in the sternites III–VI sometimes present (Fig. 
32
). These stripes are interrupted or incomplete in two or three segments, in which there are a median and a pair of lateral blackish markings instead of a stripe in some specimens (Figs. 42, 45– 
46
). STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Head: antenna eight segmented, all segments pubescent (Fig. 
31
); clypeus denticulate. Thorax: integument of pronotum smooth and shiny; midlongitudinal sulcus in anterior pronotal lobe not reaching interlobar sulcus, moderately deep; midlongitudinal (in the first half of posterior lobe), transverse (interlobar) and posterolateral sulci formed by canaliculae and well developed; humeral angles rounded (Figs. 
29
–30, 41, 
44
). Legs slender, femora, particularly fore and mid, somewhat thicker, with patches of slightly long yellowish hairs on ventral face of fore and mid trochanters and femora, in the latter, they are more numerous on the basal half; in some specimens these hairs are shorter or less numerous; mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange short hairs on median portion of ventral face of all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration; presence of a median ventral, shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; spongy fossa well developed on pro and mid tibiae. 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
33
–40, 43, 
47
): pygophore subpentagonal, posterior margin sinuate; paramere apices close in resting position (Figs. 
33–34
). Median process of pygophore somewhat elongated, subquadrate and sclerotized (Figs. 
34–35
). Parameres symmetrical, curved, with a short subapical tooth, rounded at apex (Figs. 
33
–34, 36). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately short; dorsal phallothecal plate lozenge shaped, sinuous in center of anterior margin, struts enlarged at basal half and united at the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
37–39
). Endosoma with a pair of lateral conjunctiva processes approximately at the median portion (Figs. 
37–38
). Median process of endosoma rounded, with central sclerotized structure somewhat like a “Y” (Fig. 
40
) or similar to a “T” (Figs. 43, 47).
</p>
            <p>PLATE5
.

Figs. 
29–36
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, males from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
29
, dorsal view, 
30
, head, pronotum and basal portion of hemelytra, dorsal view, 
31
, right antenna, segments I–III, dorsal view, 
32
, abdomen, latero-ventral view, 
33–36
, male genitalia, 
33–34
, pygophore and parameres, 
33
, ventral view, 
34
, dorsal view, 
35
, median process of pygophore, 
36
, right paramere, dorsal and ventral view, respectively.
</p>
            <p>PLATE6
. Figs. 
37–47
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
37–40
, male genitalia, specimen from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
37–39
, phallus, 
37
, lateral view, 
38
, latero-dorsal view, 
39
dorsal view, 
40
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, Figs. 
41–47
, males, 
41–43
, 
paratype
from Minas Gerais, 
Brazil
, 
41
, dorsal view, 
42
, ventral view, 
43
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, 
44–47
, specimen from Maranhão, 
Brazil
, 
44
, dorsal view, 
45
, ventral view, 
46
, latero-ventral view, 
47
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
There is size and morphological differences between the males of this species. The male from the state of Maranhão, for example, has a different coloration in connexivum (Fig. 
44
) and is smaller in total length, being 
17.1
millimeters. Variability in the dark markings of the body was also observed, particularly on the legs, with submedian small markings on femora in two specimens; variable extent and intensity of darkness on femoral apices and subbasal and apical rings on tibiae; variation also present on the corium of hemelytra, which is reddish on most extension or somewhat brighter to almost yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum, apex and a stripe in the central portion, brownish to blackish, and variable dark coloration (Figs. 
29
–30, 41, 
44
). However, as already described by 

Gil-Santana &amp; Costa (
2005
)

, the blackish markings on the sternites III–VII form transverse stripes, with some variability in thickness, enlarged at the lateral portion, where it may have an anterior extension in front of the respective spiracle in the sternites III–VI (Fig. 
32
). The different portions of male genitalia were shown to be similar among the specimens examined. The shapes of the dorsal phallotecal plate and struts are particularly characteristic (Fig. 
39
). The median process of the endosoma in males from different states of 
Brazil
and with very diverse coloration (Figs. 
29
–30, 32, 
41
–42, 44– 
46
) showed minor variation (Figs. 40, 43 and 
47
).
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
BRAZIL
, Bahia,

Encruzilhada, BR 
116
, Divisa, XI.[
19
] 
74
, O. Roppa 
leg
., 
1
male

[
MNRJ
]; 
Goiás
, Mambaí, Gruta [cavern] da Tarimba, 
29
.IV. 
2013
, M. E. Bichuette 
et al
. 
leg
., 
1
male

; 
Maranhão
, Caxias Inhamum (045439S - 
432616
W), 
535 m
, 
17
.V. 
2007
, Luz [light], F.F. Xavier F° &amp; F.L. Oliveira 
leg.
, 
1
male

[
INPA
]; 
Holotype
: Mato Grosso,

Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
30
.IX. 
2002
, E. Furtado 
leg
., 
1
male

; 
20
.X. 
1983
, J.B., O.R. &amp; B.S. 
leg.
, 
2
males

[
MNRJ
]; 
Paratype
: Minas Gerais,

Belo Horizonte (
19
º 
54
´S

– 
43
º 
56
´W

), 

06.X. 
1959
, Evangelista 
leg
., 
1
male

[
MNRJ
]; 
Paraná
, Fênix, Reserva Est.– 
ITCF
, Lev. Ent. PROFAUPAR, 

02.X. 
1986
, lâmpada [at light], 
1
male

[
DZUP
].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
–10, 32 [description]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
64
[catalog]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
129
, 134 [figures, citation as 
type
species]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[citation]; 

Forero, 
2006
: 
8
[citation]; 

Gil-Santana, 
2007
: 
60
[new record].
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
212
[new combination, checklist].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Redescription.Female:
Total length 
16.2–18.5
(

Table 
1
). 
Male
: Total length: 
14.6–18.5
(

Tables 
2–4
). COLORATION: The coloration is quite variable, yellowish-orange and/or with reddish suffusions, to somewhat yellow-brownish general coloration, with blackish markings, variably present in their extent on head, including collum, labium segments, distal portion of labrum, thorax, including legs and corium of hemelytra and sternites (Figs. 
48–60
). Antennae blackish with joints clear; basal portion of segment I yellowish in variable extent in some specimens; hairs and setae of antennae brownish red to yellowish distally (Figs. 54, 58). Thorax: pronotum with three pairs of blackish spots: 
1
—anteriorly on the fore lobe of pronotum; 
2
—suboval spots on central portion of hind lobe of pronotum, variable in size and extent and variably confluent in midportion, in the region of the median sulcus as well; 
3
—on lateral portion of approximately distal half of fore lobe and basal half of hind lobe of pronotum, including the transverse furrow laterally (Figs. 
48
–52, 56, 
59
). Pleurae and sterna with blackish spots and markings in variable extents to almost blackish in darker specimens. Legs: femora with base, submedian distal ring and apex blackish, with some variability in the extent or presence of these markings; tibiae with base and two rings, submedian proximal and distal, blackish, variable as well; in two specimens, tibiae almost all blackish with subbasal ring and distal portion yellowish; tarsi yellowish to yellowish-orange. Corium of hemelytra variably marked with dark spots together with yellowish areas, spots on veins, or some of these latter yellowish-colored to variable extent, to almost completely blackish; membrane of hemelytra blackish (Figs. 48, 51, 56, 59). Connexivum shows alternating blackish and yellow-reddish coloration, but the latter is darker in some specimens (Figs. 48, 51, 56, 59). Sternites yellowish with very variable blackish markings on sternites; sternite II with a transverse blackish band, for which dimensions both in transverse and antero-posterior directions are variable among specimens. Sternites III–VI with lateral large spots accompanied by central bands, which have variable format along the segments, or become a pair of median separated spots, or the latter variably fused, sometimes forming a large dark band, occupying the majority of the segment. Sternite VII with lateral blackish spots of variable size; a median distal band which can be shaped as an inverted “V” or as a smaller spot with variable size, and a pair or two pairs of small subrounded dark spots, of variabe size in some specimens (Figs. 50, 55, 
60
).
</p>
            <p>PLATE7
. Figs. 
48–56
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, 
48–55
, female, 
48–50
, specimen from 
Bolivia
, 
48–49
, dorsal view, 
49
, head and thorax, 
50
, latero-ventral view, 
51
, specimen from Ceará, 
Brazil
, dorsal view, 
52–55
, specimen from Amapá, 
Brazil
, 
52
, head and thorax, dorsal view, 
53
, head, lateral view, 
54
, antennal segment I, dorsal view, 
55
, latero-ventral view, 
56
, male from Acre, 
Brazil
.
</p>
            <p>
STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Integument mostly glabrous shiny and smooth (Figs 
48
–53, 55–57, 59– 
60
). 
Head.
Antenna: eight segmented, with hairs and setae brownish red to yellowish distally; in males, all segments pubescent (Fig. 
58
). First segment thicker than others, bare in mid-dorsal region, hairs somewhat longer than the transverse width of segment (Fig. 
58
); second antennal segment with long hairs, which are two to almost three times as long as width of the segment (Fig. 
58
). Clypeus denticulate in males. Labium thick with sparse setae, more numerous on ventral face of segment II few at the apex of segment III, and some scattered on segment IV; segment II longer than the others together and surpassing posterior margin of the eyes (Figs. 53, 57). 
Thorax
(Figs. 
48
–49, 51–52, 56, 
59
): Integument of pronotum on anterior lobe of pronotum moderately rugous or smooth; midlongitudinal sulcus in anterior pronotal lobe not reaching interlobar sulcus; deep enough to form a pair of protuberant paramedial lobes in some specimens, but in others it is shallow and there is no evidence of such lobes, even in larger specimens; midlongitudinal (in the first half of posterior lobe), transverse (interlobar) and posterolateral sulci formed by canaliculae, which vary in depth among the specimens; humeral angles rounded. Femora, particularly, fore and mid femora, thick in some specimens, with patches of long and numerous yellowish hairs on ventral surface of fore and mid trochanters and femora. In mid trochanters and femora, hairs are more numerous on the basal half; in some specimens these hairs are shorter or less numerous; mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange hairs on median portion of ventral face of all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration; presence of a median ventral shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; in some specimens this crest is not perceptible on femora; spongy fossa well developed on pro and meso tibiae. Hemelytra length varied from shorter than abdomen to slightly surpassing the tip. 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
61–71
): pygophore subrounded, posterior margin rounded; paramere apices close in resting position (Figs. 
61–62
). Median process of pygophore sclerotized, apex rounded or slightly subtriangular (Figs. 
62–63
). Parameres symmetrical, a little curved, with sparse hairs, with a short subapical tooth (Figs. 
61
–62, 64). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately long, subquadrate; dorsal phallothecal plate oval, sinuous in center of anterior margin, lateral margins somewhat bent; struts enlarged at basal half and united in the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
65–67
). Median process of endosoma subquadrate, with central sclerotized structure in the shape of an “X” (Fig. 
70
), or more similar to a “T” (Figs. 69, 71) including other specimen with darker sternites (Fig. 
60
, B).
</p>
            <p>PLATE8
. Figs. 
57–65
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, male, 
57–58
, specimen from Acre, 
Brazil
, 
57
, head, lateral view, 
58
, right antenna, segments I–II, dorsal view, 
59–60
, specimens from 
French Guiana
, 
59
, dorsal view, 
60
, ventral view, 
61–65
, male genitalia, 
61–62
, pygophore and parameres, 
61
, ventral view, 
62
, dorsal view, 
63
, median process of pygophore, 
64
, right paramere, dorsal and ventral view, respectively, 
65
, phallus, dorsal view.
</p>
            <p>PLATE9
. Figs. 
66–71
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, male genitalia, 
66–67
, phallus with expanded endosoma, 
66
, lateral view, 
67
, dorsal view, 
68
, median portion of expanded endosoma, with the median process, dorsal view, 
69–71
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, 
69
, male from Pará, 
Brazil
, 
70–71
, males from 
French Guiana
, 
70
, from male of Fig. 
60
, A, 
71
, from male of Fig. 
60
, B.
</p>
            <p>Female
: COLORATION: same as males. STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Antenna: first and basal half of the second segment of females are bare or very sparsely pubescent; first segment thicker than others, completely bare to 
20
short setae on internal face; second segment with setae shorter or a little longer than the width of the segment, with very few scattered longer erect hairs 
ca.
twice as long as the width of the segment (Fig. 
54
). Clypeus rounded in females; Hemelytra did not reach tip of abdomen in the females examined.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
As possible sexual dimorphism in eyes and ocellus sizes were not clear when examining the specimens, some selected measures were recorded (

Tables 
1–4
) to investigate this. There were other observed variations in the specimens of this taxon: all specimens except the female from 
Bolivia
and a male from 
French Guiana
have a small rounded tubercle on the ventral portion of the head (gula) anteriorly (Figs. 53, 57), as well as size variation of the tubercle among the specimens; while in the male from 
French Guiana
, in which the tubercle is absent, some setae are present on the same area of gula. Investigating the male genitalia, the different portions of male genitalia were shown to be similar among the specimens examined, with very subtle differences in the thickness of parameres or size of teeth; median process of pygophore rounded to slightly subtriangular. Those differences showed intermediate or gradual states, occurring randomly among specimens, negating any association with color pattern or geographical precedence. The median process of the endosoma showed some minor variation as well, with the central sclerotized structure similar in shape to a “T” (Figs. 69, 71) recorded in specimens with more or less dark body markings from 
Brazil
and 
French Guiana
(Fig. 
60
, B), while its structure presented as the shape of an “X” (Fig. 
70
) in a male from 
French Guiana
with paler body markings (Fig. 
60
, A). However, the shapes of the dorsal phallothecal plate and struts (Fig. 
65
) are particularly characteristic and there was no noticeable variation among specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
BOLIVIA
, 
Bolivia
Tropica

, Región Chaparé, 
400m
, 

XII- 
1949
, Zischka [? 
leg.
], 
1
female

; 
BRAZIL
, Acre,
11 km
NE de Rio Branco, 
5–10
.V. 
1981
, Penny &amp; Elias 
leg.
, 
1
male

; 
Amapá
, Serra do Navio, 

VII- 
1959
, J. Lane 
leg.
, 
1
female

, [
MNRJ
]; 
Amazonas
, Campo Petrolífero do Urucu-Coari (

04º 
53
´42,5” S

– 
65
º 
11
´16,2” W

), 
21
.IX–04.X. 
2004
, José A.M. Fernandes 
leg.
, 
2
males

; 
Ceará
, Carquejo, 
1
female

, 

III.1963, 
1
female; 
FRENCH GUIANA
, 
Nourages
[

04º 
52
´N

– 
52
º 
41
´W

], 

IX. 
2009
, window trap, Seag 
leg
., 
7
males

, 
1
female

.
</p>
            <p>New Record:French Guiana
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
: 
344</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Reduvius ventralis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
: 
280</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa, 
2005
: 
400</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
P. 
jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pothea berengeri sp. nov. from Brazil, with taxonomic notes on Pothea furtadoi Gil-Santana &amp; Costa and Pothea jaguaris (Carpintero) and reinstatement of Parapothea Carpintero as junior synonym of Pothea Amyot &amp; Serville (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae: Ectrichodiinae)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3826.3.4</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFD1FF98A516FFECFFC4FFC3DD1D3964</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.11646/zootaxa.3826.3.4</pub-id>
               <issn>1175-5326</issn>
               <source>Zootaxa</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
Figures 
1
–14, 15– 
28
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa
</tp:taxon-name>
Figures 
29–47
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris
(Carpintero)
</tp:taxon-name>
, REINSTATED COMBINATION

Figures 
48–71
, 

Tables 
1–4
.
</tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
: 
344</tp:taxon-name>
–345 [description]; 

Stål, 
1859
, 176 [key], 
184
[redescription], 
184–185
[checklist of species]; 

Stål, 
1872
: 
101
[key], 
103–104
[checklist and key to species]; 

Walker, 
1873
a

: 
47
[key], 
80
[key]; 

Walker, 
1873
b

: 
63
–64 [checklist and key to four species]; 

Lethierry &amp; Severin, 
1896
: 
131
[catalog]; 

Champion, 
1898
: 
221
[diagnosis, key to Central American species]; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1949
: 
23
[catalog]; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1951
: 
36
[key]; 

Carpintero, 
1978
: 
177
–286 [revision of the genus and Argentinean species]; 

Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
[diagnosis]; 

Putshkov &amp; Putshkov, 
1985
: 
16
[catalog]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
65–67
[catalog]; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
202
[key], 
211–212
[diagnosis, checklist of species]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
126
[key], 
135–136
[diagnosis]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[diagnosis], 
181–182
[key]; 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

: 
71
[key].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduvius ventralis
Lepeletier &amp; Serville, 
1825
: 
280</tp:taxon-name>
, by subsequent designation: 

Van Duzee, 
1916
: 
29
.
</p>
            <p>Anapothea
Miller, 
1956
: 
8
; 

Wygodzinsky, 
1959
: 
297
[as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
]. 
Type
species: 
Anapothea amoena
Miller, 
1956
: 
8
, by original designation.
</p>
            <p>Parapothea
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
[description]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
64
[catalog]; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
211
[as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
126
[key], 
134–135
[diagnosis]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[diagnosis], 
181
[key]; 

Forero, 
2006
: 
8
[discussion on validity]; 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

: 
71
[key]; 
REINSTATED SYNONYMY
.
</p>
            <p>Type
species: 

Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
, by original designation.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
differs from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking sexual dimorphism in males, with first antennal segment almost completely glabrous and second antennal with short pilosity. The rounded tylus, size of male ocelli equal to females; and eyes somewhat smaller than eyes of female are also diagnostic. Females with hemelytra somewhat longer or reaching the tip of abdomen; male hemelytra shorter, not reaching the tip of the abdomen (Figs. 1, 15, 
24
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description.Male
. MEASUREMENTS: Total length: 
17.3
; head: total length (including collum): 4.0; maximum width across the eyes: 
1.6
; ante-ocular length: 
1.9
; post-ocular length: 
1.6
; interocular space: 
0.9
; transverse width of right eye: 
0.3
; length of right eye, measured from above: 
0.5
; ocellar tubercle width: 
0.6
; right ocellus width: 
0.18
; antennal segments: I: 2.0; II: 3.0; III: 
1.2
; IV: 
0.7
; V: 
0.55
; VI: 
0.4
; VII: 
0.35
; VIII: 
0.5
; labium segments: II [first visible]: 
2.5
; III: 1.0; IV: 
0.5
. Thorax: pronotum: fore lobe length: 
1.2
; hind lobe: length: 
2.4
; width at posterior margin: 
4.2
; scutellum: length: 
1.7
; width at base: 
1.9
. Legs: fore legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 4.0; tarsus: 
1.4
; middle legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 4.0; tarsus: 
1.5
; hind legs: femur: 5.0; tibia: 
5.5
; tarsus: 
1.7
. Abdomen: length: 
8.6
; maximum width: 
5.1
. COLORATION: General coloration yellowish-orange to orange-red, with reddish, brownish or blackish markings (Figs. 1, 5). 
Head
(Fig. 
1
): with reddish markings along midline, more prominent on clypeus, almost all ocellar tubercle red, antennal tubercles and around eyes also red; well marked blackish spots behind ocelli and very faint ones in front of them, both on the ocellar tubercle; eyes blackish. Antenna: first antennal segment orange-yellowish; second segment somewhat dark, orange-yellowish basally; other segments darkened to brownish, except on the joints, which are clear, yellowish to whitish. 
Thorax
(Figs. 1, 5– 
6
). Pronotum: anterior margin, anterior portion of longitudinal sulcus, lateral portions of the transverse sulcus, lateral stripe on anterior portion of propleura, and a somewhat rounded spot on posterior portion of propleura slightly dark to brownish. Central portion and lateral margins of scutellum dark. Meso and metapleura and sterna darkened, intersegmental sutures around metapleura marked with black. Apical third of femora somewhat reddish. Hemelytra: corium somewhat orange-yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum blackish except at base; a pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion; subapical lateral portion somewhat reddish, apex darkened; membrane dark brown. 
Abdomen
(Figs. 1, 7). Connexivum orange in internal portion, dorsally, and reddish in external portion, dorsally and ventrally; sternites orange-yellowish, with the distal portion of sternite VII, posterior to pygophore, as reddish as connexivum; sternite II [first visible] without dark markings; intersegmental area between sternites II and III, where there are canaliculae, somewhat darkened; other sternites with small dark, brownish to blackish markings as follows: lateral subsquared or subrounded markings on segments III–VI; a pair of small dark curved stripes on mid portion of sternites III–IV; curved bands, which are larger in their median portion, on midline of sternites V and VI, the latter smaller; sternite VII with a very faint dark spot just anterior to pygophore and lateral small rounded dark markings; area around spiracles somewhat darkened as well. VESTITURE: Integument almost completely glabrous and shiny (Figs. 
1
–2, 5– 
7
). Antennae with first segment almost completely glabrous, with just a small yellowish-orange seta on the middle of internal face in the right antenna; basal portion of segment II glabrous; remainder of this segment and others covered with moderately short setae and a few longer ones; on segment II, the short setae length are approximately half the width of the segment, while the length of 
PLATE1
.

Figs. 
1–7
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, male 
holotype
, 
1
, dorsal view, 
2
, head, lateral view, 
3–4
, right antenna, dorsal view, 
4
, segment I and proximal portion of segment II, the arrow points to a setae, 
5
, pronotum and scutellum, dorsal view, 
6
, pronotum, lateral view, 
7
, abdomen, ventral view.
</p>
            <p>
the few longer setae are approximately 
1.2
times the width of the segment (Figs. 
3–4
). Labium with yellowish to orange sparse setae on ventral face of basal portion of labial segment II, apex of labial segment III, and on base, dorsally, and apex of labial segment IV (Fig. 
2
). Legs with short hairs on fore and median trochanters and a mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange very short hairs on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration. STRUCTURE: Head elongated; clypeus elevated and rounded; eyes moderate size; ocellar tubercle prominent, undivided; labium thick, segment II longer than the others together and surpassing posterior margin of eyes (Figs. 
1–2
); antennae eight-segmented (Fig. 
3
). Pronotum: anterior margin as a thin collar; surface smooth with a pair of short, rounded tubercles medially just between anterior and posterior lobes of pronotum; longitudinal sulcus on anterior lobe shallow, somewhat more profound in second half; in first half of posterior lobe it is represented only by four small punctures, the most anterior just below the pair of rounded tubercles; transverse (interlobar) sulcus formed by small and shallow impressions (canaliculae); both sulci interrupted medially by the pair of tubercles, not reaching each other. Lateral sulcus of posterior lobe of pronotum weak, formed by shallow canaliculae anteriorly; humeral angles rounded. Scutellum with a deep median depression; prongs short and convergent (Figs. 1, 5– 
6
). Legs slender; fore and mid femora somewhat thicker than hind ones; these latter slightly thick subapically; protibia conspicuously thick at apex, mainly in anterior portion; other tibiae less thick 
PLATE2
.

Figs. 
8–14
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, 
holotype
, male genitalia, 
8–9
, pygophore and parameres, 
8
, ventral view, 
9
, dorsal view, 
10
, median process of pygophore, 
11
, left paramere, ventral and dorsal view, respectively, 
12–13
, phallus, 
12
, lateral view, 
13
, dorsal view, 
14
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view.
</p>
            <p>
at apex, mid pair a little more than hind tibiae; small spongy fossa on pro and mid tibiae; presence of a median ventral shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted, on fore and mid femora and all tibiae, less marked on hind ones. Hemelytra not reaching tip of abdomen (Fig. 
1
). Connexivum, in lateral view, with postero-lateral angles somewhat prominent, which is more accentuated in segment II. Sternites II and III separated by canaliculae; other intersternite furrow more evident in median portion and almost imperceptible laterally (Fig. 
7
). 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
8–14
): pygophore sub-squared, posterior margin sinuate; parameres apices close in resting position (Figs. 
8–9
). Median process of pygophore sclerotized, apex rounded (Figs. 
9–10
). Parameres symmetrical, curved, somewhat enlarged, truncated at apex, with short slots on median and medial portion and a small tooth at lateral portion of the apex (Figs. 
8
–9, 11). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately short, subretangular; phalothecal dorsal plate somewhat elongated with angles rounded, sinuous in center of anterior margin; struts rather enlarged at basal half, united at the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
12–13
). Median process of endosoma subtriangular, apex rounded, with a central sclerotized structure, which has three divergent branches directed upward (Fig. 
14
). 
Female
: MEASUREMENTS: Total length: 
17–17.5
; head: total length (including collum): 
4.2–4.4
; maximum width across the eyes: 
1.6–1.7
; ante-ocular length: 
1.8
–2.0; post-ocular length: 
1.6–1.8
; interocular space: 
0.9
–1.0; transverse width of right eye: 
0.35
; length of right eye, measured from above: 
0.6–0.7
; ocellar tubercle width: 
0.6–0.8
; right ocellus width: 
0.18–0.20
; antennal segments: I: 
1.9
–2.0; II: 
3.2–3.5
; III: 
1.3–1.4
; IV: 
0.8–0.9
; [V–VIII, absent in one 
paratype
]; V: 
0.6
; VI: 
0.4
; VII: 
0.4
; VIII: 
0.6
; labial segments: II [first visible]: 
2.7–2.8
; III: 
1.2
; IV: 
0.5
. Thorax: pronotum: fore lobe length: 1.0 – 
1.3
; hind lobe: length: 
2.3–2.4
; width at posterior margin: 
4.6–4.7
; scutellum: length: 
1.6–1.8
; width at base: 2.0– 
2.4
. Legs: fore legs: femur: 4.0; tibia: 
4.3
; tarsus: 
1.4–1.5
; middle legs: femur: 
4.1–4.2
; tibia: 4.0– 
4.2
; tarsus: 
1.6
; hind legs: femur: 
5.4
; tibia: 
5.8
–6.0; tarsus: 
1.8
. Abdomen: length: 
8.5–9.3
; maximum width: 
5.6–5.9
. COLORATION: similar to male. General coloration is reddish to clear (Figs. 15, 24). 
Head
: the reddish markings on the head smaller than male or absent (Figs. 16, 19). 
Thorax
: a pair of suboval faint brownish median spots present on hind lobe of pronotum (Figs. 15, 19, 24, 27); propleura with a dark faint and irregular stripe on upper portion; meso and metapleurae and sterna fairly dark; pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion of corium of hemelytra present (Fig. 
15
) and can form a darkened larger spot (Fig. 
24
); sternite II with a pair of sublateral brownish faint sublateral stripes, and five pairs of subquadrate to subtriangular lateral spots on sternites III–VII, and a small median spot on sternite III and median bands on sternites IV–VI, which are larger in the middle portion, especially in sternite VI and almost reach the lateral spots on sternites IV–V and right side of sternite VI, joining the lateral spot in left side of sternite VI (Fig. 
22
). STRUCTURE: Head somewhat larger in profile (Fig. 
16
); first antennal segment completely glabrous (Figs. 
17–18
) or with ten setae on the internal face of this segment (Figs. 
25–26
). Hemelytra can reach tip of abdomen (Fig. 
24
). 
Female genitalia
: Posterior view of external genitalia as Fig. 
23
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution.Brazil
, states of Mato Grosso and Bahia.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology.
The new species is named in honor of the French entomologist, Jean-Michel Bérenger, for his great contribution to the study of 
<tp:taxon-name>Reduviidae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>PLATE3
.

Figs. 
15–22
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, female 
paratype
, specimen from Bahia, 
Brazil
, 
15
, dorsal view, 
16
, head, lateral view, 
17– 18
, right antenna, proximal segments, dorsal view, 
19
, head and pronotum, dorsal view, 
20
, fore femur, lateral view, 
21
, fore tibia and tarsus, dorsal view, 
22
, ventral view.
</p>
            <p>PLATE4
.

Figs. 
23– 28
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, female 
paratype
, 
23
, specimen from Bahia, external genitalia, posterior view, 
24–28
, 
paratype
from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
24
, dorsal view, 
25–26
, right antenna, dorsal view, 
26
, segment I, 
27
, pronotum and scutellum, dorsal view, 
28
, ventral view.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
The following variability was present in the female 
paratype
of this species: the pair of short subparallel brownish-black stripes in the central portion of corium of hemelytra is somewhat smaller in one 
paratype
(Fig. 
15
) and forms a darkened larger spot in the 
paratype
with reddish coloration (Fig. 
24
); the reddish markings on the head was absent in the 
paratype
with clear coloration. The sternites in the other 
paratype
have a brighter coloration, almost yellowish, while the markings are darker, except on sternite II, in which, besides smaller, forming spots, they are fainter; the median bands are larger in the middle portion and do not reach the lateral spots in any segment; on the sternites V–VI they form subtriangular spots and not bands; the lateral markings on sternite VII are much smaller, simple dots (Fig. 
28
). The 
paratype
with reddish coloration has a somewhat thicker fore and mid femora and the hemelytra reaches the tip of the abdomen. Despite the mentioned variation, all the common features between the females, particularly in the structure of head and pronotum, are prone to consider them as conspecific.
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
Holotype
: 
BRAZIL
, Mato Grosso,

Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
20
.X. 
1983
, J. Becker, O. Roppa &amp; B.S. 
leg.
[
MNRJ
]; 
1
male

. 
Paratypes
: 
BRAZIL
, Bahia,

Encruzilhada, BR 
116
, Divisa, XI.[
19
] 
74
, O. Roppa 
leg
., 
1
female

; 
Mato Grosso,
Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
10
.X. 
1988
, O. Roppa &amp; J. Becker 
leg
. [
MNRJ
], 
1
female

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi
Gil-Santana &amp; Costa, 
2005
: 
400</tp:taxon-name>
–404 [description].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>Diagnosis.Male:
Total length: 18.0–21.0; COLORATION: general coloration mostly reddish, but somewhat brighter in a few specimens, with darkened or blackish markings; legs with submedian small markings on femora; variable extent and intensity of darkness on femoral apices and subbasal and apical rings on tibiae; variation also present on the corium of hemelytra, which is reddish on most extension or somewhat brighter to almost yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum, apex and a stripe in the central portion, brownish to blackish, and variable dark coloration (Figs.
</p>
            <p>29
–30, 41, 
44
). Connexivum reddish, without markings (Figs. 29, 41) or yellowish, with approximately two thirds of each segment pink colored distally (Fig. 
44
). Blackish markings on the sternites III–VII form transverse stripes, variable in thickness, enlarged at the lateral portion, anterior extension in front of the respective spiracle in the sternites III–VI sometimes present (Fig. 
32
). These stripes are interrupted or incomplete in two or three segments, in which there are a median and a pair of lateral blackish markings instead of a stripe in some specimens (Figs. 42, 45– 
46
). STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Head: antenna eight segmented, all segments pubescent (Fig. 
31
); clypeus denticulate. Thorax: integument of pronotum smooth and shiny; midlongitudinal sulcus in anterior pronotal lobe not reaching interlobar sulcus, moderately deep; midlongitudinal (in the first half of posterior lobe), transverse (interlobar) and posterolateral sulci formed by canaliculae and well developed; humeral angles rounded (Figs. 
29
–30, 41, 
44
). Legs slender, femora, particularly fore and mid, somewhat thicker, with patches of slightly long yellowish hairs on ventral face of fore and mid trochanters and femora, in the latter, they are more numerous on the basal half; in some specimens these hairs are shorter or less numerous; mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange short hairs on median portion of ventral face of all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration; presence of a median ventral, shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; spongy fossa well developed on pro and mid tibiae. 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
33
–40, 43, 
47
): pygophore subpentagonal, posterior margin sinuate; paramere apices close in resting position (Figs. 
33–34
). Median process of pygophore somewhat elongated, subquadrate and sclerotized (Figs. 
34–35
). Parameres symmetrical, curved, with a short subapical tooth, rounded at apex (Figs. 
33
–34, 36). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately short; dorsal phallothecal plate lozenge shaped, sinuous in center of anterior margin, struts enlarged at basal half and united at the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
37–39
). Endosoma with a pair of lateral conjunctiva processes approximately at the median portion (Figs. 
37–38
). Median process of endosoma rounded, with central sclerotized structure somewhat like a “Y” (Fig. 
40
) or similar to a “T” (Figs. 43, 47).
</p>
            <p>PLATE5
.

Figs. 
29–36
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, males from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
29
, dorsal view, 
30
, head, pronotum and basal portion of hemelytra, dorsal view, 
31
, right antenna, segments I–III, dorsal view, 
32
, abdomen, latero-ventral view, 
33–36
, male genitalia, 
33–34
, pygophore and parameres, 
33
, ventral view, 
34
, dorsal view, 
35
, median process of pygophore, 
36
, right paramere, dorsal and ventral view, respectively.
</p>
            <p>PLATE6
. Figs. 
37–47
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, 
37–40
, male genitalia, specimen from Mato Grosso, 
Brazil
, 
37–39
, phallus, 
37
, lateral view, 
38
, latero-dorsal view, 
39
dorsal view, 
40
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, Figs. 
41–47
, males, 
41–43
, 
paratype
from Minas Gerais, 
Brazil
, 
41
, dorsal view, 
42
, ventral view, 
43
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, 
44–47
, specimen from Maranhão, 
Brazil
, 
44
, dorsal view, 
45
, ventral view, 
46
, latero-ventral view, 
47
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
There is size and morphological differences between the males of this species. The male from the state of Maranhão, for example, has a different coloration in connexivum (Fig. 
44
) and is smaller in total length, being 
17.1
millimeters. Variability in the dark markings of the body was also observed, particularly on the legs, with submedian small markings on femora in two specimens; variable extent and intensity of darkness on femoral apices and subbasal and apical rings on tibiae; variation also present on the corium of hemelytra, which is reddish on most extension or somewhat brighter to almost yellowish, with the area adjacent to scutellum, apex and a stripe in the central portion, brownish to blackish, and variable dark coloration (Figs. 
29
–30, 41, 
44
). However, as already described by 

Gil-Santana &amp; Costa (
2005
)

, the blackish markings on the sternites III–VII form transverse stripes, with some variability in thickness, enlarged at the lateral portion, where it may have an anterior extension in front of the respective spiracle in the sternites III–VI (Fig. 
32
). The different portions of male genitalia were shown to be similar among the specimens examined. The shapes of the dorsal phallotecal plate and struts are particularly characteristic (Fig. 
39
). The median process of the endosoma in males from different states of 
Brazil
and with very diverse coloration (Figs. 
29
–30, 32, 
41
–42, 44– 
46
) showed minor variation (Figs. 40, 43 and 
47
).
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
BRAZIL
, Bahia,

Encruzilhada, BR 
116
, Divisa, XI.[
19
] 
74
, O. Roppa 
leg
., 
1
male

[
MNRJ
]; 
Goiás
, Mambaí, Gruta [cavern] da Tarimba, 
29
.IV. 
2013
, M. E. Bichuette 
et al
. 
leg
., 
1
male

; 
Maranhão
, Caxias Inhamum (045439S - 
432616
W), 
535 m
, 
17
.V. 
2007
, Luz [light], F.F. Xavier F° &amp; F.L. Oliveira 
leg.
, 
1
male

[
INPA
]; 
Holotype
: Mato Grosso,

Diamantino, Alto Rio Arinos (
14
º 
25
´S

– 
56
º 
29
´W

), 
30
.IX. 
2002
, E. Furtado 
leg
., 
1
male

; 
20
.X. 
1983
, J.B., O.R. &amp; B.S. 
leg.
, 
2
males

[
MNRJ
]; 
Paratype
: Minas Gerais,

Belo Horizonte (
19
º 
54
´S

– 
43
º 
56
´W

), 

06.X. 
1959
, Evangelista 
leg
., 
1
male

[
MNRJ
]; 
Paraná
, Fênix, Reserva Est.– 
ITCF
, Lev. Ent. PROFAUPAR, 

02.X. 
1986
, lâmpada [at light], 
1
male

[
DZUP
].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
Carpintero, 
1980
: 
9
–10, 32 [description]; Maldonado, 
1990
: 
64
[catalog]; 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado, 
1996
: 
129
, 134 [figures, citation as 
type
species]; 

Forero, 
2004
: 
144
[citation]; 

Forero, 
2006
: 
8
[citation]; 

Gil-Santana, 
2007
: 
60
[new record].
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
; 

Dougherty, 
1995
: 
212
[new combination, checklist].
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Redescription.Female:
Total length 
16.2–18.5
(

Table 
1
). 
Male
: Total length: 
14.6–18.5
(

Tables 
2–4
). COLORATION: The coloration is quite variable, yellowish-orange and/or with reddish suffusions, to somewhat yellow-brownish general coloration, with blackish markings, variably present in their extent on head, including collum, labium segments, distal portion of labrum, thorax, including legs and corium of hemelytra and sternites (Figs. 
48–60
). Antennae blackish with joints clear; basal portion of segment I yellowish in variable extent in some specimens; hairs and setae of antennae brownish red to yellowish distally (Figs. 54, 58). Thorax: pronotum with three pairs of blackish spots: 
1
—anteriorly on the fore lobe of pronotum; 
2
—suboval spots on central portion of hind lobe of pronotum, variable in size and extent and variably confluent in midportion, in the region of the median sulcus as well; 
3
—on lateral portion of approximately distal half of fore lobe and basal half of hind lobe of pronotum, including the transverse furrow laterally (Figs. 
48
–52, 56, 
59
). Pleurae and sterna with blackish spots and markings in variable extents to almost blackish in darker specimens. Legs: femora with base, submedian distal ring and apex blackish, with some variability in the extent or presence of these markings; tibiae with base and two rings, submedian proximal and distal, blackish, variable as well; in two specimens, tibiae almost all blackish with subbasal ring and distal portion yellowish; tarsi yellowish to yellowish-orange. Corium of hemelytra variably marked with dark spots together with yellowish areas, spots on veins, or some of these latter yellowish-colored to variable extent, to almost completely blackish; membrane of hemelytra blackish (Figs. 48, 51, 56, 59). Connexivum shows alternating blackish and yellow-reddish coloration, but the latter is darker in some specimens (Figs. 48, 51, 56, 59). Sternites yellowish with very variable blackish markings on sternites; sternite II with a transverse blackish band, for which dimensions both in transverse and antero-posterior directions are variable among specimens. Sternites III–VI with lateral large spots accompanied by central bands, which have variable format along the segments, or become a pair of median separated spots, or the latter variably fused, sometimes forming a large dark band, occupying the majority of the segment. Sternite VII with lateral blackish spots of variable size; a median distal band which can be shaped as an inverted “V” or as a smaller spot with variable size, and a pair or two pairs of small subrounded dark spots, of variabe size in some specimens (Figs. 50, 55, 
60
).
</p>
            <p>PLATE7
. Figs. 
48–56
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, 
48–55
, female, 
48–50
, specimen from 
Bolivia
, 
48–49
, dorsal view, 
49
, head and thorax, 
50
, latero-ventral view, 
51
, specimen from Ceará, 
Brazil
, dorsal view, 
52–55
, specimen from Amapá, 
Brazil
, 
52
, head and thorax, dorsal view, 
53
, head, lateral view, 
54
, antennal segment I, dorsal view, 
55
, latero-ventral view, 
56
, male from Acre, 
Brazil
.
</p>
            <p>
STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Integument mostly glabrous shiny and smooth (Figs 
48
–53, 55–57, 59– 
60
). 
Head.
Antenna: eight segmented, with hairs and setae brownish red to yellowish distally; in males, all segments pubescent (Fig. 
58
). First segment thicker than others, bare in mid-dorsal region, hairs somewhat longer than the transverse width of segment (Fig. 
58
); second antennal segment with long hairs, which are two to almost three times as long as width of the segment (Fig. 
58
). Clypeus denticulate in males. Labium thick with sparse setae, more numerous on ventral face of segment II few at the apex of segment III, and some scattered on segment IV; segment II longer than the others together and surpassing posterior margin of the eyes (Figs. 53, 57). 
Thorax
(Figs. 
48
–49, 51–52, 56, 
59
): Integument of pronotum on anterior lobe of pronotum moderately rugous or smooth; midlongitudinal sulcus in anterior pronotal lobe not reaching interlobar sulcus; deep enough to form a pair of protuberant paramedial lobes in some specimens, but in others it is shallow and there is no evidence of such lobes, even in larger specimens; midlongitudinal (in the first half of posterior lobe), transverse (interlobar) and posterolateral sulci formed by canaliculae, which vary in depth among the specimens; humeral angles rounded. Femora, particularly, fore and mid femora, thick in some specimens, with patches of long and numerous yellowish hairs on ventral surface of fore and mid trochanters and femora. In mid trochanters and femora, hairs are more numerous on the basal half; in some specimens these hairs are shorter or less numerous; mid ventral fringe of short curved yellowish to orange hairs on median portion of ventral face of all tibiae; apex of tibiae and tarsi covered with somewhat longer hairs with the same coloration; presence of a median ventral shallow and thin crest, where the ventral fringe of hairs are inserted on fore and mid femora and all tibiae; in some specimens this crest is not perceptible on femora; spongy fossa well developed on pro and meso tibiae. Hemelytra length varied from shorter than abdomen to slightly surpassing the tip. 
Male genitalia
(Figs. 
61–71
): pygophore subrounded, posterior margin rounded; paramere apices close in resting position (Figs. 
61–62
). Median process of pygophore sclerotized, apex rounded or slightly subtriangular (Figs. 
62–63
). Parameres symmetrical, a little curved, with sparse hairs, with a short subapical tooth (Figs. 
61
–62, 64). Phallus with articulatory apparatus moderately long, subquadrate; dorsal phallothecal plate oval, sinuous in center of anterior margin, lateral margins somewhat bent; struts enlarged at basal half and united in the apex, which is rounded (Figs. 
65–67
). Median process of endosoma subquadrate, with central sclerotized structure in the shape of an “X” (Fig. 
70
), or more similar to a “T” (Figs. 69, 71) including other specimen with darker sternites (Fig. 
60
, B).
</p>
            <p>PLATE8
. Figs. 
57–65
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, male, 
57–58
, specimen from Acre, 
Brazil
, 
57
, head, lateral view, 
58
, right antenna, segments I–II, dorsal view, 
59–60
, specimens from 
French Guiana
, 
59
, dorsal view, 
60
, ventral view, 
61–65
, male genitalia, 
61–62
, pygophore and parameres, 
61
, ventral view, 
62
, dorsal view, 
63
, median process of pygophore, 
64
, right paramere, dorsal and ventral view, respectively, 
65
, phallus, dorsal view.
</p>
            <p>PLATE9
. Figs. 
66–71
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, male genitalia, 
66–67
, phallus with expanded endosoma, 
66
, lateral view, 
67
, dorsal view, 
68
, median portion of expanded endosoma, with the median process, dorsal view, 
69–71
, median process of endosoma, dorsal view, 
69
, male from Pará, 
Brazil
, 
70–71
, males from 
French Guiana
, 
70
, from male of Fig. 
60
, A, 
71
, from male of Fig. 
60
, B.
</p>
            <p>Female
: COLORATION: same as males. STRUCTURE AND VESTITURE: Antenna: first and basal half of the second segment of females are bare or very sparsely pubescent; first segment thicker than others, completely bare to 
20
short setae on internal face; second segment with setae shorter or a little longer than the width of the segment, with very few scattered longer erect hairs 
ca.
twice as long as the width of the segment (Fig. 
54
). Clypeus rounded in females; Hemelytra did not reach tip of abdomen in the females examined.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>Discussion.
As possible sexual dimorphism in eyes and ocellus sizes were not clear when examining the specimens, some selected measures were recorded (

Tables 
1–4
) to investigate this. There were other observed variations in the specimens of this taxon: all specimens except the female from 
Bolivia
and a male from 
French Guiana
have a small rounded tubercle on the ventral portion of the head (gula) anteriorly (Figs. 53, 57), as well as size variation of the tubercle among the specimens; while in the male from 
French Guiana
, in which the tubercle is absent, some setae are present on the same area of gula. Investigating the male genitalia, the different portions of male genitalia were shown to be similar among the specimens examined, with very subtle differences in the thickness of parameres or size of teeth; median process of pygophore rounded to slightly subtriangular. Those differences showed intermediate or gradual states, occurring randomly among specimens, negating any association with color pattern or geographical precedence. The median process of the endosoma showed some minor variation as well, with the central sclerotized structure similar in shape to a “T” (Figs. 69, 71) recorded in specimens with more or less dark body markings from 
Brazil
and 
French Guiana
(Fig. 
60
, B), while its structure presented as the shape of an “X” (Fig. 
70
) in a male from 
French Guiana
with paler body markings (Fig. 
60
, A). However, the shapes of the dorsal phallothecal plate and struts (Fig. 
65
) are particularly characteristic and there was no noticeable variation among specimens examined.
</p>
            <p>
Specimens examined. 
BOLIVIA
, 
Bolivia
Tropica

, Región Chaparé, 
400m
, 

XII- 
1949
, Zischka [? 
leg.
], 
1
female

; 
BRAZIL
, Acre,
11 km
NE de Rio Branco, 
5–10
.V. 
1981
, Penny &amp; Elias 
leg.
, 
1
male

; 
Amapá
, Serra do Navio, 

VII- 
1959
, J. Lane 
leg.
, 
1
female

, [
MNRJ
]; 
Amazonas
, Campo Petrolífero do Urucu-Coari (

04º 
53
´42,5” S

– 
65
º 
11
´16,2” W

), 
21
.IX–04.X. 
2004
, José A.M. Fernandes 
leg.
, 
2
males

; 
Ceará
, Carquejo, 
1
female

, 

III.1963, 
1
female; 
FRENCH GUIANA
, 
Nourages
[

04º 
52
´N

– 
52
º 
41
´W

], 

IX. 
2009
, window trap, Seag 
leg
., 
7
males

, 
1
female

.
</p>
            <p>New Record:French Guiana
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
Inclusion of 
P. be re n ge r isp. nov
. in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
is in accordance with the characteristics assigned to species of this genus by 

Carpintero (
1978
)

, 

Dougherty (
1995
)

and 

Maldonado &amp; Carpintero (
1996
)

. 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov
.
</named-content>
differs from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
, and most of the New World 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
by lack of sexual dimorphism in male. In the latter, the first antennal segment is almost completely glabrous and the second antennal shows short pilosity (Figs. 
3–4
), whereas in males of other 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
species these segments show long and conspicuous pilosity (

Carpintero 
1978
, 

Dougherty 
1995
). The aspect of the male antenna of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov
.
</named-content>
is similar to that found in females of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
, and this lack of sexual dimorphism had not been recorded for 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
spp. to date. It is noteworthy that while a female 
paratype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov
.
</named-content>
showed the first antennal segment completely glabrous, the other 
paratype
showed ten small setae on the internal surface of this segment (Figs. 
17
–18, 25– 
26
). Other sexually dimorphic features commonly observed in male ectrichodiines are also lacking in the male 
holotype
of 
P. b e re ng e r isp. nov
, in which the following characters are observed: tylus is rounded (Fig. 
2
); the size of the ocelli is equal to that found in the female 
paratype
with smaller ones; the eyes are somewhat smaller than the eyes of the female 
paratypes
. The latter have hemelytra somewhat longer or reaching the tip of the abdomen, while in the male 
holotype
they are shorter, not reaching the tip of the abdomen (Figs. 1,15, 
24
).
</p>
         <p>
Among other species of the genus, 
P. b e re ng e r isp. nov
. seems closest to 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, but differs from it mainly by the following characteristics of the new species: the clypeus is not denticulate in the male (Fig. 
2
), the sulci of the pronotum are much less marked, including very faint lateral sulci on the posterior lobe of pronotum (Figs. 5, 19, 
27
); the presence of a pair of short rounded tubercles medially just between the anterior and posterior lobes of the pronotum (Figs. 
5
–6, 19, 
27
). In the male genitalia, the shapes of parameres differ (Figs. 11, 36). In 
P. b ere ng e r isp. nov
. the apex of the median process of pygophore is rounded and in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
it is subquadrate (Figs. 
10
and 
35
, respectively). The dorsal phallotecal plate and struts differ (Figs. 13, 39), and the median process of endosoma and its central sclerotized structure are somewhat subtriangular, with the central structure possessing with three divergent branches directed upward in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov
.
</named-content>
and rounded with the central structure somewhat like a “Y” or similar to a “T” in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs. 14, 
40. 43
and 
47
, respectively).
</p>
         <p>
Otherwise, as no female of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
has been seen and a difference in coloration, particularly in the coloration of sternites, was recorded in 
P. b e re ng e r isp. nov
. (Figs. 7, 22, 
28
), some other differences between females of the latter and females of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
may exist and will only be known when females of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
are examined. However, variation in coloration and some other characteristics, such as the depth of the midlongitudinal sulcus in the anterior pronotal lobe in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, were observed in both sexes (Figs. 
48
–49, 51–52, 56, 
59
), whereas variations in coloration were evident between the female 
paratypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov
.
</named-content>
(Figs. 15, 22, 24, 28) and among males of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs. 
29
–30, 32, 
41
–42, 44– 
46
). This seems to indicate that these differences are more likely intraspecific and are not related to a sexual dimorphism. In the same way, the nature of the differences observed between the coloration of the male 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and female 
paratypes
, particularly on the sternites (Figs. 7, 22, 
28
), if attributable to intraspecific or sexual variation, will only be known if more specimens are examined in the future.
</p>
         <p>
Variation in size and coloration, particularly in the presence and extent of dark markings on the legs, hemelytra, connexivum and sternites is recorded for 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs. 
29
–30, 32, 
41
–42, 44– 
46
). While the more diversely colored and smaller specimen is unique from a respective locality (Maranhão State, Figs. 
44–46
), it is not possible to associate it with a variation in geographical patterns.
</p>
         <p>
A considerable variation in color and size was observed not only among specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
from different localities, but also among those from the same locality (
French Guiana
) (Figs. 
48
–53, 55–57, 59– 
60
). The tubercle on the gula of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs. 53, 57) was not described by 

Carpintero (
1980
)

and is absent in his figure of the lateral view of the head. Coincidentally it has been confirmed as absent in the female from 
Bolivia
examined here, which is from the same country from which the 
holotype
was collected (

Carpintero 
1980
). As suggested by 

Forero (
2004
)

, it seems to be a singular character, despite being variable among the specimens examined, including no differentiation between sexes and its absence in two specimens, a male and a female.
</p>
         <p>
Sexual dimorphism in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov
.
</named-content>
has already been commented on above. For 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, as no female was examined, it is only possible to record that pubescent antennae (Fig. 
31
) and the denticulate clypeus in males of this species is in accordance with what has been observed in males of other 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
spp. (

Carpintero 
1978
, 

Dougherty 
1995
).
</p>
         <p>
Through comparison between males and females of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, the pubescent antennae and denticulate clypeus in males (Figs. 
57–58
) were easily noticed, contrasting with the almost or completely bare first and base of the second antennal segments and rounded clypeus in females (Figs. 
53–54
). Other sexual differences noticed in 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
(

Carpintero 
1978
, 

Dougherty 
1995
) were not confirmed or were subtle and should be confirmed by examining more specimens. These include the following: 
1
—length: the maximum length observed for both sexes was the same, 
18.5 mm
, but males were the smallest specimens with the minimum length of 
14.6 mm
(the smallest female reached 
16.2 mm
); 
2
—hemelytral length was somewhat similar, not reaching the tip of the abdomen in all females and in some males, and in some of the latter, slightly surpassing the tip; 
3
—other measurements of the head, eyes and ocelli of both sexes (

Tables 
1–4
) were within the same range of variation or the latter seemed so close that more specimens must be examined in order to confirm (or not) possible differences and/or reach a minimal number to allow statistical inference of data.
</p>
         <p>
The male genitalia of all three species examined here revealed several differences, mainly in the shape of the parameres (Figs. 11, 36, 
64
), the median process of the pygophore (Figs. 10, 35, 
63
), the dorsal phallotecal plate and struts (Figs. 13, 39, 
65
), and the median process of endosoma and its central sclerotized structure (Figs. 14, 40, 43, 47, 
69–71
), which appear to be useful in the taxonomy of this group. The phallothecal plate and struts are particularly noteworthy, since their shape and “design” are invariable within species and seem very particular to each species.
</p>
         <p>
In general, three different situations have been observed in relation to variation in the elements of male genitalia in reduviids. Firstly, they have been associated with intraspecific color variation and/or different geographical regions (

Lent &amp; Jurberg 
1985
, 

Hart 
1986
, 

Gil-Santana 
et al.2013
b

). Secondly, no genitalic patterns could be associated with corresponding color or geographical differences (

Berniker 
et al
. 
2011
, 

Lent &amp; Jurberg 
1985
, 

Pires 
et al
. 
1998
). Finally, despite the highly variable coloration, the male genitalia exhibited very little intraspecific variation (

Forero 
et al
. 
2010
). The latter case seems to agree best with what was recorded for 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
herein. Male genitalia of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
specimens from different Brazilian states and with diverse coloration (Figs. 
29
–30, 32, 
41
–42, 44– 
46
) showed only minor variation in the median process of the endosoma (Figs. 40, 43 and 
47
). Despite the great variation in color and some morphological features of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs. 
48
–53, 55–57, 59– 
60
), only minor differences were recorded in the male genitalia. The thickness of the parameres or the size of its teeth, and the median process of the pygophore, which was rounded to somewhat subtriangular, showed intermediate or gradual states, occurring randomly among specimens, negating any association with color pattern or geographical origin. The variation observed in the median process of the endosoma in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, in which the central sclerotized structure is “T”-shaped (Figs. 69, 71) was recorded in specimens with more or less dark body markings from 
Brazil
and 
French Guiana
(Fig. 
60
, B), while an “X”-shaped central sclerotized structure (Fig. 
70
) was recorded in a male from 
French Guiana
with less dark body markings (Fig. 
60
, A), precluding an association of this character with color pattern or geographical regions.
</p>
         <p>
In some specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, the midlongitudinal sulcus on the anterior pronotal lobe is deep enough to form a pair of protuberant paramedial lobes (Figs. 49, 52). However in other specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
that are even larger, it is shallow and there is no evidence of such paramedial lobes (Figs. 51, 56), similar to other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
studied here, such as 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
(Figs. 
29
–30, 41, 
44
). As this is the main character separating 
Parapothea
(

Carpintero 
1980
, 

Maldonado &amp; Carpintero 
1996
, 

Forero 
2006
, 

Gil-Santana 
et al
. 
2013
a

) from other New World 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
genera, particularly from 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
, the validity of 
Parapothea
is challenged. It is noteworthy to highlight that, before the description of 

Parapothea 
<tp:taxon-name>jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
(

Carpintero 
1980
) in a revision of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
, the same author (

Carpintero 
1978
) recognized that the longitudinal sulcus on the anterior lobe of the pronotum could be exceptionally profound in its proximal portion in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
spp. This was similar to what was observed later in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
as well.
</p>
         <p>
The other features that were considered as diagnostic of 
Parapothea
, very strong legs (

Carpintero 
1980
), and 
17 mm
[of length] (

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado 
1996
), have been shown to be variable among 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
specimens and, more importantly, are included in the range of variation of the other two species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
examined. In fact, the femora of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, particularly the fore and mid pairs, were thick, but were inconsistently less thick in some specimens. In these latter the femora thickness was similar to that observed in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
or even in the female 
paratype
of 
P. be re n ge r isp. nov.
with the reddish coloration. Also, the range of length in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
specimens examined here varied between 
16.2 –18.5 mm
(females, 

Tab. 
1
) and 
14.6–18.5 mm
(males, 

Tab. 
4
), while in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. furtadoi</tp:taxon-name>
, the length varied between 
17.1
–21.0 mm (only males), and in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. berengeri</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, between 
17.3 mm
(male 
holotype
) and 17.0– 
17.5 mm
(females 
paratypes
). Indeed, 

Carpintero &amp; Maldonado (
1996
)

themselves recorded in the diagnosis of 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
: “species slender or robust, from 
8 to 22 mm
…, profemora slightly or very incrassate…” Coloration of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, even if considered distinct (

Carpintero 
1980
), can only be regarded as of specific value. As the present work has shown, 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
has many similarities in structure, vestiture, and other morphological features, including male genitalia structures with other 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
spp. Although 

Forero (
2004
)

had considered the possibility of the tubercle on the gula (Figs. 53, 57), observed by him in an undescribed species, could be an autapomorphy of 
Parapothea
, the value of this feature alone as such would need to be confirmed in future more extensive works. This is even more important given it has been shown here to be variable or absent in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
, as is the other feature already considered as diagnostic of 
Parapothea
(two protuberant paramedial lobes on the fore lobe of the pronotum). All these arguments reinforce the placement of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pothea</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
Also, many morphological similarities among all three species studied here were observed, including structure, vestiture, and patterns of color variation and male genital structures, suggesting they are possibly taxonomically close and their inclusion in the same genus seems to be established at this moment. On the other hand, more extensive taxonomical studies, including cladistic analyses should be carried out to assess the taxonomic validity and systematic position of the New World taxa of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgments</title>
         <p>
I would like to thank L. Marinoni, R. R. Cavichioli (
DZUP
), Augusto Henriques (
INPA
), and Luiz A. A. Costa (
MNRJ
) for allowing the examination of material under their care; Dimitri Forero (Pontificia Universidad Javeriana, Bogotá, 
Colombia
), Katrina Menard (University of Oklahoma, 
USA
), Guanyang Zhang (School of Life Science, Arizona State Univerity, 
USA
) and an anonymous reviewer for their valuable comments and suggestions; Jean-Michel Bérenger (Unité de Recherche en Maladies Infectieuses et Tropicales Emergentes (URMITE), Faculté de Médecine, Aix Marseille Université, Marseille, 
France
) and José A.M. Fernandes (Universidade Federal do Pará, Belém, 
Brazil
) for the specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. jaguaris</tp:taxon-name>
from 
French Guiana
and Amazonas State, respectively, donated by them.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>Amyot, C.J.B.
&amp; 
Serville, J.G.A.
(
1843
) 
Histoire naturelle des insects: Hémiptères
. 
Librairie Encyclopedique de Roret. Fain et Thunot, Paris
, 
681
pp.
</p>
         <p>Bérenger, J.-M.
&amp; 
Gil-Santana, H.
(
2005
) 
Nouveau genre et nouvelles espèces d’Ectrichodiinae d’Amérique du Sud (Heteroptera, Reduviidae)
. 

Bulletin de la Société entomologique de 
France
, 
110
, 
509
– 
516
.
</p>
         <p>Berniker, L.
, 
Szerlip, S.
, 
Forero, D.
&amp; 
Weirauch, C.
(
2011
) 

Revision of the 
crassipes
and 
pictipes
species group of 
Apiomerus
Hahn (Hemiptera: Reduviidae: Harpactorinae)

. 
Zootaxa
, 
2949
, 

1– 
113
.
</p>
         <p>Carpintero, D.J.
(
1978
) 

Revisión del género 
Pothea
Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
. Sus species en 
la Argentina
(Hemiptera, Reduviidae, Ectrichodiinae)

. 

Revista del Museo 
Argentino
de Ciencias Naturales Bernardino Rivadavia

, 
5
, 
177
– 
286
.
</p>
         <p>Carpintero, D.J.
(
1980
) 
Nuevos Ectrichodiinae americanos (Insecta–Hemiptera–Reduviidae)
. 
Acta Scientifica. Serie Entomología
, 
14
, 

3– 
33
.
</p>
         <p>Carpintero, D.J.
&amp; 
Maldonado, J.
(
1990
) 

Contributions to the knowledge of American Ectrichodiinae. II. Notes about 
Rhiginia
and 
Pothea
(Hemiptera: Reduviidae)

. 

Journal of agriculture of the University of 
Puerto Rico
, 
74
, 
449
– 
456
.
</p>
         <p>Carpintero, D.J.
&amp; 
Maldonado, J.
(
1996
) 
Diagnostic characters and key to the genera of American Ectrichodiinae (Heteroptera, Reduviidae)
. 
Caribbean Journal of Science
, 
32
, 
125
– 
141
.
</p>
         <p>Champion, G.C.
(
1898
) 
Insecta Rhynchota. Hemiptera-Heteroptera. Vol. II
. 
In
: 
Godman, F.D.
&amp; 
Salvin, O.
(Eds.), 
Biologia Centrali Americana
, printed by Taylor &amp; Francis

, 

London, pp. i–xvi + 
1–416
, plates
1–22
.
</p>
         <p>Dougherty, V.
(
1995
) 
A review of the New World Ectrichodiinae Genera (Hemiptera: Reduviidae)
. 
Transactions of the American Entomological Society
, 
121
, 
173
– 
225
.
</p>
         <p>Forero, D.
(
2004
) 

Diagnosis de los gêneros neotropicales de la família Reduviidae (Hemiptera: Heteroptera), y su distribución em 
Colombia
(excepto Harpactorinae)

. 
In
: 
Fernández, F.
, 
Andrade, G.
, 
Amat, G.
(Eds.), 

Insectos de 
Colombia
. 

Vol. 
3
. 

Bogotá D. C., 
Colombia
, pp. 
128–175
.
</p>
         <p>Forero, D.
(
2006
) 

New records of Reduviidae (Hemiptera: Heteroptera) from 
Colombia
and other Neotropical countries

. 
Zootaxa
, 
1107
, 

1– 
47
.
</p>
         <p>Forero, D.
&amp; 
Weirauch, C.
(
2012
) 
Comparative genitalic morphology in the New World resin bugs Apiomerini (Hemiptera, Heteroptera, Reduviidae, Harpactorinae)
. 
Deutsche Zeitschrift Entomologische
, 
59
, 

5– 
41
.
</p>
         <p>Forero, D.
, 
Berniker, L.
&amp; 
Szerlip, S.
(
2010
) 

A polychromatic new species of 
Apiomerus
(Hemiptera: Reduviidae: Harpactorinae) from Central 
America
. 
Zootaxa
, 
2522
, 

44– 
60
.
</p>
         <p>Gil-Santana, H.R.
(
2007
) 

New records of Reduviidae (Hemiptera: Heteroptera) from 
Brazil
. 
Zootaxa
, 
1390
, 

59– 
68
.
</p>
         <p>Gil-Santana, H.R.
&amp; 
Baena, M.
(
2009
) 

Two new species of 
Brontostoma
Kirkaldy (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae: Ectrichodiinae) from 
Bolivia
, with description of the male genitalia of two other species of the genus, and description of the female of 
B. doughertyae
Gil-Santana, Lopes, Marques &amp; Jurberg

. 
Zootaxa
, 
1979
, 

41– 
52
.
</p>
         <p>Gil-Santana, H.R.
&amp; 
Costa, L.A.A.
(
2005
) 
Pothea furtadoi
sp. nov. (Hemiptera, Heteroptera, Reduviidae, Ectrichodiinae) de Mato Grosso e Minas Gerais, 
Brasil
. 
Revista Brasileira de Zoologia
, 
22
, 
400
– 
404
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1590
/s0101- 
81752005000200014</p>
         <p>Gil-Santana, H.R.
, 
Lopes, C.M.
, 
Marques, O.M.
&amp; 
Jurberg, J.
(
2005
) 

Descrição de 
Brontostoma doughertyae
sp. nov. e estudo morfológico comparativo com 
B. rubrum
(Amyot &amp; Serville, 
1843
) (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae: Ectrichodiinae)

. 
Entomología y Vectores
, 
12
, 

75– 
94
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1590
/s0328-03812005000100006
</p>
         <p>Gil-Santana, H.R.
, 
Baena, M.
&amp; 
Grillo, H.
(
2013
a) 
Berengeria
Gil-Santana &amp; Coletto-Silva, a junior synonym of 
Ectrichodiella
Fracker &amp; Bruner, with new records and taxonomic notes on Ectrichodiinae from 
Brazil
, and with keys to Ectrichodiinae and Reduviinae genera of the New World (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae)

. 
Zootaxa
, 
3652
(
1
), 
60–74
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3652.1.2
</p>
         <p>Gil-Santana, H.R.
, 
Davranoglou, L.-R.
&amp; 
Neves, J.A.
(
2013
b) 

A new synonym of 
Graptocleptes bicolor
(Burmeister), with taxonomical notes (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae: Harpactorini)

. 
Zootaxa
, 
3700
(
3
), 
348–360
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.11646
/zootaxa.3700.3.2
</p>
         <p>Hart, E.R.
(
1986
) 

Genus 
Zelus
Fabricius in the 
United States
, 
Canada
, and Northern 
Mexico
(Hemiptera: Reduviidae)

. 

Annals of the Entomological Society of 
America
, 
79
, 
535
– 
548
.
</p>
         <p>Lent, H.
&amp; 
Jurberg, J.
(
1985
) 

Sobre a variação intra-específica em 
Triatoma dimidiata
(Latreille) e 
Triatoma infestans
(Klug) (Hemiptera, Reduviidae)

. 
Memórias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz
, 
80
, 
285
– 
299
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1590
/s0074-02761985000300004
</p>
         <p>Lepeletier, A.L.M.
&amp; 
Serville, J.G.A.
(
1825
) 
Histoire naturelle. Entomologie
. 
In
: 
Oliver, G. A.
(Ed.), 
Encyclopédie méthodique
. Mme

. 

Veuve Agase, Paris, 
10
, 
832 pp.</p>
         <p>Lethierry, L.
&amp; 
Severin, G.
(
1896
) 
Catalogue général des Hémiptères
. 
Tome III. Hétéroptères
. R

. 
Friedländer &amp; Fils, Libraires- Éditeurs, Berlin
, 
275
pp.
</p>
         <p>Maldonado, C.J.
(
1990
) 
Systematic catalogue of the Reduviidae of the World
. 

Caribbean Journal of Science, Special publication No. 
1
. 

University of 
Puerto Rico
, Mayagüez, 
Puerto Rico
, 
694
pp.
</p>
         <p>Miller, N.C.E.
(
1956
) 
New genera and species of Ethiopian, Oriental and Neotropical Reduviidae
. 
Beitraege zur Entomologie
, 
6
, 

1– 
9
.
</p>
         <p>Pires, H.H.R.
, 
Barbosa, S.E.
, 
Margonari, C.
, 
Jurberg, J.
&amp; 
Diotaiuti, L.
(
1998
) 

Variations of the external male genitália in three populations of 
Triatoma infestans
Klug, 
1834
. 
Memórias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz
, 
93
, 
479
– 
483
. 

http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1590
/s0074-02761998000400011
</p>
         <p>Putshkov, V.G.
&amp; 
Putshkov, P.V.
(
1985
) 
A catalogue of the Assassin-bugs genera of the World (Heteroptera, Reduviidae)
.
Kiev
, 
137
pp.
</p>
         <p>Rédei, D.
&amp; 
Tsai, J.-F.
(
2011
) 

The assassin bug subfamilies Centrocnemidinae and Holoptilinae in 
Taiwan
(Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Reduviidae)

. 
Acta Entomologica Musei Nationalis Pragae
, 
51
, 
411
– 
442
.
</p>
         <p>Schuh, R.T.
, 
Weirauch, C.
&amp; 
Wheeler, W.C.
(
2009
) 
Phylogenetic relationships within the Cimicomorpha (Hemiptera: Heteroptera): a total-evidence analysis
. 
Systematic Entomology
, 
34
, 

15– 
48
.
</p>
         <p>
http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1111
/j. 
1365
-3113.2008.00436.x
</p>
         <p>Stål, C.
(
1859
) 
Till kännedomen om Reduvini
. 
Öfversigt af Kongliga Vetenskaps-Akademiens Förhandlingar
, 
16
, 
175
– 
204
.
</p>
         <p>Stål, C.
(
1872
) 
Enumeratio Reduviinorum Americae
. 
In
: 
Enumeratio Hemipterorum
. 
Kongliga Svenska Vetenskaps- Akademiens Handlingar
, 
10
, 

66– 
128
.
</p>
         <p>Van Duzee, E.P.
(
1916
) 

Check list of the Hemiptera (excepting the Aphididae, Coccidae and Aleurodidae) of 
America
North of 
Mexico
. 
New York, New York Entomological Society
, 
111
pp.
</p>
         <p>Walker, F.
(
1873
a) 
Catalogue of the specimens of Hemiptera Heteroptera in the Collection of the British Museum
. Part VII

. 
Printed for the Trustees of the British Museum, London
, 
213
pp.
</p>
         <p>Walker, F.
(
1873
b) 
Catalogue of the specimens of Hemiptera Heteroptera in the Collection of the British Museum
. 
Part VIII
. 
Printed for the Trustees of the British Museum, London
, 
220
pp.
</p>
         <p>Weirauch, C.
(
2008
) 
From four- to three- segmented labium in Reduviidae (Hemiptera: Heteroptera)
. 
Acta Entomologica Musei Nationalis Pragae
, 
48
, 
331
– 
344
.
</p>
         <p>Wygodzinsky, P.
(
1949
) 
Elenco sistematico de los reduviiformes americanos
. 
Instituto de Medicina Regional de la Universidad Nacional de Tucumán, Monografia
,
1
, 

1– 
102
.
</p>
         <p>Wygodzinsky, P.
(
1951
) 
Notas sobre Ectrichodiinae Neotropicales (Hemipt. Reduviidae)
. 

Revista de la Sociedad Entomológica 
Argentina
, 
15
, 

35– 
52
.
</p>
         <p>Wygodzinsky, P.
(
1959
) 
Notas y descripciones de Reduviidae bolivianas (Hemiptera)
. 
Acta Zoologica Lilloana
, 
17
, 
293
– 
320
.
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
