<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1038/s41598-022-10047-9</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>Integrative taxonomy reveals cryptic diversity in North American Lasius ants, and an overlooked introduced species</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2022</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>OPEN</title>
         <p>
Integrative taxonomy reveals cryptic diversity in North American 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius</tp:taxon-name>
ants, and an overlooked introduced species
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Sämi Schär1*
, 
Gerard Talavera2
, 
Jignasha D. Rana3
, 
Xavier Espadaler4,
Stefan 
P
. Cover
5
, 
Steven O. Shattuck5
&amp; 
Roger Vila1</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <p>
Biological invasions are a grave threat to ecosystems. The black garden ant (
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius niger</tp:taxon-name>
) is a pest species in Europe. Current literature states that 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
occupies a disjunct native distribution in the Holarctic, however, based on recent work, we re-evaluate this distribution. The native range of 
<tp:taxon-name>L.niger
is reconsidered based on phylogenetic relationships (nine mitochondrial and nuclear markers, 5670 bp), DNA-barcoding (98 Holarctic specimens), morphometry (88 Holarctic specimens, 19 different measurements) and subjective assessment of phenotype. The potential spread of this species is estimated using ecological niche modeling. 
Lasius niger
is more closely related to other Palearctic species than to the Nearctic ants known under this name.The latter are described as a distinct
</tp:taxon-name>
species, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
However, DNA-barcoding discovered established populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
in metropolitan areas in 
Canada
(Vancouver and Halifax). We describe a morphometrical method to delineate 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
. MtDNA diversity and divergence is high within 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, but low within 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
.

More than 
1,000,000 km2
are suitable as a habitat for 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
in North America.This case emphasizes the critical role of integrative taxonomy to detect cryptic species and identify potential biological invasions in their nascent stages.
</p>
         <p>
Biological invasions are a major threat to ecosystems worldwide, causing significant environmental and economic damage 
1
, 
2
. Invasive species, in particular, have been identified as a leading cause of animal extinctions 
3
. Early detection and action are critical to correctly identify and halt the spread of novel invaders, but this requires upto-date taxonomy and understanding of the geographic range extent of the species in question 
4
– 
6
. This can be challenging, particularly in groups that may include hidden (cryptic) diversity 
7
, 
8
.
</p>
         <p>
Ants, in particular, can be harmful when introduced to novel ecosystems 
9
, 
10
. Five ant species are among the world’s 100 worst invasive species, representing nearly a third of the land invertebrates listed 
11
. This high proportion of ants among the most problematic invasive species can perhaps be explained by their social form of organization and ecological dominance in terrestrial ecosystems 
12
, 
13
.
</p>
         <p>
The North American ant fauna is well characterized at a higher taxonomic level, especially when compared to more diverse and little explored regions in the tropics 
14
, 
15
. Nevertheless, the general understanding of Nearctic ant taxonomy at the species level could still be improved for certain genera. Literature used to identify Nearctic ant species ofen dates back several decades (e.g., Refs. 
16
, 
17
) except for certain geographical areas (e.g., Refs. 
18
– 
20
) and taxonomic groups (e.g., Refs. 
21
– 
23
) for which more recent identification literature is available.
</p>
         <p>
The ant genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius
Fabricius, 1804
</tp:taxon-name>
is diverse and widespread across temperate and Mediterranean climatic zones of the Holarctic 
24
. While the morphological diagnosis of 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius
species
</tp:taxon-name>
is difficult, new species are still describedregularly 
25
– 
27
, and some of these are cryptic species that require complicated methods to distinguish them from one another 
26
.
</p>
         <p>
The common garden ant 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius niger
(Linnaeus, 1758)
</tp:taxon-name>
is one of the most abundant species of insects in Europe and has been rated the 7th most problematic pest animal in buildings in Britain 
28
. This ant is found almost everywhere throughout Europe, except in areas with semi-arid or sub-arctic climate. Ref. 
29
discovered that 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
has a widespread but overlooked sister species in the Palearctic, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
,

ecologically replacing the former in forest habitats. 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius niger</tp:taxon-name>
is usually an inconspicuous species in undisturbed ant communities, but is ofen a highly dominant species in modified and anthropogenic habitats due to genomic exaptations to environmental challenges associated with urbanization 
30
. This ant is most known as an agricultural pest species because of its nest building activities in farmland and greenhouses and because it supports aphids that attack crop plants 
31
. Additionally, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
is considered a household and commercial pest in residential homes and businesses 
32
.
</p>
         <p>
Taxonomic literature holds that 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
has a disjunct natural distribution, occupying both the Palearctic region and Nearctic region 
17
. Within North America, however, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
has most frequently been reported from the western 
United States17
. The current distribution and disjunct range of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
is puzzling and requires a taxonomic re-assessment of the ants currently described under this name in North America. Ref. 
33
hypothesized that the natural distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
may not be Holarctic but is instead restricted to the Palearctic region. Here we re-evaluate the taxonomic status and distribution range of Nearctic ants identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
using a combination of molecular phylogenetic and morphometric data. We further study the phylogeography of the native and introduced species within the North American 
L. niger-
complex. Finally, we use Environmental Niche Modelling (ENM) to predict the potential introduced range of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
in North America.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="materials_methods">
         <title>Methods</title>
         <p>Phylogenetic analysis with multiple markers.
We approached phylogenetic species delimitation of Holarctic ants currently identified as 

" 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
"

with a focus on North American specimens. Therefore, we compiled a phylogenetic data set representing 26 Holarctic taxa of the subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius</tp:taxon-name>17
or a part of the clade of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger
sensu Ref.
</tp:taxon-name>34
, plus two outgroup taxa (
<tp:taxon-name>L. pallitarsis</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. mixtus</tp:taxon-name>
). Due to the relatively high genetic divergence within ants resembling 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
from the Rocky Mountains 
33
, representatives of the four most divergent COI lineages were included to clarify whether they confirm monophyly of the group. The resulting DNA-alignment (5670 bp) contained sequence data originating from 9 genes (mtDNA: COI, COII, 16 
S
, nuDNA: Defensin, H3, LR, Wg, Top1 &amp; 28 
S
). The data matrix containing the alignment is available from TreeBASE (http://www. treebase.org, submission ID: 29528). At least 4 genes were available for the focal taxa (
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
: all 9 genes; 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
: COI, Wg, Top1 &amp; 28 
S
), while for outgroups completeness ranged from 1–7 genes (Supplementary 
Table S1
). Most of these sequences were published previously 
27
, 
33
, 
35
, 
36
and accessed via GenBank (Supplementary 
Table S1
). Sequences were aligned for individual genes using MAFFT v7.453 and Geneious v.6 sofware. Bayesian inference was used to estimate phylogenetic relationships under the Coalescent Model in BEAST v 
1.8.337
. Partitions were set by gene and the HKY substitution model and a strict clock model with a clock rate fixed to 1.0 were chosen. BEAST was run for 
107
iterations in two independent runs with identical input and the log files were assessed for chain convergence and stationarity in Tracer v1.6. 
A
second tree was calculated employing maximum likelihood (
ML
) in IQTREE v 
1.6.1238
. Substitution models for each partition (gene) were selected by the program ModelFinder 
39
and 10,000 ultrafast bootstrap replications were performed. The following substitution models were selected: TIM2 + 
F
+ I + G4: COI &amp; COII, TIM3 + 
F
+ G4: 16 
S
, HKY + 
F
+ I: Defensin, HKY + 
F
+ R2: H3, Wg &amp; 28 
S
, K2 
P
+I: LR &amp; Top1.
</p>
         <p>DNA-barcoding.
DNA-barcoding data analyzed in this study represent a combination of sequence data from previous publications of the authors 
27
, 
33
and public data from the Barcode of Life Data System (BOLD) 
40
under the name “ 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius niger</tp:taxon-name>
”.
A
total of 72 DNA-barcodes were compiled to gather a dataset representing ants resembling 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
from the Nearctic. In addition, 26 reference sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
from the Palearctic were included for comparison. An overview of collection data and accession numbers for DNA-sequences for all 
98 specimens
is given in Supplementary Table 
S
2. Sequences were collapsed into mitotypes using the package “haplotypes” 
41
in

R v 
4.1.142
. 
A
mitotype tree was created in IQTREE using the HKY+ 
F
+ I model and 10,000 ultrafast bootstrap replications and a mitotype map was produced using the R-package “ggmap” 
43
.
</p>
         <p>Morphometry.
Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger
sensu Ref.
</tp:taxon-name>17
from the Nearctic and Palearctic were compared morphologically. 
A
detailed morphometric analysis was performed for 
88 specimens
(n = 39 Nearctic and 49 Palearctic specimens) to identify diagnostic morphometric variables between forms in both regions. For this purpose, a data set of 19 measurements originally defined by Ref. 
26
for a taxonomic revision of Palearctic 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius</tp:taxon-name>
ants was obtained for all 
88 specimens
. This data set contained the following variables: CL, CS, CW, dClAn, EYE, GuHL, MaDe, 
MP
6, nGen, nGu, nHT, nOcc, nSc, nSt, PLF, PnHL, PoOc, 
SL
and sqPDCL (See Supplementary Table 
S
3 and Supplementary 

for definitions of abbreviations). To find a discriminant function to distinguish Nearctic from Palearctic cryptic species, linear discriminant analysis was performed as described by Ref. 
44
, afer reducing the number of variables by step-wise logistic regression in R v4.1.1. In order to compare the average mesosoma profile between potential cryptic species, images were taken in lateral view and subsequently scaled to the same length and position of the thorax. The images were converted to black and white and the average image was calculated as mean darkness of pixels using the “imagematrix”-function from the ripa-package 
45
in

R v4.1.1. Principal component analysis of the reduced set of 4 morphometric variables was also carried out in R v4.1.1. The native North American ants thus far known as 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
were described as a new species. Type specimens are deposited at the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard University (Cambridge, 
USA
). Two 
paratype
workers each will be deposited at the collections of University of 
California
Davis (
UCDC
), the University of 
Utah
(
JTLC
) and the Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County (
LACM
). The following standard measurements were taken from the 
holotype
worker, 
5 paratype workers
and 2 gynes: Head Length (
HL
), Head Width (HW), Scape length (
SL
), Eye Length (EL), Eye Width (EW), Pronotum Width (ProW), Mesosoma Length (
ML
), Hind Tibia Length (HTL), Cephalic Index (
CI
) and Scape Index (
SI
).
</p>
         <p>Ecological niche modelling.
In order to estimate the suitable habitat of the introduced 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
in North America, we carried out ecological niche modeling using the R package biomod 
246
, based on 180 presences and 182 absences from the Old World. We subsequently projected the resulting model to North America. Presence points were obtained from reviewed literature and websites (Supplementary Table 
S
4). Absence points were extracted from areas outside the climatic envelope of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
: this species is absent from the dry regions of 
Iberia
, the Mediterranean coast, the Balearic Islands, 
Asia Minor47
, the islands of Crete, Sardinia and Sicily 
48
, Africa, the Middle East, the Arabian Peninsula and boreal, subarctic and arctic parts of Scandinavia and 
Russia49
. In addition, a number of absences were selected for sites where authors have noted local or regional absence of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
during myrmecological surveys. All 19 WorldClim climatic layers 
50
and the freely available Global Land Cover Map for 
200951
were used as explanatory variables. The following models were explored: GLM, GAM, MARS, CTA, FDA, GBM and 
RF
, and a total of 20 runs were performed. Models were evaluated using the TSS, 
ROC
, and KAPPA-method. The results from all models were combined using ensemble modeling. Models were finally projected to North America using the function “BIOMOD_EnsembleForecasting” in biomod2. Areas of suitable habitat in Europe and North America were divided into three ranges of occurrence probability: 0.2–1, 0.5–1 and 0.8–1, on a probability scale of 0–1. Area sizes for each occurrence probability range were approximated by multiplying the number of raster cells with values above the defined probability threshold with the median cell size in km 
2
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="results">
         <title>Results</title>
         <p>Phylogenetic analysis with multiple markers.
The final alignment of 5670 bp length contained 843 variable sites (14.7%). Missing data accounted for 53.5% of the alignment cells and the relative GC content was 39.5%. Our phylogeny suggests that the investigated Holarctic taxa of the 
<tp:taxon-name>niger</tp:taxon-name>
clade sensu Ref. 
34
are divided into two major clades with strong statistical support (

). The first major clade (
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
group) consists exclusively of Palearctic species (
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. japonicus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. emarginatus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. balearicus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. grandis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. cinereus</tp:taxon-name>
,

the 
<tp:taxon-name>L. alienus</tp:taxon-name>
-complex, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. sakagamii</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. productus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. hayashi</tp:taxon-name>
), with the exception of an unnamed Nearctic subclade recovered as sister to the rest of the group. This unnamed subclade we describe as a new species below (
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
corresponds to what was previously known as the Nearctic form of “ 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
” sensu ref. 
17
, but includes some western Nearctic populations formerly assigned to “ 
<tp:taxon-name>L. alienus</tp:taxon-name>
”
17
, 
52
as well. Monophyly of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
was fully supported by Bayesian inference (pp = 1) and moderately supported by maximum likelihood (66% bootstrap support, 

). 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is distantly related to 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
; and 
<tp:taxon-name>L.niger</tp:taxon-name>
is a close relative of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. japonicus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
,

as well as other Palearctic taxa. The second major clade (
<tp:taxon-name>L. brunneus</tp:taxon-name>
group) within the investigated Holarctic members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
clade contains both Nearctic and Palearctic species not closely related to the taxa of interest (

).
</p>
         <p>DNA-barcoding.
The native North American species 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
contains at least 15 COI-mitotypes (n = 28 sequenced specimens) belonging to four distinct deep lineages, with divergences of up to 5.9%. Haplotype diversity was 0.899 and nucleotide diversity was 0.012. None of the mitotypes of this species was found to be widespread or particularly abundant. In striking contrast, low genetic diversity was found in 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
across its entire distribution (

). No more than 7 different COI-mitotypes were detected in samples from distant localities representing most of the known range (n = 
70 specimens
from 12 countries), from 
Spain
in the West to the Siberian Baikal-region in the East (

). Their maximum pairwise divergence was only 0.6%, with a haplotype diversity of 0.682 and a nucleotide diversity below 0.001. One mitotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
is highly dominant within the native range, occurring from Western Europe to Central Siberia (mitotype h 
2 in
).
</p>
         <p>
Recent Palearctic 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
introduction to 
Canada
.

Palearctic 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius niger</tp:taxon-name>
was introduced to several localities in coastal Canada in recent times, where at least 11 populations were found in two metropolitan areas (Vancouver and Halifax areas, see Table 
S
2 for details). Those populations consist of the most dominant Palearctic mitotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
(h2). However, in 3 localities in the Vancouver area, 
3 specimens
with a second mitotype were found (mitotype h4, 

, Table 
S
2) in syntopy with those carrying the most common mitotype h2. This second Canadian COI-mitotype (h4) was not found among our samples from the Old World, although it only differs by a single nucleotide substitution from mitotypes found there. 
A
review of BOLD data revealed that the Canadian barcoded specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
were mostly collected in anthropogenic habitats such as schoolyards (Supplementary Table 
S
2).
</p>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae
Schär, Talavera, Rana, Espadaler, Cover, Shattuck and Vila. ZooBank LSID
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Pinus ponderosa</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius
sensu Wilson (1955)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. pallitarsis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. mixtus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. alienus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius niger</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius
species.
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. alienus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius alienus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. alienus
" sensu Wilson (1955)
</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. americanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. americanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. americanus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. grandis</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. japonicus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>L. cinereus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Integrative taxonomy reveals cryptic diversity in North American Lasius ants, and an overlooked introduced species</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1038/s41598-022-10047-9</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFF534578A76FFAEFFB0FFC1FFFAFFB1</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-10047-9</pub-id>
               <source>Scientific Reports</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
Description of 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>sp. nov.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae
Schär, Talavera, Rana, Espadaler, Cover, Shattuck and Vila. ZooBank LSID
</tp:taxon-name>
: 

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
22E2743A-2F1C-4870-B318-A1F2DF2B464C</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>Etymology
: 
<tp:taxon-name>ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
alludes to the ponderosa pine tree (
<tp:taxon-name>Pinus ponderosa</tp:taxon-name>
) that is at the centre of occurrence in the ponderosa pine—gambel oak communities in the western Rocky Mountains and northern 
Arizona
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p>Type material
: located at the Museum of Comparative Zoology, Cambridge, 
USA
. Two 
paratype
workers each will be deposited at the collections of University of 
California
Davis (
UCDC
), the University of 
Utah
(
JTLC
) and the Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County (
LACM
).
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Holotype
: 
worker
, 

. Type locality: 
USA
, 
Utah
: 
Uintah Co.
, 
Uintah Mtns.
, 
2408 m
. 
18.6 mi
N

. Jct. Rt. 40 on Rt. 191, 
40.66378°N
, − 
109.47918°E
, leg. 
15.VII.2013
, 
S. P. Cover
; 
J. D. Rana
, collection code 
SPC 8571
. Measurements [mm]: HL: 0.899, HW: 0.823, SL: 0.821, EL: 0.239, EW: 0.189, ProW: 0.56, ML: 1.069, HTL: 0.863, CI: 92, SI: 100.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>Paratypes
: 
15 workers
, two gynes (

), 
two males
(

) from the same series as the 
holotype
, morphometric data is given in the Appendix, Table 
S
5 and Table 
S
6. 
CO
1 mitotype h17: Genbank Accession no. 
LT
977508

.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>Description of the worker caste:A
member of a complex of cryptic species resembling 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
. Intermediate in overall body size, antennal scape length and eye size and comparable to related species (
Table 1
). Terminal segment of maxillary palps and torulo-clypeal distance relative to head size shorter than in related Palearctic species (
Table 1
). Mandibles with 8 or rarely 7 or 9 regular denticles and lacking offset teeth at their basal angle. Penultimate and terminal basal mandibular teeth of subequal size, and the gap in between with subequal area than the basal tooth. Anterior margin of clypeus evenly rounded. Dorsofrontal profile of pronotum slightly angular (

). Propodeal dome short and flat, usually lower than mesonotum (

). Body with abundant and long pilosity, especially lateral propodeum, genae, hind margin and underside of head. Pilosity of tibiae and antennal scapes variable, ranging from almost no setae (" 
<tp:taxon-name>L. alienus</tp:taxon-name>
"-like phenotype) to very hairy (" 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
"-like phenotype). Microscopic pubescent hairs on forehead between frontal carinae long and fine. Clypeus typically with only few scattered pubescent hairs (

, 

). Coloration of body dark brown, occasionally yellowish- or reddish-brown or slightly bicolored with head and thorax lighter than abdomen. Femora and antennal scapes brown. Mandibles and distal parts of legs yellowish to dark brown. Specimens of all 3 castes are shown in 

and morphometric data are summarized in 
Table 1
and raw measurements are available in Table 
S
5 and 
S
6.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>
Diagnosis: 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
workers key out to " 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
" using Wilson’s 1955 key to the Nearctic 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius
species.
</tp:taxon-name>
However, some populations with reduced pilosity may also be identified as " 
<tp:taxon-name>L. alienus</tp:taxon-name>
" using this key. 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius alienus</tp:taxon-name>
is a Eurasian species not known from North America 
33
. The Nearctic " 
<tp:taxon-name>L. alienus
" sensu Wilson (1955)
</tp:taxon-name>
includes both, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. americanus</tp:taxon-name>
as well as populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
with sparse setae counts on tibia and/or scapes. 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
can be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. americanus</tp:taxon-name>
by the presence of abundant, long setae surpassing the sides of the head in full face view (nGen&gt; 5 and nOcc&gt; 10 vs. nGen &lt;5 and nOcc &lt;
10 in<tp:taxon-name>L. americanus</tp:taxon-name>
). Distinguishing 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from related Eurasian species (e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
) by subjective eye inspection is difficult because there are no easily visible morphological traits allowing a separation of 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
from all these taxa. 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
is therefore a cryptic species. For 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
,

introduced to North America, nest samples can ofen be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
using the average mesosoma profile (

) and by fewer pubescent hairs on the clypeus (

). 
A
distinction between single workers of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
and related Palearctic species can be achieved by calculating the following discriminant function with measurements taken in mm:
</p>
            <p>D
= − 43.792* 
GUHL
+ 113.436*dCLAN + 75.68* 
MP
6 − 0.431*nSt − 10.075.
</p>
            <p>
Negative values of 
D
indicate 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, n = 39, median, range: − 3.18 [− 5.83, − 0.43]; 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. grandis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. japonicus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. cinereus</tp:taxon-name>
, n = 49, median, range: 2.67 [0.18, 4.61]). 
A
principal component analysis plot for the four most diagnostic variables (
GUHL
, dCLAN, 
MP
6 and nSt) is shown in 

. For a definition of the variables used in the function, see Supplementary Table 
S
4 and Supplementary 

. All morphometric data are available in Table 
S
6.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p>Distribution:
Western North America: 
Alberta
, 
Arizona
, 
Baja California
, 
California
, 
Colorado
, 
Idaho
, 
Montana
, 
Nevada
, 
Oregon
, 
Utah
and 
Washington53
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p>Habitat
: Occurring in a broad range of habitats and elevations, from 
20–3220 m
a. s. l. (mean: 
1997 m
) 
53
. Typical for mid-elevations in the mountains, whose primary habitat is ponderosa pine forest and its associated communities (e.g., dry meadows, sagebrush, gambel oak woodland) or at higher elevations in meadows bordered by aspen-spruce or alpine scree slopes, but also in other habitats. Nests in and under dead wood, and under stones in soil 
53
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Lasius niger</tp:taxon-name>
niche modeling and potential spread in North America.
</p>
      <p>
According to the 
ROC
, TSS and kappa statistics, the tested modeling techniques displayed good performances for 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
(mean values of 
ROC
&gt; 0.9, TSS and kappa&gt; 0.8 across models and runs). The strongest predictors were: Annual Mean Temperature (mean variable importance = 0.32), Mean Temperature of Coldest Quarter (0.23), Temperature Annual Range (0.23) and Temperature Seasonality (0.24). The contribution of land cover was low (0.02). The model predicted high probabilities of occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
in the eastern 
United States
and southeastern 
Canada
, including the island of Newfoundland, and small areas of suitable habitat in southwestern 
Canada
and the Aleutians (

). The area with high predicted occurrence probability of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
in the New World includes the two sites where populations have actually established (which were not used in the modeling): 
Nova Scotia
and Vancouver. Further areas with high occurrence probabilities are New 
England
, Southern Ontario, the Great Lakes-region and the Northern Appalachians. Low occurrence probabilities were found for the central North American prairies as well as arctic, boreal, arid, subtropical and tropical regions (

). Considering the highest occurrence probability range (0.8–1 on a 0–1 probability scale), the area of suitable habitats for 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
is 
4,547,537 km2
in

Europe and 
1,308,920 km2
in

North America. For an intermediate to high occurrence probability range (0.5–1) we estimated 
5,371,055 km2
in

Europe and 
3,054,283 km2
in

North America, and for the widest probability range (0.2–1) we estimated 
6,155,643 km2
of suitable areas in Europe and 
6,889,745 km2
in

North America (

).
</p>
      <p>Variable<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
         <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, N = 
391
Palearctic 
L. niger-
complex, N = 
491p-value2CW [mm]0.81 [0.66, 0.90]0.92 [0.66, 1.09]&lt;0.001CL [mm]0.88 [0.73, 0.97]0.98 [0.75, 1.15]&lt;0.001CS [mm]0.84 [0.70, 0.94]0.95 [0.71, 1.12]&lt;0.001CL/CW1.077 [1.026, 1.143]1.062 [0.997, 1.162]0.043SL/CS0.97 [0.92, 1.03]0.98 [0.90, 1.06]0.2sqPDCL [μm]5.47 [3.90, 7.37]4.25 [3.58, 6.11]&lt;0.001PoOc/CL0.242 [0.212, 0.262]0.244 [0.209, 0.271]0.058nGen13.0 [5.0, 19.0]8.5 [3.0, 18.0]&lt;0.001EYE/CS0.239 [0.220, 0.259]0.237 [0.213, 0.266]0.5nGU13.0 [4.0, 24.0]8.0 [2.0, 25.0]&lt;0.001nOCC18.5 [9.0, 26.0]16.0 [7.0, 25.0]0.002GUHL/CS0.117 [0.071, 0.150]0.084 [0.055, 0.128]&lt;0.001MaDe0.00176 (19%)0 (0%)826 (81%)32 (86%)90 (0%)5 (14%)Unknown712dCLAN/CS0.044 [0.026, 0.056]0.051 [0.042, 0.061]&lt;0.001MP6/CS0.161 [0.133, 0.206]0.174 [0.136, 0.229]&lt;0.001PnHL/CS0.134 [0.090, 0.190]0.127 [0.067, 0.171]0.091nSt7.00 [4.00, 11.00]4.00 [0.00, 10.00]&lt;0.001nHT26 [11, 35]18 [6, 39]&lt;0.001nSC25 [4, 39]18 [10, 36]&lt;0.001PLF [mm]0.034 [0.026, 0.048]0.028 [0.021, 0.041]&lt;0.001</p>
      <sec sec-type="discussion">
         <title>Discussion</title>
         <p>
In this study, we discovered a new cryptic species among the Nearctic ants previously known as “ 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
”

and show evidence for the introduction of Palearctic 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
to North America. 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
, is endemic and thus native to North America (

). Previous publications mentioning “ 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
” collected in North America most likely refer to this species. Our genetic analyses also show that the relatively large sister clade of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(the clade including 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. platythorax</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. japonicus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. emarginatus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. balearicus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. grandis</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. cinereus</tp:taxon-name>
,

the 
<tp:taxon-name>L. alienus</tp:taxon-name>
-complex, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. sakagamii</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. productus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>L. hayashi</tp:taxon-name>
in 

) is absent from the Nearctic region. The exception is a few populations of Palearctic 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
found in anthropogenic habitats in the Canadian cities of Vancouver and Halifax, sharing the predominant DNA-barcode of our sampled 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
populations in the Palearctic (

). We interpret these finding as clear evidence that 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
is an introduced species in 
Canada
and the New World. Finding the same COI-mitotype for ants living in two continents is rare and suggests recent or ongoing dispersal. Recent natural dispersal of ants between Eurasia and North America occurred only via the Beringian land bridge 
33
. However, within the Old World, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
is restricted to the western and central Palearctic region and has not been confirmed from eastern Asia 
26
. Therefore, recent natural dispersal of this species to the North American continent is unlikely, due to the lack of natural dispersal routes. In addition, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
thus far has only been found in 
Canada
near cities (Supplementary Table 
S
2), a distribution pattern that is typical for exotic species and suggests that it is human-mediated. The origin of the introduced populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Canada
remain to be discovered. In addition to expanded specimen sampling, finding representatives in the Palearctic region of the COI-mitotype, found to be unique for 
Canada
among the samples investigated here (h 
4 in
), may help to narrow down the range of potential sources of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
introduction. 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
forms an unusually diverse clade that can be delineated using both molecular and morphological methods. 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
exhibits much higher COI-divergence than the usual genetic variation found within most 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius
species
</tp:taxon-name>
(

). The maximum uncorrected divergence of COI within this taxon was found to be 5.9%, and 15 mitotypes were detected in 28 sequences. Haplotype diversity was high (0.899) and so was nucleotide diversity (0.012). Representatives of two of the four main COI-lineages also differ in two nuclear genes: Wg (0.1–0.4%) and Top1 (0.1–0.3%). Also, morphological variation within 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
was observed (see ranges of morphometric variables in 
Table 1
). It is therefore possible that 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp.nov.</named-content>
represents a complex of poorly understood species rather than a single species. Investigations involving more samples from the entire range of this group, a deeper genomic scan and detailed morphological investigation involving all castes may clarify this question in the future. Finally, a population from the area of coastal Massachusetts that was hypothesized to belong to 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
or yet another, undescribed species 
19
could previously not be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>L. neoniger</tp:taxon-name>
using DNA-barcoding 
33
.
</p>
         <p>Figure 4.
Average thorax profile of 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(
a
) and members of the Palearctic 
<tp:taxon-name>L. nigercomplex</tp:taxon-name>
(
b
). Figures were created by image averaging (
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov</named-content>
n = 35; Palearctic 
L. niger-
complex n =30 specimens). Frontal view of head and detail of clypeus of the Holotype worker of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. ponderosae</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">sp. nov.</named-content>
(
c
) and a non-type worker of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
(
d
).
</p>
         <p>
The introduction of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
to North America could potentially result in a serious biological invasion. 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius niger</tp:taxon-name>
was found in eleven separate outdoor localities (Supplementary Table 
S
2). One specimen from Halifax imaged on AntWeb (casent0280452) displaying the morphological traits of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
was already collected in 1996, suggesting that 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
workers could have been present in this area for at least 26 years. Finally, environmental niche modelling predicts highly suitable conditions in both Canadian sites of introduction (

). We therefore conclude that 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
is permanently established in 
Canada
. Our samples from distant locations throughout the native European range and the introduced range in 
Canada
formed a dense cluster of COI-mitotypes, only differing from each other in pairwise comparisons by a maximum of four nucleotide substitutions per 658 bp (0.6%), despite the vast population size of this most common European ant (

). Moreover, most specimens analyzed here belong to the same widespread European mitotype (

). Possible explanations of this genetic structure include (1) a young evolutionary age of the species followed by a rapid population expansion, (2) one or several bottlenecks during glaciation and subsequent rapid dispersal or (3) a selective sweep or infection with 
<tp:taxon-name>Wolbachia</tp:taxon-name>
endosymbiont bacteria 
54
. Among these possibilities, the first explanation seems the most likely as a recent analysis of the genome of this species revealed, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
apparently possesses genomic exaptations to urbanization 
30
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Lasius niger</tp:taxon-name>
is particularly common in gardens, cities and rural landscapes in Europe, but nearly absent from closed forests 
55
, possibly representing large parts of the original European vegetation. Therefore, this species has benefitted strongly from anthropogenic land change which mediated its recent population expansion. The future impact of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
populations in North America is difficult to predict given our current information. Our niche modeling suggests a relatively large area of suitable habitat for the species in North America, but competition with native species may affect (limit) its dispersal in unexpected ways. Furthermore, on the one hand, some biological properties of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
seemingly limit its potential to cause ecological damage in natural habitats: (1) although 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
queens may facultatively aggregate during colony foundation (pleometrosis), mature colonies are monogynous, i.e. headed by a single queen only 
56
; (2) despite high ecological potential, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
is not known to produce supercolonial populations (colonies consisting of several connected nests); (3) the species shows intraspecific aggression at individual level 
57
. On the other hand, even though 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
is monogynous, the species has managed to reach an enormous abundance over a wide area within its native range, and information about its ecology is limited in its introduced range. As a true omnivore 
55
, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
has the potential to strongly compete with native Nearctic ants possessing similar ecological niches and competitively displace them particularly in modified habitats. Laboratory aggression tests 
58
between 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
and local native species would be a simple first step to explore these ecological interactions. In addition to displacing native ant species, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
may also negatively affect other native animals via direct predation 
59
, or enhancement of predation risk 
60
. Plants may be affected via the assistance of associated aphid species 
61
. This could be the main economic damage caused by this species, in addition to minor structural damage in cities 
62
. Finally, if lef uncontrolled and over generations of adaptation to the novel range, 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
may even expand its distribution into undisturbed natural habitats in North America, ultimately to the detriment of native biodiversity. We therefore propose (1) that the extent of the already established populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>L. niger</tp:taxon-name>
in North America and their impact on local ecosystems should be closely monitored and studied; (2) that active control measures should be rapidly implemented to prevent already established populations from further spread. Our results underscore the necessity of integrating molecular phylogenetics, phylogeography and taxonomy in the timely recognition of non-native species introductions involving cryptic species.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Data availability</title>
         <p>
All primary data are accessible through the electronic supplementary material (
Table S1-S
6, 

), BOLD and GenBank. Voucher specimens are deposited at the Museum of Comparative Zoology, Cambridge, 
USA
and at the Institut de Biologia Evolutiva (CSIC-UPF), Barcelona, 
Spain
.
</p>
         <p>
Received: 
6 February 2022
; Accepted: 
31 March 2022</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>
1. 
Courchamp, F.et al.Invasion biology: Specific problems and possible solutions
. 
Trends Ecol. Evol.32
, 
13–22
(
2017
).
</p>
         <p>
2. 
Pimentel, D.
, 
Zuniga, R.
&amp; 
Morrison, D.Update on the environmental and economic costs associated with alien-invasive species in the United States
. 
Ecol. Econ.52
, 
273–288
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
3. 
Clavero, M.
&amp; 
García-Berthou, E.Invasive species are a leading cause of animal extinctions
. 
Trends Ecol. Evol.20
, 
110
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
4. 
de Moraes, G. J.Importance of taxonomy in biological control
. 
Int. J.Trop. Insect Sci.8
, 
841–844
(
1987
).
</p>
         <p>
5. 
Pyšek, P.et al.Hitting the right target: taxonomic challenges for, and of, plant invasions
. 
AoB Plants5
, 
42
(
2013
).
</p>
         <p>
6. 
Smith,R.D.
, 
Aradottir, G.I.
, 
Taylor, A.
&amp; 
Lyal,C.Invasive species management—what taxonomic support is needed?
(
Global Invasive Species Programme
, 
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
7. 
Dincă, V.et al.DNA barcode reference library for Iberian butterflies enables a continental-scale preview of potential cryptic diversity
. 
Sci. Rep.5
, 
12395
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
8. 
Vodă, R.
, 
Dapporto, L.
, 
Dincă, V.
&amp; 
Vila, R.Cryptic matters:Overlooked species generate most butterfly beta-diversity
. 
Ecography38
, 
405–409
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
9. 
Holway, D. A.
, 
Lach, L.
, 
Suarez, A. V.
, 
Tsutsui, N. D.
&amp; 
Case, T. J.The causes and consequences of ant invasions
. 
Annu. Rev. Ecol. Syst.33
, 
181–233
(
2002
).
</p>
         <p>
10. 
McGlynn, T.P.The worldwide transfer of ants:Geographical distribution and ecological invasions
. 
J.Biogeogr.26
, 
535–548
(
1999
).
</p>
         <p>
11. 
Lowe, S.
, 
Browne,M.
, 
Boudjelas,S.
&amp; 
De Poorter, M.100 of the world’s worst invasive alien species: a selection from the global invasive species database
. (
The Invasive Species Specialist Group (ISSG) a specialist group of the Species Survival Commission (SSC) of the World Conservation Union (IUCN)
, 
2000
).
</p>
         <p>
12. 
Flucher, S. M.et al.Effect of social structure and introduction history on genetic diversity and differentiation
. 
Mol. Ecol.30
, 
2511–2527
(
2021
).
</p>
         <p>
13. 
Hölldobler, B.
&amp; 
Wilson, E. O.Journey to the Ants: A Story of Scientific Exploration
(
Belknap Press of Harvard University Press
, 
1994
).
</p>
         <p>
14. 
Fisher, B. L.
&amp; 
Cover, S. P.Ants of North America: A Guide to the Genera
(
University of California Press
, 
2007
).
</p>
         <p>
15. 
Shattuck, S.
&amp; 
Cover, S.Taxonomy of some little-understood North American ants (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)
. 
Zootaxa4175
, 
10–22
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
16. 
Creighton, W.S.The ants of North America
. 
Bull. Museum Comparat. Zool.104
, 
1–585
(
1950
).
</p>
         <p>
17. 
Wilson, E. O.
A monographic revision of the ant genus 
Lasius
. 
Bull. Museum Comparat. Zool.113
, 
1–201
(
1955
).
</p>
         <p>
18. 
Deyrup, M.Ants of Florida: Identification and Natural History
(
CRC Press
, 
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
19. 
Ellison, A. M.
, 
Gotelli, N. J.
, 
Farnsworth, E. J.
&amp; 
Alpert, G. D.A Field Guide to the Ants of New England
(
Yale University Press
, 
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
20. 
Glasier, J. R. N.
, 
Acorn, J. H.
, 
Nielsen, S. E.
&amp; 
Proctor, H.Ants (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) of Alberta: A key to species based primarily on the worker caste
. 
Can. J.Arthropod Identif.22
, 
1–104
(
2013
).
</p>
         <p>
21. 
Booher, D. B.
The ant genus 
Strumigenys
Smith, 1860 (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) in western North America North of Mexico

. 
Zootaxa5061
, 
201–248
(
2021
).
</p>
         <p>
22. 
Prebus, M. M.
Taxonomic revision of the 
Temnothorax salvini
clade (Hymenoptera: Formicidae), with a key to the clades of New World 
Temnothorax
. 
PeerJ9
, e 
11514
(
2021
).
</p>
         <p>
23. 
Ward, P.S.
&amp; 
Blaimer, B. B.
Taxonomy in the phylogenomic era: Species boundaries and phylogenetic relationships among North American ants of the 
Crematogaster scutellaris
group (Formicidae: Hymenoptera)

. 
Zool. J. Linn. Soc.194
, 
893–937
(
2022
).
</p>
         <p>
24. 
Janicki, J.
, 
Narula, N.
, 
Ziegler, M.
, 
Guénard, B.
&amp; 
Economo, E. P.Visualizing and interacting with large-volume biodiversity data using client–server web-mapping applications:The design and implementation of antmaps.org
. 
Ecol. Inform.32
, 
185–193
(
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
25. 
Salata, S.
&amp; 
Borowiec, L.
A new species of the ant genus 
Lasius
Fabricius, 1804 from Crete (Hymenoptera, Formicidae)

. 
ZooKeys789
, 
139–159
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
26. 
Seifert, B.
A taxonomic revision of the Palaearctic members of the subgenus 
Lasius s. str.
(Hymenoptera, Formicidae)

. 
Soil Org.92
, 
15–86
(
2020
).
</p>
         <p>
27. 
Talavera, G.
, 
Espadaler, X.
&amp; 
Vila, R.
Discovered just before extinction? The first endemic ant from the Balearic Islands (
Lasius balearicus
sp. nov.) is endangered by climate change

. 
J. Biogeogr.42
, 
589–601
(
2015
).
</p>
         <p>
28. 
Cornwell, P.The incidence of pest ants in Britain
. 
Int. Pest Control20
, 
12–14
(
1978
).
</p>
         <p>
29. 
Seifert, B.Lasius platythorax
n. sp. a Widespread Sibling Species of 
Lasius niger
(Hymenoptera: Formicidae)

. 
Entomol. Gen.16
, 
69–81
(
1991
).
</p>
         <p>
30. 
Konorov, E. A.et al.
Genomic exaptation enables 
Lasius niger
adaptation to urban environments

. 
BMC Evol. Biol.17
, 
39
(
2017
).
</p>
         <p>
31. 
Lind, A.et al.
Development and control of mound nests of black garden ant (
Lasius niger
) in farmland

. 
Agron. Res.4
, 
269–272
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
32. 
Bateman, P. L. G.Pest control in the food industry
. 
R. Soc. Health J.102
, 
242–248
(
1982
).
</p>
         <p>
33. 
Schär, S.et al.Do Holarctic ant species exist? Trans-Beringian dispersal and homoplasy in the Formicidae
. 
J.Biogeogr.45
, 
1917– 1928
(
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
34. 
Boudinot, B. E.
, 
Borowiec, M.L.
&amp; 
Prebus, M.M.
Phylogeny, evolution, and classification of the ant genus 
Lasius
, the tribe Lasiini and the subfamily Formicinae (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)

. 
Syst. Entomol.47
, 
113–151
(
2022
).
</p>
         <p>
35. 
Maruyama, M.et al.
A DNA and morphology based phylogenetic framework of the ant genus 
Lasius
with hypotheses for the evolution of social parasitism and fungiculture

. 
BMC Evol. Biol.8
, 
237
(
2008
).
</p>
         <p>
36. 
Steiner, F. M.et al.
Phylogeny and bionomics of 
Lasius austriacus
(Hymenoptera, Formicidae)

. 
Insectes Soc.51
, 
24–29
(
2004
).
</p>
         <p>
37. 
Drummond, A. J.
, 
Suchard, M. A.
, 
Xie, D.
&amp; 
Rambaut, A.Bayesian phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 17
. 
Mol. Biol. Evol.29
, 
1969
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
38. 
Minh, B. Q.et al.IQ-TREE 2: New models and efficient methods for phylogenetic inference in the genomic era
. 
Mol. Biol. Evol.37
, 
1530–1534
(
2020
).
</p>
         <p>
39. 
Kalyaanamoorthy, S.
, 
Minh, B. Q.
, 
Wong, T.K. F.
, 
von Haeseler, A.
&amp; 
Jermiin, L.S.ModelFinder: Fast model selection for accurate phylogenetic estimates
. 
Nat. Methods14
, 
587–589
(
2017
).
</p>
         <p>
40. 
Ratnasingham, S.
&amp; 
Hebert, P. D. N.BOLD: The Barcode of Life Data System
(

http://www.barcodinglife.org). 
Mol. Ecol. Notes7
, 355–364 (
2007
).
</p>
         <p>
41. 
Aktas, C.haplotypes: Manipulating DNA Sequences and Estimating Unambiguous Haplotype Network with Statistical Parsimony.R package version 1.1.2
. Available from
https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=haplotypes
. (
2020
).
</p>
         <p>
42. R 
Core Team
. 
R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing
(
R Foundation for Statistical Computing
, 
2021
).
</p>
         <p>
43. 
Kahle, D.
&amp; 
Wickham, H.ggmap:Spatial visualization with ggplot2
. 
R. J.5
, 
144–161
(
2013
).
</p>
         <p>
44. 
Seifert, B.
, 
Ritz, M.
&amp; 
Csösz, S.Application of exploratory data analyses opens a new perspective in morphology-based alphataxonomy of eusocial organisms
. 
Myrmecol. News19
, 
1–15
(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
45. 
Perciano, T.ripa: R Image Processing and Analysis
. (
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
46. 
Thuiller, W.
, 
Georges, D.
, 
Engler, R.
&amp; 
Breiner, F.biomod2: Ensemble Platform for Species Distribution Modeling. R package version 3.3–7
. (
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
47. 
Seifert, B.A taxonomic revision of the Palaearctic members of the ant subgenus Lasius. s. str (Hymenoptera: Formicidae)
. 
Abh. Berichte Naturkundemuseums Görlitz66
, 
1–67
(
1992
).
</p>
         <p>
48. 
Lebas, C.
, 
Galkowski, C.
, 
Blatrix, R.
&amp; 
Wegnez, P.Fourmis d’Europe Occidentale LePremier Guide Complet d’Europe
(
Delachaux et Niestlé
, 
2016
).
</p>
         <p>
49. 
Czechowski, W.
, 
Radchenko, A.
&amp; 
Czechowska, W.The ants (Hymenoptera: Formicidae) of Poland
. (
Museum and Institute of Zoology, Polish Academy of Sciences
, 
2002
).
</p>
         <p>
50. 
Hijmans, R. J.
, 
Cameron, S. E.
, 
Parra, J. L.
, 
Jones, P. G.
&amp; 
Jarvis, A.Very high resolution interpolated climate surfaces for global land areas
. 
Int. J. Climatol.25
, 
1965–1978
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
51. 
Arino, O.et al.Global Land Cover Map for 2009 (GlobCover 2009)
. 

© 
European Space Agency (ESA) &amp; Université catholique de Louvain (UCL)
(
2012
) doi: 
10.1594/PANGAEA.787668
.
</p>
         <p>
52. 
Wheeler, G. C.
&amp; 
Wheeler, J. N.Te ants of Nevada
(
Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County
, 
1986
).
</p>
         <p>
53. 
AntWeb
. 
Available
from 
http://www.antweb.org
. (
2022
).
</p>
         <p>
54. 
Hurst, G. D. D.
&amp; 
Jiggins, F. M.Problems with mitochondrial DNA as a marker in population, phylogeographic and phylogenetic studies: The effects of inherited symbionts
. 
Proc.R. Soc. B Biol. Sci.272
, 
1525–1534
(
2005
).
</p>
         <p>
55. 
Seifert, B.Te ants of Central and North Europe
407

(
Lutra Verlags- und Vertriebsgesellschaf
, 
2018
).
</p>
         <p>
56. 
Sommer, K.
&amp; 
Hölldobler, B.
Colony founding by queen association and determinants of reduction in queen number in the ant 
Lasius niger
. 
Anim. Behav.50
, 
287–294
(
1995
).
</p>
         <p>
57. 
Fourcassié, V.
, 
Schmitt, T.
&amp; 
Detrain, C.
Impact of Interference Competition on Exploration and Food Exploitation in the Ant 
Lasius niger
. 
Psyche2012
, 
383757
(
2012
).
</p>
         <p>
58. 
Cremer, S.
, 
Ugelvig, L.V.
, 
Lommen, S. T. E.
, 
Petersen, K. S.
&amp; 
Pedersen, J.S.
Attack of the invasive garden ant: Aggression behaviour of 
Lasius neglectus
(Hymenoptera: Formicidae) against native 
Lasius
species in Spain

. 
Myrmecol. News9
, 
13–19
(
2006
).
</p>
         <p>
59. 
Sanders, D.
&amp; 
van Veen, F. J. F.Ecosystem engineering and predation: The multi-trophic impact of two ant species
. 
J. Anim. Ecol.80
, 
569–576
(
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
60. 
Mestre, L.
, 
Bucher, R.
&amp; 
Entling, M. H.Trait-mediated effects between predators: Ant chemical cues induce spider dispersal
. 
J. Zool.293
, 
119–125
(
2014
).
</p>
         <p>
61. 
Newton, J. S.
, 
Glasier, J.
, 
Maw, H. E. L.
, 
Proctor, H. C.
&amp; 
Foottit, R. G.
Ants and subterranean 
Sternorrhyncha
in a native grassland in east-central Alberta Canada

. 
Can. Entomol.143
, 
518–523
(
2011
).
</p>
         <p>
62. 
Klotz, J. H.
, 
Hansen, L.
, 
Pospischil, R.
&amp; 
Rust, M.Urban Ants of North America and Europe: Identification,Biology, and Management
(
Cornell University Press
, 
2008
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <title>Acknowledgements</title>
         <p>
Special thanks to Matthew Prebus for specimens contributed to this study. We are grateful to Bernhard Seifert and an anonymous Reviewer for constructive comments, improving previous versions of this manuscript. Funding was provided by project CGL2016 
‐
76322 (AEI/FEDER, UE), by grant PID2020-117739GA-I00 funded by MCIN/ AEI/10. 13039/501100011033, and by the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF) via the Early Post-doc Mobility grant 
P
2SKP3_161677 to 
S
. Schär.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Author contributions</title>
         <p>
Conceived of study: 
S
. 
S
., R.V., G.T., 
J
.D.R., 
S
. 
P
. 
C
., X. 
E
.; generated data: 
S
. 
S
., G.T., 
J
.D.R., 
S
.O. 
S
., 
S
. 
P
. 
C
.; photographed and curated specimens: 
S
.O. 
S
., 
J
.D.R., 
S
. 
P
. 
C
.; analyzed data: 
S
. 
S
., G.T.; interpreted results and wrote manuscript: 
S
. 
S
., G.T., 
J
.D.R., R.V., X. 
E
.; all authors acknowledged the final manuscript.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>Competing interests</title>
         <p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p>
      </sec>
      <p>Additional information</p>
      <p>Supplementary Information
The online version contains supplementary material available at https://doi.org/ 10.1038/s41598-022-10047-9.
</p>
      <p>Correspondence
and requests for materials should be addressed to 
S
. 
S
.
</p>
      <p>Reprints and permissions information
is available at www.nature.com/reprints.
</p>
      <p>Publisher’s note
Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.
</p>
      <p>Open Access
This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.
</p>
      <p>© The Author(s) 2022</p>
   </body>
</article>
