<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <front>
      <journal-meta>
         <journal-id>10.1098/rsos.140458</journal-id>
         <issn/>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
         <title-group>
            <article-title>A spectacular new species of seadragon (Syngnathidae)</article-title>
         </title-group>
         <pub-date>
            <year>2015</year>
         </pub-date>
      </article-meta>
   </front>
   <body>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>
A spectacular new species of seadragon (
<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathidae</tp:taxon-name>
)
</title>
         <title>rsos.royalsocietypublishing.org</title>
         <p>Josefin Stiller1
, 
Nerida G. Wilson2
and 
Greg W. Rouse1</p>
         <p>1
Scripps Institution of Oceanography, 
UCSD
, 
9500
Gilman Drive, La Jolla,
</p>
         <p>Research</p>
         <p>
CA 
92093
-0202, 
USA</p>
         <p>2
Western Australian Museum, 
69
Kew St., Welshpool 
6106
,Perth,Western 
Australia
, 
Australia</p>
         <p>Cite this article: Stiller J, Wilson NG, Rouse</p>
         <p>
GW. 
2015
A spectacular new species of
</p>
         <title>
seadragon (
<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathidae</tp:taxon-name>
). 
R. Soc. open sci.</title>
         <p>1
. Summary
</p>
         <p>2
: 
140458
. http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1098
/rsos. 
140458</p>
         <p>
The exploration of Earth’s biodiversity is an exciting and ongoing endeavour. Here, we report a new species of seadragon from Western 
Australia
with substantial morphological and genetic differences to the only two other known species. We describe it as 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
Although the leafy seadragon (
<tp:taxon-name>Phycodurus eques</tp:taxon-name>
) and the common seadragon (
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
) occur along Australia’s southern coast, generally among relatively shallow macroalgal reefs, the new species was found more offshore in slightly deeper waters. The 
holotype
was trawled east of the remote Recherche Archipelago in 
51 m
; additional specimens extend the distribution west to Perth in 
72 m
.

Molecular sequence data show clear divergence from the other seadragons (
7.4–13.1
% uncorrected divergence in mitochondrial DNA) and support a placement as the sisterspecies to the common seadragon. Radiographs and microcomputed tomography were used on the 
holotype
of the new species and revealed unique features, in addition to its unusual red coloration. The discovery provides a spectacular example of the surprises still hidden in our oceans, even in relatively shallow waters.
</p>
         <p>
Received: 
20
November 
2014</p>
         <p>
Accepted: 
12
January 
2015</p>
         <p>
Published: 
18
February 
2015</p>
         <p>Subject Category:</p>
         <p>Biology (whole organism)</p>
         <p>Subject Areas:</p>
         <p>taxonomy and systematics/evolution</p>
         <p>Keywords:</p>
         <title>
biodiversity, 
<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathidae</tp:taxon-name>
, new species,
</title>
         <p>seadragon</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>2
. Introduction
</title>
         <p>
The fraction of undescribed biodiversity in the ocean is arguably high [
1
, 
2
], and new fish species are likely to be described, especially from the deeper continental slopes [
3
]. Here, we describe a remarkable example, a new species of seadragon. 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
is only the third known species of seadragon, and the first to be discovered in 
150
years, possibly because it lives in slightly deeper waters than its relatives.
</p>
         <title>Authors for correspondence:</title>
         <p>Josefin Stiller</p>
         <p>e-mail:jstiller@ucsd.edu</p>
         <p>Greg W. Rouse</p>
         <p>e-mail:grouse@ucsd.edu</p>
         <p>
Seadragons (
<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathidae</tp:taxon-name>
) are fish of mesmerizing beauty (

), with the leafy seadragon (
<tp:taxon-name>Phycodurus eques</tp:taxon-name>
) having more elaborate appendages than the colourful common seadragon (
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
). Their ornamentation helps camouflage them among seagrasses and kelp in the shallow coastal waters of southern 
Australia
[
4
]. The range of the common seadragon
</p>
         <p>
Electronic supplementary material is available at http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1098
/rsos. 
140458
or via http://rsos.royalsocietypublishing.org.
</p>
         <p>
Figure 1. Distribution and phylogenetic relationships of the three seadragon species. The range of the leafy seadragon is shown in gold, the common seadragon in blue and the type locality of the new seadragon 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
is indicated by the red arrow. The red circle represents the collection sites of the three paratypes. The maximum-likelihood tree is based on the partitioned dataset (4416 bp). Numbers next to the nodes indicate bootstrap (top) and jackknife (bottom) values; full support is indicated by white circles.
</p>
         <p>
spans the entire southern coast from Western 
Australia
to New South 
Wales
and Tasmania, whereas the leafy seadragon has a more restricted distribution from Western 
Australia
to South 
Australia
(map in 

). The two known species of seadragons fascinate aquarium visitors around the world, draw many 
SCUBA
divers into the water and are charismatic symbols for conservation of marine species [
5
, 
6
].
</p>
         <p>
On a biodiversity survey (part of the Marine Futures project 
2007
; www.marinefutures.fnas.uwa. edu.au/), a male seadragon carrying a brood of offspring was trawled off the coast of Western 
Australia
. The specimen was accessioned at the Western Australian Museum (
WAM
P 
33223.002
) as a common seadragon, and its uniqueness only subsequently recognized following DNA sequencing. Three additional specimens were located in scientific collections. The 
holotype
of the new seadragon shows a bright red coloration and with transverse body-markings similar to leafy seadragons. However, the body shape more closely resembles the common seadragon. Here, we examine the anatomy and evolutionary history of the new seadragon to determine its systematic placement and formally describe it.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>3
. Material and methods
</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>3.1
. Sampling
</title>
         <p>
Several diagnostic features of the skeleton allowed us to identify additional specimens of the new species that had been catalogued in scientific collections as common seadragons, even when they had lost colour and were unsuitable for genetic analysis. As the 
holotype
was trawled from an unusual depth, we requested and examined specimens from depths of more than 
50 m
.

Most museum specimens, however, do not hold explicit depth records, therefore we also asked for information on individuals collected on vessels, as those are more likely to have been collected offshore. A total of 
15
trawled specimens from New South 
Wales
, Tasmania, South 
Australia
and Western 
Australia
(see the electronic supplementary material for details) were located. Of these, two specimens (
CSIRO
Australian National Fish Collection; 
ANFC
C 
2269
and C 
2270
) collected near Perth, Western 
Australia
, were trawled from a depth of 
72 m
and are here designated as 
paratypes
of the new species based on their anatomical similarity to the 
holotype
. The other trawled specimens were common seadragons, unfortunately mostly without depth records, which makes it difficult to infer a depth range for this species. The deepest record for a common seadragon was from 
27 to 33 m
(
WAM
P. 
20854
; see the electronic supplementary material for details). We visually inspected 
158
lots of common seadragons held at the Western Australian Museum, mostly from the southwestern coast of 
Australia
, and found an additional 
paratype
from Perth without a depth record as it was beachwashed. No specimens of the new species are housed at the South Australian Museum (Ralph Foster 
2014
, personal communication), which holds 
60
lots of common seadragons mainly from South 
Australia
and Victoria.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>3.2
. Molecular sampling
</title>
         <p>
A piece of the tail of the 
holotype
(preserved in ethanol) was used for DNA extraction as the dermal appendages were missing in this species; the specimen was a male carrying its brood, and we also obtained DNA sequences for one of its brood of embryos in order to obtain the mitochondrial haplotype of the mother. A DNA extraction protocol for formalin-preserved tissues [
7
] was unsuccessful for two of the 
paratypes
(
ANFC
C 
2269
and C 
2270
) and not attempted for the third 
paratype
(
WAM
P 
660
) because of its advanced age (collected 
1919
). For comparison with the other two seadragon species, we included genetic samples of wild-caught common seadragons and leafy seadragons from across their respective ranges (

table 
1
). A small tissue clip was taken from the ventral dermal appendages of live animals that were subsequently released. This non-lethal sampling was considered less destructive than finclipping as the dermal appendages do not seem to have a locomotory function and are often damaged in otherwise healthy seadragons. We included three specimens of the common seadragon from Western 
Australia
(Shelley Cove, Dunsborough, 
17
December 
2005
), South 
Australia
(Encounter Bay, 
8
April 
2006
) and Tasmania (Blackmans Bay, Hobart, 
16
December 
2012
). For the leafy seadragon, we included two specimens, one from South 
Australia
(Encounter Bay, 
3
February 
2006
), the other from Western 
Australia
(Bremer Bay, 
11
December 
2005
). See the ethics statement for permit details.
</p>
         <p>
Outgroup samples included three members of 
<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathinae</tp:taxon-name>
, a group which was identified as the sister-group to the seadragons [
8
– 
10
]. We included sequences from three species of spiny pipehorses, namely 
<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathus spinosissimus</tp:taxon-name>
(Auckland Museum Marine Collections 

MA 
133942
, 
New Zealand
, Southland, Milford Sound, total length (TL) 
1900 mm
, 

May 
2006
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathus dunckeri</tp:taxon-name>
(from GenBank, 

table 
1
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathus lettiensis</tp:taxon-name>
(
ANFC
H 
6340
-09/GT 
192
, Western 
Australia
, northwest of Rottnest Island, RV Naturaliste, 
100 m
depth, 
7
April 
2006
, supplied as 
<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathus guentheri</tp:taxon-name>
). We also included 
<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathoides biaculeatus</tp:taxon-name>
(Syngnathoidinae; gift from the Birch Aquarium at Scripps, 
28
May 
2013
), which was shown to be closely related to seadragons and 
<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathinae</tp:taxon-name>
[
8
– 
10
].
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>3.3
. DNA extraction and PCR amplification
</title>
         <p>
DNA was isolated with the Qiagen DNeasy blood and tissue kit (Qiagen Sciences, Germantown, MD). Seven marker regions (four mitochondrial, three nuclear) were amplified in a reaction volume of 
12.5
µl with the following primer pairs:
</p>
         <p>
— 
12
S

: L 
1091
and H 
1478
[
11
], modified following reference [
9
], amplified 
346
bp of the 
12
S ribosomal RNA gene, using the thermal profile of 
95
° C for 
15
min, 
35
cycles of 
95
° C for 
4
0 s

, 
50
° C for 
40
s, 
68
° C for 
50
s, and a final extension at 
68
°C for 
5
min.
</p>
         <p>Table 1. Collection details and GenBank accession numbers. WA, Western Australia; SA, South Australia; TAS,Tasmania.</p>
         <p>specieslocality12S16SND4control regionS7Tmo-4c4aldolase<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>WA, east of Middle Island (male, brood)KM201546KM201553KM201563KM201574KM201593KM201604KM201583KM201547KM201554KM201564KM201575KM201594KM201603KM201584<tp:taxon-name>Phycodurus eques</tp:taxon-name>SA, Encounter BayGU182919GU182927KM201558KM201569KM201588KM201598KM201578WA, Bremer BayGU182918GU182926KM201559KM201570KM201589KM201599KM201579<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>SA, Encounter BayKM201544KM201551KM201561KM201571KM201590KM201602KM201580TAS, HobartKM201545KM201552KM201562KM201572KM201591KM201601KM201581WA, Dunsborough, Shelley CoveGU182920GU182928KM201560KM201573KM201592KM201600KM201582<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathus dunckeri</tp:taxon-name>—JF273446GU182924—————<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathus lettiensis</tp:taxon-name>WA, northwest of Rottnest IslandKM201550KM201557KM201567KM201576KM201586KM201596—<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathus spinosissimus</tp:taxon-name>New Zealand, Southland, Milford SoundKM201549KM201556KM201566—KM201587KM201597KM201577<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathoides biaculeatus</tp:taxon-name>Aquarium specimenKM201548KM201555KM201565KM201568KM201585KM201595—</p>
         <p>
— 
16
S

: L 
2510
and H 
3058
[
12
], which amplify 
522
bp of the 
16
S ribosomal RNA gene, with the same thermal profile as 
12
S.
</p>
         <p>
— 

ND 
4
: 

L 
11424
-ND 
4
[
13
] and 

H 
12293
-Leu [
14
], amplified an 
838
bp fragment of the 
NADH
dehydrogenase subunit four, including transfer RNA histidine and serine, with a thermal profile of 
94
° C for 
9
min, 
34
cycles of 
94
° C for 
45
s, 
52
° C for 
45
s, 
72
°C for 
60
s, and a final extension at 
72
° C for 
6
min.
</p>
         <p>
— 
Control region
: 

L 
15995
L-PRO [
15
] and H 
693.512
S 
5
r. 
5
[
16
], amplified a 
1036
bp fragment of the mitochondrial control region, including fragments of the 
12
S ribosomal RNA gene. The fragment has a repetitive region in the middle of the fragment that impaired the sequencing reaction. To obtain the full-length fragment, we developed an additional primer set for sequencing the flanking regions of the mitochondrial control region (CR-FlanksF 
5
′-CCCCCACCCCCTTTAAAGAC- 
3
′ and CR-FlanksR 
5
′-CGAGTCGTATGTGTCCCACC3′). All fragments were amplified via a thermal profile of 
94
° C for 
3
min, 
40
cycles of 
94
° C for 
6
0 s

, 
50
° C for 
30
s, 
72
° C for 
60
s, and a final extension at 
72
°C for 
5
min.
</p>
         <p>
— 

S 
7
: S 
7RPEX1
F and S 
7RPEX2
R [
17
] amplified up to 
674
bp of the intron 
1
and exon 
2
of the nuclear S 
7
ribosomal protein gene with the thermal profile specified in reference [
18
].
</p>
         <p>
— 
Aldolase
: we used forward and reverse primers as specified in reference [
19
], amplifying a 
382
bp long fragment of a nuclear aldolase-like gene containing both coding and non-coding regions with a thermal profile as outlined in reference [
19
]. — 

Tmo- 
4
c 
4
: Tmo- 
4
c 
4
F and Tmo- 
4
c 
4
R [
20
] amplified a 
559
bp long coding fragment of the nuclear Tmo- 
4
c 
4
gene with the thermal profile specified in reference [
18
].
</p>
         <p>
PCR products were purified with Exo-SAP-IT (
USB
Affymetrix) and sequencing was completed with the corresponding PCR primers (Eurofins 
MWG
Operon, Inc.). Overlapping fragments were edited and then merged into consensus sequences in GENEIOUS v. 6.0. 
3
(Biomatters Ltd.). All sequences were deposited on GenBank (

table 
1
).
</p>
         <p>
Sequences for each marker were aligned on the 
MAFFT
v. 
7
server [
21
, 
22
]. Most markers aligned without gaps, but gaps were inserted into the control region fragment resulting in an aligned length of 
1084
bp, and S 
7
-like protein aligned to a length of 
685
bp. Alignments were deposited on TreeBASE (

S 
15971
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>3.4
. Distance-based analysis
</title>
         <p>
Uncorrected and model-corrected genetic distances were calculated in 
PAUP
* 

v. 
4
b 
10
[
23
]. The appropriate model selected by JMODELTEST v. 
2.1
. 
4
[
24
] employing the Akaike information criterion was GTR + G for the mitochondrial dataset (control region, 
16
S, 
12
S, ND 
4
) with a gamma parameter of 
0.283
. For S 
7
and aldolase, the chosen model was HKY, and K 
80
+ I for Tmo- 
4
c 
4
with a proportion of invariant sites of 
0.723
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>3.5
. Phylogenetic analysis
</title>
         <p>
To assess the phylogenetic affinities of the seadragons, we conducted maximum-parsimony (MP) and maximum-likelihood (ML) analyses. To check for data congruence, we analysed each nuclear marker individually, while we treated the mitochondrial markers as a single locus (
2790
bp), and finally concatenated the datasets (
4416
bp) in MESQUITE v. 
2.75
[
25
].
</p>
         <p>
Maximum-parsimony analyses were conducted in 
PAUP
*, with unordered and equally weighted characters, heuristic searches with 
1000
random addition-sequence replicates and tree bisection and reconnection (TBR) branch swapping and with zero-length branches collapsed. To assess clade confidence, parsimony jackknifing was conducted with 
1000
jackknife replicates, each with 
100
random addition replicates, 
37
% character deletion, heuristic search option and TBR branch swapping.
</p>
         <p>
Maximum-likelihood analyses were conducted in RAXMLGUI v. 
0.93
[
26
, 
27
] employing the GTR + G model for each of the partitions. The dataset was partitioned for the different loci, for introns and exons of aldolase and S 
7
, and additionally for the codon positions for the protein-coding regions of Tmo- 
4
c 
4
and the exons of aldolase and S 
7
, and the protein-coding regions and tRNA segments of ND 
4
(partitions given in the electronic supplementary material, file S 
2
). One thousand replicate ML inferences were performed and clade confidence was assessed with 
1000
bootstrap pseudo-replicates employing the thorough bootstrapping algorithm (option ‘-b’). The analyses were rooted with 
<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathoides biaculeatus</tp:taxon-name>
, with the three 
<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathus</tp:taxon-name>
species unconstrained. Sequence matrices and resulting trees were deposited on TreeBASE (

S 
15971
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>3.6
. Morphology and skeletal structure
</title>
         <p>
Morphometric measurements were taken of the 
holotype
and three 
paratypes
, and compared with scaled photographs from field observations of leafy (
n
= 
25
) and common seadragons (
n
= 
20
; for details, see electronic supplementary material, file S 
1
). The descriptive morphology follows [
4
], and proportional measurements were taken as in reference [
28
].
</p>
         <p>
Micro-computed tomography (µCT) of the 
holotype
was conducted at the Cartilage Tissue Engineering laboratory at the University of California San Diego. The specimen was imaged in a Skyscan 
1076
(Kontich, 
Belgium
), wrapped in ethanol-soaked gauze, and positioned in a sealed 
LDPE
container. Imaging was conducted at 
36
µm isotropic voxel size, applying an electrical potential of 
100
kVp and a current of 
100
µA, with a 1.0 mm aluminium filter. A beam-hardening correction algorithm was applied during image reconstruction. The reconstructed file size was 
1000
× 
1000
× 
5482
pixels (
xyz
).
</p>
         <p>DICOM
stacks were processed and segmented in A 
MIRA
v. 
5.4
(Visage Imaging, Inc.), and visualized in 
MAYA2014
service pack 
4
(Autodesk, Inc.). X-ray radiographs of all seadragon species were obtained at Scripps Institution of Oceanography.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4
.
Results</title>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4.1
. Genetic distance
</title>
         <p>
The new species showed clear genetic divergences in mitochondrial and nuclear sequences of a comparable magnitude to those between the established species of seadragons, both in uncorrected and model-corrected distances. As an example, the mitochondrial markers of the new species differed by 
7.4
% to 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
and by 
13.1
% to 
<tp:taxon-name>Phycodurus eques</tp:taxon-name>
, which is similar to the 
11.6
% distance between the two known species (uncorrected pairwise distances). Model-corrected distances (GTR + G) of the mitochondrial data showed 
9.9
% divergence between the new species and 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
22.3
% to 
<tp:taxon-name>Phycodurus eques</tp:taxon-name>
, similar to the two known species that diverged by 
18.9
%. Comparisons for the three nuclear loci showed a similar pattern (electronic supplementary material, tables S 
2
–S 
4
). The mitochondrial haplotype of the male was 
6
bp different from its brood, which represented the mother’s mitochondrial haplotype. The father and his offspring were genetically identical for the three nuclear markers.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4.2
. Phylogenetic placement
</title>
         <p>
All analyses retrieved the seadragons as a well-supported clade with respect to 
<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathoides biaculeatus</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Solegnathinae</tp:taxon-name>
(

; for individual gene trees see electronic supplementary material, figure S 
3
). Among seadragons, the new species was supported as the sister-species to the common seadragon, and the leafy seadragon as the sister to this clade (

; electronic supplementary material, figure S 
3a
, 
c
, 
d
). The nuclear S 
7
was incongruent with the other markers, supporting the leafy seadragon as the sister to the new seadragon (electronic supplementary material, figure S 
3b
). MP and ML analyses gave similar topologies within the seadragons.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4.3
. Morphology
</title>
         <p>
The new species has morphological features that clearly distinguish it from the other two seadragons (

table 
2
; see also electronic supplementary material, file S 
1
). In life, the 
holotype
is easily distinguished by its red colour (
a
), and pink vertical bars that extend halfway up the body to the lateral trunk ridges (
b
). The more uniform coloration differentiates it from the common seadragon, which has numerous colourful spots and blotches (

). These spots are always distinct, even in preserved specimens (see electronic supplementary material, figure S 
1
) allowing differentiation of the two species even when the pigmentation is faded. The patterning also differs from the tan-yellow leafy seadragon, which has vertical bars that extend all the way up the body and are white with purple rims (

). The X-ray radiographs and µCT showed that the new species has 
18
trunk vertebrae with the corresponding outer bony plates (see electronic supplementary material, videos S 
1
and S 
2
). Leafy seadragons have
</p>
         <p>Table 2. Comparison of diagnostic traits among the three seadragon species.</p>
         <p>
            <tp:taxon-name>Phycodurus eques</tp:taxon-name>
(
n
= 
25)<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
(
n
= 
20)<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
            <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
(
n
= 
4)trunk rings17–181718head spinepresentpresentabsentthird ventral spine on trunk ring1616 or absent17dorsal spine on trunk ring 11 orients
backward (figure 3 
a
)

backward (figure 3 
b
)

forward (figure 2 
b
, figure 3 
c
)
colorationyellow/pink and white barsyellow spots and blue ridgesred/pink barsdermal appendagescomplex, multilobatesimple, spatulateunknownlateral trunk and lateral tail ridgecontinuousdiscontinuousdiscontinuous</p>
         <p>
variable ring counts between 
17
and 
18
. All common seadragons examined had only 
17
trunk rings. The body shape of the new seadragon is reminiscent of the common seadragon, and different from the wavelike body of the leafy seadragon (

). Morphometric measurements, however, did not reveal any perfectly diagnostic characters (

table 
3
). The new species also has an enlarged pectoral area compared to the other species (
pa
in 
b
, 
e
). Even in large-bodied common seadragons (electronic supplementary material, figure S 
1d
), the area is not as inflated as in the new species. In contrast to the backwards-facing pair of dorsal spines in common and leafy seadragons, the new seadragon has a forward-pointing pair (
ds
in 
b
).
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>4.4
. Systematics
</title>
      </sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <kwd-group>
               <kwd content-type="nominate-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx lucasi</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx foliatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phycodurus eques</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Phycodurus 
eques</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>
Phyllopteryx 
taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phycodurus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>eques</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
               <kwd content-type="mentioned-taxon">
                  <tp:taxon-name>eques</tp:taxon-name>
               </kwd>
            </kwd-group>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">A spectacular new species of seadragon (Syngnathidae)</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">10.1098/rsos.140458</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFFD9846FFBCFFEA8C58A2781854FFC6</uri>
               <article-title/>
               <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.140458</pub-id>
               <source>Royal Society Open Science</source>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:mixed-nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
            <tp:taxon-status>n. sp.</tp:taxon-status>
         </tp:mixed-nomenclature>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
seadragon (
<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathidae</tp:taxon-name>
). 
R. Soc. open sci.</p>
            <p>1
. Summary
</p>
            <p>2
: 
140458
. http://dx.doi.org/ 
10.1098
/rsos. 
140458</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
biodiversity, 
<tp:taxon-name>Syngnathidae</tp:taxon-name>
, new species,
</p>
            <p>seadragon</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
(

, 
a–f
, 
c
, 

tables 
2
and 
3
, electronic supplementary material figure S 
2a
, 
b
and videos S 
1
–S 
2
).
</p>
            <p>4.4
. 
1
. 
Holotype</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <tp:material-citation>
               <p>
The 
holotype
repository is the Western Australian Museum, Perth: 
WAM
P 
33223.002
, as 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
240 mm
TL, 
male
with brood attached; 
eggs
removed for DNA extraction, tail clipped. The species has been registered with Zoobank under the following 
LSID
: 
BEF4
C 
635
-D 
5
DD- 
4
F
70-99
B 
6- 88157
AA 
88
C 
7
C.
</p>
               <p>4.4
. 
2
. 
Type
locality
</p>
               <p>Australia
, 
Western Australia
, 
Recherche Archipelago, east of Middle Island
, 
trawled
at 
51 m
, 

Marine Futures Survey 
2007
, station MF-MI-007

, 
10
October 2007

, 34° 0 
1.589
′0 S, 
123
° 
21.55
′0 E to 
34
°0 
1.30
′ S

, 
123
° 
21.42
′ E

.
</p>
            </tp:material-citation>
            <p>4.4
. 
3
. 
Paratypes</p>
            <p>
Three 
paratypes
are designated based on morphological similarity to the 
holotype
(

table 
3
and electronic supplementary material, file S 
1
). 
<tp:material-citation>CSIRO
Marine and Atmospheric Research, 
ANFC
C 
2269
and C 
2270
, as 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx lucasi</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
), 
two specimens
, 
236
and 
259 mm
TL, sex undetermined; 
trawledwest of Garden Island
, Western 
Australia
, 
32
° S

, 
115
°

E (coordinates approximated), 
72 m
, 

May 
1956
.
</tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
               <tp:material-citation>WAM
P 
660
, as 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx foliatus</tp:taxon-name>
,
one specimen
, 
221 mm
TL, sex undetermined; 
beachwashed
onto 
Cottesloe Beach
, Western 
Australia
, 
31
° 
59
′ S

, 
115
° 
45
′ E

, 

August 
1919</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p>4.4
. 
4
. Etymology
</p>
            <p>Named for Mary ‘Dewy’ Lowe, for her love of the sea and her support of seadragon conservation and research, without which this new species would not have been discovered.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p>4.4
. 
5
. Diagnosis
</p>
            <p>
Eighteen trunk segments. Head crest without appendage. Pectoral area enlarged (
pa
in 
b
, 
e
). Dorsally enlarged spine on trunk ring 
11
pointed forward (
ds
in 
b
). Paired enlarged ventral spines on rings 
8
and 
17
(
c
). Body deepest on ring 
12
, behind dorsal spine. Spines on lateral trunk ridge not continuous with lateral tail ridges (
c
).
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>4.4
. 
6
. Brief description of 
holotype</p>
            <p>
Preserved colour light brown. Live colour ruby red, with pink vertical bars on each trunk segment and light markings on the snout (
a
). Enlarged spines dorsally on neck and trunk ring 
11
; ventrally on rings 3, 8, 
17
(arrows in 
c
; see also videos S 
1
–S 
2
included in the electronic supplementary material). Presence and shape of dermal appendages on enlarged spines unknown. Lateral trunk ridges
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>
Phycodurus 
eques</tp:taxon-name>
(
n
= 
25)<tp:taxon-name>
Phyllopteryx 
taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
(
n
= 
20)<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
               <named-content content-type="taxonStatus">n. sp.</named-content>
(holotype

| 
three paratypes)total length (TL, mm)218–401238–427240
| 
221–259trunk length (mm)67–11470–13567
| 
61–79tail length (mm)114–22198–234111
| 
92–123proportions (%)trunk length: TL25–4224–3428
| 
28–31tail length: TL45–6942–5846
| 
41–48head length: TL18–3317–2926
| 
22–31snout length: head length5 3–7 76 1–7 26 8
| 
65–74snout depth: snout length11–207–137
| 
7–10orbital diameter: head length10–138–1312
| 
10–13postorbital length: head length23–3611–2820
| 
18–24neck depth: TL4–113–75
| 
3–4trunk depth 8th segment: TL8–184–148
| 
7–9trunk depth 11th segment: TL8–176–1311
| 
9–12trunk depth preanal segment: TL6–124–99
| 
6–8</p>
            <p>
not confluent with lateral but with inferior tail ridges. Trunk dorsally forming pronounced arch, highest point ring 
12
, behind enlarged dorsal spines (
c
). Fin rays: pectoral 
22
; dorsal unknown; anal 
4
.
</p>
            <p>4.4
. 
7
. Distribution and bathymetry
</p>
            <p>
The 
type
locality (arrow in map of 

) at 
5
0+ m shows a complex habitat of a mixed reef and sandy habitat [
29
, 
30
]. Two 
paratypes
were collected from the continental shelf near Perth (
72 m
, circle in 

); the habitat at this site is unknown. The fourth 
paratype
, collected at Cottesloe, Perth, does not have depth data, as it was washed up on the beach.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>4.4
. 
8
. Remarks
</p>
            <p>
The placement of this species within 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx</tp:taxon-name>
was informed by the phylogeny of seadragons (

). The new species lies as the sister group to 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
and this does not allow for its inclusion within the other seadragon genus, 
<tp:taxon-name>Phycodurus</tp:taxon-name>
. We made the decision to place it within 
<tp:taxon-name>Phyllopteryx</tp:taxon-name>
rather than erect a new genus, as this provides information about the closer relationship of 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
with 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
than with 

Phyc. 
<tp:taxon-name>eques</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
            <p>
An expanded description of the 
type
series of 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
, of 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>taeniolatus</tp:taxon-name>
and 

Phyc. 
<tp:taxon-name>eques</tp:taxon-name>
, including detailed comparisons, can be found in the electronic supplementary material, file S 
1
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>5
.
Discussion</title>
         <p>
The discovery of a new species of seadragon represents an important finding. It is genetically distinct from the two known seadragons, with supporting evidence from morphology and habitat. Although the two previously known seadragon species were described in the nineteenth century, 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
remained unrecognized for almost a century, after being first collected in 
1919
. This seadragon may occasionally be washed ashore, and be subjected to trawling, but may not have been recognized (as was the case with the samples located for this study) owing to a superficial similarity to common seadragons. Nevertheless, it seems surprising that this species escaped recognition until now given the public interest in seadragons. A possible explanation is that it may occur in depths beyond recreational 
SCUBA
range: three of our specimens of 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
came from relatively deep water (
51
and 
72 m
) a few kilometres offshore. The bathymetric range of common and leafy seadragons is insufficiently known, but they seem to be mostly restricted to inshore areas [
4
, 
31
]. Clearly, two sampling localities in offshore waters do not make 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
an exclusive deeper water species, but the coloration of the 
holotype
may be explained by a deeper habitat: although the red colour is conspicuous when out of the water (
a
), red light is rapidly absorbed with depth and so being red may effectively render the seadragon cryptic [
32
].
</p>
         <p>
Basic biological information on habitat preferences and distribution are needed to assess the status of 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
in the wild, and underpin any future management plans. The few records of the new seadragon from southwestern 
Australia
that we currently have cannot give a satisfactory picture of the distributional range. Furthermore, the records off the coast of Perth are almost 
60
years old and it is unclear if 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
still occurs in this region. The urban development surrounding the Perth region has been significant in the past century [
33
], including changes in water quality and vegetation [
34
, 
35
] that may have also affected the offshore habitat of 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         <p>
Only the retention of the unrecognized 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
specimens in museum collections allowed for its discovery as a new species. This highlights the significance of natural history collections as a treasury of new species [
36
], even decades after their collection [
37
]. Another invaluable component of biodiversity discovery consists of exploratory expeditions such as the Marine Futures project that trawled the 
holotype
and mapped its habitat [
29
]: the on-board documentation provided the only available photograph of a fresh 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
, a currently unique representation of its natural coloration (
a
).
</p>
         <p>
Southwestern 
Australia
hosts a large number of marine fish [
38
], and is considered a hotspot for future discovery [
3
]. 

Phyl. 
<tp:taxon-name>dewysea</tp:taxon-name>
is an illustration of the surprises that are waiting in the ocean, but many open questions remain regarding its range, habitat and biology. The other two seadragons are considered Near Threatened by the 
IUCN
[
6
, 
39
], and their conservation is of public interest [
5
, 
40
]. The new seadragon is no less charismatic and deserves to become a flagship species for the discovery of biodiversity.
</p>
         <p>Ethics statement.
Non-lethal clipping of the dermal appendages with subsequent release of the seadragons was authorized by the following authorities: Department of Primary Industries and Regions South 
Australia
(
PIRSA
), exemption number 
9901842
to the Fisheries Act 
1982
, § 
59
; Department of Conservation &amp; Land Management, Western 
Australia
, licence SF 
5126
; Department of Primary Industries and Water Wild Fisheries Branch, Tasmania, permit 
12112
issued under § 
14
of the Living Marine Resources Management Act 
1995
. Sampling followed an animal use protocol (

S 
12285
) approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (
IACUC
) of the University of California, San Diego and was approved by the Department of Primary Industries, Parks, Water &amp; Environment (DPIPWE) Animal Ethics Committee (AEC) of the Tasmanian Government (AEC project no. 
11
/ 
2012
- 
13
). Tissues were transferred with 
IACUC
approval (tissue transfer permit 
T07215
).
</p>
         <p>Data accessibility.
DNA sequences: GenBank accessions 

KM 
201544
– 

KM 
201604
. Phylogenetic data: TreeBASE accession number 

S 
15971
. http://purl.org/phylo/treebase/phylows/study/TB 
2
: 

S 
15971
.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="acknowledgments">
         <p>Acknowledgements.
We thank the Marine Futures project for collecting and photographing the 
holotype
. Glenn Moore and Sue Morrison (
WAM
) are thanked for supplying the deck photo, the 
holotype
and one of the 
paratypes
. Al Graham (
ANFC
) kindly provided two 
paratypes
and tissue samples. Severine Hannam (Auckland War Memorial Museum) and Leslee Matsushige (Birch Aquarium, 
UCSD
) provided tissues for DNA analysis. We thank Phil Hastings (Scripps Institution of Oceanography, 
UCSD
) for taking the radiographs and supplying specimens, Esther Cory who conducted the 
µ
CT scan, and Rachel Berquist for assistance. Kayla Krantz is thanked for laboratory assistance. Dave Catania (California Academy of Sciences), Mark McGrouther (Australian Museum), Ralph Foster (South Australian Museum) are thanked for photographs of common seadragons. We are grateful to Mary Lowe and the Lowe Family Foundation for financial support.
</p>
         <p>Author contributions.
J.S. carried out the molecular and morphological data generation and analysis, and drafted the manuscript; N.G.W. and G.W.R. collected field data, coordinated the study and drafted the manuscript. All authors gave final approval for publication.
</p>
         <p>Funding statement.
This research was supported by the Lowe Family Foundation.
</p>
         <p>Competing interests.
We have no competing interests.
</p>
      </sec>
      <sec sec-type="multiple">
         <title>References</title>
         <p>1
. 
Mora C
, 
Tittensor DP
, 
Adl S
, 
Simpson AGB
, 
Worm B.2011How many species are there on Earth and in the ocean
? 
PLoS Biol
.
9
, e 
1001127
. (

doi: 
10.1371
/journal.pbio. 
1001127
)
</p>
         <p>2
. 
Appeltans Wet al.2012The magnitude of global marine species diversity
. 
Curr.Biol.22
, 

2189– 
2202
. (

doi: 
10.1016
/j.cub.2012.09.036)
</p>
         <p>3
. 
Eschmeyer WN
, 
Fricke R
, 
Fong JD
, 
Polack DA.2010Marine fish diversity:history of knowledge and discovery (Pisces)
. 
Zootaxa2525
, 

19– 
50
.
</p>
         <p>4
. 
Dawson CE.1985Indo-Pacific pipefishes
(
Red Sea to the Americas
)

. 
Ocean Springs,Mississippi:Gulf Coast Research Laboratory
.
</p>
         <p>5
. 
Martin-Smith KM
, 
Vincent ACJ.2006Exploitation and trade of Australian seahorses,pipehorses, sea dragons and pipefishes (family Syngnathidae)
. 
Oryx40
, 
141
– 
151
.(

doi: 
10.1017
/S003060530600010X)
</p>
         <p>6
. 
Connolly R.2006Phycodurus eques
. The 
IUCN
Red List of Threatened Species.Version 
2014.3
.
http://www.iucnredlist.org
.
</p>
         <p>7
. 
Campos PF
, 

Gilbert 
TMP
.
2012DNA extraction from formalin-fixed material
.In 
Ancient DNA: methods and protocols
(eds 
B Shapiro
, 
M Hofreiter
), pp. 
81–85
. 
New York,NY:Humana Press,Springer Science+Business Media
.
</p>
         <p>8
. 
Wilson AB
, 
Orr JW.2011The evolutionary origins of Syngnathidae:pipefishes and seahorses
. 
J.Fish Biol
.
78
, 

1603– 
1623
. (

doi: 
10.1111
/j. 
1095
-8649.2011.02988.x)
</p>
         <p>9
. 
Wilson AB.2001Male pregnancy in seahorses and pipefishes (family Syngnathidae):rapid diversification of paternal brood pouch morphology inferred from a molecular phylogeny
. 
J.Hered.92
, 
159
– 
166
.(

doi: 
10.1093
/jhered/92.2.159)
</p>
         <p>10
. 
Wilson NG
, 
Rouse GW.2010Convergent camouflage and the non-monophyly of ‘seadragons’ (Syngnathidae:Teleostei):suggestions for a revised taxonomy of syngnathids
. 
Zool.Scr.39
, 
551
– 
558
. (

doi: 
10.1111
/j. 
1463
-6409.2010.00449.x)
</p>
         <p>11
. 
Kocher TD
, 
Thomas WK
, 
Meyer A
, 
Edwards SV
, 
Paabo S
, 
Villablanca FX
, 
Wilson AC.1989Dynamics of mitochondrial DNA evolution in animals: amplification and sequencing with conserved primers
. 

Proc.Natl Acad.Sci. 
USA
86

, 

6196– 
6200
. (

doi: 
10.1073
/pnas.86.16.6196)
</p>
         <p>12
. 
Palumbi S
, 
Martin A
, 
Romano S
, 
McMillan W
, 
Stice L
, 
Grabowski G.1991The simple fool’s guide to PCR
.
Honolulu,HI:Special Publications Department Zoology,University of Hawaii
.
</p>
         <p>13
. 
Miya M
, 
Nishida M.1999
Organization of the mitochondrial genome of a deep-sea fish, 
Gonostoma gracile
(Teleostei:Stomiiformes):first example of transfer RNA gene rearrangements in bony fishes. 
Mar
. 
Biotechnol
. 
1
, 
416
– 
426
. (

doi: 
10.1007
/PL00011798)
</p>
         <p>14
. 
Inoue JG
, 
Miya M
, 
Tsukamoto K
, 
Nishida M.2003Evolution of the deep-sea gulper eel mitochondrial genomes:large-scale gene rearrangements originated within the eels
. 
Mol.Biol.Evol.20
, 

1917– 
1924
. (

doi: 
10.1093
/molbev/ msg 
206
)
</p>
         <p>15
. 
Meyer A
, 
Morrissey JM
, 
Schartl M.1994
Recurrent origin of a sexually selected trait in 
Xiphophorus
fishes inferred from a molecular phylogeny

. 
Nature368
, 
539
– 
542
.(

doi: 
10.1038
/ 
368539
a0)
</p>
         <p>16
. 
Hrbek T
, 
Farias IP.2008
The complete mitochondrial genome of the pirarucu (
Arapaima gigas
, Arapaimidae,Osteoglossiformes)

. 
Genet.Mol.Biol.31
, 
293
– 
302
. (

doi: 
10.1590
/S 
1415-47572008000200024
)
</p>
         <p>17
. 
Chow S
, 
Hazama K.1998
Universal PCR primers for S 
7
ribosomal protein gene introns in fish

. 
Mol.Ecol.7
, 

1255– 
1256
. (

doi: 
10.1046
/j. 
1365
- 
294
x. 
1998.00406
.x)
</p>
         <p>18
. 
Teske PR
, 
Beheregaray LB.2009Evolution of seahorses’ upright posture was linked to Oligocene expansion of seagrass habitats
. 
Biol.Lett.5
, 
521
– 
523
.(

doi: 
10.1098
/rsbl. 
2009.0152
)
</p>
         <p>19
. 
Teske PR
, 
Cherry MI
, 
Matthee CA.2004
The evolutionary history of seahorses (Syngnathidae: 
Hippocampus
):molecular data suggest a West Pacific origin and two invasions of the Atlantic Ocean.
Mol.Phylogenet.Evol
.
30
, 
273
– 
286
. (

doi: 
10.1016
/S 
1055-7903
(03)00214- 
8
)
</p>
         <p>20
. 
Streelman JT
, 
Karl SA.1997Reconstructing labroid evolution with single-copy nuclear DNA
. 
Proc.R. Soc.Lond.B264
, 

1011– 
1020
. (

doi: 
10.1098
/rspb. 
1997.0140
)
</p>
         <p>21
. 
Katoh K.2002MAFFT
:a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform

. 
Nucleic Acids Res
.
30
, 

3059– 
3066
. (

doi: 
10.1093
/nar/gkf 
436
)
</p>
         <p>22
. 
Katoh K
, 
Standley DM.2013MAFFT
multiple sequence alignment software version 
7
: improvements in performance and usability

. 
Mol. Biol.Evol.30
, 
772
– 
780
. (

doi: 
10.1093
/molbev/mst010)
</p>
         <p>23
. 
Swofford D.2003PAUP
*.Phylogenetic analysis using parsimony (*and other methods).
Sunderland,Massachusetts:Sinauer Associates
.
</p>
         <p>24
. 
Darriba D
, 
Taboada GL
, 
Doallo R
, 
Posada D.2012
jModelTest 
2
:more models,new heuristics and parallel computing

. 
Nat.Methods9
, 
772
. (

doi: 
10.1038
/nmeth. 
2109
)
</p>
         <p>25
. 
Maddison W
, 
Maddison D.2011
Mesquite:a modular system for evolutionary analysis.Version 
2.75
.
http://mesquiteproject.org
.
</p>
         <p>26
. 
Stamatakis A.2006RAxML-VI-HPC:maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed models
. 
Bioinformatics22
, 

2688– 
2690
.(

doi: 
10.1093
/bioinformatics/btl 
446
)
</p>
         <p>27
. 
Silvestro D
, 

Michalak 
I.2011raxmlGUI:a graphical front-end for RAxML
. 
Org.Divers.Evol.12
, 
335
– 
337
. (

doi: 
10.1007
/s 
13127
-011-0056-0)
</p>
         <p>28
. 
Lourie SA.2003A new pygmy seahorse, Hippocampus denise (Teleostei:Syngnathidae) from the Indo-Pacific
. 
Zool.Stud.42
, 
284
– 
291
.
</p>
         <p>29
. 
Radford B
, 
Van Niel KP
, 
Holmes K.2008WA Marine Futures: benthic modelling and mapping final report
.

University of Western 
Australia
. 

http://static. weboffice.uwa.edu.au/files/marine_futures/ 0_Overview% 
20
Information/MF_Spatial% 
20
Report% 
20
final.pdf

.
</p>
         <p>30
. 
Kendrick GAet al.2005
Characterising the fish habitats of the Recherche Archipelago: 
FRDC2001
/060 Final Report

.

Fisheries Research and Development Corporation and University of Western 
Australia
.
</p>
         <p>31
. 
Kuiter RH.1993
Coastal fishes of south-eastern 
Australia
.
Honolulu,HI:University of Hawaii Press
.
</p>
         <p>32
. 
Johnsen S.2002Cryptic and conspicuous coloration in the pelagic environment
. 
Proc. R.Soc. Lond. B269
, 
243
– 
256
.(

doi: 
10.1098
/rspb. 
2001.1855
)
</p>
         <p>33
. 
Pearce RJ.1991
Management of the marine environment in Western 
Australia
:an ecosystem approach

. 
Mar.Pollut.Bull.23
, 
567
– 
572
. (

doi: 
10.1016
/0025- 
326
X(
91
) 
90735
-B)
</p>
         <p>34
. 
Walker DI
, 
McComb AJ.1992Seagrass degradation in Australian coastal waters
. 
Mar.Pollut.Bull.25
, 
191
– 
195
.(

doi: 
10.1016
/0025- 
326
X(
92
) 
90224
-T)
</p>
         <p>35
. 
Cambridge ML
, 
Chiffings AW
, 
Brittan C
, 
Moore L
, 
McComb AJ.1986
The loss of seagrass in Cockburn Sound,Western 
Australia
.II.Possible causes of seagrass decline

. 
Aquat.Bot.24
, 
269
– 
285
. (

doi: 
10.1016
/0304- 
3770
(
86
) 
90062
- 
8
)
</p>
         <p>36
. 
Bebber DPet al.2010Herbaria are a major frontier for species discovery
. 

Proc.Natl Acad.Sci. 
USA107
, 

22169– 
22171
. (

doi: 
10.1073
/pnas. 
1011841108
)
</p>
         <p>37
. 
Fontaine B
, 
Perrard A
, 
Bouchet P.201221
years of shelf life between discovery and description of new species

. 
Curr.Biol.22
, R 
943
–R 
944
. (

doi: 
10.1016
/j.cub.2012.10.029)
</p>
         <p>38
. 
Hutchins JB.2001
Biodiversity of shallow reef fish assemblages in Western 
Australia
using a rapid censusing technique

. 
Rec.West.Aust.Museum20
, 
247
– 
270
.
</p>
         <p>39
. 
Connolly R.2006Phyllopteryx taeniolatus
. The 
IUCN
Red List of Threatened Species.Version 
2014.3
.
http://www.iucnredlist.org
.
</p>
         <p>40
. 
Vincent ACJ
, 
Foster SJ
, 
Koldewey HJ.2011Conservation and management of seahorses and other Syngnathidae
. 
J.Fish Biol
.
78
, 

1681– 
1724
.(

doi: 
10.1111
/j. 
1095-8649.2011
. 03003.x

)
</p>
      </sec>
   </body>
</article>
